okay welcome back to the QA for day two
of handmade hero if you are in the
twitch chat or on IRC and would like to
ask a question please ask it now and if
you could it would be very helpful the
only way that I'm going to be able to
see them is going to basically be if you
put senior Ettore cm you are 80 ori in
your message so that i can see it and
that way i will actually be able to tell
what is going on in also since we are
starting to get more serious about the
programming now i would appreciate it if
you would keep the questions to stuff
that we actually did tonight or on a
previous stream so that we can actually
focus on stuff like that other than
because otherwise we get bogged down in
questions like what are we going to do
later and maybe we'll do some streams
where we handle where we field questions
like that but i would rather focus
mostly on questions about the code we
just did so that they can so that we can
explain it more thoroughly and suss out
any things that I went through quickly
because like I said I always have to go
quickly so that we can make some
progress and that means some things will
go back too fast and the QA is kind of
where we can drill down into that okay
so let's take a look let's see do do to
do expanding this out here so we have
further lung see atoms like intern
strings yes doctor cheats they are like
intern strings basically I don't know if
there's a good explanation of atoms on
here somewhere that will say exactly
what they are I haven't touched them in
a really long time but it may be an atom
about atom tables here you go an atom
table since my table that stores strings
and corresponding identifiers so you
know that's probably as close as an
intern string is you're going to get
right without actually calling an intern
stream so I would say yes that's a fair
way to describe them certainly they
really aren't that used that much in
what we're going to do at all
let's see dudu
can you go full screen with your cam for
the QA I would rather not because I'd
rather go and be able to show code like
I just did there cuz so I'd rather not
I'm sorry about that if we if I'm gonna
do something where I talk for a long
time I could try to do that but I don't
actually know how to do that without
stopping the stream I'm not sure how to
do it in OBS I got a assign some hotkeys
or something I don't know if it has that
to switch profiles or something like
that would be nice if while using the
MSDN you could put the chrome window on
the right a little so we can see the
code oh okay
that's a good call I'll try to remember
to do that so that you can kind of see
things all right yes I will try to do
that in the future thank you for that
suggestion um let's see doo doo doo
what's the fastest path for getting a
pixel to the screen on Windows well
technically we're going to show tomorrow
the way that we need to do it which we
will be doing but if you really just
want a pixel on the screen it is
actually set pixel if I remember
correctly set pixel basically allows you
to set a pixel at a particular color and
tell it what color you want it to be and
that is exactly what will happen so if
you want to actually do that you can it
is it is this let's let's I can actually
do it for you if you want we can
basically say okay that device context
that you gave us back at the coordinates
100 100 I will set something to to this
color and and off we go
right and if we then run the application
you probably I don't even know if you
can see it on the stream but there is
one little pixel there I don't know if
is zoom in installed on this guy
it is not install in this guy so yeah
you can see it and and as we repaint you
know when we we can see that it still
stays there this little little tiny
pixel so that is actually if you
literally just want the fast way to set
a pixel that is the way but we are going
to be doing it's way too slow you'd
never be able to render a game calling
set pixel well it could if it was a
pixel game I guess but basically we are
going to show tomorrow the way to
actually get pixels on the screen
quickly well and it's
in the quickest way the quickest way is
to use the GPU obviously but we're when
you're rendering them yourselves
I'll show you one fairly efficient way
to get them to the screen let's see do
let's see yes so thank you for
mentioning this I think I should start
doing this more so things that take
actual things that take an actual string
what I would like to start doing with
those is actually start always prefixing
prefixing sorry suffixing them with an
SI or or wide which I described in the
in the intro screen but I should
probably get get to doing that very you
know a lot more so if I go ahead and
undef these these variables here I want
to go ahead and F those variables just
see what's going on here which is your
class identifier not found' yes so I
will go ahead and make sure I call the
ANSI versions of these guys just to be
clear here
I don't think get message takes one
right get message is not something that
takes a string so it shouldn't yeah
so basically the way that all these work
I mentioned a couple times is basically
all these functions can take unicode
strings or they could take an C's you
know ASCII strings basically and we want
to always be calling the ASCII ones
because if someone tries to compile our
code using Unicode settings in the
compiler they will get an error because
these are not specified as unicode
strings they're specified as ansi
strings so I'm just going to go ahead
and do that for the benefit of people
who are trying to compile at home so
when they down the source code it will
work let's take a look do you use the
same technique for creating a full
screen window it depends on how you
create the full screen window we will be
covering how to create a full screen
window using a couple different methods
potentially at least one method and
basically you'd use this method for the
way that I think we will probably ship
the game but it depends we will have to
see let's do some compatibility testing
and check it out but I will be covering
that later let's see the for loop is
just keeping the window alive right it's
not related to the actual game loop well
we have not gotten a game loop yet so we
actually aren't in a position to talk
about that too much but basically what
this is is as soon as we exit right our
app is done so if I were to not actually
do a loop here and not
not actually do an infinite loop right
then once we actually start running we
will immediately exit right and the app
will be over basically what will happen
you know if we step in in the debugger
you know I step in here I go through and
I go to create the window and you can
see the window you can off you guys to
see that flash but it's there
there's our window right it got created
it just can't be brought to the front
now because we are in the debugger and
once you're in the debugger our app
can't respond to messages which means
the window can't come forwards and so on
and so forth but point being we go right
through here we create the window and
then we return zero so that's the end of
our app it will end up calling exit back
in the C runtime library exit process or
whatever the function is in Windows that
basically terminates the running module
and then we're gone right that's it
so we in order to actually have our
application run doesn't matter if it's a
game or anything else we need to
basically sit in an infinite loop
processing messages until Windows
actually tells us that we're done now
right now we have no way of Windows
actually telling us we're done but if we
wanted to we actually could do that we
would go ahead and we would put that in
here we would put that in WM closed for
example we would do destroy window and
we would call the the default actual
stuff yet you know what like we're going
to help cover that up so I'm not going
to actually get into that because that's
a whole another equation because we're
going to do that tomorrow when we make
our window more well-behaved um let's
see
can I pre-order the Epilepsy simulator
how much does it cost yes you will get
that tonight in fact if you pre-ordered
and download the code from tonight you
will have your very own epilepsy
simulator if you download tonight's code
and try to run it I wouldn't necessarily
recommend it if you have epilepsy
although I don't know if that actually
would trigger epilepsy let's see
wouldn't we want to make it to the user
can't resize the window willy-nilly
since the game will eventually have art
with specific sizes perhaps or perhaps
we just want to try to adjust to the
size that they want the window to be and
so we will be handling that stuff a
little bit later right now we might as
well let them resize it because why not
for a certain vision cross-platform for
development code let's see where
during this stuff is all not questions
related to the code from tonight is it
let's see can experiment with what
happens when you take out H redraw and V
redraw yes in fact I don't think they're
necessary at all I don't think we care
about them at all I'm pretty sure we'd
goat in fact and we can probably just
take out own DC either we're not even
going to snap that copy of the own DC
let's take a look here that's awesome
right because it's stalling
it's toggling every time we get a
repaint message it's only repainting the
part of the window that we don't that
got obscured when I bring it back on
right because the part that's below it
now when we come forwards it needs to
repaint it and it's calling that repaint
as I drag so the faster I drag the
faster it taught that the more gets
filled by each of the toggles of
lightness and blackness so you can kind
of do some fun stuff with that okay
right
again computers they're crazy they do
what you tell them right kind of funny
so yeah eight redraw be we we don't need
those I don't know they're the force of
habit I don't think we're going to need
those let's get rid of them own DC we
don't need either let's just get rid of
style it together and see what happens
let's just get rid of style yeah it's
gone
we don't care it's fine it's totally
fine so we're just gonna leave it that
let's see
OOP to do any considerations for 64-bit
on tonight's code you want to discuss
not yet I don't want to get into 64
versus 32-bit yet because it's not
hasn't really come up super much
basically the only difference between
32-bit and 64-bit compilation is 32-bit
is basically a 4 gigabyte address space
and pointers are 32 bits because 2 to
the 32nd is 4 billion so that's how many
bytes you can address with a 32-bit
pointer right where you're off when
you're where you're talking about
individual bytes 32 64 bit mode allows
that address space to be 64 bits which
is way way way bigger it's 4 billion
times 4 billion long obviously because
it's you know 64 bits and so that is the
only differences all your pointers go
from being 4 bytes long to be 8 bytes
long right the government
it's to 64 bits so basically as long as
you write your code so that you're aware
of the fact that your pointers could be
either size which we will try to do as
we go through our code we'll try to be
conscientious about that but as long as
you don't do anything that assumes it
knows how big a pointer is you should be
able to be fine in both 32 and 64 a bit
now there are some caveats there if your
code is trying to allocate giant hunks
of memory like let's say it's trying to
allocate a gigabyte here a gigabyte
there and big blocks and so on it could
quickly use up the 32-bit address space
that it has under 32-bit windows which
is only two gigabytes for application
usually and so on and that would be a
problem for you so there are some other
concerns where 64-bit allows you do a
lot more you can allocate huge chunks of
memory and do all sorts of other things
in memory map files in those spaces and
all those sorts of things you can do in
64 a bit without to worry too much about
clogging up the address space but that
is one thing additionally that you have
to be aware of but again we are not
going hit any of that stuff
and so mostly we will be 64-bit and
32-bit clean all the time and later on
I'll be showing you how to compile to
both so that you can ship on 32-bit
windows if you want to even though that
is now a relatively obscure platform I
think it's very if you look at the steam
hardware survey there is not much 32-bit
windows left and in fact why not just
look at the steam hardware survey now so
OS version we can take a look 64 a bit
64 a bit I don't know what is windows 7
is that Windows 7 nan 64 a bit let's
assume that's Windows 7 non 64-bit so 11
percent that's 64 a bit a 4% and a point
oh seven percent so I don't know where
something like yeah you know I mean
that's something like 15% maybe on the
Steam Harbor survey I don't know I can't
do mental math in my head I'm awful at
it so I'm not sure you'll notice all the
Mac is 64 a bit all the abun twos look
like they're 64 bit so yeah so basically
if your ship in 64-bit you pretty much
got it covered but if you want to get
every last thing you know you might want
to ship a 32-bit version as well I guess
I don't know and who knows how accurate
the same hardware survey is but
it's one piece of data you can look at
to see how prevalent things are let's
see what about using locally scoped
static constables since their cause
there is no threading concerns right
well that's true but if it's Const why
would it need to be static that doesn't
make much sense to me a Const is a
constant value so it wouldn't have to be
static it can just be replaced and in
fact static and cost conflict don't they
can you even declare a static cost value
yeah I didn't think so
oh well no maybe you cannot see now I
guess you can I've never tried that
before I so yeah I'm sorry I don't
really know why you declare a static
Const maybe there's some reason you
would want to do that but yeah I mean if
it's Const then it doesn't really need
to be static because you're not going to
change it and the whole point of static
is to reserve the changes after it goes
out of scope so it doesn't seem to me
like you would ever need to make
something Const static in that way but
it looked like it let you do it so yeah
there's that
can't say I just don't I don't see it
let's see I'm compiling in vs and for
whatever reason I'm getting a compile
time error that tells me the
initialization of the variables in the
WM paint case are skipped yes you will
get that if you did not declare the
block so if I were to do this so I don't
declare the block properly right now I
will get that initialization is skipped
right and what that's telling you is
basically that you have declared
variables in here but you have not
enclosed them in a block right so
basically if it was going to when it
gets in when the switch statement comes
in here right and in fact I can't tell
you exactly what happens here all right
let's say I come in here if I were to
jump in the switch statement into the
default right so I come in here
technically because this is at the scope
of the outside scope it's at the switch
statement scope I could refer to paint
in here right I could do something with
paint like paint RC
left equals five I can compile that now
right that's totally valid you'll know
it did not compile complain about that
at all and that's bad because these
variables they just got hopped right
over so if they were to have an
initialization let's say I was trying to
initialize that like this you know this
this would be thinking oh this will be
initialized and I'll use it or something
I don't even know what we going on here
but it wouldn't because it jumped over
that code and into here so I believe
it's trying to just warn you of bad
things that could happen along those
lines hopefully that makes it sense
so device context for example is
something that got initialized here and
I could go use it down here I'll just
paint the advise context but it's like
no you can't because it was not actually
initialized right so you want to make
sure that you get oops I missed one
there you want to make sure that you put
these little curly braces of the WM
paint to make sure that these are
enclosed in that basic block there you
so get message and dispatch messages
should also have an a suffix thank you
for finding those I'm not sure what all
the things are that need those so you're
saying this one and this one are also
Unicode and ANSI standard let's take a
look verify that I guess you're saying
translate message isn't okay good so
we've got all our A's in here which is
good to make it so that people can
compile Unicode without having to worry
about that let's see let's see
your nesting quite a lot of blocks there
will you show how to get rid of too much
nesting I don't know why I would worry
about nesting nesting is fine there is
no cost to nesting really it is not an
expensive thing it's free for the most
part the compiler can still optimize as
much as it wants really where those
things are placed and how they are
cleaned up I'm sorry I guess I don't
have anything to say about that I don't
think you should worry about nesting you
can nest things as deep as you would
like to nest them
let's see my app doesn't respond to the
window close button neither desires
either desires window close is not
responded to yet we're going to handle
those tomorrow so you have to basically
if you want to kill the window basically
you just kill it in the butter shift f5
that's how you do that so we we have not
handled that yet we have we are not
handling any of the windows messages
we're not handling any of those things
at all our window is still there but I
guess some of them like minimize
maximize are handled by so you can you
can still do those because they are
handled by the DEF window proc and that
sort of stuff but close we intercepted
now if you want to if you really really
need to right now you cannot wait till
tomorrow and you need to handle those
what you can actually do is you can just
get rid of them
you can let def window proc handle those
so if we just get rid of everything but
our WM paint it's gone right well in
fact I could just do this comment that
out for now right if I actually just run
that now it will respond to wwm close
right makes sense
hopefully that's that's clear enough but
basically there's a there's a reason why
you wouldn't want to do that the reason
that I didn't want to get into this and
so I really should get into it now is
that that won't actually kill the
application it'll just close the window
so Eve you'd still have to do one more
thing if you really wanted your window
to be working what you have to do is get
rid of these so that the def window proc
handles it and then inside WM to destroy
you'd have to post
message and that's basically a call that
posts remember I was talking about that
WM quit that gets to post it out here
that will post that message which will
cause get message returned but this is
too much stuff to just to just
flippantly throw at you but that's
that's it I mean that's the working
program right there if that makes any
sense so so but we're going to do that
tomorrow and I'm gonna explain it a
little more detail so you know if you're
watching the stream right now and you're
really antsy that's what you have to do
but but please don't ya please hold that
thought until tomorrow because that is
tomorrow's really when will be when
we'll be dealing with that is the for
just a shortcut for have an infinite
loop or to the compiler just insert its
own variable for conditions yes the for
is that is the syntax for an infinite
loop it is the preferred syntax now for
an infinite loop and the real the reason
for that is used to be while one and
what would happen is if you trains the
warning level and you know what I'm
gonna see if I can actually just change
the warning level for you let me see
here where is the warning level warning
level somebody tell me where the warning
level is warning level W all so if I
change the warning level to be more
stringent I will see if this compiler
does it Oh Lord yes well thank you for
all of that let me see if it actually
weren't there it is my lord this is all
warnings in the windows header files
ladies and gentlemen windows his own
compiler can't even compile its own
header file to that warning but anyway
conditional spread expression is not
constant this is what you will get
conditional expression is not constant
and so the problem that you will have is
you will get these warnings because you
have put in into a while loop something
that can never change it thinks that's a
problem now I have no idea why I thinks
that's a problem because it's pretty
clear of someone typed wild one that
they wanted to loop forever I'm not sure
what they could have meant but for some
reason they decided to start worrying
about that so for is the thing
that will get rid of that and now you
will note that that that error no longer
shows up after all the windows headers
we get down here and all it's got is the
unreferenced formal parameters there are
these parameters here that we did not
reference and it's just warning us about
those so so we're good to go I'm going
to turn off W all for now we may turn on
some more warnings the future probably
not those because you don't want to see
the windows headers ruin us all the time
but maybe we will even do that later
because there's few tricks we can do to
get around that but point being that is
what before : colon semicolon semicolon
is let's see I said of printing to
enclose a tenant can we handle it so we
can close the window tomorrow night
tomorrow night can you explain one more
time the window Handler and the message
is infinite loop absolutely I can so
here's what happens we open a window
windows creates that window it returns
control to us we see if we got it we got
it we enter an infinite loop where we
asked Windows to give us the next
message in our message queue which it
sticks into here right this is basically
a place where it gets written and you
can go look that up it's an MSG right
msg and you can see inside the msg what
is actually contained there so we go in
here you can see it's got the window
that the message pertains to it's got
that message code the WM paint or
whatever it's got the two parameters to
the message which we haven't looked at
yet and we will look at tomorrow it's
got when it happened like a timestamp
and it's got a point which is basically
where usually where the mouse was yeah
the cursor position of screen parts
where the mouse was that's where the
mouse was with him when the message
occurred now that's meaningless for most
messages because most messages don't
pertain to the mouse but you know legacy
reasons that was included in a message
so there it is
it's going to take that sort of message
that we got Gus stick the data in here
and then we're going to check to see
whether it is a whether it was able to
get a new message for us or whether it
had WM quit or an error or something
assuming that it didn't which means the
return code will be greater than zero we
are going to ask Windows to basically
translate that message in place for us
so it's going to windows is going to go
process the data in there to basically
turn it into something slightly
different and it's basically just for
processing keyboard messages and we'll
talk about that when we actually go to
handle keyboard input we'll come back to
that and say what that does but
all that does is translate those key
part messages then we're going to call
dispatched message and what dispatch met
dispatch message does is it takes the
message and actually sends it to the
main window callback now we could call
that window call back ourselves with the
message but there's reasons why we don't
want to do that because windows wants to
be the person doing the dispatching for
a number of reasons it that's the way it
expects the control flow to be so it's
best if you don't try to feel the
message yourself once we dispatch that
message we will just come back to the
top of the loop and get the next message
so we're essentially sitting in an
infinite loop waiting on a cue and met
Windows is stuffing those messages in
the queue and we're just pulling them
off we pull one off we process it we
pull one off we process it we go to get
one and if there isn't one there windows
will basically stall our process that's
what get message does it will stall our
process until there is a message so
we'll just wait when there is a message
it'll distil give it back to us will
dispatch the message so it's basically
just waiting for message and getting
them now we will change this when we
actually go to write our games animation
we will change from using get message
using a thing called peak message so we
can just look to see if there's anything
in the queue and even if there's nothing
in the queue we will still do stuff
because we are running our game and our
game is always running right so get
message just temporary so what I could
show you stuff it's the simpler way but
we will eventually turn into a real-time
game loop where we're calling peak
message so we're going to we're going to
upgrade in some sense to peak message
over time but we're starting to get
message because we don't need that
flexibility just yet if you want to see
this in action you can do it yourself
all you have to do is actually come in
here and watch it happen in the debugger
here we go I jump in here I create my
window you can see the window flash for
a second on your machine the twitch
stream probably optimized that out we
are going to call get message and we're
going to receive a message you can go
look at the contents of that message
type it into the watch window there it
is this is the window that it's targeted
to hey we only have one window so I bet
that's the same window and if you look
they are here is our window handle that
came back from create window e.x
here's the window handle that windows
says this message is destined for that's
exactly what we'd expect here is the
message right there that's the message
that's going to get dispatched 49 401 I
don't know what message that is maybe
it's WM create like
actually see what the value of WM create
is alright well you know what there's
another way we can do that let's go
ahead and look into the include
directory this is something that I was
not going to talk about quite yet but
you know what we can go ahead and do
that
so we're going to go to Microsoft Visual
Studio directory here we are going to go
into the vc directory into the include
directory and i am going to search it
for WM create or at least I'm going to
try to oh yeah yes love this bug this is
a this is an Emacs bug in later versions
of Emacs we'll also talk about this
later when I actually have to do a grep
on the actual stream I should probably
fix that in the Emacs compact I'm going
to right to fix that in the Emacs file
so you guys don't have to deal with it
as well there's an Emacs bug basically
fix findstr Emacs you'll take care of
that for you you don't need to worry
about Emacs let me handle Emacs we are
going to search for WM create and we are
going to find out where it actually is
is it in here is there a platform I've
used your 32 no I don't okay where is
the platform SDK ladies and gentlemen
where is the platform SDK let's find out
open documents can I actually get
Windows H where is it it's in Windows
kits these things jump around so
frequently man I don't even know Windows
kits 8.1 I guess where is it
8.1 include include and it is just in
the main one yes um
Windows H there we go ok I am now in the
right directory I will search for WM
create and I expect to find it although
it's going to have to go through a ton
of these include files here to find it
there it is it has found it I'm just
searching the drive for it and it is o
x1 so that is not it it is what is the
message that we actually received it is
c0 f9 let's see if we can find that once
c0 f9 rep c0 f
is that anywhere let's see oh my lord
that doesn't look right at all to me so
I don't know what this message is what
is this actual message I do not know I
do not know what that message is at all
well I suppose it could be defined in
it's 49 401 49 401 I would like to find
which message this actually is but
windows sends a lot of messages that we
won't understand so it's not really a
problem that it does this will be
handled by deaf window proc but I don't
know what that window actually is
interesting well unfortunately I guess
you can't actually see what window that
what message that actually is we'll have
to look and see if maybe we can figure
out what that message is later what we
can do here though is we can continue
this and then I'll keep pumping this
till we find a message we actually can
that we actually expect to get okay so
translate message will operate on this
message if there's something to do but
there wasn't to do and then this fast
message right if I actually set a
breakpoint up here in in this you will
actually see that when I step over this
to dispatch message we end up in our
window callback so here's the call stack
you can see us we called we call
dispatch message right with the message
it called through user 32 DLL twice user
32 DLL is the user interface portion of
the code in Windows it did whatever it's
going to do to do just two messages
match and then it got back to us when it
was ready for us to feel the message
right makes sense and so let's take a
look at what that message actually was
49 401 we don't know that one so we're
just gonna call def window a proc right
and come back out we pop out this is
Windows code right here
assembly language we don't know what
it's doing it's doing some window stuff
doing some more windows stuff that we
don't have the source code to we
returned out once we returned out twice
and here we are back in our source code
right go through the loop again get the
next message out oh and here's this is
also awesome so you may ask actually why
we had to register this window class
right why do we have to register the
window class at all to give it this
callback when we are the people fielding
the message loops well it's because
windows message loops are all kinds of
messed up even though it looks like we
are handling the messages here by going
translate message dispatch message
window
also reserves the right to basically
just flat out call our window with some
other out of balance messages basically
anytime it thinks that it needs to
handle them so this is where most of our
Windows message will be dispatched but
like when we you saw when that happened
right I step over get message well any
time we basically yield to the system
when we call in to the system it might
cost back right there and in fact I can
prove that to you if you go here you can
see this is where we were this is where
I stepped and it went through user 32
DLL it went through ntdll back through
user 32 dll called called called cult
and eventually called us back so we
wanted us to do something here that was
right immediate it didn't want to wait
to go through the translate message it
had something it needs to do immediately
message 127 what is message 127 that's
7f can we find that one ladies and
gentlemen and I don't know if we can
zero zero 7f we didn't have much luck
before let's take a look get Ikon
there you go you wanted to know what the
icon was for our window and it thought
that was so important that it had to
call outside of the disk mess measures
ladies and gentlemen there you go what
can I say windows it makes very little
sense it a Grove eights you but is the
platform you have to ship on I'm going
to go ahead and pop our stock back out
here in fact I'm not even going to
because man that's calling all sorts of
stuff outside of our trans our Translate
message loop so I'm going to go out here
and I'm going to wait for it to actually
get out of that get message and here we
are so now we've pulled off
it's called us multiple times with
messages we did not get to feel this way
so it just flat-out cold called us and
we are popped out here with another
message for for us to translate and
dispatch it so now I can actually again
set it here jump in and you can see us
fielding that message right so so there
you go okay
that's basically how it works there's
not that much to it but basically all I
can say is yeah it was I'm glad you
asked that question because we got to
see that in action and I never really
mentioned that fact in the mainstream
that the whole reason you have to
register the window class and give it a
window callback instead of just handling
it here and using your own callback or
telling it what the callback is or
something like that is
because every window that's created has
to basically have a callback known all
the time because it basically has to it
has to be able to call you at any time
it can just flat-out call you it doesn't
have to go through this because you
could imagine if we were more sanely
designed and every message actually went
through this message queue instead of
getting short-circuited like that like
it did you could imagine not needing a
dispatch because it would just say
here's a message and here's the window
you figure out how you want to handle
that and you wouldn't even need to it
wouldn't need to define this callback
because you would always be the person
calling it and that would be preferable
in my opinion but they did it this other
way so sometimes you're actually
fielding messages in in the queue like
you expect but other times you may call
a Windows function it doesn't just have
to be get message it could be any
function really it decides it needs to
call your window back for something it
just does that's just something it's
going to do and there's nothing to do
about it
so that's how that works we are out of
time
it is 9:36 we will have to pick up
anything that didn't get answered today
so thank you very much everyone for for
joining us there's a couple questions
using output D but string a to print a
string how do you print a variable when
and how often with WM paint be sent can
you show how to look at window messages
winds by these are things we will be
doing so just hold off till future
strings and we will show all of those
things because they are all good
questions and they're all good things to
cover so we will thank you very much
everyone for joining us we will be back
here tomorrow at 8 p.m. PST for day
three of coding when we will actually
draw in a very efficient way or at least
a much more efficient way to our windows
so we can actually start putting game
images up there which is what we want to
do rather than having to use windows
calls to do stuff because we want to
write our own renderer and we need a way
to get the output of our renderer into a
window that's we're going to do tomorrow
so thank you very much everyone for
joining us I hope you were able to
follow along this is it's a fast-paced
thing because you saw we only had one
thing to do today but I really had to
speed through to get to get through it
and that's the way it's going to have to
be I appreciate everyone hanging with me
thank you for asking questions thank you
for trying this at home and asking
since the people who asked it because
they were saying they couldn't they had
the warnings about the skipping basic
block that's exactly what you should be
doing trying to stuff on your own seeing
what works exploring reading that MSDN
documentation experimenting that is how
you will get good I am giving you the
backbone to sort of see how this is done
but to really build that understanding
you've got to try it yourself you've got
to practice and that is the way that you
will get good so please keep on doing
that thank you very much for joining us
and I will see you here tomorrow night