hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero show where we code a complete game
live on stream before we get started i
don't know if you guys remember when we
did a kickstarter for our graphic novel
to do the print run last time well it's
time for book two
so if you were one of the people or even
i guess if you weren't who backed the
original kickstarter and want the second
book
or if you weren't and you want both
books this kickstarter has both of them
it is now live and it's already almost
funded so that's a pretty good thing um
but there's a bunch of stretch goals and
cool stuff so please check it out if you
get a chance uh i have the book one here
that everyone got uh who backed the
original kickstarter uh or i guess
people who backed for the the actual
book uh and it looks awesome the
printers were amazing uh
i really can't say
enough good things about the printers we
worked with they were actually a local
print shop
in seattle but you just look at it and
it looks so good uh it's one of the best
looking graphic novels i've seen
actually i i i feel like they have done
such an amazing job
uh it's a place called consolidated
press if you ever want to do
a graphic novel print run
i would use them
uh so that's up now and you can check it
out uh you can just type meow book 2
kickstarter into google you don't even
really need a link but
i'll put a link in the video description
and also if you're watching this live on
twitch i believe i put one
uh in the little twitch links
section thing that i don't even know
really where that shows up anymore but
it's point is easy to find
all right that's it for
businessy news uh i guess i'll mention
one other thing about that is that
uh we have had a lot of problems with
spam foldering of our newsletter
we send out the newsletter very rarely
and apparently this is a really big
problem
i
i don't actually know
what the
deal is i mean you would think that
email
would be a solved problem by now but you
know it's basically run by microsoft and
google for the most part um so that's
another way of saying it's a non-solved
problem because the last time google or
microsoft solved a problem it was like
the year 2002 or something
so you know i guess it makes sense that
email doesn't work but
uh until somebody actually comes along
and
figures out how to send text messages
between two people because apparently
that's a huge unsolved problem in
computer science
if you're a trillion dollar company
so if some poor little tiny company
comes along and actually sells email
then we'll be able to actually send
emails to the customers who signed up
for our mailing list until then
we apologize our mailingless mail if you
signed up probably went to your spam
folder you can go grab it there maybe or
if your mic you work if you're on
hotmail you can't even do that because
microsoft does it just flat out refuse
to accept delivery of our mailing list
as far as we could tell
so it's pretty awesome we will be
switching providers uh in it probably
and
changing a few things we might try to
start sending the email more often like
once a week or once every two weeks
instead of once every couple months um
you know our original goal was not to
spam people with a ton of messages but
apparently like either
and this is another thing that's just
amazing like google and microsoft are so
incompetent
that you're more likely to have your
mail delivered if you send regularly
than if you send irregularly like if you
send once every three months to try and
you know avoid spamming your legitimate
users with unnecessary news
you get penalized whereas if you send
things like every week or every day they
don't consider it spam
uh
this is the kind of thing that happens
when the infrastructure for the world is
written by people who got their cs
degree out of cracker jack box
and i don't know
what to say other than it's absolutely
ridiculous
we're going to try and fix it but what
it means more broadly is that when i
come here to tell you about something
like now the infinite kickstarter or the
star code galaxy stuff
um i really can't promise that our
emails will get through so i apologize
for people who signed up for the mailing
list i especially apologize for starco
galaxy people because there are
literally 5 000 people or something that
have signed up in the past
few months for a star code galaxy it's a
lot of people and most of those people
will probably not get the email that
lets them know that it's available you
know when it goes into early access or
whatever
so i don't know what to say about that
other than google and microsoft are just
absolutely abhorrent companies i hate
them and i've hated them for a long time
these are easy problems they have
trillions of dollars there's no reason i
shouldn't say trillions of dollars they
have billions of dollars they have a
trillion dollar market cap there is no
reason why they can't solve this problem
other than the fact that they are
absolutely incompetent
and
the notion
that in 2021
they do not have a solid system for
allowing people to sign up for a mailing
list that they wanted and receive it
is so embarrassing that i don't
understand how people who work on these
projects like
look themselves in the mirror i would
just quit programming if i was that bad
it's insane
it's absolutely insane and i have
nothing
i have no idea
what these people are doing all day it's
ridiculous it would take 10 seconds to
solve this problem just add a thing
called subscribe to mailing list to
gmail and hotmail it would take a
freaking day to do it then you point
that at an rss feed that's it
that's it that solves the problem
completely forever
this would literally take zero time to
implement
but they are so incredibly bad at their
job that they can't even conceive of how
they would go about solving the mo such
a
can you pull text from an external
source this was working in unix with dot
plan files in this what 70s 80s i don't
know when they added that feature it was
working with deck notes in the 70s it's
been here forever nobody had this
problem it is a trivial problem and they
can't even conceive of how they would
solve it
with billions of dollars
in r d budget
infinite time they've had 20 years
and they can't even solve
pull messaging they're like we don't
know how we would do that
it's absolutely nuts
it's a grotesque embarrassment and i
have no idea why it's still going on
that's the end of that rant but if
you're wondering why you didn't get our
our one mailing list mail that we sent
in six months
that's the reason because the people who
work on these projects have no idea what
they're doing and the companies who
employ them don't care
now
that we've got that out of the way
let's go finish our collision detector
so
uh where we left off last time is our
conclusion sector actually was working
uh fairly well i believe
but we made some changes to it where we
do sort of the voxel search version
of the problem because we wanted to
essentially you know improve the quality
of like corner roll and stuff like that
uh so what we wanted to do is we wanted
to go in here
and make it so that when we
actually uh
when something is embedded oops
start in the wrong directory
when something is embedded in like if
the gameplay code creates two objects
that are like embedded or whatever
uh
what i would like to do
is i would like to make sure
that
embedded objects can exit
so that you know if the gameplay code
does create that situation it's not a
problem i don't want the gameplay code
to have to worry about that
so if i go in here and i just open this
project
and we look at what's going on in here
right you can kind of see uh the voxel
diagramming that's happening there you
can see it uh hitting things and and
that sort of stuff uh and it works
pretty reliably now that we've changed
to this uh model where and i shouldn't
say reliable because it was reliable
before i guess but it couldn't do roll
off
uh whereas now you can see as i walk
through here it can kind of roll off
corners nicely and again that's just
because the search space is a little
wider
but we still get problems and we
specifically i believe and and you saw
it get stuck there uh for a second
specifically i believe the problem is we
don't handle the embedding case anymore
and the embedding case happens for
example in this scenario here you can
see
uh what i kind of mean
in this uh
we should probably have a way to turn
this diagramming off so you can actually
see the glove
in this situation what's gonna happen
here is the hero has an this this part
up here this head part here
the hero has an actual block that's
effectively immutable right it can't be
moved and so it's entirely possible to
have situations uh multiple
different ways where you would push
something into embedded surface using an
immutable object in this game immutable
objects can't be changed so if they push
something it will just get pushed
right and there's no way to solve that
problem other than handling and betting
um
because we want things that hop to be
immutable when they hop to something
they land in the middle of the square
always and if there's something floating
there it would get pushed out of the way
if the hop has been validated right
using the transactional movement
uh so we need to handle that and we also
don't know we might just have a bug like
getting stuck on exiting this corner
might have just been a bug but it could
also have just been the fact that when
you hop through with the immutable uh
square it forces the glove into an
interpenetrating state from which it
cannot emerge right
and we handled this in the previous
iteration of the routine but uh when we
switch to the the thing that does the
full voxel search we don't handle
embedding anymore so one thing that we
want to do is make sure that we do
handle that embedding so that we don't
end up with that problem right
all right uh so i think we're good to go
now
um
with with the with the goal here uh but
that's really yeah that's really all we
all we need
uh and
yeah like again i just not sure
i'm just not sure where that
intersection is coming from so the other
thing would be it would be nice if we
could re
produce that a little bit better so that
we can look in to see if it was a bug
but bug or no we need to fix the
embedding problem so we should probably
do that as well if i could reproduce
this that would be good i'd look for it
first
um because just in case it becomes hard
to reproduce uh there you go
yeah
uh so with that it's stuck in place
maybe we could just look and see
uh what's happening there
uh just so we know
you know
just that we have some idea uh i might
go ahead and look at at that state uh of
the glove and just just see if i can
sort of suss out what it's doing
uh i'm gonna go into
[Music]
the build i'm going to switch the build
to debug and
you know i'm just going to rebuild in
place uh because i think that probably
just works
so i'm going to rebuild the game in
debug mode so i can debug it so
now it's running in debug mode same
state though
um and what i'm going to do is i'm going
to go set a breakpoint
in the move entity routine
and see if i can
it says
program is running because f5 was hit
why am i not able to set a break point
i thought i would
maybe i'm wrong
let me take a look at what happens if i
set it manually
all right well you know
um
that's unfortunate i don't know what
remedies is doing there am i on the
latest remedy i'm not
i probably
probably should update
i should probably update to a new remedy
uh so i guess i'll put that on the back
burner but
uh so if we step through here
and
take a look at what's going on first we
have to make sure that we're on the
correct entity id
so
we probably
although you know i don't know it might
be
it might be the case that we're oh it's
that one first always but let's take a
look so if i look at entityid.value
and i take a look at wait that's
probably not right the right one
um
let me step into uh diagram filter and
we'll just because we know which one
we're diagramming
we can just use this
as our determiner
so
in here we've got the global diagram
group filter
um
or not
how is it set to zero i thought it was
set to
i thought it was set to the
oh
right
because we reloaded the code and that's
global variable so it will get reset to
zero
all right that's not going to help us so
our problem is we don't know
uh which one is the glove
right
that's the problem that i have here
and it might be that this only gets
called once per frame let's find out
because if the glove is the only thing
undergoing collision in this region
it is okay so i guess we lucked out
there are no entities that are floating
that are currently in the active region
so we just we get it for free
so if i come down here and i just take a
look at what we're doing
let's let it
create the voxel region
and let's just take a look at what the
first uh corner
setup is
so if i delete all this stuff
uh and we look
we've got the cell here
uh
i can validate what the occupied
settings are for this cell
and just see
so if you look there's really nothing
wrong with that uh if you look at
at what that says
right
um
there's clearly there clearly are exits
right
because in order to exit you only need
one
there only needs to be a corner that's
not marked as occupied
so if you look the zeros
uh here and here tell you that you
should be able to move out of here but
it's entirely possible that the
direction you're trying to move doesn't
go
that way so i guess it's hard to say but
thinking about the order in which these
are i believe it's z y x if i'm not
mistaken um we can double check but uh
if you look at the
where is it
uh we've gotta check
corners call here here
um if you look at how these are packed
in
so z
y
x
right
um so z y x packing i guess
you can see that that's consistent
so if we look at how these are packed z
y x
it looks like the
yeah i mean it's an x
um
it's a negative direction for each one
uh and then positive z so it's basically
like i guess the
the
i guess the one thing i will say is that
is a little confusing
that is a little confusing
um
i'm not sure why that would be the case
because if you look at how this glove is
embedded you wouldn't expect it to be
able to move
backwards
better than it can move forwards
right um
so that's that's a little strange i will
say
um
like if you look at how that's embedded
i
you
you know why the reason i'm a little
weirded out there is y goes this way
positively it goes up
right the screen
uh not back
so if you were to take a guess
as to which direction
the
x
went it would be pop it would be
negative for x
but you wouldn't think it would be
negative for y
uh
you know what i'm saying
so when we compile this in
unless i'm just misreading that right
which i might be because it kind of is
just like looking at some raw data but
you know unless i'm misreading that
uh if you look
here
uh and you go
down to
that first check corners
oh um okay
that's not actually
well no it is so when we pull out the
current cell
right
that should be the cell that contains us
i guess i could check to make sure that
that's actually true like maybe we
messed up that setting
like maybe current cell i like coming
from the when we push the stack this
initial cell i if that was somehow
not
producing the correct value
maybe but assuming that it's you know
the stack should start
with where the actual uh glove
is and
if we assume that we start with where
the glove actually is
then i don't understand that layout of
corners
right i i don't understand
uh
i don't understand those values
because what that looks like is that x
negative
uh
oh but that's okay nope i think i did
just read it wrong this is y positive so
y positive x negative
all right now that's fine
so uh maybe i i got nervous for nothing
but that actually does look okay right
because this this value right here which
is where you could move to
is
downward
up like forward
and to the left
this is this one here
is
upward
forward
and to the left
and that is exactly what i would expect
so why can't the glove
go anywhere
um
let's take a look uh it obviously finds
the
distance squared for
uh the you know current location to be
the best but that's because there
currently has been no selection
uh of a location
we're gonna search
now
and
we're gonna add new corners so let's
take a look at side
x side y
and side z
um so this is saying
that
for reasons i don't necessarily know so
let's double check the delta p value
here so i'm not sure why it is searching
this direction first but we'll just take
a look here
so according to this it's x
it actually wants to go positive x
so i guess it might be going slightly
that direction
i mean that's fine
there's nothing wrong with that
uh so anyway okay we're going positive x
positive y
uh negative z although uh again it
didn't this doesn't really matter we can
go in either z direction and the
settings are basically the same
on the corners
uh so
what we look first for is is here
the side x it will never trigger uh this
one because
we know that only
the negative x
has something filled in
um so we wouldn't expect that to work we
will now flip
uh and check
the other six
so now we're going to look
at side explaining the other way this
one should trigger correctly now
so that seems odd right shouldn't that
have worked because we know that side x
is now zero
and we know that
therefore one one zero
and zero one zero should both have
worked
so
you know what this is wrong
we do have a bug
so this is just a straight up
uh
like
this is just a straight up like logic
bug right like you typed in the wrong
thing probably because we've mushed this
around so many times we were checking
for different things at different times
what we wanted here is to allow you to
move if any of these
are open
right
but what this says is that if any of
them are
this doesn't really make any sense
um
so
i believe right we're looking for
occupied so if you couldn't move in this
direction it would be this
right if all of them are locked you
can't move in that direction otherwise
you can
the or
was the wrong way around that would have
been if it was saying which ways you
could go then we would say like if any
you know if any of them are
so i think that is the problem
um
it's only supposed to stop you from
moving into the next cell if you have
that you know criteria
um there are some things that we
probably have to fix uh
with placement at the end due to the
fact that we allowed that kind of motion
but that's what we want i think
pretty much across the board
uh
i'm gonna
see what that does by the way in
i'm surprised the other way worked i
guess it's just that most of the time
you're moving in the clear
so you have all four points but as you
get near obstacles that's just wrong
so let's take a look
uh still nice and solid
there
um
no issues there
uh
roll off corner roll off seems fine
i'm glad we stepped through that that
was just a dumb
that's just a dumb bug
so it looks like that let us tunnel
so that looks like a bug
there
it may not have it was hard to see
whether it tunneled or hopped over
hopping over we currently allow we you
know don't have blockers on the ceiling
uh we probably should
but
let me see if i can make that happen
again
[Music]
again the problem here is that without
you know it's a little bit tricky
because without actually seeing
what it does let me try
and see if i can actually just like
get that to happen single step
i i don't seem to be able to
uh which is kind of sucks
i was hoping we would be able to get
that to do something where we could look
at it a little bit more closely
right
um i suppose one thing we could do is
crank the time step down although if
it's somehow time step dependent then it
won't happen
um but i just i don't know how i need to
get a look at it in a way that lets me
know what i'm actually looking at here
right
so here's a much slower version of this
thing
[Music]
um
i cannot really see in
hmm well this one's a bit of a puzzler
um
i really just can't tell like i can't
tell if that's just going over the top
or not
starring sylvester stallone
um
because it seems pretty solid everywhere
else
so it seems weird that it would be
somehow sneaking through the geometry
there that said collision detection is
that kind of a problem where some
particular piece of geometry is just so
uh that it exposes a bug in your routine
like that right
i couldn't tell what happened there i
really want to be able to look at what
happened there but unfortunately i can't
um
so i wonder one thing i could do is
maybe like turn on looping
um
and see if i can get it to happen uh but
again
i don't know what i'm really gonna do
uh even if i can we need a snapshotting
feature for the collision but
uh
yeah again it's a lot of work to
implement
for a small project
um
i don't know
i'm not sure what we're gonna do here
we may just need to bite the bullet and
get something in there that allows us to
like step backwards
um
because it looks very solid
99 of the time and i can't i just can't
tell if all that's happening is just
that it goes over the top or not
right
it doesn't look like it
like it doesn't really look like it's
going over the top
but so that's why i'm concerned
but it's really hard to tell because it
happened so quickly and i don't know
that i would really be able to see
either way
um
what was happening
the fact that that happens to be a
changeover point doesn't help
um
and i guess now that i think about it i
also don't know if the changeover point
could be part of the problem
like when it changes over it's like the
collision is in the wrong place for one
frame or something like this
i don't think that could be possible but
never say never you know
can we get it to happen anywhere else
if we could get it to happen in similar
circumstances i would be more inclined
to believe it was going over the top but
if it only happens that one spot then it
seems unlikely
right
so i don't know
i don't know
i don't think i remember that those guys
left little poofs when they hop around
so i don't know this looks pretty stable
in every other case that we're looking
at here
um
so i really don't know what my guess is
i'm not sure
uh
i just do not know
um
we need to start being able to battle
enemies look they've boxed me in
uh so i don't really know
how i want to approach this
it seems very repeatable i mean i've
done it several times
right
and it seems like it is very specific to
that location
right
and it seems like it's able to get out
of the world like it seems like it's
able to tunnel to me
it doesn't look like it goes over the
top so how is it doing that
we know there's three colliders there
you can see them light up right
what's weirder still is it's able to get
back out as well
which also doesn't really make any sense
so it's a pretty peculiar
situation
it would seem
and i do think it it must be a bug
it must be a bug in the collision
routine as it stands
um
so there we go
so somehow it's able to kind of get
inside right like it looks like it's
getting inside so i think
i think there's some kind of
there's some kind of uh
like inadvertent
motion that we're allowing here and i'm
not sure what it's coming from
um
after changing to and
these obviously look correct
and
certainly that's a very permissive way
to move but it should still mean that no
matter where you move into you had at
least one
um non-colliding corner
so it doesn't seem like that should
really be an issue
um
like i can't imagine that i don't see
how that policy would ever allow
for the kind of motion that allows you
to get inside one of the other blockers
right that doesn't make any sense
furthermore it makes even less sense
because you don't get stuck
somehow
so that makes even less sense because if
you can't get stuck it wouldn't doesn't
really
it doesn't really make a lot of sense as
to how you're able to
like how are you able to get in there
you're going to be colliding as soon as
you're in there how are you able to move
through it
right
so this is a bit of a puzzler to say the
least
so i guess what i would say is you know
i don't really know any other way to
solve this other than
maybe to actually just put in the single
stepping
it's not that hard to put in single
stepping right uh you just like put
these in sort of a circular buffer and
reset them only so often
um
i assume this thing
like
i assume this thing has some way of
yeah bucketing this up we so you know we
could just do that
you know if we look at how this thing is
set up we've got these uh diagrams here
and maybe what we do is just let those
diagram groups kind of pile up
right
um
like if you imagined
this diagram reset
if you imagined that happening only
every so often
so
like if you imagined this having a thing
in it that was like
reset counter
you know
and you just said like okay
you know as we go through here
were every time someone does a reset
uh
if not group captured right
um every time someone does a reset we
just go like reset counter plus plus
and we just say like if that's equal to
16 or something
then it does this
in my imagination that would allow us to
store like 16 frames worth
of
you know
look back or whatever you want to call
it
right
um so now you can see
that just kind of getting you know
plopped on there right
um
[Music]
seems like that just keeps going why is
that not resetting is that cause
oh
slow morning
um
so that'd just leave trails right and so
if we wanted to
uh what we could do probably is
make something where it's easy for us to
keep some of these around
uh and then we can look at the diagram
uh single step uh after the
you know after the bug occurs
assuming we can get it to occur
uh which you know it seemed like it was
happening fairly frequently before
of course once we actually try to find
it there we go
so you saw that right
um
so i guess what i would say is
it's
really tough calls it looks like it's on
the top there which is really difficult
to say whether that's going over the top
let's um
let's maybe put in a hotkey so it's easy
for me to
stop it
and then we probably can like zoom in
there and look
right hopefully
i really wish this was a little easier
to make happen
um you can see that it's on the top when
it gets to the other side
uh but you can't really see exactly what
happens when the bug first happens so
it's a little bit
difficult to guess
um
again i don't think it's going over the
top because you think you'd see it more
clearly there
but i just don't know
like that clearly went over the top
right
so here's one thing we could try as well
that's maybe a reasonable thing to do
like what would happen if we just change
the heights of these things to be higher
right
um or put a blocker on top
like on the
across the like as a cap like a ceiling
um
that might be something to try as well
so that we know there isn't a hole that
way we're not looking at something that
could actually be a legitimate movement
um
so maybe that's a good good idea
i don't know
what the right way to do that is we we
have to do at some point because we
can't you know we have to not allow
entities to move upward in the world
let's look at a two
stack area here real quick just to see
um what the likelihood is
of
of us doing something stupid
so
i mean yes making them higher for
starters might just be a better idea i
don't know looks wise if it might not be
good though because it might be that
looks wise we want them stumpy like that
because just for art purposes so i don't
know what we want to do with the
blockers of course we can make the
blockers any size we want um so maybe
like just add the collision
when we're actually putting walls in
here uh
this right here
i believe uh the ad piece occluder is
for the
is specifically for the
lighting system
and so
in theory that wouldn't affect the
collision it's just this collision
volume here right
so the vol thing where that actually
gets set up
to take a look at
yeah so you you make relative here
you can see it makes traversal out of
that
yeah so i think what i would say is
looking at the collision volume stuff
here i think we just want if it's a wall
we maybe just want to extend its
collision volume uh up a little bit
further
so
but leaving the actual visual the same
it seems like probably the best call
um
in terms of whether or not it's a wall i
think on wall is pretty much
the only
thing we've got so it would be something
like you know if on wall
uh then the entity collision volume you
know max z
we want that to just
go upwards by some
amount right
uh and
i'm not sure what that should be it
looks like we have
there's like ceilings
that we were adding in here
um
so again i'm not really sure how high we
want these collision
volumes to go
but i'm just going to hack that in there
for now because i'm not sure what we
want there
let's just see what that does
so that we can get some more information
so when i look at it now you can see
it's not much
higher though
um
so we probably want it to be like
another wall heights worth is is what
i'm thinking
so we probably want to add like the full
wall height
on again or half that height or
something like that so we probably want
to just do like something like that
and see what that does for us
so let's see how tall that is
so that seems better right
um
that seems better
uh okay
so now we know that there should be no
way to go over the top there's that's
like just not possible so you can see
now like and and that's really weird wow
okay
so
you could see it still able to do the
tunnel uh i think
yeah
it's still able to do it even with walls
that high so we just have some kind of
bug where you're allowed to tunnel
through the corner somehow
um
but yeah i just don't know how i'm also
kind of weirded out by the fact that if
you look
there's like
is there somehow like
not a collider there like why is that
collider not showing up you see how
they're all showing up but not that one
but why not
when you're in the corner you should be
colliding with this collider as well
um
so that's really strange
and i don't know
i don't know what's going on there
all right well we're not out of the
woods yet i thought we were in good
shape but we're not quite in good shape
we still got some buggies uh in in the
way this is working it's it's closer
but it's not close enough
right
um
[Music]
and
this bug is kind of annoying because
it's definitely one of those collision
bugs where you're like all right
like everything seems to work fine but
just not
this one place right
um
i was able to make this happen down here
once right too but
uh
again really hard it's really hard to
get it to reproduce
this behavior
so just to be a little clearer about
what i'm talking about
so do you see how like when you go up
and push into that corner do you see how
the actual block
the diagonal block lights up as a
collider
so right
you can see like you know
those white posts sticking out there of
the
you can you can see like the collider is
active and it being checked
and when i push up into the diagonal
corner you can see that the one that's
diagonal is getting checked as well
what i was trying to say is that's not
happening over here
right like you'd never see
those
somehow that one ever getting lit up
when it's in the corner
and it should
um you can see it light up the ones
around it right like all the other ones
will light up but not that one as far as
i can tell
um
and that's weird right
so i'm not sure what's going on there
uh
does it have a collision volume
i assume it does
but i don't know so maybe i could turn
on drawing of colliders
and just see
um
it would be nice if we had a way to do
that but we don't at the moment
um i don't think
so i'll just
enable it debug wise
um
so it seems pretty obvious that's there
so that's you know that to me is a
little bit of a of a
concern
i don't know for sure that that's
implicated with this bug but looking at
it that doesn't fill me with confidence
right
um
[Music]
so why would we not see that
light up for collision
the glove
is a sphere
it's pushing in i guess because the
sphere because it is a sphere
might be the reason because the sphere
touches both sides
but not the diagonal
and it might be that it just so happens
to be
far enough over on this one that it does
touch
of course maybe the question there is
why does this one touch because it seems
like
the sides should work the same way and
the fact that they don't is perhaps
perhaps a little suspicious
um
how do we want to handle this
so
i just had a thought
is it
possible
well no
so i guess what i would like to do here
is i'd like to just be able to watch
right i'd like to see how the search
happens and what it does
you know what i mean
um
so
i think what we just need to do here is
make it so that we can single step
um
have it so that as soon as i see this
happen there's a key i can hit so i come
through here and like i see it happen
[Music]
of course it's not happening anymore but
you know
it happens there i hit like some button
like space bar right
um
and it freezes the diagramming so it
just stops it stops recording new
diagrams
you know what i mean
when it stops recording new diagrams
then i can step through the diagrams
like one by one and watch the solve
happen
um
[Music]
i don't know any way we're gonna solve
this other than that
uh
because i just don't i just don't see
how i'm i'm i'm never gonna know
i'm never gonna guess
like what
series of events allowed it to do what
it's doing
um and especially because it seems so
like like it has a rhyme or reason to it
it seems like it's going
in a very specific pattern and so it's
really hard for me to understand like
what what is actually happening there
right
um and especially because
uh
also don't know
like there could be bugs anywhere
it doesn't have to be in the voxel
search we could have a bug in the
collision code or something right
that's saying that like
you know it's not colliding
so without seeing
[Music]
more information about what's gone wrong
you know we don't really know i mean
we've got a
we've got a sphere
collision detector that we just kind of
threw in there
um and the sphere collision detector
we don't even know if that works
right
uh
so
i'm just not sure
looking at the sim region
code here
you know you can see we've got the test
sphere thing
uh
like you could easily see this having a
bug
right
um
you could easily see this having a bug
it's definitely getting to be that time
when i start getting stuffy in the fall
so
you can see what we basically did is we
compute all these things together and
then just compute one value that's like
do they intersect and you can see we
basically combine the values as like if
a and b are a sphere and the spheres
intersect if a is a sphere and b is not
a sphere and you get b rect a
you know
so you compute some values and then you
compute
all the um
possible answers right
uh and you know
off you go
so we know in this case um we're pretty
much always in one particular of these
right so in the collides at p we're
always basically passing
the glove which is a sphere as the
entity
which means that when we do uh shapes
collide we do mover is sphere mover is
sphere is true
so it's a sphere and testosphere is
false
so we know that a is is sphere is true
and b is sphere is false
right
um
so i believe that means we're in this
case right so b wrecked a sphere so a is
uh
i'm sorry b rect yeah b wrecked a sphere
so it's a is a sphere and not b is a
sphere so we're looking at this
you know what i mean we're looking at b
rect a sphere
so b rect a sphere
is just the length
of the two
less than the radius of of um
of a
so we're taking the length squared from
the center
of the sphere to the closest point on b
and we're seeing
if that is less than the squared radius
of the sphere
that seems totally obvious like i can't
can't see i see where that would have a
bug
to be honest with you
um
so i'm not sure i would consider that
particularly
particularly likely to be this source of
the bug
right
so that that doesn't seem super likely
um in the collides at p
you know there's not a lot to it
and we're drawing these things
so it doesn't seem
like there would be
[Music]
much of a reason
to suspect that either
so
yeah i just don't
so this is
this part is a little bit
iffy though
we don't really know much about refined
voxel placement
and
and we haven't thought very much about
how that might affect things
i'm not really concerned about it in
this case because
like i said it shouldn't
matter much
because those colliders are solid
so it's not like there's just a wall
there that's like infinitely thin and if
you got on the other side of it you
could move around the colliders were
treated as solid so if you moved into
him you should be frozen in place at
that point
right you shouldn't be able to move
anymore
um because when you come out of this
thing
we're not handling the embedded case
and this is why this is so
um
this is why i'm so sure there's a bug
right is because if we're
basically freezing you so if coroners
come back and they're all unoccupied so
you can't move anymore
then how are you able to
go anywhere once you get embedded in the
wall right
um
it doesn't make a whole lot of sense
so
so it feels like you should always be
trapped inside your initial cell
and you should never be able to actually
get out of there you know what i mean
um
so that part doesn't add up
hmm
yep i still don't have it i still don't
have it
it's a slow morning i'm very tired i i
didn't sleep well last night at all
so
it may be that i'm just missing
something obvious
uh and if i were more awake
we wouldn't have this problem
but i don't actually know
uh it could actually also just be
difficult
so
i'm not sure
i i'm not sure any way to really
explain that what i could do too just
really quickly here uh
is
change how we're drawing these diagrams
so you know a lot of this is not that
useful so drawing the spheres and stuff
as is not that useful
it doesn't really let us see very much
of perhaps what we want
to see and so what we could do here is
maybe draw something that elucidates
what the corner status is a little more
clearly right
so if you
imagined
when we do check corners
we're mostly drawing the colliders but
you know what if instead we mostly drew
so you know instead of like this
right
um
if instead of that
i feel like we could instead
draw like
what the corner state was
so what if we like turn this off
entirely
uh
and then
when we do
when we do check corners
anytime we do a new corner
we would draw that point
and we'd just draw whether it was in or
out
you know what i'm saying
um
like
turn all these off
and then just draw the points
so when we go in here and we test one of
these uh points
we say
okay
the
whatever the corner is that we were
looking at
uh we know that this was the test point
um
we will
we will go and say
diagram
point
do we have that
uh
we'll draw a point there
and we'll just make the point color
uh be based on the occupied
setting
so
if the field occupied
is
one way or the other way will set its
right
so we'll set the color
if it's an occupied point uh it's red
and if it's a unoccupied point it's
green
and now we'd just like be spamming
[Music]
points that
we can see
right as we go
um
and you know that looks pretty good like
as i'm looking at it it's like okay yeah
like it's there's red collision points
uh in the places where you can't place
the thing like near the wall when it
gets too close to the wall
uh and green ones where you can
and you know i don't expect to
necessarily see anything here
but i'm just curious
like what it's gonna show
when it does that hop
right
and of course it's not doing the hop now
so we don't even we don't see anything
because it's kind of interior right um
one thing i could do here to make it
easier on us to see is to just not draw
those
so when we're in the entity code like if
i want to be able to just look through
them
what i could do is in here where we go
and
render stuff
i could not draw
uh cubes
so
you know
just turn that off
you don't you don't get to do that
anymore
um
so now we can just watch
that happen right
so let's try that
of course without the cubes i can't
quite tell so you know what i'm going to
turn on the colliders as well
all right
so here's just like the collision space
of the worlds
um so here's the hallway right and
there's the doorway
um
and now i just have to get this thing to
like go through there
so that was weird like why was it black
instead of
what does that even mean
do you see that
i am very confused by what that means
like it wasn't green and it wasn't red
what does that mean
again i really need a way to pause this
so maybe let's add that pause feature
where we stop clearing
um and then we can just go take a look
at what it actually drew there because i
don't understand like that it didn't
even look like something i was drawing
it's probably something from some other
part of the code
um
which will be good information but like
i don't know why we're drawing black
points like who was drawing that
and why
um so let's do let's go to the reset
code and and make that be a thing
so
in here we've got a thing where
uh
you know
we can turn diagramming on and off
pretty easily right
uh and so what we need is a way to turn
diagramming on and off and also like
clearing
on and off or and i guess i don't know
how to say that
uh
we just need to turn the diagramming off
at that point and then i think it would
be fine
i don't know how to do how we want to do
this reset counterpart here i mean maybe
we'll just
record 32 for now which is which is
more
um
and then in the
[Music]
in the part where we do diagram is on
uh
captured i guess is the thing
so i guess we just say capture
so we just say when we say capture
you know that is the thing that that
makes it stop doing the diagramming
now i don't know we probably need to add
a button for that or maybe we don't it's
right there so i guess we just
that's all we really need
um
i just probably need a hotkey for it
because i don't know that i can do it in
time
come on
i know you would like to slip through
there please
do so
and of course now
that i want to actually capture it
it doesn't
want to do it
why
there we go
i was not able to do it in time exactly
as i said
all right so i need to add a hotkey for
that because doing with the mouse is
just not going to cut it
so i don't know which hotkey i should
add but
we'll take a look so we have the f keys
um
set up in the platform layer here
um i don't know what they're called like
debug keys or something like that
uh but there's basically like a you know
an f key pressed thing
so i want to go take a look at where
we're processing that
and
you know we'll
we'll deal with that
there
so
maybe
because we've got the
we've got the diagram thing
[Music]
this collision thing here
uh maybe we'll do
a thing that allows us to toggle there
so if you know if like the shift key was
down
or something like that like one of the
other uh debug things we have
uh so if you hit shift
as you're doing it
[Music]
shift f9
it'll toggle that state
or just set it to true
clearing it i guess you can just do with
the button
so that's just a way of like having
there be some way i can do it more
quickly than having to try and click a
button with the mouse which is not going
to really do it right
um
so if we look here like you know all
right we're going around and whatever
and then i need to i like see something
and i can hit f shift f9
did that actually do it didn't look like
there was any
no that does it
that does it all right
um all right so hopefully this will get
us something
you know maybe it will maybe it won't i
guess we'll find out
i could probably just crank that number
up higher too
number of frames captured
and once again
it proves rather challenging to actually
get this thing to go around
come on man
it really doesn't want to do that come
on go in there come on get through
you always do it you know the bug always
happens when it wants to happen it
doesn't happen when you want it to
happen that's that's the really
egregious thing about bugs
is you know they don't happen when you
tell them to
it's really the worst part of it
if bugs always happened when you told
them to they'd be a lot easier to find
it's kind of fun like seeing the weird
like springy glove thing
uh it's kind of fun seeing the diagram
of that
right it just looks kind of cool
um
all right well i can't really do much if
this bug will not happen
mr bug
this is there you go
so that's mr bug
um so now we have an actual capture
so yeah i mean like it's
as far as i can tell this is just
extremely erroneous
the collision detector says none of
those things are allowed it's it's just
able to move
[Music]
even though the collision detector says
very specifically that it may not do so
right
um so i mean really good information
so that's nice i mean
we basically know
uh
that
whatever we did here there's like a
really severe bug like we're not looking
for something subtle like numerical
error or something here like this is
like it's just it allowed this to get
placed
in this region
like you can see those pink marks right
i believe those pink marks are the
root finding marks if i remember
correctly when we added those in there
so so like if you
go to
the
part where we do the refine
uh
it's this
i believe
you know what i'm saying
um
i think
you know don't quote me on that
uh but i think it's that
so despite the fact that the collision
detector
very clearly
and unambiguously says that there's no
way to place it anywhere outside of this
little region over here
nonetheless we somehow called the
placement routine to refine the voxel
placement way the heck out here
so the mystery is
what is wrong you know how did we screw
up the routine that bad
uh that it was able
uh to somehow think it could do that
so there's even
more
bad things here than that
actually
so riddle me this
collision man
think about this diagram that we're
seeing
there's something else that really
doesn't add up here
we don't check corners
for
anything that's not connected to
an occupiable square
this is stack based we push one initial
cell onto the stack
and then from each cell
that's in the stack
when we pop one off
we're supposed to only push things onto
the stack that are accessible
right that have a green
so in this diagram
we are only supposed to push things on
that have a green
like cube
uh
touching them somewhere so
we shouldn't even see
these red
squares out here because how were they
ever reached
you should only ever be able to see the
red squares surrounding the green
squares and then that's it
so our voxel stack push
is itself broken
right um
we don't really need to talk about the
collision section at all
because we're already wrong like we
already screwed up
before we even get to the part where
we're testing to see if something can be
somewhere
we're already wrong before we ever get
there because we never should have been
able to do that
right we we should not have been able to
we never should have called check
corners on most of those places where
we're seeing the red corners
so like when we come through here
you know there's two ways that could be
happening
[Music]
um oh
so it's probably just this
so it's probably just yeah wow that
sucks that i spent all this time looking
for that when we if we had just started
working on the embed code we would have
probably fixed it it's probably just
this
right
um it's probably just that when you find
one that's completely embedded you
switch them all to false
now of course that well
before i say that though
how did you get there because you
shouldn't have been able to
so to be honest
to be honest that doesn't really quite
explain it
uh
because yes
that allows you to move through embedded
spaces but only if you started in an
embedded space if you didn't start an
embedded space
how would you ever get into you would
never test a cell that had all of its
corners filled because how did you get
there you had to move to it from
one that was filled and we can see that
that was not happening like this is
green
so
presumably
unless it accidentally
okay
let's
create a hypothesis
maybe this is what happened
maybe what happens is
our place our refinement placement
routine is capable of accidentally
putting you
slightly outside of the cell that you
were in on the previous frame
and what happens is in this one specific
case it does that
and it puts you into a cell that you're
embedded in
then the embed code which is wrong
because this happens and then we don't
process it right this is the to do that
we were going to do today
the embed code that is wrong then kicks
in and allows you to move anywhere
because it doesn't properly currently do
anything it just lets you go anywhere
right
if that were the case
then it would be
the refined voxel placement
uh routine
right
uh
the get
closest point in box conservative
would be like
erroneous
that could be it
let's test this hypothesis
because it seems like a reasonable
hypothesis
if that were true
then if i simply didn't do this
right
if i simply said
no
we will not change the corner occupancy
results
right uh
then that should not have happened
meaning we shouldn't be able to
reproduce the exact same scenario we
just saw
we could produce a different scenario um
and in fact you can see it getting stuck
there right uh so this is interesting so
so
maybe we were actually in a place where
we've got some kind of a problem with
how that refinement placement is working
um
or and or those were coming from the
fact that there's an immutable the head
part is minimal but either way so that's
very interesting so the question is can
we reproduce the same problem
if we do not allow movement
through the embedded spaces
and unfortunately it's kind of hard to
tell right because we don't know for
sure how to trigger the bug we can only
sit here and do this for a little while
and say okay if it never happens then
maybe that's the case
uh which isn't the best but you know
i'm not sure what else to do
so if that's the case that's good to
know but we still so we kind of shift
our thinking our bug is not um really
allowing us to move through
spaces that's not what the bug was what
the bug actually is is that we can place
the glove
um or place the entity outside of the
cell
that it should have stopped in
so that seems bad
uh
so
maybe what we do is try to hunt that
down
uh because that's a lot more
straightforward we can also assert it
it's something we can assert pretty
easily
we just say look this is the cell that
we said you were supposed to stop in
show me the position that you end up
picking
uh and if that position doesn't uh
truncate to the same cell then that's an
assert
right
so let's just add that assertion and see
if we can get that to fire
um
and then we can maybe look at that a
little more closely i will say that
without that code enabled that allows
you to move out of the embedded spaces
uh you can't seem to get this bug to
trigger so i do think that's what our
problem is
but
again
quote unquote what our problem is
what we really are saying is we do still
have a problem it's just not a problem
of the type we were thinking about right
okay
so i would say
let's try to focus here
on
that like yeah let let's look and see if
we can get
some more insight into
why we will be placing outside now this
part of the routine is pretty janky
uh and it has some to do's on it so we
kind of already knew that it wasn't
great
but it's unclear why it would be that
not great uh because the epsilon here
that's being used is pretty large
i mean considering the values that we're
talking about here are in the tens or
hundreds
and it's point zero zero zero one
i mean it could be that that epsilon is
too small that's not entirely out of the
question
um
but
uh
i don't know um
it does seem a little weird what i will
say is
that
i agree with the to do here that we
should be doing the tests
so that boxes are in a fixed domain
so that we don't have to do this it's
just min
of the box max and so on
but anyway
so looking at that code
i mean i don't see a lot of ways that
that
screws up uh
the way the refinement works
i guess i could believe that
may
it
puts you
past it slightly
because of the lerp
[Music]
again not super compelling
so
i guess i would say
i guess i would say i'm going to start
with
uh the assertion
so
when we
do we've got this
notion
in the earlier part of the code where we
just say okay let's get the index
for some location
what i'd like to do is say after we
refine the voxel placement
um i'd like to do a double check here so
you know
uh i'd like to do a get index where we
say for the grid tell me if this new
placement
um is going to be the same
so i'd basically say like okay
what's the
what's the new p index it's this right
uh and then i'd like to assert that the
new p index
uh is the same
as the best cell index that we said it
had to go in
you know what i mean
um so that way like any time that we
place the glove
in
a cell that isn't the cell it was
supposed to stop in
we will get uh
you know an error
right
um or hopefully
and strangely like that is not happening
anywhere
which doesn't make a lot of sense to me
i mean i suppose one other thing is
ensuring that the best cell i
like that that was actually not
embedding
so another thing we could do here is
assert
corners embedded
of course it starts embedded doesn't it
so
that's kind of an issue it would be nice
if the glove didn't start embedded so
that we could actually use that trigger
um
i mean maybe we can
do that
trying to think of how we fix that
problem
i mean i guess like we just when we
spawn the glove just spawn the glove
over to the side more so it's not
embedded
like
presumably that wouldn't be particularly
difficult
uh
yeah i mean like you know just
like that
okay
so
again kind of tricky because i'm not
sure we we do have the problem of
the hero's head
is gonna create embedding scenarios that
we can't necessarily prevent
and like is that one of them or not
how about
this
when it gets embedded we will set the
capture
so
you know i would say that's again kind
of possibly okay because of that again
the head being where it is um
so you know what's one thing we could do
is we could turn off that head collider
as well or shrink it down so that we
don't have this problem as much
um
[Music]
because again we can that's something we
can adjust later so
you know if we look at this
uh maybe we make that less wide
uh i don't even know why it was that
shape to begin with
but
that way we don't have that problem
right
all right
um so here you can see we do have a case
with embedding there i don't know to
what extent that is
i also don't know why is that updating
because you'd think capture being off
would mean that it's not going to do
anything anymore but you can see that
that slowly kind of updates which is a
little bit weird
uh anyway oh that may be because we're
hopping through the corn yet okay
anyway uh so
we could probably now go back to an
assertion and then start to debug from
there
uh so let's take a look
if we do an assert
uh the corners aren't embedded
when's the first time it fires is it
when we try to go through the wall there
or what happens
so it's when we're i think kind of
forcing like again it's i think it's
just the head collision let's turn that
off
for now
um
entirely
okay cool
so we're actually getting that collide
that like embedding
right
you know
effectively during an actual
uh
so this may actually be the thing that i
was talking about before
wow uh
is it so
what i said originally is i was like
well
when the actual movement of all of these
things
when we hop from one region to the next
region
we re-center what the world is centered
around
you know what i mean
i wonder if that's literally what's
happening if when you slide the forward
it was
actually creating a circumstance where
it puts you into embedding where you
weren't before
because you're just off by a little that
seems so unlikely though in this case
that i'm not really willing to believe
it
right
like that that's just that didn't that
wasn't the case
so all right let's start to look a
little bit more for it let's do
this
let's just
set a little if statement here that will
set saw embedding and then if we do
we'll set the capture
so this way we'll say look
uh we'll we'll capture any time we hit
an embedded case
because we like had one
like right away
yeah so we have one now
right so right there
so for starters
i'm a little confused with
like why is that why does that even
what's that even embedded in
there are no colliders here so how did
that happen
we turned the hero's collision volume
off right i mean it's not
there is no collider on the hero
so how did we end up with these
thinking they were colliding
when they are not like there's no
collision here
right
so it seems like we have
a
bug
with setting corners to colliding that
are not actually colliding with anything
right
so could we investigate that
uh what is going on there so in the
check corners call
we get the cell bounds
and we loop through
the
eight corners of the voxel
we look to see
what the corner index is in each case
and
i guess the cell i that we're passing in
is relative
which is fine it's relative to the mid
quarter which is what you'd expect
the corner code
that we read out
is going to tell us like whether we've
checked it or not
so if the corner code is zero we're
gonna have to do work if it's not we're
just gonna use
that
uh piece of information
that's already stored in the corner
so we look in there and we say okay if
it's zero then we do this test we say
result cell min plus you know
the
i guess you know we should also check to
see uh now that i think about it do we
we clear this
uh properly and all that yeah we we
cleared the voxel stack
here
um looks fine
so i don't see a problem there
so you know we go in here and we say all
right like grab out
the
cell
plus the
uh
corner whichever corner of the cell
we're on right this offsets to the
correct corner
uh and then we then just say like do we
collide there and if we do
uh then set the corner code
uh to two for collision one
uh
for
for not right
i mean it's really pretty
straightforward
at the end we read the uh corner code
out
so
you know either we updated that code
here
or we
are just going to read it from
the array unupdated
use it use it unupdated
we get that corner code out
and
yeah we said we just said it that's it
um
so that's pretty peculiar
i don't know what's causing the
those embed values to come back
the way that they are
um
those are very odd things to have been
triggered as a hit
um i suppose one thing we could do is
verify that it's not some kind of a
reuse problem
uh so we could do something like this
and say all right
make sure everyone recomputes everything
every time
uh and then tell me you know
uh are we still having this problem
and you know
we don't know but we'll try and find out
um
because then it's like well maybe the
problem is that the code that does the
caching is like wrong
so it doesn't look like it because then
it just it just hit that case again
so
it doesn't doesn't seem like that's
plausible
right that doesn't seem
that doesn't seem like the case
but i just wanted to check
because you know
so
uh what are the possible options here
look one possible option is we're
testing in the wrong place
like when we do our collides at p the
test p values that we're using are not
at actually the correct ones
i don't know how plausible that is
because it seems very
coherent in all the other parts when
we're looking at them
so why would it suddenly just be wrong
in just this one case there's not really
a lot going into this particular
equation so it doesn't seem like it's
that likely that the bug would be hiding
there
um
it's possible that the collides at p
code is just buggy
certainly and it's just producing
spurious collisions that don't actually
exist however
um
we don't actually see like what is it
even colliding with so what we might
want to do now is like turn back on
this part of the diagram code to see
what you know
can is there some
explanation
for like who the heck this thing is even
colliding with
right
um so there's a broken case right
and
where we we somehow got placed into
there
and yeah i mean you know maybe now is
the time that we just add the single
stepping because you know this is just a
giant jumble i can't see
but if i could step through it i would
be able to see like why it thinks
there's like colliders like up here when
there's no reason why there would be
right
um it doesn't make sense why there would
be colliders here when
it's clearly going to be high enough off
the ground at that point that it
shouldn't ever collide
um
i suppose there is
one question which is
uh
well we test entities to make sure they
don't collide against themselves so it
can't be something like that
um
right so there's not going to be
anything weird there
but it seems like yeah like the single
stepping is probably what we need to do
so i guess next week what we should do
is add the single stepping
um
add the single stepping
debug why we're getting those
incorrect collider points is basically
how i would classify them like they're
not actually correct
um they're points where you don't
actually collide but it says you do
you know
so fix the incorrect collider point
then
we move to doing embedding
and then we should be good
uh
but i don't want to turn the embedding
on
until i know why it's doing those
because the embedding will just quote
unquote fix this problem it will
allow it to get back out of these
situations where it thinks colliding but
before we do that we
it would be really irresponsible for us
to not find out why it's getting into
that state in places where it really
doesn't seem like it should because
that's probably just a bug and that bug
could lurk there for a while and cause a
lot of problems
so i think we want to do that first
that's the plan
uh okay now let's go do q a
if anyone's got any questions if nobody
has any questions then then we're done
ah okay so george who's who's the author
of remedy bg hello george
uh he says that the reason that the move
entity thing won't set a breakpoint is
because if you load multiple dlls that
have the same function name in them it
won't set the breakpoint on all of them
okay
uh yeah that's intentional in handmade
hero uh because it just helps if you
want to do things like have a constant
string in your code or things like that
um originally in the handmade hero hot
code reloading we didn't we unloaded the
old library and that meant you could
never do things like have a constant
string somewhere
um and we just decided eventually that
it was better to just leave the old code
loaded since hey memory is cheap on a
dev machine just leave the old code
loaded and that way things that point to
old strings can just keep pointing to
old strings and it won't just like crash
right
any other comments
questions or concerns
i suppose in general like
how does that work with overloaded
functions
or george
like if you have an overloaded function
like three different functions called
move entity and you set a breakpoint
like wouldn't that already have to loop
over all of them to set the breakpoint
or does that also not work currently
because in that case fixing that would
fix actually both problems
but i guess they're slightly different
because the overloaded functions will
have different actual link names
so maybe that's a different path but
gotcha yeah and that kind of makes sense
because the overloaded function will
have different link names so you had to
have more code than that like it's
actually it's actually a harder problem
i suppose the overloaded functions the
multiple modules is probably actually
easier you just have to have a loop over
the modules whereas the overloaded
functions you have to like
look at some table to see like all the
things that had this name that got
mapped to something which i assume is
like a debug lookup basically
but
yeah the whole the the argument hash
nonsense yeah
all right well it seems like we don't
really have any questions so that's good
so uh i guess i will wrap it up i think
we know what we're doing pretty clearly
um
so next weekend we're just gonna have to
single step
and figure out how the collision
detector is reporting those problems
that's obviously uh wrong
and i don't think if with we just
improved the debugging tools a little
bit i don't really have to be that hard
to find the reason that we're not
finding it right now is because we can't
see it right
we can't see what's going on
um and so if we can see it i think we
won't have that much trouble figuring
out what it is but until we can actually
see it
we're just kind of flying blind in there
and
you know
randomly guessing about where the code
is
going wrong
uh all right so that's it for today uh
as i said at the beginning for those of
you who came in late uh our kickstarter
for the second book of our graphic
novels up so please check that out when
you get a chance
especially for someone who read book one
um
oh no
subscriber only chat is on still crap
twitch makes this so hard unfortunately
um
[Music]
yeah
unfortunately twitch makes that a global
setting
instead
uh of a
hold on a second
we can fix this
we can fix this uh twitch for some
reason the way twitch works and this
makes no sense at all to me even a
little bit
the setting as to whether subscribers or
non-subscribers can watch the stream so
the ability to to watch the stream
that is set in the stream settings
the ability for people to
chat on the stream
is set in the channel settings
so it's like a global not per stream
now this makes like no sense because
presumably
to the extent that you want to set
either of those you would want to set
both of those in the same place usually
because like if you're doing like a
subscribers only stream and you set it
to only be viewed by subscribers you
would probably also want to set the chat
to only be subscribers because it
doesn't make a lot of sense to allow
people to not watch the stream but to
chat on the stream
it doesn't really make any sense right
um
but
uh
that's just not how they do it
so
i don't know
why that's the case
that's just the case
so let me see if i can set the channel
settings
back
so because i think i did that one time
because i was like god it's really
annoying that people can't watch the
stream but they can chat in stream it
doesn't make any sense this should be
unified and i did it and i forgot i
forgot to switch it back
all right
um
so
hey
did that work
non-subscribers presumably are now able
to chat
in theory
um according to
the world of twitch
so let's try this again
now does anyone have any questions who
couldn't post them before because
the
stream was erroneously set
to
subscribers only
as far as this has been asked a thousand
times with any news on circle galaxy
well yeah there was
and it got sent out so yeah i ranted
about this
at the beginning of the stream so as you
may or may not know if you go to
starcoregalaxy.com
there's a you can sign up for the molly
rocket mailing list here
right
uh
we tried to send one out
and it has information about what we're
doing and like the steps that are going
to be happening to get started galaxy
out
and
it got sent to spam folder by everything
so all the people who
put their
email address in here because they
wanted to find out what's happening star
galaxy i did send out something that
says what's happening with starco galaxy
and nobody got it because google and
microsoft can't program they literally
do not understand how programming works
or what it does
right
uh so
so probably like 20
of the 9 000 people who are signed up
for our mailing list got it
and the other 80
it's either in your spam folder or if
it's microsoft you just didn't get it at
all they just outright rejected it
completely if you look at the record
they were like no that's definitely spam
we're not accepting it
so
um
starco galaxy doesn't have a subscriber
limit it's if you put your if you put
your email address in here you will get
the we only send out a mail every once
in a while apparently
yeah if you have hotmail or outlook they
just refuse our mailing list entirely
they refuse to accept it
they hard bounced it they said no
so 394 people i think it was it wasn't
very many because most people who
subscribed to the mailing list aren't
on hotmail or uh whatever but they just
microsoft just flat out
denied delivery
i can't really tell you just how angry i
am with microsoft and their level of
absolute garbage programming it's so
ridiculous like
they have no right to be a software
company at all
like if you can't accept a mailing list
mail to an email address in 2021 you are
just a failure
as a team and you should stop
right
don't ship an email service if you
aren't capable of shipping an email
service
so here's what i'll say
we will try to send out this email again
we are going to do a few things
one of the things is we're going to
switch to a different provider email
backend provider we use it you can't
send emails yourself because if you send
emails yourself they'll definitely
bounce
so the only way you have any chance of
sending an email to a mailing list is
you have to go through a back-end
provider
in 2021
this is a real thing that happens in the
real world because microsoft and google
literally do not know how to program
and their mail spam teams are staffed
entirely with people who have no idea
what they're doing
like even a little bit right
it's a joke
so uh
we're using spark post we'll probably
try to
switch to a different provider
and we'll try sending out another update
we don't know if it'll work
but we'll try we'll see if
it goes to spam less often
uh you're probably never gonna get it
down to zero right
but if we could get it down to like only
ten percent of the people are having go
to spam or whatever then maybe that
would work
um
does live looping still work i think
there's probably i think there's a
little bit of an issue with it um
i'm not sure
because we don't use it very often and i
think there may have been a problem with
one of the things in it uh here's l
yeah
so we've got some kind of an issue with
the way that it is
uh
re re loading the blocks there
so we we busted something
it was working fairly recently but
yeah the some of the architecture stuff
in handmade heroes is really pretty
janky at this point and it's unfortunate
um
it's mostly just that's what happens
when you program one you know hour at a
time it doesn't really
work that well um so we should probably
fix it uh
at some point but it's not a
particularly high priority at the moment
because i can't even think of look even
if we had that it wouldn't really help
with our debuggings for the collision
sector we need something better
uh so
no it's like horrible i need to post
like a very violent rant about this
because
these people have no business calling
their services email gmail and hotmail
are not email
what they are
is a sort of pseudo email service that
sometimes gives you something right
email is when someone sends you an email
from an email account you get the email
that's email
right
if you only get that email fifty percent
of the time you're not running an email
service you're running a joke you should
call it like you know microsoft not mail
right
and maybe like gmail could be renamed
like g-e-e-mail like gee mail that would
be nice to get too bad i don't right
um
it's unacceptable this is a trivial
problem
and they turn it into a hard problem by
refusing to accept
the obvious thing which is that you just
need to put the ability to sign up to
for email addresses into the freaking
program
just make it so that signing up for an
email
list is something you do
on the on the client side
it's so freaking simple
this is just it's a joke these people
have no business running an email
service
they have no business running an email
there should have been a thing in the
spec that basically says
that you're not allowed to call
something in email service if it doesn't
receive email right like there should
have been a thing that makes what
they're doing not actually comply with
email
right
so
you know there there we we kind of
screwed up because we stopped speccing
email before we should have like we
should have specced it
differently
and we should have said like okay here's
how you do guaranteed delivery right and
that sort of thing
uh so internationalizationist the reason
that i don't think it really helps i
mean it might help a little bit but the
reason i don't think it helps is because
we need to step through what happens
on a particular frame
right
so replaying the bug just doesn't help
me i need the diagram system to actually
step me through the steps on a
particular frame so once you have to add
that you're going to you then you have
it right so
recording
[Music]
you know it can maybe help a tiny bit
to like isolate a rarely occurring
collision bug
um but it's really not going to get us
all the way which is why i'm just not
that like it's like i could go fix it
but it's kind of just waste of time at
this point i'd rather do it sometime
that's going to be more important
we don't send out confirmation emails on
subscribe
no we only send them out when we
actually mail
do we expect to finish in 2022 i don't
know we we only do such a small amount
of programming every week on handmade
hero just because i'm way too busy to
really devote more time to it that i
don't know that we would finish in 2022
because that's it's literally 50 hours
that will happen in 2022 right which is
not very much programming time or i
guess maybe 100 hours i don't know
something like that just not very much
so i know maybe but i doubt it
so clay freeman there's no advice you
can really give because we're not
actually getting flag to spam
the decision gets made before they ever
even really look at the email right it's
a it's effectively a 10 out of 10 spam
check filter email like there's nothing
in it
that's suspicious right
um it passes like spam assassin or any
of those things so it's not like any of
that they just decided that we're spam
because like maybe the spark post ip
address we come from is maybe spammy or
maybe it's because we don't send out
enough emails
right
when we were sending one a week
um
you know we
maybe that was just warm so they would
be like oh okay right
wouldn't double opt-in through
confirmation help uh yes so originally
we didn't do that because it's just more
work for the person trying to subscribe
because it's like either they wanted to
subscribe in which case they can just
get it when it comes out or they didn't
want to subscribe and they're going to
get one piece of email they didn't want
either way either the mailing list or
the confirmation mail right and both
they'll have to take the same action
which is to click the unsubscribe link
right
um
but like yeah the double confirmation
would be good
uh because we could put a thing up that
says like all right we're gonna send you
an email
you need to like if you actually want to
get this you're going to have to go mark
it as okay right
um
and so
like
you know
you should make a dmarc record so i'm
curious to know like what is the dmarc
record that we should have i don't
really understand this stuff because i
think it's absolutely ridiculous like
i'll be completely honest i do not
understand
um why most of this stuff exists because
it all seems like total non-solutions
uh
to the problem like they're all just
complete like none of this stuff should
even exist
it's ridiculous because this is not a
hard problem but the people who work on
it are so incompetent that it remains a
hard problem for no reason
right
just fix they've added like 20 things to
the delivery stuff and none of them
fixed the problem just change it so that
you just change it to be a pull system
right
it's not that hard um
but anyway uh yes i can put a i can put
a dmarc record in there uh at the moment
um
i think ours is not
good like it's not
uh
where's the
where's the actual dns this is not
useful
wanted like the whole thing there we go
well that's fine
uh so currently that's what it said
uh
and
you know like i guess one question i
have
uh is
the v equals d mark one p equals reject
s p equals reject add chem equals s aspf
equals s part
so what i don't know is
how do you actually get that to work
when your mail is sent by a third party
like because we have to use spark post
i'd send the mail ourselves but that
would be even more likely to bounce as
far as i know
maybe that's not true like maybe i
should be sending the mail myself but i
kind of thought that the idea was you
had to use a third party
it's spark post
so
i mean they support
you can even get your own ip address
right with them
like
uh
so you know but i don't know
like because this stuff is not something
that i even ever wanted to know i just
want to send a freaking email to a
customer
um
so i'm not sure
what i have to set in here that would
allow spark posts to do it properly
i don't i don't know maybe they have a
page that talks about it
the problem was
dmarc got added after we started our
mailing list so that's the reason why it
was never set up as well
um otherwise i would have went and read
about it at the time but of course the
ad things that make it
i just i can't rant enough at how bad
gmail and
and hotmail are it's just absurd
um
so let's take a look
do they have anything
like yeah i know i i'm just
can you tell me
what you do
so that's not very helpful because it
doesn't really say
much about what kind of support they
have but
but i can check
i don't know that we care because i
don't know that we're going to keep
using spark post
like for starters if they were a good
service they would have warned us about
things like this earlier right
um
and
you know the fact that we're just not
getting good delivery with them and they
didn't even like try to contact us and
tell us to change something or anything
just kind of suggests to me that like
maybe we need to go with somebody who's
a little bit more proactive right
and we had some people uh contact me on
twitter when i was posting about this
and
so we're talking to some other companies
now to see if there's somebody who'd be
willing to like step in and actually
help us actually get this email
delivered properly
uh and if that's the case then we would
just switch away
um from
uh from them right
uh
send grid i'm i don't know that i would
switch to sun grid because i think
sendgrid would be basically the same as
spark post it would basically just be a
giant nameless service and it'd be like
well
uh
you know maybe your emails go through
maybe they don't and they don't really
care super much right because that's
more or less what spark post is
they're basically the same kind of
service right
and so uh there's some other smaller
services like postmark app and sockets
lab and stuff like that
that are more like look we actually sit
there and try to babysit your stuff
and find out like how we make sure it
goes through
um
and
that's more what i would be interested
in
you know what i mean
uh clay freeman unfortunately we're we
don't have anything prepared to send out
today
if you want to just email me
you know my email address is casey
mollyrocket.com right so if you want to
email me assuming gmail doesn't put your
email in the spam folder if you want to
email me i'd be happy to let you know
when we're going to send something out
if you want to look at it
um
[Music]
and and we can see right but
yeah a centroid uh
the spark post doesn't so spark post
like all the stuff just lists us as
being set up
like because we set up spf and dkam or
whatever the hell those other ones are
called um
those are already set up
they don't have anything that says that
our this is why i say like i didn't i
kind of don't really want to use them
anymore because it's like i didn't even
know about dmarc because i don't spend
time reading about this i just expect it
to work because it's email
right but somewhere between 2015 or
whenever we started the mailing list and
now they added dmarc and spark plus
never
really let me know there isn't like a
big red warning sign on the homepage
that says like hey
you need to do more dmarc stuff
i mean they didn't even warn me i had to
have somebody on twitter tell me how to
go look and find out that hotmail hard
rejected all of our mails
i didn't even know they're the homepage
for spark but doesn't even say that you
would think i put up a big red warning
that's like all of your mail to hotmail
did not go through
but they didn't even say anything
right
um
so it's kind of an epic disaster so i do
think we would probably switch away from
spark post because i really just don't
think they're a good service
none of those things are things that
would have happened for an email service
that was good they would have obvious
ways of
sounding the alarm
when
an entire
when your email is rejected by an entire
service provider you would think that
would be a huge red flag that they would
then like look at themselves or contact
you about or at least put an automated
warning on a web page they did none of
those things right
so uh i'm talking to
uh socket labs right now
and i'm gonna talk to postmark app
and we'll see what we can do
right
no spark wasn't so sparkles doesn't know
that gmail put it in the spam filter so
that part they don't know that hotmail
bulk rejected it all they do know
because the way i figured that out was
on someone on twitter told me how to go
into the spark post control panel and
filter by hard bounces so i could see
and it showed the count and it was like
number of heart sent to hotmail
you know
some number number of howard bounces
that number
so so it knew it right
uh so they knew that hotmail flat out
just rejected us without ever even
looking at the mail
uh
per inbox right at the actual ingress it
was just like no we're not accepting
that
so
isn't there an ack in the out box
i i don't know what that means
there's a good chance that your ip is
already blacklisted on google so
changing provider may not help
so it can't really be blacklisted though
because half the people do get it at
gmail
you know
so
it's something else
presumably
like like i don't quite understand how
gmail works
in that some people it goes to spam and
some people it doesn't
the outlook one i understand a little
bit more
right
um
which is that
the
if they just flat out don't trust you or
don't
you know whatever
that makes more sense
uh
but
i did get the mail but didn't get
notification that it came what does that
mean
are the emails properly marked as being
bulk list mail um
i guess i don't know
what kind of mark
would they
have
yes there is a list unsubscribe header
um i don't know about list id
uh
i'd have to look at that
um
so so i don't know
uh anyway all this just reminds me that
this stuff all needs to get burned down
and someone needs to build an actual
ecosystem that actually works
uh this is nuts
it's
anything that microsoft or google are in
charge of just doesn't work
at all right
from the operating system to the email
to the search to anything like these
companies just can't do anything
it's it's mind-bogglingly bad
um
so
you know
at some point this has to get fixed the
solutions are obvious
i mean rss would just solve this problem
if they just integrated that into gmail
that would have been it and you never
would have had this problem ever again
right
um mailing lists would just be things
that were pull which is what they should
have been in the first place
but that's just too much for them
and billions of dollars the r d budget
just could not figure that out they were
like we just don't know how to do that
um
we're just we we have no idea how we
would ever do that we're just not
capable of something like that right
not only that but there's 50 billion
other ways they could have solved this
problem they could have just had it so
that you register your mailing list with
them
and then their users just click i want
to subscribe to this mailing list on
gmail side right
there's so many ways you could solve
this problem if anybody at any of these
companies
thought about it for 10 seconds they
could solve this problem tomorrow and
they just can't handle it right
it's so far outside of their
conceptualization that maybe what they
should do is solve an actual
problem instead of whatever it is they
think they're doing when they go to work
during the day
it's so nuts that this is still a
problem
it's just so simple
um so anyway yeah uh
what can you do
rss would be fine uh it's just that you
don't
really have the option to use it because
nobody has a reader you know what i mean
um
so you might as well not
anyway i'm gonna wind it down this makes
me so angry like i just i'm so angry
with with
those email providers
for we send out something that's
only every is it's only rarely it's
definitely not spam it's something
people signed up for and they just
they're just so freaking irresponsible
it's really
makes me unhappy
um
so anyway uh i'm gonna wrap it up
again if you missed being in the stream
our kickstarter is live now for our
graphic novel it's really really high
quality print stuff
uh i showed it earlier on the stream
i'll show it again
uh but i hope you'll consider backing it
and it does a great job on this thing
uh it looks super cool this was the book
one that we did uh in the previous
kickstarter uh and it's just like it's a
really really good
uh
it's it's just a really really high
quality graph novel i'm i'm a fan
and uh you know uh anna spends all day
drawing this thing
and uh
yeah if you're interested in checking it
out
oh wow i accidentally grabbed a signed
copy okay
um anyway if you're just in checking it
out head over here to kickstarter uh you
can just look for me on the infinite
book 2 on there you can just search for
meow book 2 kickstarter in fact no
matter where you are that'll that'll go
there
um and that will
uh do it for today for me
um i'll be back here next week to do
exactly what i said we were going to do
um oh and frackle mind mike yes there's
a backer here to receive both editions
uh
there's tiers that are just called
bundle and they come with book one and
two
um there's also add-ons
so uh
because kickstarter finally added
you know add-ons onto their system
any tier that you back you can add books
to
like so if you
back a tier and you want to add more
book ones or more book twos to it that's
just an add-on you can just add and
they'll ship in the same box right um so
like if you want to uh
uh buy you know
two book ones and three book twos or
whatever you can just do that uh it's
really easy to customize they didn't
used to be the case kickstarter used to
be actually pretty pretty tough to do
that
um because you had this situation where
uh
they didn't allow add-ons so every every
possible combination that anyone might
want to order you had to support as a
tear or what some people would do is
they'd create like these external sites
you could go to to like add things on to
your backing thing through with
a second system right
so thankfully kickstarter finally like
last year or something added
uh just actually i think i mean this
it was probably 20 20. i don't i don't
remember which year it was might have
been 2021 they added the ability to do
add-ons and so one of the real nice
things
um
that you can do now is
any other stuff you want to add on you
can just add them on and you don't have
to provide like so all these tiers where
it's just like so confusing and you
can't find it so it really simplified
the process and and it's great that they
finally did that because it's way easier
and it's not necessarily as bad for us
because you know uh we're selling more
of a simple thing right it's a graphic
novel
um but even that as you get into a
series like this is a three book series
there's book one there's book two
there'll be a book three by the time you
get to book three that kickstarter it's
like wow it'd be really confusing okay
how many book boos you want how you book
one so we book threes right there'll be
so many tiers
so
one of the things
that it helps for is that
but that's
i think
nothing compared to these people who do
like you know board game kickstarters or
like trading card kickstarters or things
like that
there's probably so many different
things different things that people want
to customize like oh i want like three
booster packs and and and two miniatures
or whatever right like
so we actually had it easy compared to
other people uh and even we found that
that having add-ons was a huge
improvement i think that it's probably a
massive improvement for people doing
like physical like
multi-set things because those were
probably just impossible to do before
right um
and and now you can do them probably
pretty cleanly just by using the add-ons
so that's cool right um
so anyway
uh
i think that's about it i will be back
here next week to do the series of steps
that i said before add single stepping
look at why we're getting the erroneous
um
red
squares
fix that then do the embedding and i
think that is the recipe for finishing
up the collision detector it's looking
good it's just we're still getting a
couple things that suggest me there's
some little bugs looking in there and i
want those out of there but it's looking
good
so i'm happy with it it just needs a
little more it just needs a little more
all right folks i will catch y'all later
uh let me take a look and see
um if there is
a
john blow stream happening
there is not
all right
i will catch y'all later thanks for
joining me
and ranting with me about emails
i will catch you guys later take it easy