hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero show we code a complete game live
on stream last time we
were programming we
determined that in order to actually do
a nice
solve for our uh entity collisions
we actually do need to do
a
wider check
on like a wider voxel check
which
originally i'd considered and i was
seeing whether i could get away without
it but it doesn't really look like you
can
now
i don't know that that necessarily means
that you want to do a full
like
a full gridded check a priori but it
does kind of mean that we probably want
to
uh at least structure the collision
check to be more like the one in the
witness where we where we look at the
region first to see
uh
like what the voxel span is and then we
do checks on we remember
which vertices we have checked and check
new vertices as we need to in order to
figure out where
we're actually going to move through
um this solver is a lot easier than the
witness because it's just an open space
free 3d solver
um
the the witness has a really
uh the witness is the very hardest
version of the collision problem because
uh it
has the the
it it isn't
a
game where you move through 3d space and
are stopped by objects
it's that can happen but the primary
thing that happens in the witness
is that
the area you are allowed to walk is
actually the thing that the artist is
telling you
so first you have to solve to figure out
where the walkable surface actually is
and then you solve for any collisions
which is a totally different problem and
much harder
in our case we don't have that we are
just doing solves for things that are
saying
i want to move through 3d space
along this vector there's no need to
solve for any movable area or anything
like that because it's not something
that's specified
instead the only thing that's specified
is
where you like things that will stop you
from doing that motion
so that's all we have to worry about
which is definitely easier
so
this should be pretty easy
um
it's just a question of
writing the routine in a sensitive
enough way
that we aren't spending too much of our
time
testing points that we don't need to
test or storing too much information and
using more memory than we should and
things like that
uh but
you know on the on the whole it's
definitely an easier problem
so i'm going to go ahead and open up the
editor here i guess i'll just type cmd
there
and let's go ahead and
do a build
so
uh where we left off was we had been
drawing some stuff and
the drawing was so that we could
investigate our routine better and and
we kind of now we did investigating
better and we can sort of see what's
happening wrong here
uh and
what we determine the reason that you
know the thing that motivates this
particular uh change
is that you can see that like we never
really test these outside points
so we never learned that we could have
placed the sphere here and the reason
for that is that we weren't actually
we
we only use things from our side to
determine whether we could have gone
into there it's not like we we use the
the cube we're moving from
uh to determine whether we could have
gone in here or not and so for example
the fact that we could have moved into
this cell and then into this cell
and gotten closer
is never identified correctly by this
routine because the routine only looks
to see whether or not you could have
cleanly moved out of a cell directly
into another cell that is closer
and so that doesn't really help because
in cases where you're trying to move
around the edge of something which is
what's happening here
it will never correctly detect that you
that l shape that it could have moved
through
and so the solution to that problem uh
with this kind of a solver
is that we would need to check these
independently as a search
where we don't require intermediate
cells of the search to always be closer
right
so
you can think of this as being sort of
in the family
right now of like a star
without the ability
to
i mean it's not really in the family
based art so
there's lots of different things for you
know like for shortest path solving and
that sort of stuff you could think of
something like dijkstra's algorithm
and those are always guaranteed to get
the correct answer because they check
everything
right
then there's something like a star which
says look we're still going to check
everything but we're just going to
prioritize checking things that are
closer than where we already are so
because we'll find the path faster that
way right
you can think about this as the a star
without the actual prioritization and
rather we only check the things that get
closer
and while that oftentimes will find the
correct path it only finds the correct
path if you didn't have to go through
something further than where you are
first in order to get there
um so it's kind of like a star without
the backtracking and without the
backtracking a star won't find paths
sometimes that's just that's why there
is backtracking
in an algorithm like a star
so
what we need to do here is turn this
into more of a proper a star
style
search obviously this is not a star but
it's similar
um we need to turn this into a similar
kind of algorithm where we are checking
these nodes regardless of whether the
node actually gets you closer or further
we check them in a certain locus to
determine whether or not
you can get further than where you are
at the moment
and what we want to do is
if we do want to use a criteria such as
we check cells that are get you closer
to your target
if we do want to employ that criteria
that a criteria has to be employed as an
optimization so it doesn't have to
happen it's just optional that it
happens so that we are speeding up the
algorithm with that but not requiring
that that be true of the final path so
that we can still find the
paths around complex shapes like this
where there's like an l or something and
we want it to smoothly find
the route around it
so
what we need to do for that
if we go to the move entity function the
way you can see that it's working
currently is it just checks one voxel
cell at a time uh inside a loop and what
it does is it exits the loop when it
determines that it's tried where it
needs to go
um and we tried some like stuff in here
where it would look occasionally to go
to other places it this was all just you
know us trying to figure out if we could
get sort of a descent
a a direct descent kind of approach to
work
and i'm pretty convinced at this point
that it sort of doesn't
uh and so i want to switch to more of of
just the open field search uh and you
know i guess we'll start out with the
very slow version of this
first and then we'll
go you know we'll uh
we'll start with the very slow version
and then we'll see what kind of
optimizations we want to put on top of
it
now it may be the case that we don't
ever really care too much about
optimizations
because remember right now our routine
is extremely slow
for the reason that when it has to
actually test a collision it doesn't
have a spatial partition with which to
do that once you add the spatial
partition the checks will become
about eight thousand times faster right
um because rather than checking eight
thousand entities it's gonna check like
three right uh so not eight thousand
times faster two thousand times faster
so
uh
when you figure that into it
it may be the case that we don't care
that much but for large motion steps to
the i don't know how fast the fastest
things will be allowed to move in this
game
but for
larger steps it may still be the case
that you don't really want to check
uh all the voxels
you want to be more
judicious about
how you
you know process them or whatever it is
you're doing right
so i do think we need to be sort of
aware of that and we'll have to think
about how we want this to work uh
a little bit you know
more carefully as we go but i'm gonna
start with the stupidest possible
version
uh and we'll we'll sort of improve it as
we go
um
so like first of all let's let's
re-enable this part of this routine um
what we're gonna do here is rather than
doing this uh inside the loop we're
going to do it outside the loop
um and we're going to do
some yeah i mean this is going to be
expensive and i'm not going to care at
first right so we're going to do it
uh in the dumb way first and then we're
gonna do it in a smarter way uh after
that
the
diagram test here
uh
this is gonna be a little bit different
so we're gonna move this and i'm going
to put two diagrams in here so we have
one here and one here
something like this
so this way we have a diagram um for the
initial voxel testing
uh and then we have a diagram
for how we move through it and we can
kind of play with those uh separately
so here in the first collision voxel
part of things what i want to do is
again sort of change the notion of how
this is working exactly
you can see here that we have a 2p and a
from p for this vauxhall
uh and the problem that we're going to
have here is we do want to bound this
motion
uh to some kind of a maximum motion so
there's gonna be a little bit of that uh
happening as well
but i'm gonna probably do that in a
different way than
uh
i'm probably gonna do that slightly
differently as you'll see in a second
but the first thing we need to decide
here is what's the maximum
footprint that we're willing to test
uh for these voxels here right and for
starters we don't have to store uh
obviously
a b32 for that we could uh store
just a 8-bit value and so what i may do
here is just say yeah there is going to
be like a boolean for eights
right
um and
the boolean for eights
uh i guess would just yeah we don't
really need
to
do much else there
um would just be so that we don't
use a huge footprint for storing this
information
the voxel dimensions in this case
remember uh we're trying you know
assuming we want to keep this relatively
under control
um how much space do we want to
use for this sort of thing
you know if we were doing some kind of a
of a
you know for you know a 4k
like a thing that takes 4k to remember
stuff
is not a particularly huge deal so if we
wanted to we could do a 16
by 16 by 16
and then we have uh this voxel here that
is
stores its dimension
and this allows us to iterate over these
and uh produce you know useful
information here
we have a couple
things that are
difficult for us to deal with right
i
this
doing this interior part here we
probably want to delay right because we
only want to spend time looking at
voxels that we actually need to look at
um so we want to do something here and
we'll have to figure out uh what it
actually is and you know when i think
about it this b8 might not actually be
what we want we may actually need
something more like a u8 where we do
like
actual testing
um
where we set it to zero and then like
one is you can be there and two is you
can't because we need to know whether
we've tested particular areas or not
right uh so
you know there's that
um
well okay
you know what
let me say that differently
maybe what if we want to preserve this
maybe we don't have to do that maybe we
just do a b8 here for tested
right
um where we say
hey there's this voc this stuff is not
really a vox stem anymore this is just
the the local cell that you're in
um and we just say whether we've tested
this particular cell or not so that we
when we look and say should i move
should i try this
location
um
we just don't try ones we've already
been in
right
that to me seems better
uh because
that way we can preserve things like
testing
um for the field repulsion which we
needed to determine like what direction
uh we were supposed to move in
and we you know without the idea of like
way a way to push you out of things that
are colliding
we would have trouble
uh dealing with times when the game puts
two things in interpenetrating
right um
so i i
i'm just trying to like
figure out how i want to work with that
but that's one
you know that seems like one useful way
so in here where we've got uh
remembrance of the testing i think i'm
gonna change the the sort of meaning of
these
so what i might do here is say look vox
dim is gonna be this other thing that's
like the total dimension that the voxel
takes
uh
and then the individual cell testing
here
uh is just gonna be
you know this
it's it's just one cube always right
um and that way
we kind of don't still have this old
vestigial remain of vox dim
not actually meaning vox dim which is
just kind of something we backed into
because the way we're testing before
so if we have a thinking here where we
define what the voxel dimensions are uh
now we can actually say like okay
there's gonna be like a thing in here
that says
whether or not we've actually tested the
particular voxel
that we're in
and we have like this concept of a
location we
need to track now
uh this stuff in a different way
so you can see here like we've got this
like best min corner a rig corner and we
do like you know um this update best
sort of thing
and that's not i mean the good news is
that's not really gonna be necessary
anymore
because what we can do here is
we know
we know that we're going to be searching
through this
space
uh
and
really what we want to do is you know
the the
the most straightforward way to think
about the algorithm is imagine you test
all the voxels
and you know which of the cells you can
possibly
stay in
right it's any cell that has at least
one corner that's not colliding is a
cell you could stand in
right
well stand move in these things are
floating so they're not even standing
but you get the idea
you start out in one of those cells
and you can move to any cell
that has some common vertex with you
that is not colliding
so you can think of it as like a flood
fill starting from there you move out to
every uh
cell that you touch
adding
it on to the stack every time right
so what we really want to do here is say
okay
after we test
this stuff
um
we probably want to change this uh
we probably want to change the way this
works i'm not sure i'm not even really
sure why we are doing it this way
since this sends all of the occupied's
to false it's always going to not do any
of these so i don't know why these are
not just in the loop
um
i see why because basically all we
wanted to do here was say look proceed
as if you could move through anything
take the best point um but we're gonna
change where you're trying to get to
right
um and that seems
that seems reasonable i guess
uh so anyway
if we take a look at how this is going
right uh
what we want to do here is
move
we want to keep a stack
right and the stack is however
uh
many places we still need to try
so you can think about this as being the
thing that tells us whether or not we
can move into a space or not because
whether or not we've tested it we would
also need a thing that says which voxel
index we're actually looking at
and if you think about how we're going
to address this we probably want to
start thinking of it this way so that we
can just use a single integer to refer
to uh the point that we're actually
using so you know we can just do
something like this um
like uh voxel stack right
and you know however many of these we
want to actually be able to track this
is way more than we actually need uh but
it doesn't really matter
um and then we'll have a box of stack
depth right
and so what we want to do here is take
the initial position that you're in and
we want to push that onto the voxel
stack and then from there we want to
test that one and add the things onto
the stack
uh that are
like neighbors to it right so the first
thing we would do here is we would do
something like voxel stack
voxel stack depth equals
something
right um
we need a way
uh to look like so something like this
right
we have a position in the voxel and we
need to know what its index is
for tracking purposes
so we need to be able to say
uh okay produce a voxel stack value uh
from
you know from some positional value
and
it doesn't really look like
i i don't know that that makes a
tremendous amount of
sense the way i've got it now um
so i'm going to kind of think about this
a slightly different way but you know
there's going to be an initial
voxel position kind of thing right
um
current voxley
we'll do it like that
so we're starting on the stack uh we
pushed one on each time through this
loop
uh
right we're gonna basically say like
okay while the voxel stack that
is not zero
right
uh we're going to pull off one of these
indexes
so we're going to do
a voxel stack depth minus minus
um
and
probably something like this
so we'll pull a voxel index off the
stack we will have to compute it now
from this so this voxel min corner cell
dim thing
the voxelmen corner will have to be
determined from this
so it will basically be
something that looks like this right
like some way to to generate
a minimum corner from an index that we
store on the stack and we could make
this actually just store corners
um
but it would be more and you know maybe
i should do that first i don't know
uh because you know be less error-prone
and then we we convert to
something that generates indexes
separately
um
the problem is you have to go one way or
the other right so i'm not sure that
that really
matters much but
anyway
um so when we come through here i
suppose what we would probably say is
all right when we pull this off
uh
the current voxel index
value would also be an index into the
tested array so in other words you know
and we could
we could double check that um
but basically we would say look if we
have not tested this value
uh then we do whatever it is we're going
to do inside the voxel loop but if not
we just don't
right so we skip
any of these that we've already tested
um
because you know we don't need to test
them
okay so assuming that we haven't tested
it uh then we'll basically say that we
have
uh and then we'll go through and
actually do the testing so we produce
them in corner uh we test for the
occupying
uh whatever right
uh we then go and this stuff uh now
really doesn't have to happen
uh i don't think
so
[Music]
so i
i'm gonna have to think rocket bean
rocket rocket come here what are you
doing over there
what are you doing
we've got an intransigent plus we've got
a transfers and puss
um
all right so anyway uh
when
when we push these on the stack
i have to think it through but i believe
we will be able like i don't actually
think we will need to do any additional
work to
make it track through
the closest starting with the things
that are likely to be closest and ending
with the things that are likely to be
furthest
and i think
so i think the reason for that is that
if you just look at this code right here
um you should be able to just order the
order you push the voxels onto the stack
should just
as long as you do them in the order from
direction we're going to
opposite direction we're going as long
as you push them in that order you'll
automatically check the things that go
in the correct direction first
right
so i don't know that we really need too
much more than that um
but i could be wrong so you know we'll
we'll see
um so we don't really need update best
anymore uh
really all we need to do
is
to to have each of the things so
we still want effectively this
right uh it still is
um
it still is exactly this series of
things
it's just that instead of it being
having a best on here it's really just
going to do pushes onto this stack right
so uh
this is really gonna be like
um
push voxel
check or something right
so really all we're doing here is push
fox will check
on each of these
as we flood fill through the space of
things to look at and we're just going
to let four coder indent this wrong
if it does oh no it indented it
correctly
that was weird
oh wow so basically like if you
if you indent a block for a coder block
indents it correctly but if you
in a line it doesn't hm that's
all
right uh i should update probably to the
latest version of forecoder because my
understanding was that got fixed and i
guess i can see why because it looks
like it wasn't actually broken it's only
when you indent a single line that it
has that problem so it's probably just a
like a
a state bug some or something right
because when you do the block it it
doesn't screw it up
um
so yeah
so when we're doing this kind of flood
fill i think that these checks are
probably not
i i think that these checks are probably
not the kinds of checks exactly that we
want the the reason for that is i think
what we want to do is just use an or
right
so i think we want to do here is say
that look if you want to move from one
cell to the other if any vertex that
they shared wasn't was
um
if any verdict that they shared could
have been moved through then you can
move through it you know what i'm saying
so i think
you know these should really just be
ores like if because that means that
there was a place you could have stood
in between the two cells right so i
think it just means this right this is
what's actually happening here
uh so if you look at how this push voxel
check would work
you can see here that this is moving
through you got one two three four five
six seven
uh this is testing seven of the
neighboring cells of the voxel
and
you know how many should there be
ideally it would be
so there's nine
at the top
nine at the bottom is 18
and then the ones right around it it's
its own self doesn't count
so it's an additional eight so it would
be 26
right
is how many you should be able to move
into
is that right
um so this moves
one two three four five six seven
um
it seems weirdly low
because
so one two three four this is one of
those ones which probably just draw it
out so there's four on the top three on
the bottom is where the seven comes from
um
so you'd add another four
i guess that number checks out yeah okay
i guess that number checks out
um
so yeah so if we look at all of the the
possible motions here and
uh
we
assuming
um
i guess
yeah so
what i'm thinking here is
we probably just want to be able to
check
um so the the tried opposite stuff you
can sort of see us try you know
we're switching to each of we switch
each of these as we go
it's unclear whether we want to support
moving in directions i guess that's all
i'm saying it's unclear that we want to
support moving in directions that are
literally like directly away from where
we're going
that might not be something we actually
want it to do and i don't know
but if you look at how many of these
pushes we're doing here
i'm trying to think if there's any way
to do this in a more efficient way
because you're just gonna end up doing a
lot of unnecessary checking as you step
through here right you you really don't
want to
have to do quite so many checks as you
flood fill
you know what so i think here's the
thing since we are now searching the
space
i guess we don't actually need to do
this
we can literally just check
up down left just the six
main directions
right
yeah
so we can literally just check the six
main directions
because if you can move
if you could move if if you could have
moved through a corner you will now
detect that case by moving first into
what you know by moving around the
corner by cubes because each one of them
is connected by one vertex
so i think that's all we actually need
and that'll be much better
so basically this is all we actually
need just the two versions of this i
should first change that to best it's
actually going to be like something like
stack right
um
so yeah it's really just pushing these
on and in fact we can have the compiler
do this for us hopefully
famous last words
um
by just doing like a negation right i
don't know if it'll actually do this for
us or not but um you know
so hopefully we can get the compiler to
do this
for us
it's always annoying to even have to
think about that
it's yet another reason why like you
should just be able to
have had in c just like
that
and it would just do it
like it's like it's not an option like
you don't get to decide whether you
unroll this loop like you will on you
will unroll the loop
um i think clang has like a directive
for that you could pass but it should
have been in the language
um
so anyway in here where we do these push
checks uh then all we're gonna do is say
uh and in fact
um
i suppose
i could do something like this
i and so that way we can just do like oh
yeah we'll test
you know we'll test the directions that
are but because we want it to kind of be
yes you really want it to be this where
you chest the positive direction first
right
and the negative direction second
like that's really what we want right
um and so
you know uh
in here where we do these sides then
it's just like uh oh well you know what
no we could let's just do this
original way was fine
really we just want this to be
[Music]
i feel like i'm getting too fancy
i was trying to figure out a way to
write that
you know fancier but i think i'm just
not gonna
uh so in here
we
maybe just do something like this
and just look it up directly
and that just seems that just seems more
sane to me
so in here we have like the side z
whatever nonsense so in here we just say
look the side z
equals
side.z or whatever and we just say
either
use it or don't depending on
which one you're doing so if you're on
zero
you use the original if you're on one
you use the negative
and that's all there is
you know
and this is just to get the compiler to
generate these checks for us
and so then we don't
need any of this we just say
okay
if
uh
i suppose this is going to be easier
said than done but yeah because now that
i think about it like we gotta we got a
bit of a brain bender if we want to
actually have the compiler generate this
for us but
um
you know for each of these
we're going to want to negate
uh
yeah okay never mind
like if we were really going to do this
we could actually try to make that
generate out of the iteration but then i
was like ah that's that's a bridge too
far
so what we've actually got is this
uh where we
we want to test each of these
uh where we say okay
you know like
here's our if statement assuming that
this passes does this mean i can get
this indentable yeah that's really weird
okay
um
so here's our
here's our actual uh checks and for each
of these we're just going to do
the
the manual check and
negate each one
and since we're only going to talk about
two of these i don't even know why i'm
bothered with these extra ones because
we can just actually flip them all
because we're multiplying the loop by
three right by having the interior
um so really we just need one like
flip check
[Music]
and we test the negative direction when
we do the flip check
so
uh after testing each of those
we know that we would push this
particular voxel um
you know onto the stack so using code uh
similar to that
and we probably we would also need some
way of preventing uh the stack
from
from growing like
too large
so we would need an assertion
at some point here
that's like hey
right and we need to
do a computation where we determine like
what is the largest
uh
you know what's the what's the largest
that this thing
can practically be so that we make sure
that the stack is large enough to handle
the largest possible search given though
you know it'll be some
proportion
of the total
it would probably be like
16 times 16 times 4 would be my guess
so it'd probably be like 10 24 or
something like that honestly which would
be really bad right which is what you
know maybe this is arguably like too
large
um
and it should be smaller that's totally
uh
that's a totally plausible
um
it might actually be times six too
yeah i mean it's just it's quite large
uh
is the problem but anyway
uh the reason i say that is because in
theory if you're flood filling the space
you know you you're going to you're
never going to actually have to push on
everything that's in the volume but you
would have to push on something
proportional to the total surface area
of the volume right um
and so if you imagine a 16 by 16 by 16
cube
um the total surface area is going to be
16 times 16
roughly times six one for each face and
it's not counting the shared
uh pieces around but you know
so
yeah that's quite a bit
uh which is why maybe this is
a bit much
you know what i'm saying um but again
you know we'll we'll cross that bridge
when we come to it
or or we won't
so when we actually do these tests to
figure out
uh what we're pushing on
then we
why
why is that an illegal size of operand
oh
um
so
[Music]
i think now mostly the problem we have
is we don't have the way to actually
produce these voxel indexes but this is
roughly what the routine would look like
uh each time through
and we need also to produce uh the
closest point
here
for each of these so um
this part is going to be uh an
interesting question depending on
um
how accurate of a guess we want
if we want a extremely accurate guess we
would need to use some kind of a root
find
so we we would call
refine voxel placement
on each
on each cell to see what the closest
point
would be
i don't think we actually want to do
that we probably only want to do refined
voxel placement when we finish
um
so that'll be
you know this
uh
this will be sort of a different
yeah a different point
so we'll probably just call get closest
point um
inbox conservative
right
and
and honestly i'm
so this is not really very good either
um so i don't think this refinement step
would actually work anymore
we would need to have some kind of an
understanding of like where we which
cell we came from
um
in order to do it that way
so how we actually do the refinement
step at the end
is
more of an open question
um
and probably has to take into account
that voxel information so
we're gonna have to do some
we're gonna have to do some fancier
footwork in here for sure
uh yeah so the problem here again yeah
is like
the pushing this stuff on the voxel
um
we need to determine
what these new voxel points are
we probably also need to do
uh some testing here to determine
whether or not we can actually put
anything in here um
because we're gonna have problems of
stepping outside the voxel
so
when we push things in they would have
to get rejected in that way
right um
so
encoding these into a 32-bit number is
pretty trivial i don't know that we
really need to do it i could just use a
v3s to start with and have the x y and z
just stored in there
uh and that might be a better way to go
at first just to make sure we don't add
additional things
meaning something like this
would be a better thing to do
and you know we don't really have
anything like this currently but you
know this is the kind of thing that i
would see doing like a
something like this for because i think
we're just going to have too much stuff
to track here so i'm going to go ahead
and say something like this
and
this way i can
[Music]
use helper functions too
right
and you can create one of these voxel
stacks and
it will
uh you know we can make some helper
functions right
so we can and you know uh this will also
prevent us from pushing things on and
it'll get rid of this basically right so
this call we won't need to do anymore we
can just have the
the thing that does the push does the
check which is better right
so we can do push box stack we
pass in
um
the index
and here we can do a bunch of testing on
the index where we say
for now i guess i can even just do this
where we say
the depth
uh will not get pushed
unless all of the checks passed first
so basically like uh
i don't know if we've got an actual so
we have a voxel grid
you know we could actually just use the
voxel grid that we have
um
so like
this
right
um we could actually do that and the
cell count we would just set to be you
know whatever this is
um
that seems plausible vaguely
yeah
i can see that being a thing
um
so we could do something like that and
then in here we would just say look uh
if it's in the bounds
uh then that's great
um
we also need to assert that we've got
room
because like i said i don't know
and then we will push it
um
so in here we're basically saying all
right we've got this voxel stack uh it's
going to use the voxel grid thing so
that we can use that for testing
uh we will uh
uh check to see whether it's in the in
the grid and then assuming that it's
inbounds that means we can
uh check for tested right
so we can say if we haven't already
pushed this on
right
um and what i might do is change this to
like pushed
so that we just say look as soon as you
push
we remember that
so we will only let you push something
on if that something has never been
pushed on before
so that seems like a good push voxel
stack
right that will work okay
uh and that way we just like throw
things on there and we know that it's
only going to add things that we haven't
tested yet
and that way in here we just do
uh
so so yeah so this
is it's not really negative right
because it's zero or one
so it's it's really just not
right if it was zero it becomes one if
it was one it becomes zero
um
as as we add through here
right
so at some point here we've got
like a current voxel eye
um
and
here we go like
pop voxel stack
right
none of this happens anymore
so
there's going to be the pop box the
stack call and that will get us uh
whatever our you know our
box corner is out of here
and so then in order to push these
it's just going to be like
for each of those sides
um
we should probably push zeon last
as well
uh for each of these sides
we want to push on the
the correct step whichever direction
that is
you know
and it's gonna be like
zero or one has to translate to like
zero to like negative one or one
so when we look at what voxel has to get
pushed on here it's like
you know there's a next voxel eye
right
and it's current voxel eye
but then
whichever one of these we're stepping
along so like in this case x
um
has to be
like
added to by either one or negative one
so if the direction we were going here
uh if it was zero then we need to go
backwards if it was
one we need to go forwards right
what is it booba
oh how you doing
did you need tummy kisses you need tummy
kisses yes you do
because you're a big tiny tiger
you're just a tiny tiger at the end of
the day
the puss arrive
um
why did the twitch track go away
nobody knows
um
this is the puss
uh yes so the reason that sphere
collision geometries help sliding around
corners with search and p is because the
points that will be included in the
movement are different
right
so if you imagine
the corner
if you're in a voxel search and you are
knocking out points
using a radius like a sphere
that's
rounded
the corners will tend to have voxels you
can move around whereas if it's hard
edge they won't
you know what i mean
um
so it re but
in the case of um
where we're searching to uh where we're
switching to the full search and not the
parcel search like we need before
it probably won't matter
um because now we're actually going to
search wide so the search and p should
be able to find
should be able to find that motion
if this if you widen the search space
enough
right
um
and i don't know i don't know what
that'll end up looking like
uh but yeah in theory like in theory we
could turn off spheres
if the search space is wide enough and
it would find it would find it without
you don't need the sphere anymore right
um
it would still it would still find it
the motion would be
like
it would be an l-shaped motion instead
of a curved motion but it would still
find it
okay
so
here's us moving around the vox oops
around the voxel
um
and
i
think
uh that's all we need for that part of
the code
um we need the pop function
um and there's a couple different ways
we could do this uh my guess is it would
maybe
make
um
so
there's one other thing that we need to
do
as an optimization
we don't have to do it yet
um
so there's something that we have to
also take a look at here which is that
at some point
you know you can terminate this routine
because you've searched all of the
places that you could have put
that that could have generated a closer
point
and that's kind of a tough one um
to think through so that's going to be
another thing right because
you know
if you've already tested all of the
space around immediately surrounding the
destination point like where you're
trying to go
um
then you don't really need to
test any more cubes right if you've
already tested all of them and found the
closest point among that set of cubes
and you know you could go there you
don't need to test anything that's like
further away from that anymore because
there's no way to get a better result
so we need to kind of like work through
that part as well but we're you know one
step at a time right
all right so
let's see
okay
so we're going to call this cell i and
we're going to call this depth just so
it's clear what's going on here uh we're
going to push one of these on each time
then we're going to take the cell i here
and do the pop
we're also going to do an assertion
that the stack depth
is greater than zero
and i'm going to have a function
called
uh
not empty
right
uh and that's going to be
this
all right
um
so we can then do our loop our loop is
just while the stack is not empty
and we'll have a push voxel stack here
uh that does a
push onto the stack with the initial vox
lie
um and because we need to do a
conditional push here i'm going to have
like a
condition that you tack on
and so we'll just see like if the
condition is true
that you pass in
um
because you know
uh
well okay so we have the if statement
here yeah maybe this if statement just
goes
on the end
right i think i liked that better
um
well you know but then again
why make it more complicated
since i already did that i guess that's
fine
uh okay
so i think that's everything there
so we push something on to the stack
initially
we
uh we need to compute what that actually
is that's fine we
loop while the stack has something on it
we
pop uh stuff off of the stack to as we
go right
um and
we actually know
now because we have one of these we can
produce the
point for like the center or the minimum
or whatever uh
like cells you know get cell bounds or
whatever
we can produce that
uh
directly so i think we can just do
get cell bounds now
where we do like stack grid
uh and then the index
so i think that just works
right off the bat now because we can
just use that code we already had
um we have a
this stuff is irrelevant now
and we've got some other things we've
got to look at
as we go
and
so yeah like
we have the problem with embedding
and i don't really know what we want to
do about that you can see here we've got
sort of this notion that like if you are
embedded in this particular voxel
um then there's a question of like how
do you get out of it right
and my assumption here is that that sort
of wants to be something that we do
um
like like i'm not sure how the what the
best way is to
to handle embedding in here
you know
um
yeah it's tough call
uh
i'm gonna leave it the way it is now i'm
just not entirely sure like exactly how
uh
yeah how we want to do that uh anyway
so
so really mostly what we're looking at
here
is this
um
the get closest point in box
conservative
i think will just work
so i think this is almost the entire
loop all we really need to do now is
just say all right this is just going to
track the best voxel
um
and then the only thing i'm not clear
about uh because you can see sort of how
this is gonna work right
so we don't
need like
like none of this stuff
is a thing anymore
right like that's not
we don't actually need any of that
um
so that goes away and
we don't need any of this anymore either
so the only question now is
first of all we have to be able to
produce the correct index for the
starting point in the voxel and the
voxel bounds so we got to do that as a
separate thing we'll deal with that in a
second
uh but then we've got this problem of
like okay so
in terms of like
the
in terms of how we like accept motion
here
we need to start off by saying
that there is like a best cell
that we found
and presumably that's like
you know
initialized to like
whatever the starting cell is like the
best cell is just wherever we are right
now if we haven't found anything better
um and then there's probably a best
distance
which is like whatever that
was so
this cell's closest point
like is gonna be the best one
um
actually no you know what i think it's
just gonna be this
so the reason for that is if we start
out embedded we don't want to consider
that to be a legitimate place to put the
player so we're going to ignore that
so then what i'd say is all right we you
know we check this distance squared
right um and this is the best distance
squared probably too
uh we figure out what we think that is
by testing the cell uh against it right
so
the 2p thing like where we're actually
going is probably more like this
um and then
uh we're going to
see how far away we get
when we try to place ourselves inside
this box as close to that point as
possible
what would the closest possible point be
we use that distance squared here which
is only an approximation because we
don't actually know exactly where we
could have placed it
um
and then assuming that this distance is
better
then we would accept that move
so this best cell i here right
best cell i is going to be equal to the
current voxel i
um
probably should just be best cell
okay
so
we step through the cells we ex we try
to track which one of them is going to
be best
so this is how we do that
we test all of the neighboring voxels
by pushing them onto the stack
and we walk the stack as we go
as it is currently this will always test
the entire voxel which will be very slow
but again we're just starting there
the minimum corner
equals best min corner thing is not a
thing anymore
that will come from the stack walk
the best cell we can now do
the get cell bounds call here
so we can just say like the best cell is
uh generated this way and i don't know
what best cell is used for
uh
looks like it's up here
so it's really the starting cell
um
so that that doesn't really make a whole
lot of sense uh there so i'm gonna
actually change the way that works and
just make this be
something that looks like that
yeah
um
so we have a problem here
which is
that
this is not really very good
the reason it's not very good is because
it presupposes that you moved along the
line
from the from
from the starting point to the final
point
and we don't really have any reason to
believe that that's what you actually
did so that line as a probe is not
useful
what would be useful however is not
clear
you kind of need to know
like how you got here
so that that's a tough one
so i'm going to leave it like this
for now
but
so
you know
like i said i i really just don't know
um
if you came in like from the side to
this cell
which is allowed now
putting yourself
at the point where like you would hit
the from the front p might be like
really wrong
you know
um
and so you know we may want to try and
do better than that
hmm
so
yeah
i think we're almost done with this
part
i don't know why this is here
um
all right
so
um this is still like very wasteful
we could cache these checks
um cash these checks
is there
right
i i mean i don't know like if there's a
saying along those lines
um from top gun
maybe
me i
anyone
anyway
so
that all seems fine
uh
so let's work on the startup
so here we go ahead and we produce like
some nonsense
or whatever
uh if you
assume that that's the minimum corner
for this voxel
and we produce the direction
constant
uh then that's really all you need
to
create the voxel stack so
if you then create the voxel stack
um
the grid
which is here
um
we want to make by setting the cell
count and the cell dimension
so we know what the cell dimension is
because it's right here
um
and we know what the cell count is uh
because it's
like
this thing
and so really the question that we then
have is what's the minimum corner now
this is obviously the minimum corner
because it's called minimum corner
but what we'll actually find if we try
to use that is no it's not
what we meant by minimum corner here is
it's the minimum corner of the cell that
you start in
but because we don't actually look and
see which direction you're going it may
actually be that any of these that were
negative would have moved you backward
right
so what we actually need to do here to
produce the minimum corner
is we need to actually like
uh
go in that direction
for as many steps as the voxel goes
and then we bound it there right
so we need to do like a
corner a
corner b
so this is really the voxel starting
corner
is the way to think about it
um
and we then need to add
uh the cell dim
uh times the direction
right
so we know we're gonna start here
and we're gonna go
you know
we're gonna go that many steps at
maximum like 16 steps at maximum
in whatever direction we're trying to go
you know in this solve
right
um
and so after that the voxel min corner
is like the element minimum
do we have an element minimum
i guess we
do or don't
nobody knows
how many min functions do we have
so it's it's just the element minimum of
those two right so it's this
that's the minimum corner
um
because this is the furthest we could go
along the direction
um
is there no how do you
convert this
surely there's a way to convert this
right
it's right there
oh
that was dumb it was already of e3
um
so that should just work
right then we have the question of like
what is the initial cell location but
now that we actually have a voxel grid
um we should be able to just
use the functions there
to get the voxel index
for whatever the placement
of the person is
right
so the initial cell index
is just whatever the
voxel grid now says it is right the
starting location
we can just get
and
use our helper functions for that
okay
so that's compiling now and i think
we're out of time
uh we'll debug it next weekend
but
that's
that's the start of
of the full search routine
and mostly what it will be right now is
very slow
once we get the once we remove the bugs
from it
it'll be very slow because it's going to
test literally
uh
cells
every time
because it never will like early out
right
um
so it's going to test them all even the
ones that are obviously very bad and
could not possibly be helpful
so
that part we have to fix
also we don't need the other thing we
should put here is like
i think the other thing we should do
here is we want to change the voxel to
only be
the size that it actually needs to be to
encompass the size of the move and then
we can clamp that
um
to be less but
you know if it was too big but we don't
want to create things that are larger
for no reason right which is the other
problem we were doing here if that makes
sense
all right let's do some q a
maybe i should actually write that code
in here instead of q a just real quick
because it's not much code
so if you imagine this is the actual
um
[Music]
span
so this is the span that the voxel is
the voxel gonna span the entire thing it
would be this
um
so
if we take the minimum of these two
and then we take the maximum of these
two
uh and then we do
the floor right you can see
uh the voxel starting corner here part
where we do the like floor to get these
to the right um
locations
so in order to find that span you know
it's it's weird that we don't have
this already
you know what i mean
um but
but we don't
um
so that's how how you know much space we
would actually need
um
to encompass uh
well actually you know what i maybe i
don't even really need to do that so
this
uh this right here
would probably be sufficient right
so when we produce this minimum corner
uh
we can also produce the maximum corner
of those two
uh and then we can produce the
total expected span
by taking the difference between those
two
and dividing by the cell dimension right
uh so that's the optimal span
when we then go to make the voxel grid
we can just say
that there is a max voxel span
and
when we then create the actual dim we
can just say that the voxel dim is just
the optimal dim
right
clamped against the maximum dim
that that is that's it
right so we can just say look
whichever one of these is smallest
is the one you use
you know i'm saying
so i think that's right
um
this is a little bit
uh tricky here because
that's good
uh so this is a little bit nasty because
looks like we have floor but not ceiling
right
um
which is weird
but you can see here like we've got this
issue where we're dividing by the cell
dim
um
and we want to make sure that we include
the largest part like the furthest part
so we want a ceiling that
value to get what the actual index would
be there
and
it's not gonna do that right
um
so i don't know i mean it's probably
this
at that point which is not really what
you want to do
um
uh
but
i i mean it seems like that's roughly
what you're gonna have to do
what's the problem here um
v3s
is there no way to like
how do i produce
an actual
dimension value from these
like there has to be
a way to floor this
to
so it looks like this one yeah doesn't
quite so you know we could still use the
other way of doing the minimum
like there's no min for v3s's here
which kind of kind of sucks
because we would like to be able to do
that
maybe we'll do this
which is not great
um but at least its thing
so
don't ask me why
we have two different words for that but
we do
it looks like we used the phrase voxel
dim here
of course that doesn't really matter so
maybe we'll just put that over here
okay
so i think that's all right and again
all right so now i will literally i will
really for reals go to the q a but i
just wanted to throw that in there
because i think we want to do that
um
so that if you're just talking about a
little tiny motion you're not going to
search this large grid for no reason is
also or you're not even going to
initialize it to a large grid for no
reason
seems also good
does your in-house editor cache tokens
for a buffer and keep them around i have
my incremental tokenization for but the
memory overhead
is pretty gross and unnecessary i'm
thinking of just fully caching the
states
like whether you're in a block comment
or not
and then caching only n lines of tokens
with lru eviction or something i have
especially i'm just over complicating
things
pushbox has a typo let me look at that
let me i'll answer that question but
thank you
um
i guess
what i would say about what your
what you're talking about with the
tokens is
what are you trying to do
like it's important to try and think
about what you're actually doing
and what problem you're trying to solve
because the answer to what you do
usually is very dependent on what
problem you're trying to solve
so if you
if you are talking about small files so
like the size of the files that we use
on like handmade hero
then
honestly like just a very fast parser
that you run every time the user hits a
key would be fine
right
and storing a bunch of state
is probably actually going to end up
costing more
than just running it because you know
like if you look
um at the size of the cpp files on here
uh
they're like you know like 64k
is like
the size of a file you know
and so if you're talking about files
that are 64k i mean you just don't you
don't want to do anything incremental
you just want to parse it from start to
finish as fast as you can every time
when the user hits a key you just parse
it again
right
um
so
at some point if you want to handle
large files
there is a crossover where now it
becomes
uh beneficial for you to do caching
where you don't want to re-parse the
entire file
my suspicion
and i could be wrong about this but my
suspicion is that when you want to do
that you probably still want to do
parsing of entire blocks at once with no
caching
and so mostly what you probably want to
do
i think is sort of what you said but i'm
not sure
of exactly what what you meant
but you probably just want to cache okay
what state affects
the
you know
save the parser state at various
sequence points throughout the file
and you just restart from there when you
touch something that's inside the file
right
um in general i would say all of this is
a giant waste of time um
text parsing is dumb
it shouldn't be done anymore if you want
to look at something that's actually
doing things the way it should be done
you probably want to look at something
more like dion
right
that ryan and alan are doing
d parsing text is stupid i don't know
why it's still happening there shouldn't
be such a thing as a text editor anymore
the fact that there is is just a good
example of just exactly how dumb
uh
this entire process is
so
what do you think about using search and
pen games this movement that should feel
physically correct like gravity jumping
etc is there an extension of your work
on the witness that would work well
there or would you go with a classical
approach like gjcare npr
um
so there's really
those are like conflating two separate
things i guess is what i would say
so
search in p doesn't have anything to do
with how you're doing collision
detection
in at all
right
it's how you are using the results of
your collision detection so search and p
can still be used with gjk
right
um
you just use a gjk solver to determine
the
uh to ask the questions
about the placement of your thing so
like even inside the handmade hero one
which is search and b right now you can
see
uh that's exactly how it works
you call a function called collides at p
and this
is
unrelated to the search and p right it's
just a thing that does a collision
detection path you could put gjk right
here
and this
would it would change nothing about the
outer routine right
so
there really isn't a difference between
search and p and search in t in terms of
what collision detectors you might use
to produce
the output
um
so search np just works fine even with
physical
stuff it's fine
um
[Music]
there there really isn't any difference
between the two they're just
search np is more expensive but more
robust
right
um
so it's really more about expense
than it is about
uh
it's more about
surgeon p is more expensive
to be more reliable
it doesn't really change what you can
and can't do
it changes the cost
so search in t is much less expensive
because you're only sampling one route
and the cost
is in robustness because you have no
idea
whether that that path is reversible
it could have just been numerical
luck
that you were able to do it and you will
have no idea if you can do it in reverse
so the player can just get stuck
and and that's it right
um so search and p and search and t
don't have different really don't really
have different
um they aren't
changing what the player could do
there or how you're testing what the
player can do
they just change
how you are looking at the results of
that information and deciding yes or no
you know
and
you can't
i mean maybe if i started working more
on search np and spent another year just
like looking at that as a technique
i would figure out ways of making it
be as cheap or close to as cheap as
search and t and then it's just like
yeah you could always just use it
but really the more important part
of
that
to look at it has nothing to do with
what kind of game you're making or what
you're trying to enable
it's just
cost
so the collision director on the witness
is expensive
you couldn't just
use it
for
a thousand entities
all moving around at once right
so
you have to take that cost into account
and say can we afford it on this
particular game is it important in this
particular game if it's not important
we're just wasting time right
you
yeah so the sandwich maker
like
uh
i would say
if you're trying to open really large
files then you're you're really just
going to have to deal with
um
with caching parser state i mean there
really isn't
so one of the reasons text files there
are so many reasons text files are
stupid and no one should be using them
for anything even though everyone is
using them for everything
one of the reasons is that they're a
giant
dependency chain
they start with the first character
the next character is dependent on that
character and every character thereafter
is dependent on all previous characters
right
it's the dumbest freaking possible thing
you could ever have created and nobody
should ever have used them the only
reason they were used even at the
beginning was because computers were
probably too simple to compliment
contemplate using anything else
they
since like 1990 we should not have been
using text files they are absolutely
stupid
and the fact that we continue to build
the backbone of computing on text files
is absurd
it's absolutely ridiculous
so
i guess i would just say
like
the concept of text files for storing
things that are not a giant series of
linearly
dependent
if you're not storing one giant single
dependency chain in a text file then you
picked the wrong file format period
and that's really the end of it
there's nothing else to say
so people can have fun all day long
creating their new fast text editors or
whatever the heck they're still going to
suck
as long as you're adding a text file
it's going to suck and that's the end
that's beginning middle and end of the
story
all right
oh is john streaming today i think maybe
what we will do is raid john then
let's rage on
low
all right i'm gonna close this out
don't store text
it's not how would one store text it's
don't store text it's not text
right look at this this is not text
these are individual functions they
don't depend on each other right
so don't store them as if they are
as
a text file is a one-dimensional
dependency chain that goes in a
direction right
these two things are completely
independent they should not be stored
as if they are
dependent on each other
this doesn't go after
this
right
it's just dumb
like all of these languages text files
parsers compilers they are all stupid
it's all a bad idea that people keep
doing
for
i don't know what the reason is
i don't know what it is they have no
imagination they haven't thought about
it they are too much of a slave to the
current ecosystem to see what's actually
important
they
don't want to actually do the work of
coming up with a new file format i don't
know i have no idea what it is
right
but like the notion that people
keep using this is just
crazy
no books aren't text either
they're not
like the fact that you
the fact that you can take a book and
open it up to an arbitrary page and
start reading means that it is not a
serial dependency right
nobody forces you to read chapter one of
a book before chapter two
so the concept that you would store it
as just a giant linear dependency chain
doesn't make any sense you would store
it broken down by first chapter then
paragraph then sentence then word then
letter right
so so like
none of this makes sense there's almost
nothing humans have ever created that it
makes sense to store as literally a
sequence of
individual letters
with no idea of how they go together it
is absolutely ridiculous there are no
things i can think of
that we've ever made where that is a
reasonable file format
it makes no sense
right
you would never store anything that way
on purpose
you know not books
not
code
not web pages none of the stuff that we
currently store as text is textual in
that way in the way that we define a
text file format
no compression makes it worse
compression means that now not only do
you not have any idea what any of the
characters are but you can't even ask
what the characters are without knowing
what all the previous characters are so
compressing a text file is like doubling
down on sucking
now you're sucking even harder than you
were sucking previously
the alternative to text is actually
store the thing you're storing
right
so if you're trying to store code store
a thing that's like here is a list of
functions inside each function here is a
list of scopes inside each scope here's
a list of statements
right
like you store the thing in the format
that it actually is
like
think of it this way
nobody stores anything that you actually
need to operate on in this format like
if you go look at like how you know like
pick anything you want
how google stores your email or
something right
they may store the body of the email
text as text because that's what email
was stupidly defined to be
but the actual structure of like what's
in which mailbox and what it is it's a
database right it's a thing that
actually has
like indexes over actual tables that say
what the crap is you know what i'm
saying
so you always have
data should be organized in the
structure that it actually is because
otherwise you get the problems all the
problems that you're currently talking
about which is that in order to display
like there will never be a text file
that can display files quickly
ever in the history of mankind it will
never be written
the reason for that is i can always pick
a problem that makes it basically
impossible okay here's a one terabyte
text file and i would like to see the
syntax highlighted version
of the last line
it's not possible right you would
literally have to load and parse the
entire one terabyte source code file to
determine what the highlighting is on
the last line
it's a stupid idea
right
the actual work necessary to produce the
correct answer there is very simple
because code is actually not that
complicated when you get right down to
it there is probably it was probably the
start of a function just a few lines
before it so you probably only need to
look at a few things to know what the
syntax highlighting would be but you'd
never know that
because that one terabyte text file
could have pound defines in it or who
knows what right all this other stuff
because the way we've defined storing
the code
is just broken
it doesn't map
to the storage format and the thing
don't work together
right
they don't work together
so just stop doing that store code in a
database
and store it based on what it actually
is
yeah i mean an example of an interim
step would be a cc plus file where you
just have functions
are each stored
separately
and that way at least in order to create
a pathological scenario you would have
to create a function that was like a
terabyte long which is absurd because
compiler won't be able to handle it
right
so at that point you're pretty much okay
you know
i mean you should still go further than
that and actually just have the code
saved as an ast because that's what the
parser is actually going to do why
bother having that step
right
so that's all
yeah if you're gonna have things like
pound defines right
then they're going to be in the database
as a specific thing right and they're
going to have like regions to which they
apply
so the way that you would parse code is
you go okay this is the code block that
i'm asked to look at
right
i look up into the pound define table to
see which pound defines are active
within this block
and i apply them
and then i display the text
right
so json is
not great but it's not as bad as like
as like ce or something right because it
doesn't have any ability like you can
syntax highlight json
more easily
um
it's still bad though
like even just knowing whether or not
you're inside
a quote
requires parsing from the beginning of
the file
right
um because it's a parody thing
unless i'm missing something i'm pretty
sure that's right
um
but there's a lot of reasons json's a
bad format i mean
they did some things right and some
things wrong i guess is what i would say
for a text format it's not that bad
but it's still text which is generally
bad
i'm not sure you would need
like specific software though
if we had just moved to asts to begin
with you would probably just have
generic ast editors
where like the definition of a language
is you put in the ast node types
right
and then files are just
are just those
you know what i'm saying
and then you wouldn't even have parsers
anymore
compilers would just take asc files
right
and that'd be that
i should get the new remedy you're right
there's fixes in there that i actually
asked for myself um so i'm looking
forward to it the new remedy is
um
it has a lot of good stuff
so so i wholeheartedly agree i'm on
three five i think there's a three six
that just came out
i want to say
yeah
um so yes i will i will go download it
i'm not logged in to itch on this
machine
um but
yeah 3.6
has a lot of good stuff i haven't
downloaded it yet i need to download it
i need to put it on my work machine as
well
um
uh oh
remedy36 is pretty crashy for you
sandwich maker that's a bad sign
we should report him though because like
i definitely want to be able to use 3.6
so if there's if it's crashy we should
report him
um
right
are there any editors or programming
languages that don't use text and can
highlight gigabyte files currently
well
i don't know that there's any
programming languages that don't use
text
at all
so ignore the gigabyte file part i don't
think there are any
uh
maybe there are
[Music]
but like i don't know
as for editors that can
highlight a gigabyte file
well i guess i don't know what you mean
by gigabyte
but like sure
in terms of if you pick some other kind
if something that actually uses
non-text
i mean you can load multi-gigabyte files
in
zbrush
right
and it just works
um so so i'm not sure what you mean
but
what happened to rad game tools did epic
by the company yes
epic bought them
um as you probably know epic games has
insane amounts of money now because
fortnight is so successful
so they wanted to
well not they wanted to they have been
acquiring
lots of game technology companies you
can go look at all the requests there's
several
and rad was one of the companies they
wanted to acquire for game technology
so along with a bunch of other game
companies
the
game technology companies they were they
are now rolled into epic and you know
their tech is part of unreal engine now
if i still worked at rad would i get a
massive bag of cash um
possibly i don't i don't know i think so
like i mean it probably depends on
you know how long you'd been at rad and
stuff like that i mean i don't i don't
know
i would assume that people got paid out
quite differently depending on you know
what what they were doing
uh for the company but you know
i'm sure you would get you would get a
good payout yeah
it's just like any other acquisition
right i mean you get a bunch of money
for an acquisition usually
especially one of these which is
uh you know they want the developers too
so they're you know they're purdue
presumably
they want to give developers like
payouts from epic that will you know if
they stay for five years they get
money that kind of stuff right because
you don't want everyone to leave
so so usually when you're talking about
acquisitions where you care about the
people who are actually working there
because you want them to come work on
your
tech
uh
you know
i don't know the specifics of the way
the compensation was for this particular
deal and i'm sure i couldn't talk about
it even if i did right
but
they tend to want to pay people out over
a few years
so that they don't leave i mean what you
know you you want them to be encouraged
to like go contribute to epic aft you
know
after they're acquired you don't want
people to just be like i'm out of here
right
um
so
in other acquisitions that may not
necessarily be the case right you can
imagine some cases where you've
got acquisitions where they you know rad
is a small number of very talented
programmers
right
so when you acquire them you want to
bring all of those people on and put
them onto things that are valuable to
you
if you acquire a company it's just kind
of whatever crap
right
um
and and you don't really care that much
then those those payouts are going to be
like more about certain maybe key
individuals but you're not going to go
out of your way to like be paying off
random people
in like the accounting department or
whatever that you don't really care
about you know what i mean
so i think in the case of rad i would
assume that most people depending you
know on how long they've been there
maybe
and how crucial they had been you know
we're probably getting different amounts
of payout but i imagine everyone got
something because
there aren't that many people at rad and
they're all people that presumably you
wanted to keep because they're you know
they were a very select group of
programmers they're not just random
people
and a lot of them are people who you
probably you know would find something
important at on fortnite or unreal
engine or whatever
there'd be stuff that you'd want them to
go do you don't want them to leave and
go somewhere else right
how still platform for svg progressing
um it's pretty good it's harder than
i would like
because
i just after like i had hoped that i
wouldn't have to deal with payment
processing stuff much
but having looked through the payment
processing stuff they are just very
untrustworthy
like
you know stripe
and paypal and such they're just very
untrustworthy companies
they do not provide you with any
guarantees that they will actually
continue to process your payments
and so
it would be a much easier problem if you
could just use a single payment
processor and trust that company but you
really can't
and so
having to do the part where you
assume that at any time
one of your payment processors or a
payment processor
will just cut you off
which as far as i can tell is the only
sane way to do business currently
because these
to say payment processors are the least
trustworthy companies in the world that
i can find like i don't know of any kind
of company short of like drug cartel
that is less trustworthy than payment
processor
it's like drug cartel payment processor
other
right
um and so because of that
you're in this problem of you have a
service you have to rely on
um which is payment processing
and you
then have to
take
what is a real what is a service that
must be reliable
and
write the part of your code that works
with that and the the infrastructure to
assume it is unreliable
so you have to take something that has
to be reliable and write it
based on unreliable services
so it basically introduces an entire
fault tolerant engineering problem
on
that
layer
right
um and so i really just don't know
it's the same story over and over again
right it's a hard problem
for no reason other than
the world is mostly
made up of people who have no idea what
they're doing and don't care
right
like the notion that payment processors
can stop working with you because they
don't like you
or because the government doesn't like
you is so bad for society it's just nuts
right
what john no you can't raid me i'm done
i'm leaving
we were gonna read you
this is not acceptable
oh dude
you guys freaking ask me about the
payment processing thing
and you got me on the stream just long
enough
that john was able to rate us instead of
us rating john i blame all of you for
that
john was just saying on the stream the
other day that he didn't he hasn't done
a lot of modern
uh high thread count
multi-thread programming and this is
what happens
right
this is what happens
when
you
transfer
you now are blocking on a thread that
itself was about to go to sleep
right
look look what you did you've you've
ruined everything
now the entire internet will deadlock
and everyone will have to stop using the
internet
um so anyway i don't really have much
else to say about that other like than
what i said before so the the payment
processing is a huge problem
um
it is it is by far
uh
the
it is by far the most
uh
so let me put it this way
if you want to write your own e-commerce
server and you know
that the payment processor is a
trustworthy company
it is not very hard
like there are
you shouldn't be a novice because
you know well you should never be a
novice if you're writing something real
anyway you should you know get good
first or
whatever but
it's not like a large engineering
problem to write an e-commerce server if
the payment processor is trustworthy
it's fairly straightforward
and
really it depends on the api of the
payment processor that you select how
easy but it might be like embarrassingly
easy
um like it can be like an extremely thin
layer
over the top of the payment processor
uh especially if they were allow like
user
provided data queries of some kind you
can almost just use the payment
processor as the database like there's
really not much to do if the payment
processor is reliable
if
if the payment processor is unreliable
which is
is true so currently there are no
reliable payment processors as far as i
know so
if you
assume that the payment processor is
unreliable now
you're basically writing a complete
fault tolerant distributed system
so you've gone from easy problem to
you know serious engineering problem
and that is just like
that's
it's that literally that difference
so if there was a reliable payment
processor who you could actually count
on you would you would have a very easy
time that that doesn't exist so now
you're
you know
you're basically just doing doing the
full work
and that's all there is
how do you test your code against an
unreliable payment processor well i mean
you just have to
uh
so if you assume that payment processors
are unreliable they can go down at any
time they can just cut you off right and
you can lose access to whatever was over
there
what that means is that any time that
something happens with a payment
processor your system has to also know
what the result should have been right
so
you have to know whether someone
previously had paid for something and
was in good standing you need to track
all that yourself
right
um
[Music]
and and you have to track it
in a fault tolerant way like you can't
lose that data right so it has to be
stored redundantly you have to have good
ways of synchronizing it and knowing if
things are out of sync and all that
stuff
um so pretty much
testing against a unreliable payment
processor it's really not so much that
you're testing against an earlier
payment processor so much as you have to
have all of the stuff that the payment
processor could have possibly done
yourself do it yourself and when you
actually go to issue payment processing
requests
you have to just assume that they might
come back that you've been cut off
and you have to switch to a different
one and your system just has to be able
to handle that right at any time
um you have to be able to just assume
that stripes stop processing your
payments so you're gonna have to switch
to paypal now or paypal stop processor
payments you have to switch to fat
merchant or whatever the heck right so
you're just gonna have to assume
right that at any time your payment
processor
may
shut you off
and
you basically need to be your own
payment processor right up to the point
where you actually run the credit card
so that at any time you can just switch
to anybody
and that's a much much harder problem
yeah
um so yeah like cryptocurrency
uh
the problem with cryptocurrency is of
course that it's a it's a catch-22 right
so
cryptocurrency
will be able to get around these
problems
for as long as nobody's using it which
is the current situation right
so if you don't care that you can't
sell to most consumers because most
consumers don't use cryptocurrency
it will work
because it is decentralized and the
government is not involved right
as soon as the market for cryptocurrency
broadens to include
the actual majority of customers
the government will be involved
immediately and it will immediately
change
over the course of a year or two
into the exact same situation you have
right now with all other payment
processors
and
um
it will be identical to mastercard
i don't know why people don't understand
that it's so clear
because
they have an army
what are you gonna do like
i don't know why people think
cryptocurrency solves this problem the
people with the army decide what you can
do with your currency it doesn't matter
who stores it or how centralized it is
the government doesn't have any control
over cash like you hold cash in your
hands it's completely decentralized
right you can go pay for drugs on the
street corner with a wad of cash and the
government doesn't know anything about
that transaction guess what
they deploy literal people in body armor
with guns
to stop you
what is the bitcoin going to do
right they will just come into your
house
and take you it doesn't matter that it
was
cryptocurrency so
it's just it's such a freaking pipe
dream it's just so stupid right like
cryptocurrency solves nothing it is only
able to evade
uh
legal control over its use
while it is unpopular as soon as it
gains enough popularity the laws will be
placed such as to render it
no different than any other currency and
at that point the entire endeavor was a
waste of everyone's time and more
importantly a gigantic waste of actual
energy that we had to actually pay for
by burning coal or something
yeah it's so ridiculous like like
imagine imagine the post-apocalyptic
world
like anyone's going to use
cryptocurrency
where are they even going to get the
electricity to run the gpus
right it doesn't even make sense
crypto is totally useless it it's it is
a
solution to a problem we've never had
and still don't have
right it's it's a literal
it is a solution to a problem that
nobody needed solved
can i make my camera bigger i can except
i was supposed to be done this was not
supposed to be
i was supposed to be done we weren't
supposed to still be talking when i make
the camera bigger it looks like this
oh this was a little too close to the
frame wasn't it there we go
i mean nfts are
i don't i mean they're just a ponzi
scheme there's not much to rant about
there because i don't know that anyone's
been like promising
[Music]
i don't know
an nft is sort of like a certificate of
authenticity you know
um
it matters to people who
are trying to determine whether a
particular item is
is the actual item or not
why we care about those things i don't
know because they only matter to rich
people who want to buy things like art
at an auction there's otherwise no value
to a certificate of authenticity at all
because
if you think about the actual
utilitarian value of any given item
if i think something looks like the mona
lisa to me when i hang it on my wall
that was as good as the actual mona lisa
in practice right
so nfts also solve a problem that no one
has except you might consider them
solving a problem that no one we care
about has which is specifically
extremely rich people
buying
like
art
on the internet
is the only pr like so it solves a
problem that society definitely doesn't
have but that a small niche of people
maybe do i don't know
and yeah demonics i would tend to agree
like i'm not sure that the nft actually
so when i say solves that problem what i
mean is it serves the same purpose as a
certificate of authenticity meaning that
much like a certain authenticity it
could be wrong
you know what i'm saying
like when you get a cervical
authenticity that this is actually the
mona lisa all your really all you know
about it is that some experts who
examined the item believe
that it is the mona lisa you don't
actually know because
you can't actually prove anything about
it right
and nfts are the same way you know that
somebody signed it and you might even
know that the person who claims to have
made the work has signed it and that's
maybe something but you don't know that
the person who claims to make the work
has actually made the work you don't
know whether that key ever got stolen
or forged especially not in the case of
the mona lisa the person's dead
right
so yeah so i i wouldn't say that nfts
can't serve some purpose they just don't
serve a purpose anyone should care about
right
they serve the same purpose as a
certificate of authenticity but a
certificate of authenticity itself is
useless to almost everybody it's only a
very small group of people who will ever
care about that and so much like
cryptocurrency i don't see why anyone
really cares
about it
and the bottom line is that for the
average citizen in an average
situation in society
they care about mass-produced art like
like we care about being able to go and
and watch you know
uh avengers end game or something nobody
nobody asked when they walked into the
theater to see proof that the avengers
end game they were watching was actually
the one that disney made because nobody
would bother to forge it it doesn't even
make sense right
so to the average citizen consuming
something
they almost never care about the
authenticity of that thing because it is
societally verified already right like
like i don't need netflix to prove to me
that the second episode of mine hunter
was signed by david fincher
like i've never asked for that in any
context nor have i ever even thought of
a reason why i would need that
it just doesn't make sense
right
um
so nfts again they're they're they're
not really for anything we care about
um they're they're basically to like
you know to continue propagating a kind
of stupid model which was like niche
singular artworks for rich people who
buy them at auction like i don't know
why we care about that i don't know why
we'll ever care about that i certainly
don't care about it now and i can't
imagine carry on in the future
so nfts
no idea why they're important
jazz rabbit no art has value to the
person who bought it in an open commerce
duplicated setting right when i buy a
painting to hang in my room i shouldn't
care
for the purposes of seeing it in my room
whether it was authentic
because what does that mean
i should just care that it looks nice
above my sofa right
that's what art does this is what i'm
trying to say with like avengers end
game like it wouldn't be a better movie
i mean first of all i didn't like the
movie but let's suppose you cared
it's not a better movie if i know that
i'm seeing the like
first print of it right it's a niche
weird
fetishistic space of overvaluing objects
for some
reason unrelated to the actual act of
looking at them
if i
can't tell by looking at it whether
something is the actual mona lisa or a
forgery of the mona lisa the value is
the same to me
right
period
and we know this is true nobody cares
about these things like
the things that people spend all their
money on like someone's bringing up the
the example of the louvre like no
the amount of money spent at the louvre
compared to the amount of money spent on
avengers endgame is is a joke
right like
the world cares about just regular
consumable art they do not care about
what's hanging in the louvre
like full stop
it's a tourist destination people go
there to have something to do
furthermore if you replaced all of those
paintings with forgeries tomorrow people
would still go there and say the same
thing
they wouldn't even know
they would have no idea
right you replace the mona lisa with a
good forgery tomorrow not a single
person who goes through that gallery
would have any idea you did that
and you know what that's not even
hypothetical i think there's literally
been times when there have been
forgeries hanging in these galleries and
nobody knew
is that true john do they really hang
fake ones a lot of the time so that they
don't get damaged by flash photography
i mean i'm not surprised
because like nobody knows it it's you
can't
not only that but
if you were the kind of person there's
some people who can probably tell
like like like the difference between
the you know the real mona lisa and a
fake there's maybe
you're not allowed to get close enough
to a lot of these images there's like a
little cordon around it you can't even
get that close to it
right so it's not like you're up there
with your face like pressed into the
mona lisa looking at the little like
brushstrokes and going ah
i noticed a difference i think this is
the like that's not how you can't even
like a poster of the mona lisa would
look like the mona lisa from how close
you're allowed to get to this thing
the mona lisa does seem shockingly small
i've never seen it in person but when
you look at like a wider shot of like
the place where it's hanging it is very
tiny
it's not the original piece that's
valuable though it's just the thing that
is
like
in your example
people still buy that game two years
after
and it's just a duplicate it's it's
right it's just a duplicate copy it's
not the original copy
there's like a fetishism around the
original
copy of things you see this even in
cases where they're non-differentiated
the first printing of a book for
collectors is more valuable than the
second printing of a book why there is
no reason it's just arbitrary right
it's like an arbitrary rule people made
up so that they could sell and collect
things for more money
and that's it
it's pure arbitrariness and so that's
what nfts are they're a way to bring
that pure arbitrariness into the digital
age
so and to that extent i have no problem
with them
i think it's stupid just like i think
auctioning off
like those items are stupid
because i don't think it should matter
right
um
but there's nothing more stupid about it
right there's nothing more stupid about
nfts than about us than about wanting
specifically the original mona lisa
instead of another mona lisa even though
you can't tell the difference
right
um
and as for like producing excess co2
that's kind of separate so you can
criticize the implementation of certain
things
and you know that's fine
uh
but
the
the idea if you could solve that problem
produce them with solar energy or
whatever then again they they become the
same as a certificate of authenticity i
don't have a problem with that
but
it does seem
[Music]
it all just still seems like a waste of
time
right
i don't see how nfts
help you support an artist when we
already have ways of doing that right
like we already had kickstarter so
we already we already have patreon we
already have the ability to mass produce
and sell games on like steam like what
is the point of the nft
it seems to me to be trying to overvalue
a work of art
to try and get more money out of it than
its actual societal value produced
right
that's what it seems like
we're not using an nft for creating a
digital use market but digital used
markets are bad
right
the problem with the digital used market
is now that means that the price of the
original games increases
by not having a digital used market it
means that the price of the games
decreases why you have so many games now
that sell for 5.99 9.99 15.99 instead of
right it's because they can't be sold
used
so instead of selling
you know a third the number of copies
because people buy them used you just
sell the actual number of copies and the
price goes down by a third which is
exactly what should happen
right
you
the idea to want to be close to the
actual thing that da vinci touched with
his hands is somewhat relatable not
important for you but it's certainly not
arbitrary it's pretty freaking arbitrary
do would you apply that to all the other
things that da vinci touched
like oh yeah like you know he probably
touched this toilet
handle or this wouldn't be a toilet
handle it would probably i don't even
know if they had
um
functional toilets for davinci so
uh this chamber pot
right
like oh i gotta i gotta touch this
this
you know chamber pot
it's just romanticizing things
arbitrarily it's totally arbitrary
right
like
some of da vinci's dna is in some
descendants somewhere do you go like
touch them do you like touch their face
with your hand
i don't disagree that this exists
right it totally exists it's still
arbitrary
it doesn't serve
an actual purpose
to allocate resources
towards things that people actually use
right
so
that's why i don't see it being
particularly important
if you look like so you look at things
and like the reasons i say avengers
endgame versus nfts
avengers end game is things lots and
lots of people
wanted to go do for some reason
right
um
that means that putting the money
towards that was useful to society
because it actually has
value for a humongous transfer society
like
300 million people
or whoever right
the people who care about a pixelated
whale
being certified as authentic
via nft
is like
three
it's not a good way to allocate money it
does not produce
a lot of value to society
to allocate money towards the pixel
whale
right
and the same is true of certificates of
authenticity it doesn't actually produce
hardly any useful value to society to
know which mona lisa is the actual mona
lisa it doesn't
right
it's a waste
of actual resources to
have these auction houses to have
experts who can identify the actual mona
lisa from the real one if they even can
to have security guards guarding the
mona lisa because it's the actual mona
lisa and not another one and therefore
worth a tremendous amount of money to
have to maintain a museum to keep it
there like
none of that is producing useful value
it's all a waste of time
right
like like there is an actual thing that
we have to do which is to take the money
and spend it on something
and you can either spend it on something
that tons of people actually go to do
and get value from
or you can create an entire arbitrary
useless system that produces nothing
like literally it's actually the
opposite it's a system for preventing
you from producing more monalisas
why
right
that's why i call it arbitrary because
it's like we just made it up
we totally freaking made it up
and it's basically only rich people no
one else is doing this right because
it's not like other people just buy a
print of the mona lisa
and it's worth like 20 bucks
right
so by arbitrary what i mean is that it
doesn't actually use money to create
something anyone wanted
right it's just we created a arbitrary
thing to make money
that doesn't actually produce anything
arbitrary is probably the wrong word
fictional
like fictional value would probably be
the right term
right
so real value
is when you don't need a certificate of
authenticity because the act of using or
experiencing the thing is it's of itself
it is the value
the certificate of authenticity
means that that thing didn't have the
value because the person experiencing it
obviously can't tell otherwise they
wouldn't need the certificate
right so it's completely arbitrary it's
creating
arbitrary value that doesn't actually
exist because no one can actually
determine
the difference
but
we created an arbitrary value there by
just claiming
that there is a difference between
one of the things and all the rest of
the things even though no one can tell
right
that's what i mean by arbitrary but
really maybe i should say is fictional
it's fictional value it's value that
definitely doesn't exist because if you
remove the certificate of varsity no one
would be able to tell right
now there is a difference for example
between a crappy reproduction of the
mona lisa and a good one that's actual
value if someone actually looks the mona
lisa and says oh this one looks much
nicer than this other one it's like a
crappy copy
that's actual value
because someone actually might prefer
one over the other they might pay you
more for the better one right for real
you don't need to convince them of
something like this one's original and
that one isn't
and i don't think it's the right
question to say does art create value
decider or not that's not really what's
important right because if you think
about society and economic systems as
ways of people deciding what has value
to them
right
then this all works just fine
my point is simply saying that if a
certificate of authenticity is what
switches something from being worth
almost nothing to be worthy to be worth
a fortune right
that is a fictional value
because it doesn't actually allocate
money
to any particular place
right it doesn't actually allocate funds
towards doing something useful it
allocates funds towards something
arbitrary
which is a certification system
right
again obviously people do care about
this
how do we know that because they do it
right
so
it's not like i'm saying this doesn't
exist as a system of course it does we
can see that certificate of
authenticities already exist what i'm
saying is it's a useless system it
doesn't allocate money towards actually
ever making anything it allocates money
towards not making something
right and that to me
is a very fictional unproductive way of
structuring anything
right
so i think the question so uh jaz rabbit
your question of what should be the
price of the mona lisa every copy of the
malaysia should be one million or wait
well let me just let's use the first
part someone probably need what should
be the price of alisa
this gets to the actual reason that i'm
talking about this
so in the real world when you ask what
should be the price of the mona lisa
then you get into the problem of like
well okay
you can see why you created authenticity
and all these sorts of things because
it's like we wanted to have a market for
this thing
so that you can pay for it or whatever
right because
in theory
there will always be a difference
between the original mona lisa and a
copy of the mona lisa there is a
difference
right
so
we then get swept up in this whole
discussion about like how do you value
the fact that there is a difference
between these two things and all that
other stuff right
the reason that i brought this up with
nfts is because nfts don't have that
there's literally zero difference
between the original mona lisa and a
copy of the mona lisa in nft land
because it's digital
so that's why they make
this system makes even less sense right
if you will once you start to think
about the fact that there's literally no
difference between those things because
someone could still argue
that even the best forgery of the mona
lisa is somewhat different than the
original
am i right
look maybe we can't really just like
totally reproduce it to within human
perception
you know
with nfts that's totally gone you know
it's exactly the same so now we are
literally just trying to make up a
reason why we can sell this thing for
more
than what it's actually worth in its
duplicated state
and i just don't think that leads to
good outcomes
right
it seems like outcomes should be based
on
allocating money based on the fact that
we know that digital goods are exactly
reproducible
well my assumption is nfts are a bubble
i can't imagine anyone will ever really
cause again when you go to the mona lisa
thing at least the romantic idea
of
the original mona lisa is at least
slightly different than a forgery
that
or like what someone said before like da
vinci's hands touch this
right
those things don't exist at all in the
nft market it's just bits
the the person didn't touch them
right they were just copied inside a
computer there's no romantic notion at
all
it's exactly the same
no one ever touched it right
it's it's the same
so it'd be really hard to sustain that
ruse
everyone knows it everyone knows it's
exactly the same right
yeah you have to but yeah do you think
davinci would would have rage quit
because wacom tablets are so crappy now
also so here's another question
so
assuming that the great masters
all used
an ipad pro
to do their painting
would they all have been arrested by the
fbi
when apple sent their pictures as child
porn to the fbi because they all paint
little naked babies all the time
like if you go look at like the sistine
chapel there's like naked babies
everywhere right
like like 90 of the stuff covering like
all these services are little like
cherubs
that are obviously babies and they're
obviously naked so would apple just flag
all that like
does apple just flag rome
as the fbi
has to go there and arrest everybody
right
they're like rome is under arrest
of course actually as i'm saying that
too like it's the catholic church so
actually if they had sent the fbi there
and arrested everybody they'd probably
just be ahead of the game because that's
what the fbi had to eventually do anyway
so maybe i take that back but point
being
you know
i i i feel like there's there's maybe a
problem there
but but yeah i mean as i said that out
loud i was like wait a minute
actually
you know the sistine chapel is maybe the
one place where if apple had sent them
to arrest everybody they probably would
have just been fine because that's
probably you know
if the value of art is arbitrarily
decided by people why can't originality
be arbitrarily chosen as value it can
and it is
right i mean it has been that's why i
was saying like certificate says the
original mona lisa right it has been
what i'm saying is that it was a bad
idea
right that was a bad arbitrary decision
um because it doesn't actually involve
people paying money towards something
they actually need
right
it's the same problem as a million
dollar car
there really isn't any use for it right
it doesn't really do anything for us
that there are all these people working
on making this
really really expensive car
it doesn't really even lead to new
information in the same way that say the
moon landing did or something like that
right
so you just have to look at how you
allocate money as a society extreme
luxury items tend not to be very useful
to society
they're basically just like a thing for
rich people to do that don't actually
have many that don't actually allocate
the work towards things that are
generally benefit people you know
so like a hundred thousand dollar car
maybe make some sense a million dollar
car now you're up at the place where
it's not about hey this is where we work
on new technology
it's really just about us trying to
figure out ways to make this car be
worth a million dollars for no reason
like gold plating it or
doing weird by hand stitching of all of
the things around it or like just stuff
that is completely useless but just like
we had to come up with ways to make this
car be worth a million dollars right
that's the original mona lisa that's all
this stuff it's ways of coming up with
making things be worth a million dollars
for no reason
just because you know there are people
out there who will pay the million
dollars the sealed mario
cartridge
that was like a 1.5 million dollars
that's like the dumbest thing i've ever
heard right
but that's all these things are they're
just ways of trying to manufacture
value in a place where it doesn't really
need to be and by putting money there
it doesn't disappear right that money
doesn't just go into thin air
that money goes into the infrastructure
necessary to support that
that infrastructure is useless auction
houses are useless
authentic authenticity verification is
useless it doesn't provide any new
things for a society right
so it's just
waste
that's the point where it's creating
nobody else benefits from it it's all of
this infrastructure
all of those people who were doing all
of that stuff
would have been better employed doing
something else
right
so you're right
i mean that's that's economics right
economics is how do you allocate labor
that's what economics is
right
and you look at these things and you say
are nfts a good way to allocate labor
the answer is absolutely not like i defy
anyone to show me
some economic model under which an nft
increases the accuracy of labor
allocation like it just doesn't happen
priceless art is exactly the same way it
does not allocate any useful work
it's all wasted work
yes video games are very productive
right so if all the people who were
curating and verifying priceless art
were making video games that'd be great
because everyone can play those video
games
right the the
billion people in the world who play
video games
are benefited right
by more people making more video games
they have better selection they have
better quality that right
so you said that as a joke but no that's
what i'm saying
making things that other people can use
that the average person can use
that is creating value
spending time doing something that is
literally useless i'm just verifying
this thing
right
nothing came of that that person's labor
disappeared
remove the phrase arbitrary think
permanent
did the labor create something permanent
verifying the authenticity running an
auction sorry it creates nothing
it's completely wasted right
if those people had instead been doing
something that created something for
society that would definitely have been
a win
yeah permanent or consumable right like
something that someone can eat might be
considered fine too right
even pyramids would be better
right because at least it was something
at least it existed
but i agree i don't know that you want
to optimize for building useless
structures it seems similar to nfts
um but at least it's permanent you could
use it for a living space
i mean you could do something with it
eventually at the minute it's just a
tourist trap but
all right i'm tired of talking to me
this stuff is kind of just obvious like
i'm not sure why i'm even talking about
it
like
there are so many things that need doing
um
that i just don't know why you would
spend time creating
things that don't need to be done right
which is basically what we're doing
with both crypto and nfts
it's just things that nobody needed
and you're just creating them for no
reason
and and they don't actually exist right
they're just fictional constructs
and it's like all of that energy all of
the work all of that stuff could have
gone into something else
something that someone could actually
use a video game a you know better web
browser
you know
better chip designs whatever those
people could have been doing
i
it all would have been better than nfts
or crypto right and especially when you
think about the fact that nfts and
crypto are actually they're somewhat
complicated so it's not like these are
completely you know useless employees
who couldn't have done anything else
they're people who probably had some
capabilities
right
um
like like this is work that could have
been allocated better and and i i i
don't know how people are actually
arguing that on the chat if you really
think
that nfts and crypto were like good
allocations of money
um
like or labor is really the thing
because the money is just a proxy right
so if you think there were good
allocations of labor that's what labor
should be spent on
i really don't know what to say
um
but
you
so the anti-bank anti-government
ideological strain of crypto is actually
fine
um the problem is they're not solving
those problems that's really my
complaint with it right like i like the
idea
that you could have like a libertarian
currency because we see so many problems
like things like with payment processors
you know shutting people off and
whatever
um you saw that with with the only fans
thing just recently
um
for example
the problem is
i don't
the cryptocurrency doesn't solve that
problem right the government will still
be able to regulate it any way they want
because they have the army
um and they can just come to your house
and arrest you right
so it doesn't really help and so
really my complaint about crypto is not
that i don't want to solve the same
problems that they claim to be solving
because i would love a solution to that
problem it's more that i don't see how
any of the things they're making
actually solve this problem that's the
problem like if someone could figure out
how to make the
universal distributed governments then
great
what does that even mean that sounds
terrible like mob rule is the only thing
i can think of that sort of is that and
we kind of have that on twitter it's
terrible right
so i don't see
the solution
right um
i don't see the solution
the payment processors aren't the
government though they're a private
institution who don't own a military and
couldn't stop selling crypto uh no they
can right
so um
think of it this way
whoever are the people who are running
the bitcoin mining
they're the new payment processors
they will just be pressured by the
government
in exactly the same way the current
payment processors are and they will
enact the exact same sets of
limitations
for the exact same reasons
it literally solves nothing
midnight son i don't think i know what
the i'm sorry i don't understand the
argument
i don't really think it has anything to
do with the password because a password
is something
that only you know
right
so it's useful in that sense
crypto does not have that property if
you want to conduct a transaction
the transaction has to be able to be
backed up by a court of law and a
government if it doesn't the person can
simply not honor the transaction i go to
the grocery store
and i use my crypto to buy um a
grapefruit and as i walk out of the
store the person says oh you can't have
that you stole that grapefruit
what prevents that from being a real
problem in society is the fact there are
courts they look at evidence
the government has police
they enforce that law and the result of
what happened in that court that's how
society functions crypto doesn't have
any answers for any of those things
that's the problem right
and so
crypto needs that it needs courts
police
law right that is what makes a currency
actually work
not that you can track an integer
tracking an integer doesn't do anything
for you we can track integers with just
a server
right
the problem is what do you have what
happens when people disagree
about whether someone who agreed to do
something for that integer doesn't do it
right
i took two grapefruits but i only paid
for one
eh
well my point is just yeah that in
general broadly speaking the government
has the police power so they're the ones
who can say what will happen and won't
happen and that's pretty much the end of
it
and the reason that payment processors
do what they do is because of the
government regulations payment
processors don't care
right
all right
couldn't decide to decide that we
switched to crypto for our currency and
change lodge accordingly um
so
you could
but if you could do that you don't need
to switch to crypto
like if we just passed a law tomorrow
that said that everyone had to accept
you know
transactions from everybody
that would solve the problem you don't
need the crypto
right so if you have this is why i say
crypto is worthless because if you have
the political will
to create the laws that you actually
wanted you could have created them
without crypto you could have just said
that for dollars
there can be no discrimination in
charges you have to process charges from
anyone for any reason always
right
and number two
you um
what's the other thing that crypto
claims to solve i don't know what they
do
oh and that no one can ask
right
no one no one can ask no one can
subpoena your transaction records
right you pass those two laws you're
done
now you've got everything that
cryptocurrency ever ever promised
right
that's it
yeah and okay so so the non-subpoenaing
part is giving crypto the benefit of the
dart i doubt i do realize that in
actuality i think most cryptocurrencies
yeah they haven't actually solved the
problem of privacy
um
so
but let's suppose someday they did
somehow
so
all right
that's it
this is all very stupid
i'll see you folks next time