hello everybody and welcome to handmade
hero show recorded complete game live
on stream um i just wanted to
do um a little bit of collision
detection work today uh
we more or less i mean yeah you know we
more or less have the design we want
i'm pretty sure i i more or less have
what i want
uh to have happen sketched out here
um but we we kind of uh
of need to
we have to start getting down into the
meticulous details here uh which is
going to be
slow and difficult so you know i have
oops
that's not where i wanted to run that um
so i do apologize uh for that it's just
gonna be
a bit of a slog and the reason that i
say that
is because um we're now at the point
where
there's it's i don't think we've got
much of a
big concept kind of thing to do now uh
we're really just gonna have to start
looking at you know
uh probably
a way to dump diagrams out because we're
gonna like debugging this is not gonna
be really possible to do
by inspection probably
so we're probably gonna have to do
something with diagramming uh unless we
just magically bingo it
early on which which we're probably not
gonna uh
and and then we're gonna have to also
look very carefully
at some you know of of uh
the the specific way that the algorithm
makes movement decisions to make sure
that those
rules actually work uh and are solid in
practice
um so let's go
ahead and do that um some folks are
asking about sarco galaxy by the way on
that let me just quickly say
um star code galaxy here
uh circlecox.com uh if you sign up for
this
um if you put your name in this mailing
list we almost never send out mailings
so the only mailings you'll get are like
when our projects are being announced or
whatever
um so uh yes this is for beginners
uh up through experts the course is
actually designed
to to basically accommodate everybody um
it's a non-linear programming course uh
it's a very very different from anything
that you've seen before i guarantee you
that
um i had originally wanted to kind of
come out this month if i could
but i know it's not going to make it
i've just got too many things to polish
up
uh and videos to finish so uh it's
coming out
pretty soon the early version the early
version
uh is is like
it's basically module based and so the
early version
um is the one that's starting at
nothing uh but it actually also has tons
of stuff for experts in it too
uh and just just to give like a little
bit of a perspective on the way that
works
so if you are if you've never programmed
anything before
or you've never programmed c or anything
like that this starts
from nothing so it's like here's how to
install like a dev environment and
here's how c
works and here's like what an if
statement is has all that stuff in it
so you can start from nothing and go
but if you're an expert so you already
know how to program c
you already know you know you're good at
all that
you can actually also take the beginner
section of the course and the reason for
that is because it's so non-linear
what you do is you go through basically
these challenge doors so so you go
through these areas that are
doing the same things as the beginner
section does but instead
of me teaching you how to do them i
challenge you to
do them in certain ways so like for
example
i might challenge you to do something
that you would normally do in floats in
fixed point
to see if you can do it right and then
i'll challenge like so
so things that i teach you how to do in
the beginner course i then
challenge you to do if you're an expert
so you can still take the beginner
course
and basically challenge yourself to see
if you know all the stuff
as well as you think you do or if it's
like oh geez you know i never thought
about how i would
how would i do this without a function
pointer or how would i do this
without needing to serialize something
or how would it write like
so that i i basically have two
ways to go through it one is for people
who have no idea what they're doing and
the other is for people
who think they should probably know
everything in there and it's sort of
like
uh a ref not normally refresher but more
like a
a way to challenge yourself to see if
you really do know
everything uh or if you know there's
parts that you're missing or
if you're if you've one of the things
that happens to programmers sometimes
maybe you're working at a job where you
just are
it's very monotonous and you haven't
really had a chance to challenge
yourself to do creative programming
things in a while
this just gives you a structure to do
that right and kind of waking those
parts up that
that maybe you knew how to do and and
they've forgotten right
so so that's the idea behind it uh you
can
get it probably you know i'm really
hoping maybe next month if not at the
very least this summer because
you know i it is finishing up i just
have to
um crank through all the stuff that i
think needs to happen
uh in order to really make the initial
one be okay it's it's an ongoing process
so like i said oh that's only the
intersection
so i i'm not requiring the other
sections be
be ready at all uh or polished at all
for the
initial release because they won't be in
there so you know
i i don't have too lofty of a goal for
when i will put out the first
like early access version of the course
uh so that's fine but
but i do want it like especially like
the the front end and everything should
be
you know uh
lined up for it so all right uh anyway
so back to collision detection
so if you take a look in here where
we're doing um move entity
so uh this render group by the way was
here for
doing debug drawing and we may start to
replace that then with some kind of
debug thing where we can stream
stuff out we'll see but if you take a
look at how this thing worked it's a
fairly straightforward routine now
actually uh and let's go ahead through
it because it's not
it's not working yet i mean it it does
something meaning it is like functional
but we only just got it working and we
haven't really
tried to ensure that it's working um the
way we think it is yet
and so if you take a look uh at what it
does when you run it
um is this this may be a debug build
here yeah this is a debug build
uh if you take a look at what happens uh
when you run it it's it's not really
uh let me
get rid of the debug build part
um it's not really working from the
standpoint of like
making sure that the code uh actually
does like robust collision text or
anything but it is working from the
standpoint of its moving things
um and they do kind of collide right you
can see but they they're still
they're like there's some tunneling in
weird ways it's not clear
um like why is that able to go through
there right so so it looks
kind of you know looking to me it
it doesn't look like if i had to guess
it doesn't look like the routine is
actually working properly yet
you know there's there's two stages
right of that sort of thing
there's um there's
does our algorithm work meaning meaning
do we do we do some things that mean
that this like that this algorithm will
just
produce bad results and that could be
but looking at that just roughly it
kind of looks to me like there's just
bugs in it so i don't think we're at the
point yet where we're assessing whether
the algorithm works
i think that all the weird stuff we're
seeing we're probably still at the point
where the code is buggy so we have to
kind of look through
and start doing the debugging work there
before we can start to make assessments
of whether this
actual algorithm design is working as
well as we hope that it will
so that's what we're doing now is trying
to clean
that up oh my goodness
so john blue was almost done i assumed
he would go for a while that's why we
started i
probably should have waited i i
apologize um
we we were we were taking a look at uh
at the stream before
and i i i didn't know uh
that it was going to end soon because i
knew it started at nine and we took a
look we started it around like 11 30 or
something and
and i was just like well it might go for
a while or it'll probably go for a while
right cause i assumed that it would but
but i guess it didn't we should have
waited uh we should have waited
so i apologize for that i hope that you
enjoyed that stream
um uh it sounded cool
i think the notes feature is awesome uh
just inject like
in general i feel like being able to
annotate things that you can then use
in code especially during the
pre-compile phase
well it's not pre-compile and ji is just
compile but like in my world it would be
meta programming right because
you know c and c plus don't have those
features
um so like uh
i feel like markup user specific markup
plus the ability to like act on that
markup is so
like solves so many simple problems that
you have
that become that would have been very
simple
right if you have that but because c
and c don't have that they become very
complicated problems right
you end up writing a bunch of stupid
code for no reason
where just the ability to like mark
something and
then have like an if statement on that
um somewhere in your code
it's like two lines of code total that
completely solve the problem that you
had and instead in c and c
plus plus it's this huge disaster
because now you're like okay
like i need to make up a system now for
dealing with the fact that i've got
these certain things that have to happen
so now i have to like rethink how all
that stuff is happening it's just really
annoying
whereas like all you really want to do
is just like tag one thing
right um so yeah so so
uh you know i think it's a it'll be
exciting to see
what john's gonna do with it sounds like
he wants to do
uh because it already kind of like jay i
started already had
what i'm talking about so you know
talking more about like pushing it
further i thought there's some good
questions like the question about how
you like
where when we had to switch to doing the
stream was i liked that question
that they had about uh somebody asked
like how do you add your notes to
something that you like you didn't write
i thought that was a really good
question it's not something i ever think
about because i tend to always use my
own stuff
but like when you're thinking about in
like the wider world and you imagine
like oh you
you know you're using someone else's
library rather than having to upstream
some patch you know you could put notes
on it if you could put notes on it
remotely like tag someone else's stuff
with a note and then
some systems can just work together by
having those notes kind of basically
pass through you know in a sense it's
just you're adding them and they're
transparent to the library because the
library's not looking for those notes
but then you know um
the whole thing kind of reminds me of
like the good parts of
gnu emax's system that used to actually
work well
which are like the ability for these
like modules that have never
thought about or talk to each other to
put like tags and hooks
on each other's stuff and it like
they're able to accomplish some really
crazy stuff
in ways that you would never be able to
do you know
so anyway um i i i do think that like
that stuff is pretty exciting anyway
back to our story
here um so just to go over how this
collision
collision routine is supposed to work
so we can start debugging it here's
where we're going to
move the entity and what you can see
here is we
first produce kind of the obvious things
that you would think of
we say here's where the entity is and
here's where the entity would go
if there was no collision so we're just
talking about basically the two
end points of the motion line
um where the entity goes from
and to uh and this is the point
so the the actual you know an entity is
a
is a volume right it occupies a certain
amount of space
so when we talk about a line what we
mean here
is that uh in this particular case we're
talking about
just the concept of the entity's
position goes from here to here
and the collision geometry is offset
somewhere from that
and for the purposes of the way we wrote
this routine we don't really care about
that
because we're not doing anything like a
minkowski some style thing here
so we don't really have to think too
hard about what this line means it's
just
this is the representation of the
position of the entity and we know that
the collision
geometry can be represented by
displacement from that
that we know right
um so if we then look at what happens
here
we have a fundamental value that we call
motion displacement size
and this value is just a value that we
are setting up at the outset to tune and
what we what this means is basically
a it's a value that is talking about
how thick do you want
something to be uh that will actually
obstruct motion right so the way that i
tend to like collision detectors is i
usually think of them pretty differently
now
especially after doing work on the
witness actually for those of you who
joined for john blowstream
from doing the the collision code on the
witness
the way i like to think about collision
detectors is not the normal way you
think about
them i tend to think about clitoris in a
different way i think of them
as making a definition of a function
that says
where the player can go and the primary
value that you that you tune
for that is what is the minimum
thickness that an obstruction would have
to be before you would consider it
stopping the player so so
you know basically the the world has a
concept
of what is a a thickness that
that constitutes like a spatially
occupying thing and the reason for that
is that i don't want lots of little
shardy sharp geometries
sticking getting you stuck i don't want
anyone creating a little tiny thin
wall and expecting that to stop anything
right
i want the game to be like okay there's
a certain bulk that's required to stop
the player
and anything smaller than that we just
discard as garbage
bad artifacts of somebody made a bad
collision thing like
that's like get rid of it right and the
reason for that is i don't like the
feel of games where every little crispy
piece of geometry
stops your motion it just doesn't feel
good so it's like no when you're
designing this game
when you put in collision geometry it's
got to be this thickness or
larger if you expect it to stop the
player anything thinner we throw out as
irrelevant
that does not stop the player don't
expect to stop the player or something
like that
so that way sharp edges get kind of
rounded out and it's easier to move
around
right um so
so that means that we take this size
here and we take
uh and we basically construct a little
voxel cell
around the player and what you can see
here
uh my font is so large because of
streaming that it's hard to see like
reasonably sized lines of code even on
one line but you can see here
uh what we do is we take the motion
displacement size
and we use it to floor the uh
place where the player starts and it's
player is the wrong term just entity
here i always say player because i think
of it as moving the player because
that's like
again witness-centric thinking since
these this that's the last time i did a
commercial
collision detection here um but
uh what we're basically doing is saying
produce a voxel cell but
but make sure that the voxel cell is
rooted
in some evenly spaced grid and the
reason for this is we want to get the
same results for movement in an area
that we would get at any time we don't
want the position of the player
to be something that actually changes
how we consider
the rules for motion so we basically put
um we basically put this
so that it's on fixed grid
in the world a fixed grid in the world
at that resolution
so we build a voxel and you can see us
doing it here
right so we build that and the first
thing we ask is
are we colliding right
uh at the position that we are in right
so like are we
inside or outside and i can already see
there's a bug in this routine
like just having walked through it
because we only finished this this this
is wrong
um that is not uh
that is not how you do that so
uh i think we just kind of were throwing
this in there and i probably hadn't like
walked through the whole thing yet and
talked about it so so that's wrong
the reason that this is incorrect is
because in general
you you don't really want to think about
collision
as you're colliding or not colliding
based on a position
if if you think about collision or not
collision as
the location that the entity is in space
then you're kind of going to open
yourself
up to a lot of numerical imprecision
problems
uh or issues that that have to do with
like you move two things
and now like they're sort of
interpenetrating or whatever
so you typically don't want to do that
right what you
or at least i don't like to do it that
way i feel like it's too error-prone
so what we really want here is not
this we actually don't want to ask about
uh the collision of the position entity
what we want to ask
is is this cell inside or outside
so if this cell is inside or outside
that is what we would actually use to
determine whether or not we could place
you in the cell or not
so this may not be a correct line of
code
uh so it depends on how we're going to
use it so let's continue walking through
the routine so
so we may we may need it
we may not um but
but uh you know yeah i can already see
like that that would probably cause a
bug if i if it's usually i think it's
going to be used
you know not right
um so yeah
okay um so then we've got here when
we're going through the cliche we've got
the direction and the side
uh vectors here and these are basically
just tests to determine
like all these are uh our tests to
determine like
when inside the voxel where are we
trying to go
like like what's the movement that we're
trying to do
yeah and so if you take a look at what's
going on in here we've
got our um our voxel that we come up
with now we say
okay you know we we start with a
particular one
that we're going to assume is the best
voxel
location that we can get and you can see
that in order to do the distance squared
we start out by saying well
the distance squared uh that we
consider to be the um
the distance squared that we considered
to be the best
so far is it oh my goodness
say hello puss how you doing
what's going on well surely
we now will be able to do a good job
debugging this collision routine because
the puss has joined us
and when the puss arrive it is good
right
it is a good programming omen um
somebody asked me last night actually uh
when i was playing satisfactory on
stream
uh somebody asked me if to be a good
programmer is it a requirement that you
own a cat
and i said well i think john is a good
programmer and he doesn't own a cat
so i guess not but he does
like cats like he doesn't dislike cats
so it might be that to be a good
programmer you have to at least
like cats i'm not sure it's hard to say
i do think that having a cat will
increase
your skill as a programmer clearly so i
do think that if
john got a cat he would become an
even better programmer uh which
seems unlikely to because he's a very
good programmer but you know
i mean we don't know you don't know how
well john might program
if he had a cat you know
maybe it would be even better so so you
because you never know
what the ceiling is what the ceiling is
for somebody
it's always worth getting a cat to check
right
you could be even better if you had a
puss
uh to help you program so you know that
that's all i'm saying
you know i'm not i'm not saying john
should get a cat i'm just saying if he
got a cat
you know he might he might even surprise
himself you might be like i thought this
was the best i could program and then i
got a cat and like i'm even better now
you know it could happen that's all i'm
saying
that's a good puss that's a good puss
so anyway we need to now the the the
core of this routine it's very simple
routine actually
you know it's maybe not as well designed
as it could be so far
because we're just sort of starting so
we may make some improvements to it but
uh it's still pretty simple even in our
first pass
all we do is we start by saying well
this is the cell that the player
or the entity that we're moving i'm just
gonna say player from now on so i have
to think about it
this is the cell that the player
starts out in uh and then we create
a uh you know a rectangle out of that
just
this is just a convenient bundling by
saying look we're going to track the
minimum corner um
of this thing as vauxhall min corner you
can see it here so we're gonna create
soft bean soft bean
i'm afraid you're gonna start entering
keys baby can you come up can you come
up here
okay there we go there we go
okay okay that's a good puss
all right um so if you if you look at
what happens here we're going to start
with this min
this voxelman corner here and here's the
motion displacement size thing so
this is is doing that uh aligning to the
grid
and then we start with this best cell by
just saying look assume that the best
place to
the best voxel cell to leave the player
in is
whatever the one is that they started on
and the distance that we're going to say
is the best like the closest distance
to the uh to the target
which is 2p right is going to be
whatever the closest point is in the
cell that they start in
right to the the place you're trying to
get to that's the closest distance so
basically initialize by saying
you're in this cell here is the the
closest we could get you
while you're in this cell is this right
uh and then we start the loop we create
the cell that you're in
which at this point you haven't actually
moved so it's just starting
it's creating the exact same cell that
you're already in uh
not it's not hasn't moved yet oh babe
okay okay that's a good puss um
so then it goes ahead and gets the
center of that cell
and why we get the center of that cell i
don't know is that of this digital
remain
yeah it is i was going to say i don't
think that's necessary for the algorithm
so i'm like that's a little bit weird
we get the center of the cell for no
reason just to prove we can
um so then what we do is we have this
uh system here which which oh pus is
moving the mouse
that's the mouse cursor is being moved
by pus now
uh so we go ahead and get the cell and
we look at the corners of the cell to
see
whether the the entity in question could
be placed at the corners of that cell
right
so that's all this is doing it just says
look we're going to look at the eight
corners and we don't do any saving of
that right now like it
we could easily save every time we walk
this voxel
we could easily save uh at least
four well i guess in some cases we can
only save one if we move diagonally
for lateral moves we can save four for
diagonal we can only save one but we can
reuse these points
right um so you know
so anyway uh we do uh
a collision check to see whether you
could place the entity at each of the
corners of the voxel
and that produces an occupy uh
[Music]
an array of occupancy to say what you
could
stand in what you couldn't and what you
can see here
is that what we then do is say if
um you know you
if the player or if the entity could
have been placed
uh in the maximal direction
of movement so meaning
uh if you imagine you know you can see
here this side parameter
looked and said uh for x y and z do we
want to go
in you know to to like to the left or
the right
up or down um forwards or backwards
right
this produces that map this side thing
here
and so this is saying if we could move
diagonally directly where we'd want to
go
we do an update best uh with that
direction
right and that's just the the movement
diagonally
towards where we want to go and then
these
are movements that are lateral like like
only
out of face so this is a movement out of
vertex of the voxel
these are ones out the faces of the
voxel that are coming off that vertex
and if you look at the update best call
what you can see here is it says all
right
uh here is the the actual cell in
question
um
that we would end up in after this move
so if we did the move that we're talking
about here
when we do that move here is
the result right the cell we would be in
and then we just say where would we be
if we did that move
and then tried to get to the target
right
and so that is yeah i mean that's the
that's that's it
nothing else to say um so we do that we
say
that's where we would be we then say oh
is that
better so like is the distance from
where we could place ourselves to where
we're trying to go
is that better or worse than the best
thing we've found
if it's better meaning that the thing
that currently the
the total distance that we were gonna
have before right
um if that's better we accept this as
the new move
right and we also say that you know we
did move so the move equals true
so we go through testing each of these
if we can
move out of a face uh or a vertex
then we do right uh and
we pick the one that will put us closest
to our goal
you know what i'm saying it assuming
that we were able to move
so assuming that something was able to
move we we accept the move
right and off we go
uh so it
it occurs to me that i didn't see
so this doesn't get used
actually um so
we didn't it looks like we didn't finish
because we were gonna use this
and uh i remember that when we were
putting it in there we were like well
we're gonna have to let people get out
of things if they're stuck
so we were gonna use this but then we
didn't um so i guess for now
uh we just turned it off but that's yeah
a bit weird
okay so when we are done
uh we it's basically we couldn't find a
place that would have put us closer
so once we can't do that we then say all
right let's find out
for the cell we're in we're gonna try
and look
along the line uh from
where we are to where we're going and
we're going to see
where uh if we can place the player
anywhere along that line
inside this cell so this is basically
just a refinement step
right um it's just a step that
tries to put the the uh entity that
we're moving
in the correct place inside the voxel
uh to to make the motion appear more
smooth
but it it doesn't contain any logic to
it right
so so technically we could just place it
at the center of the voxel cell and
things shouldn't change and in fact what
i might
argue should happen is for debugging
purposes
let's start without this so i'm going to
turn this off
so we're not going to do that
in fact and let's just do this
and what we're going to do is we're just
going to place entities
at the center of the
we're going to place them at the center
of the cell that they ended up in
right and that's it so we're going to
take refinement
out of the equation because we just want
to see
right so things should move like in
little steps if we did this
in fact the fact that that appears to
have broken
things uh is a good example of why we
should start with this because there
shouldn't be any weird this should not
be
looking like this right um that
that looks messed up so i'm not sure
why that happened oh i guess we hadn't
i guess i wasn't building i thought i
was building a release when did i change
that back to dubai all right never mind
didn't break it um
so if you take a look at at uh how this
is running here right
uh i'm moving around like so um
and everything is moving on the voxel it
it kind of looks smoother than you might
think but you can see
you can see that it's that that they're
snapping
sort of right um although man
it looks almost like too smooth uh
maybe just because that's those voxel
cells are
large i mean you can see it snapping but
it's it's shockingly let me see
yeah it's it's funny how your eye just
like i
think that it's snapping but it's funny
how your eye just
it interpolates it so well that like it
almost
looks it only looks like it snaps at the
end am i wrong
like is it actually not snapping i
should slow the time step down
we had that at one point i don't know i
may have removed it
um i should slow the time step down to c
because it sure looks like
um
uh yeah i don't know what to make of
that
uh it sure looks like it's not um
yeah it looks like we need to put that
back in like just a time
because because you should be able to
see it snapping
you know to to various locations and and
and that's
disturbingly not very snappy
um not a very good way to say that
but oops
i i don't know what to make of that um
again it might just be i'm getting too
old so you know my brain isn't fast
enough
and it like
i don't know um
yeah uh that's a little disturbing
anyway
i'm gonna draw the cell uh
real quick and uh let's
look at push volume outline real quick
and and just say uh okay so there's a
there's a rectangle three the best cell
is the is the thing we wanna draw um
the cell color we don't really have
a concept of here uh because we're
you know we're just placing the player
in this for snapping purposes so
you know this this isn't useful but you
know i'll set it to uh
um maybe a nice yellow
here and this is just me looking to see
so i can i can see what
this was we'll start by just drawing
that and make sure we can see it
which you know i can't really
so again a little weirded out because
that that should be showing up
right um
so i'm not sure what's going on here so
i want to debug this first
because i should be able to see this
pretty clearly and i'm not seeing
anything right
like you can see this this blue part
here
oh there it is so it's actually just
inside the glove
i guess those are smaller so so i guess
that's
why the snapping didn't look uh as much
as i thought
it's just because like where we were
looking at it they're very tiny
so actually that snapping i guess
i guess that's fair that snapping uh
is is so tiny at the scale we were
looking at
um that that we don't care right
um all right so that's fair uh and you
can kind of see
like uh
you can see us passing through stuff
here
right you can see that it hits that and
stops
right um so actually that particular
move
so it actually looks pretty stable there
which is
weird um
and there you can kind of see it get
stuck right
that got stuck underneath something and
can't get out so that's a good bug
right i mean i guess it's not that it
can't get out it's just it kind of gets
stuck
wedged in between things um
so all right so okay we can see that
relatively clearly now
so i'll go ahead and
uh put in a thing here where we just
look at
the uh where we look at the volumes
and maybe what we'll do i'm not sure
what i want to do here
like i said i think we may have to add
something for looking at the
visualization because the steps of this
we'd like to see them
uh and we're not really gonna be able to
see them much right like we're just
gonna see
you know a trail of stuff and and it's
we're not gonna be able to make sense of
it
it's gonna go by too fast right
so you can see like the uh you can see
the
magenta there is is the path in question
so right
and you know so here's what i will say
i don't
oh that's because bestsell isn't updated
here so uh the reason that we're not
seeing it is because we actually want to
use cell because best cell
actually doesn't get updated um it's
just
cell that we use for all this stuff
so that's all right um
all right so looking at it here there we
go so like i say it should like i said
it should look like a trail
and you can see it looks like a trail
now right
um all right so looking at that
um
[Music]
i mean i guess the first yeah i think
we're gonna like i can't see
any uh there's not like weird stuff like
those are the voxels you would expect it
to trace
right like you know i just wanted to
throw that in because i was like well if
we see anything we get a freebie but
i don't see any possibility of us
really um
debugging what's going on with just this
you know
um like you can see that
it's moving it was able to move in there
right um
and i and in theory that should be
totally impossible
right like it should not have been
allowed to move in there because
the voxel you know it looks like it's
testing
the voxel uh so
so i think we just have some core bugs
in here
like this must be just wrong
you know what i'm saying um
so maybe i'll inspect it
uh and see let me just take a look here
and see if there's anything
un unseemly here
so
in the case we want to do a diagonal
move we're looking to see whether
it's not occupied
in the maxwell direction you're going in
the diagonal direction
right side z
y x
and then it's going to update with this
direction now i guess one thing
is if these were wrong uh
so if delta p is less than zero for any
of the components
then we would set the uh direction of
motion here
and and you can see the direction of
motion it's just going to move
you're going to be moving
uh by that direction here so so the
motion that happens
is this that's the cell dim
in that direction right so
if if any of these were wrong like
like if we tested you know the x
but we moved in y or if we tested the
negative x direction but then moved in
the positive x direction
you know things like that could
certainly
create an issue right uh
and so i don't know
so so i this is what i would like to
draw and and to a certain extent we
probably
could draw that test so we could do
um in update best
we could make that um
[Music]
be the thing that draws
so we can see whether or not
you looked in a particular direction
although well you know what that's not
gonna help
us really um although i could
make it do that so so let's actually
change this slightly so
i'm going to do this strictly for
visualization purposes
what i'm going to do here is say okay
there's
like a conditional
called a loud uh and we're just gonna
predicate
the motion the the check on that
so we're not gonna like do and and you
know we could actually have
this b here for now
and again this is not because this is
how you would want to write this code
none of this is this is just so that we
can
have a better understanding of what's
going on
so if we're allowed to do this right
um then we will
consider the move and then what i'm
going to do is i'm going to move
what we put in here and in fact we can
we can
get rid of the knot as well so we can do
this
right so that up here when we do
our test uh we can put like
um occupied so we just pass that
directly
so then we can say look if not occupied
and we can move there right and so
that's
that'll be kind of nice because then why
is this not okay there we go
um so then we can we can pass those
through
and that will allow us to do a thing
that does a simple
uh that does simple drawing of which
ones were considered and which ones
weren't
for coder's indentation is still busted
for some reason
i don't i don't know if if that's ever
gonna get fixed i'm not sure why
like i i it wasn't and then it was
this is the only machine that has a four
coder on it so i don't really know what
happened there
but at some point it would be really
nice if that were fixed
that's what i'm saying um
all right so
building now
uh i think this is now the same routine
effectively
right so we're passing uh the occupied
flag
down to the update best routine and then
uh assuming that it's not occupied and
it's a better move
uh it will do the move and again the
reason for that is that should do
exactly the same thing and it seems like
it's the same kind of bugginess
uh so you know hasn't changed anything
uh the reason is now i can draw this so
now what i can do
is say uh okay like maybe there's
you know a couple tiers of this um
happening uh and then i can do like a
uh you know cell color thing
where we just specify the cell color
uh in a couple different ways and that
way we can draw the cell colors
as they were considered and we can
see what was tested and what was picked
you know uh so we
will pick a cell color here
um we'll say that things that are picked
are green
um things that are considered are like
yellow
uh and things that are uh occupied or
red
and so we should be able to see like
something
here i think oops
um
i guess that's
needs an alpha channel um
so what we want to do uh we just kind of
want
our what is the thing is it what
what are you complaining about
oh it's not complaining about that my
bad
i forgot we have to pass
something that you used to draw um
so
what is this thing called just debug
all right um so now we can see these
hopefully
and like i said i think we're gonna have
to do some like sort of
capture stuff here because i still think
it's probably just gonna go
by too quickly um i i don't think we're
gonna
see anything uh
it's just gonna be like a blur of
colored cubes
and you know uh
like you know right like i can't really
tell what's going on there
you can see what's being considered but
you can't really see
much else um
so yeah like you know you can even see
that there's a flash of red
around those
so it does seem
this is why i say like we kind of need
some capture now it does seem
like something squinky uh is going on
there
so we can kind of tell that we've got
some something buggy there's like
red detection happening around that
collision point but it's not actually
stopping
uh the move from being considered and we
don't really know why
and you know is that because and so now
this is why i say we need some kind of
capture because without it
i'm not sure how we would really see uh
this stuff
uh like what what is actually happening
so i'll do a pass through it now and
then after that i think we just have to
bite the bullet and build some capture
stuff so that we can actually debug this
because i don't think there's really any
other way to do it i certainly don't
know of another way you either get lucky
when you inspect it but
even then you're not sure if it's really
working like capture stuff is kind of
just necessary because
in order to really debug a geometric
routine you just you need to see it
you just need to see it you know so
anyway so one thing that could be wrong
is this could be wrong
right so collides at p could just be
buggy and it's producing
uh completely erroneous values here uh
or the vox alliterator may be busted you
know
there's all that kind of crap could
certainly be happening
um so we can sort of take a look at that
and see
if there's anything weird happening here
this is the routine that's got kind of
the mark for like hey we gotta optimize
this
uh after we're done with the collision
routine this is the thing that you know
iterates over all the entities computers
are so fast nowadays there's nuts that
you can even do this
um so it'll test like all 8 000 entities
or something every
every time every time it checks the
voxel
uh corner and somehow that still runs in
real time
computers are ridiculous um so anyway
uh this is the part that we have to
optimize but all we care about right now
is that it produces a correct result
even though it's slow uh you can see
it's doing rectangles intersect here
it's taking mover and test
the mover rectangle
is the one that we take the collision
volume of the entity we're testing
in this case right and the p value
uh is is where we're trying to place
right which is the min corner plus the
cell dim
offset for whatever uh vox corner we're
on
and we try to produce the corners this
way
so we go ahead and we produce the the
rectangle there
we iterate over everybody else we offset
their collision volumes
by their positions so wherever everyone
else is in the world just stationary
uh and assuming that we find
uh somebody who collides we set the
result to true so that means it is
occupied
right now that looks pretty
straightforward to me
um like it doesn't look like the kind of
thing that would have a ton of bugs in
it
um that doesn't mean it doesn't it just
means it's not something i would flag
for early
uh dissection right so over here
we more or less assume that this true
value is getting set properly
uh during class of p and it's putting it
in z
y x into the uh you know into the
array here that all starts out at false
um i don't know what the point
of this is um
other than i guess this thing needs to
know so this is kind of a waste
we were iterating a rock this is not
even really a vox alliteration anymore
right
it's just doing one cell so it's kind of
stupid to even bother using this
we'll probably just write this out
longhand
but you know it should be fine right i
mean that should produce the desired
result
it should be fine um
we don't really need this anymore i'm
going to pull this out
temporarily so we might use it later
but i just want to simplify it down real
quick
okay so when we
when we produce this you can see we
start off in assuming that we we assume
we can't
move or didn't move we set the best
corner and the original corner both to
voxel min corner
right we are then checking
the side so all of these pointing the
same direction and then we'll do a der
move
if we check z so we check the points of
the z
face either so that's going to be the
top or the bottom face
we will move in that in whatever z
direction we wanted to go
if that face is clear um
same thing with y
right and same thing with x
and i don't see anything fishy there
right
um so it basic you know it's just oring
these together
um so it's basically saying if any of
these were occupied
right uh it doesn't go that direction
if if any of them were occupied which
which is like overly conservative
right it's saying look we're not gonna
allow you to move out of this face
if anybody was blocking the face which
is which is almost
more than we probably wanted to do right
um
so we like we could probably add some
like moving out of edges
code in there right
so it's really weird given the fact that
we're
starting like that seems
kind of odd given that we're
starting from that
that we're having trouble with like
allowing people to move you'd think
you'd have the opposite
like you'd think you'd be having trouble
not moving people
so something's fishy is what i'm trying
to say
um so that's
weird in my opinion
um and i'm trying to even come up with a
argument for why that would be happening
and i don't know what it is
i don't have an argument
for why that would be happening um
so that's weird
that's that's weird um let me take a
look at how this works again so it's
taking the original move corner
and then doing the displacement that's
what you'd expect
uh producing
the noose test cell it's using that cell
to
get how close you could get in the best
case scenario
to where you were trying to go uh it
subtracts
from that and then does the delta p
if it accepts the move it sets the best
min corner to the testament corner
uh and sets the move to true
remembers what distance it was as well
yeah that just seems
that's a real puzzler for me if i'm
honest about it because that seems like
if we were gonna have a bug we would
the first bugs we would see are overly
conservative movement
meaning you can't move into a wall
um or or between two walls or something
where you think you should be able to
and so that is
so that that is bizarre
so by the way js krist there uh you were
saying it looks like the test volume is
so small
it's only colliding at the wall boundary
and when the test cell pushes far enough
into the wall it is no longer tech
collision um
so the reason that that uh
i mean obviously we have a bug so
something's happening but the reason
that that
algorithmically shouldn't happen and
that's the reason why i'm confused about
it
is because the test cells are on a fixed
grid
right so you shouldn't be
able to push the test into the wall
because you never should have gotten
there right
so what we want to see and what we're
not seeing
and this is why i say we need capture so
it's it's
it's a pain so we're gonna have to go
but write a bunch of code
so we're you know we're gonna have to
basically stop what we're doing put in
some
a bunch of code for inspecting this
stuff
um but the reason we need that is
because
there's no if the algorithm were working
as intended
there is no way for it to do what you're
talking about
right yet it obviously is
so the question is how is it able to do
that
given that it shouldn't ever be able to
none of these
because of these tests none of these
once you got to the boundary
none of those should be legal
right so somehow they are so that these
tests are like allowing it to go in
there
and but it shouldn't be able to go in
there right
um
right so the size should it shouldn't
matter
what you set that size to right this
size can be anything you want
it will still never be able to get into
the wall
logically i mean until you set it to
being larger than
the wall size right you would never
actually be able to go through the wall
because you'll always just have
your four points that are on the inside
of the wall
when the cell straddles the wall will
always be
occupied so you can't move in that
direction
right
you know what i'm saying
so uh and uh and mind mark
42 as you can see here you don't need to
do any growing because
uh you've got two collision volumes and
you're testing to see whether the
collision volumes themselves intersect
so you don't need to do any minkowski
operations because you're literally just
testing two rectangles against each
other
right um
so so
so yeah um so i think we're just gonna
have to take a look at what happens
i don't really know uh any other way to
do it uh
and if we look at the uh in-game edit
code
like we've got some random crap here
uh so it's
so so like there's random crap in this
thing
you can see for like this stuff right
um you know what i'm saying and so
we can do uh we can put in
something like maybe f9 or something
might be uh a key we're not using
right now and uh
i think there's f key stuff oh right
this isn't my editor
uh so you can't do that you can do this
yeah maybe no
um
so i don't know how to search this
effectively sorry this
the editor on stream versus editor in
real life is always
tough for me um
we need some way of looking at the f
keys
right uh we just want to go put in
you know an f key that makes sense so so
this code right here
right
um and what we want to do is say in this
code
so how did it not find that
what the heck dude
so was is that is that oh is that
because it's k and eight would have done
okay so it's eight
uh sorry l it's l that does that okay
that's fine
uh right because there it is so anyway
uh if we wanted to put in one of these
things uh so we put in like collision
detection here on nine
um then what we could do is say like all
right
dev mode memory um we've got this little
list here
uh we could just do
collision i don't know what dev mode
dump is
does anyone
all right i guess that's
something i don't think we use that
doesn't know if that's bound to anything
so you can't actually get dev mode dump
i guess it's just in there and you can't
use it
um so if we take a look at the in-game
editor
here what we could do is try to put in a
thing
that will uh that will allow us to do
the uh the editor in here so
so like you know i don't know
um
we can put
dev mode collision and you know
collision editor or something
um and you can see we've got
this i don't
really know i guess this would be the
same
and then we can just look at this camera
editor thing and see what we did here so
it you know
looks sane
so here it is uh we can make buttons
i guess uh and we probably want to
so we probably want to say
um
what on earth is that
what did we were just screwing around to
see if we could plate
and were we just screwing around to see
if we could put in little like
i don't have any any idea what that is
uh all right
so anyway uh if we want to put in a
collision section here we can
do this we could we could just say like
you know
i don't know um
here's the collision recorder um i don't
know
maybe like
like time step
should be in here um so in here i could
do like
world mode like um
time step scale
um and you know something
[Music]
where we could sort of do various scales
i i don't know
um so we'll go ahead and do
do that and and i'll ignore this for now
and we'll just build this and we'll see
what happens um
we need to have that actual scale
so in the world mode code
um let me just zoom down here
um here
we should be using a dt
when we do like collision movement
so when we do
[Music]
our update like this simulates stuff
right you can see the dt
here so i think if we
want to um
[Music]
we should be able to say that there is a
world mode like
time step scale uh
and and it just like multiplies that out
right
now if i run it now what we would expect
to see is
that no one can move right so you can
see it we just stop
we can never get anywhere uh because we
would need to initialize it to zero
when we create the world initially
um and so you know
that's kind of a separate issue so when
we initially create the world mode
um that's gonna be
probably in here right
nope i thought this got fixed
at some point evidently i'm wrong it did
not get fixed
uh so here's us creating the world mode
um so in here i'll just set the time
step scale to one
and now we should just have it operating
normally
right um and uh
you know here's the game running as
normal and then
you know we want to try and get the
looks like f9
that doesn't seem to actually be setting
that mode
did i do something wrong
is the f9 key like not something that
happens in here
so another well you know what i was
thinking um it may not call the editor
for that though
i'm not sure about that part let me take
a look at
dev mode camera just to see
where that's happening
because all that seems sane
ah there we go
so it looks like we cabined off ones
that are supposed to be handed to the
editor
not the greatest way to do that but
that's fine
so still a little weird
probably because i did that
there we go um
so this would let us set you know
extremely slow uh time step
right speed um which is what i wanted
to start with right so at extremely slow
time step
you can see i mean the thing only moves
uh along one one thing
um as it hops along
it's kind of fun uh so we should be able
to like
if we want to zoom in on
on this here
and just see it's checking
so to be completely honest
i don't quite
follow that
um
[Music]
so i think we have a bug even just
before we start
so like that's a configuration of boxes
that you should never
be able to see right because
you should only ever see essentially
like little like
tetrahedral configurations and this
is one that has
yeah like like that's just not correct
so so um it's already broken
even just looking at that i don't know
why i didn't see that originally
but um even just that is wrong we
haven't even captured anything yet and
we're already
seeing a bug so something about this
directional movement
is wrong um meaning it's
not not not even occupied because there
was no colliders
so so just like what are the boxes
that are involved it's picking the wrong
boxes
so so this right the der extra y
jersey der that set was like
wrong unless i'm misinterpreting it
you know what i'm saying it's
somehow picking these in a way that
isn't
what you would expect right or that
isn't what i
expected
oh
no that's not that's not true so all
right so
that's good information i'm i'm pretty
happy to hear that
uh because that means i've got something
to debug right off the bat
but what i do want to do there is i
would like to know
so yeah i'd love to know what
what is producing that configuration so
maybe what i should do is step through
the code there
um try to think if there's anything i
could draw
that would allow me to see who was at
fault there
um so so one thing we could do
is change the color rule
uh and say so like direction gets passed
here
what we could do is say well we don't
care about this right now so let's just
draw the direction
as the color right so then we would be
able to see
like in terms of rg or b who was at
fault
because positive and negative like we
don't want to distinguish the directions
what we really want is that we don't
have an absolute value for vectors do we
um
well we do for okay so we we do for
vectors of cindy
but we don't have um
uh we don't have one for vectors of uh
of regular nature uh okay
so let me do it this way
and we'll do it by hand there we go
um so this is just a way of making sure
that the negatives
become positives so we can just we just
see which axis
each one is uh and so if i go and look
we have to reproduce
that weird configuration but it looks
like we already have it right
so you can see here where we've got
that is the corner move right
that one is the corner move um
and so yeah i don't
i'm not sure how to interpret this at
all now maybe there's
overdraw happening here um
but how could there be overdraw because
your the movement
amount is zero so it should only check
one set like we're not seeing two
iterations
right so if you look here the
white box is the one that's supposedly
would be testing
a lateral movement right i mean
a diagonal movement
blue is testing a z move
right which means that it you know
ostensibly would be this cell here so
that's blue
um okay so
so maybe i panicked for no reason that
actually
i forgot the fact that it's not drawing
the cell that you're in
so there's the cell you're in and it's
producing the tetrahedron shape
correctly
okay so so i'm i'm less nervous i was
super nervous there but i forgot the
fact that we're not drawing the cell
you're in
so if you drew the cell you were in you
would see it right there
yeah okay so that's actually fine
um no need to panic as i had
um here oh this is kind of handy
pun intended so here is the hand
stuck inside this thing right
let's draw the cell we're in so to make
that a little easier on ourselves
and the way i'm going to do this is just
taking the starting best cell so this
thing right here
i'm just going to draw this and i'm
going to draw this in a color um maybe
we'll just do it pure block
so so that's where you're starting
i'm just gonna draw that uh
leaning on the hot code reloading here
to help us out um
so there's our uh there's our movement
you can see uh let me see
if i back up okay so we know that this
is trying to get
over here right
and you can see where it starts and you
can see it trying to
uh like it's testing these cells
and i assume that this this makes
perfect sense of why it's stuck
because this is actually a correct
result since we haven't put in the thing
that allows it to move
out that was what this was going to be
for
so we haven't put in
the detection for the case where you're
inside something trying to get out
so actually that's fine uh to me i think
i don't have any problem with what's
happening there
so uh yeah the question though is again
the same bug must be happening on both
sides
because there's no explanation for how
you would get out of that
um i have no idea it might be that this
guy moved
right um but yeah
so if i look at pushing against that guy
let me hold this down here so you can
kind of see
just trying to see how we get stuck
all right
um excuse me
so um i'm now going to say
i'm going to put this back in
and then i'm going to start doing
recording
all right um so what i'd like to do is
probably like to set up a case where
it's easier to look at this stuff so the
other thing i might do here
is i might go into the world gen code
and just instead of placing
excuse me instead of placing the
uh player in the dungeon there which is
what's happening
i might place them in the outside world
but so there's no
ceiling you know what i mean
so in here where we do uh orphanage or a
bedroom later we do this thing
and i'm just going to get rid of that um
so i'm just going to have it so it
starts up in the
the place where there's no ceiling right
and that way when i
if i right click on this here you can
see that
there's no ceiling above us it's easier
for me to look at what's going on
and also we're in a kind of easier place
for collision you know i can
just immediately uh
punch these walls here right um
and uh and and make that happen so
um so it seems pretty easy to punch into
this wall so let's make that be our test
case here
right we should not be able to do that i
i don't know i don't have an
argument for why that should happen um
so let's see if we can figure out
uh that procedure uh and again the way
that we want to do this oh
wait
so so here's a question for you
something i had not considered um
so suppose i was to say like okay we're
going to look at this
and we set the time step down to like
some really low number
is that a good number
so suppose i set the time step down to
really low number
um can i get this thing stuck in the
wall
or not i was kind of hoping i could
um because i wanted to be able to run
into
a small time step but it almost looks
like this is very interesting because
this we also shouldn't be sensitive to
time step
so that's another good clue to where our
bug is because if i
can't get this stuck in the wall at a
slow time step
it suggests that something weird is
happening with the position tracking
that's making it dependent on that in a
way that i
didn't anticipate yeah like that just
goes straight through
wow okay so there's all kinds of stuff
clues here for us
so that suggests that having 2p
placed further in
like further away
changes the algorithm which it shouldn't
do right
so that's a very important clue as well
um to what's going on here
because we really shouldn't be using 2p
for anything other than just which
direction we're trying to go
that's the only thing that it should be
doing and so
something's busted if the changing to
cause
what the time step will change is how
far
2p is displaced from from p
right so that should not
actually be affecting us so the fact
that that
is affecting us um
is really peculiar and we absolutely
should track that down first because
that's
super weird right that's super super
super weird um
so maybe it's because of this part here
i'm not sure um
like is this somehow failing
you know what i mean like is somehow
this producing
values that are
that are broken let me let me check that
real quick
so i think we never really want this
thing to be yeah well i mean
we've got work to do here but it's okay
so we have our refinement
test here it's always going to produce a
value
that's between from p and 2p if t
test is within bounds so what i might do
though just to be careful
is let's make sure it is
right it should never be able to put us
past 2p or from p on either end
so let me just quickly sanity check that
because that would obviously create an
issue
oops i closed my editor for no reason
try that again
uh yeah so should be fine
no issues uh so so that's not
implicated there
so yeah so the 2p and from p should now
be truncated
so one thing we could do perhaps is
draw these steps uh
as well right and use collides
uh in in drawing it so i'm gonna go
ahead and
and just upgrade now uh um
our our drawing of this
i got sidetracked i was thinking of
doing something totally different but
i'm like
that now we've got an even better
uh thing to track down here so
you know you got to go where you got to
go where the getting is good you know
what i'm saying
when you're debugging um so in here what
i might say is
let's draw the lerp test so
when we do these tests we get a collide
value
you know out of that let's draw that so
in here we'll draw
like a magenta or something um
like a really tiny uh
you know uh volume
oops uh
that's just the width of the cell uh and
so i guess we'll just do a
rect center dim and we'll just say look
that's the center
the dimension is going to be something
uh extremely small
uh because it's just like a point
basically
um so something like that
uh and so that way we can kind of see
like where these are
and then the the color we want to do
uh based on if it collides or not
so we'll do like uh something like uh
i don't know uh we'll do magenta if it
collides in cyan if it doesn't right so
cyan is like you could put it here
magenta is you couldn't uh and
yeah so let's just see if we can see
that at all
um so if i bring up that
uh time step test again and just you
know
crank that down to something smaller
right so there it is um
and then we try to take a look here you
know can we see
that placement yeah you can kind of see
right you can see the refinement
placement there
um very small right it's it's barely
doing any refinement placement at all
yeah so now what i want to be able to do
is i think we want um
a different thing so the time step
is great and all that's fine
um but i think what we actually want to
have there is like a frame hold
kind of a thing you know what i'm saying
so we can kind of like single step
if that makes sense and so
um
easier said than done
largely just because of routing but
basically what i'm talking about here is
inside the that little thing that was
like hey
editor uh
where we did the collision editor we
kind of want the ability to just single
step this stuff
uh and in you know in the witness like i
built this really
good one that you could like record
things and scrub through them and all
that stuff and
that's probably a bridge too far here
but
you know we could do is if there's like
a way to do like a toggle
button um
you know i don't remember any of this
stuff that we did
obviously we wrote it all because the
only person who's programmed anything on
this is me
um but uh i don't know
what we've got here for the yeah we do
so so we can do a toggle button so
what i might suggest is we have a
boolean button here
and we say well uh we've got this
um is it bundle z what's bundle z
yeah um so
we have a thing that's like single step
right that you can like turn on
and uh that'll be like a you know
a thing that when we're ready to debug
we like turn on single stepping
and uh
and then we just kind of click through
it i guess yeah it's a little annoying
because you'd have to hold down the
input
which would be annoying but uh so we
have like
highlight and interaction here so i'm
gonna i don't since i don't know
uh very much about how we wrote this i'm
just gonna
look for where we've used it uh and you
can see actually i guess there's quite a
few
um of these things here
so it looks like
looks like that was used mostly for
working in that system
in the in the edit system there so
yeah not fabulous
but shouldn't we be able to do
shouldn't this just have a normal i'm
confused
yeah so this is i guess this is pretty
straightforward actually
so basically what we would want is like
you know
world mode uh single step
and then we would just do um
edit of that thing
and this just says we want to set this
value like that's the interaction
and for debug ids uh i guess we just
want
some way of you know of producing one of
these things
i don't totally understand exactly
how this stuff is is working um
because again it's just been so long
since we wrote any of this stuff
and our debug system sucked uh i've said
that many times like it was just not
done very well
so you know that's just one of the
consequences of programming on stream
sometimes you just don't do a very good
job compared to what
you know should probably be happening um
but
uh so in terms of those the difference
there because there was like dev ids
versus uh debug ids and there really
wasn't much of a reason for this
um because you can see like there's dev
id values and then there's uh
the debug id stuff which i think
uh oh no it is the same okay
uh so i guess we did unify this so i
don't really understand so like if you
look at dev id from pointer there
um so so i guess it actually works fine
never mind um it's still a crappy system
i i think i don't want to say that it's
good
because it's not um
so let's go ahead and go to the world
mode and add that though
right here
um and so we should now be able to
enable single single stepping which will
give us a flag we can use
um to do you know some stuff for debug
purposes right um so
you know uh or not
i'm not sure why that failed
this is why i say the debug system sucks
because this should be a pretty simple
thing
but it's just too complicated like
there's too much of this nonsense
um because it tried to do like too much
stuff
really is mostly mostly the stupid part
of it
if it had just been scoped smaller you
wouldn't need a lot of this stuff
uh and so it just becomes kind of
annoying but you can see here like that
interaction did not work
right um
and so it's just kind of annoying and
[Music]
um
i mean it looks like maybe the better
thing to do would just be to not do any
of that like it looks like you can also
just do this
so maybe we just should
i mean that seems a lot easier right
um
yeah but for some reason we don't oh uh
okay i see so that's like enabled or
disabled
i guess uh so
[Music]
maybe that
what does this take this button function
enabled and then back to color yeah so
so i think
um i i don't even have to do this i
could just say like
okay you know there's a a backdrop color
and the backdrop color is based on
you know
whether or not you're single stepping
why is that still disabled didn't i say
it was enabled
oh none of the two overloads could
convert okay
so what's your problem we have
i see so there's like a more more
fancier
version which is this one and it's like
the dev id
a classifier which
in these cases it just uses zero
so i guess we don't care what that is
so we've got layout the dev id a
classifier
the label text oops
that went in the wrong place the label
text and then i think we've got all the
stuff passed
um so that allows me to turn it on and
off right
and then we can use that to to do some
like single stepping stuff where
um we can because we just need to watch
it
we just want to watch what it does when
it passes through the wall boundary
so in order to do that it's a little
tough like
um
it's a little bit tough to figure out
what i really
want to have happen there exactly
so um
i guess what i would do is i just say
look
there's gonna be a button
um that does the single step
latch
uh and
when it triggers uh
we set it
right
that is like so freaking annoying um
and i guess we're we're only going to do
like one step so
uh so we'll have a little thing that
like we can trigger
and then when we do uh move entity
like maybe this gets passed into the sim
region where we can look at the fact
that we're doing that because that's the
reason i say it's kind of a little bit
annoying
is because you know really i probably
should put it more in like a
in a purely debug state so you're just
looking at the
like a debug value but like i said the
debug system
kind of sucks so i'm just avoiding using
it you know i'm not going to go like
actually try to make it good
now
so when we're in here and we do that
step latch what i want to be able to do
is just kind of like click to move and
so what we want to do is have a thing
that essentially like you know does all
this work
and you can see that we're going to do
refined voxel placement here and what i
want
is now just a way to say like new
placement
right is here and i say entity p equals
new p
right uh and what i want to do is say
if uh
you know we should do it then do it if
not then don't
right and so the way to look at this is
uh you know if we're single stepping
i i mean the right way to do this is
like let's just say the sim region
has a like uh uh prevent movement
right and we just look to say
look if the prevent movement thing is
set then we just we just don't move
the entity uh with the collision
detector
um and so the sim region then i thought
like did this
not get fixed what am i missing
i thought this was supposed to be fixed
that you could look
i don't know i have to ask ryan about
that i thought it wasn't supposed to be
doing that anymore like nobody wants to
see
forward declaration jump points um but
i'm not sure why it's still showing them
because i thought that got fixed but i
guess it didn't
not sure what's going on there anyway so
you know if you imagine we just stick a
debug thing
in here that shouldn't actually be there
but you know it's there now
uh then what we do is in the world mode
update uh
here we just say look if
we if this was latched right
then the sim regions debug current
movement should be set to true
right so we'll prevent it um so we just
say
all right looking at the world mode and
we can also set the step latch
to false we can say looking at the world
mode if we're single stepping
right um well if we're not single
stepping
uh and then uh that
would be true to prevent movement uh and
the step latch is not set
because every time we set the step latch
we do want it to to do it right so
if this were true we want this to also
um
uh have to be
we want them both to be false right
if they're
if single stepping is true it should
prevent movement so
that's right single step turns on you
prevent movement
and the step latch should be false
because if that's true then you
should allow the movement because just
that one time
um and so when we create the sim region
here uh
you can you can see us doing a begin sim
right and
when this thing creates the sim region
which it looks like it does here uh we
want to just
like right before we do our simulate
call
i just want to do like a world sim sim
region
uh set that debug
that piece of debug information there um
correctly now when we create a sim
region
i don't really know how those are
getting pushed right now so
i might want to do a thing that's like
check and begin sim
here right and when we do begin world
change
um i just want this to probably
initialize that value
right um
and i think that's fine
because it see it's a no clear like most
things get cleared but that one doesn't
okay um
so i don't know that's just the start
so if you imagine turning on single
stepping um
so yeah i mean i guess it just kind of
works right
i mean there's a single step that's
trying to take
um
how is it able to go that far
though
can it really travel that far does it
really have that strong of a spring
i guess so well
anyway um so this does basically what i
want right
and i can step it uh and
to a particular place and you know you
get the answer
um it's not single stepping the game
right so the game is producing totally
new stuff every frame
as it normally would but uh it just
prevents any motion so we can look
at you know it the glove like trying to
get somewhere in particular
or whatever is happening right
um so i think if i now
you know go ahead and push this you know
i could push it into the wall and i
should be able to
to basically get a single step that goes
in there
right i mean i think um
so if we turn single stepping on right
and i crank it through the wall like we
can actually just watch it
do that right um
that's kind of cool so we actually
should be able to look
at that sort of thing pretty easily
actually
which is kind of nice and if we crank
the time step up it can move even
further
right so we can kind of look and see
what's going on here like even without
doing any recording yet we can actually
look at what happens when we push this
thing through
um and
you know it it's just able to tunnel
directly through that
it's it's not doing any of the stuff
that i think it's doing right
which is what we would expect because we
know
that it doesn't work but it's we now
have the ability to draw stuff
that would show us uh you know hopefully
why right like like how is it
determining that
so one thing i would like to do is draw
those
um you know so so maybe like
this is not telling us very much we know
um you know
we now know that the movement direction
checking
seems sane to a certain degree it was
weird that it
hopped on one of those so there are some
things there that don't make a lot of
sense
um but uh we we can sort of look here
and see like okay so
what does this look like
we can even look in side the wall
like so what does this look like when we
go through
and you know what's
really disturbing about that is it looks
like
it's just entirely based on which
direction you were going
it's like it doesn't matter uh
at all what direction i mean
what what the position in the world is
it's just like what direction you're
going determines
so like this occupied czech stuff here
must be really stupid um
right
like like this stuff must just be must
just be dumb
and
so so like let's let's
pretend like so we know right which way
we're going
in this test case right we're going in
positive x
so let's say i sub i turn everything
else off
right um and then i turn on the single
stepping and i go and i look
and like what happens you know what i
mean
so i turn the cell stack on and like
hey that just kind of works
right and let's suppose i cranked the
time step up
it still works or at least it looks like
it does right
let me see if i can go through there
so like that's like rock solid and works
exactly the way that i think it should
right so what
now so like okay
these are actually allowing
things that are not the direction we're
going are allowing me to kind of hop
in through there is it this
let's just here let's see
if the enabling the other
side directional stuff so so we're just
moving out of faces
do those let me tunnel they don't yes
they do
no they do there it did right
well you know what i don't know that we
tested it fairly enough so so let me
just play around with it with just this
one on
so only x motion
so no uh i don't know about that so
let's turn these on
uh one at a time so suppose i turn on
y so now we're doing two dimensional
motion
x y only out faces
can we tunnel easily or not
yes right so we were able to
we need like a wireframe toggle
if ever there was a need for a wireframe
toggle
it's now like where's the glove
right um
nobody knows where it went
um
so if just having
just those two is enough to do it
then that's great because i think well
okay
so let's try something else if i am is
it the fact that you have
two of them right is it the fact that
you're doing two of them
or is it which one you're doing meaning
would y
by itself be enough to cause the problem
so so let's test that so here's just y
motion right um and and let me see
to what extent we can get
stuck in things um here
so it seems like it's like a problem
with the fact that you can do
uh other motions right like like
that there's more than one it's more of
the issue
and part of it is like so if you're only
ever allowed to move out of cells in
that direction
so you can you can basically already see
there's a bug it's that
which is the fact that you're allowed to
move out of the cell that you're in
in the positive direction right which
makes some sense
but we don't want to allow that right so
so we do have a bug here right the bug
is that the get uh when we put you
into the box we need to clamp you
to that box right um
and we're not doing that so like get
closest point
in box is actually putting you
into the next box because this right
is what does that
so that actually probably should be
fixed
separately um
when we place the player
we we really shouldn't allow you to do
that
so when we do this this needs to be
clamped
in meaning like it has to be placed
epsilon back
so that when you're you always want to
be classified as
being in the same cell that you were in
when you started
right um
and so when we do this we want to
basically
shave off a little bit uh
of the cell right we want you to have to
start
um
on the next frame we want you to start
back in the cell that you were on and we
don't ever want you to be able to hop
into the next cell um
just by virtue of the fact that you were
placed all the way at the edge of
one right so i do think that needs to be
fixed
as a separate issue so this get this
part here where we do the from
and the two when they're you know um
locked into the best cell what we need
is this get closest point in box
function
we need a conservative version of it
right
so in here where we do um
all of this stuff
uh we need a conservative version of
this
where any time we were uh doing
the get closest point in box thing it
really should do it
conservatively right
[Music]
um
yeah uh so when we do get closest point
in box conservative then what we want is
we want to
make it so that when we do the max right
we're actually looking at like an
epsilon off of the max
um so we want to take that box and we
want to basically
like map you into it and and this is
this is a little bit of an issue because
we really want to be doing these tests
the other way around
so
because numerically speaking we would
like these all to be based off of like
zero to one or something so we have a
fixed domain
that we're testing in and there's no
reason for us not to do that
it's just sloppiness so i think we
should do this now we're
we can cheese this we would be saved
here we could easily cheese this
and the reason that for that is because
uh
cheesing it here the fact that the whole
engine
is built around localized regions means
that you can never
have large v3s so we're always in
a very small domain to begin with so if
we want to
we can totally cheese this out here
by just putting in an epsilon and this
actually will probably work just fine
you could just do this and it would work
um but we can do it better than that
we don't even have to cheese it quite
that way
um i don't think uh
but but you know cheesy cheesiness here
let's just put that in because i want to
make sure we cheese properly yeah
so now as you see it can't move it can
only
uh i can't move laterally it can only go
inside the cell it's in and it can't get
out
of that which is what i want and of
course it can move
forward and backward like so now i don't
think that would have an effect on the
bugs that we're seeing but before i
continue to try and look for the bugs
that we're seeing i do want to make sure
that didn't change the behavior in some
material way
so let me just make sure that even with
that in place we can still
get into the bad situations because i
mean
i guess i don't know for sure that that
wasn't a significant contributor to
these bugs
so i don't want to spend a bunch of time
looking for something that i can't repro
produce anymore thinking that i
can still reproduce it
okay so actually that seems to have done
a bit but not enough right so there you
go so right
so as i was saying like i wouldn't have
thought that could have produced the bug
and it
or or at least it couldn't produce all
the badness we were seeing and you can
see that we still
uh can easily get stuck there uh let me
see how easy it is to
reproduce that so it looks like if you
are pushing in two directions at once
you can reproduce it pretty easily
um you just need to be in a reasonable
location
yeah see so let's see about
what it looks like if we uh
hold down those those single step
directions uh
like so i'm gonna go ahead and turn that
on
uh and let's just see what this looks
like
well unfortunately it looks like i need
to put the glove in
an even different position to get it to
really happen i can't
quite oh but like you know what this
will probably do it right
there's a good one do that again there
we go
that might be a bridge too far here
it's like going way too far um
yeah so i don't know i this this may be
too difficult to do
uh this way i may need to add a little
bit more recording in here for this to
work
um well that was easy
maybe i can just do it that way
yeah i mean all i really had to do was
hop
and it got stuck in there right
and again i just want to check again
just to be sure
if i can only move in one direction does
it still get stuck
okay so this is even better so hopping
gets me stuck right um
[Music]
hopping gets me stuck
although i guess that could argue just
because there's nothing else you can
really do
meaning in this case you're pushing
two two things together
that i guess there's not really any
other option
for it like that is just pushing
[Music]
it's it's it's pushing from both sides
so maybe that you would argue there's
really nothing it could have done there
so that's probably not a good test and
we don't care about that because if you
push something into a wall it will come
back out of the wall
when we enable the ability of things to
move out of walls right
um so we'll have to think about what we
want to do in that
case but yeah like that's a problem
because
it's pretty easy i the the game
does not stop you from pushing into
something like that so you're
technically allowed to just push it in
that way right
um so it's hard to say right
uh so so i don't know so i don't really
want to start with that case
um but yeah like this part here
it really does seem like in order to get
stuck yourself
um it needs to have been
it needs to have the ability to move in
two directions
it just if you only have one it doesn't
seem to do it
so i guess one other question i would
have is then
what if the one that you get is the
ability to move in two directions at the
same time
right can this one get stuck by itself
or is it that you need two actual calls
to update best
right okay so being able to move through
corners
is sufficient to enable allow you to do
anything you want
right look it just goes all the way
through there
so that is great
okay so according to this
it's just legal to do that move
right um and i guess well okay so
that is actually true right it's it's
allowed to go upward
and i guess the thing i don't quite
quite understand there is how is that
closer to the thing you're trying to get
to
um
i mean i guess technically it is so i
guess that's not wrong
um so all right but i need to get myself
into a position where i can see this
thing colliding
so let's turn off single stepping real
quick
um and try to put myself in a position
where we can see it hit the wall
right the easiest way to do that might
be here
and if i now take a look that
right
and i'm gonna turn this time step up a
bit
so that just doesn't work
right and and for reasons i
do not know right like like it's
testing it's testing it should be
testing that corner
right and when it gets to here that
corner should be obstructed which means
you shouldn't be able to move
so fundamentally speaking that seems
like our
corner test is broken like this just
isn't working um
[Music]
great news because that's easier to
debug than something
more complicated certainly um
[Music]
i guess but i can't say i know offhand
uh why that would be
so that's a little confusing but
all right so if that's the case the
first thing we probably want to do
then is we want to draw like that
placement right so we probably want to
draw
um
do you have a way to draw points more
easily than what i'm doing
by the way no
all right um so what we want to do
here is just draw those because i don't
understand
okay did you guys see this the entire
time
and nobody mentioned it
[Laughter]
i like that sure we saw it
all right you don't you don't get to
pretend you saw it
did anyone mention that in the chat is
the thing
like like if i scroll back am i gonna
see anyone mention it
or not
okay all right so hey we need this
entire thing to be filled out
and we stop the first time we find one
that
that's true
so that's obviously completely bogus
because we need the entire
eight set of eight to be filled out and
we're not doing that
so obviously that's going to not work at
all
right um
[Music]
uh and and shockingly now it's
not able to get stuck using one
direction of motion all right so let's
turn on the other directions of motion
and let's see
um to
you know to what extent
that uh allows us to to prevent getting
stuck in geometry here i'm pushing
against all the walls just to see
um what's up here
much more stable much more stable now
so there's one
oh although it's not stuck
uh it's actually in a correct location
it just got on top of things
and we have to work on the gliding like
uh
code like we don't really have
a lot of explanation for how we want the
gliding to work
so that's actually not stuck in geometry
it just got
on top of things and now there's it's
it's asking to try and move into it and
of course it can't
all right um so i'd say that we're in a
that's great like we've gotten to a
pretty nice place actually
um
much more stable um
and really what we what we have now is
the problem with edge
with with getting stuck in places where
it can't go where you're asking it to go
and so first of all changing to a
cylinder which i'd like to do
will help a little bit with that but
we're probably going to have to do
more than just that um like we're
probably gonna have to do
more than just that work right
uh because yeah we're gonna have to
think about some just a bunch of
different things because like for
example
yeah moving up on top of stuff like that
that it can do
and also moving underneath people we're
going to think about what we want to do
about those things but we're going to
have to handle them right at some point
and and figure out what we want to do
there i mean maybe one answer is we
we reduce the ability to move in z in
general
you know um
but i don't know uh so yeah
i'm pretty happy with that um
this is in pretty good shape now right
that's like quite stable actually
the collision detection part of it um
it's actually surprisingly fast
considering the fact that we are still
testing
every entity every time on every corner
and in the refinement it is nuts how
fast computers are this should be dog
slow
uh and it's actually not so yeah so i
would say like gliding we have to
improve and then we have to come up with
what we're gonna do
i mean some of that is just the thing
itself
like we can improve the gliding behavior
to be better
um but the thing itself may have to be
smarter
right like it may have to do a little
bit of path finding to get out of
situations right um but i do think
that's pretty stable
though i'm not seeing it really able to
get
stuck into things at all uh
and it's this is not a this is not a
complete test obviously but you know so
you can see the only time we ever get
stuck is it gets on top of stuff
and it's trying to move down and can't
and that's why i say the gliding
behavior looks a bit
busted
[Music]
right like
it seems like it almost gets it itself
into a position
where it it may be like so that there
may be some bugs in there where it's
like gotten itself into a position where
it's
it is sort of stuck meaning
it should be it shouldn't really be able
to place itself in a place where it
couldn't move laterally
and it somehow did that right um so
there may still be some bugs in there
that are directionality based like like
you can move
up into the position but not out of
position downward
um right
so right
all right we can take a couple questions
real quick but but i think that's good
for today like like we're in great shape
we've got more work to do but that's
that's pretty good right
can you still hop push glove into the
wall i mean
yes you must be able to because there's
no solution to that problem
so you must be able to right
i guess i mean surprisingly no i can't
but
you sh the glove has nowhere to go right
i'm smooshing it between
two things that don't move right so it's
two forced objects
and it i guess it's good that it picks
the one
that's the movable one but that's
probably just an accident
of the order in which the entities are
evaluated or something so it's
look right like i don't know that that's
a
because the routine is smart um
so so no it doesn't get stuck in the
wall but
but i kind of feel like it could still
it probably just doesn't
because it gets stuck it get it happens
to get stuck in the person first
um
yeah i don't know it's better it's
better behaved than i thought that would
be because that's kind of a non
that's a situation the collision
detector alone can't solve
um and and even when it gets so so you
can see that like that's just the
gliding behavior isn't great
because like we want that to roll off
the wall and
the cylinder switching to a cylinder
might help there but we also have to
kind of have good rules for motion
um that that probably produce better
outcomes there
um because i
i just feel like that should probably
still be sliding and it's not
um is the thing
so it kind of feels like it's getting
itself into a position
where it it's not testing some
things that it should be testing or
something like right it shouldn't be
it should be in a place where if if you
were able to put yourself there to begin
with
and this thing is is a horizontal
vertical surface
you should be able to look at the voxels
near nearby right
um so so i feel like that part is broken
uh and so so
i like to look at that because i think
that that's probably broken
and not doing what it should be doing um
shouldn't you also add epsilon to the
min side of the conservative stuff i
don't
think so i i i'm not willing to say yes
or no but
um because boxes are
considered to like start at their min
and extend
to like one minus you know their max
effectively
right
let's let's see
so i guess yeah i mean
you can see this being a bit busted
like it looks like these tests are the
wrong way around
like is in rectangle is doing it one way
uh and rectangle's intersect is doing it
the other way
and so so this is probably just bad like
this should not look like it looks
um it should be that
uh you have
a one side greater than and one
equal to and one side less than and
that's not
uh what's happening here
so you know
i guess what i would say is
um
so you know uh
i do think like that part of it needs to
probably get cleaned up
what kind of pathfinding would you use
for the gloves return path
um so i don't know
i i don't know what we want to do there
because moving the glove around is like
a gameplay element
so my guess is we don't probably want
pathfinding per se we might want it to
be something that's more directly
controllable
by the player so that they can so that
it's like a job
for you and also that you have more
control over where it goes
so i'm not sure right
would you differently for collision
section in non-aabb geometry uh no that
this doesn't
care at all about that
this would work with any geometry at all
right
this this test can be any test you want
for this collision detector
so the answer is like nothing you do it
exactly the same way
i think the c model of programming is a
bit time consuming in that we need to
compile and look at the result and go
back and forth fix the problem do you
think
what would be better model programming
and i also i don't mean the scripting
language
um
what do you mean do you just mean like
to to visualize stuff better
um because like hot code reloading
helps with the fact that you don't have
to like you know i can
i can do stuff and watch it happen right
so if i'm in here and i'm like oh i want
you know it to draw something else i can
just go in here and draw that something
else
right um which i don't know like suppose
we wanted to look at what the
target was i'm trying to think of what
we should draw here
um but like if we want to draw something
like what what's the target
um that's the starting cell i could draw
like a thing that's like
you know um a uh
you know uh a white thing at the
the position of
the target so 2p
and i don't know
um so i can start drawing the target
right and i i've never closed the game
the game's still running so now i'm
drawing the target right you can see it
that's that little white dot moving
around there and i could say like oh it
needs to be bigger
like i can't see it well enough i can
just do that right
um and you know there it is
you can see it right that's the target
it's trying to get to
um so you know like code reloading is
a thing that helps with that but i don't
know what else you mean
uh in terms of like like i'm not sure
there are other things you might mean
but i'm not sure what exactly they are
right
so you can see this is an example of
being stuck
sort of and you can see that it's like
it's just
it can't move itself around that corner
which again
a changing to cylinders which we want to
do
or spheres um would help
right
would it have been worth it to make a
visualization code before actually
writing it
um
so i guess what i would say is in a in a
world
where you were you know not just
programming on stream
usually what you do is you build a
little visualization system
that's just designed to be quick and
dirty that you can just use for
everything like you wouldn't
just have for collision detection and
then you just kind of have that
and you just anytime you want you just
draw some stuff into it and it works
right um
so so i would say like uh
i i don't know like that you need to
think about it as like should i write a
thing for visualizing section before
collision deduction or not it's more
just like look just
you should just generally have a little
visualizer thing in there to begin with
you know what i mean um
so you know
so the thing that's sort of wonky that i
don't understand is it seems like it's
able to get itself
into a position where it's sticking
right
um and can't glide
like even though what's in there now
should be able to glide so that's a
little
weird um
right like
like it still just looks like it's doing
something fundamentally odd
right like if i if i go like that
it's saying i can't place in any of
those cells like all those cells are red
oh yes they are
wait a minute so
really um
you know what if we did the more
permissive version of this like how bad
would that be
so the permissive version of this is if
any if there was any way to move out
that side of the cell you do
right
um and and i don't know how bad that
gets
but we could certainly look right um
and you can see how it glides now right
um
so that might be the more correct way to
do it um
right because now it can glide all over
the place you can see it gliding much
nicer which is kind of what i wanted
originally
so yeah we may have switched to the
conservative version of that
before but
and it still doesn't quite work like you
can see it gets stuck underneath the
player
there uh you know you couldn't it was
kind of a random occurrence but
let's see if i could make it happen
again there there we go
um so you can see like well although
that's probably just because the player
is moving on to it
right and we don't push you back out so
that's actually fine
uh we're gonna we're gonna solve that
when we go ahead and do the like
what do you do if you find yourself in
like
if you find that somebody has moved on
top of you that's that's not
subject to physical motion so that's
actually fine
um but yeah that's really smooth now
like like that that glides really nicely
actually
uh you could see it you saw it around
that corner and that's
without being a cylinder
um so that's that's pretty great
actually
that's really nice and smooth so yeah
very good a little too smooth it glided
up all the way over the top
what we're gonna do about getting out of
the top i don't know we might have to
put in like collision volumes to cap
because you know the rules of the
collision are you can just go straight
over the top of those things
and you don't really want the glove to
be able to do that because it's they're
sort of more of a cutaway so you
probably have to put a ceiling
at least collision ceiling
that's not visible but there
but looking really good um
so far right
that looks stuck that looks stucky
what's wrong with that
so yeah we i don't know one of the
problems is because we
don't currently like you know when like
i said
we can push you the the thing can push
you into something
um and we don't have the code in yet for
doing the escaping which is what we
should do next time
uh which is if you get interpenetrated
if if you're stuck in something
what what allows you to get out right
and so uh that's the next step which is
you know
and we'll see because i don't know
right
so uh i shouldn't have said cylinders
because honestly we probably just want
spheres
because everything so things in this
game
that move around like walking they hop
and they don't use the collision
detector they're just only allowed to go
on squares or not go on squares
so what we probably need to do is
for floating things it's probably just a
sphere is better
so
couldn't you simply clamp to x y what
does having z axis movement on the glove
in this problem space
accomplished well i mean you just saw it
right
in this game you know you you hop around
and eventually you know you get to
places
um where you can go like up and down
levels so the problem would be you know
we're running the game
and you get here you know and then you
want to like hop
down right you want to you want to do
that
and the glove needs to know whether it
can do that or not
right you you need some code path to
handle it
so we could like special case it or
something
but we'd rather have the system if you
can do that in the game we'd like to
have the system
do like allow you to do that you know
um so i think we need to handle 3d there
you know whether we like it or not um
uh and so you know i think we want to
try and handle z as best we can
and if we have to do some hacky stuff uh
to make it work the way we think it
should
uh because it is still sort of a 2d ish
game
we can but i'd rather make it work with
z
uh you know to the center it can
i do need to make those guys collision
volumes lower because
at the moment the glove can just go
right underneath them if it wants to
right see that
um
but and just to be clear like i don't
think it's hard right we just all we
have to do is just add a collision
volume for the ceiling that's it
right and then you and then it won't go
so it's it's such a simple fix it
doesn't
really make any sense why we wouldn't
just add
a ceiling collision volume right
collision volumes
don't have to have visible geometry
so it's literally free every time we're
dropping down one of those cells it's
like totally free for us to just slap a
collision volume on
on the top of the cell and it's done
right so it seems like that's
the way you would do it because why
would you bother adding like all of this
like
hacky special case code or something to
deal with z when you can literally just
like
slop that on top and plus you're going
to need that for like the other floating
entities
you don't want them going like
out through the ceiling either right so
you're you're
you're saying something about the world
that's actually true like the world
actually does
have a blocker there right um so it's
it's not like weird
it's what is there technically there is
a ceiling
right um so
anyway all right pretty good work today
uh we're not quite
there yet to be sure we're gonna have to
do a lot more work but
loads better than what we started with
right like the original cushion detector
was terrible this one's getting
getting pretty respectable so i think
we'll
uh be in good shape eventually all right
uh but let's wrap it up thank you
everyone for joining me for the episode
handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
with series at home you can always
go to handmadehero.org and pre-order the
game it comes with source code so you
can play around with it yourself
uh if you would like to go ahead and do
the rest of
the collision detection work you could
you could go beat me to it i won't be i
only programmed the two hours a week
on this game so you've got all week
uh to beat me to the punch
pun intended uh so if you're interested
go for it that's it for today i
will be back here next weekend to
uh there's a schedule but yeah it's
already i've been on there
um i will be back here next weekend
where i will start to look at polishing
that routine up
it needs the ability to take
intersecting objects and separate them
that's the biggest thing that's missing
right now so we'll take a look at that
uh and then we'll probably add some more
visualization stuff so we can
make sure there aren't bugs in there
maybe we'll switch to the spheres as
well like a couple of those things
so we have polish work to do we'll do
that and then we'll switch back to
gameplay code because at that point i
think our collision texture will be
pretty solid
um we don't have to completely bullet
proof it yet
but you know it'll be nice and solid and
it won't be like ruining our
attempts to like make gameplay code
because it's like screwing up or
anything
so we can go back to gameplay code and
add some combat stuff in there
um and we'll see how it goes uh that's
it
till till then have fun program
everybody and i'll see you on the
internet
take it easy