there we go okay sure we are on day 1991
that's 91 hours of programming
I guess that's that's what--that's this
is our second week we're a third week
we're sort of somewhere in our third
week of programming which is kind of
exciting we we accidentally started
working on the renderer I don't know how
it happened it just kind of happened so
here we are on handmade Hiro working on
the renderer and I was trying to talk
about bases but I completely ran out of
time yesterday so it'll kind of have to
do a little bit of a reboot Ruby reboot
here and talk about bases today so that
hopefully we can get through them have
enough time to get through them if you
would like to follow along at home
definitely be sure to download de 90s
source code if you preorder the game on
handmade Hirota or Ronde 91 so unzipped
a 90s source code that's what we're
starting with here
and that way you will line up with me
alright so Basie's I have one thing to
mention I don't know if pseudonyms 73
already mentioned this potentially but I
realized kind of after I I sort of was
sleepily explaining this stuff that when
I was talking about linear independence
yesterday I realized I did have a reason
why I could legitimately say that linear
independence was good and it was I had
said minimal up here but really minimal
was just a way of saying linear
independence right because what minimal
meant in my case was I saying
you know I said if we have a 2d
coordinate system that means we have two
basis vectors and I said that was
minimal but that's that's what linear
independence actually sort of means in a
2d space you can only have two bases
without becoming redundant like you will
no longer be linear dependent if you go
up to three so in some sense you could
say that this was being able so if you
do happen to want to learn linear
algebra and you'll learn what this is
really these were sort of the same thing
you know minimal is sort of a way of
saying linearly independent and spans
the space right so again not important
really for the discussion but if you
should be doing some linear algebra
education on your own time it's probably
worth saying that that was sort of I
just I don't know kind of walked right
by it
today when I was talking about it I was
like I guess I can't really fit linear
independence there but we sort of
actually did all right so let's go let's
go to our little basis discussion here
day 91 let's talk about Basie's I'm
gonna work backwards from what I
actually want in the effort in order to
try and give sort of a better
explanation yesterday I was very sleepy
and I felt that my explanation just
wasn't very good so here we go all right
so I'm on a screen right and we sort of
already decided that you know we had
this this is what a screen looked like
but doesn't really matter necessarily
what a screen looked like we talked
about it yesterday which is that the
y-axis goes down and the x-axis goes
across which is to say that if the
coordinate that you're using for Y used
to increase you will move down the
screen right and so what I was trying to
get across yesterday is really you can
think of there as being these basis
vectors for screen space which is that
the X vector and the Y vector that you
would say where your base vectors are
essentially 0 1 and 1 0 in this case
right where one pixel you know is is one
unit right so this is like a pixel and
we keep going out in pixels right and
the you know screen itself is as wide as
there are pixels on it and the origin
right the place where a coordinate
system starts the origin is at that 0 0
pixel the upper left corner right 0 0 is
always the the origin of any coordinate
system I should say obviously the 0
chord is always the origin but where it
is it happens to be the upper-left
corner right and so right here we have
our two basis vectors right our basis
vector Y and our base effects X and then
we have an origin which is that point
right there and together we can say that
this sort of forms right a coordinate
system it's a way that we can say where
stuff is and we can pick any pixel on
the screen right we could pick any pixel
on the screen by saying what the x and y
coordinates were we can even pick things
that are off the screen by using
negative X or Y coordinates or ones that
are too large and we can even pick
fractional ones I could pick the center
of this pixel potentially depending on
how I wanted to find like I could define
the origin being at the center of the
pixel I could say that it was up at the
you know I have a number of options for
that but let's say it's in the corner of
the actual pixel that upper left-hand
corner pixel this right here could be
0.5 point 5 so I could talk about that
center of the pixel as well similarly I
could define a different coordinate
system if I wanted to for my world for
I'm sorry for my pixels where the origin
was actually in in a slightly different
place right if I imagine the pixels that
are on the screen and these are the
actual let's say LCD pixels that we're
talking about here right I could make my
coordinate system origin be right there
right I could say that the center of a
pixel essentially is you know
conceptually speaking was 0 0 and then
like each Center of each pixel is that
you know this is 0 1 this is 1 0 and so
on right and here's that x-axis that
y-axis right and I can do all sorts of
things I could also say that I wanted Y
to go up right I could say that that's
what the coordinate system look like so
if I wanted to I could have a different
notion of it where we sort of had
something that looked kind of like this
you know where this is the the bottom
left corner of the screen right I could
do that and all that so there's very
many ways I can define coordinate
systems and the only important thing is
that we have some notion of those three
things we have to have the origin we
need to know where that is right and
that's a point right that's basically
saying where that is somewhere in space
and it's the point 0 0 where will if if
someone specifies the coordinates 0 0
where will that be and then we need the
basis right we need the X basis and we
need the Y basis vector right and that
basically tells us what you know what is
going on that's the that's you know 1 0
this is the vector 1 0 and this is the
vector 0 1 where do they point right and
so it's hard to think about this
sometimes a little confusing if you're
not used to it because these are all
sort of implicit right your if you if I
ask you where is the origin well it's at
0 0 that answer is always trip the
origin of a course it is always 0 0 so
what does it mean to say we have an
origin right and the answer is that that
origin is always defined in some other
space right and that space may be actual
they may be physical in the real world
like in our case the origin of the
screen is the actual origin like of the
monitor that's what we're talking about
when we say where it is we're talking
about where the actual pixel is you know
in in real world space that's what we're
trying to draw to but there may be
fictional spaces as well like the world
space of the game is a purely fictional
space we have created to contain our
fictional world where is that origin who
knows all we know is that it is the
origin of our world and it has no real
definition of where it is right it's
purely virtual and so sometimes it can
be very confusing to talk about these
because that stuff is all very implicit
what's the X basis vector well it's it's
the vector that defines what 1 0 is but
it you know what direction does it point
in I don't even know how to define it
again in the real world
the screens X basis vector for purposes
of our discussion is what is the the you
know the line going across the top of my
monitor right so the reason that you
want to start thinking about these
though is because that's not always the
case once we start to get into
transforms and doing things which is
what we're trying to do now with our
graphics we will start to describe
origins and basis vectors in terms of
other origins and basis vectors because
once you have one of these you can
describe other ones in terms of it and
do computations on it right so for
example if I was to define a world
coordinate system we're okay we know
there's a zero zero we know there's a 1
zero vector that's the X vector we know
this is zero one vector it's a Y vector
right we've got the basis we've got the
origin right once I have one of those
and I just say that it means something
like the world space I'm just purely
defining a fictional space
well once I define that fictional space
in my head and say that's what you know
I have some notion of what it is just
mentally right then anything I choose to
define that's inside that space can be
given an actual specific meaning
numerically in turn
of that fictitious space that I've
created essentially right because again
we're creating a fictional world it
doesn't have meaning it's just it's a
fictional world of handmade hero where
is the origin I don't know right it's in
handmade hero land somewhere but once I
have this I can start to talk about
these things right let's say that's you
know that's the zero one that's the the
zero one there right so if I want to
make another coordinate system I could
make another coordinate system right I
can make another coordinate system here
if I want to and I can say that this is
what it looks like it has an origin but
that origin can now be described in
terms of this other origin this other x
axis and this other Y axis right so I
can say definitively that if you wanted
to get to this new origin you would go a
certain distance along the x axis from
the origin of the world coordinate
system you would then go up right so I
go over you would then go up the y axis
a certain distance and you would now be
at the origin of this other coordinate
system right similarly once I was there
I could then define points in terms of
that new origin and I can define the
axes in terms of the existing axes right
so what would I do to define you know to
define these axes here right well I just
have to think about them in terms of
these existing axes in the other basis
right here's that x axis here's that Y
axis well what is the definition of my
new Y axis this is my new fancy Y axis
I'm defining well same thing I just
measure it in the other coordinate space
right I just say well I know I could
define it in terms of this X this x axis
and this Y axis and so all I have to do
is just create the definition for that
and I don't know what that definition
actually is I guess you know we're
assuming that we want it to be unit
length so it kind of looks like it's
roughly at a 45 degree angle you know so
it's it's gonna be something like you
know 1 1 over the length of of 1 1 right
it's gonna be it's gonna be something
like that so let's let's actually I can
action
tell you what it probably would be right
so 1 plus 1 square rooted where's
where's the square root thing square
root there it is yeah what what just
happened
1.4 okay that is this is I feel like I
did it there it is square root of 2
that's what I wanted 1.4 so now I just
want one over that 0.707
okay so that's what I did you think I'd
remember that number by now so let's say
0.7 so this is something like Oh point
seven point seven right that would be my
new y-axis so that is like the
definition of the y-axis in this other
coordinate system right now you may ask
yourself why do I care about this at all
why are you even bothering to tell me
this well this is what we want to do to
start supporting rotation right and
scaling and I'll explain to you why we
care about these when it comes to
rotation and scaling so let's suppose I
want to define a shape right so I define
some axis system that is purely
imaginary like I was saying right and I
start defining some shape in there and I
define my little shape it's a triangle
let's say right and I know what the
coordinates are of this triangle in my
imaginary coordinate system because like
I said I defined it so I can say
whatever it is here's let's say this is
one unit along that axis is one unit
along here so I know where each of these
things is and I've now got a definition
for this shape right I could literally
encode I could encode this shape by
saying where each of these are here's
point zero is point 1 here's point 2
right I guess I'll use letters for them
let's say a b c right i can define these
where they are i can say what their
coordinates are and now anytime I want I
can sort of say well in this imaginary
coordinate system here's where they are
right well if I think about these
coordinates as a way of interpreting
them as though as a way of moving along
the coordinate system that I defined
here right it has an origin all right
and it has an x and y axis and I have a
X right a y bx b y CX CY these are the
coordinates of those points in my system
right I can always think of that
construction that I drew before I drew
that construction before where I'm
saying move along X for however big your
x coordinate is move along Y by however
long your Y is you know start at the
origin and do those two things you will
get to the point right well that
construction allows us to do any kind of
rotation and scaling of this shape that
we want to do because all we have to do
is rotate and scale the bases and by
doing that rotation and scaling we will
then be able to read off how our points
go right let's say that we wanted to do
a rotation of this right
so I rotate the bases like so right
there's a why there's an X there's my
origin and now I want to do the exact
same stuff the AXA y you know B X V Y
well I do the same thing I go a certain
distance along therefore ax I do a
certain distance up for a Y and that's
my new point right start at the origin
go like this I do the same thing here
for for that well for B I guess I go
this way there's my B I go all the way
out there go up for my C I go to the
middle and go up a long ways right and
so if I reconstruct those exact motions
right I produce the shape you see that
it's the exact same shape
well modulo my allows our drawing it's
the exact same shape constructed rotated
what would happen if I scaled it right
what would happen if I scaled it well
let's say I scaled the y axis to be
really long so instead of here where the
length of the y axis was 1 I am going to
take the length of the y axis to be 2
twice as large right but the x axis will
stay the same
well now I get exactly the same results
along X
right so my shape looks exactly the same
when when viewed on that but when I go
to up to sort of go up the y-axis I go
much longer and so my shape elongates
dramatically right see what I'm saying
so by doing that by changing the basis
we can change any shape encoded in those
faces into the equivalent shape bent
warped done whatever we want to that we
did to the bases right so what does that
look like in code right
well this operation we know how to do in
code right what's the operation in code
of starting somewhere moving along one
axis and moving along another right well
it's really trivial we just take the
origin right whatever the origin is and
I'll just maybe I should write that with
something else I don't know well I'll
just write it origin we start at the
origin right if we're trying to get to a
new point right so let's say we have one
of these points here in fact I'll use
since we're using letters before if I
want the new a the new a prime right I
just start at the origin right I take a
X and I move along that x axis I take a
Y and I move along the y axis right and
there's and I'm at my location right so
I have two coordinates a X a Y that
encode the point and all I need to know
is where is the origin where is the X
and y at what are the directions that
X&amp;Y point in and how long they are
because this is baked in right this has
a length it's a vector right and I can
produce the new point very very simple
and so what we find is just with this
you know very simple equation right
which is like the offset plus the
coordinate times the x axis the
coordinate times the y axis we can do
any kind of transform that we want that
looks like you know a rotation in a
scale of some kind and the scale doesn't
have a uniform it can be non-uniform
right
that in its most basic form is a way to
transform points it's a way to do any
kind of rotation that's going that we
want to do on points so if we just want
to move points around this is all we
really need to know right and this is
where defining those bases comes in so
you can imagine if we wanted to define a
basis write explicitly in code it's
something that just looks like you know
in origin write an x-axis and a y-axis
now again what are these defined in
terms of it doesn't matter right the
basis is just something that describes a
space in terms of another space so
depending on how you decided to use it
in the code it's whatever
this definition happens to be if I took
world space and wanted to define you
know some some little like you know I
don't know like a house I wanted some
house space defined like the space that
was you know a house that was rotated
and scaled in the world somewhere right
well I would just define this basis to
be the origin of this house space in the
world
so in world coordinates the x axis would
be whatever the house is x axis was
defined in the world and the y axis
would be whatever the wax just was
defined in the world right so if the
world space looked like this you know
and the house is this tiny thing out
here or whatever then that's what I
would encode I didn't code that as the
origin I'd encode those as the x and y
axes right and I'd be done and then any
point that was defined in this house
space will automatically be at the
correct placement rotation and scaling
that I want it to be just by performing
this transform on it right and so we've
already done a little bit of this right
we've definitely done the displacement
all we haven't really done is the
scaling and rotating of those things so
we've already been doing this part right
we've already been offsetting things all
the time the only thing we didn't do was
actually start taking into account the
axes which would have allowed us to do
that rotation and scaling right
so this is what we'd like to introduce
into our renderer now even though we
don't really have much of a way to draw
it yet what we can do for example is we
could draw some points that would
basically give us took the origin
because we could draw like a little
tripod right because we have the ability
to draw a rectangle we could do
something where we drew like this sort
of a thing you know you know the X point
the Y point and the origin point we
could we could sort of draw that right
those those things so we could see that
we were you know computing it correctly
so you know what how do we actually
define those right how do we actually
define the X and the y-axis origins easy
it's just a point we all know how to
move points around we've done that a
bunch right but how do we find these two
well here we come back to our unit
circle right and that's a really easy
way for us to be able to do that if we
have our unit circle and we sort of draw
in the world wow that's wow that was a
really bad circle let's be try to do a
slightly better circle I don't know if I
can drawing a circle on one of these
it's a little tricky I'm gonna be honest
with you okay forget it the circle this
oh my oh oh my god it's awful oh it's
just the worst oh it's like lumpy all
right well anyway point being pretend
this is the unit circle and when I say
unit circle I just mean a circle whose
radius is 1 right 1 unit sorry if I have
a unit circle and I want to take the
cosine right and the sine of that right
two values cosine sine as my angle
changes right so the angle kind of
sweeps around like this right as the
angle changes essentially what I will
get is the cosine value is the
x-coordinate of the point that would you
know that I would trace on the circle if
I went out one unit
along that angle whatever that angle is
the cosine is the x-coordinate and the
sine is the y-coordinate right so
basically this here is cosine theta and
this here is sine theta right
does that make some sense hopefully
you've all had this in your grade school
geometry class or trigonometry class all
right right make some sense so what that
would mean is well if I was to plug in
zero for the angle right so if my angle
was to equal zero well that would just
be this point right here and what is
that point if this length is one right
that means the cosine theta was one the
sine theta is zero right so at theta
equals zero that would give me a point
of 1 comma zero right that gives me the
x axis that's what that is right one
zero similarly if I was to plug in you
know 90 up here 90 degrees well my
cosine has now become zero right so if
my theta is 90 degrees then my cosine is
now zero and my sine is 1 right and hey
guess what that's the y-axis so if just
without knowing anything else if we
wanted to create a rotated coordinate
system right you can imagine using this
just directly my x axis is just cosine
theta sine theta because if it was zero
it'll give me the x axis and if it's
anything above zero
it'll just slowly rotate up the circle
just like what I want right it'll just
keep rotating rotating rotating around
right and to bridge the y axis all I
would have to do is add 90 to it because
90 degrees off the x axis is gonna be
the y axis and that's just gonna slowly
rotate around this way too right so you
know cosine of this plus 90 sine of
theta plus 90 right that's the y axis so
pretty trivial to generate rotated
things all you have to do is just use
the cosine and sine to pluck them off
the unit
Circle for you furthermore if I want to
scale either of these all I have to do
is just multiply it by some number
that's my scale write whatever I want my
scale to be after these come out I can
just multiply by scale on the outside
right scale times either of these if I
multiply them both by the same scale I
get uniform scaling if I multiply one by
one scale one by the other I get
non-uniform scaling like I squash it
right or whatever so really really
trivial now we can take this a step
further and realize that actually it cuz
we're in 2d our situation for y-axis is
really pretty basic right because if you
look at what actually happens here let's
say we've got that theta well check out
what happens when I draw on my right
angle here right oops that's no good so
what I was saying is well you know
really if you if you wanted to get this
you just do theta plus 90 and hey
there's that theta plus 90 so that gives
you that point and that's what I was
saying down here that's all good right
but if you take a look at what this
vector actually is this is really just
the same vector that we just produced
only starting with the y axis instead of
the x axis right imagine taking this
whole diagram and just rotating the
diagram 90 degrees this way right this
is exactly this is theta right here it's
the same angle right so it seems kind of
stupid to recompute exactly the same
vector effectively just to get it
rotated 90 degrees and so what you can
see by you know looking at that kind of
triangle relation right you can kind of
see there like take a look at how this
looks right this here these are the same
so this right is that right there if you
look at what happens here you can even
just reading off the diagram realize
what a smarter algorithm is for
producing that coordinate system right
if this length is going to be the same
as this length because they're the exact
same triangle right and this length is
going to be the same as this length then
we already know the length of of
these two because we've already computed
them up here right we've already done it
we know that sine theta right is going
to be this length up here right sine
theta sine theta I should use the
standard notation and actually double
notch those right so if this is sine
theta and this is sine theta then really
all I'm talking about is using the X you
know which coordinate goes into it was
going into the y coordinate here it's
going the x coordinate now right because
of that 90-degree rotation right
so basically sine theta is my x
coordinate for the y axis right and then
the same thing happens for the x axis
becomes the y axis over here right
this was the x axis before it's now on
the y axis right so what I want to do is
take that cosine and I want to put it in
here right and so you can see
essentially to create the y axis all we
have to do is rearrange just flip which
two we're doing there's one more little
rub to it though right they're going
potentially the wrong direction right
because cosine theta was positive going
out this way right and it's positive
going up here
so the cosine theta term will give us
the correct answer for the length of
this right as we come you know it's we
want it to be positive it's positive
here that's all good right so this looks
correct right that looks good
but sine theta was positive here it's
not positive here right do you see where
this point is this point is negative x
right that's positive x metrics and this
is negative x so we have to negate that
one to put this point in the right place
as it goes around right so we end up
with the y axis is actually just the
same computation as the x axis we can
just flip the terms and negate one of
them that's it right really simple now
here's the thing
you can also directly plug and chug this
I never remember them I always have to
look them up but if you plug in your
trig identities if you remember these
from grade school your trig identities
should tell you that cosine of theta
plus 90 is negative sign and that sine
theta plus 90 is cosine theta right that
those are actually trig identities you
probably would have learned and if you
happen to remember them you wouldn't
have even had to look at the diagram you
could just say up algebraically I could
just substitute in I know that becomes
this and I know that becomes this right
so that's another way to attack it last
piece of interest here because we're in
2d I want to talk about one more thing
so there's the concept of the perp
operator right and no that does not mean
perpetrator the perpendicular operator
is the operator which takes a 2d vector
and produces a vector that's
perpendicular to it right what we have
essentially done here is done the perp
operator to the x axis because the perp
operator is just an operator that says
okay if I have some X Y right I am just
going to output the y coordinate negated
and the x coordinate the same but
flipped order right the exact same thing
we did here right swap the components
negate the X right and what this does is
this actually creates the perpendicular
for any vector in the space because no
matter what vector
I draw right I can always say oh I know
that it has a why I know that it has an
X let me just interpret it's X off the
the the let me just interpret sorry why
am i I got so far today without doing it
remember yesterday I was drawing my X's
and Y's in the in different paces all
the time I just did it again it has an x
and a y there we go I can interpret its
y coordinate in the negative x-direction
right
I can interpret its x-coordinate in the
y-direction right this way
and produce a 90 degree angled vector
that's the same length as the previous
vector right the lengths are the same
but that's pointing in exactly the
perpendicular direction and this is very
handy right that allows us to quickly
generate perpendicular vectors to any
vector that we have in the plane and it
just works right it's super nice and so
that's what we actually did there but
you could see how we kind of constructed
it and you can also see how it works
over the signs of cosine so that means
that essentially all we have to do when
we want to create a rotated basis right
if we want to create a rotation a
rotated basis of theta right it is very
straightforward
all we have to do is our x axis becomes
cosine theta sine theta and our Y axis
is just the perp of the x axis right
that's it we already know this is length
one because well cosine squared theta
plus sine squared theta right Square
rooted equals one so we know that that's
true that's sort of a separate thing so
we don't have to worry about their
lengths we know their likes will already
be one and that is a trivial way to
produce a rotated basis if we want to
scale that basis we just multiply our
axes by whatever we wanted to multiply
them by right all good all right let's
see where we're at five forty five so we
got time to actually just do this now
that we've sort of basically done the
the lesson that's know don't open that
thing the wrong command prompt all right
there we go so let's go into the code
let's suppose that we want to create one
of these little rotating doodads here
right and we want to see it work
properly
all we have to do let's introduce just a
totally synthetic render function that
literally will have no use in our game
but just something maybe a club tripod I
don't know it's not really a 5 - yes -
so let's see axis marker I don't know
coordinate system something I don't know
I'm not sure what to call it I have no
idea but let's do exactly what we just
said we're gonna have an origin we're
gonna have an x-axis and we're gonna
have a y-axis right and we just want to
draw them okay that's all we want to do
we just want to draw them so if I wanted
to do that right I need to just add a
little thing here to you know add in
coordinate system like so and then I can
add something to my render group that
will allow me to push one of those onto
you know onto my um my render stack
right so here we go I'm gonna push one
of these coordinate systems render entry
coordinate system and assuming that it
came back okay so I can assign its
origin to something right its x-axis
something Y access to something Y axis x
axis oops that's not good x-axis and v3
x axis you know what might as well stick
a color in there why not right that way
we can have a couple of different ones
on the screen and know which one we're
looking at again so origin x axis y axis
okay
should work fine now hopefully if we run
this well actually I guess we've gotta
make one first we should get an
assertion because we haven't handled
putting anything to handle drawing it
but let's go ahead and actually put one
in there first I'm gonna in our game
state structure right I'm gonna add just
for the time being a little thing that
we can play with which is sort of our
you know our angle or whatever and maybe
I'll put in our scale as well you know
what I could do I could just do time
let's do that for fun profit all right
so in here down at the very end before
we before we render everything I'm gonna
say that our game state time is going to
be equal to our it's going to increment
by our D DT for frame right so we can do
stuff at that for now I won't actually
do anything with it I'll just say that
we've got an origin oh you know what I
just forgot to I don't know why I've got
this we're not actually in 3d right now
we're in 2d here we go
it's not gonna be able to draw a
three-dimensional stuff yet that's
that's a bit of a problem alright so yes
if I have my origin right I have my
x-axis and I am just hung up on on three
dimensions today and there we go and
y-axis P - yeah and so if I now do that
coordinate system system call and I push
my origin x-axis y-axis and whatever the
color happens to be let's go ahead and
make a nice yellow there that should set
us up for success now it should again
hopefully our renderer will stop on this
and say hey wait a minute I don't know
how to draw that that's the hope and
since we've never tested that let's
let's actually verify that that's true
one would hope what what is happening
what what is what has happened people
why is our code why is our code hosed
what have we done we are in the middle
of rendering groups of what what is
happen I have no idea what's happening
right now I'm gonna set thing to find
out we've totally broken it so that's
good you know sometimes you have to
break everything what did I did I do odd
there there's the clear we should get to
when we don't know and then we should
hit our invalid default case now but
apparently not I guess are invalid
default case is not working which is a
bit odd to say the least let me see what
our invalid default case says and made
dot H all right probably a platformer
huh valid default case thought code path
that kind of looks right should not have
a semicolon after it but that's not
really an issue yeah that should stop us
hmm well I can't say I know why that's
happening but what I would like to do to
debug that is let it hit that guy sooner
let's put the coordinate system so that
it happens immediately upon startup that
way we will see what happens when we
immediately step into it if that makes
sense so I don't have to kind of loop
through everything else so it should why
does it not hit it's clear so clear
should not have have been the first
thing in the in the render state am i
right like we should have had a thing
where it was where it was pushing the
coordinate system so I'm gonna go ahead
and take a look at that buffer and see
why that's not happening let's go into
handmade render group just make sure
because
pushing it render entry coordinate
system right so the type of that should
not be clear it should be coordinate
system so the first thing in on our on
our stack should be one of these
coordinate systems so let's see why it's
not alright come in here let's take a
look at our render group render group
the render groups got the push buffer
base address right in the the first
thing in it is a 0 that doesn't make any
sense to me oh because we're gonna feel
ground chunk alright forgot about that
so yeah I guess we have to actually run
into here let's try that one more time
alright now I can see what it is so how
is our push buffer base still showing
that it's that the first thing in it is
it clear someone explain that to me
somebody explain that to me
alright well I guess we'll just have to
see where our push isn't working
probably a bug that I made so here we go
we'll make the render group there we go
and look at the push buffer base step in
to coordinate system right this is gonna
make it
Oh although don't actually need this
quite step into that but thank you
alright why is this not why am I not
able to step into this coordinate system
all right so it thinks it pushed a
render element on there right it
certainly appears to believe that it did
that and the push buffer base has
actually done exactly what it should
have done which is set it to three
it sets the ah yeah there we go
asleep at the switch oh it's been a long
day people it has been a long day
I forgot to put my little header in here
there we go so that's the problem yeah
at all these guys have to have a header
for now because we don't really have
anything in particular I should probably
get rid of that because that's not
actually necessary and it's just prone
to error as you just saw me make when
you forget about what you're doing
because really we don't need this header
value to be there I'm just gonna say go
ahead and remove that so I don't make
that mistake again remove the header
because we don't actually need the
header to be listed in these guys that
was just kind of a short-term thing
that's just kind of sloppy I don't want
to remove it right now because I'd like
to finish what we were doing but suffice
to say yeah totally not necessary and I
would prefer to not have that be a
potential source of books it's just it's
just there's no need for it basically
I'll split that way so yeah we'll fix
that tomorrow but because I'd rather not
go through it right now so let's go
ahead and put our coordinate system back
in there so now hopefully we will get a
thing that stops us and says that that
it doesn't recognize the thing that it
was doing now why of course there we go
it's because we haven't put in a case
for our coordinate system so all we
should have to do now is put in a case
for our coordinate system and yeah and
then we should see it show up so in here
I'll say all right we've got oops we've
got under entry coordinate system and
all I want to do here is is grab that
coordinate system out
and I guess you know well this is in
pixels right so whatever that coordinate
system is it's actually going to be in
pixels I don't know if we want to try
translating it out let's let's I guess
leave it let's do a little bit of
translating it out what do you what do
you think about that you think that's
okay I'm thinking that that maybe that
we just do just the screen Center amount
well you know what no all right we'll
just do it in pixels so that we can see
it directly because that seems I guess
like more in the spirit of things all
right so if I do draw a rectangle I
basically need to draw some little
rectangles so that we can see this stuff
and so entry color our entry color G
entry color B right so there's my color
values I then need to have some kind of
a dimension let's say that our dimension
is going to be you know a four by four
pixel square or whatever or I guess in
this case it would be a five by five
pixels and then I will create the
p-value by taking the origin right and
now we should I think that actually
should show up although we need to
actually define it to be something that
will actually be visible in pixels so
the origin let's let's put it right at
the screen Center now and we'll say that
our X x-axis is maybe like a hundred
pixels a hundred pixels even though
we're not using those yet right so let's
see if we should be able to see a little
pixel for this and there it is right
there you can kind of see it it's
underneath me although the colors value
seems wrong which I'm not exactly sure
why that is
yeah
mmm draw a rectangle color our G and B I
feel like that should have been right
but it looked like the color was wrong
to me not the end of the world we'll
deal with that in a second but alright
so if I was to take this and then draw
the rest of those guys as well like the
X in the other two axes right all I need
to do is create the other points the way
that I said I was start at the origin
and go out along the x axis so here we
go x axis in this particular case I
don't actually need a scale for it so
that's fine and then similarly if I go
out along the y axis that'll be a point
that's one unit along that axis as well
that should give me basically that sort
of tripod of points that are 100 pixels
apart you can see them there I just
don't understand why their colors are
that way that's kind of bizarre don't
you think super weird
yeah very strange so let me check out
what Y the colors are what they are the
entry color are G and bees getting
pasture I'm gonna I'm just gonna set a
breakpoint there and see what those
colors are actually doing set to let's
take a look so what's our entry color
entry color is all zeros all right
that doesn't seem good well that would
do it about two asleep sat the switches
today there we go
okay there's our little coordinate
system right pretty straightforward so
if we want to do exactly what I said on
the blackboard now it's it's really
pretty trivial right I said what I
wanted to do let's let's let's make the
length of this be something that we pull
out on the side so there's our scaling
right of the axis let's make this be a
cosine sign and we'll make this y-axis
we'll just make that be the exact perp
the the perp that I said before if we
perpendicular to the y-axis oops right
now I don't actually know if we ever put
in sine and cosine did we I think we did
that we didn't so we have some some math
to do oh well you know what we might
have it in our in lines did we have it
our in lines no where where's our square
root for example right we have a
intrinsics square root do we have a
cosine we do have a cosine okay so if I
do a cosine of some angle right then all
I have to do is just say well okay let
me base that angle off of the time value
that's going up there and then we can
sort of have you know a rotating basis
vector or at least we should have a
rotating basis vector right and there
you can see it rotating around exactly
like we said it would on the blackboard
now let me go ahead and and sort of do
this live so you can kind of see what
happens as you play around with it right
there's that rotation so if I wanted to
write I can change the the size of this
coordinate system right by changing
whatever that scale value is there right
you can kind of see I can make it much
smaller and then I guess smaller
rotating one I can also make it much
larger than it was before and then I'll
get a much larger rotating axis system
right and again any now anything I
encode in this axis system that gets
pulled out using that formula that I was
talking about before will will still be
encoded properly right and so that's
really all there is to it yeah I can
also introduce non-uniform scaling by
scaling up you know whatever the the
y-axis is so now there's one well that's
actually me too large isn't it well be
off the screen now we have like a you
know one that's more elongated right and
you can imagine us taking any sort of
points that are in here and having those
be rotated and scaled as well again just
by taking them and interpreting them in
that coordinate system and so just a
show kind of an example of what I mean
by that right you can see let's say that
in the render group right we just had
some points that were encoded in that
axis right this is purely synthetic just
again as a thing to show for educational
purposes let's say there were some
points right let's say there were maybe
I don't know let's say there's 16 points
or something like that right and I'm
gonna go ahead and say that we'll just
render those points using that formula
that I said previously right so if I
come in here to my render group and
inside here I just render those points
directly right so I say all right for
you know P and X equal 0 P and X is less
than that a ray count of whatever the
entry points array has in it I then say
all right the entry points whatever it
is that's the new P coordinates that I'm
that I'm using there right so if I want
to generate P here I do exactly that
formula that we wrote on the whiteboard
I do I'm sorry the blackboard I do P dot
X times the x axis plus P dot y times
the y axis so start at the origin walk
out the x coordinate along the x axis
walk out the y coordinate along the y
axis and that's my new point right and
then I'll draw a rectangle there so that
we can see it right make sense
pretty straightforward so all I need to
do is actually initialize some points in
there and what I'll do here is I'll just
do a really simple grid for us to to use
there so let's say I take you know an X
of 0 I'll do X is less than 1.0 I'll do
X plus equals 0
point two five right I guess I should
say less than or equal to and I'll do
one here as well so we can have a lie as
well and then I'll just say you know all
right we've got P and X equals zero and
we'll say that our coordinate system I
will need to actually be able to get one
of these what is it render and
coordinate system there it is crying
system we'll just grab that out and
we'll say okay points P and X plus plus
equals V 2 X Y right so now we're
literally just making a grid like we're
making the X's go along quarters and the
Y's go along quarters right now I
introduce the notion here that I would
return that coordinate system so I got
to kind of actually do that right so
that it can get filled out by the
calling code return entry so and if I do
that now I should get that little grid
right or not I should get that little
grid apparently I don't get that little
grid V 2 points am I actually properly
initializing that yes p + x + plus y
equals zero y lesson that's yeah just
trying to race the clock here I got it
only only about five minutes left before
I got to stop so sorry for the
abbreviated miss of it all that looks
correct so then whereas my rendering
p.m. next weekend points B twos P or P
dot x times entry x-axis P dot y that
should've done it why did that not do it
let's let's take a look so let's go oh
wow it'd be nice if I actually used
index there we go so
get rid of that that is not what I would
have expected at all to say the least
what did I I must have initialized my
point slightly wrong as well hold on one
second there we go
we're almost there just got a debug a
few more things my X and my Y let me
take a break point there this is kind of
a sloppy way to do this I had to do it
kind of quickly so let's see two five
five seven five one right initializing
all the points properly there we go oh
but that's too many that's the problem
right that's one too many
yeah my bad that's more than what would
fit right because you can't actually
yeah so I'll have to do it basically
just in in the first portion I'm only
allowed 16 points I was I don't know why
but that's what that's the amount I did
so there now we can actually see sort of
a more a more accurate version of sort
of what the space looks like right and
you can kind of see essentially whatever
I do and you know what I'm gonna I'm
going to turn off the the recomputation
of ground buffers as well so you know we
had this executable reloaded thing we
don't actually need to do that for what
we're doing now so I'm gonna leave this
running and I'm just gonna go ahead and
play around with those those axes so
remember the only thing that we're doing
in here is we're just interpreting those
points based on the coordinate system
we're starting at the origin we're
walking out along the x-axis by whatever
the x-coordinate is and we're walking
out along the y-axis by whatever the
y-coordinate is right so now I'm just
gonna change the two axes that's all I'm
gonna do and I'm not going to touch what
the point definition is the point
definitions gonna stay the same right so
let's say that I was two
we shrink the y-axis so that it's like
the same scale is the x-axis right you
can see that now I get back to a square
right or I could sort of blow it out
significantly more and you see that it
stretches out more right another thing
that I could do is I could and and also
you'll notice that they're always
rotating around properly right another
thing that I could do is just get
totally wild with it and say you know
what I'm not gonna make these be
perpendicular
instead I'm actually going to make these
be skew right so I'm gonna take the
angle and I'm gonna add you know some
some amount do we have pie yet no if we
have pie let's just find out here I
don't think we've ever covered this on
handmade here do we have pie yes we do
have a pie I guess I'm not sure I'm not
sure if we have pie or not well I'll
just say 1.5 1/2 how's that is that
better
hopefully that's better why am i not why
am i collapsing why is that producing
the same value is that odd to you oh
because it's a hundred there we go all
right so if I was to make this be just
some offset angle so I'm producing
another angle and I just make it be
something that's not 90 degrees anymore
right you can see that I can actually
skew all of the points that are defined
in that system as well right I can be as
ridiculous as I want to be and by
morphing those axes right I'm gonna
morph all the points that are inside
them and similarly I can make something
that's you know sort of smooshed up in
addition to right and so that's really
all there is to understanding the
rotation and the scaling transforms it's
just taking those axes and bending them
and all the points because you're
constructing the points by moving along
those axes there you go
similarly the origin is the same you
know if I introduce some amount of
wiggle to that right all the points
obviously we know they will get
displaced in in much that same way right
so
I can adjust their position as well so
with origin X Y axis it allows me to
have a tremendous amount of flexibility
with how I'm placing my points we
haven't actually talked about how we're
gonna render stuff yet in that space but
we at least we now know kind of or can
see very simply how those bases come
together right so I'm gonna leave it
there because I'm just about out of time
here
so I'm gonna go ahead and say let's go
to the Q&amp;A so we can cover any questions
that we might have and then tomorrow we
can sort of clean this stuff up and you
know I'll put it to doing here to do KC
let's add a a perk operator right and
off we go
ah any questions any questions this is
kind of a weird thing here sorry I'd say
I'm in these weird points this is this
is completely ridiculous right here but
I just needed something quickly so we
could show how things were interpreted
in that space
so if you have questions please prefix
them with Q :
so I can read them but yeah chat is a
long time behind the video really okay I
don't know why that is was there some
kind of a drop frames no I guess it's
just twitch twitch is a little laggy
if there are no questions then you know
we'll be done early well of course I
took ten minutes of extra time but
because I started like 10 minutes late
do you usually worry a lot about naming
schemes you always seem to choose a good
enough name and move on no III don't
worry about naming schemes hardly at all
as long as something seems reasonable
enough I think that's fine you can
always change it later so it's no big
deal right John I don't know how many
times I have to tell you this but that
can't possibly be the variable how could
it be the variable no one has ever seen
a variable I mean like it's not even
remotely plausible that that could be
the variable it's just a spinning little
diamond thing how can you draw so fast
to use the draw pad and pen yeah I have
like a little Wacom graphite like the
little or graphite or whatever it is
Carl and Oh bloom I only partly followed
but it seemed fairly easy to get the
basic rotation up and running I'm
wondering how much more work it will be
to start rendering textures by sampling
them across the plane it's not much work
we can do it pretty pretty well so also
John I feel like if the variable did
exist it probably exists in between the
points that are rotating here somewhere
like like the variable could be in there
and we just can't see it you know what I
mean because it's invisible
I do filter on cue colons when there are
enough questions but there aren't that
many so I I flip back to the chat and
just see what's going on when there
aren't a lot of questions when there are
a lot of queue : questions Nick stop is
it possible to do realloc with memory
arena
um it like it depends what you mean by
that right so I guess what I would say
is realloc by definition is allowed to
return you a different memory block so
technically you could easily implement
that with memory arena by just
allocating a new space at the end of the
arena and returning that as the pointer
right but if you're talking about
realloc as in allowing memory to grow
then no because the arena is always
tightly packed that's kind of the point
of it so in that sense you'd never grow
a memory block in the arena unless it
was the one at the end right our
parametric's and polar functions going
to be used later on well you know origin
systems like this are basically like I
mean that's that's sort of what they are
they're like uber versions of polar
functions right
so you basically defined stuff and then
you can rotate it however you want
polar functions themselves are not
typically that useful unless you're
trying to construct a basis because
usually you're trying to do like we
constructed our bases with polar
coordinates right I mean that's that's
polar coordinates right there folks
right so you know you don't usually
think in terms of polar coordinates in
that sense they're parametric's I mean
again everything we've done so far is in
parametric right so so I guess it
depends if you're talking about
something specific
well sub-pixel positioning and
anti-aliasing be part of the software
render in the exploration phase actually
we're not really doing the exploration
phase for the render right now we're
actually just doing the renderer so
gonna do anti-aliasing and positioning
and we'll just do it so it'll be done
see here
it's like there's no more questions
probably not seeing any more questions
on programming or on the programming
we're doing I should say this could be
part of the lag as you were saying
though maybe people are just about to
ask a bunch of questions and I just
can't see them this thing's kind of
funny sitting there like that I feel
like we should make the the size of it
proportional as well so it's like you
know oh it's like a hundred but it's
plus twenty five point zero times you
know cosine angle 0.1 F times angle or
something right
so that you know it kind of shrinks and
grows like so right I mean that's really
the way you want to go right
I do like it I like the the description
of a Christmas tree Triforce that's
pretty funny
people think that's trippy you can keep
going right I mean you can just go nuts
with that if you want to right I think
we ran out of questions too but we have
yeah like basically vector bobs is what
we're doing right here time-dependent
color oh man all right well you know if
you want it you got it I'm here I'm here
for your amusement right off we go
better
I mean basically like when we add
particle systems if you guys think this
is fun like particle systems I guess
people are gonna go nuts because that's
like that's what particle systems are
it's all this ridiculousness right so
yeah yeah and hand-made 4k demo I'm not
qualified to do I just don't know the 4k
tricks Fabien could could help out with
that that's where Fabien comes in he
should he should show us how to do a 4k
demo so he needs more dots all right
look we're not gonna yeah let's not this
is just as meant for demo purposes we're
not gonna rathole from that when we get
to particle systems we can rattle on
particle systems for a little while but
that's that's probably not the best
thing to be doing at the moment so let's
leave that be for now all right all
right I am going to oh you got that's
the variable hit is now quit the
variable all right all right
let's let's call it done for the day I
think that's good enough I think that's
roughly where we want to be for that
kind of ridiculous why is that happening
all right all right well anyway if you
do want to watch it forever girl and Oh
bloom I will upload the source code as
it is right now so that you can download
it and just leave it playing on your
machine forever and there you go all
right I will wrap it up here thank you
everyone for joining me for another
ridiculous episode of handmade hero that
little weird pulsating thing was pretty
freaky
I hope you've enjoyed it I know I have
if you would like to follow along at
home with the source code and make your
own modifications to the little flashing
weird dot thingy you can go to handmade
hero org and pre-order the game it comes
with the source code so that you can
play around with it yourself you can
also go to our forums and ask questions
or use the resources there there's ports
to Linux and Mac if you want to follow
along with other platforms or if you
want to use the annotated episode guide
to catch up with stuff we also have a
patreon if you want to support the video
series you could subscribe there
and there's a tweet bot that tweets the
schedule if you want to know when we're
gonna be live that's the place to go so
I hope to see you guys all tomorrow same
time same place
5:00 p.m. Pacific Daylight Time here on
twitch when we will actually start
implementing I guess we might we might
just go for it and start implementing
rotated and scaled textures just so we
can kind of see how that's starting to
work but there's probably a lot of
Blackboard work we got to do so we
probably won't probably take a couple
days so we'll see how it goes but anyway
hopefully you will come back tomorrow
and join me for that I'd love to see it
if not have a fabulous Thursday all the
same I assume it's Thursday is it
Tuesday what day is today it's Wednesday
have a fabulous Thursday all the same
and I'll see you on the Internet
take it easy everyone