hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show we code a complete game
live on stream today we have to start
looking at our lighting system to see
how we can improve its actual runtime
performance and we have a lot of ways
that we can do that but we you know
we're only just starting out what we did
was we took the the first step of making
it so that the light tracing that we
were doing before can be done via a
spatial hierarchy now so already just
from that one change which is a
performance oriented change but it
wasn't really ever measured in terms of
performance or anything like that it's
not really a targeted optimization it
was more just okay we know we're gonna
need a spatial Harkey to begin working
with these things in some way that will
speed them up but even just from that we
already got to the place where an entire
level sized chunk of the game being lit
entire the whole thing being lit with
full ray tracing on right now is already
doing reasonably well now it's not quite
representative so we have a little bit
more we have more stress we should put
on this eventually and so we're not
really quite done knowing exactly how
slow it would be it'd probably be again
a bit more slow the reason for that is
because these trees here are currently
not being lit when we turn on lighting
for like the trees and entities we're
gonna you know I don't know if we're
quite double but we'd be more up in the
200 milliseconds per frame so obviously
we're only getting something like five
frames a second probably in reality here
which isn't bad at the outset but
obviously it's a long way from where we
need to be so what we need to do now is
start looking at how we're gonna make
this stuff work in terms of running at a
reasonable frame rate now there's a
couple things as you can see here one is
that we really need to probably call
what we're actually lighting and what
we're not so if you look at how much of
the world is being simulated we simulate
much more of the
at a time then we really need to see the
reason for that is we wanted to
potentially be able to have it so that
when you're looking at a particular area
of the game a wider region would be
simulated so that stuff that happens off
at least one screen to the side would
still potentially affect what you were
doing so for example if a monster was
chasing you from the previous screen and
you hopped on to this screen we aren't
sure yet
as a Sara Lee but we were considering
that maybe we want that to be something
where the monster could follow you over
and if all we ever did was when you move
to another screen we just only simulate
the screen you're looking at you can't
have really anything dynamic like that
occur so the idea here was that if the
world consisted of a path that looked
like this that you would Traverse maybe
we still you know simulate some number
of screens to the side because the
simulation probably isn't very expensive
at the end of the day and we can afford
to do more of it okay so that's really
all we were thinking of doing here and
given that it makes sense to have all
this stuff pulled into the system what
doesn't make sense however is us
actually processing these things for
lighting because what you can see is
that the lighting that happens over here
is never really gonna affect the
lighting that happens over here and even
if it was gonna affect it we don't have
to capture that right we're still gonna
get good lighting by just doing here
that the users never gonna notice the
error because they're never gonna even
know there was a light over here really
so in terms of visible error in the
system that's just not something that
realistically is going to occur and so
at that point it really doesn't make
sense to have this much stuff in there
so what we would like to do is more
aggressively call what is and is what is
and is not a part of the lighting
solution so that we're not even lighting
this stuff here and that will drop our
frame I'm down quite a bit just in and
of itself so I think we want to do that
before we do anything else for sure but
then in addition to that we're gonna
need more techniques here and those
techniques will probably revolve around
how we build the spatial hierarchy and
how we process the spatial hierarchy
because right now we're doing
the simplest possible thing which is
just building a basic spatial hierarchy
and recasting against it still using the
exact same methods we were using before
with no modification so I think we can
improve on that quite a bit anyway and
we're gonna take a look at that as we go
forward so let's start with introducing
some basic calling to the lighting
system so that the lighting system is
not actually going to process anybody
who's too far outside of the lighting
bounds so what I'm gonna do here is I'm
going to go ahead and I'm gonna load up
the handmade hero project and we're
gonna go and look at the rendering right
here so what we want to do is we want to
go ahead and and take a look at where
we're actually pushing this lighting on
and what I would say is when we do a
push cube to push lighting on I think
what we want to do is get rid of any
lighting that isn't inside a light bound
and I think we want to do that right
away so meaning all of this work that
we're doing to push on lighting in the
first place
while that may get simpler over time as
we optimize this more it's still work
and in so the two ways that we could
attack this problem one by just never
pushing on stuff that is outside the
light bounds and two by calling things
afterwards by looking at everything and
only processing things that are in the
light bounds I think we want to go with
the one that just never puts them into
the lighting solution at all and the
reason that I think that's a good idea
is because that way it just never even
generates the data traffic right if we
can call earlier rather than later that
seems like a better solution so I'm
going to start by trying calling early
and if we find that there's problems
with calling early and we really need to
call later for some reason we can always
switch to that I think that's how I
would like to do it so in here we see we
have light index store what I'd like to
do is say well when we have light index
store going on what I want to do is say
okay if we weren't going to use this
light because it's out of bounds what I
could do is just check right at that
head end we know that if I don't enter
this light index store branch then it
doesn't push the
lighting because we already have the
ability to specify that you don't want
lighting when you put something down
here right so all I have to really do is
say if I wasn't going to get any
lighting on this guy because he's out of
range whatever it is we could just put a
nest inside here we could just put a
nest inside here like so and what I
could do is check the bounds like in
light bounds here if we're not in the
light bounds then I can just overwrite
that light index door with zeros here so
basically when this is being passed in
you can kind of see here we have
lighting next door it's being passed in
as a zero here we know we need to sort
of clear that out light index the light
count here as we have it right is six
times four it's 24 of these right so
what we can do here is say alright if
we're gonna do we can just do with zero
size here and say we're gonna do you
know six times 24 times sighs oops
nice start late an indexed door
we can just say look we're gonna clear
out all of that so if anybody was
previously getting lighting at this
location and now they've moved out we're
just gonna clear it you don't get
lighting anymore sorry my friend okay
and we may need to work on that and make
that more efficient depending on the
circumstances and blah blah blah but for
the most part right this is all we
really need to do all of this stuff here
is gonna get cleaned up a little bit
because remember we're gonna have to put
in a little like light slot allocator
for a number of reasons and so that's
gonna be sort of a separate issue there
anyway so this is what we're doing and
so what we need to do now is just figure
out a way to test whether it's inside
the lighting bounds and what I want to
do for that is you remember the render
group has lighting enabled what I'd like
to do is in addition to say lighting
enabled I'd like to have a
select rectangle three in here which is
like light bounds and so what I want to
do is say once we get one of these cubes
we effectively have knowledge of its min
max right we know where it is because we
build that right here right so if we
wanted to we can build a rectangle and
we could say rectangle min max 3 assume
we have one of these something like that
I could specify the min corner in the
max corner and then I could say if you
know intersects at all the cube bounds
with the what did we call this in this
routine group group with the light
bounds so if they intersect then we know
that will push a light on if they don't
intersect then we're not going to
regardless of whether they told us we
want lighting or not that light bounce
is gonna you know magically make the
lights disappear if they're outside okay
so and remember when I say light bounce
I don't literally mean the boundary for
things that are illuminated I mean the
boundary for things that participate in
the lighting solutions so even just
opaque objects that do not emit light
but are receiving light those are also
discarded so the only things that go
into the lighting solution are ones that
are in this box so what I need to do
here is I need to make sure we have
these functions I don't know if we've
done much with rectangle three eyes so
let's take a look we've got a few
functions here let's see what they are
we have the rectum in max which we need
we have a point test so here's what we
need rectangles intersect so in here we
just need to say all right if the
rectangles intersect then it's inside
and off we go so if we were to run this
it's if we were to run this now
what I should get hopefully what's
happened here I was definitely not
expecting that did I clear too much of
my light oh this just stores the first
one never mind
that's actually great light and next
door can now just be cleared that way I
thought we had I thought it stored the
whole range it doesn't that's fantastic
so what should happen now is we should
get no lighting on most of these things
right or all of them because we have a
light bound that doesn't actually appear
anywhere right there there is no light
bound at the moment so what I should be
able to do is I should now be able to
set that light bound to be something
relatively small that that fits on the
screen and we should be able to see the
lighting only occurring inside that
boundary right that that's what we
should be able to see so when we call
enable lighting what I want to do is
have a rectangle three here that's like
all right the rectangle three is the
lighting bounds and when we do that
switching of it on I'm just gonna set it
there so the light bounds are set here I
also want to just take a look here
I assume the way this works is that
lighting if yeah there it is it'll just
clear that out like so
so if Lighting's not unable to just
ignores that that part of the function I
don't know if that's what we want to do
it eventually maybe we want to clear the
thing as well
I'm not sure how that monster work
eventually oops but we'll deal with that
a little bit later okay so if we want to
just have the same thing as we were
doing before we have the simulation
boundary we could pass there and that
would do lighting on everything right so
the sim bounds for example I believe are
all we would need to do the entire world
that's what we were doing before so if I
pass those I should see everything in
the world get lit now and let's see that
looks about right you know so you're
getting getting all of the stuff in
there we Stephanie still have some bugs
by the way like I remember looking at
this at the end of last stream there's a
couple things that look like they're not
getting processed properly so that's
crummy summer after you have to look at
but anyway when we do enable lighting
now that we passed those same bounds we
can choose to shrink those down to be
much more tight right so they don't have
to be the same size as everything else
so for example the standard room
dimension which tells us roughly where
we're at if I wanted to I could set the
sim bounds I could take that standard
room dimension and I could change how
we're computing the size of it right so
I could say that the light bounds for
example like so are going to just be you
know smaller a smaller size increase I
could also say that since you can see
the whole Z range I could make it so
that the whole Z range does participate
in it so for example the light Minzy
would equal the Simmons E and the max as
well something like this right so we
have the ability to change that now and
we should be able to now more tightly
bound where the light computation is
actually going to occur so if I run the
game you can see we got quite a speed
increase just from doing that because
hey there's a lot less stuff actually
involved in the light
now so let's pull back and we can see
now like all of this stuff out here no
longer participates in the lighting
solution and doesn't need to right
because this is plenty what's getting
simulated here there's definitely no
need to simulate anything more than this
range in fact we could probably do less
so we could probably even go a little
bit further along those lines and say
here that maybe we only need 1.0 times
the standard room to mention there and
that would be sufficient so if we take a
look at this now we're running at a good
30 frames per second they're not quite
60 but you can see that the lighting
solution kind of stops there
so remember looking at it here that's
probably reasonably good it's not quite
right but so we can also see now I'm
glad we can see this bug a little bit
better so if I run the game now one
thing that you can see is I'm getting
buggy behavior from this light so it's
affecting stuff that's not it's it's
sort of getting some weird light
wraparound behavior so we definitely
have some bugs in here and how we're
processing the lighting that we didn't
have before when we move to the spatial
hierarchy we're getting some kind of a
weird like spillover effect that's
happening there so we need to go check
that down as well it's gonna be
something kind of separate that has to
do with our enumeration that has nothing
to do with the light bound stuff we just
put in it was in there at the end of
last dream before we ever start started
mucking with that but you can kind of
see it happening right like you can see
that this stuff over here should
definitely not have this light source
involved with it at all but it's getting
it right and so what's happening there
probably is we've got some index
behavior that's going wrong or something
something weird is happening where
somebody who should be getting light
over here or some computation that would
have been happening over here is
actually writing to lights that are over
here or something like this right so
that's you know what we're looking at
there now the other thing I want to
point out here is this just that change
by itself though considering a smaller
region has already gotten us into
striking distance in terms of
running this at a fast speed and so if
we were to imagine moving this to the
GPU or multi-threading this on the cpu
where we're basically done right this is
fast enough now so we'll have to double
check because we'll have to actually see
I don't know at the moment for example I
don't know what the speed is like in
terms of if we actually have everything
running but should be running and
furthermore as you can kind of see
moving here slows us down because now
there's more stuff on either side of us
so we really need a good test case we
should probably make one where there's
stuff all around us so we can see how we
would actually be getting like this this
puts us back into kind of a not-so-good
range right so when we get more stuff
happening we still looks like we have
more work to do right so we still have a
little bit of a ways to go there so we
probably need to do a little more work
with that etc etc but again still think
we're in pretty good shape here because
we haven't really begun to really push
on this stuff performance wise and so I
think we're you know probably not going
to have too much trouble getting this to
somewhere we want to be but like I said
first things first we got to start
debugging the stuff and we haven't even
really drawn what's going on in any way
yet so we don't really even know how our
spatial partition is working we did kind
of a a pretty arbitrary thing to get our
space book to our spatial partition
working and we don't even really know if
we built one that's any good so
obviously we've got more work to do
there as well okay so the first thing
I'm going to do now that we've fixed
that and we've got the ability to sort
of limit our lighting to thing only
things that are potentially going to
actually be seen by the player or
noticed by the player which is the only
thing we really need lighting for what
I'd like to do now is go into the
lighting calculations and start to
figure out how I could debug these
because they're gonna be very hard to
debug because lighting is a very
nebulous sort of thing it's it's pretty
hard to know what's going on there so
we're gonna have to think of some
creative ways that we can debug this
excuse me I'm a bit stuffy today as is
often the case I think I'm sort of
allergic to everything but only slightly
not in the like I almost died from a bee
sting kind of away but in the like I'm
always a little bit stuffy alright so
what we want to do here is start to take
a look at what our lighting is actually
doing and figure out how we could start
to debug some of the pieces of it now
there's two distinct aspects of this
lighting that can have bugs and we need
to come up with ways of visualizing both
of them probably if we want to do this
well the first thing that can have a bug
is the the placement I'm gonna do the
opposite of the thing I did yesterday by
the way my feet are now too hot this is
the eternal problem so I have to take my
socks off in order to cool them down
remember yesterday they were too cold
and I de put socks on well today I had
to do the absent anyway so what we need
to do is we need to figure out ways to
attack two different kinds of bugs the
first bug that we have is we've got this
system where lighting elements are
enumerated relative to certain like
larger cube elements right so we have
cubes they're not really cubes they're
boxes they don't have to be equal with
height and depth so we've got these
boxes and the boxes are the things that
actually get raycast so when we're a
cast we just ray cast against a box when
we hit the box though we then go ahead
and look at what lighting like
individual light sample points scattered
around the box on the surface of the box
although I guess they don't really even
have to be on the surface of the box if
we don't want them to be they could even
be set apart from the box or other weird
things like this but the lighting points
that are for the moment anyway scattered
along the surface of the box those
lighting points
are enumerated relative to the box so
every box has a list by saying what the
first light sample point is and then
there's a count of how many light sample
points there are that process itself is
one that can have bugs in it separately
right so that that alone the
correspondence of boxes to sample points
that could be buggy
it can't be so buggy that it just
doesn't work at all because we are
seeing some lighting that makes sense so
it's got to be at least somewhat working
but it could have plenty of subtle bugs
like let's say maybe it writes too far
over and so we're filling more than the
number of light sample points in blah
blah blah we wouldn't get crashes in
those scenarios because we pre allocate
a big block for our lighting samples and
we don't use all of it so we could do a
number of simple things already we could
start to assert bounds and make sure
that we don't overwrite and something so
we can already start to put some things
into place that would try to make sure
we're not doing anything weird there and
stuff like that so we can start to
attack that problem just are we properly
corresponding our lights with their
boxes and so on is that happening at all
and are there bugs there so that's one
source of bugs another source of bugs is
the back assignment of them so that's a
source of bugs just the process like the
actual handling of those lights have
what's inside the letting routine right
you know I should probably write these
down because I'm about to enumerate a
bunch of them and then we don't want to
forget them as soon as I say them so
let's just go ahead and pop Milton open
open here
so what we want to do here is we want to
say one you know our cubes or I'll use
the term boxes boxes and sample points
correctly attributed to each other in
the lighting solution to our rendered
elements so the quads picking the
correct sample points because remember
once we compute the lighting solution we
now have a set of lighting points that
are scattered throughout the world and
there's a number of different ways we
can use those letting sample points one
way to use those letting sample points
is to do something like putting them in
a voxel looking them spatially inside
the actual rasterizer right
and I decided I didn't really want to do
that because it's a little bit too
error-prone in my opinion what happens
when you do that is you have to have
good ways of knowing whether or not a
sample point is actually valid for the
surface that you're talking about and a
lot of times you it becomes very
difficult to be able to determine
whether it is or it isn't and there's
entire sets of graphics research papers
believe me tons of them based on
lighting reconstruction from sample
points and there's lots and lots of
artifact issues lots of them and you end
up doing a ton of work to make sure you
don't get artifacts and I don't really
want to do that if I don't have to right
because it costs both development time
that we'd spend developing it but also
potential artifacts that maybe we never
get rid of or that you can't get rid of
it run time and blah blah blah so there
a whole sort of rat's nest there that I
just don't want to get into so we
manually correspond doors when we build
the world we say which which sample
points are going to be used for
interpolation for any given surface and
I think that's great but it means that
we end up in a situation where we have
to make sure that we don't have bugs in
that correspondence right so in addition
to the first part which is inside the
lighting solution when we're actually
doing our light tracing on the boxes are
we actually using the right points every
time we hit a box are we putting the
light in the right place of sample
points that's error possibility one but
error possibility two is that when we go
to pick which sample points to use for a
given quad are we picking the right ones
so there can be an index mismatch in
either case and we need to make sure
that we're not having that right because
either one of those is a bug and there
are two separate kinds of bugs that
could occur even though they're similar
right so then we have number three which
is I guess I'm not sure how to write
this one because I'm not trying to state
it too succinctly let me try to say it
first and then we'll see if something
jumps out that's a easy phrase so when
we move to using a spatial hierarchy
that act of creating the spatial
hierarchy and traversing it if there is
a bug in the traversal of the spatial
hierarchy that somehow produces
erroneous results with hit testing we
may falsely attribute a light hit to a
box that never actually got hit so false
light interactions or see
are there false light interactions
occurring as a result what's happen
there as a result of the spatial
hierarchy traversal so we've got these
three and these are basically
bookkeeping errors right so chances are
we don't have a lot of problems I mean
we might have Rekha in fact I guess I
should write this one down is the ray
caster producing correct box
interceptions
so that's obviously another separate
issue we might be having something where
we're getting spurious intersections
that are not right so the algorithms
busted is producing the wrong results so
these are bugs they are correctness bugs
and we have to look at those those are
just terms in terms of getting a proper
lighting solution we've then got another
one which is is the spatial hierarchy
properly constructed because if we've
got bugs this this would not produce a
correctness bug this is a performance
bug let's say for example we thought we
were producing a spatial hierarchy but
actually we still included tons of boxes
in various nodes of our spatial
hierarchy that didn't need to be there
if we did that we would easily end up in
a situation where we weren't getting as
much performance from our spatial Harkey
as we should have even with no
modifications to the routine that uses
it simply because we're including -
we're over including boxes that just
don't need to be in various nodes so
that is a kind of bug you can have that
doesn't actually produce incorrect
results we could put every box into
every node as page larkey it would run
awful it would be very slow right but it
would still work just fine there would
be no errors in the resulting routine so
there's steadily two classes of bugs we
can have inside a routine like this one
type of bug will actually produce
incorrect results possibly subtle that
are hard to notice but that are
incorrect or blatant like the one we
have right now where it's clear that
there's light going to areas that
shouldn't have light in them so there's
two kinds of bugs we can have there
certainly but then there's you know this
other kind of bug that isn't about
correctness this is about actual
performance where it's like the bug does
didn't show up in any visual sense the
only way you would know it's there is
that maybe your performance is worse
than you think it should be but more
importantly when you go to investigate
you see somehow you create some way of
visualizing the spatial park and you can
see oh wait a minute this is supposed to
only include the things in this area yet
all of these other things are being
included what's going on right so that's
a very different kind of bug but again
it's the same kind of bug for purposes
of this investigation which is that all
of these are things that would be pretty
hard to find
without instrumenting our code in some
way like just looking at the results
isn't really gonna be able to find these
kind of bugs the best we can do is for
really blatant bugs like that lighting
one kind of see that something's off but
it really you know I mean looking at
this right even sort of knowing that
that issue that we've got there
so here is a bunch of light coming into
this corner right and here is where the
light actually is now there's no way
that those two things are getting that
light it's pretty clear that they're
acting like they're sitting over here
getting light from what these guys are
getting light from or something you know
so something's obviously up there but
just looking at that I have no idea why
or how right I just I just don't know I
there's no I mean I can tell it's
probably an index issue maybe because
it's like it seems to be kind of regular
right like you can see it strobing
through as I move so it looks like we've
probably got an index error where you
know these things are getting light from
these indices or something you know I
can tell something's up that probably
has to do with innocents but I don't
really know and I don't think it would
really tell me much about the
circumstance right or how to find it so
I can go double-check the index code
that's about all I can do so again we're
really gonna need something that shows
us more information here so one thing
that we can do and probably the first
thing I'd like to do after I'd like to
go just check the code just by
inspection and get rid of any bugs I can
just find by looking after we do that
what I'd like to do is say okay let's
try to figure out some ways of maybe
like we can pick a lighting element or
pick a voxel I mean a bounding box in
the spatial hierarchy and let's draw it
and draw its children and it's light
sample points so that we can just say
like look okay just inspection wise does
any of this stuff even look like what we
think it looks like or is it just borked
you know okay so let's let's first go
through and take a quick survey of the
code and then let's start trying to
focus on a way we can actually get some
kind of a
a light debug sort of inspection going
on time to switch to coffee from coffee
to lemon water everyone knows it's time
for that so I won't even bother labor
the point okay so let's just start with
the basics here the push cube function
takes the light in next-door and when
you pass this laid in next door it's
expecting to have the letting store
written back into it so the only thing
it knows is where the light in next door
starts and that's fine if we're going to
write into the light index store we can
kind of see here that we pick a light
count and we know that the light index
is going to get advanced right by six
times the light count so in here we say
all right the light index equals the
light next door if we previously stored
one if we didn't we store where we were
and we essentially allocate one out of
here again this is a to do because we
have not really done the roving
allocation of the light sources yet that
hasn't been something that we've
actually done yet it's something that we
need to do and so that's again something
that and for all we know maybe that's
already causing a bug right we we don't
really know we don't really know what's
going on there yet so what we want to do
here is
you know what and in fact now that I'm
looking at that that does look like
something that I don't know that it can
cause a bug yet because we're sending
down the same things all the time but it
could cause a bug when things are coming
in and out of the set now that we do
call things this actually could
potentially cause one I think so I think
we may actually need to address this now
this may be something we want to
actually fix so I'm gonna go ahead and
say that that needs to get addressed so
let's take a look at how this is working
here inside our platform layer we sort
of have the notion that we've got some
number of light when we go ahead and
jump to there oh you know what you
pulled it out in here we have a notion
that there's a certain number of light
indices that we can work with so right
now we're dealing with about 16,000
light elements right that's how many you
can have and so when we write back data
we can have that many of them so what we
want to do here is we want to be able to
allocate these responsibly just like
drip something onto my keyboard oh well
so what I want to do is I want to be
able to process these in some way that
allows me to sort of do a fixed size
allocator kind of a thing on top of them
right so inside here where we do our
letting solution and I've got
information that I'm working on where I
say like all right I've got sort of my
my lighting solution which persists over
time and we do the averaging and so
forth in here what I want to do is have
a way of knowing how these things have
been allocated you know I need some way
of tracking what is and is not used so
what I need to do for that I think is I
need to just have exactly as it sounds
sort of a thing that like partitions
these light light points into blocks
that I hand out and then when someone
doesn't use it anymore I actually have
like a free store that just tracks them
and this is very easy we've done this a
lot of times before and it's pretty
trivial for me to put in something like
this what I'm gonna do is I'm going to
say that we've got
essentially a first free lighting point
here's the lighting points here right
and what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna track
this in here and say first free lighting
point like so and what I want to do is I
want to make this as fast as possible in
on any particular frame so at startup
I'll probably seed it so that it's set
up as a free list that goes all the way
through and then from there it'll always
be a free list for always right so let's
take a look at how that would work what
I want to do here is say okay when we do
this if on the index on the light
storage what we're saying here is if we
already are saying here is the light
index we want to use to store this then
that's great we will use it if this one
doesn't have it then what we have to do
is pull one off of the FreeStore so we
need to have the lighting solution
available to us right that needs to be
something that we can bake in there and
we'll figure out how we want to do that
later it doesn't actually have to be
stored in here it doesn't really matter
where it's stored it could be stored in
the command list for example so you know
we could if we want to inside here right
we could store it so it doesn't really
matter where it's stored this might be
the better place for it because this is
the thing that persists frame-to-frame
through the platform layer and the
opengl so it's probably a little more
appropriate to put it in here so anyway
inside here we could say we've got a
lighting point which we're going to use
to track with the first free lighting
point is and then inside the the
lighting points here these are things
that get pushed on right you can see
them getting pushed on like so and this
is tracking the maximum light index what
we want to do is now stop that entirely
so instead of having a light point count
here we're just not going to do that
anymore we're gonna get rid of that
probably and say we don't have a light
point count anymore we just don't know
how many there are there's just an array
of them or something like this right and
we assume that the array is the proper
size that has
as many as need to be there
and again the lighting point is one of
these things a reflected color and
normal in a position okay all right so
when we're looking at this this thing
doesn't need to occur at all although I
probably should leave in this part where
we just assert that we're not writing
outside of the bounds of the legal size
of our light solution but that's it okay
so now there's no more concept of the
light point count we just have a giant
block of them and they get allocated as
a however they get allocated that's just
how that works
so then when we come through here and we
have our light indexed or when we're
rendering these things we sort of have a
bit of a tough problem and allocation is
easy we just pull something off the free
list the hard part is knowing when to
put something back on to the free list
that's actually very tricky and the
reason that that's tricky is because we
don't know ahead of time what has
happened to the people who previously
were holding light indices right we
don't know whether they got used or not
so in order to track whether they got
used there's a number of ways we could
go about this and I'll do the dumbest
one first but we need a pretty good way
of of handling this
so here's the way I would look at this
let's go ahead and say that when we talk
about the first free lighting point or
things like that let's actually
introduce the concept of a lighting slot
essentially or a lighting chunk and a
lighting chunk is going to be basically
a package of lighting points that are
you know suck 24 or whatever like lights
you know we're gonna have a number that
you allocate at a time so you can
allocate more than that if you want to
but you have to basically deal with them
in terms of these 24 wide chunks or
something like that right so in here we
would have this notion inside the
lighting routine that maybe we say all
right
the light chunk size or light points per
chunk is 24 right nowhere light camp
gets okay so it gets used here let's say
that's fine
so this is going to be light points per
chunk and this is going to be weighed
point chunk divided by the number of
phases so in this case right we're just
talking about saying these this is how
these things are gonna get allocated and
when we allocate them what I'm gonna do
is the light index store this is
actually going to be something else it's
going to be the light chunk store which
is just saying here is what block I'm
storing this thing in so when I look at
the light chunk store and I look over
this instead of assigning this to a
particular instead of looking at the
light index as being exactly what's
stored here instead I'm going to say
that whatever we get out of here is
gonna get multiplied by the light points
per chunk so essentially I'm talking
about keeping 24 points for every one
slot we're actually tracking because
since I know we want to give out these
lights in in quantity because they get
scattered
all over a particular cube or something
I don't want to track each individual
light point because that's just a waste
of bookkeeping I want to track a whole
block that I give out in time so when I
give out a whole block at a time
I give out light points for chunk worth
of that block so then what I want to do
is say all right if I needed to allocate
a new one of these then what I can do is
I like look at whatever the first free
one was and that's again pretty
straightforward so what I can do here is
just say alright I've got in my in my
lighting platform code I've got my first
free lighting chunk and that's the thing
that says where I would get this from
so I'd say my first free lighting chunk
the light in next-door is gonna get that
so maybe I'll do if if it doesn't
already have one then give it one and
then assume that if we can get one we
will use it and if not we won't right so
we kind of want to do something that
looks like this
as we sort of push forward a little bit
on this so what I want to do is say all
right if we asked for lighting at all
then we're going to start doing the
lighting if we actually intersect the
light bounds we will process it if we
don't intersect the light Browns then
we're just not going to process it we
then go okay the light count is gonna be
fixed for now still we're not assigning
multiple different numbers for cube yet
although we could write and then we have
the slight index store where we're going
to store the light index here
if there was no lighting last frame for
this guy then what we'll do is say
whatever the first free lighting chunk
is that we've got we'll give it to you
then what we'll do is say well if this
was actually valid right if this
actually had in fact we could do the F
here before we even do the assignment if
this was actually valid then whatever is
at light index stores position right
this for the lighting point we'll assume
that that store is the free list on top
of the existing data so when you are not
used this is effectively oops a Union
here
oops
so normally connects SP ref C and n but
in the case where this is not a real
lighting point and it's actually free
then we will just store the next free
pointer there okay so in that case we're
gonna look up into the command structure
where is that here and this is how we
will pull out that information we'll say
all right the next free chunk that we've
got is going to be whatever the light
points were to begin with we expect the
next free one to be stored in there
somewhere
like so so that's it that seems
reasonable to me and that'll just allow
us to recycle light chunks as they are
freed if we don't get one that just
doesn't get lighting right and so what
we can do here is also place an
assertion in here and so this way at
runtime if we did hit this in the actual
game you would just get something that
didn't get lit which is not a huge
problem it's a visual bug so we don't
want to happen but it's not the end of
the world so we still handle that error
but in debug mode we'd like to know
because ideally we would never under
flow we'd always have a big enough array
that we never have scenes with so many
things in it that it blows out the
lighting size right so let me go through
here we say all right if we got our
lighting in next door so we can actually
process what we're doing here and I
guess to be fair we've already done that
if so really that just goes in here
so we don't really need this if anymore
I suppose well not really because this
is only in the case where we tried to
allocate so assuming we could get an
indexed door at all then we know what
the light index is so this stuff like
group light index just goes away because
we're now using an alligator we don't
keep a running tally that's gone so now
we go alright we're going to get the
lighting index from whatever the the
chunk says it should be we've got a
lightbox here that we're gonna pull out
based on that right and that lightbox
count that gets written every frame so
this this is not based on the the chunk
because it doesn't persist at all right
this is new every frame so that's fine
we go through here and just assign
exactly what we expect to assign so
that's all good and this all just works
now I suppose actually there we go
that's just that
so now when we do if light index store
this is really in the wrong place so
what we want to do here is say if we
don't intersect and this is light chunk
sorry I just forgot the name change
there so when we come through here if we
have a light chunk store then what we
need to do is we need to write back to
it in basically all cases so what we
want to do here is if we don't intersect
then we want to make sure we clear it
right so this needs to get freed and so
if we're going to clear it what we need
to do is in here the light chunk store
actually needs to get pushed on to the
free list so what we want to do is
basically have a free light chunk
function really
that works like this so we pass in the
light chunk that we want to free and
it'll free it and then we get this this
place where you the whoever on the
outside who was doing the lighting the
person who was storing where we were
doing the lighting that just gets
overwritten right so I think that's all
roughly what we want now wouldn't we get
in here and we do decide to participate
in the lighting then we're gonna
allocate if we can't allocate we don't
need to do anything because if we can't
allocate we're already we don't need to
push any on the free list we already
don't have anything to work with so we
just wouldn't actually this loop
assuming we do exit this loop then we're
all good so in here after we do our
light index situation we can we can grab
this out here like so so we don't have
to worry about that anymore either right
so I think that's it I think that's I
think that's it
so anyway this will probably have to get
cleaned up a bit and there's more stuff
that we're gonna want to do here but
that pretty much tells us what we need
to know all right now on to phase 2 so
that will allow us to free light chunks
and reuse the free light chunks to
allocate what it won't let us do is let
us know when an entity that was
previously holding some light indices
for example just doesn't need them
anymore
because it's not on the screen or
something or it got deleted right if an
entity got deleted poof then it's gone
so there's two ways we can address this
problem one is we can actually track
when entities aren't being used anymore
and say we gotta free the lighting
points I don't like that solution
because that solution is very
error-prone if we ever get a case where
we get rid of an entity and accidentally
forget to free its light we've got a
light memory leak offense effectively
which would just build up over time and
ruin the lighting solution so what I'd
rather do is have some way of just
storing whether or not these light
things were used and I think the easiest
way to do that at first anyway
and we could compact this down in fact
I'll put a little - do you want it here
compact down to a bit array what I want
to do here is just say
light point used so here there would be
a light point used array that light
point used array and I guess this call
like this that light point used array is
just gonna say whether or not on any
given frame the light points actually
got used or didn't get used so what
we're gonna do is when we actually begin
rendering this has to get cleared right
and then every time we go to use one of
these when we actually use it so in this
case here we're we're actually gonna use
whatever the light chunk is we say so
so whatever the light chunk store says
whatever that thing that got written
back in there is that is going to that
is going to get set in the light point
used array and say okay this light point
is going to get used now so we set it
equal to one hopefully that makes some
sense all right so what we want to do
now is we want to actually implement the
things that that handle this stuff right
so we've got two different functions we
need to implement here one of them is
free light chunk free light chunk is
going to take this game render command
structure here which stores all of the
data and it's going to take a light
chunk index and it's going to free it
the other kind we're gonna do is a sort
of like begin light or
I don't really know what to call this
but we're gonna call it once before we
start every frame which is a frame sweep
here this doesn't need to be in mind not
that the compiler cares what I say there
but you know to be fair this is the
thing we're gonna do every frame that
sweeps over the light points used and
sees whether any of them need to get
freed all right so how this works is
we'll just say exactly what you would
think we would say this is just a light
chunk index here zero light chunk index
is less than light data with / light
points per chunk that's how many chunks
do we have and this is a little
misleading so it's really gonna be like
so for example if we take a look at how
much light data width is it's two times
8192 I believe is that correct yeah it's
two times 8192 that's what we've got
here so that's how many light you know
things we have to allocate so two times
81 92 or can I just do answer divide it
yeah so that total number of lights
divided by 24 is not an even number
right so it means we don't actually have
all the light chunks that we might want
we actually hemorrhage a little at the
end that's okay I'm fine with that we
don't really care about that at all it
does mean that probably light data width
should be a multiple of this or we
should give out 32 / or something but
again that's all stuff we can do for
tuning later doesn't really matter so
when we do the light Chuck frames tree
we're going to go over each of the
chunks that we have here in each chunk
we're gonna see if a light chunk used
does I actually call it light point used
I did that's dumb I want to say is like
chunk used so if it's not used or I
guess what we could should say we could
do it this way if we see that the light
chunk is used we will set it to zero if
we see that it was not used to be free
it makes sense that's it so every frame
we sweep over all the light chunks any
one that was not used we free any one
that was used we clear - zero so that we
have two so we know that on the next
frame it has to get used again in order
for us to not free it when we come back
around in order to free a light chunk
pretty easy it's just those light points
there again light chunk index times
light points per chunk that's the point
that we're gonna be addressing here
again we're just using that space
effectively
this gives us a next free pointer the
next free pointer is this going to be
the commands first free lighting chunk
and then the first relaying chunk is
gonna be the light chunk index so that's
it right
very very very basic nothing to it so
all we really need to do now is every
time we go to begin
whatever rendering we're gonna be doing
in our platform layer so for example
where we deal with this stuff
the default writing codes we are gonna
have to provide memory for it so that's
fine that's really not a big deal but
more importantly what we have to do is
we have to sweep through and clear it
every frame right that's the that's the
sort of more pressing issue here so what
we want to do is before we ever do any
rendering so before anyone could do any
rendering at all where we would sort of
do those operations you can see in here
while we do well global running or
whatever and we start to do stuff here
just right at the head end we should I
guess where so let's see here Xbox
controllers processing I don't think we
do any rendering of any kind here so
here we go with our our back buffer off
screen puffer nonsense here I don't know
why that's still there do we even use
this anymore
is this actually used I don't know maybe
it is anyway so when we come through
here and we we start to do this stuff
with the game update what I'm gonna do
is I'm going to call that light from
frame sweep that's actually gonna get
performed on the render commands like so
so this is something that has to live in
code that can be accessible to the
platform layer and at least for now and
so that has to be you know in maybe and
handmade lighting dot H is a fine place
for it because it's an entirely lighting
based thing you know or I don't know
doesn't really matter where it is at the
moment because only one person is really
dealing with it
so there we go so I think that would be
fine very well
I guess commands isn't pulled out here
under what is this college game under
commands yeah um so let's just go ahead
and fix the compile errors lighting
point does not have an operator arrow
that's a good point
it definitely doesn't light point used
this is light chunk used free light
chunk conversion from u-32 Oh light
chunk store is a youth thirty-two store
so it is that is no longer used like
point count so I don't know how we want
to deal with this particular issue I
guess we need
we would need some way of figuring out
which of these light points is actually
getting used
I suppose in order for us to do some of
the things in here let me let's just
take a look here that's really the last
of the stuff the issues that we would
have so if we take a look at where light
point count is actually used in the
solution that's what I'd like to do
because I want to know everywhere we use
it and see what we want to do about that
so if I go ahead in here and just get
rid of the point count I want to see
what sorts of things we're using it for
so we loop over the points here rather
than the boxes right and then we do it I
think that might change
here we normalize them down
and here we sort of store their previous
values into a separate buffer right
so I'm not sure what the best way to
handle this problem is
hmm
so I guess what I would say is for
something like output lighting textures
I mean Mesa the problem we have is we've
got lights scattered throughout this
array and there's holes in it where
there's stuff that isn't actually used
by anybody and we need a way of making
sure that we don't do a bunch of
processing on stuff that doesn't exist
I'm not sure to what extent we want to
go though because it's mostly gonna be
dense like we're always anytime we
freeze something we're going to use it
on the next frame for a new people that
come in so it's not like we're gonna
leave huge holes lying around for very
long so I don't think we want to do too
much work to deal with that and so most
of the time here I think we're okay as
far as just you know processing light
points as as an array I'm just not sure
the only place I think we really have a
problem is we don't ever want to spend
time computing lighting at points that
we don't actually need to compute it for
because there's no box there so for
something like output loading textures
I'd be fine with just sweeping over the
entire array not using the point count
at all right just using the entire data
width and that's fine
[Music]
because I think we have to keep that
number relatively low anyway and then
for example in here we don't really ever
use I also don't know why get current
quads I'm not sure what get current
quads is doing there because we call
push quad which call itself calls get
current quads doesn't it so I don't even
know why I get current clots it's being
called there that that actually isn't is
not this routine is not dependent on the
point count in reality I don't think
push quad oops yeah
so that's only if you want actual access
to that group which we don't care about
right we're not setting anything on the
entry there so I'm not sure why we would
really care about that
I mean I guess it puts those all in a
group it makes sure there is a group I
suppose that's one thing but again you
know we know we're looping over this
many things and we know you know that's
how many each one's going to output so I
don't really know that it's all that
complicated anyway I think that's
basically it so I really think comes
down to like okay so this routine it
doesn't really matter what this could
loop over all of them right this this
could say loop over all the ones there
are and just do them and for those that
are you know invalid values it doesn't
matter right it'll just process the
invalid values and stick them in into
the data stream but no one will ever
process them so it should be fine so I'm
pretty sure that's actually fine and
even if it wasn't we could use the the
array that marks whether things are used
or not as our guide and maybe that's the
right way to do it maybe the chunk index
is the better better way to do that
for example I could do this
right so I could do something like this
where we just say alright we've got the
chunk count so for each one of these
we're just gonna do you know chunk index
times light points for chunk that's the
one we'll start at we'll go to the next
one
and so in here we'll just say if group
commands light chunk used chunk index
then push it down so basically what
happens here is we only update the
lighting if we know that this thing was
used and off we go so that gets us out
of the business of ever checking that
particular value anyway
and that leaves us with just that
routine I think right so then most of
what we have to worry about is sort of
where we were doing this information
that really should be ping-ponged anyway
where we have average direction to light
and last direction that kind of just
want to be swapped you know I'm saying
so the you know you really don't want to
have to do those copies but even if we
were going to write we can just do the
whole set for now so we don't really
have to modify back we just copy more
than we need to copy and that's fine
because that's not a particularly slow
part of the process yet
signed unsigned mismatched you tell me
is that so because this gets introduced
all right
so I think that's really all we need to
do now to keep everything actually
working on an allocation basis so this
to do this big to do is now gone right
we've got that we've got that taken care
of
so looking a little further down the
line now if we want to actually get this
running and then we've got a ton of
debugging work to do next weekend is
gonna be debug tastic looking down the
line a little bit here now we say okay
when we go into this we're gonna have to
allocate first so we're gonna have again
inside the the platform layer here where
we've got this this bit doing its thing
we've got our Amit c0 was the last thing
we do before we now we now need our
light chunk used memory here
and that light chunk he used is just
that so now we've got the light chunk
used that's going to be zero when it
passes in which is exactly what we want
and that's gonna be initialized properly
so really all we have now is the problem
of this iteration over the point count
here and this iteration over the point
count is again we could just do it chunk
wise and you only use the ones that are
are actually active in some situations
we don't care we could just do them all
in other situations we probably do care
so it's a little bit hard to say which
one we want to do there yeah
and given the fact that point zero is
never used here we also have to make
sure we can account by leaving the first
chunk open so when we take a look at
what's happening inside lighting here
when we do light chunk frames sweep we
kind of have to say note chunk zero is
always skipped because the zero light
index value is reserved for people who
don't use a light index so in this case
we never want to actually consider
somebody free who's in that first chunk
that chunk is just invalid and we're
only gonna right we're only gonna deal
with chunks that come after it so what
you can see here is kind of what happens
the first frame when we call light chunk
frame sweep it builds a free list that
runs through the entire light chunk set
and unfortunately it runs through it it
builds that free list backwards which
would be probably I don't know if we
want to fix that by running through the
list backwards on the frame sweep hard
to say but you know it's going to build
the free list everything all chunks
besides chunk zero will be on the free
list we could also assert in here that
we never try to free trunk zero
and that every chunk we try to free is
in bounds so yeah all of that seems fine
so when we loop over our emitters here
we could loop over them again per chunk
instead of looping over them and the way
we would do that is actually pretty
straightforward so if we were doing this
loop here I think all we really need to
do is just say you know start with emit
index with the first valid point and
what we can do here is say all right if
the emit index you know divided by the
light points for chunk I don't know if
this is actually the best way to do this
but if we were just looping over them
kind of straightforwardly what we could
say is look if the light chunk used for
this particular emitter is 0 then we
just skip it right otherwise we come and
and we skip skip ahead so we could do
something like that
I'm not sure that's the same way to do
it I'm thinking that the probably the
same is way to do it is the way we're
doing it before where we loop over you
know a chunk index
oops and then we loop over emitters
inside there so basically this is just
an if that wraps this guy and this is a
if light chunk used chunk index then we
go ahead otherwise we just don't this is
going to be chunk index times light
points for chunk so that's that
so this would loop us over the chump
you know chunk by chunk and I think
that's really all there is to it
this same loop has to get done in
multiple places so here for example this
loop has to occur for the point indices
as well so point index point index point
index
[Music]
there's all of our stuff for that seems
like we're missing this is correct
that's inside the iteration right yeah
so I think that's correct so this though
is not
all right so this is gonna do per chunk
the old stuff that was going to do we
were doing to update the decimate
emission and we're gonna half the rate
count every time through the duration
but then we go back up and do another
iteration again everything based on
chunks finally we get to the end this
also has to be done on chunks so there
we go and I think that's all there is to
it now we don't actually save this light
chunk used into the lighting solution so
I'm gonna have to put that in here so
like lung this is just a copy out of the
pointer so light chunk used when we go
through and we start the lighting when
we in here are in our letting test that
we can do solution light chunk used
those commands a chunk used and that's
it's really all there is to it
alright so this is gonna be an epic
disaster because we just added a ton of
stuff in here and so we're gonna have a
lot of debugging to do this is gonna be
you know this is gonna be rough but
let's at least run it and see what we
get and off we go
so it looks like we're getting an
assertion here in in our free light free
light chunk call and it looks like that
is because
[Music]
ah so we wouldn't actually be freeing
this light chunk if okay I see what's
going on there that's the case of in if
we go to free the light chunk we have to
make sure that there actually was one to
free so in this case we've got you know
one that didn't intersect the lighting
bounds so we can get rid of it what I
just realized though is we don't
actually have to do that right away we
can just wait till the next frame to
free that guy so I'm not sure if we
actually need to do that or not
because the light chunk used part of
things will automatically have that
happen so what we could do if we wanted
to is we could just just nuke that here
and there's gonna be one more thing
that's a little nasty here that also
probably has to happen actually which is
when somebody comes back into the used
set we have to sort of do a check
against their entity ID so again it's a
little more it's it's definitely a
little bit more nasty and this is again
just to try to make it so that we don't
have the issue of trying to figure out
when people stop using stop using a
particular light which is to say that if
you imagine how this is working right
now when we go through here and we look
at what comes in the light roaster we
just assume that if someone says they
had a particular light chunk that they
have it but that may not be true because
we may have jettisoned it right and so
if we jettisoned it because it wasn't
used then we don't have any way of
confirming you know confirming who
actually used it so if you take a look
in in like the entity stuff where we've
got this entity ID here which is like a
value that says which which entity is
doing something right that entity ID is
[Music]
something we would need to check to make
sure that we always have the same person
occupying a particular light chunk yeah
and so the only thing that's nasty about
that is just the degree the amount of
data that's processed for frame to
validate that information is pretty
significant right so like for example
it's not that hard for us to make that
work
when we pass in the light chunk storage
value here it's not that difficult for
us to make that work we can just say you
know you also pass in your entity ID or
whatever right and we'll track that or
your unique ID you know whatever it is
that actually has to be ratified there
it's not that bad the problem is the
processing of that array just becomes
more expensive all the time it's four
times more expensive now to process it
because it's got four times more data in
it
because it has to store entity IDs
instead of just storing a used field
that's 0 or 1 which could have been
compressed all the way down to a bit in
fact so it's actually 32 times slower to
process in a sense and that's not great
uh so yeah you know I'm trying to think
if there is some way that we could I
really just don't see it though I don't
see a way of making this
so
the only other way I can think of that
this would work and it seems like this
is just a bad idea so I don't think I
would want to do it is that entities
just store their previous letting
information directly inside their
storage and then when they pass in push
cube they just pass what their old
lighting was right so the reason I don't
like that is because entities never know
when they could get rid of that
information so when they get packed
back into a particular when they get
packed back into their storage for a
given region they're storing all that
data and that will never get freed so
the your enemies are always that big
they they have all the lighting
information still stored in them now
maybe that's fine and the reason maybe
that's fine is maybe what you do is you
then say you keep a hot list oh well
yeah this is actually it's way better
isn't it so I guess then what you do is
you say okay we just keep a list of all
the people who went into storage last
frame not people but regions and if
those regions aren't loaded this frame
then we go through and repack them
without that data so actually that's
probably just way better because it's
the exact same bookkeeping meaning you
just have to check but now you don't
have a free list or any of this other
stuff
that seems strictly better to me in all
possible ways I think that's just
smarter I think that's just entirely
smarter I think I think that is really
what we should be doing so essentially
what you could say is okay if the
lighting is not enabled we don't use
this light store that's fine but now
what we're doing instead is the light
chunks are actually these things this is
this is way better I think this is way
better so I think what we do here is we
say something like this how many lights
do you want and and where do you want
them and then I think we just go from
there right those get packed those get
packed in to the lighting array and as
long as you don't overflow the right
lighting array you're fine
they get packed in and they get packed
out
I think that's just better it it costs
some to do the pack in in the pack outs
but the amount you save in bookkeeping
seems well worth it because there's so
much Finnick eNOS here that has to get
done to track all that stuff it seems
that if you just got rid of it it might
actually even be faster because you are
doing a rote process every time that's
just not you know it just it just seems
strictly better to do that
let me take a quick look here so the
lightbox itself this thing
hmm hmm I say so the only thing I'm not
sure about is exactly what I want to
store there I'm quite certain that I
want to do this into the entities now so
I'm pretty sure that that this is gonna
be the right thing in the long run so in
here we just need to store the lighting
points for this entity right and the
tough thing is we don't know how many
there are right so we're not sure how
many of these things we actually would
store but that's okay because our entity
struct when we go to do the game code is
flexible anyway the whole goal of the
system is that these things get packed
in in a some kind of a streaming sense
and then unpacked so that's actually
going to be fine we have to deal with
that stuff anyway and it'll be okay so
most of the problem here and we can just
assume that this is how it works at the
moment most of the problem here is just
going to be that I don't know what we
want to do about making these things
flexible from the standpoint of lighting
that wants to have more information to
it so in the case where you want to
smooth lighting between two different
things or some of the more complex
lighting stuff that we might want to do
I'm not sure exactly how that stuff will
get handled since entities are sort of
separated that's gonna be tricky
that's gonna be really tricky and I'm
not sure how we're gonna handle it
yeah so just to be a little clearer on
how the stuff goes down so if we have
lighting points like just as an example
where is my belt Emeritus so this is the
part that I'm just not sure about and to
be fair this has nothing to do with what
we're talking about right now it's just
a thing that like would have come up one
way or another but let's suppose that we
have some walls that go like this and
furthermore I guess we can make a more
complicated scenario just to illustrate
the full problem that we're gonna have
so let's suppose we have a wall section
that looks like this
and we make it up out of a couple
different entities you know here's m2t
one hears entity two here's in two to
three now ideally what we would like to
do for lighting is maybe place a light
sample point here here you know here
here maybe some here here here here here
here there something like that you know
so we'd like to kind of scatter those
lighting points along the surface and
then what we'd like to do is we'd like
to sample those letting points to
reproduce the rendering as we go across
these quads so this quad here you kind
of want to sample all of these this quad
here I'd want a sample like all of those
you know and the problem is we have
lighting points here sampled per entity
that want to be shared right so you want
to you want to have a light sample point
that gets used for interpolating two
different and it is quads and the reason
you want to do that is because you want
the lighting to line up very closely
along those seams you know and so the
problem that I foresee is I don't
understand how I'm going to get that
behavior to occur in this system I just
don't know how I would articulate the
renderer could handle it just fine I
just don't know how to tell the renderer
to do it because I have no idea how I
would ever take two entities which was
stored completely separately and have
completely different data I don't know
how I would tell it oh hey these two
entities share this lighting point that
I need you to use like how would we ever
do that it seems like totally impossible
right
and you know the sorts of things I can
think of that would allow us to do that
or just really like fanciful they're
like oh I'd have to have every lighting
point is actually sort of its own you
know they aren't entities per se but
there's sort of their own identified
units they're their own identified
elements you know and those elements are
actually like
well okay all right okay um I mean maybe
I can sort of see one way you could do
this so maybe one way you could do this
is by putting lighting into blocks that
are large so basically I would say all
right you know let's say I've got a
screen I'm looking down on and you know
that's like a dungeon screen so it looks
like this or something
here's the walls right and so I've got
all these lighting sample points strewn
all over the thing like this
right I suppose what I could do here is
say all right suppose I broke lighting
into chunks where the chunks actually
are arbitrary sized chunks and are
entities so lighting is stored as an
entity some any number that you want
that you put back into you know a region
and that lighting entity gets pulled out
or maybe they're not stored in the
chunks maybe they're stored separately
but the point is they do have a unique
reference ID and so there's a certain
number of lighting point distributions
and you pull one out right so I would
say okay this lighting set of points is
you know this is point oops this is
point set X where X is some you know
unique ID
so when point set X gets pulled out any
entity can refer to this point set right
and so when you go to push an entity on
you do actually do like a hash-table
resolve for whether that point set has
been pulled out yet and if it hasn't you
pull it out and you block it into
somewhere in the summer into the region
so you effectively say okay yeah we've
got a point set that point set gets
pulled out of the of sort of the set of
lighting points that are in flight and
and you can refer to anybody in it as
part of your lighting solution I mean
I'm okay with that
that seems fine to me
and then we just don't have that problem
anymore because now you really can say
hey this is the lights that I use and if
those lights are still around great if
they're not still around then you just
have to recreate them and so that would
probably just work
yeah I mean I think that's fine that's
probably fine yeah I mean I think that
that's okay and that allows entities to
share information about lighting in some
predefined way as necessary which we
kind of need to do for like continuous
wall segments and stuff like that I
think I mean the only other option I
could think of is that when points
lighting points get added to the system
they get merged if they're the same
that's another option we could do so
that would be you just have entities
specify the light points each entity
specifies the light points that it
actually wants when these light points
come into existence they get merged
based on their location in some kind of
a spatial merge to be honest I'm not
really sure which of those is gonna be
better in the long run it's pretty
tricky
I guess I what I would say is that it
does seem a little bit like this way is
to static so if you were to use point
sets in this way well it does sound kind
of elegant at first what I'm thinking
about is assuming you want things like
destructible walls or things like this
which we might want in this game you end
up having a lot of problems because
you're gonna have to update these point
sets and you end up in a situation where
entities can't really be treated
individually anymore because they've got
this sort of information finding we've
kind of tried to stay away from that so
that everything is kind of this flexible
independent element so I guess what I
would say is maybe that's a good
argument against the point sets and
maybe what we have to do is we have to
do something where we can just say all
right light points get merged when they
come in if we want that to happen it's a
post pass that happens and you're just
gonna have to make that work because we
don't want to have to specify this stuff
ahead of time you know I'm saying so if
that were the case then yet it looks
more like this where we've got these
lighting points here where we would just
say okay entities have their lighting
points when you come in and you want to
push one of them on you push on you know
whatever the lighting points are that
you want to push and that's where they
go right that's just where that
information goes so then when you come
through here you don't have any free
lists or anything like that it's simply
not something that's ever managed
instead what you do is you say well if
these things intersect then what we're
going to do in this case is we're going
to say that we just push on like I guess
just a pointer to that information like
we just point to it really it's maybe I
get it's hard to say I mean let's do it
the most straightforward way first I
guess which is just record these things
individually so instead of the light
chunk used and what the heck was that I
have no idea what's going on here my
graphics card seems to be freaking out
so what I want to do is I want to say
that the command structure right what
that's going to store is individual
light chunk information so along with
the light boxes and I guess this could
just be stored with each box because
that's just kind of how it goes
I guess this lighting point array thing
just would not be stored at all anymore
they would just get pulled out as part
of the lighting solution right so the
emit C 0 and the light points I think
that stuff just goes away I'm not really
sure why the emit C 0 is there in the
first place let me really quick see
where that's coming from because I think
that's not necessary that was just
getting stored sort of as a long hall
thing yeah so I'm pretty sure that would
just get rolled in no no that's not true
it does get stored per light point here
[Music]
so that is kind of a light box attribute
yeah so I guess the what I would say
there is you know inside the lighting
box maybe then what we would say is that
the you know the emission value goes in
there perhaps would probably be more
what I would want and I don't know how
we want to store the emission value
maybe we want it to be her face cuz
right now we're over specifying it right
we specify the emit C 0 but we don't
really need to because the amid C 0 is
not actually necessary
to be stored here because at the
especially at the moment we can only say
that a cube comes down and the whole
thing is lit it has an emission value
now in the future I could see us wanting
to do something where cubes only like
had one face lit maybe at the moment we
don't though so you know maybe there's
top emit and like side in it or
something I don't know something like
that we could do in the future but at
the moment I think what I'm gonna do is
just put a name it there maybe and so
yeah if we just store an eval you here
maybe we just pack that in and that gets
stored along with the light box for
example I mean the other thing we could
do is just leave this pad since we don't
really care at the moment I suppose
exactly how we're doing this maybe
there's an emission value here and
that's just emission value for the whole
cube so rather than storing emit c0
which I don't really think we need to
store in here at all we can get rid of
all of this stuff it's just gone right
and we don't store any of these pieces
of information did I delete something I
shouldn't have there no I didn't so
light points are gone
light junk used is gone all that's gone
we just store the boxes and the boxes
store the emission in them and then the
points will get generated later on by
the Box information let's say so maybe
like we will have something that lets it
know how it wants to do that or
something like this but I you know at
the moment anyway we'll we're just gonna
pass that information down directly so
that seems pretty reasonable to me and
then this surface index stuff that
unpacks that'll go somewhere else so
inside the lighting box now what we want
to do is we want to say okay the the
lighting box that we generate here this
thing has a pointer in it
for the light for the storage and so
when we do light points they get stored
back into there and that's what we'd
actually be providing here is the place
where we write back or read from that
piece of information when when we want
to actually use this thing I think that
makes more sense and so I'm gonna go
ahead and undo that what did I call this
thing light store so that I really like
a lot better like a lot better and the
reason that I like that a lot better is
because now we the the decision to
persist lighting information for
smoothing purposes which is the whole
reason we needed that in the first place
is just something that can be handed off
to the entity system which is already
doing stuff like that so we don't have a
separate system inside lighting for
storing information the entity system
we'll just record lighting information
as it sees fit and when it decides that
it doesn't need to keep letting it from
a frame or it just throws it out and
that seems a lot nicer to me because
then we don't have this situation where
you know you've got sort of two
redundant systems operating in parallel
and having this kind of nasty
bookkeeping going on between them and
all sorts of other crap like that that I
don't really like the sound of you know
I'm saying
all right so if I come through here and
need to kind of clean up how this stuff
is working I don't know what that was
supposed to say no 148 million okay
that's a great note Casey thanks for
keeping that in there so what I want to
do here is I can restore a point count
now and things could work based on point
count and we'll see how that'll go in a
second I think so that should be pretty
good as well so yeah I think we should
be able to now make this work in a more
sane fashion than we were doing before
when we push these quads on here we
still have the issue if we do have to
know where the light indices line up in
terms of what we're actually sending
down to the graphics card so in this
case we actually do need that light
index to make some sense right but this
becomes a little bit more
straightforward as we go we should be
able to now just say go back to the way
we were doing it before we're lighting
this just equals group light index and
the group light index plus equals light
points per chunk like so so that method
of operation could be restored now if
they just stream out and they are unique
per frame so these light indices never
get persisted nobody stores them
anywhere no one does anything with them
we can then also say this light count
here
I guess this also come in here
this all looks right so now we've got
this light in next year and the light
brush truck all this stuff looks like
it's operating how it should when we
come through here this just needs to
know where the light next are that's
copying out and you know it did exactly
that so it keeps all track of that
information exactly as it used to
it's storing where it's gonna write
these back when it eventually needs to
to so and then this piece of code here
that that was generating the points on
the surface that can actually be moved
now out to the lighting solution proper
I believe so inside handmade lighting
but when it goes to do the actual
lighting test and do this nonsense here
before it does anything that actually
does the light propagation it can do
this piece of work here so we can do
this
I'll just bracket it so we can see that
it's able to do here and so then what I
can do is say okay when I go to push one
of these things on I just push the light
box on I don't push anything else
that'll get processed here later on
which is what I want I come through here
and I store all the information about
how this light is supposed to work and
then the light index and the light count
should be set properly on the way out of
here to correspond these two where I
said they were going to be inside my
inside my lighting solution right so
I've got two things here I've got the
storage that comes in and that's this
piece of information here and then I've
got the light indices inside the
lighting system and what I can do is
copy in and copy out that information to
produce what I wanted to produce right
okay so let's talk about how that's
going to work on the back end now that
that would be how this would work here
what I want to do now is I do need a
scratch array for this stuff for my
points so this is going to become an
actual array now and it will have an
actual point count because that's going
to be how many of those things we
actually pushed in there so that's a
real value now that actually has meaning
emits c0 and emits c1 are actually going
to be stored now too so all of this
information is going to be sort of kept
in there last admit and last Direction
are the pieces of information we would
actually need to store in the light
storage and I guess now that I think
about it I I suppose those have to be
kept in here then because this is the
piece of information that we're actually
keeping right so when we copy these out
we need some place to put them so the
lighting points themselves is I guess
you know I don't know how exactly we
want to think about this but the
lighting information that we have to
pass into that routine has to be able to
be unpacked into this so the lighting
point I guess is the wrong thing to
store what we need there is actually the
lighting memory it's like a thing that
we remember lighting state and what
that's going to have is the emit and the
direction so really this is not a
lighting point it's a lighting point
state
I don't know what that is still doing
there
I guess we previously were type toughing
these maybe we should again I don't know
we'll deal with that later with some
complaints so anyway inside here what we
want to do is we want to say the
lighting Point State is the thing that
we're keeping so that lighting points
themselves are just created as an
artifact of this particular routine the
lighting point information is what gets
copied in I and then the rest of this
stuff gets copied back out to there
right I think that's all we really
needed so at the beginning what we would
do is when we come through here and
expand these points we would copy the
information there at that point you can
see here we save the average direction
to light and then we zero the one that
we're actually using so in this case we
would be just zeroing the one that we're
actually using this copy would now
happen after this so that would happen
here where the average direction to
light gets copied out along with the
emission these copies will actually be
per elements now out to the lighting
boxes and these are per lighting box as
well
yeah so I think that should be fine I
don't think we need to keep last
direction or last omit because I think
those can actually just be warm loaded
in the place wherever they actually need
to be so I think these can go away and
last is valid can also go away last is
valid is actually a bit tricky so the
only complication I see here is
[Music]
we will actually have to do last is
valid as something that happens per
lighting point at per lighting box so
when we push this data in there we have
to know did it come did we actually have
stuff in there that's actually workable
or is it just garbage and it needs to
get erased right and it needs to get
overwritten with whatever you solve on
this particular frame does that make
sense so I definitely want to do that
per box because that's gonna have to
occur now all right so now we're
actually not too bad off what we're
gonna do here is we're going to loop
through each of these and I can actually
store I can actually restore the concept
of the point count now and this can be
made more straightforward so we have a
point count end points all of this stuff
can be done as was being done before so
what I'm gonna do here is I'm just going
to loop through the boxes
that we got as input now I want to do
this before we build the spatial
partition because the spatial partition
is going to add boxes and I don't want
to process any boxes that I don't have
to so I know that all the ones that are
coming in here are real boxes for lack
of a better term and so I want to
restrict myself to only dealing with
those you know I'm saying
so for each one of these now I could
loop through my point indices so I want
to loop through point index whatever the
box light index 0 is I want to go
through the light index 6 I believe
which is the last one here and then I
plus plus point index so now I'm going
to go through and each point index that
I have I'm gonna pull it out of the
storage right now I could just use a mem
copy here which might be better well I
don't know we can look at stuff like
that later I think the compiler should
be good enough oh well no you know what
I can't do that because I got to do this
right so I have to actually make these
things work properly so no that's that's
not true right so I need to do something
I need to something more like this right
where I go through surfaces one through
zero through five I actually get these
out I build the lighting points from
them and I should be able to do that by
actually just looking at whichever light
index we're actually talking about here
right now we know these light indices
are contiguous so what I should be able
to do is say light index equals solution
our box light index zero start with that
and push all of these in here
now if storage was valid then I could
just copy them out if it wasn't I can't
what I could do is I can make I can
basically make concessions to that later
on as we go we'll deal with that a
little bit later so what you can see
here is when you're initializing emits e
zero that's a piece of information again
that's gonna be right here now it's
gonna be in the solution so when we
release we're gonna initialize emits e
zero directly now not as a adjective the
command state and this infer me this
should basically be just whatever the
box said it's a mission was I believe we
properly store that no we did it so we
want to make this actually be
mm well okay you know what
I'm not sure how we want to store that
information so when we're sending a
mission down here I don't know if we're
sending it down how we want to send it
down if we want to send it down zero to
one which seems logical to me
in fact I'll put an assertion in here
then we can multiply it out in here and
that'll be fine this is just the boxes
emission value right and so all of them
inherit that same value so this will
initialize all the lighting points in
question right and then when we're done
here we can say if solution light point
count as we were before or point count
is less than the light index solution
point count equals light index like so
although we should actually know what
that should actually be known so to be
honest I think we don't even want to do
that that's just a waste of ifs for no
reason I think what we really want to do
is a solution point count equals group
commands light point count because they
get serialized now so there's no need to
do a bounced check so that should just
be tracked the entire way through okay
so this will distribute all of our
points as we want them distributed we
can then do everything as we were before
the copy out hat we can do in a separate
place and we'll talk about that in a
second we've got stuff we might want to
there but in here when we zero the
average direction to light just to clear
out that array that can still happen the
way we wanted to because that's just a
scratch area
Ament see zero I think is to see one we
never cleared see one I assume that's
because we clear it up here
right yeah so that just kind of gets
dealt with down here what I would like
to do is we can get rid of this stuff
now
right the emitter index can go back to
being what it was before okay so this
can just behave the way that it was
behaving again same thing with this so
we don't have to do all that nonsense
that I was doing before which I was not
liking and now what we can see here is
when this produces the new lighting
solution what we want to do is in here
this last pass you can see that it's its
operating kind of over the was going to
operate over the point four and we want
it to be able to use this last the the
sort of the last emission last Direction
information what we want to do here is
we want to stop doing it that way this
is the part now where we want to loop
over the boxes again and actually grab
the previous results to the extent that
we have them right and furthermore in
here you know we can make this B we
could actually pull this out so when we
do compute letting solution this part
here this finalization we could actually
pull this out if we wanted to and say
that that's actually part of this so we
can see it a little more cleanly here
the the two stages of the copy out and
the copy back
so you can see here where we do this
copy and storing that information we're
not going to do that anymore here
instead what we're gonna do is we're
gonna mimic what we did at the outset
where we actually go through the lights
that are involved per box and for each
of those will grab the previous
information and blend it after we're
done blending it will write it back so
basically we're gonna pull it out blend
right back now we may want to in the
future pull out the emission information
so instead of blending the way that
we're blending here we may want to blend
in a different way I know this sounds a
little confusing but basically what
we're doing right now is we're redoing
the lighting calculation every frame
which means that any light propagated on
a previous frame is not reap rocketed on
a subsequent frame so the light restarts
the lighting solution restarts every
frame and the extent to which we use the
previous frames information is just as a
blend to try to sort of keep the light
from changing too much per frame
that's probably dumb we can probably do
much better than that by saying let's
just track the propagation frame by
frame and keep what we did on the
previous frame alive for the next frame
so that the propagation just gets better
and better so we can probably do stuff
that's smarter there and I'll put a note
about that but at the moment we don't
want to go down that path because we're
just trying to sort of clean up how our
accidents and debug it without that
extra sort of complexity introduced
so that's just one thing that we should
look into in the future and that again
is just about getting a better lighting
solution for the same amount of
computation time because one of the
things that's true in something like
lighting were you really what you're
trying to get a particular you're trying
to get a particular result that you know
you can never achieve which is like the
perfect propagation of light of what
would really happen in in the real world
with these lights or something right
and you're never gonna get that the
amount of complication necessary to
produce that is it's hours of
computation potentially right depending
on the situation I mean maybe not
anymore because computers are much
faster you days but it's you know
minutes of computation let's say even on
a very fast machine for certain scenes
and so we know we're never gonna get
that so what we're trying to do is
figure out well okay we've got a certain
budget we got a certain amount of
computation we can spend what's the way
to make sure that we're spending that
computation time to get the best result
we can because we certainly don't want
to sit around doing a bunch of
computations that are throwing away
parts of the information we have
revealed that we could have used to
produce a better lighting solution so
you want to make every flop count and
that's something that we can look into
kind of later as we go how do we make
sure that for the computations that we
are that we do have time to do are we
doing them as efficiently as possible or
are sure rather are we getting as much
information as them as we can right so
the smoothing is one way to just simply
make the lighting look better by
reducing the flicker but it's possible
that we could get a lot more mileage out
of that storage by actually using it to
like help guide our solution every frame
and so that's something that we want to
kind of develop going forwards and again
that's not gonna speed us up but it's
gonna get us a better solution for the
same amount of speed and that's
important as well right okay so what we
want to do here is take a look at the
Box value here and this is that box is
valid barrel
weird that's what that lighting box
right there so if the storage contents
are not valid what we want to do here is
point to alternate storage so what I'm
going to do is going to say okay let's
say we've got lighting point state here
right
that's my storage and we sort of have
two cases in fact I guess I can just
handle the two cases if the storage
contents are valid we do one thing
otherwise we do another thing
so the point state here in fact I guess
I don't even do this if the storage
counts are valid then we're gonna do
exactly what we were going to do before
right everything is exactly the way it
was so I'm going to start with the boxes
light index zero I'm gonna go until the
boxes light index 7 / 6 right and I'm
gonna go through each of those in series
for each of those that we're gonna do we
know what the point index is I guess you
know what I should do should do it this
way right house I'm going to go through
each of the points and then I know that
we can look at whatever is in our
solution which are these things here I
know that I can look at those using that
point index directly I'm sorry I using
an offset of that index so I can say
alright my point in next year is going
to be the local index plus whatever the
initial box index offset was right so
that's my point index and then I know I
can look in the box the box of storage
to get what it was so here where I come
through I say all right the omit C 0
value of this thing wait could I even do
this the same way I was doing before
I guess I could couldn't I
only if I actually make these be
parallel but I could
you
so in other words if we said something
like this is a pointer to one of these
and it stores that right then I could do
it because now I've got an array of
emitters array of directions I could
also do it by saying that the emissions
and the directions are interleaved and
then I could also just do it directly so
for example if I was to say that
lighting point state which has the
emission and the direction in here that
those were actually just stored as part
of the point state so for example I said
this right then I could do that as well
seems plausible to me especially because
you can imagine packing this thing down
in a pretty concise way potentially to
so yeah maybe I'll do it that way
let me just see what admit Siwon is
doing here just in case there's anything
weird cuz we're not ping pong it right
now we are so you can see here we've got
like a source emit see in ad estimate
see Oh although it doesn't actually ever
ping-pong them
so I guess technically yeah if we wanted
to I'm just not sure if I want to give
up that sort of cleanliness of having
those be the direct packed arrays
because we could ping-pong them in the
future I don't know if we're going to
there was no reason to do so here
because we had to renormalize the
samples but if you look at what's
happening here this sort of copy and
clear you could imagine this being done
a lot more efficiently right so yeah
it's a little dicey it's a little dicey
so I'm gonna go ahead and stick with
what I had before I don't really want to
go down that route yet cuz I'm just not
sure about it and it seems a little bit
iffy to me so I'm gonna just say we
don't do that yet and we'll cross that
bridge when we come to it so if I'm here
and I'm looking at my box index you know
situation I'm just gonna do these
separately I'm not gonna try to do
anything fancy so if the storage
contents aren't valid then there's
really not much that we actually have to
do here we just write back the values
and that's it I go ahead and clear that
out if the source contents aren't valid
then we need to average them so let's
take the easier case first when the
storage storage contents are not valid
then we don't need this lerp here and we
can just say that whatever the solution
says that it is is what the solution
says is what it is right so if we take a
look at this here we know that our omit
c0 is just going to be whatever it is so
we don't need to touch it at all right
so we know we're going to write back
something here and then our average
direction to light is going to get
normalized which is this so we do
actually need to figure that part out so
well
we'll get the direction here here's the
omit here's the direction and so what we
want to do is we need to write back we
don't need to write back the emission we
do need to write back the direction
because we are normalizing it and then
what we want to do is we want to take
wherever these were stored in the box
itself and we need to write those back
so inside the box we know we've got this
right here so the storage for the
emission is going to be the emission the
storage for the direction is going to be
the direction and I suppose we can make
this a little bit more cheeky if we
wanted to by saying well okay so since
this only gets used in one place we can
just do it like that
and if we just abuse having the equal
signs line up we can also do this like
this so here we say in the case where
the storage contents are not valid we
basically make them valid like so by
saying you know into that storage we're
going to write back whatever the
emission was that we computed and into
the directional part we're going to
write back the normalized version which
we will also write back into the actual
array that we use that we send down to
you know the to the game right to the to
the GPU this doesn't have to be done
this way anymore
so in this case we can go back to what
we're doing before exactly as we were
doing it before this one again has
always worked this way and can continue
to work this way so that's totally fine
it can go back to doing this if it wants
to
so in here really this is all we need to
finish now this particular piece of
information has to this particular
operation still has to occur up here
just in a slightly different way I think
all that looks right so when I come
through here what I want to do is do
this blend exactly the same thing we're
doing here I want to do the double store
so basically what I want to do is say
okay I'm gonna go ahead and store
whatever the last thing was the last
thing here is gonna have to be pulled
out as well so here's that emission
value right there here's the new ones so
the new the old one will lurk to the new
one at this rate and we'll store them
both back into the things that we
actually process same is true for the
last direction so this part right here
where we're storing back the last
direction that comes in here we don't
need to normalize it because we know
it's already normalized since it had to
get stored on the last frame as a
normalized value so we're just doing the
lerp here again reading out those values
from the storage and then going from
there
so think that's everything that actually
needs to happen here I don't think
anything else needs to occur this light
index value for box this this is not
used anymore so that's just gone so now
we have some cleanup to do right we've
got to figure out how we want this stuff
to work this is actually the lighting
storage here this is something like this
no Nova right specifier I'm assuming
that's because lighting storage is not
defined
like point state that's what I meant but
I guess this is not defined
yeah it should have been because the
lighting information should have been
specified let me just take a look
entities here lighting that's BP is here
there's our problem
inside our lighting solution v3
semicolon so this needs to get
implemented and that's fine we'll do
that in a second storage equals light
store there we go and so now we're down
mostly to it so in here we don't need
points we don't need a MIT we don't need
chunk used all that stuff goes away and
we do need to however in our pushing
these things on we do need to clear it
for the commands so I don't know since
these have to be unique across the
entire time we use them I think
technically it's got to be in here so I
think technically this has to be in here
and so this is actually right and so
that is something that actually does
have to get cleared down at the bottom
right so when we do this we have to do
like point index equals zero although
actually I suppose since zero is never
used technically what we need to do is
do this plus equals beforehand so you
know this actually has to be like this
although we only want to skip one of
them so it's it's this right when we
start doing a rendering here this thing
wants to be when it gets initialized
right this thing wants to to do that
so when here when we're doing push cube
now we actually have to do something a
little bit fancier than that and we've
got a bunch of stuff we're gonna have to
deal with so let's go ahead and make
that happen this is actually a light
point index not light point count we got
light points in here that is not true so
those should be actually stored and they
are so that's good this is just box
right this is just points
coloured RGB so that needs to get
specified as part of the box as well
doesn't it because inside here we don't
actually store that piece of information
so I guess that is one downside of not
storing the light separately here this
really doesn't have to look like it does
at the moment either there's probably a
lot of stuff we could simplify here
because right now we're kind of we're
also being a little bit aggressive in
terms of what we actually you know
remember but here's the ref see and so
what I could do is when we push that on
there we could store that information so
when we do our emission value and then
in here you know we just track that
information so that I think is mostly
okay now we just have to kind of deal
with some of the fallout here that's
gonna be assigned unsigned miss mismatch
which is fine
let me just promote these to you 32s
before the subtraction let's take a look
at what's going on here the storage I
think it's called direction actually I
don't know why I type Durr let's expand
that out
and that's about it really now we just
have to make sure that when we actually
push these things on they're pushed on
in the same way right all right so now
when we do push cubed this has to be a
light point state and unfortunately for
us this is a little bit dicey it's kind
of hard to know what's going on here per
se we will I'm sure do some various non
senses
whereas this little piece here we go
this is just completely piggy actually
you know what I'm not gonna put it there
get out here I leave it where it was so
when we have these pieces here
so what I want to do here is say well
alright this will put the lighting in
here for now but eventually we're gonna
do this in a very different way so I'm
not gonna think too hard about it at the
moment what I'll do is say instead of
addressing off the piece here I'm going
to use the actual piece index and use
the lighting information like so so that
will actually not what I wanted
I just wanted lighting so I think that's
what we need now so would you push light
there same thing here
bitmap Stoke get one and then inside
push cube
[Music]
and we know that this thing has to be
that wide so again a little this is a
bit loose there obviously because we're
kind of fussing with it a little bit
what we don't have right now is a good
way of knowing whether or not this thing
was accurate before what I realized is
actually we have that information so I'm
kind of dumb for thinking I need you to
store that so if we take a look at what
happens inside the lighting box we don't
really need storage contents are valid
like that's just not necessary at all
storage contents are valid is a waste of
time because we don't need to look at
storage contents are valid instead we
can just look to see whether or not the
whether or not the normal of the first
point is a valid normal or not right so
if we wanted to we could just say okay
we've got a lighting point here so
where's the storage so this this storage
value here let's just take a look at
lighting point state that's the first
point right that's that's what that's
going to be what we can do here is just
check if the direction
of any of these is non-0 Venice valid
because it's a direction it can't be
equal to zero zero zero
although the reflected one could be if
we have zero zero zero here before then
there wasn't any information here right
there wasn't we never collected even a
single sample the previous frame so it
definitely never got a valid lighting
solution and whatever you got this frame
we should probably use right this is not
what I wanted to actually want that so I
think that correctly does everything
now we're massively over time now and
this isn't gonna work because I made so
many changes it's nuts but you get the
idea so I'm gonna leave this I guess I
could just debug the basic crashing
stuff but yeah I'll do a quick little
check is this correct No
box okay box so the storage got set to
something but that's something is not
legal which is a bit weird so let's find
out why the light boxes all come from
the solution here right says there's 67
of these presumably they all got pushed
on let's go take a look really quickly
here of where they actually get pushed
sooo in here when I push one on
presumably the storage always gets set
and so this should be a valid value
right because in order to actually get
one pushed on here
you have to actually have reasonable
data also so I'm not sure exactly why
that would be causing a problem but we
certainly could try to make it fail
earlier and give us a hint of what was
going on by saying well if the storage
value is wrong then what I could do is
just reach into it here right say okay
whatever the light story is let's just
set the direction equal to some value
right and so that should crash like
right away on push if it was actually a
problem of storing the boxes but it
looks like it's not because it's it's
trying to access this first point here
that appears to be the problem so I feel
like the box itself that are getting
pulled out is is the issue there and not
the ones that are getting pushed on so
let me go in here and just see what's
going on there if there's something
strange that I don't understand yeah and
in fact you know what else I can do let
me step into this routine and just
quickly take a look at what that box
array looks like when it actually comes
in so if I set a breakpoint here on
lighting test here's my box count at 67
let's take a look at what the boxes
actually are and even the first one
storage is garbage right so something
bizarre is happening here is it just
like that the first one gets overwritten
or are they all garbage so they're all
garbage
oh that's actually to be expected so in
order for them not to be garbage the
lighting solution has to be run prior to
throwing away the simulation state
because we're gonna write the entities
back back in so we actually need this to
run the lighting test to run that
actually needs to run in line so this
right here actually has to be done like
this because we want to capture the
information that it's given so that that
might be part of it
yeah and that looks a lot better it
looks like the last box is invalid
however
oh wait no with this it says there's 106
now this is how many boxes there were
last time it thinks there's a hundred
and six boxes this time so that's a
little bit weird
let me go back to testing what I was
testing before because by the time I get
in here I mean light store has to be set
to something or I couldn't have gotten
here right so I'm not sure how I would
get the light box count to do what it
just did
now I guess I should double check inside
the render grip here oops
inside the hand made to make sure that
I'm resetting that value correctly every
frame but I am so the only question
would be if it gets like fussed with in
some way that it shouldn't be fussed
with yeah that's that's peculiar so if
we take a look at what happens when I
step in here the first time through we
should have 67 and all 67 of them are
fine or they're not ah that's why
because we're looking through boxes that
have been added as part of the spatial
partition so on the way out we strictly
want to confine ourselves to the
original set of boxes so that's fine
that's totally fine
[Music]
so really what we want to do here is
confine ourselves to the original box
count like so all right
okay so now we're at least running
we're totally wrong this is not a good
lighting solution but that's fine for
today so next weekend will be our
debugging festival and we can get the
rest of this stuff working but now we
don't have any of that sort of really
nasty bookkeeping in there that I was
uncomfortable with I I just didn't feel
like it was gonna go particularly well
for us so now what we've got is okay
entities can store the information about
their lighting in them while they're
still in a place where it's going to
matter as soon as we detect if they've
gone too far out of there we can
jettison it so that's part of the enemy
packing and repacking stuff when we put
that in later on in the games lifecycle
and so that will be the place where that
can happen and now we just store that
that information directly back into the
entity so when an entity puts its
graphics information into the world it
also puts its lighting information if
that letting information existed on the
previous frame and if it didn't it
didn't we don't care we recompute it
right so that's way saner than it was
and I'm pretty happy with it all right
I'll go to like the briefest of Q&amp;A so
only completely on topic questions if
there's a very on topic question I will
take it otherwise
but he's right the 148 million was the
number of typhus later
ah okay great
so I see no really on topic questions is
this your usual design process a bit ad
hoc well difference you mean by design
process that's not really a very
specific term and doesn't refer to
anything in terms of trying to develop
new algorithms obviously yes you have to
be exploratory so you have to try things
and see what works once you're done with
them then you can maybe talk about a
design process which would be we know
exactly what we're doing and now we're
going to design say an API for it or
something like that or design exactly
how we want the system to function in a
shipping sense which is a different
thing so there's two kinds of design
there's exploratory design and there's
like shipping design exploratory design
has to be ad hoc because you obviously
don't know what you're doing or you
wouldn't have to be exploring a solution
whereas something where you're just
you're done you're like this is what it
is and now we just want to make it be
sort of ready packaged up and you know
designed for maintenance and that sort
of stuff that's a different process
all right look no further questions
all right all right thank you for
joining me for the episode of handmade
hero it's been a pleasure coding with
you as always if you would like to
follow along the series at home you can
always peer to the game on handmade hero
dot-org it comes with the source code so
you can play around with it I'm gonna be
back to debug this stuff next week I'm
pretty happy with what we decided to do
with the caching there that's a lot
saner than where we were going before so
I think that's gonna work out better in
the long term but we've got a bunch of
debugging and performance optimization
to do now so we just gotta like roll up
our sleeves and do that and I think we
should be in good shape so that you come
back to join me for that I may only do
one stream next weekend because I may
have a prior engagement one of the days
so either way we will start the
debugging next weekend though I just
don't know if it'll be two days it might
only be one day either way that's what
we're gonna be doing so see you back
here for that till then have fun
programming and I'll see y'all on the
Internet take it easy everybody