hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete game
live on stream we have some debugging to
do today in fact because if I remember
correctly last weekend at the end of
Sunday stream we finished up at a point
where we had done the plumbing necessary
to take light probes and push them out
into a voxel and then we could compute
on that voxel if we wanted to it's in
CPU memory it's on the CPU side and then
at the end of every lighting computation
we push the voxel down to the graphics
card and sample from it and where we
were at we finished that sort of you
know it's running but it doesn't quite
work the way we would expect it to at
the end of last stream because we put
some sample information into the light
probes and want to see if it will come
out the other end and it didn't quite
and so what we want to do today is start
to bugging that process so what we'd
like to do best-case scenario end of the
day what we'd like to get to is a clear
sort of structured art situation where
at the start of the lighting computation
we initialize light probes with some
specific data so we verify that we can
put specific data into our light probes
we then don't really run a lighting
computation because again we want to
leave a specific set of stuff in the
light probes so we skip the actual
letting computation we then output the
light probes into the voxel and we
verify that the voxel shows that same
structured light that we put in at the
head end and so that just tells us that
we've debunked like any of the sort of
pieces that could have failed there and
so that's what I really want to get to
at the end of the day and that sets us
up for the next step which is actually
simulating the lighting which is kind of
the final stage in producing a new
working model of lighting that works on
the light probes and then from there
we're kind of off into optimization
territory
like seeing if we can make sure
everything runs fast enough first by
limiting our region right now I think we
consider way too many light probes I
think we're just considering all the
light probes who to be it's way too
early for me to be up and then we go
from there
right
so let's start off just by taking a look
at what I was saying was broken about it
this is in debug mode so it's a little
bit slow but even in debug mode it's
fast enough to run and what you can kind
of see is actually there is something
going on right you can sort of see there
is some lighting showing up it appears
to be very high like above the hero or
something and we're just kind of popping
up into the bottom of that lighting
perhaps again it's pretty hard to see
most of the world is unlit right you can
kind of see that that really we're not
getting much in the way of lighting
there anyway but there is something
happening so it's a little bit confusing
because you know if we had just a
straight up like nothing's getting
transmitted kind of a bug then we
wouldn't see that lighting popping up at
the same time we're getting almost no
lighting popping up so it is a little
bit weird
and it's kind of difficult to guess
what's going on I'm curious if I hop
over to an area where there's a stack of
things here and I hop downstairs what do
we see and one of the things that I
notice is I'm still not seeing like
there isn't light up on the top level
here so if I had to guess and I don't
really know but if I had to guess what
it looks like is happening to me is that
our scale is wrong so it looks like
because I can see some lighting when I
hop up into it I'm thinking that that
our scale is wrong and the size of the
light is just very small for some reason
right so maybe when we put it into the
box ler when we take it out of the box
solar who knows what we're getting is
that lighting information is just really
really tiny so because remember what we
stuffed in like test data the assumption
there obsessional close that the
assumption there was that we stuffed in
the test the test data correctly at the
same size as like a big sphere that we
could see of a big sphere of lighting
and my first question is just did we
actually do that so curious the light
probe index right and we're looping over
it
you can see us doing our add probe to
spatial index thing here where we add
light probes into the spatial index
we're and then we come through here
and we tried to run the same code this
is exactly the same code we tried to run
the same code we were running before
where we said look let's try to put the
light in here that we were using for
putting it into the lock so directly
let's use it to put in the light probes
now one of the things that might be bust
about that is we've got this light are
see here that's a value that multiplies
the light distance itself this could be
very wrong as well because again this is
in world space and so you know this was
previously I guess in UV space actually
and so it may just be a question of the
you know might be the only bug we have
is really we forgot to update this
parameter and so just looking at it
offhand that is obviously incorrect
because this is a an equation that does
the fall-off 1.0 is the is no fall-off
so as this you know 1.0 would be no
fall-off zero would be complete fall off
right and so this value has to range
from zero to one over however large the
light source needs to be if this RC
value here is three that means that our
distance fall-off is 3x times the actual
world space distance that means it would
fall off at one third of a meter that's
a very tiny light source and hey that
happens to be what we're seeing so what
we probably want to do here is actually
change this into something that is the
correct meters fall-off so for example
we could say one over however many
meters we want here and the light the
you know let's say we want a 10 meter
fall-off of our light source I don't
know what we actually want it to be but
let's say we did that would we now get a
sphere that we could actually see
properly you know what I mean that would
be my first question and so running hand
made hero now here here is the actual
game running and there we have well so
you know now we actually do get some
visible lighting there but one of the
things that's really interesting about
that is it's apparently not really quite
a sphere the way I would expect
Wow that's a really interesting lighting
artifact as well uh so it is kind of
spherical lighting you can see it
falling off as the sphere goes what's
really interesting is it seems like and
correct me if I'm wrong but it seems
like the the answer that the light probe
system is getting at the point where the
voxel falls off to zero so where there
is where there are no light probes right
where there's no light probe in a
particular voxel entry it actually goes
to fulbright there you see them saying
somehow it's really weird but it creates
an incredibly interesting effect I'm not
sure it's a super useful effect because
it's gonna have a lot of artifacts the
way that it works so I don't necessarily
think we can harness that effect for
anything particularly cool but boy that
was interesting you know it looks like a
pac-man level inside the voxels where
they fall off that's that's a pretty
interesting thing so it does look a
little bit there like you know it does
look a little bit to me like we're
getting the correct size fall-off now a
little bit it seems like the light
intensity is a little wrong though -
it's not that bright at the center which
is a little bit weird and I'm not sure I
don't quite remember what we were doing
I don't remember if we change the
brightness there I don't think we did I
think the light intensity is the same
light intensity it was right you know I
I guess I just can't remember and so I
don't know if we're seeing something
weird happening there with that light
intensity
I guess not because if you think about
it the light intensity is at 10 and so
this is a quarter of light intensity
that would give us maximum light
intensity and so if we wanted it to be
more bright in the center
that is what I would expect so I'm not
sure what we did there I don't quite
remember I'm sorry if we change that or
not
I'm very tired today I'm super sleepy so
looking at that it does look a little
bit more correct like you're getting
full lighting there in the center region
I guess
so that's not too concerning and it does
look spherical so I think we're getting
closer but it seems like we still have
some bugs where I'm not sure what's
happening in the voxels at the location
where there is nothing in the voxel and
I think we need to look at basically how
we're handling our zero or null like our
not present value I think that's
probably getting handled incorrectly at
least that's my assumption right and
probably what we're doing there is you
know providing some lighting that's
getting thought about the wrong way I
think I kind of have a mental model even
of why that's probably wrong
so we'll see as we go all right so if we
take a look at what's going on with
these voxels now and you take a look
here at the adprep spatial index what
we're doing is every voxel we fill with
light probe information by putting the
closest light probe into the voxel at
that location when we fill the light
probe with information we're filling it
with information about the light probe
which is at a particular position right
and so the light probe itself isn't
centered in the voxel and that creates a
little bit of a problem too right and so
I feel like we can maybe start to
address some of our problems here also
with the way we're sampling things by
thinking about how this information is
getting pushed down if I go look here at
how our voxel is is was being set up
here you can see that computing light
directly in the voxel sort of has some
benefits because when you actually then
go to sample it you've getting gotten an
exact an exact answer at the center of
your voxel whereas now what we're doing
when
go through these voxels right is we're
pushing we're taking out what is
actually in the voxel at that location
and I think our zero voxel in theory
when we go through our light probes here
right one of the things you'll notice is
we actually do have a zero probe and
that's kind of wrong right look we don't
want our probe to have a position just
looking at where our light probes are
our zero probe we don't really want to
be anywhere I don't think and so we kind
of want the zero probe not to be in the
spatial index and not to have any light
in it at all right I think so that kind
of has to look like that and then when
we get the zero probe out in theory the
zero probe it's should should be just
skipped so when it comes out here
we just need to do this basically right
and say look if there's nothing in the
Pro if there's nothing there in that
particular voxel then we don't put light
into that box at all right there's this
just it's just blink assuming that we do
something like that that's at least a
little more correct now on what should
be occurring in around the voxel okay
that was surprising probably because I
think not equal zero oh wait no boy
absolute month that was correct so the
probe beam that comes out if it's
correct we use it this was the problem
right here we need to move forward every
time otherwise we'll always be stuck on
the first one right furthermore in here
yeah just looking at this I think now
that should be iterating over all of the
parts of the voxel I'm Way too sleepy
today I had to get up early my brain is
not ready to do programming
um so you can see now we're not getting
that fought that weird sort of fall off
artifact and so we're able to do the
lighting a little bit more appropriately
now and it is sort of doing the
spherical fall-off what you can see
however is now because it's based on
where the lighting probes are you know
each light probe right now has a
particular value and because it's based
on where the lighting probes are you can
really see the problem with the way
we're doing the sampling and so I think
like right off the bat what we're gonna
see here and you know we we can
certainly play with it from here we aim
and we may have some bugs in there and
whatnot but what you can see I think
right off the bat is just it doesn't
really work to do the lighting sampling
the way that we're doing it there for
like a number of reasons right like
because we're just putting light answers
directly into the voxels and trial in
healing them we lose the light probe
location information that we kind of
needed right because we compute unless
we wanted to change and we actually just
compute light at the voxels themselves
then the light lookup really needs to
work here and it doesn't work right and
so just looking at how this is working I
really don't think we're gonna get
anywhere with this particular model just
looking at how bad that trilinear
sampling looks and yeah there could be
some bugs in there maybe it's looking
worse than it should look but I just
don't think we're gonna be able to get
all the way there with trilinear I just
I just don't I don't buy it and so I do
think the you know the first thing we
may have to do because it looks like we
are are sort of pushing down the light
probes properly now I think the first
thing we may have to do is is start
actually doing our own light probe
blends in the sampler itself right in
the in the fragment shader so as painful
as it may be I do think like we may have
to do something where we are actually
pulling some kind of lookup information
out of the voxel assuming we still use
one smooth
axl because we could use other spatial
partitions right there's nothing that
says that our fragment shader can't
itself do the lookup but basically
something that tells us how we're gonna
blend these things together I think
might might have to happen right I think
pulling directly out of the voxel the
light information it's not gonna work
and so what we may have to do is
something more like okay we actually
pull out the light probe positions and
then we do our light sampling on that
information and we used you know we use
the actual position of the light probe
to to figure out where the light is
coming from relative to us which is not
the same thing right it's it's that's
quite different than the way that it's
working at the moment where we just
assume that it's coming from the center
of the voxel which is this case it may
well not be right so I think that's
probably what we want to do I would like
to do a quick check to see if where each
of these things falls in the voxel
itself so one of the things that's a
little bit hard to see right now is
where does each light probe fall in
which lane of the voxels does each light
probe fall so if I were to go into the
thing that outputs the light probes
themselves and in here we just said look
I've got a need in inside the code that
pushes the cubes down instead of doing
this debug color if I was to just set
each light probe to just be pure white
so when I run it all of those like color
the cubes that are colored sort of
randomly that are the light probe
locations if instead of that we just
push down a full white right so you can
see they're just just white now if I
then go and change our voxel to be
stuffed with something that shows like
if the checkerboard pattern so like for
example in here if I were to change the
light east light West that sort of thing
if I were to change and so instead of
doing any kind of of light packing like
in here where we're actually taking the
probe
here right if I was to change those up
and said let's actually give ourselves a
checkerboard again so something like
like this right and then I set
everything to just be a neutral amount
of light in the neutral intensity like
so so in this case we just initialize
everything to a neutral intensity for
our inbound lights like this so we have
west east south north up and down here
so we initialize the neutral intensity
and then on our checker boards we turn
like every two squares on each we turn
on red green or blue so we have red red
checkerboard along X green checkerboard
along Y and blue checkerboard of a long
C I just am interested in to say like
okay so if we look back if the game you
know and and maybe you know the other
thing that I might do there is let's
restart with without the bilinear on so
if we go over to the OpenGL renderer
side of things and we look at the linear
[Music]
call so we care we up that's their
special textures so in here we have our
voxel if we want to just have nearest
here assuming that we want to do
something like that and we go ahead and
and run the game without any filtering
my question is just what will that show
us in terms of who is like for each
lighting probe which ones are in which
places right and so if you take a look
at the way the lighting probes
are aligned here you can kind of see
I mean I guess one of the problems is
since they're actually using the
reflection equation here I do wonder if
maybe what we want to do is something a
little bit more drastic there so I think
maybe I want to do something more like
this so let's suppose we have a light
override value this is the light color
we're going to override everything with
and maybe what I want to do is make the
checkerboard pattern just override all
of the lights so here instead what we're
going to do is just like no matter what
light direction you're looking you're
gonna get the same light value you know
everywhere I guess I didn't need to
close the game but did and now I just
want to kind of see if we can can pick
out like individual light probes and are
they actually falling into different
locations in the voxel or not and so on
right and so if I hop out to like a
level here so here it's like a
particularly high zoom level
particularly like far out zoom level and
we just look at like how are these
things falling in the voxel it does
appear that like we generally get pretty
good separation right so you can kind of
see that there's plenty of voxel
resolution for lookup through all of
these including the up/down right
and so we do I think fill our voxels
pretty reasonably and I guess you know
we have to make sure that each voxel is
is filled with something I suppose and
so that's kind of a separate question so
I guess what we could do is say look if
we turn off the sampling here so so I'm
gonna nuke the override
right and so I keep closing it sorry I
keep closing the game for no reason
so if we go ahead and run the game and
I'm gonna go ahead and and hop out to
that same location with the override off
I'm curious what will happen if we then
test to see like I think part of the
artifacts are seeing here is when we are
sampling from these lights we're also
perhaps seeing some places that don't
have any samples at all which is also
probably happening but if you look at
the non trilinear version so if you just
look at the raw like sampling that we're
getting you can see that it does still
more or less look correct right so again
I think we're mostly there in terms of
like sampling things in using the kind
of sampling that we are doing here but
what you can see pretty obviously from
that is we're just not getting it just
doesn't work to look up like probes that
way blending as efficient as trilinear
through the voxel maybe in terms of the
small number of lookups Jeff Jeff said -
it's just really not producing a
particularly compelling result and so
what I think we may have to do is say
look let's take each of the light values
that we got and we'll you know say that
each probe you know we know let's look
up into let's do some kind of indirect
lookup so we can actually find out you
know where each probe was and let's
account for the positioning of the probe
when we sum the lighting there you know
or something more like that so that we
can actually have some reasonable
understanding of of the incoming light
and furthermore you know one thing we
may want to do is drop the resolution of
the probe distribution as well because
it may be that we're putting too many
probes in and that you know it's
sampling the lighting that densely may
not really work particular
well for indirect lighting because it
may be that that's just too dense of a
sampling and reconstructing from too
dense of a sampling will just have too
many artifacts because you're just
trying to fundamentally get more
resolution out of the scheme than you
can because remember the lighting that
we're sampling here is getting smacked
down very aggressively into just six
directions of incoming light which is
not a particularly good representation
of it right so it's pretty hard to say I
mean and other things that we could
point out here is we may also want to
try changing the way that we're doing
the light sampling right like with the
light storage you know going to some
kind of a different basis that's not
cube directional might be another
example of something we wanted to try
you know this is why people use things
like spherical harmonics and stuff to
just have better ways of will be there
you bell-like you know so that maybe
that part of it is the cube sampling
isn't gonna work either so we've got a
lot of things to consider but you know
we're basically where we need to be we
just need to now start playing around
and figuring out what's gonna work so
let's take a look back at that Z by a
shader again and just see like what what
exactly is happening here that we that
we might you know what do we want to do
in terms of the shader here that that
would still have some chance of running
reasonably per pixel but that you know
at the same time well let us do
something better with the lighting so
you can see here what we're effectively
doing is we're just relying on this this
sampling of the the light information
here and you know I again don't really
know there might be something we can do
here but there might not be I'm not sure
one example is for if we added another
voxel that just told us a position you
know maybe that would be sufficient so
we don't have to look up into
we don't have to do the in directed
lookup right so one thing we could
imagine here is let's suppose we added
one more voxel because we know that
seems to be fast enough is having about
having the voxel lookup so you know
suppose we took one of these here and
said alright let's let's take a position
so we'll say like light P and we'll
actually ask you know can you give us a
light position value out of this thing
and and maybe we you know it's going to
be a three-wide maybe we can pick an
encoding that lets us get some
reasonable resolution there right uh and
so and you know another thing about we
probably don't even need that really so
we probably can just just sample it in a
pretty basic way but anyway so imagine
we get a sample here we pull out a
position of a light and we could use
that to just say look why don't you tell
us where the light is relative to this
voxel right so maybe what we do is we
say okay we know where the voxel
location is right this is the look this
is like the center
sorry not centers lock so this is like
the location of the position of the
person inside the voxel space right and
then maybe you know here we can say well
where was the light where was this light
probe in that voxel space right like
we're in this voxel is the actual light
probe similarly right like maybe we get
that information out of it or something
like that so that we have an idea of
where it's coming from relative to where
we you know actually looked up in the
voxel
so doing something like that would allow
us to reconstruct a world position
unfortunately here we never really
construct a world position of the actual
voxel location itself so we would kind
of need to compute the voxel center P
before we could apply a displacement to
it but again
we could sort of cross that bridge we
come to it we could even pretend that
we're sending down a full floating-point
you know three float texture here or
something like that for the moment and
you know avoid the encoding problem and
then do the encoding problem off of the
box was a separate step but if we assume
some how we're gonna get a light P out
of this right I maybe I'll call this so
we get a light piano this somehow once
we have the light probe position then
when we actually get the light data here
we have a average amount of light that
we compute and a position that that
light is coming from right as part of
the fetch and so if we did that then in
theory we could adjust how that light is
falling on us based on our positional
offset now I'm trying to think does that
really help us you know it might not it
might require in order to do this
properly we might have to do these
fetches without the blending right so
that we then compute the lighting on
each of the probes separately and then
blend the result of the lighting
computation together and I don't really
know like just thinking it through it's
hard for me to really tell what I think
would really be happening there and when
we look at what the fall-off of the
lighting is going to be in terms of it
falling on the surface here you know we
kind of can add in the fall-off based on
how far we are from the probe
potentially but again that that's very
difficult for us to really imagine
because we don't you know the light
itself contributions falling off so I
mean just looking at this I'm just
thinking like what am I really what
would I really do with that and I don't
know so again I think just looking at
this I can't really tell what I would do
without turning off the sort of the
interpolation on the voxel and actually
just getting literal values out of it
right and doing the
myself
yeah I mean I just unfortunately can't
really I just can't really think of
anything else to do there and again you
can see why I don't want to do it
because the number of texter fetches
just goes up so incredibly much each one
of these is like an 8 way texture
catcher right
yeah I don't know
I'm trying to think in my head if
there's anything that I'm like missing
that would make this process smoother
but I just don't see it because again
like what we what we're trying to do
fundamentally speaking is use the
position of the pixel of the fragment
the world space position of the fragment
that's being lit to compute a lighting
equation that actually properly responds
to its position relative to the wherever
the light was sampled and the problem is
that when we if we just do a trilinear
filter on what we know these values are
I just it doesn't seem to really I I
don't think that's going to interpolate
as well as we need it to interpolate and
that's why we're seeing so many weird
like artifacts there we need a cleaner
way of interpreting this lighting right
we need some and it probably wants to be
more radial because lighting in general
tends to create radial patterns and
things not you know not square patterns
you know and so it just I don't really
know
I don't really know how we're gonna
solve that without again like I know the
way to write the really large version of
it I just don't know if that's tractable
we could do something where we compute
things that do interpolate properly in
linear like maybe like we use I mean the
nice thing about the the light key thing
is it's sort of a distance value in a
sense right and so the distance value
would give us a way to interpolate these
things that maybe makes a little bit
more sense so
the thought press I'm going through in
my head is that when we interpolate
things in a bilinear fashion right the
thing if we actually interpolate the
output value so like the color of the
light or whatever or the intensity of it
interpolating the output value we will
get the obviously like obvious trilinear
artifacts right so all of the way in
which you will see the edges will look
like a sort of you know it will look
like a bilinear filter it will have the
rectangular pattern of a bilinear filter
like you saw and it's you know trilinear
is just doing that in 3d so you'll get
that vertically as well as you would get
it in the plane right but you see those
sort of color washes that end up having
coronary artifacts to them like lines
going through them or coroner's going
through them and you saw that when we
were hopping through you can see it very
obviously and so the question is if we
were to interpolate something that
actually didn't have that property like
this is kind of where I'm going my head
if instead of falling down to zero and
actually producing the output value if
instead we were truck we did something
that looked more like a signed distance
field so something that was more saying
how far away am i from this thing that
maybe would allow us to create an
interpolation that works better
and so I you know I don't really know if
that's something we can construct for
lighting but it might be
you know it might be it might be that
that is something that we could use let
me run this one more time sorry I want
to see so given exactly what we have
right now I'm just curious
we have my turbo C I downloaded turbo
see the old turbo C by the way of the
weekend I wanted to take a look at it um
so as I'm like kind of hopping through
here right if I am to turn back on that
trailer I want to look at these
artifacts a little bit more closely I
also want to go make sure filling our
voxel up in as much to be should be bit
in my head and I can't see it
so if we take a look here at the
artifacts you know and you can see
hopefully what I'm talking about how you
know even inside an area that's
relatively subtle you can see the sort
of stair-stepping patterns that you get
there
and when you move over to someplace
that's that's gonna be sort of more dark
like here or like there right you can
really see the way it creates a box-like
version of this thing right so you know
when you look at a region that doesn't
have lighting you get like this sort of
boxy version of the voxel and it just
isn't you know it just isn't the the
sort of fall-off pattern that we want
however that is because it goes down to
zero
I think in those areas and it can't
really produce it's not something that
can produce a rounded sort of fall-off
in the area that we're talking about so
what I'm wondering is could we use an
interpolation in that what some value we
interpolate that is in linear space but
that when you interpolate it with a
trilinear filter produces a more rounded
fall-off right and so thinking about
that like I just want to draw this out
and see if there's some way we can tweak
it to basically not have to do anything
too much more complicated than what we
are doing and so what I'm thinking here
is like
what I'm thinking here it's like if you
imagine a typical bilinear filter what
we would get at a corner is if we have a
one value here and zero values
throughout then if you ask yourself
where is the point five value in here
then you know like looking through here
that's gonna be the point five value
right through here that's gonna be the
point five value through here that's
gonna be the point five value right and
so as you look at how each of these oops
no that's nuts wrong sorry that's gonna
be zero
that's gonna be 0.5 right and that's
gonna be 0.25 right because looking at
how this bilinear would work right
between zero and one I'd get a point
five here between zero and 1 I get a
point five here this here will produce a
zero so when we do but a linear linear
between the point five and the zero or
alternatively if you did the bilinear
blend the other way it doesn't matter
which way you go because this is a zero
here as well this is an 0.25 and then if
we further if we kept going on this
right so if we looked back you know one
more step
that's an 0.75 right
that's an point seven five there and
this is a zero here so if we were to
look at what we would get if we drop
this down a zero halfway between zero
it's like a point six two five right
I'll do it on calc to make sure I'm not
doing it wrong sorry in speed calc sweet
crunch so if we are talking about a
bilinear blend right between zero and
0.75 that would be what 0.375 oops right
so if we look at like the kind of the
pattern of values here that's an O point
one two five right
I think halfway in between those two and
this would be a 0.375 here so if you
look at these values you can see that
you basically get I think what amounts
to a pattern that looks like this right
coming through here I and so that's why
you get I believe those those values of
the you know just looking at what the
values are that you pick up if you
interpolate the light intensity directly
and output it I think you just get these
sort of corner looks like like that
specifically because you know what ends
up happening is the the voxel
interpolation is just always going in
these sort of linear waves and it's
either it's directional in this way you
know or in this way and so the question
is you know could we somehow encode this
such that when we interpolate it in this
fashion
that's not what we get right and so one
way to look at it is if you took a look
at what would happen in this bilinear
filter if we had filled it with
something else so let's suppose that we
took the you know the values that we put
in here
and you know we wanted a sort of a
distance based fall off or something
like that here so we had a one
in the light source here and we're
saying it fell off to zero here so maybe
that's exactly the same but here right
we just we say no it we're gonna
continue the distance fall-off so so
instead of clamping it to zero we're
actually gonna let it go negative right
so if the thing was that the light
fall-off was one along this then this is
like the diagonal right so if it fell
off one here we would expect it to also
fall off one here right if this is if
this is that distance you know so how
far should it fall off going in that
direction right and you know we don't
know because we don't know where the
light is necessarily coming from but if
it's a one here then we assume it's kind
of coming from maybe that direction or
something like that right so this should
actually be set to a negative value if
we use Pythagorean theorem we say h
squared equals you know a squared plus B
squared here right if we assume that the
light fall-off is 1 along here then
effectively what we be saying is H
squared equals you know 1 plus 1 I'm
sorry - right so H equals root 2 so we
would expect from here to here this
should be like negative root 2 right I
mean so it should be oops that
and so if we allowed the lights to fall
off in that fashion then what we would
get is something quite different right
depending on where you were in here you
would actually drive this this would now
could be contributing it before it
wasn't it was just clamping it's
actually essentially this would now be
contributing to the shape of this
function and it would create in theory
anyway I think some actual pull right
because you would actually be getting
some real information from it about how
far away you were right so the only
thing I'm thinking here is yeah do we
need to do something where we actually
push those values in as more like a
signed distance field like that we're
basically counting how much light should
be in there based on some kind of a V of
a location of the voxel sort of a thing
and again I just don't know I'm not sure
how to do that quite properly but it's
something to think about and so if we
were to do something like that I guess
the question is how would we do it right
let me let me try and play with that a
little bit and see what we get so first
of all in our sampler when we have get
irradiance or even when we're just
looking these things up to begin with we
kind of need those to be clamped now
because they could be like information
that would be negative like right so
when we are in the actual fragment code
here forget your radiance and we take a
look at the light delight value that
comes in we compute that light value
here by taking the intensity right and
we we use the light RGB and we compute
the color that way if we were to
actually take that intensity instead and
clamp it so you can't have a negative
intensity I think that would do what we
needed to do
probably it's worth noting here that we
have additional problems now that I look
at this because if you look at what
we're doing here too we have what is
effectively non premultiplied alpha
right which again does not distribute
properly across box filtering just the
same way like with our sprites and so
one problem that we have there is that
if we do want to encode you know for
trying to have a better encoding of the
light intensity by using that sort of an
HDR format that in and of itself is also
bad right so we kind of have a nasty
problem there this just keeps getting
worse right because multiplying the
alpha which is affected the light
intensity right multiplying that after
the fact that doesn't actually work the
trilinear that that's an artifact as
well so there's just a lot of really
nasty stuff going on here
and I'm not really sure what to do about
it
right
yeah I'm not really sure so if we were
to take let's just try a couple things
though I just I want to play around with
it because I'm I'm really feeling like
you know this is incredibly tricky and
I'm just not sure I can think it through
in my head and have any really good idea
about it so let's try playing with a
couple things here so let's suppose the
light intensity could be negative right
so in here what I want to do is take the
light value a and I want to clamp that
right so I want to say look this could
come in negative so what I'm going to do
is I'm going to clamp that alpha value
right when it comes in and so when we're
doing that sampling I want to take and
have a way for this alpha value this
light VA there I want that to be
possibly negative when we actually
sample it like when we're doing this
sampling here you know it can't really
be negative because we're encoding it
somehow right that doesn't allow for
negatives and so what I would rather do
there is say well okay when we look at
the light a VI guess what we really want
to do is bias it first so we want some
way of saying that this is actually a
range of light values that can include
negatives you know I'm saying so we're
essentially saying look this number
comes in between 0 &amp; 1 but what we
really want right is we want this to be
something that can range between like
negative 1 &amp; 1 right it's like a bi
normal number so we're like doing the
bias of multiply the alpha by 2 now goes
from 0 to 2 and then subtract 1 so if we
imagine we encode the Alpha that way now
we can encode negative values into our
light intensities and then furthermore
when we're actually encoding these here
on on the head end I believe we've got a
thing that does the encoding somewhere
know
being here I mean here we call like this
irradiance packed value so the
irradiance packed value wherever that
happens it has to respect the way that
the light intensity gets folded in here
the luck what I just said right so what
has to happen there is when the light
gets packed in here we take a look at
the maximum value of all of these and we
then have to say that we are going to
normalize by whatever that max value is
and again now I want this to be able to
be negative right
which is kind of annoying but that's
what I want so this can't be the case
anymore we basically have to just say
look if it's not actually zero we're
going to normalize even if it's negative
and go from there and so what we need to
do here is say let's take the maximum
absolute value we're going to normalize
by that and then push that back in right
so whatever the maximum value is even if
the maximum value was negative then
we're going to to push that in there
right and so the problem with this again
is that the negative values of the light
source like we kind of can't really
allow one to be positive and one to be
negative right that wouldn't work so
this is actually in fact I guess you
could do it this way so we're going to
normalize the one and if the light
happens to be negative I guess in one
direction and positive in the other we
just get problems there so maybe don't
do that right but if we try to do
something like this we would grab out
the absolute value we would invert it
based on that and if I guess now I can
leave this this way it doesn't really
matter we can do our scaling and then
these light values have to be sort of
absolute values right at that point and
what we would want to do
in fact I guess another way to look at
this would be what we want to do now is
figure out was this light generally
negative or generally positive and so I
guess another way to look at it would be
we need to take the maximum value but we
need to know what the sign was this is
awful I hate everything about what we're
doing
I just hate lighting in general this is
why I like rate racers they don't have
all this nonsense
yeah I'm really not sure how to how to
look at that cleanly because all we have
coming in here are lighting values and
what we want to do an irradiance pack
right we would need to have more
information to figure out how we would
ever make these lights actually come in
this way so we can't we would have to
change the way we're computing and maybe
this is still a good idea like I don't
know it could be but the problem is I
don't even know how to test it without
actually writing the entire thing
assuming that that's what we were
actually doing we could have to base an
entire algorithm around that concept
because in order to even figure out what
you stuff in there you would need some
way of doing that and I don't know how
we would do that so that's like really
hard even to experiment with we could
construct a fake case and maybe that's
the right thing to do to test it just
wanna make sure this still runs the old
way yeah um so you know maybe I could do
that maybe I could test it in a fake
case first see what it looks like with
that fall-off and go from there I don't
know probably worth trying I guess so if
we were to pretend that we wanted to do
that right and we so we ran things this
way so let's suppose we did this this
stuff things into the voxel directly
I believe I bracketed that properly
oops no I haven't
because the problem is this has to
happen in the other case as well so let
me see if I can get this back to just
using stuffed voxels so now we're not
like looking at the light probes at all
and we should just be sticking the light
prayer values in here directly of course
the problem is now the light distance
fall-off is wrong as well so that's a
little bit of an issue but we go in here
and take what lighter see so if I just
stuff this one directly so let's say
this is 3.0 F now which is what it was
before because this is being done inside
the UVW space of the voxel again don't
really know why we're getting oh I do
because the irradiance pack we don't
call a radiance pack here so the the
actual value of the light is not
accounted for there so I suppose here
where we do the light see this should
actually be whatever the light intensity
is divided by that max I mean it's that
true
so that's 0.1 times the max light
intensity and so you can see the problem
here is we have to divide by the max
light intensity here because we don't
call the radiance pack we just directly
stuff the value now what I probably
should do is get rid of this and call
irradiance pack right but I'm gonna play
around with this first so I don't really
want to do that with that tune a 32 so
it's a bit ugly but we'll go ahead and
run it here and so here is us stuffing
the voxel directly and hopefully that
produces a similar a little like yeah
you can see our little like light sphere
that we're moving around now right and
so my question is if I was to stuff the
values directly and use a bias value in
here so if I go into Z bias program
inside renderer and we actually like I
just put back in this code that I have
here where we clamp but we actually bias
the number so now that number can be
negative and we'll get it first now is
nonsense because we're not actually
encoding the values that's in that way
we're unpacking them as if we did but
we're not actually encoding them that
way
then we'll get garbage there right but
if I now go over here and actually try
to encode the values that way so we have
sort of a like light fall-off here and
what I want to do is rather than
clamping this light value I want to just
let it go right so now we allow the
light values to become negative and what
I want to do is clamp between like zero
and one sorry negative 1 in 1 instead of
0 and 1 so we don't have that hard fall
off and we can actually get negative
values in there as well and then we can
sort of play with it as a slot that's
see if we can create an interesting
version of a signed distance field there
in some way right
okay so we want to know the distance
from a thing that we actually are and so
if you look at this this is an inverse
distance of a thing so that is pretty
much correct it's multiplied by a value
but otherwise it's the same right and if
we go through and look yeah like we've
got the total here we're just summing so
I you know in theory I think this should
be okay and so what I think all we
really need to do there is actually
encode the value right so we're taking
the inverse total here to renormalize
this thing and I guess we maybe don't
really want to do that but when we do
that once we have it normalized we
should be able to map it from 0 2 from
negative 1 to 1
pretty straight forward from there
so I think all we need to do is like is
this so basically we just clamp this
these alpha values into range there and
I think that's all we really need
we don't even really need to clamp them
because looking at it we just kind of
divide them anyway so I think all we
really need to do is just do the bias
right so all we really need to do is say
alright we're basically just going to do
this negative one plus two kind of thing
so if we just say all right we've got a
we've got a value that'll range from
negative one to one now and we just want
to shrink that down right and move it up
oops I think that's it
and now it'll be encoded so there are
negative values right
don't quote me on that all right so now
there are negative values and the
question is what did that do to our
interpolation right and so you can see
that it did it did round it slightly
actually interestingly enough you can
see it is a rounder interpolation right
than we were getting before exactly as I
predicted so we are like you do get a
more round version by not forcing the
values to clamp we do start getting an
improvement and you can see like how the
actual artifacts now are not so
stair-steppy as they were before they're
still not what we want right you can
still see they do kind of have a
stair-step you like pattern to them but
they're definitely getting closer right
they're getting closer to a radial feel
and so keeping the sign in there doesn't
seem like a totally stupid thing but
we're still not at the point yet where
this would be considered good right
like that's not I mean maybe it's okay
but as it as a light source moves
assuming that you would see that kind of
a look to it right I'm gonna turn this
to release note so I get a little bit
higher framerate so I can watch it at a
higher frame rate interpolation wise too
but you can see like you know the
interpolation that we do there even with
just the using trilinear it does make a
difference right it does make a
difference
so length let's not write it off yet
okay let's see what else we can do there
in terms of maybe what you know what
else might make that work differently so
here one thing we're doing is is we're
doing a normalization right of the
incoming light because we're kind of
doing some some ridiculousness with
directional stuff let's maybe say like
don't do
you know what I'm saying let's let's
maybe actually just clamp it and take
that out of the equation for now and
maybe we want to do kind of a like like
let's just stop looking at the the
different directions of the voxel and in
trying to like just reduce the problem
space here down to something a little
more manageable so that we're not just
like flailing around so instead of this
stuff what I'd rather do is say alright
let's let's take this out of the
equation temporarily and let's
initialize everybody to effectively
nothing and let's just look at one
person right so if we were to just say
one person is going to directly end up
having their sort of light value coming
here so we'll just have light see and
then at the end of this right this part
we're gonna get rid of so here we'll say
alright we've got a light value that's
coming in here and all we really want to
do now in fact I don't care about this
all we really want to do now is clamp
that out right so I want to clamp this
value between negative one and one so
that it can't be out of range for our
encoding but other than that I'm not
gonna do anything to it so we're just
gonna stuff down one value that is the
distance from the light source for one
person right
and the problem now is since we're only
doing one it's a little too dim for us
to really see the edge artifacts
correctly so I'm gonna go ahead and amp
it up a little bit there just so we can
see right so let's go ahead and give it
the full power of all six directions
that's the wrong place to put that let's
do that
okay um and so now if we hop along in
there what I hope you can see is that by
getting rid of the way we were filling
the voxel we now have what would be
considered an almost almost correct
fall-off even though we're still
sampling at the exact same way in the
pixel shader right do you see that
hopefully everyone can see that there do
you see the quality of that now and even
though this isn't what I was planning on
talking about today
what do you could sort of see there was
just like a real-life example of why
reconstruction filters matter right not
including the negatives
you know clamping to a value creates
artifacts at the border normalizing
inside creates artifacts in the sampling
and what we got was you know a really
ugly effect out of something that if we
did it correctly produces actually quite
clean effect right hopefully you can see
that there and so as I'm looking at that
now that reconstruction looks quite good
all of a sudden you know I'm saying
and so what I think we might need to do
here is okay let's let's see how we can
let's see what we can do if we actually
have these sort of light informations in
here with the light normal right what
I'm concerned about is what we know is
that if we plug a sign distance field
into our traveling interpolation we get
the correct fall-off right and the
reason for that is because we can try
linearly interpolate just a signed
distance field that actually works
however if we want directionality in
there right so you can see that kind of
coming in that is not assigned distance
field anymore and so my assumption is
just inserting even just the
directionality into it my assumption is
that we will introduce the artifacts
literally just by that so if we now take
out the light C value the the multiplier
if I was to just literally that have
this so instead of clamp zero to one if
I literally just take this stuff and
clamp that negative one to one I am
assuming that that alone will introduce
artifacts if it doesn't how happy am I
because then I think we might be almost
done and we can just call it a day but
if it does then we have to figure out
what can we do that would prevent that
eventualities from occurring right what
can we do that would allow us to encode
some direction out okay what's the
problem here
oh right that's just a light normals we
need to take the light C into account
here so that actually needs to be there
so I'm assuming this won't help us right
I'm assuming that this this is not going
to be useful but I don't know so here's
that and I'm not sure why we're getting
sort of light beyond the boundary there
ah actually I do know why we're getting
light beyond the boundary there so the
problem there is that if you have two
negatives so if this was negative then
these negatives will turn this one into
a positive so we need to make sure we
actually maintain that sign through the
computation properly just quickly though
before we go down that route looking at
the way that this works I still feel
like we have the artifacts already you
can see them right it's not that nice
and we fall off anymore so I kind of
feel like just in general we already
know the answer to our question we don't
really have to go any further
so I think we kind of now need to think
about this a little bit more broadly
right
so what we know is that using just the
trilinear reconstruction from the voxel
we can reconstruct a signed distance
field which meant that if the only kind
of lighting we wanted in the game was
just a radial fall-off light well no
problem right everything's fine but in
order to have a more interesting
lighting environment we don't just want
one radial fall-off right so I guess
what I think is creating the signed
distance field and knowing that we can
try linear try linearly reconstruct it
tells us one thing we can do there but
it doesn't really give us much insight
into how we would actually be able to
reconstruct a lighting direction because
the direction function doesn't have any
sort of analog to that right especially
not when you're talking about sampled
light so reconstruction with a tri
linear filter if we know that it has to
be based on signed distance fields I'm
trying to think if there's any other
thing we could do there but I don't
think there is if we know that sign
distance fields are probably the only
thing we can actually reconstruct I
guess we're down to the question of is
there a way to take sample lighting that
we have right the actual sampling that
we want in the world and take take that
and put it into effectively assigned
distance field construction at voxel
ization time
right
and the reason that I'm not particularly
optimistic about that is because it if
we want to we need to know stuff like
what direction the lighting is coming
from right we kind of need to know that
and to be fair there are some
interesting things we could think about
doing there if all we had was signed
distance fields for the amount of light
you know one interesting thing to think
about is you could imagine saying that
the direction the light is coming from
is just the gradient of that signed
distance field right because the
scientist this field has a well-defined
gradient on it and if we said well the
direction that the light is coming from
it has to be the direction of the sign
this is field and we're not going to
encode things like east west north south
and down or anything that or we still
are but we're gonna consider each of
those things to be a scientist ins field
where the light direction is based on
the gradients of the scientist ins field
then we know that would be smoothly
interpolated from the trilinear filter
right in theory and so I really do think
we need to think pretty carefully about
this because again mathematically
speaking I don't know anything else we
can do other than a signed distance
field that would interpolate properly on
the trilinear filter right and maybe
that's just me not having thought about
try learning your filters enough maybe
there are other things we could do
mathematically that would add add
correctly in there but I feel like the
trial and error filter the only thing I
recall ever being mathematically
reconstruct a ball from the try linear
filter is a sine distance field I don't
know what else we could really do
maybe there's something I'm forgetting
but it seems like it breaks down to a
fairly mathematical process of what can
we represent in signed distance fields
because those are the things that will
be constructed without artifacts
how do you feel about that I guess I
don't know how people on chat feel about
that but that's life sorry I guess sort
of what I'm thinking and so if you take
a look at the equations that are on the
screen right now right you can see what
we were sort of doing there is we were
saying like look what direction is the
light coming from and that tells us you
know our normal to the light source
right you can see us computing that
there and we normalize that so we have
like a general direction and we're
saying this is where the light is coming
from it's coming from over here
you know we then encode that we were
trying to encode sort of light
information by saying all right
let's distribute that light to the six
faces of the cube by saying whatever the
lighting normal is that's going to tell
us how much contribution should go into
that face of the cube right and that
because so what you can see I mean I
again just want to sort of highlight the
map here what you can see is this part
of that equation right here right this
is the normalizer zero apart I'm gonna
go out on a limb here and say that's the
prop that was where the artifacts were
coming from there and the reason that
you know I suspect that is because if
you look at all of the equations that we
have on the screen right now that's the
only one that really has a nonlinear
function in it right and so what we're
doing so a trial of your filter right is
effectively reconstructing something
linear underneath it and so it's we can
expect to be able to do a linear sine
distance field should be reconstructive
all right generally generally speaking
it should be reconstructive all if we
have only one thing that is being used
in a normalization normalized fashion
which would be this length function
right here so one thing that's you know
a distance from a point we should expect
to be able to reconstruct it and we did
but here we've got a second thing that's
being normalized which is this light
normal vector
right so thinking that through I guess I
I'm gonna I wonder if we're gonna have
to actually work out the math and figure
out is is it should we expect to be able
to add to signed distance fields
together in that way because that's sort
of affected what this is doing oh this
is not really a sign distance field
either so so bear with me for a moment
let's suppose here we were to take out
this normalization entirely right so
instead what we had is we have the
direction to the light source and we
looked at that as a separate parameter
that was going to be coming down
separate from the actual light
information somehow right and so rather
than doing this the way that we were
doing it instead of putting this this
piece of information that light
direction in there well in fact you know
what let's think about it in even
another way let's suppose me were to
encode only the light sort of intensity
here and then we actually in here where
we packed the color we use the normal
for that right let's say I'm just just
throwing that out as one sort of one
thing we could try here just to see what
happens if we if we try to get that out
so we only have in the Alpha channel we
only have one thing that's a sign
doesn't feel being reconstructed and
then the RGB we put the other stuff is
there any way we could sort of make that
work again probably not unless we
actually in allowed this to be signed as
well so I suppose I'm as I'm kind of
saying that out loud I'm thinking you
know that's that's not actually correct
because the colouring value of it you
know wouldn't actually work there I
suppose so as I say that maybe that's
not not the best idea but again yeah
just thinking about this through so you
know what if what if we were to have the
direction be something that could be
reconstructed
correctly as well that's the only thing
I'm thinking because that you can see
adding that directionality in there
right we immediately got the sub
artifacting back and you know just
looking at the difference look look in
the inter you can see all the ringing
and stuff that happens in there and when
we turn that off right so when we don't
have the the light information in there
so if we literally just have light see
when we literally just have lights II uh
well actually know that one now I'm
getting that our fighting back okay that
was pretty instructive so what happened
there that was the problem I thought
that we had that reconstructing properly
but now that I look at it it's wrong
again is that just because it's too
bright so is it did I just fool myself
into thinking we had reconstructed that
properly which maybe I did maybe I spoke
too soon but I would have thought yeah
see so let's suppose we turned the light
intensity down a little bit there or I
guess what we did do is we only had one
of them I guess is one thing what we did
there
so let's say we take light C and divide
it by six just want to see what what's
up there if that's the case - it may
just be that again we don't have the
range for it which is entirely possible
as well you know and the artifact is
actually coming from the quantization
but no like that's totally busted
right so I guess let's take a look here
if I get rid of this and we nuke the
North out of here is it just the fact
that we have multiple directions coming
together that's producing those
artifacts so going ahead and increasing
the light intensity here
so okay so it looks like actually I was
wrong about that I'm now starting to
wonder is there something weird in our
shader maybe like I clearly didn't think
about this problem correctly because you
can see there is that actually as long
as it's only one of the channels it's
fine and if you stuff all the channels
with things that should have worked
properly you don't actually get that and
so the reflection function in here seems
to be causing more damage than I
anticipated so inside the Z bias program
just taking a look at how we're doing
that I'm curious here what's going on so
in here you know when we take a look at
how we're computing the you know here's
the interpolated value this appears to
come through correctly if there's only
one of them when we actually go ahead
and compute the rest of it here so we've
got like for example you know doing the
the reflection normal the interpreter
you know the inner product and so on
that alone seems to be enough to create
our artifacts so for example if we were
to drop the light down one I'm just
curious again so and allow both say well
let's let's try for example let's try
both west and south
and that still looks fine to me I don't
see artifacting in that reconstruction
let's try so what I'm doing here is i'm
just trying the positive versions of it
right so none of the negative facing
versions so let's suppose now we do the
west side the negative facing versus the
west the south and the down
and I guess to be honest I do start to
see the artifact and kind of coming back
there and so I guess what I'm wondering
is maybe I'm just wrong my intuition was
wrong about that which is you know
pretty easy to have happen when you're
doing something like lighting I guess
what I would say is it looks to me it
like it's really our box sampling that
is the problem there right because if we
do allow signed distance field
interpolation on our light values there
we are okay it really looks like the
only problem that I'm seeing is is
because of the box based lighting again
good to know right this is exactly why
we need to do this to make sure we know
what we're doing here because it's not
obvious so let's suppose I switched back
here I'm I want to know now if I clamped
my light values so that they actually
fall off they don't have the negative
values
is it possible that we didn't even
really need that that changing it to a
sign does this field was in fact
unnecessary right and I'm not sure
so again looks pretty nice and smooth
there if I now go and clamp these values
to 0 so the fall-off becomes you know
truncated I just want to see do we get
the banding or don't we okay so actually
I didn't really even need that I mean it
is true that it looks better and you get
well you know and now I guess I would
say it's pretty bad so the signed
distance field I was gonna say it's not
that bad without it but it is it is kind
of actually the more I move around it's
it's not so good so I do think the
signed distance field part probably is
important we probably need something
that it can that can be reconstructed if
we stay with the trilinear filter
reconstruction it does look like you
really do want this but it looks like
and maybe I'm wrong but it looks like
interpolating box directional ain't
ain't gonna cut it and again now maybe I
did something wrong
so maybe I've got a bug in some other
part of the map there very possible but
just looking at the quality of this
versus the quality of the box based
interpolation it's just I mean to use a
bad lighting plan it's just night and
day right I mean that looks perfect to
me basically I couldn't ask for a better
radial fall-off than that in practice
looks great everything looks perfect but
once we started putting in those box
directions when those gets summed
together it was not good at all even
though each one was being some
independently those directional values
just did not compose properly it didn't
look like right and so I think what we
need to do is take a step back and we
need to figure out how are we
going to interpolate light
directionality better than that
cuz that ain't that that's not
sufficient it's what it looks like to me
and unfortunately I don't know like I
don't have a magical way we could really
do that so we're gonna have to think
about that and it may require changing
to a different basis right it may
require using some maybe a spherical
harmonic basis I it maybe requires us to
do you know bent normals would be
another option I don't know I'm not sure
but just looking at that I just I don't
think the reconstruction is very good
with boxes
and we're gonna need something that
could if we're gonna use trailing you're
filtering we need something that a
trilinear filtering actually reconstruct
right now one thing we could do is say
maybe we just have to light directions
or something or you know what amounts to
basically like via normal because we can
interpolate that I wish I had a better
intuition I don't actually know what
happens to spherical harmonics under a
trilinear filter that is something we
probably have to investigate by we have
to actually write out what's gonna
happen if you do that reconstruction
because I don't really know I do wonder
kind of offhand what would happen if we
just reconstructed than normal right so
if we actually said like what we're
actually gonna push through here is just
the normal to the light source and we
store an average normal right and maybe
we sort you know we could start to to
normals so you know we've got some kind
of lighting information that stores you
know just various values in our RGB a
and you can imagine storing so like two
normal directions so to the like primary
and secondary lighting directions or
even just maybe one normal direction and
one color or sorry one aural direction
in two colors so basically like what's
the primary light and then what's the
secondary light so what's coming from
behind that you could also imagine doing
something like that I and spherical
harmonics are sort of like that but
they're non direct they encode the
direction into the coefficients directly
as opposed to having a secondary piece
of information that tells you what I'm
most tempted to do right now in the
amount of time we have left which I
don't think as much it's like 20 minutes
or so would be maybe like I
like to go in and see what would happen
to just interpolated normals can we
reconstruct those with the trilinear
filter properly because we know we can't
reconstruct them exactly but what we do
know is we can linearly interpolate them
and then renormalize them and
furthermore we also know that we could
encode them if we wanted to we can
encode directions as quaternions if we
want to and then the reconstruction is
even better right because the
reconstruction would be based on half
angles a set of angles and we get even
less distortion from the from the
blending of the two right so we have a
lot of options there and I guess what I
would say is I am interested you know to
know
I'm interested to know I'm also a little
bit wondering why with our light
fall-off here we never seem to get down
to black what's going on there is there
some kind of a what's happening there
did I miss something up there
because we should be getting no lighting
what are we stuffing in here so we got
east south north down up those are all
zero right so if we said West a equals
zero we should get nothing right this
should just be black entirely black and
we're actually getting some light so
I've got some kind of an encoding bug
here and I'm not sure what it is right
because here we're stuffing all values
to zero so that zero is not actually a
zero
I assume that's because of the way we're
doing the encoding here actually
producing a value slightly above zero
right I mean if you think about what's
happening there
so if this were to be actually somewhat
negative something's weird about that
because we have a clamp zero to 1 here 2
times the light value alpha minus 1
right and so what we should be getting
if this thing was 0 is we should be
getting full negative 1 right now we're
biasing it here so we can't get full
zero but you know let's suppose I
actually sent on negative 1 everywhere
now we should definitely clamp to 0
ah okay and how about point five all of
these should be black we should see
nothing on the screen all right so
that's just because our zero handling is
not correct right when we're actually at
zero we're actually producing a value
that doesn't decode directly right so
it's actually oops
didn't mean to launch the profiler so
when we encode that we need to encode
something actually that will map to zero
properly and when we're encoding it this
way what we end up with here right is
0.5 times 255 so like just to show you
what's happening there so we're ending
up with 120 7.5 which of course has to
kind of be rounded one way or the other
right and so I assume that the the zero
value is actually 128 when the graphics
card unpacks it and so I would assume
what we're getting well or it's 127 I
guess I guess I don't know I'll have to
go look at how the graphics card would
unpack that value let's think about this
for a second I'm assuming that the
graphics card impacts the value as when
the light value comes in
it's gonna take you know something it
gets like if the 1.7.5
if we round that and we get 128 and
that's what we store I'm assuming it's
going to divide that by 255 and get out
some value like that's 0.501 right so
when we take that value that value we're
gonna unbias it right so we're gonna do
two times the answer minus 0.5 that's
going to give us oops that's not what I
wanted
two times answer -1 that's what I wanted
I and then we're going to multiply that
by the max light intensity which we said
was 10 and what you can see there is we
actually get a fair bit of light out of
that now one thing that you may notice
about that is maybe that means this
encoding in general is not precise
enough and the max light intensity can't
be 10 right not with an encoding that
small and that could be part of it too
right like that could be the fact that
that encoding is it's not good enough
could be another way that we're seeing
the that that lighting reconstruction be
bad but but you know we can reduce that
and we can also try to handle our zeros
better so what we could try to do there
say no we want this to map to exactly
zero and so maybe we need to include the
biasing in there so let's take a look at
how what the GPU actually is going to do
look what the exact unpack equation is
whether there's a 0.5 Pius in there or
whether there isn't I'm not sure like
whether it's doing this exactly or what
not I assume it is doing that exactly
and so what that means is we would
actually want to subtract that value
from it right we would want we would
want to when we do the answer minus one
we would watch they want to do the
answer - 1.03 bla bla bla right like we
would want this right that makes some
sense because we care a lot about that
zero value and we want to make sure that
it actually falls off to an actual zero
value and there's a number of ways you
could do that but that's like one of
them right oops
not you there
so we can just adjust for that bias and
that's not a huge deal but we definitely
want zero to be 0 and then the question
is are we - you know how how rigid is
our where's our stair step there but it
looks again it looks pretty darn good
right in terms of reconstructing a
radial fall-off you know I'm pretty darn
happy with that I'm not sure what you
would really want if that wasn't good
enough for you right that looks pretty
nice to me doesn't it I think it does
yeah um so I think that's pretty good I
have no complaints about that and just
looking at the edges they all look
pretty nice they look like they fall off
along the geometry the way that they
should and I I would be totally you know
I would be totally fine with that
so then from there right now we just got
to figure out like okay so what about
doing something like encoding the normal
direction right because one thing you
can see here right is that the normals
just hard set to west and so what you
see is as I walk over to these you see
no lighting on those faces because hey
the lighting is directly opposite them
you come over here you see lighting on
these faces because the lighting is
coming directly from the correct
direction so these are the brightest
that can possibly be and then you got
like some limited brightness in the
areas of things that are sort of facing
more orthogonal to those right but the
question is what if we want this light
to actually have some directionality to
it and you can see as I move it around
what I would like to say is this should
be in the direction of light and this
should be in the direction of light
they're both pointing towards the light
the thing that's pointing away from the
light would be like these faces over
here like those are pointing away from
the light
right and so they should have anything
but these faces here definitely should
and so if we want to start encoding the
direction of that light in there what I
was wondering is what if we encoded that
just the direction and try to
interpolate try to reconstruct that with
the trilinear filter by taking the light
Direction doing a trilinear filtering it
and then normalizing it right so we are
trying to reintroduce the non-linearity
of the interpolation it won't be speed
correct because it will be doing a
linear interpolation that then we
normalizes so what you'll get is that
standard sort of lerp versus slurp
difference there but it you know it's
it's the worst possible case because
unlike slurp which is typically
quaternion you know we're talking about
the slurp of a vector which would be
quite a bit different than just a
normalized lerp of a vector
so I'm not sure if that would produce
artifacts that we don't like either but
what I would like to do is I'd like to
see it right I'd like to see that for
myself so let's suppose we were going to
shove some crap down there what would
that look like what I'd like to do is
let's take advantage of the fact that we
have some samplers here and what I'm
going to do is just try to jam it down
the samplers we currently have right so
instead of this stuff we're not gonna
we're not gonna code these light fires
anymore we're going to code that West
value which we did and then the light
end value we're gonna do all this a
little bit differently so I'm gonna
comment these lines out these lines go
away so actually let me do it this way
so these lines will go away we'll only
sampling the western direction now of
our lighting and that should produce no
change now right because the other ones
weren't providing anything and so all I
really want to do now is change the way
that I am like reconstructing the light
West normal so the light west normal
instead of being what it was before
where we just know that it's coming from
in western direction what I want to do
here is actually grab the light west
direction out of a texture so we'll say
that what we did is inside light sampler
East I'm going to actually have the
light Direction encoding and so we're
just gonna grab that out and use that
but I would like to I need it to be able
to be positive and negative right now
what I'm gonna do to give myself a
little bit more resolution here because
I think we can cheat a little bit in
this point is I'm going to take two of
these and subtract them I'm going to
take in fact let's do north and south
sorry so snore - south so we can encode
zero to one in our North and negative
one to zero in our side
flipped so this will allow me to do full
negative one to one without sacrificing
any precision of the 0-255 and coding of
the normal which is already not that
great of including of a floating-point
number but it's pretty good for only
numbers from zero to one
it's some resolution there so let's go
ahead and encode that we know this is
the light normal oh and by the way after
we do that I would like to normalize it
so light west end equals Naz like west
end right so I'm going to normalize it
we can try it with and without that
normalization so now what I like to do
is encode that correctly so in here we
do all this garbage and whatever I'm
actually going to add some some
modification in here so what I want to
do is say that the light normal which we
have I'm going to take and encode using
the BG RI pack function here in fact let
me just do this so usually the BG re
pack what I want to do now is say well
you know what the alpha value is going
to be nothing because we don't have any
alpha value that we need to come in here
at all and then the north and south is
going to pack in the information about
the direction of the light source so
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
take and I'm going to do a clamp zero to
one of the light normals X the light
normals Y and the light normalcy
like so and so what we're doing here is
we're just saying look let's go ahead
and give us the the positive version and
then what I'm going to do is it may be
the same exact thing for the south but
for the negatives right so what I want
to do here is clamp the negative version
so again I'm just saying look take the
positive component of the normal stuff
it into the north take the negative
component of normal stuff it in the
south and then we'll reconstruct it by
just adding those two together but you
know we're subtracting the south because
it was negated to begin with right
so that should allow me to reconstruct
the direction of the light somehow of
course we have a shader error here
syntax error
I'll expect identifier light West and
comma or semicolon
right you are sorry about that mr.
shader compiler um and so let's just
take a look at what happens if we
interpolate that normal direction now
and I'm again all I want to do now is
just see what I get for artifacts right
so I'm trying to see what kind of
artifacts I get when I do that
interpolation and now what you can see
hopefully is like let's say I stand
there what we should see is that the
reflection against the back surfaces
should be nothing right because the
lights coming from here and so that back
surface should be nothing looking at how
it reflects on the light yeah I mean
it's that looks pretty good
I don't see any artifacts really um I'd
have to squint pretty hard to look at
those to see those right
um and so I would consider that kind of
a limited success to be honest right
and you know we're don't forget we also
have some some kind of random crap going
in there that we probably want would
want to get rid of here if you remember
so the way that we were doing our
clamping here is the drip the sort of
contribution of the light source when we
multiply in the light direction that
it's coming from we're including this
sort of like biased version of that
because we have plate based lighting and
so if we were to sort of say well you
know maybe we're actually gonna do
something where we reconstruct light
directions a little bit more precisely
we probably wouldn't do that so we'd
probably say something more like just do
the direct version of this and that's
gonna be more representative of what we
would see
so that would look more like this right
and again no real artifacts there that
I'm that I'm seeing pretty much works
exactly as I would expect right so hey
this turned out to be a lesson for all
of us including me in reconstruction
today I not really thought about it much
because you know we hadn't done anything
with that trailer filtering but if you
look at the reconstruction we're able to
reconstruct those functions quite well
the cube was not reconstructing well now
that may be because we just didn't think
of the right way to reconstruct the cube
but it makes me feel like what we really
want to do is take a step back and say
okay what can't like that reconstruction
looks so nice
what can we shove down there that would
reconstruct with a tri linear filter
because it sure seems to work okay right
it does seem like the tri linear filter
we will reconstruct this lighting well
so let's just forget about the box idea
cuz maybe that's stupid and let's find
something we can reconstruct maybe
that's where Clara monix maybe that's
not I'm not sure but
you know that's that's I think what
we're looking at here let's go ahead and
go to the QA oh right it's a it's a
Saturday so the mouse doesn't work on
Linux what was I thinking
Oh alko is asking are you gonna upgrade
the stream for kur to the latest when
you and how and working on so no I
branched to my own editor now and it's
on my codebase specifically so it's kind
of a separate thing I only want to use
stuff on stream that that's like
available to the general public if that
makes sense
so I'm gonna stick with the one I've got
for us late comers what helps move the
voxel like outline of the lighting so
this is for people who missed the stream
so there's a couple different things I
and basically what I would say is the
high-level overview of it is that we
kind of have to remember that whatever
we choose as our reconstruction scheme
on the back end so in the fragment
shader we have to reconstruct lighting
from some crappy version of the lighting
right because the good version of the
lighting is everything's ray traced
always everywhere and you have you know
a machine with 20 Archie X 20 80s in it
and you can actually just run real time
full ray tracing on every scene all the
time in real time hall with no smoothing
right in some magical world since we
know we can't have that because even
high-end systems today can't do that
right you don't do full ray tracing of
everything every frame with no smoothing
you pretty much need to have some way of
taking your lighting and reconstructing
some low-quality version of it into
something that looks good and that
reconstruction itself is a critical part
of the algorithm so there's the sampling
of the lighting in the first place and
that's critical because it has to be
done quickly and you want to produce a
sort of diffuse lighting effects and
profit and light propagation that helps
make the game look nice so that actually
has to happen but the other thing you
have to do is you have to be able to
reconstruct the lighting from whatever
you sampled when you push it down to the
graphics card per pixel you've got every
sample it because you know you don't
have you got to reconstruct it you don't
you know you don't have the actual
lighting information at every pixel you
only have the lighting information at
some sparse set of locations and the
question is what can you do to
reconstruct the lighting in a way that
looks good and you almost don't care
about accuracy too much I mean you don't
you need it to be somewhat related to
the actual lighting but the most
important thing by far is that there we
go
good right because if the reconstruction
doesn't look good is it matter how
accurate it is it will be ugly and and
the most important thing in a game is
that it not be ugly right it needs to be
attractive looking because the whole
point of the graphics is that people
want to play it right does that make
sense
I and so what that means is that in the
reconstruction we have to consider what
things can our reconstruction
reconstruct well and which ones can't it
now there's a question of which kind of
reconstruction you want to use because
there's lots of ways we could do a
reconstruction we know that the graphics
card does trilinear filtering on voxels
very quickly right so in terms of
reconstructing a 3d effect like lighting
if we put down a low resolution voxel
and we ask it to reconstruct the
lighting with a low resolution voxel we
know the Gravatar can try linearly
interpolate values quickly so the
question for today was if we don't
change that right so we we stick with
just trilinear filtering as the
reconstruction you know I'm saying what
will what could we do what values could
we push into our voxel that a trilinear
filter will reconstruct pleasantly right
and so one thing that that we know that
try linear and bilinear filtering can
interpolate properly is assigned
distance field a scientist ins field is
basically saying for every point that i
specify something so each each cube of
the voxel or oblong as our case they're
sort of rectangular prisms but you know
for each rectangular solid in the prism
in the voxel we know we can only have
one thing there and let's say it's at
the center of the voxel so we know we've
got sort of a regular grid of sample
points if we try linearly interpolate
those we know that one thing we can do
is if every point in that voxel was just
recording the distance from something
right some distance and the distance was
continuous then when we actually
interpolate that we will get back out in
a correct answer right we will get back
out and actually correct distance from
the thing that will happen right and in
order for that to happen and to look
proper though we can't clamp to 0 we
could clamp to 0 if we didn't care what
the light was at zero but we do so what
we need is we need our range to extend
past zero we need to have what is
effectively resolution out in the dark
area right and what I drew on stream was
showing the fact that if you look at
what happens in a region at the edge of
the light source you have like a one
value or a positive value and then a
bunch of zero values around it that's
not sufficient to reconstruct what the
shape should have been there so the
reason you actually need a signed
distance field is you don't really care
about the sign of it what you care about
is that you have resolution of your
distance field past the end of the
lighting and we know the lighting ends
at zero intensity so that means we need
things that define what happens out in
the negative intensity because at that
interpolation border we need to know
what it looked like right now you can
equivalently do this by just saying we
don't have a signed distance field
artist this field goes from zero to
something but our actual like that where
the lighting ends is at point four right
so black is point four and zero is
actually super black right super no
lighting
um this is related to just general
isosurface sampling so you could say
like our ISO surface is now at point
five so it was zero point five and one
darkness is at point five so we have
full resolution fact we can slide where
that is anywhere we want we could say
that pure dark is 0.2 and so zero to 0.2
is the like boundary area where we
encode what happens in darkness
and then we use the 0.2 - 0.2 1.0 to
encode the light that's probably smarter
we probably don't need full resolution
in darkness that we need in lightness so
we can actually play with that quite a
bit and you know that's something we
should should tweak but if you look at
what happens if we treat it as a signed
distance field versus not so meaning we
if we have resolution in the darks or we
don't if you look at what happens there
so remember this is what the the quality
of the lighting as it stands right and
it looks pretty darn nice then we go and
we we look at what happens if we don't
use that scientist ins field so let's
say I suppose I clamp these values well
you know we can actually just watch this
happen so there you can see sort of the
outline and it's nice and encircle
alright and everything looks kind of
Pleasant if I go here and I change these
clamp values to zero now we've lost that
resolution so now the resolution that we
had in the blacks is gone and if we go
back and look at what happens when we
recompile and reload into that did that
actually work it did not
I was like that still looks like that's
gonna compile there we go
and so now if we recompile and we wait
till it to reload here what we'll see on
the border is do you see how it becomes
rectangular right can you see all those
rectangular artifacts that are now in
there right and again that's just
because now we don't know it's just
zeros out there so the interpolator
doesn't know what it's looking at and it
creates hard lines because it doesn't
know what should happen in those extra
bilinear samples it's like taking one or
two of your bilinear samples out of the
equation entirely and it really doesn't
work to do that right you need all four
bilinear samples to correctly tell you
what the function looks like when it
pass through that area and so restoring
that ability gets us what we need right
and now you can see kind of right that
we get that nice smooth interpolation
this is the same thing by the way if
you've ever seen like originally where
we did this for texture interpolation so
all I'm doing is literally like this
right this is this is exactly the same
it's exactly analogous right so if you
look at like valve I would consider this
a fairly seminal paper on this kind of
reconstruction if you look at what Chris
Greene did at valve he was a
lookingglass person he wrote if you
don't know who Chris green is it's
because he's not a self-promoting kind
of person he is probably one of the most
like accomplished graphics people he
wrote the first texture mapper you
probably ever saw in real time and he
was the person who wrote the texture
member for Ultima Underworld the first
like really full 3d game that existed in
the world
for the most part at least that you ever
played on a PC and that's him right so
anyway uh if you look at what he did
here this is exactly the same this is
what he was doing he was saying look
when we interpolate using a bilinear
filter if we're actually interpreting
the Terp lighting the color the problem
is that if that doesn't interpreter
plate properly at the borders so if we
then just alpha test something for like
a decal it looks like crap because it's
basically just like using the stair step
pattern you can see it right and so if
what we do instead is we actually track
what happens outside the region where we
actually have the full brightness what
you end up with is something that does
reconstruct properly and then alpha test
works exactly as you would expect right
and so that's all I was doing is exactly
that I was saying look let's track what
happens outside the bright area so that
we can correctly reproduce that fall-off
now like I said we don't really need all
of this resolution right we don't really
need to have like we can clamp this and
and do it in a different way right so
instead of negative one to one here what
we could is clamp it to the range of
like negative 0.2 and I'm gonna put it
to do in there even for that
and all I'm trying to say there is like
look you really don't need the the same
resolution in darkness as you do in the
lightness because all we need to do is
make sure that our borders are nicely
clean but after it after we get outside
that that border region we don't need to
know anymore so we just need to be able
to capture the steepest possible
fall-off at the border and once we do
that we don't need the resolution
anymore so we probably want to bias that
away spiney said what's the reason you
want to keep with the light probes
approach instead of using light entities
I guess I'm not sure I understand the
question what is a light entity
I mean obviously I know what a light
probe entity is because that's what
we're doing we have those those look and
those light probes are our light
preventatives but don't know what a
light entity is
hmm
so spiney says light source so yeah
again I guess I don't really understand
so just to recap the lights can be
placed in the world wherever you want
and that's separate so there are light
there are lights everywhere right
anywhere you want you can just place
light sources so any entity can emit a
light source if you want it to that's
there but that really doesn't have any
bearing on us how we actually have to
compute what happens to lighting so the
idea behind light probes is it had that
light probes don't put light into the
world light probes are there to say
where we're going to simulate light
bouncing around
right so the light probes are ways of
saying we're going to capture what the
lighting looks like in this area from
indirect light sources like things that
bounce off walls and all that sort of
stuff right and that's what a light
probe is it has nothing to do with where
light emits from light emitters are
totally separate and they can be
anywhere and they're unrelated to the
light probes right the light probes are
where we compute lighting not where we
emit lighting emit emission happens
anywhere and on any entity and we don't
care right we don't need to we don't
need to restrict where light is emitted
because emitting light isn't necessarily
expensive it is in some sense if you
want to bias your sampling to make sure
that you count for them more potentially
but in general I guess I would say the
the emission is mostly not the problem
it's the figuring out doing all the ray
casting to determine where that light
bounces and that's what we need to
restrict which is why we have light
probes instead of doing it per pixel
right because doing doing the actual
light transport per pixel is prohibitive
it's one way to think of it right
because you know there's 1920 by 1080
pixels on the screen at a minimum
before you even count like multi
sampling or transparency and so if you
just think about how many points that is
where - like where - like simulate the
bounce lighting it's it's just wait a
minute so the light probes our way of
reducing that down because we don't need
the light to change too dramatically if
that makes sense
like from pixel to pixel the lighting
probably shouldn't change too
dramatically
could you explain about the real-time
fluid simulation for games for example
how to simulate swirling smoke have you
read the paper BIOS damn on the
real-time fluid solver for games it's
really interesting in my opinion so I
guess I'm not sure which ghost damn
paper you're talking about are you
talking about the original paper called
stable fluids or are you talking about a
different paper
I mean I can bring it up for a few if
you know so you talk about this we're
talking about a later paper yo stem is
you know pretty prolific or at least he
was I guess I don't know if he is
anymore because I haven't read any
ghosts and papers recently but you know
he's he's made a lot of contributions to
gastrous so I don't know which paper
you're talking about but this is the one
that I thought you might be talking
about so you have to tell me if it is or
not this paper okay click on that link
there
to get it
[Music]
okay yeah so it this is basically the
this is basically the same paper it's
just a tutorial version of the paper
basically
yeah
yep yep okay so yes we are talking about
this paper we're just talking about a
tutorial form basically on this paper
more or less um so I guess what I would
say is I you know not today would be the
answer this is a pretty in-depth topic
so what you have to remember is that
fluid solvers trying to think of how to
give a high-level over here simulating
fluids was a very challenging problem in
computer graphics for a while
largely because it requires a lot of
computation and if you think about
what's actually happening happening in
fluid simulation in the real world it's
you know trillions of molecules that are
all moving around to form a sort of blob
right and the thing that we usually get
away with in computer graphics for
solids is rather than tracking all
trillion molecules in you know the 3d
cube that's bouncing around your screen
we just remember the general outline of
the cube right we make a boundary
representation that just says here are
the six faces of the cube and then we
just simulate it as one continuous shape
that everything in it moves together
right one like rigid shape and so this
drastically reduces the number of
computations by like a trillion right
because instead of simulating every
molecule in there we just simulate one
molecule effectively which is the cube
moving around and we just place all of
the rest of the molecules automatically
because we know where they exist build
up through this thing so it's really
simple right it just turns this really
dense ridiculous problem of simulating
the physical behavior of molecules into
something incredibly simple we know that
all the molecules just move together
right and it's a reasonable
simplification for our purposes now when
you start to talk about things
like fluid dynamics which is like
compressible fluids like smoke which
means that they can be denser or less
dense depending on where they are or
incompressible fluids like water which
is to say that water can't really change
its density if density is the same
everywhere and so you push on one and it
comes out the other end
it doesn't first create a dense version
and then slowly you know decompress you
end up with a much more challenging
problem because now you need some way of
actually simulating what goes on
throughout the entire fluid right the
entire shape and you need a way to
represent the fact that it's boundary is
continuously deforming right the shape
the can contents of this thing it's
constantly changing what it looks like
the stable fluids paper was the first
paper to apply what I would call a
backwards integration method or a
backwards Euler I don't know how you
want to talk about it there are terms
for these sorts of things it was the
first time that anyone in graphics had
ever applied as far as I know a
backwards Euler integration method into
something like fluids as a result the
fluids themselves didn't explode anymore
with large time steps previously things
were forward integrators these are
integrators that look at the current
time step backwards and forwards
integrators again the whole huge table
this is why I said can't really tell you
much about it today but I'm trying give
you the overview backwards and Foilers
forwards integrators the only difference
between them is in one case a forwards
integrator says one day when what is the
time what is my state of my system what
does it look like now I am then going to
take whatever my time step is and I'm
gonna move everything forward by that
time step using a physical simulation
right that's forwards integration
backwards integration does sort of the
opposite of that what it does is it says
all right I haven't imagined that
there's some hypothetical future state I
don't know what it is that's what I need
to find out but what I want to do is I
want to figure out what future state
would have an inverse
simulation that would arrive back at the
current state that I have right and I
know this sounds kind of
counterintuitive it's like wait what are
you talking about but the difference is
actually pretty straightforward one is a
solve and one is a expression right and
just to give you a little bit of
perspective on what that is I could draw
that really quickly I don't want to get
too far in the weeds here but the
easiest way to think of it is let's
suppose I have a position of a particle
right p and then I have some time step
right that I'm going to take right this
is my time step so this is really a
delta time right so have some times I'm
going to take and I know that like I got
some physical crap happening like a
velocity or something here and so like
the new point is gonna be some time step
times the velocity right or something
like this right so I've got a particle
that's moving through space I'm gonna
move it somewhere it's got a speed and
whatever right normal physics stuff well
normally the way we think about running
this in games if we don't know very much
about physics which is most people who
write games we would end up with
something that was like okay to compute
the new position what I want to do is
take the old position and I want to add
T times some like velocity vector that
is simulated with physics right or
something so this this is like not as
simple as as it looks like it's not just
a vector usually there's some physics
simulation with bouncing and speed and
acceleration whatever else but it
basically comes down to something that
looks like this equation old physician
plus some time variant thing equals new
position right and this is totally fine
for some things like particle physics
effects and things like we're doing in
hand-made here that we don't care too
much about we'll write this equation all
the time it's fine but once you get to
physics equations that have sort of
stiff parameters to them things that can
explode things that can go like really
off the rails if you have things that
have too much force or too many forces
acting on them or who knows what get bad
feedback loops
these Kings can explode pretty quickly
right and so what backwards integration
looks like is that's a little bit
different right what it looks like
instead is says saying well instead of
doing like a forward computation here
what I actually want to do is say let me
try to phrase what I'm actually doing in
terms of solving for the actual change
instead of just prescribing what the
change actually is right and so what you
tend to do instead is you see stuff like
saying well what if I said that I had a
P Prime right so I had like my new state
and I wanted to say that if I took away
right if I took away the actual if I was
to say how would I get back to the
original state that I had so I did an
inverted look back at the physics what
would that the solution to that equation
be right because I don't actually know
this value right so instead of just
looking at is something that's pre
solved right that's looking at it as
something that is just an expression
where I already know this and I can
compute this directly so I just
literally update the thing you instead
look of it as a solve of what would this
have to be in order to make this
equation be true right and you can think
of it sort of as saying well and I agree
this is really hand waving so I
apologize I should probably think about
how to present this in a good way just
not something I work with very commonly
so I'm not sure how to give it the
five-second overview you know things
that I'm really familiar with I can bust
out a good explanation for quickly
things that I'm like only dealt with a
little bit in the past they're harder
for me to to do on the spot but you can
think of it as sort of you know if you
imagine a diagram and I said all right
look we're gonna have
some orbital dynamics thing right and
it's like it's a thing that's going
around a circle right so I'm orbiting
I'm a planet let's say I don't know
here's earth right and the more burning
this planet I got my satellite it's it's
great right everyone's happy it's
wonderful
so as I'm orbiting this planet what I
know is that if I imagined that I could
just do the like cosine theta sine theta
pre-integrated version of this thing
well then I can just go around the
circle perfectly right but if my oral
equation was much too complicated like
it normally is when you're doing physics
it's not a simple like war but you can
just write a closed-form equation for I
have some complicated physics I'm trying
to simulate right then what I know is I
only get an answer at an instant in time
right I only can ask at this moment what
is like the force on this thing and so
let's imagine for a simple equation like
something like this where we know
everything we know exactly what it
should do just to illustrate but you
have to remember you can't do this in
normal physics the equations are much
too complicated they cannot be
analytically integral period right what
happens to something like this equation
well what we know is that at any point
on here if we were to sample what the
force is well the force is like some
thing like over the direction something
like this and the force is something
like this or something right so you know
we know that we're always getting a
force that looks like that and we
produce a motion that looks like that
tangent right it's always tangent to the
circle right but since we're looking at
a linearized version at an instant in
time what happens if we actually are
taking a time step here well if you
think about what happens on the arc I
always get a little further away right
because what I'm looking at is I was
supposed to trace off if I look at just
just a little version there I was
supposed to trace off something that
looked like this right and I had a
motion a force that looked like this and
a motion a total motion when I added my
old motion in my new force a total
motion looked like that I get a little
further away from the circle and then
the next time
a little further away from a circle
right I get I go out right and the
bigger my time step the further I go out
right because at this time step is huge
I'm away off the circle right so those
instantaneous linear solutions they're
there right for an instant in time but
when you try to take it fixed a discrete
actual time step instead of a continuous
integration it's wrong and this is where
you get into second order third order
fourth order fifth order runge-kutta all
these like integrators they try to
correct for this by if the think is sort
of maybe a parabola or
cubic then we can get an exact and stay
on there so we get an actual curved
update right and so on but fundamentally
you're just fighting the problem you're
always gonna be off right and so what
happens is in these circumstances
anything that's a forward so forward
rung to cut off forward Euler any of
these sorts of integrators they that
update the step they all do some kind of
really bad feedback overshoot right so
as the time stepping creeps creases they
just they fly off the circle they fly
into the circle and out they do all
kinds of crazy stuff right and they're
all because of that same fundamental
problem of we take a look at the
function we're sampling it and we're
just we're going off the circle right
the way that backwards ones work is if
you imagine this is really just a field
right so remember if I've got equations
that I can plug a point in space and get
my orbit out which is this is how
physics works we have some stuff we feed
in right then I could have fed in any
point right any point would have told me
an answer to that question right so when
I ask this question any point would have
told me does that make sense so if I was
here in my orbit and I asked what the
force is it's gonna tell me you know the
force is like this or something and it's
gonna tell me that the that once I sum
those forces together with my previous
velocity I get this and I
be out here right well if I asked for
out here I'd get the same thing and if I
asked her out here I get the same thing
just adjusted for how far away I'm so
the gravity gets a little stronger a
little weaker and that you know right so
again backwards integrators what they do
is say find the point wherever that is
whose motion line would point back to
here right and what that's gonna do is
tell me like oh actually since if I look
right at trying to get the right motion
line if I if I was to ask this point
well that wouldn't the the the answer in
the forward case that wouldn't do it
because the tangent here looks like that
so the inverse tangent looks like that
and I don't get back to where I wanted
to be right so the answer would be well
alright so if I look it's probably like
I don't know maybe somewhere like here
right gives me that maybe someone like
there gives me that and so what you see
is rather than a thing that adds force
to the system in some direction kind of
violently what we actually get is
something that removes force from the
system it will take less force now
because I will I will actually
undershoot right and unlike ones even
these ones that undershoot they would
under shoot kind of badly and go off
this direction or out this way these
will always find someplace that had less
energy in the system than the one before
it right then then the forward version
and so what you will find is that if a
forward version would have spiraled out
this one will spiral gradually inward
until it eventually stops orbiting
altogether right okay
so that stamp paper really all that is
is it saying let's do this let's do
something that takes energy out of the
system instead of one that gives energy
into the system so that we know that
over time our fluids will always regress
back to no movement eventually again
perfect for games we don't want things
to explode right we really don't want
them to explode
we don't care if they gradually lose
energy and reset back to their original
form because we're gonna always add some
more energy into the system if we need
to and generally speaking we want this
anyway our fluids kind of want to come
back to rest right so that's fine too so
that's all that paper really was talking
about they also do a Fourier Fourier
domain transformation to do its layers
the long start with some other things I
got here but that's really all it was
right is that super relevant to games
well yes and no it's not that important
in some sense because really we kind of
know this we know that backwards
integrators do this it was a good
contribution because people haven't
thought about backwards in boiler with
respect to fluids and so that was a
really good contribution and super
important is it what you wanna do today
not really yes you'd probably do wants
to look backwards solver in a way but do
you want to only do grid based methods
for fluids absolutely not so if you're
starting today you wouldn't start with
the Sam stuff you would start with stuff
that's kind of many generations down
from that and typically what people use
now is what are called
like mixed ways of simulating the stand
paper just does find any element so all
it does is a grid right and it
stimulates on a grid that's not a very
good way to simulate floats anymore
typically what you now do is you have
particles and a grid and you use those
two things together to simulate your
fluid if that makes sense right and so
the stand paper is good understanding
it's very good it was a very good paper
at the time is it something you want
start with today no so I guess the way I
would say it and hopefully now you maybe
see a little bit
about the backwards roller you can see
what was the important countries the
paper was that it was how do we get
backwards integrators into fluids in an
easy way
right alright I'm gonna go ahead and
shut it down Sam grab some lunch thank
you everyone for joining me for another
episode of hand made hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along with
series at home you can always pre-order
the game on handmade hero org and it
comes with the source code so if you
want to play around with that lighting
and maybe figure out what we should take
as our next step you could do that I'll
be back here tomorrow to do exactly that
I hope to see you back here for that I
think we've got a little bit of a better
handle on the reconstruction now and I'm
really happy about that so I think we
know how to push this I think we know
what to push on now
so we'll try some things we'll see what
we can do tomorrow but I'm excited about
that I think it's going in a good
direction that's it for today so hope to
see you back here tomorrow until then
have fun programming and I'll see
everyone on the Internet take it easy
everybody