hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero the show recode a complete game
live on stream yesterday we tested out a
potential method for doing sorting but
don't think it's going to work we just
kind of playing with some suggestions so
I think I'm gonna go ahead and do what
we had originally planned to do which is
just to do a full grass sort because
well honestly I don't know that there's
that much of a reason not to it seems
like a totally legitimate thing to do
and you know it's you know it's worth
having some craft code in our game
probably will probably have more of it
getting a little used to writing some
graph based code doesn't seem like a bad
idea because I'm sure we'll have to do a
little bit more of that when we do world
generation possibly pathfinding and
things like that so graphs are a pretty
common thing to want to be able to work
with and we really haven't had a lot of
a cult cause to use them yet so it seems
like it's a totally reasonable thing to
do here to go ahead and and take a look
at that so I'm going to go ahead and get
started here it is day 3 04 so you're
going to want to unpack day 303 source
code if you're trying to follow along
with me at home because that is what I'm
starting with today so let's go ahead
and get our project up here and made
there we go I and let's open up the sort
so we sort of did this alternative
version of the merge store here we
determined and actually this was thanks
to an excellent diagram poo shoes made
it there seems to be pretty clear cases
where this won't work so I think we have
to just determine that this is not going
to be something that we can use and so
you know this all of this code is
basically not not useful right this is
this is code that's not going to be
useful for us so we need something else
here and what we need here is some kind
of a an algorithm that will sort these
in terms of semantics sort by who
overlaps who and it
just take sprites that overlap it'll try
to do sorting around those sprites and
sprites that don't overlap it won't try
to sort those rights so it's kind of a
you know very a very localized very
semantic process and hopefully that will
get us to the point where we can sort of
get that working smoothly and then we'll
be able to put in whatever kinds of
operations we want right we'll be able
to say okay we can now just make
arbitrary rules about what goes in front
of what and then hopefully we'll have a
nice clean way of always having those
come out with the best possible sort
given the constraints by just pushing
them through our graph sorting routine
that's the hope anyway so you can see
here we had a build sprite graph
function that we started sketching out
and if you remember this was about three
weeks ago because I broke the microphone
and we were off for two weeks but before
that you can see we went in here and
said okay we're going to go through all
of the nodes pairwise and we're going to
see whether they intersect in screen
area and if they do intersect in screen
area we're going to use our is in front
of to add an edge between them which
which now says hey there's this bright
has to go in front of this right or vice
versa right so if a is in front of B
then we're going to add an edge it says
a's in front of be if it's it goes the
other way around we're going to add an
edge that says B is in front of a okay
so this is actually pretty reasonable
pseudocode it's it's actually almost
real code but you know we're going to
want to do a bunch stuff for the n plus
it's it's N squared as you can see here
so we're also going to want to do some
work there with spatial partitioning to
make sure that we don't actually go n
squared because the number of sprites we
have is pretty high like 2,000 or 3,000
we don't want something going n squared
on that that we would see that in our
frame rate for sure and well I'm sure
we'll implement it n square at first and
you will see it in the frame rate you
shouldn't have to take my word for it so
taking a look at this what we need to do
here is just go okay now that we have a
graph after this piece of pseudocode
runs we're going to have the information
that we need to to do the sort but we
haven't actually done the sort yet so
the next thing we need to do is we need
to just determine what should be drawn
first right and so if you imagine and
I'll just pop over really quickly here
to mr. Milton see there we go here we
are here we go
so if you think about what's going to
happen here and i suppose i should also
title this graph sort so if you think
about what's going to happen here we
have sprites and those rights are going
to be you know something like this we're
going to see that they overlap in screen
space and our rule is going to tell us
you know this one has to come behind
this one or whatever right or more
specifically a comes in front of be
right and so what we're going to do when
we have all of these here and I guess we
should also maybe make one more and so
in this case we kind of know all right
this is going to produce a graph and
that graph is going to have three nodes
in it right a B and C and what we know
is that every time we determine that
something is in front of something else
we add an edge from the thing that's in
front to the thing that's behind so in
this case a is in front of B &amp; B is in
front of C right so I'll state the
obvious thing first because you haven't
worked at grass before it's probably not
that obvious the obvious thing is if we
then wanted to draw these sprites such
that we drew the furthest one back first
right well if we knew that we didn't
have cycles and remember we talked about
cycles if we knew that we didn't have
cycles and cycles would be like if we
had a one from here to here right so if
we don't have cycles then what we can
say about this graph traversal is that
there's a really pretty straightforward
ways of us determine who to draw first
and who to draw last and so on all we
have to do is pick any random sprite it
doesn't matter which one we just pick a
random sprite and we follow its edges
until we can't follow edges anymore
right we just go doodoo and there's no
edges out of this guy so we know he is a
back most sprite and we can draw him we
know there are no
other requirements to his being drawn so
we can be drawn at any time as long as
there are no edges coming out of him
that say that there's someone else who's
in front of them right that's just a net
definition of our edge so if we wanted
to draw all this rights in back to front
order all we really have to do is just
go well start with the first sprite
follow the edges until we can't follow
them anymore draw that's right right go
back follow any other edges we didn't
follow out of that node all the way to
the end draw that right and just keep
following all the paths until we can't
follow any more paths once we draw on
all of those we've completely drawn that
connected subgraph and i could set
connected sub graph which if i haven't
already stated it is if there were more
nodes over here there's two connected
sub graphs here right these guys are all
connected and these guys are connected
but they are not connected to each other
right so each one of this is a sub graph
we could say like this with sub graph 0
you know and this is sub graph one right
so once i do that i know i've drawn
everything in this connected sub graph
right and so then all i have to do is
just make sure there are no other sub
graphs well how do i do that well it's
pretty easy again and I don't know that
this is the method will use but you
could imagine a pretty trivial way of
doing this which is every time we draw
someone we just mark them as having been
drawn so we mark this guys having to
draw and mark this guy's I mean draw
marks Kaiser named Ron now we just go to
the second sprite and we do the same
thing we do it the first right but when
we look at the first right this I guess
right rather we see it's already been
drawn so we know we don't need consider
it let me move on to the third sprite
it's already been drawn move on to the
you know the for sprite ah this one
hasn't been done yet redo the edge
following drawing algorithm which will
draw this right and then this right move
on to the fifth right it's already been
drawn and we're done so just by looping
over all this rights following their
edges to the end and drawing them in
that reverse order we would be able to
trivially take our graph and draw it
back to front very very simple so the
only thing that we really have to worry
about is the case where we end up with a
cycle because there's nothing that says
that we won't get cycles and if we have
a cycle then we have a problem because
if a is supposed to be drawn in front of
B &amp; B is supposed to be drawn Trent of C
but see you supposed to be drawn in
front of a then we will have a
circumstance where there is no actual
correct draw order for these sprites we
created an impossible scenario but the
problem is that could happen in the
world of games in two and a half d where
we're kind of fudging it and saying well
we're just trying to take to the artwork
and make it look like it's sort of
existing in 3d but we really know it's
actually 2d we're making stuff up as we
go along and we're making rules up like
this so we asked me in front of this and
this always ask me for this because
that's what looks nicer right but what
looks nicer does it necessarily produce
a consistent ordering so at some point
we will have to figure out a way to
break these cycles when they occur the
first thing we could do is just
arbitrarily break cycles and the way we
could do that is again by marking as we
go and if we ever hit something that's
on our path again we just consider that
path over that's a trivial cycle break
it just says ignore the first cycle that
would cause the actual loop to occur
that's probably not the final one will
want to use if we do find we have a lot
of cycles if we rarely if ever have a
cycle we may not care but if we often
have cycles due to our rules we probably
going to want something as more
intelligent about what kind of an edge
it added and to break to prefer breaking
edges of certain kinds that we think are
less likely to produce incorrect sorts
okay
so hopefully that I'll make some sense
for you since this is the first time
we've worked on a graph algorithm I
handmade here at least the Tiber claw
I'm going to take this in simple steps
so that everyone will be comfortable
with it so the first thing we're going
to do is we're going to build the graph
and we've written sort of that pseudo
code that's very obvious pseudo code
right we've written the obvious
pseudocode for it but we're going to
actually do the work of really building
the graph structure okay then we are
going to find cycles so we're not going
to do anything when I'm going to try to
draw with it we're not gonna do anything
with this graph at all we're just going
to ask ourselves can we detect where all
the cycles actually are right and you
know in so doing maybe we can remove
edges from the graph that have cycles so
you know you know we could say a sub 1
of this is remove them you know and then
finally we will actually do the step of
drawing the graph in order
so that's basically what what I'm going
to do in in series there and that way
you know we'll take it 17 we won't try
to do everything in kind of one pass
we'll sort of take it one step at a time
and you can sort of see how these sorts
of algorithms progress right and I'm not
going to use any fancy algorithms I'm
not going to use any fancy graph theory
here I'm literally just viewing the most
basic kind of graph work that the least
that I ever do which is to just just
tagging nodes right so the whole way
that we would be doing anything here is
we're just just putting a little marker
in those nodes and you'll see that's a
very that's very often a simple way to
approach prout graph problems that works
for a surprising number of different
ways you might want to diverse them
there is however a whole huge big field
of graph theory that has all kinds of
algorithms in it and so when we're done
with this we may find ourselves in a
situation where we want to apply some
heavier firepower if that turns out to
be the case we will but at first I just
want to show you the very very basics of
working with graphs and we're not going
to try and fit our our algorithm into
some other kind of category right okay
so here we go we know we have a list of
sprite nodes and so when we do this sort
of a be thing here in fact looks like we
have a bug in our pseudocode that should
be bound a bound be and when we do at
edge we're passing a and B there and so
what we want to do here is we've got
these sprite nodes and we want to
actually build out these sprite nodes
now the problem with this is as you'll
see if we want our our graph to be
optimized for walking which is what
we're doing like we're trying to get
from one you know place to another then
we kind of need some quick way to get
from a node to an edge right we need
some way of doing that so probably we're
going to need our sprite node to keep
that in mind now I don't know if we want
indices here or not I'm guessing that we
might not I'm not one hundred percent
sure but
if we take a look at what we've got for
sprite bound or or what is it where is
that guy yet here it is so we take a
look at what we have for sorts right
bound here right you can see we have
like this sort key and then we have the
index and the index is the thing we're
trying to draw and we have the sort key
which is the thing that tells us how
we're supposed to sort this thing and
what I would say is we don't really need
a node structure per se because we can
just use those nodes that we have we
don't need to create new ones we could
just use those sword entries that we
have so really what we need to do is
just kind of import this this stuff here
into what we've got right so I think we
want to come out here and say okay if
what we need for our for our sort key is
the screen area and then these other
bounds here or whatever then that's what
a sprite bound is now and then inside
our sort sprite bound this is where
we're going to sort of have this edge
concept here and I don't know that we
need indices for the edges it seems like
we could probably use pointers but i
don't really know which one of those is
going to be more efficient for now i
guess we can just use indices because we
will be able to look up directly so
that's probably fine but what I do want
to do is inside the sort sprite bound in
here i'm just going to chain these edges
together so i'm just going to make it so
that we have a next edge structure and
then in here we just have a first edge
structure so now when we're doing our
sprite sorting we know that we have the
sort key as well as the edge list here
and so then every time we want to add
something to it we can just go ahead and
use use those edge structures
okay so let's go ahead and start to make
that happen at let's actually make these
work to move this above here so here's
our sword entries function and so in
store dead trees we'd assume we would be
calling builds the the build sprite
graph you can see us calling merge sort
with these two pieces of information and
so if I come in here and I say okay
let's build the sprite graph here's the
count here's the entries and we no
longer have this input nodes an input
node count situation although I guess I
could just do it this way all right so
assuming that we have some input we'll
go through them for each pair we will
check to see whether they intersect and
sprite node is not what it is it's
called sort sprite bound now that's what
it was and we grabbed out whichever ones
we're talking about here we check to see
if they intersect and I believe this is
technically a sort key although I guess
no it's not now that I think about it
it's not really part of the sort key
that's not true it really is just part
of this the check to see whether we want
to sort things so technically it
probably should be in there okay so then
we check whether or not they intersect
assuming that they do intersect we then
go ahead and sort their sprite bounds
and I guess we're doing this is not
really i don't i don't know that we
really want to do this this way so i'm
going to go ahead and say let's do this
right and then our ad edge stuff is
correct so since we add an edge every
time I don't know that I need to do this
kind of a switch statement sort of a
thing so I think we could say something
more like if is in front of I think we
could just swap the two right
we could just say like swap a and B does
that make sense and I guess I don't even
need to swap them I can just swap their
pointers right so i can just say like
okay now we know that if a is in front
of be and I guess we to make it easy on
ourselves maybe we'll say well okay I'll
do it this way we'll just say that if a
is in front of B will switch it seems
weird let's let's keep a in front to be
so if B is in front of a we swap them so
we know a is always in front of B now
one thing that we could do and I'll put
it to do here is I don't know what we
want to do if the sort keys are
equivalent I guess to tell you the truth
we couldn't not add an edge so we still
have to add an edge because otherwise
you'd end up with the graph wouldn't
work properly I don't think
I don't really know that we'd have to
think about I'm not sure about that one
but anyway at this point we know that
we've kind of got an edge from A to B
because we've swapped them if that
wasn't the case right all right so how
do i add an edge from A to B and I
suppose actually die thing about since
the also since the edges are I really
only need to sort the node index I think
right I think I can really just do this
right because i actually am only going
to use this particular piece of
information so i don't know that i
really need to swap a and B in this
particular case but I so let's take a
look here so now I need to add an edge
and so oops and so if I take a look at
at what our edge structure is here right
I want to add one of these so I need to
do some kind of a thing where i'm going
to have storage space for a sprite edge
so a sprite edge needs to happen here
and then once i have the sprite edge I
need some stuff I need to know what is
the next edge going to be I need to know
what's the front part of the edge and
what's the behind part of the edge right
and so in this case I know that front
and behind i know that a is in front and
i know that that b is behind yes so the
only thing that I need to know is who
the next edge is going to be well what I
said was I want to chain and I should
probably label these a little more
specifically so for a particular edge
what I want is the first edge with me
you know with whichever sprite we're
talking about here whichever sprite
bound this is I want the first edge with
me as the front right because i'm not
going to point to edges that have me
behind because i want to traverse from
something that's in front to something
that's behind I never need to go the
other way right I never need to walk
backwards I only need to walk forwards
and so or i should say four words i
always want to walk from the frontmost
sprites to the backmost sprites because
we're drawing back to front and we'd
swap that if we wanted to draw the other
order right okay so I want the first
edge with me as front and then I this
would be next edge with same front right
with the same front value and it well
that's not exactly true it's the fur
it's the next edge yeah now that's right
if the next edge whose front index is
the same right because in the case where
I have something like this I'm going to
want to walk through all of these right
so I'm going to want to do this and then
this and then this and then this so I
want to know all of the edges that come
out of a front node towards all the
other nodes that they're marked as being
in front of right okay so when I push an
edge on since I don't care about the
order of edges what I want to do now is
I just want to know who knowed a is
right so I basically want to know my
front node is input nodes plus note
index a and so my front node has been
next I'm sorry a first edge with me as
front and I want to go ahead and take
that and put it as as changing onto the
end of my next and this is again just a
singly linked list let's go say now make
the edge that we just made be part of it
right so here we fill in the data here
we add it to the list and now we've
created basically our graph right that's
all we really need for our graph here's
all the edges now we can walk them if we
want to that's all we need okay so if
this builds the sprite graph then the
next question is well okay how would we
actually
iterate the sprite graph and so if i do
that let's do a walks right graph here
and remember that all we really want to
do like i said here is we just want to
find the cycles so what I want to do is
say okay we pass the exact same piece of
information we just assume that it's
been built already let's get out from
behind my head so we assume that we've
already built this fri crap and now we
have to walk the sprite graph like i
said before all we're going to do is
we're just going to go over each
individual one like i was planning to
before tax same exact same thing we did
only this time we're going to go over
all of them because we're not doing any
kind of pairwise stuff so we're just
gonna we're not doing any kind of an N
squared comparison you know what we need
to like get some more room here we go
all right so if we're going to walk the
sprite graph we need to start at a node
and presumably what we want to do here
is is probably do this recursively at
first and we might not want to do
recursively eventually because usually
recursive is slower than than not and
since this might be performance before
12 I think maybe not I don't know we'll
see probably it's the the part where
we're doing the trying to figure out who
it's it's this N squared loop that's the
one that we're probably gonna have to
concentrate on so actually to be honest
with you I don't think this part will
really be that big of a deal but we'll
find out all right so anyway I have to
walk this right graphic gonna do that
recursively at first so I'm going to do
a recursive front to back and all I need
to pass here is I'm just going to pass a
the input node array and the one we're
currently at right so what I want to do
here is I want to go I want to follow
all the edges recursively of this thing
and kind of fan outwards so again we've
set it up when we built the graph so
that the chains are easy to follow in
this order so I can do
a sprite edge and I can say well start
with ats you know first edge with me as
front as long as there is an edge follow
that that chain right just follow that
chain through and as we follow that
chain each time we walk one we are then
going to be in a position to actually do
something with it what do we want to do
with it well we want to call recursive
back to front again right so we're going
to again pass the input node arrayed
down through it and actually know it i
could put that here as well there we go
input nodes load index I and what we
could do here is note that when we do
this recursive typically we're going to
be passing the index actually because
that's what the person starts with so
what I could do is I could just say well
let's actually just do input nodes +
index right that way we don't have to do
it here and we don't have to do it here
either we just flash edge back right and
we could also assert here the edge front
equals at index so make sure that we
legitimately have built the graph
correctly so that we don't have edges
linked off somebody who really wasn't
the edge that wasn't the the starting
node so you can see us what we're doing
here right we pick out the one the node
that we're on from our array of nodes we
iterate over all its check its edge
chain and for each one we dispatch a
recursive call for front to back and
that's it right that's absolutely it so
now we could actually make this stuff
happen of course we've got some stuff
that we haven't done yet that would need
to happen in order for this to actually
do anything useful but you can sort of
see how it's about to happen right it
would look like this
count countries and then like this so
there we have that and now what we need
to do as well is actually do some work
in here right as it is right now we just
crawl the entire graph but if there was
a cycle we'd loop forever right we would
just keep on looping and looping and
looping and looping and since it's a
recursive function eventually would run
out of stack space and crash right it
would it would just go to the end and
and it would be would just go until it
ran out of stack space for the thread
and crash so what we want to do in here
is actually do some work right we now
need to actually do some work in here
and so that we can have a termination
criteria on the case where it cycles so
let's take a look at what we recorded
here for sprite bound and sprite edge
here they are now we probably don't
really need to mark the edges with
anything at the moment because it's the
nodes we care about cycling right so
what we can do here is we can set
something up where we just say flags it
gives us something to mark and maybe we
can call this a sprite flag and so we've
got you know sprite in this case visited
and sprite drawn like the examples of
stuff we probably want to know and so
now we know that we as we walk these
guys and we could clear those here if we
want to as well although we could also
clear them elsewhere so I'm not sure
really how we want that to work exactly
but we could for example assert that
they're clear as we're building so well
we kind of come through here we could do
something where we said like oh yeah you
know as we come through here
hmm you don't us realized this is not
going to work because this part needs to
keep this index so sad really about this
so in that case we've got the front
index in the back index and then if it
turns out that they're in the wrong
order so the B is actually the one in
front then we could swap the front index
and the back index like so and then here
we just say like okay we know that this
is the front index is at the back index
and there's no Maureen be right
better I think so so anyway when we come
through here when we grab out a we could
also sort of choice that up here right
because regret this a is going to be the
same for the entire time and so when we
grab out a there what we could also do
is just assert the A's what was that
thing flags 40 right that seems pretty
pretty straightforward okay so all that
all that being good what we now need to
do is when we do the actual walking of
this right we know when we do recursive
back to front when we do this call we
pull out what the sprite is what we can
do here is say well okay if the flags
that we're looking at here if these
flags are set so that it looks like we
visited this guy then we wouldn't want
to do this lip loop right if we've
already been here it's that make sense
and of course when we go in here we're
going to have to set the flag but this
is of critical importance the question
is where do we set the flag because we
could set the flag in two different
places we could set the flag right here
or we could set the flag right here and
which one do we want to do sometimes it
doesn't matter in this case it does why
does it matter well the recursive call
is happening here right so if we set the
flag down here it might not do us any
good right because this recursion could
just go ahead and do its little loop and
nobody ever gets marked as visited so
this will never actually happen so we
have to make sure we mark it as visited
first so that if this recursion path
happens to hit the sprite again it will
stop right so that's that's that right
and so this is a simple one of just
making sure that we never get that we
never sort of get into an infinite loop
while we are looping
now the problem here is at least thus
far we don't actually know we don't
really know much about cycles in fact I
guess I might have almost I I guess I
was perhaps not thinking ahead enough
when I wrote these down because actually
what we just did is a draw a graph and
order algorithm this would do graph
drawing in order but without intelligent
breaking of cycles so really this now I
think about it is a little more advanced
I need an ID for my recursion to detect
the cycles and I don't need that for
what I'm doing right now so I guess
really this is this is the simpler one
and that one's going to be a little more
complicated potentially but oops so
anyway hopefully you can see how this
works as we go we're just kind of
leaving a little mark that says we
visited so that we don't ever go and
process that note again so now if we
wanted to we could go ahead and do work
here right this is where we would
actually draw something if that makes
sense so you know that's that's all
there is to it not a whole lot else so
if we wanted to we could actually go
ahead and do that now I suppose so we
could do the walk spy craft and what we
need to do here is we need to have some
place to put you know the we need to
take those sword entries those sordid
entries that we will suppose way we need
to take our graph traversal and since
the graph traversal will be figuring out
what the order is that we should draw
things we need a place to sort of output
that data to write so I have to add to
my recursive back to front I need to add
some sort of a print out here like some
some output pointer right if that makes
sense so we need something like sort
spray bound you know out or right but I
don't want to pass it that way and the
reason I don't want to pass it that way
is because I need to be able to modify
that all the way back and forth on the
chain so I can't just pass a pointer
because a point
gets passed by value and I need the
pointer to essentially be passed by
reference so that I can update the
pointer as it moves and so what I'm
going to do here is I'm going to do like
a graph walk just a sort of a context
which I can put in both the input nodes
if I want to and the sorted output right
and in this case there's some
interesting there's there's a little bit
of there's a little bit of reason why we
probably want to modify our routine here
right because if this is the sort
information I don't actually need to
report back that sort information
because it's way too much right I don't
need to write back the sprite bounds or
copy ances all I need is an index list
at the end and so probably what we would
want to do here when we do sort entries
is we would probably now that we're
going from a large sort structure that
has a bunch of information necessary for
sorting down to just the draw order list
what we want to do is you know is have
an output here you know I'm saying so
that we can write those things in there
and then that is what we would
eventually want to pass so when we come
up through here we have our out index
list we're going to want to write into
that as we go and so then I'm just going
to say all right let's pass that sort
graph walk down here and then in this
case in this case we just say okay the
input nodes of the walk there we go and
then when we want to actually do
something well the thing that we're
going to do here is say okay the lock
has an out index that out index is going
to be this one that we're on
right so that's actually the entire
routine I know it may seem a little
surprising if you've never worked with
graph stuff before but that's basically
all we're going to need for the simple
in order draw because all we do like I
said is just chase it and then as we
unwind the stack right this recursive
thing as we return return each one of
those guys just pushes see on then
beyond than a on it just adds them to
that draw order and so when we're done
we just have the order walk that says
only people who had no edges coming out
of them or who had cycles are going to
get drawn first and then you know
everyone after them in an advancing
front that comes closer and that's it
now unfortunately we can't just run it
because we have a bunch of dependencies
that we haven't satisfied yet right
there's a number of things that we
haven't actually done we expanded our
conceptualization of what's happening to
include an index list that gets written
out we haven't done anything with that
yet we also haven't done anything to
address the situation with needing to
use sort of push memory although we do
have 10 memory so we should be able to
actually do that relatively easily
although we have to make sure that we
size that temp memory appropriately
which is probably easier said than done
in this case and then we also have the
problem of not actually ever filling out
the structures that we actually need
because where is it you're here it is
we've got this rectangles intersex
situation happening well nobody ever
actually made any screen area no one
ever actually computed that for our
sprites as far as I know so we're
comparing fields that nobody ever filled
out and so before this is going to work
at all we also have to go upstream and
make sure somebody actually writes down
the screen area of the sprites
hopefully that makes some sense all
right so otherwise I think we're in
relatively good shape so let's go ahead
and get this compiling a sprite edge
yeah we don't have any way of doing that
stuff just yet that is what I'm going to
have to do later this got changed its
name to that and what have we got here
right edge illegal use of this type I
know that one sort graph walk undeclared
identifier it is sprite craft walk there
we can input nodes an undeclared
identifier that is true and that is
actually not what you're supposed to
pass you're supposed to pass the walk
there in this case we need that that
walk so here is the sprite craft walk
and in this case I want the walk in put
knows to be input nodes block out index
equals out index list would I call that
I should be a ray it's not really a list
is it I mean it's just a nerd I and so
now when we call this we got to pass
that down okay so yeah I think we've got
most of stuff we want uh is it behind
there we go recursive back to front
still passing input nodes not what we
want we want that what else we get
sprite edge okay so I think we're done
so I think now all we have to do is
actually clean up the sort of
surrounding code and figure out how
we're going to get ourselves some
reasonable temp memory here so I feel
like in this case can we do we have
memory arenas support in here
we do so if we want to we could we could
go ahead and have a memory arena which i
think is what we want because we already
have all the code for making these
things work so I think we want to do
something like this right yeah and so
now since we're doing all of that and
we're going to call sort entries I think
instead of passing sort memory we're
just going to pass a memory arena here
and that way when we do the build spread
graph we can pass that temporary net to
use and that way we know that we're
going through something a little safer
that's at least going to warn us if we
screw up and you know all that stuff all
that good stuff so I guess we do a push
struct here is that we called that yeah
so that all seems pretty good the
problem of course is when we come
through here we probably don't have the
push stuff defined in the platform layer
I guess which of course is actually
including some of this sort stuff and I
don't know what we want to do about that
one problem I I mean my my thinking here
is that I don't know that we want this
code to keep running inside the platform
layer it doesn't really make any sense
that it was down in there you know we
move the renderer in there but it ends
up just being duplicated code so what I
think we want to do is is hoist this up
a little bit and instead when we do our
render group stuff I think what we want
to do is call the sort before we
actually ever finalize that stuff and I
I don't know that we have a good place
to do that you know part of the problem
is just that we don't part of the
problem is that we made concessions to
make our debug stuff all flow through
the same pipe and in doing so we ended
up in a situation which is not
necessarily bad but it is the case uh
that you know I guess I
should should illustrate it in here if
we go down and look at how stuff
finalizes you can see that when we get
down to the the code that actually needs
to sort of produce the final rendering
information here you know cure is where
it is right and so the problem is what
we actually would want to do is we would
want to do that before we ever did our d
but like before we ever got out of the
platform specific code so we'd really
want that to happen you know more you
know more like up I don't know where is
a good place for that we'd want that to
be here right where we do game update
and render we'd want to sort in here but
we can't sort in there at the moment
because we have the debug system come in
and it does it and so we would need yet
another thing at the end that calls back
into the platform layer to do that
sorting so what I think is possibly the
better way to go with this is to make
that sorting happen in pieces that don't
interfere with each other right meaning
instead of having it so that you plough
everything into the render list and then
you have at the end someone who sorts
everything together including all the
stuff from the debug system I'm thinking
that the smarter thing to do would be
that sort is actually inside the render
like when you produce a section of the
render code so that when the game
produces it's stuff that's sorted and
then the debug system produces its and
that doesn't really even have to be
sorted potentially we could make it so
the debug system just always draws an
order or does something else who knows
or the debug system also calls disorder
either way I don't care but I think
that's what we want right so I think
what we want to have happen is we want
that sort to happen in a different place
make sense so yeah so okay so that's
what we would like to do and
unfortunately you know all this stuff is
not going to happen in the next 10
minutes necessarily which i think is how
much time we've got
but we can do a bunch more stuff with it
right we can we can do sweet we can get
ourselves closer so that maybe tomorrow
we could finish it up and start
debugging all right so let's start with
some obvious stuff let's go to render
group so here's how the render group
works currently where are you push entry
push render element so you can see how
this works right you remember we push at
the beginning in the end and at the end
we push sword entries right and they
kind of stack down in there that's where
this stuff is right so we know that
we've got a bunch of sword entries and
we know that those sword entries exist
at the end of the list so what we should
be able to do is we should be able to
sort those sort of individually right
meaning if what's currently happening is
a relatively straightforward process of
ok here is the element data and here is
the sort data
we've filled up this buffer and now all
we really need to do is replace this
sort data with the actual order we want
to draw things in right but we can do
that at any time there's no reason we
have to do that you know there's no
reason we have to wait I guess is what
I'm saying because here's like the game
sort data right and here's the debug
sort data and there's no reason we have
to wait on those right we can produce
multiple ones of these and then run them
right weekends week that's well within
our ability to do and so that seems like
a reasonable idea to me the other thing
we could do and I'll have to think about
this but the other thing we could do is
not actually we could think of these as
being more separate so we could have
like to push buffers or something where
we push in elements and then sort data
and then sort data you know the element
buffer just towards everything that
we're going to need to draw these kind
of get baked down into lists or i should
say arrays of indices back into the
element data and those arrays of indices
are what we then pass down to draw and
we have one for the game you know and
one for the debug and so I'm not sure
I'm not sure how I want this to go
think about that a little bit
it would seem to me that either way
we're going to need some sort of
additional information here because for
example if you have multiple people who
all pushed into this buffer and you're
saying we're not going to sort these
guys against each other then you end up
in a circumstance certainly where the
you'd at least have to say that this
stuff gets drawn on top of this stuff
right because the debug information has
to be drawn on top of the game and so if
they didn't get sorted together you know
you would end up in that situation
I'm not sure what I want to do about
that I would say that the other thing
and it's not really obvious to me why we
didn't already do this is I'm not sure
why we don't draw in two passes like the
other way to do this is we just draw the
game data once in the debug data in the
second pass and maybe the reason we
didn't do that is because we wanted to
be able to integrate debug elements into
the game so that they sort inside I
don't know that that makes a whole lot
of sense as a as a goal though so you
know do you see kind of what I'm saying
there where I feel like we could do
something where we just do begin and end
pair and then begin an n pair in a way
that's cleaner than that you know hmm so
let me just kind of make that a little
bit more directly illustrative for you
so I guess what I'm saying here is if
you take a look at what happens with the
win32 stuff you can see that we have
let's go ahead and drop the runner
commands you can see here that we make
our render commands right and we come
through here and we give the game the
ability to add to those render commands
there's nothing to stop us from right
here issuing those render commands right
and then creating another one of these
that we then have occur down here
right where is it right here so I don't
know let's take a look inside I would
like to know what what is the clip
memory used for I'm just curious like
where do we actually use clip memory
because we pass clip memory when we call
win32 play buffer and window like
there's clip memory and we do linearized
clip Rex there so okay so we're just
pulling stuff out of of we're just
trying to make a linear version of the
clip Rex so that that is also something
that could have been done by the other
code right so there's just a lot of
leakage here where we're getting stuff
out into the platform layer that doesn't
really need to be there and just because
it's more convenient to do it that way
the time which is fine but like I said
this is kind of a situation where I'm
thinking to myself do I want to take a
step here and smooth that out where
we're that's actually done in the platen
the platform independent layer and so
that we have the sort and the linearize
happen there and then the game code is
only responsible for doing the the basic
operation of iterator of the draw list
and i think i do i think i do so i think
what i'm going to do is when a doctor i
do that right now because i think that's
going to be too much probably for right
now so what I'm going to do instead is
I'm gonna probably go ahead and and and
leave this mmm a little bit gimped at
the moment let's see here
push oops where is my push there it is
so I'm going to go ahead and and do my
make sure that works and then when we
call sort entries here I'll just pass 0
and this will just be well I guess it's
actually move this into plot from civic
fair protect you know what I could do
let's do that so now I think actually
we'd still run and our entries just
won't be sorted so there you go all
right so we won't crash so I think I'm
going to end it there and then what I'm
gonna do tomorrow is I'm going to move
that stuff inside and we'll keep the
sorting inside and then we will go ahead
and finish up our graph stuff and yeah
and that I think will be good so let's
go ahead and go to the QA case anyone
has any
questions does anyone have questions
was enabled did you discuss why you are
using recursion and any concerns with
stack overflows yes actually when I type
that in I said we probably won't use
recursion actually so the recursion is
just there because it's the easiest one
to see first but I don't know that I'm
necessarily concerned with stack
overflow I'm more concerned about the
performance overhead because I've had
bad experiences in the past with relying
on recursive functions they just they
take longer than you'd think they would
or maybe I shouldn't said they take as
long as you would think there's an extra
function call every essentially
iteration of a loop which is just a ton
of wasted work right and so I would say
that my my inclination is that there
will probably be enough fussing around
in here that we will not want to use a
recursive function for traversing
Brian wag working with grass can be
difficult do you have any techniques for
debugging them other than observing
screen renders or is that mostly
sufficient um so I guess what I would
say is in this case the out what we're
doing is is pretty straightforward so
it's possible that we'll be able to do
it with just with just observing screen
renders but I would say no in general
that is not sufficient so it might be
sufficient this time around I don't know
that it would be sufficient most of the
time certainly I've had times when graph
things are more complicated and it's not
sufficient and what I can say is there's
typically two approaches there one is
you just make something that draws a
graph yourself so you can watch it and
the other one is that you dumped to a
data format and then feed it into a
graph drawing tool right and so you know
if we end up in having trouble debugging
our graph stuff will employ something
like this one of one of those techniques
if we don't we won't but yeah I would
say that it depends on what you're doing
the techniques that I'm contemplating
using here aren't that complicated so we
might not ever run into a circumstance
complicated enough to warrant more
advanced grafton buggin techniques but
if you're doing complex things with
graphs you often can run into that for
sure and it is not and you typically do
need a visualization for that
Rome says did we address the possibility
for intersecting sprites we won't allow
intersecting sprites so that's just
considered not a thing right meaning if
sprites intersect whatever happens
happens to them as far as I'm concerned
Lumine Ian when I code I use the mass a
lot you seem to be using a lot of
shortcuts to jump here and there could
you tell me more about your shortcuts
yeah I think I documented them all on
the four coder stream I mean basically
if you if you have pre-ordered handmade
hero in the source code inside the
source code zips they're actually all in
there too for kodir casey has them all
they're right here whereas here it is so
like these are these are all the
shortcuts and what they're bound to
do you know the dev Gary Numan no I
don't think I do
yeah Sean I'm sort of snooping the chat
right now since there are no questions I
really wish razor would not make you
have an account I wish the drivers were
just on the stupid web page and you
could download them easily and all that
sort of stuff but yeah I've been meaning
to tweet at them about that because i
really like their hardware what's that
shirt this this is this is a vowel it's
a cool owl it was given to me by my
friend Matt Cornell he's given me the
only I only have two cool shirts and
this is one of them and Matt actually
gave me both of them the other one is a
is a blue shell from mario kart but done
in the style of a da Vinci look at like
a Da Vinci uber weapon sketch
all right there's no more puke Owens I
will wind it down I will bind it down
and you know what I should do to since
we have a little extra timer I should
download the new version of Milton so
maybe I'll do that as soon as I wrap up
here all right thank you everyone for
joining me for an episode of handmade
hero it's and a pleasure coding with you
as always if you would like to follow
along at home you can always pro2 the
game on handmade hero or get comes with
a source code even as we develop it you
can also go to our forum site which has
questions and answers and all kinds of
good stuff like that we have a patreon
page and go do from a sport the video
series a schedule bot you can go to if
you want to know when we're going to be
live in a Saudi I'd for trying to catch
up on old parts of the series if you're
if you're coming in New that's about it
for today I will be back here tomorrow
at eight tomorrow 8pm pacific daylight
time hope see you all here for that
until then have fun programming and I'll
see you guys on the internet take it
easy everyone