start recording there we go hello
everyone and welcome to handmade Hero
the show where we code a complete game
live from scratch no libraries no
engines all by are very lonesomes just
just me and me and the fine fellows on
the stream I don't actually know how
many people we've got tonight but
there's there's always a good crowd here
and they're always very supportive and
it seems like they're really some pretty
awesome people from interacting with
them on the forums and stuff so I really
couldn't ask for a better team to put
this game together with I could tell you
that right now now one of the things a
lot of people ask is why are we coding
game from scratch well half for
education half for fun I think there's a
lot to be learned from doing an entire
game from scratch and not relying on
other people's code because it forces us
to learn everything and we get to know
basically everything that goes on inside
a real professional quality you know
performant game engine but also because
it's just a lot of fun it's fun to go
you know spend some time doing things
just because they're interesting you
know and and so sometimes it doesn't
necessarily have to be the most rational
choice maybe you could go get a library
to do something but sometimes just once
in a while and this product is that once
in a while certainly for me and for a
lot of other people to kind of get in
there and just say hey let's play around
this for a while let's see what we can
do with it and frankly I think that's a
lot of fun it also tends to be where a
lot of new stuff is determined like
maybe you go in somewhere thinking
you're just doing something for fun and
it turns out you come up with a whole
new way of doing things that's better
than what's currently being done out
there so that's pretty cool too so
anyway here we are on day 41 which is
basically we've we do roughly an hour a
night of programming here on the stream
and so 40 hours is one workweek so
basically we are at the point where you
have finished one work week's worth of
work and we have our game running it's
got a little guy who walks around inside
of a tile map and basically what we
wanted to do was start moving from that
into something that's more of a full
game that's got like a good character
motion feel to it something that's got
some nice graphics for the backgrounds
is that sort of stuff and what I decided
we will do right at the cusp or I had to
start talking about math for real
because basically everything that we
want to do from here on in is going to
involve math that's that's more
complicated than just basic algebra
pretty much everything on the stream
that we've done so far has been stuff
that you could understand with
basic algebra skills and so now we're
kind of crossing that threshold where
that's not gonna be true anymore so I
thought like it might be a good idea for
those people out there who aren't super
comfortable with a lot of different math
stuff to just kind of start giving a
little bit of an overview of that and
maybe spend a day or two talking about
math and getting people on the same page
and then from then on we can kind of
play that as it as it comes up so I do
apologize for people out there who
already know math especially those
people out there who already know math
better than I do because obviously
you're gonna be pretty bored through
some of this stuff and that's fine you
know that's just what can I say we got
it we got to go over at some point so I
do apologize for that but hopefully you
know at the very least it'll still be
interesting stuff to talk about and
maybe you can also help out other people
on the stream who are having trouble who
are new to the math and don't
necessarily know all this stuff already
okay so what I did because I thought
this would be interesting to start us
off for our Monday stream what I did was
I decided that I'd like to sort of make
this this next hour here sort of be a
general answer in so much as can be as
one can be made to the the folks who
often asked the question and a lot of
times these are perhaps younger people
who ask this question you know people in
high school or whatever who are you know
maybe interested in game development but
don't know very much about how math and
game development relate to each other
who asked the question like do I need to
know mathematics in order to be a game
programmer or you know how much
mathematics or what mathematics do I
need to know how important is it that
sort of thing and I hear that question
asks a lot and I've never really stopped
to put together a real complete answer
usually with just what I say is it
depends on what kind of programming you
want to do if you want to be somebody
who programs you know just straight like
very logic oriented code that doesn't
really do a lot of motion stuff that
doesn't do a lot of randomness and stuff
like this then maybe you know you could
be a game programmer like a light game
programmer without really knowing very
much math and certainly if you want to
do programming in other disciplines that
aren't game related their entire like
disciplines of programming that really
don't involve any math at all
like you could probably have a career
that's really well-paid doing stuff that
had nothing to do with math most of the
time in other areas of programming but
the reality is that if game engine
programming like if actual real game
engine programming is something that you
are sort of looking at like you want to
be able to be either a full spectrum
programmer or somebody who does game
engine work the truth is that math is
actually used pretty much in everything
you do so it's almost impossible to
escape having at least you know a pretty
good grasp on a number of mathematical
topics it doesn't necessarily mean that
you have to be a really good
mathematician I know I certainly am NOT
but it does mean that you have to have
that familiarity and you have to have a
certain facility with these math
concepts in the sense that you use them
like tools and you have to be very fast
using them like tools to get work done
and that is just really the reality of
math and so what I wanted to do today
was I tried to make a list and I'm sure
it's probably an incomplete list but I
tried to make a list that was all of the
types of mathematics that just me just
just myself just I have had to use in
making game code over the past 30 years
so basically this is I'm and what I'm
gonna do today is basically go through
this list and show you why each one was
necessary and what I actually used it
for in so much as I can give sort of the
capsule summary and I think that'll
basically be the best way that I could
set us up for our discussions about math
that will go on for the next year or two
as we come to the various things that we
need I'll be able to kind of refer back
and go remember I talked about this well
now is the time that we have to start
using it and so I'd like to just kind of
go through these and see if I can
basically give that sort of high level
conceptual overview so that people who
really just don't have a lot of math
background here will sort of now know
okay like here's actually sort of the
breadth of the stuff that's actually
involved in one just one programmers
stuff that they've done over the course
of their career and yuka it's also safe
to assume that if you pick another game
programmer you'd get a different set a
lot of it would probably intersect with
mine but they'd probably have some
there that I don't have so they'd
probably know some branches of math and
some things in very expansive math that
I never had to do and don't know and
vice versa right so okay let's get
started with the basics okay so I
believe it's we're back to our little
hand in I don't know why
loves the little hand so much but it
really does seem to alright I'm gonna go
ahead and move my my thing here for
drawing I'm actually using the drawing
tablet today drawing yeah my handwriting
is not so good on tablets I apologize
for that but that's just that's just how
it goes sometimes alright so let's start
by pointing out just the most basic
thing which is that if you are in high
school I'm assuming that you probably
have done arithmetic right algebra just
basic algebra you know basic basic
algebra geometry trigonometry whoa
tree there we go I know what's up with
this pen right here and calculus
probably now I realize that some people
maybe maybe haven't actually taken
calculus in their in their high school
years but I think most places probably
it would look something like this so you
have arithmetic algebra geometry
trigonometry calculus you've had this by
the time you would be in high school
sometime maybe you'd have to get two
very senior year to do calculus maybe
you'd do it earlier I'm not sure but if
you look something like this so
obviously you know that these two are
involved in all kinds of programming
because you've already seen me do these
on the string okay so two things that
you learn in grade school you've already
seen me doing this dream arithmetic is
we basically have to know that because
that's what we're program that computer
do all the time addition subtraction
multiplication blah blah blah you've
seen me do a ton of that in the stream
obviously the computer is doing tons of
it per frame there's no question there
algebra same thing you've seen me use it
lightly so far on the stream I believe
we had to solve for something once you
saw me rearrange terms just the other
day when I wrote down something of the
form I believe I did a plus
B minus a right and I said oh I could go
ahead and and rearrange this you know I
crossed out the eight terms or something
like that and then I also did one for
the the T I distributed the term so I
use the distributive property for t I
don't know if you guys were watching
when I did that but that was something I
did the other day so you've already seen
me do like algebra on the stream and it
will only get more of that as we as we
go so you've already seen me do these
what you haven't really seen me do is
these but they are certainly there and
so I'll briefly say how we're going to
use those and how I have used those and
then we'll move on to the more serious
mathematics okay so basic geometry and
by that we really mean Euclidian
geometry so basically the kind of of
geometry that you typically learn in
high school is called Euclidean geometry
and generally you know I don't really
know why Euclid gets his name on it
maybe he invented it I don't know I'm
not a mathematician like I said so my
math history and my actual math
knowledge are almost nil so everything
that you want to know specifically you
will always have to check I can only
tell you about how I program games with
math that's the only thing that you can
guarantee so so basically yes I just
assume it's named after you could I have
no idea but York Lydian geometry is
basically the study of geometry in the
types of spaces that we typically care
about in games as a general rule which
is to say systems where we have
coordinates and those coordinates meet
at right angles to each other right so
basically you know we've got these
coordinate systems where we have an
x-axis and a y-axis and the y-axis you
know it is is generally considered
orthogonal you know it is something that
that generally doesn't interfere with
the x-axis at all so when we pick a
point right we don't have some weird
coordinate system where the y-axis is
like a bendy curve or something like
this it's always this this nice straight
thing x and y and if we have as the same
thing happens we've got this nice
orthogonal coordinate system that's what
we tend to work with in games we tend to
give points in space coordinates using
either XY pairs or XYZ tuples right
triplets I guess you might say right and
Euclidian geometry is basically John
that's that's sort of the one that comes
into play when you're working on these
kinds of systems whenever you've got
these right angled coordinate systems
that's a textbook case for Euclidean
geometry and you Kilian geometry allows
us to start doing it sort of what we are
talking about when we are thinking in
these terms right and so you've done
these sorts of things I mean I'm trying
to think about what the sort of stuff is
that you do I can't remember back to you
know in high school when I started doing
these like it's like the trigonometry
and the geometry you kind of blur
together in my head I don't remember if
things like proving the congruence of
triangles like for example if I had you
know a triangle here or something like
this and then I had another triangle
here right like let's say I have these
two triangles proving that these two
triangles were basically congruent that
because they had angles in common you
know these sorts of things I think that
was the kind of stuff that they did in
high school geometry I'm not sure but
point being even that that simple
congruence of triangles that is like the
cornerstone of three-dimensional
projection for example so when you do
three-dimensional rendering and we will
do some of that a little limited amount
even though this is a 2-d game even just
that basic stuff that you learned in
high school is actually all totally
applicable already in games congruent
triangles happen all the time
so yeah trust me even though it seems
kind of straightforward and simple even
the geometry that you learned in high
school is the kind of stuff that you
will end up using now trigonometry is
used all the time a ton basically the
the most common case of it in games is
the really simple case of when you when
you need to translate between things
that happen in your coordinate system
again you've got like an XY coordinate
system here and you have very typical
cases of trig where you've got stuff
like you have a point out here somewhere
and you want to know its angle of
deflection you know basically off of
some other point for example maybe I've
got two points like a point here at a
point here and I want to know the angle
between them a lot of times you'll do
this for game programming you want to be
able to rotate things to point at other
things or you want to be able to do
stuff like figure out you know the rate
of turning of some things that you want
them to have all these sorts of things
trigonometry going back and forth
between some angle
and some real sort of notion of what
that means in terms of a direction in
space or in terms of locations of points
in space again
the most basic stuff that you learned in
trigonometry already useful in games and
it only goes up from there so just write
stuff that you already learned in high
school we will be using on the stream
repeatedly and so that's that's a you
know a real big one it never it really
never gets old like you know no matter
how complex the thing I've ever written
trigonometry always pops up just like
algebra in arithmetic it's just it's
baked into everything because games at a
fundamental level are very spatial right
they're just very spatial things and so
calculus is kind of the one that maybe
doesn't rear its head so often in games
depending on how you choose to implement
them and the reason I say that is
because you can cheat out of a lot of
calculus you can you can sort of be mr.
chooses not to do your calculus homework
if your game programmer by using things
like fixed frame rates and other stuff
like this and when I say fixed frame
rates I don't mean like the kind we're
doing where we're saying we're trying to
keep our frame rate constant so if it's
thirty we're kind of translated 30 or
that 64 is a 60 and so on
I mean more like you literally only have
one type of time step you could take you
can only go forward in a sixtieth of a
second and you have to run everything at
that and the reason is you can just sort
of bake constants into your motion
equations that just sort of work and you
don't have to think about the
integration of things over time which is
tends to be and the derivatives of
things over time as much because you can
basically fudge your constants and just
kind of like tune things to work sort of
without necessarily having to involve
yourself in a lot of this so sometimes
depending on the game and depending on
how you choose to program it you may be
able to get out of doing some of this
but if you don't do that and you would
like to be able to support they
basically be able to write code that can
dynamically have its the basically
doesn't have to be rewritten if you want
to change what the time step is and you
want it to play identically or nearly
identically in terms of what motion
things take then calculus starts to come
into play big time and the reason for
that is because again when
talking about tea when you're talking
about time and you're talking about the
arrow of time so basically you're
talking about time steps where you've
got some kind of a delta T you've got a
difference in time between one game
State this is the game state that was we
were at before and we want to advance to
a new game state right then basically
what you're talking about is you're
talking about taking a bunch of things
that are specified in terms of
instantaneous acceleration or velocity
meaning let's say for example 9.8 meters
per second squared I believe is the
typical constant for gravity where we
are in the world and if you think about
how these sorts of things are specified
that is how gravity actually works
that's the rate at which gravity
accelerates objects and so if you want
to be able to use gravity properly you
would specify it either as 9.8 meters
per second squared in your game or you
would have some own made-up value that
you made up for what you wanted gravity
to be but in order for it to actually
act like gravity you then need to do
integrations of this acceleration which
is actually the second derivative of
position stuff we'll be getting to later
right you need to be able to integrate
this up into the velocities of objects
so that you know how fast they're going
and then finally up into the positions
of things so that you know where they
are on the screen and again integration
and derivatives which are basically the
things that step you up for my sellers
new velocity to philosophy position
that's integration going upwards
derivative
you know derivatives or what take you
down from position to velocity to
acceleration that is all you know
calculus is bread and butter and so
certainly even if you were doing a
variable time step game even the most
basic stuff again that you learned in
high school which you probably learned
this you know this base stuff and if you
were in physics you actually literally
learned this not just integration and
derivatives you learned position
velocity acceleration as well even that
most basic stuff comes into play on
every frame of game because everything
in the world
Tippett tends to have even in very non
realistic games tends to want to have
very consistently behaving physical
properties that work the way they do in
the real world just perhaps with
different constants so things you know
maybe have more
friction on them or their gravity
stronger or less strong that sort of
stuff but they still want it you still
want to obey sort of those general ways
in which things work okay so that's the
basic stuff you learned in high school
and all of it is actually useful in
games it's it really does come up in a
lot of different places and I'm only
just mentioning a few of the ways there
are lots more right for each of them now
I want to point out something just to
give one simple example which is complex
numbers right you may have seen complex
numbers in your in your high school
classes right normally a number we think
of a real number it's like three point
five two or something like this that's
our number and we just think of those
numbers as what we normally compute with
but in if you remember from your your
grade school math and so on they also
introduce things like complex numbers
where they will tell you like the square
root of negative 1 equals I and they
will start to write things that look
like that right and there are these
numbers that have two parts they have a
real part in an it what they call it an
imaginary part right and you know
probably I don't know if you were
anything like me I okay I said I don't
have a natural aptitude for math and so
if you were like me you probably looked
at that and went well I'm pretty sure
I'm never gonna use that again because I
don't even have any idea why anyone
would ever care about this right it
seems completely ridiculous turns out
not to be true in fact even just basic
basic stuff you may need to do with 3d
graphics will involve numbers that are
not only similar to this sort of thing
but are actually even more complicated
than it and I will touch on those in a
second but basically what I just wanted
to do is kind of have a have just sort
of a quick mention of the fact that even
the things you probably thought were not
interesting or will never be important
in some of these subjects actually end
up being important because most of the
stuff that you learned in high school
math is actually pretty practically
applicable to two games all right so
more on that in a second so now let's
get into the stuff
that you probably didn't have much of in
high school I don't know maybe your high
schools were more vigorous than mine or
if you went to private uh seven to
public high school private high schools
might be fancier I don't really know
so you may have had more mapping right
but now we're just going to go through
stuff I learned after I got out of high
school while working on games to work on
games so this is only stuff that was
used in game technology right this is
none of the stuff that I'm about to say
his stuff that I did strictly because I
was curious or was interested in math
these are literally all things that I
had to learn because I actually needed
to type some code into a computer right
period all right
so first of all linear algebra is one of
the biggest ones that everyone talks
about and it's it's true that it is very
important and it tends to underpin a ton
of things so linear algebra the the most
obvious place that people face it is
basically with vectors and matrices
right so you've got vectors and matrices
which you've probably seen even if you
don't have any idea what they are or why
they are you've probably seen them even
if in just 3d editing packages vectors
are of course those what we use to
represent our points in space like those
tuples like the XY and Z or even RGB in
color space right vectors are basically
one-dimensional groupings of oh I
shouldn't say 1 dimensional they are one
a matrix is a two-by-two thing right
it's got numbers in it in sort of the
it's sort of but I don't know how to say
this other than 2 by 2 it's got rows and
it's got columns let's put it that way a
vector is not that way a vector only has
one dimension to it to itself but the
vector itself is said to be in some
number of dimensions based on how many
it has right it's always one of a row or
one of a column right so it might be X Y
Z written that way or it might be XYZ
and RGB written in this way which is
actually a little more common due to
some very stuff that will get into
in future episodes so it only has one
row or one column but it has as many
elements as it wants in it so a vector
might have like typically we'll deal
with three dimensional vectors two
dimensional vectors or four dimensional
vectors are very common X Y Z W and rgba
for example are typical examples of
four-dimensional extensions of these
three dimensional vectors and basically
what they are is like I said before they
represent points in space or anything
else that we might want to talk about
when we have things that are
interrelated in some way like these are
all properties of a single point let's
say in space and we want to bundle those
together now matrices are very similar
in fact vectors are kind of just a
special case of a matrix if you will
they are something that only has one of
their dimensions filled and it doesn't
actually have you know they're not and
buy em they're just n wide and so you
know something that had more of those
like I drew before F I something that
has more of those and it doesn't act to
be two-dimensional it could be
three-dimensional could be as many
dimensions as we want and then it also
has each of those dimensions has a
certain width so they might be three by
three matrices two by two matrices for
my for my trees so typically what you
will see the first time that you'll
encounter stuff like this is again
points in space or colors very common
and then transforms on them because what
you'll typically see is you will see you
will typically see transforms of vectors
written as vector matrix math and the
way vector matrix math works is you'll
typically see it written like this
you'll basically see it done in a
fashion that sort of does this drawing
right and the way that it works is
vector matrix multiplication for example
in this case is when you take each
element of a vector and multiply it by
each element of a matrix in the order
rows of the vector times columns of the
matrix to fill in one here and then
again you do the same pairing here so
I'd have a XB y CZ and I can actually
write one of those out for you this is
not something that I want to cover right
now but just to give you example ax plus
B y plus cz right so you basically do
each term x times a you add Y plus times
B and you add Z times C so you basically
are doing that multiplication you then
move down to the next row and do the
exact same thing again so here you'd get
D times X plus e times y
plus Z times sorry F times Z try to keep
consistent order there and GX plus hy
plus isay right and so typically you
know you'll see a lot of this and the
reason that these are used is because
these matrices can encapsulate in this
format any kind of way that you could
transform a point such that it still
maintains certain criteria most of which
are ok like most of which we don't mind
always preserving so by encapsulating
the math in this way you can do scale
you can do shears you can do movement
like translation right you can do a
number of things that you might want to
do to your vectors and what's more is
matrices themselves can be composed so
basically if I have a matrix that
represents a scale and a matrix that
represents a shear I can multiply the
matrices together and get a scale shear
matrix right so this ends up just being
a very efficient way to do some of these
3d graphics things so that's typically
where you will start to see linear
algebra first now again not gonna
explain any of that today because the
day is just the overview day but we will
talk about it certainly later but in
addition to those things those are
actually very basic things that you
might use linear algebra for but linear
algebra is actually a lot more powerful
than that because linear algebra
actually at its heart is more about
solving simultaneous equations and I
don't know if you've ever seen any of
this before if you've only had high
school math you may not have ever gotten
to this but you certainly have done the
simultaneous equations part you may just
not have it seen it phrased in the term
linear algebra air or in the ways in
which linear algebra often tackles it
you will have seen something certainly
in your high school math something that
looks like this where you have 5x plus 3
y equals 0 and let's say 2x plus 2y
equals 0 right you will have been given
these equations and you will have been
asked to solve for x and y and what you
will have been told right is you will
have been told something along the lines
of as long as you have as many equations
as you
variables then you will be able to solve
the system because you just solve one
equation for the for the variable and
then you substitute that back into the
other equation solve that and then
you've got the answer right well linear
algebra is basically the formalization
of that of that process basically what
you end up doing is you will take all of
your equations that you have and you
will pack them into giant matrices so
each each row will basically be an
equation typically this sort of thing
so basically you know if I was doing
that one again where I had my 5x plus 3y
the five would go there and three would
go there we would only well you know let
me draw the 2x2 matrix of that of that
actual thing that I just wrote it would
be something like this five three two
two like so you would write this matrix
and then you would say that basically
I've got a vector that's multiplying by
that X&amp;Y right and that what I want to
do is I want to solve that again maybe
it's zero zero like we had written
before or maybe there's some actual
values in here whatever linear algebra
is about systemically being able to
solve these vector matrix equations and
basically there are processes that you
can run either iterative or or direct
that will basically solve entire systems
for you without making you go through
and have to do all the finicky you know
solve for one variable back substituting
the other one and blah blah blah so
basically you can scale this up to
things where you solve very large
systems of equations that can be huge
right now the other thing that's
interesting about that is you can
actually solve equations solve is the
wrong word but you can actually come up
with answers to equations that you
actually couldn't not possibly have
solved in you know in the regular way
that you would do mathematics for
example you might have things where you
have equations and variables that you
don't have enough equations for like
something like this
where I've got two equations with three
unknowns you can actually do things as
well that allow you to do approximated
solves or things that allow you to get
answers for things that simplify down to
show you the space of the possible
solutions if you have like more than one
if you have one or more variables that
can not be exactly software they can
give you basically what the shape is of
all the solutions like what it looks
like and spatially
so on so there's just a lot of very
powerful things you can do with linear
algebra that aren't just about
manipulating vectors to matrices and so
there's there's just a huge amount of
stuff that's involved there and of
course it's all very applicable computer
science because really a lot of it was
sort of designed to make mechanical sort
of the manual processes of algebra so a
lot of it's very intimately related to
computer science as well so anyway
that's linear algebra now mm-hmm once
you start working with multiple things
like you know like I said you've got X Y
Z all over the place and we you know
we've got all these points and typically
everything in a game has at least an XY
coordinated found XYZ coordinate and
we're trying to do all these things you
know in sort of these these
multi-dimensional spaces typically
regular calculus the kind that you learn
in high school where you just have just
basic calculus typically isn't going to
cut it and what you need to start doing
at that point is partial differential
equations right which is a form of
calculus equations or PDE s if you will
partial differential equations and what
partial differential equations are is
they're basically like what you were
doing in high school calculus only
instead of only doing it with one
variable that can change like in other
words normally in in high school
calculus I believe and I don't know
maybe your again your calculus class may
have been better than mine but in my
calculus class for example you know we'd
have T for example would be a variable
that could change over time but then if
there are any other variables in the
systems of equations they were assumed
not to change over time or these other
sorts of things right
well partial differential equations is
basically the sort of study of how you
work with things where you have lots of
variables that could be changing and you
need to be able to work with them and so
what partial differential equations is
basically about it is basically about
applying that high school calculus where
you were able to do derivatives and
integrals and stuff like this to systems
where everything could be changing so
you maybe have an X a Y and Z and all
the x y&amp;z are all things that might
change right so in that case what you
need to do is
you need to take derivatives of your
functions with respect to XY and Z and
then you need to be able to work with
them you know sort of to try think of
how to say this in the best way in order
to sort of do the sorts of operations
that you could do if you only had one
variable when you have multiple
variables and so a typical example of
this and like one that I used for
example in in the past is if you have
something like a function that's defined
in all of space so for example you know
a lot of times you'll see something
where you define it in in games you will
define some function that is space
facial so for any point in the world you
have a function that comes back and
tells you what the variable what the
value of this thing is in in the world
at that point and this could be used for
any sorts of things you know and this
function could be anything you know who
knows what it is something we made up
but one example would be lets say that
we're doing some procedural world
generation and we basically say that for
any point in the world we want to know
how foggy it is there or something right
so this F is just literally the fog
density at that point right then
typically something that you might want
to do is say for any point in the world
and you know what I may be an even
better one would be if I could simplify
it slightly to something that's maybe a
little more relatable than fogginess
let's say we have an FX of Y and it
gives us back the height right of like a
height map so it's some procedurally
generated terrain right and what I want
to know is I want to know at any point
since I have this function that gives me
back the height I want to know what the
sort of the slope is at that point like
what what direction points up the
steepest ascent of the place that I'm at
on this you know whatever this this
height generation function is well
that's a textbook case of partial
differential equations basically there's
a thing called the gradient which is
when you take the partial derivative of
a function with respect to each of its
dependent variables and you slam them
into a vector so you'd have the partial
of F X and Y with respect to X and the
partial of f of XY with respect to Y and
that would basically give you that
vector that you wanted which is to say
that
in which the height is changing so
that's just an example of something that
you might do with it it's probably a
pretty weak example and to tell you the
truth my partial differential equation
foo is really weak if I had to pick one
thing that to be better at it would
probably be this right here because it
comes up a lot in physics and I just
never been that great with them I just
haven't had enough experience with them
of really working with them to ever
become that good of them so it's
unfortunate but I'm I'm lousy at these
guys
I remember the gradient pretty well
because I did a bunch of work with
gradients at one point but I was doing
some implicit surface rasterization
stuff and yeah anyway closely on its
heels is ordinary differential equations
which despite the fact that they sound
like things that only a pure
mathematician would love they are
actually things that you do find
surprisingly common in game programming
if you actually want to do it right so
what an ordinary differential equation
is is it's seemingly a solution to what
appears to be or I should say it it
appears to be a solution to something
that sounds unsolvable when you state at
first but it turns out it actually does
work in practice you know thank you to
the two brilliant mathematicians who
figured this stuff out but basically
when you have things like if basic
calculus sorts of stuff that you might
want to do like position I mentioned
this just a moment ago position velocity
and acceleration right if you remember
from either high school physics or high
school calculus class then basically
what you have here is these functions
are derivatives of each other so a
position is where something is in space
its first derivative is velocity which
is how fast things are moving and its
second derivative again all high school
calculus terms its second derivative is
acceleration okay so if I have a
function write a function of T which is
my position then I know its first
derivative which is usually written like
that is the velocity and its second
derivative is a succession now I will
end up once I start trying to work with
these things I'll end up in a very
unsavoury circumstance once I want to do
something with for example drag now drag
is for you know you've all heard of it
with respect to airplanes and cars
certainly
if I have something like a car you know
and I'm making a racing game well that's
the awful car that's let's try that
again
let's say I have some kind of futuristic
looking car here something more like
this right there we go oh man this car
is looking good dude look at that look
at it go
look at its majesty then certainly we're
all aware of the fact that as air comes
and it hits the surface of this car it
actually imparts some force to the car
and that force pushes the car backwards
in some sense so despite the fact that
the car is trying to accelerate it also
has to contend with the fact that it's
getting somewhat decelerated in the
direction it wants to go by the force of
the air resistance or drag that's on the
car in fact they do a lot of work with
aerodynamics to write to try and make
cars as aerodynamic as possible to kind
of deflect air in a graceful fashion so
that doesn't impart as much force onto
the car as it otherwise would right well
if you start to have drag the first
thing that you'll learn in physics when
you start to talk about drag is that
it's proportional to the surface area of
the thing getting hit by the air and the
velocity of that air right how fast is
the air going well the velocity right is
in this space the velocity is in in the
first derivative of position but the
computation for drag drag is actually an
acceleration drag is an acceleration
which is which operates down here right
so that means that the force that you're
trying to well I shouldn't say
acceleration it's a force really that
you know force an acceleration you can
transfer by using F equals MA if you
remember that for this class but you
don't need to know that now don't worry
about it anyway velocity if I'm going to
try and compute it well the velocity is
the thing that tells me how much force I
have on my drag that's what tells me my
drag force right but if velocity tells
me my drag force and drag force is what
I need to integrate up to get my
velocity in the first place I've got
this nasty cycle of this the the actual
thing I'm trying to compute defines the
quantity that I need to use to compute
it so it's like you can't possibly solve
this equation it's like something that
depends on its own derivative right and
you're just like I don't know what to do
here I guess I just have to fudge it
not true that is what ordinary
differential equations are ordinary
differential equations is essentially
the study of equations that are their
own derivatives or integrals to however
you want to want to look at it and
basically these sorts of equations can
actually be solved exactly for ordinary
differential equations if you want to a
lot of the times so you can actually
make this work out precisely if you
really want to and similarly another
very typical one that's that's kind of
fun that people don't think about very
often but that's totally true another
place you'll see ordinary different
differential equations pop up is if you
want to make zooming be proportional on
distance from an object so for example
let's say I've got an object and I've
got a camera here is my camera this is
my little you know what it's an eyeball
you know my little eye that's looking at
this thing right here's my little my
little sphere that I'm looking at well a
lot of times you might want to put
zooming on the mouse wheel right and so
basically what you want to do is as you
roll the mouse wheel forwards or
something you get closer and as you roll
the mouse wheel backwards you get
further away now when people implement
this poorly and by the way I'm looking
at you a lot of 3d software vendors out
there because a lot of people implement
this incredibly poorly what they will do
is they will for when you roll the mouse
wheel or do whatever you going to do
they will actually move you a constant
amount for each click or as you sort of
drag forwards or whatever they'll
actually move you a constant amount
closer to the thing and that's awful
because since zooming when you get
closer to something the amount that it
gets bigger in your field of view is not
the same depending on where you are from
it if you're right next to an object and
you step one foot forward closer to it
it becomes huge in your field of view
whereas if you were 50 feet away from it
and you took one step forward its size
would barely change at all
so the concept that the user would ever
want to step a constant distance is
ludicrous right what they actually want
to do is they want to step an
ever-diminishing distance closer to it
so they want to basically start out with
large steps getting closer and then they
want to get smaller and smaller and
smaller and smaller so what does this
mean well it means that the distance
that you'd want to move is proportional
to the distance itself so basically the
derivative of the distance is
proportional to the distance right
classic ordinary differential equation
if we want to do a smooth
in on an object zoom smoothly over time
right animated so forget mouse wheel now
we're trying to animate in on that
object and I want to be a perfectly
smooth zoom that operates at a variable
framerate I've got a solve an ordinary
differential equation because in order
to do that I have to say that I always
want during the whole time step no
matter what the time that comes in I
want to solve that equation to figure
out what is the distance that if I was
moving continuously would always
continuously give me a movement distance
that's proportional to the actual
distance that I am right again we're
near differential equations it's
actually a very simple problem in order
if equation differential equations
Saul's sounds incredibly difficult if
you don't know them but once you know
them you're just like oh yeah that's
space that's that's like an easy
differential equation right that's like
stuff that you know an OD e person would
just be like oh yeah I did that day one
in my class or day two or something all
right so that's the calculus fellows
those are those are those are the
calculus fellows and again they're kind
of tied pretty closely into two linear
algebra here so then we get into stuff
you know I said look you clitty in
geometry stuff that you use a lot so
basically complex numbers I mentioned
those earlier where they were the kind
of five plus 3i thing
well basically complex numbers or rather
the concept that you have sort of these
extra specifiers so that numbers aren't
just real values they got more parts of
them actually non Euclidean geometry and
that's sort of that sort of complex
number concept come up again like I said
I kind of alluded to the fact that they
would in a way that you wouldn't expect
if you just want to do even really basic
stuff in three dimensions then obviously
linear algebra will get you a lot of the
way there but as soon as you want to
rotate something if you ever want to do
rotations then you step out of the world
of comfortable linear algebra and
Euclidian geometry and into the world of
non Euclidean geometry which you
sometimes still use well often still use
linear algebra to work with but again
the the Euclidean part falls away and so
you typically have to do a bunch of
stuff related to that but again not not
on topic tonight so basically not
including geometry you
geometry on surfaces that have nothing
to do with those nice pretty orthogonal
ones that I drew before it they do not
look like this where you've got a nice
XYZ instead they are stuff like geometry
on the surface of a sphere for example
and so your coordinate systems might
look something like that and they have
weird properties like for example if I
go the same distance in along the
different directions I may not get back
to the same place that I was on before
like you know it's all wet this way and
then that way I might not get the same
places if I went this way and then that
way which is you know what one of the
sort of hallmarks you might expect from
Euclidean geometry so you basically get
a lot of interesting things that happen
in non Euclidean geometry and you may
ask why do I care about that and why is
that having to do with rotations well
the reason is because rotations in 3d
space just plain aren't Euclidean the
rules that they follow just just kind of
defy your logic a little bit in terms of
what you would expect to have happen
excuse me with ordinary numbers one of
the examples is they do not commute
properly so for example if I have a
rotation where you know I'm going to
spin something around one axis and then
I have another rotation of the same
object that I want to apply where I'm
going to rotate it around another axis I
can't flip the order of these two things
the the orientation that the object ends
up in after I do these two rotations if
I do a and then B the orientation of the
object will not be the same as if I did
B and then a now sometimes for certain
rotations it will be but for the vast
majority of rotations it simply isn't
and so the attempt to represent these
rotations has been a long and difficult
battle in computer science and in
mathematics in general and there's lots
of different ways in which these are
attempt to be dealt with they in they
include the exponential map they include
Euler angles right they include
quaternions they include duals of those
right there's just a whole family of
things Oh
Rodrigues parameters
right or Euler parameters which are not
the same as Euler angles etc etc
basically there's a whole bunch of
different things that people have come
up with to try and represent these and
work with them efficiently and
especially the most popular ones in use
today which are basically these guys
quaternions and their duals
those are all about doing operations
that are in non Luc Euclidean geometry
space a quest hernion for example is
four-dimensional and it is in four
dimensions but constrained to the
surface of a four-dimensional sphere or
hyper sphere more specifically and so if
you think about that example I just gave
where I said here is a look this is a 3d
sphere I mean it's actually 2d because I
drew it in 2d but imagine in three
dimensions you have a sphere a ball and
you've got essentially two parameters
right that define the sphere I'm sorry
that that would move you around the
sphere right a sphere that is a surface
so it's only got you know two degrees of
freedom from any point on the sphere I
could only really move in any two in any
two orthogonal directions at any given
time right but another way to think
about that sphere is well we could use
three parameters to specify where we are
on the sphere right and we could just
say that the only possible sets of those
three parameters that we're willing to
consider are the ones that lie on the
sphere because three you know three
parameters would allow us to specify
anywhere in space you could be out here
or here or here right anywhere in space
3d will give us but we just want this
one sphere that's embedded in that 3d
space we could simply constrain our our
X Y Z's using some additional constraint
and I can tell you that that constraint
happens to be basically that the length
of that vector right equals some radius
values but that's that's a separate
that's a separate issue so don't worry
about that
point being we'd use a constraint to say
that it has to fall on the surface of a
sphere okay the same thing could be done
in four dimensions we could say we have
X Y Z W we have four parameters which
would give us anywhere in 4d space but
we're going to constrain it to be on the
surface of a four dimensional hyper
sphere which gives us only three free
parameters essentially but that we're
representing us for now if that doesn't
make your mind
explode I don't know what does point
being those are the sorts of things that
you have to work with and believe me
after you start thinking about them
somehow they start to become second
nature even though they are incredibly
complicated and involved weird stuff
like trying to visualize four dimensions
which no human can really do adequately
because we live in only three but not
only do Quatro names involve that they
also involve our old friend complex
numbers because not only do they
consider having two parts they actually
consider having all four parts and their
arithmetic is defined in terms of those
parts so a quaternion
will often be written in something that
looks like you know a plus bi plus c j
plus DK where I J and K are all sort of
things that resemble this kind of AI
they all have rules such as any two of
them multiplied together equal negative
one and these sorts of things and so
quaternions themselves would be very
familiar to anyone who worked with
complex numbers they're sort of an
extended version of that and again stuff
that kind of makes your head explode a
little bit if you're not used to math
but is absolutely commonplace in game
programming make no mistake about it
so yes non-euclidean geometry and
complex number sorts of stuff come up
again surprisingly often if you're doing
any 3d programming at all you will
basically butt heads with them almost
immediately all right
so beyond that we've got sort of a bunch
of other guys who I'll just mention I
don't want to spend too much time on
them because again like I've only got
what if I got 12 minutes left okay so -
what else we got in the grab bag of
things and again these are all things I
personally had to implement at some
point or another I'm only doing maths in
games that I actually had to use myself
and we're only I still got about seven
more things here to list okay so -
apology - apology I mentioned on the
stream actually already - apology is the
study you know I'm gonna go ahead and
I'm gonna go get myself some fresh room
here because these things aren't as
related anymore topology are dimensioned
on the screen basically topology is the
study of manifolds and how they're
connected in this sort of stuff now
what's a manifold well basically if I
have
kind of a space we've already talked
about one that sphere for example would
be an example of a manifold basically if
I have some kind of a space so like
before we said let's say we have a 3d
space so we have basically an X a Y and
a Z vector in our vectors and we can
specify our positions let me write that
vertically I want to get used to writing
them vertically again because you know
we're gonna be doing some math you stuff
anyway so if I've got points in
three-dimensional space you know they
could be anywhere if I start to talk
about some subset of the entire space
that basically form some kind of a shape
like a sphere but it could be anything
else you know like some kind of a weird
strip you know like a road that's been
laid down or something like this right
like maybe I've got my 3d terrain and
I've got you know here's my trees or
whatever and then there's a road that
goes through it maybe I want to talk
about that road as a surface that's an
example of a manifold a manifold is
something that is some lower dimensional
space in this case a two-dimensional
space writes a flat surface 2d that's
embedded inside of a 3-dimensional space
so it's in 3d but it's only two
dimensions worth of information right
that's example of a manifold and
topology is based in the study of these
things how they are connected how they
can be represented and sort of things
that you might need to know about them
so for example on the stream we already
talked about the concept of toroidal
versus disc topology I said basically if
you have a world where if I go off one
edge I come back on the other you know
if my guy can wrap around that's an
example of toroidal topology because
it's as if you were on the surface of a
torus right of a donut basically you
know like an inner tube because you can
keep going around in either of the two
major directions and you just kind of
loop around the thing right imagine an
ant walking on an inner tube you get
that exact same thing where it can just
walk around and around and around in one
direction and never seem to stop and
until it realizes it's just walking in
circles
it doesn't realize it because it just
thinks it was always going forward again
Terrel topology versus disk topology
would be if you could get to the end
disk topology would basically be I start
walking and I get to a barrier that I
just I can't go past anymore and so we
decided already we basically already did
a topological decision in our game we
decided to have to write toriel topology
instead of just topology just something
to think about that
topology right and there's a lot of
stuff to talk about in topology some of
it comes up and games some of it not so
often but it's it's a pretty wide field
certainly so moving on from there
Minkowski algebra which is not really a
field of mathematics I wouldn't say it's
just a thing that comes up a lot because
of G JK g JK is well not just GJ k but
collision let me just say more broadly
cuz it's not just it's not just use okay
really
it's basically collision detection and
we may even use it in the collision
detection in handmade hero basically
Minkowski algebra is the algebra of
shapes it basically does you does things
like if I have a square and a circle I
can add them together and get a rounded
rectangle that's the world's worst
rounded rectangle and basically I do
that by tracing out the circle at each
of the four corners of the square for
example and then taking that sort of
entire space that was formed by them
right typically this is used in games it
was used actually at least as early as
quake it possibly before then I I don't
know how what the earliest example of
minkowski's algebra and games is and two
typical uses of it one is the gjk
algorithm which I will not explain here
but that uses Minkowski algebra at its
core to do collision detection between
moving convex solids and and so that's
one example that's very common but
another example is just simple world
shrinkage and growing growing and what
that basically is is if I have a world
let's say this this box here and I've
got a dude in the world who has say a
spherical or cylindrical or something
collision representation I can choose to
do my collision checking always based on
trying to intersect circles with these
line segments that define my boundary or
something with this but there's another
option which is to simply shrink the
world in such a way that it now
approximates what the sphere could
actually go if the sphere was shrunk
down to a point so you're basically
taking the world and growing it by the
sphere and shrinking the player down to
the point and the collision that happens
when a point moves around a sphere
expanded world is the same as a sphere
moving around
then on expanded world so basically this
allows you to do simple point operations
or line operations for movement against
world geometry without ever having to
deal with the fact that things are
actually were actually spheres or
cylinders in their collision
representations and again I believe
quake used that in its collision
detector so that's mikowski algebra it
does come up a lot in collision
detection obviously control theory very
popular control theory is basically you
know the study of things like feedback
systems and you know Springs and these
sorts of things there's things like the
proportional PDC's proportional
derivative controller these sorts things
use a lot in robotics basically and we
use it in games a lot to control
variables that we want to control over
time so for example if we want to do
motion stuff where we have something
that we want to kind of like come you
know sort of pick up some speed and then
slow down again you know we might use
control theory to kind of do that if we
have stuff like a missile that's chasing
a target and it's supposed to turn the
slow kind of rate again control theory
it's basically all the sorts of stuff
you might do in the real world to
control real world robotics weaponry
these sorts of things that we want to do
in games to simulate the motion of
things as they might move in the real
world you know and that's that's very
common again we'll be doing that in
hand-made here a bunch proportional
derivative controls will probably make
an appearance other sorts of things like
that
definitely very popular ok interval
arithmetic what is that a lot of people
probably have never heard of that
interval arithmetic is basically a
arithmetic on ranges just exactly what
it sounds like basically what happens is
sometimes you need to compute things
over spacial areas and that's where this
really comes in handy I don't know that
that's necessarily what it was
originally designed for I don't think it
was I think it might have been
originally designed for automatic
differentiation or something like this
but point being I've used it a bunch for
area computations
what it allows you to do is it allows
you to evaluate equations on entire
ranges of values instead of just one
value at a time so you have some
equation x squared plus 5x or something
like this that you want to evaluate and
instead of evaluating it for just X you
want to evaluate it for all the numbers
between a and B all of them so if this
was 3 and this was 1700 you want to
basically be able to call X f of X and
find out what this equation can take in
terms of its output for all the values
in between there and there right and
that's what interval arithmetic allows
you to do now where do I use this I use
this when I'm trying to compute what
functions will do over regions so for
example if I have a grid system for my
game and we're bucketing things up let's
say even in a tile map and I have a
particular tile and the tile map I want
to know what the maximum water level
could be and I have a function for the
water level I want to know what the
maximum water level is in here I can do
interval arithmetic on it to figure out
what that maximum would be I'll get out
the minimum and maximum for it in one
fell swoop instead of having to do a
bunch of point sampling to figure out
where it is very powerful for that sort
of region checking I've used it a lot in
the past really cool pretty simple to
learn and very very powerful in certain
in the right circumstances certainly
okay we've got graph theory probably
needs no explanation graph theory is
basically the thing that allows you to
do all your studies of pathing and and
graph traversal stuff like this even
simple stuff like path finding on grids
is often broken down to graph theory
problems where you know we've got sort
of these sorts of searches and
technically graph theory and you might
say operations research it's it's hard
to say what you want to call these
things I'm not again not a mathematician
and I'm not a pennant on these things so
what each algorithm actually falls into
in terms of discipline I may never quite
get right they might say it's graph
theory but really that's technically an
Operations research problem but
operation research is kind of an
umbrella term I feel like graph theories
in there I mean I don't know so you know
if you really want to know try to go dig
up a good math like maybe Mathematica or
that online what's that thing mathworld
there's that thing that that Wolfram
bought that was basically a giant
compendium of Matthieu things anyway so
if you've got things like ive got some
series of spatial things and I want to
do pathing between them find out how I
can get from one to the other I want to
do stuff like figure out you know what
the widest span is or something like
this on on a level on a connected set of
levels or even tiles that sort of thing
just searches and understanding things
about layouts like that that's all graph
theory in there and studies of graph
sorts of things so pathing is the
typical example that you'll often see
but there's a bunch of other stuff that
you might want to do in there oh man
okay so I've got a couple more to do and
only one minute left we might go a
little bit of wrong a little bit long
but anyway operations wreathes research
which I wrote down briefly but I'll
write down again cuz then we've got this
sort of another thing in there
operations research I use a lot now
basically the sort of the umbrella term
for figuring out how you gonna optimize
things so you'll see things like the
metropolis algorithm right which is a
pretty powerful one it's kind of the the
be-all and end-all algorithm when you're
like I just don't know how to solve this
problem usually that means you solve it
this way with the metropolis album right
basically what operations research is is
they deal with minimizing or maximizing
something right so basically you have
some criteria and this is why it
overlaps with the path thing again if
you want to find the shortest route
between two things that would be
operations research if you want to
figure out the optimal distribution of
some quantity among different parties
based on some weight so that sort of
thing you get that again you want to do
something like figure out the most
optimal ordering for a set of ascending
language instructions this guy right
here I've actually done that before you
get you get operations research anytime
you want to try to maximize or minimize
some criteria given a set of rules that
you can use to structure something and
it's very very general right you get a
lot of stuff that can happen in there
okay so very quickly I'll just throw out
the last couple of years since we're out
of time
probability and statistics obviously is
something that we'll be using because
we'll be picking random numbers and
trying to do stuff where we determine
what like what's the probability that
the player will get a certain thing and
we want to
control that in our level design so
obviously probability the stats probably
don't need much introduction of where
they're useful you use them all the time
even in very simple ways that sort of
stuff if you want to control
distributions and other things like this
and then there's also of course all the
discrete math topics which I don't
really know very much about you
typically use leave them to the FS where
it's what you have probability and and
pseudo-random number generators right
obviously those sorts of things all
involve the study of numbers at a very
deep level and they're the sort of basis
for all that stuff so any cryptography
that you do anytime you generate random
numbers you're all leaning on all the
stuff that people have done sort of in
that field ok and so I'm trying to think
if there's anything I forgot we're right
on time so I'm hoping that I didn't of
stuff that I've done these are only the
things that I could remember so it's
possibly that I had to do some things
that I just didn't remember but I
believe that I got all of the major ones
there ok alright so hopefully that is a
a final sort of place I can point people
now that's like if you have an hour and
you want to know what kinds of math you
should know if you're going to be a game
programmer that's the stuff that I had
to learn I don't really regret any of it
I feel like all of the math I've learned
in all of those disciplines was all
pretty darn cool and it's allowed me to
always approach things with sort of a
lot more weaponry than I would have had
if I'd had to just kind of muddle
through it as a programmer and I think a
lot of the solutions that I come up with
would have been worse and so that's what
I can say about that and so starting
tomorrow we will start learning about
vectors and start programming with them
so you can see how they work and that
will be the first thing that we'll we'll
start off and that of course is linear
algebra and geometry and trigonometry is
right in that wheelhouse that's what
we'll be starting with whether we get to
any of these other ones in the course of
hand-made hero will largely be dependent
on what we need to do
but I can guarantee you we will probably
hit at least four or five of them if not
all of them in the course of the game
somewhere that is how common a lot of
these things are if you want to do stuff
right and actually kind of know what
you're doing is just hacking it and
crossing your fingers that it works so
yeah so there you go let's open it up to
questions please put Q quality Q : in
front of your question so that I will be
able to see it and please try to keep it
to stuff we've done in today's stream or
on a previous stream in fact today's
stream but it might be good to kind of
restrict it mostly to mask questions
tonight since that's all we've done
today but you know we'll see how it goes
all right let's see it got to give you
guys a chance to catch up here let's see
do you even breathe bro uh not much no I
mean I I probably should breathe more
it's true you said that toriel topology
means that if you walk in one direction
you'll eventually get back to where you
started doesn't a sphere also have this
property how do we know our world as a
torus and not a sphere that is a
fantastic fantastic question so let's
take a look actually the answer to your
question has to do with how we have
unwrapped it in and you can kind of see
it's for lack of a better way of saying
it you can kind of see with how the
motion on the torus works versus how the
motion on the sphere works so if you
think about a sphere and I kind of I
wish I may be I should eventually
install some kind of a 3d package on
this so we can look at 3d things a
little bit easier because my drawings
are not going to be very good
unfortunately but if you take a look at
what happens on a sphere right we have
an XY coordinate system in our game
right we were moving in XY coordinates
and what we were doing in XY coordinates
is we were saying that we
essentially have a tile map right you
remember us constructing this tile map
and that tile map was the same
everywhere right so you know we have a Y
that goes up we have an X that goes over
and we basically have this sort of grid
that were that where things are always
square right there's always a square and
no matter how far you go in any
direction even if you wrap all the way
around you're gonna see exactly this
kind of thing around you locally right
well if you think about what would
happen on a sphere right
imagine that we started kind of along
we're on the earth and we started along
the equator somewhere and when we're
when we're right on that equator right
things actually do look kind of like
that right they do look kind of like
they would here but ask yourself if I
was to take that equatorial line and
divide it up amongst the the tile maps
how many tiles would I have around the
equator right now remember as we go
upward we're still retaining that
two-dimensional coordinate system so
we're still talking essentially about
lat/long lines like they would be on the
earth and if you know what happens if
you ever looked at a globe basically the
space the size of the rings of those
lat/long lines
continues to diminish as you go upwards
so if I had you know I don't know how
many tiles you want to consider if I
have 32 tiles around the equator before
I wrapped around by the time I got up
here I would be down to something like
four tiles and then when I got up to the
very pole I just have like one
vanishingly small tile right so the
reason that we are a toroidal topology
and not a sphere topology is because we
enforce the fact that the dimension of
our tile map does not diminish in any
direction we always have the same number
of tiles width and height wise right no
matter where you are the width of our
tile map in terms of tiles the count of
tiles along the y-axis does not depend
on the x axis location and vice versa on
a sphere that would not be true on a
sphere we would have to basically modify
how many tiles there were as we went
upward or modify the size of those tiles
right furthermore when you actually got
up to this point all of these tile lines
would actually vanish into a single
point right and at that single point
where they vanished you would no longer
know even which tile you were on so when
you went to wrap around to the other
side of the world you could essentially
the player would be free to almost
choose to be on any of the tile paths
when they got up there right if we
didn't shrink down does that make sense
so basically there's two choices right
we could either shrink the number of
tiles or keep the tiles number the same
but have them all definition size till
they got to a singularity point and
that's what happens at the top of that
sphere so topologically speaking we
basically have no options on a sphere
for actually preserving that coordinate
system that we wanted without making
some very significant sacrifices by
contrast on a torus right don't know if
I can draw one here by contrast on a
torus these lines never converge right
basically the ring around here right and
the ring around here they never get
closer together they never the the
spacing between these is always
equidistant the whole way around the
torus right so we can always lay down a
grid and that grid never gets wider or
smaller no matter where we are on the
torus right and and that's why yeah
that's why that that is is the way it is
oh dear
well we have a bit of a we have a bit of
a problem ladies and gentlemen the
laptop has run out of batteries but
unfortunately it's the laptop that has
the questions that has the questions on
it oh boy
well that is unfortunate I guess we will
have to pause the stream for a minute
here here at 9:10 plus for one second
while I get a battery of some kind Oh No
okay that was unfortunate
lesson learned it's true my laptop can
not go uh how horrible well lesson
learned I guess I'm going to have to get
a spare but like this laptop basically
can't last hardly at all it dies
immediately basically I do not know why
I have no idea why I don't know if it's
just that the battery's old and of
course Linux always reports that it has
like half the battery left or something
and then it dies so it's like you're you
don't even get really any warning that
the laptop is about to die it just goes
away so unfortunately I will have to
restart so okay alright the laptop is
back now thankfully and so let's see
let's get hex chat open here hex chat
there we go so at least we can see the
questions again and and now all right
so please if you had a question
obviously I didn't catch it because the
laptop died so please repost your
question with the Q :
and I will reap ick up where we left off
now that I can actually see questions
again yeah fantastic
gotta get a got to get a power brick for
this room so it'll always be plugged in
if it's in here yeah do you think it's
important to clarify that many of these
subjects are things you can learn as you
need them and it's more of an overview
of math of what math is using games not
what is needed as a baseline yes well I
mean I hopefully I said that relatively
clearly when I said it stuff that I
learned as I went but but yeah you don't
need to learn it to start game
programming at all but of course as
you've seen on handmade hero you've been
able to probably follow most of the
stuff that I did and hadn't had to do
that so you kinda you'll see as we go
forward in programming exactly when each
thing kicks in and it's like that's the
that you would want to learn it in terms
of if you are starting game partly
though I highly recommend learning as
much math as you can as you go basically
like you know just constantly be
studying in the background if you can be
until you know a fair bit of math
because there's really a ton of it and
like I actually wish I knew more ah
there's a bunch notice I don't know like
I don't know a geometric algebra for
example and I wish I did I only know
like the barest little minimum of it
there's a bunch of things that I but I
wish I knew so I think you were confused
about non Euclidean geometry the space
of most 3d games is the Euclidean well
that's what I said if you remember I
said the 3d space most games Euclidean
but what I said is non Euclidean
geometry you have to use almost
immediately and the reason is because
rotations are non Euclidean and that is
not me being confused that's the truth
basically rotations
I shouldn't say rotations are not
looking the representation for rotations
that we use in 3d graphics is non
Euclidean quaternions are non Euclidean
basically they are the thing that you
will see used most often to represent
rotations and so if you want to
understand them you have to understand
not Euclidean geometry because they are
not the collodion what happens in
partial differential equations if if
scott Meyers is in a gorilla suit and
distracts you so much this trussed up in
a green car could swap your briefcase
full of compression writing code for I
would basically say that it depends
whether you are actually sitting there
trying to bring the briefcase to your
boss or whether you're observing it from
a green car waiting at a red light out
on the the airport Drive are using a
mouse or digital pen I'm using a digital
pen
do you take it stuff do you take a trail
of coke before you start the stream no I
don't I don't really take anything let's
see don't the tire tiles near the inner
part of the Taurus gets smaller than the
ones near the outside so isn't the top
isn't the topography more of a magic
cylinder in which each end is hooked
into each other well so not really and
the reason for that is just because like
I said it's topology often isn't about
the actual size of things it's about
whether there could be the things right
so try to explain this a little bit
better so basically inside the Taurus
here - apologies about how they're
connected not how big they are so as
long as they don't vanish like they do
here you're okay right the problem here
is that it becomes invisibly small it
becomes down shrinks down to a single
point and that means that at this point
there is no longer any notion of the
connectivity between the rows of the
tiles and anything else right so you
can't follow a line along here and
expect to end up in the right you know
on the right tile thing when you get
back to the to the other side right it's
kind of hard to to say exactly what why
that's the case there so typically like
the problem with the sphere is basically
that you have that singularity at the
top where everything disappears into a
point whereas the torus never has that
so yes these would be smaller if we were
talking about the actual geometry of a
torus but they never get any smaller
than that and they rewind inugami
represented through the entire way so so
that yeah you would have to ask an
actual topology for a better explanation
than what I gave because again I am NOT
a mathematician so my explanations of
things are largely based on my
functional knowledge of how they work
and not necessarily a very good pure
mathematical explanation and so really
like again they would probably give you
explanations that are more about
what happens locally on the surface and
less about sort of the more intuitive
explanation that I gave but yeah so if
you if you did want though to represent
it somehow magically perfectly you are
correct
a tourist isn't quite right because if
you wanted to represent the spatial part
correctly you would need it to not get
smaller on the inside which is kind of
impossible to do right because it's
gonna be the ring of smart here now one
of the dimensions is fine the ring
dimension that goes around is fine
because that's always the same size no
matter where you are but the there's
this one is smaller than this one in
terms of the inner and outer so yeah how
is dealing with complex numbers and four
dimensions better or more useful for
doing rotations as opposed to using a
rotation around an arbitrary axis matrix
I Det don't get how quaternions are
better so there's a lot of ways that
quarter nians are better and I will I
will show you a simple example so let's
say that you want and and I'm not sure
exactly I'm not sure exactly what you
mean by the phrase using a rotation
around an arbitrary axis matrix so I
don't know what you actually mean by
that but I'm going to assume that what
you were referring to is a rotation
matrix right so you were talking about
in our matrix which is basically a
matrix you know that looks something
like you know one of the one of these
kind of matrices sort of things right
well actually that's not quite right we
need an extra one in there that's bad so
we need a we're talking about a rotation
matrix where we basically have like a
cosine sort of sign sort of a thing I
don't actually remember exactly how this
would look it's like a negative sign
here one of these kinds of guys you're
talking about this sort of thing where
you basically have have something like
this a rotation matrix and I guess
arbitrary axis means it would be more
complicated than this because that's a
single axis rotation so I don't know how
to write one of those may
she's out by hand but yeah so you're
basically talking about a rotation
matrix that's some three dimensional
rotation about some axis so we'll say
that's a rotation matrix that's
parameterised by an axis and an angle is
that basically what we're talking about
here hopefully I don't know but let's
say that that's what you were talking
about so we have rotation matrix versus
a quaternion that's going to basically
be the same quaternion it's so it's so
you're representing it the exact same
rotation around some axis with a theta
right so basically the reason that you
want to use quaternions instead of
rotation matrices are I mean the very
first one is efficiency so one of these
matrices is going to at least run you
three by three or nine values right so
anytime you're computing with one of
these you essentially have to do a a
three by three matrix you have to store
nine values and those nine values have
to be renormalized continuously right
because basically if you're one of the
requirements for a rotation matrix in
order for the rotation is that it cannot
change the size of anything right that's
what kind of what makes it a rotation
matrix is that the size is invariant so
that basically means that every all of
the axis didn't have to be orthonormal
and blah blah blah so you've got a you
know you've got a matrix that's
basically three vectors and those
vectors have to be unit length like this
guy this guy this guy all have to be
unit length which also implies that the
rows are unit length right
so basically you've got this rotation
act just actually just it's it's much
less efficient to store it because the
quaternion only requires storing four
values right so already we're kind of at
an advantage if we're in quaternion
space because we've got four values
instead of nine and that's kind of handy
furthermore when we actually do
operations on these guys there's a
number of operations that we can do
extremely trivially on the quaternions
that actually are fairly expensive on a
rotation so for example if I want to
actually construct one of these guys
right I have to take the the sine and
cosine and fill out all nine values this
guy I actually only have to fill out the
four values that only have to take the
cosine of the thing now that's actually
kind of special because since I don't
need the sine right you need the sign
for the rotation matrix since I don't
need the sine I can often compute the
cosine as a byproduct the reason for
that and
we're kind of getting off into lala land
here but you know I'm just gonna just
thrown out some examples for you since
you asked the cosine of theta it can
often be directly computed as the dot
product between two things right so you
never actually have to take a cosine you
never have to have to do a
transcendental typically like if you
want to know the angle between two
vectors you just do a transpose beam you
get the cosine right if these were
normalized you'd get the cosine for free
if not you have to normalize that but
that's you know usually small potatoes
between compared to doing a sine Coast
which you'd have to do for this guy
right so typically you can actually
compute quaternions wholly without
trigonometric functions altogether which
is kind of amazing
whereas for rotation matrices you're
never getting away with that you've got
to do at least that and possibly more
depending on you know if you're doing
Rodrigues formulation where you're doing
the full rotate around the arbitrary
matrix you're talking about a lot of
operations to initialize those 9x9 s and
then furthermore you got to do 3x3
matrix multiplication to compose them so
every time I want to combine one H still
another I got to do a full 3 by 3 times
3x3 operation to compose the the
matrices and I don't have to do that
with my attorney and quaternions have a
much simpler composition form it's not
quite as simple as just like you know
adding them together or something like
that but it's still pretty good right so
you've got all that but you also got a
bunch of other stuff that happened with
quaternions that are much more powerful
than matrices quaternions have this nice
property that they actually represent
things sort of over the over the space
of double rotations not single rotations
and I'm not going to try explains that
what that means right now but I will
simply say that if you have two
quaternions or more you can oftentimes
deal with them rather directly as if
they were vectors and normalize after
the fact there's something you cannot do
with matrices because they will generate
quickly so for example let's say that I
have several orientations in space for
example I have five animations playing
right I have five animations playing and
I want to blend them all together at the
same time so I have five animations
playing for a guy's run it's like or
well it's maybe that's a little bit
unrealistic let's say we have three
animations playing so I have three
animations playing and each of those
animations is going to compute a
position for the guy's head his neck
right so I've got his neck and each of
the three animations well one said it
was pointing this way
said it was pointing that way and once
it is pointing this way right now
because my animator wanted to do some
tweaking and whatever you know we've got
blends between those animations so we
say that we want 30% of animation a plus
40% of animation B which leaves of
course 30 more percent for animation C
okay so that's the equation I want to
compute with my orientations to figure
out what the resulting orientation of
all these guys should be for the neck of
my character okay now this is something
you've done in our animation tools
without even knowing it right you you
you wait animations that you blend
together so we all know this is this
operation it's like I want to blend
three animations together to get a
resulting animation okay well if I want
to do that with matrix math you're
almost dead in the water actually
because you don't know how far like
these two diametrically opposed
animations are going to cause you some
pretty severe numerical problems
potentially especially if they look like
that because once you start adding 30
percent of one thing in 30 percent of
another thing that happened to be
diametrically opposed you will start to
collapse down to here so you can't just
add these matrices directly together or
you'll get really bad degeneracy as you
try to like blend these things together
and you'll end up with almost all this
animation even though that's not what
should have happened quaternions don't
really suffer from this problem too much
quieter knee is because they represent a
larger space of rotations they actually
represent twice the total space of
representations don't ask me about that
yet because we're nowhere near that
that's a topic that's probably beyond
handmade here oh but that's what they do
because of that you could actually add
these things together much more reliably
because this this situation almost can't
happen you basically get a a case where
even in neck orientations that are very
far from each other appear in
quaternions to actually be much closer
to each other than they are twice as
close in fact as matrices which means
that if you add them together you can
actually directly add them together and
normalize after the fact and you will
get much better behaved systems and not
only that but instead of adding nine
numbers together each time you do one of
these ads and then having to renormalize
the whole thing which is basically
renormalizing the entire matrix that's
nine numbers you base there just adding
four numbers together so it's just four
plus four plus four and then you
renormalize just those four right
much much cleaner so easier to construct
smaller to store easier to work with
much better numerically behaved can also
do stuff like neighborhood Inge there's
just there's a ton of reasons why
pattern Ian's are better so basically
like if you're using 3x3 mains to use to
represent your animation data or your
orientation data in 3d world you're
probably a sad panda what can I say ever
do anything with the PLAs transforms not
personally but what's going on here did
I just lose my stream
are we still live why didn't say
reconnecting you know looks good I'm
assuming I'm still live every do you
think with Laplace transforms not
personally but if I remember correctly
spiracle harmonics don't you use them in
spherical harmonics I don't actually
know I feel like the Laplace transform
is used in spherical harmonics a lot I
could be wrong about that so I don't use
them I'm not much of a rendering guy
don't do a lot of rendering code
I feel like Laplace transforms happen
these days though that's what I that's
what I feel like but I don't actually
know so that's yeah I'm not sure about
that what type of math is used in a I
specifically prediction a reaction of
two player choice I'm not an AI expert
so I don't really know what kind of math
they typically use I don't know baby
Bayesian
Bayesian networks and that sort of stuff
you know I'm not sure certainly
optimization like operations research is
an a ie kinds of things so you use a
bunch of that I'm sure but I don't know
I'm not really any experts I'm not sure
to say is all of the things shown in
math class is useful sometimes stuff
seems so unnecessary and mind killing
what's your opinion on that my opinion
is yes it's probably all useful but it's
all taught very poorly so my my
assumption is that almost everything
that you actually see in a high school
math class is actually particularly
useful however you would never know it
by the way they teach it because they
teach early typically teach it in a way
that it will be almost impossible for
you to even think of how it might be
used and only later in life when you
actually find places where you start
using it you go oh that's why I would
need to know that let's see
okay quaternions as you use them in
rotation are definitely not Euclidean
they're not like they just aren't you
cannot treat them Euclidean Li because
they have a normalization constraint to
them right and so basically when you're
doing quaternions I don't want to argue
with people on stream quaternions as you
use them in rotations are not Euclidean
period what ascends it there
can we talk a bit about what out of the
master list we expect to use in this
game yes so we'll use arithmetic algebra
geometry trigonometry calculus obviously
I don't know whether we'll use partial
differential equations or ordinary
differential equations we'll definitely
use linear algebra euclidean geometry
we'll definitely use I don't know if
we'll ever use any non nuclear charge
because we're not doing 3d topology we
already mentioned even on the stream
Minkowski algebra will probably use in
the collision detector I don't know
whether we'll use any numerical analysis
which is like iterative methods for
solving things but possibly control
theory definitely interval arithmetic
possibly but I'm not sure discrete math
obviously but I don't know it very well
so we'll probably just be using most of
what other people have done like we'll
go use someone's pseudo-random number
generator and we won't necessarily talk
about how you construct it because I
don't really know how to construct a
good random number generator graph
theory almost definitely probably in
statistics almost definitely so yeah
well the next few weeks cover the basic
functionalities that are math heavy or
will you spread it out the topics more
yeah will basically be covering them
when we get to them but now is the time
when I have to start talking about math
because there's really nothing left to
do in terms of our engine work that
isn't going to be using at least vectors
so that's why I decided to kind of have
this stream at this point in time
let's see it's nice to see you recommend
learning math so strongly can did you
learn most of it from books or did you
take courses all books really I've never
taken a math course since I got out of
high school I heard Markov chains are
also useful crossing control xxx
probability will we use these I don't
know I mean it depends on how we
implement our world generation that's
probably the only place that we'd really
have a chance to use them
obviously I mentioned the metropolis
algorithm and I feel like that's
technically filed under a Monte Carlo
Markov chain model I don't really
remember though and so you know if we
use some kind of permutation based world
generator maybe a Markov chain is
technically involved there I'm not sure
the Internet pennant police doesn't
forgive oversimplifications why do you
even bother it's a good question but the
answer is because it's my stream and
that is kind of nice because it means
that what I say goes so I try to be
pretty nice to people who write in but
if someone wants to argue about a math
thing I just don't care because at some
level it's like I only know the math
that I know and I can only explain
things that I know and so I already said
at the very beginning of the stream if
you really want to know the very
specific math terms for everything you
will have to look them up yourselves
because not only do I not know them but
I like don't think I could ever know
them all I know a lot more math that I
use day to day than I could ever
possibly really remember all the
specifics for and still be a very
productive programmer right like the
level of specificity you need to always
say the exact right thing in terms of a
math explanation is way beyond what I
think anyone who does as much different
types of math as I do could do unless
you were just some kind of like an idiot
savant or whatever right so it's gonna
happen get used to it and I'm more than
happy to have people post corrections on
the forums for people who want to know
specific math terms are like he said
that this was X here but it was actually
Y or whatever in terms of like you know
this term or that term so people want to
learn the actual terms that they'll have
links
let's see
you
so the people is saying that the stream
dropped out yeah it definitely said
reconnecting on my side but for some
reason it still says drop-frame zero
which means I feel like this counter is
not particularly accurate that's kind of
frustrating cuz it means I have no way
of knowing that it what happened
which is kind of annoying but I saw the
reconnection dialog so I know it went
down but I don't know why I didn't tell
me
OBS let's see here all right looks like
we're basically done so that is the end
of the stream thank you everyone for
joining me for a little math I can't say
it has been a pleasure program with you
because we did not program but it has
been a pleasure going over math of
course which is very useful in
programming in which we will be making
increasingly frequent use of as the
stream goes forward so I hope you will
not be shy about exploring math on your
own and kind of looking into the math
topics that we cover because there are a
lot of really important math things out
there to learn and it does take a little
bit of dedication on everyone's part to
kind of go learn math the math that they
don't know in time to do stuff in
handmade Hira so thank you very much for
joining me if you would like to follow
along with the source code starting
tomorrow with the math and so on if you
want to pre-order the game you can go to
handmade hero org and if you peer out of
the game it comes with all the source
code so you can basically download it
every night and follow along with what I
do on the stream if you want support the
video series we do have a patch run you
could subscribe to and if you'd like to
learn along with the series we do have a
news and forum site that is where I was
saying people could post corrections to
math statements I make in this code
discussion forum for example it also has
an episode guide it has a schedule for
the week posted as well it has an
episode guide that said that you can use
to catch up on past episodes that you
missed and it's got a coding resources
page with ports to Linux and Mac and
stuff like that you can use if you're
trying to run handmade hero on another
platform from the source code so
hopefully you will check that out if
you're interested thank you very much
for joining me I will be back tomorrow
at 8 p.m. Pacific Centre time to talk a
little bit about vectors and do some
code with vectors with you so you can
start to see how they work in the real
world so thank you everyone for joining
me and I hope to see you tomorrow
you