start recording hello everyone and
welcome to handmade hero the show recode
a complete game live on stream we are
here on day 3 31 and we were just
finishing up some bug's stuff yesterday
I think there's a couple little
remaining issues to check out I think we
missed one Kim reopened this one because
he said we also need to do the float one
so we should probably do that but
otherwise I think we got most of these
down I haven't heard from anyone yet on
this guy right here like I said these
are just someone needs to figure out the
macro thing so I'm going to leave this
one around we're not going to address it
because I think that's the last thing
we're not going to dress that till
someone tells me what we might need to
do to fix the macros completely like
gives us a working example because until
then I I really can't play with it much
I'd have to install clang to like start
testing it or something like that and
they don't really think that's a useful
thing to do at this point so if someone
who really cares about building under
clang wants to do that go ahead and do
that and let me know and so and if you
know if I get that I'll definitely do it
in short order this one however we can
do this was just a case of I forgot one
of them when I was when I was cleaning
this out and like I said a 331 so this
is date 330 source code that I medic
here let's go ahead and that going so
here in the printf what we were doing
before is again and I'll just say this
one more time but I think was probably
clear for most people when we're reading
ver arms off of the stack I see for
whatever reason and I'll be honest I
don't really know the reason
historically but the way that it puts
things on the stack in a ver arg
function is it will always expand them
to be certain types so if you try to put
an integer on the stack in a very arc
function it will go on as an intern
but if you try to put a care like an
8-bit value on the stack it will
actually expand it to 32 bits first
that's just how ver arms works and i'm
assuming that said something to do with
stack alignment or something i really
don't know or maybe convenience i'm not
sure but for whatever reason that's how
ver args works so it is not the case
that when you put a care on you get a
care off you put a care on you get an
int off you put a short on you get an
ant off you put an int on you get an
impt off you put a float on you get a
double off you put a double on you get a
double off right and i missed one of
those cases when we were doing that here
really this one length equals 8 really
what happens in this function is it's
always this case I believe it's always
going to be a double I don't think
there's any way to actually push a float
I'm not sure about that but I think
that's the case and so that was the bug
clang was cause I was complaining about
here with the float part still needing
you know it's basically saying hey you
know that float will get turned into a
double so when you pull off a float
you're probably doing something wrong
and like i said i think that is zach
with respect oh so that was just that
that's clang catching a potential error
that we just don't have right now but
it's accurate so let's go ahead and take
a look and make sure that we're still
working properly here with that change
and it does look like everything's fine
they're all good
so yeah hopefully now we can actually
mark this okay hopefully I actually
fixed it this time for you on okay 331
we go all right so now I think we are
down to not having any particular bugs
here that I'm going to address in short
order again this guy is mostly done on
the other parts so this part I think is
all done but this part here is not and
so if somebody does want to take the
initiative who has clang and works with
Liang to figure out how to make our
debug macros work okay with it I will
make that change so just let me know
about that and I don't know if this is
that if this solution works okay we
could switch to it potentially but
anyway someone needs to figure out like
and send me hey here's the defines that
allow it to work on clang these are what
you should use we will switch to those
so that people compiling with clang will
not have to worry about that anymore
because in theory we are now compatible
with flying everywhere else because we
fixed the other issues that make sense
all right so that's it for that I'm
going to leave that open in case we need
it tomorrow or the next day or the next
day or the next day and I'm going to go
over to our to do list and since we're
kind of coming back from a long break I
just want to kind of figure out you know
maybe what we should be doing here
because we need sort of a plan of how we
want to tie everything up I'm pretty
certain that really mostly all we have
to do is that Z fixes and then a couple
things with the renderer maybe just to
make sure that we're clean enough that
we don't spill over any problems with
our renderer that still exists aren't
going to cause problems in the game code
as we can always upgrade our render or
later right we can always make our
render better at any time and it's zero
cost to us it'll just improve the look
of the game or whatever
like if we add lighting it'll just
magically look better right but if we
have some kind of an architectural flaw
with the way that stuff is fed to the
render which we might have right in that
case then we run into a problem because
then all of our game code is written to
that rendering API and now we need to
change it we now have to go touch all of
our game code and sort of spend a lot of
work you know making that happen so you
know I don't want to leave us in a
situation if we're I I suspect we might
have some problems with the way we're
feeding the renderer so we may want to
take a little bit of a look at that as
well but like I said we don't have to
worry too much if our complete if if
there's anything that we need
additionally from the renderer going
forwards that's actually okay because we
don't have to get everything right at
the outset we just want to make sure
that we aren't having too much sort of
leakage of a bad decisions in there
because if we ever want to upgrade the
renderer we don't want to have to
rewrite all of our code that talks to it
right and maybe that's not such a huge
deal in this case in this particular
game because we do have a pretty narrow
like everything is an entity and that's
in the path that renders things is
pretty narrow like it's kind of just at
the end of the entity stuff and so you
know maybe in this case we don't really
have to care and it won't be a big deal
so you know it might not be a thing that
you care that much about but we at least
want to just look at it make sure that
everything's fine so let's take a look
here at what we've got right here is our
to-do list of things that we need to
know and I think at the moment if we
were to look at the the the stuff on
here I feel like this debug code stuff
is probably at the point where we could
you know we could probably sort of do
some of these guys there's not a whole
lot there we have the frame view not
showing bad frames that's the thing that
we want to kind of kind of fix and we
have that problem that we're still
running everything through the fairly
complicated graph sort even though we
don't really need that for debug stuff
because it's a fairly straightforward
sort so that's something that we might
want to you know fix as well
on the enemy system side of things we've
got this to do here which is what to do
about geographically disparate entities
that might only partially get streamed
into a sim region but which need to move
together as a unit you can see why
that's a problem essentially what's
going on there is let's say we have that
you know that snake creature right and
you can see we know we made one of these
guys right he's he's hopping around
there that snake guy he's five segments
long and if you think about what's going
on there with that snake dude he gets
streamed in his five separate entities
which is good that's sort of what we
wanted him to be but what that means is
that in the case where just like part of
the tail or something was in a region
that didn't get streamed in right so he
gets streamed in most him get streamed
in but part of him doesn't you know that
creates kind of a nasty situation
potentially and so there was a question
of whether or not we wanted to try and
do something with the env system to
prevent that sort of thing from
happening meaning to prevent the case
where we sort of have entities which you
know are are are left in that sort of
limbo right where they could get split
and you know one thing that I think
would be interesting to do there because
I think we actually maybe have some
options that don't involve anything
particularly complicated because we
could pretty easily bound the size of
these guys you know we can say that
there can't be something that's like 30
long probably right I don't know maybe
we don't want to say that but you can
kind of imagine what the problem is here
with these sorts of things where you
know if we if we stream part of it in
and not the other part of it in we could
imagine solving that by just saying okay
instead of streaming in just the stuff
that we're going to consider active we
could stream in again like use that sort
of apron concept stream in a little bit
past that but don't consider any
entities in the region
so don't consider entities in the apron
to be actually active right and then
what we could do is just make it so that
if an entity is part of a brain that is
active but it's in the inactive region
then it becomes active right so we could
make a way essentially to enforce or not
really enforce but make it so that you'd
never get entities that would get split
up like that because of the placement of
the streaming region I think we could do
something like that I just don't know
whether that creates more problems than
it solves or whether it's really worth
even caring about we're worrying about I
really don't know I have no idea and if
you assume that things are generally
confined two rooms then for the most
part this would only happen when
something was crossing a room boundary
right it would only happen when like one
of these guys is like going out a door
like out one door and into another room
where it can even get messed up in that
way to begin with and so again I really
just don't know about that but you could
understand like what my concern is with
it right um hopefully all right
so I don't know I really just don't know
what to do about that I'm not sure I
don't have a solid idea for it what it
would look like is in here you know when
we do this this thing this would all be
exactly the same right so we'd have the
this this loop would be exact the same
maybe we expand this a little maybe we
don't i'm not sure but what we would do
here is say okay when these things
stream in we would have an ocean per
entity right so in in the actual entity
that gets streamed in in here you know
we already have flags and what we would
have is a flag that that said whether or
not this was actually active right so
we'd have an entity flag active and by
default anything that was inside the
region that we are going to animate is
considered active and anything outside
that region is considered inactive and
would not get animated and then what we
would do is when we look at a particular
brain right before we start actually
processing the scene we loop through all
the people in that brain and if any of
them are active we mark all of them as
active so it will suck in people from
the apron region and make them active
again I don't really know if this is a
good idea or not but hey it seems like
something worth trying uh so I'm going
to go ahead and try it right because why
not so let's say we add an env flag here
called active right and inside the code
when we're going through these chunks
all I would really need to know is sort
of that again that that updateable bound
and the update safety margin kind of
thing right we sort of already had this
concept I think to a certain extent in
fact weren't we already you know we had
this thing for updatable bounds right
we had updateable bounds which were not
the same as bounds and I don't really
know oh so we actually have an updatable
we already have this concept I don't
know why it's not a flag I don't know
why it's it's that way right that's a
very good question like why that isn't a
flag i do not know i'm going to try
changing that so i'm going to say ok if
entity overlaps rectangle in the
updateable bounds i'm going to say des
flags or equals this flag that says
where the thing is active or not where
did that go there it is like active we
are and then I'm going to take a look at
this stuff here ok so we were using that
inside update and render entities so I
guess we are already doing what we need
to do here so we've actually already
written this because of the collision
stuff the way we were doing it so that's
kind of nice it means I don't really
have to worry about implementing that
new newly right and off we go so we
already have it so that nothing happens
if this thing isn't an entity flag
active so that's great so now all we
really have to do is inside handmade
brain well I guess it's not really
inside handmade brain but we want a sort
of pre pass on the brain execution stuff
where when we go through these brains
the first thing we do is Mark anyone who
mate who is part of an active brain as
being active themselves right so I
believe in world mode here we are in
execute brains so what I might do is
like okay let's do a pre pass after this
I'm sorry before this
let's do a little pre pass where we do
like a mark brain active something like
that mark brain actives something like
this and that's just going to be a thing
which goes through all of the entities
that are in the brain and does that
marking okay so the way this would work
I think we would want it to be sort of
like the snake right I'm kind of see
here I'm assuming we've got a segment
count on these brains not segments count
sorry a member account but let me make
sure that's true so we have a brain type
is type where his brain brain there is
brain so there's our entity array and so
we can just step through this entity
array for however many that there are
and i believe the maximum number that
there are should be known to us right I
feel like let's see I guess we don't
really know how many there actually are
do we
which is kind of unfortunate because we
want to sort of loop through those and
check well we must know because we can
at least assert that we're not writing
out of bounds so let's go ahead and
check inside some region here we go so
here is our sort of hacky code for doing
it you can see that we had filled with
in fact I remember this discussion where
us like I really wish this worked better
right uh in in languages like C like I
just want to say hey however many the
most number of enemies there are that's
how many I want to be treating in here
but yes I guess I guess the answer is
this sort of situation is unfortunately
all we can really do so let's maybe at
least systema eyes that a little bit
let's go ahead and try to make that
something that's that's not so that's
not so specific to that circumstance
something where we can ask how many of
these there actually are you know so
what I'm going to do here is we're going
to say let's make a little in line or
even a pound to fine let's say which is
like brain max uh you know end of the
account or something like that I kind of
want to be in the other window here so I
want to compute for brain Mack Sennett
account I want to compute how many of
this array they're actually could be
right and so you can see how I was doing
that Kier I took essentially this sort
of rather odd way of doing things but
it's the only way I could really figure
out how if I was to take a brain and go
forward the size of the brain and then
go back one NV pointer right that was
going to be the maximum one that there
was right that was going to be the
furthest out that there was
so really I could just not do that right
and say well there's size of brain and
size of brain is the whole structure
size right and then what I could do it
just say well I know that it's the race
starts here right I know that that that
array starts here and you know I'll be
honest it's a little bit weird that it's
oh no that's correct right that single
pointer so I know that it starts here so
if i subtract the offset of that thing
and I don't know if we I assume we did
off set up at some point
maybe not I'll sit no I guess we didn't
do be really not have one of those I'll
sit from struct huh well I basically
want one of these so we might be able to
just use this one I don't know if it's
baked into this in in anymore or not or
if it's if it's something that I have to
include this for I think I may have to
do a pound include for it in which case
I'll just do it myself so I don't have
to use the pound include but basically
what i want is just the offset of a
member in a struct right so all i really
want to do is say hey the offset of this
member inside the brain i want to i want
to take that and i want to subtract that
away because i don't want to count these
guys so i just want to see how big the
brain is in that sense right so once i
have that i know the total size of this
union part and since i know that's all
entity stars all i have to do to figure
out how many of them there are is
divided by that length right so that
should give me the maximum entity count
of one of these things now if I then go
here and I think like I said I'm going
to have to write that off set of myself
I would suspect but who knows we'll find
out so if i was going to do that what i
could now once i have that i can then go
ahead and say all right there's an
editing index that goes from zero to the
maximum number of enemies if there can
be in the brain and let me go ahead and
give myself a brain here to work with
and then so inside that brain I'm going
to do two loops through the first loop
through i'm going to say that whatever
the entity star i'm not sure exactly how
to access this here I guess I would just
say yeah I guess I would just say gets
lot do you have one of these
yeah here it is Oh in fact there is the
code for the offset of right so we
actually did the offset of stuff but we
just didn't do it we just didn't do it
as a macro we just did it directly which
is fine anyway so in brain slaw floor
let's see here we're calling this guy
with the pack value which is the
distance off so basically we're figuring
out what the index is there and how do
we actually get that brain slap back I
guess we haven't had to do that we
haven't had to iterate through these at
all it looks like right but what I want
here is I essentially want to do like
get you know nidhi ghouls get entity in
slot and I want to pass the brain and I
want to pass I guess this is technically
the slot index right so I want to be
able to get a you know the entity in in
the slot and then I want to say I want
to have a be 32 here which is like is
active which was false and then in here
I want to say like okay if entity flags
and Eddie like active then I'm going to
do effective equals true right and it's
another thing I could do here which I
might just do just in case for future
proof pneus because it's actually pretty
easy maybe I'll do like combine flags or
brain flags and then what I could do it
just say okay for each of these guys
like brain flags for equals entity flags
so this will just accumulate all the
flags then at the end I just say all
right if brain flags and entity flag
active that means somebody at least one
person had to have been active in order
for that flag to get set so then I would
come back through
here and say all right now take the
entity flags and Orion entity flag
active right because now everybody in
this brain it gets magically pulled into
the active region right hopefully that
makes some sense but we need to have
some way of doing that get entity and
slot because we don't have that right
now and so that's going to be something
we have to go implement now in this case
here we don't have to do anything let me
go back into the brain and do that Max
entity count thing so here is max brain
slot count and yeah that I believe is
still is going to be correct again this
offset of I'm going to go ahead and
define my own offset of for now because
we're using it in two places already
here is the type here's the member right
and it's really just this so the yeah
the address of the sky is because I
think all we really need for the offset
of I think that should do it and let me
see if that works
let me just convert that so now all we
really need to do here and you know I'm
going to put that in a useful place as
well and put that in here because this
is something I would generally want I
don't know why we didn't have it but we
didn't so now we do and Kennedy and slot
we need here in the brain so in order to
get an entity from a slot we need
something that looks like this where we
pass the brain and we pass the slot
index we're going to use right and then
what we need to do is say okay we know
we've got an env star we should probably
do an assertion here the slot index is
less than the max brain slot count
because you can't fetch one pass that
right but then we know the result is
going to be whatever the array pointer
is here right we should be able to get a
pointer to that pointer right so now
we're pointing at this guy then we just
want to go forward however many slots
we're talking about here and since this
is a pointer to a pointer we could just
say access this is like an array and
give us out the actual pointer at the
slot index right then we return the
result and now we've gotten back that
guy so we're just using this as a marker
to allow us to index into all of these
guys who happen to be in the union and
go from there okay now in theory oh duh
we've got one more thing to do when we
get this entity out we don't know if
there's actually there right those slots
could be empty so we definitely have to
check to see whether they're know
because we only want to edit if they're
they're not all right
so now we would need to actually do some
testing on this or something we're not
at the point yet where any of that makes
sense but we don't really know if this
worked at all we're strictly putting it
in there as a way to mitigate this
problem so that now it's in their
architectural e so we're aware of it as
we move forwards meaning we know we have
to kind of maintain that concept and
keep it going all right so in theory
that's okay I don't really know there's
issues that obviously one of the issues
is that if those things are pulled into
the brain well the whole point of that
apron where things weren't active is
that we don't know if they can move to
certain squares because those squares
might not be there or I might not have
their blockers in them what I will say
is I think some of that has been
mitigated now the reason some of that
has been mitigated is now that you move
to specific squares if a square hasn't
been streamed in you can't move to it
anyway so at that point you're not going
to do something like move to somewhere
that you couldn't have moved because it
wouldn't have been there right so I
think that's probably okay i'm at least
a little happier about it so that's all
right okay so let's talk about some
other parts of this here what do we want
to do here I don't know that I'm in the
mood to do anything with the debug code
at the moment I'm going to demote that
to some time when we feel more
interested in it it's not it's just not
really my jam at the moment
and yeah fixed clicking bug at end of
samples again these these are things
that I'm not sure we really need to be
doing at the moment and maybe we do
these at some point when we're feeling
in the mood to do some clean ups and
code cleanup we can look at them because
they're not really architectural like
the clicking at the end of samples is a
totally random bug that we can just fix
at any time doesn't affect anything else
in the in the program at all it's really
just not important so yeah so I think
mostly i'm going to move some of these
up here uh I don't know multiple sim
regions per frame and per entity
clocking that is definitely a different
thing and so is AI pathfinding right AI
pathfinding is definitely something that
we don't really know how we would do at
the moment I mean we know how we how we
know what we would probably do for
pathfinding on a single screen but we
don't have a lot of ideas about how we
would do path finding more in the large
what I'm assuming is I think probably
what we would do is maintain a single
path finding grid of some kind of single
path finding network for larger scale
path finding that people just use and so
I don't think we will do large-scale
searches on for individual entities I
don't think that would be necessary I
think we could just use the same search
grid in those cases so I think we can
probably just run those paths finds as
they need to be run so i guess i'm not
too worried about that AI storage I
think we'll just be stored in the
entities so i think i'm actually not
particularly concerned about this so i
think this is not i think the brains are
what i wanted and i don't know that i
need any of this stuff i don't think
there's really anything in particular
going on there it does however i think
when we do world generation uh where is
that rudimentary well Jen I'm going to
put that in here because when we
generate the world I think that's the
part where we would probably need some
of that pathfinding to occur right so
entities could kind of find their way
around so when we generate it we're
going to want to keep like a
connectivity thing I think you know
we're going to need something where we
can kind of go okay you know this is how
we created the world so we have like its
backbone and we could do pathfinding on
the backbone and if there's things like
doors or stuff they're kind of
semantically in there or whatever we
need we're going to need something like
that because there's no way to do
large-scale path fighting I don't think
for the sizes that we kind of allow the
world to be like we don't really have
any practical limits for the most part
on how big world's could be in handmade
hero and so I don't really want to worry
about if someone wants to make a really
giant world and handmade hero I don't
want them to have to do like I don't
want the pathfinding to actually be
trying to deal with that because it
would just roll over and die so I think
it needs to have kind of more of an
understanding of what's going on there
at a couple levels of detail alright so
let's see for architecture exploration
here I'm going to kind of get start
working on this to do list a little more
seriously so I think Z is probably the
most logical thing to do probably next
that was sort of what we had worked on a
bunch and we haven't quite still
finished it so I think maybe that's what
we should be working on next rendering
wise i feel like the 18,000 draw a
rectangle calls we knew what that was
that was all of our fonts right
happening there i believe so some of
these things have kind of been done some
of them haven't been a final
optimization i think we can well and
hardware rendering we sort of did we
actually did do render to texture so
that's actually done and for shaders i
guess i don't know
that we want to do those yet we could do
them we could do them I'm not sure I I
think these are things i'm going to just
kind of postponed because I don't really
care about them very much they're really
not particularly important but we would
need it if we wanted to do lighting
right if we wanted to do lighting
there's probably no way to implement
lighting in the fixed in the fixed
function pipeline and open jail so we
would have to use shaders in order to do
that there's really nothing else we
could probably do about that I so
there's that I guess is what I would say
so we will need that if we side to do
lighting so I've got to think about what
i want to do there those are probably be
done together would be my guess for the
coordinate systems we're pretty close on
that that's here basically so I think
this pass includes straighten out all
coordinate systems because it's the
final pass on that stuff to make sure
that that's actually good because we're
still a little bit of janky pneus in the
Z I don't know that we have a problem
still with projections I feel like our
project and unprotect now work properly
so I mean in some sense we don't really
have real projections like we're not
doing a full projection matrix or
anything like this but on the other hand
it seems like it's fairly solid at this
point like for example we do back
project the mouse properly now and all
that sort of stuff so it seems like
that's working okay at least at the
moment so I'm going to call that
something that if we wanted us to get
more later we certainly can assign comes
up but I don't think there's anything
much to do their final optimization here
is something that didn't didn't really
need to happen so this is like more like
extra credit
this is like final lap you know or
serious optimization of the software
renderer because we never really did
that I showed some basic optimization of
the sufferer render but we never really
tried to get down to the really
nitty-gritty of it and and make it run
really fast we did basically a cursory
kind of like obvious pass on it and that
was all we did so you know at some point
if we decide maybe after the game is
entirely done you know and our hardware
renderer will be totally fine because
we're just not stressing out hardware
very much with this game um you know
maybe we want to go back and make it
totally playable and software you know
30 frames a second and all that we could
go back and do that so but I don't put
that down there because we don't really
need to do that at the moment for the
game because we did ended up doing the
hardware renderer so we now have a way
to run quickly without the software
renderer we don't have to worry if the
software under is too slow to deal with
you know very stuff but that doesn't
mean it wouldn't be fun to go do that
optimization someday so I leave it on
there for rendering left over here we've
got particle systems and lighting are
the two big things that I feel like we
are going to need that we don't have at
the moment lighting is you know one of
those things where it's like unclear
exactly what that entails because
there's it's it's a lot of you know
lighting is always kind of a hacky
approximation thing even when you do 3d
it's hockey it's not just acting to do
tacky everywhere so I don't know exactly
what we want to do for that we played
around with it a little bit back in the
day but we never really settled on
anything because we kind of needed to
get like our layers working properly and
so we're finally kind of converging on
having that but that kind of had to do
with the lighting what I would say about
lighting is it does feel like something
that would be better to work out sooner
rather than later so I think I want to
kind of leave it on this list and what I
might say is well particle systems
particle systems are probably easier and
probably do impact how we send things to
the renderer so i might say let's do a
part
system pass after the Z and then we'll
do the lighting pass I don't care about
the 18,000 draw rectangles call thing
that's not a huge deal i don't think but
what I do want to do is there is one
thing on the debug code I want to
disable sorting because that was really
too much for it so I think we know all
this thing all this stuff
so I think most of this stuff is
actually fairly set a constant
foreground collision so we fixed all
this because we use sort of that moving
from fixed position to fixed position so
I think we just need to kind of go
through and do the straightening up of
our zpass we do need to make sure that
this sort of thing works for a collision
where you can have flying things going
over low walls or what have you but we
need to kind of definitely need to make
that happen now here's what I'd say
about this I feel like what we want to
do is at some point in here we want to
schedule a switch over to new artwork
because a lot of our artwork is broken
right now like if you take a look at
because the way that I had had just put
in our test assets I don't know if we
still have the sort groups yeah we do so
if you take a look at these sort groups
here it's just absurd like how big they
are because they include all of this
empty space around the hero and they're
aligned wrong and all this other stuff
like you can see that's the that's the
box the the actual rendered area of this
this head here and that's just stupid
it's just wasting a lot of real estate
and it makes it really much harder on
the sort as well because now there's
tons of things that say they're
overlapping and they're not really
overlapping you know so I feel like we
want to move over to cleaner art
sometime soon and I feel like maybe here
would be the place to do it so I think
we want to do like transition to new
artwork and I'm going to actually put
real artwork here I suppose because anna
has a whole set of art for us now that
you did that includes like multiple
heroes and enemies and terrain
and like all kinds of stuff that she did
in a in a couple weeks that is really
good and it's the right perspective and
all that stuff too so I feel like we
want to transition to that probably
after we do the particle system stuff
because before we start trying to work
on lighting I feel like lighting is
going to be something that wants to have
the correct artwork in there and I also
feel like yeah like it'll help with the
rest of the stuff ok so for collision
detection we definitely need to do that
I I don't know for animation I don't
think we actually need any more than
sort of what we have the moment I was
pretty happy with the hopping hero uh
and so pretty much that I think that's
mostly it we could clean up the way that
code works a little bit once we kind of
transition to the to the new artwork so
I might just go ahead and say here just
a real artwork i might say clean up our
notion of multi-part entities and how
they are animated as a part of that
transition because we probably don't
need to do much more than what we
already have but I feel like there was
some janky pneus in how those things
worked and we kind of introduced them in
an ad hoc fashion so maybe go through
there and just clean up a little bit so
it's a little bit more like how you
would do a normal traditional animation
system so we don't have to worry about
it too much so that's good multiple sim
regions per frame with the parental
clocking stuff that's that's harder
because I don't really know how we're
going to figure out where we do these
sim regions just to give you an example
of what that is
I so multiple sim regions the idea here
is there's a couple of different things
we can do in the game but what we
allowed is if you actually look at how
we wrote the code you can actually make
it so that you know the size of the
world might be massive so maybe like
this is like how big the starting area
is you know and maybe the game like
actually gets out like maybe that like
you can't even see how big a screen is
maybe the game actually ends up being
like so huge that it would take you like
you know 30 minutes to walk from here to
here if you just want a straight shot or
something so it's really large so one of
the things that I wanted to support in
the game and I don't really know exactly
what we would use this for but I kind of
think it might be nice is I think it
would be cool if there were some
autonomous agents doing things in the
world while you were elsewhere you know
so a very simple example will would be
lets say that maybe there's you know a
something random like there's a dragon
here and the dragon like flies from here
to here right that's just think it's
going to do and if you happen to be here
when it's passing by you'd see it fly
overhead right so in order to do stuff
like that we need a way of updating
parts of the world that you are not
involved in right that are not where you
are and so what I was thinking is we
could maybe keep a list of of active
entities so maybe like you know there's
a list of active entities
uh and you know we somehow update parts
of the world where those active entities
are you know so if there's an active
entity in a particular region we would
run a time step on that region as if it
were a player you know and so the only
problem with this that I foresee because
that's not very difficult to do right if
you think about what happens right now
we call that begin semaine same thing
well it'd be free for us to just call
that more than once and furthermore I
believe that thing is almost entirely
threadsafe it's really just the pull out
and the push out the pull out of the
world and push into the world thing
that's not thread-safe because once it
pulls it out its operates entirely
within its own structured set and it
doesn't ever talk to anybody or do
anything else it's or it's like kind of
all self-contained so it's actually
pretty easy for this for us to run this
across multiple cores as well we could
run for updates at once for example one
on each core and not have any problem
with that but what I don't know how to
do is deal with the part where they
coincide right so let me just show you
kind of the basic idea there so let's
say that I have you know here is the
dragon and here's the hero and here's
their update regions so here's what's
being simdi if the dragon is coming this
way and the kuro is coming that way
eventually their regions will overlap
right so eventually we'll get a case
that looks like this here's the heroes
region here's the Dragons region and
there's an area that's in common so what
will happen there is whoever packs out
first we'll grab this stuff into their
sim region and the other person just
simply won't get it and that's not
really going to work right that's going
to create all kinds of bugs for us
so what we would need to do in that case
is we would need to not update like the
Dragons region or something now that's
not that hard we can pre check to make
sure that regions don't intersect with
each other and if two regions do
intersect with what with each other we
could update only one of the other right
and that wouldn't be too bad in the case
of NPC regions but in the case of the
hero region we know we have to update
the hero region every frame so I don't
know what we do with the dragon region
at that point does the dragon just stop
moving until you actually scroll over
him it just seems kind of busted so I
really don't know what to do and we
can't call them sequentially because if
we call them sequentially then the
things in this region will update twice
right they'll get essentially two time
steps and we don't want them to have to
time steps now what I suggested kind of
over on the to-do list is the concept of
per entity clocking so the idea there is
that every entity has a clock in it and
when the update region passes over one
of those entities if that update clock
depending on how we record it can
somehow indicate that it's already been
updated this frame then it doesn't move
on this frame but it is still there in
terms of for collision purposes or
whatever uh I don't know if that would
work I really don't um
it would certainly cause problems with
the brain because what if you have some
that are that are that have you know you
can't partially update the region like
that so this is like a really concerning
thing for me I really don't know what to
do about it uh here's another thought
and it's basically saying well if we
have performance to spare which maybe we
will if we have performance to spare
there is so another thing that we could
do right and maybe this is the right
solution because because I can't think
of any other solution that actually
works maybe what we do is we just merge
the region's right so maybe if there's a
dragon in the hero what we do is we just
merge these two into a single sim region
because remember our sim regions don't
have to be rectangular we could pull
from two different rectangular regions
into the same sim region and create a
sort of other you know a non-rectangular
convex shape we can certainly do that
the only reason I'm worried about that
is that makes the cost of simulating
that sim region go up right and if you
got into a really bad scenario like
let's just just imagine the worst
possible case right the worst possible
case is this right like the hero is here
the dragon is here the basilisk is here
the Hydra is here right the manticore is
here right and I don't know this is Bob
right in that circumstance now we have
you know what is essentially you know
especially if this region is small so
the overlap is not much it's just enough
to cause them to merge but it's not very
much then however many of these we've
got that's like 6x the cost of
simulating that region right and so if
previously the way we were handling this
load was by you know not doing everyone
every frame or also
Oh using the multi threading well we
can't use different sim regions we can't
assign different sim regions to
different threads if they're all in one
region we could try to multi-thread our
region our single region update right
and then it wouldn't matter but assuming
that we're still trying to do it
regionally like that that's not going to
work and so we don't get them
multi-threading benefit and we don't get
the benefit of being able to time slice
these guys anymore because obviously the
whole region has to update it once so
that's what I'm really worried about
otherwise merge would definitely be the
way to go right and and i'm not sure
what to do about that because it seems
like anything that i might do like oh
okay well you know just pretend the
Dragons region is smaller in this case
well okay so it's pretend they overlap
more or whatever right so I feel like
what happens is when these things
converge we just end up in a situation
where we can no longer use any of the
tricks that I think we would be able to
use to keep everything running like
reasonably even if we throw like a lot
of these creatures at it you know even
if there was like three hundred of these
or something right three hundred actors
all doing stuff throughout the world
well that's really not that big of a
deal because first of all we could say
uh let's update everyone only like every
ten frames or something right so now you
just you only have 30 that need to
update on any given frame right that
right there made it much more manageable
now let's say we've got four cores right
you know ok now we essentially only have
eight updates right because each core
only has to do eight that chunks down
pretty nicely right it is start to
become it starts looking a lot more
manageable a lot more feasible once it
looks like that but I you know if they
all merge together all of a sudden it's
it's all three hundred and it's just I
think it would just be an epic as f food
epic disaster so that's the main problem
that's stopping us from doing that and I
don't really know
it's time for the QA so we can go to the
QA but i guess i would say that's that's
really i just don't have a good idea
really of of what the right way to
approach that problem is
j flea what are the reasons for separate
regions again the reason is because you
can't simulate a world with you know
millions of entities every frame because
it's just too much computation right so
what we want to do is just let most of
the world sleep and we only load them up
when we actually if it's actually
somewhat autonomous region or we think
there's something happening there right
and the other thing that we use the
region's for is to put everyone into a
single uniform space so that we can do
our computations there because we don't
actually have limitations on really how
big the world could be for the most part
in fact now I think we could almost get
rid of even the tile concept so they
could be like literally as large as you
want we could actually start doing some
crazy stuff with that if we wanted to
but anyway that's neither here nor there
the point is simply that we use those
sim regions to bring everything into a
single floating-point space where
there's plenty of precision
his Bob the guy in the tree yes let's
say yes related to jphayes question so i
was playing kingdom new lands recently
and it seemed like there was some really
bad frame rates that coincided with
battles involving hundreds vanities on
the opposite side of the world like
opposite to where the camera was I yeah
well yeah I mean one of the problems
with this sort of thing is just that
it's it's a it's an architectural issue
right it'sit's that's exactly what it is
it's I it's one of those things where we
don't have to solve it if we don't want
to because you know you can make a
perfectly reasonable 2d game that
doesn't care about any of this stuff but
I am trying to kind of show some more
advanced things that you might need to
consider architectural II and so like
you point out in other sorts of games
like Kingdom new lands or who knows what
I you could definitely get into
situations where you want this sort of
expansive world simulation thing going
on and if you don't have some way of
degrading that simulation when it is not
absolutely crucial that it's running at
30 frames a second or 60 frames a second
you're going to run into problems
because you know once you scale the
world to a certain size it's just going
to fall over so we're trying to sort of
have our architecture at its fundamental
level have certain ways of doing with
that are they necessarily the best way
to doing that I don't know we just
picked some that seemed reasonable and
which solve problems okay and we got
there you know and it seems like our
architecture at the moment actually does
a pretty good job of allowing us to
multi-thread and sort of time slice
updates to parts of our world if we
wanted to for almost for free and the
only place that it really breaks down is
the that part exactly where the regions
would merge together now what you sort
of said there were are starting out what
you said what what in so far s says have
you considered only merging with the
heroes region and deactivating one's
past that or having the region's aligned
to a grid
so that they don't overlap so I'm not
sure so considered merging with only
with the heroes region and deactivating
one's past that the problem is you can't
deactivate them because they still need
to update right is one of the problems I
need update eventually otherwise the
baskets would just stop moving right in
this case if all I did was allow like
these two these two merge well the
basileus and the manticore would now be
frozen in their tracks which doesn't
seem like a good solution it would
create some potential gameplay bugs
there right now we could do it if it's
the only thing we could think of then we
could do it right because hey creating a
gameplay bug sometimes you just have to
to make things work right you know
depending what your goals are so if
they're little gameplay bugs you know
okay it's alright and you know
speedrunners will take advantage of that
and hey that's great right if you've
ever watched the Super Mario 64 video
where they use essentially this exactly
that the deactivation regions to do kind
of crazy speed runs of things or half a
button press runs gameplay bugs are know
is that right gameplay both can be very
interesting so I'm not even saying that
we couldn't do something that I'm just
saying when I think through these
problems I try to come up with a
solution that actually works everywhere
if I can and if I can't will relax it
right so that's the reason I don't think
deactivation really works your other
suggestion of having them be aligned to
a grid so they don't overlap the problem
with that is I'm not exactly sure how to
do it right now we have this concept of
the active region and sort of the apron
and like I said we have this problem
where that apron would need to overlap
for these two regions right because even
if we ensure that they don't that the
active regions don't overlap which we
could do the aprons of them would still
overlap and there's no way to ensure the
ape razon overlap without basically
saying that the dragon like can't get
within a certain distance of the hero
right which is the opposite of what we
want so the aprons are the problem in
this case and even if they weren't i
think the active regions would be a
problem because the active region we
said was a room was one rooms worth 22
on all sides right and so if that's the
case if you're in this room
the dragon is in this room right then we
sort of have that problem of well we
kind of need to merge these you know
because they are they overlap so I don't
know maybe it's okay because hey in that
case you you could just say well the
dragon doesn't simulate the room below
and his region shrinks down to just one
room and then if you're more than one
room away you don't have this problem
but then again you still end up an exact
same problem I think maybe what we could
do is say that that there is no room
border on the other guys Sims you know
maybe there's no room border for the
other people
q Cohen terror Scout says could you have
smaller regions and load nine active at
a time so you always have every boundary
region loaded all the time I don't think
I understand what you're suggesting so I
am not prepared to say why we would or
wouldn't do that could you have smaller
regions and load nine active at a time
so you always have every boundary region
loaded all the time yeah I'm sorry I'm
not sure I understand
so yeah
but I guess here's the thing it does
seem possible that if we said that
updates were always grid aligned so
they're like room their room aligned and
if two regions would merge then those
regions the region that's not the heroes
region doesn't include that boundary
piece see I don't think that works
either because here's the thing so let's
say here is a room and i'm simulating
this room in order for me to walk out
this door I need to know that there's a
tile on the other side that I can hop on
to right so the at least part of this
room has to be loaded otherwise I can
never actually get there you know so I
think you're always going to have this
problem
cyber cyber punk hobo couldn't you just
make sure regions that get pulled in by
the apron don't have their own apron
activated I don't think that really
helps the problem though because the
problem is regions that are active right
the problem is when the active regions
the active apron the aprons of active
regions overlap or even when the active
regions themselves overlap but you know
the grid alignment would could
presumably help that problem but
assuming that we didn't you know then
it's like that that apron is going to
overlap and if the apron overlaps I
guess since it's not marked active at
that point that's okay you couldn't run
it multi-threaded you'd have to have a
different solution for the multi
threading
so here's the thing
I suppose
I suppose we could still do time slicing
and potentially get us out of this
problem so maybe what we could do is say
all right we will merge the heroes
region but we'll only merge it with one
of the neighbors so if two people
overlap we don't merge those and we
don't merge with another person who's on
the outside right we could do something
like that now we still have the we still
have the problem of the clocking because
people in this region right are then
going to get updated again on the next
frame by one of these guys when this is
dormant and so this will have updated
twice whereas people adhere and here
we'll only have updated once and I don't
really know what to do about that
uh and JP uh the actual problem when two
regions overlap is really just the
expense right instead of if you get
enough overlapping regions I think it's
just going to cost too much cpu to
simulate it right that's the only
problem if that weren't the problem then
I think you just always merge you know
you just always merge and maybe we just
let it slow down so like hey guess what
if you get into that situation sucks to
be you man sorry mr. player your flame
reframe rate tanked by a faster machine
right
because we could totally do that and
then the solution is just when things
are next to each other they do merge and
you merge till you have a single
connected region and you run that region
right mr. projection you could always
artificially keep the non-player agents
away from each other it's true I could
sort of have some sort of avoidance
there that that makes it unlikely for
this to happen and you know maybe that's
the best solution if there isn't a good
tech solution for it you know this Isaac
what do you think about a boolean flag
on each updateable thing flip it when
you update and alternate each frame
which value check for yeah that's what I
that's what per entity clocking was some
you know because you could imagine a
couple different schemes 11 way I was
thinking is just in the entity there's a
what was the last tick it was updated on
right so then when you come back around
to it you could say oh how you know
we're on tick 37 and it says the last
update was it had was tick 25 well I
know there's been that many tix in
between when I last updated this guy so
I can give him that much movement radius
or something right you know but I don't
know
james soon why does it not suffice to
use the total area of all overlapped
regions and just refused to exceed the
limit it does work it's just a you get
slower as that limit gets bigger and B
it has to have a limit and then you have
kind of bad behavior when you get enough
people together that you're outside the
limit right but again you know that
something like that is probably what we
will do because I don't know if there's
a clean solution to this I also don't
know if it's really that we're like it
just happened to be something we were
talking about right now so i thought i'd
read aya graham it just so people knew
what i was talking about it's not
something we really have to solve right
now either we can just sort of try it
out a little bit and see we don't really
know what we need out of this for
features its kind of with just a
speculative like hey it would be cool if
you could have things going on on the
map that we're happening in places you
weren't and but I just don't know how
feasible that is and maybe it's a stupid
idea we don't have to do this the game
does not require us to do this in any
way right it just seemed like something
that we were close to being able to do
cleanly so it was worth thinking about
doing because since we do have the sim
region stuff we can we can render little
pit peoples of the world without doing
I'm sorry update little peoples of the
world so you know anyway food for
thought something to think about I'm
going to go ahead and oops close this
down here
alright thank you everyone for joining
me for the episode of handmade here it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
the series at home you can always go to
hand me here org and pre-order the game
it comes with all the source code so you
can play around that at home and learn
from it and so on we also have a forum
site you can go to if you want to ask
questions about what's going on we also
have a patreon page go to thwart video
series a schedule bot which tells you
when we're going to be live if you want
to catch these episodes live and also an
episode guide you can go to if you would
like to catch up on past broadcast
that's about it for today I will be back
here for the last stream of the week
tomorrow same time same place until then
have fun programming and I will see you
guys on the internet take it easy
everyone