hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero the show we could a complete game
live on stream we yesterday came to a
sort of unfortunate realization about
how you know the game might function
graphically I had been hoping to
preserve a certain visual effect that I
liked and it requires quite a bit of
work to do so but we did that work but
unfortunately i don't really know of a
solution to one particular artifact that
it has it does seem a little bit like a
showstopper to me and so today i was
just going to talk about that a little
bit and verify that we can't really work
around it or not unless or come up with
some idea about how we are going to work
around it and yeah so that's where we're
at i'm just going to briefly demonstrate
what the problem is today is day 3 34 so
i am doing this demonstration with day
333 s code so if you want to follow
along at home that's the code to be
working with so yeah if i go ahead and
compile the current version of the code
base and then I you know boot it up you
can see when I run here uh that I've
kind of got a little bit of a stair step
pattern that i created here and much
like we said that we wanted to do before
i've made it so that now they're
completely orthographic so they don't do
any prospective transforms there right
but then what happens when I kind of go
up I still have this nice a sort of
upper floor kind of fade in effect that
I really kind of liked and I thought it
was nice but we then come to this sort
of unfortunate situation where what
happens now when the player wants to
transition up to this you know next
floor or whatever and so we just kind of
have this bad discontinuity where the
player will just kind of pop up there
and it doesn't look particularly good
right so I don't really know what the
solution to this problem is i I'm not
really sure
are some obvious issues with it and I
think they're worse than they would be
if only the hero could transition
between floors I would like to make it
so that other characters who wish to can
transition between floors for example
these little snake things or whatever
you know if they want to go down the
stairs I want to make sure that they are
able to go down the stairs as necessary
and and so on and so forth because as
you know over time at when we start to
build sort of the gameplay part of the
game you know I want to be able to have
characters but you know NPCs who are
sort of smarter the smarter NPCs let's
say who can kind of navigate around the
world a little more freely potentially
than just some of the stupid ones you
know maybe some of the stupid creatures
they just stay in one particular room
and don't really do much else but you
know some of the smarter and PCs would
want to be able to do you know that kind
of moving around sort of thing so I
guess what I would say here is I don't
really know how to solve this problem we
tried a couple things it seems to me
like there's a couple issues so I'm
gonna say what the prime that the most
severe what I think is that if you look
at what happens here it's really hard to
even tell where those stairs really even
are right because one of the nice things
about when they used to be in actual
perspective is that you could sort of
tell how they connected neatly to the
floor above them but now in the
circumstance that we see here you can
kind of see that like I don't really
even know where that floor is really
because it's in this like separate
coordinate system that doesn't sort of
work seamlessly compared to my other one
right so I really don't even know where
I am relative to it like if you look at
where it actually is it's roughly like I
don't know like on this level right it's
like here that's where it is right you
can see if I hop I'm hopping on this row
and that just doesn't look like
intuitive at all so we fundamentally
have this problem I think we're the
orthographic nature of how things are
displaced in that way just doesn't
actually work if you start to have a
real perspective transform on above
floors so not great uh I I don't I don't
love it uh so that's a big problem now I
guess what I don't know is if I were to
allow these things to scale you know
would that help enough right oh and I
don't know that that would help enough
either so there's a lot of stuff that I
just I don't know that I really don't
see a lot of potential here and so it
kind of is frustrating to me because I
like this effect and you know it we did
the work to make sure that it that it
would happen but I just don't see a lot
of ways that we can keep movement
between floors working if that's the way
if that's the situation I just don't see
it now I mean one thing that is true is
I suppose what we could do is say well
maybe you can't really transition
between floors in that way you know one
thing i could do is say all right so you
know maybe I don't really care about
stairwells anyway like who cares about
stairs I just need ways of getting from
one floor to another floor quickly and
maybe that works better I don't know it
certainly seems like something that
could be okay and in that case we would
have a situation where there'd be sort
of more of a like a like a you know
thing you jump on it bounces you up and
then another thing that you could jump
where you could jump down or something
like this right
so it'd kind of be more like a jumping
area uh and that seems reasonable
because then along only on that jump
would we do sort of the transition
between the two levels we could still
keep that sort of animated fade and fade
out you know uh and so you know in
theory I could see that being somewhat
useful I'm just not sure you know I
think that I think maybe that is is
perhaps the best way to go because
here's the thing let me just say say
something sort of game design even
though like I'm not a game designer and
I try to keep the game design talk to a
minimum I guess what I would say is I I
didn't really like the idea of the
stairwells in terms of the gameplay
implications that I felt that they had
either and the reason for that is simply
that what happens when you're standing
on the stairwell you know you're kind of
standing on this in-between point
between two screens and it's like oh you
know does it become this game about like
I want to try and get up on the
stairwell and sort of hit people from
the stairwell because then it's easier
for me to avoid people up here or you
know is the stairwell become some kind
of weird like place that you know
monsters get stuck in or whatever you
know like it's just kind of this weird
thing that that gameplay-wise I didn't
have any real reason for there to be a
stairwell it's just this thing that's
like well in the real world we have
stairs so you know there's stairs or
something right so I would say that I do
fancy the idea of saying okay maybe
there's no stairwells instead we just
have a thing that you hop on and when
you hop on it it teleports you kind of I
mean and you don't really teleport will
draw you animating to it but you don't
control your emotion between those two
you know I just hop on it and it's like
you know like a bounce pad it bounces me
up to a higher level or I can jump on
one at the higher level that has a
bounce pad down and it'll just bounce me
down right so they're kind of like
instant shoots sort of thing
and that's much nicer because then the
player is never spending any time
actually like hanging out in between two
levels because the gameplay doesn't
really support that like the gameplay it
doesn't really have any real concept of
what that would mean or why you would be
doing that or why it's interesting and
so just saying you're either in one room
or another in terms of gameplay is
actually what I would prefer anyway and
so maybe what I can do to say there are
there is no connective tissue between
two levels vertically there is only sort
of a connector pad that can go in either
direction and maybe the pads are
generally unidirectional so there's a
path that goes up but a path that goes
down if you can go both directions then
both pads exist but a lot of times you
can only go down or only go up for
example because that is another thing
that I want you know in keeping with the
concept of say being like Legend of
Zelda are binding of isaac or these
sorts of games which are kind of like i
said kind of the direction that we
wanted the game to sort of go in roughly
in terms of its structural components
for example binding of isaac only allows
you to go down right you you more or
less cannot return to a higher floor
once you have gone down to a lower floor
and there's a number of reasons why that
is a good mechanic to have and there's
certainly plenty of places in handmade
hero in terms of the design where I
wanted that to be true where you you can
only go downward and it's not really a
biting about the kind of thing in that
you can never get back up again but it
is the case that generally you're
supposed to proceed downwards in certain
segments and it will only be once you
kind of get to the bottom that you will
ever be able to return back to the top
again so in that way I think if this
makes a lot of sense so I think perhaps
the answer this problem is just to say
all right there just there isn't the
notion of a stairwell you know that's
not a thing there's just the notion of a
teleporter and pad or it's not really
teleporter i guess but just a little
convex
pad or whatever and that pad does that
that particular motion right that seems
pretty good and then I think everything
just works because the only problem
right now is the stairwell so all we
need to do is is when you're on that
sort of transition between the two we
would just have the whoever is moving
along the pad just do sort of whatever
it is whatever that linear interpolation
is between the floor zzzz and now would
do that so I'm relatively happy with
that you know I think that's fine I
think that's totally fine so maybe we'll
try that today maybe i'll see if i could
implement something like that just to
verify that that's okay because i think
that's really it for RZ i don't think i
have anything else i really want to do
with z because now we've pretty much got
everything that we want we've got the
you know alpha fading we've got we've
got sort of multiple floors stacked on
top of each other so we're pretty much
full easy capable now everything is very
smooth so I like everything other than
the effect of that stairwell and so let
me see maybe we'll just try and see what
happens if I try putting in some of
those pads as we spoke about and then
we'll kind of go from there so that that
that seems like a pretty good idea to me
and while you know while the entities
are hopping around if they hop on one of
those pads it'll spring them up to the
next level or if we hop on down pat it
will spring them down to another level
right and the way that I could do that
is just we have that notion of those
sort of traversable s'right I could just
tag one of those one of the operations
that are traversable could have on it is
that it could you know basically be a
teleport to another traversable so that
when you hop on it you sort of
automatically end up going on this this
traversable all right so let's try that
uh we don't have a lot of time left
because I've been blabbering blabbering
and whatever you want to call that and
I'm out of tea and that's no good at all
so who knows how far we'll get but let's
give it a shot okay so first things
first imma pull the concept of the apron
stuff out of here because I don't
actually want it now we had this next
floor z piece of information I'm going
to get rid of it I don't want it it
needs to go away so there it goes and
now it's gone I'm going to go back here
and take a look at this situation and
say that it's going to be going to and
so I think all we're gonna do is just
pass that floor Z and be done with it
that's all that's all there is okay so
that's nothing you know we're still
exactly the same no no change their
basic exactly what it was before so then
I'm going to go and I'm going to take a
look at those traversable and I'm going
to take a look at what we have as far as
traversable here so we have these entity
traversable point things and you can see
that we've got like a v3 P and we've got
an empty that's an occupier right so on
one of these traversable points if
someone lands on it then now we sort of
have this idea that something might
happen here right and so you can imagine
if this was sort of a teleporter or some
you know if this was one of those sort
of teleporter things then what we want
to do is have a way of this thing to
sort of say hey there's another
traversable that you're kind of kind of
go to if you're you know if you're one
of these things right and so there's
something in here that's going to be you
know like let's say that we've got
another traversal reference and that
reversible reference is you know
propel I don't I'm uncomfortable using
the word teleport because I feel like
teleport means that I'd like
instantaneously move you to something
like there wouldn't be an animation
between the two but in this case I'm not
really talking about that I'm talking
about moving you smoothly between the
two so it's not really teleport it's
more like a you know boost to it's like
I'm going to give you a sort of a boost
to it I'm going to argue over to it I
don't know exactly what the right word
for that is I'm guess I'm going to say
like Auto booster to because I have no
other idea what it should be called so
I'm just going to call it that for now
so that auto booth to is going to be the
thing that you're going to go to when
you land on one of these guys and so I
just going to sort of start by making
that be something that we set so inside
a handmade world mode when we add a
standard room here we've got sort of
this this notion that at the end of it
you know we sort of had these stairs and
that sort of stuff I'm going to sort of
nuke that temporarily so i'm going to
say let's let's say that we don't have
any of that sort of stuff and we're
going to need is some way of sort of
having these these like pads make make a
little bit more sense we're going to
have to have some way that they could be
sort of placed in an intelligent fashion
so what I'm going to do is I'm going to
say that when we when we do ad stated
room I'm going to say that there's maybe
like the notion of like a where the hole
is you know is the hole on the left side
or is the hole on the right side so that
different rooms can have holes where you
can go down a hole and there isn't the
whole isn't always in the same place
right so I'm going to have like a you
know left hole right hole or something
like that and so then if we try to come
down here what i could do is say like
okay I we've got hold down to the floor
below and so this thing would
say like okay if you wanted a left hole
and you're in the left whole area then
there's a hole down to the floor below
otherwise if you come through in here
then you sort of have a thing that's
like well we don't want the stairs
nonsense so we're going to kind of pick
put this and we're going to move it down
here and say get rid of all of that and
say okay if we're in sort of the place
where we would have had that this other
hole as well then we're going to go
ahead and take hidden that little
cleaner that area that used to have the
whole and use that directly I don't know
what we don't care about this anymore so
I feel like I'm just going to do that as
well and so now when we add a standard
room what we could do is I believe these
things are always kind of stacked on top
of each other right now so let's just
say that they stack multiple times and
then what I'm going to do is say okay
when I add the standard room I'm going
to say if the screen index you know mod
2 gets a left hole and if the screen
index and I guess I could say left full
equal screen index mod 2 and right hole
equals not left hole so basically every
other one it'll alternate like left
right left right left right left right
I'm saying so in theory well I guess in
theory what we actually have is some
kind of a
a problem with the fact that I added
oh I accidentally placed someone on
something that doesn't exist it looks
like well why did I do that let me take
a look here I probably inverted when I
did the ads gender we should probably we
gotta hurry up and get to world
generation stuff so I can stop slumming
it with these weird kind of crazy tools
yeah so I had this backwards so this is
if we want the whole right that's if we
want the whole so we're we're doing this
this is what we actually wanted to do
you go so let's go ahead and run and so
here is like that whole and I can't
unfortunately I'm unable to Oh does that
still work it did yeah it doesn't I'm
think so I was going to say we used to
have a thing where we could add heroes
by pressing the spacebar and I was like
I didn't think that's the work done it
doesn't anyway what I was going to say
is yes so we've got these these holes it
and so now what I want to do is I want
to add those little pads so that they
can kind of do the you know the hopping
back and forth so what I'm going to do
is when i add a standard room i'm going
to take the standard rooms and make sure
that i remember the previous standard
room so i can just connect them right
pretty basic so into a standard room you
know a pre room or something like this
and actually i guess uh I guess I can
just do that down here
so now I'll know what the previous room
was and so I should be able to connect
these up right you can kind of see us
going through here and adding things
like trees and whatever and we do those
sorts of things by using the indexes
like you can see here we can we can use
the dot ground part of things to figure
out like what the traversable references
that we're talking about in any
particular circumstance here right so if
I have a particular traversable
reference that I want to be able to
modify in that way I need to be able to
say that that thing whatever it is I
need to be able to tag whatever that
thing is by saying that it sort of has
this back pointer right and I think part
of the this is this is kind of a little
bit of a this is kind of a little bit of
a problem for us because we don't really
have any of the Royal gem stuff in here
we don't really have a good way of
actually connecting these things up the
reason for that is because it's already
kind of impact it you know into it's
already been sort of packed down into
its permanent storage form and we don't
really have a way of reaching back in
there to sort of take it back out right
so we kind of have the situation where
we want to sort of leave you know you
can let me let me explain it a little
more detail what I'm talking about here
and maybe this is circumstance where we
have to start building some actual world
building tools first before we can
really test this out in any particular
way but I feel that can hack it without
too much trouble either way anyway so
what happens here like let's take a look
at what happens when we do add standard
room right so what happens when we do
add standard room is we go ahead and we
create these entities right so for
example will create begin ground entity
and has a traversable like so but when
we call end entity that entity is now
act and it will be packed into the grid
at that location right what that means
is that we can no longer edit that into
edit e without unpacking it again right
because again we store everything kind
of impact format and so we're not really
able to edit it once we finish packing
it down what that means is once we've
added a standard room we're really not
able to change any of the elements or
those entities again without opening the
backup which we don't really want to do
right so kind of what we need here is we
we more need the ability to create these
entities open do a bunch of operations
on them and then pack them down once
we're no longer needing to talk about
that room anymore right so we kind of
need the concept of an editable room
it's it's basically just the sim region
right but without any of the sim part of
it and without the apron it's just like
a little room with all the entities
stored and it's still open and then we
just end them all right they go end end
end end end end end so that is the
problem that I'm talking about and
that's the thing that we would need to
be able to do because otherwise I can't
really set that teleport yet so I feel
like that is definitely a situation
where you know the world gen stuff kind
of again wants to be up there but I
guess what I could do for now is just
say well all right let's just only make
forward like things that go forward
because or backward or whatever right
that like we could we can do one
direction pretty easily without having
to actually start having a World tools
that we would need right and so the way
that I would do that is i'll just say
like okay well and you know when i
probably could even do i could probably
even do it by just making the standard
room be something that can be kept open
a little bit longer now that i think
about it because we don't have to really
call and entity I don't really remember
exactly how this works but begin entity
yes so creation buffer intact index
there's this world mode creation buffer
concept right and that means you can
create up to four out of these we could
just make that be you know a very large
number right that number could be 512 or
something and then you could create all
the entities for a room at leave them
open create all the LEDs for the next
room link them up and then close the
previous set of entries right that would
be relatively straightforward to do and
we could do something like that but
again it seems kind of janky and really
like i said the solution there is it's
not a very good solution the better
solution is to just sort of have the
ability to open up regions edit them and
and then close them as necessary i right
so it it's not particularly compelling
unfortunately either but yet so I don't
know yeah so when we create a new room
in this case we could just choose to put
the hero not on the zero with floor I
believe right now what happens is we put
the hero on the zeroth floor but I'm
going to take a look here so we do for
camera P so it's really just the camera
that determines this when we create the
world we just use whatever whatever is
closest to the camera and in this case
the camera P is just using sort of
whatever the screen base Z is so we
could just put the hero up at the top
right let me see your screen base Z we
yeah and abs tiles II as it comes out of
here would just be one off of where it
should be so we could just use whatever
the last you know kind of used one of
these was and in fact I could save that
specifically so i could say that we'll
just put you on the final screen and
that would presumably solve the problem
so if we want to do you know less screen
x last screen why why are these you 30
tues by the way shouldn't they be s 32 s
does anyone know why that is that's a
bit weird
feel like you should be s 30 tues
so since I can't use the message that
I'm going to because I think those
should be yesterday too since they kind
of go in either direction anyway so I'm
going to say last remix last screen why
and last screen z I'm just going to go
ahead and take these and say before we
do any of the updates here we'll just
kind of set these or actually I guess
we'll just set them right here right so
we'll just say like hey the last one we
created here's what it is and so then if
we want to we can make the camera up
here at the top the final one instead so
I'll just say you know less three necks
oops last screen why last screen z and
that should be AB Stiles e
yeah and so now as you can kind of see
we're starting off like on top right and
you know we we can't actually get down
there but you can kind of see that there
is something down there and so the goal
would just be to make it so that we can
kind of like hop on this thing and have
that sort of make us jump down to the
tile that would be directly below us
there right yeah and that's all I really
want to do okay so that'll be fine so if
we do that and yet all i need to do to
sort of make to make those things
connect now is just say like okay
whenever i go up a level I'll just keep
the last room which is this guy here
i'll just keep the last room and i'll
connect something at the top of at the
room above it i'll connect one of the
traversals to the one below it right and
so in order to do that I really just
need to set for one of these when we do
the ad standard room before it closes I
need to set one of those sort of
traversable targets so in the case where
I have a left hole right I'm trying to
do something that looks like this
I've got and I guess I should draw this
a little bit more conservatively here so
in case where I have a hole on the left
then underneath I won't have a hole
underneath it right and the case where I
have a hole on the right same thing
underneath it I won't have one here
they'll be one here because they're
alternating so what I want to do is say
when I build this floor if it's got a
hole on the left then what it needs to
have is a teleporter here that goes down
to their right and if I'm talking about
one that has a hole on the right then I
need to build a little teleporter here
that comes down there right so pretty
straightforward so if I see a left hole
then I need to take whatever the this
pre room thing is here I need to take
that guy and take whatever the ground
thing is and pass you know some
particular thing I guess in this case
what i will do is wear a standard room
all to say ok there's a traversable
reference and this is the target ref or
whatever that thing if there's a left
hole
or if there's a right hole will get set
differently if there's a left hole the
target riff should be yeah you know I
don't know like let's see the left hole
is like negative 5 negative 3 so it
should probably be like- you know that
the thing would be at a probably
negative 2 so we'd be hopping down to
negative 1 right I'm sorry to negative 3
and this is accessed XY yes yes and so
the Y values your one let's say it's
zero right so you know that's what the
target riff might be for that for a
right hole we've got three you know the
offset X is 3 so we kind of know that
it's definitely hopping down to three
and then we it's between negative 2 and
2 so let's just say the other one was at
the top let's say this one's at the top
so we'll say it's negative 2 as well
right and so in this case those are what
they are but of course we we have to
offset them in this this is kind of
annoying right but you can kind of see
we've got to offset them this is why we
need some actual world building tools
here because this is a mess right you
can see how this is totally
unsustainable like we're not going to
want to do this when we're actually
trying to create the real game world is
just it you know everything here needs
to be made into nice utilities that just
work okay so in this sense we can just
do those guys not really anything
particular go around there what I would
like to do is say in the case where we
have the first screen there's nothing
below the first one so I'm going to say
that there's no left hole and no right
hole on the bottom most guy that makes
sense
and and that'll be that so now if I go
back to my ad standard room to make this
sort of makeshift crappy test case we're
going to pass the target ref here and in
the case where we know that we have a
left hole I'm going to say that this
entity you know when you're standing
optical entity that I create if you're
standing on the the particular entity
that I need you to be standing on for a
left hole or right hole or whatever then
the boosts you know the the auto boost
target or whatever is going to be equal
to that target ref so like I just need
to say you know if you're at a left hole
and your offset x equals this and your
offset y equals this or you're right
hole and your offset x equals whatever
it equals and your offset y equals
whatever it equals you know I'm saying
then you're all good right so you have
left tool XY right volt XY these X wise
are whatever they were so in the case of
the left hole then like I said it's
going to be like one off of where it was
going to be like negative 2 is where the
teleporter is and the y is 0 and what
did I say it was going to be here y is
negative 2 and the X is what for I
believe yeah so that's where the club or
I guess maybe it should be on the other
side of it probably I guess it probably
should be too because you're going the
other direction i guess i don't know it
doesn't really matter but you get the
idea uh so yeah in either of those cases
then we're going to set the auto boost
to target and I think that's create the
linkage again only in one direction now
at the moment unfortunately we don't
actually have any way
to see these can these that these things
are set so what I'd like to do is just
quickly add of something fairly simple
just a really basic thing to show that
we actually set them at all so inside
the entity stuff when we're rendering
the traversable what I'm going to do is
I'm just going to add a little bit of
color there just so I can see what's
going on like that they got set at all
before I bother trying to actually wire
them up to anything because you know
like I said we have no world building
tool so it's a little bit presumptuous
and finicky so I'm going to say that
we've got a color value here we've got a
color value based on whether you've got
an occupier right like so and I just
want to make this now into something
that's a little more complicated to how
you set the color so the first thing I'm
going to do is say well let's just go
back to saying that there's a default
color this is Lex let's say the default
color that we're going to render these
reversals as and then I'm going to do an
if statement here where say like if you
have an occupier then you will set the
color to this other color right and
furthermore so here I can also say well
whatever this entity is if the auto
boost to is valid I don't know how to
test for that because I don't remember
anymore at all let's see here
traversable reference there we go so
traversable reference I don't know how
to check to see if one of those is
actually doing anything you know what I
want to do is basically say like gifts
is this a valid thing and maybe all i
have to do for that is just say whether
or not the traversable reference whether
the pointer is nominal or not that might
be sufficient because the pointer would
be null in a case where oops where it
wasn't that's anything but basically
what i want to do is something like that
if it's a valid thing that we've set i'm
going to make it like some kind of
hideous pink just so i can see that it
actually is is there right so yeah so
so I don't like I said I don't know we
don't seem to have one of those I'll
take a quick look in here to make sure
so here's a get reversible right and
that returns a pointer so you know maybe
in a it's it's just the right thing to
do to say like get traversable and see
if it returns non-null and so that seems
pretty reasonable of a way to do it so
you can see I'm not actually getting
think you're so now I'm a little bit
nervous like did those things not get
set for some reason I'm not sure I have
no idea I don't really know what's going
on right so that's what I exactly what I
wanted to know so let's take a look and
see whether or not those things are ever
being set or what's going on there okay
so yeah inside handmade world also I'm a
little bit interested to know what it
where our performance goes I'm assuming
that it's all still going to the just a
path that simple path on it yeah get
closest reversible so I just want to
make sure that that's still what was
causing us to be slow since it's very
accelerated OpenGL render commands also
seems to have quite a bit of work to do
nice it's okay anyway that's the
unoptimized build we're still probably
60 frames a second no problem when the
the optimized one so it's not really a
big deal anyway but and just like to
make sure that nothing pops up there
okay so I want to see what this is
getting set to like if it's never
getting set to anything or what's going
on there or you know or am I thinking
about this problem wrong so I just
wanted when we actually create the world
I just want to go through and watch to
see whether its ever being said at all
just to give myself a little bit of a
bearing on the situation so first off
let's see if that code ever gets called
at all okay and it does so that's good
it gets in this case it's getting set to
an index but no Envy pointer which would
not be helpful so in in that case that
seems problematic to me because we
should have had two things there should
two of those things should have been set
I would think let me take a look at that
to make sure
oh no that's okay so having the index be
set something should be sufficient so
that does seem okay so that entity auto
boost to is there so that all seems good
so I think you know now I think about
the only problem is we didn't add any
unpack code to it so that's probably all
we really need to do to fix it actually
now that I think about it yeah because
when these things going to impact here
we kind of come through it and we do we
do pack traversal reference so we have
to make sure that we're actually do
those packings like with occupying and
came from we need to do auto boost to as
well and the same would be true on the
other side of things right load
traversable reference for example also
has to be loaded so let's take a look at
that that may have been the only problem
but there could be yeah so there we go
Oh looks like I was backwards a little
bit there but ok so that's set now and
so what I want to do is make it so that
I hop on that that one's not set to the
value that I actually wanted so that's a
little bit of mistake let me go ahead
and fix that and we only have about two
minutes left so I probably won't try to
do the animation stuff yet although i
don't know maybe I will maybe ammo but
yeah so in here what I want to do is say
like okay my why I was thinking that the
higher why the was the negative 1
because I always think of why is going
down I can't ever seem to shake it but
it's not it's going up so that's
actually supposed to be a 2 there and
the same is true of this guy was was set
to the wrong values they were the low
value so I wanted them to be the high
values so I'm just going to go through
and undo that that mistake so yeah
instead of negative 2 it's 2 instead of
10 it's one and so now they should be at
the top
the things that's just that's just where
I mentally picture them it doesn't
really matter for anything but I just
that's what i wanted so i'm going to fix
it alright so now those should all be
set properly and so tomorrow we should
be able to just make it so that we when
we hop on one big boost the star to the
next one and that should be about it so
i'm going to go ahead and go to the Q&amp;A
now because i don't want to start that
yet since i won't have time to finish it
even though it is relatively simple
in the meantime I want to take a look at
the Headroom here
yes that's so basically like when we
compile in in optimized mode we are
basically entirely in the graphics which
is good that's what we want to see
certainly so
about my first question will i be able
to view it again because i was really
interested about your answer you can use
the twitch archive which keeps it for
about two weeks so you can view it via
twitch i think for two weeks and then it
disappears
are using entity component system
architecture or different different we
are using a very experimental
architecture which we haven't really
determined whether it's good or bad yet
because we haven't really gotten to the
point where we actually need to do the
part that matters when we actually get
further down the game implementation
part of the game rather than the engine
part will know but there's several
streams on this so I would encourage you
to go back and watch those if you're
interested in the approach that I
decided to take for ND systems it is not
an entity component system
although it's worth mentioning it's
definitely closer to an entity component
system than it would be to say a C++
inheritance hierarchy based nnd system
or something like that so in terms of
like things that are similar to it it's
it's closer to that that it would be to
certain other kinds
if you come for the story for the game
yet uh yeah we don't really deal with
story and design stuff on the stream so
this is just for programming I recall
when you were writing the head body
behavior code you want to ensure the
player always had control over the head
is this auto hopping going to interfere
with that uh no I don't think so because
he already does autohop right so the
body always goes on a hop right so
you're only actually able to control the
head to a certain extent like you can
move the head I freely but it has to
stay within range of the body and the
body always does hop from one position
to another so this is fully in keeping
with that and it would feel it's exactly
what I would want to have happen right
it's that the body once you commit the
body has to go where it's going to go
and the head has to go with it to a
certain extent it can you know lag by
however much we allow it to lag
can the player fall in the hole versus
jumping on purpose I don't believe so
there's no real reason why I would allow
that I don't think in the game that I
can think of in theory these could these
jump pads be on the same level and use
like jump pads in Portal 2 so I I really
don't need them for anything other than
just getting up and down between floors
so I wouldn't necessarily say that I
wouldn't necessarily say that there's
any reason why we couldn't experiment
with them if we felt like that was
important later on if it looked look
like there was something cool to do
there but i would say i don't anticipate
needing that for any pic eula reason but
torgue door will multi-part entities
like the snake be able to go through
holes I think so I don't see any reason
why they wouldn't be able to because as
long as the snake just always follows
the same rule which is that each segment
follows the previous segment once one of
those segments jumps onto the pad it
will jump the next jump will be down and
then the next segment we'll jump onto
the pad and they'll all just kind of
jump down so you know I soom that that
will be the way that goes and the same
will be true of like the floating heads
right now the heads are allowed to float
like directly to their target which we
don't want to do there they we haven't
actually written that code yet like the
familiars would not be able to go like
directly through the floor normally but
they currently can but so we would force
them to also use the pads probably
what are your thoughts on voxel
rendering and or ray tracing do you mean
to ask what are my thoughts on voxel
rendering and/or voxel ray tracing or
what are your thoughts on voxel
rendering and or ray tracing unrelated
like just retracing in general and I
guess what I would say is I like some
aspects of voxel rendering there are
obviously some attractive elements to it
my problem is just the heart that you
often want surfaces to be kind of
defined cleanly and it's very hard to do
that with voxels a lot of the time so
you kind of end up having to do these
sort of hacky things where you create
ways of like carving the voxel elements
into surface elements and stuff like
this and and I just don't feel like you
know I don't follow the literature on
that I haven't followed the literature
on that very closely lately so they may
have gotten further towards making that
clean and you know not super hacky like
it was but I never really saw back in
the last time I looked at that five
years ago let's say I never really saw
anyone who really like presented a clean
way that that was going to really work
for real right which is not to say that
it won't I just had seen the real sort
of clear way that that works if that
makes sense uh so you know that's what
I'd say about fox surrendering it's got
some really nice advantages I just don't
know how you get back if the surface
part of its going to work out you know
in a maybe the answer is just that like
hey eventually we have computers that
are so powerful that the resolution of
the voxels is so tiny that they're less
than a pixel large always in which case
then you don't care about the surface
element of it but you know we're not
there yet so it's hard to say will we
get there when will we get there if we
get there I don't know
as far as ray tracing I love ray tracing
ray tracing is is my favorite the
problem is just nobody really knows how
to do it efficiently enough yet right
even the most advanced ray tracing
engines right now just are not capable
of running a real game you know if you
if you take a look at the brigade engine
let's say which i think is the furthest
along actual sort of game engine I've
seen it just can't hold a candle to
something like you know the current doom
render or something in terms of the
visual quality that it actually produces
with animating objects and all these
other sorts of things so you know it's
got some obvious strengths you know it
does perfect reflections well and it
does things like you know global
illumination really cleanly and stuff
like that but it just can't get it
doesn't seem to be able to get to the
point where it sufficient enough to have
like big moving scenes with lots of
stuff in it and actually produce enough
noise free samples to really work you
know but you know who knows again I
think it's like anything else we really
just don't know what the future holds
because we don't really know what kind
of horsepower we will top out at so we
don't really know what what I think the
final render or quote unquote will look
like dr. s80 regarding head body the
player controls the head out of the jump
pad but then the game needs to animate
both the head and the body down right I
thought so far the head was always
sponsored two player input not tight
animation the body just followed no so
the the head right at the moment the
head is is kind of not correct you can
move the head where you would not
normally be able to move the head so for
example right now I can do that that's
totally not actually allowed in the game
what would actually happen is the head
would stop like right there right and so
you know it should be more like this
right so no the player basically the
the head is tied to the body and the
player can move the head around but when
the body is somewhere the head asked to
stay within one-half displacement so if
you hop on the pad you will get moved
down with the body and that is the way
it it is designed to work everywhere
this is the same if you were on a moving
platform same deal it will move the head
along with the body once the body is you
know is pulling the head away kind of
thing opinion on Vulcan other than it
being really hard I don't really think
of it as being really hard I think it is
being unnecessarily complicated and not
particularly mapping well to the problem
you know I think of it as basically like
not a very poorly designed API that
attempts to give you access to roughly
what the union of current hardware or
rather should say the intersection of
what current hardware is capable of
which I just don't I don't like that
goal I think that was a bad design
decision given the situation of the
graphics industry at the moment so I
guess what I'd say is philosophically I
disagree with Vulcan I don't like the
approach that was taken and I think it's
problematic but you know it is what it
is now so you know we'll probably end up
having to use it because if that's what
hardware vendors decide to support then
you don't really have a choice you know
you're this is the the real problem with
the graphics industry these days is you
know they don't give you a chip to
program they give you an API to program
and if they do a really bad job
designing that API then you're just
stuck with it so
how are holes and teleport pads going to
help us find the variable well because
in order to find the variable you must
search everywhere in the world and if
the only way you can get up and downs
with these pads but then obviously
you're going to need to use them so
any tips for someone interested in game
engines considering getting into the
chemistry not really other than what
other than what I say on the stream you
know
and also yes this year's handmade cod
will have a job fair which we will be
announcing more about soon do you have a
set streaming schedule well you know
since the stream has ended it's actually
the perfect time to mention that I
suppose so we'll just go right into that
let's go ahead and do that thank you
everyone for joining me for a handmade
hero it's been a pleasure coding with
you as always if you would like to
follow along at home you can always peer
to the game on handmade here org and it
comes with the source code so you can
play around with it we have a forum site
if you want to ask questions we have a
patreon page you want to support our
video series we have a schedule bot if
you would like to know what our schedule
is so you can catch the stream live and
we have an episode guide that let you
catch up with old editions of the show
since we just got to ask that question
do we have set screaming schedule yes
you can always find out what the set
streaming schedule is by looking at the
tweet bot and you can see here that at
the beginning of the week will give you
the entire schedule for that week and
then it will tell you every day what
that day's schedule is going to be as
well if you're just curious about that
so definitely you can follow that bot or
just come to this page and and check it
out if you need to know also typically
on this page if you refresh this page
when there is not a show live so for
example this this episode just
technically ended this little countdown
timer will count down to the next time
it's live if the schedule has been
posted so that's about it thank you
everyone for joining me I will be back
here tomorrow for the last few min the
week I'm off the end of the week but
then we'll be back here again the
following week so just a brief break
that's about it so i'll hopefully see
you guys tomorrow until then have fun
programming and i will see you on the
Internet take it easy everyone