hello everyone and thank you for joining
me for handmade hero today we are going
to be doing lighting and we pretty much
got lighting working last weekend's in
our sort of test way that we wanted to
make it work and so this weekend really
what we're doing is we're trying to push
the lighting quality forward right like
we've basically got like a rudimentary
version of it working in a little CPU
testbed eventually we will port it to
the GPU to run on there directly but
right now we're using the CPU and the
reason we're using the CPU is because we
can visualize them to plug it a lot
easier on there than we can if it's
running on the GPU so even though we
could have implemented this on the GPU
it's just much nicer and just a lot more
pleasant to to work on the CPU it's sad
that we're still in that situation but
that's just kind of the way it is GPUs
being highly non-standard as it is and
also often not having proper debugging
capabilities built into them which is
another aspect of it but so if you take
a look at the game as it is running at
the moment one of the things you can
note here I'll go ahead and and turn
loops not that's not good we don't look
at the profile if I turn on the lighting
to show reflectors and we can look at
different aspects of the lighting
solution here you can see that if I if I
just look at the reflectors you can kind
of see if I move the the light around
you can see that we have light
propagating kind of around the scene and
there are some weird flickering sorts of
stuff that happen and we're not super
sure if those could just be bugs in
there like that right there they they
could be actual bugs that we're kind of
kind of go start looking for now as we
try to solidify things and get a good
quality solution they could also not be
technically buzz they could be what are
effectively bugs but aren't really
we bug and what I mean by that is with
something like lighting transport
especially when you're simulating
multiple bounces you know we've been
really sloppy so far we're just kind of
hacking some stuff in there in terms of
the lighting transport equations it's
easy to get into a situation where you
could make a solution that can bounce
more light than it receives right and if
you create a solution that can bounce
more life than it receives then what you
create is a sort of an infinite feedback
loop right so the number of times that
you iterate the lighting you can
actually just get brighter and brighter
and brighter right so that's another
thing we haven't done yet is like ensure
that we conserve lighting when it's
bounced around in fact I'm pretty sure
we aren't doing it right now so things
like that where things get infinitely
bright could be straight up bugs meaning
like somebody typed well somebody would
be me but there is a you know typo or an
incorrect part of the algorithm so it's
actually just not functioning properly
that can be one thing but it can also be
the case that you may have types in the
algorithm properly and it's doing what
you expect them to do the problem is
just the algorithm is not conservative
and then therefore you can end up with
feedback loops like that just if the
game happens to get into the right state
with the geometry then there you go
right but either way you can sort of see
like I said that lighting is sort of
working here so we're in the position to
start focusing on whether we're doing it
well and whether the quality is there
and so on now if I turn to show
visibility you can also see the
computation occurring here for ambient
occlusion which is a part of the
lighting computation this is just
viewing just that part of it tuning and
this is an important thing to understand
this algorithm that we sort of started
off using which probably isn't the one
that we'll use in the end now that we've
got things set up and working we
probably can fuss around with a little
more but I now that we've got this
working you can sort of see that it
doesn't really do a very good job of
doing any sort of shadowing that we
might really care about right
so what you can sort of see here is you
know the ambient occlusion may take out
a little bit of what you don't want to
see in terms of light propagating the
places that shouldn't propagate just
based on like the fact that these things
are in like a corner or something like
that and that is nice that does add one
of the main things that we do want to
the image so it is good that we have
that there's no question about that but
it's worth noting that that ambient
occlusion while nice and well it is
important to the look and can be used
for that you can see right there you see
that weird flashiness
yeah it mentions your that it's family
it's it's also not really going to do
some of the stuff that we need to do
with shadowing and it's the only
shadowing that we have in there right
now
so we can forego better shadowing but
it's worth noting what it does and
doesn't do and so right now one of the
things that the shadowing does not do is
if you look at how the game is currently
lighting this area back here well you
know that should be pretty dark because
if you turn off the reflectors you can
kind of see that there's just these big
balls in the way and if I go back here
you can see that this area is really
just pretty much fine in terms of
brightness right there just isn't a lot
of darkening happening back there and
while it's okay to leave it that way
like you know the it's certainly not a
problem to have that be the case because
as we turn to smooth out the lighting
solution you know it could be that the
look of a game is just fine that way
either way but the real issue there is
just that you know if we want a solution
that does a little bit better at
preventing life from bleeding around
edges that's not going to do it for us
right that's not going to that's not
going to take care of it especially
because you know as I kind of come
behind here you can sort of see that you
know this this is getting lit all almost
you know not quite because it's getting
Arkan by these by default but it's
getting lit almost as if this wall were
not here and that doesn't really make
much sense so and again that's because
we're not really doing any work right
now to detect the real we're not really
doing much to say if a light source is
on one side of an occluder it can't
propagate light to the other side of
occluder right we're kind of just doing
ambient occlusion which isn't really the
same thing in that case right so yes so
it's a little bit confusing and it's
certainly like I said something that we
kind of have to think about how much we
want to do in terms of accuracy and how
much we don't you know really
necessarily care about it or just want
to go with something that's going to
produce a pleasant look or whatever but
the first thing first so first things
first we want to kind of work on our
letting solution a little bit here to
try and get to something a little bit
more stable and one of the things you
can see if we just show the disability
is that for the most part the flashing
the super bright flashing doesn't really
happen here so you know as far as we can
tell from looking at the two parts of
the lighting solution there are some
oddities so for example you can see like
right in here how things darken kind of
dramatically in a way that doesn't
necessarily make a whole lot of sense in
terms of visibility because it's like
okay if I'm just moving between here and
here you can kind of see that there must
be some kind of bug or bad feedback it
could just be bad feedback but you can
see how these darkened considerably more
just right along here which doesn't seem
to make a whole lot of sense again it
could be because the ambient occlusion
algorithm is pretty ghetto it's
basically like just doing
new passes of propagating or might be
through at this point of propagating the
shadow information of how much each
occluder shadows every other occluder so
you know hard to say about that
but with that in mind it's just well ok
so you know given this circumstance does
that really make it does that really
seem logical enough and again like I
said I don't know if it does but either
way if we take a look at the difference
between how much effect that's having
and how much effect we're actually
getting when we see these super bright
flashes it just doesn't seem like the
super bright flashes are coming from the
ambient occlusion path now what we can
do as well presumably anyway let's just
verify that so if I come along here and
I move along and we try let me try to
find a place where I can see those super
bright flashes some reason I'm not
getting the super bright ones we were
getting really bright ones before there
we go so you can kind of see that super
bright flash happening there for example
if we go and disable the part oh I guess
I didn't yeah I don't know why felt
compelled to restart we have the live
code reloading controlling CPU side so
that's pretty easy but if I come through
and I take the lighting part that was
just computing the ambient occlusion
which you know here is the part that
sets up the lighting should have
commented this here's the ambient
occlusion part if I was to take the
ambient occlusion part and just get rid
of it entirely so that the visibility is
always set to one right and so here is
the you know visibility oh it's set to
one if the visibility so we set to one
then in theory I should be able to see
whether I still get the sort of the
lighting issue there so if I if I go to
the show reflectors right here's the
visibility so the visible
is now not not changing in any way and
so if I assume that the visibility is
taken out of the equation entirely
device till and you can see I still get
those bright flashes so we know that the
ambient occlusion is not where the
problem lies in terms of the like sort
of slickery weirdness and so what I'd
like to do is just take a second to see
what's going on there because that does
seem a little bit iffy so another thing
is just to take a look at what degree
this has to do with feedback the thing I
can do is I can sort of simplify this
down by saying let's just temporarily
disable any iteration on the lighting as
well and so then oh and you know what I
should also just put us into the mode
permanently in fact that you know what I
could do it in just you to config to
this so if I want to in here what I
could do is say well alright let's look
at the reflectors let's not look at the
visibility let's only do one iteration
of the lighting solution and that will
give me what happens when I only do one
path and so what you can kind of see
here with the one pass of the lighting
is that my my sort of assumption appears
to be correct it appears that the
initial lighting solution is relatively
stable does not have that sort of nasty
propagation problem and so it would
appear that either we have a bug in the
way that we propagate information once
it's already been propagated once so you
know something where we're writing to a
variable in a way that's inconsistent so
if you loop through or something you get
nasty artifacts in that variable either
that's the case or what I was suggesting
before when I was talking about the
problems with having the sort of the non
conservation of light potentially
leading to really bad feedback loops we
don't know that could also be an issue
it's unclear what I will say is that
taking a look at this if we were to
eliminate and I actually goes what I
could also do here is
in addition to having that iterator
controlled we could do it here so we do
global renderer occlusion iteration half
and that could be something that we can
put in here so if we did I guess it's
two iterations I think is that correct
how many of there normally are yeah so
if we do two iterations on the lighting
path the am inclusion pass rather then
what we should be able to see is what
happens if we combined this just a
stable basic lighting solution with
ambient occlusion so here's the
visibility you can see the darkening
sort of happening there and you can see
the the lighting like so right and so
this is the combination of the two of
them
and it's sort of interesting again I'm
just taking a look to see what what it
ends up looking like so
in here if I was to say like okay let's
take this and let's switch to in config
file turning cough ambient occlusion so
and I guess I got it
if I go in here and turn on the
inclusion so the ambient occlusion
definitely does darken things down quite
a bit you know whether or not it darkens
them down in a way that we find useful
is another sort of question but it's
kind of interesting to look at anyway
one thing that I am kind of interested
into is how we're going to sample these
life at the end of the day because right
now we're just sort of reassignment to
the quads that they came from which
doesn't smooth out the lighting in any
way so because obviously we're not going
to want the lighting to be blocky like
that we're going to want the lighting to
be interpolated and so that'll be an
interesting problem as well kind of as
we go but it's sort of a separate issue
so yeah but looking at that you know it
does seem like that's actually still an
improvement there like for example the
stairs don't get that lighting because
they're sort of blocked and out of the
way so it does seem kind of like it does
a reasonable job of improving the
solution somewhat but it's not that
appreciably different right like I don't
think at least at the moment if you were
to show me these two I'd be like well it
doesn't really seem to add much right it
doesn't seem to add much in terms of
what I would suspect we would see when
we finally just do that like a good
sampling of it it doesn't seem to really
provide all that much that you would
bother running it right like it's not it
just doesn't seem like it it sort of has
enough going for it the ambient
occlusion
so I'm all muscle I'm more attempting to
say like you know if we were looking at
that part of the algorithm I think we
probably want to I think we probably
want to do something a little bit
fancier there or try to make that be a
little bit more about shadowing and a
little bit less about ambient occlusion
because the ambient occlusion again is
not it's not really that interesting in
a lot of cases it's kind of not really
what you want in terms of figuring out
where things should be darker or lighter
for light sources that are not
ubiquitous you know if you just have a
skylight that's coming in from the top
then ambient occlusion maybe is your
friend but if you have a situation where
you want to be able to move lights
around in some way like I am moving them
around right now ambient occlusion
doesn't really capture that the
properties of that very well because the
ambient occlusion sort of by definition
is really only talking about the degree
to which the surface can see the general
outside sort of world which isn't that's
really not what that is right okay so
what we want to do now is again start to
look at this lighting a little bit more
what I what I want to do is take a look
reef Li at that flashing up stuff and
just see if we turn occlusion off here
if I if I turn on viewing of reflectors
and we can sort of verify there is no
flashing when I'm just viewing
reflectors by itself so I go in here and
say I cranked up the lighting to two
passes we should see a little bit of a
problem but not as much of a problem at
three I would assume and it actually
looks pretty stable at two passes but if
I crank it to three passes yeah and you
know you can kind of almost just see
right off the bat
just the fact that it's getting brighter
kind of in the you know overall kind of
indicates that the the solution is kind
of tending to go a little bit nuts right
and so presumably what would happen is
if I kept cranking that iteration number
out we would just end up with the whole
scene being white and that is basically
what we see so I think what we're going
to have to do here is and I'm three
seems like a good sweet spot for seeing
the really nasty slashing to so that's
good so let's leave it there so I think
in terms of sort of conducting that
light around I want to start to be a
little bit more careful about this well
we'll leave ambient occlusion for now
and we'll leave it turned off so we
won't fuss with that but we'll take a
look at the compute lighting path and
let's just go through this and think
about what we're doing here and why
we're doing it and whether or not it
makes very much sense right alright so I
think the first thing to think about
here is the sort of directional nosov
the bouncing of the light I guess
because we sort of have a just an
apparent problem to think about and
here's what that that problem looks like
in my mind anyway where is my where is
Milton that is not Milton why do we have
so many things open what's going on do I
have I have more than I guess I have the
standard number of things open alright
so today's day what for Oh oops
whoa so it looks like the fix definitely
did not work whatever it is
it's really weird we have no idea what
causes that problem I need to just find
a way to debug it sometime it's the only
problem that we have at the moment with
any of the tools really we haven't run
into pretty much anything we want that
alright so day
we're the tablet tracking also seems to
be a little bit weird in this one now
gay hi
well who knows you know what I should
also do I should check so is that is
that actually just because our drawing
has gotten too large that's the other
thing that I wonder so if I was to say
have Milton open up a different drawing
so if I just said new Milton canvas
right
so if I'd then said okay open Milton
canvas no blackboard open now so it just
it just seemed like it was some kind of
a temporary thing I guess I don't know
it's so cool that Milton can undo after
you load all right well either right so
let's talk about light conservation here
so fundamentally speaking the problem
that we have is we have an emitter and
so the emitter is sending light out into
the environment and then we have
reflectors right and technically at this
point we are not doing anything to sort
of understand the fact that lighting the
amount of life is conserved so if you
imagine that what we're trying to do is
say okay we have an emitter and this
emitter output say you know X photons
per second then what we could say is
that we know that it's going to you know
in any given frame if we're running it
say 60 frames second or 30 frames a
second we know that if it does X photons
per second then it's going to do x over
30 photons per frame right so we would
or 460 or whatever right whatever
however many frames per second we're
doing we're going to divide the number
of photons with this thing shoots out so
whatever our emitter strength is that's
going to be the case when this emission
comes out and it shifts one of these
reflectors the photons are either going
to be bounced out to other reflectors or
bounced out to the eye I mean some will
be absorbed right
but there wherever the viewer is let's
say the viewer is here right here's our
little eyeball then when a photon comes
in here it's either going to come out
and hit the eye and we're going to see
it or it's going to come over here and
hit this guy right or something but a
photon can't do both right light does a
lot of weird things that's not one of
them and so however many photons come
out of the emitter if we're saying that
a photon went over to a reflector in the
scene it can't also come out and show up
for this reflector so what that means is
the color of this reflector as viewed to
the eye right and the color of this
reflector as you to this other reflector
the brightness hasit has to add up right
it can't put 100% of the photons that
come at it we'll send them over to this
reflector and also send 100% of the
photons over to the eye
right it's just not possible and so by
the same token we end up with the
problem that when we have two reflectors
pointing at each other which is that
what we have here if photons are sent
from this reflector to this reflector
then the same can't
if those those same photons were sent
back right then this reflector would be
black it would be completely dark right
if all the photons hit this reflector it
sent them all to this one and it sent
them all back right then send them to
the eye this one would be black but
that's not what our algorithms are
million at all right now what our
algorithm is actually simulating is that
if all the photons coming here we
consider this this reflector to
basically be however bright it is when
viewed from the eye or from this
reflector now technically that's not
necessarily wrong in the sense that a
diffuse of a perfectly diffused surface
does reflect light equally in all
directions but the question is how much
light does it reflect in all directions
and we have to take into account the
fact
when it reflects light in all directions
it has to divide the amount of light it
reflected by how the angle out of which
it's radiating that light because if it
doesn't and again you're just
multiplying the amount of light in the
scene dramatically right so right now we
have absolutely no we have essentially
no way of sort of keeping that process
under check I don't think so that's
problem number one problem number two is
that we are resampling the emitters
every time as well so basically we push
light into the scene with the emitters
and they are outputting the light and
then in theory when we then convict the
light around so when we're then saying
let's do secondary bounces technically
we shouldn't be looking at these
emitters anymore right because they
already put all the light in the scene
that they're going to put into the scene
they are not receiving any bounce
lighting so that's just kind of
erroneous at that point so that's the
moment in terms of a radiosity solution
this is typically what you call
solutions lighting solutions that are
like this where they bounce light around
and try to reach a steady state this is
not very good specifically because it's
got all of these sort of leakage
problems I don't like that and we're
seeing the results of that just from the
standpoint of our lighting solution
tends to sort of explode it tends to
just go out to bright white rather than
having each iteration converge towards a
smooth answer right so what we want to
do if we imagine that the amount of
total amount of light in the scene it
should be you know some specific value
whatever this is this is like the
correct total light
how much light if we imagine looking at
our iterations of this algorithm over
time what we want is something you know
we don't care how it approaches we don't
care for biased or unbiased really at
this point what we want to know is just
that no matter what happens like however
this happens we just want to know that
we're converging either from too bright
to the right amount from too dark to the
right amount or just stochastic to the
right amount but what we're actually
what our out of they've actually said to
do right now is like this right it's
just set up to just keep increasing the
light in the scene ad infinitum and so
the more iterations you run you don't
get closer to a any kind of good
solution to the light transport you just
are just adding light arbitrarily to the
scene and you don't actually improve the
solution at all right so what I would
say is the first thing that I think we
want to do is we want to start thinking
about the emitters as being a first pass
only thing so I'm thinking that probably
what we want to do is like overwrite the
emissions value sort of with zero or
something like this act or we want some
way of essentially saying once we've
done the first outpouring of light from
the emitters we don't want those
emitters to emit light anymore right
that's just yeah that's just a tenant of
the of the solution and we furthermore
could sort of say that you know we could
even think of it as basically being a
photon bouncing we could sort of say
that at the beginning you load up a
bunch of photons and again I'm just kind
of making this up as I go but you could
say we load up a bunch of photons on the
emitters and then we bounce them out and
we store how many photons the surface is
going to keep for its own illumination
versus how many it's going to send out
into the environment we could imagine
that as actually being a like a quantity
that we track right
and I don't really know if that's a good
idea but that's certainly an idea and we
can do it so the question there is just
how would we start to model something
like this and you know it's it's a
little confusing because if you think
about it it's like well something
doesn't get brighter or darker based on
how many observers there are to it right
but it is uniformly radiating the light
out from its surface and that means that
because it's doing that it is always
darker than it would have been if it was
a specular surface and you were viewing
it from the right angle because a
diffused surface that radiates light in
all directions button by necessity must
have divided the amount of light that it
was radiating by that sort of total
angle right and so all I'm trying to say
there is we need a solution that will
have the property that if it is a
diffused surface the total amount of
light that it could possibly transfer to
things in the environment must be
consistent and that's actually somewhat
tricky for us to do the reason that it's
tricky for us to do is because of the
way that we have set up this the way
that we set up this system and you know
this is just an artifact really of the
set of the sort of the approximation
that we're using if we don't have
shadowing which we don't really then if
you think about an emitter and two
reflectors right we are not looking at
the fact and I guess I should actually
say let's suppose these are all
reflectors so the emitter is here and I
get you know this emitters got light it
shines onto this reflector so this
reflector is now raining light out into
the environment and it's radiating
however much light it received it's
radiating that back out in all
directions
right so if it was taking in a hundred
photons or something then you know maybe
20 of them go up this way and twenty one
go up this way and twenty go out this
way and twenty go up this way and twenty
go out that way
right so but it adds up to a hundred
still or less than 100 if some got
absorbed so the problem is the way that
we're computing how the light bounces
around is we're saying well let's take
each pair of these and see how much of
the solid angle of the world this one
takes up like how much can this one see
and when we do that we end up looking
and seeing that we you know can see this
occluder quite a bit of this reflector
quite a bit from both here and here we
don't take into account that this part
right here is shadowed for this this you
know part of this reflector so really it
can't collect nearly as much light as
this one can from this emitter because
part of its being blocked and since we
aren't taking that into account we will
naturally increase the amount of light
that's in the same kind of ad infinitum
if we're not careful specifically
because of that shadowing that we're not
taking into account so that's a pretty
big problem there and like I said
there's a couple ways we could approach
it one way we could approach it is by
just doing photon distribution in some
kind of more same fashion and so I guess
what I might propose is the problem that
we're going to have with this is that
until we get to the end of the until we
go through everybody and do that letting
computation what we don't actually know
is how much of this sort of thing
occurred right because we have literally
no computations for shadows in there and
even if we ask them they're going to be
pretty approximate so we're
not going to end up with a good position
there but what we could do since we're
sort of overestimating the contributions
there is one thing that we do know which
is we know the total immittance right
however we want to measure it photons
Lux whatever like we you know however we
want to
that's our lumens however we want to
sort of put caps or specify our lighting
or even just an arbitrary value
handmaids whatever it is we know that
how much we started with because our
emitters at the beginning before
anything else happens we know how many
of them there were and how bright they
were supposed to be so we have some
value we can use to say this is the
total brightness that should get
distributed through the scene full-stop
right and so if we know that piece of
information then one interesting aspect
of it is we could say that at the end of
every lighting path we do not expect to
have any more than that light in the
scene so we could track the total light
as a sum and then normalize to that at
the end right now the problem with that
approach is that that's going to be easy
to do on the CPU but I suspect it's
relatively tough to do on the GPU maybe
not
you could use a hierarchical approach to
some of the light in that case but you
can kind of see why it's not maybe the
best idea because of its global nature
essentially the problem with it is you
know if I if I imagine how that would be
done here you could you could see in
this compute lighting thing we could
just have something that was like oh
yeah
you just say the total light is some
value and then we come through here and
we sum it up and at the end we divide by
that value and we're done right
so inside here we just say like you know
total light plus equals right and then
we just want to make sure the total
light matches up at the end and that's
it so we can do something like that but
then again you know you can see when
you're in a straight-line path like this
using accumulators for a global
accumulator is easy because you know you
just put it in line like that but when
you move out to a parallelized version
of the algorithm you have a problem
which is that at the end of it you have
to gather up that sum somehow and that
can be pretty tricky on GPU even though
it wouldn't be tricky on a seat on a
paralyzed version on the CPU whose GPUs
at least but unless you're using like
CUDA or something GPUs are actually
really bad that if you're just using
like a DirectX or open jail they don't
have a lot of good ways of saying here's
the concept of a thread let's have every
thread increment some variable that's
how much it did a thing X and then we'll
sum those at the end again it's just
because the shader stuff wasn't really
initially set up for it so you end up
like having to get pretty far down the
line with extensions and whatever's or
even just let go to something like CUDA
to get to the point where you have basic
threading primitives that you might want
such as value for thread or thread-local
storage whatever you want to call it
which makes that kind of solution which
makes this solution to this problem
trivial but again what I don't really
know that we're going to have access to
it in in a shader model 3 so anyway so
we could do something like that however
even that doesn't necessarily solve our
problem because it doesn't necessarily
mean that the light is saying in terms
of how it bounces around
areas because then what you what you
still might get is a circumstance where
you've got you know two reflectors or
three reflectors or something like this
and immittance that comes in here just
bounces around it here really a lot and
and Jack's the the total lighting in
this area substantially for no real
reason just because it is over
contributing it like it's its
contribution is overvalued because
you're only doing that sort of total
lighting so what we would rather do I
think if we can is figure out some way
of keeping the total radiance from
something the total sort of output
radiance from something to be fairer in
general when it's being computed such
that you know when you see it from two
places and I got my light from you the
like we just sort of having a difference
between that emitted light and the
reflected light to the eye or something
right we need some way of keeping these
values sort of more stable through the
iteration process if that makes sense
and unfortunately I'm not really sure
this is the part where probably what I
would do if I was programming on my own
is I would want to go read some of the
radiosity literature the original
radiosity literature just to find out
how they tend to structure at their
solvers so that the light that bounces
around is summed up proper in a fair you
know it summed up in a fair model right
but I'm not really sure I'm not really
sure how they do that right I'm not sure
how they traditionally set that up it's
good it's again it's going to be asked
to be something fairly careful in terms
of how you account for the light and I
don't know if the approach that they
tended to take was let's make sure we
calculate the lighting transfer
Cheerilee so that we don't have this
problem at all or if they were like no
we try to make something that converges
on the solution and we can have sloppy
calculations for how the light is
transferred and we still expect it to
come back to something reasonable right
so yeah that's what I would normally do
but I don't think that that doesn't tend
to work particularly well in the streams
so I think I'm going to have to just
kind of hack it through myself that make
sense and but I wouldn't say that you
know that's what I would advise doing so
you know in terms of this being an
educational stream what I would say is
that if you were looking at a problem
like this and you're not sure about it
and there is a bunch of literature on it
which in this case like I said this is
just called a radiosity problem in
computer graphics if it's well studied
it's not the kind of thing that you're
going to have to go digging for
extremely esoteric papers to read about
there's a lot of paper static probably
what I would do is go try to read the
radiosity literature a bit and just
tular wise myself with what that's
already done in the area so that I can
kind of you know know what what the
general techniques might be and see if
any of them are going to be you know
worthwhile here but if I have to puzzle
through with myself then I guess what it
comes down to is I'm just I'm a little
bit stuck on on this sort of problem of
not knowing about the occlusion process
I'm just not sure how you deal with that
because without some notion of the total
amount of light that you are expecting
to have I'm just not sure how you deal
with that and furthermore I guess you
know if you don't deal with that
properly you're always going to have the
thing I talked about would be over
contributing so I'm not sure so you may
just need a total light value there may
really be there may really be no
straightforward way to to make sure that
you don't over contribute if you don't
have proper shadowing yeah
it sort of seems like you just have to
have an overall exposure value it's like
here's how much light got transferred
which we know is going to be wrong
because we're not including properly and
then we just have to you know dump it
down from there and I don't know if
there's really any other way to do it
because because without an accurate
without a conservative way of
transferring the light you're always
going to have some overflow and if you
have some overflow without if you don't
have any way to measure the overflow I
don't see what you could really do
yeah I can't think of any other solution
if you want an accurate lighting
transfer it seems like you have to be
some ated now I guess what I could say
is that the that the ambient occlusion
might be enough to make it so that you
never have to worry about it
transferring too much if you do the rest
of it correctly because thinking through
what happens with the ambient occlusion
the ambient occlusion is anything
[Music]
overshadows things so the visibility
value that we compute with the ambient
occlusion is going to knock it down
based on the total amount of occlusion
there could have been and it should over
compensate so in theory this value here
is going to be reflected the fact that
it's taking up part of the solid angle
here isn't reflected I guess what we
don't know however is that that's really
true for light because the light could
be coming from a totally different angle
and the light's coming from a different
angle all bets are off
yeah I'm not sure so let's think about
this from I guess just from the
perspective of if I let myself use the
sort of total lighting approach let's
just see what happens so what I want to
know here is how much total light you
know sort of a have a value that's like
the total amount of light that should be
spread around and so you know what we're
sort of doing at the moment is we have
these lighting elements and some of this
information is dynamic and some of it
static so we should sort of start to
maybe segregate that so here's the
static information and here's the
dynamic information at the moment all
right so I believe transparency and
radius those are not dynamic right they
don't change the rest of this stuff I
guess reflect color so reflect color is
currently not dynamic either we go
probably be on this side to avoid going
underneath my head so if we take a look
at what's going on there with the PNTR
FC there that that top part those are
the values that are actually set by the
game engine sort of irrevocably and they
just remain the same the entire time so
there's no those are not values that
iterate around then we've got sort of
the front emit and vacuum it values the
front emit and back advised we're not
doing back a mission yet we should for
sprite cards obviously and then we've
got the accumulated color the visibility
in the shadow so the way this is working
at the moment is that the shadow the
shadow value and the visibility value
are used
in the ambient occlusion pass right so
these are really and technically the
shadow value this is like a transient
value we don't really use the shadow
value except as like an accumulator like
it's really just a cute kewpie for
ambient occlusion right and so what
happens is we store our result into that
shadow value it could just be like a
temporary array that was right in just
this loop it doesn't need to persist so
that's a transient value and the same is
true of a qmc right of TMC at the moment
is not used as the actual like permanent
value it's used as something that gets
transferred eventually so you can kind
of see it like in here right when we're
computing the light source information
we grab out of the source
this light color is the front emit C and
we store back to the desk the
accumulator then at the end we take the
front emit color and that's when we take
that accumulation into account right so
in here we could also say that this part
is transient right another way to write
this I suppose would be like this but I
don't I'm going to keep them with their
with their sections and maybe I'll put
it at the end
so so basically what we want to do is we
want to focus on how we would go about
approaching the light conservation
problem so what you can see here is
we've got this friend amid see we've got
the emission value and the color RGB the
emission value is just telling how
bright this thing emits right and so
that tells us the total emission only
our lights are going to have front emit
sees up to something at the beginning
and off we go now one of the interesting
things about ref C which is the
reflected color is we should not never
allow a surface to reflect 100% of the
light that it receives why shouldn't we
allow a service to reflect under percent
of light receives a because there is no
such a thing as a perfect reflected
surface so what we want to probably
recognize is the fact that the reflected
color from a surface has to be somewhat
less than the light coming in on all
three channels so red green and blue
light that comes in it has to be
reflected out at less than what kid it
only perhaps very slightly the reason
for that is if you think about trying to
do any kind of accurate lighting
solution I don't know why we're still
running the game by the way what is this
OpenGL error encountered what's the
error
they look about a GLSL shader yeah
that's no good
cannot apply dot operator to an array
what did I accidentally touch something
in the OpenGL code what was that
I do not know what it was complaining
about there hmm to see if that happens
again or if that's just open jail being
weird anyway back to what I was saying
so the problem is that if we actually
look at what would happen if we allowed
a hundred percent light transmission is
that if you have an emitter that emits
even a single photon right here's one
photon and these are 100 percent
reflective surfaces you can get a
situation with this photon just bounces
back and forth forever right it
literally creates an impossible scenario
where there's no way to ever get the
light to transfer properly right because
there has to be in order for there to be
a stable lighting solution that you can
end up with there has to be a way that
all light eventually goes somewhere you
can't have it that light bounces around
forever and expect to have any kind of
converging solution because it's the
like and bounce around forever in the
scene then there is no solution right
there is no actual solution to what the
color is of each individual surface so
typically speaking we want to make sure
for our lighting situation that our
reflectance should be something like
this so when people specify RGB colors
they can use the full range if they want
to but our actual interpretation of what
that's going to mean in terms of when we
reflect light all around we're going to
assume that what that actually means is
that the reflected light is less than
the total light that came in and we'll
assume that our services can get pretty
reflective but just not all the way
reflective 0.95 or 0.9 you know 90% of
the light 95% of the light can be
reflected out but not a hundred percent
right and and so we'll just assume that
that's the case now so moving on from
there when we take a look at this
emission situation right we now have
reflected that we know reflectance that
we know would eventually converge and we
have an emission color that we set when
we go into the sort of this iteration
thing if I want to have some idea of the
total amount of light what I can do is I
can just have that value be stored in
here somewhere
so I could do something like total light
or total light levels or something like
this so that we come here and we track
how much light is going to be emitted at
the outset of it what I can say is that
the total light levels are going to be
the sum of all of the emitters that we
have and I could say initial total light
level even just to say which one that
was so I can keep a total of how much
emitted light we started with right and
one thing I'm not wanting a percent sure
about is the emissions values how we're
ranging those I'm not really sure how
that value is supposed to be interpreted
but we know how much total initial light
there is in the scene by looking at this
initial total light level right that's
sort of our our value that we can
understand so then when we come through
here a secondary loop and we do our
lighting computation we're going to
transfer a certain amount of light every
time right so we're going to take a of
light and we're going to transfer it and
that transfer however much light got
transferred we could say that we want it
to sum up to whatever the initial total
light level was or something similar
right so on each iteration we could say
total light transfer I mean here we
could say all right every time we do an
accumulation we will say the total light
transfer
get that Valve up well gets that value
added to it so then at the end we know
how much total like got transferred on
each of our channels and we now are in a
position to potentially do something
about it if we wanted to right now since
we don't super care that much about the
reflectance values we kind of just want
to know more about how much light we did
total I'm wondering if this kind of
though does need to be sort of thought
about just as a single single power
value right like a photon power value
because we don't really want to
normalize our channels separately so
it's a little confusing right because
what we really want to do is say all
right when we come through here we've
got the specular light level the diffuse
light level what we want to do is try to
say well how much light were we actually
putting out here we really want it to be
more like this value here that we're
tracking and I guess I can do that
pretty easily
so if I do something like this because
these are non these are this is just a
series of skitters that have been blown
out so it can multiply the reflective
color later so that's not quite true
so it's actually this part in here that
I want because I don't really want to
multiply by the light color yet so one
of the interesting things here is that
that multiplication actually could have
been done at the end as well which
because the light color is the light
color regardless so if we take a look at
what's happening here
I guess it's if you want to change the
specular color and the and the diffuse
color separately to have more of a
control over the light source than it
makes some sense so I sort of see why we
did it but still so what I really want
to do here is just have some some like
this distance fall-off times diffuse
coefficient times cosine angle what I
really want here is Disputes contribs or
something like that
so that's the diffuse contribution the
specular contribution it looks like to
be done exactly the same way we're not
using this yet so we don't really have
to care about this path but I guess
we'll sort of leave it in nominally so
if I have both the specular and the
diffused contributions then what I can
do is say that the that sort of a team
light value here is just going to record
that information so the accumulate is
going to be the diffuse contributor
contribs and that's how much and I
supposed to keep this naming reasonable
will say that accumulated contribution
so once we know the accumulated
contribution we can do the total light
transfer is plus the acute rib we can
assume that since we're modulating by
the visibility we'll do that as well
right so that modulated visibility there
that gives us the total light transfer
and now we know how much light we
transferred versus how much light we
should have so what I can do there is
say here is the initial total light
level and what we'll do is we'll just
use that as a scalar value so we'll say
the initial total light level is going
to be whatever the vert zero emission
was and we add that together right so
now we kind of know how much total light
we're putting out into the scene in a
sort of happy way and we should be able
to then say well if we know the total
transfer and we know the total light
level we can correct for the wrongness
of the transfer right so what we could
say is like the correction for the light
amounts is going to be the total light
transfer
is how much we got right and we want the
total light level let's just say the
initial light level little bit close
initial what was it called did I call it
like an initial light level or something
like that initial total light level so
we can compute a correction factor
that's like we should have had this much
light total machine we ended up
transferring this much light
let's just keep those two consistent
right so what we can do is say that
correction factor applies to the total
amount of light that we end up with and
I guess the problem here is that again
that transference though we're trying to
keep the total amount of light constant
across everything so in theory what we
would do here I guess is just say that
we want to keep the total light level
constant for each go-around and so
presumably this correction would keep it
so that we've sent that amount of light
around but that doesn't really help us
with the second part of the problem
which is the fact that each iteration
will convict that much light but in
theory right
as long as we account for the number of
iterations we're doing by just divided
like by just saying each step is an
averaging step that should be okay right
so in other words the correction could
also factor in the number of iterations
we're going to do so you know we add in
the correction factor and also the
the total number of iterations we divide
by the total number of iterations
seems reasonable
essentially what we're saying there is
like okay so each time we add lighting
in we're going to add as much lighting
as there was total but we want to make
sure that we only add that amount of
light in the end meaning so we're going
to have however made like stuffs we do
if we do three lighting steps we want to
make sure that we add the correct amount
of light on each step but we also want
to make sure that we add that we are
averaging each of those steps together
and not adding the entire amount of
light every time right so that should
give us the answer there however the
problem with this is the front emit C
values again for the initial emitters we
need those to be zeroed out so the
initial emitter needs to not contribute
light anymore after the first time that
it's shot light out into the world right
because at that point it has done its
job of putting the light into the world
it's not supposed to it's not supposed
to put light out into the world again on
the next pass so what we really want
probably here is rather than summing the
accumulation maybe this just wants to be
setting the accumulation so this is how
much light you actually got right we
push the light out and we bounce it
around and so if we do that then we
wouldn't need this I think
right so again that's really pretty hand
wavey of me like nothing in there makes
a whole lot of sense I'm just kind of
again going for something see if we can
sorry I'm just trying to like puzzle it
through a little bit see if I can get to
something that seems more reasonable in
terms of convergence okay so specular
config particular C times cosine rest
angle there all right cosine is is
actually care
all right so yeah the convergence
properties there I'm starting to get a
little bit more of a handle on I think
what should be happening here because he
has it's like the iterations I'm not
really entirely sure how those emitters
should work in that way it's a little
bit tough to say but I'm interested to
see what we did so we'll find out so
anyway let's take a look at how this is
working just we can kind of get some
idea of what's going on here
so if I go into well I guess I can't do
that
let's let's set a breakpoint on the
routine lighting time looks like it's
not open so if I come through here and
you know let me compile in debug mode as
well there we go
make sure it's still working
so if I stop in here and I start looping
through let's see what the initial total
light level value comes out to be I have
no idea so six is the total light level
I assume that's because we have six
emitters outputting at one right excuse
me I and again that's not really we
probably need to improve how we're
describing that because it's like okay
how bigger the emitter is you know how
do we want the light values to be is the
light value the total amount when we say
emission is that the total amount over
the entire surface or is that per unit
surface area you know bla bla bla so we
haven't really talked about really how
that's going to be satisfied yet either
which is a bit of a problem but we're
skipping over as the ambient occlusion
so this should not do anything when we
go to compute the letting transfer here
so as we go through we look to see what
the the light distances are for these
things see sooner and so on in this case
this is a non contributing light source
one of the things that I guess I didn't
do is I don't take into account the
emission here which is probably bad this
is just how much of the light could have
transferred but we didn't take into
account how much of an actual transfer
it was based on the light color right
and that's sort of like there's sort of
this notion of how much light that
surface had to to contribute at that
point
so that now that I think about it that's
that's about the question so the only
way we could really handle that part
properly is we have to store how much
light we bounce to each surface as well
right like how much light we gave to
that surface and so I do wonder it seems
like that's custom like trying to be
conservative out the light like this is
just going to sort of drag us down into
like having to track more and more and
more values so here's the question for
you can we just rely on the averaging
part of it like let's say we didn't try
to do the sort of the sort of nuts thing
of trying to actually track the total
light and keeping it correct what
happens if we force the emission to not
be additive and instead we let it bounce
what do we get I just comes curious to
know oh and I need to build in
so you still get very flickery results
there whether whether you add right or
not so it gets like slightly brighter
but it's surprisingly not that different
which is somewhat interesting so now
let's see if I do put a correction in
here I'm curious to know what happens if
I like make the iteration count relevant
so you still get you still get a really
just get a really surprisingly
temperamental solution so yeah I'm
really confused about that so I don't
know maybe we do really need to track
the total light transfer but now you
know like when I was looking at that I'm
like well okay if we actually do want to
track total I transfer we have to
actually remember how much light could
could have been coming from the
particular source in question because so
each one of those needs an f32 that's
like how many photons do I have to
transfer potentially right because the
surface that has not had any trans
photons hit it can't give you any
protons and so you'd be massively over
calculating how much light was
potentially transferred on each path if
you don't store that value so that does
seem kind of nasty I don't know how to
get around that let's think about this
for a second is there something else I
could be doing here that would make that
work
I can't sit and really think of anything
well I mean I guess what I should do is
I think probably the best policy is just
to try ridiculous stuff until we see
where we're at and then we can know
we've simplify later right seems
reasonable enough so if I was to
actually say like if I was to do
something ridiculous like photons to
send and photons received what I could
say is like all right you know we come
through here and we say that this
element protons to send equals the
emission the photons
sieved equals zero and the initial total
light level is you know the summation of
the photons will send and initial to the
light level we'll just we could just say
photon count total photon gap so that
tells us some made-up value that's like
here's how many photons we have to send
around and off we go
so then we do when we come through here
and do the lighting computation we can
say total photons sent and when we come
through we'll say all right the source
let's go here click on send
so we'll say the photon sense equals
whatever the this particular whatever
this particular source is photons defend
our times the two contribution values
right so whichever you know however much
light works could potentially transfer
time for protoss times as the total
photon sent then at the end we could say
is all right
the total photons that we sent are going
to be however many photons we sent times
visibility here and that's a value we
can actually store right so I guess in
what I should say is sort of that when
we loop over the desk here well and I
guess just learning that value inside
the destination here and ition to the
accumulation color that we're
accumulating there I'm going to take the
photon sent or rather the photons
received and I'm going to assume that
however many photons were sent in this
path in fact I guess I should name that
the other way around this is the photons
received right so it's not all of the
photons that that were received at the
end I'll store that and the total
photons received look like this so that
gets me how many photons I received and
how many photons were received in
general so at the end when we do this
now we know we can introduce the
correction we can say that the total
photons received we want to sort of
correct those photon values by the total
photons that there are
so that's our correction factor so when
we come through here and we say let's
take our our destination when we want to
compute these next values we'll say the
photons received we're going to clear
that out for the next pass and the
photons descend are going to be however
many we received so we only send however
many we ended up receiving so then we're
just kind of convicting it around
now the emit color so we're going to
ignore all that stuff now and we're just
going to draw the photons received so in
the copy lighting out when we do this
stuff here I'm going to say if show
letting visibility else if lighting show
photons what I'm going to do is in here
say that the photon descend are going to
be what we show then what I can do is in
the config we'll have a thing for that
to share photon and now we can see what
the photon transmittance values are for
everything oh my how do we get blue in
there I suppose that this is probably
because the photons to send value needs
to be divided by the total number of
photons
stratum or time
all right so here we can see this sort
of nominal photon transference idea it
still looks busted because how are we
getting blue I don't know if blue I'm
not sure how the blue is happening there
but like yeah because in theory the
front emit should not ever be able to be
greater than zero now I'm sorry greater
than one let's do an assertion
all right so uh that does look bad so
our algorithm is definitely not right
yet because we shouldn't there should be
no chance for any element to have
anywhere near the number of photons that
are the total number of photons in the
scene right so let's go ahead and
recheck that so we come through here we
set the total photons received to be
zero we loop through all of our sources
and we say however many photons the
source had to send we're going to
multiply well in fact and we don't
really care about this right whatever
this number is it doesn't matter we're
going to get a photons received number
summed over all the sources is how many
received we're then going to say that
the destination that photons received is
going to be however many that was times
our visibility which in this case should
be one that should not be really
reducing it at all we're then going to
say that the total number received
gets incremented by that amount and
that's checked outside when we finish
the iteration across all light transfer
pairs we then say okay the correction
value is going to be however many
photons there were total we want to take
the total number of photons received and
divide by that so this is going to be
six right and this is going to be some
other numbers let's actually like look
in there
okay and so like this number is 40 point
eight five whatever that's the total
amount of transfer that occurred we only
want the total number to be at six so
what we're going to do is we're going to
take six over that value or whatever
right oops
if I can just look at the actual value
and we're going to correct every one by
the oh hi how about I actually didn't
that's pretty good
how about I do all this work to
construct a a coefficient for correction
and then I never bother to like multiply
anything by it at all
how's that sound pretty good right all
right so now we're out of the business
of of overestimating the light there
hopefully now when I run we have
something more sane okay so now we could
kind of see this looks more correct
right so it seems it seems a little more
sane however you'll notice the
flickering is still awful and so I don't
know one thing that I'm a little bit
interested to know at this point is do
we have another bug in here that's
actually what cause of that flickering
in some way I don't think so because you
know when we don't do multiple
iterations we don't see it so presume
like for example if I go into the config
here and I said the iteration cap was
one on the photon transfer there it is
I'm assuming we'd no longer get the
flicker
you know and we more or less down
so there's that one thing that I am a
little interested to know
so if I was to say that the lighting
iteration count was three like we were
doing before and in fact let's just say
with six let's just go nuts so we're
just going to iterate the lighting like
lots of times right so it really just
seems kind of nonsensical to me and I
don't know if maybe that's just like I
said maybe we've got some other kind of
bug but in this case here we've got you
know I'm going to go ahead and just
assume like here we've got a situation
where we know we're keeping this total
photon number even and just the
distribution of it is is just absurd
back to six iterations right it seems to
be like tana arbitrary where the photons
ended up which is a little bit weird to
me
maybe that's what should happen I don't
know but it seems odd and if I look at
the if I look at the photons to send
which is the only value we're actually
viewing at this point it sure seems like
it's sanely capped so I don't know I
don't think I really understand what's
going on it's a little bit troubling so
you know here's let me go ahead and
change the iteration count down to two
one
so there's one iteration and then if I
change it you know and I'm can I still
do this yeah so yeah if we're kind of if
we're just taking a look at this
situation here where we're zooming
around if I change the iteration count
to two you know now I get this weird
concentration of light on the middle guy
there but why would that be the place
where the photons get concentrated is
that just because there's so much more
transfer for things that are close
together or something
and I don't really know
but I can't oh right cuz I'm playing
back input I'm like how come I can't
rotate the camera I'm like that's going
to take back input
so the other interesting thing about
this is I almost want to take the hero
out for the moment and just be able to
move the light around so what I might
say is can we just go to world mode and
when we add player what if I just don't
give it any actual pieces actually don't
want that to running so if I run it now
I should just have just the light source
to move around right it looks like it's
got a health meter as well I'm not sure
how we have that I'm not sure I remember
how we said that somebody had health
but there must be summer it's got a nose
somehow in it hitpoints
so now I'm just moving the light right
and it certainly does seem at least from
this because now I can go into the
config and say let's increase the
learning iteration count it certainly
does seem like from that that having
those things stacked together is a
problem or at least you know it
exacerbates the problems with our with
our lighting transfer because you don't
you don't get I guess is because they're
so close together
maybe they because they can sort of
transfer light at too high of a it might
just be like a nasty singularity and how
we were doing our lighting maybe we just
have a bug in the in the distance
computation there where if things are
too close together they can transfer
light to each other extremely easily and
they just kind of go supercritical at
that point
that does seem plausible anyway
hmm
so you can kind of see that a lot of
that jitteriness goes away when you
don't have those stacked sprites all
kind of hopping up and down like they
were so I think that suggests to me that
I just need to fix the transfer function
maybe the transfer function is most of
the problem there
hmmm I say let's take a look and how we
want to go about this so if I look at
the front emit color here and I assume
that we're just setting it so so if I
was to do the summation that we were
doing before
all right here's that summation so what
we can sort of see is it's actually
totally smooth if you just have
occluders that are spaced pretty far
apart so that's pretty important
information I guess because here we are
doing like a lot of lighting iterations
let's see what happens if I crank it up
further so basically what we find is yet
you do get the light sort of the too
much light transfer problem but you
don't get the flickering so that's very
important information so we need to like
deal with that I'm interested to know if
we take the what happens if we multiply
the photon correction here I can't
imagine it's a good idea but let's just
see it does seem like it's a good idea
all right so here this is kind of nice
so our photon correction does do a good
job of keeping the lighting relatively
consistent across multiple iterations so
if I crank up the number of iterations
here it definitely keeps it a lot more
sane it's still not sane enough like
we're still doing something stupid I'm
not sure what but it still is increasing
the total amount of light it looks like
oh because this is a plus equals fit so
that's that's actually not that that
unusual if we were to do with three
equals I think we'd be very dark because
currently we don't have any exposure
control or anything like this so that's
probably not super plausible at the end
of the day but
I think we're kind of getting there all
right so I think what we've learned here
is that we need to take our distance
fall-off and we need to fix it so that
it doesn't have a bad behavior when when
things interpenetrate or get very close
to each other I think that's being a big
problem for us so we need to fix that
and then the other thing that we need to
do is then we need to figure out whether
or not or how we're going to try to keep
a lid on the amount of lighting that
gets put out into the scene it's
possible that we don't really need to do
it like it's possible that we can choose
it because it seems like anyway with
once we get down once we get rid of that
bad sort of singular behavior when
things get too close together it looks
like just simply keeping the light
relatively under control is enough so
there's eight iterations here's 16 and
that's pretty good so I guess I would
say you know it seems like just keeping
it so that we only take just keeping it
so that we are essentially just using an
averaging process for the color seems
sufficient to me I so that's good let me
see here
all right so yeah I think it why is that
kind of solves that problem for me so I
think at this point well we really need
to do I don't think we'll have to do the
photon control there so I think all we
really need to do is keep things from
going supercritical and we'll be ok
because again we're not trying to
compute any kind of exact lighting
solution here obviously so it seems like
we should be ok so let's get rid of
those entirely
all right and so now we should be able
to just have yes so now we've got some
pretty stable light in there which is
good and we can build on that and make
it better right so really what we need
to do now is we need to just go in there
and figure out why are we getting such a
bad behavior and I'm assuming it's from
the distance fall-off but we'll see why
are we getting such a bad behavior when
there is a hero added to the mix so
let's go ahead and add first back in the
body pieces and see so you can see some
of that flashing happening right and
also what we can also we can sort of see
here is to that you know these things
are bright completely white essentially
and so I do wonder to write you know
look if we only iterated once are they
white already and they are right so even
the first bounce of light makes them be
that bright
so that's kind of interesting
all right
so let's take a look at what we're
actually computing here for our fall off
that's not right file so if we're going
to do here in our compute lighting if
we're going to do the fall off here's
our distance off we have one over the
square of the light distance but that
just seems wrong because we want the
distance fall-off to be yet so prep you
know what probably this is all this is
just wrong the whole time so if you
think about what happens in fact you
know I can probably do this using one of
those softly grasping things so let's
see draft square root of x so you can
see the function that we're taking we're
looking at here I don't know if I can
zoom in I just want the I don't know if
I can tell I just want the one to one
range
they're um poor do be how do i ah there
we go
that's one looking for
so if I do that so you can see this
function here so for our square root of
x I don't know if I can change am I
allowed to change that you're not really
alright we're doing 1 over whatever the
square root of x is right so we're
graphing 1 over the square root of x
unfortunately does it save our graphing
thing that's all right it's not going to
the world so you can feed it underneath
1 here you get this court of super
ridiculous spike and I think that's
exactly what we were seeing what we
wanted was a distance fall-off factor
that basically said that the fall-off
presumably at the light source so if
you're standing right at the light
source right there we go so at the light
source looks like we lost lost Milken
again
[Music]
[Applause]
so at the light source that values to
because it will be one meaning there's
no fall-off and far away it should
approach zero now it will never be
exactly zero because inverse square law
it will just keep getting lower and
lower and lower but we'll never quite
get zero but what we actually have at
the light source the distance is going
to be zero right and so the square root
of zero is not 1 so we have 1 over the
square root of 0 it should be 1 at the
light source it's actually going to be
going off into infinity right all right
going down up it's going to be the
square we're doing at infinity which is
going to make our Valley R is going to
go down to zero which is going to make
our value shoot off into infinity so
actually what we want to do is say we
want 1 plus the 1 plus X right because
that way our value trends up towards 1
and hits one not infinity at zero right
and we did that correctly because we
were working off of the paper in here we
did reciprocal square root right but
when I type it in here I'm not sure why
I just wasn't thinking so I didn't do it
that way but that's what we actually
wanted so that value has always been
wrong and that it would explain where
that singularity was coming from so now
that we have it correct actually you can
already see that now we're okay right so
we just said we had just had a rogue
term in there and that was what was
creating that nasty flickering because
that was injecting arbitrarily like
close to infinite powers of light into
our lighting solution and hey big
surprise our lighting solution didn't
like that very much so let's try
cranking it up to eight iterations and
see if we're still stable we are so I'm
going to consider that a good victory
alright so that was just like this the
typo
there so it turns out that's what our
that is what our flickering problem was
and then now I think we're pretty good
in terms of lighting solutions just the
basic transfer working
it seems pretty reasonable right I am
interested to know if we can change the
color I don't remember myself what we
were doing here with color when we add a
standard room and took the cases in here
so we can alright so what we can do is
we could say F for color we could take
this here and do something where we
actually change the color if it's a wall
so we could do something like have it be
a very red sort of wall
and what I'm interested to see here
right is I'd like to see if we can get
some light bleeding happening at some
point which it doesn't really look like
we're getting very much of which isn't
good right what I'd like to see is
because in theory if this light is
bouncing around in the way that we think
it should then when you get in a
situation like this you should get some
red contribution coming in here right
and one way we could exaggerate that I'm
going to say one way we could exaggerate
that is if we just said that everything
was either perfectly red or perfectly
white and if we go through and look at
what we get there - do we get any color
bleeding and you know we get a little
right you can sort of see that we are
getting a little bit of color bleeding
but it's very minor and I don't know if
that's really what we should be
expecting here or not but maybe seems a
little bit less than it should I guess
would be my only my only thought there
so the other thing we could do - though
is I guess we can we can leave ourselves
with a ambient occlusion path as well
here just for fun
but yeah you can just see that that you
don't really seem to be getting very
much at the moment
you don't see me getting very much of it
and again it's hard to say if that's
accurate not that's always the problem
with lighting things like this
but I mean I guess I would say you do
get a little bit right it's just not as
much as I probably would have wanted but
you do get a little bit of that color
bleed because you know what you should
see is these big red reflectors you
should see more of a red tinge in here
and you really don't see much and so I
wonder I feel like that's the next thing
to start looking at in terms because
ignoring ambient occlusion which we need
to sort of start working on separately
tomorrow I think what I'd like to do is
figure out why we're not getting enough
of a transfer there and what happens if
I start with just one iteration right I
get none because because I shouldn't be
able to get any color bleed there with
two iterations I should have gotten some
but I don't seem to you know if I did I
got an extraordinarily little and I feel
like it should have picked up some from
that contributor because it is close
but it just doesn't seem to really have
done so and if it's not picking it up on
that second bounce it probably won't
pick it up ever I don't know it does
look like as you go through more
iterations maybe get a little bit but
I'm not sure so let's go ahead
to the Q&amp;A so it supposed to be square
in not square root I might supposed to
be let me see if I put that wrong in
there oh yeah sorry about that
I just graphed it wrong
so there you can see it passing through
one as it should right and if I get rid
of that oops
you can see how it one over x squared
has this nasty problem of just shooting
off as we get down below one you get
this nasty shooting off into infinity
right and it makes sense right because
as you get lower and lower you know zero
point one squared at 0.01 or whatever
right you get you keep getting higher
and higher as this value goes below one
so you never really want this value to
go below one and there's two ways you
can do that you can either square you
know we could do this is I have to
actually go see how we actually want to
do this this is one way to do it right
which is we can scoops we can do one
plus the square at because as that goes
to zero so it just goes up from there or
we can do the square of of one plus the
value and I guess not sure which one of
those is more correct
I think this one is probably the more
correct how many iterations are we doing
here a little bit slow
so yeah
question now we don't need to do a
global pass to normalize light
yeah because so the thing is that again
this is an approximate lighting solution
so we're not doing you know we're not
trying to do anything that's actually
going to produce a physically correct
lighting result so if I can my
preference is definitely to my
preference is definitely to make it so
that we don't have to do a path to
normalize light that would be my
preference so because we can do an
averaging process which is what I'm
doing now and it appears to keep the
lighting under control I would say we
definitely don't want to do the lighting
to to have to enforce the lighting
prepass I'm a lighting post basket
correct
and shota is it useful to convert the
surface color from RGB to y UV in these
equations as in using Y to modulate
light contribution somehow um I don't
think so
because generally speaking you want to
know the spectrum of life that you're
like you actually RGB is actually the
right space to do lighting computations
in if you're not going to go full pull
and actually do spectrum information
right but you definitely don't want to
convert to something that that doesn't
tell you which of your colors is the
color where the intensity is because
you're trying to bounce around colored
light specifically so I don't think
there's any bonus to doing it in y UV
there is a bonus to doing it in spectra
in like spectral some way that stores
more spectrum information because some
things need to know whether say a yellow
light is actually a yellow wavelength
light or a combination of red and green
wavelength lights so you know if you're
doing really high-end stuff you may want
between more spectrum information than
just three samples RG and B because that
doesn't tell you very much about the
incoming light really but I don't think
you why UV helps in any particular way
could be wrong about that but I don't
think so
do you know how much a CPU gather cost
how much a CPU gather costs compared to
a load from a linear memory read so are
you talking about
for example the gather call the the
gather instruction in avx-512 is that
what you're referring to and how much it
costs to do to have the CPU do to gather
as opposed to it's a CPU just just pulls
in a cache line is that what we're
talking about I'm not sure what you mean
oh okay I see your swing GP you gather
so again what kind of Jeep you gather
are you talking about and I am tired too
so by the way if I only do one bounce I
should not see any light on the backs of
those things right so it's what's kind
of cool is when you actually have
iterative lighting it's kind of neat
that you get some light now from those
it's not really quite right yet because
we're not doing very good shadowing or
any shadowing but convecting light
around is just good it tends to make a
nice another image
- Caleb spectral loading is something I
never heard of before can you point out
some good resources on the topic
I don't know
[Music]
so
so you might be able to search through
it this way the other thing I wonder is
does physically based rendering the book
have it in there it's pretty standard
reference on these sorts of topics and I
don't know if it actually has that in
there or not
so it's a little hard to tell just from
here but you know my hope would be that
this would have that in it this look has
a lot of you know it's a pretty good
basic reference for like I need to learn
some it's how you know physically based
rendering works I hope that it has some
stuff on spectrum but I don't know for
sure the eighth day says in the CPU it's
much more efficient to read a cache line
using in a load and not use the gather
commands is the same true of the GPU not
really so I guess what I would say is
the tricky thing about GPUs is they have
much more specific memory Swizzle
inquiry access pattern things they try
to do where they you know you can
imagine how textures they rather than
keeping like a line of pixels in a
texture that's not very good for cache
locality because they tend to fetch from
textures in little square areas right at
a time so they tend to use like a Z
pattern of some kind of Swizzle pattern
for the memory accesses and stuff like
that is not always known to you unless
you've talked to the actual GPU vendors
to find out what goes on in that respect
so to the best of my knowledge you
cannot assume that like what is a gather
on the CPU is going to be a gather on
the GPU and vice versa obviously doing
things that fetch through the memory
subsystem in a coherent way are always
probably going to be faster than ones
that don't but what is a coherent read
on the GPU is
not obvious right
[Music]
does that make does that I sorry if I
don't know if that's responsive to your
question but I guess that's the thing
that I would say is that GPUs have
highly optimized memory subsystems that
don't look like CPU memory subsystems in
internally it's not exact right it's not
like a GPU memory subsystem is exactly
the same as a CPU in all respects where
it's just like cache lines they're
linear and it's mapped directly and
there's only one way of mapping it in
blah blah blah right so I think that
it's difficult especially if you don't
have intimate knowledge of the hardware
I think it's difficult necessarily to
predict what the actual cache behavior
of the GPU is going to be at all
actually because you don't have a lot of
insight into how things are being stored
on the GPU in the first place and again
even if something appears to be linear
from how it's described or from your
perspective it says it is not
necessarily linear on the GPU itself and
the way in which the GPUs window into
its own memory causes that memory to be
organized can be quite a bit different
than what you would expect so again I
would just lean on the texture example
of a way that gather doesn't work the
way you would expect so you know you
think of a texture as being a linearly
map texture and that's how you maybe you
submitted to the GPU and whatever else
happens but in reality the GPU wants
that texture to be Swizzle dry so the
GPU wants to reorganize the texture so
that that texture is laid out in a
different pattern right I and so when we
think about how that works then you have
to think about well why does it need to
put it into a particular pattern well it
needs to put it into Pickler pattern
because of the way its memory axes
these are going to work right and so
when you think about whether something
is a gather that makes it difficult
because since you don't know how the
graphic card maybe Swizzle enough into
its memory you don't necessarily know
what is a gather and what isn't a gather
right so if you need to do a bilinear
filter on something or you need to do
your texture mapping a small area and
you're like well how coherent is this
texture mapping going to be I think it's
pretty hard to really know without
collecting some statistics or talking to
a GPU vendor really what's going on on a
CPU you kind of know to a certain extent
that the addresses are mapped linearly
things are stored the way you said that
they were stored because you wrote them
and now you're reading them you know the
size of the cache lines you know the
alignment of the cache lines and all
that stuff is very well documented
understood and that's really just not
the case on GPUs I mean I don't know for
example the GPU this machine I have no
idea how it's storing things I have no
idea what its cache line size is I have
no idea how biggest cache is I have no
information about any of that stuff we
could try to find it out but you know I
don't even know how it reserves parts of
things that are cast you know there's
all sorts of things like there's a
texture cache typically or cache unit
that pulls things in - like texture from
I mean I have no idea on any particular
card like what that looks like and once
in a while you can take a specific card
and ask a bunch of questions and get
down to like oh here's exactly how this
thing does a bunch of stuff and maybe
you care enough on a particular search
platform like and say it's a Playstation
4 or something maybe you care enough to
find all that stuff out because the
fixed platform and you want to optimize
specifically for it but you know it's
really just it's really just difficult
to sort of figure out that stuff on a
broader scale
and yet you can't really Swizzle
textures yourself really so my
understanding on that and and you know
again this could be dated but my
understanding on that is that the
problem with frizzling textures is that
every card wants textures Swizzle
differently so the way this works is
there was a standard fizzell format I
believe that was introduced for DirectX
maybe or some kind of standard swittel
thing there's like a nominal attempt at
it and I believe all cards have to
accept data swiveled in that format but
that may not be the format that's
fastest for the card so what actually
happens is every card has a different
memory subsystem typically and that
memory subsystem is based on what type
of memory and memory boss's stuff that
got set up and so my understanding and
this is fuzzy because again I don't work
with this stuff very much is it Nvidia
cards for the most part at least the
higher end ones I believe have memory
subsystems that can do the Swizzle in
the memory subsystem so they can
actually accept textures that don't have
to be Swizzle in a particular Swizzle
format because they have the ability to
Swizzle the memory controller I think do
not quote me on this again this is way
out of my area of expertise AMD cards
however because they are often designed
to target the lower end of the market
they have specific swivel patterns that
the memory controller can do and you
have to be Quizzle in one of those
formats
you can't pick an arbitrary Swizzle
format and expect it to work
it has to be the one that's whatever
that memory controller does it's
different depending on the card SKU so
my recollection is that it's actually
kind of a nightmare
in that right now you really would need
something like a query call that says
hey card what's the algorithm for
Swizzle in your thing and somehow that
would have to be represented back to you
and then you would have to Swizzle into
that format so it's not the case that
there's just one Swizzle format and you
could just store all your textures
prease whistled in that format and
upload them without having to go through
a Swizzle that is not the case as far as
I know you pretty much have to have the
car it beats whistled to the cards
format and only the card can really do
that and there is no way to query it
however I also was under the
understanding that Nvidia had some kind
of stuff on there that allowed you to
upload flat textures or Swizzle din
whatever format you want textures and it
could adapt I thought there was
something to that effect where the
memory controller could Swizzle the
addresses in that way but that's just my
vague understanding and I could be very
wrong about that
his handmade country still at the start
of 2018 I have not I don't know that
there's going to be a Sam VidCon 2018
I'm very much not sure what's going to
be happening in terms of conferences
unless somebody else is hosting
conferences I know there was some talk
of people wanted to do one in Europe or
something like that so I'm not sure but
I have not put anything out about that
certainly Brian asked see tre
improvement would you be so kind as to
give a suggestion of how you tackle
saving the day number do you prefer temp
files just keep it simple like how you
read settings i betray should I look at
how you save State look and see time you
can try the tackle on alternative this
week before I do need to become more
confident in reading writing to files so
I mean I would say that it probably
doesn't matter very much how it's done
but yes since there's a settings file
already I would say probably just
rewrite the settings file and put the
day number in there I don't really
remember what the format of the settings
file is in the C tray because it's been
a long time since I've looked at that
but yeah it looks like you could just
you could just pick the day number down
at the bottom right and then when you
just read and write this file so you
read it in and every time you increment
the day number you just save it back out
again right
yeah I mean I think that's a reason I
don't know that making it in any file is
a very good idea necessarily it's not
necessarily a bad idea since I guess
since C tre is kind of only a Windows
program anyway there's no you know it's
there's hardly any platform knobs very
part of it almost all of it is like
talking is talking to windows to get
those transparent windows to just
transparent overlays to appear so it's
not like there's any concern about it
having to be happened to be
cross-platform or anything like that
all right so if you prefer it to be in
any file yet but you can that's totally
fine as well
so I would I would say that's fine I I
don't I don't really think it needs to
be changed from that right so what
you've got in there now seems reasonable
to me
I haven't tried it obviously but
assuming that works okay it should be
fine
and so is it possible to mode change
monitor frequency nowadays so I always
try to get my game loop to run at 60
Hertz
yes and no so if you have a one of those
fancy monitors for gaming so that has
like do you think or one of those things
in then yes you can set it to whatever
refresh rate you want really if you just
have a regular monitor than no regular
monitors typically have a refresh rate
that is you know sort of prescribed
ahead of time like you know it's got
some set of refresh rates it can do and
I don't think you can just pick an
arbitrary one if it doesn't support
sixty Hertz you can't set it to 60 Hertz
right now most monitors these days would
support 60 Hertz so I would suspect that
if your goal is to just set the loop to
run at 60 Hertz
most of the time you probably could get
that mode that's not going to be super
unusual I don't think if however you
wanted your game to run it 45 Hertz all
the time that's the one where you're in
trouble right running at 45 Hertz all
the time will work just fine on a do you
think but it's not going to fly on a
standard monitor probably doesn't have a
mode that supports 45 for its update so
and I believe that mostly just that it's
really just the that the
controller on the monitor to the best of
my knowledge there's no such thing
really as a LCD refresh rate per se as
far as I know LCDs are more or less only
about a maximum rate like you can only
change them at a certain maximum
frequency but there's not like a oh I
built this LCD circuit and it can only
do 60 Hertz so I'm pretty sure most of
the time that limitation of it only
having certain refresh rates is because
the controller that's on the monitor
only recognizes those rates and not
because you couldn't have had the rate
be arbitrary which is what I think G sig
monitors typically are teasing monitors
are just a regular monitor that just
happens to have the controller replaced
with one that doesn't arbitrarily say
you can only have these refresh rates
teach you a question from Brian as an
exercise I would like to investigate the
cost of just bringing the overlays to
the top and checking first if you
overlays need to be brought forward what
should I look for should I profile the
calls should I run it continuously to
see if I get error cases I realize this
may not be the best thing to do as an
example but it was something I struggled
with I would say that I would say that
the problem is not a performance problem
so the reason I recommended checking
first is not because of performance what
I was concerned about is that whenever
you change the Z order of the windows on
the screen you run the risk of
triggering things in Windows that may
produce unwanted results so for example
you know you may end up bringing the
taskbar to the front you may end up
causing an OpenGL window to lose its
ability to do its vsync you may end up
causing you know who knows what right
and so mostly what I was concerned about
there was not poking Windows in a bad
way I don't know that there's really a
significant performance difference in
either case I don't even know whether
Windows is smart enough it might be that
Windows is smart enough to know to just
not change do any of those things if you
during this clause but that was really
the part that I was concerned about I
was concerned about the side effects
that might occur from constantly calling
those functions not the performance so
that is why I thought it was safer to
only change it if it actually needed to
be changed and not just constantly just
spam windows with bring to front
alright oops
I did not mean to close that and to
close that let's try that one more time
what is happening here all right thank
you everyone for joining me for lips o -
handmade here it's that a pleasure
coating with you as always if you would
like to follow along a series at home
you can always appear to the game on
handmade reorg and it comes to the
source code she gets all along at home
we also have a forum site go to July ask
questions a patreon page you can use
wasp or our video series a schedule Bob
between schedules you if you want to
catch us live which as you can see is
going to be in just twenty one short
hours from now and an episode guide you
can go to if you want to catch up on old
elements of the series we will be back
here tomorrow same time same place if
you'd like to see us try to push that
letting now that we've got some of those
bugs out we can try to get some higher
quality in which will be nice as well I
hope to be back here for that until then
have fun programming and I'll see
everyone on the Internet take it easy
everybody