this is sort of a little bit of a
personal session for me because I
everyone out there probably you know
some people are a lot younger than I am
obviously and are kind of getting into
the game industry but you know I can
remember when I first started working on
games when I was very little
obviously there were a bunch of things
that were kind of formative in like my
experience of making games and you know
being just a kid who is at home you know
typing away on the home computer and
whatever I kind of think back to like
what inspired me to do stuff or what
were the games I played there like I
really want to make that and by far the
one that like comes to mind for me the
most was Secret of Monkey Island and
there's this is true for a number of
reasons
one of the reasons obviously is just
because at that time I mean I think
there's many many people who consider
that like one of the defining games of
that time in gaming but there was also
the fact that as somebody who sort of
knew a little programming but was pretty
bad at it looking at that game and
looking at the other games that were in
its category at that time I could
actually see the difference in
craftsmanship on that one like even at
that time because I remember you know
right out of the box these things would
would ship and they would be like you
know The Secret of Monkey Island game
would be like this really fast fluid
experience and everything seemed to work
great and you would see like a year
later or something you'd play a similar
game there and you try to sing like
click to walk and it would wait a while
and then the guy would kind of do this
really weird path that didn't look
anything right and that's like even at
that time I was kind of like well like
this this is so much better than this
and I don't even know why and I'm not
sure I could do this but this is who I'd
want to be right like I want to be the
guy who makes Secret Monkey Island not
the guy who makes this other game right
and so when I was putting together the
the people who I most wanted to have
here my mind immediately went to that
and I was thinking like if if Ron wants
to come talk that would be like the
coolest thing ever and I was kind of on
the fence about it because I'm like well
I don't know like maybe he doesn't want
to talk about sort of stuff anymore
maybe he's not that interested in engine
program anymore and so I go look at what
he's doing and he's actually writing he
said because I thought that will be
parked like oh maybe he's like managing
that process he's like he's actually
writing a new
adventure games system from scratch
himself now right and so I was like this
is perfect so I can't wait to ask him
the questions that I've got here and
hear what he has to say so please join
me in welcoming one of my gaming heroes
so I have I have something just to prove
that I'm not making this story up for
crowd effect I have here in original
secret of monkey island mouse pad that
you gave me the first time I went to
visit you like had it in your office yes
I had a stack of those I have kept it
and my actual secret of monkey island to
box which for some reason I still kept
this as well it even has the original
DRM people right here a decoder we when
was the last time you saw a game that
easy to decoder wheeler right they don't
make them like they used to so well back
then DRM was fun wasn't it wasn't just
something that was annoying it was
something that actually had fun with
they sort of thought about that process
I guess a little bit more how can we
make this something that's not so so
onerous I guess where's now these are
like look you're just going to deal with
it there's nothing and you don't
actually own it you're just licensed
whom you read it yeah I would not be
able to bring this today what anyway
you'd be violating several trademarks
well okay that's kind of scary I
probably shouldn't ask myself question
cuz I'll just get depressed but I want
to start out by just saying can you take
us back just a little bit to you know to
sort of start things off I really want
to know about so maniac mansion was not
a game I ever had right I mean as a kid
you know I didn't actually have all you
know every game or anything like
nowadays it's kind of crazy when you're
adult you have money you can just get if
you want to see what maniac can actually
just get it but back then you know you
only had certain games so I never
actually got to play maniac mansion but
that was kind of the start of the whole
you know that's the whole adventure game
sort of like I want to say the sort of
the genre that you pioneered like that
way of looking click games playing click
games and so could you take us back to
sort of like right before that how does
this start happening like you know what
what was your experience at that time
why did you look at that and you know as
say I want to start making something
like this what you know and what was
your sort of like skills at the time
that made you think like I can you know
I can do this better or I want to go
do this thing so can you just give a
center stage yeah well I was hired at
Lucasfilm to to do porting I they they
had built some games on the atari 800
and they needed someone to pour it into
the commodore 64 that was primarily what
I did which Commodore suit before
programming so I was hired to do port
work and I got there and I became
friends with Gary Winnick who was an
artist at for the only artist at the
time it was just one yeah Gary
he did all the art for all the games it
was the only artist there and so he and
I became really good friends and you
eventually became roommates and we you
know shared a place together and we you
know did we wanted to make a game man
and at the time I kind of felt like
because I was a contractor at the time I
wasn't an employee and and you know I
felt like you know I want to get a
full-time job here and yeah I was
working at Lucasville right with Star
Wars and George Lucas and I know all
this stuff is like I don't want to leave
here and so I thought well you know
maybe if I actually you know pitch a
game and the game gets done then I'll
get hired out in full time and that
would be good so Gary and I started
talking about you know pitching a game
and we had this idea for this strange
kind of you know comedy horror game with
this weird family and you know we talked
about all sorts of ideas and we had like
no idea what the game was right we just
had we had a bunch of funny stuff we had
funny ideas and that was all that we
really had okay and and I think you know
if I look back through my entire career
I think the thing that drives me
creatively the most is fear you know
that's the second time submission today
and and it's and it's like when I get
like terrified of something it's like
all these creative gears kick in and so
I was I was looking at all these great
ideas that Gary and I had and I had no
idea what this game was and I was just
it was it I was afraid you know it's
like this fear was kicking in and we
Christmas break came when we took we we
went on break and I went down the
to LA where my aunt and uncle live and
my eight-year-old cousin was there and
he had just gotten a you know candy
computer okay and he was playing King's
Quest okay I had never seen King's Quest
before right I played text adventures
you know and all that but I never seen
kinks was before and I watched him play
this thing and it's just everything just
fell into place it's like this is what
maniac manager needs to be it's it's an
adventure game so I came back after
Christmas just all energized and that's
when we just turned the whole thing into
an adventure game and so King's Quest
obviously looks quite a bit different
than maniac mansion because it's kind of
you drive the character around it's got
a text parser you know you type in kind
of the old infocomm style so it's quite
a different game so when you came back
having seen King's Quest it didn't go
like oh we'll just mix King's Quest and
we'll swap in our funny ideas and that's
the game we're going to make so how do
we get from I saw King's Quest which is
actually pretty different to Jimmy to
maniac mansion like what did that cost
to start looking like what was it did
you start making a king of quest clone
right away and then start deviating if I
might or did you iterate on it and sort
of like as a discussion first before you
start make anything of what how did that
happen the big thing was that I had
played a lot of text adventures and I
liked text adventures but I really did
hate the parsers because I felt like I
was always playing this game which I
called second-guess the parser okay is
that I knew what this thing was right
but but did the game call it a bush was
right plant or a tree I guess since
we're talking about trees yeah you know
what what was this thing and you know
maybe the designer had put in a bunch of
synonyms or something but maybe they
didn't get the synonyms I wanted and so
I said you know it's like I can see this
stuff I just want to touch it
I just want to click it I want to say
that's the thing I wanna I want
interact with and so that's kind of
where getting rid of the parser came
from you know it's like you know what we
should just get rid of the parser the
fact is that you know even sophisticated
adventure games probably only use like
five or six verbs anyway yeah right
there are all the synonyms for stuff so
we kind of went through we picked out
the verbs that we thought would be
useful in those we just put them right
on the screen and so you just click on
the verb and you click on the object and
that was kind of where the whole you
know point-and-click thing came from
well so how did you sort of do that
process though because you know was that
something that you thought of before you
started programming the game or is that
something that you sort of like did you
start making a parser and then go wait a
minute we could do this or did you was
this just like you came back from King's
Quest and we're talking to Gary and you
guys just kind of figured this out
before you even like started really like
what was that we knew we were dumping
the parser and we knew we were going to
the verb verb etre before I start
approach so that was just already in
your head from infocomm days it just
kind of clicked were you talking about
like we don't want to do that and and
Lucasfilm had done a game previously
called a base on the movie labyrinth and
they had done kind of a verb interface
it was like the spinning wheel thing
okay you know it was it was it was very
clunky and it was cumbersome but you
know that was that was a leaping off
point for us okay so we didn't come from
absolutely nothing it kind of came a
little bit from the labyrinth stuff and
so it was clear enough from that it's
like yes could work if we just do it a
little bit let's just refine it and
simplify it and and this will just be a
much better way for people to interact
with adventure games so now you've got
this sort of idea you're like okay we've
got the idea sort of for the story and
the sort of things that we want to have
happen and we kind of know that we're
gonna do like this verb interface sort
of thing where you click on stuff but
there's still a tremendous amount of
like you know what is how do we build a
game like this right because you're my
understanding there is you're coming at
it never having a look you didn't work
on King's Quest you don't know what the
internals of King's Quest look like hand
unlike nowadays you know a game like
King's Quest or something would be
trivial to write or something like this
back then you're talking about like you
know it's cutting but things are cutting
edge just having sprites move on a
screen it's like a whole thing so hip
pixels are cutting
yeah pixels are cutting-edge right and
so what's your process now how do you
sit down and set apart in this problem I
guess we can maybe also ask a little bit
like how did you get the game prove it
you work on a spare time what happened
there like like I guess we should say
before we start out you know Lucasfilm
back then look at some games it was a
very magical place in some ways right
there was there were but by the time
that we had pitched maniac mansion they
were like 15 people okay so it was very
very small and you know I think we we
were very lucky because I don't think
George Lucas knew he had a games
division and so right we had all this
amazing autonomy to do you know whatever
we really wanted to do and there was
really no official approval process the
way it work was you wrote you know
little you know one two three play to
design documents and we just passed him
around on paper and everybody took notes
and then things just kind of bubbled up
until everybody said hey this is really
interesting and then they kind of became
projects at that point so it's sort of
like an elaborate of buy-in sort of a
thing which like if everyone sort of
starts to think that this this paper is
one we should go with then we will yeah
exactly so there was no there was no
real pitch to the whole thing and so did
you start making the game before that or
did you did you start by making that
document go like you and Gary go okay
we're gonna start trying to pitch it
internally was that the first step then
yeah I was floating that design document
around and getting support for it which
is you know where the the verb interface
came from was kind of you making that da
service yeah but that was I mean that
was probably like maybe a two-month of
Tomb of the process of pitching that
around and then you know in in typical
fashion from a couple of guys that have
no idea what they're doing we just
jumped right into it Gary just started
drawing art and I just started writing
code and we had no idea where we were
going with stuff and you know and and I
think you know that's really kind of
where the whole scum system came from
the adventure game system because you
know we took this path where I was just
gonna write this whole game and 6502
assembly
right I mean how hard can that be oh
alright so I just I just started kind of
doing that and you know again that that
fear kicked in is I realize I've been
just totally in over my head with this
there's no way we're gonna be able to
get this done which was we're doing you
know a scripting language in an
interpreted language you know kind of
came from all of that okay so that
actually sets up like perfectly the
stuff I want to talk about a
professional give you a nice segue so
looking at that process right you sit
down and you're kind of going like okay
we've got to start with some basic stuff
we got to put some sprites on the screen
and presumably like LucasArts maybe
already have some stuff you said here I
could start drawing art for it
immediately presumably there's some kind
of pixel editing thing you can do or
whatever so he's kind of making some
assets and you maybe you're getting some
stuff on the screen at what point so
what it what started like how do you sit
down and start that process again it's
the part I'm kind of interested in is
you know nowadays if I said I need to
sit down and make a point click
adventure game I know what that is and I
know exactly how it's gonna run so I can
sit down and debate a bunch of designers
in my head or something that's or start
typing or whatever and maybe follow
John's approach and say I'll just write
the simplest thing but in this case we
don't even know what it is yet at all
it's a new job so what literally like if
you can remember I know this is kind of
a weird part developing process I can't
even remember stuff I wrote in stream
last week so I realized her but what do
you actually start sit down and start
with like what was the thing that we
just started doing can you give us any
insight because I'm really clear well I
knew that the structure of the game was
gonna kind of be based on these rooms we
call them rooms and objects ok those are
the two things rooms objects and the
actors those are the three things that
made it out so I kind of knew that I had
to do that I knew that objects had to
appear in rooms I knew I needed some
system to be able to tag objects so when
you touch them with the cursor and you
know all that kind of stuff I knew I
knew that stuff you know in terms of the
language itself you know I really didn't
have idea what the language was gonna be
I mean I've kind of heard about lists
and I guess the people were using lists
for AI stuff and okay
I should probably use lists okay okay so
you know my language would looked very
Lisp like with lots of you know
parentheses and all that stuff on it and
I I just I very quickly just ditched all
that okay and I went to something that
was a little more see like okay for like
curly braces and stuff that was I think
a little more saner well how did you
make the decision so because this is
actually a mystery part too so when you
start working and you start coding up
the actors that sort of thing that's
sort of part of it I guess you could
start in 6502 right you could just start
making the hard coded versions but I
guess is what you're saying you you
actually started hard coding them
initially how did you first come to you
said fear essentially how did you first
make that leap of like you know what if
I had an interpreted thing here this
would work because that's not again now
that might be an obvious issue because
maybe you have awareness of all these
things but at that time that is not an
obvious thing to think of necessarily
had you seen other games do this did you
have some experience in the past that
made you think this would be a good idea
like how did that thought come in yeah
that came from a guy named chip
Morningstar and he works at Lucasfilm
and he and another person of Lucas own
name Randy farmer they they went on to
create habitat which is probably the
world's first graphical MMO I remember
that and I mean chip was just like an
uber smart guy okay and you know I was
just kind of talking to him about the
whole problem and he just kind of said a
whining you do a scripting language
okay just something you threaten why
don't you do a scripting language so he
just knew about it from some other
situation yeah I mean you know at the
time he infocomm had a script yes right
I mean they didn't code their stuff and
you know Sierra had one is yeah so I
mean it wasn't something that was
totally and right for but you know
getting a whole you know compiled
scripting language working on a
Commodore 64
you know there's 64 K of memory FS
machine right and so that was you know
that that was something that went really
on a Commodore you know that I think
that was the leap I had to make was
building a whole interpreted language
that ran on this little 64 K machine
you know I kind of had to convince
myself a little bit that that was a good
idea yeah well and so in deciding to
take that step was really what you're
thinking there's like okay if we had a
scripting language it will be easier for
me to script or was that more of a
decision like if we had a scripting
language other people could start
tweaking a lot which because later on it
probably that that thing changed but a
tin maniac mansion what was that yeah in
in maniac mansion you know I was very
idealistic okay at the time and I you
know I kind of thought you know I'm
gonna build this scripting language
that's so natural you don't even have to
be a programmer right okay that I can
hire like writers right and they can
come and they can use my scripting
language and they can build these games
because this thing is just so brilliant
you know that it's it's not even like
programs they just describe the game so
so I mean that was kind of my initial
thing and and if you look at the scum
language you know the commands in it are
very verbose because I was trying to
make things be very clear about about
what was happening you kind of want to
look very English like yeah exactly you
know and so a lot of the commands in the
language are kind of like that but I
mean at some level you you just can't
get over the fact that whoever is doing
this needs to understand basic logic
they have to understand you know if if
then statements and all of this stuff
that goes on and there's just no way
around that yeah kind of stuff so you
know the language could be kind of
verbose and you know English like and
very freeform in its structure you know
you didn't you didn't pass a bunch of
anonymous parameters to functions you
know instead you said actor act and then
you could just put costume this and just
you know run on all of your stuff across
it so that's why it was it was a kind of
a verbose language and it didn't look
very programmer now you're gonna make
this scripting language for the game
obviously you know nowadays it's like oh
well you know we're gonna type the
script in the script window and then
the games running and we'll just alt tab
between them or they're on the same
screen and my multi-monitor right there
but we're talking about a Commodore 64
the situation here so how does that like
what what did that process of look at
the time to because now you're like okay
how are people making these scripts and
how does the turnaround time look like
and I think like again it may not be
that relevant to the to the programming
of it so much but it's kind of
interesting just to think back about how
ago screen there was how did that
process go what was that like at the
time well we we had a we had a wonderful
development environment and the the
Lucasfilm games group was was kind of
spun off or a part of the Lucasfilm
computer division which later changed
their name to Pixar ok so there's all
those people you know they all kind of
worked in our group and so we had these
like really really smart people and you
know Lucasfilm the hi entire company ran
on these big mainframe
you know fax machines you know uniques
machines and everything and one of the
things they did was they they built
these little things that literally
plugged my Commodore 64 into the backs
UNIX machine really I would plug the
thing in and then I worked on a UNIX
terminal on my desk and I had complete
control of the Commodore 64 I could
pause it I could download stuff to it I
could upload stuff from it so I never
programmed on the Commodore 64 it was
all done on these big UNIX machines I
which was very useful because scum was a
compiled like yes and so the compiler
ran on the UNIX machines it didn't run
on the commodore 64 so the whole
compiler and the art pipeline and all
that stuff just happened on the UNIX
machines and then we just download
everything in the Commodore 64 it was
nice because we could do a lot of hot
loading stuff right we could just run
things down to the machine you know
while I was running and this was you
know in nineteen eighties yeah right and
I was very very very different years a
lot like it is today but very very
than what was happening back then yeah
that's actually incredible so does that
mean that somebody who was working on a
particular room for the game could
literally have a UNIX thing open modify
some scripts and in a relatively short
period of time see the result almost
instantly
that's insane so that is insane yeah
because we would just we would just push
the script down and the other thing
about the scum system was you know the
comment of 6040 at 64 K a memory right
but a lot of that was taking up with the
program yeah and you know I actually had
only 19 K of memory free for all the
assets in the game okay and so you know
what I what I had done was I wrote
actually chip and written it because he
was starting to work on habitat at that
okay so he wrote this wonderful memory
management system where you know all the
assets in the game were kept on this
little heap okay and the system was
smart enough to understand that okay
this stuff's old no one's using it flush
it out and if I bring in new stuff just
spool the stuff out of memory while the
new stuff is brought in right that's not
a Commodore 64 right that all this stuff
is happening so you know the whole game
is just kind of you know almost
open-world continuously put all the
stuff that just spooled in from the
disks okay so I've made the debugging
very easy on the from the UNIX theme
because we had all these assets whether
they were art or scripts we could just
pump a new one down to the heap and it
would just it would just work right
there on the thing so it was a very very
quick development so you literally on
the Commodore 64 running on the
Commodore 64 had hot loadable assets yes
during without restart yes it just keeps
running and you could swap like the guy
with a new bitmap yeah that's that's
kind of crazy
I don't even know all right I have
trouble getting networking today yeah we
did have to recut it enter the room you
were in right so it wasn't just magical
we had to do a quick reload I'll give
that yeah Wow okay well so I guess
scripting language wise how did you
approach that problem I guess I should
keep track of time because that's kind
of wanted to talk about two things it
looks like we have plenty so we're good
so tell me a little bit about how you
approach the scripting language problem
because like you said if that was
something that sort of someone said hey
why don't you do a scripting language
like oh maybe that's a good idea how did
you know I mean even how to build such a
thing right did you have some experience
of scripting languages did you let go
get learn scripting there's just in 2031
days or whatever it is I'm sure there
was a popular book at the time like did
you like how do you even know how to
build one because you know again back
then we take it for granted now that if
I want to learn how to type it into
Google how do I build a scripting
language and there's some ones to toriel
that's not the case so what did that
look like well that looked like a couple
of things when you know before I got my
job at Lucasfilm back when I was in I
guess high school I got a Commodore 64
ok so that was that was you know I'd
learned programming on the Commodore
pets and some other stuff but the
Commodore 64 I got one of those and I
just thought this was you know an
amazing device but the one problem I had
with a Commodore 64 is it had really
great graphics had wonderful you know
sid chip for doing audio none of that
was accessible from basic right a bit of
it right right if you want to access
that stuff you did like peek and poke
commands yeah you know to hit the memory
and they're super super cumbersome yeah
and you know I thought will really be
nice if there was actually a basic
language on the Commodore 64 that could
take advantage of all these graphics
right and one of the things I realized
when is hacking around with the machine
is there's there's like 20 K of wrong in
the Commodore 64 where the basic
interpreter sets but there's 64 K of RAM
so you could you bank out the ROM and
then you have a 64 K of RAM to put play
with like if you don't need the basic
interpreter okay so basically normally
the 64 K when the machine starts
the 20k of Rahm actually gets moved into
the 64k of memory
no the ROM actually sits right above it
I've been seeing address okay but what I
kind of realized was that if I read a
bite out of the wrong and then I wrote
it back to the wrong it actually wrote
to the RAM underneath so what I did was
I went through and I copied all of the
basic ROM writing it right back out to
itself banked out the wrong now I had
the entire basic interpreter I see Ram
and you can modify and so I started
playing with it and I built this whole
extension to the basic language called
graphics basic okay and they'd added
sprite commands and line commands and
sound commands and I think I think it's
kind of where my love of languages yeah
and so when I started doing the scum
stuff I kind of had this whole
experience with with graphics basic you
know of what a language looks like and
how you know I understood how basic
interpreted the language because they'd
hacked into the whole thing and figured
it all out so when I was working on this
gum system I kind of I knew you know
what it was like to go through in the
you interpret op codes and all that kind
of stuff that I had already done okay so
basically your experience with with
essentially disassembling basic yes we
would call which I did I
I printed out the entire basic wrong
okay I remember sitting on my bedroom
floor with these giant printouts and a
pencil you know writing comments because
I mean there wasn't it was not there
were there were no comments right it was
just assembly and so from that you
learned how they had done their
interpreter and so now you knew here's
how I can make it interpret right that's
amazing yes okay
okay so you you sit down to make the
scum version of the interpreter and
you're just like okay so I'm kind of get
a patterned after what I learned from
basic and we're gonna you know we have
the UNIX terminals so we're going to
make the stuff that compiles down how
you know how long does that take to get
working like how when does that start to
come online like how much your process
was that uh you know that that took
quite a while you know I was saying it
it probably took me about a year okay
from the point that we started working
on it so we had a system that we were
actually building a game in and you know
I I mean I know this isn't actually true
but it feels like I almost got fired
okay you know I definitely remember
being called into my boss's office and
having a talk okay
about how long maniac mansion was taking
and is we're gonna turn into something
so it was definitely taking a long time
and I was I mean that was just pure
inexperience you know at building we
were trying to build well sure and it's
very ambitious for the time it sounds
like the hooking it up to a fax machine
so I want to take just before I move on
because I want to talk a little bit
about what you're doing now as well and
so I wanted to ask one other question
kind of to set that up a little bit
which is that one of the things that I
mentioned kind of in the introduction as
well is that one thing I noticed about
the the Lucas arts games kind of right
from the very beginning so I like I said
didn't ever have a chance to maniac
mansion but certainly in Secret of
Monkey Island and in everything that
sort of came at RIT until I don't know
maybe something like grim fandago where
they went back to maybe like direct
control I felt like the click to move
implementation in those games was much
better than everyone else's click to
move in for an implication maybe that's
a complete misinterpretation of what I
saw but you're right
but I wanted to ask about that problem
specifically so at some point and I
guess I don't know what this point was
but at some point you decided I don't
want to drive this guy around I want to
just be able to click to move him now
was that's when you decided early on or
late on that was early on that was a
part of the whole point click interface
was we just okay to touch everything we
didn't have a mouse the Commodore 64 was
a choices a joystick
but you know we knew we wanted to move
the cursor around and everything was
just clicking looking screens you click
to walk okay so that original design
document either includes or when we were
making it we already had thought of we
don't really want you to drive the sky
we wanted to click OK which I guess
makes sense because if I already have to
be clicking on the menu things what am i
driving with like ant and so it's kind
of forces the issue a muster so you have
to approach this problem now it's like
okay this is actually quite different
than basically anything that I see at
games at that time all other games are
pretty much direct control whether it's
an arcade game or a Sierra game you're
driving the guy around so how did you
approach that problem initially was it a
big deal for you or was something just
did like what what was the mindset there
and how did that go well the issue is
obviously pathfinding yeah is I you know
I wanted I wanted to be able to click
anywhere on the screen and I wanted the
character to figure out how to get there
yes if it was possible for the character
to walk from point A to point B and he
had to walk around the table and between
some chairs and you know around the lamp
I wanted him to do that
right I didn't want him to walk in a
straight line and get stuck
yeah against the dining room table ready
walk around the table so that became you
know a you know a pathfinding issue and
you know I don't I don't exactly
remember kind of the genesis of you know
how how it all came about but we used
the system which was which we called WAP
boxes ok and and what it was was you
know if you think about the room yeah no
it's it's kind of a flat but think about
the floor then and I I would just put
these boxes and they were literally
squares ok because we didn't have the
CPU power to even have angled lines and
figure out you know the intersection
some kind of rectangle so they were
boxes you know the lock boxes and I
would just you would just I would just
them on the floor as many of them as I
needed and you know make sure that there
was an overlap you know on the lines
okay so all of the rectangles are
slightly overlapping is that what you
mean they're they share a pixel in
common so exactly overlap they they they
escalate at this point if you okay all
right okay yeah and then and so you have
all these boxes that litter the floor
about where you can walk now the hard
part is well how do you pass right right
and today I mean you just don't worry
right you do some a star thing you know
whatever it is but you just didn't have
the CPU on a wait 0.8 you know megahertz
and I was 6502 so you know that the idea
that he came up with is you just do a
lot of pre-processing and and so I had
all the boxes there was like box 1 2 3 4
5 6 ok and I had this two-dimensional
grid and you you look at the box you
were in so you were in box 1 okay you
wanted to go to box 8 okay so you just
you look up in the grid
you know box 1 I want to go to box 8 and
that number right there was the next box
you want to walk into ok so and so then
and I knew those connected they had to
right so then it was very easy to find
the connecting line and I would just
walk to the center point of the X Box
so that's like Dijkstra's algorithm did
you know that at the dawn so you fall on
just figured it out yourself
and worse than that in that little
matrix yeah that was something that we
we had to build by hand ok we didn't
that wasn't pre-processed we'd lay down
all the boxes usually we went to the
text editor and we lay out that little
grid of where you could go so it was it
was kind of a a cumbersome process to
set up walk boxes but end result in the
game yeah is instant so basically you
would click somewhere it would no that's
in well first of all it would just look
to see through all the boxes if in any
of these box it's not in the box you're
not going to go there or do try to go as
far close as it could he tried to do he
tried to cope classical so how did that
work do you find the closest box it was
it was a bit it was a vertical line ok
so it basically said like believe
searching until we
so I find a box there and then I
basically set some global you know not
global but some state for this actor
that's like this actress trying to go to
box blah so every time his box you know
every time I update his movement I go
what box is he in
figure out the direction to the next box
and go well how does that how are you
encoding stuff like that like what
direction go from box to box it was
really just straight lines okay and you
know you had to be clear careful in your
boxes because I knew that what what the
actor was going to do was go from the
point they were standing to the midpoint
of where the two boxes intersected and
so I just kind of had to make sure I
mean sometimes you know we'd have to put
a couple of extra boxes just to make it
a little bit you know feel right but it
was I mean it was pretty brain-dead you
know what I was trying to do that's well
so that's like a mystery that I've
wanted to know for I guess what 30 years
now thank you very much
yeah it became a little more
sophisticated you know by the time
Monkey Island rolled around we could do
trapezoids okay so the truck just to
make less boxes so yeah so we could do
like trapezoids it's slowly evolved so
let's jump forward now to thimble we'd
park right and you're going to this is
the only question I think that I've
asked you beforehand so I kind of a
little bit know the first answer but
everything else I don't know so you're
gonna make another adventure game and
obviously like I mean to to drastically
exaggerate if you wanted to you could
literally go get someone's
reimplementation of your thing which is
probably in the public domain now some
scummvm you could use so when you sat
down to make a new adventure game in
like what it was 2014 or 2013 we've
worked in December last year December
last year okay so so 2014 you're like
I'm gonna make a new one mmm how did
that decisions like hot what was the
motivator for that decision
the motivator was again it was Gary
Winnick you know he when I were just
talking one day about adventure games
and and we're talking about modern
adventure games you know versus kind of
the old classic point-and-click games
and it really kind of you know it felt
to me that adventure games have lost
that charm okay
they had back there okay and I really
wasn't sure why they had but if it just
felt like they kind of lost that charm
until Gary and I were talking about you
know what what that was you know maybe
it was just our innocence of the time
yeah it was that it was a brand new
genre and it was just magical yes
there's not anymore
we just when you said that charm you
don't really even know what i'd loveo
said you're just like i felt like there
was a charm here and that term is
definitely gone yeah I have no idea what
that is and you know we were just kind
of talking about that and we didn't
really know what it was and you know we
started talking about what we should
just make a new one yeah we should make
one exactly like we made them back then
with the same sensibilities the same you
know kind of art style everything and
just see if we could capture that truth
or maybe that charm was it has just been
lost to time yeah you know in some way
and you know so one thing led to another
and we decided to do a Kickstarter for
it okay you know Kickstarter is kind of
based on nostalgia tend to do very well
yes you know so so you know we figured
well we've got kind of a perfect yeah
opportunity to do this so yeah we did we
just did a Kickstarter on it which was
successful and we really have approached
the game very much as let's just pretend
we were back in 1987 and we're making a
point and clicking okay let's just use
all the same you know ideas that we had
back then and see if we can somehow you
know we capture that that charm in kind
of the way we design and the way we
build it the way we kind of think about
the game and so building a new system
for it is kind of part of that whole
mentality would that be an accurate
statement meaning like we want to create
a new VM for example because that's what
we did and we're going to do that again
it wasn't specifically that I mean I did
spend a little time looking at current
adventure gaming guys to see if any of
them would do what I
and I very quickly discarded that okay
and I think I think most of it is I mean
I love building game engines and I mean
I kind of think in some ways just you
know when I design a game it's really
just an excuse to build a game engine
that's that's all it really is right and
so you know I think a part of that kind
of recapturing everything was you know I
you know it's like what we'd kind of
promised to the Kickstarter backers was
you know they can relive playing a
classic adventures again kind of like
you know that there was this game we
made back in 1987 they've just been
discovered right that they can relive it
but but I think in a lot of ways it was
more is more about us not to relive
making it the the classic game again and
you know I do love making you know game
engines and adventure game images and
that kind of stuff so so that that
became a very enjoyable part of the
whole process for me and so when you
started building you know this this
engine from for the new game what like
and I guess it's a little bit difficult
like I said you know I want to make sure
I don't go too far over time or anything
but like approaching that obviously
there's a bunch of stuff that gets
learned before this the I'm sorry after
the stuff of maniac mansion right
because you've got you went through your
secret my key and secret Macallan to it
and obviously there's other people also
doing games like you know fate of
Atlantis or something that are using
your system so but the system itself is
kind of growing and evolving so
obviously what you just described and
you know like you said triangular walk
boxes or sorry trapezoidal lock boxes
etcetera etcetera basically like you
know from wherever that sort of ended in
your wherever your thinking process
ended and I guess maybe a humongous you
maybe would have revisited a bunch of
design ideas for internals there from
that starting out now or is what you're
building similar to the last thing you
built that say humungous or something I
don't know if that's the most current if
that was like the most current
architectural thinking that you've done
the problem or whatever how similar is
it would you say like how much is the
same and how much of its different like
what's what's the give me
little ideas it's it's fairly similar
okay you know I wanted you know I wanted
the structure of the language to feel a
lot like you know the structure okay
this gum system had okay rooms are laid
out and objects were laid out and
objects had verbs and the way that the
code for the verbs was embedded in the
objects all that stuff I you know I felt
would work really well for adventure
game so I I definitely replicated you
know all of that in the new system so
I'm interested in one thing you said
there the code for the verbs is embedded
in the object so that means that when
someone's designing something they
design the I guess unpack that so don't
know yet it's like well if you look at
the code right you you would you would
you know object and then you define an
object object a front door okay
curly brace yeah and then you'd have you
know the name of the object and flags
for the object and yeah variables for
the object then inside of that you would
then have a statement that says verb
open okay curly brace and a bunch of
code and a close brace so that was the
code that got run when you opened the
object okay that code got run and you
know that that just always kind of made
a lot of sense to me
so closes structure it's sort of it's
its own it's like a literal
object-oriented programming like we
literally have objects and they
literally do encode the things they can
do in reality in this game right if that
makes sense yeah okay and so that's kind
of just the the general idea when the
designer script or whoever's coming in
to do this particular presentation they
think in terms of objects more in
isolation in that way and is that so
that you can make multiple is that is is
it the standard maybe object-oriented I
guess approach there where it's like the
idea is that I can just code one door
and and stamp them down or like why why
do you like that I guess so what was the
benefit I like that idea because it
focuses kind of the the function of the
thing in one place okay right if there's
a a door or there's a key or there's a
you know rubber chicken or whatever it
just keeps everything compact together
this is the rubber chicken of the pulley
in the middle object right these are all
the things that you can do with the
object and the code is just right there
close you know to it so it's basically
like an organizational technique if you
will it's like so at some level it
doesn't actually matter whether the
things embedded in this or not but it
what does matter is I kind of want to
know object all the things that can do
because that's like sort of the way I
want to look at this game thing right
does that become like are there problems
there because like thinking about like
regular kind of code and maybe this
doesn't happen as much in adventure
games but like in in regular code you
end up with problems where it's sort of
the interaction between the objects is
the complex part and so it's difficult
to sort of partition it off into
separate things is that not really a
problem in adventure games or it is and
I guess that's a question it's a problem
I mean you know you're you're using
objects with other objects and entries
you know using key with the bit right
and so you know you do have you know the
door object and the key object at some
point you know one of the twos use verb
they're gonna get called and it's going
to pass the you know the key into the
doors use okay so you do you know you do
have to deal with all right but that on
the whole doesn't isn't the like I guess
what I'm saying is you're not so
concerned about seeing the code
organized that way like pairs of objects
because that's the less common case I
guess is that yeah I mean yeah I think
about things as the object is the object
and what can you not this was a four
object area program I know I mean I
don't think C++ it was anything more
than a preprocessor at that time right
so so I mean I didn't know anything
about that that was just kind of the way
that so you know working on the new game
was there any big like and maybe the
answer this is no because I guess you
did have a lot of time to refine it
since you know you actually did two
whole company's worth I guess right you
Lucas ones and the humongous ones what
you both had an interpreter well I guess
it's come both times but it's like your
you know your evolves him your evolved
scum I don't know what that
some scum I've been evolving there it is
it's wonderful so was there anything
that you sat down on like the VM side of
things or the scripting side of things
was there anything that you went into it
going you know yes I've done this a
billion times but I really this time I
kind of want to solve problem X we just
never got it like was there anything
like that but you sat down thinking
about or was it all the way just like no
like we're pretty like I was pretty
happy with where we ended up you know at
sort of like maybe at the end of the
humungous titles I feel like I got most
of the problems I want to solve or was
there some things that you're just like
this time I'm not gonna have problem
extra this time I'm gonna fix this thing
that always bothered me
does that make sense this question there
was I don't think there was a big thing
again you know I was trying to replicate
those yessuh games and I knew exactly
what I needed to do to do that and I
really did feel that the scum language
did what it needed to do with that stuff
I mean there's you know the scum
language was compiled so you know you'd
make changes and you run a compiler and
it would compile it and then you'd
upload it you know now the compilation
just happens in the engine room right so
you with it there's a bunch of steps
that have kind of been removed
you know I no longer need a heap right
because I basically have infinite memory
you know it to work with so there's a
bunch of things that are simpler to deal
with but I always like the structure I
like the way the multitasking work bents
comment replicated all of that it just
it just it worked for me so so how did
the multitasking work since come well
the monkey the multitasking with one
scum you're they're basically scripts
which was a logistic functions right and
and this is like we were saying in the
door if I have door open there's some
code in here that would be sort of the
type of thing we were talking about yes
yeah so that's gonna execute in this
commune right and but but the thing the
thing that I you'll want to do with this
gun system was I wanted the objects to
be you know a little bit self-contained
okay like if you know the clock needed
to tick and it needed to move its little
pendulum yeah I just wanted to have a
little piece of code that just moved
right I didn't want to have to have a
big state engine that you jumped into
and you had to spawn out to all the
different pieces precisely I just wanted
a little function so the one of the
coolest things to me was the scum system
had a do loop that had no until or while
okay it was just do open brace close
brace right and it would just run like
right and so that script would just sit
there and do whatever it needed to do
and you could spawn off all these
different scripts for all these
different objects and really let the
objects deal with themselves in a way
and how do you do I mean I guess for the
most part in in most circumstances
you're describing these do loops I would
know that I wouldn't have to execute one
if I'm not in the room with that object
but I would imagine sometimes maybe I
even do and so like how did you how do
you manage the fact that we could have
tons of objects doing do loops and which
ones do I do now like what did that sort
of look like I guess is that well there
were two kinds of functions there were
global functions and local functions
okay
local functions were local to the room
so when you left the room all of the
threads running that were local
functions just got killed killed right
so you didn't have to manage that so
only the global functions were the ones
that would and objects could implement
global functions or local functions
inside them so you gotta just say this
is something has to happen all the time
or something only happens when you're in
the room with this particular object or
whatever yeah like the clock ticking you
only care about that I can see if the
clock is there where another function
this may be you know waiting for the
shopkeeper to get back from looking
regular swordmaster yes that's got to be
a global function that's a surprise I
see so all right so it's taking the
example that I asked before with the
walk system right the walk box and so on
so tell me a little bit about your
approach to that now right because like
again at the time like we were saying
like okay I got to make all the boxes
and then we by hand put in like the
thing but the time you had gotten to say
the like maybe the end of the loop sorts
of slices say monkey Alan - were you
still manually entering in the walk
paths or did you already kind of yeah no
we
still manually okay so how about end of
humungus we didn't we didn't have wok
boxes because the characters in the
humungous games they didn't really kind
of walk around the rooms in the same I
guess they kind of animated yeah yeah
they were there were more animated stuff
so they didn't really have to path fine
okay so now in this game like I've even
seen the videos assembly park with you
walking the character round so obviously
it is pathfinding guess so we have wok
boxes yes so what do you still do wok
boxes do you still enter it manually no
now I don't well I did for about a month
the first month I was manually remove
myself a hand but yeah I mean the wok
box is in you know in the in the new
system for thimble we'd Park and there's
still walk boxes but they can now just
be incited polygons right right they
don't have to be you know squares and
trapezoids they can just be anything
that we can really twist around yeah you
know the objects and then you know at
runtime you know you know it'll kind of
split the you know those polygons up
into okay so you like do a generic kind
of polygon thing that you can make
whatever you want right this is the
walkable area and then we will go ahead
and test light that for you and also
figure out the connectivity that we used
to by hand and then then from there the
system is pretty similar yeah then it's
it's actually very similar okay at that
point you know the stuff that happens
under the hood is it's just we've
removed that that kind of human step
that's just all done by robots all right
so let me check how much time we got
here I don't actually know so 518 I
don't even know my handwriting is so bad
that I can't even read what I wrote down
let's see yeah it's definitely not
handwriting here oh this is five 20 it
says I think we don't have to so correct
me if I'm wrong but this was five thirty
five that I was supposed to write down
here right so we have we have easily
probably twenty or thirty minutes left
so this is this is pretty good okay all
right
so I guess
I just kind of want to drill down in a
couple things here that we sort of
already talked about but that or there
may be a little bit more a little bit
more processing let's save so you now
have a situation and I guess this would
have been true for example going back to
something like Secret of Monkey Island -
or something where you've actually have
a fair number of people working on this
game right so it's like there's a lot of
rooms to create there's a lot of objects
a lot of scripts to write that sort of
stuff
so what's the process like you know
what's the toolset like for buildings is
like like wok boxes for example right do
you tend to do a lot of like rolling
tools as necessary like was this a thing
where you know I'm maybe maniac mansion
I put in the coordinates by hand or
something and then later on we make a
tool for drawing like if you tell me a
little bit about like the tooling up
process as you sort of you know go
through the various games especially
because now I know you guys had like hot
loading on a VAX or whatever I just want
to know like like what did it actually
look like to make this thing because you
know there's a couple by the same token
you were entering Lockbox things by hand
so I have no idea I can't even guess
where things would fall on your tooling
level if that makes sense
yeah we had you know by the time Monkey
Island milk rolled around and and really
that was because you bet that might be
all rolled around will you know we were
working on PCs okay we weren't working
on Commodores anymore so we had a lot
more we weren't doing working on the fax
machines at that point - we were doing
our coding and compiling on the PCs and
were you still able to retain sort of
the hot loading stuff when you move
that's not as not as nicely really yeah
yeah I mean a lot of that stuff went
away
does that develop you know not really
just because there were so many other
benefits okay when you're working on a
Commodore 64 with 19km heat space yeah
you know when you have suddenly 120 km
deep space on a PC it's you know it's
like Nirvana right so I think you're
you're kind of
to leave some of that stuff you know I'm
the right side so you know tool wise we
did have tools we we had our own
animation tool that we did okay there
was and we had our own character and
ritual the tool that we laid out rooms
was called flam everything followed the
scum okay like flam and mucus okay so
all right you know phlegm was the tool
that you lay the rooms out in and you
know the basic who would bring the art
in the all the art was done in D paint
okay and so that would just bring in
these you know lbm rooms in d paint and
I would load him in and then you could
go through you know with your cursor and
you would tag the objects on the screen
okay and you would lay down the lock
boxes so that was all done visually okay
so there's basically like a markup
process that happens in there and so
what does that look like today so forth
in building fit will be Park similar
different I you know I I'm probably I
guess the most unoriginal person in the
world I'd built a tool that you bring in
Photoshop files and you mark objects and
you lay down so it's it's like it is
exactly the same process yeah it is well
hey man if it works it works yeah okay
and so what what sorts of stuff happened
and and maybe the answer is people just
got really good at it or what but what
sort of stuff happened once you start
expanding even perhaps on me and Ike
mansion I don't know but obviously it
probably didn't have much of a much you
could do about it but maybe later on you
know that scripting sort of system and
like the scummvm and all that stuff that
you're starting to make a significant
chunk of what happens in the game is
going through this system it becomes
hard with no tools perhaps to debug
problems like because we don't know you
know why did the clock stock ticking we
don't know right at what point or you
know did you start having or did you
ever have like tools for looking at that
was there inspection that's our stuff
how did like what what did that sort of
looked like yeah I mean once we didn't
have the
UNIX machines where we could yeah you
know look at all the memory you know we
had to do that on the PC okay so tell me
a little of that so on the UNIX machines
you would actually just sort of freeze
the cameras to see for his execution
mm-hmm and just you just inspect the
memory respect the memory yeah okay that
was that was pretty crude okay but by
the time that the the PC version came
about you know we all had kind of second
monitors you know we bought like you
know cheap black-and-white
okay Achilles monitors okay and so we
had you know the main PCB we had a
secondary black-and-white monitor which
we did all the debugging in okay and you
know at that point we could do
source-level debugger so you know we
could stop a we could single step in the
source code would just show up on the
secondary monitor and we could just you
know through the lines in the source
code so you actually had fairly ER
that's on maniac mansion even know
that's who never shipped on the PC yeah
we never had that okay so that was on
Monkey Island or that was that was
started with Lulu's really the first
full PC game okay and so at that point
you guys decided hey we should probably
have a debugger if it's tough there's so
much it's hard to like actually figure
out swinging on scripts let's do it here
Simba we'd park thimble we'd park I
don't have a source-level debugger no
kind that's one thing I don't have that
I hope to write you know someday so I
can do that the debugging is a lot
easier I mean the language is a lot more
dynamic so you know there's like a
little little debug window which I can
actually type in commands your actual
language command I say you know call
functions change variables and and you
have some kind of dumping I assume so
you like print out this object so you
kind of it's back to printf okay so
basically like in some sense now in
thimble you park you rely and I guess
that's typical like a top level or
something like this to people called
like the ability to typing code
dynamically gives you the ability to
sort of like okay well I can go in and
if I'm wondering why something's doing
something I can printouts in the state
or I can also kind of twiddle with
things and see if that you can choose
what it was or you call functions can
you kick their game into a certain state
and do you do a lot of fun
we park in terms of creating those
scripts or do you like is that do you
have people who are doing game scripting
at is it is it more similar to like the
monk down case right yeah and you're
doing yeah there's one other person
David Fox and you know it coincidentally
he was the other scripture I mean II act
mansion okay right so so it's exactly
because yeah when it was the artist
management right and I'm you're the
management and scripting and David is
doing the script it's like we're all
just older and yeah so you he does
probably the bulk of the scripting you
know I my time is probably split between
you know building the engine and doing
scripting stuff although most of my
scripting tends to be more experimental
stuff it's like I'll add some new
feature and so I'll program a part of
that and it needs that feature to see
yeah we're David will then kind of go
off and do more than that so are there
any new features in the VM that you're
using now there so that's built now that
we're like very different from the
scaling was there was there anything or
is it like no no like it is basically
scum like I just kind of did you know a
new take on the exact same thing or was
there like have you experimented you say
especially when we say experimental
scripting for features are those just
features that used to be in scum that
you have an implant in yours yet or
those new features we're like I think it
would be nice if adventure games or
players had this I mean there are a lot
of new features just just to make you
know in the language I've got coding
things okay functions we can call you
know the game is all kind of you know
classic 8-bit you know art stuff except
we have shaders okay and then do
lighting okay so so the lights in the
world actually project light okay out
and they actually shade the characters
as they walk ice engine and so you know
there's stuff like that this kind of new
and you know so you know I create
commands in the language to be able to
control the lights because I see the
lights to be able to blink on them all
these other things so it's just tying
you know all of these new you know
features that we have in the engine back
into the scripting language and how all
that kind of stuff works but what if the
charm of old adventure games was that
they didn't have lighting you're getting
Europe
you're ruining that one you know you
never know right it's like I guess there
was some though I guess when I when I
did the Kickstarter it's like my goal
was it wasn't to make a classic
adventure game the way they were yeah it
was to make a classic adventure game the
way you remember them okay right because
people don't remember those games
exactly like they were right they they
kind of extrapolate the graphics out to
much better than they realize it and so
I wanted to be able to kind of remain
true and pure to the 8-bit stuff I see
but I'm not opposed to using shaders I
see it's a really nice you know subtle
lighting effects on everything because I
think that's the way people remembered
those game okay and that makes sense so
it's kind of like saying we're trying to
we're trying to reproduce your memory of
Monkey Island not the actual Monkey
Island because the Accu Monkey Island
you might be like ah that doesn't look
so good exactly so we want to take that
away so it's got a walk I guess almost
like a fine line between it can't look
like a completely modern game because
then it obviously isn't Monkey Island
but we can't go all the way back to
exactly what it looked like because it's
too far so you're kind of like in this
middle ground of trying to like nail
what did you remember is the feeling is
this feeling feeling of dying those
games and and you know we can certainly
do a little more with the hardware you
know I can actually do scaling you know
through the GPU and I can do stuff like
that now that what's your approach been
- this is kind of a little off topic but
I just kind of realized I hadn't even
written this down what's your approach
been to music over time because I feel
like you know
in in sort of the I want to say monkey
island to maybe it kind of had very very
advanced interactive music for its time
period right I'm used system yeah the
I'm use thing and and then like I don't
really know what you guys did with the
humongous titles necessarily because a
lot of those actually featured more
heavily sort of recorded like produces
stuff which couldn't probably be so
interactive but what's your what was
your feeling about those such there was
that something you really weren't that
interested in anyway and maybe some
other people went off and did it or did
you care a lot about the music and
what's your approach to it now can you
give me yeah like I said this was never
on the list but I just kind of thought
of it and I was like should ask well I
mean the I'm you system which did
probably one of the most amazing
interactive music systems I've ever seen
okay and it was it was amazing and I was
incredible to work and it was it was
time-consuming we had you know one whole
game scripter who did nothing but look
in all the music really for stuff for
mochi I own too so you know it was
intensive to do that kind of stuff but I
mean is really became not possible with
the whole digital revolution of stuff
because I'm use was still just playing
maybe steel and MIDI cards or whatever
and when digital music hit the scene it
really couldn't you couldn't do what I'm
used it anymore and and so I think it
just kind of lost a little bit of that
stuff but you know music the music in
thimble we Park I kind of described as
fully modern I'm not a big fan of like
chip tunes and I'm not a fan of that
stuff and and so I just I felt like
music kind of embodies such a kind of an
emotional tone fair game that I really
just wanted the music to be to be full
and really nice and do you think that
like so is that something that's kind of
missing nowadays in some sense would you
say like your description of the I'm use
system or or I guess the results of the
IBEW system and having gone to digital
and sort of losing most of that is that
something that you think we kind of need
to get back at some point like as a
technological problem like what or do
you think the games don't really suffer
much from not having that technology
like what's what's your take on it as
someone who's made games with and
without yeah I I think really sadly I
think music is kind of ignored and it's
it's too bad that it is I mean I'm not a
music person I don't know nothing about
music sorry I could not I do not play an
instrument I couldn't name the notes I
tell you right so you know I kind of
entrust that there are other people that
do that kind of stuff very well but I
really enjoyed working with I am you
system I enjoy kind of interactive music
you know the in the music the thing
about the music in monkey on the - and
the immune system was that was one
continuous piece of music yes from the
time the game started until the game
ended and but as you kind of move
through the world it just slowly changed
to match the different rooms you were in
the different areas of the game you ran
and it was just it was seamless and
flawless and I missed that yeah I miss I
like having that that non-stop music
going on but it does need to emotionally
change as you work your way through the
world and it just needs to happen very
subtly so you don't realize that so
what's your approach in timbal we Park
to this we just kind of blend between
yeah I mean the pieces were the approach
that we're using the tempo we park as
the musician is writing a whole lot of
these little ten-second little pieces of
music and he's writing them so they can
chain so the end of one piece can chain
to the beginning of you know virtually
any other piece and I just have these
pools of music and I can just switch
pools and so the most that you'll lag is
ten seconds well it kind of finishes one
piece and then transitions into another
piece so we can do just kind of
wall-to-wall me that's not that far off
from my muse then it's time you sense
it's not I mean it's getting some of it
but I'm you'd do it on a note by note
basis right we're here
but that 10 seconds but so in some sense
you are I guess trying to sort of
recapture that same feel because
obviously you know you could have done
something worse like I fade one out and
fade the other one in right so you're
you're actually kind of going to a
certain distance that actually minigames
don't go like minigames actually will
not have music that can change in that
way they just kind of like fade in and
out things or it's what we're trying I
don't know how successful I'll be but I
mean there's a lot of work for the
musician right yes he has to make sure
that that a whole bunch of pieces yeah
kind of chain into other pieces too much
abruptness yeah kind of carry over it's
a lot of work on his part yeah all right
well that's actually very interesting I
didn't know that let's see let's see how
we're doing on time so I think we're
kind of getting to where we should
probably start wrapping up I think I got
actually most of the things that I
wanted to ask but I will point out the
fact that earlier in the day when Mike
Acton was up here he wanted to know if
creating cut scenes had always been a
problem and he wanted to hear that from
the person who did you guys even coined
that phrase yes I want to say you're
like the people who introduced the
phrase cuts in history so tell me a
little well first we might as well since
this is this is entirely self-indulgent
for me tell me how that comes about like
games don't have cutscenes and now they
do what what happened I mean games had
interstitials yeah games had little
canned animated sequences that was not
something we created the word cutscene
yeah that was something that we
definitely coined and and it came from
in maniac mansion you be playing the
game and the game would literally just
cut away and show you what was happening
in doctor friend's lab and Merced in his
room or weird Ed's room or something and
I mean it did it very crudely in the
fact that there was just a little timer
running and you know when 18 minutes
expired it was just no matter what you
were doing right you could be writable
of solving some really important puzzle
and we just cut away gotcha
and so they were scenes that cut away
from the game yes they were called
cutscenes and there was even a
and in the scum language called cutscene
okay and it was it was very
sophisticated command in that when you'd
run a cutscene it would kind of save the
game state away right go off and do the
cutscene and when the cutscene ended it
would just automatically restore the
game state to where you might save
before so it kind of takes the vm state
at this time dumps it go load this
entire state and then as soon as we're
done it's kind of like a you know an
excursion if you will where it's like
and then we're just gonna like full-on
romp over that with the new thing yes
okay okay so that's actually probably
one of the harder things to implement in
scum because everything has to work
right through that well that was I mean
that was definitely a sophisticated yeah
yeah really powerful so Mike wants to
know where cutscenes always a foul like
like our cut seat where cutscenes I
guess implementing them was but I mean
for the artist creating them and that
sort of stuff no no they weren't they
weren't a problem okay because you're
doing something wrong I don't know what
to say but somewhere between Monkey
Island they weren't a problem because
they were all hand coded right right
then we didn't have a tool that we built
these cutscenes on if we needed their
Sedna to walk around the room while she
was saying something we literally had
code that walked her here then water
there so we didn't have that came that
seemed you know ask that export problem
that you know cutscenes have today
because you know they're coming out of
these big tools is that so I should ask
that actually about the sort of we
talked about the multi processing thing
and creating cutscenes that sort of
stuff because my recollection again and
it's been a very long time I guess since
I played it but my recollection even
even in Monkey Island but I think almost
certainly in muck down to there were
definitely places where the the and
putting away sort of what your
definition of cutscene was there
there are definitely places where
scripted sorts of things happened in
conjunction with the player still having
the freedom to do things right so there
were times when something relatively
elaborate like this guy is gonna go walk
off the screen and go somewhere we you
didn't actually freeze the entire
players ability to do stuff I remember
there being some concurrency there even
like I said as early as monkey on and
maybe that's my memory being bad but
that's my that's correct
what did that kind of look like at that
time because you know that's sort of a
really hard problem especially you know
again when you're talking about a very
limited system that has a lot of
constraints to even just do the basic
stuff it does now we're talking about
sort of this sort of thing that was like
you know half-life 2 was struggling to
do these sorts of things right so we're
talking about how do we have the ability
to script something that has to happen
but we don't really know what the player
was doing at this time was that
something you guys thought a lot about
or was it just because hey we tried to
keep it so that really wouldn't be a
problem or what like what was that leg
at a time because that must have been
that was a really early attempt to do
something like this and you know it went
surprisingly well it's a really hard
problem yeah because you know I think
players intrinsically just want to
up everything you do ok they just do
yeah and so you know it's it's it's it's
not that we could have the scene where
you know you're following the shopkeeper
into the forest to find the swordmaster
we really couldn't plan that the player
was going to do exactly what we wanted
them to do yes follow behind him yeah
stay in the back
no it's not what players do when players
want to run up in front of him yeah well
other things so yeah I mean we had we
had to do with it we had to deal with
all that stuff and I think you know the
way we solved a lot of that stuff is is
you just cheat as much as you can okay
you know so when the when the shopkeeper
is walking from his store to the certain
master he's not literally walking
through those rooms right he he walks to
the door and he leaves and then we just
kind of do a little bit of timer stuff
there's just a timer running and so when
you walk into the next room we just put
the shopkeeper close to the exit and
just have him walk off this possibly
camera and if the timer had went went
too far then you just lost them you
didn't appear ice it's just it's all
about just creating weird little
shortcuts and cheating your way through
the problem as much as you can
well I think we are just about out of
time yet we are so thank you so much
that was like that was extremely
enjoyable don't feel like so many things
I