hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show recode a complete game
live on stream we are doing a little
graphics cleanup today we we pretty much
have stuff in a pretty pretty big fancy
if I do say so myself
please fancy position here on day three
eighty four we're going to be so you
know I'm day three before you want to
load date 383 s source code if you want
to follow along but let me show you I'm
really happy with where things are and
we're just doing a little bit of cleanup
because at the end of the last dream I
sort of did some cleanup to make it so
that we always render to a low
resolution or higher resolution actually
whichever one you want and then scale
the game and so we can do some fun
things like this where this is like
pixel art hero that we kind of made
happen right but we didn't quite get a
chance to finish everything that I had
wanted to do there because and I'll go
ahead and switch us back for now to high
res rendering here at startup yeah so I
didn't get a chance to everything I want
to do because one of the things that we
were about to do with the renderer is
and the reason that kind of I end up in
that place where you could get that kind
of crazy scaling is I would like to be
able to turn multi sampling on if the
card supports it now we're doing depth
peeling for you know are the way that
we're handling our like depth
compositing so we don't really need the
multi sampling anymore we can run
without it just fine and that's what I'm
doing right here is I'm running without
the multi sampling but you can also kind
of see that what that does is while all
of our sprites look nice and clean and
smooth and that's all good we run into
this other problem which is that all of
our sort of line work right like all of
our geometric primitives which there
aren't going to be a whole lot of in
handmade here necessarily but the ground
and walls are sort of these blocks so
they do comprise this we live again
portion of the screen even though
there's only really one thing in the
game that's a that's a cube it's
basically like a solid thing but that's
a lot of stuff that's a lot of of the
image so what ends up happening is you
get kind of jagged lines on the ends of
those and that's just a standard
anti-aliasing problem and the best
solution on a GPU for the standard
anti-aliasing problem when you're
drawing solid 3d primitives like that is
usually to use multi sampling so what
I'd like to do is four cards for people
who have modern beefy cards which this
one that is in this machine is
definitely not this is a seven-year-old
card at this point so people have modern
cards you can see that we're running
with our depth you know the depth
feeling here is still running quite well
even though that's you know over drawing
the screen many times so given that fact
I pretty much can guarantee you that if
you ran this on a fancy graphics card
you would have just a ton of horsepower
to spare so as a result I want to enable
the user to you know or the game
automatically if it detects that it has
enough horsepower or whatever to be able
to turn on multi sample anti-aliasing
here to get rid of the jagged lines
because there's no reason not to use
that extra power on the card if it's
there if it's not there the jagged lines
are fine I don't mind them they're not
the end of the world and they're
certainly not a rendering artifact we
need to care too much about but since
graphics cards already know the solution
to this and have worked out exactly how
to do it to a very good effect for us I
feel like that's what we want to do so
what I want to do now is just go into
the renderer and today I just want to
clean everything out so that it's
switchable easily between multi sampling
and non multi sampling so that the game
is able to pick which one of those wants
to do and proceed accordingly right okay
so that's all we're trying to do pretty
simple but again it involves talking to
the graphic card through a graphics API
and as you hopefully have figured out by
now that is always an exercise in
pulling teeth and I can also tell you
that we have had good fortune on
handmade hero because I have not been
doing anything
super complicated with the GPU in that
we have not hit a lot of real stumpers
that take a long time to debug because
you know you definitely can and you can
hit driver bugs which you know you don't
know are there and all these other sorts
things so we've been very fortunate
probably because we're a 2-d game and
not trying to do anything crazy like
voxel cone tracing or something like
this but it's just worth noting that I'm
making even though we've had some
troubles I'm making it look a lot easier
than it is or rather I'm not luck is and
and also the type of game we're doing is
in the sense that we're just not pushing
things to the limit that would you know
that where things start to crumble and
fall apart
alright so let's take a look at what we
need to do here first of all we sort of
did some work yesterday to simplify the
way that we're doing our frame buffer
creation you can kind of see that
happening here we now have this thing
called create frame buffer and when you
call create frame buffer you can
actually pass in a bunch of stuff here
that kind of tells you okay here's the
stuff that I want this frame buffer the
properties that I want this frame buffer
to have and it will correctly allocate
the frame buffer based on those
properties now we have some parameters
here essentially that we want to be able
to control and so what I'm going to do
is I'm going to add these to the OpenGL
system here where we can kind of say
like okay let's you know let's have some
some control parameters right so up here
I'm just going to introduce some
optional switches and the optional
switches you know what I might do I
[Applause]
might just make this its own structure
and the reason for that is that in the
future I probably want to have this be
something that the game can change at
runtime potentially like from a dialog
box in the game or something like this
or automatically like if the game
detects that the framerate too slow it
could pull off some of these switches
something like this and so what I want
to be able to do is probably you know
plan for just a little bit you don't
want to
premature about or anything but just
since it's easy wrap it in a structure
that I can expect in the future that the
game might provide this struct back to
me and it's easy to encapsulate what the
switches are here into or by shouldn't
say encapsulate because I'm not hiding
the frame but I guess bundle them
together so I want to have multi
sampling as one of the options and I
probably also want to have depth peel
count or something as one of the options
like how many depth peels do we want to
do and that's probably all we really
need here the other thing that we could
specify in the hardware rendering such
as is the resolution at which we want to
render and I don't really know whether
that's appropriate to do here or not but
I think I might just go ahead and say
that that's where that's going to come
from so I'm going to have render with
and render height in here as well and
that to me sort of looks roughly like
the switches that I know at least at the
moment are things that you could play
the game with different settings and
they wouldn't change the fundamental
rendering architecture right like all of
these things we can make pretty easily
parameterize Abul with the way that we
have the pipeline set up right now
there's nothing in there that's going to
you know make it so that we have to do
huge gyrations in the code to support
the different configurations so that
seems like pretty easy to support so
what I'm going to do here is I'm going
to start using those things like I'm
sorry going to try to make it so that we
can control these switches however we
want and then we will the renderer will
like adjust accordingly all right so the
first thing I want to do is render with
and render height are pretty well pulled
out here so I just want to check to make
sure that nobody's actually using these
elsewhere and it's behind my head it
looks like yeah so render entry blend
render target that at the moment I think
I'm going to nerf and the reason I'm
going to nerf that is because this has
changed so much from what we were doing
for that I think we don't really want to
have that be in here anymore
so I suspect we will probably you know
we might re-enable that in the future
but in for the moment I think I want to
pull that out because if we were going
to do it we'd have to think it through
again and there's really not much code
in there at the moment so I'm just going
to go ahead and and get rid of that push
blend render target situation that's
going to get out of there and and
that'll be it so I always forget that I
don't define those in this in handmade
hero I do in my own code base I guess be
32x is but not the you 32x maybe I
should just define them so I can just
type them when I type them out of habit
so really all those are right is they're
just saying hey you could make this as
big as you wanted it to be that's all
they're saying so it's basically like if
I say you 32x what it means is I need
something that's at least as big as you
32 but which you know in fact like I do
it this way just say hey by the way
here's all those X types it's basically
just saying hey it's something that's at
least as big as a you 32 but you could
make it bigger if you wanted to so I
don't care about the fact that this
thing is 32 bits I care about it can
hold at least 32 bits and really this is
kind of a holdover I don't really use it
much anymore meaning I don't have
platforms where I switch it on but in
the past in 16 in a 16-bit era a lot of
times you'd want to say stuff like this
is a-you 16 X meaning if you happen to
be compiling on 32-bit you may want to
switch this to a 32-bit value because
that may be faster than using a 16-bit
value because certain chips it was
slower to use 16-bit operations if they
have any 32-bit but in other cases where
you're running on 16-bit stuff running
32 bits much slower so you wanted to say
hey use whichever one's faster it's more
of a holdover you don't really need it
very much now pretty much like I don't
really know their prime sure there are
some out there but I'm not super
familiar with any chip right now
where you'd rather switch to a 64-bit
number then use a 32-bit number I just
don't know of one that doesn't mean
there isn't one but I don't know if it's
relevant for games if there is one I
don't know but there used to be or at
least in the 16-bit era there used to be
so anyway that's all that is it's not
very important anyway so back to what I
had typed originally that should work
now right yeah
so now that we have these Hardware
switches I'm just going to go ahead and
do the work there - maybe I'll do it
over on this side so I don't have the
risk of going behind my own head I'm
just going to double check that nobody
uses these commands with them wisten
height that's okay so what I want to do
now is and what we could probably do -
it's in that in the commands we could
have those switches placed in the
command for example that's where the
switches could come from if we wanted to
so you know in fact what I could do is
is sort of just pre you know be
completely premature here and just say
hey look where the width and height were
before maybe that's where I'll put them
because I guess there's really no reason
not to do that right so let's see here
where are those written of commands
they're right here so here are the those
parameters so what I'll do I guess I'll
just sort of more conform to what we had
here and say that instead so now you can
see on here we kind of have like alright
we're going to send down the parameters
for the game render commands and what I
might say is so the depth peel count
here and the multi sampling maybe that's
a hint - so maybe this is is sort of
understood to be how many I'm trying to
do but it's not a requirement because
for example in the software renderer we
may just want to say that the software
renderer can only do specifically just
one
a configuration of depth peeling so you
know maybe these are like hints that
basically say look this is what I would
like to be doing right now
you don't have to do that if you can't
do that right okay so if I continue with
how I was doing this and say well maybe
in here we have a thing that's like
struct game render params or setting
something like this and I pull this out
like so like I was trying to do before
then when I can say is well the game
render setting can go here and then what
can happen is inside this OpenGL render
commands loop what I could do is I could
say well you know maybe we just say if
settings have changed and I say that you
know I have this magical command which
can take two of these setting structures
so you know the settings that came from
the game and the settings that I have so
in OpenGL you know I'd have game render
settings current settings right so if I
have those two things I basically want
to say here if there was a change since
the last time we initialized everything
then we're going to initialize
everything again right and so I can
break off this initialization code then
you know essentially all of this stuff I
can break all of this out into here into
a routine that only you know will
execute when we detect that we need to
reconfigure everything and so the nice
thing about that is now what will happen
is we can change this will let us change
our settings on the fly so example you
know if we want to change the render
resolution on the fly or
we want to change like multi-sample and
stuff on the fly even though that
requires recreating these render targets
that's okay because will detect it and
will close down our previous render
targets and create new render targets
right so it's you know that'll be
that'll be easy for us to do so try to
think of what else we've got here that's
that way I think everything else is not
so I think everything else is pretty
good yeah and so the only question is
will we have to recompile some shaders I
don't know that we will but we could
make shader recompilation be part of
that process as well you know that would
not be difficult to do so like we could
have like the srgb and stuff in there
that's kind of an interesting thing
right
like just looking at here so the
compilation which is this phrase this
face here we could pretty easily right
go ahead and do that
that compilation and and that would also
allow us to have those shaders be sort
of predicated on whether or not you know
whether or not certain settings were set
and I'm going to go ahead and do that
because that just seems like the right
place to put it because that means we
would know we wouldn't have sort of this
incentive in the future to like not have
stuffed baked into the shaders when we
change our settings we could just fake
things into the shaders differently if
we wanted to now again I don't really
know that we'll ever need that but it's
easy enough to do that I feel like I
might as well just do it long in this
past because that way we won't have this
sort of it's definitely I want to do we
won't have like a headwind there
essentially where it's like I don't
really feel like doing that because
remember Rumble so what I'm going to do
here is I'm going to place the OpenGL
render commands routine at the bottom so
it can just call all of this stuff and
then what it'll do is it'll call the
OpenGL sort of compilation phase stuff
where we get in here we go and the frame
buffer creation stuff it'll call that
whenever it detects that maybe that's
something that should do so we'll just
put that right there all right so it's
start up now we just won't compile
things will only compile things when we
go to draw them the first time and so
the only steps that we're going to leave
in here is just going to be like stuff
that we know we need to do regardless
right and I don't know if we want to
have this sort of this test stuff here
this can probably move to the outside
now I mean to that sort of secondary
startup thing because honestly if we if
we really want to be diligent when we
create a multi sample buffer what we
could do now is say well we if we try to
create a mother sample buffer and fail
then we could scale back down and I
don't know if we wanted to
not yeah it's kind of a tough call so
we'll keep an eye on that and we'll
we'll see what we need to do for that
alright so this is just going to be our
opengl you know prepare for settings and
this is going to take the game render
settings that you want it to use and
what we're going to do is just at first
we're just going to say open jail-like
settings i think that's what we called
it current settings that's controlled it
we're going to say the current settings
now are now equal to the new settings
and then what we're going to do is we're
going to get rid like we're going to
jettison anything that we or like that
we already have so we have to go through
all of our frame buffers and all that
stuff and get rid of them if they're
already there right so I'm not going to
quite do that yet because I want to pull
some stuff out first before we do but
this is where this is going to go so
here we're going to do jettison all
existing frame buffers and programs and
so that will let it's like just flush
the you know basically those two sets of
state and then recompile them all so now
we don't have to do that if because now
we know we're just always going to have
to create all the frame buffers that
we're going to create and now we can
also take the opportunity to move the
frame buffer stuff kind of in like out
into a more appropriate location as well
so let's start cleaning up some of these
things here so people who use the the
width and height directly out of here
are going to have to get it out of
settings now which is not a big deal
right it's literally just symptom tactic
stuff it's it's the same it's still as
if it was directly in there it's not
like it's going to incur an extra cache
miss or something like that it's still
just sitting there right at the top but
we do have to grab it out of there so
let's go ahead and do that
there we go and now in here we just need
to actually pull out that render width
and maybe I'll just make it easy on
myself and just say like okay what's
called settings and that is it just wit
it is alright so that is mostly all we
need to do we need to compute a max
render target index here what I might
want to do is make that value a property
of opengl so what I might want to do is
say well the max render target index is
going to be equal to the Oprah maybe
I'll do it the other way around the
opengl max render target index is going
to equal whatever we compute here and
one of the weird things about max render
target index that I don't super love is
that it makes it harder to represent the
fact that there are no render targets
right so if I store the max render
target index I can't say that there are
no render targets very easily I would
have to say like negative 1 or something
because I can't say 0 because that means
there is 1 render target still in
existence so it's a little bad and we
probably want to sort of clean this up
in fact I guess I'll just clean it up
now because why not let's write this a
little bit more sensibly we're going to
get rid of all of this right and so what
I'm going to do here is I'm going to
actually I'm going to actually do a gen
frame buffer delete frame buffer kind of
a thing I'm just going to do it that way
in a in a straightforward fashion so
what I want to do is I want to go
through here and and you know go by def
deal basically so I want to say like
depth
peel index equals zero def peel index is
less than the FTL count Def peel index
plus plus and then what I want to do is
basically nuke all this stuff right so I
don't want anything in here at all
anymore because we have the ability to
create a frame buffer now very cleanly
right we can say opengl flame frame
buffer depth field buffer equals create
frame buffer and we can pass the
settings that we want here so we want
the render with the render height and
then we want depth geo flags now the
depth peel flags we know at least are
going to be OpenGL frame buffer color
but we also know that we're going to
need gaps right so then the only
question is do we need multi sampling so
now what we want to do is again use the
settings that we got and say you know
what's the multi sampling hint if the
multi sampling it is set and maybe I'll
do this so that we know one way or the
other if we're going to try to do multi
sampling then I'll say and maybe even go
a little bit further and say there'll be
a permanent thing that says on the Open
GL structure if we're doing multi
sampling then the depth peel flags are
going to have multi sampling board in so
there you can see it's like okay I'm
starting to build up something which
essentially says we're to check the
settings we cheated a settings change
we're going to lie creep repair OpenGL
we're going to do that by sort of like
progressively figuring out what we can
and can't do here so we have open jail
multi sampling and for now we'll just
set that to be whatever the multiple
hint is right but in the future probably
what we'll do is we'll only turn that on
if the card actually supports multi
sampling etc etc
so one other thing that we want here is
in our settings pixelation hint
and so pixelation hint is basically this
part right here because we had that fun
funny effect which is like we want
things to be pixelated so we might as
well support that because again since we
have render settings now we might as
well just throw a few things in there
that we might want and so what I'm going
to do is say there's the resolve flags
and the resolve flags are going to be
these flags but we're going to predicate
again just like we did before that
secondary part which is whether or not
we do filtering what we want to do is
say well if there's a pixelation hint
we'll use it and now we don't want to do
this in the affirmative we want to in
the negative because if we're trying to
pixelate then we don't want to filter
right so if we're not trying to pixelate
then we do want to filter right so
that's you know how that goes okay so
off we go we've got the render width and
render height here those are doing their
thing that we've got the frame buffer
resolve stuff going on here that's doing
its thing and we just need to pass the
resolve flags instead of the hard-coded
flags like before now we just need to
put that global resolve frame buffer
somewhere a little bit more logical so
where we're going to put that is we're
going to say there's an open GL resolve
buffer and that's all there is to that
right
so here's kind of like our peeling I
should say our peeling this is our
decrypting like we're turning the
settings in the stuff we can use
then we'll compile our programs create
our frame buffer and create our depth
buffer our deputy of frame buffers as
well I'm going to rid of all of this
because now that look at how much
cleaner that is now right
looking really good so you know we're
starting to get they're starting to look
better we need to figure out what that
def peel camp is and so at the moment
what we can do is just say well the DES
peel count is going to be set by that
depth peel count here so again just
taking it direct for now okay so then
we've got our all of our stuff here
looking pretty good we probably need to
save that def field count right that
needs to be recorded and so maybe what I
can do here is just set that directly
for the Open GL thing as many of those
as I can do directly in there probably
is a good idea right and yeah that all
seems pretty good I don't see anything
else that's particularly onerous there
and yeah so that seems pretty good and
this way too like I said now that we're
compiling these programs if we find and
we may if we find that we need to do
something extra here in the shaders
themselves as far as you know being able
to handle multi sampling by switching
what kind of shader well just a little
tiny things in our shader code it's nice
to have the ability to pass parameters
to the compilation of our shaders right
at the times when we know what our
settings are rather than having to sort
of deal with that dynamically and
potentially compile lots of shaders and
only use one of them or something like
this this way we know we're just
compiling one set and we can fully
customize them
in any way that we want all right so now
we just have to store these and so what
I'll do is say the depth field buffer
here is going to be parametrized like so
and the other thing I'll do is I'll say
well you know the depth field hint can't
be higher than a certain number right so
we'll just say like in this case you
know the depth field count or well we
might even cap it we'll just say if the
depth field count is higher than however
many we're saying the max is going to be
for OpenGL which is maybe like eight or
something or 16 which is absurd like but
hey you know you could do it we just say
at that point you really should be using
Atomics probably but you know neither
here nor there we could do an atomic
spaz someday maybe we should I don't
know if this card even supports comics
but we could do it when I move to a more
modern machine certainly so we have DES
field count and we're just checking to
see if the death peel count is too large
then I'll just cap it right so I'll say
if the DEF peel count exceeds how many
the maximum is going to be for OpenGL
then we'll cap that right there and
that'll be the end of it so now we can
sort of imply what we're what we should
have over here for our for for what the
settings should be right and what our
storage should be so you can kind of see
here we've got our programs that's not
going to change the texture format all
that stuff that's all not going to
change but we now have sort of another
set of things here that can sort of
float around we've got weather Multi
sampling is on we've got how many depth
keels we're going to do and we also have
one more thing if I remember correctly
which is where is it I thought we had
one more open tilting but now we don't I
take it back
all right so that's all we really need
to know how many def skills were doing
and are we multi sampling those know
things that really persist then we've
got the resolved frame buffer
which is OpenGL frame buffer oops and
we've got the depth field buffer and
that let's just say you can set it up to
16 because why not that's ridiculous but
I'm sure there's cards that could do it
easily especially if we switch to a
texture Atlas in the future
I'm sure there's cars that would eat
that for breakfast because 16 times over
pass with the kind of loads we're
passing it these cards and monsters
these days you know you get some SLI
configuration with a you know big beefy
23 power connector is kind of a card and
these things can render anything I mean
they can't run the Windows 10 desktop
without frame hitches of course because
no one's ever built a machine that can
do that but they can render any game you
might throw at them because you know
what's a game certainly not as hard as
drawing some colored tiles with like 5
fonts on them anyway let's go ahead and
and get this work in here because we've
made a lot of substantial changes so
what is this complaining about a sub
script array required blah blah blah
blah blah I think we just are missing a
semicolon is really all that was about
yeah ok I missed the initial error
that's why so it requires a ray or
pointer type that is probably true that
is not what I meant to put there and
then to put that I just can't take the
array count of a boolean doesn't make
any sense
so now we need to have this settings has
changed function and this is obviously
something that's kind of shared right
it's it's something that would be part
of the platform layer probably and I
don't know exactly where we want to put
it I can put it in here for now but we
could move it really anywhere but it has
to be accessible to everybody because
it's you know it's a generic sort of
thing that any of the renderers might
want to use what I might do is just say
are equal and so that way you can just
say like are these two things equal so
I'll just say like if they're not equal
[Applause]
so if I want to see if these two things
are equal then I'm going to generate a
result that just is basically the
comparison oops
of all the things in them I don't know
what I'm looking at here but I can't
apparently kill this buffer don't know
what buffer it even is that's fine so
let me just finish this up here oops so
there's the settings change and in here
I just now need that platform layer oh I
see I created a platform that CPP file I
guess I don't know what happened there
anyway it doesn't matter don't care as
long as I can keep programming I'm fine
so here we are in our equal and what I
want to do here is just take a look at
what those settings are and make sure
that compare them all right so we've got
that multi sampling can't width the
height so here they all are down so I
just want to see basically if a width
equals B width and this is just going to
be this the whole way down right it's
just going to be a a B like that okay
and this by the way is like just you
know I'll just point this out because I
don't know it might not be obvious to
people or maybe it is obvious to people
but you know a lot of times I complain
about the C++ Standards Committee as you
know and you know so sometimes I feel
like I should make that more concrete
and so when things come up in
programming I'll just I'll just explain
them so let me let me give you an
example of kind of classic how the C++
standards committee over decades always
fails to grasp like the fundamental
concepts of how a programming language
should work so take a look at what I
just wrote there right what I wrote
there was iterating in my mind over
the elements of this structure and I
just wanted to do the equals operator on
each of them right that's what I wanted
to do so suppose you are a language
designer and you're looking at this
problem the way the C++ editor many
universally in every single instance
they have ever encountered for any
purpose and I mean that 100% literally
the way they choose to solve this
problem is I go oh it looks like there's
this concept that people might want to
compare to structs to each other
so let's introduce a bunch of rules for
how if you wanted to make the compiler
generate an automatic operator equals to
each other you know where one struck
equals another struct let's let's figure
out a way to do that right and they
write this big long complex thing that
tries to handle all these edge cases and
they they battle with each other over
like these edge cases about which way
should the operator equals automatic
generator for the game render settings
but you know force trucks or classes
work and what happens if things are
private and what happens in this case in
that case and virtual functions an i
right but that completely misunderstands
the fundamental operation of programming
at no time in anyone's head when they
were programming did they think about
this as automatic operator equals what
they thought was I want to compare each
element of this structure so what it's
supposed to look like is this right it's
supposed to look like this and I'm just
making up a syntax here right something
like this right I don't know what you
would put here or like for each member
something like that right I don't know
something like this right and I'm going
to connect for each ear for each member
of the structure I want to do the
operator equals right I want to do a
member eaqubs B member and I want to say
[Applause]
you know if they're not equal or I want
to say if there's not this turns false
return true that's what I was trying to
write and by misunderstanding what the
programmers grain should be doing at
that time and instead thinking of how
the language can automate a specific
instance they missed the fact that
writing this if you just have the
language support that you now support
every possible thing that anyone would
ever want to do that has to apply to all
the members of something this can
automatically do the copy thing this can
even automatically do something where
you only wanted to copy some or compare
some right because now I can do stuff
like exclude certain members like all I
have to do is start introducing what the
CPP member thing can do like can I check
its name or can i annotate it with my
own flags right like flag no save right
and then I can just or no compare right
and then I can just in here to say oh
okay
you know if this member if if not a you
know no compare right or whatever and
that lets you build everything that you
want to build but they never get this
and I don't understand why it's like
anyone has been programming for just a
few years should know this and it's so
crazy to me that they can't wrap their
head around it it's like it's the most
foreign concept to them somehow but it's
the most basic concept and I just don't
understand they could get rid of almost
the entire spec that they've written by
just making a few of these things
it would take like ten pages of spec for
me to write something that can generate
everything they do in C++ by just
letting the programmer actually iterate
over the freaking program it's nuts
anyway gets me really worked up because
every day I have to deal with this crap
and I have to write my own routines and
my own preprocessors and all this stuff
and it's like if someone would just get
a clue we would have had all this stuff
like 20 years ago and other languages do
have it it's not like this is something
I'm making up like I'm like some
language design savant who's talking
about things that no one's ever dreamed
of before it's like basic ability to
iterate over the structures of things
and do stuff to them to generate the
code that you want to actually make is
just better program has been around I
don't even know how long since the 70s
probably possibly before then I don't
know it's nuts anyway so I'm still
typing craft like this fantastic
all right so let's see what we've got
here back to you know rant rant over so
here we are we have to now you know
finish up actually you know using these
things the way that I said we were gonna
so now we have to sort of loop over
things in a more intelligent fashion so
what I'm going to do here is say all
right we know that we have depth appeal
count between number of these things we
use render targets is now a program
conclusion where a deputy renderer you
got a sport render targets we just won't
run on cards that don't right and we
could make a special pass in the future
for one that's that only have one but
you know at this point kind of all bets
are off to a certain extent so we want
to set this stuff correctly that last
one the very last one that when the
target index is basically the depth
field count minus one
so here we come doing our clear and then
we're off and we're finished right so we
unbind the frame over that's pretty much
correct now that's really all that needs
to do let's take a look at the rest of
the places we've used make sure to
target notice that those have to change
so now we're doing is we're trying to
see whether or not the peel index is
like the last peel right so when it says
render entry and peels what we need to
do is do here is say okay we want to
know for on the last peel so basically
the max render target index here we
could just make up what it is in fact we
could just do this and in this case we
have to make sure that the DEF peel
count is greater than zero right because
we can't render anything if we don't we
could make the whole thing predicated on
that but doesn't seem very good I think
you just want to prevent people from
ever actually doing that all right so
let's take a look at the render commands
thing here
alright moving on so this is just the
initial ation initialization of that
struct which we'll deal with in a second
okay so I want to skip down to here it
[Applause]
again just pulling out settings
everywhere okay so now we're down to
just the fact that this has to get
initialized summer and we have this
super crappy macro for it I do not know
why we have a macro for it to be honest
I don't know why it's not just a struct
that is sort of perplexing to me and I
do not know why we have that so what I'm
going to do is I'm going to change this
to not be a struct because I don't see
any reason for it to be a struct so
instead what I'm going to do is do
default render commands like so and I'm
just going to make this be an inline
function like I would normally do maybe
there was some platform compatibility
thing I know at one point some folks
were like actually doing this compiling
handmade hero in like what's that
Appling Swift I think or something like
this and so I don't know there were some
weird things we did to make sure that
they could do stuff I think I don't know
I just I seem to recall this alright
I so let's go ahead and
just initialize these things and I don't
really know so we actually these are
just things come through just let the
push buffer so I really don't think
there's anything special to do here and
then we've got I'm literally doing
nothing here right I'm just so that
seems good there right the weird thing
about this is this is done every time
which I can't say I know why we're doing
that right like we don't really need to
initialize this every time at most all
we would have to do is change a few
values so it seems a little bit strange
that we're doing that way it's possible
that we might need to make some
affordances for having this be different
depending on whether or not we're using
hardware or software rendering in the
future but at the moment I don't really
know anything in particular that really
has
any effect here like you know I don't I
don't know why this couldn't just be
pulled out to something further out like
I don't see any particular reason that
this has to be inside the run loop you
know what I mean so I think we can
pretty much just do it right here all
right so now we just need to actually
pass something you know reasonable
parameter for this stuff so can let's
just go ahead and do so
we have width and height we have the max
vertex count and the vertex array and
[Music]
the bitmap array and the white bitmap at
the moment those are the things that the
platform actually does supply to us and
these are settings to do and this is X
with Max Plus buffer size and
Christopher beige
push buffer data ads that's what and say
[Applause]
and so that clear color I guess we can
just if we don't have the v4 creator
there what I can do is say zero like so
and then in here when we do a push set
up the max render target index is not
something that's getting tracked anymore
and so for render commands yeah we don't
support this anymore
someday we will okay
oh I guess I was a little bit aggressive
there where's the push buffer sighs
there it is so here's the thing that
actually creates those so we do have to
wait till there to create it because we
haven't made the memory for it yet but
that's all good and do I have the right
parameters to this saucy gentleman right
here push buffer size push buffer width
and height max per tom skerritt four
ticks or a bitmap array like bitmap so
that does look that loops here we go
so now in theory that should be getting
passed correctly to the OpenGL subsystem
I hope when we actually do pass it to
the OpenGL subsystem again in theory
what should happen here is that the
first time through it's going to just
test to see whether or not these two
structures have the exact same contents
you know or not and assuming they do
have the same content
we're just suppose if we wanted to duck
the C++ sanity all together in this case
since we care about every last little
thing being equal we could just do a mem
compare here but you know
that's that's just luck because we
happen to want to compare actually
everything so then we want to do is say
okay opens you'll prepare for settings
go through here make sure we set
everything correctly compile our
programs create our frame buffers and
then in theory we should be ready to go
now we still have some vestigial remains
sure that we have to move out because
we're still using this nonsense here
right this open jail frame buffer a sort
of gunk that we have and we don't really
want that to be happening right we don't
want any of these things anymore so we
need to delete all of this and then we
need to make this stuff work without any
of that right so now what we want to do
is we want to take a look at the places
where we're actually using this sort of
stuff and make sure that we have you
know some some handle on what's going on
so here we're trying to bind a texture
from the Deaf peel frame buffers right
well we can do that pretty easily right
because we know we've got the Deaf peel
buffers in our opengl struck and we know
in this case we're just trying to load
oops we're just trying to load a depth
buffer out of one of these right so we
just want to set the death buffer and
say hey we're going to grab the death
buffer out of this off we go it's no big
deal
everyone's you know everyone relax we
don't want to deal with that function
just yet
let me see here def does not is it depth
texture what is it
oops it's going to be in here yup handle
so it passed the DEF handle there so
that gets found then we have here the
steel to our frame before global resolve
frame buffer undeclared let's see the
whole frame buffer is second GL solve
frame buffer dot frame buffer handle and
here we're binding those peels these are
the color textures for the peels so what
we want here is OpenGL
dusty'll buffer and we want the color
handle then we've just got that we're
going to ignore that for one second and
this so here we do OpenGL resolve frame
buffer color handle and we're just down
to this so I'm going to look at where
bind frame buffer happens and what we're
actually passing here so in all these
cases we're just passing like the
indexes right and so what I'm going to
do here is I'm going to say probably
what I want to do is have OpenGL frame
buffer be the thing that we pass here
and then what I'll do is say well if the
frame buffer is a valid pointer then use
the frame buffer handle that's
associated with it otherwise just pass 0
that way you can target either type here
and it just works in theory
so okay so here we want the OpenGL
jetseal buffer for whatever that target
index is and this is going to be the
frame buffer handle right so and then
we've got here this one that's doing the
the peel index or whatever again that's
going to be opengl dot step steel buffer
and that's it so now we've just done a
ton of changes so I have no idea if
anything is going to work at all
probably not but you know what are going
to do so at this point now we've got
sort of one thing that we went a little
bit further than probably we should on
and that is specifically the fact that
we we set that multi sampling hint to
true which is probably bad so what I'm
going to do at first is I'm going to
force the multi sampling off just so we
can get things working and then I will
you know so we can debug everything back
to the way it was and then we'll work on
being able to set multi sampling it's
katroo so I'm just going to set that to
false right now so that no matter what
hint you tell it you're not going to
multiple so now we can get started so
here we are an open GL prepare for
settings you can see the settings here
that we're getting and that's just not
the settings were supposed to get right
that's just totally not even on the
table so I would like to find out why
we're getting this obviously so here's
my win main it looks like we're we sort
of did come through here
so I'm not sure what happened to those
settings exactly but let's find out so
here we go to render commands now look
at those render commands so here are the
settings and you can see that they're
correct that's what I would expect them
to be right so now the question is when
we go through to actually do the
rendering you know what happens why are
we getting something weird do we act do
I clear those out somewhere you know I
don't I don't really remember what we
did here in this part of the code
oops thank you for popping up my window
but the moment I kind of need to be back
here so off we go you know we're doing
our thing we're going into the renderer
here in a second
do setting up the input dealing with
mouse buttons and things let's just skip
over this to the game update there we go
game update and render and we're passing
the render commands here and you can see
we're passing the address of the one
that we think we're passing so when we
come in here in theory we should see
that the settings are correct you know
and they are so that's good so I'm going
to come back out here and you know
nothing nothing bad has happened yet so
now we're going to come through here and
the sounds going to do its thing right
so here's the sound stuff which we have
sounds turned off at the moment because
we don't want to have to listen to the
preparing debugging but they're they're
there so then we're going to come
through and we're going to process the
frame end stuff again that's going to do
the same render commands and then in
theory like we should be able to just
see here manage textures text refers
free that's all fine textures and slide
buffer in window so this is the part
that's it's having trouble
and and we kind of we kind of nerve
ourselves there right and so I'm not
sure what's going on so let's back up a
little bit here and let's just see
what's getting passed down so here's the
wind mane and there's the render
commands right you can see them they're
still right here so just inside win32
inside here let's see if we're getting
reasonable things here's our commands
note they're still reasonable there so
we come down in here to render commands
and we're looking at this render
commands and let's see what this has got
for us here and it's got the right
settings so I must just be doing
something stupid in here oh and yes I am
I'm passing the old settings so that's
just a that's just a typo right a dumb
typo nothing nothing - nothing -
concerning or weird happening there
that's just me for getting to pass the
new settings instead I pass the old
settings maybe I'll call this change to
settings
[Applause]
all right so now we're at least running
but we're not running correctly right
we're seeing gray screen instead of what
we should be seeing which is you know
some kind of a valid rendering of the
game so now we just have to go through
and this is the uninventive 3d graphics
programming which goes through and
figure out what we messed up right and
this is again I just want to
re-emphasize this many times until we
can switch to a better machine on
handmade Hiro normally in any normal
development environment at this point
you would switch to some kind of a
graphics debugger if you have one
we don't have one that we can use on
this machine but if you're if you have
access to say if you on an Nvidia card
and you can run insight that makes this
kind of problem where you just like I
know this is a functional pipeline I was
running it just a little bit before I
did a bunch of cleanup where I had to
rearrange some things and now I get a
black screen or whatever or r-equivalent
black screen which is gray screen when
that happens specifically something like
insight really can help you because
basically you can see at what part
things went wrong because you can
inspect individual stage in the pipeline
whereas we can't do that so what we have
to do is is you know go through the
standard blackbox debugging process
which like I said I don't mind doing on
the stream at all it takes longer but
it's a skill that you do need to have if
you're a ninja programmer because you
won't always have good tools it's kind
of a luxury in the modern era the fact
that people have made tools like insight
or render dock that do you know when
they are working or if you have a
machine on which they will work they do
offer you a great deal of insight but
it's exactly analogous to modern
debuggers where you know it's definitely
a luxury that we have something as much
as I complain about visual Studios
debugger
it's still a very good tool compared to
having nothing right and having nothing
is something that you occasionally have
to deal with you may be working on
hardware that literally just does not
have tools on it yet or the tools that
are on
are too broken to use or too buggy or
who knows what and so or maybe you're
just working on the kernel or of like an
operating system or something and you
haven't you know you you don't even have
the ability to hook up a debugger to it
right and you have to sort of bootstrap
it until you can get to the point where
that's something that can be done over a
remote you know connection or something
who knows right so you know part of
being a consummate engine programmer is
being able to do blackbox debugging for
sure so it's a good skill to have even
though like I say I would emphasize
there's no glory in it right so don't
don't blackbox debug something you have
the ability to transparent box debug
whatever you want to call that it's
really not black box more like opaque
box it doesn't matter what color the box
is it matters that you can't see through
it right
so it's opaque box versus transparent
box is really the more kind of important
thing to say but you know you get the
idea so that's the way we're going to
have to go through this but you know
we'll take it one step at the time and
we'll be slower but it's fine so what we
need to do now is we know that we had a
working pipeline and we know that I
broke it so really all I have to do is
figure out where in the pipeline I Pro
get possibly multiple places so we want
to try to do is force OpenGL hand to
show us where it is breaking right
that's what we want to do and you can
tell that there's multiple points at
which we could break right so one place
that we could break is you know at the
very end we could be doing everything
correctly but then something I changed
like made it so that we don't store the
resolved buffer texture handle correctly
and so when we go to do our final
stretch to the screen we don't get
anything right or something like that so
there's tons of things like that that
could be happening and we don't know
which one of them we are experiencing
right now so what we have to do is kind
of poke at it and see like you know
where along the lines we're going wrong
so let's just try some things first to
see what at all you know using kind of
structured art what at all it is we're
looking at because I don't know I'm just
seeing a gray screen I don't know what
else is going on so here we can see that
we're you know doing that final blit
right
why can I not there we go
and you know what that's going really
slowly I wonder if we're having
something where we're doing this like
every time or something like that
doesn't seem to be the case hmm but
anyways that's sort of what I expect to
see there in terms of the you know the
black boxing of it there so looking at
that that doesn't concern me too badly
right that that seems to be okay there
for the most part so the other question
I would have here as far as the as far
as the final stretch is concerned there
I would like to know perhaps whether or
not that texture is being read from
properly so what I would like to do in
the in the final stretch there is maybe
go into the program here I and I did you
know just figure out if I'm if I'm
running correctly so here's the the
final stretch code and what I'm going to
do is I'm just going to force the red
channel to one so that I can verify that
you know that shader is running right
all right so that's a good sign that
shader is running it seems to be running
in the right place at the right time so
that's good we don't really know whether
this texture is being read from
correctly and that's a harder thing to
test because we don't really have a way
of forcing that texture to have
particular contents in any way that's
really particularly reliable that's a
harder test to do with the way that we
have to work with
you know these we can't reach in and
poke at the graphics memory very
effectively which is how we would have
wanted to do that so let's take a look
here at how we're generating that
texture and maybe let's also take a look
at what that texture actually is as far
as which handle it's assigned to at the
time right so let's go in here and say
you know let me look at at this final
stretch call here we know that that
shader is running properly but let's
take a look at the OpenGL stretch and
just see what we're actually sending
down
so here are our buffers you know that
we've got let's take a look at them so
you can see that this this looks pretty
good to me right the frame buffer handle
of one seems like exactly what it should
be because that's the first frame buffer
handle and this is the first frame
buffer that we allocate so that makes
reasonable sense if you assume the
driver just gives them out in order
starting at number one the color handle
of seven makes sense because we do
allocate other things before this
texture handles and so forth and a depth
handle of zero also makes sense because
remember the resolve buffer doesn't use
depth testing so there is no need for a
death buffer on the resolved buffer our
def peeled buffer is similar look about
as good as you could hope to three four
or five which is the next frame buffers
in the sequence makes sense eight nine
ten eleven twelve thirteen fourteen
fifteen so all of those look like anyway
they have been created correct correctly
as far as I can tell we also have the
render width and height look about right
we've got you know pretty much all this
stuff seems seems reasonably good for
the most part again it's a little bit
hard to tell so I'm pretty happy with
that
however we have other things that could
be creating problems in here and so what
I would like to do is just make sure
that you know the when we create these
textures we're doing everything
correctly so here in open gel that's
right on the run place
I wanted my yeah great frame buffer so
here in the create frame buffer we
passed the width height and the flags I
don't know for certain if we did
everything correctly here oh that's not
where I meant to do that that's a little
bit of mistake sorry about that
[Applause]
where I actually wanted to do that was
here where we say open geo multi
sampling I wanted this to be false now
that won't change anything because that
should still have exactly the same
effect but just want to make sure okay
so yeah that's what I meant to do I
meant to kill it here not in the other
place
all right so in theory this has
basically all the stuff that I would
have expected to have the programs are
compiled the way I would expect them to
be compiled the frame buffers are
getting created the way that I would
expect them to get created so now the
question is just what is the secret
thing that's not quite right here so one
thing that's definitely true
so that depth peel count there
I'm not sure about the depth peel count
either so what I would like to do is I'd
like to go back and say you know one of
the things that I realized about having
the depth key account being programmatic
that we don't really technically support
is the fact that our final composite
really only supports four no matter what
so you know it's a little bit harder to
figure out how that would work but we
could write that shader in a way that
that would allow us to do something more
creative there so maybe we'll look at
that in future anyway so anyway what we
want to do here is figure out yeah okay
so are we getting any data on these
deputy buffers or aren't we right like
what's the what are we are we ever
drawing anything to these depth field
buffers and so one thing that I should
be able to do in least in theory is I
should still be able to use this this
sort of end part right here to you know
to blitt these two frame buffers
together so if I was to say let's take
the render width and the render height
and draw that to the draw region right I
if I was going to do that what would I
get here right so if I if I was to look
at say the depth feel buffers so here's
a def peel buffer what would happen if I
bound that and then drew from it right
so that's deaf peel buffer zero and it
looks like there's nothing on it and
that's troublesome now I can verify that
I'm actually drawing to the one I think
I'm drawing from by setting you know
again just poking in there and saying
hey let's see if I can see red so I can
so this suggests to me that our problem
is really just in the render phase it
looks like we're not drawing anything
right and so we need to figure out why
we're not drawing anything at least on
the first depth peel you'd think we'd be
able to draw something onto something
so where do we bind that frame buffer
right so if we come through here you can
see us specifying the buffer data you
can see us setting up the textures for
the test feeling but where is the open
where do we bind the frame buffer it
looks like we commented that out for
some reason I don't know when we did
that did I do that just now but where is
the bind frame buffer call oh I guess it
happens in here no it would have to
happen up here right how are we doing
this
yeah I don't really know what this was
supposed to do exactly so I guess the
problem is just we're never targeting
any of these frame buffers that's just
kind of busted yeah so I don't know
there's a couple of ways we could do
that I'm not sure which one we really
want to do but I think we probably just
want to target the frame buffer right in
here right we just want to say like hey
when you start out here we need to
target whichever one of these you're on
[Applause]
there we go
okay so that's a lot better now we're
actually seeing one of these things that
doesn't look like the frontmost frame
buffer to me to be completely honest
with you so that's a little weird and
also it's not animating which is
extremely weird I might say so things
are still bizarre but we're getting
closer right yeah and if I take a look
at what the peel index is here the first
time through the peel index should be
zero so in theory right that should be
fine I also don't know when we come
outside here and we set the frame buffer
handle back to zero I'm not sure how
that was working in the past because
that that depth peeling shouldn't have
so I think the only way this was working
is cuz of that max render target stuff
was sort of saving our bacon there so
this this stuff is actually just totally
wrong actually right we were we were
doing this pretty pretty raw so I might
say that that you know it's a little bit
hard to figure out exactly how we want
to do this but I kind of feel like what
we wanted to do is just say you know the
depth feeling happens and then you write
to the front most peel thereafter so you
kind of want to just say hey at the
outset you're targeting the first depth
peel buffer when you're no longer doing
it you're also targeting it and then at
all other times you're targeting
whatever the you know the DEF peel
buffer is
or somewhere in between there right that
seems like roughly correct to me so I'm
going to say that's just how that goes
and furthermore during the begin peel
part of things we could do this a little
bit more cleanly you know we could do
something a little bit more like hey
when we begin the peels we set to
whatever the peel index is the target
there and and off we go
yeah so this looks a little bit better
here to me I don't know it's a little
arbitrary I feel like we could probably
stand to clean it up a little bit more
than we have but it's not awful it's
like it's okay right so if we're peeling
so yeah okay so I also should say the
peeling is only if we're at peel index
greater than zero because the first time
through we're not technically peeling
yeah Wow so something's totally messed
up a little bit beyond that though right
but we're getting a little closer so
again that's just bleeding the
framebuffer I'm going to see if now if
the rest of the pipeline is working I
suspect it probably is yeah but we've
got some we've got some really other
very weird things I do wonder if that
maybe is just because we're not and this
is probably the case so remember when I
said why do we do this I think it's
because we need to reset this every time
the push buffer part of it right because
the push buffer goes forwards and then
it would never go backwards so the
render commands part really needs a like
a reset here so when we get down to the
end of it
to be look right here so after we're
done with the frame display and we draw
everything then at that point we would
want to reset a you know afraid the
render so if we take a look at what has
to happen there we'd say well the render
commands pushed buffer base needs to
poops the render command push buffer
data at has to equal the push buffer
base and the render commands vertex
count needs to equal zero right so we
just need to like reset so we're getting
there but we're not there yet
like now we we've undone the major
damage there but we're not quite there
yet you can kind of see it looks sort of
to me like we're not white depth peeling
like we're just looking at the frontmost
he'll probably I think don't quote me on
this but I think so why are we only
seeing the front most def field let's
just verify that's true or that
something like that is true so actually
let me go over here so you can see that
without it being behind my head all
right so here's peel zero so it's not
quite just the front one let's get peel
you know just the next layer back so
there's the next layer back and as you
can see not particularly compelling
here's the next layer after that so it
looks like we're not drawing so I
probably just broke that loop so let's
take a look here at what's going to
happen so we're going to come in to
render entry begin peels we're going to
look at the header that we're on at the
moment and we're going to say that's the
jump point so we're going to do a loop
here we're going to jump back to here
you want to bind the peel frame buffer
goes with whatever peel index were on
which the first time three will be zero
future times hopefully will not be zero
then we set the peeling to whether or
not we're on the first one so we're not
considering peeling if we're only going
through once we are going to be
appealing when we come back through the
second time so then we say okay the
render entry peels in this case is make
sure this is right here to target
indexed FB account and these get freed
that looks roughly correct so we come
back down through to the render entry
peels end and so at the end of that
we're going to say if the peel index is
less than the max render target index
then what we need to do is jump
otherwise we're done right if we've done
the last one we're good to go right so
if we're not done we jump back to the
beginning and we increment the peel
index which will lead us to bind the
next buffer right hopefully and a set
peeling equal to true otherwise we'll
say let's make sure we've done all the
ones that we're going to do then let's
bind that last buffer back again in case
anyone has any non def peeled wrong to
do it'll go on to the front peel so then
we've got render interview clear I don't
know that we care that about that very
much because that's literally only for
the debug system we want it to work but
we don't care about it right now
then we've got entry textured quads the
textured quads is the thing that
actually does the drawing pretty much
all of the drawing so in here when we
come through if the fielding is equal to
true or if it's equal to false there's
two different paths the false case will
not set up a peel texture the true case
will and so in that case when we are
setting up a texture to peel from you
can see us doing it here what we're
doing is saying grab the one that's
whatever that's one behind the one that
I'm currently bound to which seems like
the correct thing to do and we should
already be targeting the correct target
because we did it up here right we
should have set it to the correct target
in render entry begin peels
so here's what the problem is it looks
like is in this case we're going to
increment so we don't we never actually
run this code is what looks like is the
problem so I think I do come right
because we're going to increment over
that header so it's going to skip the
that begin so it does kind of look like
in order to do this I will have to leave
it in here like I will have to leave it
like this but which I guess that's not a
huge deal so that looks better now we're
getting that that death deal so let's
take a look and see if I have restored
us to good working order here maybe I
have
[Applause]
that's looking correct to me now I don't
see any obvious problems this looks like
it looked before the depth fades looking
pretty good all the particles look good
yes I think that's pretty good so there
we go
okay good and now the other thing that's
nice about this is we should be able to
make some like renderer settings kind of
things here as well just just out of
that sort of that platform set of things
that we have here so you know if we want
to we can now make some of these
settings these things that we can edit
so for example if we want to we can go
into a handmade left cpp and where we
set the renderer here what we should be
able to do is set a bunch of debug flags
that can be changed here right and yeah
I don't ever remember how to do any of
this stuff but let's just say that we
were going to do render commands dot
settings and pixelation hints was one of
them and multi sampling hints was like
another one of them or something
now I don't know if that'll actually
work because I never remember how the
debug system works but it looks like
that sign and so you can see us be able
to change these two and they should
change at runtime and they do now the
important thing to remember is we're not
done yet because at the moment we do not
actually delete any of our resources so
if we were to wail on this button enough
in theory we should run out of memory or
something on the graphics card right
like because we are not freeing when we
create a bunch of new frame buffers
we're not freeing the old frame buffers
so we do need to go do that but it's
nice to know anyway at this point you
know that we that we have that option so
let's go in here and see in terms of
what our other settings are I don't know
that there's anything else in particular
so let's just go ahead and try to enable
multi sampling and also let's try to
enable cleanup right so what we want to
do here in our our cleanup code is you
can you can see what we've got
I don't know how much time I have left
what what what time did we start does
this thing know to the into that now
thirty thirty three minutes until Q&amp;A it
says so so that's quite some time I
think all right so what I want to do
here is I want to say you know I've got
these resources that I allocated and you
know I can kind of I can group these
together right and say something like
this
[Applause]
that all of this stuff you know kinda is
on the table right meaning all of this
stuff up here is stuff that you don't
really have to worry about because these
like reserved lip texture vertex buffer
stuff those are things that stay around
and it doesn't matter how many time to
change it say it settings you don't need
to worry about them these on the other
hand are right so what we want to do
here is just say okay when we you know
go to do our settings change we just
want to make sure that we loop through
all this stuff we might have two free
and free it right so let's go ahead and
take a look at that here is open jail
change the settings so what I want to do
here is in fact let me just do it here
[Applause]
so what I want to do is first I want to
you know free frame buffer for release
frame buffer whatever you want to call
this I want to frame that resolved frame
buffer and then I want to loop through
and I want to free all these frame
buffers and we don't really store the
depth peel count here do we oh we do
good
[Applause]
and maybe I'll grab these two since
they're sort of yeah
and that if we did that that's really
the only reason as we create because you
can kind of see down here we only
created three resources so the only
other thing we have to free are our
programs so we just need like a free
program call right and we need to free
all of these things so this is basically
free all dynamic resources create new
dynamic resources right so now we just
need these two calls we need a way to
free the frame buffer and we need a way
to free a program and so I don't
remember much about the program thing I
know they have open till program common
so that's really all we need here and
I'm pretty sure that the shaders are
already free so let me just page this
back into my head how we were doing that
here we have a create program call right
you can see it and I'm not sure exactly
how we were doing this so here's create
program we specify that we want to
compile these shaders we then attach the
shaders and validate the program now I
think we want to actually delete the
shaders at this point I think
I think I don't know but I think we want
something like this let me just let me
just double-check
yes so I'm pretty sure yes you can see
here right like it basically says that
you can do this right away so we can
basically say like hey we don't need
this anymore just so you know and that
way we don't have to store this
information because we don't care right
so now let's say when you delete the
program delete the shaders it's
basically what it's doing so what we
want to do is is then say okay now we
need a way to delete the program proper
so when we come down here to that free
program call all we need to do now the
only thing that we have left over is the
program handle itself so we just need a
way to delete the program and so let's
go ahead and do that so frame buffer
oops that's in the wrong place frame
buffer that's good program prog and then
the other thing I'm going to do is I'm
going to set program frog to zero just
so we can see that it's zeroed out that
seems like a good idea to me anyway
and then here let's go ahead and say we
need to do our frame buffer stuff so our
frame buffer has a couple of different
things in it it's got a frame buffer
handle car handle a deft handle so what
I want to do there is I want to do like
GL delete textures and I want to delete
the texture handles and I also want to
delete the frame buffer so I'm going to
do frame buffer handle color handle
depth handle
[Applause]
let's see what delete frame buffers is
about
[Applause]
hello
so it's exactly the same so this will
delete the frame buffers and textures so
that they're no longer in use but what I
want to do is I since I don't really
know what these have and don't have I'm
going to use zero as the way of knowing
that they're not there now I think
that's allowed in OpenGL meaning I don't
think OpenGL will return zero I know
that that's true for delete framers I'm
pretty sure it's true for textures too
because you can do bind texture zero so
texture zero is not a valid texture to
be like owning so all I'm going to do
here is say well okay if the color
handle is zero don't do this right
assume that you never created one and
the same will be true with basically all
of these so they're just checking hey
you know if zeros if it's actually at a
second valid get rid of it otherwise
don't write and I think that should be
all we really need to do now I don't
know if we ever got some of these yeah
so delete shader delete frame buffer and
what is it prog handle what what is the
name of that actual field prog handle i
am nothing if not unnecessarily
consistent okay so looks like that's all
there is to it and so now I just need
those OpenGL calls and I think we're
done and then we can kind of flip back
and forth between them pretty much it
will
all right so let's go ahead and get
those we still we're not havin any
problems are because that web was a
little fishy there no dropped frames
good the when the web when when I went
slow to act as the web I always worried
that maybe the streaming has broken uh
you know or something like this this is
on Comcast business internet otherwise
known as the worst Internet service I've
ever used
if you thought Comcast home internet was
bad wait till you try their business
class service it's three times the price
and one-tenth the service all right
let's take a look what do we have for
for OpenGL stuff here we've got to have
our delete calls basically
[Music]
and or armed to the rescue
here comes the core ARB header there it
is so we need to leap program let's go
ahead and grab that why are there two of
them sweet prim pipelines okay so we
need these to leap program and delete
engineer delete shader go and it looks
like I need those as well
[Music]
like Price is Right theme music weekend
[Applause]
alright so we need those two and we also
need the delete frame buffer caulk but
don't think we have that either so I
just want to grab that one and plop it
in there there we go
and it's supposed to be delete frame
buffers isn't it yeah so that's
that's that so now I should just be able
to grab all these and that's good all
right so we've got all our up in jail
functions now and I think that should
just work
delete frame buffers is the actual call
now unfortunately there's not again
without a GPU debugging tool
unfortunately there's not a lot of good
ways to test this out so like oops
that's not what I want to do so there's
you know like if it was just us
allocating memory ourselves it would be
a lot easier to determine because what
we could do is we could look here at you
know the various size stuff that we're
looking at and we can see whether or not
we're like going up sort of permanently
or not it's harder to do in a situation
where we can't you know because it might
be the graphics card might be hiding the
fact and it won't be attributed
necessarily to our process so I'm just
going to wail on this for a while and
see where we're at
and again like it's like I said it's
really hard to say like it looks like
we're thrashing a little bit there
potentially right so I'm not super it's
hard I going to gets really hard to say
like you know maybe that's just
something the driver is doing naturally
and it's not our fault or maybe we're
not freeing something you know so it's a
little hard to know we could use a cult
there's card specific calls you could
use to figure out how much memory you
actually have on the card and it could
be that that would help help us figure
that out
yeah so it's hard to say so I'm not I'm
not 100% convinced I'm going to put a
little to do on this guy in case you
want to take a look at it in a little
more detail later so you know I think
I'm telling it the right things to get
rid of the stuff that we allocated
because you can see like I come through
here and I can look and say well ok I
compile for programs and create one plus
depth appeal count frame buffers and so
in theory if I free one plus four ah
there we go
[Applause]
ha ha let's try that one more time and
again this is not the right way to
verify this I can't stress that enough
it's just the poor person's way of doing
it at the moment
so I can't again really can't tell it it
looks a little better maybe but again I
can't tell that number is going up right
so I'm not 100% sure that everything is
okay but I can't tell because I don't
know if that's just the driver caching
more shader compiles or something like
this or whether it means I'm not freeing
everything right I and so in order to
independently verify that I need
something better than this but I don't
have anything better than this right now
what I want to do is see a thing that
says what are the open handles on this
thing and I'm not sure whether or not I
can get that so what you know what I
might be able to do is like GL get and
you know maybe I can oops I don't want
the OpenGL ES version maybe I can get
you know something here that says how
many of something there are so that I
could say you know how many of these
things do you think there are right now
and and I can verify those not going up
right so that would be nice
I don't know if there is such a thing
though you know I can get maximum zuv
stuff obviously but I don't know that I
can get a thing that actually tells me
hey how many of these things you if you
got
yeah so I guess well I'm going to leave
that to doing because like I said I'm
not not super sure about it right okay
so now I'm going to leave this out of
time here I guess I'm going to leave
this as is because it's in relatively
good shape now I'm going to leave this
as it is but I'm going to turn the multi
sampling part back on and that way we
can see what we have to do to in order
to improve that right so it oh well this
is we know what this is this is the
thing where we can't create a srgb well
no that isn't what this is this is
probably the this is probably the fact
that we can't read from a leak we are
not allowed to read from a texture
that's multi sampled as if it was normal
right I assume is what that is all right
so that's what we have to do
[Applause]
and so we've got ourselves set up now so
that we can do these switches and we
should be good to go pretty much and we
can change the resolution on the fly as
well so if we want to and so we should
be in a good position for next weekend
to get multi sampling working clean up
those jaggies and anything else that we
might want to do there i and i'm
guessing like i don't really know how
we're going to approach it necessarily
but my assumption is we probably don't
quite want to do it like we don't need
multi sampling on all of our depth
fields probably we probably just need
multi sampling on the front most def
peel would be my guess and any depth
peels beyond that probably just don't
need it that would be my guess
furthermore the z-buffer probably
doesn't really need to be done that way
so I think probably what we'll do is
just multi sample the front color buffer
and that would be it right so multi
sample the front color buffer bleed it
down to a regular buffer rest of the
pipeline as normal that be my assumption
all right let's go to a Q&amp;A
oops there we go
Gary Johansson so one of my left-field
questions do you think there is a case
we made for a GL implementation to be
written an open CL open til having class
we do natively run on the CPU and it's
compatible with Visual Studio so you
could CPU debug your OpenGL code in
Visual Studio with that capacity solve
the OpenGL debug problem or is the
problem typically somewhere else like
actual problems with a baked GPU
functionality if that all makes sense
yeah so I guess what I would say is
I guess what I would say is there's many
aspects to the GPU programming problem
and I don't think they would get solved
by what you're suggesting first let me
point out that open feel isn't the only
thing that can be debugged right on the
on the GPU you can install insight and
you know when if you wave a dead chicken
and that the full moon and whatever else
right you can step through your shader
code and that's a huge bonus right that
means that shader code can kind of be
debugged sort of like normal code and
that's pretty awesome
now I don't think that's actually
similar to how CPUs get debugged I don't
think what they're actually doing there
is interrupting the program in the
middle of running the shader and looking
at the values which is what's happening
on a CPU
I think what's actually probably
happening is they're just running
something that inserts something that
writes out the state at that point in
the shader and then pulls it back or
something and then just reruns the whole
thing again to get to the next step or
whatever I don't know but I don't really
know how much debugging support GPUs
actually have in the same way that like
an Intel chip has to bug your support
right so I don't really know about that
either way but it for purposes of most
debugging operations you might want to
do the appearance of debugging shader
code is good enough on something like M
site
to get you by and I feel like that's
really all you would get from the OpenCL
suggestion that you're talking about
there and the reason I think that is
because there's so much more to the GPU
problem than that so first of all the
biggest problem with GPU isn't really
the fact that it's harder to debug the
GPU it's the fact that you have no idea
what the GPU is actually going to do at
all right on x64 there is a
specification that says here is the
binary format that will get submitted to
the chip and here is what that will do
and it's incredibly incredibly
incredibly rigorous like as rigorous as
anything else in computing certainly far
more rigorous than something like a
language specification like the C or C++
specifications it's way more rigorous
than that right and what that means is
that a programmer at the lowest level
can know exactly what the chip is
supposed to do and Intel has literally a
hardware bug which occasionally they do
have but very rarely if it does not do
that right and the times when I have hit
a hardware bug in an Intel CPU is
actually zero they have had them but I
have literally never had that happen to
be in practice on a bug I was debugging
ever not a single time and I've been
programming Intel chips since probably
nineteen eighty five or six right
earlier than that
I don't remember I have been programming
Intel chips for a very very very long
time and that has never happened right
on the other hand on the GPU side of
things you have none of those things
there are driver or Hardware bugs all
the time you are very likely to hit some
especially the driver bugs right and
there is no specification for what's
supposed to happen at all right so you
have no idea even like what the ordering
requirements are for a lot of the things
in what you're doing you don't even
really know any of that stuff right to a
certain extent OpenGL specifies or you
know certain graphic standards set by
certain things like two subsequent draws
have to appear like they happened in
that order if they target the same frame
buffer or something like this right you
know some of those sorts of things but
that's about all you really know and so
there's no binary specification there's
no rigorous specification for anything
else
there's not even rigorous specifications
for how many of things there are right
there completely variable like I don't
know how many textures going to read
from how many frame buffers can I have
how many whatever right it's not like a
CPU where the only variables really like
memory and thread count
there's tons of variables on a card even
stuff like can it do this thing like you
know are very are not even they're not
at the instruction level they're like at
a whole conceptual level right so I feel
like when you're in that situation and
there's so much machinery you have no
idea what's going on you write this
thing it goes through all kinds of
drivers software first then it does all
kinds of things in the hardware that you
don't know what it's doing
you can't inspect any of that you can't
step into the driver you got none of
this stuff that's really the biggest
bulk of the problem and having that run
and OpenCL all that would tell you is
what happens on the OpenCL
implementation of this thing but that's
really not relevant to you I mean maybe
it would help you get stuff working
where the only problem with it is you're
misunderstanding about something in the
a
now you can step through and see a
reference implementation of it but
that's about all you would get so I
think the far more interesting thing is
to say can we stop doing things this way
and instead move towards a thing where
we have a rigorous specification for an
is a like x64 where that's what you
write and that is what the graphics card
has to execute right and the reason that
we don't do that is again because it's
GPU vendors want the ability to innovate
across all aspects of their pipeline and
they want as much flexibility to do that
as possible that'd be great
if the primary problem these days with
graphics performance unfortunately for
99% of applications it's not the primary
problem is reliability right and so
we're at a point where the trade-off of
performance at all cost is a very bad
trade-off to be making and what I think
we would much rather have is stability
like we have on x6 before where yes
every year they try very hard to get
more performance but they don't
sacrifice rigorous specification and
reliable execution to get it so a GPU is
a where we just have a binary format
that's basically the same kind of thing
as x64 that gets handed over and gets
executed on the GPU like a normal chip
that is really the thing that we want I
am 100% certain that would be better for
just about everybody except for the very
very small case of people who are only
concerned about getting the absolute
maximum performance out of every
generation which is almost nobody these
days ten years ago it was a lot more
people nowadays it's nobody right you
know it's one or two games a year and I
just don't think running our whole
industry off of the needs of one or two
games a year it's a very good idea and I
realize that's not something that GPU
vendors want to hear but I don't know I
don't think it's really necessarily the
case that the only thing people will
drive GPU sales is performance I think
stability is a big driver of of sales
and I think that there's a world out
there that does have a lot of economic
benefits that's just a world where GPU
vendors deliver reliability you know and
you know as an answer I do think there
are performance gains to be had by
having a known targetable chip also a
known target Eliza I think you know we
may get some of that performance that
you lose from the flexible changes that
GPU vendors can make under a non
specified but not having an ice ax
I think specifying an ice ax does have
programming benefits that will get some
of that performance back because now
people are not there's no driver in the
way anymore drivers have traditionally a
huge source of inefficiency that would
go away because there's now no longer a
driver right or if there's a driver it's
incredibly minimal in generic just like
you know there's no Intel you don't then
install a driver for your x64 chip
beyond just the basics of you know the
the basic windows sort of like CPU
thunking stuff
then I called up Casey I started to
program more like the way you teach and
I'm liking it so far but there's one
thing that makes you feel strange when
using struts to set up some data that
will be used by a function later how
could I make sure that I won't forget to
set some member of that struct before
calling that function is there a way to
make sure I always initialize every
member of the structure to a value other
than 0 no there really isn't a way to do
that that's why I tend to use very
specifically in most cases clear to 0 as
the default so calling something in
passing a structure that's like all
zeros is the default way to use it and
setting things involves setting things
to non zero values I would say in
general if what you need to do is you
need to ensure that everything is set
and it can be very hard for you to debug
your code if you can't guarantee that
then I would advise against passing
things as structs to the entry level
function and what I would do is make a
wrapper function around your function
that just has all the parameters of the
struct and that way you have to pass
them all right the other thing that I'll
often do is if I don't care about the
performance in that particular area
which most of the time you don't I would
say oh there's some call or some struck
that's like default version of this
thing and I call that and I start with
that always so you do struct you know
whatever the struct is foo params equals
default foo params then you set the ones
you care about then you call right as we
might why do you type this some
structure in the render layer but not
all of them
we don't really typed F anything in
hand-made here because you don't need to
in C++ but in the platform layer
definitions things that are exposed to
platform layer we have to and the reason
for that is that some people are using C
like languages and they want to use this
for just the platform layer like Swift
or whatever or things like this
I guess it helps them out it was it was
by request people asked us to do that so
it makes it easier to compile on these
other platforms like objective-c maybe I
don't know what they I don't remember
which ones they were that they were
asking for that because it made it
easier for them to do something that's
the only reason they're in there C++
code you'd never have to type def
Struck's because structs automatically
type def in C++ that's just how that
works
Nicola Casey do you remove the certs
when shipping a game yet typically you
just compile them out it's used in a
sense Vulcan provides you in ISO with
strict specification but the
initialization code is quite fat no it
really doesn't
Vulcan does not specify anything even
remotely similar to and I say and not
only does it not specify an ISA but it
doesn't even provide an interface to
what you would want and I say to be
right it's it's just not even close
right I
I mean Vulcan doesn't even have in it
the concept that things have to support
bind list right and in is a that you
would create today has to be bind bus I
mean that's just a basic tenet of what
you would want an I say to be going
forward and it doesn't even really even
support it pretty much unex tended the
Vulcan the last time I looked at Fokin
it didn't even support it at all
right like it had extremely weak support
for non-binding non-binding workflows
you know non-binding attack laws and
that should be the default flow right so
so yeah Vulcan is in no way a nice 'it's
not even close and unless they made
significant changes to it compared to
the last one I looked at which they may
have so you know I could be wrong about
saying that but unless they made major
changes to it in the the final version
they weren't they weren't even close to
defining and I said they weren't even in
the ballpark of defining an ISA and the
things that they did define the API how
they did define to work are just not
even close to right for a for the way
you would want a modern GPU interface to
work in my opinion and I believe I could
be wrong but I believe the reason for
that is wanting to support old hardware
you know Vulcan was not designed to be a
modern API it was designed actually to
be a very backwards compatible API it
was designed to support ships that are
quite old at this point
and that are quite underpowered compared
to what we would want in a modern ice ax
to look like and that's a real shame
jesse 23 I didn't quite understand how
OpenGL and multi-threading can cooperate
I believe you once said in an episode
that OpenGL context is specific to the
threads that created it so if I create
the context on a main thread can I not
have other worker threads call into
OpenGL without somehow setting the
context for each thread so OpenGL if you
don't use extensions to open jail it
doesn't really handle multi-threading
properly that's one of the biggest
problems with OpenGL and one of the
reasons why it's really still a legacy
API is that the multi-threading model
ended up in jail just doesn't work
extension wise it works just fine for
the most part if you're willing to use
like you know Nvidia extended OpenGL for
example there's you can pretty much
write exactly what you want to write and
there's only really one place that it
falls down and it's a place that's not
that bad to work around do I wish they
had extension to fix that too sure but
that's really only the in the platform
layer it's in the wiggle part of things
not in the open regular OpenGL part of
things so yes so extended OpenGL works
really great stock OpenGL is absolutely
horrible and again that's because of
this emphasis on binding and context
that you really don't even want and it
actually makes development more
difficult but it's just a legacy of how
OpenGL and they've kind of clung to it
but when you go to bind list if you go
to bind list plus MV command list you're
no longer talking to the driver pretty
much at all there's just one thing
that's like hey here's a giant batch of
Norma's amount of things to do go do it
is the only call and that's pretty easy
to keep on one thread right so but yeah
regular OpenGL no it's just I mean it's
it I could describe the various ways you
can try to get threading out of OpenGL
but really I
really you just can't you can try but
you will get beaten down severely and
partially by just this way it's
specified it just doesn't work
multi-threaded but more more than that
because you know if you read the spec
for OpenGL literally there are ways you
could make it work
the real problem is when you actually go
to try and run it it doesn't work on any
drivers and I mean literally any trying
to run OpenGL in heavy parallel
environments it just forget it
either you will just run into
straight-up non-functional scenarios or
you will end up with low performance one
of the - I've never seen anyone do get
anything else but like I said if what
you want is heavy multi-threading and
you don't mind about specified you know
being more specific to a graphics card
or to extended OpenGL can actually
support it quite well while your
submission calls still have to be single
threaded literally everything else can
be multi-threaded and you can make
almost no submission calls you know you
can get it down to just a few a frame
even for millions and millions of draw
calls right
all right are we done with queues I
think we are done with questions
probably
[Music]
alright looks like we're done
okay thank you everyone for joining me
for know sort of handmade here oh it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
with series at home you can always peer
to the game on handmade hero org and it
comes with a source code so that you can
play around with it and and learn from
it or experiment with it it's a it's a
pretty good learning resource we also
have a forum site you can go to to ask
questions
hosted by handmade Network we have a
patreon page and go to do not support
the video series the schedule bot that
tweets the schedule at you and an
episode guide which will help you catch
up on old episodes if you are so
inclined that is it for this week I may
not be back next week I don't know
there's a we're removing offices and I'm
not sure what status things will be in I
may just try to move handmade hero
streaming back to my home to my
apartment but I don't really know one
way or the other what will happen so I
can't promise they'll be streams next
weekend we'll be back the next weekend
after that I believe but yeah I I just
can't promise that
so we'll see keep keep keep in mind that
there may not be one I will certainly
check you know certainly check the
schedule but Friday night because it'll
say one way or the other on here but but
but no promises will I'm just not sure
with the internet situation or where the
machine is going to be or what's going
to go on so we'll play it by ear that's
about it for this week until next week
thanks for for joining me and I wanted
to mention again because I mentioned it
yesterday I was going to mention one
more time if you're interested in
supporting a debugger project there's a
new debugger project going on that you
know I am interested in one of the
things that we're still doing on
handmade here right is we've got a
replacement editor and we've got a
replacement drawing program that people
in the community have written right we
switched a for coder we switched to
Milton so the only thing we're really
still using is the compiler which is
Microsoft's compiler which
is okay you know I'm not I don't hate it
but we are still using their debugger
they're the buggers not the greatest
debugger and we've really cool to switch
to a debugger made by the community and
there is a project now that you can
support that is trying to do exactly
that make a debugger that can be
integrated into for coders so we
basically have like at our own IDE
effectively and if you want to check
that out it's lis a handmade network and
you can support that project you can
actually see it here it's got a patreon
page and so if you're if you're so
inclined is that's a you know project
that I'm kind of excited about and will
try to try it out on stream just as soon
as it's gotten to the point where we
could do some simple debugging with it
right we could use it in tandem with
visual studios debugger
when it gets to the point where we can
sort of start to play with it a little
bit so that's it just wanted to point
that out for people who are looking for
projects to support that might be cool
that's one to check out so please do and
then that's it for this week I will see
folks next week if we do get the stream
streaming situation set up if we don't
then it'll be probably the week after
that
but either way until then have fun
programming and I'll see everyone on the
Internet
take it easy everybody