have someone come and talk to us about
it Hann VidCon is sort of the the
overall like structural aspects of you
know how teens work at large game
companies or how the whole process you
know how hiring works how do you
management works things like you know
coding guidelines all these sorts of
things there's tons of stuff involved in
that and I just like can't really offer
much insight into it because in a
project like handmade hero again much
like the asset scale session with Chris
we we just don't run into any of these
things but you know having a team work
well is just as important as having the
code work well if not more so and so
I've invited Marco Kugler from Blizzard
to talk to us about how basically their
their studio functions and answer all of
the questions that I actually often get
asked on screen but unfortunately can't
answer because I really just don't have
that kind of experience to to give sort
of a good answer so please welcome Marco
and we'll be talking about
so give us some background because this
is new to me too
like how where did you get started in
game programming you you've worked at a
too big engine companies like high tech
and Blizzard so tell us a little bit
about your backgrounds for people who
don't know you already ok so I mean as
many in here I probably started out as a
hobbyist just being interested in
playing games and then trying to figure
out how they function and I'm from
Germany so I went through kind of school
there studied computer science there
wasn't a lot of kind of game curriculum
out there so a lot of the knowledge was
kind of like self-taught you'll find
people online and maybe collaborate on a
few projects some folks might recognize
like flip code or or communities like
that so so that's where I kind of got to
ask my questions and had knowledgeable
people give answers and then after I
finished my computer science degree I
was like thinking about what what am I
going to do with it there's this scary
game programming thing and maybe there's
a safer thing that is like staying at at
a university and maybe doing like
computer graphics research and stuff
like that so I was like well I'm gonna
give this games thing a try I sent out a
bunch of resumes mostly with graphics
demos and a company that at that point
hadn't released anything called Crytek
they were the first to respond I got to
interview and was hired to work on the
first console project that critique was
going to work on on the original Xbox so
xbox crisis
No No
[Music]
yeah the the project like I arrived and
I was supposed to be like a gameplay
programmer on that and within a month it
got cancelled okay so then they moved
everybody over to work on farcry and
that's kind of the first game that I got
to work on so I got to do that for the
like final year of that as a game play
and at the end multiplayer programmer
and just fixing things working on weapon
systems and first-person shooters and
then because Crytek is kind of like a
small company at that time right
how big is small I think it was up to 60
people like 60 people that shipped
farcry and the lead programmer of farcry
left and they were like oh we need a new
lead programmer so I ended up being the
lead programmer for crisis at the start
of that project okay and then because
titles mean very little things that
small companies yes then at some point
the person that was tech director on
that game he left so they're like all
right I guess you're gonna be tech
director of that okay so yes for people
who are unfamiliar with the term and
also even for people who are the company
to company there's definitely some
variation there it's not quite the
Hollywood model where it's like this job
means this specific thing can you say
late for Hollywood it means something
completely different
yeah you're talking to more like a Texan
yes so I mean more how their roles are
very really decide so the director does
you know this and this right in our case
tech director at different companies can
mean sort of very different things so
can you give us a little sort of
background on at Crytek what's the
difference between say a tech director
and a lead programmer or something like
this um I think so
at Crytek the structure was you had the
game team and you had the R&amp;D team and
the R&amp;D team worked on the engine and
the tech director was similar to the
lead programmer they're not lead game
programmer but lead programmer I said
and as such you were interfacing with
the engine team and kind of making sure
that the needs of the game are met by
the engine obviously since we're kind of
primarily like the engine was developed
for crisis at the time a lot of those
needs were very entangled and because of
kind of the graphics background I had I
was able to speak Rd enough to be able
to talk to those guys and yeah kind of
their learned all about 30 modern
workflows at the time of just being able
to rapidly iterate on stuff and yeah and
then after after crisis at some point I
was like I want to not work on the
first-person shooter and I have always
liked desert and and now I worked on
something that me being in Germany is
probably gonna get recognized but
somebody over here when I sent my resume
and so I took the chance to to talk with
lizard and I was playing Wow at the time
so as a lot of people were and yeah got
to interview for that as an engine
programmer God because Crytek
always kind of wanted to work on that
and had the chance at the end but there
were just a lot of kind of proceeded
positions from the people that kind of
found that yes for me and the core
engine team there and at blizzards I my
application data for Blizzard was
basically me kind of looking at World of
Warcraft and kind of deducing well you
must be doing these things and these
things and this is kind of maybe how
your engine works and without having to
go in and redo everything
there's maybe this list of things that
you could be doing okay in terms of like
making the game look a bit more modern
and
not appraising it but remastering some
of the old parts and yeah you kind of
sent them a list of low-hanging fruit if
you will you were like I think the
zoning is you hard for you to do and
you'd get some bang for the buck out of
this looking from the outside in yeah
making a lot of assumptions over how
things work those were all though
hanging fruits yeah and I think not
everything on that this is currently
done yes okay there's a lot of things
you wouldn't expect how they were done
the way they were done okay that's and
so how long have you been tech director
there so if in tech director for almost
four years okay
I went some time I guess the third tech
director on on world of warcraft and
I've been at the company for seven and a
half years okay so I guess let me sort
of ask some of the questions and you can
go anywhere you want with usage or
please don't feel as you have to say
anywhere within them but let me start
off by asking some some fairly basic
stuff and you kind of one of the things
that I wanted to ask you kind of already
started getting into it which was how
you apply to branch out with Blizzard
for example so yeah let's talk about
that sort of whole segment of how the
company would be run so it start may be
about giving some idea of what is the
team structure wizard in terms of the
programmers you know how do they get
hired like what how do they break down
into two teams like that give us some
idea of what it takes to actually make
the company function as a programming
team at this point right so yeah one
thing to say is that at lizard isn't a a
firm rule like one way to view Blizzard
is more like there's Blizzard and then
there is a bunch of semi independent
studios that which work on different
teams so like I work on team two which
was the second game play a game team
that Blizzard kind of had at the time
and yeah like you have the people that
work on the RTS stuff there's folks that
work on
I'll blow over watch hearthstone and so
forth and then you have also on the
engineering side kind of shared more
shared teams like battlenet there's a
huge group they were online platform
stuff and then corporate applications
things that like groups of people that
work on say the performance appraisal
tool that you run like reviews or
something literally mechanical aspects
of running the company are you know they
might automate some of these yeah and
these teams all work at this
traditionally when I joined the company
they were almost autonomous and over
time like especially like in the last
four years or so there's been a shift to
trying to share more technology between
those groups and and trying to
standardize a bit more because it just
doesn't scale right nice and there's you
have like an engine team here here here
here and so that they really are fairly
separate meaning you know it's maybe a
library gets passed back and forth but
for the most part it's fairly insular in
terms of the stuff that ships and
Warcraft is not the stuff that ships in
Diablo or something like this yeah if
there's knowledge that gets exchanged
there's I think like some folks call it
code stealing because we tasted because
co-chairing like starts implying
maintenance and support and that gets
difficult for people that have their
production schedules to to kind of
manage but as I kind of said that that
is shifting a bit at the moment so in
terms of the structure of World of
Warcraft as tech director I'm
responsible for like the teams that
build kind of the internal tools we use
for development the team that is
operating the live service the client
team and and kind of infrastructure
teams as well and I interface with other
groups that deal with like this
how we build a data center and this is
the hardware we need to deploy in China
or whatever in order to make things go
fast and the engineering groups that
that I have in particular are trying to
go mentally around fake the space so we
have gameplay which I actually have 2d
gameplay programmers that report in to
me because the the group is fairly large
and we we try to minimize the number of
people that folks have to manage I do
suppose that a game like World of
Warcraft has considerably more gameplay
programming than perhaps you know at
least for its time certainly a
contemporary game that was not massive
multiplayer or is that not true um so
the original World of Warcraft was
shipped I think with 10 engineers Wow
and a team of also like a core team of
40 people that I think at the end was
like around 60 12 years ago and I think
about four years of development time and
that's that's actually very clean for an
MMO I feel like that's probably pretty
tough - pretty tough to go into that and
and have it work out that well I think
people didn't know what they were
getting into and that's why they were
able to put to do it and the way it was
described to me at that time is that a
lot of people I mean obviously we were
super passionate about like MMOs and
EverQuest and those things right
so but they they had like they didn't do
anything super super awesome okay but
they didn't do anything shitty okay and
so they they got a mean like a mean
level of systems that work reason to be
well enough to support this thing right
which i think is really the criteria for
having clean ship right it's like you
have to make sure everything is up to
the competency level necessary to make
the game be what it needs to be right
and you know yeah if you
ended up with a system that's really
good but then one of us is really bad
the bad ones gonna cost you a lot more
than the Goodwin visor you probably
right right yeah and I mean there's
probably some stuff that we should get
into later about how those assumptions
that were made like for like 16 years
ago aren't really contemporary anymore
and and what things that weren't shitty
in the past the work that goes into
trying to fix that up as as we kind of
go along but anyway going back to team
kind of structures so we got gameplay we
have server those are the folks that
work on the actual like server code as
well as kind of the like maintaining the
life service then when you say maintain
the life service you just mean like I
guess I'm not sure exactly things
because you know content could be a part
of that technically like so what do you
what do you mean by main to in that
sense so well life service the the game
is running let's say somebody discovers
a dupe okay okay so server engineers
will go analyze that the game is running
people are figuring out a way to break
servers or make them crash and they so
there's sort of like an emergency team
in some sense in monitor performance the
health of the service from a from a
server standpoint but it's not
monitoring its it's also analyzing kind
of the bottlenecks of the code making
sure to deploy strategic fixes
rolling those outs and there's different
disciplines on the server team we have
something called reliability engineers
that that try to troubleshoot kind of
before it even gets to to other
engineers and the team just to kind of
point them already in the right
direction they also do a lot of
deployment of of data hot fixes and like
hot fixing as a whole is probably
something that we should also cover
later hot fixing yeah there's a bunch of
good stuff there
I'm keeping notes yeah then we have
database programmers Wow
lives and breathes kind of with its DB
database
programmers in this case mean people who
are programming and off-the-shelf
database where people are programming a
database that's custom we are using
Oracle ok and they're writing database
like they've read in programs for or to
Oracle yes got it and there's as the
distinction kind of between the static
database which is the world itself like
where are the spawns in the world and
all that stuff and then the persistent
DB which is all your player data like
the items you know and spells and stuff
like that yes
so that kind of covers server then we
have tools team that works on our editor
and other various tools that you start
assembling localization tools and and
that type of stuff then engine graphics
engine we used to have kind of a shared
Mac team at blizzards we just this week
I think decided that like one of the
programmers is now gonna be embedded
with the engine team so because Mac team
means basically there is a centralized
team that just does all the Mac boarding
for all of the other teams even though
they're completely different engines and
so on right they they work more as a
graphics abstraction and an OS
abstraction team and most of the engines
initially were kind of tx9 based but the
backends that I've seen on WoW since
I've been on Wow where there was an
OpenGL back-end for Windows there was an
OpenGL back-end for the Mac there's a
metal back-end for the Mac there's a dx9
back-end for Windows there's a dx11
back-end for Windows and we'll see what
else we can collect in the future and
you're just yeah as your as kind of
technology moved along your these things
become only soft supported and they
become unnecessary once we can drop
support for Windows XP we probably don't
need the X and
anymore so so that type of stuff and I
suppose that the tail on that support is
much longer for you because massive
multiplayer games you know can sell
worldwide and you are going to be
supporting like you know hardware from
people who've been playing for yeah how
many years at this point you could have
been playing what you said 16 is that
the number 16 was the beginning of
development malgo yes a 12 would be
their release so you might have people
who have literally been playing for 12
years on some windows XP box we do we do
and it's depressing if you look at you
look at percentages or whatever of that
right and any go like well it's you know
it's like 1% but it's 1% of how many
million right and then the cycle is it
may be worth to keep it alive and it's a
royal custom player right yeah whatever
it's like someone who's with you all the
time he's got to feel bad right because
you're like well if we turned up through
this thing then but I mean yeah yeah
Windows XP gets increasingly harder to
afford and especially if you rely on any
kind of third-party libraries or
whatever righteous they will stop suit
like they've dropped support a long time
ago right so just trying to get things
to compile you you need to hack around
kind of like what else to do out of the
box red cannot do it yeah say in your
language it yeah switch it over so then
engine UI is a specialized team so they
work on role as well as a lot of and I
mean yes as an MMO there's there's a lot
of UI but then we also have to support
an add-on ecosystem and infrastructure
so the community gets to solve all the
UI it'll pause that we kind of commit
yes then just this is a staggering
number of teams that you have to
basically I have 90 direct reports at
the moment okay so just kind of working
my way through systems
is a group that deals with a lot of the
infrastructure whether it's like build
systems or for content delivery like
being able to stream like you want to
install a partial set of the builds you
can still play
we background download stuff while
you're kind of installing on the fly
because I think Wow is installed right
now is 45 gigabytes or something like
because it just keeps adding content and
because it just keeps yep and we don't
yeah we don't really deprecated the old
stuff because somebody might want to log
in at some point and wants to be in gold
Shire and level 2 yeah that's where they
stop okay then we have a little bit of
an odd team because we it's hard to find
a name for it share technology and the
spirit behind that was to take some of
the parts of the WoW infrastructure and
D Wi-Fi it so that it could be more
readily shared within the company but
all right now those guys are focusing a
lot on our DB kind of systems that both
our internal development tools rely on
as well as deployment tools okay so they
were originally and you know intended to
sort of be almost like a mmm code mining
where we would kind of say this is good
or something else let's try to get it
out and and packaged up in a way that
people could use it but they're kind of
committed to something else the moment
yeah there was some like some efforts
were done there we're like wow
schenectady out and then we started
sharing that with the overwatch team and
they added UDP support to it because we
didn't really write their first person
shooter so baby writes these things and
then last but not least is automation
who are also a bit new to kind of the
WoW team like there was an automation
group that was within blizzards and and
some folks that were supposed to do
stuff for
for Wow as a whole but just make to ease
communication we kind of started
embedding them and now they're part of
the team and they did a lot of the
stress testing we have some automated
systems that do performance measurements
so as we're building content you know
these automated systems that are
monitoring the like building of the game
are monitoring the running of the game
um whereas it both so the performance
measurement tool is basically loads up
certain maps of the game and will place
cameras around the world and you know
get kind of all six directions or
whatever and then create heat maps of
the data because we have a lot of
content creators and staying on top of
everything as it's being created like is
very difficult I can and you kind of
need to back into that not for me this
is all the art there's committed stream
but more like this is all the art as
it's being put together and then the
earlier can work on performance the
better I'm sure a lot of people kind of
know that it's easy and simple but but
yeah there's just phases in the project
where you're paying more attention to
here's new feature development and then
at the end comes the OH all this pretty
stuff you may it doesn't really work on
our min spec anymore so we're gonna have
to start removing it and and making sure
that that happens early I think is it's
important so these are sorry and like
that was kind of the performance side
but they the stress testing that was
more a server performance type of thing
where they have a way of simulating kind
of user clients on the server and they
spawn up like hundreds of thousands of
them zero and then see what happens and
see where the breaking points are gotcha
yeah okay so that's actually it
tremendously sort of vast thing to
manage I guess so
it's kind of a fairly tree like
structure at that point I'm you said you
have nine reports which is actually a
lot there but it is those each
represents fairly large skews mean how
big are these these teams I guess um so
total it's 65 engineers including the
leads and that that work on the
engineering team of world of warcraft
okay so the teams themselves aren't huge
the teams themselves we try to keep them
small some are a bit bigger than we
would like because it means that like
somebody who is managing like I'm
managing nine people and ideally we'd
like to have it around five to seven per
manager I see but some of the new
arrivals with like automation they it
just is the structure we have I'm not
sure I do have a partner in this which
is Jonathan moon Shaw he's a engineering
manager so this is something which again
not every Blizzard team has but some
Blizzard teams do have and the
engineering manager partners with me and
the the leads to kind of manage more the
career side of an engineer at the
company okay whereas the lead is
responsible for the kind of yeah the
more the work itself like the actual
engineering work that that person does
obviously that's not a clear you know
water water oil right yeah it's not a
perfect split yeah
but having somebody to help off tank
certain problems getting a second
opinion or a second partner for for an
engineer to reach out to to help with
career growth and answering those
questions it's been very valuable so
let's talk about that a little bit
that's one of things I definitely wanted
to hear about so if you wouldn't mind
could we walk through for people who
like you know maybe they haven't had a
job in the game industry before so
either they're you know a student or
somebody learning at home and wants to
someday working a mystery or there's
somebody from a different discipline
you know they do web development or they
do you know I mean any really any kind
of development and wants to come to
games and you know knowing it's gonna be
kind of a different structure there so
look if you wouldn't mind could we can
we to start with West's like how do
people come to Blizzard I mean even you
yourself who was coming in at a fairly
high level in that transition actually
did submit a resume which was yes so
could you talk a little bit about since
you have a little bit of knowledge about
that process
where do potential candidates come from
and how do you find people who may
become you know you want to interview
this person or whatever well there's
many different paths right so obviously
kind of a simpler one is you you've
already worked in games like I did and
and then you write a resume and you send
that in and you apply for a certain
position and people will kind of look at
that resume see how much you're aligned
with the job that you're applying for
and then there's usually and this is
kind of the same for everybody there's
there's a phone screen where you have
like a 30 minute or 1 hour kind of phone
conversations and some small kind of
technical checks that that happened
during that time just make sure that
you're going to be able to survive in
the code base that you're going to land
in I see and then that leads to usually
an on-site interview and just so again
for so I have a good handle on it so you
know resumes are coming in from a formal
submission process yes so there is you
know I go to a website and submit it or
something like that happens there's
recruiting an HR who will look at like
they will pre screen based on
conversations that we have with them to
kind of guide them for the fit that we
are looking for in a certain position
and then you will get a bunch of resumes
for like a game play program or position
I said and then we we basically look at
those and we say
you know like these three candidates
look interesting can you maybe set up a
phone screen and then that leads to and
that phone screen is with actual
engineers a team that is not an HR or a
recruiter doing the phone screen the yes
the phone screen gets done with usually
the the hiring manager which is the lead
and our engineering manager and
sometimes I'm in there too and the
recruiter still tries to be and like the
touch point for the person so if he has
any questions about the interview
process the company the area you know
like how does relocation work or are
those things
that's usually the the recruiter that
would be answering those questions and
then yeah the actual technical part of
the interview gets done by the engineers
on the team and the people that you'd be
working with and then when we invite
somebody over for for an interview
there's a programming test that we
administer I say um and then the first
part of kind of the interview is let's
talk about the test and okay the way the
test is done is it's a a bunch of
programming questions C C++ and it's
intended not to be kind of the thing
that decides whether you get the job or
not right like we compile it doesn't run
I actually had to do this test with
words and anybody that has to write C
code with word no that's what I was I
was brought into a room there was like
there was a laptop it didn't have any
development environment on it so and
there you load up the dock file and then
you
so strictly out of curiosity so now it's
notepad plus plus or whatever so you
actually get something that understands
code okay there's gonna say that that's
a very odd thing for an engineering
candidate to walk in and see a tool that
would be more appropriate for like the
writers on the team or something that is
but how did that happen nobody knows
that we totally make sure that you both
face all your keywords correctly just to
emphasize that you know like whether you
forget a semicolon or not doesn't really
matter so just like sketch it out and we
don't want you have to worry about like
you're not familiar with developer
studio because you came from a UNIX
environment or something like that
generally I think the spirit behind the
word file was that you shouldn't be
given something that you can run right
area still has that criteria and that's
also why we're not like if it doesn't
work it's not the end of the world but
the idea of the test is to to kind of
start a conversation right and there is
usually more than one solution to one of
the problems and then you can talk about
the trade-offs and why this is faster
versus that and aside from just a kind
of the raw skill of oh yeah I know how
to manage memory or you know I I know
how to deal with a linked list or
something like that right and so just to
sort of get a full picture of that
process I think I understand it pretty
well now but yep the the part where we
do a phone screen yep
we're looking potentially for different
things on every phone screen meaning
depending on what we were hiring the
person for we might be talking about it
in Sun screen or is the phone screen
like fairly standard it's like every
phone screen is gonna be this way
because it's just a entry into the
system and then the code test is the
thing that maybe changes depending on
the candidates you know prospective
position so the phone screen has
there's like a very small kind of fixed
side to it which is a set of again like
C C++ type questions just kind of
general computer knowledge just to get a
little bit of a baseline and then I
think like the rest of the phone screen
is more about you see a resume and
you're trying to kind of like everybody
writes a resume in a different way right
some people are better at highlighting
what they did versus others and it's
about kind of understanding the
candidate more like you've worked on
this thing what did you actually like
what did you do
what were your responsibility is for was
something cool that you worked on why do
you want to be a blizzard while you're
looking for a change like some of the
initial kind of questions that you would
have for a candidate and then and then
the actual test is more while we have
like a few variations we don't have a
lot of variations on the test and the
idea is though for like somebody even
coming in at an associate level they
should be able to finish the test and
they might take the fall a lot of time
where somebody more senior is able to
either give better answers or I finish
the test faster and and those are kind
of good things to to lead up with like
what do you think of the test what were
the things that you spent more time on
than others right and and that just
helps kind of set a few baseline things
for the rest of the conversation right
and so in some sense I guess if I go to
the first part of that phone screen is
sort of saying like we're gonna you know
we saw this resume we think this might
be somebody who we might be interested
in we're gonna try and help make sure we
regularize these these resumes a little
bit like basically help people who maybe
you know aren't good at giving us the
information we actually want so that
we're not discarding their resume out of
hand if you will right and you know okay
so for the code test obviously you
wouldn't want to say what they were but
can you give some sort of like a
example of something that's not what you
get for a coat test in terms of
complexity level like okay you know how
hard of a test are we talking about here
in term you know and I know that's a
hard question answer cuz code there's no
universal difficulty scale but like you
know what's it on the order of in turn
in that terms is there any way you could
give us some idea without divulging you
know at the thing that you want to keep
safe I mean probably if you because we
don't change it a lot you could probably
Google for it although we're going to
change it after this now but mostly I
would say data structure type questions
or answering a like analyze this data in
a certain way or data transformation
like using this input produce this
output type of things so you just kind
of want to see if they understand the
fundamental concept of like let's take
some input that we have this
well-defined let's build some data
structures that we will need to do
something to it and then let's get it
into the output format can they do this
process yeah and it generally says you
know try to you know take runtime
considerations into account obviously
correctness matters as well and yeah and
a few of those there's just a bunch of
trade-offs and memory management is also
a part of it because that's I think one
of the skills that were like it's
getting harder for people to learn Yesi
cuz they're like with unity and unreal
out there there's a lot of people that
like start learning game development
that way yes and they might not
necessarily get exposed to what it takes
to actually make something which is why
yes I think your your video series is
really helpful and I deal with that
thank you and yeah and it it does come
down to like hey why is it inkless
faster
slower than you know iterating through
an array I see like do they do you
actually understand by that which is why
that happens right so those are kind of
things that we deal with in the code
test then depending on if you you know
if you apply for an engine position
there's other stuff that you're going to
talk to outright that is much more
specific whether that's how to implement
certain effects or dealing with 3d math
type problems animation and like those
types of types of things so that's kind
of for like the interview part obviously
is kind of the same for everybody then
there is the yes I've worked at a games
company and this is my resume we have an
internship program that is very popular
unfortunately which means that somebody
mark to get into somebody will say you
know I I'm okay with like one of the
leads will say I'm okay with taking on
an intern and I think that is like a
three month period or so and then
through our university relations program
there's a bunch of in like resumes and
applications that are being solicited
through that nice and then you get a
folder with 120 applications for one
internship for one internship and
obviously that's that's kind of a long
shot but one of the things that I've
seen at least is that after this interns
sometimes return I see and then there's
also kind of a part of the program where
there's the possibility to offer them
already kind of a job so that once they
finish there are there in the pipeline
sir exactly so that they kind of know
what their future might look like right
and could you just briefly mention
something you said there you said
University Relations program yeah what
exactly does that entail because I mean
it's that yeah I guess I have no I
imagine some things that could be but I
have no idea um I think I actually don't
know but that's I think there is with
internships it's also it's kind of which
area do you do you service that from so
I think University Relations is a bit
more local in general working with
universities near Irvine so it doesn't
like a university in Europe for example
like where you went to school might not
be if you have a certain curriculum I
it also as a contact point I think for a
university to reach out to to start
making a connection I say but the extent
to how far they go I actually don't know
the details of that okay so that makes
sense so so basically like yeah the for
the intern positions that's a pretty
massive influx of resumes right is it's
similar for your full positions is it a
hundred and twenty people in a binder
not where we see them it is probably for
recruiting like there's I don't know the
exact rate of job applications that we
get so yeah I feel that we usually end
up picking between like we maybe get
like three or four resumes on kind of
the first pull and then if if those if
those don't work out then there's a
trickle that comes through I said then
once we kind of find the candidate then
and we obviously close that position
okay yeah actually for a universe like
for four people fresh out of school
other than the intern way it's it's
almost the same like you you send in
your resume and ideally like the things
that we like to see is maybe some hobby
project type experience right I think
there's a lot of value in like having
started a project and kind of having
gone through a life cycle and
a project can be a game a project can be
just I'm working on this library that
does this thing right but but something
that you could in theory give to some
other person for them to run right I
think that takes a certain level of
preparation that is very valuable
um so seeing some completed work that
the person took initiative to create is
going to be something and in that will
stand up it'll stand out and and so I
guess one question I have there is that
is that something that the whole sort of
pipeline knows I mean is that something
that you know when HR screening the
applicants that they are going to also
see that and go oh we know that the
engineering team likes to see these
things so we may you know we won't
accidentally sort of cull those out when
that was possibly a good thing or or is
it is it more like well by the time it
gets to I wish it I mean it's it's fuzzy
okay right it depends on which recruiter
you're working with and over time like
the longer you work with a certain
recruiter and we have one that is kind
of assigned to our team like they start
learning obviously kind of the things
that you're looking for so it's yeah
it's like a feedback loop and usually
when we see like a good resume like we
will highlight that as well so that they
kind of know I'll you know this is the
type of stuff right but yeah project
experience making it easy to like if you
made a demo like having some some video
up there as kind of a first like easy
way to to consume it so I don't install
thousands of yes more programs that that
helps right and I guess that's just
general advice for if you're trying to
go get a job easier you make it for the
people screening resume you've got to to
know that you're awesome right the the
better okay yeah that's a good point so
I bet a lot of people don't necessarily
think of it that way but yeah it's like
hey how can I make it
that when you go to look at my resume
the important parts are very easy to get
to and if there's something that I've
done that I think is a particularly good
example of why you should hire me make
it one click like make it I just click
and I can see it and some people feel
like they'll have a link to their github
or something like that so you can
actually look at some code and that is
pretty awesome okay yeah all right so
that's that's actually really great I
mean that was a that's so much of the
stuff that I've often asked is the
answer is in there actually okay what do
this said because a lot of times you
know people ask this and the game
industry is so different now from when I
you know got into it that I my
experience is meaningless like it has no
bearing on how you know one might get
into the game industry today just need
to hire people so it's it's really kind
of kind of nice to have that picture
okay so did I is there anything I should
have asked about that that I didn't ask
before I go on to sort of the next part
of that which is not gonna be about
maybe the hiring process um there's so
we we kind of covered the how to I think
also like a cover letter I think is very
meaningful and conveying why you want to
be there so why what brought you to
Blizzard yeah kind of the motivations I
think they speak volumes sometimes and
and making sure that that is in a cover
letter I think is super helpful okay and
yeah our engineering manager will always
be upset when he sees no cover letter
really okay yeah there's like just
sending about the bunch of resumes no no
personal touch or or something like that
so it's kind of it's quite literally a
smaller make it personal I mean it's
just again applying for any job if you
tailor it more to like the job that
you're applying for you're more likely
to you know when somebody is screening
it they're more likely to go like oh
yeah like he actually wants to be here
for these reasons and that's great and
and that matters
so you know putting that part of the the
PI plant side so let's say I am one of
the people fortunate enough to you know
make it through this process and you
know I'm gonna get a job here right so
it's like make me an offer we you know
we move out there whatever is happening
what's sort of I guess what does the
person expect in terms of like what did
they do day one like in other words
talking again from more of the beginners
perspective so obviously like in your
situation you know your expectations
well I already know game development I'm
just coming in my my things gonna be
about learning this team and this engine
and whatever but for somebody who's
never worked in the game is for and this
is their first job right you know what
is it like to come start working there
day one and sort of like what are the
expectations around what someone who
works in the game industry is like going
to start doing in in their you know
inaugural year or something like so
they've won actually like Blizzard does
something different there on day one
okay one you arrive and you're actually
there's kind of a big onboarding type of
meeting with a bunch of people that are
starting kind of the same week where
there's like HR talks about some of the
some of the things like health benefits
and health insurance and things that you
might not really know how to deal with
and I think this is all the paperwork
that we need to do and that type of
stuff then there's something that
Blizzard does as well which is talking
about kind of the company core values
and and there's a scavenger hunt for you
to kind of explore the campus so you
know where we like we I think Blizzard
when they moved to the current location
it was three buildings now it's 21 Wow
and there's there's cool statues there's
museums you know you should get enough
information that when a friend comes and
visits you you can show them kind of
around and find the cafeteria and and
that type myself so that's kind of day
one and then at the end you arrive at
the team and you you do kind of a hello
but that's your first day so you really
on the team is kind of you're literally
taking care of business the first day
that happen yeah but in a fun way like a
they do stuff that like usually one of
the executives will be there and be
there to ask questions to write like so
you might get lucky and mike moore has
time to do that type of stuff right so
so that's I think pretty cool then the
second day you should arrive to a
desktop that's been set up in the area
where you're gonna sit the code has been
downloaded and compiled once and that is
stuff that gets kind of set up first
time so instead of doing the four hour
let's build the game the first time oh I
did not have access to this network
source
oh my my SBN password is this or
whatever so so that ideally is already
taken care of sometimes we miss a few
things but that we try I think is is
already kind of cool and then you the
the lead for the team that you got hired
to will usually end up spending most of
the day with you okay just kind of
walking you a bit through the codebase
and usually they they have kind of a
smallish problem picked out for you two
to kind of deal with that keeps you in
like one or two files so that it's
fairly isolated and it might be a low
bug or a reminder that sits on some
backlog right
so this
sort of a thing where the EU has done
some preparation for your arrival where
they've literally the bug list and gone
this would be a good thing for the you
know the new hire to take a look at
right let me go and you know give that
to them try to ease you in and explain
only enough to kind of solve that
problem you might already have the
solution right but yes but yeah and then
have that person ask questions and we
encourage asking questions and just
start taking a lot of notes there's
weird nomenclature like a lot of there's
weird nomenclature that you have to
learn a code base that means something I
remember on the the engine team when I
arrived I always just like it was do
that this do that that second what is it
do dad like why what does the detail do
dad yes so it turns out the detail do
that is like of the procedural
vegetation that's okay on the ground
okay and and and a map obj is a it's
more like a building type of thing but a
chair in theory it's also an object in
the map right actually it's it's just
it's different right
so there's a lot of kind of ingrained
terminology that you have to get used to
and you you kind of build a little
dictionary a lot of console commands in
order to kind of start up stuff like
working on Wow a lot of people they'll
be running their own kind of local
server on their machine that they would
then connect to there's also there's
also servers that are running for the
team but depending on what you do you
you might have to control your own
server right and that just is kind of a
lot of stuff that you need to teach
somebody initially just to here's how to
actually have your version of the game
talk to a thing right right because
you're dealing with getting programs
connected and having getting a state
established which is right you know not
actually that typical in in you know
sort of more you know straightforward
game development I suppose yeah
but yeah then ideally you're working on
that project and when you're ready to to
check in you'll get your first code
review so we we talk like every check-in
gets code reviewed we tend to prefer
kind of well up to now we preferred
in-person code reviews we are switching
now to do more kind of asynchronous code
reviews because the number of
interruptions is high is high and and
being evil able to keep people kind of
in the flow state I think is it's useful
and so sometimes there's massive code
reviews and being able to crowdsource
them is good also a lot of sense so what
are if you could talk a little about the
code review process is there anything
particularly I mean I suppose most
people probably roughly know what a code
view is but is there anything particular
about a code review at Blizzard that's
you know or rough sketch of how how it
works a rough sketch well for example
who even does the code review right like
I check in 94 somebody who is who's new
to the company of the person that would
assign the task is going to be the lead
right so they would do obviously the
first code review
ideally explaining kind of this is this
is why we do this this is why doing a
like these are the people that you
should be getting code reviews from and
and there's usually like a set of more
senior engineers on each one of those
groups that are named that would be
targets for a code review and then
depending on the subsystem there might
be kind of yeah here's the the guy that
deals with all the spell stuff okay so
if I'm doing something in there that I
don't understand he would be kind of the
go-to person okay but ideally a specific
person who is obviously the person has
to code reviews there's a subject matter
expert as you're kind of have to go to
write like
yeah if you're dealing with this is how
the DB autogen
works you go talk to this person okay
and those wouldn't be the tasks that
you'd be given on day one yes or two
because yeah
that's that's kind of dealing with a lot
of sensitive systems that could ripple
through yeah and create 50 and ammonium
mega tasks so why don't we get to Giga
tasks that's okay so you know from that
point after you know their first
experiences that are they kind of now in
the assignment pool in general I mean
probably getting that there's still a
few more like you you buy mine use them
you're kind of widen their kind of their
their expertise in the systems that they
deal with try to keep the complexity
level obviously fairly low don't give
new folks necessarily mission critical
tasks they're kind of nice to have that
as we're because we're on wow we're
continually we were working in a lot of
branches and simultaneously and there's
a complexity that comes with that that's
again something you need to usually
explain to somebody
there's systems that automatically merge
your changes from this branch to this
branch so when you check in and somebody
else has modified stuff upstream then
you're like oh now I have a merge
conflict and then it's like help I have
a merge conflict right and right that
becomes kind of a teaching moment at
that point okay
yeah all right so that that makes that
that's a really great picture right like
I already feel like I should stand that
process much better okay like person not
working at Blizzard to now he's actually
doing work on the codebase so before we
get into some other stuff here because I
think that that's really like almost
everything I wanted to know about that
okay that stuff from having done this
for several years now at Blizzard
what are some of the things that you you
know maybe I guess I'll put sort of two
parts of the question out there and you
can take them however you want or
whatever first thing would be like what
do you think makes a really good you
know team member for one of your teams
like you know having gone through the
process of getting people and you get to
be like this was a really good hire or
we're really happy that this person came
to work for us like what are the sorts
of things that you find sort of make
that that difference you know is it you
know are they personality or they attack
are they whatever and then the other
part would be sort of what are the
things that in general when especially
talking about sort of like people who's
you know maybe first or an early job is
that Blizzard as opposed to you know
maybe more of a veteran programmer okay
what are the things that you wish they
came in knowing that they don't know or
that luck maybe could do a better job
this has nothing to do with you know is
this person you know capable or smart or
can do the job it's more dislike they
haven't had this experience and so we
have to teach them these things that we
wish they already knew because we know
they can do them but now we have to kind
of do that education process does that
make sense yeah it makes sense it's a
hard quiet question yes takes no where
to start so in terms of like good habits
in general are I don't understand
something I'm gonna ask a question and
it's totally fine to ask a question
right like I actually I think fairly
like new programmers that it's their
first job there may be afraid to ask
questions they're going to try to solve
the problem on their own and because
they don't want to be the guy that just
got hired you know and and the first
task I'm failing why am i failing I
can't fail right so so just it's
perfectly fine to ask a question right
and and leads I mean should be good to
kind of detect that and and kind of CEO
haven't heard
so I'm gonna check in a bit and see
what's going on and and the thing is
that you're all kind of working on this
together everybody tries to do good and
and that is the other thing like in
terms of things that are kind of a joy
to work with are people that don't get
upset when something isn't done the way
that they would prefer and they like
should try to see the good in what was
done before assuming that they're the
bad that they perceive you know that the
person was maybe aware of doing yes
except sometimes they weren't right so
it's just like kind of that interaction
style but people that are like where
it's their first job it's often the
first time that they're working with
like other engineers ah right
so I think that like some folks can be
more territorial than others and and
ideally people just don't really care
about that that much I see right so yeah
I'm not structuring it really well but
these are just yeah these are like being
proactive when I see a problem don't
assume that somebody else is going to
see it I say bring it up which goes in
the same sense of the asking us across
asking questions being able to bridge
the gap to art and design like it's easy
for engineers to kind of focus on the
tasks that they have and that usually
can lead to like on big teams in
particular can just lead to a disconnect
that if if it doesn't get broken down
early enough right like design things
they're getting this you're doing this
because you have your task in front of
you but your task while it's in front of
you might already be changing and people
are bad at updating things so so
fostering communication I think is
important like the folks that
do well I think are the ones that aren't
afraid to walk over to the artisan
designers when they get their task and
say hey I need to do this thing for you
let's talk about that right okay
and so it's really like communication
super important and is that mostly like
interests creation just being a person
who is able to have a good conversation
there he's really are talking about or
are you also talking about if this
person has some art you know sort of a
little bit of background in that so that
they can express themselves clearly I
mean is let's bonus okay I understand
exactly when you speak to me art I like
I understand art and when we talk
designer we talk designer okay like
that's awesome for working on Wow a bit
of a weird requirement but some some
that isn't necessary but helps a lot is
actually having played the game at least
at some point in your life in order to
understand which probably isn't that
hard of a requirement but but for some
people that's just not a game that like
they stay away from it like think some
people actually go like this is too
time-consuming yes like or depending on
where people are at in their lifetime
like it was fine while I was at
university or maybe on my first job but
now you know like Tom's transom well
yeah families and kids and and that type
of stuff
right but knowing the the lingo is super
helpful in communicating when somebody
says hey there's something that happens
in gold tire or an organ or there's this
thing that's broken and it's already
played the game they already know what
you're talking about where is I mean I
was joking at some point maybe we should
have kind of this is the map of Azeroth
and you need to at least know where a
few places are
it's an interview question is like
geography test I'm bad enough for
regular geography geography - no but
alright it's just I mean it's something
that if you don't know it you're going
to very quickly pick it up there's
obviously a bunch of shortcuts how to
get around the world but yeah we we also
like people that I would say probably
half of the team or so still actively
play the game which is pretty good for
the games industry I think in people
that play their own work surprisingly
high I think and and that just fosters a
lot of discussion that is usually very
useful and it also means that you just
you get more credibility in a way by
when somebody asks you hey we need to do
this thing and and you go but it might
break this other thing yes and without
playing the game you might not have a
right obviously not something that you
can absolutely require and some people
do it more casually than others yeah and
and and that is perfectly fine
all right so cover kind of communication
being proactive about things while being
great engineers in particular you had in
mind when you thought about that but
there's I mean there there are people
who you can give a big task to and
they're able to run with it organize it
together with the help of a producer
maybe and they're able to break tasks
down like big complex tasks down then
before maybe jumping into coding having
a quick kind of check-in all right I'm
making some like noticing that they're
making some important decisions and and
being able to loop in the right people
at that point
to get feedback gather all the
requirements maybe some of it changes
and then there they're able to you know
the ideal engineer then is able to
execute it you know at the time that
they said it would take there are no
surprises that happens all the time okay
so now we're kind of because we have
fantasy geography and the engineers
it's a fantasy game no oh you're asking
for the ideal so exactly what I wanted
to know certainly yeah and yeah you win
some of those battles and you lose some
and you just try to kind of move on and
and coexist and not step on other
people's toes in a in a large code base
and yeah I think those are kind of the
things that I'm looking for so the
second part there's like what are the
things that for the newer people who you
get are people who maybe haven't had a
job in the game history before or this
maybe even their first job like what are
the sorts of things if you've had
candidates like that who come through
who you hire what are the sorts of
things that you feel like they you know
the education process prior to kinda
buzzer could have been better at
preparing them for the things you need
them to do again so kind of factoring
out there you know how good they are as
an engineer it's just for what have they
had the opportunity to learn already I
think it's really the project experience
like maybe it's somebody who has only
studied computer science have they've
worked with artists and designers do
they understand the game development
kind of process like when to make a like
when to maybe make a prototype
when to like how to like some of the
newer folks they tend to be very like I
know it all as well okay right they'll
more so than older folks oh yeah
Noldor like age wise but I come further
back to Piper young younger folks can be
very knowledgeable and they they know
everybody were mentioning C++ and and
usually we get a lot of like in my own
programming I'm able to use all of these
things why can't I use these things on
your project right type of complex C++
features super fast features and like
supercilious eleven lambdas all that
stuff like when when that was a hot
topic like that became a hot topic on
the team because some folks at the
moment we switch to you know then the
version of Visual Studio that starts
recording them it started kind of
popping up in the code and and then we
tried to put a bit of a stop to it and
then that was like why are we stopping
this this is like like this is part of
the language how can we say we're C++
developers or we can't do this and you
try to just kind of deal with things
like well let's actually like everybody
the moment you introduce a feature like
that like everybody on the team needs to
understand the feature and especially
some of the people that are on game
development teams that have not been
using those features for a long time
they might not even get exposed to some
of the new language features and and
they're sometimes the folks who have to
give advice on what should your code
look like yes and and and there's like
we we don't necessarily think as a
community we may not even have learned
all the best practices around some of
these features right so doing that
slowly and deliberately and kind of
vetting it through what is this going
like as a ripple effect what is it going
to do to the codebase I think those are
are things that you then have to stop
some of the the folks that haven't
worked in large-scale projects right
that have only been coding for
themselves and that is kind of tricky in
that
it's naysay means like no don't do this
right well I need to explain it in order
for them to understand the perspective
to on it is kind of one of those things
where like you know you kind of have to
have gone through one of these things
where it's like oh yeah and then we
tried to port to the this and that
compiler didn't support lambdas and then
we had to read like if you've gone
through that once and someone says let's
not adopt these things earlier it's like
oh yeah like I understand why you said
that but if you've never had those
experiences it's pretty hard for you to
connect to it like you know
empathetically in that sense because you
you don't see those downsides that
they've maybe gone through with the ISIS
and it's just people's eyes aren't for a
code review people's ions that aren't
trained necessarily to look out for the
bad things like you're starting to
capture by reference and at some point
somebody just starts not capturing by
reference and then inner loops get
slower and I like wow like how did this
happen right I see
yeah in life time management that's
another thing that I think people should
understand a lot more kind of coming on
to a team memory management lifetime
management resource management a
discipline of like they might have come
from a place where they were happy to
get things working nicely to actually
knowing that everything you do it's like
wow we always say kind of dies by a
thousand paper cuts and making sure that
you're not adding paper cuts to the
trivia to the did the messes is it
important to the movement do the wound
yeah heavy scarring okay so so sounds
like to to assert degree that those kind
of fell into two categories there in
terms of things that you want to know
one is it sounds like just kind of
general lower level programming things
like you know have some solid
fundamentals around like like you know
I've I don't always rely on a garbage
collector or something I know how I
could do this myself I need to or you
know I have some idea of what it's going
to take to know when these things need
to kind of get cleaned up or something
like that which rather than just
expecting something to do it for me and
then the other one is seeing
more like well there's gonna be
decision-making kind of at a higher
level in some of these instances like
you were saying about you know what kind
of code stuff what kind of coding
practices to use when to make decisions
about kind of your micro time management
like will I make a prototype here would
that be effective sure those are kind of
more like just like a loose experience
things where we just kind of have to
have a taste for it almost if you've
written the more code you've written the
better your the the better you tend to
be at those things right and also
knowing that I don't need to take
something towards the bitter end to
fully understand it like if you're only
trying to solve this problem you don't
have to solve all the other problems as
well I resist in that space right all
right I think yeah I think that's that
that might be everything I have on the
like non code side thing like that
essentially the the sort of I don't know
which one call it the window into like
the actual like employee side of game
development did I miss anything
you know I mean I guess I should say cuz
you know it and I don't so I may have
you know well I think we like not every
engineering position is kind of the same
you see like if you're working on the UI
team there are our best C++ practices or
C pepper practices and then there's like
Lua as a thing there so those are
certain skills that matter then if
you're on the tools team where you know
other tool sets my or toolkits might be
things to to kind of learn and just have
good understanding of time but yeah it
then gets very domain-specific right
yeah right yeah whatever the particular
yeah and working Wow like you're going
to probably get confronted with a DB at
some point right Oracle back inside of
this so understanding a little bit of
how relational the B's kind of work it
helps right because unlike another game
project which maybe never need to know
this thing here you you are guaranteed
at some point you will have something
that relates to very very likely yeah
relates yes yes okay so we've got about
15 minutes left I think I'm not mistaken
so you had mentioned two things kind of
while we were walking right through here
you said you wanted to talk about
sixteen-year-old assumptions so yeah I
mean there really aren't a lot of games
that have to have a lifecycle of 16
years at least not at the scale of wow I
would say so right yeah so I think like
a lot of the problems that we deal with
right now on world of warcraft there
some of them are just very simple
assumptions that were made a long time
ago and and they take a lot of time to
undo actually so for example the last
couple of years we kind of went through
this where in the past it was completely
acceptable to just say hey you know like
once a week for like eight or twelve
hours we're gonna take the service
offline and we're gonna be patching
stuff and we'll fix things in the DB and
we'll deploy things and we'll install
this software in the data center and and
do that and and nowadays I think if
you're you're starting from scratch you
probably would try to operate with like
zero percent downtime right and just
kind of have systems where you're doing
like a be deploys red green like
transition drain this set of servers
spin up this set of servers migrate
people over so which is a lot more
involved certainly which believe it or
not there's fundamental architectural
decisions you need to make to so on Wow
there's just a lot of the effort in in
terms of like what the engineers and the
project to go towards paying down tech
debt so probably like it's hard to put
in numbers but like 25 percent of the
time that engineers spend is usually
seeing older systems like that in order
to just provide kind of a more modern
experience like even like on the engine
side that might be which was like one of
my first things that I worked on was hey
water is a like flip book texture oh and
let's make that look a bit more modern
and make sure you can see through it and
flex off intersections and reflections
and their type of stuff right so that's
like one way of paying down tech debt by
the way you have to do it in a way that
nobody has to go back and fix up any of
the art because now it's time for that
because they're working on the next
thing and the tests run on Windows XP
and all these other things we're excited
yes yeah you know has to run on Windows
XP XP is probably 32-bit for a while at
this point okay we while we were the
first game that had a 64-bit version at
Blizzard which is kind of funny because
we're also the first game that had two
dx11 back-end but yeah there's it's just
you're you have an open-world game and
you're like players do what you don't
want them to do and yes and you're
allowing add-ons to function within your
process space as well right so you don't
really get a lot of memory management
control yes
so like running out of memory on 32-bit
is like the number one crash that we
have read it in Wow
yeah because especially players will
have a diverse set of other processors
running for their you know team
management things or whatever they're
doing you well as long as it's not part
of your process base you're usually fine
because that's true I guess and they so
yeah yeah and I suppose there might be
running or are they always running on
32-bit Windows it will they'll be
running the 64-bit executable if they're
on a 64-bit machine so well Windows XP
you don't get an option right yes that's
so then I think there was a bit of a
problem where when you were installing
windows 7 there's like two disks in the
box
and if you don't know you've picked you
put top 130 to it yeah and that may or
may not have been good so so even though
you have a perfectly fine 64-bit machine
that can run software you didn't know so
I think there's a lot of cases like that
out there
then I think there are some people who
run 32-bit clients on 64-bit OS s
because actually of tech debt that we
created for ourselves which was we in
order to prevent people from running out
of memory we would actually cap some of
the the settings on the engine right I
was like phew distance gets reduced a
bit extra details on other things right
so people that don't look at that
carefully
like the way we capped it was wrong we
we basically allow you to move the
slider to the right okay but we didn't
show you that we're actually capping
things I say so people are assuming that
they're running at max settings except
on 32-bit they're not ice and then if
they run 64-bit on their system with the
same settings you get slower it's slower
so I run 32 bits so that was one mistake
I wish I could take back then some
people run 32-bit because that's where
the bot software Oh allows hooking more
easily so there's entire efforts on just
trying to deal with cheaters and I guess
somebody would just say to upgrade to 64
bit makes that a little bit harder at
least yeah so a lot of time gets spent
on that tech debt in general is also
content creation sites our art pipeline
is horrible
we're currently spending a lot of effort
and trying to make that a bit more of a
modern experience and a lot of the work
on WoW is just done like you need to add
a new feature your and it's very late in
the process so you're very cautious to
not disturb anything
yes and then that starts adding a lot of
kind of special cases only for this one
Thursday which then you need to spend
time on going back and fixing up and
yeah and I find myself writing mails of
like it's okay for you to add this flag
as long as you add a task to remove it
like in two months it's like a sunset
provision on this this fix yeah
the to kind of understand how big that
problem can get when not managed
properly we in order like a spell is
kind of a basic execution unit that
designers have okay so when they want
something in the world to happen they
cast a spell okay and the spell isn't
necessarily what you perceive in the
game as a spell right it's something
that affects the change yeah like they
can cast a spell at an area with a
300-yard radius to find all the players
that are there and then they have some
diverse script that they run to pick one
of those and then I say cast another
spell that that guy and like it'll like
spawn the unit that is going to follow
that person got it and then they cast
another spell that says oh now make a
beam that goes to that unit and then
where that beam hits there's a pull
spell that will do damage and that now
is like a laser beam that is following a
person and if you look at wow if you
were to recreate Wow
right I think you would build systems
that are just like well we're gonna have
the beam system that can follow a player
and you know like that's that but we
have five spells for that okay because a
designer was able to do it right and
nobody kind of saw him doing it
so because everybody goes like I if I
had to do that I wouldn't want to like
can somebody just make a trace thing for
me well I mean in general both design
and are usually come at things from the
perspective of you know I have a set of
fix tools and I'm trying to get an end
result so it's yes it's especially
especially good designers and artists
will oftentimes push thing as to a place
where maybe it you know it's a little
more complicated than you like but it's
also what makes them good probably right
yeah yeah I mean good designers and
artists can do great things with yes
with very little yes but that comes with
you know with the comprises right
and and these things just grow very
unbounded right so yeah so we've got
five minutes left and I have one thing
that's hot fixing okay so you because
you mentioned it like you said I wanted
to talk about hot fixing so tell me
I'm fixing like hot fix thing I actually
think is one of the things that we do
better at and because we have different
ways of hot fixing certain types of data
can you can you give me some like what
do you want the definition of hot fixing
to be forthright hot fixing to us is so
a binary hot fix is something like a
client binary hot fix is me fixing your
executable on your machine okay so the
server will needs to send you something
and it's going it was part of our
publishing pipeline it's like it's like
a patch right and we're able to do that
like from you checking in a fix
we're able to give that to a user in
about an hour well what then we have
data hot fixes that just get applied to
the server that are like the server
receives the data and then gives it to
the clients yes so that they can fix up
their data
and that allows us to tweak you know
like like the damage that this spell
does by X percent without yeah without
having to restart everything and then
server binary is you know like when a
server crashes there's a mechanism where
it can pick up like a fixed version of
the binary that won't crash so that we
can roll that out and like hop fixing is
super important for us internally
because we the way we develop the game
we're all kind of working on one DB so
when you go into our editor and you
change value of a spell and you save
right now that goes to a DB that we
share on the floor and your edits are
affecting kind of this stuff I see the
moment I would restart my server I'd be
picking up some of those changes right I
see so although as you were saying
earlier although people are running a
server locally on their machine they are
not running a database locally on their
machine right so like I could literally
be trying to do something and think that
I tested something one way and it turns
out that somebody right in the middle of
my tests had done something and now but
that it sounds like a relatively
difficult problem actually yeah I mean
not to solve I mean to this is again
like a good example of work that we're
currently doing in order to like as the
team grew there's more like people
stepping on each other's toes because of
the way the infrastructure was yes yes
and at the start you're just like oh
we're all editing the same stuff we're
seeing changes immediately iteration
yeah it's a feature and it it kind of
goes a lot to to the promise that Chris
was explaining of like so how simple
decisions done like many years ago like
the DB is central storage it's very easy
to add a column that is our version of
instead of having an asset on disk right
like the DB is almost the asset that you
load yes by the way all spells are
loaded by the clients
oh we're adding them at a rapid rate
was blowing over memory boundaries and
and those types of things so we have to
also do compression type work too to
kind of get the data stay at a
reasonable level because not everything
was built in an asynchronous way and yes
and all of that but yeah one of the ways
to actually remove edits is to to then
move to a more local workflow and that
is like one of the larger
transformations that we're currently
trying to get through in modernizing the
tech yeah and and what's kind of strange
about this is like when I joined
Blizzard I thought all right there's
this like wow it's running as a service
you know they gotta be like really
careful to change anything because you
could break so much right and I arrived
into a culture were just like yes we're
rewriting these systems like massively
and is there automated testing or unit
tests that they have to run through well
not really
we rely actually a lot on like PTR
testing so we we invited a lot of people
to be kind of test or see the new
content early but help exercise the
systems as as a player would and that
also gives us good usually good load
kind of characteristics it that you
don't quite get if you're just running
bots against your infrastructure because
Bob is never going to behave the way a
player does but yeah seeing kind of this
no it's not set in stone there's
actually a lot of interesting work to do
to modernize kind of the content
creation pipeline to modernize the art
pipeline to be able to give get more of
what you see is what you get type of
workflow is going like when I again like
when I joined it was you were making
some tweaks to the level and then with
or at or an asset like you we're moving
a tree and you had to run a map gen
process that would then move the tree
okay and then you fire up your client
and your serve
and then you get the tree in the new
location okay so and rather than
changing all of that at once it was like
hey maybe we can make this more like a
like a console style work though that
when the client is running the editor
can just tell the client like move move
move your tree and then you get a bit
more kind of instant feedback right yes
but yeah that's that's kind of the work
we do in terms of dealing with tech that
hot fixing is like applying a hot fix or
changing data is almost the same unit of
change that we currently send to our
server and being able to do that locally
is stuff that looks really really
interesting to us right now cool so I
think we are exactly at like 90 right
here yes sir
thank you so much that was awesome
[Applause]