hello whatever foul I'm glad you could
catch a stream live as well never this
feel it's your birthday today
really well happy birthday are you doing
anything special for your birthday
you're still watching handmade here oh
so that's what you normally do
it's like it's a special birthday
handmade here though
I feel like a handmade hero needs like a
sponsor like on podcasts you know like
before the podcast starts they always
say like this episode is brought to you
by hmm you know poo box a box full of
poo that arrives at your door every
month or whatever and I just don't know
what what the box would be like it would
be or could be mattresses I guess
mattresses boxes or website builder
maybe CSS could be our sponsor create
disgusting barely functional web pages
in just several months using CSS
you mentioned on Twitter being
interested in the hiring process that
includes an option for people to record
themselves doing their normal
programming work is there a way you
think the industry could be led to
feasibly adopt that I do think so
actually I so I think it's already
pretty feasible what what I would
recommend doing if someone were so
inclined
I guess maybe handmade network might be
a place for this to happen I'm not sure
but what I would say is there just needs
to be a central place called like
programmers looking for work via streams
dot-com or whatever right but yeah it
could just be like a subsection of
handmade Network right and all it is is
just a listing randomly ordered so like
every time you go there just picks a
random order so there's no like bias in
like you know who you know you you you
don't get a higher placement because
your name starts with a or something
right just a random list of streams of
people who are streaming their
programming regularly so it just links
to their YouTube channel so you can go
watch so that way if you're like I need
to hire an engine person let me go see
what the streams are and like you can
just go do it right if those were like
coalesced in one place I think that
would be all you'd really need I think
people would start going there when they
need to hire engine people cuz they
don't know where to get them I mean
nobody knows right it's like there's not
enough engine programmers out there so
it's hard to find so I think if you just
had a central clearinghouse it was like
look you go to this page and anyone with
a youtube channel that's been updated in
the last 7 days let's say that's a
programming stream that has submitted it
there it goes up on there right and
there's some may be loose curation where
people can flag streams if they don't
appear to actually be programming so if
people like start submitting streams to
it that aren't programming streams then
you can nuke it right but I feel like
that would be sufficient and then people
would just start going I think you have
to tell the industry to do it the
industry wants to find people
I mean they pay headhunters to find
people lots of money so if you just had
a service you could go to find streams
and you know a tech lead can just spend
a day like browsing through people
finding one and that seems fine I don't
think that would just work probably have
I seen the rlm parody rlm I don't think
I know what RAL M is parody of those
nerd box services that send you some
cheap stuff in a box every month I
haven't but I did see like or here I
should say the onion did a fake podcast
one time that was pretty good actually
it's just a parody of all these stupid
podcasts and it was like the they're one
of the things that they had an ad for in
their podcast was box box which is a box
of boxes that comes every month like
different shapes and sizes of box and
like different materials um and I
thought that was really good I haven't
seen the rlm parity because I don't
think I knew what rlm is
I started my first partner job a couple
months ago and have been thrown into an
unfamiliar codebase a couple times now I
would have wouldn't have said sir
previously but now I'd say the hardest
part of learning a new code base is the
threading that's nothing it crazy if
it's not brought out carefully before
yeah
so I 107 agree with you and I would
actually say that threading is a very
large looming issue and the reason I say
that is because there's no question that
single threaded speeds are not really
gonna improve hugely much so it's
obvious that like things are getting
faster mostly because they are able to
run in parallel what that means is that
we have really no choice but to use
parallelization if we're trying to push
any boundaries you know it's just like
web development or whatever where
everything's slow and takes seven years
to complete then maybe not but in the
like world where you're trying to push
some kind of machine performance not
like handmade heroes all right but we're
not you know we're not going for broke
right we're this is a more basic
learning stream we're not trying to
produce world-leading visuals or
anything right or world-leading physics
simulation so when you're trying to like
push those boundaries you end up in a
situation where like you really want
everything to be carefully threaded and
to work really well and to take
advantage of as many courses you can get
sometimes heterogeneously so you know
cores on the CPU and course on the GPU
and the problem is just that threaded
programming is incredibly complicated
single threaded programming takes a lot
of things for granted and a lot of
people can't even do that right you know
it's hard to be good at architect and
code for single threaded once you throw
a multi thread into the mix it's very
difficult and people tend to coalesce
around a couple strategies like you know
job system kind of stuff but job systems
really aren't very good it's the other
thing especially not
Eric job systems that you just kind of
force your multi-threading upon there
they're just not very good and if you
look at some of the more advanced work
that's attempting to get more
utilization and less cost of
synchronization and stuff like this out
of threading you realize it's just a lot
of subtlety there right and so I feel
like it's it's really bad and I've
certainly had a slow painful learning
curve myself on my latest code based
learning how I sort of want to do things
and it's it's just really tough there's
a lot of competing concerns I would say
really the biggest thing that I find is
so demanding about it is that really
there's two sort of separate and
completely opposing forces which is you
want things to be as local as possible
as often as possible which argues for
trying to keep things on a particular
core as much as possible but at the same
time you don't want cores to be idle
which argues for you moving things
around cords as much as possible right
and so I kind of feel like you know a
lot of the techniques that I would
probably advocate now for in single
threaded programming where I'm like you
got to kind of do things custom to the
to the job at hand otherwise you end up
with these big sprawling code bases that
are too slow and too dumb and all this
other stuff I feel like the same thing
kind of applies in multi-threaded
programming and I'm not really at the
point yet where I'm confident in sort of
saying how to do that right but I kind
of feel like we're seeing us probably a
similar pattern developed where it's
like people are throwing these
one-size-fits-all solutions at
multi-threading and that just it doesn't
work if you actually want clean
efficient high-performance programs I
think it's actually really challenging
and it's just saying like I'm gonna have
a job system or Q or whatever the heck
it's just that's not gonna cut it you
really need to think about how you do
your load
saying how you arranged your various
data structures for a locality and who
is gonna manage what and how often other
people are able to steal work from each
other based on which data sets which
data structures their need to inspect
and you know you see it an alarming
number of papers if you read the
literature that are basically of the
form hey if you take a look at the
performance of this thing that people
said was good for multi-threading it's
actually slower than single threading a
lot of the time and you know you have to
be really careful about that sort of
thing you need to actually make sure
you're not spending all of your time in
these generic systems and the way that
they lock each other up you have to
really think about it and I think
customer old stuff is really very
important for multi-threading just like
it is for single threading and we have
to sort of start building up our
repertoire of how to do that easily
efficiently and quickly and nobody is
right like we're very few people are so
I really do think it's a looming issue
and it's gonna I think it's gonna play
out very similar to a single threading
is we're gonna have all these big
bloated systems that claim to be the
right thing to do they're all gonna end
up being really crappy and we're gonna
have to come back around to like okay we
have to we all have to learn how to
actually be good programmers here and
know some basics about how you make
these things you know what are the
fundamental core ways I can distribute
work how do I write those quickly and
custom customize them easily for my job
that I'm trying to accomplish and how do
I measure whether I did a good job like
I think that's what we're gonna have to
look at in the future certainly and I
think the work being done on GPUs kind
of argues for that you've seen them do a
lot of work around how they distribute
stuff on the GPU and it keeps changing
and keeps becoming more specialized to
what exactly what's being done and I
think that just gives you some idea of
how if you actually really want to do a
good job you can't just say I don't know
here's some generic scheduler it's not
generic it's very specific and you're
gonna end up in things like okay on 16
cores I want to dedicate two cores with
that share and l2
to do this one data structure and it's
much more efficient than letting it
bounce around and these other cores can
sort of divide up the work evenly
because that work is very spatially
incoherent so I don't care about whether
the data structure bounces around cuz
unlikely to be in the catch anyway like
you're gonna see a lot of stuff like
that I think and that's just my gut
feeling
I don't have any evidence for any of
this because it's way too early and so
you know I'm not saying this is this is
like obviously the case or anything I
just it seems like the way it's going
and so I would just say yeah
multi-threading is is a huge topic
that's coming down the pipe I'm sure
most people are doing it poorly right
now I'm sure that includes me and you
know ten years from now we're gonna have
some strong opinions about it but we're
just we're just learning like the basics
of how we sit down to make
multi-threaded programs that are where
we've thought about the right stuff
instead of the wrong stuff and so that
we can write them you know bug free
really quickly like you know again a lot
of single threaded techniques I've
developed over programming for a long
time you know I don't get that many bugs
when I write you know code in certain
ways because I've kind of like trained
myself how to avoid a lot of the common
things where I would have had bugs
before right and and none of that's true
in multi-threaded now so if I sit down
to write a multi-threaded thing I'm
probably gonna make a lot of stupid
mistakes right and spend a lot more time
debugging them and I think that that's
again it's like a practice and a
training issue like as I get more
experience with multi-threaded code I
think I would make less mistakes and I
could write a multi-threaded thing
cleanly without a lot of pitfalls more
more likely as you get that practice
right and so you you have to build it up
it's a different discipline in a lot of
ways and you have to learn new
primitives and new ways of writing the
code so that you can still write custom
things that execute quickly but that
don't lead you to obvious
multi-threading pitfalls because there
are so many of them right that exists
either performance pitfalls or just
correctness pitfalls
can you explain cache misses and how to
avoid them I'm coming from the Java
world I've never had to think about that
well so I guess what I would say is you
probably should have thought about them
in the Java world because Java has
plenty of problems with cache misses as
well right any program that runs on a
modern CPU has issues with cache misses
and so if you care about the performance
of a program you do need to think about
how caches affect what you're doing so I
can give a pretty brief overview and I
think we're gonna have a somewhat longer
hand made hero today just because we
didn't have one yesterday let me give
myself a little more time here but I
would like to explain cache misses a
little bit
so the thing to understand with modern
CPU design and and let me just
III have a honestly a better handle on
sort of modern CPUs now than I did when
we started Hammond hero because honestly
we started handmade hero I was still
mostly my brain was in the sort of Xbox
360 Playstation 3 era which honestly I
mean it's it's wrong to not to call
those not modern CPUs and they obviously
are modern CPUs but they don't really
resemble x64 cores of of today hardly at
all
like an Xbox 360 cpu it's it's just I
mean I would say it's it's almost
completely a different mental model
almost but since having to work on meow
hash I had more time to sort of dig in
to how modern CPUs like the modern X 64
cores actually work and so I I
definitely like from when Hannah Hiro
started to now I've had some not related
am a hero experience which allows me to
kind of have a better grip on it I'm
still not I wouldn't consider myself an
expert on modern X 64 cores
by any stretch of the imagination but I
definitely have a lot better feel for
what's going on then I originally did so
I you know I think it's probably a good
time for us to update sort of some of
that discussion right compared to what I
might have said earlier on streams so
here's what I would say about caches
so typically when you think about how a
processor works in general when you
first come at programming you really
don't think about them at all right
you don't even probably think about
memory much other than that there is
something in the computer that stores it
and so when you're dealing with a
language like for example especially in
something like Java where you might not
really even think about memory per se
because Java is not really about
pointers and such so you cut it kind of
abstract away some things that you maybe
if you were programming and see you
would think about when you're looking at
something like that and you start
programming your you oftentimes don't
really internalize what it means to have
memory and caches right so you'll see
things where you know you might think
about having a you know a big array of
integers and you're talking about you
know I've got 4096 of these integers in
here and then you know I can put things
into here by saying oh you know the
sixteenth one of these integers equals
something right and then later you know
I can ask what that is and I can say
like okay I want to extract one of that
you know those things out right and so
when you first start programming you you
think about memory in a pretty abstract
way and maybe not at all where there's
just there's this semantic concept of
storage where I just ask for some number
of things that get remembered I put them
in there and when I ask to them they
come back out right and that's you know
totally fine for understanding the
correctness of a program it allows you
to think about how the program's going
to work but what it doesn't do is tell
you about how fast the program will do
its work right and so that's where you
really start to think about things like
memory bandwidth and caches is when you
go from sort of like the behavior or
maybe I'll just say the correctness when
you think about like the
correctness of a program like what it's
going to do right and you know we I
guess we could use that with the what
here right and then at some point when
you want to get more advanced you have
to start thinking about the how like how
is it going to do that and that's where
the performance aspects of things come
in to play right and so memory bandwidth
and caches are a fairly large part of
how modern CPUs achieve that performance
and so you have to stop thinking about I
just ask for a big array of integers and
I magically get it and some stuff
happens right and you have to start
thinking about where do those integers
live how is the computer actually
remembering what they are and how do
they moving move around during
computation right during the actual work
that the computer is doing okay and so I
think the most productive way to think
about this sort of thing in your first
pass when you're first trying to
understand this stuff is to say all
right I have to imagine that there's
almost individual like people you know
individual like sections where work is
being done in this chip and they have to
communicate with each other and it takes
a while to communicate right so rather
than thinking about the CPU as like some
monolithic structure that's just like I
don't know there's this CPU and it did
some stuff right you need to start
thinking of breaking this piece down
into sections and those sections are
actually separated by physical distance
and they need to communicate right and
so you have to start thinking about the
CPU as having maybe I'll draw this
diagram with a few basic blocks and we
can talk about sort of what they are so
we can think about having a block that
you know of the CPU that we're going to
talk about which is the thing that sort
of decides you know what to do and when
right there's sort of like a scheduler
of some kind okay this is part of our
CPM and then there's a part of the CPU
right that's capable of doing actual
work right there's like a there's like
the the thing that can actually add
numbers together right there it can it
can produce actual results you know I'm
saying then somewhere off in the
distance there's your actual main memory
right and this is the thing that stores
stuff it's when you buy Ram that's where
it goes right this is this is our RAM
over here and then in here we also have
sort of a number of other sort of places
we have to talk to you and we'll draw
those out now right there's a thing
called an l1 there's thing called the l2
there's the thing called an l3 right and
there's a thing called a rat all right
and so the way this stuff works is
there's a bunch of logic inside each CPU
core right so this is a core here
there's a thing inside each CPU core
which is actually looking at the things
you told it to do right so this stuff
here it's actually looking at the
machine code that was generated from
this stuff and it's figuring out what it
should do now I know that sounds a
little bit weird because you told it
what you should do you're like I told
you to put 45 somewhere and then I told
you to get it back for me and I'm gonna
do something with it like I'm gonna add
you know 12 right so it feels like you
already told the CPU what to do you're
like here's the code right but the
problem is a modern CPU is a huge amount
of silicon with tons of stuff it can do
on it tons of ways it can do work and
what it's trying to do is maximize the
use of that silicon right and so when
instructions when it looks at
instructions that you give it it's
actually trying to figure out what of
those instructions it could do right now
and what would it need to do them okay
so let me give you an
example let's suppose that we took this
code over here that I wrote we were
talking about correctness let's suppose
that in this thing I had said maybe
something slightly a little bit more
complicated in this but almost the same
thing so I I did say big 16 equals 45
right somewhere in my program then a
bunch of stuff happened and then later
on down here I said I want to get that
big 16 back right I'm gonna add one
thing up here I'm gonna say that I also
also write here set y equal to something
like 32 so I wanted to get that thing I
stored in a big 16 back I want to
actually do something with it so I'm
gonna do like an S Plus that an X plus
equals 53 and then I'm also gonna do a y
plus equals 12 right so you know even
just the same as Java you wouldn't
really be thinking about much that's
going on here but you wrote this stuff
and this is what you wanted to have
happen right and so why do we have all
this crazy stuff happening here why am I
saying there's this stuff what are all
these things and what's the scheduler
why does it have to exist why does it
just do these things in order right and
the answer is because when this when you
look at how these things are designed
right this part here that can do work is
actually broken up into many parts so
the part of the chip that can actually
do work actually has lots of little
things in it these are typically called
al use but there's other names for
different parts of them al used to
answer arithmetic logic unit but you've
got lots of different pieces of the chip
that can do work and each one of those
pieces has to go through a bunch of
steps in order to produce its results
now I'm kind of getting a little bit
ahead of myself here because I kind of
went down the road opinion rather to the
complete explanation so let me sort of
explain why that is when a CPU needs to
do work you have to imagine that it's
actually electricity flowing through a
piece of silicon right it's not a magic
abstract thing it's actual electrons
moving right well that might not be the
best way to say it but it's electricity
flowing right and so what happens is if
I want to take a number and I want to
add two of those numbers together I
actually have to have a physical
representation of what a number is and
that's where we get binary right and we
get the concept that we can represent
things in electrical form by having a
series of lines each of which can either
be you know charged or not charged
however you want to look at how the
electricity like it's have a certain
amount of current or not or so on and so
forth right and I don't do electrical
stuff so don't ask me to explain that
part but we know that we have a way of
breaking this down and representing
these numbers inside wiring inside a
chip right but that wiring flows at a
certain rate so if I want to do
something like add two numbers together
well I have to do a couple of different
steps right
I've got wires flowing in here that are
binary wire encodings of the number 53
right and I've got binary wire encodings
of whatever was in X and these things
have to merge together right to form an
actual set of wires that's the output
and when I want to do these things in
floating point or when I want to do
relatively complex operations like the
add has to carry right it has to like
know if I add two things and then and
you know I add two binary ones together
it's got to carry to the next one it's
just waterfall pattern whatever right
you have to imagine there's this huge
series of kind of wiring happening on
the chip and the problem is I want to
drive this chip as fast as I can right I
want the clock rate to be as high as
possible and I want data to flow through
it as fast as it can
well let's suppose that I've got these
stages of these wires coming in and they
do a bunch of stuff and eventually out
here I get an answer right so I got this
huge circuit and it's got to go through
these steps get an answer well if I
actually set the clock rate of my chip
such that here is the start of a clock
right clock begins and here is the end
of the clock so when I talk about a five
gigahertz chip
it means that this whole thing is
happening at a rate of five gigahertz
right it becomes almost impossible to
build this circuit that in a way that
doesn't melt the chip down right pushing
enough electricity through a small
enough space to make all this stuff work
is just too it generates too much heat
and it doesn't work right
and so what chip designers do is they
break each operation inside one of these
logical units they break each one up
into a clock so I do an add-in like a B
C and D steps and I say that my ad takes
four clocks to complete right I start
issuing the ad here it goes to the first
part is you the ad the second part of
the ad next then the third part of the
ad then the fourth part of the ad and
it's a pipeline right so I actually take
four clocks to complete my ad but as
soon as the first clock finishes where
this a is done and it comes to here and
goes to B right as soon as the first
clock finishes I can stick another AB in
the beginning so that these things are
constantly flowing through the logic of
the chips one clock at a time like
buckets handing them off right but each
operation takes a certain number of
clocks to complete and this is why when
you go look at instruction tables if you
ever look at the instruction tables for
next 64 it'll say things like well this
instruction has a throughput of one
cycle but a latency of four cycles like
what does that mean
well it means that I can issue one of
these things every cycle if I want I can
keep feeding these into the pipeline but
when I first feed one in I have to wait
for clocks for that one to come out so
as long as I have a lot of them to do it
will appear as if they're getting done
one every clock but if I just wanted to
do one of them and I have to wait for it
to that one to finish I'm gonna wait for
four clocks right so this is a little
bit out of the scope of what we're
talking about I just want you to
appreciate what's getting built here and
how complicated it is right so even
before we get too out of
processors which are processors that can
do things in orders that appear to be
correct but that are not actually the
order you wrote them in even in an
inorder processor you end up with this
part of the CPU because you need to be
able to schedule what's going on even
amongst these deeply pipelined inorder
things right so you need this part of a
chip even if you're in order meaning
even if you're just doing things in the
order the programmer wrote them because
just knowing whether you can issue
another thing require some logic but
things get way more complicated inside
of x64 because in the modern x64 core
it's actually out of order so what does
that mean well let's now go back to what
I was trying to talk about before so
here's the code that we actually wrote
and what you can see in this code is we
assigned some value to something in
memory restoring here's some the
sixteenth element of this big array we
assigned the number 45 to it we did a
bunch of stuff and then later we asked
for that number back and we're gonna do
some work on it right well this
scheduler is actually able to issue
these things in arbitrary orders so long
as they produce the correct result
what that means is when the scheduler
looks at what's available here it's got
some things okay I've got 32 which is a
constant anybody working with I need to
get whatever was in big sixteen I need
to add 53 - oops - this one right here
whatever the result of that is and I
need to add 12 to whatever the result of
this is right it's actually free to
issue these in an arbitrary order which
means it could decide to do this pair of
operations first because it's completely
independent of this pair of operations
right it could also decide to do them in
the other order it could decide to do
this pair of operations first and then
that one why because they're not
dependent on each other so this part of
the chip this scheduler part is capable
of choosing different orders for things
based on what would be the most
efficient at the time okay so why am I
seeing all this when you asked about
caches well the answer is because one
you start to think about caches you have
to understand that this part of the chip
exists there is an actual part of the
chip that's trying to find things to do
this part of the chip is always easier
to understand the work unit because it's
literally just a series of these it's
Leary's just a series of pipelines that
are capable of doing work and you throw
something into them and later on it
comes back out right but this part is
harder and this is the part you need to
start thinking about in order to
understand caching
okay so what's caching well this these
things I wrote in here are the caches
what do they do
well imagine we didn't have them so
let's imagine first that CPU didn't have
him because CPUs didn't used to have
caches back when you had a Commodore 64
there was no cash on that it doesn't
have a cache right 6502 I think that was
or 68000 also the chip in the Amiga
right great chip no cache on this right
so if all you had was Ram what you have
to remember is if you look look at a
motherboard sometime right go look at
the thing that's inside your computer
the CPU is like here right and the main
memory is like here there's like these
sticks of memory that are sitting in
there that distance is massive in CPU
land just getting over there to get
something and bringing it back
takes a long time because we're talking
about five gigahertz the speed of light
at the speed of electrons is not that
fast
when you're talking about five billion
times a second mm-hmm and you start to
talk about inches which is how far these
things are separated right so if every
time the CPU needed some information so
for example you wrote this this thing
here you stored some information
somewhere in memory and now you went to
get it back if every time it needed that
it had to go ask main memory for it and
bring it back
CPUs would just be a crawl they would be
about 300 times I'm not making this
number up they would be literally like
300 times
than they are now it's brutal how slow
it is to go that far to get information
right and so what would typically happen
inside the CPU is the scheduler would do
everything it could to keep things
running so it would look at this piece
of code here right and it would say on
each one of these okay I've got to issue
a memory request for this I got an issue
memory request for it for well not for
this well I guess it does because that's
the write back the values but you know
maybe these are in registers who knows
anyway point being it would be very slow
but it would look for as much as it
could do but it would just constantly
run out right so it would basically it
would issue some instructions but then
it would constantly be sitting there
waiting on that roundtrip why because if
you look at the amount of time it takes
for this this takes like 300 clocks to
do and these operations like to add they
only take like 4 right so every time you
were gonna go do an operation you would
have to wait 300 clocks to get the thing
you're gonna operate on and then you'd
be done like that for clocks to be done
right and so all of this silicon would
just be idle most of the time because it
would have nothing to feed the the units
that do the actual work it just couldn't
do it I'd have no data there's no data
so what the counters are designed to do
is the caches are designed to speed up
this round-trip by exploiting the fact
that most of the time when we do work on
data in a CPU it's predictable which
memory it will operate on right that's
what a cache is a cache is a thing that
tries to predict what Ram the CPU will
ask for and it tries to have that
information
closer to the CPU core that's going to
want it then the actual RAM and so the
clocks for accessing these caches
are much more favorable than the 300
clock round-trip so main memory maybe
takes 300 clocks to get something out of
l1 which is the closest possible type of
cache takes about one sometimes two
depends on the situation but it's very
cheap right so it's even faster than
like sometimes one of these operations
some of these operations can take
several cycles l1 can be even faster
than an operation that's how fast l1 is
l2 is more like 16 clocks right so it's
still it's quite a bit slower but way
faster than this still 10 times faster
20 times faster than a main memory fetch
and then l3 I don't really remember what
the clocks are on it but you know again
it's between these two and it probably
depends on the chip but you know
somewhere in between these two is gonna
be the ll3 rate and then as you might
imagine each of these pieces of memory
because we're like the way these work is
these are actually on the cpu most of
time this one might not be but these two
always are so the l1 in the l2 caches
are like welded on to a cpu or per core
and the way that they work is they are
just like sitting right next to the
compute units feeding them with data as
fast as possible right
as a result they can't be as large this
l1 cache is often something like 32 K
right so you know main memory these days
you might have like 64 gigabytes in even
a home computer right mm-hmm could have
something like that certainly most
computers these they have 4 gigabytes
even a phone will have 4 gigabytes
sometimes right so you've got a ton of
this memory 32 K tiny little bit of
memory right then you've got an l2 cache
who knows how big that is it's usually
on the order of megabytes what 2
megabytes who knows how big it is 1
megabyte something like that right no
that's not I'm wrong about that that's
it's it's more like 256 K I'm sorry I
misspoke it's like 120 26 K I don't know
- usually that's my this is where we're
on the order of mega bytes when we get
up to l3 cache I don't think you
typically have megabyte l two's I could
be wrong about that somebody look it up
there's a good place called wiki chip if
you don't know about it that has like
all processors on it and how big like
their caches are and stuff like that so
you know don't take my poor memory for
it go look it up but anyway point being
whatever CPUs in your machine you can
look up exactly what these are okay so
what actually happens inside the CPU
core is whenever it goes to operate on
data it doesn't ask main memory for
stuff what it does is it asks the cache
so when it comes down here and it says
hey I need this big 16 value I need you
to give me that what it does is it says
ok let me ask the l1 cache and see if
the l1 cache has it if the l1 cache has
it I can get the result back in 1
o'clock that's three hundred times
faster or more than going to main memory
great but the l1 cache may not have it
if the l1 cache doesn't have it what
will the l1 cache do it'll ask the l2
still 16 clocks we saved 20 times the
speed we save right very very good so
we're gonna ask the l2 cache next does
it have it if so then what happens is
there's two types of caches there's
inclusive and exclusive in an inclusive
cache what that means is that the the
data is stored in all the caches so for
example if I ask the l2 for something
and it doesn't have it it's gonna like
figure out what it is and put it in here
and then will also put it in the in the
l1 right whatever the data is will like
get filled into each of these caches and
they'll all hold it whereas an exclusive
catch only one cache holds it right or
and you can you don't have to have them
all operate the same way you can say you
can have different designs where like
the l1 and the l2 are inclusive so it'll
get stored in both of these but the l2
and the l3 are exclusive so it won't
store it here if it's here and it won't
store it in either of these if it's here
right so inclusive and exclusive can can
be across any set of caches that's just
how the hardware
- choose to do it or whatever right and
so what happens is it's like I said at
the beginning it's good to think of
these things as people communicate
mature because they kind of are what
happens is the chips like I need this
piece of data it'll ask the l1 l2
doesn't have it'll be like hey l2 do you
have it the l2 will be like no I don't
l3 do you have it no I don't mean memory
do you have it of course you do because
your main memory you have everything
it'll then come back back back and now
the CPU can have it right
so it's this communication chain right
that that goes and gets it okay um and
so what we're gonna come around full
circle to here right is you wanted to
know what our cache misses and how do I
avoid them well hopefully now you can
almost sort of answer that question for
yourself when we talk about getting when
we talk about that scheduler asking for
this piece of memory that it needs that
it knows it's going to need to execute
something when it asks and the answer is
I don't have it that's a cache miss and
when the answer is yes I do have it
that's a cache hit now when you say
cache miss or cache hit it's an
incomplete statement because there's at
least two often three caches on most
CPUs right so what that means is when
you say cache miss you have to say which
cast you're missing maybe you said meant
you missed all the caches or maybe you
meant you missed only a few of the
caches and which one you miss how many
you miss versus hit determines how slow
that return of information will be right
so let's suppose I ask for a piece of
memory this memory I need here where I
put 45 in so what happens when I put 45
into that piece of memory well when I
need to actually write this back there's
actually a thing here there's things
called right back tables and there's
these there's lines that actually come
here somebody we should do like I'm
going to spend three hours talking about
how an X 64 works because it's there's
all these parts in here but basically
what happens is there's a
piece of the chip that's responsible for
like handing things back to the l1
that's actually like rights that are
going back right so there's read lines
and write lines and what happens is you
know we end up building up these things
that have to go out to the l1 when they
go out to the l1 so like I did this
right I changed some values I put 45
into some piece of memory it's got to go
out here into these cache like there's
the 45 eventually gets written out to
the l1 there's the 45 the l1 informs the
l2 there's the 45 the L the l2 informs
the l3 there's the 45 it reforms to
memory there's the 45 it's stored there
later as we're doing stuff we only have
32 K of cash in our l1 right so what
happens is eventually it gets used it
gets used up we're doing stuff and we're
swapping things in and out right the
chip is trying to predict what you're
going to need and keep this l1 as filled
as possible with stuff but eventually
things have to get removed there's only
32 K and you're accessing all this
memory eventually what happens is
something gets removed from the cache
that you actually wanted that 45 we're
gonna use again but it gets removed
because there wasn't room for it right
and maybe it also gets removed from the
l2 because again we just we you we were
touching all this memory and doing
operations like right in here in this
stuff we're doing a bunch of stuff we
used a bunch of axis you know we ax
bunch of memory and then eventually we
come around and we want the 45 again
right here's our here's our code big 16
we're asking for that 45 again again
even in Java you know there's no Polly
nur's here or anything it's just I
needed some values that I that you know
I was using before right so I go to ask
for it what do I find
well the l1 is a Miss right I get a Miss
on l1 because that 45 is gone it's out
of there I asked the l2 what happens
that's a Miss as well so I've missed the
l1 and the l2 but I asked the l3 it's
still in there so what was my cache miss
sure miss or cache hit I missed the l1 I
missed the l2 but I hit the l3 and
that's the first thing to understand
these cache misses and hits when you say
I'm gonna miss the cache or hit the
cache you're actually need to be more
specific if you're actually talking
about for us reading which passes caches
did you miss and which caches did you
hit it's very likely to have an l1 cache
mish cache miss there's only 32 K in
there it's less likely to have an l2
cache miss but it's still very possible
to descend it's very unlikely to have an
l3 cache miss but if you're actually
working a large amount of memory then
you can and so then you're out to main
memory and that's the slowest right okay
so let's talk about a more complete
picture of what's going on as I said
we've got a scheduler this scheduler is
looking at all of the things that you've
put into it that it can do what it's
looking for are things that are
independent right or what we could call
dependency chains which are syriza's of
instructions that require the results of
each other to execute right so if I say
int X equals 5x plus equals 17 x equals
x shifted by 2 x equals x plus 5 right
if I talk about these kinds of things
now obviously they're all constants so
actually the compiler could all do this
but you know let me try giving you
something a little bit more realistic
let's suppose we have some function of x
and y and I'm going to do some stuff
here I'm going to say X plus equals Y X
shifted up by 7 X mod Y something like
this not equals Y these are all
dependent instructions I need to do this
ad before I can do this shift before I
can do this
maude right so what this looks like to a
modern CPU is a series of dependent
instructions it can only issue them in
order because it can never it can't
start this till it knows what this is
going to evaluate to and the same is
true here
on the other hand a similar function f
of XY that looked like this s x plus
equals 5 y by itself shifted up 7 x mod
y right this instruction and this
instruction are linearly questions are
linearly that's majors on the turn are
independent I don't need to know this to
start computing this right and so the
scheduler knows it will need the result
of both of these to compute this but it
will not need the result of this to
compute this nor will it need the result
of this to compute this so these are
independent why am I talking about this
well this is what actually determines
whether a cache miss of any of these
caches l1 l2 or l3 actually causes a
performance stall in your program
because when you look at a block of code
what you need to know as to whether
cache misses will actually affect that
piece of code significantly or not is
you have to know what will the CPU
actually be able to execute at the time
when the cache miss occurs ok so let's
talk about each of these if you've
missed the l1 cache write or let me
rephrase it a little bit more positively
if I hit the l1 cache basically there's
no very little chance that you can stall
the processor at all right and the
reason is because the l1 cache can
deliver information to me at 1 o'clock
latency so basically every cycle that
I'm issuing that I'm trying to do work
the l1 is there ready to provide
information now I say sort of
because there's one more thing we didn't
talk about which is a thing called IPC
IPC is instructions per clock and what
ends up happening inside modern
processors like the modern x64 course is
this scheduler doesn't have to eliminate
it doesn't have to limit itself to only
issuing one piece of work to the cores
every to the work units every cycle in a
modern x64 a core it can actually issue
up to four instructions per cycle okay
so there are additional complexities
even when analyzing l1 cache usage and
those additional complexities are of the
form because the l1 can only supply two
cache lines per clock back to the CPU
core in most architectures I think now I
I don't know about Zen 3 your Zen
whatever the new Zen is that they just
released I actually don't know what that
l1 CAC cache providing is but at least
on skylake and sky like X and coffee
like in all the lakes all those new
Lakes from Intel
so the l1 cache can actually only
provide to the CPU core 2 cache lines
worth of data so again just to give you
a more complete picture because I'm in
the mood to explain what does this mean
well
what it means is we now have to start
talking because in all of that
discussion you'll notice I never said
what it means I me just said Kanna we
store the number 45 and it comes back
right but well what do you mean the
number 45 I mean that's not very
specific
what are these caches actually storing
and how are they storing them well you
wouldn't really need to know if there
wasn't such a thing as a cache line but
there is and so you do and so here's how
that works
caches don't move things around on the
order of bits so when you say 45 well I
could encode 45 in six bits right I mean
that's just basic binary math but the
question is how many bits is the cache
going to move when I ask for the number
45 from memory right and the answer is
the cache always treats things in
multiples of 64 bytes it just doesn't
know whether to quote there it just does
64 bytes is called a cache line and the
cache will never to the best of my
knowledge move something smaller than 64
bytes around so now we get into some of
the subtleties of the way that this data
is partitioned what this means is when I
look at my instructions for clock and my
cache line size these things start to
become very relevant why because when I
talk about a cache miss or a cache hit
I'm not just talking about the one byte
the four bytes the eight bytes I might
have needed for the particular
instruction that the CPU is executing at
that time like my ad right I'm actually
talking about moving a whole 64 bytes
around and because I'm talking about
moving a whole 64 bytes around it starts
to matter how my data is arranged in
memory because if I ask for even just
one bite of a 64 byte chunk I'm gonna
get the whole 64 bytes back and it's
gonna evict a whole 64 bytes
from the l1 the l2 and the l3 to make
room for this new 64 bytes of memory
that I asked for if it's you know if
it's not in the caches so whole chunks
in 64 byte groups are getting moved in
and out okay so what that means is when
I look at stuff like cache performance I
have to start thinking about these
things on a modern CPU I have an IPC of
4 that means the maximum instructions I
can issue in one cycle right is for each
of those instructions have operands
write an instruction can like add two
things together that means it needs two
inputs right I can issue four of them
that means I can have up to eight inputs
right on one cycle so when you start to
look at this 64 bytes right of a cache
line and we can get even worse than this
I'll talk about that a second or even
more demanding right so when I start to
talk about this cache lines what did I
say I said the l1 right can provide two
cache lines per clock that means my l1
cache even if it's completely hitting
the cache so I'm 100% in the l1 cache
I'm not missing I can still only provide
two cache lines per clock that's the
maximum rate it can send the stuff back
right what that means is I can operate
on at 128 bytes per clock out of the l1
cache and a maximum well 128 bytes
whether or not that's going to be enough
as a lot of ramifications first of all
even with an IPC of 4
let's say I'm going to issue well now we
get into some other things about how
many units we actually have but let's
suppose we're going to do try to issue
three instructions okay
and I'm gonna pick an instruction that
actually can issue properly across
across three across one cycle three of
them so I'm gonna do three things called
a P ad and what a P ad is it's basically
the sim D units adder right so I'm going
to do P AB and I'm gonna do three of
these P ad calls right
okay so one of the things about a P ad
is that a P ad can take a memory operand
but it also needs to have a register
involved so for example let's say I'm
gonna do P ads and I've got a register
in here so the registers are going to be
whatever I don't know XM m 0 XM m 1x m
m2 right and then the thing I'm going to
be adding in each of these cases is
going to be some piece of memory right
so there's some memory there's some
memory it's a memory alright so what
actually happens here well first of all
we've got some limitations and I'll talk
about each of those limitations in turn
just cuz we're fully down the rabbit
hole now so you might as well get in
there so when we look at what happens we
know that the l1 cache is sitting over
here right and it's ready to go
we know that the scheduler is looking at
this stuff and it's trying to figure out
what it can do and we know we've got our
you know our actual work units down here
and they want stuff to do right and so
what's gonna happen when I look at this
code well the first thing that we could
say about it is that looking at these 3
P adds this apart we're not really
talking about just mention it offhand so
it's on the table we would need at least
3 P ad units down here right in order to
issue 3 P ads in one cycle if I wanted
all of these things to issue I need at
least 3 P ad units down in the work part
of the chip to actually send them to
because otherwise when I send the first
one in the second one on this cycle
there's nowhere to send the third one
right
now fortunately I picked an instruction
that has three units P ad is a unit that
P is something that there are three work
units in the chip that can actually
field so that would be fine so I could
send all 3x down to the work units no
problem okay next thing we look at need
to look at is register usage are these
all independent xmm 0 X and M 1 M 2 they
all are so I don't need to really like
worry about dependencies here because
I'm not writing to my registers well I
could talk about the rat up here where
did I put the rat the rats here
somewhere this guy the register
allocation table is the thing that's
responsible for that part of the the
process but we're kind of skipping it
for now
it's not really related to cash
performance but it is an interesting
part of the chip so anyway we're gonna
ask you three of these P adds great
we got three work units no problem right
but each of these P adds requires us to
look at some memory and actually get the
memory that we need right and who knows
what these are so maybe these are like I
don't know I I need to look at like EAX
plus like 50 and EI x plus 256 and like
EI x plus 5/12 something like that right
so I'm gonna go look at memory I'm gonna
do some ads it's gonna be great I know I
can issue all three you'll be good but
when I look at this part suddenly we've
got issues okay
so what are our issues well there's
actually two reasons that we won't be
able to issue all three of these in one
cycle I could I think even do something
a little more squirrelly here but I'm
not going to cuz well what happens is
first of all you look and the l1 cache
wouldn't actually be able to help us
here we couldn't get this information
out of the l1 cache in time
why because ax + 50 e^x + 56 + EI x + 5
12 these are all on separate cache lines
right remember a cache line is only 64
bytes so this would require one cache
line this is clearly on another one
because it's more than 64 bytes away
from this and this is more than 64 bytes
away from this so the l1 cache actually
wouldn't be able to hand us the memory
in time and this instruction stream
would stall just on the l1 cache but
there's actually another reason it would
stall right it would stall because there
actually aren't three address generation
units inside the the X's before anyway
there's a thing called an address
generation unit and what that is is the
thing that actually handles the cache
line like filling and matching and
determining what this AB even produces
right so in order to produce a fetch
from memory you need to have a free a GU
there's only two AG use on modern x64
like skylight cores right so actually
there's two reasons that we can't issue
three of these per cycle right so what
does this tell us
well it tells us you know someone didn't
tell you know was pretty smart in a
sense because if the l1 could issue more
than two cache lines per clock chances
are it would never get the chance to
because since there aren't enough AG use
on the chip in order to actually send
three memory requests to the l1 what
good is it gonna do that it could
fulfill three right so you would tend to
call that a very balanced architecture
right
you didn't provide too many AG use or
too many cache line fills so that your
silicon is just sitting dead that would
be considered a mistake probably right
because we over engineered one part of
the chip to deliver things more quickly
but the other part of the chip can't do
it right it doesn't work so that you
know keeping that in mind right there
are limitations that the l1 can impose
but oftentimes they're simply not going
to occur because actually the aju
becomes the blocking factor in in the
first place now there is one other
reason that I should mention specific to
Intel chips as far as I know I don't
know if it's true on AMT so I've never
tested it but actually on Intel chips
there's a weird thing which is there's
an l1 l2 fill penalty that is
undocumented I have no I've never gotten
someone at Intel to confirm it they
literally don't return my emails when I
ask them about this don't ask me why but
it turns out when you actually ask for
memory at a rate that the l1 should be
able to achieve and the l2 should be
able to achieve you can't actually get
the l1 to give you back data at the
speed it should because if it needs to
take to accept incoming data from the l2
on a particular cycle it seems like it
can only provide one cache line so
normally if the l1 is not receiving a
fill from l2 it can do two cache lines
per clock but if it's receiving data
from the l2 it seems like you can only
do one cache line per clock so it's like
one cache one of those cache line fills
it should be able to do is like taken up
with an l2 receive that makes sense
again this is completely undocumented
I've never seen it mentioned anywhere
but it
absolutely happens and most people will
never know about it because they're not
usually doing things at a speed that's
tweaked enough to actually need this
it's pretty hard to get the chip into
this state but if you do it doesn't work
right you end up with with not getting
the l2 bandwidth you expect because of
that l2 l1 fill alright so hopefully
have given you a sense of just how
complex all this stuff is if you want to
start actually looking into it so the
answer in the specific of how do I avoid
cache misses is incredibly complicated
the real answer is learn everything you
can about the CPU architecture you're on
and actually work out what it's going to
have to do when you're working on what's
working on the code you're writing and
figure out exactly how those misses
might affect you and how you could avoid
them I realize that's not a very good
answer to give to someone who's just
starting out because that's a lot of
work and it's very complicated so how do
we generalize some rules of thumb for
the beginner well the first thing is
learn the cache sizes that's the most
basic thing you can do learn the cache
sizes for the CPUs you're targeting
learn how big is the l1 how big is the
l2 how big is the l3 why because you
want to start thinking about how to
organize your data so that data that's
accessed frequently can fit inside these
caches right try to start packing your
data down so that if you have stuff
that's pretty random access that you're
doing a bunch of work on right try to
get it under 32 K try to get it under
256 K right try to fit it into a smaller
amount of space because the smaller that
frequently-asked access data is the more
cache hits you can get the more
sprawling the data is the worse right
so that's thing one
think to is try to arrange your data so
that things that will be looked at at
the same time are close to each other
and things that are not are far away
right so remember the cache is not just
about size it's also about arrangement
the cache must move 64 bytes
every time you ask it to do something
right it cannot move a subsection of
that so I'll give you a simple example
let's suppose I make a linked list right
actually you know we know ninda how do
you know let's suppose I make an array
okay I'm going to make an array of data
and I'm gonna operate on that data I'm
creating a struct that's in that array
and that struct has the following stuff
in it int X care name I don't know it's
64 into y okay
so let's suppose I've got this struct I
want to make an array of these actually
I'll use big again I like that name I've
got a big array and I've just got a ton
of these right I've got 6 5 5 3 6 of
them so I'm just got a ton of these
things right and I'm operating on I'm
doing all kinds of stuff well let's
suppose I have a important loop in my
code and it looks something like this
you know for everything inside big I'm
gonna go through and I'm going to take
you know particular big dot X and I'm
going to add you know 5 to it and I'm
going to take a particular part of Y
there and take Y and add 7 to it and
this is like super performance critical
right I'm doing a ton of these I do it
all
all the time it's a really hot part of
the code well look at what happened here
because this structure is organized such
that I have X right where is X it's at
offset zero from the struct so wherever
the struct is it's at the very first
byte of the struct where is name well I
know that this is 32 bits of an integer
right so that's 4 bytes so name is at +4
off of my struct where is y y is 64 of
the name right in between in and X so
it's going to be the plus 4 of name plus
the 64 that it took up so it's actually
going to be at plus 68 right do you see
where this is going this and this are
the two things that I use inside this
loop but they are on different cache
lines right so how concerned should I be
about this well the first thing you
might say to me is okay Casey I can
solve that all this move into X up here
right so now I've got int X int int Y
right and that way haha they're both on
the same cache line because now x and y
are at 0 and plus 4 and the next thing
is actually at plus 668 right I'm sorry
the next thing is actually a plus 8 and
runs out to the end right but actually
that didn't do anything why didn't it do
anything because now all you've actually
done is you've you know you've changed
what the alignment might be but it
probably still isn't that good you're
still you know like think about how this
would have laid out in memory if I'd had
two foods next to each other even before
I did that swap the next in X was coming
here so the Y in the X were actually
gonna still be on the same cache line
secretly right the X of the next one
would have been on the same cache line
right so how can I fix this well the
right thing to do was to say let's split
these up right just split these up into
big one in big two
phoo one in food too and so then I've
got here struct through one that's just
gonna have my XY right and then futu
we'll just have name what does that
allowed me to do well now right I can
actually fit eight pairs of XY z-- into
one cache line and this big name
structure that I'm not even touching on
this particular time in this particular
hot piece of code that's going to some
totally separate cache line right so
that has dramatically reduced the number
of cache lines I have had to touch in
order to do the work that I was trying
to do before how much well if you look
at how many cache lines I was processing
before I was processing 65536 right how
many cache lines each of these things
was what like this is 0 this is for 864
so it's like 72 bytes right for each of
these so it's that right
it's 6.5 to 6 times 72 over 64 this is
how many cache lines I had to touch
before right that's what was happening
now arguably maybe there were times when
it would have lined up and you wouldn't
have had to touch this particular one so
it's maybe a little less than this
potentially there you go whereas in the
other case when this thing is only 8
long right then I've got 6 5 5 3 6 times
8 over 64 right this is way more
favorable it's basically 72 over 8 it
was this many times more cache lines
roughly speaking right so I would expect
this to actually run like nine times
faster in some cases right because the
or I shouldn't say nine times faster
it's touching nine times more cache
lines in this case so depending on how
much cash bandwidth is compared to what
I'm doing I could expect a massive speed
up just by this small organisation
right reorganisation so that's number
two you know organize for the cash and
that just involves what do you actually
use often together put those together
and get the other things out of the way
so that each 64 byte cache line you're
actually using is filled with good stuff
right and sometimes this requires you to
do alignment you also want to make sure
that you don't spread across cache lines
unnecessarily so you want to try and
align things to the cache line
boundaries right and we've shown how to
do alignment memory linemen on handmade
here oh you don't know what that is and
so there's one more rule of thumb that I
add in there and that is do you have a
Prefecture right now not all CPUs have a
prefecture so it depends on your
platform but x64 CPUs definitely do what
is a Prefecture well if you take a look
at what goes on inside the CPU when
you're trying to get really good usage
out of these caches one of the things
that's typically true is your memory
usage patterns are typically not
completely random right so oftentimes
what a CPU will have in it is something
that looks at which cache lines you're
asking for and tries to extrapolate
which ones you will need and it will
pre-fill the cash or prefetch as the
case may be right so what is a
Prefecture do a Prefecture will look and
say are you you know accessing every
eight cache line in a row right like I'm
asked I asked for cache line zero then 8
then 16 and you know blah blah blah am I
asking for them in strictly decreasing
order did I ask for zero negative one
name to name three and a 45 right from
my pointer like how am i accessing these
cache lines if you can provide a
dick table simple access pattern the
prefetcher will be able to ask for
memory long in advance of being needed
and pre fill your caches right so linear
you know simple access patterns can help
you take advantage of that prefecture
and ensure that all of the caches get
filled before you ever ask for them
right so this helps a lot when you're
processing bulk data I got a run through
a gigabyte of data well guess what a
gigabyte of data don't fit in the cache
so it doesn't matter if I you know try
to organize it or any of these other
things there's only so much I can do
it's got to feed a gigabyte data through
main memory how do I try to make it so
that I'm not constantly waiting on main
memory well this is how you want to try
and make as straightforward of an access
pattern as possible so the prefecture
can do the work of pre filling the cache
what does this do for you
well main memory can operate at pretty
high speeds these days you can get
somewhere around so let me think of what
this is it sits around to get get a
cache line back you can do that in like
in like five-and-a-half clocks use like
six six four o'clock I'm sorry I just
don't remember the main memory per clock
rate right now so if I have well
actually I guess I kind of do I think
it's like 5.5 bytes per clock some
around there six bytes per clock I don't
really remember exactly what the main
memory speed is but it's not that bad
it's something like six bytes per clock
let's say and so what you want to do is
when you know you're gonna be throttled
by main memory because you're just your
plowing through a crap-ton of data you
still don't want to give up on the
caches because they're still actually
important because the prefecture can
move things so that you're not waiting
the full 300 clocks right 300 clocks to
retrieve a single cache line would be
horrific for the actual speed of the CPU
right at 16 bytes I'm sorry 64 bytes
back to the core in 300 clocks would be
point 2 bytes per clock that's terrible
right so you can do way better than that
by just making sure that you actually
kind of inform the chip ahead of time
and that's where you can get that's what
what these linear simple access patterns
are for now what if you don't have a
simple linear access pattern there's one
other thing you can do they're called
prefetch instructions and what you can
do is you can use prefetch instructions
which are literally just things you
insert into a loop to tell the processor
what you're going to be working on next
right and you try to give it something
fairly far out so it can go to main
memory and get it prepared for you
insert prefetch instructions that's a
way of telling the prefetcher look this
is not a simple access pattern I know
there's no way you're gonna be able to
guess it so try to use my hints about
what to grab right ok so that these are
the three like simple rules of how to
start avoiding cache misses learn what
the sizes are and pack your data as
tightly as possible to try and get under
those sizes organize your data so that
things that are likely to be used
together are close together and you're
not wasting those 64 byte fetches on
crap you don't need just to get a little
bit you do need right trying to make all
64 bytes actually important and then
fine finally use simple access patterns
or insert 3 fetches into your code to
inform the CPU ahead of time what you
will need right ok so I realize that's a
ton of stuff to talk about but it
really all important there's so much
more in here we haven't covered all of
it's important you can actually get
problems with the register allocation
table you can get problems with these
things here there's there's a thing that
happens in that part of the chip
actually that's pretty interesting
itself which is you've got sort of these
work units and then you've got the l1
cache and in between there there's
actually these things called line
buffers and basically what happens is as
you sort of fill up work that's you know
I've modified memory that goes out to
these thing called line buffers and what
the line buffers are is they're
assembling up pieces of cache lines so
that it can later tell the l1 cache to
do an update of a full search before
bytes rather than like taking just like
four bytes of output that this thing did
you know and sending just four bytes
over so it's it's kind of like an
assembly station that tries to put
things together and what's interesting
about these line buffers is there's a
limited number so you can end up
throttling in here on line buffers that
are going out you can also throttle on
line buffers coming back so basically
what happens is these work units when
they need to do work that scheduler is
trying to find the results of things
sometimes it gets an instruction and it
goes where's the data for that
instruction oh the data for this are
just actually out in a line buffer let
me grab that back out of the line buffer
because I don't need to go to the cache
to get it and then I'll feed that
through the work unit right so there's
all these sorts of things gonna be
happening in there and it's fairly
complicated of what's happening right
all this stuff is really really
interesting and when you go down looking
at it it's incredible all the stuff
that's going on inside the CPU and all
of its both incredible and very
primitive when I say things like it's
looking for it's not looking for
anything it's a really like tight little
set of circuits that just do the best
they can at sort of heuristic aliy
grabbing things as they're necessary it
can fail all the time it actually has a
number of fail
cases where it doesn't assign things in
the optimal way and so things that
should reach a certain peak throughput
won't because the scheduler just it
isn't like a huge logic system it's not
like a program that in there that's
super comp K that's running it has to be
incredibly fast so it's actually fairly
simple circuits that are just kind of
doing basic work that happens to usually
end up picking the right instructions
but sometimes it just doesn't right and
the reason for that is just because it's
it's a guessing game right without
perfect knowledge if I have three units
that can do this particular instruction
and two units that can do this other one
but one of them is the same so one of
the units is shared between the two well
if I need to do this instruction stream
perfectly I may need to guess to not put
it on the shared one now because another
instruction is going to come down the
pipe that needs to use that shared one
so I should really do it on one of the
other ones right but maybe that same
choice would have been a mistake at a
different time because the shared ones
gonna be used for a different thing
right so when you have work units that
can execute multiple different things
and they're overlapping it's a very hard
scheduling problem we could all write a
program that would do it perfectly I'm
sure but it would be very expensive and
could never be made in the small amount
of silicon that's necessary to keep this
thing running at a super high rate of
four instructions per clock so you can
see why you get these sort of
interesting failure cases out of
something like this right okay so again
cache misses incredibly complicated to
analyze why are they so complicated
analyze because the chip is super
complex and a cache miss all it means is
that a particular set of an instruction
dependencies have to stall until we get
the results that either is or isn't a
huge deal for your algorithm depending
on what else can be executed right so
that's why I say it's not trivial to
understand when a cache misses costly or
when it isn't or how to architect better
to get less cache miss penalties because
it's all dependent on what else to the
scheduler do
maybe you've got 300 cycle cache misses
going on all the time but the algorithm
that you actually executing every time
you get one of those pieces of data back
actually takes 300 cycles itself because
it's really complicated right you may
never see the cache miss right you may
never see it because the amount of work
you're doing is more than the cost of
getting the memory so the chip because
of the scheduler is good at hiding cache
misses from you as well this gets even
more complicated once you get into hyper
threading right so if you have a chip
that's capable hypo threading but you
may or may not have but a hyper
threading chip is a chip whose scheduler
can scheduler from more than one thread
at a time so I have you know thread a
coming in here and I have thread B
coming in here thread a hits a 300 cycle
cache miss no big deal I just start
executing thread B right and so hyper
threading can even make it less obvious
how a cache miss will affect the
performance of your processor because
now it's fight it's it's basically like
filling work from two threads at once
and that ping pong in between those two
threads is actually super important
right and so that's really the you know
that's really the the truth about caches
they're incredibly incredibly hard to to
really to really explain how to avoid
right there is not much of an answer
beyond really learn your chip I mean
learn it inside it out and then find out
by actually doing profiling looking at
performance counters you can use like
vtune or perf on linux to actually look
how many cache misses i'm getting how
much am i stalling on those cache misses
are they actually costing me time or
aren't they well how many instructions
per clock am i issuing right until you
actually dig down in there it may be
impossible to really know until you
she look at the raw data and the
performance numbers you know it's it's
it's something that that is not obvious
until you actually start to look into it
how much you may or may not be affected
by caste because it's not as simple as
simply counting the amount of memory you
use because there's so much more going
into it because of that scheduler let me
try to since we've gone all the way down
this rathole let me try to answer the
questions that I've got this is kind of
turning into a handmaid job that's how
it goes sometimes let me try to scroll
through those questions that have to do
with cashing and I'm gonna try to answer
those let's see
okay is there a way to transfer data to
the cache manually so that answer
depends entirely on the CPU and I guess
the way I would say it is on the x64
there really isn't a way to transfer
data to the cache manually in a
mandatory fashion meaning you can't
force the x64 to do something with the
cache look like I just don't know any
way of doing that I don't think it's
possible but what you can do is is
suggest to it what to do and that's like
that prefetch instruction that I talked
about
so the the prefetch instruction is an
example of instruction that gives you a
it's and one of that in a new tab there
we go um the prefetch instruction is
example of a way to strongly suggest
that it do that and so in that sense you
can sort of force it right it's just not
mandatory so what you can see here is
this mm prefetch instruction basically
says I'm gonna give you a pointer and
you know I don't love I'm gonna use the
you ops table I don't love the intrinsic
guide for talking about actual
instructions because that's intrinsic so
I kind of prefer I kind of prefer the
you up table for that so I'm gonna I'm
gonna load up all the goodness here all
right
so these are the actual instructions
prefetch MTA prefetch t0 prefetch t1
prefetch t2 so what these instructions
do is they say look i'ma tell you that I
need to use a particular cache line I'm
telling you I'm gonna need it later and
I'm gonna try and give you enough
advance notice that it's long enough to
go to main memory to get it if you need
to and then furthermore depending on
whether but I use MTA t0 t1 or t2 I'm
also gonna try to tell you what I think
you might need to do with that cache
line right so prefetch t0 is basically
saying I think we're going to need this
in the like closest level right I don't
know that this has exclamations of the
instructions in here I guess when I said
that this was the best thing to use what
I actually meant is totally not that so
sorry about that we load it up in here
actually I guess I can just jump to it
straight here
where is my pre-fit there it is okay so
what you can see here is here's the
prefetch instructions and I've got a
couple different ones they all take a
memory pointer it doesn't matter what
that pointers bottom bits are because
it's just going to fetch that cache line
right so remember a cache line is a 64
byte chunk of memory aligned to 64 bytes
so the bottom six bits are irrelevant
doesn't matter what they are they're
right sorry bottom five bits are
irrelevant it only matters what the high
bits are because they come in chunks of
64 right and so when we actually fetch
we're gonna say the pointer to this
cache line no matter where the is inside
the cache line doesn't matter that whole
cache line I want you to know I'm gonna
use it soon and then based on which of
these hints I use t0 t1 or t2 or the
special NTA which we'll talk about a
second this tells me how I expect to use
it a t0 fetch says give it to me
everywhere I want the t0
I want the the l1 the l2 and the l3
cache is all filled if I say t1 that
means
well I'm not quite sure it needs to be
all the way down to the 32k l1 cache so
maybe don't bother right put it only up
in the l2 and l3 and then t2 is saying
just the l3 right NTA is different than
these what empty what MTA says is look
I'm gonna use this thing real soon I
need you to make it be available to me
but I'm never gonna use it after that
for a long time so don't put it in the
l3 don't put it in the l2 if somehow you
can not put it in the l1 go ahead and
don't but maybe just put it in the l1 so
I can use it right away and then let's
get rid of it so don't pollute anything
else right
so basically it's saying this data gets
used once and not multiple times don't
pollute the cache minimize the cache
pollution now that may mean it can use
some special side Channel who knows when
the processor architects are free to do
whatever they want or it may mean it has
to fill the whole thing it depends on
the architecture whether it can do
anything with that NT a hint but it's a
hint it's it's you announcing what
you're going to do and the degree to
which the processor can actually do
something about that depends on the
processor right so that's one way
there's another way it can do it it's
called a non temporal store can't
remember the instruction for that there
you go
so some of the when you're working with
bulk data like that and sort of in a
similar situation where the prefetch NTA
might be involved where you're saying
look I don't need you to fill these
caches because I'm not gonna touch this
data multiple times I'm loading it in
once and then I'm writing it out and
then we're never gonna see it again
right so don't pretend I'm gonna keep
accessing because I'm not the same is
true for right pollution so you could
think of that as read as cache pollution
that happens on a read I'm reading data
the CPU goes oh he's reading this data
let me feel the caches but you're like
no I I'm never gonna use this again
don't pollute the caches if it's not in
there already don't put it in there just
give it to me once and we're done right
and so the same thing is true for right
pollution and so these are ways of
writing to memory and saying don't put
them in the cache just write them to
memory I'm not gonna ask for them again
for a long time so don't pollute my
cache with them right so those are the
two ways that you can try to micromanage
the cache but again these are hits the
processor is it's you're not really
telling the processor what to do you're
telling the plus sir what you want and
it may or may not do something
based on that so that's probably about
all you can say there are other
processors so for example let's suppose
we take the dolphin processor is a
processor that was in a machine called
the GameCube from Nintendo which you may
have or may not have heard of or used if
depending on how old you are that
process or did have manual cache control
I believe it had a 64 K cache I think
and the way it worked was you could
treat as 64 K of cash or 32 K of cash
and 32k of local memory basically so
when you put the machine into that mode
it would say 32k of my 64 K cash I'm
just gonna trust that you know what to
do with it and you could tell it exactly
how you wanted it filled so that's an
example of as a PowerPC derived chip
with manual cash control for real right
another good example of that would be
the PlayStation 3 the PlayStation 3 had
regular caching on its main processor of
which had only had one core but then it
had these things called SPU's which were
the main workhorses of the processor
they were effectively very fast DSPs and
those actually literally only have
manual cache they were literally a 64 no
256 K I think they were 256 K of local
strapped on memory to each one of these
SP use of which there were eight seven
something like that and all of it was
manual so you basically would queue up
you were like here's the memory I'm
gonna need the axe power I'm going to
need you did work and it was very
predictable so you tried to like do the
exact amount of work and then a new
piece of member would come in and you do
work right and so basically like the
SPU's on a Playstation 3 are a good
example of
manual cash there was no cash on those
SPU's that was controlled by like a
CPU logic thing I don't think could be
wrong about that though I never really
program SPU's all right you 64 bytes the
cache line size on every CPU yes
actually
so historically speaking no obviously
those cache line sizes have varied
throughout history certainly but
nowadays for whatever reason maybe it's
just the optimal number I don't know
you'd have to ask a hardware designer
maybe Y 64 bytes tends to be it but
you'd be hard-pressed to find a consumer
machine without a 64 byte cache all of
the modern AMD chips are 64 byte cache
all of the modern intel chip repair
tests I think even all of the typical
ARM chips on like an iPhone are 64 byte
caches so there's probably something out
there that's not but like yeah it's 64
bytes which is great we happen to be
living in that rare time period where
everything you program for is 64 byte
caches little-endian what a great world
right I'm sure it's not gonna last cuz
some friggin hardware guys gonna come
along and decide to do big endian again
or change the cache size to 26 bytes or
I don't know what but you happen to be
in a time right now where it just like
it happens to be 64 byte little endian
everywhere and that's really nice it
simplifies things for a programmer who's
trying to do performance oriented code
takes some things out of the equation
when you're doing cross-platform
targeting I tested me on the news energy
processors I have not I would love to I
don't have one someone wants to send me
a computer I'd be happy to test them AMD
if you're out there send me as some of
your latest machines and I'd be happy to
test me on hash it's the fastest hash on
Intel
let's see this is also important for DMA
memory yes well so the SPU that's sort
of how it worked right and it's
important to remember that DMA memory is
just is really no different from regular
memory that we have in aces before it's
just a little more explicit about how
its programmed but you actually kind of
need to think about it the same way even
on a processor such as the x64 skylights
that we're using here that don't feature
explicit DMA memory it's still sort of
is the same thing you're still trying to
schedule memory to get into the CPU at
the right time to use it which is what
DMA is all about and so your thought
process between an explicit DMA chip
like the SPU where there's no behind
your back caching it everything's
explicit you have to set up chains and
tell them when to come in it's really
not that different today because you
still now today just have to think how
do I get the CPU to basically do the
right DMA schedule that I wanted right
and so it's very similar thought process
and a very similar optimization you're
trying to think about how to structure
your code so the right stuff comes in at
the right time how does the processor
handle multiple programs right at the
same time in regards to the cache so the
answer there is I it depends really what
you're talking about when you say what
gets handled so inside so let's let's
just go this is turned into an all-day
cache solution so let's just go why
leave anything out right so let's
broaden our picture and start talking
about even more complicated crap that
goes on in here because it's really
complicated
so let's suppose we look at a block
diagram of a modern CPU right um well
you know what we can instead of my
crappy drawing die pictures of am teeth
red refer to
let's see so I want that's what I want
[Music]
can I get someone who's actually
highlighted them cuz I'm not you know
like I said I'm not a chip guy I'm not
qualified to walk you through the die on
a on a send chip just from looking at it
right but but sometimes you can find
people who have who have got the die can
I get us into in today did they do is
into
here we go do they have oh but they okay
so they don't they don't have the dye
shots on here though so I guess I guess
we're sticking with this um so I I may
not be able to find a good one here us
that's kind of hoping for a good a good
dye shot
so there's some good ones here ok ok ok
so this is an example of a die shot of a
CPU core right and hopefully what you
can see here is that these things these
boxes that I'm drawing when I say like
here's a box of you know logical
processing unit or whatever crap like
that is I'm drawing a semantic picture
of a CPU and so I'm not trying to draw
like what's actually the desired CP or
anything but actually if you go look at
an actual CPU it's actually kind of like
that it's not it's different but it's
not that different and what you can see
is things actually are a bunch of blocks
like they actually are regions of the
chip that do actually function as
coherent units that have to literally
talk to each other and so what you can
see here is it's not marked but I'm
assuming this is the l2 cache here right
kind of strapped on to the l3 so you
know you can kind of see how this works
depending on how the chip is configured
you can see that each of your cores has
some of its own cache and some of the
cache is shared right and so typically
what happens in a modern course is
because the core count tends to keep
increasing this kind of structure
becomes more and more complicated you
tend to have actually fairly difficult
work you you tend to have to do a lot
more thinking about how the memory is
going to get routed now in this case
it's pretty simple you can see what
would happen if a particular core wanted
a particular piece of memory it would
ask its l1 which I don't know where that
is actually on here but I assume this is
the l2 it would ask its l1 maybe that's
this stuff here
I don't know does anyone have
yeah so you can so you can see I was
right about the l2 but I don't see the
l1 in here so I don't really know like I
said I'm not qualified to analyze dye
shots so I'm not gonna try and guess but
you know somewhere in here there's an l1
when it misses it's going to hit this l2
the l2 is gonna ask the l3 when it
misses and the l3 because it's the thing
that's shared is sort of like the
central arbiter so the l3 is the thing
that's going to say oh you know what you
wanted this piece of memory bad news
core zeros using it right now and you
can't have it or something like that
right before I go into talking about how
that sort of thing works which is
germane your question I would really
like to find a die shot of as n2 CPU
because I wanted to show you this
getting worse because that was actually
simpler and this is as n2 CPU is gonna
have a more a more complex die gosh darn
it
okay okay okay this is be good enough
it's not really a diet though well maybe
this would have it not sure okay so the
only thing that I wanted to kind of talk
about before I got into like what
actually happens with the cash there is
that if you look at this sort of block
diagram which is not as good as a die
shot but if you look at how the new like
Zen's architected let me start by
talking about yield because this is a
Mira Torre answer so we're just we're
going all over the place and I apologize
but I'm just giving you the full thing
computing is complicated what can I say
so modern CPUs are incredibly hard to
make and if you don't believe me I would
highly encourage you to just go look in
fact Fabien Giessen and myself have
recently been trading links about what's
called extreme UV lithography which is
something that they're having to do now
in order to try and get chip production
speed fast enough that small at the
really small feature sizes that they're
trying to do and I would highly
recommend going and reading about
extreme UV lithography not because it's
really all that important to know but
rather because if you just take a second
to think about just how nuts it is to
make a chip nowadays that can kind of
help inform your thinking about why some
of these things are the way they are
right it's just hard to give you a
slight example extreme UV lithography is
a way to well let's look at let's just
this is all just reinforcing stuff so
I'm just going to talk about it alright
so how do I make a chip how do we how do
we just make a chip at all right
uh well you know you go read online and
they're like hey we got this new 7
nanometre fab right at TSMC right this
is the kind of stuff you'd read this is
our new 7 nanometre fab TSMC and we're
using it for making the you know the the
new rising chips you know and blah blah
blah right what what is what does that
mean what's TSMC what is seven nanometer
what's a fab I don't know right
well obviously the easiest thing is well
TSMC is a company right you can look at
them here they are right they're a
company in Taiwan and they make chips
right they actually make the physical
chips that you use so they're a like I
don't know what you call them a
third-party fab I don't know how you
would describe it but you know a company
like Intel they have their own fab and
their own fab technology which means
that when they go to make the latest eye
9 chip that you're going to buy and put
your desktop processor Intel itself owns
the fabrication facility they're
actually here in the u.s. usually I and
they will go with there's something I
think they have them in Isreal as well I
remember all the locations they have
fabs now until does but they'll go they
they may have some in China I don't even
really know where they all are but point
being they they've got their own fabs
owned by Intel operated by Intel
employees right they will make the chip
they're tsmc is an example of a
contractual fab you send them the chip
to fab they send you back the silicon
right so they're making the chips
they're on your design so what that
means is any of you out there anyone
listening to the stream you could fab
your own chip that's as good as a
zambese chip right now
TSM see it's probably not I'm gonna take
your order for one chip no one's gonna
want that right they want you to place
an order for a million chips or
something right but if you could find a
way if you ran a Kickstarter and you had
your own chip design TSMC will found
that chip for you and they'll
the best stuff they've got right so so
unlike Intel who couldn't care less
about your chip design tsmc is an a
place that is literally there to handle
chip times to and back comes a chip it's
great anyone can do it anyone can get
into the chip business if you want and
have access to some of the best fabs in
the world the Taiwanese are very good at
making chips TSMC is an excellent
foundry right it used to be that Intel
was way ahead they're not anymore
it's a bit of a it's a bit of a race now
but but you know Intel used to be way
ahead but now it's not as bad largely
because Intel's moved to ten nanometer
was what they call ten nanometer which
is basically actually the same size more
or less as TSM see seven nanometers so
they're not the names are confusing but
okay so first of all there is a company
somewhere maybe it's in tell me miss TSM
see there's also a company called global
I think that does this there's a bunch
of places in the world and what they do
is they actually make the chip they
actually make a physical thing that is
the chip and how do they do this well
they take a ridiculous absolutely absurd
thing I think it's called a silicon
ingot but it might not be called that
[Music]
let me see if I can find a picture one
of these things there it is they take
something that looks like that and I'm
not kidding it's actually like this
incredibly freaky looking it looks like
somebody did like a rendering it looks
like when they first introduced
reflection mapping into video games it
looks like that that is what it looks
like it's bizarre
right and what this is is an incredibly
incredibly incredibly pure piece of
silicon I have absolutely no idea how
they are made I don't know if anyone
knows how they're made
and I'm not really making that up like
there's some kind of crazy process
that's like they take this sand they
mined from certain places and they make
them into these things and like you know
the basic idea is known but the places
don't tell you how they do it because
certain places get really really pure so
I don't know maybe everyone knows now
but there was a time I I want to say and
you know I almost want I wish Fabien was
here I'd ask him for backup on this cuz
he follows this stuff too and he follows
it probably more closely than I do but I
want to say at least for a time there
were some companies that made the
silicon ingots and like nobody there was
like - and like nobody knows how they
did it like it was just like these
places make this really pure silicon and
like nobody else can make it as pure
right it's just this weird like trade
secret thing so I may be way off base on
that but I want to say that was the case
it may not be the case anymore but point
being somebody makes these silicon
ingots and then these silicon ingots are
turned into wafers and what that is is
it's a thing where you basically slice
and I again don't know how that process
works but that's not so that that I
don't think process is so bizarre you
slice off a circular section right now I
don't know why it's not a square because
that would fit more chips on it but I
assume it has something to do with the
fact that maybe silicon crystals can't
be made in a square or maybe there's
some other reason you know I've never
really thought about that before but
that would be a good thing to go look up
I bet there's an answer somewhere as to
why they're circular but they always are
you always see it's a cert it's always
circular so it's not the shape is not
arbitrary its circular and so there's a
reason for that
nothing in the CPU fabrication world is
accidental
so trust me there's a reason I just
don't know what it is and it's either
that there's some reason the machine
needs it that way
or it's because they can't grow silicon
in any other way and so I just don't
know but it's obviously not great I
would think because you know all chips
are designed to fit inside a regular
square region for tiling and so I would
think you would want it to be I would
think that you'd want it to be
rectangular in the optimal case but it
ain't so there you go anyway so in order
to fab a chip you gotta have this
looking and get you slice that into a
silicon wafer and then we have to
actually manufacture something on the
silicon wafer right it doesn't help us
just have a silicon wafer we have to put
a chip on there somehow
right we have to get an actual chip to
form on this silicon wafer hmm now again
I'm not a hardware guy so take my
explanations with a grain of salt and if
you're really interested in this I
really encourage you to go read about it
there's tons of great stuff it's you you
can spend a whole day just reading about
this stuff that's really entertaining
even if you just are never gonna do
anything with it it's just a really
entertaining really educational thing to
go explore so I highly recommend it but
what are you gonna do you've got this
silicon and we're starting to talk about
things that are so so darn tiny so let's
go back to that thing seven nanometer
fab well what is that seven nanometer
part now right well seven nanometers is
some name they give to a particular
process where you can put things onto
the silicon where the smallest detail
measured somehow and we'll get to that
hand waving in a second measured somehow
is 7 nanometers across ok so you'll see
different claims Intel currently claims
to be on 14 plus plus I want to say
they're trying to go to 10 nanometer and
then 10 plus + 10 + + you you think I'm
making these up when I say these things
it's it's like C++ or something right
Intel fab roadmap I swear I am not
making this stuff up right right there
on 14 plus plus right now they want to
be they wanted to be on 10 so this is
what they wanted they wanted tend to be
here it got slid out to here where is it
this is what they wanted right they had
wanted to be on 10 nanometer what
they're calling 10 nanometer in 2017
they totally failed it was a disaster it
didn't work at all and so they had to
basically slip out and so this is what
they're trying to do now they're trying
to do 10 in 2019 10 plus next year 10
plus plus in 2021
at which point they're hoping 7
nanometers on scale 7 plus 7 plus plus
now you may look at this and say well if
TSM sees on 7 nanometre now in 2019 what
the hey they're not going in 70 animator
till 2021 aren't they way behind no the
reason is because what you pick for that
nanometer it could be anything
how big is one transistor how big is one
gap of one transistor how big is the
this the bat right if you're a chip guy
you know what all these things are I'm
not but the point is different people
measure in different ways and so it's
very much like any kind of tech
marketing speak it doesn't mean anything
it's just a label they put on a fab and
what you really care about most of the
time is something called transistor
density and now maybe that even that's a
little bit wrong but what you're really
talking about is how much can I fit in a
particular unit of space right and so if
you look at the transistor density
that's really a better measure of what
we've got here and you can kind of see
here's a graph for 1971 to 2011 you can
see how many transistors were packing in
there and you can see it's a pre linear
progression on a logarithmic scale right
so this scale is not linear you can see
it going up by tens not not linear at
all there right that's to that
out to there this should only be 190
right it said it's a million so you can
see it's a logarithmic scale so that's
that doubling that Moore's Law curve you
hear about so this is a logarithmic
scale so it goes up linearly and you can
see they just keep trying to pack more
transistors in there over and over and
over right so that's what you're really
looking at more is that transistor count
and so if we look at seven nanometer
transistor density versus Intel 10
nanometer transistor and so if we just
come by if we like kind of look at these
lithography processors I'm not sure
where a good place to look at the table
would be but
I feel like these tables if they weren't
quoted was exactly what I wanted but
unfortunately they're kind of all messed
up
so I guess I I'm sorry I just offhand
I'm not sure exactly where to find the
transistor densities of the various fabs
yes so I mean here's Intel's marketing
gunk anyway right
I mean go find the transistor densities
but the point is those labels are
meaningless labels so you have to go
look up something else to find out what
really is going on there and transistor
density is a good way to do it so that's
one metric you can kind of use to
equalize across what is TM SMC versus
Intel versus whatever right but anyway
we're going bring it back around when
we're talking about actually fabricating
one of these chips what we're talking
about is we have a particular process
and that process is a series of machines
and steps that we go through in order to
produce a image of a trace you know a
series of lines on the silicon features
on the silicon that will then be able to
have electricity flow through it to do
the thing we want it produces the actual
chip the integrated circuit on that
silicon and the smaller the feature size
that process can produce the more we can
pack into the same space the more we can
pack in the same space the less power is
consumed the faster it could run at the
same power because it has you know the
electrons have less distance to move
right or however you want to look at
that and so we're trying to shrink it
down because we get more performance or
more power savings every time we do and
so when we look at something like a 7
nanometer fab a 10 minute meter fab
whatever we're talking about what we're
talking about is a specific
configuration of machines that will take
a silicon ingot into a silicon wafer
into a machine put the stuff on it that
needs to get put on it and kick it out
and then that thing on that wafer is the
chip we use now those wafers are huge
you saw them in there you know they're
like that big so eating one chip per
wafer it's lots of little chips and then
we cut them out right
so what happens is the fab silicon ingot
comes in we chop it into wafers the
wafers go into our machines the machines
image the chip chips on there we take
the wafer out it's got tons of chip we
cut up the chips and now we have the
chips and we sell them to you right no
problem is some of the chips won't work
these won't work
why won't they work well let's talk
about the actual fab process and why
stuff doesn't work okay so in order to
fabricate a chip when you're talking
about something like seven nanometers as
a feature size let's see here
can let's do this for me okay 2.82
I think does that do that right meters
is too greater than a six ten to the six
nanometers okay good so we are talking
about something in this case I guess
obvious meaning I kind of wanted it to
not do it in scientific notation I was
hoping for but ten to the negative six
so let's see here so that is one two
three four five six they do that right
we're looking at something that's about
that big right an electron a single
electron is about that big right
wavelength of Tron so here we go mm-hmm
again not my strong suit so those of you
who are physicists I don't know if
around the stream right now I may be
doing this kind of wrong and I apologize
so I encourage you to look at this all
yourself I'm not a hardware person I'm
not capable of explaining this stuff
correctly so take a look and salt but
the wavelength of an electron right this
is how big it is right this is the
wavelength okay now what you'll notice
that's so that's its oscillation right
the region an electron oscillates in one
point two three nanometers we're talking
about fabricating features that are only
about five times larger than the actual
movement of an electron that's how small
this crap is right very very very very
very very very small is what we're
targeting here right so what does this
mean it means that literally anything
that goes wrong
anything will ruin the chip a single
tiny little speck of dust will ruin the
chip a vibration at all will ruin the
chip anything that happens during the
imaging of that chip that the tiniest
little blip and it will be completely
ruined I'm not sure what the best way to
underscore this would be other than
saying a speck of dust will ruin the
chip that's a good example that's why
they all where you see they when they
into fabs this is what everyone looks
like because any piece of skin that
flaked off dandruff a piece of lint from
your clothing that will ruin the entire
batch right and so everyone is basically
asked to wear you know what's it's not a
hazmat suit but it's not far right and
so it's so sensitive another way to look
at it would be
if anything happens right this is a
point zero second point zero seven
second power outage anything an entire
like months of chip output because they
go through these like stages of
production can be ruined it's so precise
it's so precise okay and so again that
it's just so important to understand so
let me just walk you through we were
talking about this extreme ultra ultra
violet ography so how do we actually
start putting things on to the silicon
or creating features on the silicon
right well what what they have to do one
way we could do it right yes they use
what's basically like an electron
microscope kind of right we could shoot
focused electrons in a beam and we could
literally like X out the entire chip
like right like almost like a television
used to do with the scanning CRT we
could like literally carve into the
thing like with a literally just you
know it's thinking like a laser cutting
things right we could do that and that
would probably be like the most precise
we could get right and the problem is
this would take forever if you were
literally carving every little thing was
like electron forget it right that would
just take forever
each chip would take so long to make
that they would cost tens of thousands
of dollars for like one chip right like
the cost of today's most expensive CPUs
would be the cost would be how much the
least expensive CPUs would cost if we
were making them that way it just takes
too long so what we need is something
that can image a chip quickly it's got
to be able to carve way more than just
generating like a single little like a
single little point all the time right
and so what we're looking at doing is
we're trying to create something that
can do a lot of you know fire a lot of
carving at one chip at the same time
kind of more like the way that you would
imagine silk-screening a t-shirt or
something so you end up with something
that's called like a mask and the mask
is something that's designed to have a
whole bunch of stuff on it that we can
shine something through and carve a
bunch of the chip at one time so it's a
speech really is a speed issue if you
went to a hardware guy today and say I
want to pay you a billion dollars and I
want you to fab at like five nanometer
for me they could probably just say sure
no problem
I can I can make one chip at five
nanometers out it's a no problem we've
been able do that forever
right but it would take a huge amount of
time and energy and expense to do it
because they'd have to do it in like one
of these ways that would you know be
very slow in carving so fab technology
is not just about can we make something
that small the answer is of course we
can we are good enough to do that now
the problem is it's too friggin slow
right okay so what is extreme
ultraviolet lithography well extreme
ultraviolet lithography is trying to
make wavelengths of light that are very
narrow right so we want the again
because the wavelength of the light is
going to determine what kind of feature
it can cut if it's wildly oscillating
hugely that's gonna be only be able to
cut fairly large features if it's nice
if it's more narrowly oscillating can
cut much more narrow features right so
we're trying to do is let's generate
some light with extremely short period
wavelengths coming narrow and we'll
shine that through a mask and cut the
chip that way right so what's extreme
ultraviolet lithography well as you
might expect if we look at the spectrum
of light here's an example the light
that we can see is within a spectrum
that goes from high energy to low energy
low energy spectra anything down in the
Reds we see into infrared and all this
stuff
Aref mtv shortwave am right this stuff
here that stuff is wide you wouldn't
want to cut a chip with radar because
the beams are huge right but the other
side the purples where we stop seeing
purple and can't see it at all and it
goes up into ultraviolet UV light is
perfect for cutting it gets smaller and
smaller and smaller and smaller and
smaller and smaller
really really tiny right up till you get
to x-rays now I assume and I couldn't
tell you I just assume that the reason
we don't cut chips with x-rays is
because x-rays pass right through stuff
so you can't cut a piece of silicon with
an x-ray probably because you don't know
if the x-ray will even hit it that's my
desk
I don't know that could be complete load
of horse poop and I apologize but I'm
guessing that's walk but I don't know it
might just be that we haven't quite got
it right yet and pretty soon maybe in
ten years we will be favics with x-rays
but I don't know there must be a reason
we're not doing it because obviously we
know how to make second x-rays but we
ain't using enough lab chips so there's
no reason for it but what we are doing
is we're trying to get right up to there
so extreme ultraviolet is like trying to
fab a chip with a wavelength of light
that is almost an x-ray like it really
it's almost an x-ray but it's just
barely not why that's the smallest
wavelength we could use that isn't an
x-ray right and then we're gonna use
that to image our chip well isn't that
great here's the problem how do you make
light that high of a wavelength
how do we get some of that right well I
don't want to pretend to be a physics
guy so I can't really tell you how the
best ways are to make light that's in
that spectrum you know I got no idea I
just don't even have the faintest idea
of the sort of stuff that goes into this
but here's what I can tell you in the
fabs that are trying to do extreme
ultraviolet lithography right now
they're literally doing something like
this they have a laser in the bottom of
their fab that they amplify to
psychotically high-power just big old
laser it generates a beam of light it
goes through amplification stages to
make it extremely extremely powerful if
that gets routed up into the fab the
actual fab floor where they have a
precisely timed aperture for this laser
I shouldn't call it an aperture don't
know that's what it is but timing system
I should say where the laser is designed
to DoubleTap and I mean this literally
like the way you kill a zombie like
DoubleTap like shooting twice at little
tiny droplets of tin that fall down into
a chamber and the laser hits the tin
twice one time flattens the tin and the
next shatters the tin out into a cloud
of tin little tiny teen atoms I wish I
was making this up but I think I'm
actually describing this correctly ask a
fab guy but I'm pretty sure I'm getting
this roughly right when the tin is
destroyed in this way that laser hits
tin and destroys it happens to produce
extreme ultraviolet wavelength light but
it produce it in all directions so then
there's this big parabolic collector
that tries to take all of that light and
focus it back into the fab machine it's
actually gonna use it okay focus it back
into the fab machine and now the fabrics
you got to control it what's the problem
well here's the thing there's really no
way to reflect extreme ultraviolet light
really it's too small it'll just
get absorbed in almost anything so
actually they have to build these really
special mirrors I can't remember what
they're called
[Music]
I'm sorry I just can't remember the name
save and find it
so I'm sorry I can't remember how you
build these mirrors but they're called
something like a Murphy mirror or they
have this weird name that you have to
use there's a couple different kinds I
think you can use and they use a
particular one
[Music]
so yeah I'm sorry I guess I can't
remember the name of it but anyway point
being you have to construct these things
incredibly carefully and just to
underscore how ridiculous the wavelength
of light is that they're working with
normally in a lithography machine you
use a combinate
you don't have to use mirrors for
everything you can use lenses so you can
use things that like refract light and
focus it in different ways
apparently UV light is so the wavelength
is so high that actually you cannot they
don't know how to build a lens that will
work with it so you can actually when I
say they use a mirrors they actually can
only use mirrors apparently you cannot
use a lens so anyway shatters the Tim
produces the UV light they have
specially purpose mirrors that will
focus it and then the mirrors try to
bounce the light into the pattern that
will then flow through a specially
created mask onto the silicon to
actually image the chip right now keep
in mind this is just one pass all of
that has to happen just for one imaging
pass on the silicon typically you
actually end up having to do multiple
passes onto each piece of silicon to lay
down different features and their
reasons for that are will blow your mind
even more it's because when you're
shooting things at it obviously because
you're the light is not coming straight
down it's coming down at different
angles the pits and values form
shadowing regions and so you have to
like put different parts in different
times and to try and make sure you can
create the features of the right shape
without shadowing from where the light
comes in and all it's it's nuts I mean
again I really encourage you to read
about this stuff if you care about
computing it's so fascinating you you
will find it really interesting I
promise just go on a random tour of the
internet and see where it takes you on
that stuff and
you will really it's really fascinating
stuff okay so anyway how do we go down
this rattle and why did I want you to
understand just how hard it is well once
you get an appreciation for just how
crazy hard it is to fab these things
that are in your phone and in your
computer and everywhere else well you
start to understand just how easy it is
for something to go wrong so when you
take that wafer of chips they're not all
kind of work right you're deep you're
dealing with such precision engineering
like kind of which we cannot relate to
it all in the software world any little
tiny defect and that chip won't work
what that means is one of the biggest
things that a fab has to care about
after that first thing which is how fast
the chips can be made so that fab speed
is what's called the yield the yield is
one of the most important parts of fab
technology and it's like once we image
one of these wafers that has you know 50
chips on it how many of them will work
how many that will actually work and for
those that don't work can we fix them
right because sometimes you can go in
and correct a defect and then then it's
not a wasted chip so that yield is a
hugely important factor and that's a
percentage twenty five percent yield
right means one out of four chips work
right that's low we you would not want
to see a twenty five percent yield
alright so if you imagine the defects
are distributed on a chip right I want
to give you some perspective about what
happens when you change the surface area
of a particular chip right so let's
suppose that I found a wafer
I'm just make these numbers up let's
suppose that I have 50 chips well let's
do it 100 to make it easy on myself even
though that me I don't know if that's
the time out realistic number but let's
say I have 50 chips on a wafer okay so I
want to make these I'm sorry hundred
tips on a wafer I make these hundred
ships and I know that my yield rate
right is 75 percent right so out of a
hundred ships 25 will be defective and
75 will work right that's just what's
happening so off these roll from the
production line every time i image one
of my wafers i have 25 defective chips
and 75 working chips that's what i'm
gonna get right but now let's say i want
to ship a higher-end chip and that
higher-end chip is basically just the
same chip but it has more right so
previously i was taking up the space of
one of these chips but now what I want
is a chip that's actually two of these
chips together right so I'm doing a
bigger chip but it's gonna have more
cores so each of my chips before I had
eight cores now I'm gonna make it twice
as large let's go have 16 cores and I
can sell it for more money that's why
I'm doing my enterprise customers will
pay more than twice the cost for this
right well what happens now well now
I've got 50 chips right and if you think
about what have happened here what's the
yield on those 50 chips that rolled out
so instead of a hundred ships I had 50
well in order for one of these chips to
actually work it means both of the chips
on the original had to work if either
one is defective I can't sell the chip
as an expensive chip anymore maybe I can
sell it as one of the cheaper ones right
but I can't sell it as one of the higher
end ones so when I want to produce one
of these higher end ones
what happens to my defect rate here I
know before that my chance was 75% of
getting a working one of these chips
well on the same process with just a
wider chip what's going to happen two of
my chips
have to work so it's 75% times 75% right
0.75 times 0.75 that leaves me with the
yield of was it 56% I remember 56% I
think I'm doing that right if you're a
hardware guy correct me okay
so when I do one of these wafers right
and I started with 50 chips I was going
to fab I'm only gonna get 25 best case
probably 24 chips out of this but look
at what had happened up here
I had 75 working chips and 75 divided by
2 it's 37 so if I could have just taken
this this run of a hundred before if I
could have just taken the 75 working
chips and welded them together rather
than having to count on them being next
to each other and working my yield went
from 24 chips out of a 50 chip run to 37
chips out of a hundred chip run through
the same wafer size right so it's hard
to overstate just how much better this
is it's not 2x but it's close right
it's like 1.5 X 1.6 X what is it
yeah 1.5 X that's really good I
shouldn't say close to 2x but I mean you
know it's really good oh my god
right I mean just imagine the difference
you know if you had a chip that cost a
thousand dollars right you're talking
about having to sell it for if it's if
it's 1.5 X more yield right you're
talking about being able to reduce that
price or keep that much more profit
right 1.5 X more of that or maybe even
$500 chip right that's really good okay
again why am I telling you all this what
the heck does this have to do with cash
sizes or how they work on multiple chips
well guess what this is exactly what AMD
did okay they literally did what I just
said here instead of producing their
chips as saying let me produce a chip
with 16 cores on it by producing a chip
with 16 cores on it they said let me
produce 2 chips with 8 cores and weld
them together that's what they call
infinity fabric
they got some stupid name for it I think
it's called infinity fabric maybe that's
not what it's called
yes I think so maybe it's not called
infinity fabric I don't remember what
the welding is called if any fact might
just be the exterior bus way to see what
I don't remember there buzzer sir what's
the infinity fabric is that the welding
all right
okay I think that's what we're talking
about then yeah that looks right but
anyway who cares what it's called point
being
that's what AMG does right so they have
things they have what's called a chiclet
process I think is what's usually called
in ministry which is to say rather than
thinking about fabbing chips which has a
poor yield rate when you try to make
them bigger let's think about having
small things and welding them together
and let's focus on making a technology
that allows us to weld them together in
a way that can work right okay so
hopefully now you can start to see what
I'm bringing this back to right now we
can talk about cash between cores okay
SIPP lit based designs are going to win
I think we can pretty much just say that
and the reason is the thing that I've
just said before you just get more
working chips out of the fab period so
you're simply going to always be able to
deliver more cores for your dollar in a
chiclet based design Intel's gonna do it
AMD's in the lead right now because
they're doing it they can offer these
like huge core chips for way cheaper
it's how it's gonna go right what this
means is that caching between chords
even though it was fairly simple a few
generations ago is now even more
complicated so the way you typically
have to think about these things is you
have to think about them as what's
called a Numa architecture a new Numa
architecture is a non-uniform memory
access architecture and what it means is
that increasingly true on the CPUs of
the future and even the ones from today
from Andy for example or there's a whole
variety of chips which this is true the
organization of the caches and how they
talk to main memory
is not symmetric procore okay so just
like I told you that the right way to
think about you know the CPU is to say
break it apart say that there's work
units and a scheduler and l1 l2 l3 main
memory right
just like I said start thinking about
these boxes as separate things that have
to do work and talk to each other the
same thing is true for multi-core so
think about cores themselves as being
scattered around here's my cores right
memories out here somewhere
maybe memories out here maybe it's
easier for these two chips to talk to
this bank of memory than these 2 chips
right maybe this part of the l3 is
closer to these chips and this part of
the l3 is closer to those maybe the l2
is shared between these two chips and
the altitude right who knows but what
you have to start getting comfortable
with if you actually care is that you
have to start drawing diagrams of who
can access which memory quickest right
and what happens on for example a thread
ripper which is a huge high leak or
count but highly memory constrained chip
i believe it actually starts looking
something like this
and forgive me if this diagram is not
great but i believe it looks something
like this
so I think this is not a complete
diagraph thread Ripper or anything like
that it just I'm trying to give you the
idea of what some of the memory access
patterns look like I think they have
cores that actually can't talk to memory
and cores that can so like you have a
core that sits behind another cores l2
and it's got to kind of go through it to
get to the l3 or something like this I
don't want to try to explain this
because again I haven't studied the
thread Ripper it's not exactly what I'm
saying
but it's it's something that complicated
you actually to start realizing that
certain of your cores literally can't
get to memory without going through
another core so that means these cores
are tightly coupled together with what
they're going to have to be doing and
these are completely not right and so
again Numa non-uniform memory access you
have to start getting the thinking into
okay I gotta learn if I really want to
get the maximum performance I'll ship I
got to learn where these caches are how
big they are
which course there's a tear attached to
and what the cost is for moving memory
between them right similarly Intel chips
you know like Knights landing this is
like a Xeon oops I think they're called
a Xeon Phi chips they have a thing
called a ring bus architecture on them
and what they look like is something
like this
so here's my course 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9
of course I don't know how many cores I
have they go around in like a bucket
brigade so the time it takes core 8 to
talk to core 4 is like drastically more
than the time it takes for 8 to talk to
9 because it like stuff goes in this
order always right these are like not
gonna work I don't think anyone's
pursuing rim buss ring bus architectures
anymore but I like I don't think but
that was a real thing so you had like
actual like motion of the memory
information and kind of a circular
pattern anyway so you need to know Numa
right that's one thing you need to start
understanding where the caches are how
they're arranged and which cores talk to
which caches and how and then you all
end memory banks as well because you can
have multiple memory banks - especially
on multiprocessor systems you will have
like certain prosecco processors are
closer to certain memory banks and they
need to talk to each other to send data
from the either banks across right so
Numa very important start to learn the
block diagram of your system but then
you've also got another thing which is
called meze meze is the protocol by
which caches and cores talk to each
other and talk about who can access
which cache lines at which time ok and
what this means I believe is like what's
the different ones it's like shared CMA
these I can get right exclusive
mutated and then you know I should
remember these by now I never do
modified an invalid yeah I knew it's
like I knew it something that invalid
and modify okay so there's a thing
called the meze protocol and this is the
actual logic by which the cache knows
what to do and so that cores can operate
on the same information and not get
woefully out of sync so what happens is
remember I told you that there are 64
bytes that move around in chunks and
these things are called cache lines well
once you start thinking about two cores
here's core zero
here's core one well maybe these both
have their own l1 cache and maybe they
each even have their own two then they
share in l3 right so what ends up
happening is the l3 sort of becomes like
an arbiter for who can do what with
cache lines and win if core one needs to
read from a particular cache line then
rather than saying I need to have this
cache line and I'm the only person who
should ever have this cache line right
maybe core zero also needs to read from
a particular cache line it's the same
one so we're both going to read from
cache line a right we would like both
cores to be able to do that so what we
do is we have the concept of a shared
cache line which is to say both of these
people say I'm just going to read so we
can share this cache line right and when
we do we mark it with an S right it is
shared what does that mean well it means
if I need to modify the cache line now I
can't really necessarily do that because
I know core 1 is using it as well right
or somebody else is that's what that
shared mark means right
so what we need to do is we need to have
a way of invalidating that through the
cash so what will happen is if cor one
now needs to do a write to that cash
line that means core zero better not use
it that way anymore because it's stale
data so what happens is it says I need
this line exclusively now right what
that will do is that will propagate out
it will wait
it will allow core zero to basically
take an accord want to take an exclusive
luck on that cash line and so that will
force this into an invalid state of the
cash line right what that means is now
when this person needs to read it it
will have to go back and get it because
it knows that it's wrong now I don't
actually know the complete transition
diagram for how these work inside the
cash but it's probably in here right
yeah here you go
there for me to the states of the cash
line can be each of these things right
so if I modify a line in the cash
someone else has to marketing theirs is
invalid right if they market is modified
I've got a marked mine is invalid and so
on that meze protocol here oh this is
the thing I want the state diagram the
meze protocol tells you what the states
of the cache lines will be and how they
will be moved through and that is
exactly how your processor is thinking
about how to move the caches around so
if you want to understand what happens
with multiple cores you need two things
you need to understand your Numa
understand what diagram the cache how
the cache is float throughout the course
and you got understand meze how the
caches will invalidate each other's how
the cores will in valley each other each
other's cache is such that they can
maintain right consistency right and so
when you're programming from
multi-threading that becomes very
important you don't want your cores to
have to keep stealing each other's cache
lines for exclusive writing so you want
to try and maximize the degree to which
cores that do writes are writing the
cache lines other people aren't trying
to use
Coulter fig says 64 byte cache lines are
pervasive due to the burst size of DDR
controllers so basically what called I
forget suggesting here our cult of
rigged I guess it's probably how it is
maybe cult cult to frig I don't know
call tough rig is saying I is that DDR
controllers want to want to send things
in 64 byte sizes and hence you want cash
signs to be had science makes perfect
sense again I don't know enough but hard
to say but that would make perfect sense
right arm also moved from 32 bytes to 64
bytes so yeah so I guess episode
everyone's on 64 bytes now I guess row
said the process for the silicon Inga's
is called the crawl ski process again
don't know anything about that Sancho
Panza asks why don't they focus on
increasing the cache sizes is there a
hard limit to it or are they happy with
the sizes as they are so there's a
number of reasons why they can't just
arbitrarily make the cache sizes bigger
and they are as follows one I again the
more cash you include on chip the bigger
the chip gets so that defect rate
increases and it's right it's just cost
more right - the bigger the cache is the
harder it is to make it fast because
again you have a cache is large there's
more routes that you know you need to ok
it's a physical thing it's got to get
actually it's got a store charge and
return charge back to the chip went back
to the processing units right the actual
processing logic the bigger it is the
less able you are to make it fast right
so having 32k a fast memory isn't that
hard to do on a chip 64k harder 64 sorry
128 K very hard to tease Kate
extraordinarily hard right you start
just running into the square size law is
just really making it hard for you to
make sure that
you actually get the data in so there's
a there's a hard speed limit as well as
a yield problem that you fight so
they're always trying to give us the
biggest cash as they can it's just it's
expensive and difficult to do isn't the
wavelength and science electron kind of
the same just different models no idea
not if his guy couldn't tell you Oh
print if Armen said they they had the
privilege of wearing in a bunny suit at
an it was that was you think at that in
at Infineon that's awesome cubic Caleb
says if the probability of failure for
one ship is PF and the probably feather
of two combined chips is denoted PFC
then PFC is two times pf- PF x PF okay
so you're saying that if the probability
of failure of one ship is PF then PFC is
two x PF - PF x PF okay so I only did
this one part here wait why is this the
case you're gonna have to explain it to
me though cuz I'm not sure why that
would be
hmm so yeah I mean I guess I don't know
why I'm willing to take your word for it
was like I said I don't know the extra
math but I just giving example there
because shouldn't it be the case that if
we imagine defects being placed on the
die isn't the chance that I end up with
a defect on one of the two chips just
going to be the same as it would have
been for one of the chip I don't quite
get it but I guess maybe it's because
your chance of getting two working ones
is higher due to the fact that the
distribution of defects is more than
just random in that sense
see if I can work that out so let's say
I had
eight chips on here right one two three
four well let's do one two three four
five six seven eight nine ten let's say
I had ten here I and I was saying that I
had a 75% chance of getting a working
chip right so what that means is I've
got well I guess that's bad because I'm
cinnamon so let's say have an 80% chance
so eight of my chips will work right I'm
expecting to have a twerk and to fail
right so that means that I there is a
defect on two of their two defects that
will fall somewhere in this chip and so
I'll get like one here and I expect to
get like one here or something like this
right and so these two chips will be out
but my other chips will still work right
so assuming that I then changed to
taking these chips two at a time right
so now I'm saying I've got a b c d e
only five chips that i'm manufacturing
then what are the chances i guess that
the that these chips work I would expect
two of the chips to not work in the case
that I have above but how many times
with the defect fall on the same chip
right I guess would be the saving grace
right well the times we can enumerate
how many times there that the defects
will fall in the same chip it would be
when it's a B right I mean another way
say it would be like I got a place to
defects how many ways can I place two
defects on these chips total so they
would fall on the same ones so there's
the a B defect
there's the CD defect the EF defect the
gh defect and the IJ defect those are
the only ways that I can really place
them right
but I could place them in either order
there I suppose so if I just look at how
many there's going to be there's going
to be five defect patterns or you can
look at this ten if I swapped which
order they were in in which I would only
lose one of my chips right the rest of
my defect patterns which is going to be
what I have to put a defect down on one
of these and so I can
my first defect can go down on any one
of ten right and then I put another one
down on any one of nine so I've got 90
possible ways I could do that I think
that's right
my probabilities are always bad so I've
got 90 possible ways there in ten of
ways that I could end up with only one
defect so in one out of nine times I
would get four chips right and eight out
of nine times I would get three chips
does that make sense I think
seems seems right and so what I was
saying before where it's like well if
the probability is is you know if it's
80 percent or rather so it's 8 out of 10
to get a working ship before
now I'm gonna say that it's 8 out of 10
times 8 out of 10 right which is going
to be 64 out of a hundred
right or sort of like 6.4 out of 10 so I
think that's roughly what I'm talking
about here so 6.4 out of 10 I guess I
really want to know what this thing is
out of nine though so that's not quite
as good I'd like the tsunami to be the
same but I'll just divide that divide
them out and see what I get
this is not great math here folks this
is point one one this is point eight
eight
this is point 64 right okay
so I've got a point 1 1 chance of
getting four chips a point eight eight
chance of getting three chips well
actually I guess I shouldn't have done
it this way because we don't care about
that number what we know right now is
that we're going to get one of these two
cases each of these times right so what
I can do here instead is just say let's
multiply this out one out of four times
I get oh and and here I'm getting I in
this case I'm getting an 80% chance of
the yield so if I I have to actually
multiply this out to figure out how many
chips I'm actually gonna get so out of
the nine times I do this I'm gonna get
four chips once plus eight times three
chips or 24 right so that's 28 chips in
this case out of that run right whereas
here what I would have expected to get
for the number of chips I'm gonna get
here if I'm doing nine nine batches of
five chips at a point eight times point
a failure rate I'm expecting me at
twenty eight point eight chips or twenty
eight chips are you sure I'm wrong I
must be missing something so why is it
why is that the case
it's the union of either chip being a
dud - the intersection of both chips
being a dud since this is already
accounted for in the Union okay all
right well anyway point being my math is
too weak and I'm too tired right now to
really work that out but I will take
your word for that that that's actually
the equation is is actually supposed to
be this for the defect rate so I think I
may have over counted slightly so if the
probability of failure in this case like
we're saying before
Kirito i oversimplify it should just be
Bayes theorem and these events should be
independent so just multiply the favor
right but that's what I did right let's
end it this way since we're basically
done now I am like I said many many
times during this I'm a harder person
I'm just trying to give you overview I
don't know what the actual defect rate
could be there all I can tell you is the
defect rate is substantially worse that
is for sure
if you're trying to fab a larger
pristine chip versus smaller chips you
can combine the working ones together
after you already know they're working
right and the reason like I said it is
kind of obvious even if you don't know
the exact details because that's not
what we do here on handmade here oh um
because yeah you can first fab smaller
chips see which one's worked and put
those together and if your way of
putting them together is more foolproof
doesn't have as high a defect rate then
you get o in right and so that's you
know where that comes from
alright so
close this down that ended up being a
handmade chat we did not do any
programming today but that's okay
sometimes we don't so I'm gonna wind it
down
it's been fun chatting with you we will
not actually call this day 5:45 this
will not be a hammy hero day this will
just be a handmade chat about caches
I'll be back next weekend to actually do
some programming and then on that
weekend we will not be chatting instead
what we'll do is we will use our new
entity structure where we actually use
some caching but that was not the CPU
kind of caching to start improving our
entity system and our lighting system so
that's we're gonna be doing next week on
here I hope you'll join me for that
until then
yeah if you do want to work on the
source code of handmade hero obviously
as I say every time you can always
pre-order it on handmade hero org but
that's more for next weekend until then
I hope you've had fun discussing caching
with me and I will see you next weekend
take it easy everybody