okay hello everyone and welcome back to
handmade Hero the show recode a complete
game live on stream on Twitch no engines
no libraries just us and well we were
coming back from break we it was it was
pax pax 2015 this past weekend and so
because there are a lot of people in
town and people would be visiting pax
and all that sort of thing I decide it
was better to have a week off since we
take weeks off occasionally let people
catch up give my voice a slight rest cuz
oh my god pax is one of those things
where your voice totally gets taxed as
well you know there's parties and things
and you go and and you are trying to
talk but it's so loud wherever you are
that the Theia the old voice Vox gets a
little ripped up the vocal cords get a
little bit ripped up it's true but we
are back now and everything is fine my
voices is not in great shape it's true
because it's still pretty Horace for the
weekend but it's certainly in good
enough shape for a grumbly throaty
version of handmade hero so what I'm
gonna do today is I'm gonna kind of go
over debug services how to think about
them the way that they should work and
then we'll probably get started
implementing them but I don't suspect
we'll get very far because I got a sort
of lay a lot of groundwork first you
know it is typically when we come back
on a Monday and we're starting a new
thing I got to spend a little bit of
time getting everyone on the same page
so that everyone kind of knows what
we're doing and so that's gonna take a
little while but assuming that we have
some time left after that happens we'll
actually start coding and then this week
should just basically be I think us
going through and putting in a bunch of
debug stuff a bunch of infrastructure
for doing debug stuff so in case we do
through some program I'll just remind
everyone it's day 176 that means if you
want to follow along at home if I do do
some programming today after the
exposition handmade hero org if you
pre-ordered the game you will want to
unzip the previous day so what day 175
source code and that's the source code
that you want to start with if you're
trying to follow along with any coding I
do on the stream but mostly I think well
I don't know mostly who knows maybe
it'll go quickly but a lot of times
discussions take a while especially when
it's a brand new topic like this
so mostly we will probably be talking
about what we need to do so that
everyone kind of understands where I'm
coming from and what we're what our
goals are all right so debug services
what are they what are we talking about
here right and one of the things that we
get a lot of times you notice in the
questions in the QA on handmade hero a
lot of times when there are new people
to the stream they ask something along
the lines of what do you think of
test-driven development right and this
is a very common question I don't really
know why I guess I garner from some
people's explanations to me after the
fact that a lot of people ask that
question because like test-driven
development is like a kind of buzzword
in the web development space right now
or something like this and so you know I
often get that question and you've all
heard my response to it I mean what I
usually say is games really aren't about
test-driven development because the
things that you can test with
test-driven development in a game are
not the harder things to debug so yes
you know could we do a bunch of tests of
it and driven development for the
components of handmade hero absolutely
would it find some bugs
absolutely might we do some of that on
handmade hero also absolutely yes to all
of those things but just test-driven
development save you a ton of time on
game projects no and the reason for that
is because the sorts of bugs that really
keep you up at night and cause
significant problems in games are not
the kind that a unit tests can find
typically they are much more subtle much
more algorithmic much more temporal
problems that take place over a long
period of time sometimes minutes
sometimes hours of gameplay and they do
not admit themselves to easy simple unit
tests that you can just run and that is
why a lot of game development you know a
lot of big games a lot of established
game teams will do things like very
highly randomized testing of games where
they have like BOTS that basically walk
through and do random stuff trying to
find
Crash's and games we're trying to get
stuck in places and all these sort of
sorts of things
it's why they we do betas and early
accesses and stuff like this to try and
get players to find them although a lot
of times people now just kind of use
that as a crutch but you know even if
you're a very very good team and you've
done a lot of really hard work on the
engineering you're still in a situation
where like really crazy consequences of
long chains of logic in AI and stuff
like this can produce situations that
would have been extraordinarily
difficult for you to find with something
like a unit test so you you know that's
a very common thing to see and the
second thing that it's very common to
see as far as debugging is is the stuff
that I want to talk about now which is
sort of debug infrastructure and debug
services that are built into the game
and what these are designed to do is
allow you to sort of try to coax those
bugs to the surface more readily and
equally as important provide
visualizations that will allow you to
see bugs that would otherwise have been
very difficult for you to perceive with
when they actually happened or are in a
convenient way and maybe you'd only see
the results later on or in some kind of
secondary fashion that would be very
hard to discern where you know what had
actually happened right and so debug
services are sort of a core part of
pretty much any game development that
I've ever seen certainly any kind of
project that's professional quality and
that's of any kind of complexity always
has debug services built into it and
these sorts of things will take the form
of a debug console that can have console
commands typed in like from the quake
days that sort of thing became very
popular and has existed in a lot of
games debug overlays HUDs like heads-up
displays just for the programmer graphs
overlay overlaid sort of drawings on top
of the normal rendering of the game that
show additional quantities that are not
labeled all those sorts of things right
and the goal with these is twofold like
I said one is to try to coax bugs to the
surface and what I mean by that is you
know oftentimes you maybe you look at a
scene
and it rendered and it looks like maybe
there's some kind of problem with
something but you're not really sure
like it's almost correct who knows right
and so maybe you open up some rendering
console or some rendering heads-up
display that has some sliders and you
dial some you turn some things off you
dial some things around and in so doing
like you know turn off foliage turn off
shadows look at it that you know in so
doing you you can actually go in and see
Oh yet there is a bug there and was
getting covered up like we're seeing
masked by these other things right and
so sometimes it's about like having ways
that kind of bring bugs to surface
another thing would be like you know
some kind of debug thing that populates
you know puts tons more AIS in the scene
than there normally are like stress
testing kinds of things right it's ways
of dropping stuff in ways of pulling in
a boss monster to a place or pulling
more things in putting them in more
projectiles and all that sorts of stuff
just ways of of making the game get into
situations right away that it normally
would be rare for it to get into so that
you can try to coax those bugs to the
surface that may have only been found by
some play testers sometimes rarely right
and you don't want those to go out the
door but there's no way you probably
would would be able to hit upon them all
of them very reliably if you didn't have
some way of sort of forcing them to
happen a little more strenuously right
so that's one way and the other thing is
when you know you have a bug right when
you're fairly certain that there's a bug
but that bug is very difficult to sort
of pinpoint right so we know we have a
bug we see something happen it's clear
that the bug is a problem maybe we have
a repro case maybe we don't have a repro
case but we know that there's a bug and
occasionally we do we at least once in a
while we do see this bug but it's really
hard to know where the bug is coming
from or why right and the debug service
is one of its most essential functions
is to allow you to perceive where that
bug might be in ways that you would not
have been able to do with the debug
services and a classic example of this
would be once in a while you have a slow
frame okay so the game is playing along
at 60 frames a second it's all great
occasionally you get
and it's it's you miss a frame right you
see this little like hitch it's like a
little stutter right what happened well
without any debug services it's almost
impossible you'd never know right I mean
you know if you were talking about just
literally running the game how would you
have any idea what random thing happened
on that one frame that caused that right
it could be anything and so what the
debug services might do is like have a
way of say tracking where the time is
spent per frame and it just keeps those
in like a rolling buffer or something
like this
and when you have a slow frame you just
hit a key and it pause it stops all
recording and you know you've got your
your frames there and you see that
there's one that's got a big ol spike on
it and you can click on it and you can
go in and see where all the time was
spent that frame go oh okay I see what
happened
the AI spent a ton of time in this
function I must have some kind of a
weird performance bug in that function
I'm gonna go look at it and see if I
can't find the problem right and that
that may very well lead you to be able
to determine what the problem actually
was
whereas if you'd never if you didn't
have that kind of visibility that kind
of visualization you would never even
know to look at there right because
there's so much happening in a game that
it's such a rich sort of landscape of
different things you know that are
taking different amounts of time you
would never be able to do that and so
you know that's again really what the
debug services are about in a lot of
ways is about sort of capturing
information from the run of the program
in a way that you can then look at it
after the fact to figure out what
happened when you know that a bug has
occurred but you really just don't know
why like it's you don't have that sort
of intuition for the bug of like oh I
see what's happening I know where that
is and yet the more experience you are
at game development the less of those
you have certainly so debug services may
be slightly more useful to a novice than
to a pro but even no matter how good you
are even to a pro there are often times
when you know when you get when you're
talking about a full mature game with
you know all of its components working
together I don't care how pro you are
you will still have times where you're
like I really just don't know
what is going on here and without some
debug services you would be very
hard-pressed to figure it out okay so
that's what debug services are in terms
of concept now what are they in terms of
implantation like how do we actually
want to go about tackling this problem
in a way that makes it easy for us to
not spend too much time working on our
debug system because any amount of time
we spend on the debug system is
subsequently not time we spend on the
game so we're only saying time the debug
system because we think it'll save us
time programming later right but we want
to make sure that we have enough so that
when we get those hard bugs we do have
the capability of finding them so how do
we make it so it's easy for us to make
debug services that can be useful
without taking too much of the
programming time for the project just
for making debug services right and so
what we want to do is we want to focus
on highly leverageable debug services
that will allow us to get a lot of bang
for the buck right stuff that will allow
us to do a lot of different kinds of bug
finding and bug visualizing activities
without having to do a whole lot of work
right and so what we want to do is we
want to sort of focus on the nature of
this bug finding and like I said
typically a difficult bug is a bug that
happens where the the manifestation of
the bug and the cause of the bug are
separated right are not immediately
correlated in terms of your you know
your a perception of them right because
any bug where we can immediately where
we see the bug we know exactly who the
culprit probably is is not probably
something we need debug services for it
now it might be at when we talk about
diagramming a little bit it's possible
that you still can use debug services to
get a leg up even in those scenarios but
in terms of like those really hard bugs
the ones that we really really really
want to make sure that we can find they
are typically separated by some amount
of code you know time or or location in
the program right they're separated
and so typically one of our biggest
weapons for battling that sort of thing
is a log right and when I say log I
don't necessarily mean something like a
UNIX log where it's just a big text file
filled with stuff that doesn't really
help you what I'm talking about is more
of a way of recording information such
that later on we can query it right or
display it in a useful fashion so let's
take the example of a thing I was
talking about before we have a frame
spike right so we have something where
we've got the run of our program right
and here's the frames as they're coming
out right and we're like totally fine
this took 16 milliseconds this took 16
milliseconds all of a sudden this frame
takes 35 milliseconds and then this one
takes 16 milliseconds system takes 16
milliseconds right by the time we
perceive that right it's way too late
because what we you know even if we
inserted something into the game that
when a frame took longer than 16
milliseconds get halted right there the
horse is already out of the barn right
the time already got taken so knowing
that the previous frame took 35
milliseconds doesn't help us at all what
we want to be able to do is start at the
beginning of that frame or something and
walk forwards right what we'd like to be
able to do is say I want to step through
the frame that took 35 milliseconds or
something like that right I want to see
what happened in the frame of 35
milliseconds so finding out here right
is the earliest we could probably find
out about that and that's way too late
and not to mention the fact that if
we're just looking at it without some
kind of a halting thing it's actually
like way out here that we actually sort
of respond to that so the horse is
already out of the barn the frame is
long gone and so what we want to be able
to do is we want to be able to add a
minimum record some amount of
information about this frame into
something that will keep it for our
later inspection right
okay so the simplest sort of thing that
you could imagine doing right is let's
just say that we had some kind of a log
right and this log is just gonna store a
data about what takes time when right so
in our code right if you if you remember
we've already actually if that's no good
I actually need some old rad game Tools
command prompt that's good this guy
there we go if you remember in our code
we already have a bunch of debug debug
timers things right and so you see here
we have these cycle counters right like
how long these different things took and
so a very basic thing that we might do
is if we just recorded what these were
every frame then we could easily figure
out at least for the things that were
timed did any of them take longer than
they normally should have right so you
can imagine in this log recording
something like okay let's just record
the debug timers so I have something
like you know okay for timer zero we had
some kind of a you know whatever it was
one millisecond or whatever right and
then we had you know timer one and then
it had something like five milliseconds
right and so in our log we could have
some of this information yeah so that'd
be pretty good and what we want to do is
we want to abstract this like right here
you know I wrote a really rudimentary
one we'd want to sort of pull that out
into a way that was really easy much
easier than it was to add these debug
cycle counters such that it would be
pretty cheap for us to just drop those
everywhere in our code right
so that basically every last subsystem
in the game and even portions of a
subsystem could have these debug timers
and then our log for every frame you
know it's not gonna be too big right
we're talking about you know for a you
know 16 K something like this for framed
peanuts right can just store all of our
timers so then when we have a slow frame
we can just go back and have some kind
of a readout that will tell us who was
the culprit you know who's the slow
thing very very straightforward right
okay
so let's extend that notion perhaps a
little bit more okay so if we really
wanted to you know if we if we if we
wanted to take that a little bit further
right then there are certainly some
things that we could do with the debug
services that would extend the
capabilities of this log so one thing
that you could imagine doing right is we
already know that we have the capability
to replay stuff in our game we have that
so you could imagine when we run the
game if we wanted to we could store the
initial state of the game out to one of
our little storage files right and then
as we came through if we're writing out
all of that information if we wrote out
you know what our looped live code
ending if we had that just running all
the time then what we could do is when
we got to any individual frame like you
know if we were talking about this frame
right here we have the capability of
starting at the beginning of the program
and letting the input run up to the
point where it hits here and then
breaking like setting a breakpoint right
we could do our debug interrupt that
would allow us at any time to say okay I
would like to be able to step through
the slow frame and actually see what
actually happened the time that it was
slow right and that's pretty awesome
because that would allow us to not have
to guess about what actually happened
inside a particularly slow function we
could actually just see and the only
thing that's a little annoying about
that is well it might take a pretty long
time if I played the game for 30 minutes
or something like this or 10 minutes it
might be annoying to wait a whole 10
minutes to get back to that point and so
one thing that we could consider doing
in our debug versus the game is like
checkpointing right so you know
something like every you know every 30
seconds let's say we just checkpoint the
memory so that we can always jump back
to the earliest 30-second part and then
play the frames forward till we get to a
place where
we were trying to inspect the code and
break right there right again it's stuff
that we've already mostly written so if
we wanted to sort of start to bring that
system out more to the forefront we
could have some pretty awesome
technology therefore for finding bugs
that are very transient in nature in
that way right so that's a pretty good
system and we probably should look into
doing that since we've already done most
of the work there is however a pretty
big caveat which is that although that
will be very good for debugging our game
code at the end of the day it won't be
that good for debugging multi-threading
problems right because we don't control
how the operating system does its thread
scheduler you know it chooses when each
individual thread runs it and we can't
reproduce the possible deadlock
conditions or possible memory overwrites
race conditions we can't reproduce those
really without a heck of a lot of extra
work on our part trying to sort of like
insert ourselves in between the
operating system and our code and all
these other sorts of things it should be
a pretty major investment so there are
limitations to this but if we assume
that most of our bugs will not be in the
multi threading arena that we might want
to find this way then this would still
be a big win if we assume that most of
our bugs would be an alter turning arena
than this would probably be a waste of
time because it's not going to help us
really find those it won't be able to
reproduce them exactly unfortunately
that's just the nature of the beast
unless that particular multi-threading
bug happens to be very reliably
reproducible given certain initial
conditions right because this certainly
does reproduce those initial conditions
okay so those are some things we
probably want to start thinking about
right so we want to have something like
a you know performance counter log
we probably want to have a frame
recording and jump because we already
sort of have most of that so we probably
could do at least something for that and
then the next thing that I wanted to
point out is we probably want some way
of into art in addition to this sort of
locking of performance information which
will allow us to find things like slow
frames another thing that we might want
to what do is like log stuff like our
memory consumption right like memory
consumption layout so you can see how
our memory is being used right and then
another thing that we probably want to
do is sucks like diagrams like
diagramming right and that's a pretty
big one so let's talk about that one for
a second so what typically happens in
these sorts of scenarios where we're you
know you've already seen it happen a
bunch when we were working on like our
world representations for example or you
know even just the LAT very last thing
we did fonts right well you know we're
doing this font work and we're kind of
flying blind right because I would say
stuff like oh okay you know we want to
make sure that we have like a baseline
and we want to make sure that like the
base of the cue lines up with the
baseline or whatever or like the a you
know is sitting directly on the baseline
bla bla bla bla bla right but we could
never really draw the baseline you know
it was always it's always a big deal to
draw these things because of course you
know we our render is set up to render
the actual game and to do stuff that the
game wants to do but stuff like just
drawing a single pixel line or a
rectangle around something to like
highlight it or something like this
right or put some just a little debug
string and in there you know that's
attached to something like you know a
little thing that says baseline or an
arrow that goes between two points right
so you can see that you know something
like a vector all of that stuff may be
totally useless for a game but that sort
of stuff could really help us when we're
trying to debug our code that deals with
anything spatial anything that is
inherently geometric in nature because
if you think about what it's like to
debug something in your
oh you know I want to debug this vector
and you look at something that's like Oh
one two three nine five seven you know f
comma two point three nine whatever you
know blah blah blah you look at that and
your brain you know even I've been
looking at these kind of numbers for how
many years now right your brain just
isn't that fast at constructing the
relationship between lots of things that
look like this right I mean I can do it
you know I can sit there and kind of go
okay that's about here this quadrant
public right I can do it because I've
had a lot of practice and when I have
that about things that way I can but
it's much much slower right if you could
instead just have a thing that goes like
oh I'm trying to bug this algorithm and
it just drew out all the things for me
and made the little math diagram
whatever right you know that I needed
you can immediately see stuff trivially
that's like oh this vector was supposed
to be perpendicular to this thing but
instead it's like pointing off that
direction right it's supposed to be
there and tear that takes you know a
split second of your eye to look at and
it immediately knows that and it would
have taken several minutes of looking at
the values and going oh wait that
doesn't seem like it's in the right
quadrant you know whatever right and so
diagramming for game development is like
a really really really important tool
because there are so many things that
have that sort of property of there
being lots of correlated values that
form spatial relationships that if
you're always trying to bug those by
just looking in a watch window it's
gonna take a lot longer to find those
bugs and some subtle bugs you may never
find and they're always kind of a little
janky you're not sure what's going on
and if you'd had some visualization code
you would have been able to find them
you would have been able to gain more
insight in the problem you also might be
able to do things more optimally you
might hit upon performance wins even
just because now you're looking at the
problem being Illustrated out and you
can sort of make more you know better
conclusions from it right okay so we've
got about a half hour left here so I'm
just gonna go a little bit further into
this and then I think we can probably
start talking about how we might want to
implement some of these things may pop
over the code and just go
so diagramming right and you know all of
these sorts of things they're all sort
of temporal again in nature right so
what we want to do is we don't really
want to have lots of separate things we
don't want to have like the memory thing
as a separate system and the performance
counter is a separate system and the
diagramming server says I don't really
want that what I'd rather be able to do
right you said everything kind of go
through this log and the reason for that
is because again game programming a lot
of the subtle bugs they happen across a
lot of time in space like they're not
really localized the hard bugs the the
easy bugs are the ones sort of localize
there's the ones you don't care as much
about the debug system so what I want to
be able to do is I want to be able to
capture things like diagrams right I'd
like them to go into the log so that
when I have a problem on the previous
frame or something like that
I know that I can just sort of run the
frame and then like inspect the diagram
or something like that and not have to
worry about like oh you know I got a run
some special thing and like stop the
program and go into the code and turn on
some stuff right and in fact you know
what that's something I should talk
about a little more broadly right let me
talk about that a little more broadly so
I could make the point a little bit
clearer okay
so one way that I could do this right is
let's say I have some diagramming tools
whatever they are and I have a piece of
code right and the codes doing something
we'll make it really basic a lot more
basic than probably something you would
really care that much about debugging
but you know just for the sake of
illustration we have something and we're
like okay you know a is gonna be equal
to B plus C right and these things are
vectors so they're all like
three-dimensional vectors or something
well in our game they might probably be
two-dimensional vectors I don't know
well we've got yeah we've got
three-dimensional vectors right so if we
have a bunch of these vectors here right
and we're going to do something where
we're adding them together and you know
we suspect that there might be some kind
of a bug in this code like maybe the B
vector is wrong we suspect that like
it's being passed in as the wrong value
or I don't know right
for Patrick pretended with something a
lot more complicated okay so what I
don't really want to have to do is
change the structure of this code at all
right the thing that I really don't want
to do is I don't want to have to modify
the code in any way to add my
diagramming so for example if this was
in some kind of function foo right that
takes some parameters and here we go the
last thing I want to do is have to pass
something in here like modify like the
control flow right and whoever calls it
and whoever calls that I don't want have
to pass in some debug services thing
right I don't want to have any setup I
don't want anything to happen there like
that what I want to be able to do is I
want to be able to just straight ahead
mark up this function I want to be able
to do something like draw you know a and
then draw you know B draw see you know
that sort of thing I want to be able to
have something where I just sort of add
I want to always add things in I never
have to change anything here and then
furthermore I want to be able to leave
that there right I want to be able to
leave it in so that I don't have to take
it out figure and then find oh there's
another bug in it later and add it all
back in right so I want it to always be
you know it's it's always add right
you always always add debug code in you
never take debug code away right so I
want it to be part of the the crucial
part of the bug system I want to be
really free to add the stuff in here
right I want it to be able to be like
turned on and off easily so I can just
kind of put it in there and forget about
it I don't want to have to do any work
sort of to pass things through or
anything like that and then like I was
saying before I want it to go through a
logging system and the reason for that
is sometimes these diagrams I don't know
which diagrams I actually need to look
at until it's too late
right and again we can mitigate some of
that with this system here right we can
mitigate some of that with the fact that
we maybe have a way to record and play
back to a particular place right
but even in that circumstance let's
suppose we have some kind of a thing
where it's really easy for us to figure
out when something happens a little bit
later and it's hard for us to figure out
how should I put this let's say it's
pretty easy for us to maybe find the
bogus one of this these after the fact
but it's not so easy to know which one
it actually is when we're stepping
through it and so for example let's say
that we don't have any wit criteria like
this this foo gets called like four
thousand times or something right it's
like some kind of a high use function we
have no way of knowing which one of them
is wrong we don't we just don't have any
idea all we know is something went wrong
right well if I have to know which one
is wrong in order to like turn on the
right one to see the diagram that's not
gonna help me and I also can't look at
4000 diagrams at once so what I want to
be able to do is just like record them
all so they all go into the log and then
have some kind of a way to quickly scrub
through them find the one that looks
wrong and then go okay I see which one
that was what's that you know what's the
actual mark up on it and maybe you know
this thing has in it some kind of an
info call right as well that allows me
to like say something about which foo it
was you know like some index or
something so that when I find the one
that's wrong I go oh smoking gun it's
you know number 37 or whatever right so
that's the kind of nature that that's
the kind of thing that I want to have
happen right I want everything to go
into a log so it's not so important that
I'm able to like kind of pinpoint ahead
of time who the culprit is I want to be
able to annotate the information in a
very fast and flexible way that does not
require changing the code around it in
any way I want to be able to leave debug
code in there without a whole lot of
cost to me because I don't want to have
to constantly worry about going in and
if zero inge and uh nifty rowing and all
this other sides I want it to be like
nice and easy to just kind of turn it
off turn it on in a particular area
right
and I want to be able to make sure that
I have some way of if I can write
annotating that stuff with with
something that helps me find out which
one I'm talking about so that's mostly I
think that's pretty much all the basics
right everything that's you know more
subtle and more sort of advanced in that
I think we'll just kind of run into as
we go and I can sort of point it out but
hopefully you've got kind of an idea of
the sort of things that we're going to
be trying to do here right so I'll add
one more we'll call this tuning fiddling
that's sort of unrelated to these right
and this is what I think before this is
more about bringing bugs to the surface
inspecting but being able to kind of
like poke at bugs a little bit and what
this is is right now you know we have
loop live code editing that's true and
so our need for tuning and fiddling
support is substantially less than it
would have been right there's really not
a whole lot that we would really need to
do if we didn't want to we could pretty
much use loop live coding for almost
everything if we wanted to so I we may
just not need this right but I'll just
mention kind of what it is so in our
world right if we want to have the
ability to fiddle with parameters or
tune parameters right we don't actually
need that anything other than just the
code because what we can do is at the
top of our code right at the start of a
frame we just set each parameter right
so we just do like per am
right per m2 equals six right whatever
and so every time through all we would
then do is we just go in here we change
this value to a 15 and the code would
just reload and now it would be a 15
right so that's so we really can just
use that that's fine and that supports
every possible thing we might want doing
code so in a lot of ways it's it's just
much better than what you can do
otherwise but if you were a game that
did not have support for loop live
coding which is most games the tuning
fiddling thing is about getting some
stuff on the screen that lets you do
that so typically what they'll do is
they'll have a little hood you know here
or something and when you drop it down
like maybe you can expand it right
and it's got the parameters in it like
pram one pram two pram three right and
there's maybe like a slider right and
you can slide the slider back and forth
to to set whatever the value is or turn
things on and off like there be
checkboxes that sort of thing right and
so that's really not super necessary for
us we really just don't have the need to
do that probably because we can lean on
this for pretty much all of that and it
is a pretty much a superset of this
because this can't represent
relationships between variables very
well so if I want to go in here and say
it's six plus per am one if that's the
change I wanted to make no amount of
sliders is gonna let me do that where is
this trivial for me to just type that in
in the loop live code I think so we
pretty much have way better than this
thing so we probably just don't want
that but I'm just putting in here so you
can kind of see that even though like we
don't need it it is something that you
would typically included debug services
and you know maybe if we find that
there's something that wouldn't be in
the loop life code editing that we could
put it in there right and so what you
know and now I think about there is one
way we could sort of have some of that
which is just like things that are not
settings but that are actual like
triggers right like things that are kind
of like you know I want like a little
menu of like jump to region
you know like jump to the snow region or
jump to the rainforest or whatever I
don't know who knows right whatever's in
the game maybe I want like a little menu
of things I can just quickly do
something that is less probably you know
obvious how you do it in code you know
we could rig something up but it's not
as clean it you know this isn't probably
the nicer way to do that and so maybe we
want to add something like that I don't
know we'll see how much time we spend on
debug we don't want to spend you know
months on it right so maybe we don't
bother with something like that because
we don't need it as much but it's just
something that's worth pointing out so
there you go that's what we're basically
talking about here so
again what we'd like to do is we'd like
to start exploring how we can build a
system that allows us to start achieving
some of these things and we've got about
20 minutes left so we can probably start
right now there I don't think there's
anything you know this stuff is not
particularly complicated right with a
debug system it's pretty obvious kind of
when I you know as I'm saying it I think
hopefully everyone's like okay yeah that
makes sense I can see why that's useful
there's not a lot of mystery to what you
would want really the it's more of a
thing where the important thing is the
subtlety of how you implement it because
the sorts of ways in which you implement
it can make a debug system drastically
more or less useful and so really the
finesse involved in building a debug
system is knowing you know the exact
right ways to integrate things and the
exact right ways to do things it's a lot
more about that than it is about any
sort of you know high-level concept
because the high-level concept is pretty
obvious what you want to do is just as
fancy as tough as you can as you can
spare the time for to do these sorts of
things right where you're kind of
recording information being able to go
grab it back and display it in as useful
way as possible right and we can all
kind of sit around and imagine what the
best possible system of that might look
like and so most of it again is just
going to be in how long does it take you
to make something and how good is that
something it's all in the sort of like
actual act of programming it and so this
was very intentional I'll point out it
was very very intentional when I did
this code I intentionally made it really
really lousy where we did the debug
cycle counters and the reason that I
made it really lousy was specifically
because I knew we would get to a point
when we wanted to do actual debug
services and that would be the time to
start talking about it so I really
wanted this to be lousy so I could show
you why it's lousy and why something
what you know when we do something
better you could see the contrast and
why it was better right so let's take a
look at our renderer we use these debug
cycle counters I forget what it is begin
time block right
so we use these cycle counters now what
is the number one thing I sort of harped
on in there when we're talking on the
the blackboard there when I was talking
about marking up code I said I don't
want to have to do a bunch of work to
mark up that code right and you can see
that even though we made it be sort of a
global activity so it's true that I
didn't have to pass like a debug
services pointer in here so that's okay
good on us we didn't do that what you
can see is that it's not free for me to
add this line this begin timed block
line still costs actual programmer time
to go and work with and the reason for
that is because these things are like a
table that are defined with enums and
enums kind of are in here right and
whatever so we do have a cost and I
don't like that right I don't like that
cost at all what I would rather be able
to do instead like let's say we wanted a
time draw mat right I want to be able to
just go begin time block and say that I
want this to be called draw mat or
something and then I want to come down
here and say end time block right I want
to be able to do something extremely
simple and better yet I probably want to
be something like this where I don't
even have to begin and end it if I don't
want to it'll just automatically end
itself if I say that I want a
self-closing block so I can just stick
in one line of code and then I want that
to just do everything for me I don't
want to do anything else right so first
things first we can do the beginning end
part right we can get that by using and
you know again another question I often
get asked on here may hero why do you
use CPP if most the time to program and
see well like I say function overloading
good operator overloading good and
here's the the part that I've alluded to
many times I've said constructor
destructor pairs can be useful for
marking up code here is the exact
situation in which it is so let's go
ahead and show that just first as a
totally separate thing right because I
can I can actually do that separately
from even talking about the other stuff
so if I wanted to make it so this begin
time to block end time block when it's
around something so convenient like that
if I want to just get rid of one of
those calls and make that right how do I
do that well we know that if I was to
make a constructor or a destructor for a
siik struct right so I come in here and
actually I guess I don't know well you
know I kind of want these to be exposed
to the platform layer so well you know
if I do that yeah I probably don't want
to do that because if I did that I would
I would sort of incur this problem where
the people who were trying to link with
this from C can't quite get at stuff so
I'm gonna keep it separate we're gonna
make a separate file for this year I'll
just call it a handmade debug H or
something like that and we'll sort of
put it separate so I don't ruin anyone's
day who's trying to compile on other
platforms all right
so if I came in here and say all right
there's gonna be a thing called time
block an inside time block is gonna be
you know we're gonna leave it
essentially the same as it was for now
it's gonna be these things yeah you know
what someone else someone was asking
this as well not to put too many things
on here but there was something that we
were doing where we also were checking
for the compiler being compiler MSV c or
ms it was this right someone was saying
that they really wanted the debug cycle
counters to work on Linux and you could
they were saying you could just do this
where you you you actually can call our
DTSC now from LLVM for awhile you well
actually it might have been our DTS CP
that you couldn't have called so I don't
know but either way some have been
asking for this on the forums so maybe
we'll just go ahead and stick that in
there for them and we'll yeah we'll
we'll stick that in there and I hope
that that does the trick for them I
don't know if it will or if it won't but
there you go so there you go anyway
that's separate issue sorry about that
just that's a little aside for the
people who are compiling on LLVM systems
so they can get their art a 2ct are DTSC
so if we take a look at what used to
happen in that function right what used
to happen in that function is it would
call begin time block with the ID first
and then it would call end time block
with the exact same ID at the end of the
function right so we had a function that
essentially was doing this
right and we want to replace that with
something that just has this yeah so in
order to do that we need something
that's going to be called at the
beginning of the block and something
that's gonna be called at the end of the
block right that's the two parts that we
needed and so what we can do is we can
sort of lean on it sort of make a fairly
unusual use I suppose of C's C++
constructor destructor pairing to say
all right suppose I had a thing called a
time block right and then that time
block had a constructor and a destructor
this is the first time we've seen
anything like this on handmade Hiro
suggests in case you're uncomfortable
with those C++ tried to formalize the
concept of initialization and shutdown
of pieces of data which is kind of a
ridiculous idea because data doesn't
have that concept inherently it's not
something that actually exists but you
know they were not the brightest bulbs
on the tree so they decided that that
might be a good idea so what they did is
they said that well whenever you create
one of these time blocks let's give the
programmer a way to write a function
like so that is called to initialize the
object and then similarly when the
object is going to go away for whatever
that means we will have a function that
you can call on the object that will be
automatically called on the object that
can allow it to do any kind of shutdown
work that it needs to do right and so
the way they introduced this was by
saying all right if you define functions
inside a structure and those are of
course called member functions which is
not something we're probably ever gonna
really use much of on handmade Hiro but
you know just you know those remember
functions are called members cuz they're
a member of the data they're part of the
data as well just like you have data
members right that's a data member of
the struct this is a function member of
the struct and for those of you who are
wondering they don't take up any space
they don't actually exist in the
structure it's just a strictly naming
convention sort of thing but when you
start to get into weird C++ things like
virtual functions that are not
particularly useful they there's a
little bit more of a reason why they
kind of are more in because there's
thing called a virtual table and all
these other things so we don't
to get into but point being when you
just have a basic struct no virtual
functions you introduce some member
functions like time to block here right
those are essentially called with the
knowledge of which object they were
called on right which which sort of
piece of data they were called on so
normally right if I have something
outside here I have a function and I
want this to operate on you know one of
these x blocks right and I will name to
something else like foo I have to pass
in the time block right I'll call it
this for fun like so I have to pass in
the time block that I'm going to use and
so if I wanted to for example set this a
member here I would have to do it like
that
right I pass in the block we're gonna
we're gonna do into this foo function it
sets it to five now on the other hand if
you were to use and I'll go ahead and
finish that off if you were to use a
member function right if I was to
declare this inside the struct like so
and by the way there are two syntaxes
for doing this you can actually still
declare it outside if you want to it
looks like this right it's kind of just
again this is C++ stuff that you really
just don't have to know but I'm just
kind of mentioning it for those of you
who are interested to want to read about
it separately or something like that if
you declare it but it's free to also put
them in here if you declare it inside
like so then what you can see is that in
C you don't ever actually need to pass
in the thing that its operating on
because it's implicitly going to pass
you a thing called at this pointer
that's why I picked this name to be to
be cute it's gonna pass you a pointer
called this and that pointer points to
whichever one of these you were going to
be operating on and whenever you call
this function you actually use a special
syntax in C so if I actually had one of
these time blocks right like so I don't
call the function like this anymore I
call it like this and this whatever this
object was whatever this sort of data
piece of data the struct
gets past as the this pointer into this
dysfunction right that's just C++
ridiculousness
it literally doesn't do anything it's
literally just a rewrite of the thing to
look like this right that is absolutely
the beginning and end of it right but
it's just a syntactic shorthand because
they were trying to introduce
object-oriented programming concepts
into C it's just a shorthand and
furthermore it's shortened even further
by saying that the this pointer is
always implicit if you use a name that
would have been in that object so for
example here this this thing has an A
and you can kind of see that I'm I'm
referencing that a here it knows to just
put that ahead of the A's right so if a
is not something that it knows about it
kind of knows oh wait he probably just
meant the a that that was in this this
struct right ok so again I'm not gonna
cover that stuff in much detail because
we really don't care that's a bunch of
C++ stuff and none of which we're really
going to use except for in these very
specific circumstances where I want to
abuse some language feature to do
something that's kind of not all that
related to probably what it was intended
to be used for in the first place but so
if we take a look at this time block
situation again they introduced two
special member functions one that is
called every time one of these things
comes into existence and one of that is
called every time it goes out of
existence and what that means is that if
I was in a function and I made one of
these right well right here on this line
it will call what's called the
constructor which is if there was a
member function named the same thing as
the struct that will get called right
first before anything else happens right
on the Declaration when it gets declared
before anything else happens that will
get called then at the end of the scope
right because remember if this was like
int a equals 5 when we enter this scope
a becomes equal to 5 when we leave the
scope a is is technically undefined that
way goes away right as far as we know
programming wise right as far as the C
is concerned the same is true of our
time block right it has some memory on
the stack when it's declared here when
this scope exits that memory on the
stack as far as we know is gone we don't
get to count on that any
or it's it's gonna get reused for
something else who knows what happens to
it right but point being we can't just
write to it as if we have the time clock
anymore at that point when the stack
space for a is reclaimed the destructor
which is the same name whatever the
member whatever the struct is named a
member function with the same name but
with a tilde in front of it as you see
here that will be called so what we can
do to get this sort of begin time block
end time block what we can do to get
that to happen is we can insert one of
these times lock structs and we can have
because once we insert that we can have
a constructor and a destructor which
will get called at the top of the block
or wherever you first put it right and
then when it goes out of scope which is
exactly what we wanted right so if we
create this struct time block all it
would need to do is remember whatever
that ID was because remember we've got
begin time block the two things it needs
to call our begin time block and end
time block right and so all we need to
do is actually figure out whatever that
ID is going to be and of course we know
that the ID is just gonna be some kind
of an integer right I mean I don't even
know what we actually declared the the
thing to be when we did this it doesn't
look like we even gave it an actual enum
value I feel like it was just kind of
arbitrary so I guess we don't even know
but we can just say that we have an ID
here for the time block we pass it in
and so you can see right away that we
have a bit of a problem right I think we
started with five minutes left so I'll
just finished up what I'm talking about
and then we'll go to the Q&amp;A we have a
bit of a problem right and in fact what
I'll do here is I'll go ahead and finish
this up we'll go we'll make that time
block thing here we'll kind of get rid
of that I'll jump into a may render
group and I'll just fur it for the time
being we'll kind of test it like this
and we'll say okay time block here is
our block will pass the render group to
output that's what we want right
everything should be kosher it's all
good but you can see that we've got a
problem
oh well and of course I actually have to
also include our debug services
obviously would be a good idea all right
so let's go ahead and put
in there and made debug that H of course
I don't know if that's gonna be the most
efficient place to put that we're gonna
run into some to some nastiness there
and there's gonna be some some stuff I
wonder if I can do this I think this
might be the best way to do it but that
we'll get to that little bit later all
right so moving along oh right and one
other thing that we're gonna have to do
there is we can't really use these
things directly because they were made
to sort of graft on some sort of a piece
here right to the debug recycle counter
ID stuff so we would actually need some
way of sort of replicating this without
that and that's a little bit janky I'm
gonna go ahead and do it this way
something where I just kind of you know
do this sort of a thing you know I'm
saying something that calls a little bit
of it a more internal one so let's see
start cycle count star star i/o that
actually is totally fine yeah that's
totally fine it's it's the it's this one
right here that was the problem right so
what I need to do is duplicate that I'm
gonna make an internal one that just
uses the ID as is like so yeah so that
way we just have it use it directly and
then begin time block is I say the real
that that end time block is just gonna
call this one
with that graft it on like so okay so I
think that should all be good I'm not
entirely certain but I think that should
all be good but then we kind of have
this situation where we have to start we
have to start dealing with with this a
little bit more intelligently alright so
like I said I'm gonna go for a couple
more minutes just so I can kind of get
that get this finished up so if you look
at what these guys do again now I can
sort of call the correct one here like
this and everything is fine for the
beginning time block you can see that
everything just works out great
for the end time block we have a much
more significant problem right this ID
is passed into the timed walk here we
don't actually know what it is by the
time we get to the destructor because
these two things are not
actually in operating in the same stack
space at all right so what we need to do
is again introduce a member variable to
the time clock right something that's
actually stored so that when we actually
have this happen on the stack it can get
passed and you know I always bag on C++
and I always say how awful it is and you
know just because I want to continue
that trend you can even see here just
how lousy this feature actually is
because there actually is no reason why
you would ever want to store the ID all
I'm trying to do is make a paired set of
calls that pass the same ID in one place
and another right but of course they
never add features generically to C++
they always add these features in this
way that they conceived of them so even
though C++ has the ability to add things
at in a block which then can correlate
to something that happened at the end of
the block
they of course added it in the most
useless way which was bound into this
constructor destructor concept which is
not at all what you want and bla bla bla
bla bla right so instead of again the
smart thing to do would have been to
make that feature the ability to add
things at beginning you know that
correlate across two parts of the scope
timing and then building right there
constructor destructor stuff on top of
that they of course just added this
janky thing that doesn't really ever
work right for the things you want it to
do and no matter which way you want it
to actually use it it's always gonna be
slightly wrong right and that's the
thing that's so infuriating about C++
but we work with what we have
yeah you know you go to the compiler
with the language you have not the
language you'd like to have right that's
famous Donald Rumsfeld quote anyway so
inside this time block thing we want to
be able to store this ID so we can pass
it later right so this is actually going
to be like ID in it and in here we will
actually store that so that we can now
pass it all the time right both both
blocks so that takes care of one problem
that we have but we actually have more
problems than just that
all right so what are the problems that
we have well problem number one is begin
time clock and end time block right if
we take a look at what those actually do
here and actually I'm kind of surprised
I must be missing something as I'm how
surprised that we didn't have another
error to start cycle count I think
should have been on there oh it's
because n times block counted is
actually the one that we really wanted
yeah
- I D that's that's the problem right
there right it's actually start cycle
count so okay good yeah I just kind of
ruined the variable so this thing here
we actually want to be the start cycle
count right we actually want this thing
to be subtracted right here but again we
had the exact same problem the starting
cycle count we don't actually have right
because the starting cycle count would
be declared on the stack in here and
this is where we actually want
subtracted so the starting cycle count
also has to go in here right and so if
we look at what has to happen with begin
timed block we need to pass in again
that start cycle count here so that
whatever it actually was going to be it
would snap it with the our DTSC right so
whatever that's gonna be that just
happens right here
and so in end time block well I guess
the other thing I can do is I could do
it a little bit a little bit sort of I
don't think I had to do this not such a
janky way will kind of be deleting most
of this in a second here but it's kind
of wanted to just get into a little bit
more of a fuzzy state so this would be
start cycle count we just passed that in
right and we'd subtract it here from the
RDP SC which is what we wanted yeah okay
so if we were gonna do that when we do
our end time block we have to pass the
start cycle count which means that you
know in here for the automated one like
we were using before it can actually
just do this and it will work right
whereas in our other case we're gonna
have to do this stuff this part right
here probably somewhat manually right so
what we could do is for example we could
do a begin time block in this case and
we could pass
nothing for the IP or we could just say
starts uh you know time to clock right
and then we know because we know what
this does
we know that in here we would just make
one of these right start cycle count
time block so now when it does begin
time block when it goes to snap that
cycle count right
it would know that it could put it in
here of course again we have that
problem I guess we need to do it like
this
where we don't want to declare a new one
on the stack right if we can avoid it so
we want something that's gonna look more
like that and this guy would just be
doing something you know more like this
hopefully this makes some sense this is
just kind of abusing these macros again
not particularly pretty but we're gonna
kind of we'll probably clean this up
considerably in a little bit okay so
anyway so we have our beginning time
clock but you would pass in to the begin
time block sort of secondary function
you'd pass in that start cycle cap right
like so and then we can just have it
work on on whatever we want so we'd have
this gonna have this actually now work
like that and it would be less it would
be less janky then when we do our end
block right we also have to pass it in
and time block so but now I think we've
got it paired properly which is which is
going to be better
oops I got to put on scare into this so
those are sort of calling into the more
you know sort of the more underlying one
looks like I've got yeah just got to do
one more thing before we call that you
have to do that okay so almost all done
but the last thing we need to do here is
when we call this rank when we're
creating this block
we're actually passing into this that ID
in it we have to actually pass in the
debug counter for now but I could also
you know what I could just do it like
this right and do debug cycle counter
and then whatever the ideas right
something like that all right
so that is pretty much it for you know
for fuzziness mostly that was just me
explaining stuff right you can see in
the end it's really really pretty basic
if we want to actually do this macro all
we have to do is just have a sort of
struct with the constructor destructor
pair that we can use to sort of ensure
that this will get called at the
beginning and end of the block then if
we do time block and we instantiate one
of those on the stack it will call the
constructor which will snap the initial
time just like we were doing before it's
essentially calling the game time block
but just because of how nasty macros are
we had to kind of do a bunch of fussing
to make it okay and then when we go out
of scope we can call n time block just
like we were doing before and it will do
the operation that it's supposed to do
right we use the storage of the struct
itself to remember the important
information that we need so that when we
call the destructor it you know it
passed the same information again that's
kind of a shortcoming of C++ that you
have just can say that you want that
story because you didn't really want it
stored you just wanted it passed in two
different places but hopefully most of
the time the compiler is plenty smart
enough to optimize that part of it out
because you can see that those things
are constant so we don't have to worry
about too much but that's you know
thanks to the compiler being smart the
optimizer being smart not yeah thanks to
C++ actually us Express what we wanted
to Express okay so that's about it again
we're out of time because most of today
was me just explaining stuff but we are
now in theory also actually working so
our you know you can see our debug
counters are still on there and I think
they probably are working properly
although I'm not gonna even bother
checking because it doesn't matter since
tomorrow we're gonna start doing some
much more interesting stuff with those
debug counters all right so I will go
ahead and go to the queue and the a so
we can sort of get that started if you
have any questions about what we've done
for these streams please go ahead and
put aq : in front of it
of course since it was mostly exposition
today this is probably mostly questions
not about what we were coding
because presumably that was not
particularly complicated we only did a
very little bit of coding but you know
if you have questions about sort of the
overall concept of the debug services or
how they should be structured we can
totally take those now
soy sauce the kid is there a way to
determine how much overhead the debug
takes when it is enabled or is there
such a thing as debug levels so you know
obviously there's really only one way to
determine how much overhead the debug
takes and that's to compile it out right
and one of the things that you've
already seen is that we have even in our
own thing here we have a way to compile
it out right so we have handmade slow
and handmade slow is a thing which you
know includes all of the debug stuff we
have handmade internal which is
something that that includes all of the
sort of the developer annotation so we
obviously have sort of some pound
defined controls over whether stuff gets
included and if we want to test to see
how slow the debug code is making us we
can always just run with it compile
completely away and so that's one thing
that we will be making sure that we can
do very easily is just flip a switch and
have all the debug code disappear
because yeah it's gonna take some
overhead and that's fine but we don't
want to be in a position where we have
that overhead in if we're trying to ship
the fastest possible version on like you
know a machine low for lower end
machines for customers that are buying
the game we don't want that code hogging
things up
psi 9 why not use a simple template that
would remove storing the ID eg template
ID in ID struct time block well the
reason for that is again so yes the
template stuff is sort of one of the
ways that they tried to then address the
fact because remember templates were
added about about ten years I think
after C++ first kind of came on the
scene I'm not sure if it's actually ten
years it's probably ten I don't know
something like that seven years maybe we
could use them but we really don't need
them like I was saying we could use
templates to get rid of that but this is
not actually like any optimizing
compiler that's any good at all it's
gonna eliminate the ID as being constant
so it really just does not cost us
anything
so we literally just be like wasting our
- no compile time and like introducing
more language features that we don't
actually need to use just to illuminate
something that actually won't ever
happen that makes sense insofar as would
you agree that there is a similarity
between test-driven development and
writing the usage code first yes I would
there's a similarity although I think
it's very important to just to note that
they are actually fairly different in
that if your mental state is I'm trying
to write test code for this thing in
order to drive its development that's
very different than I'm writing the
actual code I think we'll use it because
one implies you are trying to find like
edge cases and good coverage of the
thing and the other is actually implying
that I'm just gonna try and see what's
the most convenient way to use it and
you really want to be talking about the
latter not the former chai latte Qin OA
or quinoa probably would you consider
functional programming for game
development yeah we do it all the time
actually the important thing is you just
don't really want completely functional
programming but oftentimes in pretty
much anything and this is nots was there
it to game development you want small
parts of the of the of your program to
be written functionally you know things
that don't need to access a lot of state
you want to write them functionally if
you
because it eliminates the possibility of
error based on state that you can't
easily observe is is being used right
when you can see everything that gets
passed into something and it's a really
clear well known set and you know that
there's no side effects that makes it
just easier to eliminate a class of
potential bugs or potential things to
consider when you're working with that
code and that's very handy so I don't
think functional programming is
particularly useful as a if you to do it
took you know in a totalitarian sense
like I don't think writing a whole game
functionally it's a very good idea I
don't think it's useful because like
everything else functional like a
functional style is a tool that you use
to accomplish something and when that
tool lines up well with the task at hand
it's very good when it doesn't it's very
poor and so procedural code is a lot
better for certain things and so what
you want to do is just kind of
understand the pros and cons of each and
use the right one at the right time how
does the start cycle count get stored in
the struct when you don't explicitly set
start cycle count equal start so
counting it or something like you did
with the ID well I kind of do and really
I mean you know like I said we kind of
want to clean these up so I'm gonna kind
of change the way these work tomorrow
when we actually kind of do a pass over
these to change the debug cycle counters
is something a little bit better just in
general but if you take a look at what's
happening here this begin time block
underscore it's gonna get expanded to be
this right so we actually are
initializing start cycle count from our
DTSC you know so it live is literally
getting initialized it's getting a slice
to whatever the clock is at that point
JAF Catalan do you get heisenbugs where
the bug happens only when there's not
any debug code running absolutely
there's really nothing you can do about
that that's just gonna happen probably
you know will it happen this project I
don't know it's anyone's guess
but it it's always a possibility and I
you know like anything else it's very
unlikely that you will go a whole
project without one really hard to find
bug right so having the debug services
is not something that guarantees that
all bugs will be easy for you to find
and that you'll always find all your
bugs quickly and or anything it's
totally not that's a kind of a pipe
dream unfortunately so you will
absolutely have the kind you're talking
about where it's like oh you know this
debug code would probably find the bug
but the bug only happens the debug code
is turned off darn and then you just
gotta roll up your sleeves and debug
that particular bug the old-fashioned
way but the important thing to remember
is what you're going for here is it
overall savings in time so the point of
the debug services is yes you will have
a few bugs that maybe they can't help
you with and those bugs will still be
very hard but the point is for the 90%
case or the 80% case they are gonna help
you find the bugs much quicker and you
want to save that time and and and you
know so it's still very valuable so the
structure gets called right when it goes
out of scope yes
C++ actually has extremely long
extremely draconian extremely hard to
follow set of rules for when destructors
get called and in what order and all
these other sorts of things and if you
are the kind of person who is passionate
about C++ because your your you know
your mother didn't love you as a child
or whatever the other reasons are other
people you know sort of cling on to it
is you can spend a bunch of time
learning all those things but assuming
you don't care about that and you don't
really care about C++ so you just want
to know a good rule of thumb for like
when destructors get called the rule is
they generally go in the inverse order
in which things were constructed right
so if I have something where you know
I've got a function here
and I've got times block a you know BCD
and you're like well you know what order
to those constructors that called in
generally they just peel backwards from
from you know it's sort of in reverse
chronological order if you will
so if D was the last thing constructed
right because they get called the
Constructors get called in the order in
which you see them a B C D so I would
see the timed block constructor call for
a then the one for bead then the one for
C front one for D when this brace gets
hit and they go out of scope I will then
see the calls in the opposite order
destructor for D destructor for C
destructor for B destructor for a and
the reason for that is you know kind of
relatively obvious if you think about
the sorts of things that C++ programmers
might start doing with these kinds of
things when they you know get a little
more hog-wild typically what you might
do is if this got constructed first if a
got constructed first I may pass a to
like you know to be right because since
a is already constructed B could start
referencing something in a well if I now
call these destructors in say the
original chronological order ABCD that
means a would get destructed before B
would get destructed but be potentially
has a reference to a and may try to talk
to a during its destructor so what they
tried to do is have the order of
destruction mirror the order like and I
literally mirror like flip right the
order of construction so that if you
started passing things that were
constructed to newer to more recently
constructive things they could then peel
off in the same order getting destructed
and so again C++ has crazy ridiculous
rules that nobody you just don't want to
know stay sane and don't bother reading
the spec but if you just need a good
rule of thumb for basic scenarios that
is usually all you will need to know to
keep yourself in relative control what's
happening
how are we doing
looks like no more questions
it does appear there are no more
questions yeah
Patrick hombre says community fight all
right well I'll let you guys fight it
out and I can go ahead and close this
down like so and we will wrap up another
episode of handmade hero thank you
everyone for joining me for another
episode of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along at home
you can always order the source code on
handmade hero org basically well I
should say you can just order the game
it comes with a source code so if you
preorder the game you get the source
code right now so that you can play
along with it home and all that other
good stuff we also have some other stuff
you might want to check out we have a
forum site which you can go to ask
questions or get a community community
annotated episode guide there's
community ports to Mac and Linux people
have been working on other stuff like
that if you're interested in that check
it out there we have a patreon if you
want to support the video series you can
always subscribe to that it's very much
appreciate it if you'd like to we also
have a tweet bout the tweets to schedule
so that's cool and also over the weekend
I've finished up the github stuff so
this week I think we will probably be
starting to try and roll out kind of
cautiously community access to the
hammer here at github so if you are
someone who has been asking for the
community github stuff we can start a
little thread on the forums to start
talking about how we can start testing
that I don't really want to send out
everyone a key right away because I'm
afraid that if there are bugs with sort
of that interlink that you know it could
get kind of hairy if everyone starts
pounding on it at once and then it turns
out that there's a bug and now everyone
can't you know if then the whole world
gets deleted and github crashes and and
I you know delete everyone's open-source
project because I did something
accidentally wrong so hopefully we can
avoid that scenario by doing a sort of
slower more methodical rollout and
verify that's actually working for a few
people first so we'll try and do that
but then hopefully you know by the time
next week rolls around we will have
ironed out any problems that there were
and we can just open it up for everyone
so everyone get in
and have a little party until then yeah
until then I hope everyone has fun
coding I will see you guys on the
Internet and I will be back here at 5
p.m. Pacific Daylight Time tomorrow so
we can go ahead and start making some
much better debug cycle count timers
which i think is going to be kind of fun
actually I think that'll be pretty good
so hope to see you all then until then
have fun programming and I'll see you on
the Internet take it easy everyone