hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show we coat a complete game
live on Twitch this is well really this
is kind of like a little bit of a detour
you might say that we're on where we're
I'm kind of like III wanted us to have
some debug code and I kind of got into
it a little bit and so for the past few
days we've been sort of like working on
cleaning up the debug presentation so
that we could do some fancier things
with it and we sort of did a little bit
of that yesterday we kind of cleared out
a bunch of like global stuff and like
consolidated the state and so today what
I'd like to do on image area so I'd like
to go through and add a little bit more
of a UI story so we kind of set the
stage for that yesterday a little bit
and what I'd like to do today is kind of
push through that and maybe get us some
things like some buttons we can interact
with or something like that again so we
can do stuff like quickly have access to
turning off or on the profile or other
things like that and I'm not sure
exactly how we want to do it so we're
kinda just gonna push on it a little bit
and see what happens now I have some
ideas I was kind of thinking about
something that I kind of wanted to try
potentially that's that's sort of a
little ridiculous but sometimes
ridiculous things are the best things
right it's hard to know sometimes what
it sergeant it is hard to know sometimes
how these things should go so I might
try something like epically ridiculous
like something so ridiculous that it
just has no right working and then if it
does work we'll just be like I do not
know how that happened but you know
we're happy that it did or something
like that I I'm not sure so yeah so
we'll see again and I don't really know
there's there's some things about the
C++ preprocessor that I suspect that one
of the things I would like to do
probably is it's just not possible to do
but I don't know so you know we'll we'll
see all right so let's go ahead and get
started here today I think we probably
won't get into some of the crazier stuff
that I was
talking about that'll probably come
maybe tomorrow the next day for any
right now it's day 191 we're gonna be
doing some coding we're gonna be
probably doing a little bit of UI coding
so if you want to follow along with that
unpacked day 190 source code into a
directory somewhere that's what I'm
starting with
again that's if you pre-ordered the game
on handmade here org you should have
access to all that sort of stuff that's
what you want to start with if you're
trying to follow along at home let's go
ahead over to the code itself and see
where we left off we had just done some
stuff for the profile window and we
basically made it so that we could make
a little we could just kind of control
the size of the profile window there
right and that was just sort of a
beginning of sort of getting rectangles
in and a little bit of that
conceptualization there and that's all
good and it's kind of running in there
so what I'd like to do now is I'd like
to sort of continue pushing down that
direction and say let's try to get
something where now we have some concept
of like you know various sort of I don't
know if you might call them a widgets or
whatever they are some sort of concept
of like pieces of stuff that we want to
display like these things so that they
can be turned on and off and you know
using some some kind of a control some
kind of a thing we could click on or a
you know a menu or something like that
so some sort of a thing like that that
we can use to to sort of get pieces of
the debug codes like this you know in a
state where they're not bothering us
right they're not they're not kind of
getting in our way when we don't need
them so we can turn them on we can turn
them off and that sort of thing right so
that's what I'd like to start doing
again very very simple and nothing
particularly crazy going on here but
that's what I would like to have happen
I like to get us into that position
going forwards and again yesterday we
also made sure our loop live code
editing work with the with the debug
stuff so I believe all that stuff should
work fine I should also check to see
whether our elke stuff works with the
debug and it does look like it works
pretty fine so that's actually kind of
nice too because it means that we will
have the ability to go in there and if
we have kind of bugs that are difficult
to repro if we can get them into a loop
we can look at the perf stuff in there
as well perhaps even freeze that stuff
for all I know I'm not sure if that will
actually work or not though
yeah I guess we can't well yeah that's
right we can't we have to sort of think
about how we wanted to have that happen
because if we if we bring that sort of
loop live coding stuff in a little more
properly we're gonna have an interesting
dichotomy there which is that the the
recording is recording all of our input
and so we wouldn't be able to interact
with the debug code at all at that point
right you know what I mean so it's kind
of interesting in that state sense and
so that's also something that we might
want to look at but all I wanted to make
sure at least at this stage was that our
loop plug code everything also work just
fine with that
but it looks like everything's fine in
that regard so we should be good to go
so let's go back over here now and see
what we can do in terms of getting some
stuff in terms of getting some stuff
happening so what I think I'd like to do
is I think I'd like to maybe make the
right mouse button a bit of a sort of
what I would call in UI terms a clutch I
usually use that term to refer to
something where it's kind of like I push
this thing down and I go into some kind
of mode where I'm like able to get at a
lot of menus and things so like what I
kind of envisioned what I want is I just
want the game and the games just running
and doing its thing and then if I hit
the right mouse button suddenly like a
whole bunch of UI pops up that I can
pick from really quickly
right so like some kind of like a radial
arrayed menu sort of a thing with like
maybe some sections where I can pick
things turn things on and off that sort
of thing and then you know it's it's if
you right-click it just comes up and
then you can picks that from it if you
hold down the right mouse button maybe
it lets you sort of just move in and
release for like a quick sort of turn on
turn off sort of a situation I'm looking
for something I'm looking for something
a little bit like that
so what I'm gonna do here is I'm just
gonna come on in to our debug stuff here
and I'm just gonna start coding that in
there right and obviously we have
something that we can start with
something very simple I said I wanted to
turn on the profile stuff so again that
good think too hard about
I'm just gonna add a boolean here for us
that says whether the profiles on or off
in terms of whether or not it's
displayed right and so when I come into
the thing that does the overlays and we
look in here it's pretty easy for me to
kind of look at this stuff and say okay
this is all stuff that has to do with
that profile and so what I'm gonna do is
I'm just gonna bracket it in the if
nothing weird again really basic stuff
here I'm gonna bracket in in the if go
ahead and make that predicated on
profile on right and so now it should
actually if I run the game it shouldn't
even be there right cuz that on that's
gonna dis going to fall up to false so
until that gets turned on it's not going
to be there and so now our goal is to
get some UI in here that allow us to
flip that boolean into the on state okay
so again really basic really really
basic thing we want to do so I'm going
to need some information here I need to
have some information about what the
interaction is like for example I need
to be able to figure out whether it
attacked me that sort of stuff again one
of the important things when you're
coding anything and I try to say this
often times is it's kind of evolved a
little bit of handmade hero I think
before handmade hero I hadn't really
crystallized so much exactly what it is
I do when I code which again was one of
the big reasons for handmade hero is
just want to kind of show how do I
actually get things done so that other
people who are like I would like to see
how someone gets thing X done they can
at least see how I get it done which may
not be how other people get it done or
may not even be a great way to get it
done but it is how I get it done
and in that that is in this particular
case and in pretty much all throughout
him a hero I always start at the place
where I know what to do and I work
towards the place I don't know right and
a lot of times I would say like right
the usage code first or things like that
but it is true that if I don't know the
usage code then I actually but I do know
the implementation code I started the
employee code like what I actually do is
I start at the place that is certain and
I move towards the place that is
uncertain it seems like that's a much
truer way to state how I actually
program then trying to boil it down to a
specific rule which won't necessarily be
true in all cases so it seems like I do
tend to stop
with like what do I know has to happen
and let's make that because that's the
thing I'm most likely to get right and
then let me move towards the thing where
I'm not really sure what it does because
by getting by going from something I do
know to something I don't know I advance
sort of like I get closer to what I
don't know with things I do know and
make that jump easier to make
conceptually and so that's exactly I'm
gonna do here if I want to make a radial
menu and all this stuff and I've got I
don't know you I and you pick things and
it turns things on and off that's a lot
of stuff to think about right that's a
lot of stuff to consider and a lot of
times people will Ravel they'll kind of
go down and think about it and draw
pictures and diagrams and and make a UML
thing or C++ classes but they don't
really know and it's it's kind of and
that doesn't help it just complicates
matters right instead what I like to do
like I said start with something you
know we know how to draw stuff let's
draw the radial menu let's just figure
out how to draw the darn thing right I'm
just gonna say we've got a function I'm
gonna put it in here I don't even
necessarily care what it's called I'm
just gonna say draw radial menu I don't
even know if this should be a function
or not I just want some a scratch pad I
just want something to to call in to
where I'm gonna get this render group
right in here and I want to also have I
guess my debug state probably and I'm
just gonna say in there I would like to
draw myself some kind of a menu and and
you know what let's not even say radio
minute because what I really want it's
just the debug the sort of the debug
main menu it's just that it's the thing
that comes up when you hit that right
mouse button and then I'm just gonna
call it and I'm gonna call it all the
time so I'm not even gonna think about
the UI the UI is not even on the table
at this point we're just gonna
straight-up do whatever comes to mind
for drawing the menu assuming it's
always on the screen and we'll work
backwards from there so the first thing
I need to do is I need some items right
so again not get thinking about it at
all I'm just gonna say I have some menu
items I'm gonna pretend I just have them
right here I don't know how many menu
items I have I've got some okay so I've
got menu items
and the menu items are just gonna be
some things that I ups that I could
select right what are the menu items
toggle profile or output I don't know
graph toggle profile grass sounds like a
good menu item to me certainly right
what else might I want to do we had that
frame rate counter toggle frame rate
counter right that was the thing that
was up there
let's see loop you know mark loop point
right of the you know if I want to do
loop live coded think or something like
that
draw entity bounds right something like
draw world chunk bounds or toggle world
Chuck bounds something like that so I
have no idea if those are things we
actually want to do all I know is I need
some menu items so I'm making some menu
items now we have them and we are good
to go all right so if I need to draw
menu items well I'm gonna have to loop
over the menu items that seems like a
no-brainer so here's my menu item index
right and then I can get that menu item
menu item name or maybe just text write
text of the menu item I might say and
then we've got menu items plus menu item
index yeah so if that's what if that's
what I've got for the text I just need
to know where I would display that text
right because I have ways of displaying
text I've got a thing here which is just
debug text out at right so that's all
good so if I go in here and I do debug
text out at
oops I know that I've got a point and a
string I just need to know like I'm
gonna put the string at this particular
point so all I have to do there is say
okay I know the text that's the text I
want to show for my button so all I
really need to know now is where is the
actual button like what's the location
of it
and so if you think about if I wanted to
do something where it's like a radial
menu where they're kind of like I said
around a circle around the point or
something like that
right here we go day 191 if we wanted to
do some kind of a radial menu so that
I'm like the mouse is here and you'd go
down and you get something like this and
it's got like the menu options you know
but kind of come up in this sort of
fashion you know like that if that's the
sort of thing I'm doing well you know we
know what the points are the points are
just going to be going around the circle
going around like basically the circle
so whatever the radius of this sort of
like radial menu is whatever however far
the distance should be
that's certainly pram parametrize well
that'd be like an r-value and then we
would know that however many of these
guys we have you know we've got some
kind of an end here which is emit a
number of menu items I want to make it
so that I'm going to divide the circle
into that many things right so if I have
you know let's say I've got here one two
three four five six seven eight right of
these that I want to layout well that
means I need to make you know one two
three four five six seven eight segments
of the circle so I should be able to
divide the entire you know I should be
able to divide the entire tau right by
eight and that's how much to advance the
angle by as I go and then of course I
can always get the arm of the circle as
we talked about before by just using the
cosine of the angle and the sine of the
angle the cosine of course gives us the
x-coordinate the sine gives us the
y-coordinate as we go around the circle
and multiplying these guys by the radius
will move us out from the unit circle
out to the outer circle where we want to
be so I should be able to get the point
to start the text out there now we have
an additional concern if we want to make
this menu look nice and that is that we
want to probably Center the text around
that point
whereas what we've got right now is
saying that starts at that point like as
a baseline and does that so our circles
gonna be wonky and it's gonna look kind
of like that at first
but that's not the end of the world
that's totally fine to get it going and
then we'll look at how we might fix the
sort of centering issue as a separate
thing all right so I'm gonna do exactly
what I just said again really really
straightforward here is the the text P
that I want to create we've got in our
handmade map we already sort of set up
how we're gonna call these sorts of
things I don't know if I ever made an
arm function looks like I didn't make an
arm to arm to is a very common thing
that I do might be in here I suppose but
I doubt it
yes not so what I will often do I just
find this is a really handy function
because I will often make a v2 function
here for the for a 2-dimensional vector
like this and it's just called arm two
and you pass in the angle and all it
does is it returns you the vector that
is the cosine of that angle you know and
the sine of that angle that's all it
does and so what that does is it makes
the sort of the unit arm oh you know
with this is the angle it makes a unit
arm in that direction starting you know
again at x equals one and kind of going
around the unit circle and so if I know
that I've got you know an angle step of
however many of these menu items I have
if I know that however many menu items I
have times the total distance around the
circle what I should be able to do is I
can find that angle whatever the angle
I'm at by just saying however many menu
items I've gone through so far I would
like to
to be that far around the circle right
again very very straightforward so then
I can just turn that into an arm with
arm to and then take whatever the radius
of my menu is which again is something
that we can just parameterize I don't
know what it should be but maybe it's
five price.you more than that but you
know however made 200 pixels something
like this we take that menu radius and
we multiply it by the arm and that's
where the text should be and so once we
have that again it's really simple to
kind of just place it there and then
we're pretty much done
for all intents and purposes oops don't
know why did that don't want a pointer
to the pointer I just want the actual
pointer so if I do that you can see that
I've now got my radial menu again like I
said it's not really centered properly
I don't believe although actually it
kind of looks like it is did we actually
do but that that's weird that doesn't
seem like I gotta say I'm a little
surprised at how that looks I'm gonna
draw my circle I feel like it's good to
draw my circle I'm gonna do a push rect
just so I can see the circle a little
bit better just so I can understand
what's going on there cuz that doesn't
look like what I was necessarily quite
expecting I want to make sure I don't
have a bug right so I'm just gonna take
a quick look at what happens if I do I
push rect here okay so I'm gonna go
ahead and grab a push rect I'm gonna
stick it in so I can just see what my
circle actually looks like so I'm gonna
do a rectangle Center remember what we
called these min max
rectum in dim centre-half Tim so
centre-half dim is just gonna be at the
text be and then the you know I'll just
do something that's you know I don't
know two pixels or three pixels so it's
actually I guess we'll just do one
that's that's two pixels on either side
something like that I don't know maybe
maybe you'd do a little bit more
something like that so there's my region
wrecked again and then I can just drop
this right in place of that so there we
go that'll draw what we want I think and
the color of this I'll just draw it in
white White's fine all right so there's
my circle and yeah I guess it I guess it
is really it's a circle there it goes
it's just kind of not intuitive like
when it's on the baseline it's really
hard to see how that circle works but
you know you can actually see that that
is that is a nice and scribe circle
there so I think that's just about right
okay
so again I don't know what the first
thing is we should tackle there but I
think what I'd like to do is I'd like to
maybe start to think about texts as
having a particular rectangle that we
can access and the reason that I'd like
to do that is because I want to sort of
take text and be able to like I said I
want to Center the text around that
point potentially that's what I'd like
to do and so what I'd like to have is a
way of getting the dimensions of the
text now we already have a debug text
out function right and so I could make
this so it kind of just has an ability I
also think I probably want one of these
it takes the font and takes maybe the
render group right something like this
you know nah
I'm not entirely sure I want to do that
but so you know what we'll we're gonna
leave that for just one second what I'm
gonna do is I'm gonna assume that I have
you know something like this going on
and then we're gonna address that in a
second so if I come through here you can
see that it's basically the exact same
code as what this would be right it's
the same code as as text out but what we
would do is when we actually go to
output a glyph we would want to include
that in our rectangle right we need to
do all this exact same code and so I can
just make a thing here that's like you
know internal rectangle - oops rectangle
that's like get text dimensions or I
don't know something like that but I
really don't want to do that and the
reason I don't want to do that is
because I'm afraid that these two pieces
of code will fall out of sync so what
I'd rather do is maybe make one function
here that's like you know I'll take the
bug text out and we'll make that sort of
be a wrapper here and then I'll take
this and make this be something like
debug you know do text op or something
or a debug text op and what that'll do
is that will take some of this
information in but then what it actually
does will be dependent on some kind of
an operation code okay so it'll be
something that's like sort of the the
sort of Buber text function you know
it'll take this stuff like so what is
the font info actually used for it's
getting okay so the horizontal bands man
that's your stuff so that will take all
this stuff and it won't need to do any
of these and it'll do this and then when
it kind of comes down through here all
of this code would be the same like that
would all do exactly what you would
expect it to do but then at the very end
it would sort of have some opinion
about what was going to happen here
instead of doing of pushed bitmap it
would actually just do some kind of an
if on the up about whether it was
gathering information or actually
drawing right and so you know I'll do
something like say okay if op equals
draw text or something if the opposite
draw text then we'll do it else I guess
right we're now will only have one other
op techstop sized text or something and
what I want to do here is include in my
rectangle again that that's sort of the
part of the the other rectangle that's
actually here right so what I want to
know on this push bitmap call is I want
to know for that push bitmap how big the
actual bitmap is going to take up
because I I sort of have the dimensions
here right for it so I know how big it
should actually be so I should be able
to just go ahead and reverse that out
right so if I go into here
handmade code render group if I go to
push bitmap you can see that it's kind
of got a thing that it does here to
figure out exactly what it's going to do
in terms of like how things are aligned
and where they're going to go and so
what I would like to do is I'd like to
get some way of accessing that
information in a way that doesn't
involve me actually calling push bitmap
right so what I want to do is pull that
out right as something that I can access
separately so something like bitmap dim
or something or like bitmap you know
used bitmap dimension or something like
this where this stuff here can be
received in a reliable way
and so if I did that we would just it
would get one of those
like so and it would just be exactly
that code and it would be like get used
bitmap dim or get bit mapped in
something like that it would take
exactly what happens here right so that
stuff is is all used I don't know that
it actually needs the render group
probably because the basis is going to
be important there so I assume that we
would do something like this yeah I
assume we would do something like this
and so then there's the the basis as
well I guess would also be part of that
so you'd get back the basis to size the
alignment you'd get back all that stuff
and then I guess yeah I guess that's
really all that would need to happen as
far as I can tell that looks about right
and so we would just do something like
this use bitmap Tim Tim Tim sighs did a
line get P yeah and then the basis so
now we know that code has been kind of
pulled out and we can use it whenever we
want to figure out what would actually
happen with this stuff so then this guy
can just be changed to actually use that
right so he can do something like that
bitmap Tim and he doesn't do any of that
stuff anymore he uses this as sort of a
pass through passes the same things that
he was passed we get that information
back
like so and then I think we're good to
go
yeah yeah so that's also Jim basis
that's also Jim basis but that's about
it
and so then somebody in here could
easily do that instead so instead of
calling push bitmap you'll just get the
dimension and again past the exact same
stuff so I guess I have to pass these
things here so I'll just have like
something like fit map scale or
something like that
bitmap scale and bitmap offset and now
I've pulled those out into common
computations as well so then I know
again that these two can be very very
very similar code paths that will not
fall out of sync right okay so now I can
get that dimension back and let's just
double check I want to make sure that
this actually works at all so let's
actually clean up the compile errors
here and get it to the point where we're
fairly confident that it's working all
right so just clean that up and then go
ahead and make this work with the text
out stuff and so I'm just going to
introduce a thing up here where we just
have something like Iman debug text
operation we're just close call it up
debug text up raw text debug tech stop
sighs text and that way we can just pass
that operation in you know what do we
expect to do to this guy and maybe I'll
actually put that more primal so after
you kind of get you know maybe you pass
that as the first thing that whatever
you're going to do it's and now
whoops what is the problem oh right we
need to actually get the loaded bitmap
don't we so that's actually passing the
bitmap ID here you know so that's a
little trickier right because if we have
we have to get the actual loaded bitmap
that can always fail and but as far as I
know we do actually need we will
actually need that bitmap information
because we don't that stuff is not
actually in the bitmap info it's in the
bitmap itself right so there isn't
really any way that we can short-circuit
that process we would have to be able to
do it where we kind of where we kind of
see what it is so I think what I'll
probably do is say since we don't care
very much about this sizing if we if the
asset that we're trying to size isn't
there we'll just we won't bother because
it won't be rendered this frame anyway
we'll just assume that we don't actually
care about that at least for the time
being so I guess what we'd say is we'd
say get bitmap like so
and then we would just go ahead and try
to get the dimension of that thing of
the bitmap and if we don't get the
bitmap back we just assume that we don't
actually process that piece of text that
seems fair enough right so if we want to
do it that way
we just come in here and we can call
this now and again like I said I kind of
want this stuff to be a little bit more
sane I would like this stuff to be a
little bit cleaner than it is so I might
also do a little bit of cleanup there so
we're gonna go ahead and pass the fact
that we're trying to draw the text that
will pass the debug state the render
group the font info P and the string
okay so that should be everything and if
we run that we get what we expect so
everything's fine so now what I want to
do again let me just quickly I'd like to
quickly clean this up this stuff doesn't
have to happen every time right so the
debug state itself when it actually goes
ahead and does this debug State right
here
once we have the render group we could
just say that we also have our font
stuff so what I'm thinking is we just
say okay there's like debug font is here
and the debug font info is here as well
and we just say that when we do the
debug begin thing right
debug start I don't know why I call it
start and not begin it's just kind of
weird I usually call things begin just
seems like a mess-up
you know what I mean but what are you
gonna do so yeah if I if I go in here
when we actually sort of do our render
begin when we actually start the
rendering happening where we do begin
render at that point we have a valid ID
for our render group passes and so I
should just be able to do this right
here you know I should just be able to
say okay we're going to do a push font
and we're going to do a get font info so
that we just have that information
available like so um that's all I really
wanted to do with that that's that's
basically it right and so then when
debug techstop comes in here really all
it has to do is see whether it had a
font or not it doesn't need this stuff
to be passed to it it doesn't need any
of that stuff it can just assume that
that it got that oops you know I should
do I should have done it differently
what I'd like to do is just grab those
out like that and then just do debug
state under group loaded font debug
fonts 8h a font
you vote wanted though okay and I'm just
gonna do a check on the font if we got
the font then we assume we're good to go
and could keep on trucking right
I could also if I feeling really frisky
I could actually just go in here and and
also do that where we sort of say okay
and in fact I could just do it this way
as well assuming that you have both of
those you're set to go to town okay so
that should do it
I think and that will sort of get us out
of the business of having to check all
those things and load them in every time
so we have loaded fonts we have a GG
font info or what is it just a font and
that's all we need so let's take a look
debug oh that's wrong debug state
okay so debug fonts this stuff doesn't
need to passing this now that can all go
away so it just looks like that which is
much saner I think I kind of wanted that
to be first don't ask me why just
personal preference
oops and then that looks good
alright double check make sure I didn't
break nothing all right so that's all
good
everything is copasetic so now that I've
got that straightened out I should be
able to get the dimensions of this font
pretty easily when I get back this
bitmap dimension thing you know that is
going to tell me exactly what rectangle
I actually need to think about right
because let's see where that is that
you've mapped in let's get that up in
here where it can be more easily used so
year's bitmap dim is going to have all
the information we need right it's gonna
have the the transform basis I don't
know if we should save the input P but I
don't know we will for now but anyway so
if we have this stuff this is sort of
the transformed version and it's got the
size the alignment and so on I guess we
do want these because they kind of tell
us where we what what it things were in
this sort of original space before we
transformed it so if I just want to get
the dimensions out of that what I want
to use is the size and the P for that
right so I can do a rectangle that's
like you know the glyph dim and I think
what I should be able to do is say I
want a rect min dim where I say whatever
it told me the P was and whatever it
told me the size was that's what that
what that's the bounding thing in the
input space of of that glyph and then I
can say if I was trying to get a
rectangle out of this guy right I'll
just stick rectangle returning for now
we might want to something a little
fancier later but we'll do result here
inverted infinity rectangle like so and
then I will just return it so we start
with nothing we start with the the
rectangle that contains the opposite of
anything and then every time through
here I would just do whatever that
result rectangle is I do take that glyph
and I'd include it so what I want to do
is say I want to I want to Union these
together right I want a union of the
existing thing and the new thing and
that you know if I just keep unioning
those together I should get eventually
what I actually want MTD basis result P
looks like for some reason it spilled
down in here
that's just oversight on my part okay
let's see rectangle two is what we
actually have right yeah my bad Oh
rectangle two in rectangle two I uh we
only have one of the other huh
where's my inverted infinity rectangle
when you need it inverted infinity
rectangle - I do we have so we don't
have I think I want that to be like you
know I think I want one of those for
everything right I want I want a
rectangle - version of that for sure so
I probably wanted to I in a two so that
I can return that do I have I do look at
that okay so I'm gonna go look at the
rectangle to code and just stick this
kind of in there there it is so now I've
got that and I can go fix this situation
this is going to be like that now yeah
and off you go so this is a to I this is
a to that's to rectangle min Jim aren't
these both V twos
I guess Dimpy is not so will convert him
don't know why we can't convert him
we'll take a look at we must not have
one of those and then we want Union we
want to have one of those for our
rectangle too as well so it looks like
we did some of these two rectangle two
eyes but not rectangle two again this is
why I say this sort of thing normally I
would met a program if you like using
templates that you are okay with them
templates will solve this problem for
you as well and so you know just so you
know this is the exact same code there's
nothing happening differently here so
normally you just go ahead and you
generate that because there really isn't
any there isn't any magic to it right so
okay let's take a look
okay oops forgot one it happens it
happens
believe you me and finally we don't have
a way I guess to convert from a v3 to a
v2 which is just seems like an oversight
right you want to be able to just go oh
you know you got a v3 as input no
problem just copy the members we do have
and out it comes alright again running
just fine everything seems kosher now we
can use this function and see whether
we've actually done anything useful or
whether we have just made a giant mess
of everything by saying okay we've got
text out let's also make sure that we
have debug get text size or something
and again that is just gonna take
exactly the same two things here
so in fact I guess we don't really need
the P either we can just say we've got
string and oops got string and we are
going to make the result be debug text
op debug text size text we will place it
at zero zero and that is all
oh yeah pass the debug state okay so if
we do that we should now be able to draw
the boundaries of our text and see if
they're at all accurate right so we
should be able to now do something like
we get a rectangle to back that's like
our text box right we go ahead and use
the same string and then we could draw
that right we should be able to drew a
push rect outline where we or you know
what we can even do just a regular push
rect for now since we don't have a
pushrod outlet it takes a rect I don't
think and I'll just go ahead and make
you know some kind of a dark bluish
backdrop around the text that we can
look at and verify that it's in the
right place so I'll just go ahead and
pass the text bounds to that and that
should do it
so now we can see where we're at oh and
of course I should probably put them at
the right location as well so I should
probably offset this guy by whatever the
P the text P actually is I assume we
have an offset function don't really
know it looks like we have one for
rectangle three but not for rectangle
two let's see here
so we just need this guy and that's
about it none of the two overloads could
convert rectangle to and V to offset so
it's actually that way and that's that's
it
Hey look that is pretty much exact right
and so again that was a pretty good
transformation that I did there again
good code transformation to know if you
want to do the exact same piece of code
but have two different results come out
of it sometimes especially if you're not
as super concerned about the performance
of that since this is the debug code we
certainly aren't oftentimes it can be
much nicer to go let's write it once
let's pass the operation through as
something to do and what this is really
doing is it's getting it's sort of a way
of working around C's limitation of not
having a good way to do things like say
closures where you can just pass some
entire set of stuff you want to do down
through some function that does things
to it you know
functional programming languages have a
lot of other things that you can do that
make this less of a necessary thing but
again C C++ not designed by the smartest
folks not not the brightest bulbs on the
tree so they of course added like 8
billion language features and just only
recently address some of these and of
course adjust them in like the worst and
most Awkward way possible and so you
know your mileage may vary if you decide
trying to do that so I tend to still
stick to the C way of doing things which
tends to actually just work out a lot
much better lot better in practice which
is to just pass an OP code through and
off you go so there you go
so now that we have that if we actually
wanted to Center again which was kind of
the original goal of having that so now
we can kind of get our text balanced and
all that sort of thing centering is
really pretty trick trivial at this
point because we know what the Tex P is
and we know what the bounds are so all
we really have to do is just take what
those bounds actual
are we would just say get to the
dimension of the text bounds and we just
subtract half of them off right and that
would would line us up with the with the
center and so now you can see there's
the point and you can see that the text
is perfectly centered around it again we
still kind of are drawing the the size
of it originally at the location which
we don't really need we can get rid of
that now and in fact I can just get rid
of the whole thing that makes sense so
that's again pretty cool right
now we've got sort of a radial menu
there that's centered around the point
we can double check that you know
everything kind of works fine by just
saying let's say we've got a lot of of
items there and there they all are right
and that's all good again we got it sort
of think more about maybe how we're
gonna lay this out exactly because
things at the top are more problematic
than things at the bottom so we might
want to not think just because the way
of text works so we may need to do some
other things there but for the moment
everything seems to check out just fine
let's also just go ahead it mean it
seems pretty straightforward as well to
just go ahead and make it so that you
can pick things when we come in through
here you know we've got again that that
Mouse be the location of the mouse right
so it'd be pretty free for us to go
ahead and pass a mouse key in to the
actual function if we wanted picking in
care again really really trivial there's
that Mouse pee when we come through here
we just want to know which of the menu
items are you closest to let's say so
all we have to do is just keep a best
distance and the best distance of course
would start out at the at the highest
thing and then what we do is we maybe
say best menu index something like that
right and again this is just quick and
dirty and then you know tomorrow cuz I
guess we've got we've got about 10 to 12
minutes left on the clock so I just want
to I mean no sense in burning 12 minutes
I might as well implement something in
the 12 minutes so you know we start out
with some kind of a notion of what the
best menu index is and then I come
through here and I say as we go through
and maybe you know what I what I do with
the best menu at X is also set it to
something that's not actually
valid like that right so yeah the best
night is Jax we go through and now we're
just gonna see like who is actually you
know what maybe the maybe oh they also
just say let me call that hot menu index
or a new hot men index something like
that so we'll figure out what's the hot
menu index we know where the text is
because we can go in here and say all
right let's bake in that that thing
where we're gonna draw it right that's
where we're gonna draw it oh you know
what I guess we don't really want that
though we want to leave it this way I
guess
so that's the center point of the text
which is probably what we want to
actually measure although you know we
also have the text bounds so I guess we
could just do whether you're how close
you're out of the bounds I don't know
what the best one is to do I'm gonna do
the simpler one first I'm not sure which
one I want either one of them is
actually really simple so we'll just do
text fee for now we'll just do text fee
for now so we got distance if we go to
our math library right I think we've got
business between or something like this
or a length right yes we've got length
squared and make this that distance
squared so I can just do what's the
length squared between the the text
feeding the mouse P and that's this
distance squared if the best distance
squared so far that we've come across in
all of the buttons is greater than the
distance that we see here then this must
be a closer menu option right and then I
just say that that's gonna be the new
one that I'm gonna take so once I have
that information now I know which menu
item is is hot on this round through and
so when I get to the end here I could
just say okay I now know which menu item
is hot and maybe I want to have that
sorted here or something so I say like
best menu index or something or hot menu
index you know and then I say all right
I've got my DX take hot menu index
equals new hot menu index there we go
and for the last thing that we'd want to
do ok debug text out at has a slight
issue to it I realized we don't allow it
to change color at all which is probably
not what we want so we probably should
do a color thing here what we pass in
and then when it's doing its color
instead of initializing it just
initializes it to that and then if you
use some of those overrides it could
still overwrite it but that way we can
leave specify what we want the color to
be so that's all good we're coming here
to our renderer we can now choose to
render in a different color so what I'll
do is I'll just say oK we've got a menu
item color so this is the item color
here the item color is just going to be
I don't know white for now but in the
event that this menu item index that
we're on is the debug States hot menu
item index so it's what the person's
hovering over then we could just say let
the item color equal something that's
going to show that it's selected like a
yellow color or something like that then
we can just pass that in when we draw
the text right so I'll pass in the item
player and then I got to go make sure
that passes through length squared oops
wanted the distance between those two
and debug ticks that app needs to take
that color and pass it through so there
we go and you know now we know what the
person's picking right whatever they're
closest to is what they're what they're
picking at the moment so that's again
pretty easy
nothing really say about that other than
it's really easy right you saw it happen
make a little radio menu not
particularly difficult and if we really
want to write we can just kind of finish
things up again maybe we just end today
just with before you know we go any
further with that maybe what we do here
is we just say oh yeah you know - we can
also ask about that precedent if the
precedents if you will maybe I just go
ahead and stick that in here for now we
don't really have anything better to do
with our lives or ourselves we will just
do something like this so we'll grab
this in here we'll first take that mass
P and then what we'll do at the end this
will say you know if you if you press
the mouse button
on one of these guys it'll it'll do the
option and maybe I want right maybe I
want write down or write up kind of a
thing maybe maybe I want it to go gay
yeah you know I've been at it again
we're just sketching this out it's it's
it's not hard so we'll just go ahead and
say all right there's menu active and
and that's that's all there is
so I'm going to take it back I don't
think we're gonna bother with any of
that we'll just pass it in the mouse pee
and that's fine and then we can just out
here implement that debug menu stuff so
again this will be really really simple
all we have to do is say if input mouse
buttons
right is down and dude down then draw
the debug menu okay and the other thing
that we can need to do here is we need
to make sure that we're centered around
something logical so well I guess we
don't need to do that quite yet but
we'll talk about that in one second so
we'll draw the debug menu and then what
we can do is say if it didn't if it you
know if it's not right if the platform
mouse button right handed down blah blah
blah if we know that it was up then
let's just see if the half transition
count is greater than 1 right because at
the half transition count is greater
than 1 it means that they let go that
frame right and so if they let go that
frame we would want to potentially
execute something and so what we can do
is we can just say you know all right
fine
let's see what you know let's see what
you actually hit you know what would you
actually would you actually hit and
there's actually there's a little
something there's a little something you
know we probably almost want to do that
because we want to process the last
mouse movement I would think so I'm
gonna go ahead and do that as well right
because you don't want to on the frame
where they let up we want to look at
what that mouse PS and find what the
closest thing was this time before we
process it and so I'm just gonna see if
the many ways Eero we have toggle
profile graph that's actually a
so we can actually process that one we
can just go ahead and say alright if
that's the case then the debug state
profile on equals not give us a profile
on right so again pretty straightforward
nothing nothing particularly odd
happening here but you know I should be
able to do this now in theory although
I'm not actually seeing that happen I
wonder if this case is not quite hitting
right input mouse button splat for mice
button right half transition count
greater than zero that should have
worked
why did that not work is the question is
the question so I would like to know I
would like to know also I suppose
another thing we should say here is
these things don't have to happen
anymore while I'm in the neighborhood
I'm just hanging out ain't no thing
might as well get rid of that okay get
rid of that to do it was a stupid to do
anyway so I just want to see what's
happening here why we never hit my case
does this case not happen it does happen
hot menu index is one really
oh I was picking the wrong one I'm kind
of dumb kind of dumb that way yeah so
our radial menu is now sort of
operational but obviously we've kind of
got a couple of the things we don't want
to do oh you know what - we have that
right mouse button pressed pause thing
let's just go ahead and make that on the
menu
yeah and so we'll just do pause
debug collation or toggle debug
collation so that's really all we need
there now for those two things and so
the only thing I was gonna say is it
doesn't come up where we click the mouse
button it always comes up in the center
right so what I'd like to do is say okay
if it ended down right then I'd like to
do the same thing here where we have
like if the half transition count was
greater than zero that means they like
clicked it they clicked it and so what
I'd like to do is say the menu P right
our menu P at that time when first goes
down it is gonna be wherever the mouse
was at that point in time you know I'm
saying so there's a there's just this
concept of the the menu P where it
should be and then in here whenever we
figure out where the text actually is
we're just gonna offset that by whatever
the menu P is that way the menu can move
around with the mouse and is more like a
normal radial menu you know so now you
know if I if I look at the full screen
version of this I can kind of go
anywhere I want to write and do toggle
profile graph or toggle debug collation
right so now I actually have a fully
functional radial menu just not very
pretty yet so we should probably do a
little work on it but I've got a radial
menu and it only took a you know a few
minutes would that take 30 minutes 45
minutes and I don't know how long we
started into that but pretty
straightforward right not not much
all right so again sort of wrapping up
we have a lot more work to do before we
would actually consider this UI in in a
state that I'm gonna be happy with it
because right now it's it's kind of very
disparate you know I I don't like the
fact the menu items are separated from
these things and it's a little you know
it it just all we did was just put in
the base code for using it and so this
is gonna be a fairly classic compression
oriented programming style thing I'm
gonna do here next time on tomorrow's
handmade hero we'll start to pull out
some of what we just implemented into
something that's a little more coherent
by sort of lifting up a little bit but
that's the basics and now we have a
radial menu and radial menus are good
and so we can continue to kind of like
explore that as we go forwards let's go
ahead and go to the Q &amp; A so if you have
questions about what we've done on
today's stream please post them to the
chat nap but a Q : in front of it so I
can see it
I think you added v 3x y 4v 3 2 X 2 VG
conversion I did you're right I think I
did that smarter isn't it past me was
smarter than then then future me past me
was smarter that's just better because
then you control which ones you grab
right yeah
even if the menus in the circle get
cluttered we could make it so that each
button in the circle led us to another
circle layer subset of buttons yeah I'm
not like I said I'm not sure what I want
to do with this yet in terms of because
I mean I'm gonna see what options we
actually end up having in there but
we'll kind of get we'll kind of get
there once we we haven't really figured
out how we're even going to layout
things in this circular menu yet so you
know next time well well dive in a
little more and as we go we'll kind of
figure out how we want them in used to
work flock 93 can you explain a bit more
on the closure stuff and how to do it in
C I didn't quite understand it so the
closure stuff is just if I have
something where I am going to say it's a
good example let's say have something
like do complex iteration over things
you know and I'm gonna do some iteration
where I walk a treat so in fact you know
what you don't even have to guess I'll
just load up some actual handmade Hiro
code that actually has to do this and
then you should be able to see what I'm
talking about okay so you see this thing
here get world chunk for example so get
world chunk what it does is it looks
through a list and it figures out which
world chunk it wants by comparing each
thing you know it first figures out the
hash it goes into the right slot in the
hash it then goes through and compares
and tries to find a particular one if it
didn't find one it will like get a new
one and and all this other stuff right
there's all these things that it does
and so if you wanted to write something
now were you like I want to write
something that just does something to
everything in this list or something
like that or you know something that
maybe you know what not even sure that's
the best one it might not be the best
one to illustrate it because there's
there's a slight twinge to that one that
makes it not as good
what's the best place in him ah I got I
got it
uh so at least I think I got it okay so
let's say we were to take something like
this so here is a very complicated thing
draw a rectangle slowly right here's a
very complicated function if done that
does a ton of stuff it then has a bunch
of code inside where it basically says
okay for every it does a bunch of work
to figure out all the pixels and whether
the pixels were highlighted and all this
stuff and then inside it has what is
essentially a shader it has the code
that's like for a given pixel I want to
compute what the color should be how do
I do that and that's all in here
now if we wanted to make multiple
shaders right the logical way you would
do this is you would have in your
programming language a way to say oh by
the way I want you to just have a way
for me to say all of this external
iteration code just make that code be a
reusable chunk and I just want to
replace this part here so I'm gonna
stick something in here that's like do
the stuff semicolon and then I want to
be able to call quote-unquote this
function and tell you what to replace do
the stuff with and so that it can access
all of this information right that's
like the most basic use that's not even
a closure that's just a macro almost
right but oftentimes that thing itself
wants to have access to a separate stack
frame so it wants to have access to
variables that are not necessarily known
by this function so for example let's
say that one of these is the normal
mapping thing and it needs access to the
lighting environment whereas the other
way we might call it doesn't do any
lighting so it doesn't need access to
that so what we want to do is pass in
not just the code to execute but also a
little stack frame a little set of data
that goes with it that it can just go
ahead and do right and so you know other
programming languages have a variety of
things things like closures which allow
you to encapsulate this the data that's
referenced by something by a piece of
code into itself to be passed through to
somebody else where they can do stuff
with it and then it can come back to you
and have done the things that it needs
to do in your stack frame right it
allows you to kind of mix these stack
frames together in a very useful way it
allows that but more importantly it is
also just even separate from the closure
part of it the fact that you can sort of
pass code into something and have that
code execute inside another piece of
code is something that C can't do and
C++ recently added lambdas which kind of
allow you to do some of that stuff and
that is the thing that I was saying we
don't have if we don't want to go down
the C++ nightmare route so what I did is
sort of the poor man's version of that
what I did is say okay let's just put in
that place where we would which right
here in that place where we would have
wanted to pass in the tech the thing to
do will actually just put all the code
in there and just have a variable that
tells us which one to do and since
branches are relatively cheap it
probably isn't that bad right so that's
what we did and of course we don't have
full closures so these things cannot do
anything like have data that comes
through that only they know about like
the thing I saying before they can't
really talk to someone else's stack
frame or do any of the convenient stuff
like that that we might want but like I
said for up for a poor-man's version
it's totally usable hopefully that makes
some sense
why did you use radical menu or sorry
radial menu for helical menu why did you
use radial menu over lists or other
format I didn't I just no I at least
want a radial menu we will probably also
put in a list the radial menu is good
for quick picking so I probably want to
have radial menus for just a quick turn
on and off and then I probably also want
a more like linear drop-down any sort of
a situation for picking other things so
we're gonna do them all Elvan it would
be cool if the menu items are aligned
with the circle borders that way there's
less chance of Tex colliding yeah we
should also wrap the text a little bit
so there's more stuff we want to do
there Elvin you mentioned she doesn't
officially support closures did you ever
make an attempt to hack it maybe buy
functors or something like that not
really although I do often times do the
thing where I have multiple manage
stacks like you've seen me doing
handmade hero and some of that sort of
gets into closure II territory but no
I've never tried to hack closure
specifically in any real way have you
ever considered a debug output for the
stream where we can see your keystrokes
you mean like something that sort of
just puts like ctrl G at the bottom when
I hit ctrl G or stuff like that no I
haven't really and most of the reason
for that is I don't I mean I'm not an
Emacs I'm not a passionate Emacs user so
I don't really care if people learn how
to use Emacs I mean hopefully there's
some better editor to use soon maybe if
if mr. fourth-dimension gets for code or
up to up to speed we can just be using
that instead but yeah
elleven often times are using someone
else's API engine you end up having to
fight with it to have it do what you
want from it do you think that is a sign
that one should leave that API and try
another write his own instead of
fighting all the time it's a tough
question I the answer is that it depends
a lot of times that's true you know if
you're if you're using unity or
something you're probably gonna spend a
lot of your time fighting with it or
whatever and and it's just like you're
making you're making a trade-off of
basically saying yeah this thing is not
gonna be architected to do what I want
to do it's just this kind of thing that
is whatever it is and I'm just I'm
rolling the dice and saying that I bet
that I can save time in the long run by
using unity because they've because of
all the code they've written for me
versus all of the aggravation and time
I'm gonna have to spend trying to get it
to do certain things that it's doing
wrong or that doesn't do right for my
game and you're making that judgment
call right so sometimes I would say no
it doesn't mean you should switch right
it doesn't mean you shouldn't use unity
because the total time to develop the
game may still be shorter if you use
unity than if you don't right especially
if you're not a very experienced
programmer or something like that right
so sometimes you have to think of the
fighting as the cost of not having to
write the code yourself and it may end
up being a win right again it all
depends other times if you're really
fighting with it and it's not working it
may be the fact that like okay you just
can't do this you're gonna end up
basically rewriting almost the whole
thing yourself anyway in c-sharp you or
whatever just to work around all the
things that it doesn't do right that you
need it to do and then yeah it was a bad
idea to like keep using that thing you
know and unfortunately there's really
that's a really very tough decision
especially for a novice game developer
make knowing which one of those is going
to be true is very very hard and it's
closely related to another similar
decision which is what thing to use
library engine right for example you're
a novice game developer you don't have
the skills to make an engine should you
use Unreal Engine or unity right or game
maker and you know unless you've built
things in all three it's very hard to
know the answer to that question right
because yeah you will fight all three of
those you will fight because things that
you will want to do it will not do in
the way you want to do them or the way
that your game needs them done that will
happen which one of them will be the
least fighting right and so it's
definitely a case it's definitely the
case that those are all very hard
decisions
fighting is definitely a sign that the
thing doesn't do what you want it to do
the way you want to do it but that
doesn't mean you need to stop it means
you just need to be aware of it and beat
and understand that everything is a
cost-benefit trade off and if you start
to sense that writing maybe a particular
component from scratch or a whole thing
from scratch is going to be the better
way to go then you need to do that right
and that's again unfortunately the kind
of thing that's very difficult for a
novice programmer to make because it's
it's about experience in a lot of sense
and there's really without being burned
a few times and seeing how you get
burned it's oftentimes hard to know just
how hot the pan is right so that's
that's an issue certainly what I would
say in in and this probably doesn't go
for any of those things because because
in in those cases I think most of time
before fighting it's probably because
it's janky there are certain cases very
limited cases but certain cases where
you're fighting the API because you
actually don't know what you're doing
and an example for this for of this is
probably like when I was say 20 years
old if you had shown me the
i completion ports API in Windows I
probably would have said it was stupid
and I would have or would have had to
fight with it to get it to do what I
wanted to do nowadays I think the i/o
completion port API is like pretty darn
close to perfect and that is just
because I get how a certain type of code
should be written now and I get what it
needs to do to be performant and I get
what it needs to do to be properly
multi-threaded and until you know all of
that stuff a very well-designed API may
actually seem stupid or confusing or or
that it has something wrong with it but
it's actually you who are correct that
happens fairly rarely but once the mount
does happen and you know I suppose it's
not a surprise that the i/o completion
port API is an example of something like
that because that was designed by some
really really great operating system
guys like back in the day of cutler days
so you know
are you ready for the world to end
tomorrow script about crazy Christians
uh no I would prefer that it did not end
tomorrow I would really like to ship our
first game at Mali rocket so if they
could hold off on the end of the world
until after we do that I would really
like that a lot
psi 9 since through I worked out quickly
is its own translation unit are you
going to write that code and straight as
of instead of C intrinsics probably not
although if we wanted to try that as
just an exercise sometime we could I
probably wouldn't do that before we ship
the game though Qbert Caleb wait isn't
for coder already better than Emacs some
of it is the like refresh time and and
some of the stuff is but there's a bunch
of things in Emacs that I need that
doesn't have yet and so until it's up to
that level of functionality I can't
switch
Cooper Caleb can you go into detail and
I have completion for it since you
brought that up no because we're out of
time and trying to explain why out
completion ports are a good API would
take a long time so that's probably a
topic that's better saved for it for a
different day all right
I'm gonna wind it down wind it down
save the blackboard all right
thanks everyone for joining me for
another episode of hand made here oh
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
with handmade here at home with the
source code yourself the source code
actually comes with a pre-order of the
game so if you preorder handmade he
wrote up if you preorder handmade hero
the game on here org it comes with a
source every night after I'm done I
upload it and you can grab it play
around with it and experiment so if
you'd like to do that check out handmade
here org we also have a patreon page you
can go to support the video series
that's always much appreciated we also
have a forum site you can go to where
you can post questions and you can talk
to other members of the community or use
a anti Oso guy they've put together it's
really handy and there's also a tweet
bot the tweets that schedule it used to
be track has a stream live that is the
place to check out speaking catching a
stream live I would like to do some more
UI coding tomorrow and I hope you do too
if that is the case please come back
here tomorrow
5:00 p.m. Pacific Daylight Time again
where we will do exactly that until then
please have fun programming and I will
see you guys on the Internet
take it easy everyone