hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero this is the show where we code a
complete game live on stream I don't
really remember what I said I was gonna
do on Monday again yesterday was off but
I believe I believe what we were going
to do was start to sort of develop a
little bit more of the meta game
structure of handmade hero now handmade
hero is designed and this is just again
my own personal preference I am not a
game designer so handmade hero is mostly
designed by just putting in the things
that I prefer when I play a game and
trying to figure out things that can go
in the design that will force us to
tackle interesting programming problems
and show you how to do professional
quality programming so I'm not trying to
say that this is the correct way design
a game or anything like that but the way
that I prefer games is to have very very
little mini game I tend to like a game
to get right into it and I like as much
of the experience as possible to take
place in the game not in a series of
menus and so the more menus and stuff
that pop up in a game or the more
frontmatter there is in a game the less
pleased I typically am with that so
handmade hero is not designed to have
very much meta game but it needs at
least two pieces of metal game I think
in order to sort of have the field that
I would like it to have and that is that
when you boot the game I would like
there to be some way of playing an intro
sequence and the reason for that is I
would like there to be a sort of just a
little bit of context to the experience
and since handmade hero is very much a
direct action II kind of game I don't
really feel like that context should
come as minoo sort of embedded in the
game because the game should have a very
quick flow to it it shouldn't have a lot
of interstitial elements to the game and
so I would just like that to to take a
more traditional old-school approach to
it where there's just some kind of like
an attract mode where if you have not
indicated to the game that you
would like to start playing yet it will
show you a little bit of a story and so
that's why we implanted those cutscenes
those are kind of what I imagined be the
attract mode so I'd like to have the the
metagame consists primarily of just once
you start the game you are watching the
story and the story will just kind of
loop until you decide to begin the game
proper and when you begin the game
copper you will be placed into the game
experience and you will play and I don't
want to have a lot of other stuff so I
don't want to have a lot of things like
pick a save slot I don't want to have a
bunch of stuff like tune the options do
you want music like I don't want any of
that I just want it to be right and you
start and you play and the absolute
minimum amount of stuff should happen
otherwise there shouldn't be anything
else in there right and so right down to
the part where like if there were gonna
be options of some kind in the game I
would want you to basically hop the
character around to set them rather than
having something that pops up that's a
different experience I got like a menu
experience so that's kind of what I'm
thinking
and so really they'll only be two
primary modes to the game there's the
attract mode and then there's the game
mode but even just implementing that
that basic idea still requires you to
tackle essentially the entire meta game
problem which is to say that the game
has to understand that it can be in more
than one mode right and creating a more
complex meta game is really no different
it just means there are more modes right
there are more things that can happen
more variety like a broader variety of
interactive sort of vertical slices of
your game where it's gonna be like okay
here's the game one here's the option
menu here's the save game selection
there's this that the other thing right
and so you the programming is basically
the same as what we're gonna do here
there's just more of it and since I
don't like those things I'm not going to
do them I'm gonna skip those and we're
going to try to put everything that we
can into the actual game experience as
much as possible and if we find that we
need some kind of options or some kind
of other things like that we'll put them
that into the game as much as we can all
right so let's go ahead and and see
where we left off this is day 226 so if
you pre-ordered the game on handmade
hero org day 225 is really the one that
you want to go with you want to unpack
that source code and that way you'll be
in the same state that I am today and
oops
Enix I wonder if that's a good editor I
don't know what Enix is that sounds
wonderful so if I compile here I just
get myself set up let's go ahead and
start this guy the last thing that we
sort of did the last feature we did was
sort of the fade in and out oh and that
reminds me
looking at this another thing that we
never really knew was why our fade
appears to be highly nonlinear right
that was another thing that was kind of
a little bit confusing when we when we
tackled it right it didn't quite seem
right and it made me wonder do we have
some kind of a weird bug in the system
where we're not treating our colors as
gamma corrected properly you know or
something like this I don't really know
but the point is simply that there does
seem to be something that's that's not
happening correctly right so that fade
was also think I don't know that we want
to look at that now it's kind of off
topic but it's definitely something that
we should look into eventually so so
yeah so where we left things was this
this will play and then if I actually
start the game you know it does exactly
what you would think so I hit the
spacebar and you can kind of see that
you know I end up with my my hero again
and we're in there and I can also hit if
I want to I can hit escape and come out
and we're back to the the cutscene again
and if I had space I go back in right
but you can see that and of course
creates a new player in a lot stuff so
we didn't we don't even have that that
part of stuff working either right we
didn't do any of this stuff but
primarily the first thing that I want
tackle is just that notion that when I
return back here and now I'm in this
this mode where I'm watching the
cutscene what I want to do is when I
return to attract mode it should kind of
be aware of the fact that I have
returned to track mode to attract mode
it shouldn't just go back to where
we left off in the cutscene that's not
what I wanted to have happen I would
want to go back to like the main a track
screen and then do some kind of thing
where it started the cutscene all over
again regardless of where you exited and
so in order to do that I need to have
some way of understanding when a mode
transition has occurred and so that's
what we're gonna have to deal with now
I'm just gonna wait till Krampus comes
in because I like it when Krampus comes
in there he is
hello Krampus alright so let's go ahead
a little bit dry
I forgot my drink that's never a good
thing when I forget my drink alright so
let's take a look at where we are if you
remember we sort of had the notion of
the cutscene here we're inside the the
this state right here of the the game
state we created a plain cutscene and
the plain cutscene controls this code
that we did that plays cutscenes
so that if you initialize one and you
tell it what you want to do you can then
update it as frequently as you want and
it'll continue playing cutscene so we
did that that all works fine but all we
did for switching between the cutscene
and the game is we literally just check
to see whether any of the witty heroes
existed in the game that's it like
there's nothing else that we've done and
so what that means is again when a hero
gets created or when a hero gets
destroyed if the number of Heroes goes
down to zero then suddenly we'll be back
in the cutscene if the number of Heroes
goes above 0 to 1 then suddenly be in
the game but the game itself is never
explicitly aware of that transition
right we have no idea when we transition
from being in the state of having heroes
and playing the game and back that you
know or in the state of not having any
heroes and watching the cutscene and we
need to know what that actually you know
we have to have a way of detecting that
transition because if we don't detect
and respond to that transition we will
never know when we need to reset our
cutscene yes and so that's the part that
we need to make a little more formal
here and so that's the part that I'm
going to try to start formalizing as we
move forward okay so what I'd like to do
is say well you know maybe we've got
that handmade cutscene thing so maybe
what I really need to say is well you've
got handmade of track mode so I'm just
gonna consider there to be a handmade
attract mode right and we kind of know
what handmade a track mode is it's this
right it's this right here and I could I
suppose if I wanted to you know I guess
now I think about it there might not be
very much in that file I don't really
know so maybe we could sort of keep it
simpler and say that you know maybe that
just goes here in in handmade cut seeing
that H I'm not sure right so we could
say like okay you know maybe there's
just a thing that's like you know it's a
tracked mode or whatever in in a tracked
mode or a track mode State it might be
the the best way to say it in a track
mode State we bundle up the sorts of
things that actually that we you know
need in order to play the attract mode
so there's one right we've got the the
cutscene that there might be there and
we also probably have something like if
we wanted a main menu and then um a menu
but so weird I'm looking for whatever
you want a title screen let's say so if
we you know we've got the cutscene that
place if we just want to think that's
like you know ham a hero
press Start to begin or press keyboard
or whatever you know if we want to that
screen that just sits there for about
you know 10 seconds or something and
then the cutscene starts playing if we
want something like that to happen so
it's more a little bit more like in
arcade game or if we'd rather have it to
start the cutscene right away play the
whole cutscene then go to that that
title screen then start the cutscene
again any any sort of setup like that
then we need is some notion of which of
those we were in right we would need
sort of like a sort of States there
right
okay so you could imagine doing that one
of two ways when I could have like
something cure that's like you know a
title screen like a boolean and I said
it and that's whether I'm playing the
cutscene or not or whatever but my
assumption is that whatever mode
handling we do for handling the fact
that we're either in the attract mode or
in the game mode we could presumably
just use that same mode handling to
handle the difference between the title
screen the cutscene and the game all
three of them right so what I'm assuming
we would do is we'd say something like
this which is like game mode and we just
say okay there's game mode title screen
there's game mode cutscene and there's
game mode playing or something right for
world right where I'm off in the world
something like this and there might even
be yet another one I'm not sure
depending on how we want to do that
which is that there might be like a
world game mode and a sort of like
options game mode we're like you know
let's say for example we want to support
multiple save slots you could imagine
like when you start the game you
actually start off like in the orphanage
and there's different like rooms and
each room is a different save game so
you hop into the room that you want to
play at that time you know that's again
sort of its it's like a menu right it's
just a menu created in the game and so
that you know depending on how we might
want to do it that could also be a
different game mode I don't know it
might still be the world game mode but
I'm not sure so that's just something to
think about just something to keep in
mind but let's say for now that we only
have the three that I already know that
we want so that we can work with those
instead so if I wanted to do that then
what I'd say is all right we've got our
game mode and this is a you know
whatever it is this is the mode right
here and then what I would have to do is
I'd have to have some way of of having
you know different storage for different
game modes or different stuff like this
right so I'd have to have some way of
of creating basically like holding
holding place for these things and so
what I'd like to point out here is that
each of these things that we're talking
about each of them kind of wants to have
its own storage and most of them or
perhaps even all of them but regardless
will get like shut down sort of
altogether so in other words when I'm
playing in a particular game world you
know it's gonna do whatever it's gonna
do and it's gonna have all that storage
when I'm done with that all of that
storage is just gonna go away right and
the same is true of like the tunnel
scene of the cutscene or whatever when I
start it up it's gonna do some stuff to
like make that happen but then when I
shut it back down again you know it's
not it's not gonna need to retain
anything right and so that to me also
suggests that I'm gonna have some kind
of a sort of like I'm gonna have some
kind of a blind point to read kind of
thing here right so I'm gonna do
something where I saw the card I've got
a game mode and whatever the game mode
is is gonna kind of determine what I'm
doing and then inside you know in
addition to that I need to store
something that tells me what's going on
so maybe I have something like okay I've
got the attract mode state and this is
the attract mode or whatever and then
I'd have the the like the world's state
and that would be here and we have stuff
like that already like we have like
worlds to our world here right and that
would be something for example that
would you know might become sort of the
state of the world now I'm not gonna try
and pre guess that I'm just gonna
continue from from this basic premise
I'm gonna start pulling things out and
just see where it leads but you can kind
of get you get the idea right you kind
of can start to see where I'm going that
all right now I don't really care too
much about this being an allocation
style thing so what I really could do
too is just say that we always actually
have a tracker but I'm gonna do it as an
allocation style just in case it's a
large thing they can get flushed
completely and so we can kind of see how
that goes what we want to do with that
right all right so let's slowly start to
piece that looked at
use this apart let's slowly start to see
what we can do with that so I'm gonna
say that inside this I'm gonna have two
different kinds of things I'm gonna have
something that looks like this right I'm
gonna have internal ooh I don't know why
is that do we know why that was oh right
it's handmade here oh the active line
shows blue for some reason I forgot that
but that's I think how it's supposed to
work yeah it's weird that I didn't think
that was supposed to happen it's been
happening also had never struck me as
odd on 11 million previous dreams for
some reason just then it did don't ask
me don't know why all right but yeah
that's supposed to happen right that's
how we do it on handmade here we've been
doing it that way for for a year rains
getting old anyway so I'm gonna do an
update and render title screen you know
and I'm gonna do an update and render
cutscene and so then I can just kind of
put this in here so it's like okay
that's what that is right and yeah I'm
gonna replace this guy with a switch on
that game mode so instead of just
looking at this exactly well we'll see
we're gonna leave this here for a minute
what I'm gonna do instead is I'm gonna
switch on whatever our game state says
the game mode is right so we've got this
guy cure this game mode and then we've
got we know that it could be these
things and so I'm gonna say okay here's
the title screen here's the cutscene
here's the world so there's three
different modes we could be in and of
course we also have I don't know if we
ever did an invalid default case do we
ever do that one I kind of like this one
I never remember whether we did it on
one hand meter or not see invalid code
path yeah we did
I like invalid default case because we
that game mode should always be set to
something valid hopefully and the other
thing we can do here is also if we want
we can set it to something like game
mode you know uninitialized or none
which is like by default when we start
up we've got no game mode we could all
say this like that I don't know that we
really need to do that at the moment so
I'm going to leave that out but you know
sometimes it's good to have a zero value
that's like kind of the amounted set
alright so in here we kind of already
know what this is going to be we're
gonna call whenever we're in the
cutscene mode we're gonna call you know
update and render cutscene we know in
worlds we're gonna do update and render
game and I suppose this this could maybe
more properly be called update and
render world and finally in the title
screen we've got update and render title
screen which is just something that will
create at some point I know that I want
a little title screen there so I know
we're gonna have one up at the moment
that really actually gonna do anything
it'll just probably be a blank screen or
who knows what'll be we'll figure out
something something okay so there oops
tried to cut and paste I failed
okay so let's try this
there we go and so when I call update
and render title screen I'm gonna get
this these sort of things here now the
problem with this is I probably want to
have a way of passing these guys just
about everything that there is to to
have well you know I don't really have
to I guess because since I'm using a
switch statement never mind it doesn't
really matter so this would be fine so
yeah if I want to have this well I
really need to do is make sure that I
pass it all the things that I know that
I need which is really just these these
things write these things and I need to
know a couple different things that we
didn't actually have like I need to know
the DT and probably honestly a men need
more than just the DT I'm probably
actually also going to need the whole
input I feel like it's gonna have to
respond to input so it's probably going
to be something that takes that directly
and then for advanced cut seeing this
thing where we're and also for here
where we get that current cut
see I think again I want that to refer
to this attract mode state right or
something like that probably I don't
really know maybe maybe I don't even
need that I don't know we'll see
but point being yet and here I think
what we would do is expect there to be
some kind of a wrapped up storage that
would be used for these guys I'm not
sure exactly what it would be but it
looks to me like we've already kind of
done it right here we're so you know
this might be like something like
game-mode cutscene right and and it sort
of has this information in it I think
that might be a little bit more logical
with the way that I would want this to
work right okay so let's see so we've
got game-mode attract doing something
like that game Oh cutscene and game-mode
worlds something like this those are the
three things that I've got right now and
so yeah once I call into one of those
guys look I do update and render world
right it only makes sense that it's
gonna get a pointer to one of those now
if this doesn't actually exist yet but
these two should so I've got game of
cutscene and I've got game mode attract
we don't really know what the attract
mode has in it at the moment so I'll
just stick a team in there or something
so that it's got something but we'll
play with that a little bit more later
and then we've got the cutscene which of
course is this guy and that one already
does kind of exist as well alright so if
I want to do this where we're gonna do
make it for cutscene I'm gonna do this a
little bit differently now I'm gonna I'm
gonna change a little bit how I would do
this right and I'm gonna say that the
maybe the outside the the code outside
is going to sort of give me an arena or
something to work with something like
that right and what I'm gonna do is I'm
gonna say that this arena
whatever the arena is is gonna get
passed in here so it's basically in a
say hey I need you to like make the
intro cutscene or whatever I want you to
destroy your state in this particular
arena and so off it goes right it's
gonna do whatever it needs to do for
that so this would just be like okay I'm
gonna do a push struct I'm
Syrena for playing cutscene I'll get one
back I set it up and then I returned it
and that's how I initialize the cutscene
right so if I did something like that
then I would also have something that
like sonic cutscene but I don't really
need to show anything down because I
know that the person outside can just
jettison the arena and everything's fine
so for now I'm just gonna assume that
Moe's don't need to be shutdown they can
just be jettisoned because that's
generally probably what I will end up
doing most of the time all right so if I
make an intro cutscene like that that
sort of allows me to store the cutscene
information and then updating it is a
simple matter of passing that back right
so something that looks like this
that's the entirety of what we currently
need to do but we're gonna probably move
a little bit more code in there in the
future we'll find out but that's
basically what's going to happen we're
going to be doing the plain cutscene
there and update the render title screen
would be you know something similar I'm
not sure but that's gonna have in it and
it's not a plain cutscene where it's a
game mode cutscene go to cutscene and we
do render cutscene a time this is gonna
take a game mode cutscene as well I
believe right yeah and so we'll see that
might be a little too tight but we'll
see now we probably could say you know
this advance is not particularly
interesting so we probably could just do
something where we just do that right
and the render is not very interesting
either so we probably could just do this
these are probably things that can just
be handled like that without
overcomplicating things so I might just
do it like that there's not gonna be
more than one cutscene playing at once
presumably so we don't really need to
overcomplicate it but if there was gonna
be then you could kind of you could
imagine right that sort of thing having
happening okay so let's see here where
we're at we've got our game mode
cutscene
Rena's supposed to be pointer and isn't
which is bad and that seems like that's
fine spelling wise is challenging better
than that seems fine there we go all
right and so that's all that's all
pretty good so once we've got that then
we just have this title screen guy to
work with an Abbe game mode title screen
which we don't have anyway lets's title
screen where the cursor just went so
game mode title screen and that seems
reasonable to me okay so that's all good
now we just need to get those guys into
somewhere where they can be seen game
mode attracting game mode cutscene now
the problem with that is they should be
in here already so I'm wondering why
they weren't I'm not 100% sure game the
cutscene those should be in there right
game it off as a trap yeah current
cutscenes make intro cutscene so now all
we have to do is actually sort of
formalize the notion of switching into
game modes right okay so how am I gonna
do that well first what I have to do is
start to pull out all of the
initialization code into something that
will allow me to like understand what
mode I'm going into and actually do
something about it right and so if you
think about it like all this code right
here it's like for simulating the game
and doing a lot sort of stuff then we
have all this startup code that's in
there that just initializes the world
not stuff we don't actually want that
all that happened when we start up the
game we don't want to create a game
world when we start off the game because
no one's playing the game yet and
furthermore we might have to do that
again sometime if the person like exits
that game and restarts a new one right
like maybe they exit that world they
didn't want to do that world so they
exit and come back in or who knows what
happens right so what I'm going to do is
I've introduced another function that
just allows me to change what game mode
I'm in and that function will be
responsible for initializing whatever
the game mode is so I'm gonna do
something like set game mode
and set game-mode will be something
which just kind of you know allows me to
to say I'm going to do this this other
thing you know whatever whatever the
mode I pass is is what I want it to be
right so I'll pass like game state and
I'll pass game mode and it will set
those right so basically do you like
game state game mode equals game mode
that's what it's gonna do something like
that so how's that gonna work well first
it has to clear out whatever the
previous mode was right so if I have
whatever the arena is I'm gonna just
reuse the same arena although in the
future I may actually ping-pong them for
reasons we'll see a little bit further
down the line but for now let's just
start with the with the simpler approach
you can see it what I'd like to do first
to say all right so there's gonna be
like a ton arena and instead of a world
arena I'm actually gonna call that
something else I'm gonna say that that's
basically the mode arena right I'm gonna
say the arena that's that's being used
for allocation here is actually the mode
arena
that's where everything is gonna come
from right and so what I want to do is
say well the game state mode arena is
gonna get cleared and I don't know if we
have a clear for our arenas do we we
don't not that I see anyway yeah I don't
see it so I'm gonna introduce one here
which is just clear and this is no
different than if we just did a begin
temporary memory and then end temporary
memory but I'm I don't want to call it
temporary memory because it's not really
that temperate temporary it's pretty
much permanent up until the point where
we decide to clear it right so it's it's
it's semantically a little bit
differently and I'd rather not mix those
two so I want to have a way of clearing
it and clearing it's pretty
straightforward if you look at what
constitutes an arena for for our
purposes here there's really not much in
it right and so the if we initialize an
arena for example you can see what
actually happens here clearing an arena
for all intensive purposes is is just
going to initialize it that's all it
does so if I were to say okay just
real reinitialize the arena but
reinitialize it with its own base planar
again that would just clear it out it'd
be like all of the allocations never
happened right and we could just
allocate again to our hearts content so
what I'm gonna say is all right clear
the mode arena that's all gone then
switch on the game mode that we pick
whatever that is and based on what it is
construct a new thingy whatever the
thingy is and so we already know what
those three things could be at the time
right there the title screen cutscene in
the world but as you can sort of see
from this you know we we sort of don't
we don't quite know right exactly which
of these things we don't know what we
might need to pass right because imagine
for example you know in make this little
explicit imagine in here right when we
do make intro cutscene or whatever let's
suppose there was more than one cutscene
we might want to play well this set game
mode if you were happening to pass
cutscene to it you wouldn't have to
actually pass which cutscene you wanted
but that would be a parameter that
wouldn't get used if you're doing say
the title screen and so you'd end up
with set game mode would be taking like
all these parameters all is basically
the union of all the parameters for all
the different game modes and that's not
particularly good right that gets
unwieldy pretty quickly and not really
something we want to have to deal with
so what we would rather do it's
something like begin game mode or
something like this where we're just
gonna say and I guess you know we we
could even still Klotz that game mode
but instead of doing a switch right here
instead what we'll do is we'll let the
person who is actually trying to do it
whatever they were gonna do set up
whatever that dependent state actually
is so we won't bother doing anything
other than just saying we'll clear out
the old mode and off we go
that seems a little more sane to me
okay so if we wanted to do that then all
we have to do is make it so that when
you try to do something like one of
these things where you play something so
for example play intro cutscene might be
the more sensible thing to do here what
we'd say is okay that's gonna be like a
set game mode call that's that game mode
call is going to why is that yeah that
set game mode call is going to take the
game state and I'm sorry the play trick
cutscenes gonna take the game state
we're gonna call set game mode on the
game state with the the state of playing
cutscene right whatever that is and I
know it's here somewhere there it is
right so that's gonna clear anything
that was happening before changes to
this mode which is the cutscene mode and
then what we're gonna do is we're going
to actually create that game mode
cutscene ourselves and so then we would
just say oh the game state cutscene
right this guy equals whatever we just
made you don't have to return anything
because that's just going to do it and
so that would consume changing a mode
similarly in here if we were to say okay
play title screen we'd say okay game
state same thing
literally we just do okay so title
screen game mode cutscene is actually
now gonna be game of title screen and
then we would set something in here but
we don't have anything to set really at
all but you know I don't know we have T
right result T equals zero this one why
is there no result T equals zero here I
don't know that seems like a bug to me
but anyway so then we have a result T
equals zero then we have game state
title screen equals result and now we
can play the intro cutscene or the title
screen and both will work right okay
so let's step through now and and fix we
change that arena situation let's step
through that this our initialize arena
initialize arena needs to be fixed so
that's just we gotta pass the size as
well there we go so now I'm here like
doing the World Arena what we actually
want to do there for things like andsome
probably what we would really want is
for this to no longer be actually
looking at the game state much that's
just kind of what we would rather it do
we kind of don't want game state to
really be there that's really we would
just want it to be world right and if we
look at what's what's in handmade world
H you know this thing right here this
world is probably actually the thing
that should be holding most of those
other things that we've got currently
sitting in the game state now I don't
know that we actually want to do too
much of that yet but you can kind of see
where that's going like that's what we
would prefer to have happen I think
because the game state should be sort of
like the overall structure that can hold
multiple different game modes that are
happening in it and so again I'm not
really sure we want to do there but
that's a mutation we probably want to
make so we'll look at that but I don't
want to do that quite yet I'm gonna
leave that a little bit more outside of
of what's going on here and so for the
moment what I might do is say anywhere
that we were using World Arena cuz let's
take a look I don't think we're using it
often I mean it's it's used often but
not that often you know you can see
there's just a few what I might do is
try to push that over so that the world
arena actually is in here right so there
really is a thing that's like rolled
arena and so instead it's going to be
something like well all right we've got
the world right so the world comes from
gamestate world we've got the world and
I want you to always use this world
arena instead right something a little
bit more like that I think that's gonna
be saner we'll see how it goes as we go
forward
oops let's go ahead in the place game
state world world so that should be fine
okay so step game mode is something that
we would like to have exposed a little
more broadly right now that's sort of
buried in here about I'd like to do is
say hey anyone can call that if you
would like so let's put that up there
all right and so here when we've got
arena this is gonna be the game state
mode arena so those things are all going
to come out like all the modes and all
that stuff is just going to come out of
there
so then I'm here with the world arena
stuff again this is just like ad lo
entity that's just stuff I would like to
see that come out of a specific sort of
arena that's in the world just again
it's preparation of kind of moving these
things into groups where we sort of have
a concrete notion of what part of it is
like world based stuff and what part of
it is not you know what part of his
other things like the title screen and
again this may seem like overkill and
for our game it may honestly be but
again I kind of watch out do this
because a lot of games have a lot more
meta state than handmade hero does and
so I just want to show how to piece it
out into something relatively clean
because whatever game you might want to
make may have a lot more option menus a
lot more whatever I don't know what but
it might have a lot more whatever that
is so let's do play intro cutscene get
that going there alright so update and
render title screen this is going to
take all this stuff presumably and I
would assume well I don't really know
what it takes let's find out so update
and render title screen is going to take
the assets at the render group the draw
buffer and the title screen
update and render cutscene I think takes
subsequently the same stuff although I
think it also takes the input group and
it probably isn't gonna take title
screen it's gonna take the cutscene and
let's go ahead and I don't know why I
can never capitalize cutscene properly I
seem to be really bad at it
yeah gonna render cutscene and there we
go check arena mode arena and then we're
good to go
alright so now there's a couple things
that we haven't done yet obviously one
of which is when we create that world
here we now when we whenever we
initialize the worlds we need some way
of of putting that arena in there so now
when you do this and you do initialize
world you're gonna have to pass a memory
arena that's the arena that you want it
to actually use for its allocations
right
and so in here where we do World Arena
like we were doing it before and we do
this this sort of thing right we
actually need that to sort of happen we
need that to happen
in the bin here you know so in order to
do this what I'd like to do is kind of
move that in here and and say okay and
and you know what I could when we do
this I could make it so that I just look
and games it directly but I'm not again
not really capturing this code right now
I'm just gonna I'm gonna do a little bit
differently so anyway when I do
initialize arena to initialize this this
arena what I want to do is just use I
think all the rest of the memory after
you know what's you it when you go to
initialize the world it's supposed to
use all the rest of the memory or
something like that
I don't really know right but something
like that and so if I want to do that
what I want to do is I'm gonna get sort
of a parent arena I'm gonna get a thing
that's like I'm going to go in here
where whatever the here is and what I
want to do is I want to say hey however
much
is left which I think we have right do
we have that get arena size remaining
right what I want to do is say when we
initialize the world I want to just get
whatever there is so I'm going to get
the ring size or remaining of the parent
arena and that's actually what I want
and that's isn't that sub arena we
already have that yeah we have that so
it's like sub arena this is the arena I
want to initialize this is the arena
that I'm coming from I want to get I
want to use however much there is and
that's all something like that so that's
what I want to do and so then what I
would do in here inside handmade tubes
and made STP what I would do in here is
when we actually do do initialize arena
this guy can now initialize the mode
arena and we can move forward with it so
then when we look at all this stuff we
could see like World Chunkin meters and
all that sort of stuff that is really
just this this is all part of the world
thing right this is this is this looks
like this right so we've got all this
sort of stuff happening here yeah we'd
want to take the this world stuff we
want to initialize and here we want to
pass it that that mode arena so if you
look at what all this stuff does all of
this stuff is just for initializing the
world right every last thing in here has
nothing to do with paying a cutscene at
all it's all just initializing the world
so again what I'm going to do is I'm
going to just like we did update and
render world I'm gonna do a thing here
where we do like initialize world or
something
right something like that or or play
world I don't know what we'll call these
things but what I want to do is have it
so that all that stuff actually happens
in one of these as well just like
exactly analogous to what I did in the
cutscene thing so right here where I
pulled those things apart I'm gonna pull
them apart again just exactly the way I
did before and play world will do
exactly what play intro cutscene does
create a world that you can play and set
the mode to be playing that world
okay so initialize arena and there's
audio state these are all in fact I
guess even this stuff here all this
stuff is really just all of this stuff
it's really just part of that world
creation right every every last little
thing in here right all of this all of
it everything all the right down to play
cutscene right so I'm gonna pull that
out and I'm gonna put that up sort of
isolated into a thing where what its
gonna be like okay this is how we play a
world there you go
and then we're gonna deal with it
separately that's gonna be a separate
thing
okay so let's I'm not gonna deal with
that quite yet
what is this ground buffer this ground
buffer width okay these guys know what
those are doing there exactly there
probably for allocation purposes hmm I
guess ground but I don't even know I
know what I want to do with that I
suppose they were used in both places
I'm gonna do a little to do here get
these into a more reasonable location
but I'm just gonna go ahead and find
that for now so I don't care about that
at all at the moment okay so when we do
initialize world I think this is all
good there we go so now I think we're
totally good and we've got that sort of
play world thing happening so let's just
start by seeing where we're at here is
running the game we fade out we fade
into the cutscene obviously that's what
we expect cuz we set up we said we
called play cutscene in our
initialization and that's exactly what
we're seeing
pressing the oops I do not know what
just happened
I literally have no idea ah
so gonna say pressing the button is
gonna run code for the world stuff it's
not quite gonna do that it's gonna look
in through here and it's gonna start
trying to do stuff that it can't really
do right because the world has not been
initialized or anything like that so all
of this stuff here like that that tries
to create a new hero and stuff that is
not actually what we would want right
that's not none of that stuff is is
actually able to sort of occur because
we haven't actually created a world
right
but the cutscene part is working fine
and that's what we would expect so now
we need to do is kind of make that world
stuff happen a little bit better a
little bit more straightforwardly and so
what I want to do there is I want to
kind of figure out how there's some
things that will probably be persistent
in the game state for example we
probably want something like our who is
joined in the actual game like who's
what what heroes are actually can who
signed in basically like who's involved
in the game that is probably persistent
so I suspect
oops that controlled hero this kind of
thing here I suspect that that is
actually going to want to be in the in
the actual game state itself but
everything else probably wants to move
into the game the game-mode world
basically whatever you want to call that
and I'm not sure again where we want to
really put that it's a little bit
confusing because world already sort of
meant this sort of storage thing that we
had here but I'm just going to probably
start to just dump stuff in there and if
we need to split that file into two
later we can do that later
that's not really my concern at the
moment right all right so let's go ahead
and see what happens here if we just
have this thing called world I'm gonna
see what happens if I just start dumping
stuff in there so let's say I take world
here and I make that show up over here
for now and I don't know that I really
need game-mode world but maybe I'll do
it that way so this game-mode world and
soak down fear this also like you
gamemode world and then i'm it's gonna
pull out all of the stuff because all of
it only really pertains to a particular
world right so all of this stuff is all
that yeah like every it looks like every
last bit of this right that's all gonna
come out here and that's all gonna be
part of the game-mode world you know
what I mean
and so in here we've got all that stuff
and there's obviously an active world
that is kind of being played at that
time maybe there'll be other more than
one world struct for all when we know at
certain times when you're playing I'm
not sure but point being that's what
that'll look like and now you can kind
of see exactly how this is starting to
shape take shape now we've got a meta
arena and a mode arena I don't know what
the meta arena is to be honest I've
completely forgotten does that what does
that do I don't know I'm getting rid of
it who calls it I guess this was a bad
time to get rid of it well we'll leave
it out till someone complaints anyway so
if we go ahead and start to I guess
start to clean some of this stuff up so
that this stuff works
I gotta go ahead and figure out how to
make sure that everyone is defined
properly I don't remember what happens
it's low entity it looks like that's
just defined right in here for some
reason and so it was like pairwise
collision rule all of these things that
are related to that are all in here and
so is like particle cell and and
particle and all these guys and so what
I'd like to do is I'll go ahead and move
those for now into where they now more
appropriately belong which is in here
but probably will split that will want
to split that up even more in the future
so let's see in can made a CH we now
have also the problem where like a
simonetti for example is is gonna be in
handmade sim right
I assume that's where we put it's been a
long time but I bassoon so and here we
go there cemento t but I'm assuming that
we also probably refer to world things
here like for example we probably refer
to world positions that you can see
right there
when we're talking about sim region so
we kind of have a problem where we've
just got too many things that depend on
each other and of course sea forces us
to deal with this which is a really
annoying aspect of it because there's
absolutely no reason we should have to
manage this sort of stuff
but unfortunately we kind of do and so
we have sort of a for a declaration
conflict there where we have to define
semana T and I don't really want to move
sin and I don't really want to move some
entity I really don't want to move any
of this stuff so that's kind of annoying
but what I could do is I could put low
entity in a slightly different position
could I do that well you know what I
could do I could just make world
position be in here for a minute which
is not where I want it but you can see
this is again like I said it's just
really annoying it's just a really
really annoying aspect of of programming
in a language that doesn't understand
that files should have nothing to do
with dependency it's just stupid but you
know that's that's you code you go to
two handmade here with the language you
have nothing language you'd like to have
so anyway if I go ahead and do that then
I just need to switch the order in which
these two things happen
we just do it like that and presumably
we'd be fine and yeah and so that would
be it world's got to come second and sim
region comes first
oops I switched the wrong ones there I
meant to do the H files sorry about that
this is what I actually wanted to do
world dot H some region dot H I just
want to do that and then we should be
hopefully a little bit better world
chunks the same way so you can kind of
see like I got to move the things that
our primal here and that's just really
annoying so I don't know maybe we can do
something a little bit more with that
wait okay here is the compromise here's
what I'll do this is less bad I'm just
gonna make a handmade you know world
mode dot cpp NH which I don't love but
that would just allow us to get out of
the business of having these in the same
file right there we go problem solved in
not a very saver way but that's just the
way the
voules all right so then if I go back to
handmade H then we can just do okay
world comes first sim region comes
second and world mode comes last
same thing with here world mode actually
that probably wants to go way down at
the bottom probably something like that
okay so test a few sand tests normal I
probably those were a little overzealous
that's probably those are just test
things so those can probably stay in
here for the time being until they just
get removed entirely and so that'll be
fine
random series definitely should be there
so don't know where that's not they're
random
should probably just be at the top
that's definitely a math e sort of a
thing so that's fine audio state again
audio state totally should not have been
moved that was just again a little bit
overzealous these two guys should
probably be for the time being still off
in handmade H because we really haven't
formalized something like what sound
just playing or anything like that
so that should be kind of left for later
all right so now let's see what's going
on we got to pour it all this code I
probably shouldn't have done this with
so little time left in the stream but
you know you got to do what you got to
do and so we'll see what we can do
alright so get low entity is now gonna
be something that's called on the on the
world mode and so all of these things
are gonna force this to kind of go
through a really annoying process of
just kind of moving through server but
again it's not really a big deal it's
it's just a little bit it's it's just a
little bit of pain that you got to go
through sometimes when you want to make
a large change but it's really just it's
just a minor annoyance it shouldn't be
really something to worry about too much
and not like something I worry about
very much either a lot of times people
will do coding things to try to prevent
themselves from having to do some of
these things and I I just don't think
that's a very good idea I prefer to just
go through this kind of cleaning up
every now and again and and partitioning
and you just kind of bite the bullet for
those that limited amount of time yet to
do that that
usually much better than trying to do
extra layers of insulation and stuff
that make your code a lot worse than
uglier just for the sake of not having
to go through an hour of of this kind of
thing or something like that right so
anyway let's go ahead and put this in
here so get low empty state this is just
going to be game-mode world no call that
rolled mode or something like that and
that's just going to do game state world
mode guess not sure what else we could
call that I don't really know they're
not great names I admit that but what
I'm gonna do
alright and so then all of these things
presumably like entity reference all
that sort of stuff all of these things
actually are not really using the game
state anymore they're all gonna use
actually that game mode world pretty
much exclusively right there's not gonna
really be much game state stuff
happening anymore
so I think I may be able to just blank
it say at the game state game state
that's just gonna be game mode worlds to
our world mode I think I can pretty much
just say that across the board and so
furthermore I think I could probably say
that like game state is just always
world mode I think and we'll find out
but that's what I think will be true and
it does look like that's very likely so
add collision rule again so now these
guys we've got to kind of get those
pulled out a little bit more so we've
got add collision rule and actually a
lot of these things in game game world
mode right a lot of these things are
probably going to go in here so I'm just
gonna grab them out in fact you can kind
of see a lot of them right now look at
all these guys these are all really none
of this stuff none of this stuff is
actually generic it's all part of it's
all part of that so this is all going in
there and then we've got ground chunks
those are not
related to that so that's all good this
is all fine that can stay but okay this
all this stuff that out here all this
stuff is is again comes into the new
file as well this is all stuff that has
to do with the game world okay all that
goes there and then that should be just
about it okay
so let's keep going we've got add
collision rule there that's gonna be on
the game on the world mode to add
collision rule and I guess this is the
same thing is gonna happen here
basically everywhere we would have had
game state game State it's gonna be game
mode world mode and all the rest of
these guys game state are going to be
will note as well
there's a lot of them folks there are a
lot of them it would seem if you ask me
but that's fine yeah that's just way it
goes sometimes look at all of these my
lord
okay so let's see what else we got
add collision rule where is that
collision rule chemo world world mode
what's the O it probably was predefined
and it's probably predefined wrong there
we go
problem solved okay and this is probably
you instruct pre declaration so let's
keep going
okay so play worlds in this case play
world this one actually does want to
remain the same so there are a couple in
here that we want to keep probably just
that one fine not too many more what is
this stuff fast we don't have a world
mode yet okay so that's actually fine
too really all we want to do there is we
want to allocate one of these so we just
need to say that this is going to do a
like a exactly analogous to the other
thing we were doing here
so when we start out to play a world
inside
what could I not get to my handmade
cutscene we wanted to the exact same
thing we were doing before right for
play world we want to do set the game
mode to game mode world that clears this
out then we want to do a game mode world
world mode close game world right like
that and then we want to allocate
basically all the rest of the stuff that
we can get right so that that's totally
fine
right so let's see crown shunk updating
and ground chunk rendering for the world
I'm not sure how exactly we want to
handle that stuff I guess we just passed
the translate in I'm not sure I'm not
sure what we want to do there
I can leave the ground chunk stuff in
there because it does seem relevant so
maybe this stuff does want to be there
yeah I don't know let's let's try it for
now we'll see I'm not sure what I think
of it but we'll see so if I wanted to
leave that in here let's just we'll just
drop it in there and see what happens
probably fine possibly fine I don't know
all right
so chunk diamond meters is not a member
of game-mode worlds that's probably true
I agree with that
that is actually it's game mode worlds
that is also yeah okay
so this should be world mode world world
mode world probably should dereference
those seems like a pretty long pointer
shame to crawl for no apparent reason
but doesn't really matter at this point
so let's see get rid of it meant from
identifiers are not found so does that
mean assets has not been specified quite
yet I guess that's what that means let's
take a look here maybe move that a
little bit lower no asset has been oh no
it hasn't been nevermind there we go in
fact asset should probably be quite a
bit further up shouldn't asset be like
more like there yeah okay so let's see
fill ground chunk cannot convert to from
game mode world game state
what does fill ground chunk expect
I suspect a game state but why does it
need a game state do we know feel like
this could be a game mode world right
and I feel like that's probably actually
better because that also reduces that
like sort of long dependency chain there
as well so then we would just do okay
world mode world mode and this is
game-mode world goals mode and I'm
pretty much out of time but oh well so
this stuff is now what we would have to
sort of concentrate on a little bit more
I'm gonna go past it just a bit just to
make sure what's going on here
so please sound I'm gonna not worry
about the sound stuff for right now so
I'm actually just gonna go ahead and and
comment those out because I don't care
about sound at the moment and let's see
teasing a petition we don't care about
that at the moment either if I'm gonna
leave it in there just in case we want
it later
let's see controlled Heroes subscrip
and let's see initialize audio State in
game update and render so we initialize
the audio state we would want to do that
I guess before we do the mode arena so I
don't know why we set it up that way
that's kind of a little bit weird it
seems like we would rather do something
in fact how is that doing what it's
doing I don't really know I don't really
know what that's doing I feel like that
wants to be in its phone arena
I feel like this wants in fact to be
honest with you I feel like all this
stuff wants to be done in a way that's a
little bit more should I put it I feel
like all this stuff wants to be done in
a way that's a little bit more systemic
than what is being done at the moment I
feel like what I would rather do right
is do something like this
this is the total arena you know and it
just says like okay I'm gonna initialize
the total arena and that's gonna do this
and that way I can just do like okay you
know I might want different arenas for
different things so I do okay let's say
there's a sub arena that's gonna be for
the audio something like that and to be
honest I don't really remember how the
audio stuff works I assume it just keeps
a pointer to the arena it's using yeah
that's what it does so I'm just gonna
say okay there's sub arena you know and
we give that a megabyte to work with or
something like that however much we
decide we want audio state space to take
so there's gonna be something like this
it would be from the total arena and
then we would do the same thing with
with our game the mode arena right so
the mode arena which is gonna hold the
rest of this stuff that would just take
the rest something like that then we
initialize we pass the audio arena like
so and all would be good now the only
problem is this guy's got to stay around
so we need this thing to be in here
although really what we probably get to
do is have the audio state itself
allocate that I'm doing too much cleanup
at once not really amenable to an hour
stream but when I get into my head that
I'm putting something up I like want to
clean it all up that's just the nature
of how I tend to code so it's hard to
leave things as messy as I have to leave
them on the stream sometimes a lot of
times most times you might even say but
that's just that's just the nature of
how the show has to go so anyway I'm
going to do like to do move this into
the memory it's just the audio system
proper and we'll try to do its own the
time okay so let's see we've got the
audio arena
and we made that one we've got the yet
remaining arena size remaining total
arena go Ashley I'll just say play the
intro cutscene that looks a little bit
better to me it's certainly a much
thinner than it was skipping control of
heroes again and just finishing up the
rest of this the audio arena is now in
the king of states we don't need this
pointer at all anymore do we
is that even what is that even doing
nothing that goes away and then we have
again just that control with the delete
entities update and render world
transient state connect where everyone
from game state to game mode world so
that would just be world mode this I
believe and yeah so now I think we're
pretty much all good and this is just
the only part that we haven't done yet
so that should leave us at a reasonable
stopping point I think I'm not sure I'm
irate about that I don't know if I
actually am yeah yeah and then what's
this complaining about controlled eros
is not a member of game-mode worlds
that's true that it's not and so that
also probably has to be nerfed for the
moment okay so that's all good
Kiros exists and quit requested so this
can be if there doubt and so now we're
at least a little bit cleaner but we're
not quite done yet
but we'll have to hold off for tomorrow
cuz I'm just about out of time I just
want to make sure that everything's
still running okay which it is but now
we will not get any launching of the
game and so that's what we'll do
tomorrow to sort of finish up that
cleanup and then I think we'll be in
pretty good shape
alright so the probably be hard to do
Q&amp;A because we haven't quite finished
yet but if you do have a question
specifically that's something that we
just did we still have about seven
minutes for questions so I'll try to
take a few quick ones
or not could just not have any questions
that works too
actually how did the memorias work at
the moment memory Riina's are just
blocks of memory which gets sub
allocated out so they are kind of just
like you you take a giant block of
memory you start at the beginning and
every time someone wants something just
put it to be put it wherever the next
slot is to fill it in that's all they do
at the moment
2:38 well since no one's asking have you
heard about AMD open sourcing a lot of
their GPU stuff I have not although
that's probably a very good idea for
them because traditionally the biggest
problem with AMD has been driver like
inability to get their drivers story
together so having more eyes on that
problem probably good if that's what
we're talking about but don't really
know if that's what you're talking about
because I haven't seen thing you're
referring to
excellent - the world wanted changing be
prefetched like the cutscenes changing
yes potentially and that is one of the
reasons that I said that the the
clearing the mode when you set the mode
may not be how I leave it eventually I
may have it so that you create a new
mode before you actually switch to it
and can have them hanging around for
longer there's also some other reasons
to do that like if you want to crossfade
between them or do stuff like that so
that may happen but you got to do it you
got to get at least to the part where
they're partition first elleven so if i
metagame do you mean the pregame stuff
yes just anything that's not the actual
playing of the game directly is like the
metagame the happy pumpkin hi I just
finished my first semester computer
science in school just learned some
basic Java but it's wondering and if you
have any tips moving forward also you
know of any colleges that have good
computer science departments I'm sorry I
don't really know much about
school-based computer science it's not
something I have a lot of experience
with my tips going forward is usually
that you want to spend as much time
doing your own kind of programming as
you can and if you're just in game
programming then you probably don't
really want to be programming Java
because people don't generally play up
program games in Java you want to learn
C C++ because that's that tends to be
more the standard language
if we're sorry so slow night the chatter
upped it into a flame were over the
execution of opportunities and games
okay
or exclusion is option menus and games
very well that is always fine to flame
war culver fly wonder if there's took
reason you put the three game modes
trucks into a union just because I know
I only have one at a time that's it
Elvin so I have this generic USB
controller that's not being detected by
X input any ideas how to go about
detecting it use direct input or try to
use an Xbox controller emulator or
something well you know if if you just
want to get access to it yeah you could
try direct input if directed but doesn't
work you could also try raw input and
try to access it as an HID device but
that requires you to do a bunch of extra
parsing so you know that's certainly a
harder harder route to go
alright looks like no more cue colons
alright alright thank you everyone for
joining me for another episode of hand
made hero it's been electric coding with
you as always if you would like to
follow along at home you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero org
and it comes with a source code as we
develop it so you can follow along with
the series if you're trying to learn
programming that's always an easy thing
to do we also have a forum site where
you can ask questions and check out an
anti episode guide maintained by the
community we have a patreon page you can
pledge to if you want support the video
series and we have a tweet bot that will
tweet the schedule you're trying to
catch the series live and speaking of
catching it live I'll be back here
tomorrow 5:00 p.m. Pacific Standard Time
if you would like to see me finish the
cleanup we did today and get our mode
switching working a little bit more like
what I would prefer so we'll be doing
that tomorrow hope to see you here until
then I hope you guys have fun
programming and I will see you on the
Internet take it easy everyone