alright hello everyone and welcome to
hand made here oh sure we could a
complete game live on stream we decided
on taking absolutely ludicrous paths to
lighting yesterday because I I guess
because I was feeling saucy and so yeah
we are going to go in a ridiculous ride
and probably it won't work because most
the time when you try to do something
with rendering that's kind of weird and
experimental it doesn't work but that's
just the way it goes and like I said
yesterday we already had I had a success
with the Deaf feeling I suppose about
that worked out really great actually
and I'm super happy with it so why not
press our luck why not roll the dice
place yeah probably it's not going to
come up with you know double sixes every
time but you know you can't win them all
but you certainly not going to win if
you never roll so let's go ahead and and
get started because there's nothing to
talk about we talked about it yesterday
it's the the the die has been cast so to
speak I suppose we just don't know what
it's going to be coming up as so today's
day 394 you're going to want start on
289 3 for the source code if you're
following along with the code at home so
let's go ahead and open up the open up
the project here oops
that's not I still handmade that
sykesville handmade and I'm going to go
ahead and just run exterior at and we'll
talk about what our first steps are
going to be so right now we have a
simple directional light source attached
to the main character here that I can
move around right so ignore the main
fact that the main character is moving
around
we're just care about the little light
source is moving around right and so
what we're going to try to do like I
said is we're trying to put in a real
more global illumination scheme right so
I want lighting that has some work
characteristics of real light than a
simple directional point light that's
direction what I was good point light is
not directional then a simple point
light scheme we're not in this path
trying to improve the quality of surface
response room
that's kind of two big parts of lighting
that you want to think about one is
surface response and that's how much a
surface can represent like real-world
surfaces or you know different
properties of real-world surfaces even
trying to be artistic such as how glossy
they are was a very nice atrophic
reflections whether they ship the
reflections whether they have oily
finish whether they produce like the
rainbow kind of a hue right from
incoming light those are all properties
of how incoming light is redistributed
on a particular surface for the benefit
of the viewer and that is not what we're
looking at now right that's the
reflectance function and we're not
really looking at that now for this game
we probably won't do much with that it's
not a game that cares about materials
its hand-drawn artwork its cartoony
there's not a lot of room for like
here's my oil finish Chrome mech thing
like it's not that kind of game right
but it is a kind of gamer we're
exploring interesting world and it would
be nice to have interesting lighting so
the part that I'm focusing on now is
like the light transport part of things
right it's the part where light is moved
around the scene and so we could do
something relatively simple which is
just like the light that I've got here
right that I'm moving around where we
just have a bunch of those and that
wouldn't be too hard for us to do but
that produces kind of relatively hard
edge stuff as you can see and isn't
necessarily the kind of look that I want
it's more of the flashlight in a dark
room kind of a look they might make more
sense in a horror game not as much sense
in a sort of fun exploration II Zelda
kind of a game it's not it just doesn't
give that I kind of looking for more of
the soft you know redistributed light
kind of look and so it's the lighting
transport that we're really looking at
now and what we decided to do was the
harebrained scheme where basically I'm
going to essentially treat it like a
multi grid solver multi grid solvers are
not traditionally used for lighting as
far as I know they're traditionally used
for fluid dynamics and the way they work
is they try to
treat things sort of like admit map if
you imagine that it's very expensive to
get large-scale things to happen over a
grid that's very fine so for example if
I'm trying to compute the lighting at
every pixel computing that could be very
expensive so what if I just do a mipmap
process where I look at successively
smaller versions of the lighting all the
way up to like a single pixel
encompassing the whole screen compute
the lighting progressively from there
down and spread out the results so that
at every stage I'm just computing some
little local lighting but I spread out
large effects by having that NIT pyramid
do sort of the works the reason I think
it's a harebrained scheme and I really
have no idea whether it's going to work
is because light is not a fluid and if
there are theoretical physicists on the
stream I apologize for saying that
because for all I know like is a fluid I
certainly don't want to pretend that I
understand quantum dynamics or quantum
mechanics I suppose I should say I don't
however what I mean to say is the
lighting transport problem as we
typically look at in computer graphics
is not a fluid simulation the reason
it's not a fluid simulation is because
typically the participating media is
just not there you're talking about
light traveling long distances in a
straight line and you really don't have
this sort of situation where you need to
sort of diffuse energy the way that a
fluid does where fluid is only really
interacting with the fluid directly next
to it so it's a harebrained scheme Multi
grids not really a great fit for it
however one of the things that is true
in general about lighting is that
nothing is a good fit for it it is a
problem that defies any good solution
Monte Carlo methods were pretty much the
only thing used at the high end for
accuracy and they are incredibly slow so
it's not like we're issuing some a
really fantastic perfect scheme that
produces fantastic lighting in a short
amount of time that doesn't exist so we
are just looking for something that
gives us an interesting artistically
pleasing result
that bears some resemblance to how light
actually works that's all we really want
and so it's something that I think would
be fun to try few minutes all right so
there's two halves to this problem that
we have to solve one of them is
incredibly easy one of them is more
difficult the one that's incredibly easy
is we have to get our lighting
information down to the render in the
first place because up until now we have
not had lighting so there's no point in
telling it whether things are lit up
since nothing could light up we are now
going to have the ability for everything
in the game to be lit if we want and
when I say everything I mean literally
everything
if this scheme works anything in the
game could be emitting light no matter
what shape it is even so things like the
entire cubes that the hero is standing
on right now could be lit up itself and
that would actually spread light around
to the world that would be awesome don't
get your hopes up again harebrained
scheme probably not going to work so
with that in mind that is one half of
the problem I think I hope I'm not sure
probably I don't know we can't ignore
that part of the problem for now because
all we really need is one light source
to start practicing with to get the rest
of the team working and I suspect that
will be the easier way to deal with it
because that way we can isolate the
transfer problem we're having to get
lighting information out of our depth
field passes will presumably be more
difficult than just writing it directly
into a buffer with its own separate path
that we can verify so what I think I'm
going to do first is take this point
light source that we've got here and
renders that into the system to start
with as its own separate completely
one-off path that feeds the lighting for
the lighting path and the reason I want
to do that again is because I want to
take the rendering of the depth peels
into the light buffer out of the
equation first because I feel like we
could easily have bugs and bats that
would lead us to believe the other part
isn't working so let's get the other
part working as
we can first with lights that we specify
mechanically and precisely so that we
can set them to someplace that we know
with the color that we know in a very
acidic way we can look at the bitmap and
see that there is one light in the place
we expect it to be at the start and then
we can look at each successive
resolution of our multi grid up through
the upward propagation and then the
downward propagation to figure out
whether what we're doing makes any sense
at all or whether it's just dumb right
okay and so the second part of that that
we have to deal with is the fact that we
got we're going to need normals in in
this situation as well and so that's a
little bit harder to come by but what we
can do is assume that everything is
pointing upwards at the beginning and
just do the light transport with a flat
surface and then work our way up to
light transport with something else so
we have a lot of options here we'll do
the best we can we don't know whether
they'll work out okay but we're you know
like I said we're going to take it one
step at a time and we'll see what we can
do all right so let's get started at the
end of last screen we already created
some scratch base for this stuff to
occur and that was the thing called a
light buffer and what we did in the
light buffer is we made a structure that
would contain the things that we
actually need so we have 2 frame buffers
here right I don't know why this is not
called frame buffer it should be so
let's go ahead and change that there we
go so we've got two frame buffers here
these frame buffers are not representing
different information they're
representing effectively the same
informations their only difference is
they're representing different right
styles so one of the things that happens
in OpenGL and it's really annoying and
stupid but it's just the way that
graphics cards work and they have to do
it for validation purposes because don't
have every direction it's a long story
we don't need to go into right now but
just the way things are is that you
can't just point something at a texture
and say that's what I'm drawing to
instead you have to create this object
that sort of swapped textures into it
and then gets validated and so what that
means is for every combination
textures we might want to write - we
have to create a corresponding frame
buffer object and lock it down if we
don't we run the risk of paying a
extremely high upfront cost every time
we switch to that writing scheme since
we know that every time through the
light buffer we will only have two
different lighting schemes we just
create a frame buffer for each of them
so that the validation process can
happen once and never again that keeps
us from having that hiccup so that's why
we've got these two so the right --oil
frame buffer is the frame buffer that
writes to these four at the same time so
there's a frame buffer that has these
four as color buffers which means that
as we write in the shader we can
actually omit one thing to each of them
the point of that is on the upward
process where we gather our lighting up
and we successively swish it down to
smaller and smaller resolution texture
Maps to do bigger and bigger transfers
we want to be able to average all of
those together at once a lot of take
basically a set of four pixels smoosh
them together and write out one pixel in
the lower res map every time we take
that sampling down one step so that's
really what that is for what the write
all frame buffer is the upward sampling
process which is producing coarser and
coarser averaged versions of the
lighting the right emit frame buffer is
the way down so once we have that we
know that the surface colors at any
point and the the XY of the the
direction and the depth at which the the
lighting surface is being considered for
any particular point those are not going
to change any more because we were
producing them whole cloth on the way up
because remember we basically start with
empty textures all the way in our mid
period except for the base level which
is the one that initially as the
lighting written into it so what we need
to do from there is condense those and
creates the new ones that's where
writing everything on the way down we
don't need to touch the surface color or
the position or direction of the surface
elements because that's just known and
it doesn't change the reflectance
properties of a surface aren't going to
change right they're just known now so
now we've built the mid pyramid it's
done what's going to change is the light
transport so what we do on each step
down the pyramid is we take a look
what the emitters are nearby and we add
in light to the front and back of the
particular element that we are
considering at the next level down right
and more specifically we do it for a
couple different ones of them right and
so that in that in-and-out process like
I said because it's writing very
different things we create tube frame
buffers because we don't want to blow a
bunch of rights on the way down for no
reason because remember we're going to
want to optimize this eventually we're
going to want to make sure that we're
not spending about two bandwidth
unnecessarily and if we just wrote the
surface color texture in the NP flex
again or even just flushed zeros out to
them it's just bandwidth we don't need
to spend because those textures only
need to be read from they don't need to
be written to at all and so that's a
really important part of the process to
understand okay and also I should
mention whether things it actually also
gives us a feature that we might want
which is that the surface color texture
and the NP texture for the lower level
version is actually something that we
could read from in the same stage right
and that's a sort of thing that I don't
actually know yet it may be that we
actually need two more textures in here
right we may need an emit up in and emit
down and the reason is because we need
to read from different ones that we
write to potentially and so that I just
don't know yet I'm not sure if I think
we might and we'll see when we write the
code it'll be obvious but the reason
that I say that just to be clear is the
way that this thing is going to work is
essentially you can imagine
looking at at these bitmaps right so
here we've got a two by two and here
we've got a four by four so in any
particular stage of this algorithm we're
going to be looking at two by twos that
expand to four by fours more or less
right and what we're going to be doing
to it you know you got to kind of think
of it I suppose as being a whole grid as
well but what we're going to do is we're
going to say something like well we need
to update the lighting information for
this cell right and maybe what I should
have done is said we're going to update
the letting information for this cell
right and in order to do that we would
say well what's the bilinear sample that
takes place like right here because
that's where that cell Maps to in the
upper level bitmap right and so in order
to do that we're going to look at these
four cells worth of lighting and compute
a lighting adjustment for this but it's
delighting adjustment right that's the
important part it's going to adjust the
lighting at that point it's not going to
overwrite it completely it's going to do
a plus or minus at least that's my
assumption we'll see when we talk
experimenting so what we can do is we
could write an add to it and if it's
floating-point and supports
floating-point add in as a blend mode
then we would be able to just let that
happen but if it doesn't support that if
it doesn't support floating-point add is
a blend mode which I don't know how many
cards do then we need to read from this
texture to figure out was there in the
first place so we can do the add and
then write the results out if that's the
case we really can't read from and write
to the same texture in the same pass
right that's not allowed that's why we
have a blending unit if you could if you
could read and write from one texture in
the same pass you wouldn't need a
blending unit right there'd be no such
thing as blending because if you wanted
to blend with the result you just set
the destination buffer as one of your
input textures it's a much cleaner way
to do it much more powerful problem is
it's much more
because now everything has to be
serialized so that's why we have a
blending unit so if the blending unit
supports add great I think we're good to
go
if the blending units doesn't support
add I think we're going to have done a
separate texture that we write to so
basically this right here would be you
know vo you and you know final front
commit or something right I don't know
but it would go down in that way so
again not a problem at all we don't care
about that because it doesn't increase
our bandwidth much at all because again
we're not reading and writing from
another set of bitmaps what we're doing
is substituting one of the places we
were writing to with a different thing
so while it could affect the cache a
little bit since these are passes I
don't think it would cut the tummy out
of the cache by then I don't know maybe
the top of apartment they wouldn't be
much hard today so chances are this
wouldn't affect us too much but again
you never really know obviously if we
can do it with less sex ratio we should
because it can't hurt but again like I
say it could be the case that we need to
add in there I'm not going to turn about
that it's it's not as bad as having to
add more that we're actually using at
the same time because that's the thing
that we really want to try and keep down
because we're already pretty high here
with 4 textures at the same time it's a
lot of textures to write to at the same
time and keep in mind it's going to go
it's going to get worse
those four textures could expand to 8
textures or 16 textures eventually
depending on how we choose to view the
Deaf feeling if we choose to smush the
depth going down into a volume texture
so or a texture array where we just have
one texture that has three levels that's
probably the smartest way to go and
that's probably how I'll try to go and
the max case it'll always just before we
won't have to worry about it but if we
choose to have those be separate
textures that becomes a little bit more
complicated the reason it goes a little
bit more complicated cuz at that point
we've got a lot of texture handle
sitting around 16 is the maximum we
could probably expect to use we would be
using that maximum that doesn't thrill
me right I don't like to be up as a
maximum number for anything if you can
avoid it but you know if we have two
reactors
my suspicion would be yet these will
probably expand to volume textures or
texture arrays probably they don't
really need to be volume textures for
any particular reason
in the sense that we don't need to look
them up by arbitrary UVW what we really
just need to be able to pick 0 1 &amp; 2 or
3 we're going to read from each of the
frame successfully so texture array
would be fine for our purposes alright
so anyway here we go let's let's get
started we know what we need to do it's
just going to be a bit of a grind to do
it and again it'd be pretty easy to just
write this code but in GPU land it's
going to it's going to take a bunch of
gyration and happy dances and weird
shaders and all this other sorts of
thing
so ok let's start off by creating a very
simple process what we want to do here
is create a shader that's going to write
a light source into the base level map
of one of these maps so that and then
draw that to the street so we just want
to dress this case we could see it so
that we know what it's doing because if
we can't see these things we're never
going to know if they're working right
so what I want to do is I want to be
able to look through those different
parts of the map so in addition to that
what I'm also going to do is I'm going
to do something up here we're going to
have a totally nutso crazy situation
where inside the OpenGL renderer I'm
going to let us pick out what we want to
view so that we can view each level of
those texture Maps in series as we go so
what you can see here is at the end we
kind of have this thing that we were
using before where we were like here's a
blip frame buffer right we want to look
at what's in this this frame buffer here
right so what I'm going to do is I'm
essentially just going to hijack this
code and turn it back on so that we can
view our frame buffers directly at the
end looking at exactly what they look
like right and I don't really remember
if this does a stretch but I believe it
does I don't know that we really want
the stretch to be changing our pixel
values so what I'm going to do is I'm
going to set it to nearest neighbor
sampling
so that we can actually see the big ol
pixels because for this we really want
to know exactly what's getting written
we're not looking to produce a visually
pleasing image right now we're looking
to do is verify results and so I don't
want any adulteration of the pixel
values I know exactly what they are so
then what I'm going to do here is we're
going to say well we've got a light
buffer right and we've got four things
in the light buffer right we've got the
front the back the surface and the NP
text right so what I want to do here is
I want to basically blitt those various
things to the screen separately and I
guess now I look about look at it maybe
I don't really want to use the frame
buffer buffer because that would only
allow me to display one thing it is time
right because I can't I can't blit I
mean what much the same other time we
only allow me display the color buffer
zero right I don't know if GL it's flame
buffer allows me to go from one frame
buffer to the from one attachment to the
other let's take a look if it does if it
does then I'll use it if it doesn't I'm
going to use an actual texture fill
because then I could pick out whichever
texture I want which is what I'd rather
be able to do so let's take a look here
at GL frame buffer and let's take a look
at what it's going on so dip my eyes
we're close okay color buffer bit say
which one it does
it does not seem to it does not seem to
it all let's see what happens if I say
[Applause]
I'm just curious if anyone discusses
this
so you can do it it looks like okay so
we can actually pick out anyone we want
so that seems fine to me
I'm fine with that so all I really need
to do is keep that bleeding and what I
can do here is insert a GL Reid buffer
call where DL color attachment right
gets added
[Applause]
you know something can add to that where
we pick out which one we want so what I
want to do curious when we're viewing
these I want to basically be able to say
okay buying the frame buffer whatever
the the light buffers that we want here
call that buff index and I want to go
ahead and get the right all frame buffer
because that's got all four of them in
it right and what I want to do there is
say okay I'm going to read from the
right all frame buffer for whatever
light buffer we chose I'm going to read
out of it whichever index you know one
through four zero through three here
we're going to set the viewport to be
whatever the viewport actually is that
we can see and then we're going to blitz
eyes of that buffer was now
unfortunately figuring out what the size
of that buffer was it's actually a
little bit annoying what I might do here
is just store those values right so if I
wanted to know how big each light buffer
is that's actually kind of annoying to
figure out because it's a successively
sample of thing so when you're on the
ends one you have to be tracking what
the original size wills and all these
other sorts of things so instead of that
what I'd rather do I guess is just have
it so that we say like okay you know
which one of these are beyond
[Applause]
which which one the buffers and then
what I'll do is I'll just say well we'll
look up what it's with is in the buffer
itself and I'll tell it I so what I can
do there is say like hey let's go ahead
and record that when we're actually
initializing so in here we obviously
know it here right because we've got the
text within the TEC type that we've
computed by using the sort of successive
divide process so what I want to do here
is say okay the text with oops the text
within text types will be stored so
those will now be known then what we do
is we can do this lit and that will give
us a full-screen view of what the buffer
looks like whichever one we pick and so
for the moment I'll just set them both
to zero and so when we run this we
should just get a black screen right
because even though we're rendering the
game right and you know if I if I were
to make this in a zero the game would
just render immediately after rendering
the image of the game we're going to
just blow right over it just overwrite
it with whatever is in that buffer so
now when I write to that buffer I'll be
able to see what is there right I'll be
able to see what's actually going on so
one thing I'm not sure about again I am
assuming that she'll flip frame buffer
will do the right thing and convert
floating point to 8-bit I'm assuming if
it doesn't we have a problem we're about
to see whether we have a problem
so off we go so let's start again let's
start simple we need to start by
stuffing the stream buffer and so what
I'll do is I'll just make up some dummy
things here I don't
want to be on that side of screen
because my head's in the way let's start
must be over here what I want to do is I
want to have some functions that I can
use to get this leg started so probably
what's going to happen right is we're
going to draw a bunch of stuff to the
lighting like the lighting prep will
happen so let's do fake you know fake
ski lighting or something
so we'll see the lighting with something
completely arbitrary like one little
light source and we'll let that happen
then we will go ahead and run the actual
by the equation so then we'll actually
do like a light transport or compute
light transport and again all that has
to do is just operate on the light
buffers so the lighting happens entirely
in these buffers nothing else has to
occur at all so we're kind of okay at
that point everything happens in there
then we'll draw one of the buffers out
right
so our job is to write these two things
so let's write them your sake speed
lighting fish if you'd like transport
and compute light transport is just
going to be like
I assume it's harebrained like the
rabbit or is it harebrained like the
follicle who knows so this we don't care
about just yet because before we can do
any language France where we have some
lighting in the buffer to begin with so
what I want to do here is I want to do
fake seed lighting to put something into
the lowest-level buffer buff hero to
seed it out right so I want to fill the
world with a
fake version of lighting that we can
play with right or do that I'm going to
write a shader that shader is going to
try to write to those four textures and
it's going to write some procedural
geometry that we make up in the shader
out to those things right and again the
whole point of doing this is because I
want to isolate these processes because
I'm anticipating having to do a lot of
work to get this lighting to behave
correctly and I don't want to worry
about the transfer of things yet because
that will just give me this huge
complexity at the beginning I don't need
I want to be able to make a shader that
just produces something simple like a
sphere right and check out how that
well-understood thing is behaving with
the lighting before I try to go okay now
we've got the actual handmade hero
geometry coming from death feels and I
was above a lot a lot right so nice 2d
simple letting transport nothing weird
happening first and then move it up
alright so this is going to be something
like this right in order to do the fake
seed lighting we actually don't need any
active texture units so we're just going
to do like a fake feed lighting you
begin and program thing and we'll go
write that program right that's printer
we have to write in terms of what we
want to draw it's basically the same as
this stuff right here right there's
really nothing else to it in fact you
could argue that we could just pull this
out entirely in fact let's do that
[Applause]
not a great name but this is what I want
to be right so it would basically be you
give it a frame buffer handle and then
you give it a width and height and it
would just take it from there right and
then you know when you come back you're
all good so I think we probably want to
do like begin screen fill maybe any
screen fill something like this because
this has to get in there as well
[Applause]
young Sam so let's take this out for one
hot second just a hot little second and
we do open jail be on screen fill em
screen fill I I'll just test it out with
what we're currently doing to make sure
it still works
[Applause]
so that's good and then 15 lighting can
do the exact same thing so we're going
to pretty much only write in the fake
seed lighting we're only going to write
to the base level because everything
else we filled in by the lighting
transport process so we really only need
to write to that bottom buffer that's
the only one that we're going to write
to so in order to make that work we just
need to pick out which one of these
we're going to use we want to write
everything so we're going to call it the
right all frame buffer at this point the
width and height are specified inside
the buffer itself so those are not a
mystery so that's pretty much everything
that we need to do there now again what
I'm going to do here is I've turned off
a call to that because I want to make
sure that that code still works and it
looks fine so that's good and so now we
can turn it back on okay so this is all
we really need to do
I'm confused first authors I'm like that
wallet X I kind of think maybe it needs
to be a little clearer there we go
I'm like what am I looking at there we
go
so all we really want is this GL drawer
is here that's all we really want and so
in this case I suppose it could probably
do that because we don't really have
anything else to look for but so that's
all we need to do to fill the screen
with something and so all we need now is
we need to actually write an all I guess
since this is a lot of work but yes all
we need to do now is have an actual
shader that will write something into
this geometry another is going to be fun
because we got to go look up the GLSL
but I never remember for outputting to
successive render buffers I don't
remember how it corresponds output
colors to output textures to color
attachment I can't remember whether you
need to use this exact array or whether
it just lines them up in the orders are
declared being GLSL is something weird
as always but we just need to go look up
what it is and then we should good
alright so moving long before we do any
of that of course we have to actually
create something to compile our texture
so let's go hunt for some texture stuff
here we probably want something like our
multi sample resolve because the multi
sample resolve I think yeah as you can
see it's the kind of thing we want
that's just based on the text board
doesn't take much in so let's just grab
this multi sample resolve program and
let's go ahead and make ourselves a new
version of that somewhere here there we
go okay so we want this to be compiled
fake ease lighting and this is going to
be
you're the key lighting program and the
yeah I don't know that we have any
defines at this point that go in here
because it doesn't use any of this stuff
that you would normally need it's kind
of just the version number that's it the
vertex shader does nothing as always and
so in this case for the fragment code it
wouldn't be sampling from anything at
all it wouldn't have any defines or
anything so we're literally just looking
at just the basics here like so so what
I'm going to do here is just try to
figure how to write something to each of
these buffers right and what I'd like to
do is essentially do something like this
[Applause]
I'd like to make sure that each buffer
is getting targeted as I expect so what
I would like to do is something like
that corresponds here so we say okay
there's the front emit vacum eight
[Applause]
surface color MP text right I would like
each of these to be writable and I would
like to write something to them that I
can identify so this is just structured
artwork folks right it's just saying hey
I want to know that I'm targeting each
of these bitmaps properly so I'm just
going to output red green blue and
yellow to each bitmap so it's filled
with that color
that way we can then verify that
released writing to the buffers we think
we're writing to basic basic basic stuff
for step one and again what we'll have
to do here is go look up the GLSL a
protocol for targeting multiple color
attachments we've not done that yet on
handmade 0 and obviously we need to do
that
and I don't remember what it was so
that's all we should need there are no
variables to this shader at all because
it's just creating geometry from whole
cloth we probably will want to specify
the light so I am going to go ahead and
copy the the lighting stuff out of the
depth feel sampler because we want this
debug light P we want to specify the
debug light P because that way we can
move the light around we're not going to
anything with that just yet but we will
eventually so I'm going to in here I'm
going to have a uniform vector II light
P and that is just B where the light is
right again only reason for that is so
it'll move around with the hero
so once we've gotten that going now we
can compile the fake C lighting the fake
Steve lighting program again doesn't
really have very much in it it's pretty
straightforward I'm going to go ahead
and cut this out here I'll put that in
there so this is just a speed lighting
and all its going to have just the debug
light P that's that's it pretty boring
and so then down here we've got that
actual 1 6 seed lighting take the
lighting and when we actually compile
our of our programs right here we also I
think freelee's at the top here let's
see 1 2 3 4 5 6 get we've got all those
guys in there and that's it okay so that
should actually compile the lighting and
so now the only thing we need to do is
actually use that program we're already
calling use program with it so then we
just need a thing that does use program
to bind that one variable so when we
look at this guy that should be
basically everything there is so I think
we just need to pass that set up to it
and that should be all there is I think
we need to keep that light P around
though which makes it a little bit
trickier because this is happening kind
of in a debug location but that's okay
that won't be too bad so looking at that
again we can just delete all of this
because that's not human used to be
there so now we do use program begin
here what we need to do is have some way
of passing that render setup down now
what we can do in the meantime is just
capture it out of the render texture
quads like the first one so you know
here where we do setup that we could say
if not debug setup we could just say to
basic setup people set up to do KC
remove this and then all we need to do
is just cache this and so this is just
taking the first one right I don't
remember what this is defined as just
render setup so you can see there I've
got this debug step thing I'm going to
set it to zero initially I'm going to go
and set it when we see the first one and
then at the end I'm just going to use
that right that's the one that I'm going
to use I'm going to check to make sure
that we've got one of those and if we
don't have one of those then we're not
going to do anything but that's about it
so let's see what should I did I not do
that probably left to find the biased
program there we are and succeed
lighting
[Applause]
we go so in theory that will run the
safety lighting program in theory it
will have access to the big light and in
theory it will show us one of the
buffers now what we're seeing here is
actually already kind of interesting to
me I don't know if it's interesting to
you but we see green screen what's
interesting about a green screen is if
we're looking at the first texture right
remember what happened when we created
these so when if we if we look back and
maybe it maybe I'll put it up on this
one so when we do our open gel in it I'm
not sorry not our children are changed
to settings when we do our settings
change you can see we create these
favorite prints we attach you know
attachment 0 1 2 3 and you can see like
front emit text is the first one all
right
and so if I go down here and I look at
our fake scene lighting program you can
see that front emit is the first thing
we write to but we wrote read yet when
we mu frame buffer zero texture 0 that's
not what we see we see the back emit
which is actually color attachment one
right so I'm going to just double check
that we're actually picking out the read
buffer properly but I think we are the
other thing I need to probably do is
make sure we restore that read buffer in
case anyone else was camp we're counting
on it but yeah
so I think what that suggests to me is
again that there's probably some
protocol we have to look up in jail so
I'll tell it where to write to because
it's not just writing them in the order
that they were declared right which I'm
not suggesting that it should that's not
like something it should be doing
anything I would just said if it did do
that we wouldn't just be red not green
coming into that first texture unless
there's some other bug somewhere else
right in the program which there might
be all right so here we go
GLSL and up with reference card for the
benefit of folks at home let's go ahead
and zoom in on that and so what we want
to do here is we want to go down to the
OpenGL shading language 1.5 which is
what we were currently using I believe
and see if there's a way to target
multiple outputs from it hopefully there
are hopefully we won't have to bump the
shader version to do that so taking a
look here you can see we've got in our
fragment language right there's an out
float for the Frog depth there is no out
float anywhere for the color or out Veck
4 for the color I so I'm not sure
exactly again but this is going to tell
us what we want to know right I don't
see anything here to me I don't see
anything here that suggests what goes
where so I think that should probably
Drive us over to the spec I don't want
this one because that's a little bit too
late where is the spec page
here there it is so we want probably
open jail 3.2 shading language 1.5 there
it is and so when we look at this what I
want what I'm trying to get to as
quickly as possible is just something
that tells me how to line up my output
fragments with the bound color
attachments for the frame buffer and so
I don't know where that's going to be
exactly in here but we can take a scan
to the table of contents and see it's
really just a no groups so just an
overview
[Applause]
okay
I guess one question is can we write to
more than one at once
maybe we can which would be bad first
years everybody's the open-celled
pipeline is the built-in residual side
killer Friday almost discard oh well
this suggests that it was old that was
already deprecated so if it's already
been deprecated that there must be a way
to do it in this new language so what's
the new way pray tell let's yell farken
of FK is the preferred you simply
declare these outputs in the fragment
shader using the out storage qualifier
does that mean I just declare one of
those writing to GL fragment at n
specifies the fragment data that will be
used by the sub config function pipeline
for data n that's all I really want
so can I do that Wow typing it's hard
let's go shopping
[Applause]
alright so what we need to do here is
just say at the end of our situation
nope here are our buffers we are writing
to them 1 2 3 we've got front emit
vacuum it surface color empty tag and
we'll see if the shader compiler likes
it or if it thinks too bad
hey looks like that worked so now what
I'd like to do is now that it sort of
looks like we're writing to our frame
buffers properly each of those kind of
getting the value that we expect what
I'd like to do is actually double verify
that and of course we're going to need
this for the next step which is actually
doing something real with the fake
lighting real sake letting
is I want to be able to interactively
toggle between which one of the things
I'm viewing right so I want to be able
to both step up and down the myth chain
and I want to be able to change which
texture I'm looking at the the front
back surface emitting you know whatever
kind of things so I'm just going to hack
in something to the open jail here that
allows me to do that because normally
the open gel layer doesn't really have
any notion of that and the external code
has a new way of poking at that but I'm
going to let it I'm going to let it poke
at that so what I'm going to do there is
just say like okay let's suppose that
our lighting buffer maybe this is
something that can be edited in the the
current settings or something like this
so maybe in the platform layer right
here's the settings what I could do here
is just say like okay in addition we
could say is like debug light buffer
index and debug light buffered text
concise right and these two could be
something that the OpenGL layer picks up
if they're set to something like so do
we get past the settings here where it's
actually not that way it's actually
command settings right yeah if we should
just do this
[Applause]
all right um yeah just let the compiler
bring you to the correct lines they're
cute so once we've got that set up we
are free now in any part of the code to
push that around right and oh I thought
I should make sure it's clear is it not
cleared first are we not clearing that
let me verify that's actually happened
that looks like that's not a cleared
value yeah that's not a cleared value
apparently why is that not a clear value
dare I ask
so now what I can do is introduce some
debug keys pretty much anywhere I want
they could be in the game that could be
in the platform layer that basically let
me kind of you know swizzle around
between those now the game itself if I
remember correctly doesn't really get
much in the way of debug keys the
platform code if I remember correctly
just gets like what the state of the
controllers are and stuff like this
right I think see here yeah so it
doesn't really get that kind of stuff so
what I'm going to do is I'm just going
to put it in the win32 layer for the
moment I what I'm going to do is just a
like okay where were these
are getting set oh you know what I just
realized that's not a good place to put
it I take it all back the settings are
things that effect the compilation and
that's not appropriate for that purpose
[Applause]
these are compilation values so that's
really not appropriate place to put that
so we really should probably put those
in here okay so now what I want to do is
inside there I want some way of poking
at those values just randomly so what
I'll probably do is say like okay when
we when we access the keyboard here
maybe I'll just give myself some ways to
getting some debug keys and here you can
see we've got some kind of weird stuff
like the loop live code editing still
being taken care of there for example
and so what I want to do is I want to
put some extra ones in here that I could
use to control this so what I'm going to
do is I'm going to say like okay VK code
in this case let me use like plus and
minus I guess and maybe I'll just use
plus and minus with the shift key down
or not
[Applause]
by the way someone routing a bug that
was a good bug to write in that had to
do a sign extension for this gentleman
right here which we do need to fix it's
kind of interesting so I don't want to
fix it yet because I'm pretty sure I put
it on the github but I want to talk
about it let me just make sure that it's
on there I'm pretty sure I put it on
there yeah I want to talk about that one
in more detail so we're not going to fix
it right now we're going to fix it when
we look at that bug because I wanted to
talk about in a little more detail but
what I wanted to do was take a look at
the shift key with them I feel like
that's an L pram that comes in through
WMT down that we can just check let's
find out let's see is that here does not
appear so so I will probably use get key
state then I don't want to get a sync
keyed state and I don't want get key
state actually do I
I just want regular get Tuesday that's
what I'm looking for
thank you so I just want a thing that
tells me whether the this key is down or
not with the return value the higher two
bits one the key is down otherwise it's
up that's the only thing that I really
need to look for it's a short so it's
going to be bit 15 did we do this set
please gate somewhere else yes right
here of course it's behind my head so I
couldn't actually see it but oh well
so if we want to know if shift is down
we can do this I'll put this up at the
top so that anyone can use it here shift
key was down so look at DK shift and
whether one should set up 15 ands with
the properly if it is demonstrate keep
it down
so in here we can just look to see if
the shift keys down so this is the plus
so what I want to do here is say well
the OpenGL layers debug light buffer
index plus equals 1 in this case or
minus equals 1 and the other case I
think I'm probably going to want these
to be s 32 s so that it can wrap
properly and when we come through here
what I'm going to do is say if open jail
give AG light buffer index is less than
0 factor your nose girl just do this
[Applause]
uh hmm I guess clamp 0m is really what
we need here and so we want this to be
something that goes from zero to the
number of life lepers we have and in
this case that is specified in the
actual OpenGL setting itself if I
remember correctly it's just light
buffer count and this it has to be
between zero and three right it actually
should be life over account minus one
that's the maximum value it can be and I
guess in this case we can do this as
well so yeah if I do that clamping here
then we know that those will always stay
within bounds no matter what happens
with the other parts of it right and
then when we grab these out here we grab
out the embassies and use them we can
actually avoid probably ever actually
doing this because we're always going to
be doing it just to pull them out one
time like so so we can probably just do
that and then we just need to write the
clamping function and I think that's the
only thing left to do in this case and
then we can view any level of the
texture and any sub component of it
which is what we need to do for the
debugging purposes all right so let's go
ahead and write this clamp function you
can see right now we've got one for real
values but in this case we want one
that's going to work on s thirty twos
[Applause]
it's the same function you could
probably use a template for this I don't
see any particular reason why it
couldn't or Macra okay
and so in theory now we can like bump
those values so actually I'm just make
sure that I before I'd do that I just
want to look at this one more time
this is not what I want it should
actually look like this anytime you get
the plus key it should add so it should
really just be which one you're looking
at I think I probably want the other way
around actually I probably want it so
that plus and minus moves up and down
the levels of detail and then if you
hold down the shift key then it changes
which texture you're on right I think
that's what I want that looks
surprisingly ineffectual or feel
surprisingly ineffectual I should say
all right so let's take a quick second
to the bug this let me go ahead and run
now what I'm going to do here is I'm
going to hit plus so now I should have
moved to a new frame buffer which means
there should be nothing in the frame
buffer and I shouldn't be getting that
flit right so now if I come through here
and take a look at it I want to see what
the light buffer index is and it's still
zero so something's busted there
all right so if I get the plus key or
the minus key all right so I'm not
actually getting anything there why am I
not getting anything there it's handmade
internal not set for some reason win32
press is pending messages to its message
if we get a key down message it should
come in here if was down is not equal to
is down then we should process these
which should include the P the l equals
oh you know what do I need to use the VK
code for this let me look at the windows
VK codes I'm not sure if maybe you can't
use ASCII code
because it looks like we're coming
through this path we should be coming
through this path okay but it doesn't
look like we're actually getting it
doesn't look like we're ever actually
able to match the VK code of equals or
minus which we should be able to match I
would think just to verify that that's
true I'm going to set it to instead of
plus and minus I'm going to set it to
zero and nine just to see what happens
so yeah so those must just be VK codes
that don't line up with the ascii so
let's see what those actually are we
should be able to do that using like the
test project pretty easily so if i just
go over to who our stupid test project
we made go ahead and plug those hamsters
Visual Studio alright so if I've to VK
underscore I should see well okay there
we go I should eventually see an
autocomplete that shows me all the VK
codes so I would have thought there was
like a VK plus on here or a VK equals
again I don't know if there is see no
maybe not but either way let's say I
pick VK our control and I do go to
definition here is the VK code
definition table you can see it all
happening in here and they don't define
anything that lines up a basket code so
those are gone so it's only like ones
that you have to use specific VK codes
for
but I don't see it on there well I guess
one thing we could do is just see what
the VK code is when it comes through
right I mean that's easy enough so if I
switch back to our other project what is
it now I don't need to save that but
thank you so if I go ahead and just run
the program right here's the program so
and I hit the equals key and so what's
the VK code 187
so what's equals and what's plus so
equal definitely comes through as a high
key code it comes through as 187 all
right let's see are they defined so 187
are they defined in hex oops almost
knocked over my copy there well if it
did knock it over read spill-proof
thankfully so 27 there in hex
though yeah so we are looking for BB as
a value right and so what would that be
so it's V k OE m plus apparently is what
we're looking for and I guess by that by
that logic we're also looking for VK o
am comma I don't ask me why that's just
the way it is I guess that's not what I
wanted so now plus and minus should work
properly it does appear to + shift+ does
not appear to be working properly unless
our output code is busted so let's see
here
debug life left text index I'm going to
go ahead and set a breakpoint there and
see if that is working properly
so let's need to do so that is adding
debug life left text index plus 1 there
it is right and so what I should be able
to do now is go take a look at what
happens in this code the life text index
is 0 the text index is 1 so by setting
the read buffer to GL color attachment 1
we would think we'd be able to read out
of that buffer and blit it but it
doesn't look like we are because we're
just getting a black screen now what we
don't know is we don't know who is at
fault here right we don't know whether
the
is failing to target the correct texture
or whether the right is failing to
target the correct texture right we have
no idea which of those two things is
true so if I go over to our OpenGL code
again at least we know we're picking out
the right thing so if I go over here and
I want to take a look at what we've you
know what we're actually doing for our
right eye I don't see a lot of ways that
this could be wrong unless we're
misinterpreting what they meant by
defining the GL frag data to be zero to
the number of buffers because it's
pretty straight forward it's an Outback
four it's an array of four so I guess
there's a couple things I don't know
when outputting to multiple frame buffer
color attachments I don't know if they
have to be GL enabled so let me take a
quick look at that
[Applause]
framebuffer on the table of drove a
fixture indexed on the half-open range
to max draw buffers the frame buffers
cable maps from these indices to name
color buffers in the frame buffer what
so wait you're telling me you double
bind these why what is the point of that
so basically we have to set GL draw
buffers from zero to the number of
buffers we have to set that separately
in addition to having bound the buffers
the values in bus must names to the
collaboratory bearer for the default
frame buffer buffer next what is the
point of that ah okay wouldn't you just
create another frame buffer if you
wanted to swivel I don't understand
GL always has such weird legacy stuff in
it we're just like what is the point of
this why do you introduce indirection
after in direction after indirection all
right so yeah maybe that's all there was
that we have to specify the additional
mapping table which can we do we ask
that some of that per frame buffer I
don't know who knows
anyway let's assume we have to specify
the frame buffer because sure seems like
it was associated with the frame buffer
object making yet more work for the
driver of course so let's go ahead and
and take a look at the settings change
code where we actually create these
frame buffers and then I'll just call GL
draw buffers with this code so in this
case we want four in this case we want
to and in either case
[Music]
[Applause]
it's just going to be this all the time
anyway so cannot convert from GMO
initializer list with zero when L is
converted to this type good point
I see your point
and so that GL drawbars call must be
also an extended call I guess for ARB
draw buffers yeah all right here we go
make sure it's exactly what we want
first
all right so that looks like what we
want so we'll put it in here and we'll
just cross our fingers so if I want to
put that in there what I need first is I
need a definition of it somewhere right
so let's just stick that in there here's
type def and then we need to do the
little dance of acquiring it so we run
and we're calling it now and we can get
an error so that's nice but we still
don't know if it's working ah very nice
unfortunately it looks like we're
getting multiple pulses on that so I
would like if I don't know if that's
just a that may just be a keyboard
glitch or it might be because we're
accidentally setting like the reed
buffer and then that changes how things
behave later or something like this so
let's just make sure really quickly that
we're properly handling the pulse there
so in up Jill sorry inventory - handmade
where we actually check that for e m+ so
in here I think we want to make sure
that this
yes we want was done we want to make
sure what's done is down to this
so I don't really know exactly let's
take a look maybe this is this actually
could be related to the bug that we were
so fixed which I could have discussed
now as well let's just take a look at
what that is down tends to be so let's
just say we have test out and I do a
lisp printf and I say like is was is and
I just do a percent X sin x or actually
I do something like this so this is just
basically shoving it out the debug
course so we can take a look at it
yeah I and I'm going to run it so now
what I should be able to do is take a
look at what that happens to be so 0 is
1 1 is 0 0 is 1 1 is 0 0 is 1 1 is 0
that looks like what we would expect
let's run it in windowed so I can watch
it happen
as I click so here's the output so that
looks correct to me that's that's good
oh but you know what it's going to
happen two times because for all of
these things here we actually want like
these to happen only on is down so I
guess in this case these should actually
be moved into here
[Applause]
right
so now let's take a look at this a
little bit more stable there we go so
now we can look at every texture in
theories and we can also look at every
level of every texture right so that's
great so now that we have the ability to
debug that what we want to do is now try
writing some fake lighting into a bitmap
and again this is just a set us up so
that we can start this process of
debugging the lighting transport because
I'm going to write some stuff into a
shader and there's going to be bugs in
it and we're not going to know what the
bugs are or how to fix them unless we
can see very obviously what's in those
textures and even then it might be a
little bit hard but we'll do our best so
what we want to do now is we want to go
ahead and look at the dot compiled fake
speed lighting here this is our code so
what we can do here is we can start by
putting in to our front emit and vacuum
it we can start by putting in some sort
of information that we know to be
plausible so what we know about for
example RNP text and also one of the
things that we know about all these
frags is I guess they're all they don't
have an alpha value so I do know whether
that means I should output vectors still
because the shader would like to see it
that way or whether I can just have put
them exact threes because there's no
alpha value so I guess before you do
anything else maybe I'll just go ahead
and do that let's find out what happens
if I change these two vector YZ does the
share accept that or do you always have
to output an alpha value right
so it looks like the answer is it needs
to be oops
oh now could just be that so it looks
like maybe I can do that I don't I'll
let the Internet at large tell me
whether I can or cannot let other people
test this on other cards which they
often do every night when I post the
build I don't know if that's actually
legal or not but this is what we're
actually doing meaning none of those
textures have an alpha Channel so I
don't know whether OpenGL would be
happier with me explicitly saying here
are the RGB values there is no a value
or whether it would like to only see an
a value and throw it away
so I don't know which of those is more
appropriate but for now we'll just stick
with actually generating what we
actually have which is this there there
are no alpha values in these textures
they're just RGB textures so now when I
go to write this out we've got a front
emit in a vacuum and we've got a surface
color and NP Tech so what I'd like to do
here is I'd like to go ahead and start
playing with these values and put some
things in that might be sensible so what
we said we would do remember for our
encoding interiors we said that it would
be NX and z-depth right what I'm going
to do is I'm going to leave the depth
value at a constant and the NX value at
a constant for most of the places and
only where we put the light source in
will I change them so what am i do for
that as we say that the default value
for all of these is something that does
not emit any light the surface for now
we'll just be colorless it'll just be
gray
that reflects the light that comes back
to it let's say it reflects the light
that comes back to it at one seventh of
value one thing that we have to be
careful about let me just throw this out
there right away as we start moving
towards more physically accurate
lighting and by physically accurate we
not any huge quotes because we are in no
way trying to physically
accuracy lighting but all I mean by that
is as you start adding more elements of
physicality to your lighting you reduce
the ways in which you can set your
parameters so for example we are now
adding the concept that light gets
transported around the scene once you
allow light to get transported around
the scene a value of 1 for reflectance
is no longer plausible there is no such
thing as light that bounces around
forever
so you will start to get subtle bugs in
the lighting that has nothing to do with
the lighting transport that are actually
just because your values are physically
implausible so once you vacillate around
the scene it's important to respect the
reality of the physicality of light
which is that there are no objects in
the real world that you commonly observe
that about 100% of the photon bottom
they all absorb a little bit so even the
brightest white paint in a room bounces
photons at like 90 percent or 80 percent
or something it doesn't bounce 100% of
the photon that's why your room isn't
infinitely bright right if all the
photons always bounced off all the
objects all the time every surface would
be as bright as the light for the most
part right that's not actually true but
they would be a lot brighter that's
telling every surface would be a lot
brighter because you would never get any
absorption so when you look at a
particular part of your wall what you
would see is the inverse square law from
the light source and nothing else it
would just be that so everything in your
room would be like a uniform brightness
there was just inverse square law and
cosine angle and that's it you would see
no other diminutive ation of the light
source so something that was in shadow
would not really be in shadow right it
would be still bright because light
would get there eventually because it's
not getting absorbed by anything right
so even though you would still see what
I said initially was was way exaggerated
it's not true you would not see
everything to be as bright light source
but what you would see is no real
shadowing right because things wouldn't
absorbing light so the only thing is the
only thing that would create like a
shadow effect was the fact that the
light had to travel further to get
somewhere that's the only thing you
would see and so everything that is in
shadow right now would be a lot less in
shadow because the light would still
always find its way there it would just
be a question of it taking longer so the
inverse square law would be more in
effect right but that's it
normally shadows don't come only from
inverse square law normally shadows come
because every time light bounces it gets
significantly weaker on the bounce so
you're not just seeing the inverse
square law what you're actually saying
is inverse square law plus the
absorption so every time the latest the
surface you lose 30% of your light or
something right and that's not that's
not at all what would happen if the
light kept bouncing okay so that's it so
in order to prevent our scenes from an
officially bright I'm going to actually
start making them absorb a little bit
when you get a surface but that's all
then for the MP text what I want to do
is if we're including this is in X and Z
depth what I want to do is have
everything point upwards and I want the
depth let's say for the moment that
could be zero because we don't really
need to care about that right yet but I
would like the light source to be higher
than the surface so that it shines down
on it so what I'll do is I'll bump it up
for the light source so what I'm going
to do is create a synthetic value just
like if a light right else not so we're
going to have this buffer be surfaces
everywhere and light in one place so
what I want to do is have a way of
saying what the light source where the
light source is and one of things that
we specified is we specify a light P so
the location of the light so what I want
to do here is a these are B trees I
don't know why I'm using vector E I'm
going to OpenGL power lamps all of a
sudden for no reason so these VIII's are
satisfying what we're going to write the
service what I want to do is change them
if we're in light so I actually don't
need the else clause I suppose because I
set them to the default files already
but that if we're in the light I'm going
to set the front emit and the back emit
to do different colors I'm going to have
a red light coming out one side in a
green light coming out the
there why just because that way we can
see the difference between front and
backside emission I'm going to set the
MP Tech so this is the depth again that
depth is going to be kind of closer to
us so maybe what I'll do here is I'll
set this one to one and I'll set this
one to zero or maybe even more I'll set
this to like 10 and this to zero so
we've kind of got a lot of distance
specified in there and then what I'm
going to do is say the direction of the
light source is also going to be
different so the direction this light
source let's say is it's pointing 1 so
so it's shining a red light out the
right side and a green light out the
left side of it that's just what it's
doing right that's who knows I don't
know why this is what it's doing okay so
that's our our emission set up a surface
color for the light doesn't make any
difference because it can't really
bounce light around because it's an
emitter but you know so let's just say
it doesn't pass white it's only shines
light out light doesn't bounce off it
for now who knows why so taking all this
into account what we all what we need
now is some way of saying whether the
light starts what I want to do for that
take the distance to the light so the
distance to the light is going to be
whatever location we're at right now -
the light location right so what we need
to figure out is we need to figure out
like this PA - light PA right
I should say Delta - light and then
we've got a distance to light which is
just the length of the Delta - light at
that point it's a pretty easy thing to
say whether we're in the light we just
have to have a light radius how big is
the light swords right let's say the
light source is a you know a 1/2 a meter
what left that's pretty big a quarter
meter it's still pretty big tenth of a
meter let's say so it's a tenth of a
meter a decameter light source so if the
distance to the light source is less
than the light radius you are inside the
light and we'll set it otherwise we
won't and that's really all we need we
just need now to have some way of
translate
from the fragment p-value to a actual 3d
position in the world so in order to do
that we need some information but we've
got GL frag cord right we've got the GL
frag cord XY we know that's going to
range from 0 to 1080 or whatever so we
can just hack it again this is a totally
hacked lighting setup just for testing
purposes it doesn't have to be
consistent doesn't have to do anything
smart it can be completely dumb and
that's totally fine so let's just assume
that the the V value here let's just
assume that the distance from the light
P in this case is not going to depend on
these so we'll just set the disc P to be
whatever the light Z value actually is
so we know that that's not taken to
account and only need to do is make the
GL frag cord be something that roughly
corresponds to what we want so let's
take that value in two parts here let's
take the X and the y let's go ahead and
try to normalize that out so if we
expect to be running the GL fried cord
from zero to Cheney let's suppose we
subtract you know half of 1080 right so
if this was our our our situation here
writing something like this and the same
over here I guess tighten we should be
19:22 the x-coordinate not the
y-coordinate so we've got those two
being what they are we then want to try
and scale them a little bit so that's
just kind of like you know reese enters
them and then we want to scale them a
little bit so I guess maybe what I could
do instead let's do it this way let's
convert it to like a UV style so let's
divide it by the total so now range from
0 to 1 and then what I can do is just
take negative 0.5 and add you know in
half the value just sort of scale me to
a 0 to 1 range right now 0 to 1 range is
probably going to be too small so we
probably wanted to Jack that range up a
bit so maybe we'll say
like you know artificial range here and
will say that we are 10 in each
direction right so there's our art range
negative art range - art range negative
art range - our range now this is going
to be wrong we're going to have a weird
it's going to be abusing the I'm not
correcting for these the same way in
fact you know I could do it I could just
do them both by 1080 and then it would
be correct is not correct but it would
wouldn't be obvious or maybe I'll do
that so let's go ahead and and picture
of any compiler errors we've got here in
our shader read eclair built in named
frag data so I guess that does have to
be a back for right as we're looking at
here NP text parser so let's take a look
alright that requires semicolon so it
looks like it does want you to be before
it that's fine we can only we can just
write just to the X Y Z's of them and
that should be okay
and I guess technically if we really
wanted to we can say that this were RGB
because that's really the color output
that's probably more accurate way to
state it all right so now we've got
these a we're kind of right - already
not great
like I'm not seeing anything on the
screen which is not fantastic so what
that means is we're really never getting
inside this this distance the light here
is never becoming a valid value it
seemed we're only in time room saw time
so really all we have to do here is fix
that calculation again that probably has
to do with the dis key again that frag
cord I feel like should be roughly
correct but then again I don't really
know I feel like it should be ranging
from 0 to 1080 in Y and 0 to 1920 in X
but maybe I'm wrong about that the light
key again should just be you know should
be what it is what I can do to
double-check that is I can't
the Liedtke temple temporarily to just
be a zero
oops
or maybe I can can't monitor you for
okay let's use LP instead then
what happened really clear built-in
names you'll frag data so does that mean
that it doesn't that I just shouldn't
declare this that I should leave it
undeclared because it's giving me a
warning like it doesn't want that am i
interpreting that correctly would it
prefer that I just didn't put anything
there and let's let's I mean let's see I
guess if that's the case so if I did
that let me see if the surface color of
the MP tech got written anything to them
yeah they did so I guess it just wants
me to not declare that at all it's going
to take care of it and don't bother read
eclair in it I guess so again the only
problem I'm having right now as far as I
can tell is just I need to stabilize
this deal fredward better oh wait you
know what we started it at 12:15 so I
have 15 minutes left
I'm not almost out of time that's that's
not true so yeah so all I have to do is
just get this computation working more
sensibly and then we should be good to
go because this if this zero zero zero
here what am I getting wrong about these
these coordinates here so this P minus
LP take the length of the Delta to light
the light radius whatever the light
radius is then we say distance to light
listen light radius it should be set to
these values here so if we were to set
these just to something regular so if I
just said this B equals GL frag cord
I something like this or if I just said
something like that and I set the light
PA to something like let's say I set the
light radius up to something like 10
pixels wide I could just do all this in
pixels and map the light forward for
example and I should be able to see that
work the way that that would happen
would just be to say like this is a v2
that's set to the frag cord the light
position in this case is going to be
let's say half of the value we expect so
1080 sanction 20 community so just going
to be the middle pixel lines the light
radius is going to be 10 pixels we
should see a temp LexA blob and center
and screen right and we see in the upper
corner which is pretty weird so why are
we seeing it half size you saw that
right you see what I'm saying up there
in the corner what's it doing why is it
we set it at half of the screen
resolution so unless we're drawing
something twice as large as the screen
for some reason that shouldn't be
happening which you know maybe we are
I'm not sure but it seems like that's
busted am I missing something
Frank critics why the light position is
1920 1080 and we're having that so that
should be right in the middle of the
screen we're taking Delta to light and
we're doing this P minus LP
I guess if the frag cords so here's the
question do the frag cords actually I
not have the Delta offset added to them
yet
I always forget what they're actually at
okay so it's zero zero is the bottom
corner so that's what I was expecting so
is this a half light texture for some
reason so if I was to take a quarter of
that would I show up in the center of
the screen I do so what that suggests to
me is that this texture is smaller than
I think it is and I don't know why so
let me just do a quick check to find out
why because I would like to know so in
here we're we're creating our textures
you can see we've got a width and height
in here that are set to the render
within the render height and they're you
know we go when we start so let's go
ahead and jump in there when we're
creating these so we can see what's
going on I'm going to switch out a
hexadecimal views because we don't care
what that so the render width and oh
nevermind
I guess we're rendering at 960 by 540 oh
right probably because this card is too
slow to render at full resolution it's
rendering it half resolution okay don't
care
totally fine with me just want to make
sure I knew what it was all right so
that's all good and so let's try to get
again the rest of our stuff working
where we can actually put the the light
position in here so if I wanted to do
that what I could do is again take two
LP take the light position which is now
needs to sort of be REE centered because
the light position again is going to be
sort of in in meters and now we want it
to be in pixel so what I can do is
multiply it by this scalar here to sort
of say like okay let's multiply it out
to the correct size in in in pixels here
but I don't really know what the scale
factor should be exactly it can be very
approximate because again we're just
using this
I just need to be able to move it around
right so you can see that that's all I
need to be able to do is that now it's
not going to be centered properly as
well to what I would like to do is I
still like to do that offset so let's do
the offset for the center of the screen
and let's make this a little more
gradual that so like so so here this way
I can sort of move this light around
slowly which is all I really want to do
right and so now what we should see is
there's there's the the light again
that's kind of coming out of the light
source here's our front slide lighting
or backside lighting here's our surface
reflectance and here is our directional
vectors right so we have everything that
we wanted to have in place everything is
now correct and so what we need to build
next is we need to build the down
sampler right we need to build the thing
that takes and builds the like
progressively down sampled versions now
we only have ten minutes left it's
probably too little time to do that but
since this is just basic down sampling
we could get started on anyway it's not
a huge deal so let's just go ahead and
do that it's the it's the one that goes
the other direction the back propagator
where the the most of the smarts are
going to live so let's take a look at
the compute what do we call this thing
compute light transfer
so this compute light transport here is
going to be two phases so first we've
got the upward propagation so this is
like
[Applause]
and this is the downward phase so the
harebrained scheme begins below this
we've got two phases the upward phase
and the downward phase we're going to
stick it to do in here because we are
not going to try and do the downward
phase until next week we will try to
just sketch out briefly the upward phase
and you can sort of see what this is
going to look like so the upward phase
is basically to read from a larger
texture map and write to a smaller
texture map averaged values and that's
it that's all it's going to do so what
we're going to try to do here as it goes
down is we've got these light buffers
and we know how many there are so what
we're going to do is we're going to go
through and we're going to say we have a
desk light buff index that desk light
buff index is going to range not from
zero which is the first one that's
filled in by the initial fill by the
initial lighting capture what we're
going to do is we're going to take one
is the first we're going to write two
right we're then going to write it
successively to each greater one as we
go that means that the source light buff
index is always going to be the desk
light buff index minus one so we're
going to start on source viewer right to
desk one source one right to desk two
source two right so it just kind of goes
upward as it progressed it and so that's
how that's going to work and we are
essentially going to do a again another
full screen fill style thing where we
each time fill the entire
a texture with a new set of sample so if
you look at what we're doing probably
the opengl screen fill back and forth
this is probably fine for our purposes
actually this is exactly I think what we
want to do so I'll do open Jill being
Vince real open Jill and screen Phil
should do it right so let's go ahead and
take this so open Jill begins can you
fill an open Jill and screen felt in
this case we're going to take frame
buffer handles here and write to them
this is going to be the desk buffer
handle this is going to desk buff and
that's going to be a light buffer we're
going to writing everything so it's
going to be the right all buffer and
we're going to it's going to be you know
as big as it was and we're going to
write to all the pixels right we're then
going to do a use program begin used
program and it's going to be a new
program which is going to be the good up
multi grid light up so we have a multi
grid light up programs there's going to
be a multi grid light down program that
will do the opposite direction that's
going to be more complicated and in this
case we do have to bind some textures
we're going to be reading from all four
of these textures actually on the
previous level so it's going to be kind
of a audacious nightmare scenario that
looks something like this it would be
nice for us to probably stop doing this
crap because we you know there already
are in extended OpenGL ways of binding
textures directly to a slot
unfortunately we aren't using we aren't
we aren't doing that so let's just have
a bind texture call here which is like
you know slot index I guess we would
meet yet you know it Adam
I don't even wanna be with it right now
so anyway we could have a call to a
single call that has all three of these
in it let's let's just do it let's just
good I'm just getting tired of it so all
this would be is just a gon M slot GOP
num type and then gon handle so it's
just like slot type handle uh and then
so yeah what I would say is we just be
able to call open Joe a line text and in
this case we want to do the front text
[Applause]
so texted one two three
none of these are multi sample buffers
so actually we can just use do texture
2d and it's going to be front back
surface color MP type right so it's
gonna look something like this we bind
you to the textures and off we go
we then want something that's going to
clear the textures because we have this
sort of problem where the active texture
handle kind of gets set Wankel e so at
the end we want to do something like a
geo active texture you know GL texture
zero something like that
so that's it that's the entirety is of
that sort of like binding nonsense and
really that's most of what we need there
I need to go ahead and flush this out we
need the source and just like buffers
here so open gel light buffer the plus
source quick buff index and OpenGL tight
buffers plus just like index so those
are the two we have their death buff
should just be desk and I think that's
everything
so really at this point we need boots we
just need the program and then we're
done I'm going to go a little over time
because I'd like to just go ahead and
get that program sketched in and then
that will set this up next week to be
able to do the whole algorithm because
we basically could just copy this
routine here change the textures around
a little bit and be ready to start
fussing with our stuff right okay so
this is going to be kind of like not
sure which one this is really going to
be the most like I guess it's going to
probably the most like this one honestly
so compile compile final stretch we're
going to need some parameters here to
help us out but we can add those in so
let's make this the compiled multi light
up here's one as I call it multiply
multi grid light up oops
[Applause]
so yeah reading right sRGB is not going
to be on the table yet I don't think
because we are just going to have
everything in float for a while later on
we might have to work out whether we
need s RGB encoding for some things to
make it more efficient right now I don't
want that at all
in theory there should be no parameters
to this whatsoever
I don't think unless we do want to pass
using these it probably would make
things easier if we did because then we
don't need to use the frag coordinates
hmm
see the thing is I think we're going to
want to do our own sampling and the fact
that we're going to want to do our own
sampling makes it a little bit harder so
we might just want to stay out of this
business altogether let's see if we can
the problem that worries me is is what
we're going to do when we get down to
having too few text textures too gives
you texels
to do two to one so that that part
concerns me because if we start out at
1920 by 1080 eventually we get down to a
certain resolution there's nothing left
to do
two to one sampling on and we would end
up with artifacts there as as the the
two-to-one resolution drop bleeds in so
at some level we kind of want that UV to
work so so you know I guess I'll just do
it I'll just leave the UVs in there
we'll see if that how that does we're
probably going to have to be a little
bit careful as we go all right so in
this case we've got
sources and depths that we've got source
emit tech
front emit text we've got back
[Applause]
we've got surface colored because you
don't need tech on those and then source
okay so these are coming in and we need
to do the same thing we're doing before
which is writing to GL frag color so
that means this is out of the question I
guess we do want tech on these because
I'm going to sample them right away so
maybe we just say text and then we put
in here that we're going to sample from
them so we just say oops I guess maybe
I'll do it this way so we here will say
source front emit and each of these is
just again going to it's just going to
down sample in in the future we'll
probably get more fancies with how we're
doing these things but for right now
we're going to start with a simplest
possible thing
[Applause]
so that will sample from the textures it
will use the proper the proper bilinear
blend to do the sampling which i think
is probably roughly roughly what we want
but again we're going to have to play
around with it and it will probably want
to increase the quality of it so we'll
just let this do its thing and then
we'll write to our GL fraud data the way
that we were writing to it before so
what I'm going to do there is I'm
literally just going to cut and paste
this exact thing and what we're going to
do here is we're just going to literally
assign the desk to the source and that's
all we're going to do for today I don't
know why we stuck Tec on the end of this
[Applause]
ok so now we need to actually make these
programs and these programs are going to
be a little more complicated in terms of
what they actually look at then say our
fakes to you buddy program which didn't
really have to do anything so we've got
two of them both light red light up
program that's what we're gonna do now
multi grid light down programs that's
the one we're not going to look at
moment the multi period light up program
it's really just textures so it's going
to be like this sort of thing and so
let's go ahead and take a look at these
goods
so the multigrid light up program is
going to need to specify all of these it
doesn't really need anything else this
the frag UV that will come through but I
believe that's already handled in common
so it doesn't really need that at all so
I think all that we need to do is that
and then we should be able to just do
our successive lighting from there I'm
pretty sure that's it so let's go ahead
and after we do come the multigrid
compiled let's set those samplers and so
we basically want this code to happen a
couple times here and we want it for
each of these salsa gentlemen so yeah
each of these source front emit text
[Applause]
source vacuum it tags source surface
color and source and key text that
should give us the full compile now we
just need to actually bind it in there
and I'll put both of them in there for
now we'll play grid lights up program
like red light down so those are both in
there now and we need to actually call
them so when we have a settings change
they will get recompiled
[Applause]
and that will happened right here and I
think see use program begin multi good
let up yep that one needs to be fixed
and use for commands is usually just
goes the common one right
okay so compile multi grid light up I'm
going to go ahead and put compiled multi
grid light down in here as well and
let's see we thought use program begins
here where we're going to use the multi
grid light up we need to then actually
have that do the binding that it should
do and in order to do that let's see
where that's at it will not eat any
rendering setup and it should just find
these in order so it should just the
source front limit source back sort of
surface source NP so all it really has
to do is bind those samplers that's
that's all it does and then it should be
able to run the program now we probably
have some errors in there but like I
said I'd rather just finish this up for
now that's not a very clear error
message to be completely honest with you
did you care you know did you want to
tell me where you found the error by a
chance
I guess in this case maybe we need to
get the info out of this thing first so
let's see okay fine so step the next
statement can you give me some more info
here leave vertex errors fragments
errors program errors okay
so let's see a vertex shader has no
problems fragment shader had a bunch of
problems so let's take a look at this
probably just typos since we're not
really doing anything in the shader yet
it's just a stand-in very very simple
okay
so first of all these need to be v3 they
probably also need to be RGB here
because by default it'll sample of bogus
alpha so let's see float to highest
three components that may be it let's
let's see what happens under validations
here okay
so now we've got here we're looking at
texture cept that that initial frame
above zero if I look at the next one up
I'm not seeing anything so it doesn't
look like we're properly sampling from
these quite yet and part of that also we
have to make sure that we're not using
any miss mapping on those but otherwise
we might just want to leave this for
next week I'll do a quick check to make
sure that there's nothing obviously
broken but that should basically be it I
also don't know why this is set to
version 130 I think since we need
version 150 on stuff we should probably
just change to version 150 everywhere
but we haven't done that yet so you know
we'll see all right so anyway let's take
a quick look and just make sure
we know what's going on here we're
passing the fragment you view stuff in
here and we're sampling from that as we
go
we're pulling those out we're just
writing out exactly what we sample into
the output that's about all that's going
on again nothing particularly fancy so
we want to make sure I guess that we're
writing to the correct thing and reading
from the correct thing ah but that's
about it so here's the loop we have the
destination light buffer index as one
and reading from the source light buff
index of zero you can see us pulling out
the source and desk here so the source
we begin to screen filled to the
destination we're writing everything so
we begin right to the destination we do
use for going to begin on the mud-filled
light up we bind textures to zero one
two and three
with the front emit vacuum its source
color and NP from the source which is
what we want we then oh hi we then don't
draw anything so we did have at least
one obvious error say the least but we
still don't see anything else green so
that was not our only error right but
not trying anything obviously it's a
problem so there's that so let's again
just quick check because you know just
kind of leave things in a reasonable
spot let's make sure we're actually able
to write so what I want to do here is
again set these values to something
known so what I'm going to do is I'm
going to overwrite the front emitter
with pure red so what I should see is I
should see the whole screen filled red
but when I go to switch to the next
texture and I don't so what that means
is it's not our texture sampling we
actually just aren't properly writing
anything out right now because that
front emitter should get written out to
here and at the moment at least it
doesn't appear to be
out at all so we've got a problem with
just writing in general not a problem
with our actual shader so let me see if
I can track down what that actually is
we've got compiled multi grid light up
and multi grid like down both being
called presumably we've actually got
that cute like transport oops
cute like transport so presumably we're
actually okay here we in presumably
we're targeting this right all frame
buffer is the same thing that we're
doing in our fake sea lighting so in
theory anyway in our fake seed lighting
because we were able to write to
everything there we should also be able
to write to everything here right that's
the you know that is the only thing that
would really make any sense to say the
least
so something bizarre is going on there
where for some reason we are unable to
write to our source here even though
we're using substantively the same exact
stuff so I don't know what is wrong in
this case what I would like to try and
again this will be a little bit of a
oddity is what I would like to try here
is what if I actually use the fake food
lighting on every level I just want to
see what happens there it's going to be
a little bit wrong it'll it'll put it'll
move the thing up to the upper corner at
the next step because the coordinates
will be wrong but that's okay I think so
let's go ahead and and see if we can do
that I'm just curious what happens here
we go compute like transport oops
[Applause]
so there's a plus and you can see that
we're able to write to it so there's
just something wrong with our program
that we're not understanding in this
case and I don't know what it is so if
something's busted with the multigrid
light-up program where it's not actually
covering the pixels properly or
something right we don't actually know
what that something could be yeah at the
moment but we know we're targeting the
right frame buffer here so we just don't
know why we're getting into a situation
where we can't write to the textures
we're trying to write to not using this
program because I like I said I've set
or at least I thought I set in the
fragment code here I thought I set the
front emitter value so that should have
overwritten frag data zero with a clear
read image let me go ahead in this case
and try setting everything and we can
try to figure out why we're not seeing
anything because that doesn't make a
whole lot of sense to me so that means
we've got a stupid bug somewhere so
that's like no pixels are getting filled
whatsoever why aren't any pixels getting
filled what is the bug here
I oh you know what probably because I
deleted the input position so it was
outputting garbage that's kind of a
mistake you know what I'm saying
not not great not not really very good
let's try that one more time there we go
[Applause]
salary was being targeted properly all
right a dumb typo nicely done
so now let's eliminate these and
hopefully now we're in a position where
at least we're ready for next week
to sort of work on that filtering so
there we go okay so that's perfect so
you can see as we go up in resolution
we're doing exactly what we expect to do
now which is letting that lighting do
what it wants to do right it's it's
getting lower and lower res each time up
same is true for each of these not sure
why it looks like we're getting read in
both cases there what's going on with
that source back image so it's back your
mid text runs a quick test surface color
fried UV do we bind something wrong
does it look like it so let's just see
what happens here so here I am on the
texture 1 or texture 0 and you can see
that that looks correct Here I am on
let's say texture 3 and that also looks
correct right Here I am on texture -
that looks correct Here I am on texture
1 and that is wrong it looks like we're
writing out when we write to the back
emitter we're actually writing out the
wrong thing now that could just because
we're sampling from it incorrectly like
source vacuum it somehow is getting
something else in it so let's just
double check all those so that's I think
the only problem so far source front
emit source front emit source vacuum it
right so sort least these two look
correct source front source front source
back source back pentacles front back
equals back flag data zero is front back
data one is back so I seen nothing weird
there and source front admit Tech and
source document X in both cases I both
look ok as well right that all looks
pretty correct to me so then when we do
the bind
for a multigrid light up we do zero is
the front emit tech and that presumably
is how we said they should be right 0 1
2 3 0 1 2 &amp; 3 I don't see how we're
getting that problem B does anyone else
see however getting it that seems a
little bit weird
additional semicolon of G will get you
from a local source vacuum hit text in
compiled shader
where's the additional semicolon ah
thank you stream you guys have better
eyes than I do
there we go
so that's all we need good - good all
right so now we have basic up sampling
that setup same thing it's actually down
sampling but we have the basic up
pyramid working so I I guess that's
about it
so I'll go to a brief Q&amp;A now though
we're not really done the things so
so any questions on what we're doing we
said I slowed up well for next weekend I
think because now we've gotten sort of
the dredge work out of that and it
should be relatively straightforward to
now start spreading but it's going to be
a hard road to travel because presumably
when I actually try to implement the
lighting it's going to be a huge kind of
like thing like we did when we were
trying to get the depth stuff working
well and we eventually came for the best
feeling and it worked really well but it
takes some experimentation to get there
so if this lighting does work in the end
it's definitely gonna take a bunch of
experimentation to get there it's
probably not going to be the very first
thing we tried
frosty ninja is this going to be pulled
out of the final ship to put pull aside
as DLC content to charge for um yeah we
need we need a handmade hero season pass
and you if you don't buy a season pass
you're not going to get the debug you're
not gonna get the debug view man like
that's the debug view is like DLC you've
gotta you got to get the season pass for
that four bit lighting ideas for a good
IDE integrated bugger for Linux there
aren't any
you could try QT creator it's got a lot
of bugs like a lot of bugs in the
debugger which is kind of funny but it's
the closest thing I found because like
it can at least see disassembly I think
sort of sometimes when it's in the mood
and it can usually sort of inspect
things and it usually can sort of save
your breakpoints and stuff it breaks all
the time all the time and it crashes all
the time I was trying to bug and all
those sort of things like that so it's
not a good experience but it's probably
the best one I've seen and it lets you
debug things you haven't built inside QT
creator which is important for people
like me unlike a lot of there's a lot of
ideas you can only debug something you
build inside the IDE which is useless if
you use an editor that isn't the IDE
I guess not useless you could still try
to build you could still set up a dummy
build I guess or something
t7 samurai could you recap outline the
idea for this lighting scheme basically
just take a look at yesterday's dream
that's what the whole thing was about
the idea is just it's just going to be a
multi grid lighting scheme which means
we're going to propagate lights at a low
resolution version of the scene and then
push them down to a higher resolution
like light lighting versions and keep
going it doesn't have a high probability
of working I've never heard of anyone do
it so I didn't have a better idea
Zillah rezku will I be able to pay money
for an expansion that crashes every so
often yeah I think that's called a Intel
integrated graphics part all you have to
do is buy if you want your game to crash
every so often you just need an Intel
driver I think you're good to go
is this a single-player game or will
there be some networked multiplayer
features a single-player game
[Music]
doesn't leave us any more questions on
here
all right doesn't look like there's any
questions I'm gonna close down
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for Alexa to hand made here at the
pedicle a with you as always if you
would like to follow along terms at home
you could always peer to the game on
handmade hero org and it course comes
with the source code so you can program
along with me and experiment with the
source tree if you want to ask questions
we also have a forum site you can go to
we got a patreon page if you want to
support the video series we've got a
schedule bot you can go to if you want
to know when we're going to live and we
got an episode guide they help to catch
up on old episodes that's it for this
weekend we'll be back next weekend for
another four hours of handmade hero
coding where we will try out the
lighting and we'll probably have
something working next weekend and by
working on me not working but we'll have
something that does lighting or at least
computes lighting poorly and so then
we'll kind of have to take the next step
and go how do we make it really work and
give us something we can actually ship
which ought to be interesting since this
is the totally different algorithm then
I've seen done before so who knows we'll
see what happens until then have fun
programming this week and I will see
everyone the internet take it easy
everybody