all righty hello everyone and welcome to
handmade Hero show recode a complete
game live on stream today I want to take
a look we started playing around with
room layout last weekend and I would
like to try to do a couple things to
that code now that we're just informed
by us playing around with it
specifically I feel like just from
playing around a little bit the sense
that I got in trying to make a fairly
simple routine was that it was too
cumbersome to talk about the layout of
rooms in ways that was error-free right
and so there was a lot of like problems
with thinking about how to do things
without having off-by-one errors when
you're doing like sort of tile based
layouts and things like this and so I
think what I gained from doing that
playing around with it last weekend was
that I would like to maybe make
something make some code that manually
lays out some rooms in a known pattern
and figure out what how to make the sort
of the API the the the way in which we
talk about where rooms are and how
they're placed I'd like to get that
right before I try to write anything
more complicated like the code we were
playing with so because like I said when
you start playing around sit like this
and you're opening up a new section of
the code a section that is brand new
where we haven't really done anything
with anything like it previously it's
important to kind of feel it out and go
how is coding here gonna go and what do
I need to be effective here like what
what am I look how can I do it so that
I'm not spinning my wheels and wasting
my time what do I need right and so what
I would like to do here is I would like
to start pushing that forward right I'd
like to figure out how I can I sort of
get a good I guess we're looking for is
a good semantics in place for
talking about where rooms can go where
they did go and how I want them placed
and I don't think what I picked at first
was good I think it was bad and I'll
explain why in a second so if you
remember we sort of had this this
concept in here of a of a volume where a
room could be placed and this was just
some integers that said the meaning the
max right it's a pretty straightforward
idea uh and I don't think there's
anything I obviously wrong with this
right I don't think there's some kind of
horrible design decision here but I do
think there was a problem with the
interpretation of it and you remember I
actually said I'm not sure if this is
the right way when I did it and I think
when I did it when I actually you went
to use it I think that confirmed that it
was in fact not the right way and I like
to do a little bit differently
specifically what I chose to do was say
that the min and the max were actually
exclusive sorry the min was inclusive in
the max is exclusive so this is a fairly
standard interval technique it's
basically saying that and it's a tense
it's like how triangle fill and stuff
like that tends to work those kinds of
fill rules and the reason for it is if
you have a an understanding of how
something is laid out and you put two
rectangles next to each other starts
that one's min is the other one's max
you don't want them both to fill the
same column and so let me draw this out
for you we've talked about this a little
bit when we talked about fill rules and
I just want to kind of cement the reason
why these sorts of things exist and then
talk about the problem that I had with
it that prevented it from being good
so specifically the problem is as
follows
we are on a tile map grid and so when we
talk about the tile map grid what we end
up talking about or what we were talking
about anyway and maybe we don't want to
still talk about it this way which is
why I'm bringing it up but what we were
talking about is imagining that we have
a set of integers mapped to effectively
the tiles okay so what that means is
that if I was to say take integer 3 that
is this column let's say an integer 7 is
this row or something like this so it
would be 8 9 10 11 whatever so this is
just some a random section of the grid
and so what I now have to do is say well
I want to talk about a room and a room
is a collection of these tiles that
happens to be rectangular at the moment
right now we don't really care if it's
rectangular at the end of the day but
we'll probably build it up out of
rectangles even if it's not rectangular
so we do want a convenient way of
talking about more than one tile because
talking about each individual tile that
comprises a room especially when most of
these rooms are going to be rectangular
because the screens rectangular and we
want to fill it with a room I it's just
very cumbersome and unnecessary right it
would not be a smart way to do it to
pass like a list of all of the tiles
because there'd be like you know a
hundred tiles in this room and we'd be
passing a list of a hundred integer
pairs instead of just passing two
integer pairs than men in the max right
so you can see why this makes some sense
why we want to do rectangle based
referencing of regions for all kinds of
purposes and so what we're gonna end up
here with some way of saying look let's
suppose that this is the region I'm
talking about now we all know what that
region is I colored it in its the region
that includes you know 4 8 4 I'm sorry
four nine five eight five nine six eight
six nine that's the region we're talking
about so there's no ambiguity in what
I'm trying to say
but there's plenty of ambiguity you know
how I want to encode that so one way of
encoding that is by using intervals
right a min and a max by saying this is
the range that I'm going to do and
there's very there's a lot of different
ways that I could imagine talking about
these things for example I could encode
this as 4 through 6 comma 8 through 9
right and this is effectively a interval
that says everything including the
number specified is included in the
region right so when I say 4 I mean
everything to the right of 4 and 4 and
when I say 6 I mean everything to the
left of 6 and 6 in mathematics shorthand
notation oftentimes they will use
brackets or parentheses to indicate
which of these they mean so oftentimes
in mathematics literature you will see
something to represent this as brackets
4 comma 6 and that means I want the
interval 4 through 6 including 4 and
including 6 on the other hand if I
wanted to instead represent this as 3
through 7 7 through 10 that suggests the
boundary right so now I am telling you
the numbers that bound the region but
which do not themselves include in that
region so I don't include 3 or 7 they
are not actually in the interval they
are on the just just outside their one
passed it right and in mathematics you
would often write that and again I want
to put a little kavion this because
I don't quite mean you would often write
that but parentheses are usually used to
talk about excluding that one digit
that's actually on the end so you might
say three comma seven not brackets three
seven which would have hoops which would
have included three two seven now the
reason I say not quite is because this
presumes that we're talking about
discrete things only not that kind of
discrete at that kind of screen when you
write this kind of an interval in
mathematics more generally you're
actually just talking about literally
the position on the number line that is
three is it included or not but two I'm
sorry 3.0 oo-oo-oo-oo one for example
would still be included so in our case
we're talking about the first thing that
would be included if three is not
included is four in real math not real
as an actual math or not fake math but
real as in real numbers when you write
intervals you're talking about the
infinity of numbers not just the
discrete ones but if we're only talking
about those sweet ones then again maybe
that makes more sense either way doesn't
matter to us we're never going to use
this notation I just wanted to point out
that you've seen this before if you've
taken high school math classes I would
think at least would have had a part
where they mentioned something like this
or had a little bit of something like
this so again the concept that you need
to talk about whether or not the
bounding value is in or out is not
specific to tile maps it's not specific
to fill rules it's not specific to
computing it's actually something that
even mathematicians have to deal with
all the way back to the time when
computers were not even a thing that
anyone thought about they still had to
think about whether or not when they
talked about a particular number as the
bounds of a region did they mean greater
than or greater than or equal to right
because that's we're really talking
about here right in this case we're
talking about greater than in this case
we're talking about greater than or
equal to
and so that's a very common thing it's
not unique to us it's it's common in
math in general but again just wanted to
put that as a side it doesn't matter
that's common to math because whether or
not it is common to math or not we still
have to deal with it here so what we do
know is this common to us and so what I
want to talk about here is how we're
actually storing this and the
consequence is that we end up having
when we when we work with these things
okay so the problems that that I want to
make sure that we handle properly and
the things that I want to look at more
carefully and maybe we're doing fine but
I just want to look at them and pull
them out in two reliable things that we
can count on so I don't have to think
about anymore is we have to pick some
rule for how these things are talked
about and not only do we have these two
options
meaning include or exclude the two
bounds we have the option of doing it
heterogeneous ability heterogeneously
such as include the three well in this
case it would be include the four don't
include the seven right similarly don't
include the three do include the six
right so we actually have in this case
four viable options here for how we
might want to include this include
encode this one is exclusive of both one
is inclusive of both one is exclusive on
one inclusive on the other and the other
one is the opposite right and again that
just corresponds to all the
possibilities there are there's two
possibilities right include exclude and
so and we have two things we can include
or exclude so it's two times two equals
four possibilities right so the one I
chose was actually this one and that is
the the convention that's often used for
fill rules generally which is that the
min is included in the
Max is not included now why would you
want to do that the reason that you'd
want to do that is because it allows you
to set the min and the max to the same
value and not overlap so if for example
I know that I want two rooms to line up
I set their min to one value and their
max to the same value and I know that
they're touching right so that's what I
did I'm just not sure that's the way
that makes it the easiest to talk about
and so what I'd like to do today is I'd
like to go in and start to look at what
were the sorts of things we were trying
to do just in that one simple routine
that was like looking at how it would
have to bound a room in order to touch
all the things that was supposed to like
a but all of the rooms that was supposed
to a but I wasn't a very complicated
routine but it was kind of complicated
to get right just because of all the
like off-by-one confusing miss of it
right and so I would like to figure out
how to sort of talk about those things a
little bit more conveniently in a way
that's semantically easy to remember so
that we don't have to worry as much
about that as we're programming okay I
don't because it's gonna be too slow
we're gonna get bogged down if we're
constantly having to like think through
and debug these sort of twiki like does
this thing actually line up where we
think it does kinds of stuff so I just
want to look at that and see if that is
doing what it should be doing and that's
what we really want to look at right so
here is the code in question and what
you can see is we have some pretty
straightforward kinds of stuff for the
connection just like hey could I go in
this direction or couldn't I that seems
reasonable just mean and then I start to
look at well which side was I gonna do
am i doing the min side or the Mac side
of this thing which you know Mike which
way am I trying to go out and what we
find here is we find that we call like
clipped min or clipped Max and we say
stuff like well okay I need to clip the
minimum to whatever the maximum was and
I need to
at the maximum to whatever the maximum
was like plus one right um and it's just
like I guess that that's not that big of
a deal that's just saying II there has
to be some volume to the room so really
you know I could have done it that way
which seems still symmetric so that's
pretty reasonable then when I'm going to
clip the minimum I'm flipping that to
the the minimum of the maximum I should
say to the air with all units that's all
right so these actually don't look as
bad as I as I as I thought they might be
and we can make this a little more
standard let's take a look at these guys
here so you can see there's a bit of a
of an asymmetry here though that I don't
necessarily love right this part is not
great we would like these to look
symmetric I think like we really I just
don't think fundamentally want to have
these kinds of lines like asymmetric if
I want to shrink the thing in by the
interior apron I think you would want it
to look symmetric now the reason it
doesn't look symmetric at the moment is
because if we're going to clip the
maximum to something in order to overlap
by one I've got to make sure that I add
one to it because it's not going to
include where it is whereas on the other
hand on the inside I don't have to do
that right now let's make sure that's
actually correct
but I'm pretty sure it is look if I go
ahead and run this by the way it should
just produce a bunch of connected rims I
don't know why that didn't load my
project yeah
must've like closed the project last
time or something um so these rooms are
lined up the way that I think that they
should be right let me go ahead and undo
this and I should verify that they are
not yeah
so that's kind of an example of an
asymmetry that I don't love and you know
again I say what I'm looking for it
curious I want ways to talk about these
things that don't accumulate off by ones
because if you accumulate off by ones
then the programmer always has to be
thinking about whether there's an off by
one in there and if there is they have
to manually correct for it and that's
what I did here but that's not really
good and so for me I think looking at
this if I was to say that the maximum
included where it was then I think this
maybe becomes more symmetric I think so
let's suppose that the max did include
where it was what would this look like
well if the max included where it was
then the minimum volumes so let me talk
about one of the things going on here if
it's not obvious one other thing that's
a little bit of an issue is that when we
talk about mins and maxes we're actually
we have two layers of that going on
right now not only do we have the min
and Max of the region we're talking
about but this is actually talking about
a minute a max of those men and maxes
right because we're talking about a
region where we can place them in and a
region where we can place the max so we
have a volume for minimums and a volume
for maximums and so I think that's also
what's causing the trip repair because
for example let's suppose I wanted to
have the max include its own line well
at that point we still sort of have a
problem the reason for that is that when
we're clipping the
minimum volumes maximum location it can
be we need to make sure that that
doesn't ever go below a legal limit so
if I were to switch that I think I would
just have to I'd have to end up
basically doing that right it would move
where the plus one was in this case the
max of the minimum so the furthest the
minimum can be in terms of where the
other room compared to where the other
rooms maximum is yeah obviously that
can't be any less than the maximum of
that room right it has to all be to the
other side of it so both the min and the
max have to be to the other side of the
maximum so now I guess I'm I guess I'm
not I'm mistaken since everything is
inclusive and the min and the max could
be the same value
it really looks more like this right so
if the min and the max are actually
included bounds I think that regularizes
the handling a little bit it basically
says look the minimum has to move to
this line the maximum has to move to
this other line right and I think that's
just it so I'm gonna go ahead and
experiment with that a little bit but
that seems better to me just looking at
this routine and looking at what will
happen if I change the definition of
what happens there it starts to get rid
of some of those like okay this one has
to have a plus one this one asset like
now it's like everyone gets the same
modifier and that's what I'm looking for
I want to wait a uniformly think about
that and it seems like that's just
better
again there's obvious reasons not to use
that sort of a rule in other context in
this context it's just really looking to
me like I want to do it that way so I'm
gonna try doing it that way and then
we'll see what happens as we go forwards
so when we have like the infinity volume
in the inverted infinity volume those
are both not gonna change because we
don't care whether the like those are
initial like giant things or completely
impossible things and they don't really
change one way or the other so that part
is not relevant so the only parts we
really care about are these things here
where we've got sort of like mini
dimensions for rooms and that sort of
stuff so when we subtract these here we
need to take a look at what the results
will be in this case if we have a Max
and a min that are the same they'll
subtract to one if there's yeah so so
really what we want here is is I think
the same thing that we have it I think
to be honest sorry if we have the same
they'll subtract to zero so we need to
sort of say that the dimension of the
room is goo is one more than whatever we
would have computed right so I think
what I'd like to do here is just you
know have some sort of
so I can talk about them either way and
we could actually make these be points
as well if we wanted to don't know that
we really care about that one way or the
other but but we could right we could
call this destruct of of Jen points
maybe I will
we'll do that a second so if we want to
have a thing here which base says like
you know and maybe this is more like a
Gen B 3 if I want to be able to say get
dim on one of these Jen Williams this
allows me to say give me the the
computation we would have done here and
I just want to make this expand by one
so that allows me to get this sort of
understanding of the dimensions of the
thing that's got our assumptions about
the fill rule baked into it so that
other people don't have to constantly
think about what that fill rule is the
fill rule will just automatically sort
of be taken into account when you look
at the fat fill so then here this
routine can now use that and the same
check will now work because the fill
rule has been baked into here so you do
get back the number of tiles that are
included so that seems fine the maximum
volume stuff will still work because we
just use the mins in the Max's that
there are so that doesn't really affect
get affected by the fill rule because
the fill rule is consistent on both the
inner and outer volumes so it just
carries through and the rest of this
stuff pretty much just works exactly how
you would expect creating the Union and
the intersection again still the same
although for the intersection I have to
think about whether there's any special
considerations I don't think there are I
think it's still fine
all right so let's keep on going here so
now when we get to this part for example
the min and the max is don't overlap
anymore this is particularly important
because in the previous version the min
the max did so when we say door at we're
actually going to get one of the values
as the one we actually want and you can
see here when we're getting it we we get
the min of the door we get the the min
line so wherever the door at is we can
just use that column as the map
and the mean is just the column before
it so this is now the correct way to
place the door in there now we could do
this another way which is to do use
one's men and one's max which I suppose
is kind of a more interesting way to do
it potentially which would be to do
something like this oh you know I don't
care we'll just call it that so so
that's fine and I don't mind about the
asymmetry here because this is the kind
of asymmetry I actually coded myself
right I basically said look I'm gonna
start on the min and I know that like 1
back for me is the max so this is all
the right thought process this to me is
not a concern these up here were because
the thought process was the same on
either side but I was getting two
different equations that's the thing
that flagged it for me as like I should
look at this more carefully this is not
one of those that is totally fine all
right so I think all of this is probably
final though we may have to look at it
again yeah so so there is one aspect of
it which is that this part here it's I
think this is a greater than right
because you include the max
right
I'll have to think about how I want
these to work
I think these technically also are a
little bit off right I think it's this
because the maximum allowed dimensions
for a room are if you were to add that
to a min you would get one more than
what you actually wanted right now maybe
you could argue what we really want to
do here is just talk about dimensions in
a different way like we could talk about
a room like if we chose we could say
that the dimension of a room is one
tiles worth is zero that's a size zero
room two tiles is a size one room right
and if you did that you wouldn't need to
put any of these in there because then
the max allowed dim would just already
have the negative one in it so the max
allowed dim for a 16 tile room would be
a 15 right I don't know that I want to
cross that bridge I maybe that that
would actually be the right thing to do
and the code would be simpler everywhere
I just don't know if it's the right
thing to do
I I just want to point it out because
you can see it right you see it
hopefully what I'm talking about
but I don't know if that's what you
would want think that sort of one thing
is that remains to be seen
yeah
all right so let's move on I just want
to get this old code working and with
with the new sort of rule now when we go
to room Jen we can actually sort of just
quickly fix that the part of this code
that actually requires the room vol is
minimal you can see it really only
happens at the top here so when we
actually go to generate the room we can
obey the new fill rule pretty trivially
when we look at the X count and we
subtract these two things here all we
really have to do is that right now if
we want to make it a little simpler
ourselves we don't really even have to
do that what we can do instead here is
talk about one of these Jen VIII's right
and just say all right look get me the
dim of the room volume we know that that
will automatically compute all these for
us and it'll compute it with the fill
rule so we don't have to know if the
fill rate changed we would just work
which is kind of nice as well so we can
just do that and then this thing keeps
on going just fine this is a standing
room stand-in generator anyway this is
code we don't care about so we don't
have to worry about this part too much
but we will be looking at this code
later on and seeing what we think of it
all right
so is in volume also has to be changed
here and now that we're sort of getting
these bought these Jen Williams things
that we could probably pull those out
into a separate file that has what we
want in it so we could see all of the
Jen volume stuff and in kind of nicely
compacted form so let's see here all
right so we're not quite there yet as
far as placing rooms is concerned but
that's basically what we need to do so
let me go ahead and pull this out I
would like handmade Jen volume or I
don't know if Jen v3 Jen math I don't
know
and again these are like just
special-purpose routines that that
happen to work however we want them to
for just this particular case so they're
you know they're not real math routines
they're special kinds of math routines
so let me just go ahead and take a look
at everywhere that we're using these
sorts of things there we go
here's some of our initializers and
again all I'm really doing here is just
pulling these out so that you can see
them in one place relatively easily
there was a little bit more down here
all right so now we can kind of go
through and make sure that that stuff
works just debug it and then start to
use it which I think hopefully it's a
little bit better than what I had before
in terms of just the reliability of
being able to think it through I hope
will increase and who knows maybe it
won't maybe that was a waste of time
cannot open include file handmade gen
math really
Oh whoops they got put in the wrong
place my dad so these two actually want
to be in code not sure what happened
there no big deal though all right so
now I think we can go ahead and what
what was that what was that
why would what what was that does
someone want to tell me what that was
why did dividuals - he decided to take a
few seconds to do whatever it was gonna
do it doesn't always all right so now I
think we can go ahead and step through
or take a look more closely perhaps I
should first just actually make sure
this stuff makes senses at face value
but then we can go in step two and see
how to make sure that we we get this
stuff right so as for its in volume like
I said I think that's right now because
we're saying the min and the max are
both included for our infinity volumes
and inverted infinity volumes those are
again both what you'd expect they're
just setting large inclusive or soar
opposite bounds one of the other
forgetting things like testing minimum
dimensions of the room we just need to
get the dimensions of the rim which we
do here and I think we do correctly here
which is one more than whatever the
difference is we then just say look if
we're greater than 4 or 4/1 then we're
good to go for get maximum volume for
again still just taking them in the max
and the two inputs that's the same for
clipping we just always clip to the
actual value that we're given which is
exactly what we think should happen the
Union and the intersect are not changed
they should just be the same and so all
that looks fine so we must have
something in the actual usage code or I
just like skipped over something there
accidentally but we should have
something in the
usage code that I busted and did an
update because that all looks fine
alright and that actually makes sense
because I guess we got to go
double-check that we're clipping
properly to that we're clipping to the
things we actually want to clip you uh
so yeah the minimum has to be clipped to
the max plus one that makes sense the
max has to be clipped to the max I feel
like this is also I feel like doesn't
everything just have to be clipped to
here
maybe I'm wrong about that but I this
shouldn't really affect anything I think
but I believe when we're clipping
basically what we want to say is the min
and the max of the minimum can now not
go past that bound and of course the
maximum also can't go past it on the
minimum side it's basically saying hey
look I need to set the minimum needs to
lie on this line right but the the
maximum just can't go past it and the
same is true here it's basically just
saying the maximum value of the minimum
now can't go past this line and the min
and the max of the Maxwell are set to
that line so it has to be there so that
seems right to me that doesn't seem at
all odd or unusual here where we're
clipping the min in the max to the
interior apron that seems fine
so that all seems good so I would say
it's probably this code down here that's
a little bit borked because all that
looks fine to me in here we've got the
dimensions we're iterating through the
min of the max just our with minimax our
we take a look at whether we exceed the
maximum allowed dimensions for that
particular dimension in question
assuming that we do exceed the maximum
dimension in question we want to just
set the max equal to wherever the
minimum is plus whatever the allowed
dimension is minus 1 that seems fine
I don't see a problem with that so then
we say okay if the max as a result of
setting it that way would have exceeded
wherever its minimum location could have
been we need to move it to that minimum
location and then we need to set the
minimum to be whatever the maximum is -
yeah so we're setting it off of the
other direction now again that seems
fine then we look to see okay if the min
volume is greater than whatever its
maximum was allowed to be then we can't
actually fill it and then we go ahead
and do a place room so yeah I don't know
I don't see a lot of error there but
then again you never do do you place
room in volume I'm gonna see if we ever
get there just so I know who's at fault
here so it looks like that routine at
least thinks it succeeds not only let's
see what the volume it actually gives is
negative 4 to 4 day to 4 to 4 mins Eid
and Maxie so it actually created a room
it's to two things high which was not
really my intention now I think about it
that's because this is the initial room
let's try in here
kind of item to get here negative 20
negative 8 0 2 negative 5 0 0 again a
perfectly legal room so it looks like
that code is actually working probably
let me just fix one slight problem here
which is the initial room placement
actually should look more you know like
let's say that because it'd be negative
for name of 3 and negative 2 and
negative 1 or the first for 0 1 2 3 or
the next 4 and that's what it should be
set to so assuming we look at that oops
what we should see now is we should be
able to see in the the actual thing that
generates the room data right I don't
know where that went off to it's this
code but it just didn't end up on the
tabs there so in this code we should be
able to see now why we're not actually
placing a room here so what's our
dimensions it's 8 8 1 that seems very
reasonable X count why count
Z count negative 4 negative 4 0 it seems
like that should be producing a valid
you know region so I'm not sure why we
weren't seeing anything hmm I guess I
must have done something weird there may
be an initial height of 2 created some
kind of a confusion I don't know why we
have to oh maybe that's why vigils to
excite because I had another visual
studio running maybe if you try to run a
visual studio on top of another visual
studio it takes longer to load or
something I don't know I don't know why
it would so yeah just looking at just
looking at what that did that seems
pretty pretty straightforward now we're
not quite there yet because we should
have placed well I guess I don't know we
may only be placing two rooms right now
I'm not sure but but either way that
seems a little bit more saying to me I'm
I'm much more okay with that
then I was with the other way round so
let's try to let's try to make something
with with this understanding of what a
volume is let's try to make some code
that like lays out a particular
organization for what we want right so
how hard is it to manually code a
particular layout so let's say we've got
the orphanage here and we know exactly
how we want it it's just it's a fixed
layout right we're not going to let the
generation code do anything when it sees
orphanage it's got to layout exactly
this thing right so how would we go
about like coding something that looked
did a particular layout so let's let's
actually make how I want that to happen
so let's say there's like let's say
there's a hallway here and I want to
have bedrooms off of it
something like that and maybe there's a
hallway here maybe this is the same room
probably not say these are both hallways
so you got rooms off the hallway and
then maybe you've got the kitchen I
don't really know I don't study
orphanages I don't know how they would
be laid out this is the main room and
then maybe there's the backdoor area
look maybe this is actually the side
alley and this is the forest path in the
forest entrance and this is the garden
hello wait for a sense for the garden to
be in the back wouldn't it maybe take
everything
I guess technically there was a
tailoring room here
I know that seems reasonable alright so
what I'm going to do is I'm gonna do two
different steps the first step is I'm
gonna make something that basically
looks like this horrible diagram here
and tries to lay out exactly this the
next thing I'm going to do is I'm going
to try to make something that uses its
effectively a an unlocked able to make
the orphanage expand based on what the
player has you know unlocked right and
we don't actually care about unlocking
at this point it's not relevant to us
what we care about is whether it makes
it easy for the code again to talk about
stuff like does this room exist or
doesn't it exist does this hallway need
to be here or not that sort of stuff
and again the reason I'm doing this is
because I want to get I want to convince
myself remaining skeptical I want to
convince myself that talking about
inclusive on their bounds volumes I want
to convince myself that that's the most
error-free there or the least
error-prone way of discussing what tiles
a room encloses because I'm still not
sure that's what I want I just suspect
that it's what I want and until I
actually see more evidence though I
don't want to commit to it so we're just
gonna do those two steps again they're
fairly straightforward but they were
gonna require me to do a bunch of
thinking about how to specify room
bounds and that's exactly what I want to
be doing because I want to see how many
mistakes I make and if those mistakes
are related to that part of the code
that I'm talking about right that should
give me a litmus test as to whether or
not this is a sane way of describing
what I'm describing okay so what I'm
going to do here is I'm going to start
to talk about these rooms a little bit
differently I'm gonna do the same thing
that I did before where I just generated
all the rooms
in question and
I don't know if the backdoor path I
think what we're really talking about
here is there's like two hallways those
hallways at the moment are not
represented so we need those two
we need the like front hall and the back
hall and these are actually gonna be
more up in here with I guess will a
basic hall spec kind of thing these are
hallways I don't know if that's always
spec so these are just gonna be and
again we're not carrying about the spec
stuff yet that's just a placeholder to
sort of say hey look somehow we're gonna
have to talk about what's in a hallway
in addition to the fact that it is a
hallway and so that'll be where that
stuff starts getting expanded on when
we're ready but not yet so once I have
these rooms now I want to be able to
place these rooms and in some in some
way that makes sense and so what I want
to do is say all right let's put on hold
this notion of connections that are
nonspecific and let's start talking
about connections that are specific I
want to tell you where I expect these
things to be placed and then from then
from there on we can
[Music]
get a little bit more fancy right so
looking at the diagram here what I want
to do is start to talk about how
connections can be placed around around
a room I guess would be the way to say
it and so I need some way of
articulating that and I don't know what
the right way to do it would be but I
suspect that it might be something like
this so a connection is a side plus an
ordinal and then what I will do is say
that as I say what side you're connected
on I can effectively give you an ordinal
that says where you are so the zeroth
connection is here the first is here the
second is here the third is here right
and that'll give me a way of just
placing things along the sides of rooms
and then I can just iterate over them
and put them there and so in here I can
just say look when we're doing this
connection let's say now there's an
extended version of the connection call
which actually specifies what side
we're on I believe we have a what was it
called box I believe we have surface
indices that can help us here we can use
this to talk about what side of the
thing you're on in a consistent way that
we already built like a bunch of
information about so what I should be
able to say here is I want this
connection to go in this specific
location and let's let's do that so
going from the main room to the bedroom
that's not what that is anymore let's
say that this is let me let me actually
lay these out specifically on the
diagram so we know we're talking about
here a B C and D as well
hero so let's just say that's like
here's the hero's bedroom
here's a B C and D looks like there
might be an e here across that bridge
when we come to it also maybe the maybe
we want this to be you know what let's
let's let's make a slight change let's
make this a little bit more sane let me
redraw this so if this is the main room
let's say that we've got kitchen and the
tailor here
let's say that the hallway runs like
this
[Music]
right so we got the ABCD bedrooms here
and then let's say that the hero bedroom
is like right here and I feel like I
kind of want this because I want these
other bedrooms here to kind of be
available
the reason is like if we wanted to have
some save slots I was thinking that
maybe the save slops slots just mapped
to a bedroom so basically like you know
this is slot a slot B and slot C for
save games and so maybe the way that you
start your game is you pick which one of
these you want to start in and then you
hop out into the hall and go right maybe
that's how you saved your game - you hop
back in right so I don't know I'm just
throwing that out there but let's just
leave it like that because I feel like
that's how I want to do it and so then
we would just have out here here is the
forest path area
here's that side alley and here's the
garden yep
so that seems reasonable so let's go
ahead and and just make that happen
right so here we have the main room and
we know there's a bunch of stuff
connected to the main room so I'm just
going to go ahead I'm gonna just nuke
this stuff because I need to kind of
rewrite it from a diagram which is a bit
different than it was before so I'm
gonna go ahead and try to make that
happen
so from the main room I'm gonna say that
we can go like that's the westward
direction right so I'm going to say for
the main room we could go to the kitchen
and we can go to the tailor and I'm just
gonna say just a priority like I was
saying before that these will just be
ordinal based so that will just say that
the kitchen comes first and the tailor
comes next in that order for now right
as we start to play this a little bit
more I might have stronger feelings
about how that should work but for now
I'm just gonna do it that way because I
don't have a particular other way in
mind that I think is somehow really
awesome or you know whatever so then I'm
gonna go ahead and say all right we know
that we've got to the south
we've got the front hall let me do these
in in counterclockwise order like a like
a good boy
so blocks index North is the forest path
so now I'm seeing right like how those
are connected there but not saying
exactly where they are yet we'll get to
that in a second so I want to have those
that's all the connections for the main
room there are no other connections from
the main room for the back sorry the
front hall let's do the same thing so
starting on the east
we've got bedroom B and ND
I don't really care what order they go
in but if we wanted to be the same as
this diagram we would have D first then
B it's going again counterclockwise
around the ring and and then I need to
connect myself to the main room that's
already taken care of it's right here
and I need to connect myself to the back
hall and a and C so there we go now one
thing that I suppose is a little bit
tricky here is it's hard to say for a
given connection the order in which the
things get added is different depending
on which room you're talking about
so I suppose now that I think about it
it kind of needs to be not that right
counterclockwise is not sufficient
actually the reason it's not sufficient
is because let's suppose I'm talking
about a connection between these two
rooms furthermore let me do something a
little bit more specific sooo given what
I was talking about before the order in
which these things connect
I guess yeah all right so I'll be honest
maybe it's not true maybe you could
always add them in the order that makes
it so that it's correct order for both
rooms but the point that I was going to
get to was just that it becomes a little
bit finicky because you're like well the
order in which I add these maybe the
order should just be strictly in
ascending and I think I wanted that
anyway it's just easier if I just do
strictly ascending or strictly
descending order on a connection that
makes it easier because doesn't matter
what side you're talking about if I'm
talking about this side and I want to
know the connections here I know they
just go from like smallest to greatest
or whatever right in order and vice
versa
no matter which side you're on that
seems like just the more sane thing so I
don't know it may not matter but I think
I may do it that way so I think I may
say look let's just make it so that we
say we always go from smallest to
greatest so coming back here Taylor
would be first kitchen would be second
forest path and Hall are the only things
on their side so those don't matter so
then coming in here we've got it would
be d B and C a and then we need to check
to the back hall
so now that we've got that connection in
place we can connect up the the bedrooms
in the garden right now we only have one
let's let's call these let's actually
just do what I said I mean why not and
so here I'm just going to say all of
those are connected and then of course
also you can get out to the east is the
garden and then this is just a chain
these have very few
this is just like garden goes the alley
alley goes to the path path goes to the
entrance and that's it so that creates
all of the connections and says what
side those connections have to be on and
from there actually we could imagine our
layout routine as we get further into it
just taking it from there
what I want to do here though is
actually just be a little more
prescriptive than that which is to say
that I may want to just specify the
sizes of the rooms because the thing so
once it knows all of this information
the only really thing it has to figure
out is how big each room is right so
that's the like parameter if you will
that needs to get solved for for lack of
a better term how big is each room they
said it that's that's the space of
parameters because whether or not a
particular layout will succeed or fail
is just how big is each room and to like
make that a little bit more concrete
when it went to lay these things out if
for example it didn't make the hallway
long like that it wouldn't be able to
fit all of the room connections on it
without overlapping some of these okay
but I want to be a little bit more
specific than that what I want to do
here is actually sort of say how big the
rooms are and then have all the only
thing that layout routine actually is
responsible for is just making sure that
it places the things on the connections
that are that it's supposed to place
them on right and that's it so let me go
ahead and prescribe some of that stuff
so I want to set the size of all of this
stuff all right take a catacomb there
main room save slots the front all the
backhaul the bedrooms the tailor room
the kitchen the garden the fourth path
the floor suicidality okay so I do want
to do one thing and that's nurse this
why don't if this if I don't have the
side alley then I don't have a cycle in
my graph and if I set the sizes of any
of everything and don't have a cycle
then I think the route the room should
pretty much be always fairly easy for
the routine to lay out and like I said
we don't actually need to solve anything
yet to have them be laid out so what I
would like to do is set these sizes
reasonably so the main room is going to
be like a larger room maybe something
like a 16 by 16 the tailor room and the
kitchen
maybe those are like eight
sixes something like that
I don't know if six wide is quite long
enough for a kitchen in a tailor room
but I don't know let's say that it is
for now then we've got the hallway
that's just gonna be like a narrow room
maybe five wide let's say and it will be
fairly long though then we've got the
bedrooms those bedrooms should be like
pretty small
I guess that will just make 8 by 6 be
our standard size for now all right so
then we want a backhaul this is going to
be opposite of the other one this is
gonna be more like a sixteen by five
right the save slots maybe your rooms
pretty tiny
sorry Hiro and there's three across the
bottom so this actually wouldn't quite
fit along the bottom so you know maybe
more like that again sorry sorry Hiro
you're so tiny maybe we'll expand those
out so the garden that should be pretty
big I think as well and then there's no
alley at the moment the forest path
again should be probably a pretty big
area the forest entrance can be a more
narrow and then the side alley
just as an involved um I'm gonna go
ahead and pass the generator here
because generally speaking we just
passed generator as the first parameter
to things because it's sort of the
context the things operate in and we
don't know if we may need it to look up
parameters and stuff like that
get memory or do other sorts of things
so it would be nice if those things were
available alright so now we have to
actually add these informational
functions that we've created in so that
we can specify specifically more
information about these rooms and so on
alright so when we do actual connect
there's this other version of the call
that I wanted now you might ask why I
didn't just use the direction mask from
a the reason was I didn't like it being
specified at the end and the reason I
didn't like it being specify at the end
I guess this isn't a mass this is just
the direction I wanted to say let going
from from A to B put the direction in
the middle right and so this is just
another way of talking about one of
these and it can just be turned into a
regular connect call and we can actually
have this be a call directly to connect
that all it does is create the mask from
the from the index right and we have
that get surface mask here we don't have
one from a box index I don't think but
we should we should add one
so get surface max mask from one of
these again very straightforward but I'm
just gonna leave it that way so you can
see what's happening you have to wonder
why I'm doing this weird shift up thing
right and furthermore I guess since this
is only ever one direction here I can
just make this a surface index so that
the compiler will type check that and
make sure that someone doesn't pass more
than just one direction there and when I
say more than one direction I mean like
more than the band One Direction so let
me let me just call that our connect
call Co and an ECT not the defunct
peripheral ki an ECT let's go ahead and
build I've got some typos
[Music]
there we go I don't know what these are
here what did we call that as a tailor
room yes tailor room here a bedroom is
not a real thing anymore Hiro bedroom is
just gonna be like let's say hero save
slot a so now we just need this ability
to set the size of a room so that we can
pre say how big we want it to actually
be and again this is very similar to a
Kinect call in the sense that it's it's
adding sort of information to the layout
that says I'm constraining where these
rooms can be this is saying I'm
constraining the room to be specifically
this big so there's some DMX maybe I'll
sleep in this because there's a dim X
and a gym why there's probably also
technically a dim Z but we can just
assume that it's one most of the time
because we don't really use height a lot
our engine supports rooms that are fat
in that way hmm and maybe someday we
will find use for them but you know it's
really just not like we typically will
expect to have rooms stacked on top of
each other we will not expect to have
rooms that are too tall maybe there'll
be a reason to have it at some point I
don't know what that reason would be so
it's good that the engine supports it
but I don't actually know that we care
so anyway when we go in to set the size
here what we want to do is talk about in
the sort of world Jen descriptions where
we talk about what the room has and what
its spec is what I want to do is say
look in in here we know that this is
what the volume of the room is we want
to set that and we can do one of two
things either we could just say that if
the volume of the room is set to
something on entry we need to use it or
we can have something in here which sort
of additionally specifies that there was
a volume constraint
the room and so for example what we
could do is say here is a volume which
says what the minimum maximum volume is
right I and we could set that by default
to the infinity rectangle there which
says what the minimum maximum volume can
be anything you please I and then we go
from there
so I don't know how we want to set that
at the moment
[Music]
I am unsure about that so part of me
like that generality the other part of
me goes well really that's not what's
going on here
like I think most of the time if we care
this what what a room looks like it's
probably going to be specific right so
I'm guessing that we really have
something that's a little bit more like
or something like this so you know we
set a required dimension and if the
required dimension is not like zero zero
zero then we know that we've like said
it has to be this size like it has to be
this many rooms big you know I'm saying
so I'm thinking that we've got something
more like okay this room's required dim
I don't know why I made four of those
so I guess that would technically I mean
Einstein taught us there were four
dimensions right and the time is one of
them so I mean who are we to disagree
with Einstein he is you know a
historical figure to be reckoned with
and I certainly don't want to have to
argue with him that there aren't four
dimensions because he will probably
prevail in that argument and where would
that leave me anyway the the required
dimensions if we set those then when we
go to place a room we know that we don't
really have to think about the
dimensions much anymore we can just sort
of place rooms with the dimensions that
we encounter and so then we can sort of
simplify that routine that we were
looking at or I don't know that I want
to actually get rid of it here but you
know I guess basically saying this
placement code as it stands is not
something we're going to use right
in fact we just don't need that
particular place room call so in here
when we kind of scoot through things so
I'm gonna go ahead and and do sort of a
an excision on this and say that we're
just going to assume the volume is
they're trying to think of how I want to
do this so I think what I want to do is
sort of rewrite this loop this part I
don't care about anymore we don't need
it and so what I want to do I think is
try another one of these
uh so I want to do basically what I was
doing before or at least something
similar but what I want to do here is
say okay if I don't know where this room
should be yet then I sort of place it
based on I mean mmm I want to rewrite
this routine so that I always know where
the room is before I start to visit it
right so when I pop a room off
I expect to already know where it is and
all I'm gonna do is place the rooms that
are next to that room and push them on
the sack I think that's what I want to
do you notice my hesitancy here
but I think that's what I'm gonna do so
I'm just gonna try and stamp that so
heres my much time do I have by the way
I've got 15 minutes left right yeah
which I think it's good
a second here let's see here okay
so I'm gonna take a room and I want to
sort of loop over the things that are in
that room the one thing I do have a
little bit of concern about I'm just
trying to get how to to structure this
so what I think I want to do is say okay
the first room I I know where it's gonna
go
it's gonna go inside its prescribed
volume like so and you can see here like
I feel like this is starting to argue
for actually allowing those VIII's to be
like added together and stuff because
you can see that we would save some time
by just doing this right so that would
probably be okay
so I'm gonna take the first room I'm
gonna place the room and then what I
want to do is I want to loop over all of
the connections to the room and place
them now what I can probably do here
just say all right let's push this room
and that'll be our loop we grab a room
we we assume it's generation index has
not been set
[Music]
well that's not quite right either is it
no that's fine
so we do set its generation index
we push it on assuming its generation
index has not been set we visit its
neighbors and place them assuming if we
don't we don't I'm not sure if that's
quite right in that case you'll just
look like this
so you'd push the room on the stack if
you if you don't match the narration
actually you place all of its neighbor
rooms who haven't been placed yet I just
don't like the way that feels it does
kind of strike me as I think about it
although I want to be centric on a room
and spinning it that way it seems like
it doesn't want to be backwards the way
the other one was so maybe I just leave
it that way
I don't know maybe that is the better
way to do it it's not quite sure so
anyway if we assume that then we would
do it this other way where we just push
the connected rooms on like so and they
stay the same
and then so really all we're doing here
is we're just gonna say there's rooms
the room is placed by rote
so we look through all of our
connections till we find a room that has
already been placed we know where along
the line of rooms we should be and we
put ourselves there right the thing
that's a little annoying is it just
feels like this is going to do the same
placement like multiple times although I
suppose to be fair what I can do is
place everything along one edge at the
same time
that actually doesn't seem so bad
so yeah inside here where we say let's
loop over the connections to this thing
and you kind of see how that goes here
in fact it looks like this sort of thing
we don't really need the push connected
rooms call anymore because it's just
gonna do exactly this thing but that's I
suppose neither here nor there in fact
yeah you can sort of see what's going on
here if we actually did this if we loop
over these what we would say is let's
get the connection if we haven't placed
that room make sure we put that room on
the stack you have to visit it but more
importantly we want the other case now
as well so we're actually gonna do
something on both in the case where we
find a room that has been placed then
what we want to do is place ourselves
relative to that room right so here is
the actual call this would be like you
know and then when we're done we assume
that the room has been placed now the
confusing part is if we've already
placed the room we don't want to place
the room again so in a sense what we
really want to do here as well is just
double check ourselves I suppose
and only make sure we place ourselves
once
and that seems reasonable so when we go
to place ourselves really all we're
asking for is what's the min X min Y min
Z but because we know do you know what
our volume is since all the volumes have
been prescribed so far but that's not
exactly what we want to do here quite
yet
and the reason for that is because we
don't actually know how many things have
to be placed along this edge right so we
want to do is say all right for this
particular connection we want to like
place the connection right so we want to
sort of say for for whatever this
connection is or a long edge I guess we
want to basically say the other room is
a known good room like we know that it
goes in a particular place and we're not
confused about its location or size so
we're gonna say from there using the
direction that we the the edge of that
room that is what we connect to we want
to place ourselves and all the other
people who also share the same
connection so in order to do that we
need to and I guess that could set the
generation index itself I suppose so
maybe let's say that and maybe we'll do
this
so we need to figure out what direction
we use the connection in so like what
direction we're talking about there and
I don't quite remember how that worked
but I thought we had actually talked
about that before there's like an
inversion version of this area yeah but
get box mass compliment right um so what
I want to do here is just say I want to
know what direction I use this
connection in so I kind of want to call
that's like for me what direction does
this connection go in
for the time being I kind of want to
assert that it's just only got one bit
set I don't think we have his character
doing for the time being I would want to
make sure that no one was trying to do a
fancier placement with this particular
connection because obviously we're only
whole we're only going to do ones in
this situation where we are talking
about a single direction for the time
being right but I yeah I'll just ignore
that for a moment so miss a direction
equals get direction or room and I'm
just gonna say for this connection what
direction I guess it's it's this room
from the other room to me what direction
is it going right and then we'll say hey
that's the edge we're talking about here
so I want to figure out what the bounds
are of that edge and we'll do that in a
second but that's I think this sketch of
the routine right we're just going to go
through and place rims along the edge
and then when we're done we assume that
we did place that room so in this case
this it's it's really we've already done
this this call it's this right and so we
can sort of leverage that up here by
saying well we're just this is what
we're doing so the direction mask for
whichever room we're coming from it's
either gonna be the compliment or the
thing that was stored there depending on
which room we're talking about because
the connection can go either direction
so when we talk about getting the
direction for the room it's really the
fur it's the preamble to the could go
direction which just tests it after that
right so what we want to do is is
probably just reuse this code I could
probably just do this and say okay the
dirt mask is actually just get direction
for room like so on and so forth
maybe we call that Gator mask from room
and I think that's mostly what we're
talking about now in the case where yeah
like you can see where we don't know
whether we're we have not placed the
room that's on the other side then
that's just something we want to revisit
later in their routine so this is just
crawling out and placing anything it
thinks it can please rooms along edge
will be much simpler than what we did
before it'll just start at the min and
lay the rooms out according to their
height if it runs out of room it'll just
be an error right and that's it so to do
that we need to do first is say okay
let's loop along everything that matches
that derp mask we really kind of want to
assert the derp mask here so I kind of
want to do a bit scan to figure out what
the index is and I want that bit scan to
be a single value right because we're
sort of saying this is a special purpose
routine that only works if you know the
data looks a specific way because it can
we're sort of crawling where we're
learning to crawl before we can walk
here so we're we don't want this mask to
have anything other than one direction
specified and when I say one direction
specified I mean the band One Direction
so if I if I come into a replace rooms
long edge I want to sort of get a an
index
where I can sort of say look give me the
box and next to corresponds to this
direction mask and it's just an error if
it doesn't right I just want you to
assert if it doesn't that means we're
outside the bounds of what we're playing
with right now and off we go so that
would be something like okay here's the
derp mask
let's bit scan it which I believe we
actually have
and so let's just use the the least
significant bit set and we'll just do
that will assert that there was one will
assert care that it found one that's
actually reasonable right so it can't be
it can't be outside the bounds of the
legal indices that we claim to have and
finally it has to be equal to the
original if we reconvert it right so the
dur mask has to be equal to what we
would get if we then tried to convert it
back to a mask now why am i doing that
part that's to ensure that you can't
pass something with more than one bit
set so I'm going to ensure that you set
a bit I'm going to ensure that that bit
was within the range of bits we allow
and then finally I'm gonna ensure that
you only had one set because if you had
more than one set if you turn this back
into a mask it will only have one set
and this will have multiple set and you
will get an assertion failure because
you won't actually match all right
so moving back to the generation code
now that we know that we actually
haven't in next then what we want to do
is just step over the room connections
that we have here so this this same code
here is what we're going to to operate
with so if I if I opt to iterate over my
room's connections what I want to do is
say alright if the other room that we're
talking about here is a room that has
not been placed yet which would look
like this then we're gonna place that
room it's gonna be the sort of room
everything calls that when you climb out
like lots of different rooms I think it
helps to name them once you get down in
here so I don't know what we want to
call this like the original room or the
the base room let's say so I'm gonna
call this the base room and say that the
base room is like a different thing
right and so that maybe then we can say
all right then there's the the other one
will be the one called the room by Tommy
Wiseau and that way we're just talking
about the room is the one we're
operating on and the base room is this
other thing that we don't really care
about anymore right
so this would place all those rooms we
have to figure out how we want that to
work again we're only talking about ones
that share this particular directional
mask however so I want to go ahead and
make sure that the directional mask
ann's properly so the connections der
mask and I guess I have to make sure
that I know could where's the could go
direction call that's the I actually
just want to make that call I want to
make sure we're only gonna do it for
connections that actually match right so
from the base room I want to make sure
that if I pass this dur mask that I
could go that direction
so I think that's all good I need to
actually have a version of the function
that works that way
so one that doesn't have the dim side
thing one that just has the test mask
right so that way I have the test masses
being passed in and I just want to know
if I could go that direction from the
base room is is this is this actually a
is this connection actually legal to go
in the direction that I'm trying to
place it in it's not them don't want to
do it because it's not one of the ones
getting placed in this slight in this
edge cycle so when I'm going to be
placing the rooms along the edge here
what I want to do is say as I place each
individual room I'm gonna kind of move
myself down I know what the dimensions
of the room have to be but I need to be
able to place them off of an edge right
so here's the part that actually
requires a little bit of finesse what I
need to be able to do is I need at this
point when I actually place it I need to
be able to use some knowledge of of how
big this room has to be so the room
required dim right I need to be able to
take that required dim in line up the
room so that it lines up with the edge
that I'm actually placing it on and has
that size
so in order to do that I think we want
to go from min to max generally speaking
like I said along the edge so I want to
do something where I'm basically saying
like my min edge P is gonna be starting
out getting using the der mask I want to
be able to get what that minimum is and
so if I look at what my boxed s-- value
stuff lets me do here I should be able
to say using those surface params like X
and s and positive I should be able to
use that to decrypt essentially what I'm
being asked to do so if I use the
surface index here that I got out of my
term asked then when I get the surface
params I can look at the axis index and
say that whatever the room that I'm in I
can now ask what its minimum value is
for that axis so now I know what the
minimum and maximum values are that I
could place along my edge right
I know what those are so as I place
things I know how to place a long
Vantage actually quite well right what I
need to do is take the room by Tommy was
oh and I need to put its volume for that
axis index and and you know I'll just
grab that out into an easier to talk
about Fang so I grab out which axis I'm
talking out that is the edge that's the
placement edge then as I go through each
individual room I'm going to say for
this volume I want to place the minimum
at wherever I'm currently residing so
again just talk about the maximal number
of things here so we can see them all
I want to start there right I know that
I need to place the maximum of that room
at whatever the required dimension would
be minus one again because we're always
we don't talk about fill there and then
I need to advance at edge P to be
effectively this value now I can shorten
this a little bit just to be if I want
to be cheeky by essentially doing that
because that's what we're actually doing
here and then using at HP minus one to
set where I want to be now when I'm done
with this I want to see that at edge P
is less than or equal to the max HP
otherwise we overflowed this the size if
we actually want to keep those rooms all
placed along the edge this is what we
would need to do so I'm just gonna
assert that again this is a very simple
version of the edge placement routine
now are we done no the reason that we're
not done is that just places the edge
information right what we haven't done
now is lined up these rooms with the
other axes that we care about and so
what we need to do is based on the
directional mask that we're talking
about here we need to figure out how
everything else would have been aligned
based on that particular mask so we know
a particular Exynos and we know a
direction the question is what happens
to everything else right what happens to
everything that isn't talked about in
the edge axis we have two off axes right
and so we have one case we probably have
two different ways we might want to talk
about this and and specifically that's
like if the connection was along Z or
not like is it an up-down connection or
is it not an up-down connection right
would be one way to talk about that and
and those are you know different
depending on on how we want to think
about them right
but this connects the the thing
is most of the way that we want and so
what we're trying to figure out now is
how we would talk about these other
things right and what we need to do here
is we need to set up the mins and maxes
so that they align properly and let's
take a look at what that would entail
diagrammatically speaking right so I got
a ghost and I'm running out of time
so what I want to do here is say all
right in the case where I've got
something happening like this we know
that this part of the layout the part
that did that and that is now taken care
of what hasn't gotten taken care of is
this part right so what we want to do is
we want to figure out are we setting the
max or are we setting them in of the
other directions that are involved and
then we can sort of push those we can we
can set those up the way that they
should be set up right and to a certain
extent I think that's just going to look
something like this
we need sort of the other axis
and you can see how this is something we
could actually pull out into other code
as well so we want to say like look do
we align these things to the min or the
max so if we align them to the min then
what we want to do is we want to set the
maximum in this case is the first thing
we want to set and we want to set the
min to be equal to the maximum -
whatever the dimension is right and then
there's that plus 1 because the
dimension is always slightly different
right so you can see there we've kind of
got like alright we're replacing the the
room along the edge then we need to know
what we're going to place here and in
this case we know that this is going to
be whatever the base room had I just
want to start one prior to that so
that's where this room would have but
right and then furthermore the opposite
version of this would be true we know
that if we were going to align to the
max then what we would do is take
whatever the max was move one out from
that and then you know do the exactly
symmetric process here right
and that's it that again is gonna happen
for the other two axes right the other
two I'm sorry the other axe
it's gonna happen for both axes that we
care about again we can can we can
consolidate this a little bit in a
second here or probably you next week
but that's all we're talking about and
so what we want to know in this case is
once we get the surface index we want to
know you know what the other axes that
we're setting actually are I'm not gonna
belabor that point too much we're gonna
probably again pull that out into
something a little bit more usable so
what I'm gonna do here is just say we'll
set these up by just doing a pretty
simple switch statement here so we know
we've got the surface index and I'm just
going to decrypt it manually and then I
think like I said this is something we
can make a little bit more programmatic
in a second but I just want to leave
this ploy sketched out and then we'll
come back to it next week
alright so in the case where we're doing
west and east then axis a is one axis B
is two right in the case where we're
doing south and north then axis a is
zero and axis B is two and then if it's
up and down it's the other ones right
then in terms of other amen other be men
if we're going to the west then be lines
up with the men and a lines up with the
man I guess
that's not actually quite true right
so B actually wants to just be equal to
it in this case right look I think we
actually just want instance we don't
have up and down connections yet let me
just do this because we actually don't
need to do that at all now I think about
it you can just have it be equal to that
so the other a is really the only one we
actually need there and this is not
necessary
so right now we're just gonna do those
and we'll do it slightly differently
when we get when we start supporting me
up and downs as well
hips so South it lines up with the men
yes and North Atlanta with the max so
that's fine
and I think that sets up the volume
properly I think notice note we are not
setting up the doors right now so we
actually still would need to set up the
doors but other than that I think we've
got everything sketched in here if the
doors are pretty easy to set up they
just get set up in the middle of these
things so it's not particularly hard for
us to do it but that's what we want to
do right so I'm gonna leave it there I
think and we'll come back because I
don't have I can't really go any later
than this today so I'm gonna leave it
there and go to quick Q&amp;A but the
[Music]
interesting
so from this room it's got some kind of
a non-symmetric connection so that'll be
interesting to look at I'm gonna leave
it there and I will come back to it come
back to it next week I don't necessarily
not want to leave it running though I'm
tempted to just look at it really
quickly push connected rooms from the
first room
you
Orphanage for its entrance whoa but
what did I do did I miss up something in
the Kinect call
okay so that's not great to say the
least
okay so I think that's fine potentially
I should go and check that maybe because
I did something stupid but let's find
out what room it's on if that's from the
orphanage forest entrance so that when
the orphanage forest entrance should
only have
that's north it should only have a North
from the main room yeah to the forest
path forth to the yeah so that should be
that one should really not have so you
know now I think about it this assertion
really isn't valid because you do have
bigger rooms connected to smaller rooms
so I it's really we really can't assert
until we have we just need to assert
that the rooms don't overlap that's the
only thing that we can really assert
there so that at that assertion is
actually bogus so yeah all right so at
least things are running properly now so
I I just need to debug everything and
we'll do that next week because I just
want to go to brief brief Q&amp;A before I
have to go I and yeah you can watch next
week when we go debug it
Viterbo said the edge axis is wrong
gives a direction of the connection not
the axis the connected room should align
- I'm sorry I'm just not sure which part
of the code you're talking about
which part of the code are you talking
about
oh I su think yes okay okay okay I see
what you're saying these are inverted
right so the edge axis is actually this
one and the surface axis is actually the
other one right because we're talking
about the direction we're connecting
along
I suppose while we're here I mean I can
just do
right so basically if we're traveling
west then the edge axis is actually
going to be the y-axis and the alignment
axis is going to be the one that we
actually are using right I don't really
need this at the moment so yeah so
that's actually more like it but I don't
think that really necessarily will help
us yet
I think that's not quite sufficient yeah
because that should have just made
everything be mirrored look at this
again
can the next thing be fashion is such a
way to form a long empty corridor or a
stairway up and down to connect two
rooms
well connection is not doesn't really
mean that connection means to abutting
regions so that's actually not you would
create a room that was the shape you're
talking about you mentioned a few
schemes to go that the Xbox 360
controller has a crap potentiometer do
you have an example controller with a
good one not really I haven't played
around with them that much to look I
suspect most consumer controllers have
poor potentiometers because they're
trying to be inexpensive and people
can't tell that well the game developer
just has to kind of like hide it all I'm
only going to take on topic questions at
the moment have you think to use a
constraint solver algorithm for room
lighting I guess I'm taking it you
weren't here last weekend that's that's
what we started talking about originally
but we want to we have to get there kind
of slowly right you can't just start
with a constraint solver can the hero
have the ability to dig the ground and
fall through to the floor of the room
below it yes if we restrict that to only
diggable surfaces because we need to
wait and make it so that you can't dig
in places because we'd fall out of the
world if there was nothing below you so
you could make digging sure but it would
have to be specific to a particular
ground tile type
if you want to you can raid a bug on
that as a future request in the github
alright I'm gonna wrap it up thank you
everyone for joining me for the set a
hand made here oh it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along with the code at
home you could always pre-order the game
on hand mahir org and it comes with a
source code so as it gets developed you
can play around with it yourself that's
it for this weekend I will be back here
next weekend to get all that stuff to
bugged and then we should have our sort
of ability to play around with some
basic room designs and moving around and
things and then we can start to look at
stuff about how we want to actually go
about doing some of the more generative
stuff where we don't completely specify
say the sizes of rooms and we let it try
to solve for how big they would be or
should be or where they should be in the
case where they could be in multiple
places that's about it until next time
thanks for joining and I'll see you all
on the Internet take it easy everybody