all right so hello everyone and welcome
to hand made here the show where we code
a complete game from scratch on Twitch
live with no libraries no engine
everything is coded from scratch because
when you do something from scratch
everyone knows it tastes better this is
like when you make the chocolate chip
cookies and they're fresh and awesome ok
not the store-bought ones that are all
crusty and moldy and nobody wants that
nobody wants a licensed cookie ok you
don't want all of that weird you know
sort of the artificial flavors and
colors you can't even read the label
you're like looking at it I don't know
what that's in there you don't want that
right you don't want that giant build
soup that's not going to work out for
you but from scratch that's the only way
we do it here it's delicious it's just
like momma used to code and that's how
we're doing it here on handmade hero
anyway we have some debugging to do
today because we made some changes
yesterday and didn't have time to go
through and debug them and so I want to
go ahead and do that because I hate it
when we know we've got some digging to
do and haven't done it yet so if you
want to follow along with that debugging
and along with that chocolate chip
cookie metaphorically speaking today is
day 72 so if you have pre-ordered the
source code and downloaded that you want
to unzip day 71 source code because
that's what I am starting with right now
so if you want to follow along with it
that is that is the way to do it so
let's take a look some people on the
forums were writing in what they
suspected the bugs to be and they might
be right we don't know like I said I had
to stop last night I did not have time
to step through and debug it so we don't
know what you know what we actually did
we don't know what might be wrong but
somebody did send in one bug that's
definitely a bug whether it's our butt
or not it's definitely a bug so let me
go take a look at here I will point out
to you yes so when we were doing our cut
and pasting yesterday we had one
cut-and-paste problem which is we have
not yet checked the Z coordinate for our
rectangle three right again we don't
even we haven't there's probably tons of
bugs
our math library just to be clear
because like I said we're not really
concerned super much about bugs at this
point we're just trying to our
architecture stuff when we get when it
gets time to really sort of get them to
it and we have everything in place where
we want it we'll probably do more sort
of testing and battle hardening of some
of this stuff so yeah we've got some
bugs in it but when someone points them
out it's good to fix them this is
obviously one of them we were not
checking the z-coordinate here is for
our is in rectangle you can see that
most of the rectangle code is not
actually based at all on actual elements
that's the only one that is so when we
change is in when we change rectangle
dimensions when we went from two to
three that's the only thing that really
had change it seems like everything else
is pretty much just in terms of the
underlying vectors and dozen really have
to change so there is that the other
thing that someone wrote in and pointed
out which is also a bug is inside our
world code yesterday we were just kind
of going through again and part of that
giant change removing everything going
directly to three-dimensional everywhere
was that when we were doing a sort of
the the words that where is it at here
the thing that we were using only for
temporary world building it was this
chunked position from tile position this
thing right here when we were doing our
multiplication to multiply out where the
tot where stuff was in tile space we
were using chunk diamond meters we're
really opposed to be tile side meters
right because these are in tiles not
chunks that we wanted to do here and so
that was actually making the world it
would make the world much more sparse
because they've read every you know time
we were thought we were putting things
kind of at tile boundaries and again we
don't have tiles anymore so this is just
a positioning aid so we could still kind
of make some tile based stuff before we
go and do something more complicated but
it's definitely a bug so yeah I guess
this is no longer had a marred product
either at the moment because this is
actually just going to be multiplying
this vector by a scalar and that's about
it and let's take a look here okay so
that's two bugs that people wrote in and
found on the forums kind of nice to have
it's kind of like having a giant set of
code reviewers who just like look for
bugs all taking her
but I it's kind of a real nice bonus
of doing all this stuff live is and and
and having the source code available
right is this like you kind of get free
debugging services kind of cool anyway
but so I I don't know if that will
actually fix the problems the initial
bugs were having it might not and so
well and that for some reason it looks
like changing that because we were not
getting this yesterday looks like
changing that was causing a problem with
our our map into chunks face call it as
well so I don't know what that's about
that seems a little bit odd why is it
complaining
well sorry I'm pretty thirsty let's take
a look at what we computed here get a
little warmed up here all right so we
have an offset which is going to be
whatever what is this actually computing
XY and Z no no that's not what I wanted
to view I wanted to view this we're in
the wrong space here that's I want of
view 132 is the offset what is our tile
though this is just an hour thing to map
back to our canonical coordinates our
tile relative is still yes so this is
another one of those once the things get
large so you remember I said this
yesterday in fact I was like when we
were writing this I was like well we can
we could take advantage of map in a
chunk space and just do it that way but
it's going to be a precision problem
well this is exactly the precision
problem I was talking about right as
these numbers get larger the precision
is going to go down and we end up in
this circumstance where it's having
trouble figuring out you know which
which tile it goes in but which top
chunk it goes I should say but we don't
super care about that right now but what
I do want to say just again is like
eventually what I think we're going to
want to do for building the world we're
going to do the same thing we did for
simulating the world since we want to be
able to build really huge world's what
we want to be able to do is just build a
local region doing everything in float
and then
move that region over so like when we do
you know based on rooms or we we sort of
say here's an area that we're making and
we make that area and then we can sort
of move our like focus over somewhere
else and then do again all of the stuff
around a local coordinate origin and
that again is just to let us scale to
like these really really huge worlds
which again we don't necessarily know
that we need but I just saying I wanted
to show how to do on the stream because
it's more complicated than just throwing
everything in a float and then that's
never letting the world get big enough
to care and it may let us do some fun
stuff like allowing you to generate a
game it'll take you a year to play and
and somebody would do it you know that
if we shipped a game that took a year to
play there be a player who would not
only do it but stream the whole thing
right so who knows you know why why
fight it
why fight it just just do the code and
let it go so so I think we don't super
care with that we can just expand our
epsilon for now but that's really and we
already have the to do about it which
basically says we're going to have to
certify this we should be able to week
when we do our Rica nautical eyes we
should be able to really get that
epsilon down to essentially nothing once
we are never once we are not relying on
the build world stuff because we're
always going to be around that local
origin and we should be able to make it
so it's really not that bad but for now
that's definitely the case that we're
going to run into those and I don't know
how bad we're going to run to them let
me double check to make sure that's yeah
I just want to make sure that that's not
something else but see what the chunk
game is here chunk Jim actually look at
the chunk / - yeah wow that's off by a
lot that's off by like 0.01 right that's
just I that's just a really really large
error but yeah I don't think there's
anything bad going on there I really
just think that's you can't build the
world that goes out that far and expect
to get that that level of error there is
that even gonna be enough I thought be
not yeah so maybe that's not enough to
do oh well alright so I guess it was
just that fact that we were spreading
the world out that was it everything
else was fine
we looks like we did everything else
okay as far as I can tell from here
anyway looks about right to me
awesome site so we'll have to do a
little bit of work with that apparently
you can jump up over the world now check
this out when I yeah
I'm able to kind of go up into the next
tier and then land back down we're gonna
we'll have to take a look at our Z
handling as so our Z handling is is not
quite right yet that's for sure
so we'll have to take a look at that but
that's okay that's what we're supposed
to be doing currently anyway that was
awesome
I don't know why it's kind of weird it's
like you jump twice and do it alright so
let's take a look at that look let's
take a look at that that's pretty funny
and I want to see what's going on there
as you can see we also on our little
to-do thing here we've got some other
things that we want to do with C so I
think you know we'll just kind of spend
some some more Z time I want to take a
look at what's going on here with this
particular bug I know that we kind of
quit we hastily moved the processing for
the Z equations of motion right we move
those into we rolled them essentially
into the the rest of the computations
for the equations of motion so they
operate exactly the way that they used
to operate right and so the way that we
did that was we went in here and we made
the acceleration of the guy be negative
9.8 which is negative m/s squared that's
the that's gravity right this is just
it's just gravity and then what we did
is we just rolled that into the
acceleration and allowed it to get
computed along with the acceleration
that was going on in the horizontal
plane and that seems ok I don't think
there's there's anything strange going
on there it doesn't look like so I think
we can probably say that that's fine
for now then what we did at the end is
we took a look to see whether the
location of the guy was below the the
sort of the low bar right below the
Jimmy below the the ground if you will
which is zero and if it was we would set
it back up to zero and again that seems
fine nothing particularly weird there
but one thing that we didn't sort of do
too much about was the sort of the thing
where you actually do the jump code I
believe where is our jump code there it
is I believe that our con he rode easy
handling maybe a little where is it now
it looks good so what's our our DZ is
three so we'd be going up
so we're flat setting the velocity of
our guy to basically go up whenever the
the DS that you know that space bar goes
down if that's the case I would have
expected the jumping to look roughly the
same as it was looking so it's a little
bit odd that it's not and I'm not sure
exactly what's going on there so I kind
of think we may have to step through
here and just take a little look at
what's going on because I can't Intuit
anything obvious it's going wrong there
again we pull out the Z here right in
order to get the entity Z we use meters
to pixels as we were before and we just
kind of roll that into the y coordinate
and that's how we're having him jump up
and down but he used to go much further
and so now I'm wondering why he is it
and so let's just go ahead and see what
happens the first time through that
seems pretty reasonable to me so
I don't know but all seems fine so and
then I guess we also have the other bug
to look at which which I'm going to look
at separate I'm going to look at after
this one which is why you're able to
kind of push yourself up into the next Z
bracket and not go back down I guess
that would happen if the jump height if
you could get high enough in the jump to
go up then really this I mean
technically this right here would do it
right because if you can jump let me
draw this out
hello there we go so the thing I'm
thinking about here is just we we do
that is what would happen the jump code
would do exactly what I just said in the
case where you imagine all right this is
a side view and here is the current tile
ABS tile Z so this is like this is our
ABS tile Z that we're on right we're in
this chunk right I should actually say
ABS tile G we can just say our trunk Z
right so we're in this chunk right now
and here is another chunk right well
when we jump up right our guy leaves the
sort of the baseline which is zero and
if he were to cross up high enough that
he went above the next chunk Z right
chunk z plus one then when he came back
down his we're just checking for his
position his relative position meaning
his position relative to the camera
right to go less than 0 and if it is
this relative the camera goes less than
zero then we just go ahead and say okay
he he stops right he stops here so you
would always jump up and land on the
thing it would be kind of like you know
a Mario situation or not Mario I guess
Mario didn't si do this but you know in
a platformer where
you're standing on something and you
jump up and then you can pass through
this thing this other platform but then
when you land you land on it you know
you go up like that
that's essentially what's going on here
because we're not preventing you from
jumping up through things and then
you're landing on them and we don't even
check right all we're doing is checking
for less than Z less than zero that
again that's the camera relative Z all
we're doing is checking for the Z less
than zero and since we're only checking
for the Z less than zero what that means
is that it doesn't even matter if
there's anything there right you don't
do landing on something you just have to
go above the zero line and come back
down so probably that's roughly what's
happening I'm guessing but that still
doesn't explain why we're seeing why it
looks so weird when you do it like I
don't understand why we're getting that
sort of behavior where it's that little
tiny jump like that it just doesn't it
doesn't look right so I want to debug
that first and find out what's going on
there and maybe that will also be a clue
to what's going on I want to take a
quick look to as how for how we update
the camera here I just want to see how
that worked so it looks like we we are
just using the chunk Z for the camera so
right now we're not even really doing Z
tracking the camera
other than the chunk Z so I feel like
that shouldn't have really been a
problem oh nope that's the problem right
there
yeah so we actually are we're fully
tracking the guys motion with our Z so
really when you were jumping you were
seeing the offset of the guy and the
camera was following him up so that's
actually what was happening and that's
the cause of the entire problem if we
didn't do that I think we'd be okay well
actually I guess I can't quite do that
yet since we didn't write that code yet
but so let me just comment out the
camera following and now we should yeah
we should have the ability to jump the
way we were jumping before and we do
yeah looks about right
yeah so okay I'm not sure exactly what
we want to do with that for the moment
we can do this and then because really
what we want to do is we want to go
actually work on ours our Z stuff anyway
so it's possible that we could do a
thing where we kind of do only we do
only the x and y coordinates of course
these are world positions here so we
can't do that directly but what we could
do is something more like you know this
sort of thing where we take a chunk X
and we do that one chunk X so on
actually know what I could do to I can
just do I could just save the Z can Z
offset and grab off whatever that
actually is right so here's offset dot Z
and then I can go ahead and just say you
know what the new camera P does equal to
stored P but then we restore its offset
Z to whatever it used to be right like
so and that would prevent the camera
from tracking us in Z and then we're
back to you know what we're doing for
now we should still be able to yeah
there we go
we should still be able to virtually
jump up a level by just keep jumping
because remember we don't cap your jump
height you have infinite jumps so I feel
like we should still be able do that
reliably and we can and that again just
moves us up one layer alright so that
all makes reasonable sense I think
nothing particularly weird going on
there to me
but now we get down to some harder work
here we kind of got to think about some
of these things I have to admit I kind
of want to do this one I know that it
really I don't even know why like it's
one of those obsessive things it's like
why do we even care about that at all it
doesn't even make any sense
Ike I just want to do it just because I
had said it was a puzzler and then it's
like we we solved it without even
realizing it and I just want to do it so
I kind of feel like I'm just going to do
that um because I want to I don't have
any other reason I don't have any other
reason I just want to see if we could do
it so if you remember when we first did
this I was like well you know we have
these world positions which is saying
where guys are in everything and then we
store the entities we store where they
are in the world via these you know
these worlds entity block structures or
whatever right and if you know what if
you if you're looking at world entity
blocks you know where that world entity
block was in terms of chunk X Y &amp; Z like
the chunk x y&amp;z is stored in a world
chunk and all the world blocks are off
of a world chunk so why would we then go
ahead and store in the entity what its
position was because we don't we don't
need that right and so I feel like we
can get away with no longer storing this
right meaning we can still use the world
position structure when we want to talk
about a full world position but instead
in in the actual entities themselves
right we wouldn't need to store this
world position at all right we could
just we could just get rid of it
entirely I think and instead just use
the offset field in there inside the sin
entity we could just use all we really
need the story's just what the offset is
from its chunk that's the only piece of
information we actually need it because
the chunk XY and Z will just be implicit
when we iterate over them right and so I
guess we do have one thing here where we
try to store the invalid information in
world entities p apiece director
whatever there but we maybe will get can
get rid of that too I don't know so
let's just try it I just want to try it
and see if we can solve this puzzle er
which we had set up way back from when
we originally did world positions so
what I'm going to do first is I'm just
going to flat out get rid of this right
it's going away I'm going to see what
code actually used it okay and something
I do all the time right use comment
something out and see where all your
compiler eyes are now I know everyone
whoever accessed it right so all right
change it any location well chain
generally location only accesses it to
set it basically right let's see where
it actually cares about that it looks to
see if it's valid but we could get rid
of that like I said we could make it so
that people have to pass in some
additional thing if they want invalid
things so it seems like when we do
change entity location raw all we really
needed to know is where they were before
right so we don't need to store it we
wouldn't need to know where what chunk
they were in so we need to know like
where they came from world chunk wise
but that's about it
so it would mean that when we do change
any location we would have to pass in a
old position which we used to do right
we used to pass in an old position and
we would have to do that again in order
to do the removal so do we care about
that basically what it would mean is
that our sim region when we unpack our
entities right we would have to store in
in the same region something that allows
us to get back to where it where the the
thing was right and I'm not sure that's
a bad trade-off that seems like
something that might be totally fine
[Music]
yeah I think I think I like that better
basically all it needs is it needs to
know what the world chunk is to
basically be able to remove this thing
and so we could just flat-out store a
pointer to whatever the world chump was
since we know that the low entities in
there we know that the world chunk can't
get removed so we could just say that
you know when we do our sim entity when
we pull something out into simulation we
kind of just say oh you know we we go
ahead and say there's the there's the
world chunk which ever you know chunk it
was in it's from this chunk right and
then when somebody changes the location
of entity they just pass in whatever the
world chunk was where it used to be
right so we pass in a world chunk here
would say this is where it's from you
know and then it would say where it
wants it to be now and we wouldn't
really need this new P init thing
anymore probably in fact I don't
actually know why it was doing it that
way
yeah why was it doing it that way
I do not know why I was doing it that
way it's a bit wonky to say the least
but there we go
so anyway yeah we pass a from chunk or
you know when old chunk basically right
and we could say this is old chunk as
well and yeah and then we pass in the
new P let's just go ahead and try that
we would get rid of the the old P new P
thing we would say don't worry about
that at all and we don't really care
about grabbing that old P out at all I
don't think yeah I don't think we care
about this at all we we only really care
about being able to set it to invalid so
I guess we'll leave that in the case
that the new P was not valid that got
passed in so we'll change Trinity
location raw to take the old chunk and
it'll just do that that way doesn't have
to do a look up there anymore so that
actually saves us a hash lookup and a
traversal - well no just a hash to come
I guess save as a hash lookup so that's
good
and then at the end when we do the new P
assuming that that actually was correct
we don't have to store it back I guess
all we have to do is in the low entities
sim entity it's it's a it's offset I
guess now gets retained right so we
would retain whatever that new P offset
was and that I think is about it we
don't have to initialize this at all so
I think that's it and then when I go to
change in any location raw right I come
up here and now this just takes a world
chunk and this is the old chunk so and
we don't really have this assertion
anymore we would then have to say this
this code actually I guess excuse me
it's a little more complicated because
we don't we can't actually ask about our
in same chunk well actually I guess we
can if we have world chunk that actually
does have the information that we need
right so if we go to loop Stephon here
yeah that actually just that so what we
could do is say
if old chunk and noopy are in same chunk
you can just pass old chunk there and
then are in same chunk we just need
another one of those one that takes a
world chunk right and it can still do
basically the same thing but now instead
it just checks off of a pretty
straightforward that works exactly the
same way so that's good so if that's the
case we don't really have to do anything
about it I guess then when we go in here
if there was an old chunk then we just
don't call get world chunk we already
know what it was right so we can just go
ahead and say that chunk equals old
chunk that seems pretty straightforward
right we don't even have to do any if
because we already did the if so we can
just get rid of that entirely and that
goes away so there it is
right bingo then we go ahead and check
for new P that handling should be
exactly the same I don't think anything
change there at all so just leave that
the way it was and that's it right I
can't think of anything else
particularly weird oops gotta rename
that because we kept that PAP in so yeah
that seems about right so when we do get
sim space P we have a slightly harder
situation to deal with here I suppose
because now we have to be able to pass
this stuff properly to we have to be
able to forward the chunk information on
right so we do get grit world chunk I'm
sorry we do get some space P we want to
pass that world chunk in so it can
reconstruct where the guy should be that
makes sense okay so if we're going to do
that let's take a look at how that would
function so who are all the people that
call get some space P just want to take
a look at them so basically if we load
in any reference we get one from the
symmetries week we have to pull low
entity out ah darn that's going to kill
us isn't it is there I don't think
there's any way we can fix that ah
well I tried you know I tried to solve
the puzzler but we couldn't solve it so
this is the thing that'll stop us
basically entity references will stop us
because the entity reference will not be
able to figure out what chunk the entity
is in because it doesn't query by
location so sad so sad we almost did it
but we can't can't do it so now we know
that's fine
we know the puzzle can't be solved well
you know maybe someday we'll still be
able to solve it but you know for now
anyway unfortunately it can't be solved
so let's go ahead and back that out and
be disappointed about it at least I'm
disappointed about it because I was kind
of hoping we would be able to but and by
the way I should also mention this is
not uncommon for me I often try things
like that
just because I kind of want to tubes did
I not restore that to its its games um
that's not uncommon for me I often like
try something I'm like I want to try
this thing and then eventually through
the code somewhere you find out I can't
do it right and then happens to me all
the time it's very very common but I
still like to track us sometimes it does
work and you never really know until you
try it may be that you could have known
that one I don't know that was kind of
complicated it's hard to remember all
those sorts of things so alright so now
we know I'll write that here to do it
seems like we have to store chunk XYZ
with each entity because even though the
sim region gathered doesn't need it at
first and we could get by about it
entity references pull in entities
without going through their top chunk or
I should say world chunk
and thus still need to know the chunk
XYZ all right well it's sad it's sad I
wish we had an owl of disappointment to
go with that RL shame we don't but if we
did it would be flapping its little
wings right now
all right well another to do down though
so we are making progress on the things
we wanted to do this week and let's take
a look at what we have next which one of
these two we want to do so Minkowski
inclusion test for sim region begin
updatable bounce that's pretty easy we
might as well do that let's go ahead and
continue that because that's a good
progress towards E and then maybe
tomorrow will be our day where we start
working on this up-and-down situation
because that's really a thing where we
were we're kind of have to put on our
our for instance caps and and have a
bunch of for instances like for instance
I'm going upstairs for instance I want
to go into a cave for instance I want to
see a boss that's below me on a lower
floor you know for instance is you know
I'm talking about right for instances
maybe you don't but anyway so Minkowski
inclusion testing that's pretty easy and
it's not even really you don't even have
to do Minkowski you could we can we'll
talk about this because it's not even
Tevan have to be phrased in terms of
Minkowski but basically all I'm talking
about is we have currently inside our
sim region this concept of the entity
gather where we go through in fact it's
right here right we go through all of
the things in the world that are within
a certain boundary and we basically ask
like what you know for all of the
entities here which one of them which of
them overlaps this boundary and those
are the ones we're going to put into
this either simulation right it's a
spatial it's a spatially bounded
simulation and we did that because we
know we can't simulate all the entities
in the world at a time so we're just
simulating them in little geographic
regions so that they can like interact
with each other in that region and then
we can simulate other regions and so on
now the problem with the code that we
wrote in the reason
I said we should update it just to kind
of be a little bit cleaner about it
problem with the code that we wrote is
that currently it doesn't actually
respect the concept that entities
themselves have a size and so what was
happening before and this has nothing to
do with Z specifically this was true
even when we weren't talking about Z but
it makes sense to handle it in Z as well
because we we also want to start talking
about entities in this way as well
essentially you can imagine our entities
right R have some kind of boundary that
we could talk about
and since we're mostly working with
we've been working with sort of right
rectangular prisms here we've been
working with you know things that are
like a cube but stretched I don't have
boxes right or a a B B's we've been
working with access aligned bounding
boxes right access aligned bounding
boxes we've been working with these and
you know we've been doing some stuff
like our collision sort of works
properly with them and we do some stuff
that respects the bounding boxes and our
entities right now have a width and a
height right but they should also now
have a depth so that's one thing that we
need to add which is the concept that
entities have like an actual you know
size so we should probably change this
concept to be a v3 in the entity that
basically stores their dimensions along
all three axes right that makes sense
but the other thing that we should do is
in that gather we should use this now to
see whether entities overlap or gather
region so if this is our gather region
and there's an entity that's right there
well its center point might be here but
its bounds extend all through you know
three-dimensional space right its bounds
extend outward and right now when we do
our inclusion tests all we're doing is
we're just testing the position and
we're seeing whether that position falls
within this this boundary now that
doesn't really help us very much
because we could have an entity that
should be in the boundary but that's not
being counted because of this especially
if energy was somewhat large so what
we'd like to do is we'd like to do our
inclusion test to test against
overlapping
with these other you know with these
other rectangles right and so we already
know one way that we could do this right
we could do this with the Minkowski
which is basically we you know we take
whatever this distance is here and we
add it on to either side right of this
rectangle and we take whatever this
distance is here and we add it on to
this one right so that we produce a new
testing rectangle and then we just test
against the point that's one way we
could do it but we could also choose to
do it another way which is just to do an
overlap test to see whether the two
rectangles overlap and honestly it's six
of one half dozen or the other I don't
know that it really matters which way we
do it but we have to do one of those you
know we have to do something we also
have a related problem and this one I
don't know if we're going to try and
solve or not right but what that problem
is is right now we have a tile chunks
right we've got these tile chunks and
the tile chunks store our entities right
so when we do a gather so here's our
gather region what we are currently
doing is we're looping over all the tile
chunks that are gathering touches right
so we're looping over these nine you
know squares right we're looping over
this one this this this this this this
this this and saying give me all the
entities in there then test them against
the rectangle that's how we're doing our
gather to avoid testing all the entities
in the world every time which would be
prohibitively expensive with the number
of entities we're going to have but what
if there was an entry in this up here so
this guy right this top chunk is not
counted but there's the editor here who
just has a really large bound right he's
very big or perhaps more likely imagine
if instead of being here our gather
region were aligned more poorly right
because you know the gather regions
allowed to be anywhere it wants we're
not placing restrictions on how the
camera moves at the moment the camera
can move anywhere it wants so suppose
instead my gather region is right here
right that includes these guys it does
not include this tile chunk because it's
on the other side the gather Ethan
starts on the other side of touch on so
if there is a guy who is right on the
edge and who isn't particularly large
he's only that big he still won't get he
won't show up right he won't be tested
he won't even be looked at right it's
not that he'll fail the test because I
could write the test properly so that he
would would say he was in but we'll
never actually even iterate over him
because he's stored in this tile chunk
not this tile chunk and this is the
first tile chunk that we start using
right so there's multiple ways we can
approach that problem and I think I'll
probably take a the sort of the look to
oh I'm tired tonight
it's yawning Johnny here the problem is
that we have to solve it either in the
spatial partition either in the tile
chunks themselves or in our Gavin and
the way that we would solve it in the
tile chunks is for example we could
double store our entities so for example
any entity that's straddled a tile chunk
could just go ahead and be stored in
both top chunks right totally fine no
big deal the other way we can do it is
in our entity gather we can displace the
entity gather we can say let's expand it
by the radius of our largest entity
right because that's how far it could
extend over and that would guarantee
Blee get it so what are the pros and
cons here why would we choose one of the
other well expanding so expanding the
gather right if we were going to expand
the gather that is the problem of it it
has to handle the maximum entity radius
right if all our entities are similarly
sized totally fine
because it really wouldn't be a problem
no big deal but what if we have a giant
entity
so what if at one point we have an
entity that's like 12 screens large I
don't know how we do that or why but
let's say we did well now this is really
bad because now our gather region has to
gather tons more child pile chunks every
time looking for a giant entity even if
there's no giant envy anywhere near
where we're gathering right so it's a
huge waste of resources all the time so
that's the problem that's the thing that
it does not do well right this is the
bad part on the other hand doubl stores
right or I should say multi stores are
the opposite basically what they are is
if we all if we have similarly sized
entities if we have mostly similar sized
entities right so if we have mostly
entities that are all the exact same
size and now we're just storing all of
these entities doubly all the time we're
just wasting a ton of work storing and
pulling things out of our store just to
handle that one once or twice where we
have that giant entity right if we ever
do now if we actually do have that giant
envy then maybe this was a win because
we don't have to do this expansion all
the time but we do have this problem
we're like okay if mostly we're never
actually taking advantage of that then
really all we did you know if we never
have that single giant entity right if
if if all entities are small then this
was a total lose right and we don't
really know which of these two we have
it's not clear so I'm not sure but
that's basically the way that works is
they're there to trade offs and we don't
really have very much information with
which to make that trade-off so I think
what I'll probably do is I'm going to do
this simpler of the two right because
when you have no information you might
as well do the one that's least likely
to cause bugs and be a strain on the
code so instead of worrying about
storing things and removing things from
the Space Foundation overlapping let's
just go ahead and introduce a Maxum
entity radius right we already
a safety margin and we'll have a max
entity radius and we'll just say that
we've got whatever this is you know the
maxim entity radius is like five meters
or something and then our sim regions
will just get updated by whatever that
is
so we'll say you know add radius - we'll
do that bounds there and we'll say in
fact is this bounds that we used
anywhere else we'll make sure it's not
bounce bounce bounce bounce bounce
bounce bounce it's not so we'll go ahead
and just say that that's going to be the
maximum radius maximum radius maximum
radius that way we just enlarge that
collision region there and off we go now
what we also can do is we can also say
we could make this a global thing right
and we could sort of say that we try to
prevent there from ever being a case
where we know about an ax T that's going
to be that larger than that or something
like this so that's an ad that's ten
meters large right which is pretty big
but you know maybe someday we
accidentally forget and we create one
larger than that
so it would be nice to sort of it looks
like I've even got a thinner calculate
this eventually from the maximum value
of all n ad radius plus our speed so we
know that the update safety margin is
now going to be the max entity radius
plus whatever the speed / / DT is as
well here right excuse me there's always
a lot of nose blowing on the street
I feel like twitch users are subjected
to my colds and allergies which I don't
know if like misery loves company or
something I don't know if like spreading
it around is is helping me I don't think
it is
anyway so we don't actually know what
the DT is here we should probably figure
that out so we'd have a maximum radius
and we'd have a max entity velocity
right and you know maybe that's you know
who knows what that is it's 10 meters
per second I have no idea but we
multiply it by the DT so we'd say you
know what when you open up a sim region
you've got to tell us what the DT is
going to be and then we would just
multiply that out so now we know that
the max entity velocity actually I
should put it here right plus DT Max
Energy velocity so we basically say okay
that actually is correct now and now all
we would have to do is actually sort of
very validate or try to validate that we
never exceed these maximums right and so
we can sort of do that in a loose way
and maybe there's ways so we can put it
to do here that was like to do try to
make these get enforced more rigorously
of course more rigorously but what we
can also do is sort of have those here
in the sim region we could just go ahead
and say we have max entity radius in max
entity velocity right and we could set
those so we would say all right the sim
region sets those and then when it's
doing a processing it'll check it'll
actually just flat-out check when it's
doing stuff to make sure that that's not
going on right okay so first off what we
can do is we can start well you know
what else I'll do I'll go up to here
let's see let's see where is it where is
it move entity so in move entity we know
what the velocity actually is right we
actually have in sort of a feel for what
that velocity is going to be and so we
can actually check in this entity VP we
can say right here you know if entity DP
you know if the length squared of that
gives greater
than the length squared of whatever that
maximum is Maxima velocity right so if
our if our velocity for entity that we
would have been computing if that's
going to be above it you know we could
actually for now I guess we could just
assert it in the future maybe we want to
clip it right I don't know if that seems
like good idea but we could basically
say you know assert that we're always
less than whatever that that max entity
velocity is and again I'm just doing the
length squared because we don't actually
care about what the actual length is we
just want to know if it's greater than
or less than so we don't need to do the
square root in there we can just go
ahead and say check the length squared
against each other and they'll tell us
so what I might say in here is you know
upgrade college physical motion routines
to handle capping the maximum velocity
so that we just know it would never
exceed it even if we made some gameplay
code that tried to it just would always
cap it so for now we'll assert but then
later it seems like it would be a good
idea to go ahead and actually enforce
that right yeah so there we go um let's
take a look here that's right that's not
a nice grid square that's already scalar
okay so we've got our DT in here
somewhere
so I think it's called DP for frame is
it no it's not what is it where is my DT
DT it's just input DT right is what we
called it input DP for frame close
enough I feel like they should have
given that one to me so I think that
should just still work the same way that
it was working oh so I guess our entity
velocities are much higher than I
thought they were too oh that's that's
oh wait no that's not a bug that
actually did mean it exceeded it right
because I actually I did not multiply by
the DT in begin Sam right I just store
it out if I remember correctly I just
store it out our max entity velocity
right yeah so yeah so I guess we're
already above 10 m/s how fast is 10
meters per second I don't even know
let's see I think we looked this up
before do same bolt speed 23 miles per
hour so 23.5 mph in meters per second oh
man
he runs just a little bit faster than
the maximum velocity well that's okay
because we probably want things that can
go even faster than Usain Bolt in our
game so we probably want quite a bit
faster than that we'd probably want
something like 30 because at the end of
the day don't forget our frame time step
it's dividing out by it that's how much
we're growing by so three divided by 30
would only be one would be one meter
that we'd actually be expanding by so
that seems that seems fine that seems
fine okay
let's try that again yeah so now at
least well known oh wow all right so
we're still getting some velocities that
are higher than that it's kind of crazy
Wow
oh right I jump hot faster than that
that's so our jumping code is a bit
wonky is jumping at nits at negative 30
meters per second squared is that Oh No
okay I know what that is that's just
because our velocity doesn't stop when
we hit the ground okay I was like that's
not right and it's not so yeah so what
that was was since we have not actually
done much with our Z motion code yet
when you hit the ground we don't zero
out your velocity so your velocity is
able to just keep building in Z ad
infinitum so really what we need to do
when you hit
ground right is we need to set your your
Z velocity to zero as well right
everything should zero out yeah yeah so
that I was gonna say what's with that
but that's not true yeah so we should be
fine now
I think there's I don't think we've got
it now we've got a problem now at least
I'm pretty sure we know yeah so that's
all good
that seems fine no big deals there okay
so that's good and now we just have one
more thing to do before we can complete
that to do we're doing that that growing
which is nice but we need to actually do
the rectangle test now like I said I
just want to do a rectangle test that'll
include the dimensions of our actual
guys so what we're going to do is first
I'm going to say let's go ahead and make
their actual width height I'm gonna I'm
gonna just make that B bit like a dim
look at their dimension right so they'll
have like a width height and depth down
right and so I'm just going to change
all the code that used to be with the
height and change that to be actually
using the dimension right so this will
be dim X right and this will be dim Y so
and then we'll go in here and I guess I
can just change
Cinda height to send dim dot X oops dot
Y 2 2 2 2 2 again and then I can do sim
dot width and change that to Sam dot dim
dot X and that should do that and again
presumably in our collision detection
still works okay it does so that's good
everyone's happy yeah ok
and so really all I need to do now is
start giving these guys some Z at some
point but honestly we don't really care
about that right now
so all we need to do to finish up this
particular part to do is inside the sim
region we would like to actually compute
me oh you know what we're actually even
using it in here so we could just start
doing this instead of that nonsense we
could just say
right let's start using the z course
there isn't one so that's fine but at
least we're using it now there we go
so there we've got our x y&amp;z dimensions
so that's fine is this though shouldn't
these be halves yes they are so that's
my Costigan ammeter and not the radius
so that's fine
yeah so that's all good so they don't
have to do is modify my rectangle check
and I think that's all we really need to
do from now and then we can end right on
time in a nice Pleasant fashion so when
I'm doing that I think what I want to do
here is when I do my is inside rectangle
I've got I've got to is in rectangle
calls right I've got here and here so
I'd like to do is I'd like to just ask
if the rectangles overlapped and so I
think I'm just going to go ahead and do
a special purpose call for that that
does the math in there so that I don't
have to do it in two different places
since I'm already doing it in two places
so I think I'm going to do is just say
if entity overlaps right rectangle so
what I'll do is I'll say okay you know
we've got we've got a desk P I'm not
really I don't know that I want to
actually pass the actual entity here so
I think all I want to do is I think I
just want to pass the rectangle right so
what I'll do is I'll say all right god s
P here's our rectangle and then I just
want to I need to actually pass the
dimension of of that guy so so desk dim
right entity overlaps rectangle so so
that basically and then later when we do
is inside rectangle here that would be
the same thing to be entity overlaps
entity over left rectangle we'd pass
whatever that same space P was and then
we'd also pass the low
sym dim right and then I just have to
implement this function so I need to
make a little function here which
returns a boolean right I think this is
probably just a really simple function
and what that's going to do is going to
take the P the dimension and then the
rectangle three for the bounds right so
I think I will probably do this by
testing by just doing the Minkowski
thing that seems like the easiest thing
to do for now
so I guess what I would say is the grown
like a grown rectangle equals add what
do we call it add radius two right I
think we'll just do that we'll add half
the dimension so that it grows I'm
pretty sure in fact we could actually
have an add diameter to call as well add
radius to which which does that half
this doesn't do it by I mean we'll just
we'll just leave it this way because if
we did we'd have to just multiply by a
so we'll just leave this way I will do
it add radius two that'll expand our
test region by the dimension that we're
looking for and then we can just go
ahead and return the result which is is
inside rectangle again but with that
grown rectangle and now we test the P
again and we're done
right so that's really all I want to do
there and now we're actually testing for
overlapping as well which you just
prevent us from having bugs in the
future where we're missing some entities
that we should otherwise be getting and
that's about it
so there really isn't much more to it
that's all there is all right so I think
that basically we're a little ahead of
time here but I guess that's basically
all I wanted to do today we figured out
that I'm going to put our four instances
in here
so I think all we really have to do now
is actually figure out how we want to
handle the kind of going up and down
things and it's gonna it's going to be
some work because we don't really know
what we want to do there and we don't
have a lot to go on so that's definitely
to be some explorations going on to you
know for us tomorrow so it does seem
like we probably get to that I don't
know if we'll get to to this stuff
before the end of the week probably not
but we should be able to at least get
done with our Z stuff and so that's good
and yeah looks like we've got a lot of
good stuff coming up here I'm looking
forward to this this just should be
pretty good but we're pretty much done
for today so let me go ahead and start
the Q&amp;A here and I will go ahead and and
tell the bots that it is time for the
Q&amp;A if you would like to ask a question
about what we've done on today's stream
or on previous dreams please go ahead
and ask it now put a Q : in front of it
so I can see it and if you want to ask
questions that are like off-topic or
don't really have anything to do with
the coding that we're doing right now
those are cool but not for right now ask
those at the beginning of the stream
basically what we do is about 15 minutes
before the stream starts I answer
off-topic questions or whatever so if
you want to save those for tomorrow we
can do them just come about 15 minutes
before the stream schedule start and we
do off topic questions then so let's go
ahead and go to the Q and the a if we
have any Q&amp;A that is
not much it looks like
yeah well maybe we won't have any Q&amp;A
maybe we won't I see nothing
again please remember to prefixed your
questions with Q :
because I have a little filter thing and
I only look at things that have Q : in
front of them because you know basically
like there's there's chat and stuff on
the stream and stuff that's not directed
at me so I filter that out so I can just
answer the questions as they come up we
had a bit of a troll problem today hang
on yeah I don't know do we need to make
a private IRC where it's a little more
controlled or something I don't know
what to do about that
I I don't yeah I I don't love the fact
that the moderators are having to deal
with all this ridiculousness
because they shouldn't have to do that
like and I don't know it would be nice
if twitch was more serious about the
trolling problems and was actually like
did some placing themselves and tried to
separate things into trolls non trolls
and that way if you want trolls on your
stream you can have them if you don't
you don't or something like that but of
course there's not that much of it so
Carlin W Blum question pasta was gross
what does that even mean all right this
is nonsensical I have no idea what that
means
what was my grade on APCs is that you
mean Advanced Placement computer science
hilariously and this probably does not
bode well for the state of computer
science education
I got a 5 on the AP computer science
test which was the highest you could
possibly get despite not having
programmed in the language the test was
given in for seven years I want to say
it was given in Pascal like anybody
programs in Pascal and I had programmed
Pascal since I was like nine and I still
got a five which is terrifying
I don't know what that says because if
you're not a frequent programmer in the
language that the test is given and you
should not get the highest score I don't
care what kind of grade inflation is
going on there that's just the case
let's see what math classes did I take
in high school and what grades you get
these are all off topic but that's okay
because I know trust me if there's any
actual on topic questions because
there's no sense in filtering out
off-topic questions if there are no on
topic questions but
I noticed a bunch of your functions are
inlined is there a difference between
using regular functions and inline
functions so not the answer is not
really like a part of that is because of
the way that we're programming so the
way that we're writing this right now is
we use the thing that a lot of people
call the unity build which is not
actually have anything to do with unity
the game engine so it's a little bit
confusing Lee named perhaps but
basically the way we do it is our build
is like a batch file that just builds
one file handmade dot cpp and all of our
code is in it essentially and the way
that the reason we have multiple files
is just logically they're broken up so
that I can bounce back and forth between
them and Emacs easily but they all get
included into the same file as just
pound includes and built that way what
that means is that the compiler always
has access to all of our functions
during the build so technically in
lining I don't even know if it does
anything meaning the word in line when I
put it here for our build I don't think
it maybe does anything at all because
for the most part the compiler will see
all of our functions and can decide
itself which ones it wants to inline
usually when you use inline if because
you have moved something to an H file so
that you're giving the compiler the
ability to inline it because you've put
it there and it's getting included in
all of your compilation units but we
don't have that situation here so really
it's more inline is really just mostly a
note for me that says what it's mostly
about me saying whether I think it's a
small inline double function or not but
the compiler probably doesn't really
care
and that's might be relatively true I
don't know since I don't use normal
build processes ever
anymore but that might also be kind of
true with link time code generation for
all I know like modern link time code
generation will go ahead and inline all
kinds of stuff for you that you didn't
bother to make visible and other
compilation units so I don't know that
depends on how good the link time code
generator is right but so the answer is
yeah like inline used to mean more than
it does it used to basically tell the
compiler to expand something directly
inside every place that it was called
it no longer means that really it's
always been optional I believe
specification wise and now it is
optional definitely in practice meaning
the compilers definitely do a lot of
their own thinking and do plenty of
inlining for stuff that you didn't mark
in line so even if I didn't mark any
overlaps rectangle in line it might very
well inline it even when I do mark it in
line it may dot and so if you actually
care about performance a lot and really
do want to know that something's getting
in lined you actually have to take
additional steps the the word in line
does not actually make sure the compiler
in line something there's like a force
in line compiler directive you can also
often use that actually means something
will literally be inlined and is the
compiler will not try to stop you and so
we may have to do stuff like that when
we're doing optimization work depending
on circumstances I don't know but on the
whole to answer question in line really
kind of meaningless these days and it's
mostly more it's more of a note for me
than anybody than the compiler because
really all it says the compiler is hey
maybe you shouldn't line this and the
compiler is free to say like no yeah I
didn't really I don't really like it and
then anything that isn't marked in line
it can still in my memory by valve
question date something - how much
longer do you think this is going to
take well each day is only an hour so if
you think about it 72 hours is like one
and a half work weeks roughly a little
more than that one in two thirds work
weeks every one through that so on date
80 will well done 2 weeks worth of work
which is very little so I suspect it'll
probably like 600 days maybe I feel like
we've got to do at least three four
months of coding to make a game from
scratch right and so if you multiply
that out to an hour a day you're talking
about you know 600 days something like
that so we'll be here for a long time
because that one one hour days is not
very much code right we don't get to do
very much and I'm talking the whole time
too so
you
could you take a look at player
collision they spawned very close to
each other they spawn very close to each
other happy vertex what do you mean by
they spawn very close to each other uh
I'm not sure what that means
sorry I don't understand that and also
to answer the question out the almond
milk I make it myself
now which is a bit time-consuming I
would like to purchase it from the store
but unfortunately the store brought
versions have just tons of stuff added
and I really just kind of want to plain
almond milk oh and for the person who's
asking what the streaming schedule is
it's basically really easy to find you
can just go to this tweet spot here if
you if you go to hammy hero org if you
click on the tweet spot the tweet spot
tweets the schedule so every week it
tweets the schedule for the week and
then every day it reminds you about when
it's on so if you want to follow it the
tweet bot is your friend are there any
good uses for 40 vectors yes there are
two very very very very very common I
almost say ubiquitous cases for 40
vectors and you've already seen one of
them if you've been watching the series
but we haven't actually used them yet
so we might add a 40 vector for it so
for D vectors among other things from
the use you haven't seen is quaternions
so quaternions are a four element vector
and they're basically stored as X Y Z W
and they are stored they're sort of
stored you can think of them as being
stored sort of in a 3:1
sort of partition basically the the
first three numbers store the axis of
rotation so like it's quadrillions or
store rotations or array of store
rotation values so if you imagine an
axis of rotation and an angle around
that axis right so I have something that
I'm spinning around like the axle of a
car right and the wheels are spinning
around it I've got an angle of rotation
theta
I bet an axis of rotation we'll call
that V quaternions can be thought of in
two parts one is the W component which
is just cosine of theta over two and so
whatever this this theta was it's cosine
of Phi over 2 and the V component is
this the XYZ is just sine of theta over
two times V times that right and so
that's a four a four element vector that
typically is stored as a vector for I
store it as a V for in my code we won't
probably ever use these in hand made
hero because we don't have to really do
full 3d rotation work in handmade hero
but that's what they're used for a lot
in engine code I used some today in fact
at work for number two as the one you
have seen before colors so oftentimes
you'll have RGB a colors right and so
again a 3.1 storage but you know
typically that stored is a vector four
and we could go do that right now and
hamate hero
we just haven't but that's probably
something we will do eventually so you
typically will have a thing that stores
colors that way just for utility a lot
of times
[Music]
let's see do you tend to order your
functions in any sort of order or even
flow wise do you tend to always put one
above the other or do you never think
about it so yeah because a/c is kind of
crappy and it it can't call a function
that hasn't been declared yet the reason
that I sort my functions the way I do is
because I tend to put all the things
that get called by functions above the
functions that call them so I don't have
to have additional declarations so I do
do that sorting beyond that the only way
I really sort is file wise I tend to
split out my function so that functions
that tend to go together like ones that
all work with simulation you know or
once it all work with entities or
whatever go into those files so that I
can keep them separate and look at them
more cleanly but that's really just
because editors are lousy and don't do a
good job of visualizing some of that
stuff but that's so that's that's just
purely organizational in that sense will
you extend your bankowski collision
implementation to deal with rotation
arbitrary convex polygons in the future
so we don't really know yet what we're
going to do so rotation I don't think we
ever actually need because I don't know
that we're doing much with rotation we
might I'm not sure so we'll have to see
if we ever have rotation and in terms of
our arbitrary Comics polygons probably
yes I suspect we will want that at the
very least we'll probably at least want
circular or oval regions or rounded
rectangles and things like that if not
arbitrary polygons so I'm not sure hard
to say but possibly but who knows I
really don't know it's worth noting that
collision detection doesn't work with
rotation in terms of animated rotation
there really isn't a collision solver
that handles our that properly handles a
continuous rotation
you can write ones that do essentially
like search based handling of of that
kind of thing but there's really nothing
that's not iterative in time that
handles animated rotation at least
enough that I've ever seen so rotation
that animates is kind of problematic and
usually people don't actually handle it
properly they usually just use the
rotation from the start or the finish or
they bisect in between but there's no
way to handle it a do exact collision
between spinning things that are
extruded unless you went up in dimension
I don't know if you can you might I
think it's still nonlinear so yeah I
don't know what you would do like gjk
probably wouldn't work I'm not sure so
yeah so that's kind of a tough topic
there really aren't very good solutions
for that or at least they're not that I
know of you can't always have to do
something a little janky whereas n just
to be clear to contrast that with things
that don't have an animated rotation
meaning if you just assume that the
anime rotation was constant across the
time step those can be solved exactly
usually like with G JK or something you
can get those exactly right but those
schemes don't work when the when the
rotation is animated so you tend to have
to augment whatever the collision
detector is with something that
approximates that like maybe like I said
subdivides it or does something else or
takes the conservative maximum area then
the rotation would do and does that test
and then if that fails then it does the
subdivision you know stuff like this it
gets it gets much nastier so you do want
to cut try to avoid those if you can
because you you're always going to have
kind of a substandard solution if you
really want to do completely accurate
rotational collision detection so it's
best to try and figure out ways to avoid
it if you can
why is win32 mouse handling so annoying
so if you're having annoyances with
mouse down and mouse up and that sort of
stuff I would probably say you might be
happier using raw raw input mouse and
just querying the mouse directly you
might might have better luck with that
but as to why it's so annoying it's
because yeah it's it's windows you know
I mean they and it's it's true on a lot
of platforms actually a lot of platforms
just don't think through how to pass
input on to the apps properly and so
they end up with a lot of problems like
and Windows is definitely one of them
they don't do a good job handing input
to the application they never have
probably never will you see when will
the z-index of the entities occur what
is the Z index which Z index are you
referring to quit sacado
and as for whether anyone here is old
enough to miss the great space coaster
there is no good news that is good good
news with Gary is all I have to say
about that
do you ever foresee the project getting
to a stage in which you accept pull and
merge requests from other developers to
fix bugs add features or other things of
course you would first have to start
using version control before your hard
drive fails so I would probably say I
don't know that I'll ever do that but
the code for the game again will be
released into the public domain two
years after the game ships so at that
point anyone who wants to can host I
mean it'll be public domain at that
point so anyone who wants to be able to
host their own repository and if there
wants to be a community maintained
edition they can go nuts
and for the person who's asking why does
the player even need to jump they don't
we just threw that in one day because
someone asked about it so we threw in
the implication of a jump and since then
it's just been fun to test the Z
movement because we know we're going to
have things like flying enemies and
stuff so it was just in there for
testing the player isn't going to jump
it's not really a game where the player
jumps but it was just useful for testing
so it stayed in eventually it'll get
removed when we're when we've got all
the Z stuff worked out exactly we want
it it can it can go I see what you're
saying
happy vertex you're saying if you want
to create multiple characters to play
then they'll spawn inside of each other
yes we haven't done anything about that
there's two ways you could handle that
and we what we'll probably do is I would
say we have this here I can add that for
you there what's the plan for robustness
we'll handle that so basically like you
know implement reprojection to handle
interpenetration or something we should
we should go ahead and do the work when
we do this through this here basically
like right now we don't handle what
happens when things get stuck in other
things right which can happen any time
the game creates an entity on top of
another entity or something that what we
want to do is make that code more robust
and have some ways that that can be
resolved and that also will fix problems
with floating point imprecision where we
do solves and we move something and we
move it a little too far so it ends up
being technically inside something else
we'd like to be able to make it so that
that's not the end of the world like we
want to make it so the clintons has to
robusta that and so yeah we'll probably
do that we won't probably it to it this
week but we'll get to it when we soon
let me do the collision detection pass
of just shoring things up and leaving it
in a state where we don't have to think
about it anymore until we do you know
the final version
what's the most elegant sexy piece of
code in the game so far I don't know
what a sexy piece of code is necessarily
it's probably the most sexy thing that
we have right now is the fact that we
can do the loop live code editing that
is pretty darn cool basically that's the
thing that we have where we implemented
it so that the entire game is
essentially able to rewind itself and do
stuff that's cool like that so if you
want to program it you can set things
called loop points like there I just set
one and then you can loop and then it'll
play back that section and while you're
doing that you can actually edit the
code so while that's happening you can
go in here and say oh you know I want to
edit the code I don't know what we want
to do exactly like maybe we want the
hero where's the hero in fact I can just
I can actually just go ahead and and put
this down here for now all right put
that up there put our code down here so
you know if we want to go ahead and and
change like the way the hero's drawn or
something like that we can go and do
that like maybe we want to give him a
second head that's what I like doing I
think I've done that a couple times
right just give him you know another
another just another noggin right we can
just do that and so basically all of our
code is live you give it as many as you
want actually right and maybe you want
another one on there that's totally fine
so the fact that we can edit the code
live in and in a loop so we can change
what happens on user input and
everything is pretty darn awesome like a
ton of game engines just don't even have
that and they're you know fancy
commercial engines that cost money and
stuff so it's pretty cool I don't know
that we've done a lot of other sexy
stuff because right now we're working on
engine architecture stuff which usually
isn't sexy but I don't know what you
consider sexy you know everyone has
their own definitions of sexiness so
what program to be used for the
blackboard reusing mischief
if I'm not mistaken in your code you
didn't need to use any forward
declarations and come up against if the
dependencies until now is this by chance
or did you try in your head not to have
them while writing new functions trucks
uh well I always sort my stuff by who
calls who so that part wasn't accidental
that's just how I do that so I don't be
again so I don't have to have the Sigma
Z and again that's just because C and
C++ are stupid and require forward
declarations i it's just it's purely
laziness on the part of the language
designers and compiler writers that that
is the case largely the language
designers because they design it in such
a way that it's got things that don't
work properly
um but either way well ignore that for
now so basically what ends up happening
is I do do that sorting I just don't
have anything right now but that needs
to call cyclically there is one case and
we just we added a forward declaration
right there
where was it oh sorry it was in sim
region right so add entity the way that
that worked because it pulled in
references the act of adding an entity
could add more entities so we have one
forward declaration here right and so
I'm not trying to prevent cyclic things
they just don't tend to happen that
often they're kind of fairly rare in my
code I find so we just don't have that
many and everything else I just sort so
I do do that sorting so that I don't
have to cut cut and paste to make
forward declarations
chrysocolla
enemies drawing back to front I don't
know when we'll do that we'll probably
do entities drawing back to front first
of all I don't know that we'll probably
ever do enemies drawing back to front
will probably draw any front to back
because it's usually faster
so we'll do enemies drawing front to
back probably when we do the renderer
will there be a hand made hero
convention annually after the game
release yes of course they'll be one
before the game releases of course we're
going to have a hand made hero
convention
are you implementing any advanced data
structures and would you recommend
learning assembly to aid in optimizing C
programs any tips on practice so we have
implemented some advanced data
structures our chunk store is sort of an
advanced data structure it depends on
what you consider advanced like it's not
advanced advanced like I've written way
more complicated data structures than
this before but it is a data structure
that is you know it's a hash table with
a linked list inside it so you know I
mean is it advanced no is it you know
more than a linked list yes is it more
than a hash table yes so I don't know
like you know where you want to put that
it's not super fancy but it is more than
nothing so you know advanced might be
the wrong term but we're implementing
data structures that are not just
exactly what you'd find in a book that
are amalgams of that we haven't had to
do anything yet that was fully out there
like occasionally I've employed data
structures that are like totally wild
and that don't really have a
classification I don't know that those
are going to call furthermost
things the reason that those common data
structures are the classic ones is
because you tend to able to build
whatever you need out of them and so you
know who knows as for learning assembly
language I think a simulator is just
pretty important to be able to know you
don't necessarily have to be able to
write assembly code you have to be able
to read it because understanding what
the compiler is doing and looking at it
and understanding why things are slow by
looking at what the CPU actually has to
do is pretty crucial
being able to write whole programs the
same language isn't necessary I don't
think most of the time
let's see is there such a thing it's a
hardware cursor as a compared to a
software mouse cursor the answer is in
the old days yes there was okay so at
first there was no difference then there
was a difference then there was no
difference again and then there was a
difference and then there was no
difference again in the early early
early days there were only displays that
you basically set pixel values in and
that got displayed and so there was no
such thing as a hardware mouse cursor if
you're going to draw one you just had to
draw it a lot of times they used XOR
drawing to pick it up put it back so
that they didn't have because they
didn't have multiple been have double
buffering and they didn't have a lot of
copy bandwidth and that sort of stuff
then because mouse cursors became such
an important thing and also because
sprites were common which is basically
what a mouse cursor is sprites were
common in game hardware hardware in
general had the concept of sprites mouse
cursors often were then implemented with
hardware that actually was doing the
overlay and so then there was definitely
a difference between a hardware mouse
cursor and software mouse cursor then we
went to two 3d graphics right where we
had a hardware that was doing 3d and
eventually it was doing all sorts of
bitmap compositing so now there really
is no difference between a hardware
cursor and everything else on the screen
the hardware the graphics hardware is
doing all this compositing its
compositing the mouse cursor and the
windows and the fact that these things
are blurred and all that stuff is all
going through the hardware and so we've
gotten back to a point now where calling
the mouse cursor a hardware cursor it's
kind of meaningless because everything's
composited by the hardware not the mouse
cursor specifically so it's kind of big
goes through phases so you know the
answer is it depends there certainly
always have been differences and then on
differences in differences and so on
alright looks like we are out of time
and we've got most two most of the
questions anyway so I think we're good
I think that is a good place to stop for
today
again we will be back here same time
same place tomorrow to take a look at
what we want to do with Z try to now
that we've got Z flowing through the
pipe line properly everywhere would be a
good chance to kind of go what are we
doing here maybe make some 2 layer
structures and allow you to walk between
them and figure out what we're gonna do
because yeah really that's what we got
to figure out like how is that stuff
going to work so I hope you will join me
to come back tomorrow to join me for
that let me go ahead and save our
mischief blackboard area and of course
if you would like to follow along at
home with with these episodes it's
pretty easy to do if you want to
pre-order the game it comes with a
source code so if you want to follow
along the source code it's pretty easy
you can go to hammy here org and do
pre-order and you get a download link
and then every night after the stream
you can download the source code which
is pretty cool and of course you'll also
get the game once it's done and once we
start doing builds of the game regularly
you get those and all that good stuff
it also comes to the art assets that we
use so you can use those for testing as
well we have a patreon that you can
subscribe to if you want support the
video series that's linked up there as
well we have a tweet bot that tweets the
schedule at you so if you have a Twitter
account you want to know when the
streams going to be on that sort of
stuff that's a good place to to go and
just follow or do whatever list it or
something and then we also have a site
you can go to where there's a forum for
asking questions and there's some coding
resources ports to Linux and Mac and by
the community and stuff like that so if
you want to follow along a different
platform than Windows you can do that
there's a bunch of good stuff up there
so highly recommend checking that out as
well
and yeah that's about it I hope you will
join me tomorrow for the next episode of
handmade hero until then please have a
wonderful Wednesday and I'll see you
guys on the Internet