okay hello everyone and welcome to hand
made here on the show recode complete
game live on stream on Twitch no engines
no libraries we show absolutely all of
the code that is necessary to run a game
in a modern setting ladies and gentlemen
I have been away for a week and a half
due to unforeseen circumstances and so
today I think we have sort of the the
highly dubious situation of will I even
remember what the code is doing right
you know it's been it's been paged out I
obviously work on I have a full-time job
so you know I don't I I don't only get
to think about handmade hero I have to
actually be working on other things as
well so it's going to be rather
interesting now when we left off on the
last episode I was going to what i did
was i basically showed how you end up
with this iterative precision problem
and i showed how to fix it by doing back
calculation sort of implicitly
calculating things instead of doing them
as what's actually called a digital
differential analyzer I believe sort of
the idea of adding things incrementally
so we kind of covered that and I was
going to say okay we should probably
also do volume that way and I was going
to do that the next day we don't really
need to do that now we have it to do in
there if we want to fix that with the
volume we can but it doesn't really
cause us any problems we're not actually
hear any problems with it right in the
San mixer so I think it would probably
be better do today since we're starting
a new week after being out for so long I
think we better is just to start
something fresh and just assume that the
sound mixer is good enough for now and
obviously as with all of the parts of
the engine if we come to a point in the
game development where we find that the
engine does not do something we need we
will just go ahead and revise it at that
point and that's generally a good idea
anyway because you don't want to go
spending a lot of times implementing
engine features that you don't ever use
or implementing engine features in a way
that you don't need and that's why of
course I always say you want do things
in an exploratory fashion so you kind of
only do things as you need them and that
way guarantees that you're not spending
a ton of time on stuff that
doesn't need to happen or spending a
bunch of time on something and you make
it in a way that turns out to not
actually be appropriate for the task and
so we've tried very hard to take that
approach as we've been sort of building
our engine here exploring things and
pulling in new things as we go only when
we can kind of see a real use case in a
real way in which they can occur and try
to keep things simple in cases where we
don't feel like we get have enough
information because we just don't want
to rattle on something that may turn out
to be nothing or unimportant to the
final game at the end of the day it's
worth noting that no matter what you do
when you're programming when you're
making a game every hour that you spend
programming is going towards something
and if that something doesn't end up in
the final game you wasted that our and
so it really does pay to make sure that
when you are doing your programming you
try to do it in a way such that you
don't spend a lot of time working on
things that never see the light of day
and again that's sort of what we're
trying to do here so with that in mind
what I'd like to do is get back to the
asset system we wrote the sound mixer
just so you can see what the needs might
be for the asset system and so we will
probably come at the sound system it
from another direction a little later on
when we actually go to add sound to the
game in some kind of meaningful way
where we want to actually play sound
ambient sounds and some music and stuff
we'll put that into the game and then
we'll revisit the sound mixer and see
are there things that we need to change
so we're sort of looking at it if you
will from two different sides and the
side that we need to look at right now
was what does the sound mixer probably
need from the asset system right and so
that way we can finish up our asset
system later on when we go look at the
sandwich for me direction will be what
does the game code want from the sound
system and what we'll do there is we
probably won't change the sound mixer
much because obviously it's it's pretty
straightforward how it works and we now
know that it lines up with the asset mix
your well so we like that but the
interface to the sound mixer like the
playing sound struck since that's a that
will probably change dramatically
because really right now that's only the
the very minor sort of layer that the
simplest possible thing we could put two
have sounds play that's what we put in
place there right and so we will have a
chance to kind of revisit the mixer
again a little leader and not maybe so
much about what the mixer is actually
doing in the actual mixing code which is
probably fine mostly the way it is now
but in terms of how we might want to
drive that mixing code we will probably
build that out a little bit more but
again don't want to do that right now
because the better time to do that would
be when we actually go to add a little
bit of a soundscape to the game because
that's the time when we will actually
know what those things should look like
all right so fill some philosophy out of
the way I'd like to go take a look at
the asset system now and sort of page
that back in to our brains and talk
about what we want that to do and maybe
start kind of writing some code that
will start to push the test code that we
have right now out into a sort of a
place where we can start to define that
asset system okay before I start in case
we do get to programming today because
on blackboard for a little bit to talk
about what we're going to do and give
you some of the background of it as I
always do when we start a new section
but if we attend if we get through that
and we start programming today today is
that day 147 which means that if you're
trying to follow along home with the
source code if you pre-order the game I
am a hero org and you want to start with
source code I'm starting with today
unpack day 146 is source code that is
what I am working with and that is what
you will want to work with if you want
to match my code all right so let's go
ahead and talk about the asset system a
little bit and what we want to have
happen here because we've done the work
now of defining sort of how the asset
system works you know what i should do
by the way let's take it let's zoom out
and just look at what this looks like
it's like very long lines and it kind of
goes oops and then it kind of goes
anything i wonder if we should start a
new like branch of this tree it's right
you can kind of see it's this long
skinny thing and it just goes down and
down and down like it's crazy right I
wonder if we should just start a new one
somewhere up here
and like kind of start a new like branch
going downwards so here it is right
here's here's some of this stuff it's
kind of funny I don't know I don't even
know why we save all this but I'm going
to go ahead and start it like right here
or maybe like right here this is going
to be it so alright so I come in here
and let's make this up to sort of the
size that it would be there we go de74
and I'm just going to come over here
right and there's going to be my my new
day ok so here is day 1 47 right alright
so this is asset files we already you
know I'm pretty happy with our ask that
systems actually kind of cool I think
already the tag based matching stuff is
pretty sweet in my opinion like I really
kind of like the way that worked out and
I think it's going to be interesting to
see how it goes going forwards but what
we need to do now is take this you know
to sort of completion and say well we've
got two things we got to do we've got to
figure out how we want to define our
asset files and then the other thing we
have to do is figure out how we're going
to deal with memory management in the
asset system because like i said the
asset system is kind of a special case
really in our system of we want it to be
able to sort of act like a virtual
memory system right kind of like the
operating systems virtual memory system
only with more predictability and more
control for us and what so what we
wanted to be able to do is when in the
game we are working with assets what we
want to be able to do is we want to be
able to sort of have a potentially giant
asset footprint like you know 16
gigabytes uncompressed of assets or
something like this right but if the you
know user only has like two gigabytes of
memory or something or four gigabytes of
memory we want to take you know however
much of that we're affording to assets
and use that as sort of like a scattered
window into all of the assets that we
have and and make sure that we're only
pulling in the ones that we need for the
situation of the game as it stands right
now will we ever actually
use that functionality I don't know it's
definitely the sort of thing that I'm
sort of showing you because it's
something that I want to teach and it's
something that you often do want so
we're going to write the asset system as
if it will need to page but you know
will we ever necessarily get to the
number two to the size of assets where
this becomes a problem that's not
necessarily clear right we may end up
only having four gigabytes of assets
total I'm compressed or something like
this and so the game never need could
you know and everyone who runs the game
has eight gigabytes of memory I don't
know right they could add but again you
know I kind of want to show this because
I want the game to be scalable in that
way and so we're going to say that one
of our goals is to make it so that what
we can simply set a working set size and
then no matter what that working set
sizes you can have as many assets as you
ever want if the artist pile in 64 gigs
of assets as long as you've got
somewhere to store them it will work
right so that's one thing we have to
handle that is the harder of the two
things the simpler of the two things
that we need to handle is the asset
files they're a little related but right
now I just want to focus on the asset
file part of it and what that is is
that's moving the thing that we've got
right now which is a collection of sort
of random bitmaps on the drive random
wave files on the drive and a little bit
of code in the game that says which
one's of those match to which ones to
which like IDs and which segments or
whatever what I want to do is move from
that to the concept that we've got a
unified structure on the disk that
represents all of the asset information
that we actually need to process and so
we can you know distribute the game as
one nice file packed file that has all
of the stuff in it and is easy for the
game to get around and load out of and
whatever right so let me talk about that
for a bit and explain to you sort of
what the goals are cure and how it works
and what's going to happen okay
so as you know we what we've decided to
do is we kind of have our asset system
kind of expands in in tears if you will
on the game side of things right so I'll
just say here is what the game code is
actually thinking in terms of right the
game's code is thinking in terms of two
sets of things right it's thinking in
terms of types and tags right so it will
ask for a particular type of thing like
a hero and then it will ask with tags
and the tags will be things like oh you
know maybe I want a male and female hero
so there's like gender tags or something
where I can say which one of those I
wanted and then if you know the the
artists have put in multiple female or
multiple mail or you know any any
combination the two maybe maybe we've
got a bisexual hero or whatever it well
that's not really gender that's that
sexual orientation let's say we have
sexual orientation we have straight
heroes gay heroes bisexual girls maybe
we have everyone on the Kinsey scale so
like you can be from zero when did it go
from zero to 5 or 0 to 10 I remember
what the Kinsey scale was it's probably
all been debunked by now anyway but
let's suppose we've got that we want to
be able to do is you know have the
artist put in anything that we want to
match these tags and then when the game
code says I want a hero that's on the
Kinsey scale of 0.2 what it will do is
it will find the closest hero sprites
that match whatever that is right and so
we could add that for everything hair
color maybe he's on there let's say you
know maybe we've got stuff like age you
know is the hero 20 or is the hero 50 or
as a hero for right so that's the way
that the game code thinks about things
and the reason that it thinks about them
that way is because we're trying to
decouple the game code from the actual
asset table right so the asset table is
the thing that actually has individual
assets in them right so there's things
in here where we've got actual bitmaps
okay and those bitmaps are like you know
the 30 year old hero and the 50 year old
year on the four-year-old here or
whatever right and we don't want the
game code to have to think in terms of
specific bitmaps
we wanted to be able to think in terms
of types and tags where I can just say
you know what I've got it I want a hero
here's the stuff I know about them I
don't want to care whether the artist
drew exactly that thing or not I want
you to just get me back whatever the
artist drew that's as close as possible
to representing this thing right and
that way these two things can be updated
independently the game code can start to
think more about stuff as necessary and
add more tags and more parameters those
tags and the asset table can be updated
by the artist by adding new things so if
the artist sees the game it's like oh I
don't like the fact that the old hero
still looks kind of young I'm going to
make an even older model for the hero
and put that in there right you don't
have to update the game code at all the
game code stays exactly the same you
don't have to recompile it you just
update the asset table and the asset
table will now have an older looking
hero that it pulls out and you know
allows you to sort of make a more
accurate depiction of what the game was
actually expressing in terms of its
gameplay variables right so so this part
we've done a good job specking I'm happy
where that I think that's good and this
part the asset table we actually have
kind of specified and you can see it in
the code if we actually look I haven't
opened the editor yet so let's go ahead
and actually do that but if you actually
look at the code in handmade asset eh
you can see that we we've actually done
a reasonable job defining what this
tables actually look like you can see
that we've got sort of a set of bitmaps
and they have these infos associated
with them sounded photos and bitmap
infos those are the two things that tell
you about the actual asset like you know
whatever how big it is what the what the
bitmap file on disk was you know the
stuff that's necessary to kind of load
it in and use it or whatever right and
then we have the tags and the tags are
all of sort of those again those things
that we've tagged assets with and then
we have the assets themselves which use
the tags right so the assets say here's
my tags you know points into this table
right choose me
so what I've been kind of doing there as
we've been going through is working out
that structure right I've been trying to
work out what that actual structure is
and it's we've kind of sort of made it
here and this is what we actually want
our file to represent right we want our
file to be able to represent these
specific things so that when we load the
game we have all of this information
that is what we know that we actually
want and so let's go over what these
things actually are and talk about how
we're going to store them on the disk
and so on so they're kind of in reverse
order here in terms of who you know in
terms of who references what reverse
order is kind to tend to be a thing in C
because since C doesn't requires forward
declaration right C requires you to
define or hard to declare something
before you use it typically C
programmers get in the habit of defining
things in reverse order right if tags
are referenced by assets you tend it rep
to talk about the assets second and the
tags first right you go from the thing
that does the leaf reference least
referencing thing that does the most and
that's why they're kind of sword in this
order but that that's neither here nor
there that's just a sort of see
programmer idiom right so anyway if you
take a look at asset type right you can
see how we defined it and what it is is
an asset type is just a set of assets
that all correspond to the same logical
thing as the game might ask for it with
an enum so for example if the game asks
for a shadow and you know again we don't
know that these are the types were
actually going to want they're just ones
we put together for testing but if the
game asks for a shadow then what it's
going to do is it's going to look up the
asset type shadow in that array and
going to see how many assets it has that
are of type shadow right so if you take
a look at how that actually works here
you know we take a look at what this
asset table thing actually does what
that means I'm going to just draw it out
what that means is we have asset type
kind of as our most primal this is our
most important step of the
classification in the file right we've
got asset type and when asset type is is
it's indexed right we've got 0 1 2 3 4
so on right it's indexed here and these
are
actually become innumerous right we
define these as a numerate so they're
easier to use in code but those
enumerates are still there just
corresponding to a flat table right you
know and so this right here maybe shadow
right this right here maybe hero who
knows what they are you can see them
here where are they there they are right
you can see them here and we have like
head cake torso that sort of stuff all
that all that goodness right so hero
would be a bad example it's really more
like head cape torso right so we have
these asset types and what the asset
types do is they themselves you know
inside here actually are a sub
addressing there's they're sort of
referencing into a separate table and
that separate table is the assets table
right and if this looks a little bit
like a database to you that's because it
is kind of like a database when things
get stored on disk they often tend to
look like databases because hey guess
what that's what a database is it was
the thing that was designed to represent
data cleanly on disk anyway we've got
sort of the concept of we got a
first-hand account kind of a thing here
right and so what the way that we store
the asset ranges is by in this table
here where we've got our actual assets
right and again the assets are by number
as well 0 1 2 3 4 and so on what we do
is for any given one of these we say all
right first there is a number in here
which says the first asset right that
corresponds to that type maybe that
first assets down here let's say it's
for right so it's saying this one and
then it's got some kind of account that
says oh there are three assets total
right and so five and six are all also
this one right so it kind of refers to
this range right this three lets us know
that range so what that means is in the
asset array we know that we've kind of
packed them in here we've got these
these assets right if that makes sense
okay now we have something that we want
to consider at this point and that
something is how exactly we want this
loading to work and I'll just explain to
you why there's something to be aware of
here the thing that we need to be aware
of here is that if let's say we had to
asset files instead of just one right if
we have one asset file that has all our
assets in it this what I'm about to say
doesn't make any sense it doesn't matter
but suppose we were going to have to
well when you use sort of convenient
packed a dressing like this where you
just kind of go okay all of the assets
of one type occur at the same place in
the table right the problem that you get
with that is that you then lose the
ability to have multiple discreet ranges
of the same asset if you only have one
asset file that's not really a problem
because asset build time you can always
just make sure that the ranges are
contiguous and you maybe it might have a
problem with incremental if you're
trying to be incremental about how you
link things but since these are only the
tables and tables aren't very big you
just rewrite them every time that's not
like that they could be a blah blah blah
blah blah right but if you wanted to
have multiple asset files and for
example a case we might want to do that
is you've got the original access from
the game and then you want to ship an
expansion pack right I've got the
original assets for a mate hero and then
I want to ship handmade hero to you know
our sorry I guess I should say handmade
hero you know DLC or something Abner co
embraced chocolate wine expansion or
whatever right and it's going to add a
bunch of different chocolate wise to the
game and all this sort of stuff right
well the original game maybe maybe
already had chocolate wine right and so
it had some kind of entry into the truck
into the table that said you know down
here it said chocolate wine right so
when the game wanted chocolate wine and
asked for chocolate wine right it got
this range back and it said Oh chocolate
wine starts at entry 16 and it goes for
seven entries there are seven types of
chocolate wine
right but now we come here and we've got
you know this is this is asset file one
right this is the this is the original
assets right this is the original now we
come in here and we say oh well okay but
there's the you know there's the there's
the Abner combrer expansion right pack
or something right so we've got the
expansion pack and that's just all
chocolate wine so it's got a thing in
here in the asset type table and it says
oh okay yeah there's chocolate wine
right and it goes you know from from 12
to nine and it's got 930 different kinds
of chocolate wine in it or whatever
right well the problem is now there's no
one single range that actually has all
that stuff in it so what we really want
to do I think in order to support
expansion packs and stuff like that is
we want to make the asset type table on
disk be a little bit different than what
it is in memory and we probably want to
merge on load right do kind of some kind
of emerged on load type of a thing and
what that would look like right is we
would say OK in the asset table in these
files instead of having the asset table
go 0 1 2 3 4 and having the index imply
the numeron what we should probably do
is have the innumerous stored in it so
entry 0 actually then says what a
numeron are you actually referring to
are you referring to chocolate wine are
your friend that wouldn't you know what
are you talking about and then what
we'll do is when we load those asset
type tables in we will merge the same
chocolate wine from this one chocolate
line from that one will merge them
together into a contiguous array in
memory so our game can be nice and
efficient in memory and have everything
stored all in the same place when it has
to deal with chocolate wine but on disk
we can have multiple different chocolate
wine sets and this also helps with
incremental linking in the sense that
when we build our asset file we can
incrementally add on to the end of it if
we want to and we can add on to the end
of the asset table without having to
really rewrite or shuffle anything right
because we just add a new entry later on
for whatever that thing was so I think
that's the way that we would want to do
it right
think that's what we would want to do
I'm just pointing that out so anyway yet
we've got assets we've got lots of types
that refer to ranges of assets right and
the assets themselves are really just
things that refer to what you know first
of all what you need to actually load
the asset right so we've got we've got
the like whether it's a bitmap or a
sound it's going to have this this info
struct right associated with it so one
of these is going to have is like it's
got the asset info whether it's a bitmap
or a sound and that would be more
expansive than what's shown here right
because this care file name thing would
go away because we wouldn't be
referencing files externally anymore we
would be actually including the data for
the file directly into our asset pack
file so you know we'd actually have a
lot more data here we'd have the offset
probably in the file where the data
chunk lives we'd have how big it was
we'd have the metadata for it so for
example for bitmap we'd have what its
width and height were that kind of stuff
right so you know and sound we'd have on
my channels it has all that stuff right
so we'd these infos structs will be more
expressive once we no longer once we
remove file name from them and kind of
take them up to sort of a full directory
metadata entry for this this thing right
so the assets have two parts like I said
they've got the tags right and they've
got the info the info is relatively
straightforward it's just everything we
need to define the actual specific sound
or bitmap that we want and the tags like
we said before are really just again
another reference into an array of tags
and the tags like we saw here right
we've kind of got the tag up here asset
tag is a very simple thing an asset tag
is nothing more than a int and a float
right it's just that's all it is so
these are just a raise of instant floats
so this can be stored on disk directly
this can be stored on disk directly this
can be stored on just directly with the
enum kind of addition and when we load
these out we will pretty much be able to
just flat load them exactly as they are
mods
if we want to know compress them for
loading or something like that as well
we could do that but other than that we
can just basically load them in and
directly use them the only part that I
think we're going to want to do in prop
that the only parts i think we're going
to want to have signed of like a
actually interpretation step that
actually looks at the data before sort
of putting it into use is this enum part
where i think instead of having the
asset type table being loaded and used
directly we want to consider the asset
table as something we that's a type
table soon we load interpret and then
throw away because we want to build
basically a merged asset type table from
the from the the assets from from the
sort of multiple tables that we see in
the actual in the actual files so i
think that's how we want things to work
and like i said there's really not that
much to understand here it's very very
straightforward how we're actually going
to do these things I think most of them
will look on disk exactly like they do
in memory minus any kind of compression
that we do to compress the tables you
know we'd probably stick eventually some
kind of like an LZ compressor on there
or something just to show how to kind of
keep to reduce the sizes of those things
or whatever even though really they're
never going to be all that big probably
but point being modulo that there's
really not a whole lot else that we
would need to do and so looking back
here at these sorts of things what we
could do is now start to define what we
want that asset file to actually look
like and how we want to actually load it
and process it now if you look at what
we were doing down here you can see we
wrote this code that you know if you
look at what this code is here in
allocate game assets really this code
that you see here this is all and i said
this multiple times we were writing it
this is all just code that simulates
building essentially the asset file in
memory right this is essentially code
that's that's pretending that we had one
of these asset files already made excuse
me right and then it goes ahead
and uses it in place right so what I'd
like to do to kind of start us working
here I'm going to leave that as it is
because you know we've got the game
running and for those of you who are
kind of playing along at home you may
want to always have the game in a
running state so I'm not going to break
it I'm just going to leave it kind of
operating as it is but what I would like
to do is sort of break that part off a
clone of it if you will and make a
program whose only job it is to make a
dummy asset pack file that we can start
loading right and so I want to do
essentially exactly the same thing that
this thing was sort of pho doing here
and I'm going to do that sort of outside
right so what I'm going to do is I'm
going to open up our build up bat and
I'm going to give myself another piece
of code right I'm going to give
ourselves another sort of sort of a
build target if you will right and so
you can see here we've got our various
build targets the only one that I'm
really concerned with here is probably
this one so what I'm going to do is I'm
going to put a little thing in here
that's called like asset file builder
build and you know this probably I we
won't really probably do a whole lot
with this code because again it's only
for getting things SPECT and for testing
but you know I heard for the time being
I would like it to be in here as part of
the build so what I'm going to do is to
find a little thing called bug handmade
test or maybe I don't know if I should
have tested front maybe something like a
test asset builder something like that
right and I don't care about it
producing a map file or any of those
other things we can just go ahead and
have it do the standard stuff that it
does so I'm going to pop back over here
I don't know if we want to separate out
things into like test directories I
don't think we're going to have enough
for that so I think what I'll do is just
put it right in here
and I'm not going to put the handmade
sort of precursor on it so that it'll
just be clear that it's just a piece of
test code and not something that's part
of the build proper so here we go I'm
going to make that there and I'll just
go ahead and make kind of a you know a
standard boilerplate thing here like one
might normally have something like this
right and they'll get it compiling so
let's see oh right don't want to do that
for Maine there we go and so now I
believe if I'm not mistaken that in our
bill directory we should now have a test
asset builder pxe and there we do have
exactly that if I do test a set builder
I don't know if we added that the path I
don't think we did yeah so I have to do
backslash you can see that I can run it
just fine and so basically what i've
done here is i've made a stuff now a lot
of people ask me things like you know
because on handmade hero we don't use
libraries and we don't use an engine we
don't use anything pretty much we do
everything from scratch and part of that
is obviously for educational purposes
but another part of it is actually
that's actually how i develop like my
code base at work right now has almost
no libraries in it whatsoever it isn't
even really even using an stb library at
this point it's literally one hundred
percent from scratch using absolutely no
libraries it doesn't even linked with
any windows libraries besides kernel32
it's like the most non-dependent code
base i think i've ever done in my life
but a lot of people often so it is true
like I actually do do things that way
often times but a lot of people ask me
like you know what libraries would you
use if you're going to use them or or do
you really never use libraries that's
our stuff and the answer is I you know
typically I don't use libraries in cases
where it's code I want to last because
my experience has been if you ever use a
librarian code that you want to last
you will just end up with a maintenance
nightmare on your head as on your hands
as that library either fails to support
the platforms that you needed to support
fails to continue to be updated
introduces bugs has bugs whatever so in
the code that I ship I tends not to want
any libraries in it and again sometimes
are exceptions like the stb libraries
that I think are well done and that
imposed a very low rate on you sometimes
those can be worth it but in cases where
I don't care if the code lasts at all
then have at it and so in the case of
this test asset builder for example this
would be a perfect example of a time
when it be fine to use libraries right
and so for example i'm half totally
happy to use the c standard library here
right because i don't care at all this
is just code to build a testing there's
absolutely no reason for me to even
think about anything that I you know or
even care how it's as long as I know how
to use the library it's not going to
cause me a headache right now I would
say go for it so this guy can be written
in just standard vanilla see I don't
care at all about it and I'm totally
happy to use like standard i/o for the
file i/o and all that sort of stuff
because I don't foresee any reason why I
should care about that right so that's
an example of a time when when I'm
totally happy to use libraries and would
use libraries and I hope maybe that
helps answer that question in action as
with an actual example that people can
relate to so what I'd like to do here is
write something that's going to write
out one of these tests asset files right
and so if we take a look at what we were
doing here we have you know this this
sort of stuff we've got all this year
right what I'd like to do is basically
recreate exactly what we are doing in
the game in a file and once we have that
then I'm hoping that we will be able to
swap out like basically do a giant if0
here right swap out the code that's
creating the
stuff on the fly with something that
just loads from the file and then all of
this stuff can just be vaporized goodbye
right and then we are left with
something that is exactly what we wanted
an asset file that we can just load and
we can pour our assets into it all we
want and the game can load them and the
other nice thing about doing this this
way is for people who do not want to use
the art assets that I ship and who are
making their own stuff or who are going
to make a game of their own after
handmade hero that work similar whatever
this could serve as the starting point
for your asset Packer however you wanted
to do it from whatever source arts that
you have since you know it's going to be
different from how I'm going to pack
them or what artists we use and so on
alright so first things first what I
want to do here is I want to start you
know by saying okay we're going to write
an asset pack file and so I guess we
really don't need to talk about multiple
files ever we could just have a single
file called out right that's going to be
you know the the file that we actually
write to and we're just going to open
one of those in the right the whole
thing to it then closed right that's all
we're really going to do here so we can
do that and what we're going to do is
we're going to want to add all sort of
these add these these things to it and
then sort of write them out right so
what we may have to do in the interim is
I don't know if we want to try and do
this in sort of a single pass method or
we want to build them up as we go
probably if zero leaves out as well here
we go but what I will do here is just
say all right let's go ahead and take
this out file will f open again a new
this is just using the C standard
library to do file i/o so we'll f open a
file this will just be called like test
dot handmade cure assets I don't know
does anyone have an objection to HH a
as the final extension hopefully not so
we'll just go ahead and do that if you'd
never use the C standard library before
our Genesis just it's its way of doing
file stuff it's like create file in
win32 when we covered that F open is
just saying I want to open a file with
this name and a pass it what kind of
operations are going to do on it w means
i'm going to write to it be means it is
binary and this w is also the part of
what that implies in addition to just
the fact that you're trying to write to
it is also that you expect it to kind of
erase the file if it already exists so
it's got a like an implicit overwrite
concept in there so what we're going to
do here is we're going to say okay you
know if we are able to open the file
then we want to do a bunch of stuff to
it and then f close it which says we're
done with the file right that's again
the sort of close handle equipment like
we looked at win32 the sea level in the
sea runtime library so we open the final
we're going to do a bunch of rights to
it and then we're going to close it and
that's really all that's going to happen
here nothing too fancy and so the way
that we're going to do this I think
until we have sort of a a reason not to
I guess I guess what we should do is
just kind of gather up all the stuff
that we did here you know I think
because we want the flexibility I'm
gonna say let's just go ahead and let's
just go ahead and and define it first
and then then do the right at the end
that seems like maybe the easiest thing
to do right so we're going to assume
that we have all of these things to find
here and then we're going to loop over
all of them writing them out into the
asset pack file as necessary I don't
really know if that's the smartest thing
to do maybe we want to be incremental
I'm torn how we want to write this
because if we want the asset pack file
in general to be able to be appended to
incrementally then that would argue for
just setting up the code in that way to
begin with so that we actually practice
that but if we wanted to just be
something where you you tend to do the
compile on the right and you don't
update it incrementally then you
no I don't know um I really don't hmm
because there's other things to think
about well you know what I don't care
we're just gonna let us go this way and
we'll see how it goes if we want to add
more stuff to it later you know we
always can right ok so what I'm going to
do here is I'm not going to care at all
about this code in any way like this is
going to be absolute crap code that
really just doesn't matter at all
because only force pecking out the file
thing and so what I would like to do
here is probably just say we're going to
have these bitmap assets or whatever
right so I want to go ahead and just
make sort of a way of actually of sort
of holding those right so I have the
file name so this is just the bitmap
asset I guess I'm going to have the file
name there i'm going to have whatever
that that offset thing is right that
sort of alignment I guess is what we
called it right I'm going to have those
two things that are going to be
specified and then I've got these asset
types here so really this code is pretty
much going to mirror the code that we
had before right in fact I probably can
just grab it I don't even know if I need
to really do any work I can probably
just clone this code exactly because all
of this code is all debug anyway and all
would be deleted from here eventually
either way so if I go ahead and put that
this stuff in here here we go with our
with our various things where we add
bitmap info and all that sort of stuff
we can simplify this a little bit right
we can simplify this a little bit by
just saying okay we only need the file
name and the align percentage hear it I
guess look and see how we do that we
don't even need those slot IDs for the
most part but ok so what we want to do
here right is you want to take this code
and we're basically just trying to
buffer up all of the stuff that we need
so that we can then look at it and write
out the tables for it as well as the
data right so if we take a look at these
here yeah
I guess that's this we probably want to
change a little bit to the way these
work but will will hold all that hold
off on that for a second so yes so all
of this stuff is probably just fine we
can get rid of the referencing of the
assets here and just actually pretend
all these things are global variables
because they can be global variables to
just hang out in here right all this
code is going to be building things
basically the same way right so I'm just
going to literally just we appropriate
this code because why not right so there
we go and debug add bitmap info can
probably like that never gets called
anywhere else does it you know it's not
that's not really a thing that happens
so we should probably do is just have
that be in here right you probably just
just in line that I don't even know why
we made separate ones for it originally
it doesn't really seem like a good use
of anyone's time or energy but that's
what we did who knows why so i'll go
ahead and paste those in there so we can
port that in that way later okay so when
we do begin asset type right and then of
course the other thing too is now all
this debug code that we had in there
right all this debug code comes out to
here right like like so there we go so
yeah we can change these guys okay yeah
although we probably I don't know if we
want to actually keep our standard
defiance or anything there we probably
do so I might as well just go ahead and
grab those from handmade platform which
I think we can just include right we
should be able to do this right handmade
platform dot H and that'll work yes in
fact it works quite nicely so I think we
could just do that we can make these
guys br30 tues for now so and then these
guys can can stay u32
there we go all right so you can see
what i did there basically what i did is
i just said all right i want to use all
the same types and stuff just to make it
easier on myself so I just went ahead
including have a platform beige because
there's no reason why I can't right I
can just use that same header file even
though we're not going to define any of
the stuff from it we can just use the
pipe defs and stuff alright so then
we've got again sort of the same stuff
we had here where we've got the asset
type and all that stuff right what we
want to do here is is pretty much just
totally use all the same stuff that we
have right I think all of this stuff is
is pretty much just what we want right
so we can use it like so and there we go
and then for our asset types here these
things I guess I don't know you know we
could even do now that I think about it
we could even do something even more
ridiculous for the moment we could
actually just include this asset type ID
thing here mmm you know I don't really
want to do that so what I think I'm
going to do is make that I'm going to
pull that out into a separate thing
there's going to be a sort of a handmade
asset ID or sorry i should say handmade
asset type ID dot h and that thing is
just going to have this just this one
thing right and that way it can be
shared amongst various tools that might
want it such as this thing without
having to include everything else right
so there's going to be a handmade asset
type ID include here and then this you
know this code can just include the same
thing so when it includes a SAT H first
I can just include asset type ID age
right all right let's see how we're
doing about 10 minutes left maybe 15 and
we started about five minutes late
alright so what we want to do now is we
want to just clean this code up and make
it so that it works with our you know
our new stuff here so what we need to do
is a handmade assets at H we have these
arrays right and so we want to do is
actually pull out all those arrays that
we had and just use them right so here
we go and what I want to do now is I
want to say well you know what we don't
even really care about this stuff so you
know what this is just a you know large
number just because again don't care
about this at all don't care about this
code in any way I guess assets lot is
not necessary at all right we only
really have we only really have these
other things here right in our case very
large number doesn't even have to be big
right because we're only doing tests but
you know in theory there's going to be a
lot of these things if you were actually
building the real asset backed by so
yeah okay so there is everything right
that we actually have a good asset tag
sounds bitmaps and asset types so that's
that's all the stuff that we actually
have and I guess the bitmap info and
that stuff is the only stuff that we
don't have here and so we should I guess
we'll grab these we're going to modify
these pretty heavily obviously and and
we'll do that I guess in a second well
we probably will get to that today
actually okay so yeah so these things
here or again we don't probably care
about actually representing those ID
specifically so that's fine and we can
make the align percentage into two
different things to avoid having to pull
v2s into this for no reason and then I
think we're good so I'm going to go
ahead and just finish kind of
porting this out so it's no longer oops
it's no longer working off of that
assets bit let's see here cannot convert
from asset star star oh right i read
that star okay and align percentage x
the line percentage why well this is
actually gonna be this code right here
so i guess we don't really care about
this much at all so i guess this brings
us to something that's kind of odd which
is that the slot ID right is sort of a
thing that we use for maintaining like
loading information stuff in the runtime
game and so in here it actually means
something a little different right in
the actual file slot ID really is
talking about where the data actually is
for this particular asset right like
where the actual information is so i
don't know that we really need slot ID
anymore what we're probably going to do
is have something more like a u64 that's
like data offset right you know what i
mean it it's really going to be
something that says here's where the
actual data for this asset lives and
there's not going to be like this sort
of separate slot ID business for it I
don't think because the slot idea is
really something for the run time too
because if you look back at the handmade
asset and you look at where the slot
stuff is where is that that's that slot
you can see that this is really this is
not an on dis thing this is like just
storing the state of the loaded you know
storing how something's been brought
into memory and what its status is and
so I think really we don't care about
that so really right here we've just got
this data offset and the slot ID part of
it when we look at the asset I'm trying
to think I guess I do
understand why do you even need that
slot ID because why wouldn't you just
why do we even have a slot ID why isn't
the slot just part of the asset am I am
I on am I missing something here because
that seems very odd to me right that
seems very odd it just doesn't make any
sense in fact i'm looking at i'm looking
at this here and I just I don't even
understand why we do it that way maybe
there is a reason but I'm looking at
this and let's let's you know maybe this
is something that I want to address
right now even because i think it's just
dumb so let's remold and we'll build our
our actual gain here right here we go so
looking at this I just don't understand
what the point is of the slot ID it
doesn't seem to really serve any purpose
right because you have the asset itself
and the asset itself should just have
the assets lot in it right I mean why
wouldn't you do it that way like what's
the what is the slot ID actually do for
you because you could just return your
own self you could just return your own
index so the index into the asset array
would just be the slot ID is that I mean
sure seems obvious to me I don't really
know why you wouldn't do that and even
if you didn't want to include it in the
asset structure itself well you could
still just include it you could just
have a separate array right so I don't
understand I don't understand the point
of that so I'm just going to try that I
want to see what happens if instead I
just do this right
I want to know what happens so what i'm
doing here is in order to test my theory
that it doesn't matter i'm gonna let the
compiler guide me towards figuring out
whether it does or not so what I've done
is I've removed the two separate arrays
that we had replace them with a single
array and I'm just going to let the
compile errors guide me to see whether
that was a good idea or not so you can
see here we've got this this thing we're
looking up into the bitmaps so I'm just
going to go ahead and change that to
reference into slots which should be
exactly what we want same thing here to
reference into slots when we load a
sound again just same exact thing here
it's just looking into slots I don't see
any reason why that wouldn't work
against lots when it loads slots again
so all of these things can just I mean
there's really no reason we know the IDS
don't collide if we don't want them to
write slots again we've got sounds here
slots again and so here we go so yeah so
it looks to me in my opinion the only
thing that we were getting from that is
the fact that we could compress sort of
that we had bitmaps and sounds being
addressed separately right so the number
of bitmaps went from zero to bitmap
count the number of sounds what from
zero to sound count means and so those
were the there are two overlapping
sets of slots there right but I don't
think that really buys anything because
why do we care about that you know sort
of compression what we could do it what
we should do I would argue instead is
just have the asset itself store a
pointer to its info struct that just
seems way smarter to me because that
mirror is what happens on disk as well
so all yeah this this I think that was
just generally speaking kind of a dumb
kind of a dumb idea and in fact we may
even want to make it so that it's all
just one array it doesn't even matter
and we just have a union for the two
bits of info that you
aid because if you look at like for
example in here what the actual amount
is if the amounts are fairly similar
size wise then we don't even really need
to represent the two of them separately
like that so so I don't know I think
that may have just been making things
more complex for no real reason so
here's what I'm going to do there I'm
just going to go ahead and try that as
well because you know I feel like it so
there we go and then I'm going to say
all right we've got a union asset oops
here asset bitmap info bitmap asset
sound info sound right I just think
that's more interesting so I'm going to
go ahead and do that and that means
we're also going to get rid of bitmap
infos and the sound infos and the bitmap
count in the sound count as well
probably I think those just go away
right so off we go and let's take a look
so when we do get bitmap with a bitmap
ID really all we have to do is a cert
here that it's less than the asset count
right and and so on that's really it
asset count we could try to verify that
the thing we could have like debug
information here that's whether or not
the thing is a sound or not if that
makes sense but I don't really know how
much I care about that we'll see if we
have any bugs of that form so sound
infos is not a member of game assets you
are correct so if we want to actually
get the sound info what we'd have to do
is ask for just the assets assets ID
value sound believe that's it right and
the same would be true here right if
we're trying to get the bitmap info for
something we would have work assets
assets
top bitmap right yeah and so I really
think that's pretty much it in terms of
what's going on here sound and let's see
to pug used bitmap counts so debug a
bitmap info now we're going to do
exactly what I said we should do before
we're going to put that right here so
assets lot ID is just not a thing
anymore instead we're going to do it
this way where we do asset bitmap file
name and asset bitmap dot a line
percentage that just seems better all
around anyway oops kept an address in
there and then we've got let's see ads
sound info same thing here asset count
and we've got our sound infos so that's
just going to be assets ID values I'd be
valued that sound there we go and yeah
what did I just do accidental that's not
what I wanted there we go so bitmap
count bitmap infos and bitmaps all these
things just go away goodbye those are
gone we then have our total asset count
I don't know what our total asset count
actually is i guess we just did 256
times asset count for these guys so i
don't know the asset count is now two
times 250 sativa no that's just we don't
care about that again that's going to be
corrected by our file stuff alright so
assets assets last music slot ID dot
sound there we go and that's just
reaching in there to change that one
value so I think that's really it if
that makes sense I think that's all so
let's see if that works
it does not at all let's take a look at
why it doesn't work I devalue bitmap
what are you asking for here ID value
zero slots is null what do I not
allocate slots I must have missed
something that looks like i missed
something stupid let's take a look oh
well that's just me not ever actually
bothering to allocate that slots slots
so yeah that was just a slight oversight
there never bothered to actually
allocate the array
so my bitmaps are broken as you can see
but my sound is working which is
interesting kind of amusing all right so
what did we do wrong there let's take a
look we have our sound asset and our
sound like I said we have our sounds are
working just fine wait a minute how did
this what happened here wow that's the
problem you never finished the slot ID
thing so slot IDs are supposed to go
away that's the problem yeah that's just
that's just crazy and also how did add
sound info still how did add sound info
still work okay so this is also kind of
focus yeah let me go ahead and put this
in here here we go there we go so this
should also be something that kind of
just just happens directly in here i
ported that a little too literally so
what we want to do here is say asset
sound a file name that sound a first
sample index sample count next to play
there we go okay and for good measure
you know what i think i might just
return the asset from this one as well
cuz why not there we go even though
we're not going to use these eventually
alright so now i should get some errors
on the slot ID which was what was
actually supposed to happen and so all i
need to do now is actually return the
asset index because that's always going
to be the actual index that we want
right we no longer have to think about
the slot ID the asset index is fine
alright so in this case we've got the
asset index and we in fact now we don't
even need to look up the asset right the
result is literally just just this so
that's kind of cool to now we don't have
that dereference which is which is
awesome right let's take a look here
reduce asset slightly same exact thing
the result is now just there
so this simplifies a lot of code too so
I kind of like this change sorry I'm a
little over i think i just we should be
ending right now but I'm going to go
another five minutes just to finish this
change up because I think it's a good
change so yeah we've got assets as we
don't need do any of that this music is
actually just the thing we actually
wanted right we already got the asset
back so now we can just set it so that
code got simpler and and of course this
music itself well unfortunately that's a
little tricky though because we don't
know what the actual index of the asset
is when we added it which we actually
need here so that's a little trickier so
add sound asset what we may want to do
here is actually return the index not
the asset pointer right so we could just
return the asset index here and I don't
know if we want an actual asset ID thing
we've got bitmap oh well I guess we've
got sound ID and bitmap ID which is what
those are right so there we go so you
can see here we've got the actual value
so our bitmap ID or I should say a
bitmap ID is just this guy right there
we go value take it's not value I don't
even remember what it is result and the
same would be true here for the sound ID
right the sound ID is going to be this
guy there we go and so now when these
guys come back right it's actually going
to be a sound ID that comes back for
this music and then assuming that it's
the last one how is this working it's
the lits actually the last music that
was supposed to be right
there we go do we have an is valid for
these guys I don't know if we actually
do we do so if last music is valid then
what we would want to do is say you know
the last music asset Jimmy the last
music asset it's sound next to play
right excuse me it sound next to place
value is going to be whatever this music
whatever its value was right oops
connect resides UN 32 is it actually you
in 30 to the next to play next to play
there we go all right
okay so I like that a lot better so
there we go we kind of did a nice little
architectural change their they're just
simplify things so now we have a much
more straightforward thing we just have
assets lots assets and tags the slots
could be unified with the assets
probably you know if we wanted to I
don't think that would be a problem
right you can imagine because right now
we've got the assets lot go ahead and
pull that down here to where the actual
asset is so there you go you can see the
asset here and so you can see that
really all it would be is is these
additional pointers for slots so I don't
know if we want to do that we could
unify them we could not there to
parallel arrays now probably doesn't
matter whether we do or if we don't but
you know if it turned out to be some
kind of cash locality thing that we
actually cared about maybe we would but
we can leave it like that for now so
that was pretty nice i like that change
simplifies this stuff quite a bit
reduces the amount of code anything that
reduces the amount of code is good and
so that's pretty much I think what we
want to do there so yeah I'm going to
leave it there and I'm gonna say that
the test asset builder will be what will
pick them back up on tomorrow we've
already kind of gotten a little bit
through it but you know will we should
probably be able to get writing out a
file tomorrow and and then maybe the day
after that we'll do reading that file
into the actual game so yeah I'm pretty
happy with where that is for now let's
go ahead and go to the QA and so anyone
who has questions now is a great time to
ask them put kyouko in front of them so
I will see them
around how many luck is the product so
far I don't know we've been keeping it
pretty good I always forget how to run
this tool I think you can I just say the
directory block and made so so a 300
looks like I don't know how many it'll
be by the time we're done but you know
game code can kind of tends to
proliferate that amount so i feel like
you know we'll probably be able to do
the engine in in twenty thousand lines
of code no problem right probably less
but the game code may may make that a
larger number
you mention LZ compression of assets
will we write the compression algorithm
well it will 'verily swill right the
decompression part well I don't know
that will bother writing a compressor
but we will write a decompressor again
everything from the asset pal up I'm not
going to cover so once we expect the
asset file that's the end of that will
just assume that somebody somewhere is
writing out our asset file in the spec
that we've defined so
are we using bitmaps for any other
reason than how easily they can be
processed we're not really using bitmaps
if that makes sense the reason that
we're loading bitmaps right now is
because they were the easiest thing to
show people how to load as an example
when we were sort of like teaching the
very basics of programming stuff so
really the asset pack file will not be
storing things in BMP format the asset
pack file will be storing them in just a
raw you know raw pixels basically right
so yeah we won't really be using bitmaps
the actual shipping code and probably as
early as next week will no longer be
using bitmaps at all only the thing that
packs the asset file would potentially
be loading bitmaps but like I said
that's not really of our concern what
does Union do when used in the struct it
basically says that these two things
overlap in in storage right so if you
have a union here like this one what it
says is i don't need both of these at
the same time i'm only going to use one
of them so overlap the storage so like
these two things here it Alec you know
when I say asset I'm saying I want space
for both the UN 32 for the first tag I
set and the unit 32 41 past the last one
right I want these two I want storage
for both of these but here because asset
is either a sound or a bitmap I know I
only need one of them so I just tell the
compiler hey store these overlapping and
I'm going to address one or the other
based on which one I want and I don't
care I don't need you to store the data
separately so what will actually happen
in practice and in fact you know what I
can show you this let me actually show
you this in practice so you can see what
I'm talking about so here's the thing
here's the code to add a bitmap asset
right so if I come in here oh this is
adding tags which I don't really care
about let's let's add an actual bit my
best there we go so here's the asset
struct
okay in memory right and you can see me
expanding it out so here's the SS struct
here's the two things I asked for
separately and then here's the two
things that I asked for it to be
overlapping right now what you can see
about these things is that if I were to
take their address right so like let me
take the address of asset first tag
index right and now let me take the
address of one pass last tag index oops
you can see that the addresses are four
bytes apart because they're separate
places in memory right in fact if I go
to a memory view here and I copy this in
so now we're looking at oh god what did
you just do Thank You visual studio so
if I look at these right you can
actually see that they're at different
locations right so now if i write to
them right you can see i just wrote to
one of them and you can see it updated
here and now we're going to write to one
and you can see that i wrote to update
it here right so there and now then
they're stored separately right they're
two separate values so if i wanted to i
could change this one right i could say
it actually is a 10 and it understands
that right there's that's where it is
right in memory but now what happens
when I access the shared struct so now
i'm going to say bitmap file name equals
this thing well watch what happens right
here's bitmap file name and here's sound
file name do you see how they both
change and the reason for that is that
the memory is the same this right here
is the memory for that thing right and
it's using the same memory for both so
now and when I when I talk about a line
percentage it's going to overwrite this
these values because they're stored in
the same places right you see how it
over wrote those because the memory for
storing them is the same and so if I go
in here and I change sample count to
something right i overwrote what was in
the Y parameter because they're oh
they're in the exact same place in
memory so that's what a union means a
union means basically overlay these two
things in memory because I know I'm only
going to use one or the other at a given
time and so I don't care if their memory
coincides
did I see an off by one error on a
signing bitmap ID that increment correct
let's take a look I'm looking at the
wrong code first of all so I'm not sure
which code you're talking about if
you're talking about this code that is
as as expected this is saying i want the
next ID that's available which is this
one and once I've taken it I want you to
increment it so that it is no longer
going to get used by someone else right
same is true for the one down here so so
I don't think so unless you're talking
about something else
okay so looks like only off topic
questions are left i'll see if there's
any useful ones opinions on specialized
game film universities like digit pen no
i do not have one I've never been to a
specialized university or university for
that matter at all as a student so I
really don't know much about them any
thoughts that Unreal Engine 4 no I have
not used Unreal Engine 4 how do you
start learning c c++ school or
self-taught self-taught I learned when I
was pretty little kid have you
considered having a keyboard cam so we
can see your lightning fingers no I
haven't maybe someday we'll do a stream
where I just point it down I guess at
the at the keyboard did you program
during the weeks missed on handmade hero
no I never touch handmade hero except on
stream so there's never any code changes
that are not broadcast live ever well I
should say there are never any code
changes that aren't recorded sometimes
our coach James aren't broadcast live
because either twitch goes down or my
internet goes down or something like
that in that case they don't quite get
broadcast live but they are all recorded
and they are always available on the
YouTube archive and most of the time
ninety-nine percent of the time they are
broadcast live all right looks like we
are done looks like we are done for the
day all right good work today people
those a good that was good for the first
day back I think we are in good shape
let me go ahead and save our miss chief
here so yeah thank you everyone for
joining me for another edition of
handmade here it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always I'm pleased
with where we are on the asset system I
think we're in good shape for tomorrow
to kind of start writing one out
and loading it in well we probably write
it out tomorrow loaded in the next day
but it's all looking pretty good and I
like that sort of cleanup we did to the
SS system today it took a little
complexity out of it that I think was
not necessary and that's always good
sometimes the most productive work you
do will be with the Delete key that is a
quote that I am happy to to say I did
not make it I believe Rudy Scylla Bracy
said it first back when he was an intern
at Microsoft I've no idea what happened
to him but he said it in this true so
anyway thank you for joining me if you
would like to follow along the source
code at home you can always pure to the
game on handmade he roared it comes with
a source code and you could download it
every night from a link that you will
get in your email when you pre-order you
can also go to our forum site and ask
questions on the forums if you're trying
to learn it's a good place to go there's
also an antidote guide maintained by the
community some hardworking folks who
actually go there and annotate episodes
for you to view it's pretty darn awesome
actually there's also some ports to mac
and linux that people have been working
on in case you want to follow on a
different platform before we get there
so good stuff like that there's also a
patreon page if you just want to support
the video series you can subscribe to
that and we also have a tweet but you
can subscribe to if you just want to
know when the series going to be live it
will tweet the schedule every weekend
and it also tweets like upcoming in an
hour kind of tweets to you so if you're
trying to plan around it it's pretty
easy to follow that's about it for today
I hope to see you guys all back here
tomorrow 5 p.m. pacific daylight time on
twitch just like today until then have
fun programming and I will see you guys
on the internets take it easy everyone
you