hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero show we code a complete game live
on stream uh we
currently need to
add some things
to our visualization in order to track
down a bug i believe we can still uh
trigger in our collision detector
um i can't quite remember
uh last week if we
were still able to trigger it reliably
but i'm pretty sure we were
i'm pretty sure it's like you go
up here
um
and you
right at this intersection here we've
turned off all of the textures
on the walls and stuff so you know
they're just like the blue outlines
right now of the collision geometry
and if i
throw that glove up in the corner
like that
um my recollection is that you could get
into a situation where it will tunnel
you know what i mean
um so it'll it'll like tunnel through
uh
and you know i'm
totally failing to do it but you know
there was there was a bug here or at
least i thought there was
i
and i don't remember if maybe like we
ended up in a situation where we can't
really reproduce it very well because we
fixed something
um but i thought we could still do it
and then what i was saying is that in
order to find that because it's very
like hard to
uh debug something like that
uh without some way of
being able to like sort of step through
it and see what happens uh the idea was
gonna be we we need to do something
where we
uh where we like can single step through
things so i was like you know what i'll
do is i'll single step through it
now why i cannot redo it i'm not sure
like i said you know i i have so much
stuff to do during the week i forget
usually like where i left off
uh on doing seven handmade heroes so it
could be that we changed like changing
the way that the uh embedding code
worked
makes it so that this doesn't happen
anymore or something
but i could have sworn
that we at least had
i mean i remember saying i'm like next
week
we'll have to do this
it's been two weeks
um so i give myself a little bit more of
a pass
but the fact that i can't make it happen
is sort of depressing um
so that's unfortunate i'm not sure what
to do about that i was i thought
uh and maybe i'm wrong about that but i
thought that we
were still having that and maybe we're
not
um okay so at least we're still having
this one
there we go so if i walk backwards
through here
um you can see it getting stuck in there
so hey i've got something i can debug
anyway which is all we really care about
uh
as far as like putting together the
system
so
what you could kind of see happening
here right
uh there's a few things that are going
on um
to be honest i'm not 100 certain uh i
think what we did is we have a thing in
there that stops the recording whenever
uh somebody
whenever it uh triggers a case
where
yeah yeah i remember this now
it stops the recording
um
whenever you end up in a case
where you uh
you find yourself
colliding on
all four points or something like that
or more or all uh all eight where you
find yourself embedded
um it stops recording or something like
that i i don't remember the exact
specifics but like we can go and look at
the code
and
that should not be happening
like well like in these situations as
far as i know
uh
we we probably shouldn't have that hap
happen
now i don't know if that's actually true
because um oh wait no i do i was gonna
say because there's like the head on the
guy that could push us in that's what we
did we removed the head collider
so when we move through the world
the glove can move anywhere it wants the
glove is basically unconstrained right
now there's nothing forcing it uh into
like a bad position or anything like
that right
so
the fact that it can get stuck doesn't
make any sense
right it shouldn't be able to end up in
a situation where it gets in that case
like that right
um
it should not be able to do that uh
because
the fact that it can do that
means that it somehow has a like um
it somehow
left itself in a cell
that when it ended
it thought that cell was open
meaning it was a cell that could be
moved through
but when it started the next frame
it thought the cell could not be moved
through
now it's worth noting
and this is a very creepy
uh
coincidence so it suggests that maybe
this is also
implicated in it
you may have noticed that this why is
this drawing
i'll make this full screen
why is this drawing over here
right
it doesn't make a lot of sense does it
um
well
you have to remember that this
we did the extra work in the engine for
this game which is you know just because
i was trying to show like interesting
things that you might
want to do if you program
we did the extra work in this game
necessary to make it so that there's no
bounds on the world size
so
basically like you can make the game be
you know as large as you want
and in order to facilitate that we made
it so that the camera itself only moves
in a very small range of floating point
values and we just map the world into
that local range so that the floating
point values work
right
so that
operation every time you cross a
boundary like re-centers the camera
and so when you see that happen
that is because the camera
re-centered to a new location which is
here
and in doing so it's still drawing this
because these are recorded without these
are recorded in just a debug recorder
the debug recorder doesn't know where
they are
it knows just where they are relative to
the camera
so
the reason that this is very troubling
is because you'll notice that the glove
only seems to get stuck
when the camera moves like that
right the two places that get stuck
are the two times right that you
have the camera recenter
now when the camera recenters
it is true that the floating point
consistency will be slightly off
because since everything's relative
location
uh is
to one center which is the previous
camera origin
and then on the next frame everything is
updated to be relative to a different
camera center
which is the new camera origin
the floating point computations from the
first one will not match the floating
point computations from the second one
so it is theoretically possible
theoretically possible
that you could have the exact correct
placement of something
such that when you change the camera
center something that was just floating
point rounding away
right
from being considered in betting
suddenly isn't floating point rounding
away
from being embedded
that's entirely possible
right that's entirely possible
however
the reason that i'm not
even a little bit without further
investigation willing to say that that's
what's going on here
is because it would be really strange if
literally like both doorways that we
happen to walk through at the beginning
of the game
both had that exact crazy floating point
rounding scenario happen
when you walk through them every time
right
it doesn't seem super plausible to me
that that could be what's going on
so i'm worried that there's some
more severe problem
that has to do with camera recentering
that is causing
a much more likely to occur failure of
that kind
um and that is why i would like to
investigate this because a a floating
point error of the kind that i just
discussed
is not something you would expect to
happen very often it's one of those like
rare cases you know
so
i'm worried
i think we have a more serious problem
and i would that is really what i'd like
to investigate
um
and the fact that i can't reproduce the
other bug we could go back and watch the
video from last uh from two weeks ago
it might be that like this was just an
embedding bug problem
uh that we fixed
um
because we had like not had the
embedding code turned on properly or
whatever it is
so
maybe that's just not a re maybe that
just can't be reproduced now like maybe
that bug is is basically gone i'm not
sure uh so so i'm willing to give up on
reproducing that one temporarily uh
maybe we can go watch the video
uh later and see
if that's what we did but
uh in general yeah i would say
seems reasonable seems reasonable
um you know that reminds me
644 i should double check before we
start programming did we check in
last week
i'm so busy these days i
have no idea what's going on most of the
time
but i want to make sure we checked in
the latest one
uh code codebase
yeah 643.
so that's all
good 643
and 644.
so i think that's it that's really all
um i just want a ways of polishing up
this collision detector and i feel like
i need um
i just need a bit way to step through
this better if i'm going to be able to
do that
it's a bummer that this happens to only
occur at that
recentering point and the reason that
that's a bit of a bummer is because uh
that means that
the drawing of it will be kind of wonky
like it'll have to draw in a different
place that's okay because i guess we
don't really care but it's still like
kind of that's too bad right
it's the worst case for us for debug
viewing
because we don't track the location of
things like that we could try
um
and the way we would do that is that
when we call recenter we would also call
recenter on the debug drawing um and
maybe that's worth doing
uh
there's like a call
um that we call
here right
and
you know this nonsense
tells us what we're gonna do for moving
the camera stuff around
right
and so you can see here there's like
the camera target p and the camera p
uh
are updated
via this function
inside the world mode
when we call update camera for entity
movement
which is here
uh you can see
that there's like
already a little stuff that updates like
a few things just like oh you should you
should place it relative to this or
whatever it is right
so you know we could do a thing where we
just
pass like a
into the diagramming system we just like
pass
a thing that will update stuff based on
this change
and
i mean maybe that's worth it if you look
at the diagramming system
it wouldn't be very difficult to do
uh
you know if you imagine
just a thing that's like
this
where you say like hey offset the debug
diagrams
uh
where you can update them or whatever in
fact i think it should be like
probably like this
uh if you have something like this and
you just pass in an offset
uh to like you know whatever it's gonna
be
we should be able to do something like
this
where we loop through all these guys and
by the way uh if you see what's
happening here
uh
one of the things that's kind of
annoying this is why like unions are not
the best thing sometimes
is if these had just been expanded you
could basically just do this in a
polymorphic kind of way automatically
right
the fact that it's a union means we do
have to check to make sure that it's
something that actually has like points
in it
you know what i'm saying uh like one of
these things
and to be honest i forget what overlay
was even supposed to be
i don't know if overly doesn't really
have any parameters so i think it's just
these
um so it's not the end of the world but
you can see why you know sometimes it's
easier if you don't use a union it's
just a quick case of whether you're
trying to
um
keep things like compact or not
but basically like you wouldn't have to
do this switch
you would just offset the points
if you weren't doing this
right
um but it's still really easy
so it's not worth getting um
you know upset about but you know it's
just an example of something to be aware
of
so in this case we don't have anything
to do in the default case there's
nothing
so we don't have to but
if we did have other things that we
wanted to change offsets of we would
so that's it
uh and now all we have to do is uh go
and actually call this with some offset
variable
that will move the things to where we
need them to go
so it would be something like this
where we said like you know all right
the old
blah is something the new blah is
something
i don't know whether the target p or the
regular p are the things that we want
here but i assume it's target p
not camera location
um because the camera location just can
move all around or whatever right
so i'm assuming that when we do our like
sim you know our simulation center i
guess it's just this right
if we wanted to look at the difference
between those two things we could just
like actually check
and do that update i
think
because all these things happen first
that actually like you know we might
want to just do it this way
where we just go up here and say
um
when we are going to
actually like when we actually
start
start the frame
that's when we would do the offset based
on whatever we're going to set the
camera placement to
um so like right here where we do like
the camera transform or whatever we're
going to do
it might actually be here
that makes more sense for that
probably
um
yeah
so that's my guess and
we may already have the information that
we need i'm not sure
but we may already have the information
so if we look at like game camera
we're keeping
one of those
right
and
we may already have a thing that says
where it was last time i don't actually
know
uh but like we have to do this for the
lighting
excuse already
like when you look at lighting center we
have to do this already
uh
it may be that we keep that in the
lighting system but you can see why i'm
like
meh
uh you would imagine that this would
just be something yeah like
so you see how
like there's
information here about the origin
my assumption is that we just like
probably kept that in the lighting
system but you know um here
so you can see like this last origin p
here is kept inside the lighting system
so it's kind of do like a duplicate
piece of work if i keep it in two places
so it kind of feels like we don't really
want to do that
um
but i don't know
it depends how you look at it
uh whether you want to unify those or
not
but what you can see
is this test
right here
um is doing exactly what we were just
suggesting
we take like the
lighting and we move it based on when
the camera changes
and you can see
it you know just proceeds from there
after having done an offset
and then it just keeps going
so
you know
do we want to do that do we want to do
that i'm not sure
for now i think i might just say
maybe systems do this themselves to
avoid
uh people
getting out of sync in like calls
so
you know
here's another thought
maybe we
actually just
roll this into
a offset that everyone uses
so like
for example
what we could do
is say
that
at the
top of the frame
we tell you what the simulation center
is
like this
and then maybe the it just does this
itself
so like
there's in the diagram system there's
just like a call
you know what i mean
um
and maybe this goes away
so there's like a
a set origin thing
and it takes like a world position
uh that's the origin and the offset is
like it will compute it
you know
so
i think i like this a little bit better
that i think
has a higher chance of working reliably
so like if you imagine in here we're
just like all right you know there's
one of these things
um
and we just do like
if they're not equal
if they're not equal we just update and
the offset is just like subtracts
the movement that we need to get
ourselves uh between these two i have to
think about this i always think of this
i'm bad at these sorts of things
i oftentimes get it wrong
oops
uh i oftentimes get it wrong here the
[Music]
nice job
let's try that again
uh
so if i want these things to be relative
to the new origin right so i've got
things around an origin a and i'm going
to a new origin b
then it means that i need to take yeah i
should just do this out longhand um
this is where uh computer aided algebra
should just be built in to editors
but
yeah
doesn't matter
anyway
uh so you know i've got something like
the origin a
plus the the offset right
and it is
uh needs to be equal to origin b
plus the new offset
right maybe i'll use u and v
so v is the new offset u is the old
offset right
and i need these two things to be equal
so a plus the new offset and b plus the
old offset have to be in the same place
i think that's roughly what we're trying
to do here
so if i need to now solve for like what
this
value is
right
um
i need to do
i need to subtract this over to the
other side right so i need a like minus
b plus u equals b or whatever right
um
so
a minus b is the value that i would want
to add
to the old one
um and so it is subtracting the new
origin which is the opposite of what you
would normally think
so unless i screwed that up that's why i
say often get this wrong like you know
my guess was the wrong way round which
is exactly
i guess you could say my guess was right
in the sense that i guessed that this
was wrong
um so you want to
subtract
the old origin from the new
you want to subtract the new origin from
the old origin
so you want it to look like that
which is the opposite of what you would
do if you weren't trying to re-center
right so that's why it's a little bit
you know
it's a little bit squeaky now that all
that said may i may just have done it
wrong cuz like i said it's always wrong
we'll know pretty quickly because things
will not
work
uh but that's my first guess right
uh okay so
um
[Music]
it looks like world position is not
known at the time that the diagram
system is included or something like
that
i
which is true
right you can see it here
so
yeah
the one thing i would say is this
probably doesn't need to be out here
anyway
so we could also just do this
all right and that would probably be
fine
all right so we do need the diagrams cpp
file though
uh that does need to be moved down below
like
the world
uh
code because otherwise wouldn't be able
to do any of that i don't
know
maybe there isn't one of those
let me see maybe i'm wrong about that
maybe i don't have to do that
yeah okay so i guess i don't have to do
that there just isn't an art an article
for those we'll take a look at that in a
second
um
let's take a look at subtract
so we will need the world here right
which i guess makes sense because it
needs the dimensions of things
so the only thing we don't have here is
an r equals
uh
we have r is we have r in the same chunk
which i suppose is good enough in this
situation maybe but it's not really what
i want
um
so it's weird that we don't have one
that checks for exact
equivalence
um
so i suppose that's okay it's not
it's not maybe quite right um
so so i don't
i don't love that but
i guess that's just how it is sometimes
okay so diagram set origin needs to take
the worlds
um but other than that
it's fine
uh
and
wow all right so that wasn't very good
oh uh right so
that is just because
uh these
are
some of them use these as a radius right
so we do have a slightly different thing
that happens here
uh this
fear
uses that one as radius
not sure if there are any other
[Music]
gotchas there
um so let's try that again
so yeah like like see i am again wrong
so i wonder why my math was wrong on
that
probably because i didn't think it
through quite right uh about what was
actually like the math probably wasn't
wrong but the
the setup for the equation was wrong
right
so why was this math
wrong
first let's make sure that actually was
math wrong because flipping the sign of
this would if i was just wrong about the
setup would produce the correct result
then
but it may be that this is wrong too so
maybe that i'm just doing something
completely wrong period in which case
the math was the least of our concerns
um
still seems wrong
like i don't know what that's supposedly
doing
okay so maybe this is just wrong in
another way and we don't have to worry
about the math part of it just yet
all right
so
i'm not sure why this would be incorrect
because it looks roughly like what we
want right if we have origins that move
we just need to update ourselves for
those origins by looping over the
diagrams that have already been
included in the system
uh for previous frames basically
and change
what they're relative to so that they're
now relative to the new center
right
that seems relatively uncontroversial to
me
um i i don't understand why that
wouldn't work
it's possible that we're producing the
wrong offset here
but
i can't immediately see what else we
would be doing
one of the two ways of having that go
should have produced the right result
and then we could have worked through
the math of like why which one is
correct or not correct
but since neither one does it means that
something's wrong structurally
right like this is just wrong
in general
uh and i'm not sure how that result came
about
um
so
hmm yeah i'm not sure why that that
seems like it should have been pretty
straightforward but i guess it wasn't
so
it shows you what i know
not much
so the top of each frame we set the
origin to the simulation center that is
going to be used to produce the stuff
and that's where everyone will do their
relative
submissions from here on
so it seems like that should be
relatively straightforward
the simulation center itself doesn't
really move
uh other than in hops right like it
it moves like clunk clunk clunk so it
only happens every so often
and so most of the time
this is going to be zero and then on
certain frames when it changes it's
going to be something non-zero when the
origin changes
uh and then it you know it does this
thing
the chunk part i don't know if maybe
that part is wrong which seems like it
could sort of be
i don't know
subtracting the new center from the old
center
is almost certainly correct i'm pretty
sure our math was right
so i'm pretty sure that this is actually
what we want
um and it did a very uh
counter-intuitive thing
so let me look at what it looked like
again when we did the thing that i
thought was correct because i want to
understand that a little bit better
you can see that it like hops it like
moved the thing back here
somehow
and i do not know how
right like that
that is very confusing
um
the simulation center went
forward by
not really even that amount like that
doesn't seem
maybe that was a simulation center
delta
i mean maybe it was
because it would have been like the
simulation center would have been like
something like here
and then the simulation center would
have been like something like here
probably right it's hard to say
uh
but like if you look
you know it's i don't know
somewhere like there
so i mean i guess i could believe that
that was the the amount
and so if you look at what's happening
that
move
it it offset it by an amount
it's almost as if it's still using the
same offset from what it was before
but having done the offset for this it's
almost like it didn't update the new
center but is offsetting it properly i
suppose maybe that would be what happens
if you offset by twice the amount that
you thought you should offset by or
something but i don't know how we would
produce that because we don't multiply
any of these things
in that way if we ran this twice
it should not
do it twice because this would stop that
from happening
right so once you get the old origin set
you won't do it again
so how did that happen
how
the question is how
um so i guess the thing about simulation
center
is
you know
in theory anyway
i think
uh
in theory the simulation center
i should also check all these these p
values which is what i'm doing right now
but i believe they're all yeah all these
p values are correct
uh
so i don't get it i do not understand
why this would be causing a problem it's
very strange so i suppose what i'll do
is i'll step through and i'll look
through i'll look at to make sure these
change when i think they change
um
we'll start there
just in case i'm like totally wrong
about that
uh which is easy to do when you only
program on something every once in a
very
short a very long time right
it's pretty easy to
to make that be wrong um
so like yeah if we go
let me just go into the diagram code i
guess
and just set a breakpoint
on
when this happens
so
in here like
hmm okay
so we should see it hit this breakpoint
one time
uh which is at startup right when it
first goes to render the world's
presumably it would hit that
okay so the fact that it doesn't hit
that break point unless remedy just
isn't setting the breakpoint properly or
something
that seems really weird right because
what are the chances that the
last origin p
was all was
already
the the cleared to zero last origin p
was already the origin p is it just
because we do happen to start literally
at zero that would be
cool
but weird
so let me just check the first time we
call in here
um
and see what those values are because
now i'm just like what
so that's what we would expect right
it's uninitialized ver okay
so i guess this is okay
uh it really is the r equals thing when
i was like this doesn't look right it's
not right so we have to do the r equals
thing okay
i mean good to know
so the other thing we could do here is
say look if these two things don't
produce
an exact value we could do this
you know what i'm saying
uh so like if if they're not
correct
so that was it
um i think that was the entirety of
that completely explained what we were
seeing
so we can move on to
seeing if there are other problems with
it
okay
let's try again
and now we're good
perfect
so i think that was worth doing didn't
take very long and would take a lot less
time if i had actually had an r equals
call it would have called it that it
would have worked
uh but hey doesn't matter
anyway uh so as you can see we're still
doing the thing in the collision routine
where if it hits that case it stops
recording the diagrams which is what we
want so that we can step through them
and see how we got into that case and as
you can see now you can see what i'm
talking about there's just too much like
this is just a record of everything that
happened over several frames
it's way too much to be able to see
what's going on so even though all of
the information we need to understand
the bug better is in this diagram we
can't make meaningful sense of it
because there's just so much garbage we
can't see it
so that's why i said we just now need to
make this thing um
actually work where i can turn on like
single stepping
and then have like some controls here
that let me like like scrub
right so i can just say like like move
right and then move
and then move or whatever
right
um so i just need to add something like
that which actually shouldn't be that
hard to do it's just a little bit of
busy work
um and what you can see is we've already
set up like the part of the code that
we haven't actually been using
but it's this whole begin end part we
already set up diagrams to do this they
already have begin and end like around
relevant sections
so if you look at like the code in
question like move entity
it already has
like an underscore begin
oops
so
we should be able because there's a
begin on each stack walk
and in the refine and over the entire
thing
we should be able to make something that
just like hops along those begins and
ends
like without
uh
without much trouble so like we don't
really need to do any additional work to
like figure out
what we should be viewing for single
stepping because we already like we we
knew when we started this that we wanted
something like that
so it shouldn't be particularly
difficult for us to actually make that
happen now
right
uh i also there's a couple things i'm
not entirely sure about
like we had some tech stuff in here and
i don't know if we ever actually
yeah so i guess we kind of did
so we haven't there's a couple other
things we haven't done like like do we
want to like put the text up there and
it's like that we may not need to do
that we may need to i don't know
but anyway so if we ins just have like
the diagram and begin and end stuff what
we can do here is probably just
make it so that we keep some kind of a
counter so we have a like you know
diagram
index
or something like this
and it's a little bit more complicated
because we kind of need like a stack
for it
where
we will as we do begins
we have to track like which one we're on
at each level
because these things can be nested
and we may want to be able to like drill
down
or up
or whatever
um
and that just seems like the most
straightforward way to do it
so we'd have something you know like
this
or
whatever and when we go through here
whenever we do a diagram begin we would
increment the diagram
depth right
and whenever we do a diagram and we'd
decrement it you know
and
when we hit a begin we would
increase the diagram index
at the depth that we're currently at
right
so if if we're at nothing
and we hit a begin we increment the
diagram index for the zeroth depth but
then we
update the depth plus
one so that now any begins
if we hit a begin
it's like a sub diagram right it's at a
lower depth
or whatever
we know that we can't
do anything about it if the diagram
depth is
not you know is is outside of what we
track so we're sort of pre saying like
look you know i don't know how deep
these things go but not very deep
right like you can't just stack diagrams
inside diagrams entire diagrams
infinitely because a i don't even know
what good that would do anyone you know
one or two levels deep is going to be
the most that you could ever really use
effectively because otherwise would take
you so long to navigate right
um
but then once we're sort of in that mode
we should be able to use like the arrow
keys or something to like navigate
through these so then what we need is
some idea of like what the match level
is
right
so we need something that's like
you know
um
in the diagram group itself
which is this thing
uh we we need some idea of like what
this
you know
what this thing is going to do so you
know maybe i don't know
um
maybe we like have an actual thing
that's like oh you know there's there's
like
handmade diagram max depth
maybe we just make this thing
to be honest i think 64 it's just stupid
like it would just be unwieldy to use so
we're not gonna do that
so maybe we do something like this uh
and
we have like an at diagram
and then we have a like
a diagram filter depth or something
uh
i'll go like this
does that make more sense
and then what we do here is we just say
well when we're drawing these things
uh every time we hit like a beginner and
end like we're gonna have a thing that's
like a
past filter something
and every time through here we're going
to set like past filter equal to
something
and
when we
go to do drawing
like in any of these things
uh
we will set that up
and we'll just won't enter this case if
it's not there
something like that
now because i want this code i don't
really care how fast this code is
running
i i have no reason to believe it will be
particularly slow
so i'm just gonna make a little easier
on myself
and i'm going to put
these cases at the top
uh so that they are processed
prior to the switch
statement um
although now that i think about that we
still want the diagram color thickness
and text part to probably still have
been
to be honest though no we really don't i
mean
i do think those probably should have
been reset as part of this
this should have like reset those anyway
uh
i'm not sure how we want to deal with
that going forward all right so maybe i
take it back
maybe we'll leave this in there it's a
little annoying but i guess i'll leave
it in here so let's suppose that we
actually have
um
just a thing that's like should draw
and i go in here and i just
like nuke these
cases
so we just don't
draw stuff
in that case
and like there's a phantom one here but
you know we never implemented that
so
all right and so whenever we hit diagram
begin and we do one of these things we
need to do a computation to determine
whether or not
we're going to pass the filter or not
um and whenever we do like you know we
do the begins and the ends or whatever
we need to update this past filter
value
to
come from something that we compute
so we do stuff like look if we can look
up in here then whatever like should
draw
is just going to be equal to whatever
the old
uh assuming we can look it up
uh is just gonna be whatever the old one
was
and the same would be true here where
like whatever we determine the like
should we draw this thing or not
is going to come from here as well
so
uh in a sense like
that always happens
but we also like update the past filter
thing
and i think
i could be very wrong about this but i
think this is actually pretty simple
so like this is just
the the past filter for this is just
whatever the current state was so we
assume that children are always drawn if
they should be drawn if the parent
should have been drawn
but then if
like the filter depth
uh is
like if where we're at if the diagram
depth
that we're currently at
is like less than
the diagram filter depth
so like if they were both zero
we don't do the test
if diagram filter depth is like one and
we're at diagram depth zero
then at that point
we would be filtering so we would check
to see
whether we would filter on this
index
so the diagram index at that diagram
depth
um
would have to be equal to hours
right
i believe
i guess technically this is
supposed to be after because if it was
zero it would be this way so
so
uh
if these are equal then
or i should say if they're not equal
would turn it off
something like that
i want to say that's just sort of
what it is
i'm not sure it needs to be
really any more
complicated than that
all right so we'll go back over that
again in a second but i think that's
roughly what we want
so now we just need some way of actually
navigating through these things i think
we could already start debugging this a
little bit because
uh we can now go like make sure this
code works for no filtering right
so it should be that if with no
filtering it would work
uh
i suppose i need to start should draw at
true
though
um
which i think is what we want
because otherwise things will never be
drawn because the the root has to start
at true
um
so
i think that's correct in that it's like
you know it draws the thing
uh and so now we just need a way of
setting it uh
so that we can set the
that's
i don't know what that is
this is some kind of four code or flurry
thing look at that
if you would like purple things to be
purple
you can click on them
with the right mouse button
i do not know what that does like what
is that
i i have no idea what that's even meant
to do
i feel like ryan needs to tell us what
that is supposed to do
something it's definitely doing
something non-trivial like it's it's
doing like a rectangular selection of
empty space
like
i have no idea what that does
anyway
so if we look at the codes where we've
got
you know
single stepping and whatever
uh
i guess we can do something where we say
is single stepping we don't even really
care
i guess um
about single stepping anymore
like we don't
need that
at all
i don't think we could just have a reset
button
um
okay so that's for we don't yeah so we
don't really need
we don't really need that for this but
we'll leave it on there so so this is a
different thing
and that's fine
and we'll leave that in there
but i'll then do like
a thing down here where we do
you know label f
and we'll say like
a
diagram
uh filter
something like that right
and then in here i can just put in
[Music]
a
i guess i don't know
if editable
px is the right thing it might
be
i mean probably not but
maybe it is
i mean my guess is it sort of is
um because like we can set the
yeah we could just have two sliders that
are like
what depth do you want to be at
i mean it's probably the only you really
you probably only really want a slider
for the second one so maybe you want
like a button
excuse me
for the first two or something
uh that are like
we want one for stepping like forwards
and backward or up and down the
hierarchy so like
up and down
and those would just be like
whatever that group was
this stuff here
the diagram filter depth
for
uh like if you go up if the diagonal is
greater than zero then
you know you would
do something like this
so we
we
i don't know why that's in there it's
not even remotely right there we go
so we just have like a value and we we
move it like up and down
depending on which one we want to do
so we can go down to like lower levels
of detail or greater levels of detail
um
i don't know how this thing label f
works is it just like percent
yeah it looks like it
so you know if we just have percent u
percent u
kind of thing so you can see it
um
so we just do like
there's the filter depth and
there's the filter index at that filter
depth
and this really
uh since
i think that's right um this is actually
not quite what we want
so in this case like when we do these
labels
we need to like this part
you
do want to do this
and you want to do it that way
right it's the filter when you do the
depth it's like the depth minus one but
that means that when it's at zero
you would
turn it off
so i think what you really want is this
where if the diagram filter depth
is zero you like print some other thing
that's like
something like that
um
yeah
i don't know how this got to be
something other than layout there
probably bad
uh
auto complete but
so like in theory now we should be able
to control one of the parameters and
then i just need like a slider for the
other one or something
so
uh
this will allow me to like filter
a different level of the hierarchy but i
can't step through a different diagrams
right
um so if you like imagine like okay
we're looking at something like that
um in theory like you can see in fact it
already is sort of working
if i'm filtering out like
that's like
the first diagram on each frame
that's the first sub diagram
on each frame in theory
it doesn't look like it's quite correct
so i think we screwed it up the filter
but that's
what it would be
and then we need like a little slider
here i don't understand why these
oh
because i put it in the wrong place
probably that probably about the label
and then the thing
okay so now if i look and i just say
down
there we go and you can see that it's on
the thing perfect all right so i think
that's all good that seems pretty
straightforward
um so then maybe what i'll do is
put one of these in there
and i don't actually have one of these
for integers it doesn't look like
but i could use float for it anyway
um
and then just map the float
map the float to
a valiant right
so like if i wanted to
um
i can do something like this
and when we look at the depth here i
could just do something like okay look
if you just convert this to a u32 then
then that's what it is
um and then we can just have like a
standard slider
i guess
that's like
whichever one of these
we're on
and we don't
really have a maximum here so i don't
know
[Music]
i guess it would just be from zero to
some very large number
right
so then we just have to make the
filtering work but i think that's
roughly it so like you know you get
stuck
or something
um you can
what what is this complaining oh it
doesn't like
it doesn't like something about the way
i called this function
i must have made a mistake
uh so here it doesn't like this
oh i see why
that slider isn't valid
if we are below the the you know
if if we are below the depth
so if we now go down to one of these you
know in theory we can now change like
which one of these we're looking at i
don't know what oh because this is a
float
still
so at uh at this point now we just need
to make sure the filter is working
properly but i believe now we're like
setting the values in this thing
so
you know if we
if we step down
i'm just gonna do some
random stuff here
all right
so that's
a stuck diagram
so now we should be able to make it so
that as this thing rolls we like draw
different stuff and it sort of is doing
something but it's like the filter's not
quite right you see what i'm saying like
it doesn't advance properly or something
so we just need to go debug this code
make sure that we're passing in
something reasonable here
but other than that
i think that's all we really need
all right so let's take a look at what
happens here so on the first
we always need to look to make sure that
the diagram depth is within bounds
and that's fine
uh the depth just goes up and down as it
should
that all seems fine um
when we look at the diagram depth we say
okay
whether or not we pass the filter is
just whatever the previous value of
should draw is
which starts out at true so the first
time down we would just set it to true
for sure
we then look at the diagram depth and
see if it's less than the diagonal
filter so let's say we set this to one
so this is zero the first time through
we would say is the index that we're
currently on
which is
also zero
um if that's not equal to whatever the
filter should be
then we set the past filter value to
false
okay so this is wrong
should be that
although i guess it doesn't matter
because we haven't done this yet
um
otherwise we just leave it what it
should be
i suppose this actually is is
unnecessarily verbose so
really you could just do this
right
i think that's how we actually
oh we actually need there
so anyway uh first time through right we
would set the diagram index to zero
uh
or rather the diagram just would be
equal to zero so if the diagram filter
index is something other than that it
shouldn't draw so it should draw to
false
it will remember that
for its children
right
uh if it pops back up
but that's all the past filter thing is
doing
so
we increment the diagram depth and then
you know let's just ignore anything that
happens down there we get into some
other begins or whatever so we do
another begin but in siri like when we
hit the diagram for that one it would
pop back up and just look at whatever
the past filter value was that it was
setting
uh and it will reset should draw to
whatever that should have been right
whatever it was before we went into this
thing
so i suppose the problem here is that
this should actually be set prior
meaning
that
should be set before we do anything else
with it because should draw is the value
we actually are using and the past
filter thing is what we'll restore it to
okay so that was definitely wrong
i don't know that that's enough wrong
so we probably still aren't quite right
but let's just see what the behavior is
now
for the next
round through
okay so there's some gunk
uh let's suppose we go down
a level
two levels
um
okay so now we're sort of working a
little bit better right you can see us
drawing the stuff
right
uh at level two if we went down one more
you can see us testing the spheres
right so that's kind of nice
this goes up way too quickly
um which is a bummer
so like maybe we do need something a
little bit different there but yeah like
our slider code is kind of crap right
um
so i think this is all we really need i
think we're good now that seems to be
working it was just the restoring of the
stack was wrong
this is kind of garbage uh the editable
px code
we need like a step
value in here you can see
uh it's it's this nonsense
the dx value
um
[Music]
so what we might want to do is something
more like this
like if you didn't specify dx then it
will do that
but otherwise it won't
that way like for things like this one
we can do like oh you know what's the
delta x value
uh when you move like i don't know maybe
it's like 10 pixels per
or some crap like that
this is not a good ui obviously right
it's just a debug ui so we don't really
care as long as we can use it it's fine
so then when we do it here
like that's
better right because i can get like
fairly precise
now which is what i want
um
and so
when it gets stuck as like so
um
now if i go down to one of these
i should be able to like
yeah
i don't know why that is happening
so if i go past the total number
that is somehow
relevant i'm not sure why
so i think we still have a bug like like
this doesn't make sense at filter level
one
it looks like we still have a bug in
there like that
that's not right it shouldn't be like
all of those things are not
on diagram level one right
so like each one of those should have
been stepping through there
so there's still some kind of a like not
quite right thing in the stack
processing as i originally surmised but
then talked myself out of
uh so we're not quite right so we save
in past filter here what we should what
we were doing
so that we can restore it when we come
back
right which is all this that's all this
code does it all
it's not very interesting
um
this seems pretty straightforward
otherwise i'm not sure why we're getting
a problem with stepping through
we look to see whether or not the
diagram depth
is
less than the diagram filter depth like
that is just
keeping us that's so that we don't have
to
like
that we won't only just pick one child
if we can draw like all the children of
something if we want to
so that seems fine like i don't see why
that would cause this problem
and the diagram filter index also looks
fine so so hmm
so one thing i would like to do
let's assert the diagram depth of zero
at the end because one thing that we
don't really address here is what if
there are unbalanced like what if our
code that syncs is wrong
yeah
so it could be that actually just the
code that we're actually calling that's
like calling this is wrong
meaning the places in the code where we
have a diagram begin don't match
and that would do it right
so let's just double check to make sure
that that is a thing
because it might not be a thing
and then we would have a problem
so here's the thing where we've got a
diagram begin and there's the diagram
end and that's fine
here's the thing where we've got to
begin for move entity so that means
there has to be one like all the way
down at the bottom and there is
right
um
here's one inside the
the walk here and it's got an end as
well
so they look
balanced though
right
those all look pretty balanced to me
so
[Music]
yeah i'm not sure what happened there
seems like that should be pretty
straightforward so let's take a look at
what's going on in there
because that maybe that would give us
some insight into what the bug is in
this particular routine
i think we're almost done with what we
needed for stepping through and seeing
what happened right
and then we can
you know add the code that we need
so what is the value because we'll know
whether it's an underflow or an overflow
which would be good
so it's like there's just one unclosed
one of these apparently apparently right
um
and i guess we don't know which one it
is but we actually could put in
something pretty you know
it would be pretty simple for us to
figure out
like
where this ended i guess
uh but so we know that like we've got
just one open
that didn't get closed
right
one begin
that didn't end
because the depth is one if we had an an
additional end
the diagram death would have been
like you know 42 you know 4.2 billion or
whatever it would have been
that
right
4.3 billion
uh
so we know that we've got an open that
doesn't get closed somehow but i'm not
sure how that's possible given what
we're actually doing since we just
looked and saw that that really wasn't
the case
maybe what's happening is we're breaking
out
of that loop
yeah yeah yeah so it's just that right
there right
um so i don't know how we want to deal
with that there's a couple different
ways one is we can use like a
constructor destructor pair
to like force
this to be done i tend not to like those
kind of things
very much
right
um and the reason that i don't really
love those kind of things is they create
kind of like hidden code that's hard to
understand
like you had to just know that like okay
there was like a thing that would
automatically like clean up the diagram
end code when we broke out of the loop
because it's got a destructor that you
can't see
so i'm not sure that's the best idea
because
you know
uh it seems like we could pretty easily
just allow this code to finish
instead
and it wouldn't really
be
a huge deal
um
so let me think about how i want that to
work but i don't know that i'm i'd be
disinclined to like wrap it in the thing
i don't love that idea so i think i
might just not do that
um
excuse me
so effectively what we're doing here is
we're checking to see whether this cell
is already in the target cell
and if it is
we just stop looking
that's all this is it's like an early
out right
so the first thing to note here is it's
not really
um
it's not really even yeah
it's not really even something that
it's not even really something that we
want to have happen because when it
breaks out of here it won't even draw
this diagram so what was the point
um of some of this stuff we would never
see the last box either if we did want
to like re-enable this particular case
to run so you can see why i'm not
thrilled about this
so
maybe
what i do
is i just say look there's going to be a
like
um
like a found best in here
right
and maybe what we do is we just say like
okay found best equals true in this case
that way we can still run as much of
this as we want
we can also say if found best
here
so we don't have to do this but that way
that way we exit the loop at a
controlled point which i think is just
more important to me at this point
in the
in the thing
right
so i would prefer that
to the alternative
um but you know you could do it either
way if you did we we have done things
before where we did like a constructor
destructor pair
to mark begins and ends of loops
so you know if that's something you want
to do i'm not going to get mad
but
in this particular case i didn't like
that
uh i
i didn't really like that solution so
yeah i'm less inclined all right so back
to what we were trying to debug before
well that's interesting
there is something that happens in that
case in that particular case
um oops i don't know how that got there
um
there are no other breakout or breakout
loops
in here
so we have one other bug
right
like we have a bug of a different kind
because
i don't i don't recall seeing any other
way
that you could break out of anything
without completing your diagram maybe
i'm maybe i'm wrong maybe i'm missing
something
but at that point you look at what's
happening in here there's there's no
real way to jump out of this anymore
and the rest of the things aren't loops
so i don't know
i don't know how we would
get that result so that's still
troubling right
let's see if we can make it happen in
debug mode so we can see what kind of a
of a beginning pairing we have
we should turn off lighting one of these
days or just fix it so that it's not so
slow
because debug mode actually runs
totally fine
in a lot of cases although i suppose
with collision detecting being
completely unoptimized that we would
have to do as well which is what we're
working on so i suppose we don't really
have that luxury at the end of the day
too bad
so i'm not really doing anything here
i'm just seeing if i can make
um
a uh
you know
make a trigger like make it trigger that
path where the beginning ends don't
balance
um
while in debug mode so i can inspect
easier
not looking good
in release mode it's pretty easy to
trigger if only we could ever step
through anything
you know imagine a world where like
someone made a debugger where you could
actually step through release mode code
and inspect anything ever
how much easier this would all be but of
course you can't
because the debug information
that they create is so bad that you
can't ever find it out
[Music]
r15d
what the heck was diagram depth
it's a u32
all right
same problem
so it feels like breaking out was there
another break statement or something
that i missed
i don't think so
so again not really sure how that is
managing to happen
there isn't like a return
you know in here
um
so that's a puzzler
i don't know how it's managing to do
that i do not know
and with completely unoptimized it may
be very difficult for me
to actually like step through and see
how it's able to generate that result
you know it could be this
in fact that is what it is i suppose i
do have to do that
which is to say that once you do set
capture it won't record anymore so the
diagram end
won't work
i suppose we could as well not really
so that's
that's all that was
i guess that one's not that hard to find
so
it's okay
question remains though why is our
filter broken it could be that our
filter
isn't really that broken but i think it
still is so now we just need to go
fix this part and
so at least now that works properly
right
so now we can step through the moves
that occurred
right pretty easily
and that's nice so we can look and see
like okay so we know that like
this one right here
is the one where we had the issue
so the one right before it
if we look let me go down one level
well that doesn't work very well does it
so it looks like we're able to step on
the top level but when we go down to the
next level down i can't really step
through what all of these things are
right but i'm not sure why so we have a
little bit more work to do here we can
step through
we can step through the top level
so we can see like everything that
happens leading up to it but we just
can't get down one level from there but
i thought we were supposed to because we
definitely have
one more level of information don't we
like inside like each time through here
there's a beginning end
right
so each frame we've got one
here
and each
cell of the voxel we've got one here
so we should at least be able to step on
level one and two
but for some reason we can't
so again still a bug in the filtering
code presumably
where for some reason we're not
filtering correctly at the
level below it's like no matter what we
set it to it only shows us the first
step
or something
why would that be
there's got to be something here that's
counter-intuitive
that makes it so that we can't
when we descend twice
so when this code path
runs twice instead of once right
so you hit the first begin it's a frame
you do a diagram index increment
uh
and
yes
i do know what the problem is
when you do a diagram index increment
you also have to clear whatever is at
the depth
that you're going to move into
because otherwise it wouldn't work so
basically when you go to do this
right
um you need to do
[Music]
every time you end the diagram the
diagram index at that depth has to get
set
back to zero
right
because otherwise it'll just keep going
up forever and you'll never yeah so on
the first one we probably could have
done it but then by the time you
increment the top guy to a certain
number you've incremented the lower
indices too far
and they don't get reset right
so now
if i do like
this
or whatever
go back to the one i was on
i believe that's the one i wanted to see
second to last one i go down one level i
should now yeah i should be able to like
just step through all of these and see
what the heck it was
right
so now we can watch the collision solver
like work over time
we can start at zero
so you know this is where
it started on this frame
it looked through a bunch of these and
it found where it wanted to place the
thing eventually you know whichever one
that was
we'll have to look and see which one it
was we go down oops
we go up
and we go to the next diagram this is
the one where it fails basically
and we look at what we're actually
seeing here
you can see that where it is placed it
finds them all to be read
right
so if
i actually look carefully where that is
right
it's like
this one right here
if i go
up
to the previous frame
it sure doesn't seem to be producing
like you can see that it doesn't think
that those green ones
it never even has one on the front row
there where those green ones are
red
right
hmm
and you can see like it's true about the
shift
so i think that actually is what's
happening
what that suggests to me
so for the simulation centers
um
there is some kind of a like
so
i think what that suggests to me is we
just want these things to be on even
movement levels so you know
the unembed code would solve this
problem but i don't think we want to
have this problem in the first place
so like when we look at the motion
displacement size i think what we want
to do is make that be
you know the trunk dimension for the
world should be related to that
you know what i mean
and so when we're like setting the chunk
dim in meters
uh
you know
this stuff right
the fundamental unit should be a
multiple
like
what we really want to do is make these
things be like well defined relative to
each other
so the motion displacement size and the
fundamental unit are like not
similar values to each other
and i think that is
where we're getting this problem then
as a result
if this were 1.5
we wouldn't have a problem
if it were one
point
um
so 0.125 times
you know
uh
12 or 11.
so 1.375
would be fine
right that would work
so a slightly different dimension for
everything
would presumably work okay
although as i say that you can see that
it actually didn't
right
but i believe that if the chunk if the
actual way that things move although i
guess so you know what i just realized
this may be pointless
we may not always move
uh a even chunk amount for simulation
centers
in fact we know that didn't happen
because when we looked at the simulation
centers they had like garbage in the xyz
so like
yeah simulation centers not moving by a
constant amount each time is definitely
an issue
so like
i don't know what we want to do about
that i do think we want to make sure
that this is
uh
fixed
i don't think we want to allow that to
happen
where the voxel slides relative to
things
but i'm not sure what the best way to
solve that would be
thinking it through i want to go look
and see how we're actually doing that um
like how does this thing decide
those
values
um
because i don't know
like how does it do
the simulation center
in the first place because i don't know
you can see here it's like oh like
map into chunk space get the simulation
center for this room
you know
i assume that's like the only real place
that simulation center is set
um
besides there besides the initial
setting right
so really our problem here is just the
simulation center itself is never
rounded to the actual fundamental values
which it should be
so that's i think
all we would need
right
so like if you imagined
something like this
this simulation center
is like
hey here's the here's the offset
right
um it's going to do a map in a trunk
space of this if you then took the
simulation center here and you just like
zeroed the xyz
you know what i mean
um
or you rounded the simulation center
i gotta think about this a little
but just like for numerical accuracy
purposes i think you really want to do
that the i mean there's another way you
could do it which is just to offset the
thing
and maybe that's just fine
but it seems like you would like this to
be correct
so you'd like the simulation center to
always be snapped to a fundamental unit
boundary
right
um
and i guess
when i think about it
this is actually fine
because you don't really care what this
fundamental unit is really
um you only care that the simulation
center is always snapped to the motion
unit
right
so really that would be fine
as long as it's always snapped to 0.125
so in other words this
thing here
if you just always insisted
uh
like literally you just did this
right
where the simulation center
is always set
to
like some kind of thing where you
you
do the same kind of like re-centering as
you were doing before
in theory that would always put you
uh
add a value truncated that now
um
[Music]
it assumes you started there
so that may not quite be right
um
but basically if you just do that one
offset so that now you're always aligned
to that voxel
now i would argue you won't have that
particular bug
right
that particular bug we may have other
ones
and of course we didn't
not
100 conclusive but
but we didn't
so i think that's a good start but you
know i don't know looks like we have a
one here that's a an issue though right
it's like a detected one here
and that has nothing to do with it
because that's not a camera move
right the camera doesn't move
on that boundary
so you look here we can say hey what
what happened there exactly
um
so somehow
it decided it needed to stop
this one but i don't know why
all right this is the one it actually
needs to stop sorry
so somehow it decided this one was
colliding
but what was it colliding with
there's nothing there
that just seems straight up buggy right
like there's nothing there for it to
collide with in the first place
um all of those are
non-colliding
so it just like returned collision for
all of those but there's nothing there
right
so that just looks like straight up
buggy code for the collider so that's a
good thing to debug as well
so i think this might actually be
something i want to do
um
so we kind of want like a call
that's like a line to
movement grid a line to movement
voxel or something right
where
this
will happen
um
like something like this
and
we probably need seldom in here because
we use it again right so this this kind
of needs to be
um something that that also exists in
here so
you know there's that
but
to a first approximation
it's this
so this way when we come through here we
can say like well simulation center
equals align
the thing
right
and
it returns a v3
and voxel starting corner
will come from calling it
and then it just needs to be something
exposed to the outside world
so i think that's fine i'm not sure
um
like again it kind of needs to be
something
there's this part here where it's like
setting the simulation center
uh to something
and so that's a little bit troubling
because
you know
we need this to be correct and it's not
going to be
and so what we really want here is for
this to be
ideally we would like this to be set
later
right
so ideally what we would like this to be
is for this to be just like
always set to all zeros or something and
then it moves to the correct location
so this is kind of annoying because it's
hard to reset this properly
i'm also not entirely sure
like this part here right
so i guess that's just gonna work now
that i think about it because it's
already always going to be set to zero
anyway
so i guess that's okay it's not
the best thing in the world but it's
okay
so i think that's okay for now uh maybe
we'll put off to next weekend
debugging the uh we have like a
collision detection problem there right
so in here we had a problem where
we
had the glove in a place where it could
totally move just fine but the collision
detector said like no it couldn't
and there's really not an explanation
for this
uh because
there was
no more for it to go so it doesn't make
sense i mean nowhere nothing to collide
with so it doesn't make a lot of sense
why would we be seeing that um
uh anyway
again
though
uh getting much closer now to solid
um and i like the fact that we now have
really good tracing in there so i can
step through and watch
and see what the heck it's doing
because that's really the only way to
debug these things there's no other way
to do it right
so you can see if you play around with
it for a while you get into these
situations again and here i assume this
is exactly the same bug where it's just
maybe maybe our sphere collision
detector for example is just buggy it's
not very good
um
because again like the other time too it
wasn't even on a case where the camera
moved so it wasn't even something that
could really be
explained away
um
in that context right
uh yeah and i mean that's just floating
in the middle of nowhere like there's no
there's nothing for it to touch
so it looks like our sphere tester like
has some kind of a bad or just some
other aspect of the system right
um
where it's testing these and thinking
they're failing so that's our next
that's next week
but otherwise i think we're good
i think we are now good
right
um so
i like the fact we fixed the camera
thing i like the fact that we're now
around to the box so properly we have a
bug in the sphere collision section or
just the way that it sets the values so
it could be that the collision detector
is returning the correct value
and in fact
you know what we can check that really
easily
when we do
the collide
thing uh
so when we do this collides part we
could just draw that in here right as
well
so in shapes collide uh when we do this
stuff
we know what the result is
uh for colliding and not oh well i guess
we only draw it if it collides
oh okay
so the fact that we saw those fears is
just wrong
so actually
we already know
uh
that it's wrong
it would seem
right
oh
so of course it's hard to get it to
trigger which is what you'd expect you
know if it's some kind of subtle problem
in our collision detector right you
can't just there we go so you kind of
have to wait a little while to get it to
go
but what what it looked like in that
routine to me
um
very you know pretty clearly right
uh is that if we're diagramming and the
result is that we collided then we draw
it but if it's not
colliding
then it never will so in fact this is
like meaningless
right
we never we never actually do that
we only come in here and draw it if
that's the case
so what that would suggest is that when
we look
at you know wherever this thing ended up
right there
uh
the fact that it draws all of these
spheres is just blatantly wrong there
are two that look like they collide the
bottom two
uh but those top ones there's nothing
for them to collide with like there's no
actual
there's nothing for them to touch
right
so that's just like we got a bug in that
which is you know
and what's what's really kind of strange
about that in fact
um is that they're supposed to be a
secondary thing that we draw here right
um
meaning if you look
at this code
you can see that it always draws like
two spheres a sphere in a box
or two boxes
now we know it won't be two boxes
because one of them's a sphere
so we know that it will be this
set
furthermore
there shouldn't be any spheres
um
i don't know if there's any other
spheres in the entire game right now
other than the glove
so we pretty much know it's this these
two cases
and furthermore we know that when we
call this code
we always pass
the mover and then the test
so we know the mover which is a is a
sphere
and we know that b is presumably not
so we know that this is the code that
we're running
and there should be a box
right this box b
so
somehow
and we don't know how
there is supposedly a box that we are
colliding with that is here
that's what that oh well no that that
line might not be that i shouldn't say
that we don't actually know what that
line is
um but like
there's the line
so there's a box here
that we're colliding with
and like there is no such box and when
you draw it like because we are drawing
the box
it's not there
like we don't see any box
show up
you know
you know maybe it's like a very tiny
little invisible box
i don't know
so that's
particularly odd
we do record what box we think it is
like this box b
thing here
right
so one thing we might
do
is we might want to
like we might want to
dump the data for whichever diagram
thing we're on in here or something
so that we can see what the actual value
of b is because it's like what is this
box it's like a phantom bug box
right
and we just have no idea we don't know
where this phantom bug box is coming
from
it's some magical mystery box
like the magical mystery tour
that doesn't actually exist there
right
so i don't know
that's going to be a puzzler
that's going to be a puzzler for next
time
we have no idea what it is
and i guess we'll leave it for next time
any questions
but we're not quite sure right like
we're now quite sure what's going on but
like something that we can't see like
the size of zero or infinite or
something right
so
yeah it could be like very large it
could be like a huge box
that's so big you can't see it
that only existed on that one frame for
some reason
i mean it can't be the hero's head i
don't think because we disabled that
collision box
right
so
this
would that would do it
but it ain't there right um
so
that's why we're not considering that
possibility
you cannot move diagonally in this game
no
can only move
in the cardinal directions
yeah we definitely can write that it's
just we uh we need some we just need to
add in our debug display something to do
that
which is what i was suggesting we do
last time so we can see what the value
is is that thing the other thing that we
probably want to do is like be able to
tag the entity or something
like
if this entity when we do collides at p
and we loop over the entities if we had
a thing that basically said like oh
pass a like like each entity gets tagged
with like which generator function
generated it
then we can also print out like what
type of entity it was
right like who generated this entity
you know
um and that would help us
to determine like what kind of a thing
it collided with as well
but yeah i have no idea where that
box is coming with
all right
yeah refinement is still running
it could be
that uh the tunneling was happening
because of the camera movement thing too
right
which we now fixed
yeah the entity cache system is still in
this is all going through the end of the
cache system
um
i don't think the entity cache system
could explain this though because we're
drawing what we think so let's suppose
there was a phantom entity on that frame
that the cache system erroneously said
was there
we should still have seen it drawn
right so the fact that we don't see
the thing that it's supposed to collide
with suggests that it's more of like a
garbage value problem
because somehow there was something for
it to collide with that we don't then
draw which doesn't make a whole lot of
sense
right
um
no i don't think the mystery box pushed
into the wall i think that was probably
the camera changing when you hop across
the threshold it would change
be embedded
and then be able to go go through it
because of the tunneling right
that's what i think
that's that'd be my guess anyway
so i don't think this this particular
part has anything to do with the camera
moving the reason i say that is it
seemed like i was able to get it to
happen without being at a camera
threshold at all
now maybe that's false
but i thought that's what was able to
happen
because i thought we were able to do it
just in this room
without
the hero moving out of the room i
thought
um
i could be wrong about that
but i mean look right like we never
changed the camera and and it did it so
it seems like it's just one of these
things that like is some kind of garbage
value problem where we're just like
doing something totally wrong like you
know
misattributing the location of something
but like you know we weren't moving the
camera and it just recorded collisions
for all four of those points even though
none of those points are colliding right
so like somehow just stationarily you
get in a situation where it suddenly
thinks a bunch of things glide and they
definitely don't
now it could just be like this routine
is just buggy like it could be that like
this math is wrong in a subtle way or
something
right
so it's not
necessarily the case that's coming up
but again this is the part that really
is confusing me
unless it actually is drawing this thing
somewhere
which maybe it is
i mean i guess we didn't actually try to
determine that there's
nowhere else
for it to do this but
um but you saw what what i mean right
like we're not even moving
uh the
the game camera is staying stationary
this entire time
uh and we were able to get it to happen
so i don't think it's required
it does seem however like i had to move
out of where i was though slightly
like i'm not able to get it to happen
just in here but when i moved up here
i was able to get it to happen
of course that may just be a random luck
again this doesn't trigger very often
right it seems to take thousands of
frames to get it to happen
so it's kind of one of those
unpredictable bugs where you're like i
can't really make generalizations about
when it doesn't doesn't happen because
it's so rare that like who knows what
the you know
what the actual thing that precipitated
the bug was
um
but you definitely saw it happen we just
don't know how to make it happen more
reliably than that unfortunately
no post stream i really only tr i try to
take only questions that are on topic
pre-stream you can ask general questions
because we haven't started yet
not that we always really adhere to that
rule but we should
well this is a very hard bug to
reproduce apparently
there we go
um
so you know
you can see it light up boxes as they
get hit right you see them lighting up
the boxes that it hits
and then
oh
my led strip just
got wanked
that was bad i know what happened there
um
so you can see here like when we hit
this case
uh
who is the box that is getting hit like
nothing in the entire world
seems to be highlighted white
right there's it's just not there
so it's not like a very large box it's
not an offs like some random entity over
here is getting hit
like there's nothing keyed
the entire time nothing is keyed
right
so i don't
know what this could be colliding with
because it doesn't actually show
now just to underscore this point
if you imagine like here right
what you can see is every time you hit a
collider you see like the wall light up
that's the thing it hit
right so you can see
that
every time you look at one of those
sphere hits it it shows you and
furthermore it shows you the direction
it's in right so like that little thing
there is like oh it's over here right
the little white line
so like that's what i'm talking about
when i say we've got a bug is that like
it's pretty clear this is a nonsense
collision so the result that we're
getting when we think this thing has
collided it thinks it's colliding with
something
but it's not even ju it's not even a bug
in this math
it's a bug in the input to the function
somehow because the thing that we
suppose the cloud with does not exist
right
it does not exist
and so we don't know
and it's pointing
right it's pointing somewhere
they're pointing to different things
even like look at that
like
it says we collided with two things one
there and one there
right but we didn't
like we definitely didn't
the line going off to the left is where
the move was supposed to be going
towards i think
right
so that's like oh you know we were going
we were trying to go this direction on
this frame it wanted to head over this
direction to here
is all that is
i believe
um
don't quote me on that but i believe
that's what's happening
uh the direction vectors aren't
normalized
it's literally just a line to the center
of the other thing so like it thinks the
thing we collided with it thinks is
centered there
and centered is the wrong um term here i
guess
you know uh there's another possibility
which is that the diagramming system is
broken
uh like maybe this is a valid box and
it's drawing it wrong
in some cases or something i mean i
don't know exactly why that would be but
like
you know it's not entirely out of the
question
there is one thing that's a little weird
so let's think about this for a second
so let's take a case where something is
colliding and it draws
it correctly
like there or something
um
it's true that the get center function
like something is weird
right because
that
that is the center of the sphere
it is the closest point on the box
okay that is what it's doing
never mind
um so that is what it was supposed to do
that's fine
um so yeah so like we don't know whether
it's a box or a sphere intersection i
guess
um which maybe we should draw so we can
see it
um but yeah like if you look there it's
like oh yeah what's the closest point on
the box quote-unquote
and it's like there
like okay so it's the closest point on
the box is there for what box there's no
box at all that could possibly have that
be the closest point
right
so not only is it not drawing this box
supposed box
so we don't know what the heck the box
input is
but it also yeah doesn't have that that
property
now it's possible that we created like a
phantom box that's inverted
and a phantom box that's inverted
maybe would
like suppose we pass it we come in here
um
and and we look at like a do we have a
house volume for other things i don't no
i don't think we do but we if we look we
could see in um like the rectangle
code
um
which i guess is in here i don't
actually know
so
it's called has area here i guess but we
could so we could check to see if this
thing has area
right
um
so we could do something like oh if we
collided
and we go in here and we say like oh we
collided with a rect with a box
right
so
we're in one of these two cases and we
just say like look let's just assert
that it has area
um so in this case it's a that is the
box and in their case it was b
we could just see like is this some
weird like inverted box but even that
should draw
so i don't think that would be the case
but i don't know
evidently not
so so this might have something to do
with it right this might have something
to do with it what
oh those are little tiny
pictures of step into interesting
um
so let's just see
who these people are who don't have any
area
um
so like here's a supposed box
right um
yeah so so there are things that like i
guess are going into the collision
section collision detection system
that have no area
that's disturbing
that's uh
that's kind of disturbing so wait a
minute
are we just like setting people who have
no collision volume are we saying that
they
does this just not filter on something
that should be filtered on that may be
what's going on here maybe we don't have
a bug after i mean we have a book but
so do we not have a like thing for
participating in collision or not
it looks like we don't
so really
yeah i mean this is not very good so so
maybe
actually this is our entire problem
maybe actually
this code
when we do shapes collide
uh
has to have volume
right
so yeah let's just do that so when we do
move entity in here i think we just
yeah i mean like i think we just checked
the corners
uh
only for things like
for ha for that actually have collision
volumes
i guess we just assumed that was
happening but it definitely wasn't
so basically if the if the collision
volume is not valid then we just don't
test the thing we should probably just
have a flag for that but
uh you know we didn't
so
that's
probably just all it was i guess we
actually have entities in there that are
stuck that are set to like not color
just fake things like
you know
markup things we used or whatever
i'm not sure that's actually what it was
but that was definitely a problem
because we don't want to be processing
those anyway
right
um
we don't want to be processing those
anyway
all right so i don't know that we
actually fixed the bug i think next week
we'll have to look for it
in earnest
uh but at least we now know that that
we're not like checking a bunch of
things that don't that weren't supposed
to be colliders which may have caused us
a lot of problems
right
so
all right
all right i'm gonna call it
that all seems good
all right folks so i'm gonna wrap it up
thank you everyone for joining me um if
you do by the way we our kickstarter for
meow the infinite is still going
it's actually halfway through
it did really well this time
so
it's it's doing excellent but it's only
about halfway through if you're
interested in a cool graphic novel
series i would highly highly suggest
checking out
our kickstarter for meow the infinite
book two you can get book one as well
um
i will post the link
into the chat
but i think there'll also there's also
like a link
um
at the bottom of the twitch
page
thing
uh right like the little like
if you're on a platform where twitch
shows the things below the video
whatever you want to call those um
but i will
pack those in there
yeah meows backwards i have to flip the
camera so remember uh people didn't like
that i faced away from the
from the programming
so the camera's flipped when it's tiny
if i if i switch to big
uh if i switch to big
then it's then it's right
you know what i mean
but in tiny and tiny i have to be
flipped so that i point
right
so
um
so anyway
check that out if you get a chance
um it's pretty cool
and
uh i will be back here next week
for looking at if this bug still exists
or not we may have just fixed it but
i would like to go also see maybe like
look at what those entities were like
why we have entities with zero collision
volumes uh are they actually supposed to
be there they probably are they're
probably just like
um placeholder entities for things that
are like not they're like logic things
or whatever so they might be valid but i
don't want to assume they're valid
without actually looking at them and
seeing why we're creating them in the
first make sure they're not just like
garbage that gets generated by the world
generator
incorrectly right
um so i would like to take a look at
that and have a better understanding of
why we had those entities there in the
first place so we'll do that
but
uh i think that's about it
uh thank you for joining me please check
out our kickstarter if you get a chance
and i'll be back here next week
to
take a look at
the that stuff and and maybe start to do
just like a spatial partition for our
collision detector because
um it's still really slow because it
checks all the entities in the world for
every one of those collisions it's
amazing that it runs as fast as it does
it's so weird how fast computers are but
we need to fix that because it should be
basically instant but right now it's
very slow
so we'll do that next week
and i hope to see you back here for that
until then uh i do have more stuff i
guess coming out this week
so there'll be some live streams this
week
there's a cryptocurrency interview
happening if you've been following that
series of cryptocurrency interviews
um that'll be happening i have a very
special thing
happening this thursday that uh i think
will be very interesting i don't know
how it'll go but
uh me and jonas curatzis from that the
person who was the wrote the talus
principle and if you ever played that
game he's a writer
uh that game companies like hire to
write
the stories for their games and and that
sort of stuff right
he and i are doing a babylon 5 season 1
recap because he's like a huge babylon 5
fan and i'd never seen it before and i
just started watching it
um and so every time i finish a season
we're just going to do like a live
stream
where we talk about
uh
the season
right
um
so so this thursday there'll be a live
stream too with me and jonas carazzis
about that uh i apologize if i pronounce
that name on my greek pronunciation
sucks
uh
so for any
greek folks out there listening i
apologize for pronouncing
his
his name wrong i'm sure he rozzies
in greek is pronounced different than
that
but
actually so is jonas probably i don't
know
um i don't know the pronunciations of
these things you can sort of hear it but
like if you're not a native speaker you
can't really hear it right you know um
so you tend to butcher it but anyway
point being you know who i'm talking
about
um he also made a bunch of cool games
like the sible claim everything and
uh
he
uh does like a audio
like a like a a radio play thing too
i don't know
a lot of people out there probably know
who he is already but point being
uh we're going to talk about it
and i'm looking forward to that because
i think that'll be a lot of fun too
so we have a bunch of live stream stuff
happening in the during the week as well
uh but i'll be back here for handmade
hero on sunday as usual
uh the following week
so until then everyone please check out
the kickstarter uh
and
i'll see you on twitter i guess and now
i'll go look
for someone to raid