hello everybody and welcome to handmade
Hero the show we code a complete game
live on stream we have to do some
thinking today about how we want to
proceed with our lighting now that
things are actually working in the
OpenGL driver and we sort of have the
nice luxury of actually being able to
debug our graphics card stuff now and
you can even crash and we can still
stream because we're now on two separate
machines one for streaming and one for
programming and one of the things that
happens not to it's not too infrequent
actually when you have a when you have
to do sort of graphics code that's a
little unusual or does anything that
could be a little squirrely you often
will crash your graphics driver that's
just something that can happen and so
it's pretty nice now not to have to
worry about that we can just crash the
graphics driver all we want and it's no
big deal so when we left off yesterday
we get this running here when we left
off yesterday we were kind of playing
around with the way these things kind of
get set into voxels and as you can see
we sort of we ended up in a position
where we now can play around with the
lighting and try to for how we're gonna
get these sort of voxel based samples in
there we sort of have two separate
problems that we need to address and
also I should mention that I think I I
was kind of sitting around thinking
about some stuff that I like I was
wondering about some depth occlusion
stuff today actually I think last night
as I was falling asleep I was thinking
about it and after this I would also
like to revisit how we're doing 2d
sprite compositing into the 3d world
because I thought of some things that I
didn't try there and I would be
interested in trying them at some point
so I have to remember to do that just
put a little mental to do in there like
something I wanted to think about a
little bit more just kind of work work
through it a little bit differently than
we had been but that's neither here nor
there anyway
so the situation as it stands right now
is we backed off we we kind of like went
down to a coarser grain thing and sort
of took a look at what that would look
like if we had smaller and smaller
voxels just so we could sort of see what
the difference was with various lighting
you know different Lighting's we could
use and the way that we're storing
things right now is we have a voxel
lookup that allows any pixel that wants
to try to figure out what its lighting
value would be to go ahead and calculate
the lighting if it wants to from any
number of sources based on a linked list
that's invoke CIL's that it can look up
into based on its position so any
particular point in here right there's a
voxel and you can see it because we now
have sort of chunked lighting in here
there's a voxel at each sort of position
that's about you know sort of a square
this big and it's a fairly elongated
because there's less of them in Z so
there's like they're longer than Z and
what you do is wherever you are in the
voxel you can look up and get a linked
list of computed reflect reflection
points like basically points where the
lighting has been computed that you can
interpolate between and the problem that
we're going to have with this obviously
we have some work to do to try and make
this work cleanly but the problem that
we're gonna have with this is as we want
to interpolate the lighting we're gonna
have problems where we have to make sure
that our voxel is about the same density
as a lot of examples that we've put into
it
hopefully the leg samples actually are a
little more dense than the voxel itself
so that when things are interpolating
they can always have some points to
interpolate between now the first thing
I want to do today before we get any
further into this is just try doing a
basic trilinear blend so for any given
pixel wherever it is it'll do the
lighting on essentially like a the same
way that we would sample a texture if
you will or something like this where we
blend between the lighting sample the
computed lighting sample
values in each of the four voxels or
something like this right and I guess
what I should do first is kind of go
over what the problems are that we're
gonna have why we you know why this is a
bit of a tricky situation that's gonna
require some finesse to try and get
right and so on and so forth so here we
are
I'm day 409 by the way can you is there
a way to get Milton to not have a title
bar or anything probably not that's
gonna say we have this sort of nice for
coder when we when we load up the code
here we have the sort of no nice no
title bar thing I leave the file bar up
for people because they asked for it but
normally on my dead machine I get rid of
that too so you get this short of just a
nice screen of just just the code it
would be kind of neat for Milton to get
rid of its title bar too because then
you could have like nothing right it'd
just be a big blackboard but that's kind
of a minor thing I should just go do it
myself the source code is available send
a pull request anyway on day 409 what I
wanted to talk about here is the light
interpolation and so the problem that we
have with light interpolation is we have
the idea and I'll draw sort of a voxel
trilinear case here so that we can sort
of work towards that we have a voxel and
we've got somewhere in this voxel we
have a pixel that we're trying to light
on the screen right and so what it knows
is it knows we're in the voxel it lands
so it knows for example that it's in
this cube of the voxel well it's not
really cubed because it's it's i think
the z direction is less sampled i don't
remember exactly how we left it set up
but point is it's probably about a cube
it's more like a
it's a right rectangular prism of some
kind so anyway we have this this place
where we want to compute the lighting
and we know that it's inside a
particular cube of the voxel or right
rectangular prism as the case may be and
what we want to do is we want to then
take some measure of the lighting we've
computed and apply it to this pixel that
we're trying to light now all we have
inside this text box low rather is a
linked list right so we've got a linked
list of lighting samples and the
lighting samples have like a position
and a color right so they sort of say
well you know I was over here and I was
this color or I was over here and I was
this color or whatever and so there's a
lot of different ways that we can try to
work with this right so let's start with
the simplest possible thing we could do
and the one that would be the cleanest
to implement and easiest right and who
knows maybe it's even like what we
should do I mean it could be that it's
fine but it has some drawbacks and I'll
say what they're in second so one thing
we could do is say well just forget it
like don't bother storing this
information at all let's just store
whatever the average color value was
that right and then just use that as the
lighting done right if we did that so
each voxel positioned just all the voxel
had in it was knowledge of what its
color value should be light wise then in
each of these locations I would have one
color and so I could just take using
trilinear interpolation on these eight
samples I could just take whatever the
location of the pixel being filled was
and know what it's lighting contribution
what kind of light it was receiving
strictly based on that right that would
be all I would need to do
and so that's one thing that we could do
and if we were gonna do that then what
we would do is rather than store rather
than compute with the reflected light
was at those points we just record the
incident light at those points during
our letting pass and that's what we
would store here so we know that the
generalized like amount of incident
light at this point is blah
now we chose to do something a little
bit better than that in terms of what we
store Jimmy which is that inside here
what we actually store is a position and
a color which is to say that we have
multiple pieces of information about
where inside this box all our samples
were taken so that if we for example
took one thing on this side of the box
law and one thing on this side of the
voxel then we could use interpolation
within the voxel itself without looking
outside the voxel to actually give more
information about how color varies over
the voxel interior to its own volume we
could actually vary it based on
information strictly related to this
voxel without even ever looking outside
the voxel which gives us even more
information right and so the problem
with that is that once we have a
particular piece of information
regarding what happens inside the voxel
we now no longer really have any way to
figure out what we would do about when
we get to the edges of the voxel right
because let's take the simpler case to
draw where we were doing this as
bilinear interpolation because there's
the problem exists in in any dimension
it doesn't matter whether you're in 1d
2d 3d etc so if I'm in two dimensions
and I had exactly the same scenario then
what I was proposing is the first and
easy solution is if we pretend that
there is an incident light value at the
center of each of the quad of the
squares of my quadrilateral here for by
the interpolation and I've got a
particular pixel I want to fill then
it's a simple case of bilinear
interpolation as we said before to
figure out what the color
or into this case incident light should
be at this point because bilinear
interpolation is very straightforward
and we know that it will be continuous
right when I get to here I will be set
up to be exactly on this line so that
when I get when I continue across and
try to figure out pixels over here or
whatever it will be continuous the
entire way right it's always blending
between two things and when it gets to
the you know to the one of them it's
exactly at that one and then starts
blending towards the other one so
there's no like there's no
discontinuities in the blending at like
boundaries where something like bad
where you'll get like an edge and ng
artifact you don't like right so the
next question is well what about you
know sort of the more the fancier
approach or the more detailed approach
where we store multiple like samples per
voxel in a linked list like we're doing
so in the 2d case what that would end up
looking like is rather than having
things in the center you might still
have some things in the center who knows
where you have them but you have
something more like this where there's
sort of a scatter shot right amount of
stuff in here
and there's no real rhyme or reason to
where it necessarily is right it could
be anywhere inside here we don't really
know and so the problem with this
becomes when I have someone let's say I
take roughly the same position I want to
compute this pixel and what its color
value is and I don't really know how to
do that because I don't have any way to
do bilinear interpolation on it right so
what I need to do instead is I need to
have some way of interpolating various
scattered sample points and what I did
just through and really quickly was
essentially a radial fall-off so that
what I did is I took you know the
distance from each sample to the place
we were trying to sample and I let it
fall I let the contribution of each one
fall off as it gets further away now
that actually works just fine you know a
radial fall-off weighted contribution
like we did is a totally fine way of
coming up points certainly but the
problem with it is that it doesn't
actually help you avoid the
discontinuities that will happen once
certain points fall out of your sample
set and the reason for that is because
let's say we end up sampling pixels
along a line here and our range of
fetching is one voxel to either side
well I'm going to actually weight the
contribution of this point right up till
I get to this voxel boundary and then as
soon as I cross the VAX abound reaiiy
will no longer consider this point which
means that at the point when I when it
would have fallen out I had better have
driven its contribution to zero but I
didn't do that right I didn't have any
guarantee that a samples radius was
confined so what we probably would need
to do if we wanted to make that work is
we'd need to force you know if we
weren't gonna do anything fancier in the
scheme we would need to make it so that
each individual lighting sample how to
fall off that was no more than a voxel
and a half basically right or one voxel
depending on how tightly we wanted them
controlled we would need to make sure
that when you are fetching voxels from
neighbor voxel boundaries you don't
consider any voxel that could fall out
as you cross into the next boundary so
basically if you imagine that a voxel
the furthest possible voxel and the
closest possible voxel right let's do
this so imagine the closest possible
voxel is right here on the corner right
and what's gonna happen is as soon as I
cross out of here right as I'm sampling
in this direction as I'm stepping
through pixels this way let's say this
voxel right here had better not have a
radius that can extend out into here
right because if it did then its
contribution would be nonzero some some
actual nonzero
value right at the edge and then as soon
as it crosses over it would become
instantaneously zero so rather than
having a fall-off that looks you know
like this or something
it's gonna have a fall-off that looks
like that right and that you will
perceive as a discontinuity in the
lighting very very obviously right so
that is kind of what we're trying to
deal with here right is making sure that
we would have some kind of a blending
scheme that isn't going to have that
problem and I think that so the easiest
thing we can do to fix it right now to
just try and move it to something a
little more sane is to make sure that
the radius we take whatever the smallest
radius is in our voxel dimension and we
just make sure that things can't
contribute past that right so that
they're never going to have a have more
than one of those radii so we can see
what kind of a difference that makes we
don't really know whether our code is
bug free yet because we haven't really
spent much time playing with it so we
don't know if there's other problems in
here as well but you can see that
there's very clear voxel boundary
problems right you can see we're not
drawing those voxel boundaries that's
just lighting discontinuity that you're
seeing there right so we can take a look
to see what would happen if we changed
our shaders to have that property so
when we compute the Z bias program I'm
sorry when we compute the lighting in
the Z virus program if we wanted to make
sure that that lighting would would not
pose a problem then what we can do is in
here we have the inverse cell dimension
and the voxel mid-corner
what we could do is figure out a useful
way of talking about distance that was
sort of mapped into the voxel to begin
with and I guess what we could do is
multiply by the voxel inverse seldom
before we compute the distance for
example would be
one way to do that so when we do this
subtraction for example here we've come
up with a distance what we could do here
you say all right what we want to do is
is multiply this by the voxel inverse
cell dimension so now we know that all
of these distances are going to
effectively be expanded or contracted
properly so that a distance of one in
any direction of the voxel is is going
to mean we went to what we went one
whole voxels worth of space right then
when we do our clamping to make sure we
clamp between zero and one
in theory I think that would do it now
unfortunately we're not actually we're
not square right so I don't really know
if that's okay um that's a very
interesting that's a very interesting
color pattern so what I will say about
that is it did sort of do what I wanted
to do which is sit for voids the
discontinuity unfortunately it creates a
very weird effect so I'm not sure we
really want to do that quite that way
but it's kind of interesting that is
very look at that that's very odd so
maybe that's not the best idea I have to
think this through a little bit of
whether that's even really the correct
way to do it but point being we can also
test it slightly differently here we can
do when we do our length squared we
could say well whatever the voxel size
is supposed to be we can whatever the
smallest voxel size is we can go ahead
and make sure that we don't blend at any
further than that right and so the way
that we would do that is we just say
well the distance squared function that
we're going to come in here when we take
the length squared of of this when we
take the length squared of the Delta we
can just divide that by the max distance
squared right
and that'll make sure that that will be
orbit you know we can even just make
coefficient so we have to do it divide
obviously we could just do it something
here we do this norm constant right so
we just have to compute some value that
whenever we cut a length squared that
length squared is going to be some
arbitrary value right it can be
arbitrarily far so it doesn't have to be
something that's just a voxel size right
and so what we want to do here is say
well okay we want to make sure that we
force the value to be clamped at a
particular position I guess you know the
other thing we could do here too is we
could adjust this value as well in fact
I guess that's really all we have to do
after we compute the length squared
we're gonna take our sort of value and
that's the maximum distance really all
we have to do is this because this is
already our maximum distance here right
so our max blend distance is then gonna
get subtracted by the distance squared
in this case if we wanted to keep it
squared we'd have to square it so really
you know it'd be that but subtracting
two Squared's really isn't something you
can quite do that way so if we really
wanted to be act about this we would
probably also want to square root the
distance I'm not sure how sane that is
in terms of performance but it's
probably not too expensive in shaders
these days probably just for
instructions or something like that
maybe even less maybe just two anyway so
when we do a max blend distance here
what we could do is square root the
distance squared something like this and
and actually get an accurate fall-off
that's based on a linearized radius as
well and again I don't really know to
what extent we want to do that or not
but we can I should probably put in
something like that to keep it the same
as our other code so that just leaves us
with the problem of having to pass max
blend distance in again max blend
distance in this case is just a maximum
side of a voxel the problem is we don't
actually know what the maximum side of
the voxel is because we're only past the
inverse cell dimension now what we can
do is invert it and get that right we'd
rather just pass it in but we can if we
need to we could actually pass that
value right or figure it out because we
know that the max blend distance is just
going to be the minimum value right and
did I define a I defined I mean I didn't
do that either
well it's just going to be the minimum
value which I believe we can just use
min of whatever the inverse cell DIMMs
are so each of these inverse L dims if
we were to just invert them like so
right and get back the actual cell
dimension then we would just take
whichever the minimum was and that's how
far we want to go now in our case
there's no point in doing this divide
three times and then taking the minimum
because we know that whatever the
maximum value is will produce the
minimum value here so what we could do
is just say 1 over the maximum value of
the cell dims themselves right so that
ways like whatever your highest number
is we'll do 1 over that and that will
give us our lowest number and that would
be the maximum blend distance there's no
sense in doing this math over and over
again every pixel so this is really
something that should just happen and be
passed down
but you know right now I'm just kind of
hacking it in there to see whether it's
something we care about at all
oops it's Vox in seldom
yeah so anyway I what you can sort of
see happening here is this is roughly
done exactly what I wanted to do I guess
you could say so if you look at what's
happening here we're getting kind of
exactly what I would have wanted to have
happen which is that we are keeping
everything constrained to about one
voxel size and there's no
discontinuities so I really can't
complain about that that's basically
what I wanted the problem of course as
you can see is that the samples are so
sparse that there aren't even samples in
some of these voxels right there aren't
even samples at a lot of these voxel
locations and so as a result what
happens is when we try to blend together
we just get nothing so you know there's
nothing in this voxel right here for
example and it creates just a little
pools of contribution with nothing to
blend them to right and if you're
wondering why they don't blend out to
zero the reason is because we normalize
the lighting right we are we're blending
together only insofar as there are
multiple samples we don't include
nothing as a valid sample in the current
state because we really don't ever want
to be in that position so again you know
what we can do here of course is we can
drop the size of the voxel down to
something very low and that allows us to
always have enough samples but then we
start having this problem also of of the
voxel not really doing much work for us
and so we kind of have to sort of think
about how we're gonna do something a
little bit more sane with that right but
let me go ahead and
so now we this is with the voxel
dimension dropped very low and you can
sort of see that with with how low the
voxel dimension has been dropped you can
sort of see that now we have we always
have multiple lighting samples
everywhere in the in the scene right and
I guess like it's kind of hard to tell
whether this is a particularly good
interpolation of those samples however
because one of the problems we have
right now that we probably would have to
fix is just not like we have to have
some method whereby we could visualize
where our samples are so we can toggle
between that you know in some kind of
relatively clean way because you see you
get a lot of these sort of bubbly
effects here and that's actually just
you know I don't know that that's
necessarily anything buggy because
that's probably what you would expect to
see in the circumstance where you had a
a radial basis sort of a radial fall-off
for how you were summing things together
right that's not that that's not that
strange that make sense so yes so we
kind of just need to figure out some
ways here that we're gonna be able to
again to get around that so a couple
different things we could do like I said
before we could just try to do lighting
computation at the voxel boundaries
themselves right so that we always try
to do stuff that you know ends up
creating a light an incident light value
at individual voxels and then we try
linear interpolate between those that's
a totally sane way to try and go about
it you know and I'm not sure whether
that's
same I'm not sure how saying that is
specifically I will say that yeah it's
sort of working okay I mean you know
it's not that far from a usable solution
at this point which is kind of nice like
it sort of does work in terms of you
know when I'm down here and I recompute
the lighting and this light is here like
it kind of does look like it's roughly
confined to that or whatever right so
that's not bad but yeah but anyway but
we're still pretty far away from having
something that I really consider good so
yeah anyway so the question is just how
do we move forward from that and I'm not
sure right I'm not sure exactly what the
easiest way to to go forward from that
is whether I should try to figure out a
good way to integrate these samples
together and still keep multiple samples
for voxel or whether I should assume
that we're just going to compute
lighting in the voxel itself and let
everyone try to compute their lighting
from that yeah and I don't really know
[Music]
you
so there's a couple things here the
first thing that I'd like to take a look
at is we may be kind of doubly
contributing here because we record the
lighting values at these locations and
then we also multiply by the lighting
values at these locations I'm kind of
interested to know what happens if I
just use the lighting sums directly I'm
just curious
okay so we're not we are not storing the
lighting premultiplied by it the surface
we are just storing we're just storing
the light value so that's good that
means that our colors are not sort of
double like getting double weighted
right which is what we want good so this
remains a valid calculation and I am
happy about that so I guess my next
question is if we were to do some denser
lighting sampling we're computing
lighting at all of the vertices and I
guess I'm not really sure why we get
some of the patterns we get there though
well actually that does look kind of
accurate because we're moving little
tiny lights around one of the problems
we have is our lighting computation
itself has not been GPU accelerated yet
so I can only take it periodically which
means we can't see really how it moves
you know and that affects the
interpolation obviously like whether the
interpolation would look good in motion
we don't really know either but one
thing that's definitely true is we're
just not getting a lot of bounce either
like you know the lighting here doesn't
really flood in much in the way that we
might want it
to either which is not perhaps the best
thing in the world
and you can see that these patterns are
kind of weird they don't make a huge
amount of sense to me I'm assuming
that's because of the way the fall-off
is written right now when things kind of
combined together there's probably a
little bit of weirdness there so I'd
like to look at the samples again if
possible or perhaps even just adjust the
samples so let's suppose that we were
going to do something a little bit more
Squinkie there
we're inside the like voxel let's try to
make the voxels still be relatively
relatively large
and so I believe you know this is
roughly just looking at the lighting
samples right like this is more or less
telling us exactly what where our
lighting samples were I think I don't
know that that's necessarily true but I
think that's true and so you know the
lighting samples are getting placed sort
of at these four points on a cube right
and so you know what you'd want to do
here is you want to just kind of look up
the ones that are related to you I mean
you really just want to fill between
these for example in these cases right I
mean what you really want is to just
kind of say well alright I've got these
and let me let me just kind of fill
those in but the tough part right comes
when you know you want to do sort of
these corners here you want this to kind
of fill down to this light here and I
don't know it's just it's kind of tricky
so figuring out how to like gather these
back up is a kind of nasty problem which
is not surprising there's a lot of
Papers written on this sort of thing for
lighting gather kinds of filtering to
try and figure out you know from
multiple lighting samples what the
lighting value at some new points should
be is actually you know it's not easy
obviously but
and I guess I'm not really sure to to be
honest so I guess I see what's happening
here so these are bright because there's
these yellow lights that are here and
they're lighting up the red and these
are bright from this guy so that's why
you kind of have these two two bands
there that's all right yeah so here's
what I'll say looking at this right it
is still the case that these these
lookups just aren't grade right because
let's suppose you outputted a scene that
looks like this I would argue that
actually you this is probably dense
enough of a lighting computation to be
okay you know
I mean I would say that that's a that's
a totally reasonable amount of lighting
to be able to interpolate between to get
some kind of a relative idea of words of
what the color of the service should be
and so the voxel lookup scheme just
isn't really sufficient here like what
you really want to be able to do is is
sort of more of a give me the view of my
closest points and that's not
necessarily what the voxel is gonna be
good at is the only problem because the
voxel is always a fixed size whoo-hoo
you know the voxels always a fixed size
and so there's not much it can really do
about that
you know it's not gonna be able to
really adjust so you kind of want there
to be more of a I guess almost more of a
flood fill kind of a thing like if you
were gonna use a voxel you kind of want
all of the voxel cells to eventually get
pointers into them that tell you you
know other points where the closest
points are and at that point it really
does seem like you just want to compute
coloring for each voxel in some other
way
yeah so I don't know so I'm kind of
leaning towards saying you know we
probably want to do some kind of
pre-processing on the voxel there and
maybe send something down for the voxel
where the voxel is kind of more of a
just each voxel cell says a rough in
radiant direction and the reason that
I'm a little hesitant about that is just
because you get into situations where
you have a single voxel cell that has
more than one like primary piece of
information in it that's important you
know
so in that case having you know the
linked list I was kind of thinking would
be the way to get around that problem
but I'm just afraid that storing these
things and like this maybe isn't the
best idea I don't know I'm kind of
should to know what an on gradient Wash
version would look like I want to know
also where if we flood fill with closest
point basically what that looks like so
rather than doing you know a light sum
like we're doing if we just picked the
closest point
I wonder what that'd be like I also
don't like how many voxels we have to
look in you know there's just a lot of
them and that doesn't seem good either
so I think what I may do let's start
with sort of something simple which is
let's start by just summing eight voxels
total and we'll go from there
so in other words we're gonna start by
doing something that's like this sort of
thing
let's just get this down to a more
manageable number one two three four
five six seven eight I so if we sum the
voxel lighting let's assume that we're
going to compute a voxel that's like our
base voxel and we're gonna go up one in
each direction right but not back one so
we will do you know this sort of a thing
and let's assume that what we'll do
there is we'll look to see which voxel
we're talking about when we produce our
voxel I so if you imagine that this were
the voxel just taken in cross-section
there what we want to do is say well
okay do it this way before what we were
doing is let's say gathering all of
these let's start by just saying okay
we're only gonna gather let's take the
center point of a voxel and say if
you're in you know if you're on this
side of it right then we're gonna use
these voxels but if you're on this side
of it then we're gonna use these voxels
you know what I'm saying
so basically break it up into so that
we're talking about like the center
wherever the point is that we're looking
at we're gonna go back to the like half
voxel boundary and use the voxels that
make sense for that particular
interpolant right and another way to say
that and perhaps an easier way to
envision it as well is if we just said
well okay maybe we just go ahead and say
that voxels at our sampled at their
corner and are inserted into on their
corner so on the insertion side we could
do it that way that way we're always
just taking the that that way this math
is actually already correct because
whatever the floor is if the samples
were here here here and here then
whatever the floor
is is already you know you're in this
voxel so now you already know your inter
plating between those four points
correctly and that's where you should be
right so basically what we could do is
is that I don't know if we really want
to we don't have to do it that way what
we would do is just in is just increment
by a half voxel before flooring and we
would get the same answer so we could
just do it so that things are still
voxel based I don't know but there's not
much of a difference there either way we
just have to make sure that we insert
the you can see that the lights are kind
of clipped now we just have to make sure
that we insert the lights on on the half
boundary or look up on the half boundary
since I kind of want the voxel
dimensions in here anyway I think I'm
just gonna say let's start passing those
down and then we can use them you know
uniforms don't cost a whole lot to have
so I think I'm just gonna say let's have
the cell dim in here as well and that
way when I go to do the flooring hmm
excuse me
well actually know what we've worked I
don't even I still don't really need it
though I'm kind of fine trying to find
an excuse to have the cell game in there
but I don't really need it because since
I multiplied by the inverse dim I can
just add point five at that point right
before the flooring so before I floor
the point to find out which ones I'm
gonna look towards I could just do you
know
that right and that makes sure that I'm
gonna be in the right based on voxel
centers I would be in the right the
right region but yeah again that's not
really gonna help us too terribly much
until we have something a little more
sane to use there because if we don't
actually do light samples at the Centers
of each of our voxels then we yet would
have a problem so let's try though just
putting light samples at the Centers of
the voxels I mean it seems reasonable
enough there's not that many of them
even at the moment even if we did them
all but I what I could do first is just
say any voxel that actually is sort of
in the region of something we could put
something in and do a lot of computation
there so we don't have to have quite so
many but yeah so all I was trying to say
here was if we wanted to make it so that
we're based off centers of voxels so
that we know that like if there was a
letting sample at the center of each
voxel
and we wanted to go within them just
adding the 0.5 keeps the flooring value
so that as I get up to here
I would actually move forward so let me
just make sure I'm doing this right so
normally when we floor right it's gonna
keep us inside this voxel for anywhere
inside the voxel right so the voxels are
gonna be this one are gonna be these you
know what I think about it's actually
subtracting 0.5 is the way that I
actually was drawing it though so it's
not actually adding 0.5 I've got it
going the wrong way because what I said
I wanted to have happen was that if I
was in here I wanted to be these which
means this voxel this voxel this voxel
and this voxel if I went here I wanted
it to be these
so I actually want to subtract point
five beforehand not add point five
that's actually what I would want to do
to make sure that I have the voxels that
I wanted because I'm actually going
backwards not forwards right no I didn't
like that at all what did I do
that's a bit strange why didn't it huh
I'm not sure why I thought everything
was out in the other case that's a
little bit weird but anyway this is the
case where we that I was discussing
where it would where it would pick the
right voxels for blending the center
points of those voxels so yeah if we
want do something like this the key here
would be we'd need to make sure that
each voxel though does have something
there in order to bi-linear between them
and if we wanted to then bilinear
instead of doing it we could write the
bilinear code right now so you know the
light sum or whatever would just change
to being something where it would
normalize itself after the fact so for
example if we wanted to do that here
what we could do is something like this
where to me when we go to some of the
voxel lighting up we do the sort of
blending inside here and we'll figure
out you know at some point how that's
supposed to work but we would maybe
figure out the blending based on the
centroid of the voxel as well if that
makes sense
like we we would probably want to we
would probably want to compute the
lighting value at the centroid of the
voxel and blend between those it's kind
of hard to say well let's keep going
with this here this is a bit wonky but
I'm gonna do it anyway
so anyway we have our result value here
you can see us computing it and what I
want to do is at the end I want to
normalize the result value so I'm just
gonna say if the result value had
anything at all then I'm going to take
the result value RGB and multiply it by
the result value a over you know I say 1
over the results H and normalize it so
that now no matter how many things we
weighted together we will always
up with an even wait I'll get rid of
this stuff
and then we just need to actually use it
down here still so this this still wants
to be Jimmy I use let's see
and so in here when we get these voxel
values back like these are gonna be a
little bit more complicated now so this
these are like each of these is going to
be a light value we don't need an alpha
value because we wouldn't really be
using alpha anymore
so we'd really just be returning just
the RGB value what we'd want to do here
is say okay we're gonna capture each of
these separately
right this would be us capturing each
voxel value that we could get so this
computes the eight voxels that are in
our neighborhood what they're letting
contribution is and then we can lurk
between them right I think we defined
our own lerp that has the order that I
like right didn't we yes so we can do
based on the Vox the fractional amount
of Z you know we can do each one of
these and all I'm gonna do here right
all I'm doing is taking the various
voxel pieces and doing lerp salong them
along the edges so those lips that would
take Z out of the equation because now
we've got basically we've we've taken
our cube and we've lurked all of the Z
lines so that now we just have a square
then we would do the same thing it's
just successive right so take Z out of
the equation
now we're taking
why out of the equation and so hope you
can see kind of what I was doing there
I'm just saying like alright look we
need to do a trial interpolation so
first let's produce a bilinear
interpolation from the trial
interpolation by taking the Z coordinate
fractional bit which I need to actually
produce here oops
so if I
take the vox position do the floor of it
like so and also have a box F like so
this is basically saying what's the
fractional amount that's left over so we
can interpolate by that so we take the
points of our cube and we say alright
each one of those we're going to take
the Z spans on the cube and lurk between
those to produce a square right then
we're going to take those in to produce
a line and then we're going to take that
to produce our point and that's it
1:22 huh unexpected opening brace hmm
you did not expect my opening brace well
why didn't you expect my opening brace
oh I see so here's the the while loop
did not have the brace in there yeah so
that does not look like I did that right
however because that should have
produced a more by linearly blended
result which it doesn't oh I know why
because it's still also this is not
actually yeah this is this is not just
blurring these together it's still doing
the contribution based on the distance
so what I want to do here is just sort
of smack these together and pretend that
each voxel has sort of a constant
illumination at it so in order to do
something like that again yeah I can get
rid of a lot of this code temporarily
and just say like okay when we go
through here and we look at the light
values rather than having the
contribution amount let's just blend
them together directly like that
so that still doesn't look right to me
because now we should be properly
handling the case
well properly handling the case is
little bit wrong but we should blend to
zero in Kate like we should be seeing an
actual even blend so let's debug this
and get this down to the point where we
don't see errors like that yet because
if we take a look at what's happening
here if if we're if we've eliminated the
position of like if we eliminated world
P right because you can see world P now
no longer appears anywhere in the some
code so since world P is no longer in
here we expect some voxel light should
return the same lighting value
regardless of what who calls it right no
matter when you ask as long as you ask
for a particular voxels lighting value
your you should get the same thing out
you should never get a you know a
different value out then in for two
different pixels that you're trying to
sample you should always get the same
one out so when we call it here when we
produce whatever the voxel fractional
amount is we should be able to do stable
bilinear so that you always get
predictable values as you go through
right so that tells me that I'm not
quite doing this blend properly I
believe and so we need to figure out why
so first off when we do our vox p here
I believe that shouldn't that looks like
it would produce the correct value we're
starting at the negative 0.5 for the for
the range there in terms of producing
the flooring value which seems correct
and once we produce a florid value ah so
this is backwards we actually want to
subtract the floor from the p-value to
give us the fractional amount is
positive not negative so that would have
been a big problem there
let me just protect the rest of it here
the box index is just being produced
from turning that into an integer which
it already is has been florid so it's
just converting from float to int we're
then summing the the voxel lights in
each of those locations which again now
if we if we stuck with exactly this
scheme we wouldn't even need to store
linked lists anymore we just put the
lighting values directly in the voxel
although we might still want link list
to keep the voxels sparse if we if we
store a lot of lighting data in there
okay so that's more correct like that
looks more like what I would expect to
see right and looking through here right
you can kind of see now we always have a
stable by linearly filtered lighting no
matter where we are right so that all
looks about right again the problem with
that of course is that we don't really
get if we were to try and use this
scheme as the way we were interpolating
our lighting we of course end up in the
problem again of this light map
resolution is just not particularly high
and it's regular and we have to figure
out some way to make sure we always get
samples the voxels and so on and so
forth right I just wanted to sort of get
what that would look like so I think
that is roughly what we would want to do
anyway in terms of figuring out how
we're going to interpolate though I
think
you only want to look at eight voxels at
a time looking at 16 just seems too much
that just seems like like way too much
actually it was more than that it's 27
right how many was it we did to all
permutations so we did yeah we did 3
times 3 times 3 it was 27 so I think we
want to keep it to something like that
but whether or not we want to still try
and use more information about where
those lighting samples are I'm still up
in the air about that because I feel
like I don't know that still might be
kind of necessary so what we could do in
this case is yeah we I mean we could
still try to do something where we're
we're lurking between these values but
we still make the values B we could
still use the lighting information in
computing so we basically say okay what
would the lighting be if I was in this
voxel okay what would the lighting be if
I was in this voxel what would the
letting be if I was in this voxel right
we still could interpolate that if we
were so inclined I don't know that we
are but we could and so we could do is
this if we make this in theory we could
make this still take that into account I
mean that is still possible so if we
wanted to we could still do it I think
the old-school way if we wanted to and
it would not really pose a problem right
so we could still say okay can compute a
contribution here and that contribution
in theory could be anything you want I
think so because since we're doing the
bilinear it will always properly fade at
that point on the way out so I think you
could compute the contribution anyway
you wanted probably
I mean don't quote me on that but that
seems like that seems like correct so if
you wanted to take the contribution of
something and say that it's whatever the
length was and then oops and you know we
could even say just I don't know what
over the length I think we can make up
any value we want here and you know who
know we have to start we'd have to
actually go try to think about what the
correct value what the correct rating
would be but in theory you should just
be able to just do whatever you want and
then you the bilinear takes care of the
fact that you are computing it
differently in different areas so you
don't actually get any discontinuities
and that does appear to be the case
right so at that point we really just
have a lighting sample problem and I
don't know again like yeah so we could
take a look one more time at what
happens if we just force a lot of
samples into the same place
let's keep let's keep the Z sampling up
a bit because I feel like you know what
why do I keep changing this I don't even
know why we don't even really need this
right now this is not necessary just go
do that
that's a little bit odd I'm not sure
exactly what we're seeing there I think
that's just our blend amount not being
particularly smart so maybe that one
over is not really great let's let's
let's try and fuss with that a little
bit so let's say our contribution is
gonna still be one minus the length that
might be a little more saying I should
really think a little harder about what
we want to do for blending because I'm
kind of just just ad hoc here that looks
a little nasty why are we getting and I
guess we don't really we don't really
need to renormalize unless we're over
one would be the other weird thing like
we could do this as well right which is
kind of even weirder that fall-off seems
a little too stiff as well potentially I
don't know like maybe it should be
something more you know where lights
have a bigger radius than one just
making stuff up but something like that
starts to look pretty reasonable right
you know it's not going to win it any
awards for best lighting certainly but
it's you know getting to be something a
little more useable
right I mean that that is lighting you
could actually start to use you know and
we haven't really taken into account
than normal stuff yet either so we have
to kind of think about this a little bit
more and work on our lighting
computation as well but you know we're
getting there and again a lot of that
problem just seemed a lot of it tends to
be like how are we gonna bin enough
stuff into enough places to really get
it going okay right but you know that's
that's starting to be plausible to me
right look I think we're starting to get
somewhere so if we had a if we turn turn
the crank a little bit on this one start
to get a little bit further down maybe
figure out start to look at how we're
computing our lighting and maybe write
some things into the into the voxels
that tell us directional information you
know I could see this being something
that is not completely useless right
because like for example if we knew the
directional the the incidence direction
here we'd also know stuff about like
this should not be lit down here right
but right now it doesn't know that
because it doesn't know what direction
lights coming from and furthermore we
can't differentiate between like these
sort of siding pieces here right not
that we really care about underside
lighting too much because we'll never
see it but I mean you know it could
cause other problems like it well you
know you'd have the same problem if you
were on the other side like over here on
a thin thing in fact you can sort of see
that happening right now right see how
that's lit and we don't want that to be
lit
so but that like I said that's kind of
getting there like I feel like we're
sort of getting a little bit closer now
we've got a way to kind of smear
lighting out into the environment and
produce something that you know could be
could potentially start to use game wise
and and that is a good thing I think
right now it's a little too soft and
again we don't know the direction from
which the light hits the surfaces yet
and that creates a problem because
without that piece of information we
don't actually have a way to compute
what the lighting should be how the
lighting should attenuate based on
surface angle and we do want that as
well and the reason we want that right
is to so we could differentiate surfaces
like here so you can kind of see how
this is all just really smooth but there
should have been a hard edge there cuz
this is a hard edge so the lighting
should change on the surface a little
bit more dramatically than than it does
so that's another one all right all
right stretch time okay all right so
we've got a little bit time left so
maybe what I'll I think what I might try
to do is I think I will try to go put in
a little bit of directional information
there I think that sounds like a good
plan to me
so in other words when we store these
light things in here we've got the color
I may try to store the direction as well
so what I'll do is I'll just say like
okay you know we send down the this
light data with stuff and I would like
to also send down I'd like to also send
down a light direction trying to think
of what the best way to send that down
would be
and if you look at this stuff you can
easily see how there's a lot of ways
that we can make this smaller and more
efficient as we would go forward when
when and if we need to so for example if
we do have that sort of lighting Texel
thing you can see how the lighting Texel
that's sort of discussed there it has a
full floating-point value for its
position but we probably don't need a
position because remember it's confined
to a particular voxel we know that it's
in a particular voxel so we could just
have that position be relative to the
voxel corner at which point we could
probably store it at sixteen bits per
coordinate maybe even eight bits per
coordinate and be fine because
quantizing those values probably
wouldn't matter right we don't need to
know precisely where this lighting was
computed we can know like approximately
where it's computed and that would be
fine so you know we can imagine getting
that down to like au 32 even probably
for the position and the same would
probably be true for the direction so
I'm not gonna do that right now
but it's just worth noting that we could
do that so if we needed to in the future
we could easily do something where we
had more information here about what was
going on in that respect right so what
I'm gonna try doing here is I'm gonna
say let's go ahead and make a V for like
directional piece of information here
I don't know why I'm bothering to keep
track of how big these things are this
is not 8 megabytes anymore this is
something we don't know what it is I
mean we know it's 8 times 8 times 8
times 2 so we actually do know what it
is I guess we were keeping score 8 times
8 times 8 times 2 its 1024 so it's like
birth that really is that really that
small so that's fine and based on how
few lighting samples we're taking that
make sense right we don't need a voxel
to be huge if we're only taking 4096
lighting samples at maximum if we were
able to increase that lighting sample
number up to a higher number that would
probably argue for increasing the
resolution of the voxel because the only
point again the voxel is pointless we
wouldn't use the voxel for any purpose
if we didn't have to care about
computation time the voxel is purely
there to make sure we don't spend a ton
of time looking at letting samples that
are far away right that's the only
reason it's there so it only needs to be
it only needs to do that and in order to
do that effectively it just needs to
have a size proportional to the number
of lights that are actually being
computed right right now our lighting
computation is not particularly good
that is some old water I'm not drinking
that and so we don't really need the Vox
will be particularly big in the future
we're gonna have to tune these a little
bit more intelligently and you know
figure out what we're doing with them
but for now that's fine all right so
there we go that's our current situation
let's see if we can fill out this G with
something reasonable if I was going to
fill out this D with something
reasonable then what I would be able to
do is stuff a value in here where in
addition to C sampler we would have D
sampler like so
it's you know I if we wanted to we could
actually make the C value B well I don't
know what we really could let's leave it
at this so anyway if we have a D sampler
in there then when we actually look up
the color value for the light we can
actually look up the directional you for
the light so here's the light D like so
and once we look up that lighting value
in there we are able to use that as part
of the attenuation or any other kind of
value we would want so once we have the
contribute a stonking sample that we're
taking we could also add in something
there where we multiply the contribu
bias
you know the cosine for example again do
we have the macros for that yet we don't
have any macros
all right anyway where we have a cosine
so that we can take well I guess we
don't actually be cosine it when I said
that this will produce cosine for us so
we can take the inner product of the
lighting direction so we know where the
light is coming from and whatever the
world normal is so that'll give us a
cosine they'll tell us how coincident
those two are and as we get further away
the lighting will contribute less right
so that's really all we need to do to
get to get that working that's that's
really about it so most of the work is
going to be plumbing here of getting
that D value down to the system so let's
go ahead and take a look at the render
group entry here we just need some way
of passing down whatever this is going
to be so we just need something that
like passes down a pointer value to that
to that D there and yeah
oops
no we're push lighting is there it is so
really all we need to do here is just
copy that pointer out and that's gonna
be an f32 here so and when we have those
values in the opengl side of things we
just need a way of making sure that
those get pushed through I think that's
all we have to do there and then when we
actually sort of set up the SI sampler
doo-doo-doo
where is it there it is when we actually
submit these textures yeah we have to
put lighting D in there and this one's
gonna be it's not going to be the same
format right this one's gonna be floats
for now and the internal storage format
for it is a log S it's specified
elsewhere yeah so we've got these sort
of hard-coded here
active texture 2 3 &amp; 4 which we it isn't
fabulous so we kind of just made those
line up just out of whimsy there that's
alright I mean what could possibly go
wrong
I'm sure it will be fine yeah anyway let
me actually go ahead and finish this
though so when we bind this guy this is
gonna be exactly the same code as this
only it's gonna be float instead so this
is a floating point texture like I said
we probably don't really want to do that
you know to be honest we don't yeah we
really don't need to do these as floats
at all but but for now we just are so I
feel like we don't want to introduce
complexity of like figuring out
quantization and stuff like this for no
reason so that's why I'm just at the
moment leaving everything in its normal
form without trying to smack anything
down into a smaller space or quantize
something that we don't need to just
because as we're experimenting with
lighting I don't want to introduce
additional things that could create bugs
which then we think are yielding
improper results or throw away some
experiment cuz it doesn't work when it
turns out the only reason it doesn't
work is because we had like a bug and
how we require
or something like that so that's the
only reason I'm keeping something like
this in floats we absolutely don't need
vectors in here and we probably won't
you know in the final version Everest or
anything like that but just you know
keep that in mind that's that's what's
you know that's what's going on okay so
now that we've got that straightened out
I just I'm not sure that it's gonna find
those correctly let me look at how that
was working so if we take a look at
lighting see I guess it really just does
depend on the order so it would just
knew that it was gonna be like okay
texture sampler def sampler Phoenix and
pursue sampler do simply look up sampler
somehow it knew that these were where
those were gonna be uh which is kind of
nuts
you
[Music]
so here's the Z bias program right and
you can kind of see you can see in here
it's gonna call us use program began and
that's gonna go through here for each of
these GL uniforms and it's gonna set the
sampler index to be like 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
right so it literally sets them in this
in that order that they showed up here
right it's texture sampler depth sampler
next sampler see sampler D sampler look
up sampler I mean that's that's the
order they're gonna go in so if I look
up lighting see where that's actually
it's let's see where that's actually
getting bound in here then it's texture
sampler depth sampler P neck sampler see
a sampler put any you know hey it does
line up so you know I guess that just
works alright implicit castrum Veck for
Tyvek 3 sorry about that
I didn't mean to that should be right in
here
okay so now at least in theory we are
taking into account the lighting
direction everything will be black as it
was there because even if we did
everything right we are not filling out
that lighting direction with any
information so what we want to do now is
we want to figure out a way when we
compute the lighting to put something
useful in there right so when we're
packing this stuff down and we're
setting the stuff up right here you can
see us doing this computation you can
see us computing the color value that
we're gonna have here and you can see us
sort of sticking that value into desc
see what we need to do here is stick
some value into into the directional
component right now the problem with
this is it's harder than it looks
because I don't think we tracked this
information so we're gonna have to
actually do some work to go in and put
in tracking this information I believe
but in terms of like render elements
here I don't remember where we defined
lighting elements I'm going to look so
here's the lighting elements and what
you can see from the lighting elements
is that although they store they're
normal they don't store a any particular
idea of what direction they're incident
light came from right and so the actual
amount of color that they should be
proof that they want to say is here
we're not really tracking that quite
right yet so we kind of have to go back
into the lighting computation code which
is okay because that's code now that we
actually have to start improving and
probably turn into GPU side code I'm
guessing I'm not sure because it depends
on how
we want to do this long-term but we need
to do something with that code so that
it runs in real time or runs over a
series of frames and gradually updates
its results or whatever else we're going
to decide to do with it but whatever we
decide to do with it we have to make it
so that it outputs solutions every frame
rather than being something that you hit
f1 to do right so if we're gonna do that
we need to go look at how our lighting
is being computed and when our lettings
being computed we need to sort of put
that information in there
so let's where's that's not what I
wanted let's go into render group here
where the lighting is getting computed
which is here and we're skipping the
ambient occlusion right that doesn't
actually occur yet and here's the
compute lighting so you can see what it
does is it has some number of iterations
it goes through each of the elements it
casts out a bunch of rays to see what it
can hit and retrieve and then when it's
done it goes through each of the well I
should say that this source index here
is it going through those to see whether
there's any shadowing when it actually
finds something that if that it hits it
goes ahead and accumulates the color
value from whatever the this particular
one was right so let's take a look here
so here's the ray caster right it's
gonna cast some number of rays from
[Music]
wait what is it gonna do
this is very weird how did we end up
with this structured like this this is
the the problem of having to have two or
three months out for however long it was
with the Intel chip fiasco
so we're looping over each of our
iterations which makes sense we're
taking each destination so that we're
going to update our lighting elements
right we're taking a set of rays and
initializing some directions we might
cast you know off those rays and then
rather than looping over the Rays we
decided to loop over the sources and
then test whether the Rays hit for that
particular ray
it's just a strange way for me to have
structured this and I realized we were
playing around this code a bunch so
maybe I hadn't you know maybe we kind of
backed into it but it seems like you
would loop over the Rays first and you
would loop over the sources second
because otherwise you're computing the
transference like why are you computing
all of this stuff if you're never gonna
use it right you only do this I mean
you're granted the optimizer probably
doesn't have any trouble figuring that
out because you can see that the only
place that result is used is inside here
so there's no real problem with that
like it's not you know it's not awful or
anything but it's just strange like I'm
not sure why you would be doing it that
way
I'm not sure why you do it that way and
I'm also not sure why you would store
all the Rays simultaneous like that
because if you just looped over the Rays
then you don't care you don't have to
store them in a separate array right
that is to some really strange stuff
that is that is just purely peculiar I
feel like we should reorganize that to
be clear because again I just don't see
any reason for it to look like that it's
very counterintuitive and I realized
that the reason for that is probably
because we added we started with a sort
of bi-directional radius transfer kind
of structure which is dest source N
squared and then we added the REA check
inside so it makes sense I guess why end
up this way based on we did it but just
because we did it that way doesn't mean
we should leave it that way so it kind
of feels like this should get unspun I
don't know want to know if I want to do
that right now because we might want to
wait till next weekend to start that but
that's probably something we should do
I'm gonna put a little
so yeah I think that's probably because
I don't see any benefit to doing it the
way that we're doing it it seems just
purely it seems like just purely more
work so I'm just gonna assume that that
was because of the way we happen to do
it and that there's no good reason for
it
anyway point being when we actually do
this summation and we're accumulating
our results into a qmc one of the things
that we do that we can tell about that I
suppose at this point is well let me
take a look at where Kim's he's even
used
you know I don't it's just even right
because if this accumulator is getting
this doesn't even really make sense to
me so in order for the closest hit ray
index stuff to work you have to have
checked all the sources first but this
looks like your accumulator it looks
like this would be order dependent right
like yeah this is just not right
I mean that just does not make any sense
to me whatsoever
so I I mean I yeah but that really
doesn't make any sense to me so I think
that's just kind of bogus and probably
not something that we really want to use
because you can see this closest hit Rea
index equals tear a thing we're
accumulating a value but we don't yet
know what the closest hit value is going
to be right so in order to know that
this is the closest value we have to
have looped over all the sources first
right and this would have to be Akuma C
equals result not plus equals result
right and we would need to store one
result per Rey yeah this is just this is
just kind of garbage like I don't think
that is it all sane I'm pretty sure it's
not saying
I'm just gonna edit this now because why
not
so if we take a look what's going on
here what I want to do is produce our
piece of rate information so forget that
like that's done that's over so what we
want to do here is we want to produce a
redirection right we want a Rea
direction here all right and we want to
loop over a number of rays so how many
race we're gonna do I don't know
actually you know I guess I shouldn't
believe that quite we're going to see
how many we're doing eight rays all
right so we're doing a trays and then
here we've got a ray direction and
that's the right direction that we
picked all right we've got a closest hit
let's just keep one of our f/32 max and
then we're going to do this nonsense
here
okay so we computed our array direction
we don't need an accumulator because
that well I mean we do but it's gonna go
outside right so for a particular array
we go through and we now test all the
sources to see whatever the closest hit
was right to camera looks like something
that can be computed outside it's not
dependent on the Ray so then we do
through all of our sources and we really
don't need anything but the light
distance here
so this ref C emits C stuff can go in
here so really all we're doing is
checking to make sure the light is not
on top of us right but assuming the
light's not on top of us then off we
would go we don't really need to do that
yet though I don't think because we can
actually do this stuff now on the
outside so for each source ray we would
just go through and say all right we
know what the ray source n is because
whatever the Ray direction is time
source and there it is we can do this
testing all just works and then if we
eventually make it into the closest it
stuff here where we know we've hit this
particular source
sorry I don't know why white did what I
just did there I didn't mean to do that
I meant to do I meant to do that
so we loop through the source indices
and we just figure out which one the
closest it was right so we would just
keep instead of an array of these we
just keep one and we'd also keep like a
you know source hit so on so that
figures out for this Rea who did we
actually hit and when we know who we
actually hit out here you know if source
it is not equal to what we set it to at
the beginning so if we actually found a
hit then and only then would we come
through and do this stuff right
so in the case where we actually have a
valid hit and we know it's the closest
hit then we would actually come through
here and compute the lighting transfer
between the two of them right and then I
think we're actually done it's just a
qmc ever set to anything
so as we come through here yet this this
right here would be like the qmc plus
equals total light I guess right so
that's all of the lighting contribution
that comes in and then when we're done
with all that and we've accumulated all
of it across all of the Rays for that
destiny oops for that destination then
it would get summed in I think that's
actually correct
[Music]
so yeah this to light here gets
normalized eventually by the light
distance do we actually use to light in
here no we don't so this is actually
in here and the only problem that we're
having to make sure we don't test it
against itself because it will always be
its own closest hit since it's right on
top of itself obviously so in here we
have to do a thing that's like if source
index is not equal to desk index right
[Music]
so now that's reorganized to be more
sane here we're taking however many rays
we're doing and we're sort of waiting by
that I guess we just need to have that
be a constant
and off we go
now in order to see whether I just
completely ruined all of our code or not
obviously we have to stop doing this
because that will kill any we are still
not setting those D values so that would
immediately kill anything that we did so
hey there we go now we've actually got
our lighting back and I think it's
actually working
more correctly now perhaps although I
don't actually know because I'm not sure
like it's kind of hard to tell without a
more we don't really have good lighting
testing code at the moment we don't have
like a Cornell box or something we can
set up to see whether our lighting is
getting better or worse when we make
changes like that but it looks roughly
the same to me and so we haven't
destroyed it too much anyway so that's
the good news
all right so now that we took care of
that how much time do we have left here
what's the status
13:11 so we've got four minutes left so
we're not gonna get very much done in
four minutes but that's okay let's go
ahead and try to do this so we've got
our D value here and I'm what I'm gonna
do for our D value is I'm gonna say that
for these lighting elements we we really
want to sort of start to converge on
like a more sane structure for these
letting elements and figure out what
we're trying to actually say here and so
what I want to do is have some way of
producing like okay you know for the
lighting we want to canonical values
there's like a you know incident light
and a you know I I think technically
it's it's generally called a vent normal
but I don't really love that term so I'm
gonna call it like average direction to
lighting to light and so the two values
that we need is like an RGB value that's
like here is how the light is is you
know kind of coming in incident - oh did
we just lose our net connection ooh
so I guess I'm talking to myself here
looks like the net went down I'm looking
at it here and and all of my programs
are basically on the left here saying as
of about two minutes ago three minutes
ago everything is down and that's that's
not good
yeah well so sorry there will apparently
not be any QA but the recording is still
up so the YouTube will have the correct
video so sorry if anyone was watching
the stream it looks like network
providers has has gone down anyway so
what I want curious I want a value that
says here is how much light is incident
on this location and I want another
value which is like if you had to tell
me one general direction where the light
was coming from and you know obviously
the light comes from many different
directions so it's not like you can
really say definitively here is where
the light it's coming from because the
light is coming from everywhere but if
you had to say one general direction
where the lighting was coming from where
would that be something like that right
and we probably want that average
direction to light to be something that
comes that's gonna be more sophisticated
eventually and sort of give us a little
more information about how we should
attenuate the light based on facing
direction because that's really what we
want so if the direct if
lighting is coming sort of evenly from
everywhere we would maybe have a tuning
value and maybe what's that's what our
fourth parameter is but anyway that's
what we sort of need to to get to right
and that's what we'll talk about next
week and I won't I'll just leave the
lighting where it is today okay so
technically this is the QA I can't take
QA because as far as I can tell all of
the internet stuff is down so I'll have
to contact the internet provider to find
out what happened but you know we will
get to that at some point
until then yeah I will just close the
stream as normal thank you everybody for
joining me for another episode of
handmade here it's Mel Patrick coding
with you as always if you would like to
follow along series at home you always
can by pre-ordering the game on handmade
hero or get comes the source code so you
can play around with it you also have a
forum site you can go to if you want to
ask questions we have a patreon page you
can go to transport the series and we
have a schedule bot that tells you when
our episodes are gonna be live if you
want to catch them live there's an
episode guide it's down at the moment so
you can only get it's not quite up to
date yet I don't know what's happening
server wise I don't run that stuff but
hopefully that'll be back and functional
again soon but that's about it I will be
back here next weekend when we'll take a
little closer look at the lighting until
then have fun programming and I'll see
everyone on the Internet assuming my
internet connection comes back at some
point take it easy everybody