hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show we could a complete-game
live on stream yesterday we implemented
depth feeling and surprisingly I it all
went very well so it took a lot less
time than I thought it would because
since we don't have the ability to debug
the GPU on this machine I thought we
were going to end up with a lot of
blackbox debugging to get that working
but it turned out really that wasn't the
case at all however we do still have
something to debug for today which is
the parts that come back to the depth
feeling which is the thing that
composites the to depth feel results
back together again into a final image
that is the only thing that as far as I
know anyway that we have now to get
working that we didn't have working
before and so that's what we're working
on today this is going to be a black box
debugging session though as I had feared
we would have to do during the death
feeling but didn't have to because again
we don't have the ability to debug
anything on this machine normally and
that's okay because it's good to show
this sort of thing because sometimes
when you are programming if you are an
engine programmer as is what we do on
the stream it is not always the case
that you have good tools a lot of times
you may be given a development
environment to work with on say a new
console that's coming out or something
like this where the state of the tools
is very poor and you don't have a lot in
the way of debugging and you just have
to make do with what you have and so
this is not well well it's not really
the way you should go about doing GPU
programming on the PC these days because
you could just go buy an nvidia card and
use insight to do your basic debugging
it's not the case that this kind of
debugging is dead forever or anything
like that blackbox debugging is
definitely the kind of thing that always
come back and rears its ugly head and
probably will for as long as we still
have technological progress in the
hardware space because the bottom line
is tools don't always come online as
quick as you might want and so at least
when you're on the front lines of
development you find yourself in
positions where you have to do
to debugging without real debugger is
fairly often so that's the position we
find ourselves in today but fortunately
for us as I said the depth feeling part
of things went relatively smoothly and
that's probably the more complicated one
to debug because here we are not
comparing depth values or anything like
that we're just dealing with taking two
color buffers and merging them together
so hopefully this will not be
particularly complicated by comparison
but again it will still be something we
have to do in a blackbox fashion if
you're starting to debugging with me
today
today is day 382 so you'll want to start
with day 381 source code for this
debugging let's go ahead and take a look
at where we left things I can sort of
show you the situation as it stands let
me go ahead and open for coder up here
and our project here we go and now I
will run it and basically what we're
seeing here is we just have a black
screen if we actually run the final
composite the way that it is currently
written right that's the bug is we're
not seeing anything so something is like
just fundamental is wrong with that call
now if we look and just to give you a
refresher in case you don't remember or
weren't here yesterday with where we're
at we have produced two frame buffers
and here is a blit of the first frame
buffer that we have produced and what
this is is it's just the frontmost pixel
so using the Z buffer we feed all of the
sprites and all of the ground cubes
right we feed all those to the GPU we
let it use the Z buffer to pick
whichever one is closest and we just
keep the closest so there is no blending
happening here just the closest and you
can see that the fringing the sort of
black pixel fringing you can see where
the shadows would be is all black right
and that's because those are all alpha
values they have an alpha of something
but they're not blending and this is
important that's what we wanted we
wanted a frame buffer that just had the
color values of the frontmost pixel and
the Alpha value of the frontmost pixel
so that's what's in frame buffer zero
then frame buffer one is the other frame
buffer reproduced and what that is is
it's whatever
the one pixel behind the front buffer
pixel was so we render the scene twice
you render it first to get that front
pixel and then to get the pixel that's
one behind whatever that front pixel was
and you can see what that going on here
you can see right here a good example of
that here are those trees that we were
seeing instead of seeing the trees we're
seeing the ground plates behind the tree
right and so we're seeing straight
through the true where the trees outline
was and then where the trees were not
we're seeing beyond the ground right
because the ground was there so now
we're seeing what was behind the ground
and so that's exactly what we wanted
these two frame buffers look basically
right they basically what I wanted and
so now our challenge is to take these
two frame buffers which appear to have
been generated correctly and we need to
merge them together so that we can
output the final result which is the
front buffer blended with a back buffer
based on that front buffers alpha value
that's all we're trying to do very very
simple to texture blend where we take
you know you might think of it as a
decal blend basically we're taking one
texture and stamping it on to the other
texture using the alpha value of the
first texture to determine how much
blending there should be that's all
we're doing we're not doing anything
else so it's pretty straightforward but
we've got some problems here what the
first thing I quickly hacked within at
the end of last stream so it's not like
we spent a lot of time on it we may find
that there was just some very basic
simple mistake but we have to figure out
what's going on so here's what we know
so far we have set ourselves up to try
and pull from two textures and draw a
single full screen quad which is
obviously going to get drawn as two
triangle since graphics cards don't draw
claws they draw triangles well most of
the time of you cards have implicit
rasterizes on them and I think nowadays
you could probably draw a quad if you
really wanted to I don't know how much
they expose that but that's neither here
nor there the point is simply that this
will get drawn as two triangles we're
outputting it as a triangle strip
because there is no such thing
I feel quads and modern OpenGL after you
move away from compatibility mode they
got rid of quads entirely I have no idea
why they got rid of Kwas entirely I
literally could not tell you all I can
say is that they don't have anymore so
we're drawing a triangle strip that
triangle strip consists of the four
corners of the screen and it's using a
shader called peel composite which we
wrote whose only job is to pull from
these two textures that were the frame
buffers we just looked at and draw them
to the screen now what we know from from
just a few experiments last time and I
can show you this if I set the clear
color here and clear the color buffer
what we will see is that we do at least
get a red screen and what that tells me
at least for the most part because if I
was to take like you know let's say I
took this GL viewport call and again
just we're just playing around this just
to sort of make sure we know what we're
doing here if I was to sort of play with
this call I just want to see it's the
viewport because I don't know if the
viewport the GL clear actually believes
the viewport and it looks like it
doesn't if I remember correctly and I
don't know if I really do
the only way to get clearing to respect
the viewport is to actually have GL
scissor enabled so if I want to play
around with that I would have to sort of
play with these two here and and put a
scissor on as well so let's go ahead and
see what that does here okay so lets me
go ahead and let me divide the whip here
just to see because i want to i want to
make sure we know where our viewport
actually is and that our viewport is
correct because i don't know if it is or
it isn't okay so what i want to do here
is i just want to ensure that there's
some sort of semblance anyway of of an
understanding that we're setting the
viewport correctly so what i'm doing
here is i'm just playing with the
parameters to the viewport and scissor
call because i want to see that we've
got that viewport set up properly right
and that did i black solutely type
written for one of those I think I may
have so there's Jill scissor through our
region min I take let me just back out
here a little bit go at should be like
that I don't know why I type divided by
four there nobody knows so that's what I
wanted to see again this is just me
because you know black box debugging
everything is on the table we don't know
what's wrong right
I know I've made a mistake somewhere or
there's a driver bug some Eric we don't
even know if it's our mistake but it's
probably our mistake because we're not
doing anything particularly complicated
right but either way doesn't matter
there is a mistake somewhere ours or
theirs we don't know anything about
where it is so I'm just starting from
first principles and going okay let me
verify that I even know where I am
drawing to so with the with a clear of
read of the color buffer bit and a
viewport plus a scissor I can guarantee
that now I at least know what the
boundaries of the drawing region are
because when I was seeing the whole
screen red I had no way of knowing
whether I was just seeing like a giant
viewport that extended way beyond the
screen and that we're just clearing a
small portion of it or whether I was
actually looking at the whole screen it
looks like it was correct that the
viewport was just the screen I'm going
to leave these in place and just try to
get the draw working to that smaller
area for the time being okay so I want
to look at a couple things here but
again the first first things first I'm
going to switch this clear now over to
blue so that when it clears it's going
to going to show blue and then I'm going
to use red as the color that I draw in
the shader so I'm going to pop over to
the shader now and I'm going to I'm
going to simplify the shader down until
I know that the shader does literally
nothing oops
I'm in the wrong file till I know that
the shader does literally nothing but
draw red right I don't want the shader
to do anything basically other than
output
bright red okay
so what I want to do here is say alright
let's make sure that we are always
drawing pure red out and it looks like
that's basically what we're doing here
but I want to be even more explicit
about it so what I'm going to do is I'm
going to go and I'm getting completely
Nerf everything in the shader so there's
literally nothing in the shader now and
then what I'm going to do is I'm going
to set the shader explicitly to a full
alpha red color and that result color is
the only out we put so it should just
draw pure red and if we go up here and
look at the vertex shader the vertex
shader just takes the position directly
and outputs it so hopefully that as well
would be a clear and unambiguous shader
so now I have to see if it gives me any
areas because I'm not using any of those
values it isn't so in theory that shader
is compiled properly again that's just
you know in theory so now what we should
see is this this program that we've
created is something that you just draw
red wherever it is right so it doesn't
matter what you send down wherever it
fills regardless of what the texture
values are we should just be red and the
reason that I'm doing that is again I
want to take as much stuff out of the
equation as possible and I just want to
get it to where I see something red
right because we know now that we're
drawing to the right area of viewport
wise but what we don't know is whether
we're ever actually drawing anything
through the shader and since the shader
is set to pure red and I'm not seeing
any red on the screen at all I can only
assume that what I'm seeing here is some
kind of a problem with the way I'm
specifying the vertices like they're not
actually being set to what I expect them
to be or something right now the other
thing I can do here is I can clear
everything so I can clear the depth bit
and the stencil bit oops
and what that'll do is just verify it
you know I thought I turned deaf testing
off in Siri depth has to be up I just
want to make sure and by clearing the
depth buffer first I know that there's
no Z buffer getting in the way and I've
disabled the desktop def test here so in
theory that should not be a problem but
I just wanted to make absolutely
positive okay all right so now we know
we're drawing to the correct frame
buffer and we know we're drawing to the
correct region and the reason we know
that is because we see the blue
rectangle so I at least know that much
we are not reading from these textures
so in theory I can just get rid of these
textures entirely because we're not
reading from them and hopefully that
will ensure that there's nothing weird
going on in the texture side of things
again those calls should have had no
effect whatsoever and we're not seeing
any effect there so that's good and so
now we're just left with what I think is
our fundamental problem and probably the
was the original problem altogether the
only problem that I think we actually
have so far which is that I'm not
actually specifying vertices correctly
so they're not actually constituting
triangles that we can actually see that
is my assumption for what is wrong but I
don't actually know that that's just my
assumption so what I would like to do
here is I would like to go into the use
program begin of peel composite and I'd
also like to just verify what some of
the values that we're setting are to
make sure that they're plausible and
that there isn't some kind of an error
value somewhere that we're not seeing
right because even though we haven't set
up to issue a hard error anytime that
the OpenGL driver thinks that we've made
a critical mistake
we will see those but we could easily
get in a situation where it returns a
like oh I didn't find anything for this
vertex stream that you asked for or
something that is maybe a legal
pass-through error right it may be not
really technically an error in which
case we wouldn't get notified about it
or something right so I just want to
come in here and make sure that the
things that we are sending down that I
do expect to be set are set so you can
see for example transfer mine
there is no transform set in this
particular shader so I expect it to be
all you know negative one basically and
that's what it is so that's okay but for
example this one well actually these are
now because we remove them so those
don't have to get set either but for
example these right here should have
values and you can see that they
actually do appear to have values
extreme zero stream 1 and stream 2 or
rather location 1 1 2 &amp; 3
does look correct there now what I don't
know you know I don't know if location 1
is the correct location obviously
because there's no way for me to know
that that's just what it told me but I
assume that that's correct and you know
there yet I assume that that is the
correct value we don't really have any
way of knowing and so here we go we're
setting off sets into textured vertex
we're using just a buffer that's already
sort of set up here I believe although
you know is this array buffer actually
enabled and active I guess that's one
thing I don't know let me make sure that
we didn't miss something here so it
doesn't look like it because it looks
like we leave the the buffer bound the
entire time for the most part so it
looks like that should be fine I'm
assuming that's something that happens
in here I don't actually know but let's
see so there's the old gen buffers and
there's GL bind buffer so it looks like
that is just always going to be active
and in theory there's nothing else we
need to really do there so that I
believe should be fine so it seems like
that use program begin is working
relatively well and it seems like yeah I
don't see any other particularly onerous
things happening here so the next
question is well are we sending down
this vertex data correctly because maybe
we're doing something stupid where we're
not putting the data into you're not
putting the vertex data into a format
that works properly with the rest of the
pipeline so let's take a look there let
me
this and let's just go take a quick look
at what we're actually specifying in
those terms
so you can see here if this is the
vertex code for our other shader the one
that is working properly the one that's
drawing all the sprites and that's or
even drawing the faces of the cube so
you can see that what happens when we do
our vertex in ingress here is we create
a vertex that's basically got you know
what I was just thinking I don't know if
the W coordinate of a vertex defaults to
1 or not we're setting it to 1 here but
we're not setting it to 1 the other one
and if the W coordinate was 0 that would
be a problem potentially for us because
the W coordinate of 0 that doesn't go
through a transform of any kind would
end up dividing by 0 potentially so
let's just double-check that right this
right here where we specify this vert P
it's a V for incoming and you know what
actually it wouldn't even be the default
value it's actually going to be a value
right here so I think I think this is
really my mistake this looks very very
much like a suspicious maneuver here I
kind of forgot we had this special
vertex format that we've been using to
do the biasing which means that we
actually passed four values not three as
a position so it's not even filling in a
default value for W it's filling in our
value for W and what you'll notice here
is C will complete an incomplete
initializer list like this with zeros
and so what we're actually getting is
this and that's a problem because the W
coordinate is the synthetic divides it's
going to happen with that W coordinate
that's going to divide by 0 and probably
not give us very happy results so what I
would assume is that that right there
may be a really big problem for us let's
see what happens if we reenable that by
putting a 1 in there so that's looking
really good there we've got red coming
and I assume that we're actually seeing
the actual coverage region being the
correct you know the whole viewport I'm
going to just just see if that's true
by switching these to something that has
just just a tenth apron there on it
right so we can kind of see what's going
on and verify that it actually is
drawing to the region I think it's
trying to because again just like I did
when I push that viewport in smaller
than the screen to see that I could see
the apron I want to do the same thing
with the shader to make sure that I know
that I'm passing down values that are
lining up the way that I think it so
that looks pretty good to me it does
look like roughly 1/10 again that it
should not be a symmetric apron it
shouldn't be symmetric because we're
talking about clip space where
everything's negative 1 to 1 that means
motion in X is going to be further it's
going to move further than in Y because
there's less total distance that's
that's spanning that negative 1 to 1
range so that looks like a fair apron to
me it looks like what I would expect so
I'm going to go ahead and change it back
I think that's looking good and I'll
also now go back and change the viewport
to be specifying the correct viewport
region by reel imitating these offsets
that we had in here and restoring it to
the correct oops
restoring it to the correct size and so
now I think if I can get rid of that
scissor test there as well and I can
also get rid of my clears and I should
now be able to do just a straightforward
use of of the shader to draw without any
of these other business right I should
now get a very clean result ok
so now we're seeing full screen red
that's great that's what I want to see
that's exactly right so now I'm going to
take out these gifts I'm going to allow
the textures to get set again and again
we're not reading from those textures so
at this point nothing should happen we
should just see a red screen and we do
so those are not interfering which is
great and now I want to go down here and
I want to pull off some of these other
things that we had first of all I'm
going to take out the f0 oops that's the
wrong f0 no that's right if 0 take out
the f0 there we go and now we should see
again that red
with no errors hopefully yep and so now
I'm going to take away the the rgba the
part that's actually doing the the
read/write and now we're going to see
whatever the actual color the shader is
producing which may be completely wrong
but okay that's not too bad actually
it's not what we want it's obviously
still a little wrong but our composites
actually working now and so that's good
news so now we just have to debug the
code in our shader which is where we
wanted to be yesterday when we just kind
of hacked it in if it had work the first
time if I'd remember that 1.0 in there
all the rest of our code was right
Cheers
this is water so I guess you don't
technically cheers but eh whatever so it
looks like the good news is almost
everything's working correctly the bad
news is we do have some work to do here
in terms of figuring out how to do this
blend properly and not messing anything
up so let's start with the basics let's
start with verifying that we can read
from our frame buffers and write the
results in without getting anything
particularly strange happening okay and
so the way that we're going to do that
is in here where I've got my result
color RGB what I want to do here is sort
of comment out the actual code that's
doing anything specific here and I want
to just take a look at what peel 0 is
right because that's that first frame
buffer that should just have exactly
what yet so you can see already we're
off to a bad start in terms of our data
because I'm looking at something here
that's clearly not the right color
values and so we've had a question to
ask ourselves first which is why is our
peel zero value coming out wrong and
what I wonder here is I want to make
sure that we're not it this is probably
an sRGB issue of some kind although I
don't really know so I want to I got
some work to do here to figure out why
we're seeing this sort of errant color
stuff going on so the first thing I want
to do is I want to take out the
possibility that any of this other
nonsense that we're doing is actually
causing a problem so what I want to do
is I'm just going to comment out well
not really comment
I'm going to f-zero out the code that
does the you know srgb conversion just
in case somehow those got set now they
shouldn't be set as far as I know who
although they may be getting said uh
more on that in a minute
actually yeah there's there's some
complexity there okay so you can see
that we get the right results there so
when I was about to say this shouldn't
do anything I was like glad I tested
like no it did do something so what I've
got to say when I kind of was like it
won't do anything and then immediately
thought oh wait maybe it will if you
remember correctly AMD
kind of gave us the middle finger a
little bit before because we had tried
to create our frame buffers with an sRGB
format but it wasn't letting us do that
when we were in multi sample land right
if you remember correctly however now
we've got a case where we're mixing
textures and frame buffers together and
the frame buffers that are doing the
rights those didn't have srgb
potentially set on them necessarily
right or they may have but we're setting
the flag here as if they weren't etc etc
and again that's because we weren't
getting a reliable answer from the AMD
driver it's supposed to support that
process for us it's supposed to support
multi sample sRGB but it simply wouldn't
let us create one we tried to create a
surface multiple times we tried a lot of
different ways and it never actually
worked so if we come back here and we
take a look at what we're seeing here
this OpenGL default frame buffer texture
format there that's kind of a big old
red flag there because I think that
default frame buffer textured format is
getting set to not be srgb and that's
going to cause us a bunch of problems so
since it's set to not srgb that means
the reads and writes won't actually go
through the sRGB pack path on the frame
buffer right but they will come in that
way on the read like we could have all
kinds of problems there so let's turn
this off first and then let's go ahead
and do our blend let's let's just not do
any of the of the suggested stuff we'll
let it go and let's just do our blend in
see if the blend is working roughly
correctly at that point right all right
so this is looking pretty good it's not
quite correct but it's looking close to
correct we have some issues to address
but some things are looking really nice
and I think we just have a little bit
more work to do in terms of our
representation you can even see that
those beautiful shadows are in there
correctly in a lot of places which is
kind of Awesome
but we definitely have some places where
we're getting some kind of nonsensical
results you can see those like with the
little heads the way they're kind of
disappearing in weird ways and all sorts
of other things like that so we have
some strange things there now some
things this scheme would not quite work
properly for and one of the things that
this scheme will not work properly for
is too many things layered on top of
each other that have alpha right because
we're only processing one layer of alpha
right now and for something like
particle systems that's not going to
necessarily cut it we probably don't
want to do depth peeling any more than
we're already doing it though in terms
of if we want support particle systems
what we should probably do is just
handle particle systems in a separate
pass or something like this so I'm not
too worried about that because we can
just split the particle systems off what
I'm more worried about is some things
that I think should be working and
aren't working so what we really want to
focus on now is a couple of those things
so for example right here you can see
something that I think should probably
be working but isn't and that is the
sort of halo around the hero's head
where we got kind of a bright region and
so what I think that bright region is is
again I think that's a failure to be
doing the srgb properly so I want to
kind of go through and clean up the sRGB
net and try to get that working a look a
little more cleanly we also have some
places where the shadows appear to be
munched and I think I don't really know
but my suspicion is yeah that's I think
what that is is just if two shadows
overlap each other the depth feeling
scheme again won't really work and the
reason that that def peeling scheme
won't work in that case is just because
we end up in a situation where we can't
peel that mate
right we've got too many things to peel
now one of the interesting things about
doing the DEF peeling is we're starting
to put ourselves in a much more powerful
situation in terms of making trade-offs
though there which means that even
though that sounds like it wouldn't work
with only two death peels I think we may
be able to instead of breaking our
shadows into a separate pass or
something like that we may actually be
able to do something more clever there
we may be able to do something fancy in
like a softie gentleman kind of a way
that will allow us to do something
clever with multiple overlapping shadows
such that even with only one def field
we may be able to get away with
something there so let's push forward a
little bit so what I want to do now is
this is looking pretty good and I don't
really think I want that multi sampling
to be happening anymore because it's
looking like the DEF peel is way better
than the multi sampling and even if we
went to three depth peels I think that
might not be too expensive if we had to
compared to most sample I don't really
know it's hard to know how much the
multi sample costs we haven't done a lot
of profiling of it so it's difficult to
say but what I would like to do here is
I would like to go ahead and if zero the
set temporarily so where we do this test
texture here what I'd like to do is just
say you know what forget it
let's just assume that you got that and
let's let's just go with with the let's
just go with the non multi sampling for
now so let's see what happens if these
get set to srgb I'm just curious what
we're going to end up seeing here and so
lo and behold it is exactly like I said
if we do have the srgb enabled properly
so that now we have srgb textures and an
sRGB frame buffer what you can see and
maybe this is a little bit too much to
ask from the streaming situation so I
guess when I say what you know you can
see I guess what I mean is I can see the
halo around the hero is now gone so the
srgb is now working properly which
exactly what I hope for and so that kind
of takes care of that and so now we're
just down to a few remaining problems
there's a couple of things here that I'd
like to take a look at and again I think
I know what most of it is but you know
we've got to take a closer look and also
see what we can do to fix it so what you
can see here is there's a few
weirdnesses we're getting some fringing
around the edges of the trees when
they're not over something we drew and
I'm not 100% certain why that is but I
suspect this has to do with how the
background colors are sums together and
what I suspect is happening there is
perhaps the clear color is not getting
modulated properly or something else is
happening they're not sure what's going
on but I do feel like that's probably a
problem so if in fact if you think about
what needs to happen now I think I could
pretty much just guess what's happening
there directly I don't think I need to
investigate it much further actually
because I think it's actually it seems
almost straightforward I think what's
going on there is the we've got two
buffers and we're adding them together
when the alpha value in the top buffer
is zero we need the color to also be
zero because we're treating it as a
premultiplied alpha and if we're
treating it as a premultiplied alpha
what's very important to get correct
there is that we can't have anywhere
where there's color in the buffer that
wasn't multiplied by its alpha value the
clear unfortunately will do exactly that
so that top buffer that front buffer
actually needs to be cleared to zero not
the background color because it's
supposed to be a premultiplied alpha
target right so I think what we actually
want to do here is in this targeting
next thing what we want to do is say
well only the final peel really wants to
do that so what we want to do here is
say where we do this clear with the
clear depth clear color situation what
we want to do is actually do this in
sort of a
predicated way where we're going to
actually clear to pure zero if it's the
top one because we don't want it to have
data anywhere that it should show
through to the bottom so what I'm going
to do here is just say if the target
index was greater than zero do the
normal clear but other
why don't right and so now hopefully I'm
hoping the trees will show up properly
the top and they do so that's great news
in fact if I rotate them here you can
see that that fringing is now gone and
so that's really good and so we're
starting to look really nice here
actually everything's pretty smooth and
so we're just you know honestly the only
thing I really see now is though is when
we've got multiple overlapping alpha you
know elements that seems to be a problem
so I guess what I'd like to do here is
I'd like to figure out a way to maybe
mitigate that problem so what I'm going
to sort of say is what if we were to say
something like instead of using the
depth test on alpha things maybe we
force alpha things not to go through the
depth test on the peel and we use their
alpha values to make a judgment call
about them or something right
basically what I'm saying is if we were
to draw if we were to draw alpha objects
in in a way that doesn't respect the
depth buffer you know with that would
that be sufficient
[Music]
so I want to think this out loud a
little bit because I guess we actually
have a number of different things we
could do here and I really don't know
which one of them would be the most
logical there's a really simple one we
can do but but there's a couple things
so first of all one thing that I'm not
really sure about is I'm not really sure
about whether you can kill just the
death right and that's so so you know I
don't really know I don't know if you
can do a predicated depth right so I
just let me just talk this out with you
so that you know where my head's at and
what I'm so that what I'll do will make
will make sense so here we are on day
382 and we need to deal with alpha plus
Z buffer
because that was actually looking pretty
nice and one of the interesting things
about it too I don't know if you can see
it because you know again there's some
bugs in it the other way but you'll
notice that now when are like those
little head particles for example when
those don't overlap we now have the full
range of alpha and similarly remember
how banded our shadows used to look now
our shadows are perfect so basically
with the exception of the overlapping
alpha kites we're really nailing it with
this depth feeling it just produces a
much better image and again we've done
nothing in terms of sorting here so
we're just letting the GPU do all the
dirty work
and that's pretty great so I really like
this one depth field solution but we
could even consider going to more than
one depth field but what I want to do
now is just think it through what we
might need to do because it seems like
depth field for for sprites is like
perfect right it seems like it does
everything correct so the only problem
is the def peel for alpha is not quite
good enough because when we have two
things that go over each other but for
sprites where the alphas just on the
edges it works great right so we have a
couple options here let's just talk
about them a little bit so first of all
let me just say what the standard
procedure is a lot of times when you're
dealing with transparent objects a lot
of times people Bend they're transparent
objects and draw their transparent
object in a separate path so what
happens is you know we could do
something like that and we have three
passes and we composite those passes so
for example pass zero here right is
going to be our front pixels and they're
the opaque pixels right so things that
have that the only alpha on them is
actually going to be when they blend out
to something you know and then there's
pass one which is our back pixels that
are opaque
and then path two would be the
transparent objects and that way we
would always basically like the
transparent objects would just kind of
mush together into that buffer and we
could try to do something clever there
with how we blend them together maybe
just always use additive blending for
our Translate stuff I don't know but
again you know just thinking about how
this would work we'd have problems here
if we didn't want to sort these guys
which I don't I want to let the z-buffer
do it we'd have problems there where we
have you know again those if we want to
do shadow sprite compositing I feel like
that's going to be a problem we probably
have to have two passes one for additive
one from subtractive or something like
this for when shadows overlap each other
and all these other sorts of things so
what I wonder is if we're doing the
peeling and we end up in a situation
where we're doing these passes is there
a way we could do something smarter I'm
just interested to know could we do
something smarter with the width the
depth where could we do something where
we use the fact that we know something's
alpha or not to do something smarter
when we're doing these passes when we're
doing the two def peel passes right
because let's take the case of two
shadows that overlap each other for
example right if we know we have
multiple shadows that are overlapping
each other we really only need to take
the darkest one right so if we knew that
the only thing that we ever had with
shadows all we'd have to do is go well
if I've got a shadow I could remember
the fact that this is a shadow
potentially right so write something
into the depth buffer or the spare you
know a piece of the buffer that we
weren't using like say the Alpha value
right because the the destination alpha
on past one is not used like here we use
the RGB and a of the front pixel right
this uses everything but here we only
care about the RGB a is not really used
right and right now the only reason
we're using
Elsa at all is because in that pass we
just save the alpha so we can back it
out later but we could just back it out
at the time we write it there's no need
to actually store it here so we could we
have a fourth channel where we could
store information that we're not using
and that information could be like a
total shadow amount or who knows what
right so we could do something there so
if we were if we were just trying to
render shadows there's no question that
we could do that relatively cleanly but
of course if we were just rendering
shadows we could also just do them in a
second pass right if we if we already
bend our shadows we could do them here
so I don't know that that gets us out of
anything we could just do a shadow pass
basically right and that would be fine
but I don't know let's once we broaden
it out so we've got shadows and we've
got fading right is basically the two
things that we've got at the moment so
we've got things that that want to
darken what's underneath them and we've
got things that want to fade out so they
are there but they're fading out right
so it makes me wonder
it makes me wonder if we were to just do
a three pass solution where we do past
zero pass one as we're doing now and we
basically force anything that isn't part
of an opaque object so you know anything
that's got an alpha value on the object
I'm trying to think if that would be
sufficient I mean other thing we could
do is just say the heck with it and do a
bunch of def peels right just really
force the GPU to do to go crazy and
basically do effectively n depth fields
which is kind of like doing the atomic
version where we just do for death deals
and say the heck with it
I don't know I do not know well I do
know is I should have crossed my V to
distinguish it from a two so I'm really
not sure what to do here I really don't
know I would like a better idea of what
I should do here and I'm just not sure
what the what the cleanest approach is
because I don't know yet I'm curious to
just see if we could set this up to set
an arbitrary number of depth feels right
so I'm wondering what would happen if I
did that so let's say that we wanted to
do you know more depth deals than the
amount that we're currently doing you
know and so if we were going to do more
depth deals
I guess one thing that's kind of a
little bit interesting is I wonder if we
don't if we really don't have to do it
quite the way I was doing it because one
of the things with deaf peals is we need
to separate we need to separate deaf
buffers but do we really need to
separate frame buffers because I don't
think we actually do I think we can just
keep accumulating into a separate frame
buffer going from front to back and that
would allow us to not have to do a final
composite at all right to be clear about
what I'm talking about if we were to
draw the first frame the first peel we
know that's the front pixel right if we
simply drew onto the same frame buffer
again if we just draw to this frame
buffer again using the the depth peel
technique so we have a separate depth
buffer but if we just threw it on again
I feel like we could just use
destination alpha blending to do the
blend at that point all we do is use the
destinations alpha value to do one minus
whatever the value we're writing in and
write to the frame buffer using a
standard blend mode right using standard
blending and I feel like that would
allow us to accumulate depth field as
many times as we want and furthermore we
could actually make that be parameterize
on the frame rate so as the frame rate
degrades we'd you know on slower
machines we draw a fewer times and you
to have more artifacts but as if you
were on a higher-end machine it would do
more depth passes and improve the
quality does that make sense again I
don't really know if this is the
technique that anyone uses but it's just
kind of interesting
I feel like it's it's interesting I kind
of like it I kind of just want to go
with it
so let's imagine that we were going to
do that and let's imagine so so let's
pretend that that's basically just how
the renderer worked is we just keep
accumulating and we draw as many times
as we feel like we can based on the
quality of the machine that we're
running on so maybe we support like you
know eight separate depth peels right so
it's basically doing the same number of
fills as the multi sample one was but
now with perfect perfect alpha
compositing you know on a fast card we
could just go ahead and do that on a car
that was really slow maybe we only do
two or three depth fields and you know
occasionally you see some artifacts when
you have lots of things on top of each
other or something like this it's just
an interesting idea it's kind of like it
and so I'm gonna try it I don't have
anything else to say about it other than
that that I find it interesting and I
like experimenting with things that I
find interesting
so maybe what I'll do is I'll just say
that this max rendered target index is
is just always kind of going to be two
at this point because really what we're
talking about here is we're just going
to have like a ping-pong buffer scenario
and so when we do when we create these
we're actually not going to create a
separate frame buffer every time we're
just going to create the frame that
we're just going to create one image
frame buffer and the only thing that
we're really going to be doing having
more of is the is the depth buffer so
we're going to have to death buffers but
we're only going to have one image
buffer if that makes sense so let's see
what happens if we do that so what I'm
going to do here is say okay we're going
to take the the image buffer here which
is this part this this bit right here
and I'm just going to say instead of
calling
text image 2d I'm going to skip this
part of it this fine textured text
handle 0 gen textures thing I'm just
going to skip this part of creating this
image and I'm always well you know what
I'll even leave that in for now because
I guess I don't have to get rid of the
creation of it we can get rid of
creation later when I verify this to the
Technic I want to use what I'm going to
do is when we call GL frame vertex QD
rather than using the texture handle 0
that we actually created for this frame
buffer I'm actually going to use the
global frame buffer texture handle for
slot 0 always so we're always drawing to
the same color buffer we're not always
drawing to the same depth buffer right
that's basically all we're talking about
here so this way we can kind of swap
which one we're drawing to based on
which death buffer we want to use but
we're not going to change which color
buffer we write to so we write the first
one in and then we have that buffer we
switch to the other one so that we can
read from the the texture buffer and
then we can keep ping-ponging back and
forth and I think that it just work
alright so then the other thing that I
want to do is just change this shader
then to skip the read and just to just
all it's going to do is just bring just
that one basic texture to the front so
this stuff now would go away basically
and all we're going to do is we're going
to say hey let's take the the fragment
color from just one of the buffers right
so skip all that stuff and just say
result color equal to0 that's all we're
going to do right alright so now what we
need to do is we since since we're only
going to see frame buffer 1 we need to
now turn on blending and actually make
what I just said a reality so what we
need to do here is we need to re-enable
blending because we need to actually you
know operate on the frame buffer and so
we need to do is set the GL blend func
and we need to set it now to something a
little more sensible than this right so
the first time through we want to just
write it something like this basically
so we're not we have blending on but the
function actually doesn't do any
blending and in fact I guess what we
could do is actually disable the blend
entirely and set the other blends
function correctly I don't know how we
want to do this it's tough to say but
anyway we could disable the blend here
and then later switch it back on and so
to switch it back on what I'm going to
do here is say okay let's go to here so
when we end the peels right so we do the
begin peels and then feels when we jump
back to do this peel count here what I
want to do is it's the first peel and
we're going through right then we do
want to do no blending when it's the
second peel that we're coming through we
want to enable blending and we want to
set the blend function to be something
that's going to take the background the
pixels that are behind the ones and
blend them in with a destination alpha
so what we want to do there is say well
we want one - destination alpha for
whatever is currently coming in so the
background pixel is going to take it's
going to take the frame buffer which is
now the foreground pixel right thing
that's in front of us we're going to
modulate ourselves by that destination
alpha and then we're going to just take
whatever is in the front buffer is just
already pre multiplied so that we could
just take right and draw so that should
composite on top in theory and then what
we have to do is when we are so when
we're oh I put that in the wrong place
sorry this is actually the first time it
comes through it hits NPL so now it
needs to switch to the mode for the
second peel right so here we go so now
what I'm expecting is something kind of
similar to what we have before it's not
quite right here so I didn't I didn't
quite do it correctly but you're getting
closer so if we enable blend and we have
1 minus s alpha GL 1 here I'm going to
have to figure out why we're not quite
getting what I expect there and we are
drawing with no blending here correct so
that in theory should be filling the
destination alpha channel and we are
clearing the destination alpha to 0 as
well so that should be correct as far as
I know seems right to me but we're
definitely not getting what I would have
expected so what I would have expected
here is is basically the same thing we
had before what's a little weird about
it is we are getting sort of that in a
couple places so it's a little weird
because we're getting sort of that and
sort of not which is a little confusing
because I would have expected it to be
more wrong than that but at the moment
yeah at the moment I'm definitely seeing
some things that are like those
artifacts weren't there in the other
path and we should be able to get
literally exactly the same thing that we
got in the other path and so I want to
just figure out what I messed up there
because I definitely messed up something
so let's see here well I guess one thing
so here's one problem we don't want to
clear the other buffer anymore because
we only have one color buffer now
so we only want to set up we only want
to do the clear at all like this clear
needs to not happen right so we only
want to clear the depth buffer on any
buffers after the first buffer we don't
want to clear the color buffer because
that's just erroneous right now that
didn't help us at all but you know that
that was one of the artifacts we fixed
before us we have to keep that in place
so let's see now
so when we are doing those that seems
like it would be reasonable we're
drawing to the first frame buffer first
and we are drawing with blend disabled
which is what I would expect when we hit
the first set appeals we're not blending
so we should fill the buffer up with
colors I guess one thing I can try here
is just disable everything in the second
pass so what I can do is I can just say
hey you know what let's take a GL blend
song of zero one so it doesn't change
what's in the destination and that
should give me a little bit of a better
view of what got written first right so
that to me looks like exactly what I
wanted to see in that first frame buffer
so I don't see anything particularly odd
there to be concerned about so it looks
like it's the second pass that's really
doing the weird stuff whatever that
weird stuff is so I'm going to go ahead
and now do the opposite of what I just
did I'm going to set it so that now I
only see the second pass so this will
only draw what's in the second pass I
won't see anything that was in the first
pass and so looking at these honestly
again
that that looks correct
ah I know why I can't do this so because
I only want to render once the blend I
only want to render the closest thing in
right so that I can't just render
everything because the z-buffer is still
doing the sort and I only want to blend
the one that actually passes the the
front most pass right so I really don't
have the ability to do exactly what I
wanted to do which is to just sum into a
single color buffer I need to color
buffers all right so I do need to do the
death peel the same way that I was doing
it basically always
so if I want to do successive summations
I need to smack down the color buffers
so that they can be added together in
that way so I don't think there's any
way to do an incremental version like
that at the very least I would have to
do every time I did a depth peel I could
smack it down into the existing depth
peel but into the existing like
summation but I do have to use one extra
color buffer all the time right
I don't have the option of sort of doing
the I don't have the ability to do the
sort of cheesy always some into one
buffer thing because I need to let the Z
buffer do the sort every time yeah so
unfortunately that means I can't quite
go infinite like I was thinking before
without having a smack down you know a
thing that actually smooches down to
takes two color buffers and merges them
at the end of every peel that's not the
end of the world but it is more
expensive right so I'm trying to think
of how I want to do this it's obviously
more efficient to just do it in one so I
think what I might do then is I think
what I might do is say let's suppose we
want to do us four depth fields or
something right so I set max friend
wrote argot in next to three and I
generate that many of these buffers it's
more buffers than we actually need but
I'm just going to try it for now they
get cleared out so what I want to do
here is I want to say if render target
index equals max render target index
then we're at the last one and that's
make clear all the rest of them we got
cleared to zero I think it's how we want
it right then what I do here is I'd say
well okay we always want to bind the
peel count buffer whichever buffer that
is when we come through here
and we always want to pull when we when
we are doing that death test we always
want to pull from whatever the previous
rounds depth buffer was so in here where
we're doing peeling oh so we're already
and we're already doing that so that
would produce a number of of those
buffers and what we could do here is we
could do a four I loop right where we
set the active texture so we could say
oh you know peel index Max render target
index and we just set it this way so
that like sets up all of the peels
properly and we could wind down the
peels in the same way so we just say
like okay you know nuke the peels the
same I don't really know if I need to do
that or not
I never sure nope until what state needs
to get unset but you know you get the
idea so we could do something like this
and that would give us you know as many
of those as we wanted right we could we
could just do as many as you wanted but
the only downside there is that we do
then need to go like okay we need a
bunch of different samplers here right
we need all of these additional samplers
to get those additional depth feels
right so then we end up having to do you
know multiple peels there and I think in
this case if we always are just doing
the summation everything is modulated by
its alpha so I feel like only the final
peel needs to actually be the one that
gets the fix up for the Alpha I believe
right so oops
so we've got a modulator on there we
don't care about that so much so we're
adding peel we're adding each of these
peels together because those are all
they should all be well now so each one
of them is pre modulated by its own
alpha but it's not modulated by anyone
elses alpha so we need to add them
together in sort of a like you know
progressive fashion here so we need to
do is say well peel 0 is the color that
it should be so we need to modulae
what's underneath it by 1 minus PL alpha
right so everything that's underneath
peel 0 gets modulated by peeled zeros
alpha now everything that's under it
also happens to be like peel 1 right RGB
which now also has to modulate everyone
else by the inverse of its alpha right
so 1 minus peel ones alpha and you can
see how this kind of goes right so maybe
what we want to do here is kind of build
it up from the bottom to make it a
little cleaner to read so what we want
to do is say all right we know that peel
3 we've already adjusted the RGB of it
to be correct so we know that our result
color can start out being equal to peel
3 which is the bottom most of the layers
that we're processing so the next what
we do is we lever up one we say peel to
RGB we'll add that in and we'll take
whatever the thing is that we had
previously gathered and we'll modulate
that right then we'll do that
again and then we'll do that one more
time
and so in that way we sort of like take
the bottom one composited composite
composite it as if we're basically doing
the blending ourselves here
right so now of course we've got to
debug this nonsense that I've just made
but hopefully that won't be too hard all
right so let's just assume that this is
pretty reasonable here so we start with
peel threes colors we got a like in case
we do want to turn back on this stuff
let's go ahead and make sure that's
correct okay so we sample these peels
out here we're good to go I guess one of
the things is we've got to make sure
that all of these are correct and what I
want to do here is I just want to I just
want to go ahead and say like maybe
these things were going to be a little
bit more careful about now so I'm going
to go ahead and get rid of these parts
we don't use like so and I'm going to
put in here
this is maybe an array so in the OpenGL
program I'm going to call this oh well
you know what we still need a depth
sampler for the other one and what I'm
going to do here is I'm going to have a
peel sampler and make four of those now
we could actually use in a raid property
for these actually but I'm not going to
do that at the moment okay so we're
going to put these down here because
they're kind of special at this point
and what I'm going to do is I'm just
going to make it so that we kind of need
what I want to do at this point is I
want some way
setting these locations in a more useful
fashion because like right now we don't
really have the ability to do something
sensible with the OpenGL program in
terms of doing those settings right and
so what you'll notice is we kind of have
two different types of settings here if
we go if we go kind of look at how this
is working and see what happens in use
the program begin you can see that we've
got you know like a couple different
things that we've set here right and
then we've got these also these vertex
outside pointers which are sort of a
separate thing now the vertex that ships
we don't really change much nor do we
change the program handle much so those
can kind of say but if you look at
what's happening here we kind of have
two different programs right we've got
the OpenGL or we've got the the what's
the word for it V bias program you know
and then we've got the peel peel
composite program and they really now
are completely divergent right like this
wants those and this wants this right so
what we'd like to do is we'd like to
have some way ideally if we're going to
do a lot of these we'd probably want
some abstraction for this where we can
kind of say here's what each one takes
but in this case since there's so
divergent I don't know that I really
care about that so I'll probably just
make two different versions of the use
program thing right it doesn't seem like
it really makes much sense to do
anything fancier than that at the moment
at least I can't think of a reason why
we would if we have lots and lots of
shaders you'd want to figure out some
way of cleaning that up so that you
didn't have to constantly be fussing
with it but I don't really see that
being particularly useful thing to do at
the moment because we really just don't
have enough stuff to make that be
necessary right
so even in this case I think I may just
do it like this well you know what here
we'll do it like this or maybe like that
so since we've got some shared stuff
here let's just target the shared stuff
and make that easier and then in here
we'll actually call these what they are
you bias program you bias program
geocomposite program right and so now
what I want to do is say all right when
we do use program begin and use program
ends then in this in this sort of model
they're going to pass the common part
and then in here we just have use
programs again use program end for
basically like the other everyone else
right so we say ok we've got the V bias
program and you know what use program
end is the same for everybody so I guess
that one doesn't really matter so we
really just have a different use program
begin and we've got two different news
program begins we've got one for the V
bias program and one for the peel
composite program and both of them want
to do use program begin for the common
section and one of the nice things here
is render setup doesn't need to happen
for the comments section so actually I
think that doesn't get a pass through
only this one gets a pass through and
now we can eliminate that dead version
of the setup that was happening before
which is kind of nice too so then what
we can do is say alright we know that we
we know exactly what we're doing here we
can just say you know peel sampler
exactly can you do it this way so this
way no matter what we set that to that's
how many you know peels it'll do and you
know or we could parameterize with
something else later if we want to be
variable like I was talking about before
and then in the case of the Z bias
program now we've got all this other
nonsense that gets set and that one and
it can kind of come down here into a
place where it makes more sense right so
now that's looking much nicer right much
much nicer and I don't think we really
have to change much in the rest of the
code we now can get rid of the dead code
here of the setup that we were passing
as a dummy variable because now that
won't happen which is nice
and
and get rid of that and so now we need
to do is just this is a device program
not a regular program so that's fine and
these are always just going to be on
common right so that's all good
there we go and now what we want to do
is is these folks want to write directly
into their special kind of programs
that's for whatever they do and so you
know a couple of these will be common
going into the comment section such as
that the handle and the vertex IDs like
these like so and so that we could also
pull out right we could make that be
something that's shared between them I'm
not going to do that just yet
because it seems like kind of a waste of
that for a little bit but you know we do
this one more time and it probably would
start to make some sense you know all
right uh so peel composite program like
there we go and so now we've got a bunch
of the bugging work to do to get this to
work properly you can see we're still
drawing okay for the front buffer but
our peel composite is not doing anything
right which is fine right we we kind of
hack that stuff in there we need to be a
little more careful about what we're
doing so let's go ahead and and check
first of all I'm just going to go ahead
and rename this path here I want to look
at what each of the paths looks like so
here's peel 0 right that's the that's
the first peel there let's look at peel
again that looks pretty reasonable
nothing super out of the ordinary
we're still - not great not great so
what's going on with our peel - here oh
right we're not drawing anything to
those yet so this has to be a little bit
a little bit more sensible so peel count
I'm going to change the peel index at
the moment so let's go ahead and let's
let's fix that here to be peel index and
so when this goes through and does peel
indexed here what I want to do now is I
want this to be able to go higher so
effectively this will just keep looping
when we do open when we hit the end
we're going to keep looking looping
until the peel index reaches the final
you know the final render target so the
first time through it'll be at 0 second
time 3 will be at 1 next time it'll be 2
next it'll be a 3 and that'll be the end
and it'll flip to the last one I think
we want to wait to 1 after that if I'm
not mistaken because we want to draw to
each buffer so we actually want to do
the loop each time through so we want to
do like if it's less than or equal to
the max vendor target do this right and
then as soon as it exceeds that then we
will assert that that we're at that last
one
no no I'm incorrect because when we come
through here we actually increment it's
on the end so we want to wait till we
get to that last one and we've done the
last one then we are actually done and
we flip back to zero okay so let's see
what peel two looks like now there's
peel 2 again it's even further drilling
backwards and let's finally take a look
at now at the last view which is peel 3
so there's peel 3 and you can see it
gets really pretty far back
and so that's good news because again
like you know if only if it only takes
for depth deals to do a good composite
yeah I'm pretty happy with that
ok so we've got four valid peels what we
don't have is a compositor that works at
all our compositor is complete garbage
right now we can tell that because all
we see is a black screen and that's not
a very compelling composite if we were
to ship a game that just consisted of a
black screen with a framerate counter
while certain streamers would be very
happy to see that it hits 60 frames a
second perhaps they would not be very
happy with the fact that it was an
entirely black screen you may not be
surprised here as well that's not that
hard to hit 6 period second for the
black tree not that I'm certain that
some people couldn't quite do it so for
example I'm quite certain that a number
of games you see these days could could
manage to somehow still not hit 60
frames a second with a black screen but
you know what you can do let's go ahead
and take a look at what we messed up
here so I'm interested to know what's
going on it would appear and I guess I
don't know for sure but it would appear
that something is a bit suspicious
because I don't really understand when I
run this I'm just a little perplexed
because I'm looking at it here and I see
the this is it's not a completely black
screen the framerate counter is there
so everything that's drawn at the end is
working and if I look at the peeled zero
I see that framerate counter on PL zero
which is exactly where I would have
expected it it's not there on peel 1
right it's not there on peel - yeah and
it's not there on peel 3 so what's
interesting to me is how we're ending up
with black pixels when somehow the
framerate counter still shows through
properly and that's on peel 0 so if we
were just copying peel 0 in I would have
expected to see everything on peel 0 not
just the frame rate counter that's not
what I'm seeing so it's a bit odd to me
so this ought to be interesting let's
jump back here a second I just want to
make sure we are still creating all
those textures we are so that's good
just make sure of what was happening
there so let's let's hop down to
composite compile peel composite and
take a look at what I did for the code
here because I probably made some stupid
mistakes here if we're lucky they won't
be too hard to spot so let's take a look
at what we're doing here's our result
color in our result color just is a
successive it's a series of successive
blends with its you know the underlying
peel layers pretty pretty much right off
the bat what I'm going to do the same
sort of debugging I was doing before I'm
going to start by just looking at the
different peels see whether or not like
getting them right so here's me trying
to copy just peel 0 straight across and
I want to see what I'm getting so it's
interesting about this is if I copy peel
0 straight across I see effectively just
nothing on the screen which is not at
all what I would have expected right so
it's a little bit weird I don't really
understand what I'm seeing now I want to
take a look at what the alpha value is
because I don't know if blending is
still on
but let me just set the Alpha value to 1
because I really don't know what's going
on there right again like I just really
don't know so let me take a look at peel
1 so everything is basically black all
of our peels that we were just viewing
we're not actually getting them but we
are getting the frame rate counter which
is mystifying at best all of the peels
are black except for the frame rate
counter appears to be basically what
we're looking at right okay so how are
we getting that how is that happening
right what are we seeing here I have no
idea whatsoever because taking this
stuff out of the equation yeah I don't
know what's going on now what I could do
too is I could it's zero this stuff out
in case maybe there's some kind of a
NAND situation going on but even that I
don't think should have affected it I
don't anticipate that being a problem
I'm now going to go ahead and just take
it one step further I'm going to force
the color to read to verify that I'm
even seeing what I think I'm seeing in
this case so that's good so we are
actually filling the screen with what
the results are here it's just somehow
when we are sampling these actual
texture peels we're really getting
something that somehow only drew maybe
boggles the mind it's obviously
something that when I see it I'll be
like Oh duh but I really don't know
where it's coming from
because I don't understand how I'm
seeing that frame rate counter player
you know plain as day when if I draw the
frame buffers themselves I'm seeing all
the actual additional data in there
right it's a bit strange so the question
is how are we how is that happening
what's going on there so you can see me
binding the textures here I'm going
through each of the peels and I'm
binding the textures to the successive
texture units by using global frame
buffer textures with the peel index
which I believe is again correct I don't
think there's any
usual about that and I am Chi think
seeing those happen properly I'm going
to take a look at the used program begin
to see if there's anything weird going
on there that's setting things up
exactly the way I would have expected
and again it's just setting the various
peel samplers to to be what they are
right there's nothing again nothing
weird going on there we can bear who
through you can clearly verify that the
I don't know
so coming through here we also expect
blending to be disabled at this time
I'll double-check that it's disabled so
I'm going to go ahead and disable the
blend but I don't see what that would
have to do with anything and again it
doesn't have anything it doesn't do
anything which is what I would have
expected when we bind frame buffer zero
we should be writing clear of anything
we shouldn't be having any weirdness
there as far as I can imagine so this is
a real a real bizarre one I cannot could
not say really what's going on there if
we saw nothing I would have some
theories the fact that I see something
makes it pretty strange I'm going to go
ahead and regress now again I'm just
kind of grasping at straws here I have
no idea what's going on so what I'm
going to do here is I'm just going to go
ahead and gather up just that just the
very first texture
didn't quite it didn't tell me what
failed oh but I know what failed those
all need to be defined obviously you
can't just start talking about variables
that don't exist yet
so here is one that literally only
samples from the peel 0 sampler at that
frag UV and then it goes out and it
draws it right with this so what's
interesting about this to me what's
interesting about this to me is I'm
wondering if this is just a problem with
wrap around effectively so what I'm
interested what I'm interested to know
here is so if I turn on that frame
buffer blit and I look at what the frame
buffers are via that path right what we
know is that if I go via that path I see
a correct image this is what I expect to
be in peel 0 the fact that I don't get
anything when I come through this path
suggests to me that maybe I'm setting
some state that is not getting properly
unset later right so basically what I'm
wondering is let's suppose that I was to
do this first right so I'm just going to
do this first and then I'm still going
to do the blitt at the end I want to
know what I see now if I look at peels
are okay so what we're seeing I don't
know if you can see it but there's a
flash at the beginning of the correct
stuff and then it turns to incorrect
stuff and so what I think is happening
is the first frame is working properly
but we're leaving some state set that
wraps around to the next run of the
program that then causes us to fail the
next time through so I think we're just
leaving something set that we can't
leave
and so that's I think all we're really
chasing here so let's see if we can
figure out what's going on
with that with with regards to that so
the another question might be are we
doing these clears correctly every time
I think we are so I that doesn't look
particularly to fish so let's let's talk
about this here for a little bit let's
see what's going on we bind our frame
buffers in here we're doing our use
program begin use program and correctly
there we're setting our active textures
so I'm wondering if maybe it's just you
know what I think it is I think what
it's we're not setting the active
texture again so I think what's
happening is here right this active
texture where we used to go backwards so
it would set the active texture to zero
at the end we now aren't doing that so I
bet that was the only problem if that
active texture is not getting set yeah
so there we go
so that was the only problem with that
that that's a typical problem in OpenGL
because it's got so much state you know
you set something wrong and it carries
over the next frame and suddenly you get
these weird bugs you are expecting so
that's the okay par for the course no
real no real biggie there so let's go
ahead and allow our reads to continue
now and we'll enable this slowly one
step at a time to try and get back to
now to the composite pass and see what
happens so here we're going to run again
we're still seeing only buffer zero but
that's good because we're reading from
all of them doesn't seem like there's
any big problems happening there I'm
going to turn off the like sort of over
right at the end and here we go let's go
ahead and run that so now in theory we
are actually compositing we don't know
if we're compositing properly but we are
at least trying to composite and what
we're seeing here is it doesn't look
particularly good for us like it looks
like we're really only getting two
levels of it basically looks the same as
when we only composite it twice so I
think I'm not really doing the other
alpha composites properly possibly
because I'm not doing the premultiplied
alpha correctly but I'm not sure
so we need to take a little bit closer
look at that we also then need to
straighten out our shader SIM text read
sRGB let me go ahead and take a look by
the way at that caters semtex read srgb
that should be getting set correctly now
I believe so I think we can re-enable
this as well let's just double check
yeah
so now I think we're doing everything
it's except for actually respecting
those peel composites they're not
working properly and I am not sure why I
think I've got this set up properly but
I could be very wrong about that but
just to walk you through it again if you
imagine what's happening here I'm saying
whatever the third peel is we start with
that color
we then blend two on top of that so we
we take whatever the value was of two we
modulate away whatever the value of
three was there by the inverse of that
alpha of whatever pl2 was we then take
peel one and we do the same thing we put
that on top of whatever the combination
the resulting combination of the
previous view was and then finally again
we at the very end we just go ahead and
do that one more time four peels zero
and I feel like that should be doing the
compositing properly but I don't really
know so let's make sure we're creating
the peels the way that I think we should
be because if the Alpha values are
incorrect that would certainly do it
right so let's see what we're doing here
if we are doing depth feeling we we bind
whatever the previous depth texture was
obviously and that's fine
and that's what we would expect when we
do the Z bias depth field here program
that is using a different program we
could check to see whether that program
is correct we need to see blending
should always be off so GL blend should
always be off I think and it does look
like it is so that's fine
[Music]
and it's disabled entirely anyways it
doesn't even matter what the Alpha
function what the blend function
actually is so let's take a look at the
peeling program I don't know if maybe
there was something in there that could
have been wrong
obviously we discard the discard looks
like it was doing the right thing the
Alpha values get passed through without
the fog but but that seems fine I mean
that looks pretty reasonable that looks
like it should be writing out fair alpha
values and so I'm not really sure so you
know there is one more problem that we
have here that I'm not sure exactly how
we would mitigate it
so there is one more problem we have and
this could be the problem that we're
actually seeing in fact now that I think
about it so the other problem that we
have and this one's a little trickier
is when we are depth peeling we don't
really handle the case where two things
are at exactly the same depth and just
right on top of each other right and in
this case the only places that we're
really seeing errors right now are
exactly those cases right that is
exactly what we're seeing
like basically everywhere our shadows
are actually correct except where the V
values are identical I think don't quote
me on that but I think that's exactly
what we're seeing so in that case the
depth peeling isn't smart enough to
figure out what to do right because if
everything is at the same Z value you
would have that problem so let's just
see
I'm just curious for sake of argument
let's suppose that we went into the
particle systems for example where we do
see errors currently where those things
overlap and if we were to say well okay
what if we jittered the Z values of
those things so that they weren't
exactly at the exact same C so when we
do this push fit map call for example
here we're passing this p-value down the
p-values that we're using I yeah is it's
always but we're only operating in x and
y it never changes to z right so when
things respond the Z value is always set
to zero right you can see it here it's
never set to anything else so if we were
just to set the Z value randomly instead
like so would we get a more correct
behavior with our particles that's what
I'm interested in seeing right and it's
hard to say it still looks like they
have the similar problem I don't know if
that's enough separation let's just try
it with something really absurd
well so I don't know that still looks
kind of wrong so I'm wondering if we
really if we've just got a bug that's
separate from that because it does kind
of look like when they it looks like
whenever they pass through each other
you still get that bug and I don't know
I don't think that's the Z because I'm
now setting the Z randomly right for at
least I tried to maybe that's not
getting used I don't know
but I think it is because it's just
setting it's just using the particle Z
and so I feel like it's kind of correct
there like I feel like that's going to
use that's three value it's not a fair
test because I mean it's possible that
that's not really moving the Z values
like I would have wanted it to do
hmm
so I think we may need a more controlled
test case for this because I think it's
going to be too hard to guess what's
going on here with that a little bit
more context it does seem like you know
I feel like we definitely would have a
bug in the in the shadow case where the
Z values would be basically the same so
I do feel like that might be part of
what we're seeing in some cases but it
feels to me like we're getting bugs in
places where the Z value isn't
necessarily the same and so that feels
like not really what should be happening
I also feel like now that our that we're
using correct like we're actually using
correct v our particle spawn should be
fixed to you know instead of spawning up
in Y which is what they were doing
before they should spawn up in Z right
because that was what was supposed to be
happening and we were only using Y
because we didn't really have real V so
now that we have real V I feel like our
particles should be spawning upwards so
there they are right so that's better
right and so since we kind of want a
little bit of jitter there I feel like
we probably want to give it some more
like this
to know why I'm tuning this right now
obviously it's just you know sometimes
it's hard to wait why did we why is this
doing seven times that what why wouldn't
you just do why wouldn't you just make
that be seven I don't know what the deal
is with that but anywhere we're going to
fix that as well
so that's more correct right that's like
what the what it should actually be
doing there I feel like they want a lot
more poof to that they want to let
they're gonna want to if we're honest
now granted they should really not be
spawning a bunch of heads you know
that's true but if you imagine them
spawning something reasonable
I like how they fall down to the grant
to the floor below I wonder if we went
downstairs if we would just have stuff
falling through the floor that we would
then see like just coming at us like
from above I don't know if it makes it
down here it doesn't look like it does
oh yeah there's some over in the corner
pretty soon going to have to actually
write some code to let this guy move
around for real it's getting to be kind
of a world that you want to actually
explore and build some stuff in I hate
to say it I hate to say it but it's kind
of true um so yeah so I think we just
aren't doing the compositing math
correctly I think I think that's mostly
our problem here
and you can see when this guy jumps
behind the hero which I don't know if
you can see this but you get fringing on
him so it kind of feels like we're still
only getting one depth feel instead of
four and I don't think that the Z values
being equal can necessarily account for
that and maybe it can like maybe all of
those bugs are just because the Z values
are are the same but I don't know if
that's really plausible I you know it
seems probably a little bit not that
plausible so I want to see here let's
suppose that I stopped blending in any
of these other colors here
so that does not fill me with confidence
because the back peel should have
something in it and I'm asking anything
so ok let's turn off the invert the back
alpha you know computation so I'm seeing
nothing for PL 3 right I'm seeing I'm
seeing literally nothing if I just write
PL 3 I see nothing that is not good
what about peel - I see nothing for peel
2 so for some reason I'm not imagining
things when I say that it's like we only
have two peels because we only seem to
have two fields which ain't great so
let's see here we create some number of
render targets and those render targets
are supposed to all be roughly
equivalent we then go through and clear
all of them to zero except for the very
last one which again I I think is
correct but we're not we must not be
doing something right because you know
if we should at least see that clear
color come through right I mean it's
real weird so yeah when we're coming
through here any time to peel index 0 1
2 it should come through here do the
loop draw in there and set peeling equal
true and so when we're doing the rest of
this stuff in theory that should draw
right I mean I think that you know that
should be what's going on I don't know
maybe that's not what's going on
[Music]
I feel like feel active texture should
always be getting set correctly now
because we restore it at the end like we
should so that seems okay I don't see
why we would be having a problem with
that I would like to know what happens
if I just blip them directly so there's
steel zero
subscribe plz that's just just
straight-up weird so if I look at the
peeled here I am getting them so it's
like I'm not able to read from those
textures I wonder if that has something
to do with this card like is it possible
that this card is so old it can only
read from two textures at once I mean
that's really old but but that could be
the other problem is maybe I'm setting
it up wrong so maybe like I'm asking
when I do that shader compiled I'm
asking for the wrong name or something
or using the wrong is it are these
written wrong peels 0 1 2 3 sampler
let's let's just I mean I let's just
look at what that does when we compile
it right because I don't know let's just
hop in here and see what we get
so peel zero sampler and peel one
sampler got non values but those were
the two that we're working but what is
this
oh that's okay that's because we comment
easier than that all right that's fine
so yeah so now we know that's definitely
not the case because when it compiled it
it only did a read from one texture
right it compiled those other words out
entirely so it ain't that right so let's
see here when we come through we don't
want to be here we want to be back in
here so when we use this program let's
see if we're doing something stupid in
the binder
hello there we go
oops I wanted to look at that so here we
go we're going to call this successively
with the GL uniform is that the correct
GL uniform it looks like it is because
that's how we're binding these right so
that seems right where we just bind each
one to successively incrementing values
and then we just use like geo texture
plus the peel index to bind
sure seems right to me
the fact that it seems right doesn't
super help us because it's seeming right
and it being right are two very
different things and we are seeing a
black screen so what's going on why can
we only read from samplers 0 &amp; 1 and
when we read from 2 or 3 even if they're
the only sampler we see nothing is this
something that we've done incorrectly
when we were storing the values at the
beginning because you know we're kind of
a little bit legacy at this point when
we do the the render target index stuff
you know we do were we storing these
values in an inappropriate way so global
frame buffer textures global frame
buffer depth you know these get assigned
in some kind of weird way that doesn't
work properly or you know who knows what
here I guess I can check that pretty
easily by just looking at what that
value actually is that would that would
be pretty straightforward so if I came
in here I guess I could check this
anywhere don't have to check it at the
bind time but I'm going to check out the
bind time anyway so that comes through
here and and we're taking a look at what
we're binding
what does global flame buffer textures
look like I mean that looks pretty solid
right seven nine eleven and thirteen is
exactly if they were just getting
incremented if it's getting allocated in
order that's exactly what you would
expect to see so for some reason right I
can I can lit it here and if I blitt it
it's good if I copy it directly it's not
good
so one thing I do worry about a little
bit is we're not setting the myth map
so I mean we shouldn't really be getting
I'm just going to go ahead and make sure
these get set so you know one thing that
could be happy I don't see why it would
only happen for one and not the other
one is we could be getting a situation
where it tries to do mipmap sampling and
since there are no nip levels it doesn't
properly do that
yes so I don't know what's going on with
that that's a good question
so what I want to do here is again when
we're creating these I just want to make
sure that when we sample from them
they're not getting MIT mapped because
we don't generate any MIT maps for them
it shouldn't have mattered because if
we're seeing that none of them should be
getting that mapped but you know I don't
know I'm just worried about it so that
I'm going to do that anyway
so in here where we do after we've bound
the texture I'm going to set that
parameter just to ensure that it's never
can never do that
all right so that just basically turns
off any possible magnification or
magnification filters and we'll see what
happens I don't feel like that should
have anything to do with it but I just I
don't know okay apparently it did I have
no explanation for why that was the case
I can only tell you that apparently
those textures were trying to MIT and
the other ones weren't or these got set
somehow on textures on the other texture
handles prior that's really weird but
turning off MIT fetches it must have
just been mismatches yeah so okay that's
fine I guess so coming through here
let's just go ahead and and see if we
can re-enable some of these fetches here
so now can I fetch three correctly I'm
just wondering
so that looks like three pretty pretty
good can I re enable the alpha
adjustment for the background three I
can so that's good and then I don't
really know if that should be happening
we need to think about that math look
better what happens if I actually come
in here and try to do the full blend and
and did that does that work it does
appear to work and you know everything
looks quite nice doesn't it
I got to tell you what if we were to
turn off our render volumes here have
you have you have you wondered that
question if I was to just end if that
looks like we still are drawing that one
right there but that's looking like a
pretty respectable rendering right now
to be completely honest with you
that's looking pretty darn good folks
and I do think now we could play with
that effect that I wanted to play with
too which is that that effect right
there right and so what I'm interested
to see now is since we can play with
alpha a little bit more suppose I was to
make that be an outlet clip plane now
and so the way that we would do that
right is the same way we were doing the
fog before and so you know in the OpenGL
renderer right we would have we would
have sort of the same stuff that we were
doing with the fog where we've got where
is it so this bit right here so we kind
of have the like fog start distance fog
and distance right we would have a way
of saying like a you know clip alpha
start distance and clip alpha end
distance you know and those would they
would do exactly the same math so where
we have this fog distance here and we
have the fog amount we'd also have an
alpha amount and it would do a clamp gr1
map to range and it would be the clip
alpha start distance the saw distance
clip alpha and distance and we're just
taking another range there and producing
just like we produce the fog value we
produce an alpha value and then what we
can do is we look we're all ready we're
prepared to do it right
we already did exactly this we're just
going to take that alpha and multiply it
by that alpha that's log base alpha and
so if we want to do that right we just
need to add the ability to pass those
down
so there's the clip what would would I
call it clip alpha start distance and
clip alpha and so those those two values
are now getting like remembered you know
and we can have those on here as just
another thing that gets set like so and
so in the render group we would just put
those into the setup the render setup
and so it's literally just a copy and so
you can kind of see like what I'm doing
here you would if you have lots of
shaders this is the stuff that you would
need to start automating the ability to
define something in a shader and set it
somewhere else and not have to
constantly do all the piping by hand
because it you know can definitely drag
you down I don't mind doing this by hand
because I know we you know don't really
have very much hair so if we had 20
shaders it would start to get kind of
onerous right and at that point you kind
of want to you know do something a
little more reasonable so let's take a
look at the fog start distancing the fog
and distant stuff here I'm going to set
the clipped alpha start distance and
eclipse alpha end distance I'm just
going to yeah set those to basically be
nothing like they were before and so the
fog starts to since that stuff is just
hard coded here is you can kind of see
and so what I want to do is say well
whatever the near clip plane is is going
to be any time we're doing that fog the
fogging I'm going to go ahead and say
all right let's set the clip I also
start distance and set the clip alpha
start just misses even your clip plane
so it's right on there and we're going
to set the clip clip alpha end distance
to be you know where we want it to
actually start fading in or you know
which is shouldn't shouldn't be too far
off probably I don't know but we have
interesting thing here which is that the
start and end are kind of inverted so we
really want to do the opposite of that
we want to map the range backwards but
we can just do that directly in the
shader so I don't really know how we
want to do like in other words I think
we could just do this if that makes
sense
because we want it to fade out as a good
coaster I don't remember if the way we
wrote it will actually handle that or
not so we'll find out in a second but
let's go ahead and quickly just see if
we can get this working before I go to
the Q&amp;A because I'm just interested to
see that effect alpha amount is
undefined right you are sir and we do
apologize for that what we could do here
is to say screw it there we go okay so
now we have to see whether we can get
this effect working in a reasonable way
we are actually passing down values now
and it doesn't really appear to be doing
anything right so that doesn't look
particularly good so what I want to do
here is I want to play with this a
little bit more let's put it in the
right order because maybe that clamp
that clamp probably doesn't work right
if you specify than the opposite order I
don't really know if that's true or not
we probably wrote the clamp wrong
because we're just done so let's see if
we come through here yeah again I'm not
seeing any alpha there so I'm not
feeling very good about that
so just because I'm not really sure
what's going on there I'm going to play
with the shader a little bit directly
first to get it working there because I
would like to see what's happening
before I try to make sure the piping is
correct which is a separate issue right
so the first thing I want to do is again
same black box debugging techniques what
I would like to do here is say well okay
let's go back to the alpha amount
concept and we'll multiply by the alpha
amount and what I'm going to do is take
that
frag color I want to take else amount
and just reduce it so it's always have
so what I should see now is everything
should go to half alpha right and it
does so that's pretty cool and hey check
out how often this depth peeling is
right like we just set everything
outside and it worked like the whole
world is transparent and it basically
works like that's kind of nuts because
we're not sorting anything so that def
feeling is just great for these 2d games
you've got the fill rate to spare I kind
of feel like you should just do it and
you know on a higher-end hardware you
could use the Atomics but man that's
really compelling you just throw it in
there and it's like hey guess what I
sorted it for you
happy birthday so anyway obviously the
Alpha amount is working so our problem
here is that we're not actually mapping
this range quickly and so let's try to
figure out what's going on there so I
want to make the range go backwards so
basically as we get further along the
range the Alpha should get higher right
but actually that's okay so that's what
should happen so I think we're alright
so the clip alpha start distance should
be you know however far away we want to
start from the camera so let's say we
start at 1 and we go to 2 so that should
give us some fog between 1 and 2 where
it's alpha fog so that the Alpha of
stuff should come in at that point and
it doesn't which is just bizarre
oh I'm just stupid I am mister stupid
pants the third so that's just yeah
that's just me being dumb the these
aren't the near and far clip planes that
we're using so what we really want to do
is take the near clip plane and set the
alpha start to bat and then we want the
near clip plane which is actually pretty
far out it's not 0.1 stepping in set the
near clip plane plus you know I don't
know a quarter meter I'm not sure how
far and we want to go for the Alpha
probably not far anyway
that should be now more correct of
course I still don't seem like it works
so that wasn't the problem
that it was a problem but not the
problem apparently so let's go back here
and see what happens I'm going to start
it pretty far out so I'm going to start
it at four and and go to five and we
should be able to get some alpha
somewhere right like somehow it's just
not working at all and I don't know why
because it seems like we should be able
to get some values in here in the Alpha
amount and we know you know we know
we're getting we know that that if we do
get a value in the Alpha that it does
work because if we come in here and
again and we set alpha amount to 0.5 we
do see alpha happen right I mean it is
the contribution is happening so somehow
this clamps are one map to range for the
fog distance is never producing any
actual alpha so what if I just made it
the entire like a huge swath right and
what's our near clip plane set to right
now does anyone know so the near cliff
plane is the near clip plane is set to 5
so what if I just said start at the near
clip plane of 5 and go to 10 that's a
huge range we should see alpha or along
the whole way ok there we go there we go
so what's a little bit odd about that is
if five is the near clip plane and our
alpha should be zero there why are we
still seeing anything and what I'm
thinking is the problem there must be
our frag color when we pass down the
frag color ah when we pass down the frag
color we are not taking account of
premultiplied alpha so really we need to
multiply the entire fragment color by
that alpha mount because it's
premultiplied alpha lovely that's what I
wanted to see okay
so now let's back out these things to
something that maybe should make some
more sense we had a couple different
stupidities in there it was like a
festival of stupid
so now let's see if we can get something
working properly here so if it starts if
the fog starts at the near clip plane
start distance end distance and I don't
know extends for one unit presumably we
should see an alpha band there but we
still don't
hmm I wonder why not if I set this to
five and I set this to 10 what happens
still nothing
so here's a question am i setting those
properly in my haste did I forget to
actually set those I probably did didn't
I
yep nice job dude the festival of Sioux
City continues there we go you do oops
which by the way is another reason why
you want to automate these kinds of
processes for doing a lot of them
because it's easy to make a stupid error
like that all right so that's better and
a clip alpha start distance now should
properly be able to be set based on the
near cliff line so that whatever you set
it to it will fade out nearer than your
clip plane like so so now the problem we
have is in your clip plane is actually
fading those things out a little bit too
early right so we probably do want to
tighten this up a little bit and we
maybe need to put the near clip plane a
little bit further back to I don't know
so that's a pretty interesting effect
and so now the other thing that I'm
thinking right is I think we might also
be able to improve upon that upon that
technique a little further as well like
I think we may be able to make it do
some smarter stuff with with respect to
like fading out things that maybe we
don't quite want to maybe we don't quite
want to depth feel as much but yeah
anyway I'm going to go ahead go to the
Q&amp;A
so it doesn't seem to quite line up with
the near clip plane because if you look
it's like it's weird the the near clip
plane is like clipping stuff out oh yeah
you know why that would be - the reason
in your clip plane is clipping stuff out
is actually because the near clip plane
is going to clip without regard to the Z
bias so
that suggests split see here or with
regard to the Z bias I should say so if
I come in here I'm just curious to see
how did we actually do this flog a matte
fog distance is the Z vertex X Y Z so
the one that modified my scent - the
flower direction and that's not actually
the one getting pushed down now that
that should make us fog out faster
though so that's a little bit strange to
me but it does suggest that what we
really need to do here in terms of near
far clip plane is we actually need to
take that near clip plane and bring it
back in and do something where we leave
enough of a distance for the bias to
clear it right so I think we actually
want to do something here like possibly
even this much I think we want something
like this
we do get some some gunk in there that
we're getting there
could you try disabling the
randomization of the ground tiles II I'm
interested to see if that'll adversely
affect the sexiness of the depth peel I
think it would definitely make the depth
field less interesting I mean it also
makes the visuals less interesting you
know what I mean
one of the reasons I wanted those uneven
like those tiles like that is because it
just looks better and it can it gives
the player understanding of where the
tiles are in a nice 3d way instead of
only making it the about like a tile
bitmap or something but yeah if you just
want to see it become less sexy we can
totally do that by just taking out this
so now we're just a flat plane there
right
well it's still kind of cool honestly
so it's cooler than I thought it would
be I guess
the debug menu is broken now yeah so I
feel like probably the clip alpha stuff
is I needs to be not like we need a way
of turning off the clip alpha because
the clip alpha is going to zero out the
stuff in the debug menu so I guess the
one way to do that would be here is we
just say like hey the clip alpha
distance is actually like the flower
clip plane or something I think that'd
probably work I don't really know now
that did not work okay how would we do
that
um I feel like that should have worked
okay I guess I don't technically know
that it's that either so I should just
double-check so here's without that yeah
and that's so it is the clip alpha that
that creates the problem so you want
this to clip to one point oh right I set
it the wrong way sorry it needs to be
the near clip plane so it needs to be
like near clip plane you know -
something because you always want
everything that's drawn to be like in
front of the end you know so there you
go
pragma script says for depth feeling
would it be possible to discard all
pixels in the second layer that have an
alpha value of 255 in in the front layer
because they are not interesting for the
composition anyway yes we absolutely
could if we just wanted to save like
fillrate we could totally do that
unfortunately I don't really know how
you would do that without a little bit
of work so you don't get to use the like
I guess the question would be how do we
pipe that alpha value over there though
because since we're drawing in two
separate buffers we don't actually have
the Alpha value of what's in the other
deaf people before so we'd have to pipe
that buffer in and actually read from it
so I worry that the amount of savings
you would get from not doing the right
might be offset from having to have a
whole other texture query happen at
every pixel so it's not great you know
so I'm interested to know you can see we
still get some problems there with the
death feeling right where you forget
some black sort of crunchiness there and
I do wonder if we can improve that
further
I think we definitely have some problems
with the Alpha clip stuff so we need to
do some work on this probably next
weekend we'll just do some finishing
work on these shaders and stuff and try
to get it really dialed because we still
got some bugs we still got some some
definitely some bugs in there
Alex Calvo I'm behind on day 130 just
finished the Simbi threat introduction
what feature of the game eventually
forced you to use the GPU totally love
the software rendering I think it's
because I wanted to do pure I wanted to
do actual 3d I don't remember to be
honest we will definitely go back and do
a software renderer for the final
version as well so that you can still
switch between them right so we'll go
back and do like a def peeling one if
that turns out to be the final way we
render we'll do one of those where can
you go there's nowhere to go there's no
more stairs stairs to nowhere the bridge
to nowhere but I don't remember what it
may have also been a speed issue like we
may have been like we wanted to do
something speed wise that we couldn't do
I don't remember I really couldn't tell
you somebody probably mid below might
know better than I do
but it would be pretty easy to now to do
a a software rasterizer if we you know
to if we have it exactly this way in the
future because you know we know exactly
what we need to do now and we have
everything baked down to a pretty good
process so we could probably you know I
don't want to do it now because we may
still change some things about the
rendering as we go because we're still
kind of flexible in that way but it's
the game going to be more 3d gameplay
wise we planned I know it's still just
totally 2d so it's not going to change
gameplay wise at all it just I just feel
like it plays and feels better when
things are rendered in 3d for whatever
reason even with sprites they just feel
it just feels like a more coherent world
to me when the camera moves around and
to get a little bit of that depth you
know
and Napoleon yes Jeff feeling is being
used for objects for order independent
transparency with the sprites the only
problem we have right now is we don't
have a discriminator for depth
interpenetration so like if two shadows
are rendered at the exact same layer
exact same Z and they overlap you get a
problem you get a bug so we I don't know
what we want to do about that in the
future like I don't know how we want to
approach eliminating some of the
artifacting they're probably not
something I care about right now like
everything looks good enough right now
that I'm like okay we can put the real
art in here we can get the game all good
and like playable and fun and all that
stuff and then at the end we can go back
and go alright how are we going to iron
out the last few this view bugs and so
on
can you go into more detail on what
fixed layers two and three from being
all black it wasn't an old card only
being able to read two textures but I
missed the extras yes so sorry about
that I didn't really explain it for you
at the time because kind of a well known
bug amongst people who program OpenGL
they're just like yep that it's that one
again
by default when OpenGL starts up I it
assumes that textures arm it mapped it
assumes that they're map mapped so even
if a texture has never had any myth
level specified and we'll never have any
nip level specified OpenGL considers it
myth mapped until you tell it otherwise
what this means is that if the texture
ever gets sampled in a way that it
thinks it needs to sample from one of
the MIT maps of the texture instead of
the actual texture you will just get
black samples because there are no MIT
maps to the texture so basically we've
only specified one myth level myth level
zero or rather no myth levels the base
texture right it hasn't been missed down
so depending on how you want to use the
terminology level zero is the only zero
that's present so if the card ever wants
a sample from level one for some reason
it would get nothing because there's no
data there now the reason I didn't
suspect that right away is because I
would have assumed all the peels were at
the same nip level but apparently that's
not true for some reason and either that
reason is because there's some weird bug
going on in the driver or I don't know
what or somehow the fact that we wanted
no myth that we want to turn this
mapping off got set on text the first
two textures and not on the third and
fourth for some reason I don't know how
that could be possible either but yeah I
don't know so basically what I would say
is right now I couldn't tell you why
only two and three we're doing that but
I can tell you that what fixed it was
turning off the myth mapping so it seems
like it
some kind of a weird bug there in terms
of like thinking it was associated about
it shouldn't have thought it was
supposed example from the map so that's
weird too
because we are sampling basically
one-to-one so I really don't know but
that's what fixed it is turning off the
mid mapping and the way that we did that
was just setting the filter to GL linear
because it defaults to MIT map linear
MIT MIT linear textile linear right
do you actually have to have wireframe
models to be considered two and a half D
or would this count as well so two and a
half D I would say that that is not a
really well defined term in the industry
honestly but I would suspect that yes
this is two and a half D because there
are actual 3d objects in here and
everything is actually placed in 3d for
real so that's basically what two and a
half D is I think like two and a half C
is basically saying some things are 3d
some things are 2d is typically how I
interpret that phrase you know like doom
or something would be two and a half D
potentially right it does some things in
a 3d way and some things in a 2d way and
off you go even quake could be
considered to an after you in a sense a
weight Note could because they Denver
they they did full 3d and quake so is
there a two and a half D game like quake
traveling if there is a game that
rendered environments in 3d and the
sprites in 2d it probably was a few of
those but I can't think of them offhand
so there's a bunch of two and a half
these sorts of things like that and I
suspect we would follow that category
but I don't know it's not a real precise
term
you can refine your own render
definition for handmade hero or for
handmade development uh yeah I guess
what I would say is I don't know that
it's a really useful thing to categorize
stuff as anyway I mean this is a 3d
renderer it renders things in 3d some of
those things happen to sprite cards but
that's true in almost all 3d renders
like even fully the most 3d thing you
like battlefields 1 or whatever the most
recent like fancy graphics thing you've
seen probably uses sprite cards
somewhere for like particle systems or
something right
so I feel like really handmade hero for
all intensive purposes point is a 3d
game right and it's a free D game that
uses 2d sprite graphics in a bunch of
places but it's basically all 3d so I
don't even know did it make the
difference two and a half D 3d I don't
know two and a half D might be better
reserved for things like doom where you
can't rotate the camera like we can
rotate our camera right
Alex Kelbo is the floor below us being
drawn completely and the one we are on
top of and the one we were on on top of
it or is the one below being clipped so
that only the pixels we see through the
holes are drawn um so right now we do
not do anything to try and do clipping
two holes so the whole bottom floor is
being rendered and my you know
assumption is that we will never really
have a fill rate problem on handmade
here oh and maybe you know if we do have
a fill rate problem my anticipation is
it's going to come from something like a
orgy of particle effects which we won't
want to address in a different way
anyway that wouldn't have a lot to do
with layer clipping like that because
we're just not going to be stressing the
filler into the cards that much I don't
think even this old card is not really
caring about the fact that we're over
filling the screen four times and four
times times 4 times basically right like
16 times and it's just like whatever
so I don't think we're really going to
stress the fill rate that much unless we
get a particle system orgy in here
all right I'm going to wrap up
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for them sort of handmade here oh
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you want to file long series
at home you can always peer to the game
on handmade hero org and it comes a
little source code so you can play
around with it we also have a forum site
you can go to if you want to ask
questions we have a patreon page if you
want to support the video series
schedule bot if you want to know when
we're going to be live and an episode
guide which you can go to if you want to
catch up on old episodes that's about it
for this week I don't remember what
schedule is for next week but check the
schedule bot I'll post it Friday we will
basically just do some cleanup next week
and then I think we are on to art
integration so I think we'll start
working on how we're going to plan to
get the new art in here because we kind
of have like everything penciled in the
camera works just fine you know we got a
plenty of work to do to improve it and
all that stuff but everything works
pretty good so I think at this point
you'll I start building out you know
actual game looking stuff and starting
to see like what we're missing you know
basically feel like you know what do we
need to improve in the engine that's
based on just actual stuff that we're
doing so hopefully you know hopefully we
will find that we've done a good job
giving ourselves a tool kit for for
putting the game together and those
things that we haven't built yet we can
find good ways to build that's about it
for this week
I will catch everyone next week until
then have fun programming and I'll see
everyone on the Internet
techies everyone