all right everybody uh let's take a look
today
um
at
moving the glove around so we kind of
decided last
week
that we were going to try to
uh just store movements in entities
we're going to say like look there's
going to be a certain
series of movements that you can
queue up so you know you get something
and i believe it's in
here
where we have
um
this so what we decided to do was say
all right there's gonna be this move
pattern
and the move patterns are things that we
can define that are just gonna be like
game designy
so move patterns are things like how
enemies attack or how a glove works or
even potentially how enemies move
sometimes so i don't know what we'll use
it for but this is our experiment it's
just what we decided to implement we
need to pick something implement first
just so we can get started and see how
it goes
right
um
so uh
what we expect to have happen is we
define some of these move patterns such
as a glove punch pattern
the patterns are direction agnostic so
basically they don't care whether you're
facing like
left up right or down
they are
written always to point to the right and
then we assume that when you trigger one
of these it will be rotated into the
correct direction
so uh we define a move pattern and the
move pattern is some number of moves we
don't know how long this should be here
but whatever it is it's going to be you
know there's going to be some
max number that's however money we think
we'll ever need and then we set the move
count how many of those we actually use
because probably most moves are going to
be like a lot less than eight eight is
really kind of tediously long so like if
you're gonna do a glove punch you
probably don't want it to go to eight
squares right
um but in general you know two three
four something like that
uh when you then trigger one of these
the move pattern gets copied into a move
queue and the move queue is per entity
it consists of these entries and they
are basically like a finalization of it
it's like here is the delta which
direction i'm going to move from my last
position plus you know any flags like is
it interrupt or interruptible am i you
know able to collide during it you know
who knows what
and i
again we we also kind of decided well
we're gonna need some way of saying how
stats affect what you do when you move
like whether you do damage
uh whether you you know how much you do
how fast you move
and so we decided as well we're going to
probably have some move square types and
we haven't really decided what they are
right now we just call them a b and c
but you know eventually we'll have
some idea of what those are and the
stats for things will just be based on
that so
basically a move pattern will be
something like you know move move strike
and so we'd have maybe move is one of
these and strike is one of these and
maybe big strike is one of these or
small strike you know what i'm saying
so we have some move square types and
those move square types are all designed
to be uh
like things we will tune for game design
and then the
actual stats are never
uh
are never just vague like they're never
like oh here are some stats the stats
are always tied to a type so for example
if a particular glove
has a particular damage stat
it's never just here's the abstract
amount of damage this glove does instead
it is here's how much damage this glove
does on a move movement here's how much
it does on strike here's what she does
on big strike right
so you could have gloves that don't do
any damage on movement and only do
damage on striking you could have drugs
drugs that's good gloves or you could
have drugs i mean maybe there's
you know prescription illicit i'm not
sure over the counter even
um
you can have gloves that do the opposite
right gloves that that do attack on move
and don't attack on strike or attack on
both and all that and so the idea there
is just to give us room to start working
on the game design
um
so that there's enough because you know
i mean this is a supposed to be a
roguelike kind of feel so we we need
enough room for the design to have a lot
of variability uh a rogue alike that's
the same every time is not gonna be very
interesting so you have to have
i think some variety in how the attacks
feel there has to be like oh in this
build it was all about doing a small
amount of damage to a lot of things at
once and in this other build it was all
about doing a lot of damage to just one
thing at a time right
and so you kind of need there to be a
room for that and so that's that's the
design that we basically just kind of
like quickly sketched out
um again it's just a guess we have no
idea but we need something to type in
first so that we can start playing
uh that's and that's all this is just
something to type in first i have no
idea if it's any good
um and i'm not a game designer so i'm
not supposed to know right uh that's
that's something someone else you know
would would be uh in charge of normally
uh and so in the brain code when you do
something like trigger and attack we
started sketching out like how this
would actually work using that system
um you would get something like this and
this is probably going to be reusable
code eventually
because we probably want you know in
general the ability to cue a pattern up
like this so this is just we put it in
here because this is where we have to be
developing it but you can kind of see
there's nothing specific to the glove
about this actual piece of code it just
does a cue right it
looks to make sure there's room in the
queue for the movement so that it won't
start adding things to a movement that
it can't finish
and we made that be an assertion because
i think that's just a bug we should
always make the game design so that you
know it's free for us to set these
numbers to the maximums we're going to
use in the game design so it shouldn't
be an issue right
um and then we just go through and we go
through the moves and we add them in
rotated to fit the current facing
direction
you know
um
and that's it
right it's very simple uh so that's how
we would cue up movements i think that
probably just works uh i mean there
might be some bugs and i haven't looked
at it closely but
i think that's it right
so you can see this will be pretty easy
we'll just have a cue we'll we'll pull
this out into like a queue if this turns
out to be okay
that's what you end up with
and so really i think all we're
really in need of now
is just for the entity code to be
pulling things off of this movement
queue
and executing them you know what i mean
uh so we kind of need a way to
to we kind of need to start working on
that aspect of things
um
so
there's a couple things that are weird
about this and again like i think we're
just gonna have to feel our way through
it
if you look at how
uh movement is working currently
effectively what's going on is the brain
code is synchronizing the movement of
things across the frame so like for
example well you can see it
uh happening right here actually um
right you can kind of see this dude
hopping around
right
um we're outside the lighting region now
so everyone is going to get lit by the
same light uh when you're out you're not
really supposed to be looking beyond the
blue boundary but for now just ignore
the lighting um
the uh
this dude who's hopping around
the way that that works is that the
brain
does those movement requests so they all
kind of
happen at the same time that's why that
works right because the transactional
movement system would otherwise it would
create a problem
and the problem that it would create is
if these guys moved in a different order
then like the person here wouldn't be
able to move until this guy moved so
they wouldn't move in sync like they'd
move like one frame lagged from each
other because
like the first person would have to have
already started to move out of the
square that they're in before the person
behind that person could have started to
move into it right
um
so that's kind of an issue
and i'm not 100 certain what we're going
to do
long term we can keep doing it that way
um but you could imagine a world where
we wanted everything to go through the
movement cue system and really what the
brains did was just they they queued up
emotion here
and those cued up motions have to be
retired by somebody right
and when they are they might fail right
like and so you get into that situation
i was just saying where you have this
sort of
uh
off by one kind of a thing where oh this
guy
in the entity list happens to come
before this guy
and so what do we do
um and so we kind of have to think about
that and the answer might be that since
we're now going to be more or less doing
everything on the grid anyway uh as we
move towards
you know simplifying the code down and
just doing something more grid based
always
it may be that we just want
to uh
it may be that we want to switch to a
multi-pass approach there
and and i don't know
like
but
you know what we could do for example
is
the move cues get retired
you know um
we go through the move cues and they get
processed as requests to move somewhere
and then we resolve those in a second
pass so that if if it just so happens
that one person requests a move into a
square that another person requested to
move out of those get resolved properly
you have to be careful like because if
you start getting into stuff like that
you end up with what basically amount to
physics dependency chains
you end up in a situation where like
with something like this
where
you know it's hard to know how many
passes or in what way you you
uh resolve them you know
and so it's not oh it's not clear to me
like right off the bat that that's a
smart thing right like i don't really
know
um
whether there's fruitful ground there i
i really just am not sure
so uh i'm gonna kind of ignore that part
of it for now and just focus on moving
things that don't have that constraint
and we'll start there and then we'll
kind of like
go further right as we go
and figure out more stuff
um so okay
so
let's start thinking about how this is
going to work if we push you know if you
imagine us doing um something like this
what do we want to have happen here um
oh that's a bit weird
did i set one of these wrong it looks
like i set one of these wrong when i
pushed up
it looks like it pointed in the wrong
direction
that looks correct though
doesn't it
action up
ended down
this so this must be
yeah this is a bit strange so so why is
this this way
the facing direction
is going to be the a tan of the x vector
right
and i mean i don't even know why we have
it that way we might as well just set it
up above so we don't do an a tan but
that's just wrong i'm not sure why it
was set like that
what am i missing there attack
is our how is our facing direction is
encoded as
i think as an angle
although i guess i'm not entirely sure
how we encoded that i don't remember but
that should be
correct for atan right
i mean i'm looking at it there's attack
x
and it sure seems like it right
i mean a tan of one zero
oh uh
duh
a tan is y over x sorry so it was okay
uh the y x part it was just the the
attack x instead of y a tan always
i've never really understood the the
order of parameters there we go
i was like i knew that was right like
what's going on so now it's correct when
i push of course you guys couldn't tell
it was wrong because you can't see which
keys i'm pushing but you know trust me
now it's correct
so what we want to do now is we have to
try and figure out how we want uh the
glove to move so the first thing that we
have to figure out is where does the
glove really sit and
i feel like you know it's just going to
be too difficult to figure out how this
game would work exactly
if the glove
uh occupied a square completely because
we kind of want the glove to be floating
in the same square as the hero right
um like we we want the
we want the glove and the hero to be in
the same square i think
um
and
so we don't really want to consider that
illegal if we said that the glove and
the hero both occupy a square
then
i mean you could make that game but then
it becomes a little bit more even more
tetris-like as a game right because now
you have to worry about like fitting
um
like you have to worry about whether you
can have room to turn
like if i turn this way then the glove
has to go into this square and if it
can't then i like can't turn that way or
i can turn that way but the glove stays
here right
um
i mean one of the things that sucks
about this sort of thing if you're not a
game designer is like as i'm saying that
i'm like i don't know that's like
kind of interesting
i i don't think it would make sense in a
game like this because this game is more
actiony if it was a puzzle game
that sounds
good right meaning a puzzle game
you know that's
very that seems very logical
for an action game
i'm just not sure why you would care
right like
like
i i can't think of hand of a reason why
that would be something we would need
like what are you going to be doing in
the game differently because that's true
you know
[Music]
um so i don't think it's really worth
trying that um
like i don't really think it's worth
trying that so i think i'm just going to
put it in
um
it it's it's you know it's it's in the
same square
uh and so
that part is kind of a little confusing
now because i have to think about how it
interacts with the move cube but i think
more or less uh what's happening is
if the
when we're looking at the glove
if we are in a situation
where there's nothing in the move queue
then i think that's like our return
pattern right
so uh
we want this code to be setting it to be
moving back to a location next to the
hero is what this code does
uh and we want this code to
uh
this code is just pushing the things on
to the move queue and the entity code
will presumably take care of moving that
stuff forward i assume
i don't know uh it's kind of hard to say
where that code should live maybe that
still lives in the brain code but
so this part here we should be able to
get working at the moment um and if we
go look at the animation floating code
uh like now we have to start actually
thinking about how this stuff's gonna
work right
uh so we've got this where we've got
hopping and we've got floating
and you can see us doing like a a lerp
here to move from one place to another
and
hmm
sorry i'm very allergy today for some
reason
i'm not sure why it's raining i feel
like my allergies should get better
they're not actually bad just a little
bit stuffy
um
so
the question is
how do we square the part about it
occupying or not occupying things you
can see here it's doing like an
occupying and it came from and it's like
lurping it's doing the lerp and that's
fine
but
we don't actually want it to occupy a
square
we just want it to float through the
you know
and so i guess
part of the problem
is that
we we need some way of of marking
[Music]
what the entity is right now
meaning like when it does
those occupying steps
we need a way of saying something came
from somewhere or is going to somewhere
without it actually taking up the square
because when something is going to be
ephemeral it's supposed to float through
things
right
um
so
in the transaction system
right when you move around
so
you can actually see
uh in here
transactional occupy
does the
occupying thing right
and so like i guess i'm just trying to
think about like how do we want to move
this forward because i think we kind of
want to just redo this stuff a little
bit
right
um like i feel like we kind of want to
just
move to a system whereby we
can just
i i guess the right way to say it would
would maybe be that i want to kind of
regularize this stuff more
like right now it's very ad hoc and
anyone can call transactional occupy and
of course transaction occupy is
reasonable so you know you know that
people are occupying a particular square
or not
but
i think
if you look at how occupying
itself
works
so in here you can see
um
when we do update and render entities we
go over the entities here
and you can see that it does a thing
where it like
um
not that one
it's actually the unpack
where is that
it might be that they're just stored
been a long time
so i guess it might be that they're just
stored
um
so maybe that's not true
i
you know previously
i was i was thinking that the occupy got
unpacked but it looks like they're just
stored along with the entity
i guess
um and again it's just like it feels
like this stuff wants to be simplified
down now like we should probably just
have the grid
um
and
the grid
is
doesn't require people to track occupant
occupancy because occupancy
you just unpack into the grid and you're
done right
um
[Music]
and so yeah i'm just the reason i'm kind
of a little hesitant is i just don't
know in which order i want to do these
things i want to clean up a bunch of
this stuff but i just don't know which
order i want to do it in
so i guess what i would say is since it
looks like there's no real harm at the
moment because the occupying is
completely up to you whether you call it
or not and it doesn't actually do an
unpack
um
because i like it does not look like
there's an unpack uh
for that right like i don't
how come i can't go to next error
well it doesn't matter
um
because there's it in there's nothing in
the unpack that actually sets this as
far as i can tell
uh then i guess we don't have to worry
about this right now but i would like to
do it at some point but since there
isn't
i guess that means that we can literally
set uh the entity to just come back
and at the moment it would do probably
too much of a lurp
uh way too fast of a lerp
normally
it probably should be set to do
something smoother but
at the moment i think we can just set
the occupying
to
uh to be where i set the um
the destination and the occupying
without actually doing a transactional
occupy just set them
and that will actually move it properly
so i guess we can do that i guess
right
so if we don't have any moves then i
think all we really need to do is to set
um
yeah it looks like like it like i mean
it looks like we just
we can just literally cold set this
stuff
so we're gonna want to clean this up
this isn't good uh this this needs to
get regularized a lot there's way too
much code going on in here for this
stuff
so it's definitely on my radar of stuff
that needs to get fixed for sure
but
um
for the moment i think this will still
work so if the move q count is zero then
i think what we want to do
is uh is check to see whether or not the
glove occupying equals the body
occupying meaning are they in the same
square
um and if they're not then you know if
they are in the same square we don't
really have to do anything
but if they're not in the same square
then we need to set uh this stuff
right we need to set the the anim
floating
and we need to set these to be equal to
the right
uh stuff so we want to say that the
glove
occupying should be the body occupying
um and the glove came from
should equal the glove occupying so
it'll just return right it'll return to
where you know the body is
in that case
uh but like i said this is way too much
work uh this stuff we now want to kind
of collapse into something small and
reasonable because this is very simple
what we're doing here it's just over
complicated by the fact that it was
generic 3d before
um
so anyway so now we want to do is get
that working so that it will actually
lerp right um
and so
i guess i'm not sure about
well that should
so that should work so we should debug
this real quick and make sure we know
why like we should make sure that works
because i think as it is that should
probably work because it should hit this
case
um
[Music]
i guess i'm not sure where t movement
gets advanced
okay so t movement is always advanced uh
so that's fine
um
so that should work and so why this
isn't
uh
doing alert on the ground p because i
think we should hit this case
i mean i don't know for sure but i think
we should get this case
uh i'd like to see why that's not
happening
so i guess one reason that might not be
happening though is also if i
accidentally hit a key
but i didn't there so the move queue is
still m is is empty so there's something
up with that so let's take a quick look
and see why that case doesn't hit
um
or if it does hit why it's like doesn't
actually result in anything
because i think that should already even
before we clean up the code it should
trigger the lerp case
and it's not triggering the lerp case so
that's a bit odd and
i want to know why
okay so in this code uh
we've have it all so we right here are
wondering do we ever come through this
code
uh another problem
well okay
so we do come through this code the
glove occupying the body occupying are
not the same
right
let's take a look at the glove data here
real quick
or the g love
so if we take a look at the occupying
um
[Music]
it looks like the glove is not occupying
anything
so that's kind of weird
i guess it must not have been set when
it starts
but it's definitely targeting something
right
um
so
i'm not
quite sure
why that would not therefore animate
right
um that's a bit peculiar
but
we can take a look at update animation
and see what's going on there
now unfortunately we don't really have
any way excuse me
um
we don't really have any way of
checking which one is the glove which is
a little annoying
uh because we'd like to just take a look
at just the glove itself
so we probably need some way of of
getting that
narrowed down but
um
seeing
what's going on here
like everyone is at t equals one
like everybody
so why you wouldn't have movement from
in movement two it should just be equal
to movement two
right i mean
so that's just really kind of strange um
like that really does seem kind of
strange i don't know why we would
i can't say i understand that because if
the t value is always set to one and
movement two is going to be the
destination of the thing
um
which we set to the same one as the body
then it doesn't make a lot of sense to
me why it wouldn't be following around
right
i mean there's there's bad like this
code is not good because there's i could
list off a number of things that are
wrong with it right um
but like
it should be moving
at least slightly
it's we should see it kind of jerkily
move to where it should go and the fact
that we don't see it move at all is
weird
hmm
what am i missing
i'll take a look at that update
animation code
so
i mean
there's not a lot of code there
ah the ground p of the entity just kinda
yeah i'm not seeing it i'm not seeing
why that that seems like it should work
and it's especially weird that it
doesn't
um
the glove stuff doesn't really get
overwritten anywhere as far as i can
tell i guess i'll double check maybe it
does
i mean that's the only place we set the
animation type
so that's really strange it seems like
that should be set we should be hitting
the floating case and worst case it
should just be kind of jumping to
movement 2
where it says get some space traversible
of whatever the entity is occupying
that seems like what i would expect
right
now i suppose
since we don't know which one is the
glove i suppose
one nice thing to do would be to like
you know
be able to mark this clearly so we can
tell that it is or isn't the glove
right
so when we do this entity id here
we could also assign like a debug
name to it
you know what i mean
uh and that would be a way for us to
sort of quickly know who we were dealing
with um
i can also sort of save when the glove
gets created
and look at what the glove
id is there
and maybe that's easier because then i
can actually even just set a breakpoint
for that
so in here right you can see where we do
the glove and the glove
creates the
you know the entities for it
again nothing really weird happening it
it's it's literally just
you know add entity it sets it to
floating here
collision volumes we don't know that
we're really going to use
all that much
um
so i guess what i'd say is
maybe we'll just set a breakpoint here
at add player
uh and i'll just look at what the glove
entity id actually is
and then we can look and
see if you know just somehow the glove
not get
updated i mean it doesn't make sense but
you know we'll just see
so here's add player
here's the glove
and you can see the id
right there
so we're looking at 10 845
right
so now if i just go into well i suppose
i can leave a break point on this
there's not
really a reason not to because the next
time we run we'll want to look at the
end of the idea again uh it probably
would be the same
but
just in case it isn't so that we can
make sure
um
so now if we go to that entity code we
could just see like all right
what happens does that particular
entity
come through
so like there's our answer i guess
is that entity didn't come through
uh at all
so let's make sure it's still there
yeah so it's still 10 8 4 5
here when it's getting set
to
floating um so maybe it hadn't been set
to float yet although it seemed like it
was set to flowing when it was created
so
should it come through
there it is so i guess
it has to hit the first time
so if we look uh
at what the t value is the t value is
zero which means it won't move from
where it started so we wouldn't expect
to see it move here at all i guess
right
um
so this first time through that's fine
let's see the second time through
so now it should move like it should
place itself
halfway in between these two locations
right
um
i mean that's what should happen
unless i'm totally wrong
so
we have a ground p we have a from a two
i don't honestly have no idea how this
could be the value of ground p at the
moment
so so maybe that's part of the clue as
to what
is wrong here because you can see we
have oh can i do
is there a way to
can you do
um
i guess not
is there no way to specify this as a
vector3 basically like
there's the matrix mode
what am i what am i typing in wrong is
it m
i thought there was a thing for this but
i forget
it's mtx okay okay okay
gotta learn my remedies
or not
address expression which this is right
because it's e
although i guess it's an array
so maybe i'm wrong about that do i need
to do this
like why does this say identify or not
found
this isn't that kind of weird
george help us george i don't know
what's wrong here i kind of wanted to do
this but it doesn't look like it works
for some reason
although maybe like you can only do
so is it that you can't put a different
thing in here like you can put
okay it would be cool if you could just
put whatever you wanted
you know
like it would be cool if you could just
say mtx n by n and then it just did that
that would be cool so i guess we can't
do what i wanted to do so never mind
but point being
back to our story
um if we look at these vectors
we
we don't have a story for how the heck
how is this set to one
like how is that possible
because that it's always going to be
zero if it's lurping between these two
things
so how the heck was
like like it must be getting set
somewhere else
right um
i also don't know what the difference is
between p and ground p at this point
so there's a lot of stuff like cleaning
up this code is going to be nice because
there's just a ton of stuff that's left
over that none of it's necessary and
just gets in the way
i'm just trying to look and see if
ground p gets mucked with here
i don't see that happening though
by the time i exit this routine
does it change
oh i should have pinned that
like what
how did that suddenly happen without us
seeing it happen
right like
that ground p thing is nuts i don't
understand what i'm looking at here
um
oh wait no we're not in the same guy so
that's fine sorry no no here we go
same thing though
like i do not understand how that got
set to one who set it to one
we clearly should just set like a
break point on
this um
and see who is actually changing that in
fact i guess i could even just search
and see where that's happening
so this is the problem
this entity p entity this right here
actually that's what it is
all right
so
so this is just
total holdover
right
this is total holdover
um
there shouldn't be two of these anymore
there's no need for it right
um
it's totally unnecessary
i don't even really know what i can't
remember why we had to have both of
those things
previously
um anyway
but since this is grid based
we do want to have a ground p
in a sense we want to have the v2
like
this is
we want the notion that like here's
where you are in space
in the plane and then you're floating
this high off of it we do want those
things to sort of be dealt with
separately in a sense
but
i don't know why we would need to store
the ground piece separately
um
so
yeah i don't think we even need this
stuff anymore
i think all this is just to solve
problems that we just don't have anymore
so i'm going to go ahead and say i think
we can just kill this
i think i think we basically just this
is just to hold over this so this is
step one is we just get rid of ground p
entirely
i just don't think it's necessary
um
so
like you know
the
i'm gonna comment this out for now
yeah so so basically like you can see
too here like
one of the reasons that
okay i kind of get it too
because the thing was hopping we
probably want didn't know that we could
just zero what we really need is just a
way to get
the ground plane there so we don't
really care right so
if you think about how this stuff works
we can just say look the debug light p
is this and the z of it is this we don't
have to actually
um
worry anymore
about that because we know that zero is
the plane where the people are so i can
see sort of why we had that because
otherwise as you hopped around you would
have been bobbing up and down so we were
kind of trying to i think keep there you
know make there be some
um
we were trying to have there be some
idea of like a smooth value you followed
but we really don't care about that
anymore because we're always in the
plane now
right
so um
yeah
so i think we're good
um of course yeah that
that's a little bit less good but we'll
deal with that in a second
um
so okay so i think we just have to push
forward on that stuff first because yeah
that has to get cleaned up because
that's just going to be a complete
disaster
um
separate from anything else
um all right so now we're back in
business and you can see the glove doing
the thing that the glove is supposed to
do
um
exactly as we would expect
uh like i said we have this problem of
we're going to have to set the
um
we're going gonna have to do the
interpolation slightly differently you
can see how that like i said the glove
kind of jumps right
um and we're gonna have this problem
where uh we need to look at where the
glove currently is
and do the interpolation and it's
probably a slightly different way but i
think we're okay otherwise i don't it
should be doing more of an interpolation
than it is right now that's more jumping
than i would expect so i think there is
still something a little bit off about
that let me just make sure i'm right
about how that's jumping
yeah so it should do more interpolation
than that it's still way too
fast so i'm not sure
we have some slight error
in thinking about how that's happening
because no matter what i slow this down
to
you can see the glove goes there
immediately right
so that's a bit strange
um
i'm not sure why that it that's not what
i would have expected
you like i don't quite see why that lerp
i mean there's the lerp and we do know
the t value
actually
you know it's got to be animating
reasonably right
so i'm not sure why we would be we
wouldn't be seeing some amount of lerp
there
between the from and the two
unless the came from is getting set
you know overwritten
and and i don't know
that one's a bit of a mystery to me
like i could see that happening if came
from was getting overwritten with
occupying again like when we came
through here but
it doesn't
make a lot of sense to me why that would
happen
like
oh some reason we
forgot to set that to glove so we were
still setting bodies t movement
separately i was thinking this is
probably something we want so that it
only can do one move at a time but
that's sort of a hack we will want to do
something more than that anyway
all right that's more what we were
expecting
yes
so now we do have
that
that is working correctly
we now want to do like a bit of an
offset or something like the problem
that we have now is that it's right on
top of the hero exactly
which is what we want
um it means the code's working properly
now but we want the glove to float sort
of to the side of the hero
and
so we need this like a notion sort of of
an offset
right um
that rotates around
when the hero rotates around
right the glove has to have an offset
relative to the thing that it's going to
um and that
like in other words in here where we're
figuring out where the thing should be
presumably you want to have
you want to have something that's like
plus offset right
um
and
[Music]
there's two ways to do that um
you know one way
so if you went into
uh ad player
and
you looked at
this part where the glove gets created
there's like this glove piece
right
um
you could just make the glove piece be
like offset
and
you know it's hard to say
what we want to do there i i don't
really know but like you know let me
show you what i'm going to give you a
for instance
um
so here's what happens if you give it a
constant offset right
so the glove
is now properly offset from where the
hero is which is you know what we sort
of wanted
um
and we could also give it an up like
probably wants to be up
you know slightly
probably not a huge amount but slightly
um
and ooh
what the heck did i just do
i don't know what i just accidentally
did there so we're gonna undo that and
redo that that way
uh the point is we
we can offset those and leave that as
just a thing that's in the piece code
like it's kind of like the peace corps
right
uh and we can we can position that
however we want
uh the problem with this approach is
that it's unclear
um what we then do for rotation because
when the player rotates the
the glove will not
will not go like we would expect it to
go to the other side of the body right
so there's different ways we could do
this and i don't know which one we would
want to do one way
would be to say that those offsets are
going to be relative to the orientation
of the person so
when something changes its orientation
its piece offsets rotate with it kind of
like
a parent-child relationship would be in
a normal like 3d package
right
so that's one way
to do it
another way to do it is just to control
that manually
and say that when we push in a different
direction we just set the offset to be a
different thing
um
i don't know which of those makes more
sense uh largely because
i just don't know how much
utility
this
has i assume
i assume that
my thinking is that in general we
probably want to just keep a separate
offset that's not the way the pieces
work because the pieces are just ways of
gluing things together
and we may want that to rotate
but
we also
want
perhaps that to be
we want things like the glove which
we're moving around separately as as
their own movable pieces
we probably want those to also have this
notion
of where they are in the world
that's not
just about where the piece is but also
where the entity is
right because like what's happening now
is the glove as an entity still has its
location at the center of the square and
it's just the piece itself the
renderable piece that's doing the offset
and so i just don't know
um that's a tough one
all right here's what i'm going to say
about that
that i'm going to push to later
i'm just going to do the move cue stuff
because that's what we were working on
and
let's just get the glove punching
and then we'll address the offset stuff
separately
so it's just going to be kind of on the
side like that we can see it just fine
and we know we have to do one of the
solutions to that problem but just
i guess i just want to be slightly
further down the road uh before i make
that decision for now
that's just i don't know
that's my feeling on it
i'm gonna let this guy in
get out of my way
um
so i think yeah i think we're okay
i think i'm just gonna get the glove
punching for now and and i'll think
about how i want to do that
as a separate issue that you know we
need to solve but we'll
we'll figure it out
sorry for some reason i decided i wanted
to go through the dungeon
i really love the lighting it took us a
long time to figure out how to do it
well
but
i gotta say the end result is pretty
fabulous
some weird bugs in there with some
alternating lighting things
all right
yeah
miles big c that that was sort of
what i was worried about right
like
like there's nothing wrong with doing
the fixed offset thing but it just it
feels like for something with a glove
that's like flying around as its own
entity
it feels like you need a more of a thing
that's like
it's just a there's an offset that says
where this entity wants to be relative
to the center of the square
not
this that the entity is quote unquote at
the center of the square and just this
renderable piece that is the whole
entity right is offset it just feels
like that'll get ugly as we go so it
doesn't feel right
um and that's why i didn't really just
want to use that as an i didn't want to
automatically say that was how we were
going to do it because it doesn't
i'm not thrilled about it right
so that's you know that was just my
thinking but anyway so assuming that we
have the move q thing
um i guess what i'd like to do is say
okay if the entity t movement is greater
than one that means you've like finished
the movement that you were on
um and if that's the case then i
i want to like pop something off of the
move cube right so if we've got a move
queue
i
this code right
i want to like
like move through the move queue
quote unquote
um
and i guess
technically this is not gonna be like a
fifo
it's gonna be more just a stack that
gets cleared entirely because you can
queue up some moves but then you can't
do anything until they complete
if you do that
um so really your only option is ever is
cancel right
um
so i think we have a move q count and a
move q index really
and so the move q index like goes up to
the move q count and then completes
so i think what we would do here is say
okay if
if the entity t movement is one we pull
something off right if entity t movement
equals one
um
we could even do this
we would say okay
if there's a move queue
else right
so if there's a move queue if the entity
move q index is less than the entity
move oops
and the
move q count
um then that means we want to like
process this move cue index and then
increment it right so we would do
something like this
right
and when we pull this entry off of the
move queue whatever it is
we grab this and we try to
do it
whatever it is
that's on there
right
so
we have one of these
the delta is really the thing we're
looking for
so we would say
on the delta
um
[Music]
we would look to see whether we can get
a traversible
in that direction
so
in the same way that we've got and again
all this code is terrible now and needs
to be
removed um because we don't you know
since we settled on grid
most of this code is just garbage with
none of it's necessary you could just
have an actual grid right
um and it would simplify all of these
calls and you wouldn't need to do nearly
as much work
so that's coming at some point
but
you know
uh we have to do set aside a day to
basically say like okay
wipe all this clean and just do
just a grid
so uh what i was trying to say though is
when we're doing the move cue stuff
when we pull out the delta we would say
okay
this entity is at a particular location
and it wants to move in a particular
delta right
and
this is the delta it's going to use
i think we have a function that works
like this yeah
basically no move in z just moving in
x and y
um and so then what we're going to do is
we get the closest traversable to see
uh
where this target is
um
and assuming that we actually get it
uh then we would
we would move the person to that
right
i
[Music]
otherwise i don't know what we're gonna
do so if there's nowhere to move i guess
we just
keep
going
[Music]
so we would probably let it wrap like
we would
we always do this
right but if we don't find it reversible
then we just skip to the next move
probably
so on the next frame we'll try again and
move in a different i don't know oh
that's going to be a gameplay decision
that when we
once we start thinking about that i will
presumably have an opinion i have no
opinion now
so the traversable reference that we got
back for this
is going to be the so the entity is
going to have it came from that equals
it's it's occupying
uh and it's going to have an occupying
that is now
whatever this traversal is
um
so now we have to figure out how to
actually make this go uh for starters
i guess
maybe we should draw these so so i'm
just thinking out loud here
so let's suppose that somebody has a
move q count
we should draw that
i think
so like probably something like this
where we say let's let's go through all
of the things
on here
um
and
let's draw like boxes at the locations
where they are
um
i guess
not really sure
um
but like let's suppose we did something
like this
so we want to push a volume outline
um i'm just going to make like a white
uh
cube
that just goes
wherever the thing said that the hop
would be so basically this code
right
um so loop over all of these
i don't know what radius it should be
um
probably pretty small
so then i just so i can see like if any
of this stuff gets pushed on like like
i'm not seeing anything there so i don't
actually know if this actually works
so let me set some break points and see
but you know it could be that the
drawing code doesn't work either right
we're throwing all this stuff in there
who knows
i also think probably we would need to
push it upward slightly so it should
probably be entity p plus that
v3
um
this should probably be like half up as
well
just because otherwise we might not see
it right
might be embedded in the ground
but uh so let's see if we can set a
breakpoint now to see what happens in
the brain
[Music]
like are we actually ever setting this
so that would happen
here
so i don't know the glove stats probably
prohibit this actually
so we probably have to start actually
doing quote-unquote game design
in add player when we create this glove
the glove is going to have to have stats
for that right because if it doesn't
then you can't move it at all
so the glove stats have to have a max
move group count
of something
right and we'll set that to one
for now
um furthermore when the glove gets reset
and again all this code is probably
going to come into reusable like
functions like you know push move group
reset move group that sort of thing
um
the move q index is also going to have
to go back down to zero so so really
this is wrong
this stuff probably looks more
uh like this
this is wrong like we got to kind of
reset how this stuff is working
um so here it's going to be more like
okay if the glove move uh
q index
is equal to the glove
if the move q index is equal to the
glove move group count meaning we've
finished
right
then
you can do this
and reset
otherwise
i think actually when i said that code
was wrong i don't think it is i think
that code is still correct
all
right i'm not getting anything there so
i still have set the breakpoint because
it's not actually doing anything
we do have this this will pass now
that
should be fine
we have an attack pattern
so that should be fine so i do want to
set a breakdown because i don't see any
glaring errors
at the moment
so let's set a breakpoint there
and just walk through it once
let's see what the heck it's doing
okay
so uh first things first what are the
glove stats i assume we set them
correctly
what
did i not set that
you guys realized did we do something
dumb we did
so
yeah so uh this is we're now gonna have
to start doing real game design um so we
have the base stats
those are the actual ones we set the
stats and the static accumulation stuff
that we're going to have to actually
start dealing with now because we now
have real stats and we have to start
thinking about like how modifiers
affects that's all that stuff
we'll get there eventually
let's try this one more time
yeah so we're gonna have to go get that
stuff working now
all right so we have base stats
and we have like
uh we have now
we're gonna have to do like actual
unpacking
right
insobot is such a good
bot
everybody loves instabot
it answers all the questions
i feel like insofar as needs to like
uh
like
like use like gpt3 now or something and
have like insobot just do everything
like insobot will just take take over a
chat entirely
it'll just do the stream by itself
um
so
so we have this
uh advanced entity stats thing
and i think
maybe the right thing to do here is that
this was supposed to acquire the base
stats when it starts
i think
um and we weren't doing that that might
be the way that
that works i don't know again this is
now getting into game design territory
so
i don't know how we want to do that
stuff exactly because i'm not sure like
what we want to be able to do here but
that was the problem is that the stats
were never set right
okay so
uh now we
okay so there are boxes now being drawn
um they're not particularly good boxes
uh
so so maybe we need to like fix that a
little bit
um
so i'm not sure exactly how we would
draw these
because
they're relative to where you started
and we don't really know where you
started like that's not something that
actually got saved
um
we could however do a traversable like
we could get like traversable
uh
so what we could do here is do the same
thing we do in animation
right we could say like look just give
us
give us the base that you were moving
from
well or i guess moving two is now the
correct one because we're showing the
future things
so we could do something where we say
all right the target p
um is actually at your occupying
location then plus the delta
that's probably a more stable way to
draw it right
might still be wrong but
you know
yeah so that worked pretty well actually
um
so
uh
we now need to get the reset part of
things working so the reset part
is a little
harder so when this happens
um
i feel like this case should have
occurred
but it didn't
so i'm not sure why we didn't
return to where the
body was
that's a bit of a puzzler
hmm
yeah technic beam i want to know when in
sabah will become sentient as well but i
don't know when
ah
all right um
so let's just take a look at why that's
not returning because it looks like it's
working properly also i assume it
rotates properly
yeah
so really we just want to know why our
glove didn't return and i have no idea
um so that's
one we got to take a look at so why
wouldn't we hit that case we should have
the nadt movement
gets advanced every frame when it gets
to one it will do this case until the
moveq index equals the move count
and then it won't it'll just clamp
um so we should
be able to hit here where we do move q
index equals move group count
oh no
typo
should probably make those more distinct
looking
so we're tracking two different
quantities there
good
um so the other thing we can test too is
if i change the stats of the glove to
allow a second one
i should now also be able to like chain
these right so if i do like
that and then that
so that's a little odd
so when i cue both of those up it
doesn't
hm
it still used the old facing direction
to cue them
the secondary one
why would that be
can somebody please
explain that behavior
so this somehow is using the wrong
attack pattern
attack
x and y
unless i'm just misunderstanding what
happened uh
so that's peculiar
what book are you guys talking about
something written in 1977
oh no okay
i see what's happening
so
that's the problem is this attack
it's we wanted a went down so it's it's
queuing up
i see okay
can we do a went down on these or do we
not have that
the adolescence of p1 i've never heard
of that book
not surprising i don't read any science
fiction so why would i have but
so we don't have any kind of a went down
kind of a call
that's kind of weird because we have the
like half transition count thing
that just seems kind of weird
doesn't it
shouldn't we have a like
like a thing to say that something
went down
as opposed to
just being held down
well anyway
so we'll want to do something a little
bit fancier here
right
because we probably want to
do the half transition counts like
if you tap multiple times on a single
frame somehow like within a 60th of a
second if that's even possible on usb
um you would still want to queue them up
right
so you can see now like we're able to
cue movements up however we want
game design wise we're going to have to
make a bunch of decisions about like how
fast this stuff should be
how fast the return should be
i'm guessing the punch should be
considerably faster than that well
although you know who the who the heck
knows right it's probably going to be
more like some gloves are really fast
and some gloves are really slow
and you have to deal with it right i
mean that's probably the right thing
um
right
so that's tough i don't know
hmm
yeah i don't know
anyway um so i think that's
basically what i wanted though that
seems like that works now
and that's roughly correct uh
the question now is going to become like
how do we want to do
collision
like what's the definition of a
collision in our system
and since it's grid based i think
roughly the definition of collision is
going to be like
if you would be occupying the same
square then you have collided and you
take the action that you would take
right
um
yeah i i mean
i think at this point that is roughly
what i want like like
you know it would start out much simpler
than this right so the initial way you
would do the initial thing you would get
for your for gloves
that attack pattern
would only just be like one thing right
so the initial one would not look like
this
it would look
you know
like this
right so the initial one would look like
that
so it's just you punch out right it's
it's the simplest dumbest possible punch
right
um
and we probably want the speed to be
significantly higher so in there like
the the t values
need to be
set to something sensible
so like if you look at how the entities
work currently the t values should be
driven in here
right like
for each time you move you should be
setting a t value
for the move
right now it's not that way and
everything's in lockstep which is not
really what you want it would make sense
for an a strategy game but for an action
game
it doesn't make any sense
um
so i do think like
you know probably
what we want in here is when we set the
movement
stuff
um
like here you would do
something like this
you know
um
and probably like that animation setting
thing would would be like we probably
want that to be
you know
an actual function you call
just to start making this a little bit
more sane
remember what this thing is called the
like it's an animation type or something
so you know you would say like okay the
dt for this entity
gets set and the animation for this
entity gets set at the same time
so
when you do animation equals you're also
expected to basically be saying like
what's the speed
uh the t movement on that i guess we'll
just say gets set automatically as well
right
something like
that um
and then from then on we just say like
yeah you're always going to call this to
set the animation and you're expected to
provide
like here
that's now just like we're going to set
the animation
uh and again this is just me like slowly
deciding like how this code should look
and as we know more
um about how we want the code to look we
want to start cleaning it up right like
because once we know what we're doing
we want to make things a little bit more
systemic so that we don't have errors
we just want to make things where if you
know you always do
x and y at the same time then you want
something that just like does that
automatically so that everyone who's
doing it can't accidentally forget right
to do one or the other
so that's really all i'm doing here is
just starting to aggregate slowly like
pull these things up together
to put them into
what i think is roughly how they should
look
that's all
uh that is okay so
so this i'm not gonna touch for now
though um because the the floating head
things are we we just haven't really
implemented
um
so they're just gonna stay
kind of weirdly nerfed i guess this one
would work
i don't know what a brain monster is
even to be completely honest with you
um i'm not sure what's a familiar i
don't even know which these things are
anymore they were just test things that
kind of got pulled
sort of slowly
uh through the code base as we
like changed other things and we're
working on other things
they
you know
um
they kind of got like
yeah set in this kind of weird way so
i kind of feel like this stuff probably
also is going to end up being
like shouldn't this part be
in the
non-stop
portion because something that's in the
middle of animating that gets paged out
of this set it's like we don't
we probably don't pick up that animation
we probably reset at that point right
so it would be a little weird
i would think
but i don't know
uh so that all looks fine for now like
those guys are hopping around and it's
all fine
um so now inside the actual entity code
let's see if we break anything by
switching to the new dt that's there
so instead of this that's just like four
which was just like some hard-coded
thing which you know we just said like
that's what it will be for now
um we're gonna set it to be like
parameterized per entity so the entity
itself just says like here's what i
think
um
my animation update rate should be
okay
so
uh
all the hopping people are working now
and so now we just need to go to the
glove
and when we set the animation for the
glove we set it to something and that
would allow us to set it to be a
particular speed or whatever right
um
that
would be
so
so really i'm not sure
where and or how
we
want to set this
good
uh
this part is
a little more confusing so
like if an entity's movement rate is set
to zero then it will never advance to
the next thing which seems bad and maybe
we want us to special case that like
zero just means you immediately switch
to the next one
i'm not sure
i'm not sure what that should do
that's that's a difficult call
um
yeah hmm
i say so i'm not sure how i want to deal
with that i i'm guessing that we want
something like
and i don't know i'm just just vaguely
guessing here i'm guessing we want
something like when you go to process an
update for an entity if the if the dt
movement
is actually zero then it just sets t
movement to be one exactly
right
so like
you know if nd dt movement equals zero
or
you finished
either one
right um and i don't know how i want to
deal with that i'm just i just haven't
really thought about it much right we'll
see
but it's probably something like that
right
so
while we're doing punches here right uh
like i was saying you probably want the
speed
uh for this to be
different than it is at the moment
um
so i don't know what the speed wants to
be it's but it's probably faster than
hopping right
um
so like that's probably more like what
you would normally expect
um
how do you get how am i getting three up
up three
that's a bug
anyway
all right so i think that's good enough
for now
uh with the attack pattern speed yes the
attack pattern does define the speed so
basically
uh
you can see that um
we've got it here and we've got it here
so
we that is what will happen eventually
uh
in the code
in this part of the code
[Music]
so this part right here
when it does this it will do you know
it would do
a set
for
the
the dt movement
right
uh i did not do that yet because i mean
i guess i could do it now because i
don't know that these are set properly
yet they might be
um but i think
like
the glove
so
so yeah we have to go set the glove
stats but we can do we'll just do that
and that's fine
so like if we set this now it won't work
is my point um but but we can just go
set the gloves that's not hard and
that's all we would really need
so for the move we could set the speed
here right to and and now we just need
to make sure we actually go set it uh in
the glove stats otherwise it won't do
anything
but we can definitely do that what we
would need to do here is say okay the
base stats for the glove when we set the
max move count
we would need to set the base stats for
the other
things so
the
the move cue like
or move square a b and c
we need to set these to something right
and who knows what they should be
um
but now we should in theory if we wanted
to if we switch back to that sort of
other test one where we say like oh the
attack pattern is is going to be this
now
um
because there's a b and c we could now
go to the glove and
set it so that like one of those is
really slow like like the in between one
is very slow
so it goes like slow fast slow fast
right
so again uh
not a lot of interesting stuff there
just sort of getting the basics down so
we can start to work on
the
feelings the feel it feels of the
gameplay uh
which will acquire us like doing a bunch
of tuning code here
um if that makes sense
uh was pressed okay thank you yeah we'll
we'll deal with that stuff a little bit
later
all right i think that's i'm going to
call it for today that's fine we're
we're more or less where we need to be
so that's good
um i will be back here next weekend to
probably we'll do like
try to do damage next
and then we'll maybe collapse down to
grid which is a big change we have to
make and i think we'll just simplify
everything so we'll do that
so we can pull out a lot of this code
because there's just too much code in
there right now that doesn't really do
anything
um it's just there to support like
not being on a grid
you know
uh all right so that's it
i'm gonna look and see i don't know if
john's still streaming he's probably not
um but if he is
we will go there for sure
um so give me one second to
see but uh yeah i guess i'll stop
recording first so thanks everyone for
joining me and i will see you next
weekend
and and soon you'll be sent to jonathan
blue