hello everyone and welcome to handmade
here are the show recode a complete game
live on stream he right here on twitch
with no engines and no libraries it's
just us an old-school programming here
we have built ourselves quite a bit of
stuff over the past hundred and sixty
hours of programming and we're kind of
getting to the end of our engine
development here slowly winding down to
the point where we will have done all
the stuff that we wanted to do for
support and we'll sort of be moving a
little bit into game programming but we
still have a couple big things to go and
right now we kind of got to a point
where we could if we want to call our
asset system done but I kind of wanted
to talk about a couple other things
related to it just to sort of give some
perspective on it right now what we did
yesterday is we finished transitioning
our asset system over to something where
it uses a relatively fixed amount of
memory to operate so it will free assets
when it needs to load new ones it'll go
find ones that aren't used or haven't
been used recently free those and
loading new ones so we've done that but
the way that we did that is I just I
showed how to do the structure of that
given that you could ask for and give
memory back to the operating system so
the operating systems virtual page table
was basically substituting in for a
general-purpose allocator for our
purposes which is actually probably fine
and 64-bit but I don't know that it
would be fine in 32-bit I'm not 100%
confident that and unfortunately we
don't really have a lot of great ways to
test that at the moment since we don't
have the full game done we don't really
know we can't just run it under 32-bit
and see whether the asset load and usage
patterns happen to create problems or
not so I don't really know but what we
might want to do for at the very least
is take a little bit of a look at
writing our own general-purpose
allocator in there for educational
purposes and you know we can write it in
such a way that it's free for us to
switch between the two right and that
way we could get a little perspective on
it but still always have the ability to
switch to the opera
systems 1 if we find that that's more
expedient or more useful so I think that
might be what we'll take a look at today
but before I do that let me point out
that today is day 160 if you have
pre-ordered the game on handmade hero
org then what you want to do is unzip
day 159 source code into a directory
that is the source code that I am
starting with today and so you will be
able to follow along at home if you
start with day 159 all right so where we
left off see here let's go ahead and
load this load this up where we left off
is we had we had everything kind of
working and paging out assets and it was
just we were forcing it to use a very
small asset size a total asset footprint
and it seems to be doing that just fine
we can do whatever we want and it seems
to handle it no problems with that and
yes we still have like heads spewing out
of us that's just something that happens
now it again there's no reason to be
alarmed about that it's all fine but
what I was saying was that if you take a
look inside handmade assets EPP what you
can see is that we were calling and
allocate function we have these two
things acquire asset memory and release
asset memory and what we were doing
there is we were just basically punting
to the operating system and asking the
operating system for a new set of pages
every time we wanted to store an asset
and then releasing pages back to the
operating system every time we got rid
of an asset right so if we wanted to
what we would do here if we wanted to
basically do the memory allocation
entirely ourselves is we just want to
replace these two functions acquire
asset memory and release asset memory we
want to replace those two functions with
functions that we could implement
ourselves that would allocate or free
the memory right so that's you know
that's what I mean by writing a
general-purpose allocator
you notice that these are completely
general the assets can be free to any
time or allocated any times there is no
stack like structure to it which most of
the things in a
are happy to use and that is why we get
away with not really needing any
general-purpose allocators or any other
things like that anywhere else right
essentially by structuring things so
that they operate on stacks what that
basically gives us is it gets us out of
having to deal with any lifetime issues
so that's why we don't need a garbage
collector right or anything like that
you know we don't need to or we and we
don't need smart pointers doing any of
that stuff right so it gets us out of
that and it gets us out of having to
write something that does allocation
placement because we know that things
just come in in order right so basically
structuring this taxes actually gives us
this twofold benefit it allows us to get
a not have to worry about lifetime stuff
so no garbage structures no smart
pointers that stuff right so that's
great
gets rid of all that complexity and any
kind of performance problems all that
stuff is gone
and it gets us out of the notion of
having to figure out where to place
things in memory which is kind of a
separate thing from lifetime management
and that of course is is because things
just can come in and order and get
popped off in order right that's the
nature of a stack and so what we have in
the asset system is we don't really have
a lifetime management problem because we
all that stuff is very clearly known and
the asset system itself does you know
its own least recently used tracking of
that so again it's a kind of a virtual
memory scheme in there so we've done the
work to figure out what kinds of
lifetime stuff we want to have happen
and so we don't need any of the other so
we don't need some IRA pointers or
garbage collectors or that sorts of
things because we you know again once we
actually write the algorithm that we
actually want for hat figuring out life
times which was that sort of circular
link list thing those other things are
extraneous we don't need them but we do
have the problem of where to place the
memory right and that is the part that
we are left with here right so what you
could imagine is if we were to take sort
of a giant chunk of memory and say all
you get mr. asset system is that giant
chunk of memory what are you going to do
when we do acquire an asset memory how
are you going to manage that right how
are you going to deal with what's going
happen as that stuff gets allocated and
free and we talked about essentially the
you know the fundamental problem there
which is that you know you've kind of
got this this structure happening and if
you imagine what happens in our stack
you know you allocate asset a then you
allocate asset B and then you allocate
assets C and then maybe D and E and
there are all different sizes right
currently and so on and so what we want
to do is we want to say okay at some
point we're gonna have to allocate a new
asset right and that's gonna be asset H
but we're filt we're full up there's no
room for asset H in here right so now we
have to figure out we want to evict
least recently used people and maybe you
know we start to evict released recently
used people we get into a situation
where we can't fit it so maybe B was the
least recently used right now if B was
bigger than H or the same size as H we
could just slot it right in there
right but unfortunately for us if it's
not then H can't fit and so then we have
to evict the next you know we have to
evict more things right like maybe a or
something right and then we would know
oh okay H can fit in here and so then
we're able to place H right and you can
see that's pretty pretty hard problem
you could see that if you really needed
to make this very tight and very good
you could sort of see this being
actually a very big time investment on a
project if like if you felt like this
was crucial to the success of your game
for example which it's not going to be
in handmade hero because we have
probably plenty of memory to play with
but if you are like really obsessed with
getting the smallest possible memory
footprint and the most possible asset
preservation you can see how this would
be pretty complicated because in this
case like you might look and say oh well
the least recently used was B the next
most recently used were like was like E
and F right and enf taken together will
fit H but B won't
and since freeing B doesn't help us put
H in there we just shouldn't freebie
right we should free these other guys
instead
and that's a really complicated thing to
think about because you need to think
about like where they are and like what
will happen when you free multiple of
them you know what if it was like II was
the least recently used and then B and
then F and so then you'd have to know to
like free e skip B leave it there free F
and then you'd figure out that it would
be big in it right you can see this it's
really pretty complicated right so
hopefully you can kind of appreciate
that this is sort of a whole domain of
interesting problems memory placement in
fragmentation management that's where
stuff it's like a whole field and you
could choose to spend months if this was
your jam or if it was very important for
something you were doing like optimizing
this sort of stuff and I say optimizing
I don't mean like fiddling with Cindy
like to get like cycles down or whatever
I mean algorithmically thinking about it
and changing how your algorithms worked
and building interesting data structures
and doing you know who knows what now I
might also suggest that if that was what
you were gonna do though that may be
picking one of the other options that we
had further up the chain like making the
asset files be broken into tile so that
you know you always load things of
similar sizes and stuff like that that
may have been a smarter thing to do
right
and so you might make different
decisions if you decide this was the the
thing that was most important to you as
well and that's the sort of a separate
issue but again if it turned out that
you were in a situation where variable
allocation was necessary and it was
crucial it's kind of this whole separate
field that you could go into and look
into and we're not gonna get that hard
core on it because there's really no
need for us to do so but I just wanted
to kind of make you aware of that so
let's talk about this a little like how
would we go about implementing something
like this as a very straightforward kind
of a thing so you can kind of imagine
what we would have at the beginning is
we just have a gigantic empty piece of
memory right we just say like oh you
know we'd have and to be fair we might
say that we don't have one gigantic
piece because maybe windows can't on
32-bit windows you know maybe we
use two gigabytes well that's not
realistic maybe we want to use one
gigabyte for our asset storage or
something fairly large and on 32-bit
Windows it can't find one gigabyte of
contiguous memory or something like this
and so out trying to out virtual a lock
one gigabyte as something to give our
app might just not work okay so we may
need to do is say okay we would start
off with some series of things some
series of free regions right so it
wouldn't it only be one big one it would
be something like a few regions that we
get handed from the operating system
right so we've kind of got a set here
right and each one of these is something
like you know maybe each one of these is
is 256 Meg's right I don't know or maybe
it's like you know maybe that's even
that's too big I don't know what it
would be be whatever we can get away
with 64 megabytes who knows right
so we'd have some number of these chunks
and we would need some kind of a free
list basically some kind of a thing that
manages the memory that we've got where
we could sort of say okay what I need to
allocate something I going to take some
space from one of these things that's
free right and we could fill them up
initially just like the stacks so then
we could put something if we needed to
put something in there we put something
in there and now we know that it's got
less free so now it's got you know fifty
nine megabytes free or something like
that right
who knows so something like that and
then what we need to be able to do
eventually and that's pretty easy right
and when this gets full we could just
put it in the next one
so what we need to do is basically have
some kind of a list that sort of says
okay here are the things that we've got
free right here are the places we could
put stuff and when we need to put stuff
we look to see if any of them can hold
it if they can we put it there if we
don't need oh right and so where things
start to get more complicated is when
this starts to get oh you know this is a
start get a little bit trickier but you
know if you think about it that initial
situation where I just have a couple of
these free that's really old
the same thing is gonna happen once I
start getting fragmentation right if I
have some guy in here who's got like a
couple things right
free or a couple things filled and then
I free something out of the middle right
and maybe free something out of the top
then really what I could think of this
as being is just another set of
fragments here right I could just think
of us as having more fragments here is
one free fragment and here's another
free fragment right so in some sense you
can sort of see that like we could start
to think about the memory as sort of
this concept of some series of blocks
which could have stuff put in them in
each of them has like a size right so
each of the allocator each of the the
memory reasons has some size and it's
like this much memory is free and then
in some sense when we're actually doing
the allocation we don't really even have
to think about the parts that are filled
in some sense right we just have to
think about the thoughts that are free
because the allocator just needs to know
is there a chunk of memory that could
hold this thing that I'm trying to put
in it right that's all it really needs
to know so whereas things start to get
more interesting in terms of having to
think about the actual field space is
when stuff gets freed right so if I take
a view of this block here right if I
were to just view this block right of
stuff where I filled it here and I
filled it here but it's empty here in
here if I were to think of that as just
disjoint regions right here's region a
here's region B and I've got a and I've
got B right well that would work fine
for allocation nothing wrong happens to
allocation we would just look at a and
say can we fit something in a we look at
B can we fit something in B and party on
right but what happens when we free this
block right here right it's between a
and B if this block got freed then a and
B are now actually not separated anymore
there's a contiguous thing there so they
can actually become a bigger single
contiguous block for allocation purposes
right they can become you know a B C
this whole block right so even though
when we're allocating we don't actually
care about the filled space
we do need some way of knowing that
there is free space I'm sorry of the
filled space we need some way of knowing
that there's filled space because the
only way we can know to recombine memory
back into bigger chunks is if we know
when we free the free space where it lay
will in relation to the other chunks of
memory right so that's how that works
that's that's what we're gonna have to
do now what if some of the things we
know well this is an asset system so
basically there's no small assets right
so basically what we're talking about
here is we don't have to worry about
things like someone allocating one byte
or sixteen bytes nobody to me allocating
small things people are gonna be
allocating things that are like 64 K or
something right there gonna be
allocating chunks that are reasonably
sized and what that means is we're never
going to have really any situation we
could we can pre declare that we're
never gonna have any situation where the
free space itself couldn't fit a fair
bit of data in it right we can just that
can just happen right it's not an issue
and so what we could start to do here
just thinking about it right is we could
start to think about saying well okay if
we just wanted to do this in a very
inefficient fashion you could imagine
doing something where we just we have
lots of memory right and those blocks of
memory are laid out such that every free
block of memory you know kind of on its
either side has some information about
what comes after it right or who it is
even something like this right so you
can imagine that if we freed this block
of memory and we wanted to know if we
could merge it with the block above it
right you could imagine us doing
something where we actually have some
information about that block stored
right in sort of in lines with the
blocks themselves right you could
imagine some kind of little like header
information that's in there in such a
way that we wouldn't have to you
an out-of-band piece of storage for it
and so that we wouldn't have to pre work
you know we wouldn't have to really
worry so much about how many there would
be because it's just a block of memory
and however many chunks you dice it up
into those chunks themselves would store
little pieces of information in them
that let us know what we would do with
those chunks later right so I don't know
you can you can kind of see what I'm
getting at here there's probably some
options we have for just putting in line
with the memory the information we would
need to do say the merging operation
right that's plausible so yeah so
there's stuff like that and we can start
playing with that so the real thing you
know and if you think about that
operation it's not very complicated I'm
gonna free this thing I need to check to
see whether I merge it up or merge it
down or both right that's a pretty easy
thing to conceptualize like it's not
that hard to figure out how we're going
to do it
that's like really not something to be
too concerned about what's a little bit
more concerning right is the allocation
side so let's say we've got all these
things let's say we did this simplest
possible thing and just strung them
together right so we've got you know
something that looks like this right and
we've got some stuff that's actually
being used in there like so something
like this so let's say we need to
allocate something and what we have is
some kind of threading so we can kind of
go like okay the first free block is
here and it points to the next free
block and that points to the next free
block and that point is the next free
block and that points the next free
block right so what we could do is when
we need to allocate something we just
walk all the free blocks right we just
walk them all all the way through and
after walking all the way through we
just make a decision about what we want
to do in terms of which one we want to
put it in right and presumably the one
we would want to put it in is the free
block whose size is like you know
closest to the size we were looking for
because that leaves the least fragment
or another way to look at it would be if
we were to put this this piece
this asset into this block what would
the leftover block size be and how well
do we think that leftover block size
will actually do we think that left very
much will be usable for anything else
right and one of the interesting things
about our system is that when we load in
our asset files we actually could spin
over them quickly once and determine
what all the asset actual asset sizes
are right that's something we can
actually do and so we would know for
example our rough histogram if we wanted
to we could we could imagine something
where we could actually plot you know we
could say here's a histogram of sizes
where we go like here's a sizes okay
we've got you know 4 K assets and 8 K
assets and 16 K assets and 3 2 K assets
and blah blah blah right and we know we
have some distribution of these things
right something like this we are
actually in a position to make a
heuristic call somewhere right we're in
a position to sort of say if we wanted
to figure lis accurately what the
chances are that we're gonna hit an
asset you know that's in a certain size
range right because if we know that like
you know there's 4,000 16 K assets right
but there's only you know 200 or
something not to scale so you know if we
know that's the case then we would not
be super concerned about something that
left say a 17 K size because we'd be
like well we'll probably be able to fill
that but if the opposite were true and
we had almost no 16 you know we had no
assets less than 16 K but a ton of
assets greater than 16 K we'd be pretty
nervous about leaving at 17 K fragment
because what are we gonna put there you
know very few things could go there so
you know there's stuff we could do like
that
so yeah so that's the situation as it
stands at the moment and you know it's
it's pretty complicated what we're
dealing with here we it's like I said
this is this is pretty complicated code
it might be one of the most complicated
things we do on handmade here oh is this
this part of the asset system right the
whole and with when you when taken
together the whole like okay background
assets are being streamed in and they're
being used in the ground chunks and and
they have arbitrary memory sizes and all
the sort of stuff right you can kind of
see how there's a fair bit of complexity
here compared to say the renderer which
despite the fact that it's a very sort
of you know it's very mathy and it's
it's very intricate it just doesn't have
the same level of sort of I want to say
interlocking pieces it's more like
everything is a very well isolated thing
it's like here's how we fill a pixel and
it just kind of happens right there and
it doesn't have like all these sort of
competing things going at the same time
like this like the asset system does so
really I think the asset system is
probably one of the most complicated
parts when you think about it that way
so anyway yeah so we've got about a half
hour left so let's just you know let's
just play around let's see where we get
we won't try to do anything particularly
fancy here but yeah I mean point being
you can kind of see why there's a fair
bit of complexity here
and there's some things about our asset
system the fact that we have background
threads using the asset system is also
mixing more complicated because it means
that at the point where we allocate
memory we can't necessarily guarantee
that we can free memory at that point
and other sorts of relatively complex
things such as that right
is that actually true though
that may not be true that may not be
true at all to be honest with you I
think I may have been operating on a
slightly false assumption it may be that
we actually have a lot more flexibility
there than I was gonna say because when
an asset is being loaded its state is
set to queued and we never free an asset
whose state is set to queued so actually
I guess we can just free assets just
fine in the middle of that so I don't
really know why I said that
in fact the evict asset stuff I may just
have been wrong it may be that we can
just flat out evict to the assets like
in the middle of that thing because move
header to front never is allowed on
locked assets so assets that are in the
background ground chunk stuff can't be
happening so it's only happening when
assets get used and assets used only in
the main thread and so I feel like yeah
I mean it's oh my feel like almost we
actually can evict assets right in the
place where we actually need to to do
the load so I may have been wrong about
that I feel like we could almost do it
this way now that I'm thinking it
through a little bit more which is that
we could make it so that up here evict
assets as necessary right we could make
it so that we only do this step when we
do a choir asset memory right so we so
evict assets as necessary is not
actually going to be is not actually
going to be
it's not actually something that has to
be pumped am I missing anything I don't
think I am I really I just don't think I
am I don't know I could be wrong about
that we'd have to think it through very
carefully obviously but I feel like
that's a fairly safe statement to say I
feel like you know you can just evict
assets as necessary we can just call
that when we do an acquire and when we
go to do an acquire asset memory that
could be the time that we call it Victor
assets I'm gonna try that I'm just gonna
go ahead and do that here and then I'm
gonna get rid of the call to evict
assets as necessary that's in here right
so evict assets if necessary it's just
gonna go away
maybe I just you know because I thought
before we would need to do that and I'm
just wondering now me I just don't know
if I was wrong or not I don't know if
maybe I'm just forgetting like the the
crucial reason why that's not true
but yeah so let's see that down here we
got to get rid of this this asset memory
sighs it's not necessary anymore release
asset memory is here we go let's see
it's not really a good test cuz with
anything that involves multi-threading
you know just running it and if it works
does not really definitely tell you much
because you could easily have like race
conditions that just don't happen
hardly ever you know
so yeah but you know it doesn't
immediately fail which is something you
know it lets you know that you're not
completely wrong
it just doesn't let you know that you're
right but the reason that that's
interesting is because I like that
aspect because what that means is that
really we can just do a victus it's as
necessary as something that is part of
our allocation process right and that's
kind of nice I like that all right so
let's see what goes on here let's see
what we need to do for our asset memory
stuff here since I don't actually know
right so let's see we've got add asset
header to list and a little bit map and
all these other good things so when
we're doing this stuff when we call
acquire asset memory if I wanted to
change this wire asset memory if I
wanted to change acquire asset memory to
allocate out of our own memory instead
of calling the operating system here is
the part where I need to start to figure
out how I am going to do that and so we
kind of had before we had our arena we
we had like a sub arena set up for this
right in here we said you know sub arena
right and I think what I want to do
there right is I I want to kind of
change that around so that instead of an
arena which is not really what I want
anymore because this is not going to be
like a stack like we were using what I
want instead is just to get that chunk
of memory right so I want to get rid of
this arena here and remove anywhere that
was using it which i think is literally
just the allocation here right but what
I can do now is I can go ahead and take
some of that memory so if I were to do
something like you know struct asset
memory block or something I don't know
yet
again this is I'm not really doing
anything serious here I'm just gonna
sort of throw one of these in here so we
have like an asset memory block and
we'll just I don't know call that first
block or something and here we just have
a
total size right and then we'd have like
a used size so if I was just gonna
duplicate essentially the memory arena
stuff first then you know we could kind
of kind of start working from there all
right so if I were to do that then what
I want to do is when I get my assets
here I'm gonna make a first block thing
I'm just gonna go ahead and get the I
guess what I want to do is is get the
the entire size of memory that I want
right which is going to be this this
size parameter here the thing they pass
in I'm just gonna grab that so I'm going
to do like a push size onto the game
asset arena thing I'm gonna get that
back and I'm gonna say that I've got one
of these asset blocks at the top of it
for now
right asset memory block there we go do
push size on that so now we've got that
and then I'm gonna go ahead and say that
the first block total size right equals
that size and the first block use size
is gonna equal the size minus the part
that I've actually used for storing that
header right so I'm just assembling one
of these little blocks in there right
that's what I'm doing total size equals
size oh that's a pointer there we go
and yeah I don't actually need that to
be a memory index because we're not
gonna let it get that big but we'll just
do this for now all right so if I do
that now I've got this block and I'm
just gonna go ahead and sort of
duplicate basically what we do in the
arena just as a start for acquire asset
memory right so as a start what I'm
gonna do is I'm gonna say okay we had
this thing with this platform allocate
memory we're gonna go ahead and pretend
that that doesn't exist anymore right
that's not a thing so off it goes and
I'm gonna do the same thing with that
release asset memory I'm gonna say okay
you
we don't have that anymore and so what
I'm gonna do like a comment these two
note okay say this is the platform
memory half right and then what I'm
gonna do is I'm using I'm just going to
I'm just going to go ahead and no I
can't I'm just going to go ahead and
implement the simplest possible thing
here right so for starters I need to get
a void pointer which is going to come
from like that first block right so I'm
going to say I have an asset memory
block or whatever it is I'm gonna get to
that block out of the assets and then I
am going to just grab the memory right
so I know that the asset that the block
right after the block is where the
memory starts right because I just put
the block at the top of the memory and I
know that the block itself records how
much is used oh so I guess now I think
about it I actually kept used size in
there that may not be a good idea that
may not be a good idea I you know I take
that back
go to size I'm gonna do it this way I'm
gonna say that the total size is
actually this and the use size is zero
in fact that was the wrong computation
for use size anyway that was just like
that so the total size I'm gonna say is
actually however much we allocated minus
the asset block size and then we haven't
used any of it yet okay rather than
saying I could have initialized use size
to be the size of the header all right
so yeah so that's where the result would
be and then block you size right would
increment by whatever the size is that
we were trying to acquire and so I'm
going to assert here that they used size
is going to be less than the total size
and if theory that assert should fire
because we will run out of asset space
and we're not able to free anything yet
right
so yeah let's take a look
plus equals sighs okay and let's take a
quick look here
there we go so eventually we just run
out of space and that is the end of it
right that is the end of our little
party we hit the assertion that says if
I were to actually you know this this
this thing is is that big right it's
this is how many bytes it's got in it
this is how many bytes we're using so
we've got this much left right before we
hit the end of the block oh wait what
total size - block use size how is the
use size oh we actually went over there
that's no good
I want block use size plus size right
that's what we actually want let's try
that one more time there we go
that's more like it so this is how much
we have left but the size of this
particular asset is this so it won't fit
right and so what I want to do here is I
want to then try to at this is the point
when I actually detect this right what
we want to do is now instead of that
being assertion what I want to do is say
if what I would have done like the block
size plus the size if that would
overflow like if I can't find a place
for it then I am going to on effect I've
put it in here as an assert after the
fact if I would have overflowed then
that is the time when I actually would
start to evict things right so it's
almost it's it's really just a thing
that's going to the right it's we want
to see when we hit our memory limit and
when we find that we literally can't put
anything else in there that is the time
to then go start reclaiming stuff right
but I hope that make sense okay all
right so that's what we want to do okay
unfortunately we don't have any ability
to actually free stuff yet right we have
no way of doing anything like that
because when we do a free on something
we don't even know like what block it's
in right like we have no idea so we need
to start figuring out some way of
keeping track of this stuff so again I'm
gonna do something that's I'm gonna do
something not particularly intelligent
right I don't claim that this is at all
good I'm just gonna sort of start to
work my way through the problem of
getting this memory into some sort of a
flexible shape that will allow us to
fulfill the requirements and they may
not be great
it made the performance might not be
great of it or whatever but I'm just
gonna try to sort of work through it
to figure out what I want to do here so
I'm gonna do is I'm going to introduce
an asset memory block sort of I don't
want to call it tag does that mean
something in our asset system already so
it's sort of an asset memory block
almost it's like a little thing it gets
inserted like a waypoint or what do I
want to call this it's it's sort of like
a partition I don't know what I want to
call that asset memory block barrier
stripe marker how about marker right so
these black markers what I want to do is
every time I allocate something I want
to insert one of these block markers so
that the block marker will tell me what
it is that I need to do right with this
thing and you know I could actually just
use asset memory block for that
potentially
in fact that may be the easier thing to
do instead I can do a separate thing so
let's say I've got this right it's got
the the total size you sighs I'm gonna
change sort of the way that it's
conceptualized I'm just gonna say that
my asset memory block right oops
just has a size that's all it has right
so I know how big this asset memory
block is but it also has sort of a a
notion of where it is relative to other
things right so there's also asset
memory block like that's the previous
block from this block right and maybe
there's a next so if they're like let's
say these things are threaded through
here and there's a size and then there's
like whether or not this block is used
right so there's like something like
this right so I'd say asset memory block
flags asset memory used right so instead
of having that sort of stack based thing
I'm just gonna make like this little
kind of lame little guy right who just
kind of sits there and says what's going
on with this thing okay so for her to do
that
how would this now look well at the
outset now asset memory block when we
create it it's going to be different
it's gonna be a little bit different
right so what's gonna happen here is
we're gonna push size on this previous
is gonna be equal to nothing right next
is gonna be equal to nothing I don't
know if we want to EE link that guy
probably not cuz my guess you know I
don't know
that's a good question maybe we do want
the it to be circular maybe we do want
it to be circular I don't know I don't
know let's just do it why not
I'm curious so there's our memory sense
and all right we've got an asset memory
block here and we're gonna we're just
gonna we're gonna go for it
we're gonna just go for it you know what
fortune favors the brave people okay I
just how that goes so I'm going to say
that we've got this memory Sentinel here
right and it's got a flags of zero and
it's got a size of zero because they
can't store nothing right and it's got a
previous pointer that points to itself
and it's got a next pointer that points
to itself right and then what I'll do is
I'll say that I want to insert a block
into this list so what I want to do is
say insert block and I want to insert it
after the memory sentinel that's what I
want to do and this is the memory for
that block right and this is the block
size right something like that and then
the insert block Hall is just going to
be in charge of like sticking some
memory in to this thing right so there's
the memory and this is the asset memory
block that it comes before so this is
the previous block right that makes
sense
so how do we do that well we've already
seen how to do that it's really really
basic right like I said we just say that
the block itself the sort of control
feature for the block has to go into the
specific location itself there's some
reasons why you know I feel like I kind
of want this to be aligned as well which
wouldn't quite be at the moment so you
know we might do something more like
this just thrown that out there
so yeah just just because we want this
thing to be on 128 bit boundary but
that's kind of separate we'll get we'll
get to that stuff a little later on down
the party line anyway so when we're
doing this what we want to do here is is
and I guess we could call that a memory
index but or usage before so what we
want to do here is we want to stick the
block into the the memory thing we want
to probably also assert that the size is
greater than the size of one of these
things cuz we're never allowed to
actually make one smaller than that or
we can't fit the control block in it
right we would then say that the blocks
size is whatever the size is minus the
part we just used just like we did
before and then we would go ahead and
link it up again just the standard link
listing here where we say like okay our
previous is our previous and our
whatever was after our previous is our
next right and then we just do the
standard thing here where our previous
next is is now us and our next previous
is also us right so we just kind of
insert our link into the into the
rolling link there right
okay so now we have our memory blocks we
know that the flags field
I guess well we didn't actually set that
so we know that the size field but we
didn't set the flag the flags field to
be zero because it's not used so that's
that's just how we would insert that
block and we would probably return it in
case the person who was adding it asking
us to add it wanted to do something with
it right so yeah that's all fine nothing
particularly fancy there and so in here
I'm just going to put that up at the top
so we can do that block insertion stuff
so now we will have inserted a block and
so now if we wanted to allocate memory
and again this is going to be some of
the worst code ever for the moment we do
acquire asset memory we just need to
look first to see is there a memory
block that could actually hold what we
want to hold right so we're literally
just going to do that like this we're
gonna say we're gonna say asset memory
block instead of first block we're gonna
say find block for size we're gonna pass
the size that's going to return us a
memory block if we got a block back we
will assume that that block is able to
hold us right so we'll do an assertion
and say that the use size the size looks
right we'll do that thing is to assume
that it could fit in there
right and then we'll just go ahead and
make that all that same stuff that we
were doing before block you size
listicle size blah blah blah blah blah
right all that stuff just should just
work right oh wait I'm sorry
but except for this part so what we need
to do now since this block is going to
be used we need to slip the lock right
we need to slip the block in half we
need to use one part of it and reserve
the other part of it
so I'm gonna basically say something
goes here not that and and then what we
have to do is finish the rest of this
loop so we want this thing to go until
it actually is able to place it so if we
do find block for size and we are unable
to find a block right then what we want
to do is we want to evict an asset right
we want to evict whatever the asset is
that we could yeah that we could have
evicted we want to be able to do
essentially this path right so while
we're in this loop we want to say okay
find a block if we found a block to put
it in put it in that block if we did not
find a block to put it in right and by
the way we're done at that point right
we don't have to keep looking if we did
not find a block to put it in then we
have to start evicting assets right so
then we would do something where we go
like okay we would go ahead and say take
the asset memory header the lease is not
really used one we would assume that
there is something too free so we start
trying to free it we come in here right
get that asset we free the asset we
would want to do this until we actually
freed an asset right so this one would
also want to do something where it would
say okay start with the previous go
until you hit the Sentinel and always do
header you know always walk the list
kind of backwards right as soon as you
find one that you can evict evict it and
you are done right another thing I guess
we could do is right here just see if
the block see if the block that we were
if it can be asset from we kind of know
that that's the block we want so really
I guess it looks like this something
like this first we try to find a block
to the size from then on we just use
whatever block this asset was actually
in and we want evict asset to return us
whatever that block actually was right
and so here is evict
when it goes to release asset memory we
would want that release asset memory
call it to tell us what the actual block
was that it released so that we can
check that resulting block to see
whether or not we could put the asset in
there right does that make some sense
it's kind of an optimization right so I
could do something like this for now
right I could do something like this for
now to do actually do this instead of
just saying you're gonna do it right and
so what are these things look like right
what do these things look like
well fine block for size again if we
just don't think about performance or
anything else we're just trying to make
it work it's not - and this is probably
not an inline anymore it's probably not
too tricky right fine block for size all
it does is scan through all the blocks
and if there is a block that is not if
it finds a block that could have space
in it that's a you know if you find the
block that's not used I could fit it it
could return it ready we could literally
be that simple right we could also find
the one that was the best match block if
we wanted to
right for now we're not going to do it
so it's going to do right best match
block and in here I'm just gonna loop
through all the stuff so we've got asset
memory block block equals Sentinel next
right
so that's asset memory Sentinel right
I'm gonna say that I loop through well
the block is not equal to the memory
Sentinel and we just kind of walk that
chain like so yeah and so when I look at
a block I say if the block Flags is not
used right so if whatever it is is used
that would come back true so we do like
that it's a black flags it's not you
then we say if the block size is greater
than or equal to the size we want right
then we can use it now there's a caveat
here which is that actually the size
that we need it to be because we're
going to use up the block oh wait no I
take it back
there is no caveat it's fine I think
we'll find out okay so we're gonna come
through here and what we want to do is
say here's our results this is the block
we would say the results equals this
block and we are done
and we return the block back so this
just cancer who think tries to find a
block that we could put it in as soon as
we find one again we're not doing a best
match we just there it is we just give
it back
right happy days everyone's happy you
were done right and so that would find
it and then the question is what do we
do when we actually find it right well
what we do when we find it is we have to
take that block and either split the
block in half or just use the block so
if the amount of space that was left
over was going to be appreciable we
would split the block if it wasn't then
we wouldn't right so here we go you take
the block we do fine block for size
right if we found the block we say let's
assert that however much the block size
is is less than the size that we need
I'm sorry all the way around assert that
the size that we need will fit in this
block right and I just want to double
check well I did insert block we do set
the size properly to be yeah to be what
it so we figure that out we then go
ahead and get the memory for the block
so we say okay the result here is going
to be just right after the block that's
that's what the memory we're actually
using is but because we're only using a
certain amount of it we may then want to
split the block in half right and if we
were to split the block in half well I
guess there's a couple things
here so first of all we want set the
black bloc flags right we want to set
the the fact we want to record the fact
that we use this block right so the
black flags are now going to be set to
use and the other thing we want to do is
we want to set we want to see if the
block size if the remaining size
basically right so the memory index
remaining size if the remaining size is
going to be anything appreciable that we
could actually use so whatever we'd say
if remaining size is greater than I
don't know let's say if the remaining
size is greater than threshold block
split threshold right and that's some
kind of a thing that's just like you
know what it's gotta be at least 4096
it's got to be at least a page I'm
making this up it's probably something
bigger than that right but let's say we
do that right so if it's at least that
we split it right so if the remaining
size for the block split threshold then
what I do is I do an insert block in the
remaining section right right so what I
do there is I say okay the block size is
now actually going to be the block size
minus whatever the part is that we're
going to use there right so yeah
whatever the block size was before we're
shrinking that down and and we're gonna
actually use this this bit right that's
correct right block size - size is the
remaining size yeah the block size we
subtract that and then we say okay let's
put the let's put the actual block a new
block header in it's going to be
inserted after us right it's going to be
whatever the remaining size was and its
location
oops it's location is going to be
wherever our wherever our result
plus the size that we used right like so
and that'll automatically link it up and
off we go right so yeah pretty
straightforward not particularly
difficult we now have the result
although the void star needs to be out
here or we won't be able to return it so
that's how that actually works but that
seems about right to me yeah so that's
all good and so then the only thing that
we would need to do to follow that would
be in release asset memory we would then
need to be smart about that as well so
we need to recover the block right so we
need to do the asset memory block block
is gonna have to be equal to you know
the memory minus one right we need to
kind of back it up one so that gets us
our block back and then we can just go
ahead and say oh the block the flags are
equal to you know and equals not so we
can clear that asset memory used we can
clear it out say it's not being used
anymore and then the only thing we
really need to do at that point is take
a look at our previous and next and
merge them right but I'm not going to do
that now because we're running out of
time right
if I only got about three minutes left
so we'll just do merge now that's one of
those things that like I just type a ton
of code in there's no way that's gonna
work so this is just gonna be a crash
festival will debug it tomorrow
how is it that every time every time I
say it's gonna be a crash it doesn't
crash how is that okay that's more what
I was expected to see but it still
didn't crash alright at least I can say
it's a bug festival so we have a ton of
work to do there obviously that we need
to figure out and make sure thing is is
more copacetic than that so we got a got
take care of all that and we will take
care of all that but for now I'm going
to go to the QA and and take questions
so if you have questions about what we
just did please ask them now put Q colon
in front of your question and and I will
be able to see it there we go oops
questions and answers
questions and answers I'm feeling good
about this as stupid as this algorithm
is I feel like it's more fun to write
this yourself so you guys can kind of
see how you write a general-purpose
allocator even a really lame one I think
is more fun than just having the app
having the operating system do it so I
think we're gonna go this I think I'm
gonna pull out the operating system one
and we're gonna do it this way
James Woodman given that this is an
optimization problem it seems like we'll
want to have a system for profiling
asset use and eviction and check its
output periodically as the game and
assets grow over the next year or so
should this be on the agenda in the near
term so actually it is on the agenda in
the near term already you will notice
that I put this next and that is because
now we have I feel like we have
sufficiently complicated stuff in the
game already in the engine that now is
the time to be able to see that stuff
because yeah we want to be able to know
stuff like how many assets are evicted
or allocated per frame we want to know
stuff like what how many memory blocks
there are how how fragmented they are
like we'd like to see that stuff
we've got threads we'd like to see what
the threads are doing you know so
there's pretty much no question that we
want that and so we've you know we've
gotten things up and running you could
make a game with what we have now right
we've got renderer we've got asset
system we've got like good stuff in
there we've even got sound playback
already right so I think now is the time
to kind of go all right let's put some
debug code in there so we can actually
visualize everything and kind of tighten
things down and you know cuz some of
these other things like doing lighting
or whatever is kind of just a it's just
a visual quality improvement but it
doesn't actually look you could ship
this game without ever doing this to do
right we just wouldn't have to have we
just have boring lighting or something
right but this is definitely something
that we wouldn't really be able to ship
the game without and have a high quality
because we just we need be able to see
this stuff I'm not clear on what happens
in the else when we fail to find a block
could you go over it
sure well first of all keep in mind
we've got bugs so what happens in the
else is probably wrong but yes so here's
how this loop is starting to take shape
we know that we need asset memory we
start out by saying okay try to find a
block in our linked list of memory
blocks that the asset could just go into
right if we find one then this is the
part that just splits the block in half
and stores the asset in the first half
right and if you can't split it then it
just doesn't bother
right otherwise if that means that we're
out of memory essentially meaning we
have filled all of the memory that we
have to fill and possibly including
fragmentations so we it doesn't mean
we've perfectly filled it but we've
mostly filled it right we then look loop
through all of the assets in the order
in reverse order of recents recently
used right so the first asset we will
look at is the one that we last we
touched the furthest in the past because
our assumption is that the thing that we
used the longest amount ago is the one
that's least likely to be necessary on
like the next frame right so we come in
here and say okay what's that asset if
that asset is like has a valid load flag
set so it's like we've looked and seen
that it actually is loaded and not like
in the middle of being processed by a
background task or something right then
what we do is we just evict it goodbye
it's gone right and when we evict it
that frees up some memory so that allows
us to then ask again for a block we go
back through the loop and see if we can
find one now now the reason I put it to
do here was because there's no reason
for us to keep looking through blocks
again once we free this because when we
free this we then know that the only we
know that there were no blocks that
could hold us before so when we free
some memory we know that the only block
that could possibly hold us now is
whatever the block was that was created
by that free and so that's why I say
like that's we want to go ahead and do
that shortly right
why do we need to check the remaining
size versus the threshold why not just
use the remaining size if it satisfies
the request size so these are two
different things so when we do find
block for size we assume that the block
it returns if it returned a block can
fit the size so we always place the
asset bare if one comes back right this
is the code that places the asset there
right we mark the memory block is used
and we place the asset there okay so
this check is only to see whether the
amount of memory left over in the block
warrants creating a new free block in
that location to be used later because I
don't want to bother if there was only
if there wasn't enough room to ever
store an asset in that block we should
not bother right in fact I could do a
thing here was like to do set this based
on the smallest asset size right and so
it's basically just saying don't bother
creating a block that we're gonna like
think about in the future if nothing
could fit here if we know that our
biggest I'm out if we know that our
smallest asset is 16 K big then we never
need to create a block that's smaller
than 16 K because nothing could ever go
there right so yeah but that's not
really so okay that's not really true
there is a separate thing that could
happen if the block after this block got
freed and wanted to take some of the
memory from the preceding block right
that could happen so what we could start
doing you know I could put it to do here
and be like to do actually record the
unused portion of the memory right in a
block so that we can do the merge on
blocks
when neighbors are free right so we
could do that as well snafoodle how come
this memory management system is
strictly limited to game assets and not
other things as well well the reason for
that at the moment is just because we
don't have anything else that needs it
in the future if we find that we have
some other part of the code that wants
to do general-purpose allocation for
some reason we could pull this out and
use it there but that would be the time
to do it right not not now prematurely
what will the GUI handle what what GUI
grumpy giant 256 if this were a
commercial product would it make sense
to use malloc instead here or write your
own anyway for managing assets well I
guess what I would say is if this were a
commercial product I might have gone
ahead and said I actually want to do all
the necessary work to do like asset
tiling and making sure that I actually
never have to do general-purpose
allocation I might have I don't know
that I would have but I might have
most of the time I try to make sure
everything that I ship goes through just
fixed block allocation so I really don't
know is the answer I don't know I
certainly never called malloc but you
know if you really have a
general-purpose allocation thing to do
then you know that is roughly what
you're using so that's fine right so
yeah I mean I think I think if you
actually determined that you really
needed a general-purpose allocator and
it wasn't just like for example what
we're doing it now where it's just kind
of like yeah it would be interesting to
do one so let's do one if you really
determined that's what you needed then I
would say yet you I don't know that I
would use even you necessary use malloc
I might go try to find a public domain
or open source allocator that I felt
comfortable using and and integrate that
into the codebase so that I knew that it
would be the same on all the platforms
and not differ based on the C runtime
library that I happen to using because
that I don't love that I don't love not
knowing what my malloc is doing and if I
use the C runtime libraries that means
every platform will do it differently
and that doesn't thrill me so so yeah I
don't know if using malloc would be the
right call but writing your own
allocator isn't necessary you could use
one that existed much like in hand
material in general we write everything
from scratch because that's the point of
the project that doesn't mean that if
you found a open source one or something
that you trusted that you couldn't use
it right like I said before you know I
like sometimes to use like Shawn's Shawn
Barrett's libraries right they're good
and so I don't I'm it doesn't bother me
to use that like it might bother me to
call malloc which I don't necessarily
trust cuz I don't have a whole lot of
confidence in the people who wrote it
necessarily any possibilities using
Markov chains probably not
it's looking like Vulcan if it gets
released on timely manner is going to be
a good choice for hard when during I
just read that you have control over all
memory to avoid any unknown allocations
explicit memory management in Vulcan
allows applications to use custom
allocation strategies for example to
allocate all memory upfront and avoid
any allocations during rendering so two
things about that
one I am on the Vulcan Advisory Board so
I cannot really comment on Vulcan things
due to NDA
second I would say that that statement
may be a little misleading but I can't
really say much else about it without
being NDA ish I would be interested to
know where you read that and who was
saying that because I don't even know
who was actually allowed to say
something like that yeah I guess I can't
really say much about that other than I
find that statement to be highly
misleading although it could technically
be considered true depending on how you
wish to define some of those words and I
can't elaborate because and I'm not sure
why whoever said that was allowed to say
that in the first place have you thought
about having a prefab asset that people
could use to make more complex assets
like a whole house with functional doors
I don't know what that means
the cuy mentioned in the to-do list ah
the GUI mentioned in the to-do list
you're talking about this that's just so
that we could like when we get all this
debug stuff in there it's you're gonna
need to be able to like view stuff that
wouldn't all fit on the screen or you
wouldn't be able to see the game if you
stuck it all on there so we kind of need
a little GUI for like being able to pick
what am i viewing in the debug view
right now you know what I'm saying you
keep saying split the block in half what
do you mean so what I mean by split the
block in half know where my pin is there
it is
what I mean by split the block in half
is that here's what I'm looking at right
now right we've got a little bit here
where we've got you know a previous
pointer and a next pointer right then we
have flags and we have size or whatever
right so we've got this little header up
here and then we've got some memory
right so this is just a chunk of memory
that we can use for stuff we come
through and in this part of the code
here we say find a block we get back a
block so what we're talking about is a
pointer to this thing right so we say
okay great
we found a block will place the asset
right here right and then we have to see
how big it is so maybe the asset takes
up this much space which means that this
is a pretty usable chunk of memory right
so when I say split the block in half
what I mean is I now need to make a
marker that says that this is available
so what I do is I make a new header and
I stick it in here its previous pointer
points up to this guy this guy's next
pointer now points to here and this next
pointer points to whatever this guy was
pointing at so I've inserted this block
into the chain I split this block in
half and inserted this secondary block
the the into it and then whatever is
remaining is is now available for use
again because this is used but this is
free that's what I mean by split the
block
mojo Bhoja this is where I read it from
and there you've you've pasted the link
copy link address I will see if I can
load up that link that you have pasted
it looks like it is a link from image
tech blog
let's see Ashley Smith I do not know who
that is
Vulcan is a next-generation
high-performance graphics and computer
if your I developed by the Khronos group
okay here is the summary of Vulcan
extracted from the official press
release
let's see where this is allocation when
you call GL tech storage 2d and OpenGL
the driver has to allocate memory for a
2-dimensional or one dimensional array
texture of the function and the memory
allocation process represented black box
in Vulcan over the marry allocation is
done by the application this means that
the application knows more about what
type of memory is using and more
importantly how much memory is using
which would be more useful for
applications that are memory bound this
isn't conscious treating out of memory
or explicit memory management volcn
less of a so I don't know what I'm
allowed to say now let's say all I would
say is I would give this blog absolutely
zero I would ignore absolutely
everything you see in that blog that's
all I have to say about that well the
debug GUI have a cool console like quake
or unreal no I don't think that would be
a good use of my stream time
alright looks like that's the end of
questions
I see no more all right so I will wrap
it up
do a little rappy poo let's see here I'm
kind of excited about this little memory
thing even if it's lousy
I cut I'm the kind of person who
actually prefers code that I completely
know how it works to code that may be
better but that I don't know because it
just allows me to think through
everything in a way that I can't
otherwise I don't know so I'm kind of
excited about this we'll have our own
little memory a little memory guy and
maybe well at some point try to make him
even kind of good at first it won't
matter it may never even matter really
because computers are very fast and this
is unlike this is not something that
happens that often you know it's
something that happens a few times a
frame and at that point you have a lot
of leeway right it's not like pixels
where there's millions of them being
filled so who knows but anyway it's kind
of cool I'm kind of happy we decided to
do it or when I say we I mean me but you
know I mean it's a royal week anyway
let's go ahead and close down here close
down thank you everyone for joining me
for another episode of handmade hero it
has been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
with source code at home if you
pre-order the game it comes with a
source code so that's something you
might want to check out you can go to
handmade hero or you can do it with a
little pre-order button that's all it
takes and you can play around the source
code I updated every night after we
finish coding here we also have
hopefully this weekend well finally I
can get maybe the github access stuff
working I'm looking forward to that
only because I noticed people like that
and I have been doing the work of
keeping the github up to date and I
think it's working
you know how git is but I think it's
working
so hopefully that will also happen a
little further down the line we also
have a patreon page if you want to just
support the video series you can
subscribe to that and we have a forum
site where if
you want to ask questions or take a look
at an anti episode guy there's just good
resources on there for people trying to
learn from the series there's also a
tweet bot that tweets the schedule so if
you want to catch live this stream live
that always lets you know when it's
gonna be live i broadcast the schedule
at the weekends and then every day kind
of gives a little reminder tweet to let
you know when that's when it will be for
that day so that you can plan to see it
if you would like to so that's about it
I hope everyone has enjoyed our brief
little foray into general purpose
allocation which we will continue
tomorrow 5:00 p.m. Pacific Daylight Time
right here on Twitch and we'll try to
get everything kind of buttoned up a
little bit for our basic general purpose
ocular we should be able to have it
working fairly nicely tomorrow I think
it just might not be very efficient at
finding memory blocks but hey that's
okay things can get more efficient later
so that's it everyone thank you for
joining me I hope you have fun coding
until I see you tomorrow until then take
it easy everyone