hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode a complete-game live on
stream we are going to take a look at
our octahedral light Maps today which
yesterday we debugged the encoding of
them and I think we I mean I I guess I
don't know but I think we did that
pretty well we looked at the results and
they seemed pretty coherent we had
definitely had some bugs in there and we
fixed them and now it's looking pretty
good so if you take a look at where we
are at at the moment we can go ahead and
jump in here to the handmade hero build
and you can see that if I draw which in
here and here this is the death maps
which we're not computing it and
actually haven't really decided how
we're gonna use what we've got them in
there just because we wanted them as
placeholders if you look in here you can
see the light map and as I move from
side to side you can kind of see the
light that moves with me is moving side
to side on the map as we might expect it
to in the octahedron we tested out the
channels using structured art they seem
to be right we don't know exactly that
they're correct I mean we did some
fairly reasonable validation that it
seems to be unwrapping them properly but
you know it's hard to definitely
definitively say so I don't want to you
know say that we've totally nailed it or
anything but we do sort of have a fair
reason to believe that it's that it's
operating at least somewhat reasonably
so from there I think what we want to do
is twofold one we want to actually
introduce the part of this you know what
this is too low we're gonna we're gonna
lift up this microphone a little bit
Oh mic stands you're always so hard to
work with there we go so anyway we want
to make sure that this is able to be
sampled inside our shader reasonably so
that's the part that we really want to
focus on but we also if you look in here
if i zoom this in a little you can see
that at the moment we're also not
filling in that there's sort of like a
separate little piece here where we're
not actually filling in the in-between
areas so I don't know if you can let me
try and get into a position where you
can really kind of see that better so if
you look like in between here there's a
gutter all the way around these there's
a two pixel gutter everywhere and that's
so that there's a one pixel ring that we
can put around each one where we just
copy whatever the proper part of the
octagon is I'm sorry the of the
octahedron is so that we make sure that
when we sample towards the edge of our
octahedral map it smoothly wraps around
to the other side and that's to avoid
like obvious pops in our lighting when
you go from you know when you happen to
go around the cracks where we chose to
cut the octahedron and unwrap it so
that's basically everywhere that so if
you imagine the octahedron has the top
and the bottom parts so that bottom part
of the hemisphere it's basically all the
cuts in that are unwrapped so just to be
concrete about that so that people who
are maybe still having a little bit of
trouble you know what can me there we go
maybe people who are having a little bit
of trouble with the octahedron
understanding exactly what it's doing so
for people who are not 100% clear on
what's going on there if you take a look
inside the original paper this is the
diagram in question that we've been
referring to it's very clear it's good
and if you look when we unwrap you can
see that the top part of the sphere maps
to the top part of the octahedron which
unwraps cleanly with no cuts so
basically anything
in the upward-facing part of the
lighting will be fine the downward part
of the lighting as you can see has cuts
and it cuts everywhere so each seam here
is a cut so there there there and there
are all cuts in the octahedron and the
unfold right these are unfolded pieces
that when they fold back together you
know meet back up so in order to
consuming prevent cuts there we would
have to fix that now one of the things
that I would point out when you're
looking at this lighting there's a lot
of things that we might want to think
about here and we don't really know yet
which side of the hemisphere which which
hemisphere or which side of the sphere
we want to be most important you could
imagine if you were to place these light
probes or align the voxel I should say
if you imagined aligning the voxels so
that it was always above the player like
it or right in line with the player you
could imagine wanting to do the opposite
kind of unwrapping so if we were always
talking about these lights being like
mostly up above the scenery then you
probably would want the bottom to map to
the continuous tik Lluis region and cut
the top right and that's a trivial
change for us to make it would be
trivial for us to change our octahedral
unwrapping so that we flipped which Z
got cut and which one didn't I
so in fact you could just negate the Z
on the way in to both routines and that
would do it right negated on the way in
negate on the way out and off you go so
if we wanted to we could also change the
bias and so if we find that we want to
have the bottom you know if mostly
lighting is getting sampled most from
the bottom and less from the top of our
hemispheres that would be a change to
consider and again it's totally within
our power to do so right it's pretty
easy so basically all we want to do now
is do that film and start sampling back
to he'd run inside our shaders and in
order to do that there's a couple things
you want to do
we also probably want to get the
lighting distance factored in here a
little bit we're not really doing that
at all I don't think at the moment so
let's take a look at all of that and and
just try to get ourselves into a good
position going forwards where we
basically just have like some some
semblance of the lighting working in a
way that we understand so all right if I
jump over to lighting you can kind of
see down at the bottom where we actually
fill this stuff out so we've got our
routine here in the the test light
sphere which is put filling in the
sphere at the moment that's not really
gonna do much distance attenuation I
don't think is it oh it does so here we
do distance attending to attenuation so
we've got distance attenuation
we've got angular attenuation in here
right so we should generally be able to
make this lighting look reasonable just
from what we've got here so let's go
ahead and try to put that into our
shader like we were talking about before
and we'll just see how it goes excuse me
allergy season is coming up as you know
so what we want to do here is we want to
get our sampling working and then we
also want after this process here to
fill in those cracks so that it's a nice
contiguous sampling all around and we'll
do both of these things today hopefully
although I don't know if we'll be able
to debug them completely before the end
of the stream so here's the fragment
shader and you can see inside the
fragment shader that we've sort of
implemented the the first part of things
we sketched out how this would go we we
do the octahedral unwrap we call sample
lighting for each of the voxel elements
and then we blend by however far through
the voxel we actually are and what you
can sort of see here is that there's a
there's sort of a way we could debug
this already right
we could start debugging the voxel
interpolation by using these as actual
colors and looking at what we get so for
example if we wanted to we could write
something more like this right and so
now when we go up here into the sample
lighting call which actually don't know
where that is right there it is where
we've got a box offset and a box you
know so a fox I in a box oh maybe right
I oh I don't know something like that or
D Vox I maybe if we've got these two
what we can do is say oh well you know
what why don't we just output as the
color the actual offset value right and
if we did that if we if we change that
aspect of the shader what we should see
now is our as we move as we well we
don't have to move as we look through
the world we should see color gradients
that represent where you are in the
voxels right and we kind of do so you
know you can kind of see that at least
the voxel interpolation isn't total crap
you can see that as you go up you hit
voxel boundaries here like there's the
blue and then it resets and there's the
next one you can see here that we've a
lot of oxalá aligned with the grid
squares which is something we wanted
right and so you know we know that the
voxel interpolation is at least not
completely borked
it looks pretty reasonable right and so
that's just one way again of trying to
eliminate the number of things that
could be wrong here insofar as the
interpolation of the voxels go that's
one way we can sort of you know try to
try to eliminate failure cases right try
to eliminate the things that that might
be bad
so alright so given that's what we're
doing here when we actually go to sample
this lining we kind of need now to start
filling this routine because we've got
everything else we figured out the
direction we want to sample it's this we
figured out the locations we want to
sample it's these we're calling and
requesting those samples and so the only
thing we're really not doing is actually
taking the sample and if we were just
sampling into one light map this would
be pretty easy all we would have to do
is use this acht X this is like a UV
coordinate basically to look up into the
texture and that would be the answer
that we were actually looking for right
so it'd be quite simple the problem is
because we're using an unwrapped texture
atlas we actually have to figure out
where in the texture we're even going to
sample from and we need to use use the
vox ID vox i part of things to even
figure out where that happens right we
have no idea how where this actually
would be so we don't know how to
interpret this UV coordinate at all we
just have a UV that's handed to us and
we don't know where in that texture to
sample so remember it's this giant
texture this is a small subset of a
giant texture right that has all of
these little light maps and the acht
Bart tells us we're in this little 2d
box we want a sample so in order to make
any use of it we've got to figure out
well where is the box right we've got to
figure out this the the actual
dimensions and location of that box
inside the texture so that we can apply
this oft to that as an offset right so
fundamentally what we need to do here is
we need to take a texture sample and we
kind of want to take two of them even
though we don't really need to take two
of them quite yet because we don't have
anything in the depth channel that we
cared about but eventually we're going
to so we'd like to support that just as
an optional feature as we go but if we
go through here and say all right we've
got two samplers we've got a light color
sampler and a depth color sampler we
know we're going to want to take a
texture sampler here a texture sample we
know we want it to be by
linear and we want to have like a sample
UV that we're going to use so we know
that it's going to look something like
this where we take a sample UV we feed
it to the texture sampler we get back
some results and then we know we have a
result that we're going to return right
and the result X Y Z is going to come
from the light color and the result
depth is going to come from the from the
depth map right now we could also just
pack all these together and honestly you
know trying to think through in my head
I don't actually know why we didn't do
that does anybody know why we didn't
just make a four-channel texture anyone
were we just really dumb I mean when I
get to this point in the code I'm like
why the heck are we using to texture
samplers where we could have just used
one texture is am I just am I am I just
did we just not think of it I mean there
are some really esoteric reasons why we
might not like for example if we wanted
to use 16 bits for storing the depth
sample or something so maybe that's it
let's try to make ourselves feel better
and say that the reason we did that is
because we really wanted to be able to
store 16-bit or 32-bit depth buffer for
this lighting let's just say that it's
probably not true probably totally false
but let's just say that but I have a
feeling we're probably gonna end up
switching this because that just looks
stupid so that's really stupid oops but
there we go
so this is what it's going to look like
so eventually we'll probably just take
one section
and we'll roll these all into one right
so you know because we don't need the
depth to be super precise right it
probably could be stored as 0 to 255
just fine so it's just frustrating
anyway it doesn't matter point being
we'll do whatever we do it's fine
everyone's happy we'll figure something
out later and you know maybe this wants
to be more HDR as well maybe we want 16
you know I probably want one texture
that's 16 bits per channel it doesn't
matter
forget about it we do stupid things
sometimes everyone makes mistakes it's
okay
sample lighting needs to have this UV
that's the part that we don't know right
so we've set everything up we're passing
in all the information what we don't
know is what the sample UV is so
fundamentally our job today is to figure
out what this sample UV should actually
be so we can figure out what the
lighting actually needs to be at that
point and if you look through here where
we've got this sort of using the diffuse
color and so on that part we may want to
roll in here but I'm gonna assume now I
don't know but I'm gonna assume that it
would be probably the right call
efficiency wise to do our lips first so
get our light values lerp down for the
light coming from that direction first
and then anything that we want to do for
light computations would kind of come in
here right so I'm assuming we would lurk
first and then do it but I don't know so
if we want to get fancier later I mean
we could go ahead and have something in
here where we say Oh like okay we
actually do some kind of light blending
in here I don't know so I guess I
couldn't really say I don't have a I
don't have a real solid understanding of
how we're gonna integrate these yet
that's going to come a little bit later
for right now let's just say we're gonna
blend all of the lighting first and then
modulate or do a reflection vector or
whatever we want after that so we're
just gonna we're just going to take the
raw
action vector and look it up in the
light map blend that together as a voxel
blend and then do any modulation or
anything we're not going to do on each
individual lookup a separate sort of
modulation or specular or anything like
that right so we may want to switch that
may not be what we want to do in the
long run but it's sort of what we're
doing here right okay so when we sample
the lighting we're gonna go ahead and do
this and we just need to figure out what
the sample UV is so the acht is kind of
a known quantity that's the offset
inside the Texel square that we actually
need to use and so we kind of know that
dimension upfront I would argue right we
kind of know that we've got a constant
it's in other words it's never gonna
vary that's just the UV span like the
this the region in UV space taken up by
an 8 by 8 right so an 8 pixel by 8 pixel
area in this thing we know that we've
got a like an acht map dim value here
that we're gonna measure this by and
this is a 2d multiplier this is a hat
amarte product here the Ox map dim
itself is going to be different in U and
V and the reason for that is we're
looking up using actual UV coordinates
not pixel coordinates although you know
I wonder if we should be using because
you might not I don't I don't know if
you're able to do by linear with
straight pixel though do you have to you
may have to pass you views for that so
we're gonna we'll stick with you these
for next it doesn't really matter which
one we use to be honest anyway so the
octave is going to be different it's
going to be a different height and with
the they're not the same so this is an
actual to D value it's not a single
scalar that multiplies the size of this
thing it's two different scalars because
it stretches it since we know that our
texture is non-uniform so even though
it's a square these are two different
values we then need to do an offset and
the offset
needs to put us at the base so we need
to say like what's the acht map you know
min P basically what's the minimum
position of this thing and and I guess
we could say maybe UV right and this is
a UV dim like these are both in UV
coordinates in UV space we're not
talking about pixels or texels here and
so this opt map min UV that's the main
thing we're going to have to compute and
this acht map UV dim is actually we kind
of need two of these right we need a you
know we need an interior right so the
the 8x8 part were actually that we're
actually using for sampling and then
there's the wider part that has that
gutter right and so the acht map menu v
is going to be based on a different
value right that's going to be based on
the Vox I plus the DeVos I right that
that combination there gives us a
numerical index that and in fact you
know what we got it because these are 3d
we got to actually do the unpacking so
we're gonna get an absolute indexing
here right and then we have to
essentially emulate this gigantic mess
right because we now have to figure out
okay exactly which pixel are we talking
about here
right and in order to do that I'm gonna
take the octave part of this I think for
the most part we're gonna try and make
this we're gonna try and make this basis
make a little bit more sense but you can
see that it's basically gonna be the
same exact equation so if we come in
here we've got this oops I'll leave this
like this for now if we're trying to
look up these in U and V s we have to do
the U and the V separately right so if
you take a look at the Z the Z is just a
u value right so this right here would
be just a u value for the Z I'm sorry
the V value for the Z and for the Y it
would be just a V value
right so if we look at the I'm sorry
just a you value right so this is just
just X and this is just Y now TX and T
why we don't care about right because
and the reason we don't care about them
is those are actually coming from here
right the TX and the tyr the interior
look up and so this is just the part for
getting us the base the Y says this is
just the the equation we need for
getting us the min corner right so we
know we have the Z it's that we know we
have the y oops it's that we know we
have the X it's that they all came from
Vox I Plus D Vox I so we have an index
that we can use we then also have the V
and the you now if we knew what to
multiply these by right so we know we
need a hot dim squared and öktem squared
right and we know we need these we know
we need those and we need them in UV so
we need this right as a UV span so we
kind of need something that's like I
don't know how we would say this this is
a Z span right that that seems good
right that is how many pixels across we
would have to go I've said that's how
high pixels down we go for a Z span
right and if we look at what's gonna
happen here since we're actually doing
lookups in Z we don't actually need the
öktem that we don't need the X part of
this right so if you think about how big
a Z spans actually going to be that
part's already taken care of because the
texture sampler is gonna do that offset
we were doing it manually but actually
Sam's gonna do that so the acht exterior
dim like this right moving by one octave
C rear dim is all we actually need and
we need it in UV space
right so that's fine so that's how we
would get our Z span but then we also
need here we need a way to Spezza to
move around for our eye and so we've got
our atlas wise man and that's actually
going to be you know this value oops
so it's an ox exterior and I guess this
is a should say V dim right we have an
ox exterior vdm here or UV dim dot Y
rather and then we have an ox exterior
UV dim dot X here and then we need the
number of these things that we've
actually got right so whatever the the
voxel like this is however many there
are for the you know this is light
lookup voxel dim right however many
there are times whatever the exterior
dimension is right and that's the why
span so we would have atlas Z span here
we would have atlas Y span here and then
finally we would just need the Atlas
expand and that is again just a single
one right so those are the actual
multipliers that we need and you can
kind of see that these are the same
multiplier right and so if we wanted to
we probably could simplify this down a
little bit by just saying like oh well
this is actually just that if we
pre-multiply this thing right so if this
was light lookup voxel dim x iy right
plus I dot X then we could just multiply
the whole thing by the X fan which is
this right and then we know that the Z
is just moving by the Z span which is
this and then we've got our equations
right
finally we know that this is actually
the min UV that we actually want right
so this we can create just on the fly
here by saying it's a V to you and the
values are that and that right so at
that point we've got you know I don't
know a reasonable argument for what we
would want to set up here to do our
voxel sampling we would get the menu we
would sample it except for one problem
this will put us at the minimum corner
but it won't account for the border
right so we need to move ourselves in
one pixel right so we need one more
value here which is the Ox exterior to
interior step right we need you know we
need one pixel one texel in X&amp;Y to get
us from the border region into the
interior part where the UV lookup will
actually occur so I think this is how we
place ourselves into the correct voxel
and you can see that there's a bunch of
things we need to actually specify here
right we need a bunch of values to be
specified in this thing and those values
specifically are the light lookup voxel
dim which we already have then we need
the octa-core UV dim in X&amp;Y right and
then we need the acht exterior to
interior step oops and then we need the
Octomom inter UV dim right
so we essentially need to make three
different values its these they are 2d
values so in each case we need to
actually define some floating point
stuff here right and off we go now we
can also sort of to be honest we don't
have to actually compute these ourselves
here we could actually just let the
shader compute them for us which we
might want to do because all of these
things are going to actually just be
based off of the total dimension of the
texture right and we kind of know what
that actually is if we get one more
value so if we take a look at where the
light lookup Fox will dim actually is we
note that we've got the other thing here
which is the light color lookup square
dim right and that's all we really need
to do to find that UV coordinate
fortunately for us I think
I think these UV coordinates because we
know they're they're always going to be
the same I think I think it just divides
out because if you think about it no
matter what the square dimension is it
should just always work well no that's
not true because of the 1 pixel extra
thing so yeah I mean I think in this
case we may we may need to do a little
we may need to do a little thinking here
about to what extent we want this
sampling be uniform because as I'm
thinking about it the sampling is gonna
be different if we allow these two
lookups to be different sizes right so I
do wonder if maybe we just want to call
it ahead of time to say look we're not
gonna we're not going to do two
different dimensions the only reason I'm
hesitant to do that is because when you
look back at the at the original paper
they use two different resolutions right
so
if you go not that paper if you look at
this paper right my recollection is that
here we go so here's the resolution of
the depth map here's the resolution of
the light map and I believe they're
different let's see do they actually say
anywhere I don't actually know if they
do I'm looking I thought it said
somewhere in here what the resolutions
were I just it's hard to read papers
online I apologize it's definitely the
case that it's it's one of those things
that's easy to do offline but hard to do
online let's see
resolution we encode a circular
irradiance in 8 byte octahedral and 16
by 16 octahedral for depth right so they
very specifically double the depth
resolution and so I you can see and they
duplicate the butter gutter regions of
both so like I really don't want to have
to do that because you can kind of see
why right we have to compute a
completely different look up in if we
want to have different resolutions if
they're the same resolution we can just
use one UV coordinate to look up into
both maps or even combine the maps
together and so I really would have
wanted to not do that if I could have
but I'm guessing that in their mind they
were like look the computation is
cheaper than the texture lookups on any
of our high-end parts anyway so we'd
rather just get more resolution for the
depth map than
then blow out the XP either have less
resolution on the death map or more
resolution on the color which would then
lead to slower sampling times because we
don't have the texture cache as
frequently and bla bla bla right so I
guess I don't know but my assumption is
they were making those trade-offs and
just decided that an extra computation
in terms of how to do the lookup is not
really a bad thing but I'm pretty sure
that you do have to do it that way and
again the reason for that is because the
16 by 16 is not saying now there is one
way you could do it if you used a 2
pixel gutter instead of a 1 pixel gutter
on the 16 by 16 s that would make the UV
coordinates work the same right I mean
I'm pretty sure because then the steps
are the same you have a double the
resolution so the UVs divide out cleanly
there's no difference I don't think at
that point so I'm pretty sure that would
actually work and so maybe you would do
that maybe that's what you would do you
would do 16 times 4 in I was 16 plus 4
instead of 8 plus 2 or 16 plus 2 and
that that would allow you to use the
same one so maybe we'll just say that
that's what we would do if we had to if
we had to make that version work and
we'll just say look there's only gonna
be one lookup in here right all right
and so in this case we need one more
thing here we're gonna want the the
light the light lookup square dim and
this is just going to be whatever the
dimension of the square is versus the
dimension of the voxel and again I'm
trying to figure out does that just
divide out and I don't really know I'm
thinking it might in fact let's just do
these on the whiteboard to see if it
does because I'm thinking that it should
because if I know that I could sample
two different textures with two
different size squares as long as the
voxel dimension is the same that
suggests that it must divide out so my
intuition is telling me it should let's
find out if that's true
day five 579 voxel Atlas you v's so
let's just work one through so I know
that I have a dimension value that is
the voxel dem so we've effectively got a
you know a V like a vdm value and this
is the same for all dimensions
it's like 32 you know maybe it'll be 64
someday but it's something like that
right we know that we have an octahedral
dimension and we know that that is eight
at the moment right and we also have a
like padded dimension let's say and
that's 10 right or OD + 2 right so this
is what we've got currently and we know
that the way that we're doing these is
we're putting them into an atlas that
looks like this it is and I'll just
simplify these two like V o and P right
so we know that we've got a dimension
this way of our texture is V squared
because we're storing an XY sheet across
right it's V squared times R oh right
because we also need I'm sorry RP
because we also need the padding right
there and then we know similarly that
our our vertical is V times P right so
we've got V squared times P this way
we've got V times P this way and that is
the dimension of our texture so if we
now want to talk about something like
how far does you know what's the UV
dimension for one of the for an oh right
I want to know what the value is for
over V squared P right that's the amount
of movement inside texture space that I
would need to have right so if I
actually multiply this out I would get
something like this I would have o over
V squared times P but we know that P is
actually o plus 2 right so I would end
up with like V 2 times o plus V 2 or
sorry - V - right so you know we have a
problem where we have a V here I mean
other way to do it would be to not
expand it out but you would just have V
squared x o+ - right and so in this case
we have another sort of way of looking
at what this value is going to be its V
squared over oh oh plus 2 right so
there's like a ratio here it's au over o
plus 2 V squared
you know I'm saying so we do know to a
certain extent if we multiply this by 2
everything in here would be multiplied
by 2 right because if we double the
padding double the Oh double the V right
if all of those things got doubled they
would all cancel each other out nicely
right so I do think it's true that we
can compute this without knowing the
specifics here in a some sense right but
the problem that we would have is we
yeah like I'm sorry you know that's that
I don't know why the V squares on the
bottom
so the one over V squared is the primary
thing that we're looking at here and the
oh / o plus two you can see it's almost
1 right so it almost doesn't do anything
but it's just to account for that
padding so if we didn't have the padding
this is why I kept saying the padding
the padding right if we didn't have the
padding we wouldn't need this thing
right so what that means is to find the
min point we're fine so the min point
would just be you know all we needed for
that was the padded dimension so that's
just going to work out to be the padded
part right so in order to find I guess
what I'm saying is in order to find the
a few of these things we don't have to
care what their values are because for
example two step two
whatever the square part is the acht
exterior UV dim this is just always 1
over V squared right and the reason for
that is if we we want to step by this
much well if I want to say I'm going P
over one of these values like V squared
times P right the P's just cancel I
always get 1 over V squared right so the
octet steerer map is really easy it's
just 1 over the this right
and the only difference between the two
values is we know that going across we
have to square it right so the exterior
UV dim is really pretty straightforward
it's just the square do we have square
in here yeah we do so producing that
exterior UV dim is trivial and does not
depend on the square itself it's just
going to be and straight forward offset
so what that tells me is maybe I don't
have to panic as much if we look at
what's happening here you can see that
basically that part is going to be the
same so this part is going to be the
same this is the part that would change
so the interior UV dim and the exterior
to UV to interior UV step are the parts
that might change however even this one
I think wouldn't change cuz it's just
one over well no that's not true I think
this one does change because the the
size of one pixel relative in either
case is going to be proportional to how
whatever the dimension was so this part
we do have to change so the acht you
know if we look at this we've got if we
were sampling from two maps so we've got
a sample D in a sample C right the
octant earier to UV step C and D and C
and D these the interior UV Jim and the
interior UV step those actually do have
to be changed I think we'll see but I'm
pretty sure that's the case so when we
actually do these here now these have to
be done double right so we've got the
exterior to interior step UV step how
did I break those yep season these at
the end
so we've got the color one and the depth
one and then these two now have to be
based on two different values so we do
have to know like look we do have to
know both of these like so so we're
gonna define them both and so in here
we've got the light lookup voxel dim and
in here we want to say all right we've
got the light lookup voxel sorry the
light color lookup square dim and the
light depth lookup square damn right and
we kind of want these we probably need
to know for lack of a better term here
we need to know the padding separate
from the dim right so in some sense we
kind of want this to be the padded bit
right I mean I don't know we can just
take the padding out I suppose but you
see what I'm saying look it's a little
bit confusing there but anyway let's go
here let's go ahead and try to define
these so the exterior to interior UV
step see is pretty straightforward it's
just 1 over the total dimension in each
case right so it's one over and one over
here and in this case we've got a square
and square and you know what I'll be
honest now I'm looking at this I'm
thinking this doesn't everything you
know all we needed was actually that I
can just put these in the routine as
long as they're constant the compiler
will take care of it for me right so I
can come in here and just say alright
here's these values that we actually
needed to have right
and so if I go through here and just say
alright here's all these constant
vectors that I need to define so I've
got 1 V 2 that's the you know sort of
the the exterior dim that's always
constant we only need one of them
then I've got essentially all of these
loops and the interior step versions are
again pretty simple they're just one
pixel over the total dimension of the
texture so let's go ahead and compute
that so the total dimension of the
texture in in our case is going to be
the square of the light lookup voxel dim
and going XY z-- it's the square cuz
that's somebody there are and then I
have to multiply by however big the
light voxels the lookup themselves is
right so the color square in this case
and then in this one it would be very
similar only it's not squared so it's
just the light lookup voxel dim times
the light color right because there's
voxel dims worth of them and they're
this long so I believe that's the
correct inverse look up there then in
here we've got the interior step 4d
again same exact equation the only
difference now is instead of color we
would change it to depth right
so that's almost everything now we just
need the interior versions of these and
again same equation more or less the
only difference now is that in addition
to doing the interior UV the only
difference now is instead of just going
one we're going to go however big the
interior part is so that's the light
color lookup square dim and it's going
to be minus two in this case because
we're removing the padding and that's
how big the interior would be now I
think we've got the complete lookup for
both that produces an actual light
sample we probably are buggy here so
it's probably not going to work
and we gotta fix the compiler errors but
I think that's actually it so once we do
these computations which remember these
are all free they're dis constants so it
can do those when it compiles the shader
and we shouldn't have to pay for them so
all we're doing is this one ad we're
doing these small ads and multiplies
here so a couple F Mads and then one
more sort of F mad and an addition here
to get us to where we need to be for
each sample and it's really not that
expensive so doing two's not hugely
problematic I mean that's not gonna I'm
not gonna lose sleep over that compared
to the other stuff we're doing in here
so I'm gonna go ahead and say let's try
and get this to sort of start working at
all so I'm gonna see if we've got any
compiler errors here I mean that's is
that even a question of course we do and
we're gonna go ahead and fix those so
let's take a look at the fragment errors
that we've got implicit narrowing of
type from Veck for so we need to see
what that is oh I thought oh I I'm
behind in our movie I thought remedy
displayed text nicer than that normally
I thought it gave a little like
scrolling window here I don't know when
that stopped
George did that go away
Thomas stir thank you George yeah uh
yeah that's what I'm looking for so you
can see this really nice printout that I
new remedy had it I just didn't remember
how to get it so if you look here you
can see we've got a problem where we
were taking effect for and turning it
into avec three I guess so I don't know
where that's happening let's take a look
and see oh it's right here top that
should be an R so we're basing the
red-green-blue channels and then the red
channel of those textures sir alright so
now in theory we're sampling lighting
and I'll be honest this is actually
closer than I thought we were going to
get if you look at what we've got it
sort of actually is doing some lighting
it's clearly very buggy like you can see
for whatever reason on this half of the
screen it looks like any normals that
are pointing in a particular direction
or something or wrong or I don't know
exactly what's happening there but you
can see that's it's actually sort of
doing some lighting and it actually is
following the light as it moves so we're
not totally screwed up here but we're
not right like you can tell we've got
obvious issues and they somehow seem to
be screen related in some ways so that
part is kind of confusing that's gonna
because of the reflection vector and in
fact I can prove that see how I move
around that's gonna because of the
reflection vector so we've got some
issues there let's do some quick just
spot checking of the code and then what
I'd like to do is go ahead and move from
spot checking the code to trying to
figure out if we can maybe in addition
to spot check in the code I want to have
some way oh crap you know I just
realized
I keep making this mistake the
octahedral unwrapping gives us negative
one to one so we actually just want to
be in the Centers of these things which
actually so that's pretty cool so if we
use the center instead that also
eliminates one calculation right that's
interesting so if we go from the center
outward instead of from the corner then
you actually save one computation
because you don't care how big the
border was right this if you just don't
do that right then everything works
right so if you get rid of this and just
say up opt map Center UV then you don't
care how what the dimension of the thing
is because the span is always half of
whatever the total step size was right
so it's always just going to be the
light the voxel dim point five hmm I
know I'm not explaining this well but
just hear me out
I believe what I'm saying is true we'll
see in a second so you can see this
exterior to interior step UV see
nonsense we have here but actually we
don't need to do that because whatever
the acht exterior UV dim is that value
you can see how that value divided out
the size of the square it's always just
going to be one over however many
whatever the dimension was minus the
square size if we just do the octet ste
riyer UV dim by half so if we just say
go half
that always gets us to the center and
since we know the exterior you dim is
not dependent on what we decided the
square resolution was it should just
work so that gets rid of this nonsense
entirely right now I can see why they
were measuring from the center smart
people wrote this paper I said that
before and I meant it
right that's clever because now it
doesn't matter what the resolution is so
the only part that we have to care about
now is the span here and the span is
[Music]
going it's gonna have to be halved but
other than that it's fine
right right am I am I missing anything
so I want to say you can just do this
what we've got here and and you're good
to go
I don't think you can get rid of this
though I'm trying to think I can't think
of any way get rid of it and that's
again because the padding the ratio of
the padding to the size of the square if
that changes I think yeah I don't think
it's anything to do right that's my
thinking so let's see och map Center UV
is just a nominal a change so we should
be good to go here
so again like better but still wrong I
guess is how I would describe it right
we're getting there but from the looks
of it there's still a reflection vector
lookup error of some kind because there
shouldn't be discontinuities as we
rotate around there now one could argue
that there would be discontinuities
because we're not copying the border
pixels so that's true but they shouldn't
be as hard as that I don't think I mean
maybe I guess we should do the copy
first just to make sure that's not an
artifact of the sphere cut that we're
seeing there so cuz the bilinear filter
cause that I mean I just my intuition
says that that's a harder edge than the
bilinear filter off set could have been
causing but I don't know so I'm not
willing to necessarily say that that's
100% the truth yet right but still in
very encouraging because like I said it
for a first stab at it that's actually
remarkably good and you know if we look
at what we're getting for lighting here
I'm pretty happy about that right like
I mean that's a pretty good diffuse
lighting scenario there yeah so you know
again looking at what we're getting here
it looks like those to me look like sine
quadrant changes so when I look at that
I say okay that's right down the middle
of the screen fourth because we're using
a reflection vector here that's gonna be
when the X goes from positive to
negative so we're getting an error in
flipping the sign from positive negative
again I don't know let's do the copy I
mean why not we have to do it let's go
do the copy and try to get that copy
correct and and then we'll come back to
this because it's sort of working it's
not right there's some bugs I don't want
to debug something that I don't know if
there's just an artifact in it already
because of the fact that we're not doing
the seams properly and so I don't want
to I don't want to say for sure that
that is a problem one thing I could do
to sort of give us a little bit of
perspective on when that whether that is
a problem or not is when we actually do
the UV dim see UV dim D here so when we
couldn't compute these values where we
take the square Jim you know and we
divide it out what I could do is take
out an additional part of the span so I
could say like oh let's go narrower on
that let's let's actually divide it down
even a little bit more and see if that
produces less of an artifact right and
what I'm seeing here to me it's like no
it really doesn't right so to me I think
that's a pretty clear indication well
you know what no I I really I just look
and I couldn't tell you oops I just
can't I just can't make a call
sorry I don't think it's this but I just
I can't be sure I'm sorry so let's go
ahead and do the copy and maybe that'll
be the last thing you do today I don't
know if or you'll have time because we
have what do we have like well I you
know we got an hour
more or less
we have an hour I don't know maybe we
have an hour so maybe we will be able to
finish it and then go back to the shader
but I don't know the point is when we're
actually doing our copies here so you
can see us out putting our voxels here
but what we need to do after we do the
output is we need to actually do a
separate pass to do the copy so
effectively what we would get here is
one of these again basically this exact
same loop right and not sure what this
is about
hot corner and light amount yeah we
don't we're gonna we're not gonna do any
of the same or I don't think actually so
we're just gonna nerf this goodbye oops
alright so what I want to do now is I
want to go through and we're gonna do
another one of these which goes over
each voxel square but unlike the other
ones instead of iterating over the
square we're actually going to iterate
over the outside right so we're gonna
have a thing that looks something like
this it's not gonna look exactly like
this because we're only gonna probably
do half of it because each half is gonna
do its own thing but it's gonna look
something like this
right and we're gonna have the T Y copy
and the T X copy we have to decide which
one is gonna handle the corners I mean I
don't know but let's just say that it's
gonna be this one I think it would be
that way is that right yeah so the T Y
side will copy the whole thing with y
exponent you know what maybe let's think
about it let's let's do the opposite of
that so the horizontal one will do the
whole row and the T y1 will only do part
of the row right and so to do this what
we need to do is compute these voxel
coordinates and I
think we want to kind of make this a
little bit more systemic here so what
I'm guessing we want is sort of a
function that would work to compute
these based on the fundamental values so
we probably want like a voxel look up
here and you know I don't know so we
want some way of computing a voxel
offset from an XYZ so we want like you
know X Y Z T X T Y like that and then we
want to compute this value so we want
this to be something we can just get
right so we want this to happen we
probably want this to be wrapped so we
don't get surprises if people pass in
expressions for the x y&amp;z that would
then like disaggregate or something like
that so maybe something like this and
that way we can say okay yeah like we're
gonna fill these things and you know
what the the we can do this just by
doing a C and a D here
and and now we've got both so now we can
just kind of do these anywhere we want
and again we'll try to make this a
little bit more systemic later but for
now I don't care I just want to test it
and see if we can get it working so I'm
going to compile this I'm gonna switch
to using those macros and make sure that
they still write out the correct stuff
with what we have now so I want it to
look exactly like what I'm seeing on the
screen here and let's go ahead and and
put that in there and that should do it
right
so now if I recompile assuming it
actually works I can go ahead and check
to make sure it's still computing and
filling right and it does so let's go
ahead now and go into this part where we
do our copy and what I need to be able
to do is copy the voxels edges properly
and if you look we can use this diagram
to guide us because we know that we're
unwrapping stuff in this way and we know
we need to copy these pieces out so that
they line up and we can use the like
sort of the winding of these things to
make sure that we copy them properly so
for example we know that this edge right
here is this right so we know that we
need to take whatever was like right
here and put it right there you know
what I'm saying to you we need to like
copy those we need to copy from one part
of the triangle to another part of the
triangle in order to get the correct
sort of pixel that we expect to be there
right and similarly like this corner
pixel here this one probably wants to
be that and this corner pixel wants to
be that you and I'm saying so we just
have this kind of we got to figure out
what we're doing right but we we more or
less have to do a block copy over to to
make these things line up right classes
are dirty
in fact I'm gonna clean them so this is
going to be hugely annoying and we
probably will have to do some kind of
structured art to make sure that we
actually get the results we think we get
and to make matters worse we don't know
if this is upside down or right side up
so we're gonna have to think about that
meaning I don't know what they drew here
right I don't know if they drew X Y
positive or Y negative yeah I'm saying
to you hopefully it wouldn't matter
because we just ended up with the thing
flipped and since the it you know that
would still you know be symmetric as
long as we don't as long as we don't
flip in one way and not flip in the
other way we should be okay but who
knows alright so take a look at this we
need to do these copies and so for
example like in each of these cases we
just need to copy what's on this side
over to what's on that side and the
annoying part is this got to be flipped
right so it's gonna be mirrored in a
sense so you know if you imagine what we
would be doing for the indices here
let's just imagine for the X's right and
we'll start with the X's let's say that
we're going to do like copying along the
bottom edge X's so we're going to have
the XYZ that were on we're going to use
a T Y of zero because we're on the
bottom edge we're gonna assume this is y
up for now and it would be if this is
yeah I mean it would be so that whining
is proper this would be the negative Y
quadrant so if we were copying
in the the low Y which would be here if
we started at this base location here so
TX of zero I don't know what we're gonna
call this we're gonna call it X off for
now if we started at the base location
here and I wanted to do a fill of the
light voxel sea side of things if I was
to take the X off here so I'm going to
fill in this one
this pixel here right and in fact if we
look at it we might almost want to do
the corner pixels separately because I
don't really know what they're gonna be
so maybe I'll loop both of these this
way and we'll handle the corners in a
specific way I don't know if I want to
do that but let's just toy with that so
if we're just gonna fill in this gutter
here what I need to do is take the
opposite of that so I need to basically
do something like this right and I guess
we want to do that as well I think so
let's take a look at what that does if
we just do that copy what is the
complaint there we go right so right now
we're not doing any copying there and
we're gonna try and do some copying now
I may turn on our little like thing that
we can tell what's going on copy wise
because this doesn't help us super much
to see what we're copying and what we're
not because we don't always fill in the
whole square so what I'd rather do here
potentially right yeah what I'd rather
do here potentially is be able to I'd
like to be able to see the whole thing
filled so if we go
back to our test code and just turn on
the like color quadrant mapping so that
we know that everything has a value in
it then we should be able to debug our
test code a little bit better right so
we can see here what we've got uh you
know what else I can do because we we
spent the time to do all this stuff I
can also turn on the mag side of things
so we can zoom in right which I think
would be nice so if we have our V span
here and I think we used to set it to
0.03 to get a lot closer to the action
right so what we could see here you know
for lack of a better term is I don't see
any copying happening at all right now
that makes sense because now I think
about it we didn't go up one right so we
were copying from nothing to nothing so
actually this X off what I actually want
is maybe like bottom row and then like
or or you know row zero Row 1 something
like that
so I'd say like all right let's take row
zero start and then we'll do Row 1 start
here and that should give me the first
copy in the set right
or not oh yeah
you have to act to actually make those
be different values but you see I'm
doing right I gotta get from a row that
has data in it to a row that doesn't
right so there you can see the copy
happening unfortunately this is all
zeros in here in terms of the X and the
y and the Z so we don't see any actual
values in there so it's a little hard to
know if that's copied properly but
that's what's actually happening in
terms of the fill so now I need to do
the the copy for the top and if that
happens the same way so this is going to
be like the row you know n start and row
and one start so it's like N and n minus
1 and so that's going to be whatever the
actual full dimension of the square
would have been you know I'm saying all
the way up and then all the way up
backed down by one and so now we're
doing both copies for the top and the
bottom in theory right and again that
looks like about right unfortunately we
can't quite tell the reversal because on
that row everything kind of bows out so
it's a little bit hard to tell whether
we actually did our inversion properly
let's cheat slightly and see if we did
this don't ask me why I didn't just say
to there but let's do two and three so
that we're actually copying this and
that right because that will show us
whether we actually flipped it or not
and so that looks good right we're
seeing that flip and that's what we
should happen so I'm going to go ahead
and assume that's at least somewhat
correct there and we'll move on now to
the to the
mmm-hmm vertical line instead and I
still don't know what happens with these
pixels on the outside to be completely
honest with you I assume you set them to
the average of all four corners because
that's what's actually there
sort of or is it or should it be I guess
maybe it should be the opposing corner I
really don't know so anyway this is
actually more or less the same here this
equation is going to be mostly same it's
just it's we got to flip it to operate
in Y instead right so I'm going to do
that the cheesy way which is going to be
slower and but it's I just want to make
sure I do it correctly but we're gonna
do it with full offsets so here's the
full offset version what we want to do
here is specify these values precisely
so that they give us what we need so
we've got our T Y values our TX values
are going to be fixed in this case so in
one case it will just be 0 and 1 right
so we're gonna copy from the slightly
inside border to the outside border and
in the other case it will be right the
it'll be exactly the same as as this
whole situation right so in this case it
will be we're gonna copy
oh that's X that is X we're gonna copy
from here to here right and since that
value comes up a lot hmm
I want to do like light color lookup
squared M minus 1 and I'm just gonna
call that n because if we just call that
n this becomes a lot easier to read
right so you know I'm trying to there
and so if we just call that and all of
this is like oh it's just going you know
it's it's it's much harder to read it
when it's all blown out like that but if
we just call that final row n then you
can kind of see more directly what I'm
doing
hmm excuse me
all right so here again this is exactly
the same it's just and it's getting
copied from n minus one and so there we
just need to do like what are we doing
with T why right we know that we know
that T Y is everywhere in here but the
question is like okay so what what do we
actually do with it
and in this case we know that we're
probably going to copy we're gonna copy
from T y2 like going backwards from T Y
right so in this case it's gonna look
exactly like the previous one right
we're gonna discuss invert the T wise
and then in this one we again can do
exactly the same thing because this
equation is handling all of the
unpacking for us so we should just be
able to do to flip copies exactly the
same way and I think that's what we need
I think so now I think we're good
with all those extensions the only
difference is we don't actually have the
corner it pieces right and I also have
to go make sure that that we don't pull
from the opposite side like we might be
so like it may not be that let me just
double check because I don't know what
it is so yeah no it's the same right
it's like these two were neighbors that
would have folded in on each other so we
are copying from here to here right and
the same is true for here like that
lined up with that right so we're always
copying from like the other Avenue so
these are now the only ones we haven't
filled in let's go ahead and fill those
in and in order to do that it's just
going to be a series of these right
so we need to write for pixel's
what are those four pixels well it's
just the 0 0 and 0 0 n and n n right
those are the 4 pixels we have not yet
written and where do we want to get
those well we just want to get those
from the correct corresponding side so 0
0 wants to come from n minus 1 n minus 1
because that's the far corner right I'm
assuming this right I don't really know
what the best value to fill in there is
but I'm assuming that's the thing you
can't actually that you won't have
access to otherwise you're gonna you're
gonna be blending towards that far face
if you were going over this that that
side because that's where you're gonna
wrap around 2 so n 0 right and just to
point out where those are so 0 0 is here
it's going to map to n minus 1 my 1 so
we want to put that 1 here and 0 is here
right so we want that one to come from
over here which is going to be 0 n right
the same would be true here right so you
flip the coordinates and then the final
one which is writing n n is just going
to be like 1 1 right and again these
actually shouldn't be 0 right they
should be 1 because they're in 1 from
the edge I think that's it so I think
that copies everybody we may have some
bugs in there that's that's gonna be my
first pass at it and there's a fully
fully filled in map now if I go back and
stop nerfing so we go to here and we
actually fill in light values we should
now have a full map so everywhere this
yet should extend out right you can see
it now I don't see any evidence that
that improved right so that to me now
you know we could still have a bug
in the way that we're filling it out
certainly so you know I don't want to
assume that it's fine but you know I'm
just trying to I'm trying to look here
and see about that I will say that that
doesn't look reassuring like I will say
we may have some issues with how we're
feeling I mean what I wonder if we're
maybe slightly off like we're 0.5 off
somewhere so we may have some bugs still
in that map and I'm not sure how we'd
debug that we may have to go in and be a
little bit more careful but I would say
we've got a problem here that isn't
that's that's separate right that it
looks too severe at this point I so I
don't think it's just a case of of
having a I don't think it's just a case
of having a blending issue right so
let's go back to the shader and look at
what we were actually doing and see if
there's any indication of of maybe
something busted here we can first check
our octahedral mapping just to make sure
that there's nothing weird coming out of
there so first of all we do know that R
is normalized wien so that's good right
so that helps us ensure that we're not
feeding bogus values in here when we
produce the actual octahedral we take
one over the number one norm times R
times XY right and that is what we want
to reduce this to an octahedron so that
seems correct to me
I don't really see anything yeah so once
you get that octahedral then we're just
looking to see if Z is less than zero
and if C is less than zero then you can
see we do the optics why we multiply by
the sign of the original which is what
we want times 1 minus the absolute value
of the inverted version that also looks
right that looks proper to me I don't
see anything weird about that that will
produce negative 1 to 1
so we're feeding a negative 1 to 1 value
into sample lighting as the octahedral
sample we have our voxel lookup which
itself could be called into question
here although I don't actually know that
that would explain those lines are not
voxel related there they cut straight
across voxels so I'm gonna go ahead and
say our voxel indexing is probably not
wrong our voxel ar-ar-ar moved from a
voxel index over to a light atlas might
be to a specific square that could very
well be wrong but I don't believe our I
don't believe our index in particular
being wrong would cause any particular
problems of the kind that we're looking
at and in fact when you look at the
places where it does work it's crossing
voxel boundaries without a seam just
fine right there's a voxel boundary
there and there's no light seem right
it only gets a light seam at the XY
boundary not at any other boundary right
so yeah so I don't know so looking at
that the question is what about all this
garbage so we have a voxel index we pick
a toc map center UV by taking the voxel
index multiplying it by the light lookup
voxel dim
[Music]
because we're gonna move that far and
why and to produce the UV value so
here's the in fact let's do it this way
so I can read it easier so yeah let's
take a look at what's actually happening
here we'll move this down one and we'll
just take a look at these two in and of
themselves so here we're seeing alright
for the actual Y that we're gonna use
we're gonna take whichever voxel index
in Z we were looking at and we're going
to move by however big the exterior UV
dim is right in Y that seems fine we've
gotta go we'll have to go verify that
that's actually correct this value is
correct which we'll do separately but
that seems right and then to move to the
center of it we're gonna do we're gonna
move 0.5 of that exterior dim which
should put us dead dead smack in the
middle right now for the akhmet Center X
we're gonna say and do that now we're
gonna say we've got however many Vox
they're on a side times the Y plus the X
that unpacks one sheet and then we're
gonna multiply by the X and again that
looks pretty solid and both of those
again go through this so that part
should be totally solid we then say wait
No okay we then say all right we've got
the total interior dimension of the UV
dim that's how much we want the octa
cover right it's going from negative one
to one we need to change it into going
however far we go for an atlas lookup we
know we've got the interior dim here and
we want to divide that in half because
the dim is if we were going to 0 to 1
we're going negative 1 to 1 so we need
like half of the size of it because
we're gonna reach half in one direction
in half in another right we then take
those and look them up into the sampler
and off we go so that seems plausible
that seems plausible that seems like a
lookup that I wouldn't expect to fail
too much there and so let's take a look
at our optics terior UV dim stuff here
and see how that stuff gets computed
right I again I'm gonna split this just
so I can see it easier so what we end up
with here is we've got the exterior
dimension is just going to be however
yeah I mean in X it's just going to be
we know we have light lookup voxel dim
times light lookup the fossil dim number
of these things so to move in UV it
would just be 1 over that count and the
same would be true in Y so that seems
uncontroversial right I would say
let's take a look at this in a little
more detail so here we've got the color
lookup squared dim minus the padding
over whatever the dimension is of the
total texture that seems good this is
the number of texels we want to span
over the number of texels there our
total which is what we would want right
this Y value that is totally wrong all
right so our Y value is complete garbage
though right because our Y value is
exactly the same thing as our x value
the only difference is that we don't
have the square right so the Y value oh
wait that was the D value well alright I
know it wasn't so it this just looks
wrong this is just garbage so I think
that was just a typo there probably
because we can't read this because it's
in this like kind of an indented format
but that looks fine right it's this is
the dimension and we want to divide by
the total number of pixels so it should
be those two things right and if we
wanted to do the D version of those it
would be the exact same equation the
only difference is we would have the
depth constants instead of the color
constants
right
all right unexpected semicolon what's
the problem okay so this means yeah all
right I think I've got that properly
parenthesize now maybe we'll find out in
a second all right
so that was definitely a difference
we're getting some we're getting a
different kind of bug now so you can see
like our lookup was definitely in
question there and so we should probably
keep pushing on on this all right
so if we look at this now I think this
is correct the interior Dempsey which
we're using down here right so that's
for our sample CUV
and then we've got our sample D UV in
both cases the Centers that should be in
the same place and it's only the span
that that should change so looking at
this right we've got minus two because
we're using just the interior dimensions
of this thing and we want to divide by
the total number the total size of one
of these textures which is going to be
this and I think that's it is there
another bug in here somewhere
I don't think so I don't think so but I
don't know that's yeah no III don't know
I don't see anything particular there so
I guess I'm not sure there's anything
else to be gained there so at that point
I feel like this should be looking up
roughly correctly I'm just not sure
we're still seeing some really bad
artifacts there and they look very
pronounced right and they're right in
the sort of octagonal way so it looks
like it's either a lookup or a blending
bug right and it's weird because inside
a particular region I mean that looks
like an octagonal region so I want to
almost say that almost looks like it is
just a blending error like the sides
don't line up right or we're unpacking
wrong or something right it's very close
so I think I mean I think what we're
literally seeing there is just the
octagonal boundaries right so I'm not
sure what we're doing wrong but we're
gonna have to sort of figure out where
our blend is is busted there because it
looks like we've got everything mostly
right now I don't know maybe not
but it looks like we've got everything
mostly right but we aren't quite somehow
like the blending is not quite working
or we're sampling - we're not expanding
to the right region now I guess what I
would say is if you think about what's
happening here the interior it should
so the problem that we're gonna have is
half the interior no but that's okay cuz
we're in the middle we're right in the
middle in between two pixels at the
middle and we're going to be going let
me just make sure that this is the
correct that everything is correct in
terms of actual quantities because maybe
I'm actually off by one and we'll see so
if you imagine what we're doing here
we're actually talking about so we've
got a grid right and we've got on the
side here like around this grid we've
got a gutter but this is the main grid
that we want to look up right and we
believe at least if we are doing the
math correctly so far we believe that we
start here and what we want to do is we
want to take a value from negative one
to one on all axes right like this and
we want to make sure that we end like
right here so we want like we want to go
out by exactly 4 right from where we are
so we want to make sure that we take
whatever input value is and we multiply
it by exactly 4 that's what we're going
to be doing I think right we have the
light color lookup squared dim which is
8 we subtract I'm sorry which is 10 we
subtract you from it which is 8 we
divide that by 5 which is 4 right so it
is 4 divided by the total size of the
pics of the map which should be exactly
4 texels in UV I think and so the
question is would then actually is that
actually true so let's suppose that we
then said okay so that's like 4 texels
so let's say we had one texel and the
map was too wide we would want to be
going Oh point five is the size of one
texel and 1/2 is 0.5 so I mean it seems
like these values are correct right I
mean it seems like we're getting the
right values there and so
unless there's some other weirdness
there I'm not sure what to make of that
let's go back to structured art just for
a second
and see if maybe we can fill some things
in here
in ways that would allow us to know what
we're actually seeing so I'm just gonna
try to feed structure to our into our
system and see if I can't suss out what
some of these bugs actually are right so
one of these things about this is I can
sort of see where we're looking at in
here by looking at some of the color
changes that I observe right so in
sweeping this line across like that
right and looking at where we get
individual boundaries you can see that
the lighting bug boundaries line up
pretty much exactly with the octagonal
boundaries so that part does seem pretty
significant right I mean it's worth
noting now if we furthermore take a look
at which boundaries we're looking at
here we can see some things like we can
see that like the purple side or the
mean the grace I don't know how you want
to call that the the way these line up
may go like this you can see like we've
got the green one here and the red one
here or maybe it's purple I guess I
should probably take off the modulation
so hold please
here you go so when we're doing this
here what I'm gonna do instead is I'm
just gonna say like alright forget that
I ever told you to do that let's just
make it equal so here's the world
according to just full-on the light look
up right so there's there's only only
the light look up is actually happening
here and so now we should be able to see
like which values we're getting back now
if we look at what's happening here
you can see that there's you know
because these things have different
light vibes
these ones are always looking towards
the the part of the Octagon here which
is the downward facing positive Y
negative X I'm sorry upward-facing
positive Y negative x right and that's
probably right and this one is the one
that's facing the other direction so
like you know we're looking down in this
thing so it's going to bounce when the
reflection vector bounces up the
incoming light is gonna be coming from
here or here depending on whether you
bounce in either direction right so that
is correct that is what you would expect
now that tells me something really
important right just working through
that I've learned something already in
fact I've learned enough that I think I
can go take a look at something right
away that might help us figure out where
our bugs are and that is if we switch
back to the if we switch back to the
actual lighting and we look at the
lighting bug we know that it was between
here and here is this same well we have
a lighting seem there right you can see
the lighting seem there that's not a
copy point right
that's not a point where we're copying
so I don't know right like this bug this
lighting seam right here that's running
right down there
nobody's comping that that's that's just
these things directly right so how is it
possible that we're not smoothly
interpolating between those two
okay wait is this an owl of shame is
this analogy mix I think this may be the
first I'll real like deep deep I love
shame we've had in a while I mean
looking at this you should know
immediately what I'm about to say right
uh-huh but I think we're gonna have a
shame owl situation here in a second so
yeah sorry about that
oops where's our where's our open jails
here yeah that's that's not great
you know why might you have a lighting
seam anyway anyone want to guess why you
might have lines well one reason you
might have it is if you don't actually
ask the card to ever blend anything that
would do it right oh so much nicer as it
turns out so now let's see what we
actually gets when we turn on the real
lighting here and you know if we want to
avoid the owl of shame we really hope
that there's some other bug there but we
don't know so we'll see we might get
shamed in a moment
Wow that looks like there's a lot less
seams in it all of a sudden we still
have some popping I'm not sure it's
totally right but all the seams I was
looking at before are now gone right so
that's an alle shame hold on
so definitely an alum there we probably
still have a little bit of bug finding
to do but that was the majority of it so
like hardly any seems visible now I mean
that looks clean pretty much everywhere
let's try turning the shader back on and
see what we get if we modulate the color
but I'm guessing it's probably just fine
now
oops yeah that looks a lot like lighting
yep so I guess what I would say is you
can kind of see here there's so there's
a couple aspects of the lighting now one
thing we want to note here is the
lighting is now very directionally it
wasn't before because we weren't really
taking that into account but now that
with the light probes it kind of is so
now you can see it's very it's it's it's
using this since its using the specular
lookup right and we may want to keep it
that way or we may want to use some
blurring to add a diffuse term in there
that takes light from all directions in
you know what I mean
for so we may want to do that and the
way we would do that is just by blurring
our map here by using a lower mid levels
of this map for example so it's not that
hard to imagine doing something there
that that would be not very hard for us
to accomplish certainly we could also
just take more samples of the same map
right is another way of doing that so we
could take some additional samples there
but either way like yeah totally working
so our arterial mapping is is pretty
solid right now there is something
that's troubling me looking at this I
see something that looks kind of a
little bit like a scene here I'd like to
investigate a little bit more so I may
go ahead and keep this out for now and
just take a look at what we see along
that line so you can see there's a
really hard lighting seam coming across
there and you can you can kind of see it
coming through there I suspect that is
now more of a but like maybe our copying
is not as good as it could be you see
those lines right so I just want to look
and see to what extent are those lines
coming from the from the wrapping border
right and you can kind of see that they
are like along a little bit like well
you know what let me turn off the blend
at the same time I did well it's it's
really hard to see
yeah actually you know what looking at
that I guess I wouldn't actually even
say that it's not that's not really a
seam there it looks like it's straight
down the middle actually of the pink so
I guess maybe not that looks like it's
maybe that lining right in there and I'm
not sure I don't really know what to
make of that then so I can create a seam
sort of here between the white and the
pink right but that's not a copy that's
just an actual thing I'm assuming if I
turn this off I won't see a seam there
I'm assuming yeah and I don't sew the
seam is actually running this way right
and I don't think that is a seam that we
create I don't think so
that could be wrong because again here's
the line between like pink and white you
can see it kind of creeping up on you
there and so a line this way would
really just be that I don't think it's
there and I don't think it's there I
mean maybe it is but it doesn't look
like it so I don't really know why we're
seeing that seam and that's a little
troubling like I don't have a theory for
why that's to me is there now it's
possible that's actually the lighting
somehow right I mean it could be that
that's actually what we've sort of
defined because our lighting is a weird
debug light floating about the
character's head and it's a specular
light so I mean it's entirely possible
it's right for the definition of right
where it's what lighting we said we had
right so that's certainly possible but
it's hard I don't
want to chalk it up to that if I can't
prove it like I want I would like
ideally some way of of ensuring that
that's actually what I'm seeing there
right and I also see that little pop
like the lighting gets brighter when the
character pops up like that I'm not sure
what that's from either right
so I feel like there's maybe possibly
still something going on here that I
would like more information about
there's just there's some hard edges
like I see that and I am concerned so I
feel like there's still a little bit
going on there that might be expected so
it might be fine but I don't really want
to count on that I would I wish we had a
way I would like a way of making
something of investigating that further
right trying to think of what exactly I
could do to help us investigate right
like what could I do to provoke this so
that I can see a little more clearly
which part of the equations that's
coming from you know I'm saying so like
I'm just wondering you know what what to
do there what interesting thing here
would be well what if we said R equals
Naz world in right so we just sample the
lighting rather than reflecting we just
sample the lighting from which direction
you're pointing right and so now we
would not have any changes based on
based on the view direction we just have
changes based on your normal so the
normal in question is what
the lighting and you know do we see any
seams right so we can sort of see our
our distance fall-off there is happening
in sort of a radius right we can see
we're getting a light hiccup in
brightness and I'm not sure what that's
coming from so I don't know if that's
just because as the light gets higher up
it actually produces a brighter value or
if there's a bug in when it crosses over
a particular boundary you know there's
so that to me is also an unsolved
problem but so looking at this that's
pretty good lighting interpolation right
I don't have any real complaints about
that but I don't know and I don't see
any seams so that suggests to me that
it's the that the the seams might be
possibly induced a little bit by however
we're doing our reflections I'm not sure
it may just be because reflections
produce smoothly varying normals and we
don't have any of that here these are
all normals that don't smoothly vary so
it would suggest that the what we're
seeing is a bug as the normal moves
through things and I just don't know
I just don't know so here's one thing I
will say let's go back to this and think
for a second about what's happening here
I wonder to what extent these are
actually getting placed incorrectly so I
want to know what the octahedral value
here would be at the center of the Texel
but this is not probably going to give
me that is it because let's suppose that
I want to know what I'm going to get at
the halfway point right I mean let's
think about this for a second so on the
far edge which direction am I actually
trying to sample from that Texel right
it's not actually the farthest over let
me let me draw this out for you it's
hard with the owl but hey if you didn't
want to have to program with an eye on
your shoulder maybe you shouldn't have
screwed up so you know riddle me this
Batman so what we're doing here is we're
picking out a particular Texel and we're
producing the Oh ex-wife from it but if
you look at what we're doing where do we
actually want a sample well we want a
sample like here right we don't really
want a sample here
that's an in-between value and that's
going to be by linearly reconstructed so
we really don't want to put that here we
want to put that here right so if I want
a sample at the in-between texels that
means that we're in the actual
octahedral sampling space am I going to
be well if this
boundary is negative 1 and this is 0
that means this boundary would be
negative 0.5 and this boundary would be
0.5 am i right or am I wrong just go
ahead and say you're right negative 0.75
0.25 0.25 0.75 right so my boundaries
are demarcated at the actual whole
number values the interior center pixels
where I actually want it's not negative
1 so this is not the actual equation
that I wanted right what I actually want
to do is push this forward by 0.1 by
half a pixel so 1/16 right I want that
nudge you know and I'm saying to you I
want to go halfway in between although
it should be one sorry one eighth
because it's negative one to one so
that's times two yeah yeah what's that
right so I actually want to be halfway
in between if we look at what these
values are I don't want this this is not
what I actually wanted right when I
produce two these values because this
maps from negative 1 to 1
what I wanted was actually this
right I actually wanted to offset by
exactly by exactly half a pixel as I
went so that's actually the direction
I'm trying to sample here if I'm not
mistaken let me go ahead and run a
compiled
and that's what we actually should have
been sampling I would argue right now
unfortunately just looking at it I don't
think that helps us at all it still
looks like we've got the same error here
right so changing which direction which
sample direction we were actually using
I don't know it doesn't seem to have a
huge impact there like if I go and take
that out
that's the offset right so if I do this
right now let's go
and turn it off so this is the old way
and we'll wait till it till it finishes
recompile so you can see that it
definitely it's different right but and
I think it's more correctly what we want
not that we care if this routine is
correct but I think it's more correctly
what we want the only problem it doesn't
seem to actually matter right like it
doesn't seem like it really gives us any
less for it for the seam right it seems
like the seam is still totally there
right
so I don't know so let's go ahead and go
to Q&amp;A but I think that's something that
I'm gonna want to look at next week
because I don't feel like we've quite
got all the bugs out yet necessarily and
even if that doesn't turn out to be a
bug it's at least something I want to
understand I don't like looking at
lighting things like that and seeing an
issue all right so let's go ahead and go
to Q&amp;A anyone got Q's
can you vary the light height to see its
impact do you mean animate it or do you
just want me to go change the value just
to something higher III I'll do either
I'll do whatever you want I just
I don sure which which one you're asking
for but I guess I can go do either of
those two things something of which one
you wanted to see either way okay can
you draw in the light probe positions
yes we well but we're not using light
probes so you mean the the light atlas
locations the probes we have actual
probed locations and those I guess will
now go away
they might not though because they say
where we're gonna cast from but that's a
separate issue okay yeah but I can I can
go fix that drawing light probe
locations will require us to
[Music]
so actually drawing those I guess the
easiest thing would probably be to use
this routine here and just draw a debug
box there so for each one of these when
we do Vox Center P I think that's
probably what we would want to do so we
would draw a debug like I think that's
probably what we want so we probably
want to draw a debug box I don't
remember what that call looks like so
I'm just going to try and grab it here
there it is so if I wanted to draw those
I would just do it here probably so I
can say all right push debug box we've
got the lighting solution the box min
the box Max and the box color so for box
color what I'll probably do here is just
pass down the light color I guess right
seems like the most sensible thing to do
I don't know maybe it's not then for the
Box mannan Box max I would just do Vox
Center P - box our and box Center P plus
box R and then you know I don't know box
R is that I'm not sure so this would
just show us like where these things are
looks like we've got too many of them
actually though because there's just too
many box lines there
so let's do something where we just do
when we come through here oh whoops no
that's just because I do too many of
these so we'll do it here
that was one per pixel that's obviously
way too many but hopefully we can draw
each of these I don't know maybe we
can't but we'll see for now actually
because I won't have I could do an
aggregate like color but I'm just going
to do this instead we'll just do pure
bright at that point and we'll see what
happens
so I think that would be it um still too
many looks like so we could do a
narrower bound here or we could try to
increase the number of debug points we
got I don't know how we want to do that
exactly but we've already got a lot of
them is that really the case how many
how many of these do we have it's gonna
make a nasty problem for us render wise
if we have too many of these but blue -
I'm sorry - times thirty-two times what
is it so it would be eight twelve Oh God
so let's try to narrow this then that's
too many boxes so let's try to narrow
this and just say look if you know Z is
greater than or equal to hot game over
to and Z is less than or equal to hot
damn / - right oops
I don't know how to do this we can just
do a smaller cube but I'm not sure how
yeah so I mean I guess we could do this
like how about this
so or how about this something like this
we just need to leave this so that we're
not drawing too many so we'll just say
look we've got some function here it
does something or maybe it's a pound of
time I don't care
we pass three things down or just one
thing down rather and we say like
alright if V is greater than equal to
hot dim divided by 2 - hot dim divided
by 4 I don't know actually it's good to
do it this way if ax greater than equal
to hot dim divided by 4 and V is less
than or equal to hot dim divided by 4
you know from the other direction it's
just a narrower region alright so maybe
it'll work
we just need to narrow that number down
so we're not drawing so many of those
cubes and so how many we got now I guess
we don't know oops so how much would
that be so that's 32 so it's that would
be 32 divided by 2 to the third times 12
so that should have worked although I
guess with other debug lines it might
not so I guess we have to go even
smaller than that so let's do it the
other way this is a real pain in the
butt
all right let me try to make this right
so that closes that guy again and that
closes that guy
all right so in theory we are now
drawing these in fact there they are
right and they're in the wrong place as
far as I can tell which seems bad oh and
that's totally true like how are we
getting that as the Vox Center P okay so
that's totally wrong sorry let's fix
that yeah this is using the light uvw so
we need to be able to compute the actual
light location which we don't have here
so let me go ahead and actually try to
compute that so if you look at the Vox
min corner can actually see here like
how this is working
so if we were to take the XY Z here and
take the it's the hot DIMMs min corner
so I'm not sure it's this right so if we
wanted to know where the box was its Vox
Center P is whatever the minimum corner
is for this thing and then we're gonna
have to take this and I guess that can
kind of come out here right
and then what we would need to do is say
take the min corner of this thing of the
hot corner and add to it whatever our
actual dimensions of this thing are so
whatever the Vox Center P is and we
would also need to move by that the size
so whatever the Vox dim the actual Vox
dim size is so like the cell size is
actually essentially so that would be
voxel dim and so that should place us in
the correct like world space location
for the voxel I think and so those are
the light probes themselves I'm guessing
the flash is coming from like the light
hop going between two voxel cells that's
not we don't quite have the I don't know
although you know what it might be it
might actually come from a discontinuity
in the actual Z ground interpolation
that's actually probably what it is I
doubt this is actually a lighting bug
so I think that could actually be a Z
discontinuity to be honest so I think
what we'd want to do here is be a little
bit more like careful and see I sorry I
missed a bunch of these questions should
you get our copy from the opposite flip
sides of the octal mapping so the
bilinear blend will blend correctly not
sure what that means we tried to do the
correct copy right so the gutter is
around this outside right and so if you
look at where these would match up with
right where does this go well it goes to
here right so when we do the copy we
want to copy here to here and here to
here which is what we did right this is
here that is there right
am I am I wrong so as far as I know we
copied the gutters in the way that the
action the way they actually go around
the octahedron so unless that's not what
you mean
as far as the lighting height let's see
if we can get it to wig out on the on
the debug light position so if you look
here we've got this world mode debug
light PE nonsense and that debug light P
is something that takes whatever the
ground P is and just like hovers it
right so if we were to take that value
and smoothly vary this thing you know
somehow we could definitely make
something that was going to you know
so here we can just like very this thing
using DT which we don't really want to
do for anything real but it's pretty
easy for us to do it here so we can just
say like look why don't you add to this
like the sine of T crappy and we'll make
it hover by like 0.25 or something right
and that makes it so that this will go
up and down separately to see if we can
find that that error there oops this is
an f32
and so we can just make that like thing
like hover in place and
[Music]
so there you can see it hovering up and
down and I don't see a pop in that right
and so if I I could make it hover up and
down quite a bit more so than I think
the hero does ever
so there is a pop there right for sure
you know what I'm thinking actually now
that I'm seeing what it's doing
I guess that pop is just actually true
because it's a point light source we're
treating it as a point so when that
point moves below a certain probe that's
just what's gonna happen it's gonna
instantaneously go from being visible
above it to being invisible right so
unless we add a cosine fall-off there
and even if we didn't the fact that it's
moving it could move straight through
one of these things and in fact it will
because we're lined up with it exactly
so I think that may be somewhat
unavoidable I mean don't quote me on
that
but that may be somewhat unavoidable and
and remember we're not doing an inner
product for the lighting right now which
we should be doing and you know what now
I think about it without that inner
product that could also explain where
some of these seams are coming from
right because that's a hard
discontinuity let me see what happens if
I just put that into our Z bias program
so if I come out here to the Xevious
program and I just say all right so you
know we're gonna want to actually do a
clamp 0 1 cosine fall-off curve here
right so when we actually do our light
lookup and we're gonna actually like
combine these here before I go and
actually you know include them I want to
do some kind of a of a clamp and
fortunately I don't pass the normal do I
so we kind of need we kind of need this
to come in there how is that going to
work
so the
so the our value is as that point light
is moving through we you know I sorry
I'm not gonna throw that and that's a
little bit too much to throw in so we'll
see later but
all right so I think we're good I'm
gonna leave this and we can take a look
at that the popping but I'm assuming
that that's what that is as it goes from
one probe to the other you can actually
see where the probe is so you can
actually see as it passes through the
center point that's exactly what's
happening right
so that's like what's happening all
right we can fix all that so I'm not too
concerned about that at all
so I'm gonna go ahead and and nerf this
here I don't really want that in there
long term that was just to see if I was
right but it looks like that's the case
all right so I think we're good with
that and I'm gonna go ahead and call it
for today let's make sure that
recompiles everything's good all right
boop boop
thank you everyone for joining me for
the facade of handmade hero sort of
pleasure coating with you as always if
you would like to follow a series at
home you can always pre-order the game
on handmade hero arc it comes with a
source code so you can follow along with
it from day to day I will I think I
forgot to upload the video from
yesterday I will upload the video from
yesterday to be sure until then everyone
have fun programming and I'll see you on
the Internet
Diggy's everybody