hello everybody and welcome to handmade
hero we are going to be taking a look at
the lighting code today because uh when
i did my survey last week of stuff i
wanted to improve i was gonna say like
oh we we should simplify the lighting
because it's too complicated and it
doesn't look good enough and whatever
because that was like my recollection of
it
but actually when we looked at it um i
realized the lighting actually seems to
look quite good
um like looking at the lighting here
uh it actually looks quite nice and i
was like uh maybe we're actually pretty
close to having like high end lighting
that that actually is pretty good uh so
i i think maybe i spoke too soon i think
maybe we just keep this
um but there are a couple things that i
wanted to take a look at today
uh because i think there are some things
we can do to improve it so what you can
see here is like the best case for the
lighting this is what happens if we
effectively sort of in nor ignore
um
any high
uh
sort of any high frequency updating to
the lighting uh you can see that it's
quite laggy right now like you can see
it takes a while for the lightning point
to come in so this is a long-term
average blend of the lighting and you
can see that it does look quite nice
when you give it enough time right but
it's too slow
and what i sort of looked at uh the
other day
is that if you actually look at the code
and how the breakdown of performance
looks in it in fact i think we can still
sort of see that here
um if we go into the profile
so if we take a look at uh the the
actual like clocks here i don't know to
what extent i can i can actually look at
these but
um if we actually look at the the way
these clocks break down here if i
remember correctly uh this so you can
see the lighting takes all the time
uh that's that's our pretty much only
real expensive thing we do because we're
doing it on the cpu we haven't
moved it to uh the gpu which we still
might do someday there's a lot of
efficiency to be gained
by moving it to the gpu not necessarily
because the gpu will do it all that much
faster um
it's really not so much that it's more
that because the gpu is the thing that's
doing all the pixel fill uh the fact
that we have to move the data
from the cpu to the gpu every frame is
kind of a waste
of everyone's time
so you know there there are some
efficiency gains to be had here but in
general that's taking all the time but
if you look uh you can kind of see that
we're still like almost getting 16
frames a second even just at the of 60
uh 60 frames a second um we're not quite
hitting it uh reliably but we're close
and
this is with full 3d on the lighting
which we sort of decided we don't really
need the 3d uh and we're probably not
going to stick with the 3d which means
that
a couple things one if we eliminate the
stacking that's going on here right if
the stacking gets eliminated
uh then there's far fewer light probes
to compute
right now i don't remember the exact
z-stack for lighting i think there is uh
some kind of a parameter here that we
threw in there that um
actually i should probably go to the
handmade directory here first before
opening up the editor
um there is like a
set of parameters here that are um
that are related to that
uh i i don't actually like i said it's
been a long time so we looked at this so
i don't actually remember exactly what
they all are but there are like
basically like dimensions here for it
um and you can kind of see that like
there's some
there's some parameters here for tuning
what the voxel dimensions are going to
be for like the lighting
and in a lot of cases we could just
simplify this down quite a bit
and while we i think already call out uh
we don't sample light probes that are
just floating in space and that don't
actually do anything
um so we may not save a whole lot of
processing time in the cpu side for that
we would be
drastically reducing the footprint of
the thing that we're producing because
remember
we have to send this voxel down to the
gpu every frame and if we cut out uh 16
layers of that texture
then that's a dramatic savings both in
terms of like cache footprint
on the cpu side
because remember right now we're also
still using floats we haven't converted
to something smaller than float so these
textures are quite large
so you can kind of get the feel for just
how much savings we could get here
similarly right now i think we're under
casting we were able to
optimize the raycaster quite a bit and
while i don't remember the exact
breakdown between how much time it's
currently taking
uh for us to
to basically do like you know how much
time is going to take us to do raid
casting how much time it's going to take
us to do
uh blending of the texture maps if i
recall correctly blending the texture
maps was a major part of the time sink
which means we could now because the
raycaster is much faster cast more rays
per texture blend
which would get us much more high
frequency lighting for the at the same
quality level right
uh well not exactly the same quality
level necessarily or although perhaps
it's hard to say
so i do think there's like a lot of
things we could do here uh that we could
use to sort of improve
the state of our
uh lighting system
that don't really require us to do much
hard work right like like we're not
confronted with any real research
problems for those things it's literally
just like okay
cut out one dimension of the lighting so
it's just flat plain
um
and it's still doing the lighting
calculations in 3d right but just
doesn't it doesn't calculate stacks of
light probes it just calculates one
sheet of light probes
huge savings for no visual quality
elimination there right uh almost
nothing
uh gets
gets
you know eliminated and that and that so
on
right uh so
all that's good and then similarly we
don't really have uh
we we don't have much limitation to
casting more rays
uh on every frame i don't think i think
we could crank that number up a little
bit
and it would probably be a pretty
substantial improvement in the lighting
for not a huge hit uh to the frame rate
so i think we probably want to do that
um i want to see how hard it is to
actually remove the z sampling here but
i think that's like the first thing i
want to do uh to just get rid of that so
that we're just talking about one sheet
so the light lookup voxel dim z just
goes away basically right
so this is going to be a pretty major
change it's not difficult but it's going
to be
a couple different steps of making the
change so i'm going to try and do it
slowly so what i'd like to do first is
just see what happens if i change this
to 1 right
if we just eliminate one of our of our
uh light look up voxel uh dim z's here
and maybe i take a a quick second a hot
second as well to just look for light
look up uh voxel dim z to see how many
places this is actually being used
because again i don't really have a good
feel for where what that say to that
code is right now because we haven't
worked on it a while
so you can see here where we initialize
the dimensions of the voxel uh lookup
system right
and you can see us doing this make light
atlas we have the
um
the the
[Music]
make light atlas function here
you can see the way this works is it
basically takes any arbitrary voxel
dimension that you want here and
produces
information that it can use to
index into the voxel
now if all i do is change the dimension
in theory if we wrote this code
correctly it should still all work
um one problem that we're going to have
is the lighting bounds are going to be a
little bit trickier for us to compute
now um i mean in some ways they're
actually simpler for us to compute but
we have to go find where that's going to
be
so when we make uh this light atlas for
example you can kind of see that well
you know when it makes the light atlas
it doesn't really think much about the
actual um
like you can see this uh light atlas
tiles dim
uh that gets passed in there
it's thinking more about just like the
texture that has these
tiles in it it's not really thinking
about where they correspond in the world
right that's not a thing uh that they
actually um are used to we're this is in
the profiler i don't even know why we're
looking in that code um hold on a second
how do i get back to the search or the
list
can i do that i don't know if i can
let's let's list again
light
look up
voxel
see
oops
there we go
um so yeah we do have that lighting
profiler which we built separately which
we could also do uh but again i really
just only just mostly care about the the
lighting stuff in the actual code here
let's go over here
uh you can see this is the open gel
initialization of the light look up
voxel right you can see it here you can
see it making the light atlas uh and and
you know allocating
uh this the actual space that it needs
for it and all that sort of stuff right
and uh
like i said so in theory we should be
able to set this to one but we could
also eliminate a lot of the code
complexity here by removing that
parameter entirely uh so that's also
something we would want to do
now in the actual world uh code in world
mode where we're actually running the
main game loop here
which is in in here this code here if we
take a look at the lighting calls
you can see here we do sort of a pass to
gather like stuff that's going to be
in the lighting right
and you
can see
down at the end after everyone has done
everything we call update lighting here
and you can see us passing like you know
a bunch of of primary values to this
thing
so you can see for example us passing
this world mode fundamental unit yeah
you can see us passing like the the two
atlas is down uh you can see us passing
like where the lighting is going to
occur and so on
uh so in the update lighting call you
know it's gonna rely on
uh let's see here we go it's gonna rely
on
what it gets
as these particular values here
to
deter determine like the span of this
voxel grid and you can actually see the
calculations of the
lighting area right here uh every time
that the general size of this thing
changes or whatever happens it
recomputes like how the spatial grid is
aligned and what the walk to it's called
a walk table uh
that we made here it's basically the
thing that allows us to walk through
nodes of the voxel for raycasting and
things like that
um and as far as i know these are sort
of aligned with the lighting grid i
don't remember us using two different
spatial resolutions for those things but
i could be wrong because they there's no
real reason they have to be uh
equivalent but i think we may have made
them equivalent because of certain
efficiencies we could gain from it if i
remember correctly
um so then if you take a look at what
happens here
after we you know ensure that this is
built because this only happens like
once right this only happens if you
change fundamental lighting parameters
um so it's probably only going to happen
once in a run of the game
uh at startup in here you can see update
the alignment of voxels to the view this
is the part that actually tries to like
keep things aligned
and you can see that it's going to do uh
when it
it detects that something
when it detects that the camera has
shifted away from where the voxels are
it shifts the voxel and tries to align
the lighting voxel to wherever the view
is viewing and the reason for this is
because lighting is very expensive so we
only want to compute lighting just where
we can see we don't want to compute
lighting anywhere else and you can see
uh these two set min corners here are
the things that actually like figure out
where the uh atlas grid and the spatial
grid are here right the spatial grid
being the the thing we're actually using
uh to do raycasting and the atlas grid
being the thing that we actually compute
the atlas grid will in general be
smaller than the spatial grid because we
only need to store and compute lighting
values really in the area we can see but
we may need to keep a larger field than
that for spatial intersections because
we want to be able to cast outside of
the visible region to see what we hit
sometimes so the spatial grid is is
potentially larger right
so my question here is again the
it's the z component that i just want to
know about how are we doing like how are
we figuring out where to center
uh the v component right
if you look here we've got sort of this
notion of the voxel cell dimension that
is presumably just going to be whatever
it is right the
the atlas's voxel dimensions are
presumably set to something constant we
can step in here and uh investigate them
certainly but then you can kind of see
it trying to compute like where it's
going to align these things
and presumably to actually set the
dimension of this i assume that the
actual dimensions of this were kind of
just determined by how many cells there
were and what the dimension was
it's going to set the position of this
relative to the camera center somehow
and my concern is that i don't know
whether that's going to be set
appropriately
um for
what we're currently doing if we reduce
this down to one voxel uh
one voxel height right with no no z
stacking
i need to make sure that it's actually
centered around where the player is
which would be a trivial thing
and obviously would be what was
happening if we had started out saying
we're just going to be 2d only but
because we were always 3d that probably
isn't currently the case
right now fortunately i don't really
have to guess uh now that i've looked at
the code and just like it's working the
way i think it is right nothing
particularly weird
um i need to take a look and find out
more specifically here
uh can i you know just draw
where this lighting bound actually
exists right like where is the lighting
actually occurring
um and to the extent that we want to do
that i think we already have the code in
place you can see here there's a thing
that draws the lighting bounds um and so
this this piece of code just this one
wrecked out line here
uh i believe will we can make uh draw
the the part of
we can make this draw like sort of the
thing that bounds the area that we're
actually lighting um now of course i
don't actually know
it looks like though
maybe that's not true anymore uh because
the light bounds don't get passed down
here so i suppose
we actually need to draw them in here
which i suspect we do like i suspect
it's this right here right um when we do
push lighting
render values so this is actually the
one we would want which shows the hot
voxel rectangle here
um which would allow us to see sort of
where we're actually computing the
lighting at right
and you can see how it's completely
black right now and you know i'm
assuming that that's mostly just because
again like the the lights aren't
actually
uh they're there to this this boundary
is going to be too narrow right
so our first
you know our first goal is to just get
this working at only one voxel high and
also i can test to see like how
[Music]
um
like i i can
i can test to see like how flexible this
is like if i set this up to something
else like eight would it continue
working so at what point does it
actually fail in terms of setting the
lookups just to let us know if it's just
if we've got bugs or something so you
know you can see here it looks like if
you make it that high right it's still
working just fine
um if we drop it down now to four
still fine right so it's just when you
get it down small enough it no longer is
working properly maybe because we have
some bugs at the boundary maybe because
the size is too small so the lights are
like outside of it
right we just don't really know but
there's a two high one and it's still
working just fine so i suspect really
mostly what we need to do here is just
to make sure that the
uh voxel the the way that we're actually
doing this light look up voxel
here uh doesn't have some kind of a bug
in it when it gets down to one like
maybe that's the case here or it could
just be that this is now too thin and
it's not picking up uh light sources for
some reason right we really just don't
know uh what the actual problem is so
you can see i'm walking around now in
there
um
so you know
take a look at this more carefully and
i'll set this up to 2 because that's the
lowest version that's currently working
but again we can kind of see that like
there's no real reason
that we need the lighting bounds to be
particularly large because
even just setting it to two it looks the
exact same now right like the game
really doesn't look particularly
different this way you can see a couple
bugs
again with that height problem as it
moves up and down you can kind of see
that the lighting voxels uh we're
hopping in and out of you can see like
we're missing samples as we get too high
so and the other thing that i guess i
would say is i also am not sure we want
to drop to one
uh we may want to keep it at two because
we may want a high and a low sample on
each tile to give it some
a little bit of uh
of range there so to be completely
honest i don't actually know that we
don't want to leave it at two but even
just assuming like let's assume we do
want to leave it at two uh we still
probably want to go ahead and try to fix
the way that the heights work here
because we don't really want to move up
and down in z anymore like our our new
um kind of rule that we decided when we
just looked at what was good for cost
benefit analysis um
for the game is we just want to keep one
uh level and we're gonna eliminate this
kind of stairwell stuff right we're just
not gonna have it anymore because we
decided it just wasn't interesting
enough for the cost that we were paying
so
assuming that we're going to do that it
means that now like the actual z
range of the lighting isn't really going
to change those values are just going to
be fixed in space
and we can't assume something like oh
we're just going to pick some bounds
between you know negative 1 or 1 or
something like that
we can
we can do
some kind of a
just a re
some kind of predefined value that just
tells us what these z bounds are going
to be and we're just going to go from
there
what that would translate to uh in
practice is things things like the sim
region
uh and other things like that are always
gonna end up we're gonna be taking z out
of all of their computations
and so what that means for the lighting
system is when it goes through here to
do like the update lighting
as it does uh whenever we do this sort
of set min bounds here this all of this
stuff that we're looking at uh to see
whether the centers moved and that sort
of thing uh we're not going to want to
to have z be involved here at all right
we're going to want to
uh always adjust after the fact the
values we're using to compute the
alignment of the grid
to just assume that z is not a thing
so if you
[Music]
take a look at what's going on here you
can see we have like the origin p and
the last origin p
set up here
um
in theory
so in theory i i think probably i would
start by locking
the
i would start by locking
like the
the
sim regions to always have a constant z
then i assume we also because this
tracks the camera
i assume we would also need
we would also need the camera z's to be
ignored
um
and i'm not sure exactly how i want to
do that you know
you can see here like there's an origin
p and a sim origin p that are passed in
here
um and if we just start to assume that
those are always zeroed you know i could
do something like say
that the sim origin p
uh
you know if you take a look at how these
world positions work there's like a a
chunk z at an offset uh if we always
just assumed that all the z values were
zero you know what would this look like
so if we said like look the chunk z is
always zero
um and the offset z is always zero we're
just never going to allow
uh anything other than that to occur
so
let's just
zero these out here
um if we always assume that those are
zero
what happens like let's just look
because that's the entirety of the data
that's coming in here
in terms of alignment so if we just take
z alignment out of the equation
where does that actually put our bounds
right
so you can see them here
uh and you can see that they are
probably
well i mean it's really hard to say but
they're probably a little too
uh
they're definitely oriented a little
wrong in the sense that this should
actually be moved up right um
considerably
uh and
you know honestly it looks like it
probably is high enough though so mostly
it looks like what we would need to do
is just shift this upward right so when
we look at what the origin z values are
there it looks like uh you know it looks
like the alignment of those is is off in
that sense now there's a couple
different things we can do here but the
first problem that i have is i don't
know
who is off right
if we're going to switch to a new
unified like we always assume we're on
chunk z zero
um
are these
on that chunk or not right if we take z
out of the system
it could be that the lighting is now
properly aligned and these are all just
high because there was no reason in the
past why they should be aligned because
we were just assuming you know z can be
anything so we wouldn't have been like
particularly careful to make sure these
fell within our uh appropriate 2d range
so the other thing that i i think i
would like to uh
try to do here is to draw in the sim
region so let's suppose that we
take a
let's take a look at the outside here
where we're actually calling update
lighting
so if you take a look at what we're
actually passing for those values
you can see that
after the diffuse atlas and the specular
atlas here
uh we're passing the symbol origin p so
it's this lighting sim center
and lighting center right those two
um if we go look at where those are
coming from
you can see them here
uh the simulation center that should we
should always peg to xero as well
outside of this because everyone wants
to do that now
and the lighting sim center you can see
is using that camera
simulation center there and that also
now wants to be pegged to zero so
probably if we move these outward a
little bit we can then also see
uh
to what extent those are
align with the world and maybe we draw
like something in there that lets us
know
uh where that's happening so
let's try to back this out here and
figure out like exactly where
um
where is the right place to make sure
that these are always clamped so if we
take a look at the
like if we take a look at the simulation
center
in fact
actually
these are the same right
so these are always the same value it
looks like sort of uh i mean not exactly
the
this is calling map into chunk space
uh
using the simulation center of i guess
whatever the world camera rectangle is
so wherever the center of where you're
looking is right
um
so i suppose not exactly
but
yeah like
if you look at these two values they're
basically just being derived from each
other right this simulation center is
still the thing that matters in this
case
and this is probably
this is just looking at what the camera
rectangle is that we're viewing and
saying the center of it is going to be
uh where that you know
where we actually take
um
the the lighting to be aligned so
this
this will take care of itself but this
wouldn't right because that world camera
wrecked you know is is going to be
computed
um in a different way so you can see it
calling get camera rectangle at target
uh with a focus z here
and this computation
is going to produce some kind of a up
and down range right
so let's take a look at how that's
actually working
so get camera rectangular target here uh
it's it's basically just saying look
we're going to unproject the the cube of
visibility
uh and we're going to produce it here
with a rectman max right
so
to be honest i don't know that we really
want to play with that uh i'm guessing
really what we want to do is just
flatten these rectangles down uh to
exist within a
predefined sort of range right so that
we basically like take the camera rec
that comes out but we want to flatten it
so that we're generally talking about
looking at um a range close to zero and
z
because otherwise you know we other
there's really nothing wrong with this
on project that tells us that the region
that we're actually looking at here
let's take a look at that world camera
rect
where we're actually viewing that
we can push that as well
so this is going to be a white
volume that's overlaid on top of what
we've got here
so you can see here
the the two different actual
rectangles in question
so what we see here is the camera view
volume and what we see here is the
lighting volume so
uh
don't ask me why they're quite so
off-center aligned
they're um
[Music]
i think we decided that hopping
backwards you'd be less likely to
because the
the camera sees more forwards than it
sees backwards i think we skewed it
intentionally there so i don't think
that's a bug i think that's actually by
design uh but you know you can correct
me if i'm wrong and go back and watch
the tape
um
so looking at this you can see
that uh honestly it's it's pretty
reasonable right um
like like that actually looks
again about right
and
yeah so you know really i think just
making sure all of this stuff now exists
at a predefined z range which would move
everything down and we'll probably have
to change the world gen to move
everything down a little bit uh is
probably fine so the other thing i guess
i want to do is at any given time here
i'd like to
[Music]
render what is effectively like just
where is the zero
axis
so like
you know if i was going to to do a
negative
one to one cube like where would that
cube sit um
or maybe just a
yeah i mean i think that's the right
thing to do so let's suppose i did a
negative uh one unit
to a one
let's suppose i throw in a yellow cube
that looks like that
uh and
where is that right
so this is just saying like where is the
origin in our space so that we can see
how we end up aligning these things
um so what you can see there is that
yeah we are floating a bit above
uh
and
well you know not really i guess it's
not that that much above it's hard to
say a little bit above
where the zero region is so if we were
to pat uh if we were to sort of align
these things directly to zero uh you can
sort of see we would be right in the
middle boundary of that which you know
honestly is is not that far from where
we are at the moment
um but if we were to do that uh you can
kind of see how we would need to make
sure we span enough on either side to
make sure that we're you know within
reason there but you're not too bad
right not too bad
okay
um so now that we have and you can also
see as we move around you can see how
the origin shifts remember we use a
relative origin so that we never run out
of float precision we're always centered
around the origin roughly
so as you hop around the game as you can
kind of see the outside of the game
shifts the origin in order to keep that
space you know relative properly
so my guess here
uh is that yeah if we just kind of first
lock the simulation center z and then
lock the lighting center well the light
center was sort of automatically locked
to it
um
that should pretty much do it
so in terms of simulation center
to be completely honest with you i do
not remember exactly how we set up those
i think the simulation center just gets
shifted around as the camera like we
basically have a camera
update routine that runs at the end
that's like i don't know where we call
it exactly but it happens
somewhere in here update camera for
entity movement um update camera for
entity movement is really the place i
think where we shift the simulation
center around it all
um so
yeah like if you take a look at
uh how this works you can see that the
camera itself moves around uh with this
map into chunk space for camera pdp and
target p uh the simulation center part
of things
i don't know when we actually update
that
uh for it
let's find out here
right here so you can see
uh this this code here where we see that
we're inside a room
you can see that the simulation center
when we map into trunk space it's
basically always pushing
um this align to movement voxel version
of the simulation center so it's always
kind of
uh
taking this room volume minzy as a
simulation center
i i want to say
that we could literally just zero that
out so you know this is how we used to
do it uh and now we can literally just
say
we're taking z out of the system
and i think that would be it i think now
no matter what we do we would never
shift upwards or downwards right
for simulation center for simulation
center
so taking a look at it now right
again the simulation center itself
is not being drawn so we may want to
i mean it sort of is that zero box that
we've got in there but the simulation
region i guess i would say so if we
wanted if we want to show this the
simulation region i believe this right
here uh is what does that although it
looks like for some reason yeah it's it
does the bounds on x y so i think this
is
um
i think this is probably not exactly how
you want to do it
because
we're sort of already assuming that it
gets centered around zero which we kind
of know the access system is so yeah i
mean i guess i guess what i would say is
that that is showing the simulation
center right because everything is
centered around the simulation center
um so as we hop around now we should be
always pegged to zero so there shouldn't
ever be
a a simulation center value uh where the
z is anything other than zero
which means that as we go like for
example down into lower levels now it
shouldn't shift and you see that it
doesn't right it used to
um so now we're we are going lower down
um and the the actual simulation center
uh should not
um you know we won't even really be able
to see where we're going but uh should
not ever shift downward to follow us and
you can see it doesn't we're down in
this second level now
and you can see that although the camera
rectangle clearly is shifting downward
right um the simulation center isn't
right
so i think that's step one um
step two is that we don't actually want
the camera
so when we do the camera uh rectangle
that we pass into the lighting we don't
ever want that camera rectangle to have
that offset either so i think what we
probably want to do here is again head
that off at the pass
so that when we do our lighting values
and we are computing those two uh
offsets one of them we know is always
back to zero the other one we should
also make sure we constantly peg to zero
and so if we look here at the simulation
bounds
we know that these should always be
pegged to zero properly when we get down
to here this part this get center world
camera rect
that may produce an offset in z and so
at least for the time being
i'm going to go ahead and just peg that
so that the the chunk z is going to be
zero
and the offset z is going to be zero
uh just to make sure that now the
lighting rectangle is also properly
always floored to
zero
which will give us something that should
always float right sort of on
um
that that boundary now one of the things
that you can see here is that the the
the way these two things span is going
to have to be adjusted slightly and
again that may mean
adjusting this stuff or it may mean
something else
right we we have some flexibility in how
we do this
but if you look at what's happening now
you can see that the
uh the lighting rectangle is properly
sort of floating
at the z equals zero area and it can't
actually or shouldn't be able to move up
and down right
so you know
it can move sort of in other directions
you can see there's a bit of a of wiggle
there which i'm not sure exactly what
that's from
the hopping comp you know the hopping
introduces a little bit of bounce there
but it doesn't it doesn't appear to be z
bounce i don't know maybe it is b bounce
let's make sure it shouldn't be
it's kind of hard to say
right
but at least in theory hopefully we
aren't getting any z bounce now because
that
the offset in z should be zeroed it
shouldn't really be
um
possible to get something that's not
z zeroed out out there right
um but that's the only thing that isn't
derived off the simulation center it's
because of the world camera part that we
could get a z offset there so this just
prevents that from happening and then of
course this part should always be peg to
zero now because we don't allow the
simulation center uh to everybody ever
be anything else either so what we can
do here is we can put in some asserts
like for example i can assert the
lighting sim center here
that it's chunk z is always zero and i
can put in another assert here uh that
the offset
z is always zero um
uh just to make sure that we're actually
getting that like that we're not uh
somehow introducing some wobble uh in
fact i could do that in a more opportune
place as well what i could do is
actually go to the update lighting call
so when it gets passed in here in fact
we could assert that we're never getting
anything else uh from our sim origin
um or our lighting origin right so
neither of those two things
uh anymore is allowed to have a z offset
so you know it's just
not going to happen
um so now if we run that
we should be able to get like a hard
crash like it would would assert and
stop if any time anything was non-zero
so it looks like it's not right
so uh we may have to do some other
tweaking to it but but now we're at
least fairly uh you know assured that
we're not getting
any kind of
you know
basically any kind of
errant motion in z
all right
so we now have to decide how we want to
actually structure this i would say that
uh you know i don't have a particularly
strong
opinion about
where i want the
origin of the world to be
you know like what should be the lowest
z value that we contemplate uh being
able to see
so
my feeling is that we just make that be
zero
so in other words anything
that's below zero will not be tracked
right
so
[Music]
we just assume that maybe the world is
built a little bit higher than zero and
if there was a pit or something that pit
it it's just like a blackness at zero or
something
um and so things don't really get
lighting when they fall if they were to
go past zero
you just get the lighting from whatever
was at zero you don't you don't keep
getting lighting going down or things
like that right
so uh again that's less realistic but
we're sort of saying like we're taking z
out because it just doesn't give us
enough bang for the buck there so let's
go ahead and uh actually sort of make
that assumption so what that means is
that this the lighting voxel is kind of
aligned oddly
it appears that when you pass in
the uh
z at zero it's it's treating that more
as like a center point rather than a
minimum right
um and that makes some sense for the
other components but it doesn't make a
whole lot of sense for z right
um and so when we look at what happens
here we can sort of simplify a bunch of
these things because now we don't have
to have so you know for example we had
when we did block copy atlas
you can see in here we've got a whole
bunch of stuff to handle like z
which now we would no longer have to do
right
um so this sort of stuff would would
simplify certainly uh because it removes
one entire set of the loops here we
could we could simply simplify a lot of
this code
now i'm not going to bother with that
because we could only be introducing
bugs at this point
because we know that stuff works for the
full case so we don't really need to get
rid of it but what i would like to do
first is say well okay let's figure out
why this is how this is aligned in z and
kind of change it a little bit so that
it's always aligning ourselves to zero
and up because it just gives us
something we can
be more uh
we can be more afraid of it now you know
saying that maybe that's wrong because
since we're
since we're providing a center for all
the other axes maybe we want to provide
a center for that too you know i don't
know it's hard to
make that call so we could actually also
say the opposite right which is that we
we are passing in zero as the center and
we kind of go up and down from there um
that's also a plausible thing we could
say so maybe you know that makes more
sense let's take a look at this code
first before we decide
so
you know here's the alignment
code
it first says look let's find out
um if we were to take the origin p which
is where we want to compute the lighting
let's find where that offset is right
you can see it computing the offset here
um and then it says well
where was the last where was the last
place we did this right
so it just tracks the center
that's all it's doing here
um and then moves the voxel based on the
movement of the center makes perfect
sense no worries right
that would be the same no matter what we
did because that's just tracking
relative movement so the point whether
we pick the center or the corner or
anything else doesn't matter as long as
it's the same point each time that code
will work because it's just sliding the
voxel to match the world space
so
really this is the code here
that we're talking about
um and what you can see is this is the
part where we compute those corners
you can see us doing a minus 0.5 of the
hot dimension so you can see us doing
that computation is as is coming out
from the center
so i guess what i would say about that
is
probably we just want to keep that um
like because it's just a simpler
computation so we probably do want to
say zero is like the center point
um and so the world expands a little bit
up and a little bit down from zero
uh and we just kind of change a little
bit like when we're looking at something
like the room gen code uh right now
things are sort of skewed upward and
maybe we just don't do that anymore
right uh so when we're talking about
figuring out where these walls actually
occur uh we instead of what we're doing
right now we sort of shift them uh in
another way so like for example when we
take a look at how the uh the p-value is
getting set up here the uh you can kind
of look in and see how this this is some
pretty crappy code but you can see get
minzy center p
right uh it's asking for a tile
where is the uh the center point at the
minimum z value it's going to come back
uh with this
we can sort of say well all right how
were we defining these tiles and maybe
what we need to do is say that these
tiles are defined uh as being a little
bit downward or something from where
they were uh so that things are aligned
a little bit differently
if we take a look again get minzy center
p you can see here where we point the
tile uh and we want to get the total
volume of of this tile right here is our
definition for what a tile uh consists
of
it's
like wherever the relative index of this
tile is is the minimum p-value uh times
the tile dim
and so
the relative index z right like if it
was zero
um
would end up being at zero for this
particular thing
and you know really we probably want
that to be offset a little bit right so
the total volume total tile volume here
like this probably wants to be offset
by some value if this is the minimum p
uh for
you know
for this tile
uh and another way we could look at this
is these values if we're going to take z
out of the equation
maybe these values are always cold set
right like maybe it's always negative
one you know to one or something like
that
i'm not sure uh if we look at the floor
height we have a um
i'm not sure where this v
value uh
actually gets computed but we have this
concept of the typical floor height here
um and the typical floor height
is
just a thing we picked
based on like okay how many meters
should this be
you can see that it's it's three
of whatever the fundamental unit is
right like that's how big uh this thing
was
so what we presumably want to do here is
have that value uh be reflected in that
like it should be basically
negative half of that and negative
and positive of that right
so the tile dim value here
we really want the z to sort of be
centered around that in a way right
so
you know maybe the right way to look at
this is to say well it's
minus half so it's if it was centered
around this dim it would be something
more like this
right
um
i also don't really know why this is
being computed this way that's a very
strange
uh
way to compute this you know
this is just kind of weird code like
normally wouldn't you just do this
i mean
right the max p is always one tile dim
away from the min piece so why you would
multiply them both for no reason i have
no idea
um so you know it would just i would
assume that this is how you would
normally do it uh so
yeah i don't i don't really know uh what
was up with that but you know
[Music]
you got me
um so anyway uh looking at at how that's
aligned now you can see that
excuse me
um you can see that we now have first
that's a bit weird i'm not sure why the
lighting looks like it's down there
i'm going to have to we're going to have
to take a look at that a little more
carefully
but you can see now that
everything is sort of aligned a little
more sensibly
where we're going positive and negative
of the uh you know
if this right here is the origin so z
equals zero is right in the middle of
that right is the way to think about
that
uh then you can kind of see how now the
world is sort of built a little more
sanely around
around that value right
now it's not quite what i would like
because probably the floor should maybe
be more around negative one would be my
guess
um so we're you know we're not quite as
aligned as i would like but we're more
aligned and also coincidentally the
lighting now works um
uh around the the only problem we're
getting is for some reason we have a
weird like the camera
is not actually aligned to like where
the camera is looking
does not actually seem to be aligned to
where the world was constructed and lit
so we've got some kind of a bug with the
camera thing there but that's all right
well we're getting there
we're modifying one thing at a time
right
so it seems straightforward relatively
straightforward right to take z out of
the equation there
um and
you know
it's not immediately clear exactly how
uh we want this code to function
but this seems
reasonable right uh that seems
reasonable and we can look into this a
little bit further
um so we could start to say like all
right this relative z index gets taken
out of the equation as well so like we
know for example that this is not going
to be a thing like there's no rel index
uh so on the tile right
when we look at the relative index of
this thing
um what actually tile rail index where
is that
that's in
ed yeah this guy right here right
um so the relative index here that we're
using we know that that will always get
pegged as well and that we don't really
want to iterate over any of those values
it's just going to be real index x and y
and again we'll slowly peel that off
like we'll probably change um
the gen v3 here we'll change that
from a gen v3 to a gen v2 at some point
and just remove that third component
entirely
because it's not going to be involved
so um yeah okay
so let's take a quick look because
before i go any further i'd like to
figure out why
the
uh remember the things we're looking at
here is this is the lighting bounds and
this is the camera uh like what the
camera says it's looking at
and i'm not
quite sure i understand why these two
would be uh offset in the way that they
appear to be because
if we look at the camera
i mean
maybe this is just a case of the camera
offset is computed like we didn't really
look at how that was being done so maybe
it's just case of forgetting the
specifics of that
but if you take a look at how this works
uh you can see the simulation center
here
um we're using directly we know that
that's a line we're looking at that
that yellow cube
um
and
so we we know that everything's uh
presumably working properly here except
for this world camera rect
the world camera rect is just doing the
the
get camera rectangle at target here with
the focus z and this
uh here this focus equals 0.5 times
world mode camera expected focus uh
minzy uh expected uh focus max z so
this
here
is
presumably like erroneous the way that
we're thinking about this is not correct
right
so what this function is doing is it's
saying at this distance from the camera
please compute what we would see
and you know
i can understand
why we were doing that because we
imagined we were going to have complete
uh freedom of how far z would be and so
on
when we pass this value in
i don't actually know
those are presumably camera relative
right i don't actually know let's take a
look
because i'm not sure
so
so okay you can kind of see a bit of a
oddity here right um
the expected focus minzy and the
expected focus maxi is getting set based
on where you are so you can kind of see
why this would be wrong so these
actually now want to be pegged values um
so yeah i mean
you you can see
pretty much why this is this is broken
because if we're taking z out of the
equation this is still trying to compute
some bounds about where the z is going
to be focused on right
um and you can see us doing a bunch of
of work here to do stuff like setting
the camera um
z values because we were using
uh some dynamic alpha blending to get
rid of like floors that were above and
below us all of that can go away now
right we don't actually need that code
anymore which again is why i say like
it's going to be good to remove this
code because it was extra complexity
that really wasn't getting us very much
um
so yeah so this code doesn't really need
to happen
because it actually isn't camera
relative it's actually
literal in the world and so what we're
expecting now is that look we're just
focusing on z zero that's that's the
focus that in the world from now on um
is that z zero we're never going to let
it go uh anywhere else really
that's just where it is
uh and so now what we need to do is
figure out like where that's going to be
it's a little bit weird that
didn't produce something centered around
here so that focus value might must not
really be world relative
um
i'm not entirely certain um
because that's a bit strange
right
if we look at that world camera rect
that computation if that's uh world
relative we should be able to produce
you know we should be able to pretty
much plug in any value that we want here
so that's a little bit odd
uh that plugging in focus e of zero so
maybe that's not let me look at how this
code works just so i can see how we were
computing it
so i get camera rectangle at distance
it's this one right here so if we
do world distance from camera z
so okay so that is camera relative i'm
so confused right now that is camera
relative it didn't look like it was
camera relative though
so how let's let's look at how are we
computing this here
uh those are
those are derived from
uh target expected focus right
so
target expected focus
room focus z and entity focus z so all
right room focus z
entity focus z how are we updating those
okay so it is relative to the camera
right
all right so
what's the focus z here
uh
relative to the camera
is this measured
so i don't we would need to know the
camera arm here so you know what i could
say
uh
i could leave this
quote-unquote computation in place
although i think we probably just want
uh expected focus z
uh
[Music]
to just be a value on its own so so
maybe we'll just say look the focus z
is this
and then we'll we'll eliminate that
that actual value
so from camera
we will say
world camera where was the
if
if this is our camera why
world mode camera expected focus z that
is not the actual camera
again too much complexity
uh you can see why i want to do one
simplification pass
so uh it's the game camera
is the thing that generates the camera
because the actual camera is just for
rendering right
uh you can see here we've got all of the
target expectancy all that stuff so this
i'm going to simplify down to just
expected focus z
and
that we don't really need to compute
every frame it's just going to more or
less be well i mean i guess we do if the
camera like pulls back or goes forwards
so i suppose the yeah i mean maybe we do
kind of do it every frame for that
reason
but that's all we actually need so if
you take a look here you can see there's
uh this camera arm concept right
which is like the camera z value which
is presumably just something we build up
here
yeah
so the camera z value well we're even
just passing it in right so when we do
update camera for entity movement you
can see us passing in the camera z here
that's the camera z axis
right
so i would say we just back out all of
this code
we just nuke it from orbit because the
only person who cares about this value
now
is going to be the person who sets uh
that lighting offset value right so when
it when it tries to determine
what the camera rect is
this right here
we can use the camera z that we
ourselves computed to figure out this
value trivially because it's just
wherever the camera is
it's that it's not producted with that
axis right it's just a measure along
this axis how far away the camera was
so we no longer need to do this because
we're not actually going to be we're
always going to peg our z distance so i
think that basically simplifies all of
this code uh like all of this code will
now go away uh which is great because
like i said
it's too complicated right
um
so
yeah uh
although i guess now that i think about
it too though the only thing that we do
want to do is we probably still do want
to pass it in after we trim all the code
because in order to produce the new
target location
we would still have that z-arm come out
of it so it still needs to kind of know
like how far it should move out based on
what it's looking at
um so so i'm going to just trim this
code really quick here
but then we still do kind of want it
just for this we don't need
this anymore right
but we do kind of want to trim all of
this stuff so i think all of this goes
away
um the entirety of it um
yeah
none of this still exists
but but i spoke too soon we still do
want the camera zx so because it needs
to know how far
out it needs to know how to move the
camera
um how for how far away uh
how far pulled back it needs to be right
so so that's okay
um so now we just need to take this uh
piece of code here uh we don't care
about any of this so this focus z mac
and the like the fog params uh we're not
really gonna do those anymore right uh
so
but we can still set these
uh i don't know exactly what the values
here want to be but
i don't know these can be set to like
something fairly
fairly wide here temporarily but i'm
going to put to do in here and just say
simplify all this code now that z
doesn't vary
so
we're going to do a few simplification
passes here put the camera z back in
there
um
and yeah we don't care about any of this
stuff it's just printing that stuff out
um and so now i just need to go and make
it so that we compute that camera z
uh
offset this expected focus here
so
the camera z would just be the inner
product sorry the expected focus z so
this value that we want here
the expected focus z which we can get
rid of the
that in the actual game camera we don't
need it anymore um this is
always known
uh we can just say look wherever the
camera actually is
um the expected focus z is just the the
measurement along the camera z axis of
that so we just need like the camera
position here
right is all we actually need because
that off that back from zero is is all
we really need to know
now the problem that we're gonna have is
that we don't actually uh
the expected focus z value there like
how far far back it's gonna be
we do need the two we need the the
target and the world position we need to
to measure those uh so we need you know
we effectively need like
uh target
i guess we would need like camera pose
minus camera target right
can't quite spell today
um
we would need like the camera position
minus the camera target for the expected
focus z value
and in order to uh produce that we
we presumably already have put we
presumably already computed those camera
uh
those camera values here right
so like for example in order to set the
camera transform we would need we would
need this information
right um
so
camera zero t i assume is the value that
we actually
uh
are looking for
here for
[Music]
just quick take delta from sim
so
subtract remote camera p from canvas
image center so yeah you can see like
delta from sim is where the camera
actually is right it's the camera p here
um and
i guess we don't at the moment i don't
know that we look at the target but
i guess we know the target is always at
zero anyway so we probably don't care
because the x and y displacement
well but we kind of do want to remove
those
because
we only want just how far away
uh it's going to be and
it could add to the appearance that it
is further away
along that axis right i mean is that
true or is that going to take it it's
going to be entirely
yeah so i'm not 100 sure about that
[Music]
so i think i'm just going to recompute
the value here just to be sure
because i don't i don't want this to be
at all wrong so i'm going to do like a
camera
target to camera
something like that
uh so that we can take a look at the
game camera here and say look we've got
a p we've got a target p
um
and
maybe i guess i also don't really know
though uh
to what extent this is doing sort of a
chase movement like if this is
interpolating towards here then the
camera p as it currently exists i guess
we don't really know
um
you know we don't know how far it is in
x and y
although we do kind of know
so i guess all of this again because we
know that the camera has to it's just
the intersection with the zero plane is
is where it has to go we could just ask
for that intersection
um from the
you know from the the p value right so i
suppose we
j just because we don't have
uh the target p value i suppose uh we
could just say
well if we know where the camera
is looking currently we know how far
away that it's going it's going to have
to be
uh to produce that z value so it should
be possible for us to
uh correctly set this because again we
know that no matter how the camera moves
because the camera does change its
position in z we're always looking back
towards
um
[Music]
the z zero value
so in theory right we should be able to
just say well the ratio between
the just a straight you know
this
uh
the ratio of movement between the z
vector just pure z
and whatever the camera's current uh
z
like the direction the camera is
currently looking
that's just going to be the camera's z's
z value right that's that's how slowly
it goes
forwards in z
so whatever the height is of the camera
right whatever the the um
i think we call that what delta from sim
right it was called delta from sim
so
uh
delta from sim
where was that value is right here
uh
when we compute this delta from sim
which just says how far is the camera
off of zero because we know that this is
always zero z right so how far is camera
off of zero
we would know just right from that
uh
we immediately already know uh
just by looking at that z vector what
the distance to the z plane would be
right
so the delta from
sims z value
that's how far in z just vertically the
camera is off the ground
um and the order of the subtraction
there
when we look at delta from sim it's
going from the simulation center to the
camera so it's a positive value right
because camera is higher than the zero
plane always
um
so when we look at that uh value we know
that this is a positive value we know
that the camera z
uh presumably if this orientation is a
you know a right-handed coordinate
system
uh
we're going to
i guess i don't really remember exactly
how we set it up but i believe z comes
out uh
back towards us in the screen so we're
also talking about a value that would be
going coming up away from the z plane
there
so assuming that those are both true
then really all we're talking about is
like a divide here right the amount of
time it will take it to take it to
intersect this plane right is just going
to be how far it has to go divided by
how fast effectively it goes along that
vector and that would be the expected
focus z value right
um
so i think that's pretty much it
uh
but you know i could be very wrong about
that um if that makes sense
all right so let's try and get that
debugged properly because i think that's
all we really want to do is to say like
look that's okay so that's going to be
like our focus value right so let's take
a look at this code and see how that
actually works i also don't know if this
is supposed to be negative meaning
negative motion
along it so if we look at get camera
rectangle at distance we have to kind of
know which which world distance from
camera z
because it's phrased that way i would
assume that world distance from camera z
uh effectively means that the value is
going to be positive but i didn't
actually know that right so
uh we have to go kind of verify that's
the case when you look at unproject for
example
uh and you look at this world distance
from camera z um
you know
what is that actually saying here so
it's it's creating a
from the origin of the camera basically
it's subtracting the distance times the
z
so yeah so i think this value is
positive right i think this value is
positive
um
that's being passed in here but i could
be wrong about that
so let's take a look uh if i switch to a
debug build so we can inspect these
values more um just
turn to
the o2 to an od here
i i'm going to set a breakpoint in there
um
somewhere
let's get a little more room here
uh i'm going to set a breakpoint in
there so i can inspect uh how that code
is functioning and we'll just take a
look at it so
here is us reaching the
the delta from sim line
uh let's take a look at what these
values work out to be so we've got delta
from sim and we've got camera z
so here are those values this is what
you would expect right so if you take a
look at what we're actually getting here
you would expect a camera
z value to not have any x component in
it because we're looking straight down
uh we're not looking there's no slant on
either side we're just slanted in y so
we're just so we expect there to be a y
value relatively small a z value
relatively large that's exactly what we
see so this makes perfect sense
let's take a look at our delta from sim
that is not what i would have expected
so that's confusing and maybe a source
of our
errors here uh maybe it takes the camera
a little while okay so it looks like it
takes the camera a little while to chase
where to where it should be all right so
now the camera is it's negative 2.8
back in y but its z value is zero
um
so that definitely means i screwed
something up there probably in my
overzealous setting of z's to zero
i must have accidentally uh eliminated
the camera's ability to move up off of
the floor
uh which is going to cause a huge
problem right
specifically for this
uh because if this is zero and the
camera's like flattened to the floor
uh we've got issues so i'm not sure
what maybe i'm thinking of delta from
sim incorrectly let's take a quick look
um at how that works but yeah i mean
looking at it
uh yeah
it's definitely not good so if we take a
look here at update camera for entity
movement um
just thinking about what the z offset's
going to be
um
let's go down and take a look at how
this is being computed here
so
uh
in terms of where the camera is going to
end up
um
so i
i guess this
this value here
is set per room about how far away
you want the camera to be but that's
okay that that should be right
i mean that
that seems correct right
um
so you know i i couldn't say i really
couldn't tell you
uh why that was coming out incorrectly
the only thing i could really think of
is if the room centers
are just set totally wrong
um so that it just so happens that it
comes out to a zero value
that seems unlikely
but obviously we don't really have to
speculate we've got a debug build here
so
i mean heck
i'll just take a look
um because that that part is like you
know
um
we we do have to make sure that the
rooms are set so that they make sense in
that
in that way
and we don't really know exactly what
they are set to
so let's take a look and see just so we
know about that piece of the puzzle
because right each room in the world can
have its own sort of like how far do you
want the camera
uh pulled back so if we step in through
the code here and we take a look
um
i'm gonna
go ahead and say we can skip to just
like when we find out a particular
in-room value here we'll see
okay so it looks like the problem is
that the room bounds are wrong in z so
it looks like you're not in any room at
all
right um so maybe that's just a separate
problem that we have to fix and maybe
that that was that could be our only
problem probably not but it could be
so uh when we actually create these room
bounds i guess i'm not sure
where we were doing that in the room gen
code uh obviously when we create this
stuff
we're sort of procedurally generating
these things so we don't really uh have
any
particular
you know
we never really thought very much about
where they would be in z because again
we were never thinking that it would
just be flat plane
so
i don't actually know yeah like how this
uh
this particular thing is set up to work
so uh you know one thing i might say too
we probably do want to adjust this but
the other thing we would probably want
to do is when we take a look at that
update uh camera for entity movement
when we're looking at the test bounds we
probably don't want to use z anymore
either for that inclusion test i mean
really we probably just want to
uh consider anything in the x y uh
just just use x y is the thing that
determines whether you're in it or not
right um but
so if we take a look at how the layout
code works here uh you can see us making
sort of these
you know volume
creation for rooms here
uh
when we actually go to set the collision
volume
uh of a room which i assume
may be
in the room gen code i'm not sure who
sets the actual
room
like who actually creates the room
collision volume itself
uh
this
is not it uh
camera room
so
[Music]
you can see
the get room volume call
and
it returns the room dim
here
uh and uses the camera room p here which
is getting the center of the room volume
so when we set this room
you know this this whole thing again is
um
this whole thing here is is all using
this rectangle three setting this room
dimension here
is probably wrong
yeah you can kind of see like how this
is getting set right
um
so
really the z bounds on the room dim and
i think you know i'm taking this really
slow but again i want to rip out a lot
of this code because it's complexity
that doesn't need to be there
um but if we take a look at how the room
dimension stuff is working now you can
kind of see that like we don't really
want room dims to exist in this way
anyway
right uh so like the min room p max room
p
uh stuff here where we do
you know where we where we adjust this
stuff
um
you can kind of see that the z is just
not what we want right um so when we
actually come up with the room dim here
this stuff is just not this is not
helping
so
presumably this most straightforward
thing to do
would be to
although you can see the add radius to
it's weird there's like a grid region
versus a grid rack this is this is a bit
weird
but you know if you imagine the room dim
here
uh
if we just move
the min room p
uh z or you know
we could probably just do this
so if we want to add you know a radius
of
you know a z value of like five in both
directions to make the room larger right
uh we
what is this
looks like a typo there
there we go
um
we should be good to go right
and let me take a look at this code now
again
yeah so now it does correctly find a
room and in theory uh we would now have
an actual camera position so let's just
take a quick look at that
before we go any further okay
so
now it looks like everything's square so
it looks like the problem that we were
having before was just that yeah you
weren't considered to really be in a
room
but now all of the bounds appear correct
and wow check out that frame rate this
is the debug build
talk about the lighting getting faster
remember how slow the debug use build
used to be
switching from 3d to 2d not in just in
terms of world complexity
pays
a lot of dividends
uh it's it's not subtle right
um
it's not subtle yeah
so
uh here's the the lighting again let me
let me just take a look here at
i'm curious now profile wise
yeah i mean we're like we're like locked
60 frames a second easily now
um
and we haven't done anything like all we
did was reduce
the the lighting computation to to
uh being the 2d portion and you know
off you go
um
so we're still
we still haven't done a lot of the stuff
we want to do here but we're getting
closer
um
[Music]
so that's good we now have to fix like
our fog so do you see how there's like a
haze
over the world here
our fog parameters are now kind of set
incorrectly because
we're not really taking any care to set
them
and you know we don't necessarily want
to get rid of the fog code because
we don't really know if we're going to
want you know stuff like that
you know just a simple way to like add
some fog in the game or whatever we
wanted to be able to do stuff like that
potentially um so my suspicion would be
that we don't really want to eliminate
that uh
you know out of out of hand so
next thing's next
uh we want to go set that fog code
so that we don't um
so that it's properly bounded to a
reasonable region around where we're
actually looking uh
in the world right so you can see here
here's our our fog value stuff and
my assumption would be that
uh since we know the expected focus z
presumably we can use that
i you know we we are computing
um
a real focus z value now right uh that
that we're using
[Music]
to um to
we are we are computing the expected
focus z value and we're producing we're
producing it correctly right
so up here it's it's free for us to just
say well we can do that right off the
bat
and then we can sort of like set the
fogging
properly based on that so again i don't
really know what these values want to be
but we can certainly set them to
something more sane for the immediate
moment uh than what we were doing before
right
now we do need the camera z value
uh which it looks like we don't extract
yet at this point
um so we just have to move that down
below
uh maybe
keep these things together like here's
where we extract camera values and
here's where we compute
values dependent on those
um
but yeah
and and maybe i'll delete this to do as
well because we we we don't know that
zoom out very like the camera does pull
back and and zoom in we're not going to
remove that uh particular value right
um so now we can see we don't have the
weird fog overlay um because you know
like as you can see uh we've we've
recomputed the value to be to more
correct so the fog code's still in there
in case you want to use it uh but now
it's you know it's not having the same
uh erroneous range computation
so you know we're slowly but surely
moving towards where we want to be um
and let's go ahead now and
yeah and keep going forwards along this
axis
so we still have a bunch of things that
we need to work out
so one of the problems that we will have
right now is that we don't actually have
any coherent theory for where the light
probes are placed
relative to
where the
actual geometry is right
so we're not really taking any special
care like right now we're not even
drawing where those light probes are so
we have no idea like where these light
probes are located and you know probably
we want them to be aligned to this grid
in some way or you know we want them to
be doing something intelligent
as to where they are and we don't really
know uh what that is at the moment and
with specific uh specifically
we want to make sure that the z height
like where the probes are located in z
is going to be pretty important because
we know that we're only computing two so
we would probably you know all things
being equal we would like our z probes
probably one at around floor height like
a little bit above the floor and one
like a little bit below the ceiling or
something is probably where we want them
because anywhere else is really just not
giving us very much valuable information
because we know that everywhere
that we sample these light probes is
going to be basically in that area right
so there wouldn't really be much of a
point to it if we place them in any
other way
so what we probably want to do is now
actually go make sure that that
placement is at least somewhat
uh sane right and i don't really know uh
to what extent we left in the code for
showing where those uh atlases actually
are uh but i think we had some
code in there for that
uh at some point but i guess i don't
really remember
so sorry about that
um so let's take a quick look let's see
do we have any code for this i don't
know if we do
um
it looks like draw
debug draw octahedral values
he sort of does that
so we could use that
that looks like basically what we've got
um
that looks like what we'd
what we'd mostly be looking at
so yeah i don't really
know uh but i think that's probably the
most sane one
so
yeah like maybe we call
maybe we try to actually just call debug
draw octahedral values
i
and
yeah i mean i don't know
debug draw
octahedral values
so it looks like at least we'd seem to
think that that's a plausible call that
we could make
um so i'll
you know try running it
and we'll see what happens
it looks like we don't have
uh
enough
so let me let me actually
see where that assertion actually is
firing
i like the new timer what do you guys
think of the new timer by the way
i just want to see where this is
complaining
uh so it looks like actually this is
just kind of messed up though
um
like the get tile unclamped is
maybe bogus
right so it's like this is actually just
kind of buggy what's the
what's the deal here well that's
obviously wrong
uh hold on a second
okay
yeah
um
uh
yeah no
so
let's uh let's
fix this code uh cause this is just
picking complete garbage values i'm
gonna go ahead and say that now that we
don't have stacks of these things maybe
we can draw them all
because there wouldn't be too many for
debugging purposes i don't know that
maybe too much
uh i'm not sure uh but if we
if we did say something like this for
starters that's an easy solution
to to the problem
um
because yeah that so that was just some
random debug code that picked arbitrary
placement yeah so there we can see uh in
theory those those uh locations
let's go ahead and and switch back to o2
so we don't really have to debug that
now
um and we can kind of see where these uh
voxel values are sitting so
you know here's the here's the lighting
voxel
uh you can see that it's
it's actually not
bad like
uh that's a pretty reasonable placement
for these
uh i would say actually
um
[Music]
it's it's not bad
my
main complaint with it
would be
that
the
[Music]
at least currently
they're too high
i think
um
so you know maybe they would want to be
i don't know are they too high maybe
that's that's not true also the fact
that there's that few of them i think
also we probably can just do this i i
don't know that we need
um
the to to clip out
that many of them we might just be able
to draw them all now
um
i lied
all right you know hey
what can i say i was i was being overly
optimistic
let's try a quarter of them
there we go
uh
so you know okay so you can see all the
light probes there they are
and you can see the lighting
computations that they've got
uh
i would note that
there seems to be some pretty weird
stuff going on so so i think we have
some kind of buggy behavior
occurring in here which you know
uh we'll have to investigate
but like if you look at some of these
light probes some of them don't make a
whole lot of sense so
it may be because there's hidden
occluders uh in the ceiling area or
something that that may be occurring
here right
uh so i'm not sure but like it's not
there isn't a lot of
of explanation
as to why that voxel is not picking up
any light
right
so it looks a bit
it looks like we've got some additional
buggy behavior going on in there
that
you know these things are not quite sam
they're not quite stepping through the
world correctly or something right
there's no there's something amiss
uh in in in there right
and one thing i can do is is draw those
occluders it may just be a case of like
uh floating point jitter but
let me go ahead and draw those uh
occluders a little bit better so that we
can um see them more cleanly
so if we were to do that
that would be in the collision code so
in the in the collision drawing code if
we just turned that on
i
like
you know
here
so this lets us kind of see
uh how this stuff is set up um
but you know
if you just look at this you can tell
immediately like that's just wrong
you know what i mean
like there's no way that's a correct
lighting value you know these things
can't all be picking up the light that's
right here and this this is not
so we've got some buggy behavior
happening now uh and you know again this
is probably as we kind of go through and
try to clean out
uh the way that this stuff is being
computed we're gonna have to
deal with the fact that these are
a little bit wrong now
one problem that we
be looking at here is when we
changed the way that the tiles were
being
uh
aligned we changed so that they were
aligned on their center points now which
means that like the lighting voxel is
shifted a half tile relative to where it
was they used to be in the centers of
tiles now they're on the corners right
now that may actually be desirable so i
don't know that i necessarily want to
fix that
because i may want to have them uh
exactly
exactly in that configuration that that
may actually be exactly what i want
so what i'd rather do is sort of work
through the code and just clean up some
of these
some of whatever these errors are here
right like i wanna
uh i wanna fix that so that that i
uh
i wanna find out why we're getting uh
no lighting samples on some of these uh
grid points
in a very like suspicious regular
pattern right like you know
you
don't see any lighting values coming
from these for some reason but i don't
know why uh so that's like very
suspicious
right
um
big bright ball little tiny
little tiny not bright
you know what i mean
um so we clearly have some debugging
work to do there
uh but otherwise i think we're
getting into better shape right uh
we're we're slowly making progress here
towards something a little more
reasonable and
i do really like the fact that the frame
rate uh already is massively better
uh just from that one change to two
layered to two layers of light probes
instead of like you know the full depth
of them
so again making a lot of improvements
just by reducing from from 3d to 2d in
terms of world construction without
actually giving up the 3d nature of
what's happening on the screen as
apparent to the player in really much of
any way at all so i do think it's the
right call bang for the buck wise uh for
what we've got
okay uh so given that
uh
we have a bunch of things we want to do
and
uh
unfortunately i guess i'm not sure
exactly where
to start because we want to kind of go
through these systems one at a time
and kind of clean them up and button
them up a little bit right
and so we want to start removing
some of this complexity and
you know there's so much complexity to
pull out now
uh that i'm not really sure
where would be the most profitable place
uh to start
i think i'm fairly comfortable with the
decision because just looking at how
much performance benefit we got back
from just eliminating z layer
uh it's kind of crazy
if you think about how much of a savings
we're going to get in terms of code
complexity
uh if you even just look at the lighting
code we got that performance benefit
without actually optimizing with that
knowledge because one of the things that
you have to remember is we actually have
complete
light stepping tables
that include stepping in z so like the
compute walk table here
produces uh
values that include the possibility of
z-stepping
even though now there is no z-stepping
meaning we can just bend things in one
bin and z everywhere
and remove one entire type of voxel step
from the entire system right
so there's just a tremendous amount of
benefit we can get here
and
i'm just not sure
there's so many places we can improve by
making this simplifying change that it's
just kind of scary
uh because you know gosh where to start
and what's the right order to do it in
right
so i really just don't know um
and my guess would actually be
hmm
what would my guess be
my guess would be maybe we just
maybe we just say something like
we
now can just do straight yeah
if we're just regressing to a 2d
grid because now we know that we just
have a flat 2d grid and we can just do
all of our
computations on the 2d grid
we could
also
just say that from now on we don't
actually have to store a spatial
partition at all
our 2d grid is just stores what's the
height
of the occluder in that grid
right
i mean
the the amount of computational
complexity we could reduce there seems
pretty vast
because we could just say like look
we're locking down to the 2d grid now
and that's just how it's going to go
and then all of the like then all of our
raycasting could just be directly on the
2d grid and doesn't have to actually do
a pass where it even spatially
partitions anything anyway
because it doesn't need to anymore right
it knows it's just going to do grid
stepping
and the grid could just be unpacked
directly right
um
so it's really hard i mean man just
thinking this through
it's really hard to say
uh
the the amount of simplification we
could do there is so so vast
that
you know like i said that there's so
many potential options for us it's hard
to decide uh which one to pursue first
because they all seem good um
they all seem good
and
so
[Music]
i'm just a little bit paralyzed by too
many this is this is a good problem to
have i guess
uh too many good options at once means
it's hard to decide where to start and
starting on
picking a good order will pay dividends
because it will be less work overall if
you do it
in you know sort of a
good order
to begin with
okay
i guess first things first
i would like to find out why we have a
regular pattern of errant
sample drawing uh like what's going on
with these
uh
sample spheres why
are we getting this
odd like
you know
why why is there this fake sort of
occlusion
happening here where
you know you can kind of see that for
whatever reason the
there was no light hitting these samples
even though they're clearly pointing in
a direction where they should have hit
something
i mean
remember we're using indirect lighting
here so
that means not only did they
not hit a light source they didn't hit
anything which even supposedly has any
light at all like like they didn't hit
the floor somehow
so that suggests to me that they are
somehow being maybe erroneously marked
as being inside like some kind of a
volume
so that they can't cast like like maybe
they're just having some kind of a uh
they're hitting some kind of in
i'm not sure what the word is
we have tests in here to say if you are
inside a volume or something don't cast
right there's basically a thing that
tries to prevent you from wasting time
casting out of a light probe that's like
inside something and the example would
be like you know this one in here uh you
can you know there there'd be a light
probe you can't see that's in here
i think we like detect that you're
inside a volume and then don't cast
light or something like that
and so uh it could be something like
that and and i suppose it wouldn't be
that hard for us to test because
inside full cast uh i believe
the
this
um
is inside here
is basically the code for that
so
you know
uh i think we could just say well if we
just said if zero
um and prevented that code from running
um that would
all right so that that basically tells
us
that that is what that that that's what
that was
uh apparently that that inside outside
check
uh was was totally
totally wrong right
so i think there's some kind of bug
going on here with the spatial partition
like because of the shift in cell
alignment or something like we're not
properly
we're not doing this correct somehow
uh like we're we're doing a check
because because the way this code works
is it just loops through here
uh looking at the leaves so of the
spatial partition
looking at the leaves of the spatial
partition and asking the question
do any of the things in the spatial
partition in this box uh enclose us
right that's what's happening
uh here
and if any of them do enclose us then we
just don't cast so it thinks that some
things in the spatial partition are in
closing which means that our spatial
partition is currently broken slightly
so something that we did with those z
changes
is causing our ability to do our spatial
partition
uh
the code that tries to do
the geometry for that spatial partition
is now like wrong
in some way
because there's no way that this should
be
that should just not be happening right
now in terms of being able to draw the
spatial partition i don't know what
we've got for that we probably did some
of that at some point right
because
we would have needed to debug what that
looked like over time
uh you know during grid
grid build spatial partition right like
we would need to debug this code
and
[Music]
um
but i don't really see anywhere where we
were drawing
the spatial partition that we could
re-enable right
so
uh
that brings me to the first decision
that we'd have to make here
which is
do we
just say well the heck with it
we know we can simplify the way that
these spatial things are working anyway
do we just say we're not going to bother
debugging that code we're just going to
vaporize it
and
replace it with
a more straightforward
cell walk
right
and that seems like the right thing to
do
because i don't know why we would bother
simplifying this code i'm sorry uh
debugging this code only then to replace
it with new code which we would then
have to debug as well so it would kind
of seem to me like the best policy would
be to just simplify the code first and
then debug the simplified code because
if we're going to have to debug it
either way
it
would seem
right
uh
like that would be the smart call
um
[Music]
so i guess we're just gonna do that
that's that's my call it might be a bad
call um
because sometimes it's a bad idea if you
don't have the current state of the code
working to switch to a new state but i'm
just thinking like well uh i'm gonna
have to debug both of these either way
so
yeah right
so if we take a look at grid build
spatial partition here there's two steps
of simplification we can make i'm gonna
say we should make uh the removing z1
first
and then the next one we can make is
just having it so the spatial partition
actually isn't a spatial partition so
much as it's just a grid
that records like effectively like the
space that
array can pass through or something
similar
so if we just assume that the spatial
partition no longer has a z coordinate
at all
uh you know what's that going to look
like i guess would be the first question
so if we were to say that the spatial
partition
as we see it here
and you can actually see it you can see
a grid leaf right
you've got a box min you've got a box
max
and then you've got like color and
emission and so on
um
if we are to simplify this down you can
we can still keep all of the
all the 3dness of those so that we can
have like partial occluders
uh in grid cells we can keep all that
uh and the main difference here would be
that the
the spatial grid itself
would just lose its z stack
right so like the
the indexing into this thing
would lose the z part of the index
you know what i mean
um
so as we're like stepping through here
you can see like it
has this sort of grid index
uh that's going on here and this step
just uses stepping from the table
so it just uses this this d grid right
so in the compute walk table function
you can see here where it loops over uh
you know it loops over the directions
that you might be going z
positive and negative y positive
negative x positive and negative
um
and then it it goes in and looks at what
the you know the table entries are for
that thing you know what i'm saying
so if we were just to take z stepping
out of the equation
um
i like our little debug checks here
uh if we were to take z stepping out of
the equation we would basically removing
these parts of the z for loop here
and you can see we've got this flat
index from function
which packs things down based on their z
index
so you can see like the index z is is
right here that would just always now be
zero
right um
and the grid cell count in the voxel
grid its z value would also always be
zero
right uh i'm sorry uh one right
so i guess let's just try to make this
change
so
so when we
yeah um when we in in the lighting here
uh this is gonna be it's gonna be a bit
of a nail biter but when we in the in
the lighting here go to set up the
spatial grid
um
you can see the spatial cell count
uh is the value that we're actually
asking for you can see
uh
this this happening here the atlas cell
count
which is
determined by
uh whatever the vox dimension which is
two right
um
this is
all well you know it would just produce
one by default in z
actually
uh
so that will do the right thing i think
let's take a look
but
to start with
we don't even have to clamp that value
down because i think it will always
produce one anyway if it's half the
resolution of the
spelling so although this part here
atlas to spatial grid index offset uh
that part
would would not
right
that part would not so let's let's yeah
let's
let's take a careful look at this
i'm going to go into the lighting code
here and set a breakpoint
and
there we go
is that only set once yeah
just wanted to make sure that it's only
set once which is what i said before but
i was like well let's be sure that this
only gets set once
so here's the voxel cell dimension
um which is just the fundamental unit in
all directions here's the spatial cell
count
which
is 14 by 10 by three
so this three here we really just want
to set to one right we want to kind of
get rid of that
so
uh i'm not sure to what extent
that
you know this this part has to make sure
that it would encompass all of the
geometry right so the spatial cell count
two times voxel cell dim
you can see the spatial grid is like
is
based off of
how the atlas is set up it's it's twice
as wide right like so
for every there's a there we've been
at basically a rate of
two grid squares like you know four
tiles two by two
and
so this hat would have to encompass all
of the z
uh direction right so when we do the
atlas grid here this spatial grid would
have to be its z would have to be set a
little bit differently because we want
it to encompass the whole thing
right we don't really want it to remove
anything
uh whatever we push down here it should
take right
and then the z value should be one
and
again that came from because atlas cell
count should be set to two here so when
this divide by two it will just be one
so it's really this atlas to spatial
grid index
that part right there
that offset is really the problem so
the atlas to spatial grid
offset
this
um
i don't really know
what that's even really designed to do
anymore right like
i think the basic idea there
is that you want
the
spatial grid to include one tile
outside
of
wherever you're casting
right
um
so i imagine
but don't know
uh i imagine that like that becomes a
zero so that we
it's always just one
in in that direction and then the
spatial grids alignment which i think we
really we're going to want to have we're
going to want to draw right
uh
the dimensions of this are going to have
to be set carefully to make sure they
include everything
you know what i mean
so i assume that there's something that
would go on here
the
you know that would well let's draw it
first and then make sure that we're
keeping it
in some kind of a saying
uh
some kind of a sane
location
so solution spatial grid
total bounds
and i'm going to draw that
maybe that gets drawn in green
um
and we'll just see
we will see
all right
um
so
i think that makes sense to me like it's
designed to have an apron and i think
that's good so really the only thing we
need to do is make sure that the
z-bounds span the correct sort of
distance which they don't currently
right
so if we look at how
the z-bounds are set up we want in here
where we do this dimension
we want to
include
uh
enough height so that it encompasses the
cell dimension like of z right
we need to encompass three layers of z
because we're not adding those in
so
we actually want something like this
which is like spatial
dim spatial cell dim
we want to take
what we would normally use as the
dimension
and we want to
uh
we want to
make sure that it's like three stacks
you know what i'm saying
it wants to be three three high so oops
that's a regular v3
not a v3s
so we want that spatial partition to be
three high uh and if we look at what it
looks like now
um hopefully it's more aligned
although okay no it's not it backed it
down from there all right so the
alignment code does something weird with
the z there uh
that i don't quite understand so let's
take a look at why it decided to do that
because i'm not sure
why it would align it in that way
um that's that's a bit weird
but we're looking at this code here
and
you know here's how the spatial corner
works it takes the min corner and it
it moves one cell dim off okay so i see
why
right
um
if it's going to move one cell dim off
then it's going to include that huge
uh that huge amount so we we don't
actually get the benefit that we wanted
there right
so we need to do something here where
we're going to move one cell dim off
in
but only a third of a cell dim off in
the other direction right so
um
again i'm not sure
how exactly we want to do this but it
would look something like this
right so we just effectively be saying
well look the z is handled differently
than the other two axes because it it
just is the whole thing
uh there's no tile apron
it's just the whole thing right
so
that is now an aligned spatial partition
that is now in the correct place
right
so uh
all right you know that's a start it's
not perfect but you know it's a start
if we take a look at the
[Music]
walk code now we need to remove the
concept that you can really move in z
um
so when we are looking at a
a sample
um
we need to just yeah like
the thing that i'm just not sure about
is whether we want to keep the notion of
the spatial grid and the atlas grid
separate anymore anyway or should they
just both
so they just be completely collapsed now
uh and and i really just don't know
but
um i realized i think i understand
basically why we're having the problem
too with the spatial grid versus atlas
grid offset
because i think i said something wrong
here so that's not these are not
directions these are the offsets
of the um
these are the offsets of the probe point
inside the spatial grid
that's what those actually are
uh and so
you know it's it's how you would walk
the spatial grid based on where you are
inside it
so there you go so z in this case
doesn't exist because you can't step in
z
so
we want to pull that out
um
as the next step when we walk through
here and we look at the remainder there
is never going to be a remainder in z
it simply isn't allowed you can only
step in x and y
uh
that's just how that works right
when we do
uh get octant four
um
it's going to have to
understand
that we are doing that so i'm not sure
hm
that one's a little confusing
um
i'm not sure exactly what that does
let's take a look
so
so really the octan index is just
something we use for packing the answers
in here right
and now octan index would just become
quadrant index
it's just a way to load the table
right
so
so really
that's all
that is the
this would be instead of get octant four
you know it's gonna be get quadrant four
and we pass the remainder in here we
would assert that the remainder z equals
zero because you're never allowed to
have anything else and we'd never shift
that one up so now whereas before
there could be eight answers coming out
of this there's only four
possible answers now
so
the quadrant index
uh
is how we would pack these in
when we go ahead and do our
testing for sample directions here we're
also going to have the problem that we
go through the directional indexes to
see which one is greater and all that
other nonsense
uh we don't want to do that anymore
either so like the dimension index here
is just going to be two
uh we're you know we're not gonna ever
uh
contemplate the z value
uh at all
and
so then i would assume
i'm not sure what do we do with envy ray
d here let's take a look
yeah you can see like we're
we're just computing those two values
so really if we just change the
dimension index here
to two so we never check the other ones
um
we never really need to check this
equals uh
that's just never gonna happen
because we know that it you know
wouldn't matter
so
that's basically saying if 0 and 2
are both the same
then it uses two and picks best m2 we
know that's never allowed anymore
because the best dim can never be two
um so we are pretty much always going to
do this
uh
always
and we're only really comparing between
the
x and y now
right
so we don't even really need to do like
this t best
at all we can just look at the
difference between
zero and the the zero index and the one
index so we could simplify this down
quite a bit we don't care about doing
that here obviously
uh but you know
so i feel like all this is fine
uh the only thing i would be a little
bit worried about here is that the ray
direction
when we do this divide
uh
we
wouldn't have really
conditioned it but that's okay it looks
like
so i think this is okay
uh
more or less right uh we want to make
sure we never take that step
so when we get down here i would just
assert
uh that best dim is not equal to two
uh like you know i could be even harder
and say
uh
that it has to be one or zero can't be
anything else
because it's only going to step in one
direction or the other
and then
the quadrant index is
you know
going to get followed through here so
there's our quadrant
index i'm just going to look and remove
octan index everywhere
so this is quadrant index
and
yeah this is just the
lookup into the walk table based on on
the quadrant index
so i believe that should be a fairly
straightforward change
but i don't actually know so let's take
a look
it looks like we did still have some
people uh passing
[Music]
a
remainder z call here
uh
so
that actually
makes sense though because we didn't
neuter this calls
uh
z test right
so
[Music]
when we are calling
when we are calling this code
uh to get us the quadrant index that
actually does make
a fair bit of sense there
uh
because we need to remove the z
from
uh our request and get caught quadrant
four because we're passing
one here right so the remainder value
is producing an
accurate estimate of where we are in z
and we don't want to do that right
uh that's actually correct
like that assertion was telling us
something valid right
okay
um
so i think that should be computing the
quadrant table properly
uh but i also don't know where we
allocate those tables
um
if it actually
needs to be doing uh
like
where we are when we're doing this max
desk count here
um
the max cost per ray
is
so you know what it's already factored
in so we're already not going to push
more space on because we have the y and
the x are now the only two things that
we iterate over to produce the table so
it won't ever allocate ones for z
so this stepping is now i think
computed correctly in that sense right
like it it's now
that's now okay like i think that's
actually fine
so
when we go to do grid build spatial
partition here
this part we have to take a look at as
well because the
i i hope now that all of the things are
still getting inserted in this page but
i guess we don't actually know
uh whether that's true or not
so
hard to say uh but
i think
we are now properly walking through
uh
only 2d and we're properly aligning
um if that green box is correct
uh the spatial partition so i think
i think
we're probably okay
that said
the initial lookup
in to where we would be in the spatial
prediction is probably
well i don't know it might be wrong
this code right here where we do initial
grid index and we get a flat index from
the half atlas index plus the spatial
grid index offset because that atlas to
spatial grid index offset now has a zero
z value in theory we should always be
addressing with a zero z value
into
um
the spatial partition but i would like
to take a quick moment to see
if i'm right about that
um
because again like it's important that
we never
now ever use
uh
z in that way
so if we look at the atlas to spatial
uh you can see the z value is zero there
the half atlas index
is all zero so the z value that we would
be looking at would also be zero so is
that true like most of the time
hopefully
i'm just taking a look at what this
half atlas index z value is
right
um
but it looks
like there you know it's always pegged
to zero
for all intents and purposes right
all right um
so
i guess now that we're probably only
stepping in two dimensions
uh now would probably be a good time to
debug
some of the lighting stuff that we are
seeing
so uh let's try to do
um
[Music]
let's try to do an inspection of the
spatial partition
somehow
uh
maybe we just insert some new code to
draw it since it doesn't look like we
really had much code to draw it
so maybe we
uh the octahedral
um
because we're in a failure state right
now where there's no lighting being
generated so i should be able to safely
turn off the directional drawing
because we don't need to know that like
we can see that the lighting is being
computed incorrectly just by the fact
that there's no lighting
so i can turn off the probe directions
uh in the octahedral the debug draw
octahedral values
so we'll start there
and we'll say yeah don't
you know uh don't draw those directional
uh values the debug draw color this this
thing um let's just not we just aren't
gonna do that
so now we'll we'll only be drawing
um
just the boxes because i would like to
see where they are right so i would like
that
maybe because there's less i can also
draw the actual atlas
because it's not drawing the little
lines anymore
uh so now we can see like that's the
complete set of light probe locations
so that's good
uh i will turn off the colliders for now
because we don't really need them
they're just adding visual noise
uh because we know that they are roughly
exactly where the things we see on the
screen are and they just extend up
higher if they are walls
that's about
it right
um so you know here's here's just the
the general thing we're looking at
and now let's try if we can to
draw the spatial partition in some way
so if i go ahead and do
something like
debug draw
spatial grid or something like that
uh we wouldn't be taking any atlases
because these are just this is its own
like david s pumpkins it's its own thing
uh so we should be able to go ahead and
take
the spatial grid
and
step over
the actual
voxel
so we know we're gonna have you know
just x and y here for the
the spatial grid right we're basically
going to have something that looks like
this
and the
voxel grid itself i can kind of pull out
as spatial grid
like so and
we can loop over the actual
uh
dimensions of the spatial grid
uh here so we've got the cell count
x and y uh and we can also assert
that the spatial grid cell count z
equals one
right
now in here i mean the first thing we
can do is just see what the actual grid
locations are
uh because we should be able to do that
by just calling get cell bounds
right
so if i want to i can say like look just
where is this thing like like where is
the spatial
grid of this thing we'll start there
so if i said get cell bounds and i said
uh it's you know x y zero
what would be
what would you claim that that looks
like right and i and i'm gonna have to
put a color in here
uh so since we're using green it's it's
maybe it's it's green
for now
and if i call this
uh right after the octahedral values i
should be able to yeah figure out
what that looks like
um
little
parentheses nonsense there
so push debug box gets cell bounds
and
then the color value is a v3 not to be
oops a v3 not a v3s
what is debug pushbox complaining about
uh solution
get cell bounds that's a rectangle three
which is what we want oh it's a v4 i'm
sorry takes alpha as well oh isn't that
fancy
okay
um
recalling the code now
we should see the actual voxel
right uh which in this case is is you
know just tall
thin boxes uh that's exactly
what i would expect there should be no
vertical dividers
right because there's only one
layer so there's our you know
our voxel
now i'm gonna do
a little bit of like a color variation
here
um now because i don't care about
well actually you know what though let
me ask one quick question
were there four
well eight i guess
light
uh
locations here
it does look like it
so i do think it's correct in that there
are eight per cell which i think is the
correct number right
so
so that looks like it aligns
the way i would expect
that that looks fine
um
[Music]
i think that's fine
right
i think that's okay
uh but you know we'll we'll look a
little
closer later all right
um so i'm gonna
why is the
why is the compilation there we go
um
i'm gonna do one
other thing here with the coloring just
so we can see it a little bit better i'm
going to
maybe like alternate between two
different colors so so like maybe
we do something like
uh
i don't know x
this is just
who knows
right
um
something like this nonsense so i'm just
gonna make like some kind of a
way of making neighboring cells use like
a different color
you know what i mean
uh so maybe like some cells are
uh
yellow in some cells or magenta or some
cells cyan i don't know something like
that
maybe cyan and magenta let's let's do
cyan magenta
um so that we can sort of
alternate between
them in some way that you know allows us
to
see the different cells more clear
cleanly
now the problem is they're going to kind
of overwrite each other because they
abut
um but you can kind of see you know
that there's like now there's like a
checkerboard pattern
you know right
um
of these things and so if i shrink them
slightly
so let's say we do a
bounce here where we say
shrink this
ever so slightly
so
um
you know
just just a little bit
so that i can see these uh just so i can
make sure that my checkerboard is
correct um
what is the complaint
that's the complaint
probably safe to start using auto now
these days right can we do this now
yeah
so you know we could start using auto
sometime on handmade hero if we wanted
to i don't know if we want to it's
really not that necessary but you know
saves you a little time
all right
um so in theory
now if we look uh we should be able to
see sort of a checkerboard pattern there
right and you can kind of see it
uh there's like a checkerboard pattern
of magenta and cyan
and
you know the only reason i'm doing that
is because if we get rid now of the uh
let me
when i said shrink i meant shrink for
some reason i instead of shrinking
i enlarged
oops
don't you hate it when you enlarge
instead of shrink
um with this one weird trick anyway uh
you can look and see
[Music]
the checkerboard pattern which i just
wanted now so that if i go draw
the things that are supposedly in these
spatial partitions
i would be able to see sort of like
which space partition they were in by
their color
at least a little bit
so let's go ahead and take a look at how
we pull things out of the spatial grid
now so if you look at the
um
lighting code here you can see that
we've got these like
nodes and leaves
um
you know i think the nodes literally
just say how many leaves there are right
um
that's it
uh
and i do think that like
you know in the future we can probably
get rid of that in direction entirely
because we know that the geometry is
relatively simple we could probably just
say
that there's four boxes or eight boxes
per cell and that's the end of it
and that would also simplify the code
quite a bit
um
so yeah
anyway
so if we look at this code uh
if we get out the spatial
node from i'm assuming that we can
simply make a call to get that right
where we can
ask for the flat index
uh and
grab out the
the node directly from there right so
you know this kind of thing
so in theory we should be able to say
like hey
uh get us whatever the flat index
uh is
for the particular node that we're
talking about
which in this case uh
we already have it's this
so if we want to do a flat index from
the node index here
in theory we just passed the spatial
grid
and it should just do it
right
um
so that should pull the node out
and
after we have the node we should be able
to do
just the simple leaf loop here
which gets us all of the leaves
and so then really all we have to do is
look at the leaf and and draw it right
so
if we look at one of these
one of these grid leaf structures
you can see we've got a boxman and a box
max we can just
pull out all four of them
and draw them one at a time
uh
i don't actually remember what we
defined our v3 so it's it just looks
like this right so we can literally just
like go through
all four of them like with a foreign
loop
right you can just say
um
hey
let's
let's loop over those in fact we could
even do this
loop over the
boxman
[Music]
maybe like this x
dot e
right so however many there are
uh that's how many we're going to loop
over
uh and then we can literally draw what
the boxes are supposedly in this thing
so
we would know
that the box is like you know
the bounds for this thing
are erect min max that's going to come
from slicing off of this you know
v3
uh this this sort of cmd wide
v3 value
i wish that the cats have definitely
decided that they don't love my
microphone
they're not fans of it
um so they keep knocking the cord down
which is always good
let's put that back up
uh so we just need to grab out the you
know the x y and the z of a particular
slice
which is pretty easy to do
um i don't we may actually have
extraction values extraction uh routines
for that
i don't actually remember but i'll take
a quick look because we may we may have
a way of you just grabbing out a slice
uh because it's something you want to do
when you're debugging yeah you can see
it right here so
we can just
use get component to do it
and that should be pretty
straightforward so
um
we want to take the boxman
and the box max
and again we're just slicing this array
to
grab out the cmd portion you know into
it into a scalar portion to use debug
routines on it that's it
i
i guess i'll do
box bounds here just to disambiguate it
so that it doesn't use the same value as
this this is the cell bounds so we'll
call it cell bounds
and box bounds so that we're clear on
which bounds are which
and now i just want to look and see like
what are we looking at like
what's in the spatial partition right
and so
uh i'm gonna start by turning off the
cell boundaries
so that i just i'm only looking at at
leaves here
and then we're going to see we're going
to just debug the spatial building code
till we see
correct stuff
right
so right off the bat you can kind of see
the problem
uh
some debug system nonsense there
uh it looks like we're really not
putting anything in here
you know what i'm saying
so it looks like we're getting an early
failure uh when we're trying to build
the spatial partition
uh we've got some error probably with
our the way that we're handling our z
right
uh where we're thinking that nothing is
actually included in the
uh in the region
so
would assume
i would assume that this is a simple
case of again just not like treating
these values like because we we didn't
quite uh produce the values to be
completely correct here
so uh when we did the zeroing out the z
so if we take a look at the grid uh
build oops
grid build there it is
so we take a look at grid build spatial
partition here and we look at what we're
passing in
we start by talking about a thing called
a clipping region which starts with the
total bounds which is what we'd expect
we then reduce the total bounds by one
cell and there's your answer right there
so that would completely eliminate our z
uh
so
so we don't want to do that
right uh
so
we want to do a clip shrink here
uh that looks like that and
we want to get rid of the z
so this way we're keeping the full range
uh that obviously was a huge issue so
that's you know we had to fix that but
we're probably not quite done yet
um so for starters we need to prevent
that shrinking of the clipping volume
and uh looks like somehow that didn't
change anything which is odd but oh well
um and then when we go through here
and we walk through all the boxes that
are in the lighting solution
you can
uh see us sort of looking at we
we're getting indexes for those mins and
maxes
um in the spatial grid right and then
we're looping over them
uh and figuring out like where they will
reside
so
that looks fine like i will have to step
through it and see if i may be missing
something but that looks fine
uh
then we go through here we do clipping
uh to the clipping region
which which should should not really be
a problem
um
this should all just be zero let me
assert that z equals zero here
um
because
like
we never really want
anything else
uh but yeah
the cell bounds that come out of this we
viewed those and they were right so that
should be okay
um
so so yeah i'm not
i'm not really seeing
what's screwed up about this routine but
obviously something pretty basic is
um
[Music]
so
ah
uh
this is our problem
right
so
[Music]
so we set the apron on z and we never
want that right
so the apron
for terminating the grid walk
must
we never ever want that to
count z as part of the apron so
i don't know if that really has much to
do with it here but that was certainly a
problem so that would have cleared out
anything in the spatial partition
at that point
so
uh
let's take a quick look here we got a
um we're pushing a few too many things
down uh so let's let's take a quick look
um at
turning this off we need more
we need better debug diagramming sport i
think we added reasonable new ones but
this lighting system uses its own which
is kind of stupid uh unifying those
would would be nice right
all right so here's our
you know supposed
here's our supposed
um
you know
spatial elements
for lack of a better term
and i'll be honest they don't
look convincing
to me
um
there's a lot of
kind of gunk in there and i'm not sure i
totally understand
why
you know what i'm saying to you
so
what's what's going on
amusingly the lighting now works again
so it was that term the fact that the it
was setting the entire grid to the
terminator the termination apron
um
because it happened to be on the edge in
z which was true we just don't ever
allow you to go off the edge and z
anymore so that's not an issue
um
there's something weird about
the
about these boxes right like like i
don't
i don't really understand what i'm
seeing
they're
really kind of incoherent
uh with respect like they're very sort
of like oddly aligned in in weird ways
so it feels a little off like like
either i'm drawing them wrong or
something
uh at the same time
they you know they do seem
accurately placed
like around like say the heroes
uh
there's the light i believe that is the
light that's hanging above the hero's
head
or something or the hero's collision
volume or whatever
um
it's not actually that inaccurate it's
following the hero correctly and stuff
so you know it's a little it's a little
confusing to me because it it doesn't
look that off
so i am having a little bit of a hard
time pricing what i'm seeing because
it's a little confusing
um but you know at the same time like
like what the heck is that
right
and amusingly
uh
those
boxes there which seem to coincide with
light sources like that's where the
light sources are as well
um
those
seem to be the places where we were
getting the weird
uh non-lit
uh probes as well
so i feel like there's just some basic
stupidity going on here
uh in a couple different ways
so we kind of need you know we can see
like that's a light
where where the lights are we get these
extra overlays
and
we probably need to fix that in fact
this may have been a bug that's been in
here for a while
the thing that says whether you're
inside something or not may have
incorrectly said don't be a don't probe
if you're inside a light
which is wrong
um
because lights are not supposed to be
occluders
you know what i'm saying
so
so that's a tough one uh
that's a tough one how we're supposed to
handle that i'm not sure
uh
maybe the way you handle that is like
so
when you hit
something you gather from the light
probe in that area right and
so the way that the actual
lighting function works where you
you do the casting right you do the grid
raycast this
thing um the transmission level
is
gathered from
a second
emission there we go
hit emission
so
you can see this like izzy mission
um
value here that allows light sources to
inject light
into the system
and so
really this like any true
this thing
really what should probably happen there
is we should have written out the
emission value if you're inside a light
source then your emission should be the
light source
value right
uh so that's confusing
so so i don't really know like
so really i think that's not uh it's not
appropriate like that doesn't make a lot
of sense you presumably want this thing
to properly set the emission value here
or something right like that's just kind
of it's obviously garbage so we probably
want that to be uh fixed right
all right so um
so that's busted
but that's not really the problem that
concerns me at the immediate moment
right
problem that concerns me at the
immediate moment is why this looks like
such a tangled mess um
i guess part of it is that there are
ceilings
right like
like there is a ceiling here
these things
um
so
there is that and then i don't know
about some of these side
uh
things here
[Music]
it's a little hard to say
um
what we're actually looking at
one thing i do think is really weird is
i don't understand why these lights are
so big
i guess one reason the lights are big is
to make them easier to hit
or something
but it's a bit odd right it is it is a
bit odd
uh but you know looking at it i don't
know it's it's at least we did figure
out what the primary bug was there i
think which is the fact that it was
setting the terminating apron
uh to the wrong thing so that's a start
but we're still a little bit
far from
from good here so let me take a quick
look let's uh
let's get rid of debug draw spatial grid
uh the call here and let's just look
again at what we're actually looking at
now in terms of you know
the look of the world
so it's like not fabulous but it's it's
like it's just off it's like you know
you can tell that's it's still a bit
buggy
but we've eliminated the really
egregious error right
um
and frame rate wise
were excellent uh if we look at our
frame rate here we're
totally
rocking 60 frames a second just fine now
um
and i think we could crank up the
lighting quite a bit now
so yeah i think we're okay
so really we're now looking more at
figuring out what's going on with the
light transport
the shift to off-center has clearly kind
of made it screwed up a bit and so
figuring out what's going on there i
think is our next goal
um
increasing the light shading rate
would be good too
and that's kind of a separate issue so
let's look at that light shading rate
issue uh so the light shading rate issue
is we would like this to look more like
say that
um
which is probably a bit aggressive so
you may probably won't be able to get it
that good but if you take a look at what
happens
um when we increase the shade uh the
response rate you can see how noisy how
much error there is because there's just
very little smoothing
going on
um and again that's just because it's a
stochastically sampled thing and we're
also not sampling it particularly
brilliantly like we don't necessarily
we're not horrible with our sampling
lighting but we're not great
um and so you can see it's better or
worse at certain times like you know
it's it's actually not that bad there
there's only a little bit of flicker
but in order to improve the quality of
this what we want to do is cast like
more rays
so that we can reduce the the degree of
lag so
if we go down to basically like um
if we're going at 60 frames a second
and we use a quarter right so it'd be
it'd be uh
it'd be four of those sixtieths of a
second right
um that would be a pretty reasonable
response rate and we'd only have to
cast uh about
you know i don't know what the threshold
would be here so
maybe seven times more raise maybe
four times more rays let's suppose let's
look at 4
over 60 here or 5 over 60. how bad is 5
over 60 i don't really know
um
so response rate wise
so the quality of 5 over 60 isn't
perfect but it's pretty good
so i would kind of say like at 5 over 60
i think we'd be okay um
quality wise so that's four times as
many arrays which i think we can do
like i think that's plausible right
what is going on here by the way why is
our apron code
like somehow
missing
uh
we changed the z and like our apron code
doesn't generate an apron on the right
border
on the positive border side for some
reason right
more more stuff as we go simplify we'll
have to like
you know
make that work a lot better
uh anyways so
yeah
i wonder if that's a good place to call
it for today uh
but yeah looking at the at the
difference here you know
a difference between
of casting maybe four times as many rays
isn't like that bad right uh and and if
we cast four many four times as many
rays we would have that quality
while still being um as responsive as a
20 over 60 which is pretty responsive
like that's pretty fast right so we'd
have reasonable quality at fairly high
responsive that's that's pretty darn
close i don't think anyone would notice
like uh
would notice that as being laggy
um so i think we can get to roughly this
speed uh
which would be great and that's
because and and we might even be able to
do better than that because like because
things will be much simpler now we can
optimize that rate casting routine more
than we did before
uh because we might be able to do things
to like you know we might be able to
make some clever optimizations now
knowing that z is is off the table which
we previously couldn't really do
so yeah uh so i think that's all right
uh but again
gonna have to do uh some work to get
there so one of the ways that this thing
currently works
if you look at how the grid raycast goes
so here's the grid raycaster right
the way this works is it takes a ray
origin
and it does a cast of that ray through
the environment using
you know it's it's a wide cast in the
sense that it it compares against
multiple things in the environment
the rays themselves are not wide it
casts a single ray
uh for the for this walk right
um
and then when it's done
doing the walk
it does the sample
to pull out of the voxel right
what the lighting is there
uh and then it writes that into the
spectacle
at that location
right
now to be honest i don't really remember
why this is as wide as it is
so if you look at what it's doing here
uh it's blending
with
it's blending with five times four oh
sorry six times four so 24
uh 24 floats
which is all eight
uh
octahedral locations
but i don't
quite know why that would be happening
uh
i see
so in a single step of this routine we
actually do
eight raycasts one out of each
direction
of the octahedral so then now i do okay
so we just write we cast eight rays at
a time not wide just we do a loop over
eight rays and then we blend them back
in one step which makes good sense
um
i mean sure
so that all seems fine um
and it seems to me like we could run the
grid raycast more times
so you would think that that would mean
that basically like this routine
we could just run it multiple times
right
so
and and to be honest uh
probably you'd get more efficiency by
welding that into grid raycast where
grid raycast itself actually did it
because then you wouldn't
do
the load modify right
multiple times for no reason
so it'd be more efficient if grid
raycast could have built into it the
idea that the sample direction
could be updated inside that loop so it
would just do that loop like a few times
right
um
so i do think this is a little
inefficient
if we updated it the way that i'm
suggesting
i
but that said so if we look here at the
way that the
light sampling is going you can see here
that's like entropy index
uh and it's you know
it's got sort of a
it's got sort of a way of looping
through
to pull out which directions the rays
are getting sampled in right
and
presumably we base that off of uh
[Music]
you know
presumably we base that off of some kind
of what is entropy frame count used for
by the way
absolutely nothing
all right
um
so like the sample point entropy and the
light point entropy
are the two things that are updated i
believe let's take a look
light point entropy
is this ever used
so light point entropy is not used
because uh we don't sample light sources
specifically anymore
right
um
all right
so
really it's just sample point entropy
that gets
sort of walked randomly as it goes
uh and the entropy index here
gets added every time after the full
cast gets called
i mean
these are all precomputed lookups into a
table anyway so i'm not quite sure
[Music]
that this makes a ton of sense how we're
doing this here
like
do we actually care
about entropy
in that way
i i can't imagine we actually do
um
like i would be surprised if we saw a
huge difference
uh in in the way that stuff works right
it seems
unlikely
so i don't really know about that i also
think that the way that this is set up
here doesn't make a whole lot of sense
either also this doesn't need a loop
over z because z can't ever be anything
anyway so it's only ever going to be a
loop
over x
because the atlas
uh can only do two well that's not true
i guess we have to do two layers of it
so that's not entirely true
um
so i would say this entropy index value
probably doesn't want to be updated here
that seems unlikely probably what wants
to happen is something like this
so inside full cast it can update the
entropy based on how many times it does
this so maybe this is a you know a
pointer
um
and so in here it would be more like
okay
you know uh star entropy index
uh
and
that's how the entropy index comes out
of this thing
uh
and then we do an entropy index plus
plus in here or something right
um i don't think this is great like i
think we'll probably want to change this
thing but i'm just kind of see what
happens if we hack this in
so uh that should be the same now as it
was yeah
um but we should now in theory be able
to like
loop this
so in other words if we want to
uh
in this piece of code here we should be
able to do something like
uh
do multiple samples so you know there's
like a sample batch and we just say all
right there's going to be like eight
sample batches run every frame
or something like this which should
which will slow things down a lot
but i just want to see if it works
yeah
um
so
oddly enough the smoothing is not as
much as it should be really there so i
think this is still a little bit
busted
so i'm just gonna play with this value
and see what happens
yeah so i think i'm like thinking of
this wrong or something because that
weirdly doesn't seem to change what's
happening and weirder still like it it
doesn't have as much of an effect on the
frame rate as it should i guess it kind
of does i mean that's significantly more
than it was but this is 16 times the
amount of raise so
that's a lot
so in theory
it should have been able to produce
sort of an equivalent
so i guess maybe part of the problem is
because the
it does it doesn't
it's just taking more samples
of the same world state it doesn't
diffuse
as many times as it should
meaning this
um
this atlas
like update doesn't run
so it could be that that
kind of has
a lot to do with it right like the
the casting the more raised doesn't
really help if those
casts aren't then fed back through the
system
maybe
i'm not really sure
uh
so that's a tough i don't know
that's very strange makes me think maybe
we've got some buggy
assumptions somewhere else maybe that's
making the lighting flicker more than it
should right
um
that's that's kind of my hunch there
right uh
so i don't know about that that's that's
a little yeah i'm hmm
because the lighting values that are
actually getting interpolated would in
theory be a lot more stable now however
it is true that if they don't write back
to the diffuse
texture then
maybe that lack of convecting the value
around does make a difference i don't
know
that's a tough one
that is a tough one
um
so
i guess i would say well
uh what happens if you run this thing
multiple times which would be much more
expensive so this will slow down the
frame rate like pretty viciously right
um
but i'm just curious to see if that is
what
would happen then
so if we did a
four
sample batch here
right
and we just ran this thing
multiple times then what happens
so something seems up because that
should then
spread the values out
multiple
times it should be the exact same
lighting as the one that we were doing
before
right
so
i guess well i do i have to change the
the blend rate though i mean maybe i
have to change the blend rate that's i
guess another question
right so the update rate maybe has to be
set down again to something small
right
so yeah i'm not really sure what to make
of that i think we probably want to just
go hunting for bugs i think we just
we're really seeing like other things
now but man the amount of performance we
get back is kind of sick because like
i'm just throwing in times 16 to the
left times 32 and the thing still runs
at like 30 frames a second
so yeah i guess i guess the answer
really is
don't throw out the lighting code
because it looks like we can rescue this
uh
it looks pretty good um so yeah i think
it just needs a little bit of meticulous
care here
uh to re-clean it up but you know
yeah i mean there's some weird stuff
going on that i think we can fix but
there's it updating basically like
locked like it's very
very
like almost no procedural no perceivable
lag
and it's perfectly smooth
so really there's just this weird like
there's some weird stuff happening where
that when the voxels shift
that like as we move so i think there's
just other bugs here so if we just go
actually take care of this
um
i think we're in good shape
uh i think we're gonna get our fully
dynamic global illumination
and just have our cake and eat it too
um so maybe i'll i'll stop for today
it's been about three and a half hours
that's a pretty long time to go without
a break
um
so i guess uh yeah i mean
i'm i am relatively optimistic about
that
like that just seems pretty promising so
i think we we might just be able to just
have this thing work and it's going to
be okay which is kind of nuts
um
but but i think that might be okay so i
think we just have to go through now and
be a little bit more meticulous about
removing z
you know what i'm saying
um
because it's pretty clear that our space
partition is messed up
and
because we were
we they the way that the lighting system
works is it's very uh specific as well
about
making sure
that it
aligns the
[Music]
atlases and the spatial grid together
and i don't actually know if that's like
currently
still working properly either with the
way that the walk table is computed you
know what i'm saying
like you can see here the starting
location uh
having
being based on some
[Music]
some
ideas about where stuff is in the world
relative like this starting location
bakes in knowledge of how the atlas
is centered relative to the spatial
uh
grid
you know
and
so
i'm not sure whether that stuff's
correct either i think it looks like it
roughly is because they did look like
they were aligned in exactly this way
and we now don't care about the z value
right
because the z value doesn't matter
so
so i do think we're roughly correct but
again you could see that there was just
you know there were definitely some bugs
in there so my assumption now is just
that like yeah i'm going to have to kind
of fine tooth comb it
but i think we can use this i think it's
actually pretty good
uh so
maybe we're just kind of done with
lighting it rather than having to
simplify it
what we have may just be good enough and
so let's just debug the 2d eyes version
of it and and then we can just have it
and that'll be nice
um because that just takes a huge thing
off the table for us
so that's pretty good uh that's pretty
good
uh i would say like
also 32 oops 166 is surely not going to
be good
uh 16
might be more aware what we can afford
uh i mean obviously we might get some
more optimizations out of this but
um in terms of like looking at what's
feasible to do uh at 16 frames uh 16
milliseconds of frame
this is closer to it so i think i would
be more comfortable saying this can hit
60 uh than 32 so i think we might try to
see like can we make sure the lighting
is stable at 16
um
and and go from there right
so we'll see
we'll see
all right uh maybe that's good enough
for today i and next time what we'll do
is we'll try to pick up where we left
off here
and take a look at
what can we reasonably do to
clean up the spatial partition
make sure we're actually intersecting
rays properly probably put the debug we
have debug code that draws ray
intersections look at those more
carefully make sure they look plausible
um
so we
can kind of get rid of obvious errors uh
in the system there
so
that's probably all we really need to do
um
yeah
so i think that's all good
i think that's all good
all right folks
so i think i'm gonna wrap it up i'm
gonna wrap that up for today
thanks everyone for for joining me
uh and we will do another stream soon
where we
take a look at
the
just debugging that spatial partition
and trying to get that walk
straightened out
so thanks everybody
and uh
soon before next sunday uh possibly yeah
i might i might stream more frequently
yeah
um so thanks everybody
and i will be back uh to take a look at
that code uh sometime soon take it easy
everybody