so here we go welcome to handmade hero
the only show that where we code a
complete game live on stream and you
know III is going on right now and and
you may wonder how come none of the big
press conferences like Sony and
Microsoft and Electronic Arts and
Nintendo how come none of them have
announced handmade hero for their
platform and the reason is because
they're just too intimidated by how
awesome our code is right now and
they're like we don't want this handmade
hero saw for a renderer stuff that they
did to be we don't want people to find
out about this because if they find out
about this they're just gonna look and
go oh my god like we didn't need an Xbox
one we could have done all this on an
Xbox 360 right or whatever and and they
don't want that they've you know so
they're trying to keep it under wraps as
much as possible but what can I say
we're still here and we're still doing
this optimization and we're still making
some pretty amazing stuff and you know
the eventually they're just gonna have
to recognize that and come to terms with
it but we'll let them do that on their
time because we don't want to push them
to accept something before they're ready
you know that's just that's just a
recipe for disaster so we'll just keep
going and then next year's e3 clearly
will be the year where you know pretty
much I mean I don't want to say
definitively but pretty much all three
platform vendors are gonna have to
announce a handmade hero for their
platform otherwise are they really gonna
be relevant at that point you know
probably not so anyway we'll keep an eye
on that as it unfolds but for the
meantime we do have some work to do here
before I jump into it let me simply say
that we are on day 137 so I'm packed day
136 of source code if you want to follow
along with where I am and where I am
today is we got our asset system working
pretty fancily actually and and we've
got quite a bit of things happening now
that are pretty cool but there was one
big missing
Keis in our asset system so far that we
had to take care of and you can see we
left it in there as a bug at the end of
last stream you can see it happening
right now
like when I'm moving down it's not
picking the right asset and we knew why
that was even the head of time I had
said that it would happen and it did the
reason is because we do not have
matching of values in our tag system on
periodic boundaries and so when you get
something like an angle that's periodic
it does not know how to match the
closest thing and we need to fix that so
why don't we spend a little bit of time
on the blackboard today just talking
about exactly what's going on here and
then how we can fix it right so let's
take a look here I'm gonna go ahead and
close that down so just get the
blackboard going so here we are in day
137 and so we want to do periodic tag
matching and I believe it was chocolate
Dino who suggested yesterday a very good
suggestion if I do say so myself which
is that in order to handle all tags
uniformly perhaps we could simply
introduce the concept that all tags were
periodic and the ones that we didn't
actually want to treat as periodic we
would simply give a large period and so
I think that's a pretty good idea so
first let me just explain exactly what
we're dealing with here and then I'm
gonna maybe work out a little bit here
how we might do exactly that which is to
have everything have a period but just
set it large so that it wouldn't affect
things that we didn't want to be
periodic and we'll see how that goes
okay so what's our problem our problem
here is that we are using a function
called atan2
right we used it yesterday and what
18-to does is it maps from a direction
vector right so it takes one of these
little XY vectors that we had in like
our velocity right and it can basically
turn that direction vector that we've
got into an angle right some angle that
says what direction something is facing
and that's a very useful thing for us to
have because it gives us a scalar that
we can use as a tag value
to match against so that we can just
dump sprites into our asset library at
any angle and they'll automatically get
picked out depending on what angle the
player is moving or anything else is
moving that we want to use this this
sort of technique for right but the
problem is as this spins around right as
this spins around its periodic meaning
if we were to rotate you know 360
degrees we would be back at where we
started we would not be at some other
angle and what that means is that we
need to make sure that when we do
matching we can't simply look at the
scalar value and say oh you know this
this scalar value is zero and this other
scalar value is 360 those are very far
apart so they probably don't match we
can't say that because actually these
are the same right and so we need some
way of determining that these things are
actually very proximal to each other
even though the numbers appear very
different and that is the periodic part
of it now what we know about eighteen
two is that the range of atan2 it
actually gives us back numbers that are
symmetric around zero so if this is
theta equals zero what ATM 2 actually
gives us back is not 360 degrees of
rotation but rather it gives us back
negative 180 and 180 so it gives us back
180 degrees of rotation this way and it
gives us back negative 180 degrees this
way and of course if you want to talk
about that in terms of radians it's pi
radians backwards or I'm sorry PI
radians counterclockwise and negative PI
radians clockwise from the the sort of
positive Y axis this way right so what
that means is we want to encode our
animation I'm sorry our asset matching
to be PI and negative PI but we want you
know we want them to be marked that way
so we'd have like something at 0
something at you know half PI something
at PI and something at negative half pi
but then we would want things that
negative PI for example to match against
the PI things and so on right so we want
that to work relatively well now this is
a pretty easy thing to talk about in
terms of how we might parameterize this
right you could easily see us encoding
this as saying okay this parameter has a
period of
pie right and what we could say by that
is it means it goes from negative pi to
positive pi that could be our encoding
so there are always symmetric about zero
and they go from negative to positive
some value and that value is the range
right so that'd be pretty easy and then
if we had some other values that we
didn't want to be periodic we could
simply say that they ranged from like
negative a hundred thousand you know to
positive a hundred thousand or some
really large number that we knew would
not interfere at all with the numbers
that we wanted to encode and as long as
that was at least twice as big as
whatever the biggest numbers we were
trying to encode where we would really
be in no danger of introducing any kind
of false matching so that's not a bad
idea the question is if we were to
actually do this encode encoding those
ranges is pretty easy how do we actually
do the matching and so if we have
something here you know and we've got
something here right like an angle a
that comes in or we have something here
that's an angle B that comes in and we
want to match it against something that
was set here as as being a value PI how
do we actually do it so that both a and
B are measured as relatively small
displacements off of pi instead of B
being measured as some very large
displacement off of pi going the entire
winding around the circle right what are
we going to do exactly to prevent that
from happening right and so what we want
to do is we need to come up with
something called a neighborhood operator
okay so we need basically a neighborhood
operator and when a neighborhood
operator is is the neighborhood operator
is something that takes two of the
values that you want to talk about in a
particular space and produces their
closest possible proximity right meaning
in our case we don't really necessarily
in in in some cases like for example
when you're working with quaternions
when you use neighborhood and
quaternions you actually care about
producing the actual value that is being
neighborhood in this case you could
almost say we don't really care about
that
we only really
need the result of sort of the
neighborhood operations to be
differenced and so if we were to say
that this neighborhood operator let's
say was n parentheses some angle rank
that we're passing in here and what we
wanted to have that do is sorry two
angles and what we wanted to have that
do is say that when it comes out we get
whichever one of these we wanted to
define as being the one neighborhood it
may be it's the first one we get out of
theta prime which is guaranteed to be as
close to fee as it could possibly be and
still mean the same thing right so in
other words if what we get put in there
was something that was wound all the way
around like this and we wanted to
neighbourhood it right so like or if we
just had a and B right what we would
want to get out for an a prime right
would actually be negative the negative
version of a right it would be the one
that winds all the way around and comes
back here so that a is as close to B as
possible rather than a being very far
away from B by being encoded as a
positive winding right so you see how
that would work if I said I want a
neighborhood a and B and I want you to
produce a new a that's in the
neighborhood of B what I would want to
do is take that a which is currently
positively wound and wind it negatively
even though that's larger negative value
than negative PI when subtracted it
produces the smallest distance between
the two right and so what I was saying
here is we don't actually need a
neighborhood operator technically
because we never actually care about
producing that a so really all we want
to do is sort of a neighborhood distance
if you will right so we want to do is
something which essentially says I want
to take the neighborhood operation right
I want to do the neighborhood operation
and then I just want to subtract
whatever the the the neighborhood is and
then take that as the result that's all
I really needed right and so I never
actually need to produce the
neighborhood an operator I only really
need to produce its distance and so that
could also actually make things
potentially a little simpler for us as
well
like I said sometimes you do need to do
neighborhood in this case I don't think
we actually do the time that you have to
do it is when you are doing
interpolation because then if you can
imagine us trying to interpolate and we
want it to go smoothly from B to a we
would need to actually produce that
negative a and know where it was so that
we can interpolate to it because simply
getting the distance between them is not
actually going to be useful right but in
this case we only care about that
distance so how do we do that
right how do we actually figure that out
and what I assume we would like to do
here is we could probably assume right
that for any value that's positive we
know that if we know that all the values
are in in the range of pi to negative pi
which which we can do what we can say
that everything has to be in the period
range right if we know that then when we
look at these guys we can simply say
okay positive and negative values are
always negative
neighborhood into other positive or
negative values right because if I have
any positive number there's no way to
pick up two positive numbers where the
negative version of that number would
actually have been closer right if I
have these two guys here or even like
this guy in this guy or whatever there's
never a case that moving this guy on to
the negative would actually make him
closer because the furthest apart they
could ever actually be right would be on
the poles on either side here I could
never actually get them any closer by
making a negative I'm only ever getting
them a little bit further away right so
what we really need to do here probably
is just test the signs right if the
signs of our numbers are different then
we know that they are not in the same
neighborhood potentially right and if
they're not so so we probably what I'm
assuming anyway what we want to do is
say okay first we could say we want to
see if the signs of the two numbers are
the same or different if they are
different then we're in a situation
where neighborhood inge may help if
they're the same then it wouldn't right
however
now that I think about it we may not
even really need to do that that's
actually absolutely a little premature
so let me just talk about what we will
do to them at that point and then I can
say probably we don't actually ever need
to do the check because we can just skip
it anyway so let's say that we did have
two numbers like here where we've got a
positive number and a negative number
and what we want to do is we want to say
okay we've got B and a and we want to
figure out how far apart they are we see
that their signs are different so what
what we want to do is change one of them
to be the opposite sign right so we want
B to become positive even though it was
negative and it's pretty easy for us to
do that right
this negative winding here right like so
is really just the positive distance
around the full positive range which is
pi plus however much that distance this
this extra amount is here right so if I
took negative pi or I should say rather
if I took be right which is this
position and I said I want to go from
this negative pi to be right so that'd
be plus pi right it would be minus minus
pi if that makes sense I'm gonna start
from negative pi and I'm gonna go to be
right so B minus minus pi which is plus
pi right so what I would get there if I
do that is a positive winding that's
this far right that's exactly that far
however far it would take to get from
here around right and what I want to do
then is say well in order to get there
in the first place I would have had to
have gone pi right in order to get to
the starting point so that would be plus
another PI right and so lo and behold
what that actually is right is just B
plus the full range right it's however
much the range is which is two pi right
so it's just B plus the range is what
maps B from a negative number into a
positive number right does that make
sense okay
so that's pretty easy the other question
is well okay let's say we had a number
that was positive so this is for a
negative right for a negative this is
what we would do we take B and we'd add
the range right now what would we do if
we want to do the opposite if we wanted
to take a positive number and move it
into the negative how would we do that
right well same thing right if we wanted
to make it negative what we do is we'd
say we'd start here we want to figure
out how much that is how much is that
well it's going to be going to a right
and it's going to be going to a from PI
right so it's minus PI right does that
make sense
starting at pi going to a but of course
to start at pi I'm sorry to start at
negative PI and go there I would need to
have subtracted PI to begin with so it's
another PI subtraction and hey guess
what it's a minus the range to do the
positive version right so we have our
positive version is this our negative
version is this and so really all we're
talking about here to do the
neighborhood operator is just to say
whatever the value is that comes in
right in terms of our of our
neighborhood and write whatever the
neighborhood and this is not really a
neighborhood operator I shouldn't say
because I mean I guess I'll write it out
the whole one just four four five right
so if we wanted to do neighborhood of
theta and Phi right then basically what
we have is we have a two pronged thing
we have in the case where theta is is is
less than zero right and also fee do
this way and fee is greater than zero
right so
traffic ahead oh you know I gotta admit
this is kind of strange this has nothing
to do with what we're talking about but
I realized I've totally forgotten how in
regular math notation you write and I
only ever think about things in C now
and like you don't write it that way
right you you write it different you
write like a different symbol right
there's other symbols or something for
it Wow sudonym 73 if you don't mind if
you're on the stream right now if you
could remind me at the end what it is
it's totally like it's falling out of my
brain completely I only think of and as
that and that's not a math and at all
all right anyway ignoring that sorry to
go down tangent there so we have
basically a case where they're separated
then we need to neighborhood otherwise
you know basically in any other case
it's it's this right we can just return
it so if they're the same sign it's fine
if they're different signs then really
all we have to do is say okay I just
need to know whatever theta is I'm going
to add the range of the of the thing
times whatever the sine of theta is
right because if the sine of theta well
actually I should say I'm going to
subtract the range times the sine of
theta right because if it was negative I
want to add the range it was positive I
want to subtract the range so really
this is the entirety of the neighborhood
that actually has to happen so what I
was saying before is we don't actually
have to produce this we only have to
produce the actual difference between
the two and since we only have to
produce the difference between the two
we can actually just do both of them
right what we can do instead is just say
all right what is this you know what's
what's the what's this distance right so
that's that's some that's different zero
right and then we can also do this one
here we can also say all right also give
me you know theta minus the range times
the sine of theta right
we can also do that - fee absolute value
and that's the other distance these are
the two Canada distances and then we can
just take whichever one of them is less
right so we basically don't ever
actually have to do any checking to see
which one it is we could just produce
them both and then take the the max
right are the min rather so we don't
actually need a branch if we don't want
one we could write one it doesn't really
matter one way or the other this is not
probably gigs possibly thatx that
expensive right but I just wanted to
point that out all right so anyway if we
wanted to add this periodicity to our
asset matching right then let's open
that up
here's handmade asset what we want to do
is we need some understanding of what
those periods actually are if that makes
sense and so what we can do is say in
that asset you know when we have our our
tags here we probably don't need a
period for every tag because really it's
just the tag type that determines it so
really all we need to do is have
something in here that's like tag period
right and the period or a like I guess
it's actually half tag period maybe it's
what we'd say or half tag range and that
half tag range is basically when we when
we go in to to the asset tags we have
those IDs we know that we can only have
tag count of them so we really just need
to store them once for every type of tag
that we might have and then we just set
it right and so what I'm gonna do since
most of the time I think we don't really
care about this it's only the periodic
ones which are going to be less frequent
than the non periodic ones what I can do
here is just say ok when we Nilla
initialize the game assets I can just go
through the tag types right like so and
for each tag type I'm just gonna say
that the half tag range a bat tag type
is always going to be some very large
number right
it doesn't really matter what it is just
something that we're never ever gonna
type in right that's just not gonna
happen
it's not it's not something that we'd
ever actually have right and so when I
set that then what I can do is just for
the few that I actually need periodicity
and we don't know what those are ahead
of time at the moment but we know we
have at least one so far so we'll set
that one we know for something like
facing direction we know that it's just
pi that's how far it goes in either
direction and so if we have that now
what we can do is we can use that but
whenever we do our tag matching to make
sure that now we actually match in a
reasonable way right so here's our best
match asset when we actually do our
difference here what we want to do now
is actually take that neighborhood a
difference so what we're gonna do is is
do something like this you know we can
have an a value right like so and a B
value like this and then the difference
is going to be a minus B but what we
would like to do now I don't think we
have a function for sine so I might just
do since we don't really care too much
in here see here Oh
sign up there it is so we could actually
use sign up you can see at the moment
it's not a particularly good
implementation it actually does the the
if here although I don't know the
compiler might be smart enough to fix
that and that's also an int we don't
have a sign up for things so I think I'm
just gonna do the simple if I'm just
gonna say if a basically well you know
I'd have to check checking the sign of
the two different things to see if there
I don't know maybe I will write it in
terms of sign now I think about it it
would be a little annoying
so I'm just gonna assume that someday
we'll implement a better version here
right and in there we go
so we now we've got a sign up there we
have it
so I'm gonna go ahead and say the sine
of a I'm gonna take that the assets I'm
gonna say the tag the half tag range of
whatever the tag type is like so so
whatever the tag type is the half tag
range of that we want to add the full
range so now that I think about it
actually we could just store tag range
because do we ever actually just because
it's plus and might yeah okay so maybe
we just want tag range we take that tag
range if you multiply it by the sine of
a right and then we're going to go ahead
and subtract from that right like so so
that would do our neighborhood for us
right that would pick the the OP the
other version so what we can do here is
do like I said a d0 and a d1 here is our
new a value and we can subtract B this
way like so and then I'll go ahead and
roll those absolute values up in here so
that we have them like so oops so that
will produce our two differences and
then what we can do now is we can just
use whichever of them is the least right
we can say minimum and then when we use
that that will give us a better match
right so now let me go let's change this
back to tag range like so on we go and
we could switch it to tau 32 which I
know that was the people we're excited
about that well okay one person was
exciting stellar seven was really
excited about tau so you know let's keep
it going let's keep the Tau rolling and
so there we go
so let's go ahead and and step into this
so we can see how that works
we want the asset group stuff I don't
know if that's loaded here game assets
of course it's not so let's go ahead and
open it up
handmade asset dot cpp here we are
handmade asset dot cpp let's take a look
at that match
we'll go ahead and step in here so what
are we matching against we're matching
zero and zero not particularly
interesting at the moment that's okay so
we take the difference between those two
guys and unsurprisingly that's going to
be zero and then this guy is also going
to well and so we can see it doing it
here it's producing the other possible
difference between the two values which
is a full towel and that's correct so
then we're going to take the minimum
over those two which should still be
zero and off we go
right and then we take the weight we
weighed it and compute the total DIF
that way so I think that's probably more
correct now in terms of tag matching and
so we should get a nice yeah and we do a
nice directional feel to our guy now and
so now we're loading the correct assets
periodically and we haven't actually
done anything which present prevents us
from using a periodic asset so that's
also good so that's really what we
needed to do today so we're kind of done
we've got a half hour though so then
what I'd like to start working on some
other stuff one thing that we have
that's leftover that we need to fix is
the fact that we currently are not
actually we didn't go ahead and do our
displacements there we still have those
displacements happening as you can see
the they're the shadows are in the wrong
place and so on
that's because we had those
displacements encoded in here like so
and we've never actually gone ahead and
backported those displacements so what
I'd like to do is I'd like to go ahead
and just see what that standard
displacement actually would be I think I
can just if it's the same
it looks like it's exactly the same for
everybody it's 72 182 for 4 basically
all of them what I'd like to do is just
take a quick look and see if there's any
reason I can't just use the same one for
everybody what I can probably do here is
something like this just for the time
being I think you can do something like
this I don't actually remember let's go
to debug load bitmap that actually takes
a line percentage
so top down a line okay so I wouldn't
quite be able to do it that way what I
would have to do is something like this
loaded bitmap temp array who knows what
that is or you know what I guess like
well me me alright let's do it this way
let's do file name like so so what I'm
going to do is I'm just gonna grab all
these files I'm gonna shove them in here
right like this pretty simple we could
we could we could even because we've got
time in the stream we could even go nuts
something like this something that was
absolutely ridiculous and I don't even
want to know what I just did there but
Emacs macro that up there we go so now
we've got all of these guys in a file
name array I can go through each of them
I can go ahead load them bitmap v map
equals debug load bitmap and then I will
take file name you know I ordered a 10
Quiles keyboard recently because I
really enjoy on out I fit the stupid
insert key all the time but the zero key
I'm really looking forward to that not
happening I never really want to be in
overwrite mode almost never
so yeah alright so anyway let's go ahead
and finish this up file name plus the
size so there's our fit maps that we're
loading and then I can do top down a
line of these guys just to see top down
line loaded bitmap and V to align align
X over this so that does the safe ratio
which is what we wanted so here's that
so that will produce that top-down a
line for us this is basically a no op
here so just give us something to break
on
so that should do it right let's see
oops top Cataline there we go alright so
now if I go ahead and take a look at
what those come out to be I can I can
see the thing that I actually wanted to
see of course no I can't because Visual
Studio is fighting me every step of the
way as it always does you cannot see
bitmap because it's undefined okay thank
you so much that's wonderful
I guess I will actually have to do
something here just to make the debugger
not be awful okay there we go now taking
a look at the bitmap here is the actual
line percentage it's a point five point
five wait what happened there shouldn't
this have said it I don't understand why
am I still looking at a point five point
five that doesn't seem right
does that seem right to you guys it
doesn't seem right to me I want to know
what happened there let's go ahead in
here alright so we've got those set
recalls top down a line oh it doesn't
work the way I thought it does oh did
the stream go down
it says reconnecting that was pretty
weird hmm
well I don't know what just happened but
I'm gonna keep on going don't know if
that was meteor 4 that was twitch twitch
is been acting really strange lately
let's ignore it and keep going anyway so
top down the line just do it this way
and now I can start getting those values
that which is what I wanted in the first
place okay so let's take a look at the
results and now this is looking a lot
better so it's point that's let's so
let's just save these guys we've
basically got a 0.5 and a 1 5 6 so let's
see if those are the same same the same
the same the same all right
so all of those are basically exactly
the same so that's all good nothing
weird going on there so that's all fine
so all I really need to do then I guess
I need to actually go back and grab
these guys so well I really need to do
then if I want these to be correct is I
just have to make a V 2 which is the
hero line and that hero line is what
we've read out which is 0.5 and and
0.156 etc right and so now that every
time we do an add bitmap asset we can
just specify that that alignment value
here like so and I think that's about it
I think that's all that we would need so
there we go
off you go and let's see if that does
any better for us yes there we go so now
everyone is aligned properly and that's
all good and so I think we are now at
the point where the asset system is
doing what we need
to do so yeah I'm pretty happy with that
I feel like and at least I don't I don't
really know at this point I feel like
we're probably at the point where we
want to go ahead and I mean I feel like
we're at the point where we want to
start talking about the asset file
format now right I mean maybe it's a
little premature I don't know but we
kind of now have a situation where we
could reasonably say that we have an
asset file format here's what it is
and here's how we want it to work right
and we could do that so I feel like
we're at the point where maybe it's
worth thinking about that I don't know
that's just my that's just my my gut
feeling because we now do all the mat
asset matching that we wanted to do like
I said before I don't actually know that
we want to ever have anything where we
use descriptors in the asset file format
I think we want that always to come from
the code side so it kind of feels to me
like that may be the end of it right
that kind of feels to me like that may
be it so let's see here
everything feels pretty smooth no issues
yeah so I think we're good I think we're
in good shape
so yeah so I'm trying to think now
handmade H so asset streaming is is
basically in there's a little bit more
we would want to do so let's just let's
just came for
kind of fixing for finishing this guy up
right and in order to do that I think we
want to do a file format right that we
load the assets off of disk and then we
have to do our memory management to make
sure that we don't have stuff sort of
willy-nilly and then I'm trying to think
if there's anything else we really want
from the asset streaming system or if we
can just check that off as being done I
can't really think of much else you know
if we have to optimize it later we have
to optimize it later but that's not
something we have to address right now
what we could do I suppose is before we
do the file form I actually know we
could do maybe we start on audio right
maybe audio is a good idea maybe we
bring that up here and we basically say
let's get these two guys done together
because if we don't have audio in the
asset loading stuff then that would be
yeah that would be a problem obviously
right so we've got about 20 minutes left
maybe we'll throw in audio loading so
that we know that that's actually
working and yeah and then we could go
ahead and and do the file format once we
know that it would support both audio
and video that seems pretty reasonable
to me all right so if we're gonna do
that
we already did part of what we need to
do for that right we have asset slots
for sounds what we don't have at the
moment and we also have tags for sounds
right what we don't have for at the
moment is actually any way to load a
sound right we don't even have
we don't even have anything like that
and so when we have something like load
bitmap work here we have and we have
load bitmap we we basically want to make
an exact copy of this conceptually but
instead of doing it with bitmaps it
would do it with audio so instead of
doing the work necessary to load a
bitmap out it would do the work
necessary to load a piece of audio out
right and so what we want here is
something that you know looks basically
like exactly the same you know something
like this where it does this but for but
for sounds right so here sounds here's
the ID value from them we set the asset
state of them and does exactly the same
thing we then begin a task for it you
know we get the task out but instead we
would we would do like a load sound work
here and then we would just fill out
exactly the same stuff only it would be
instead of a bitmap or something like
this it would be some something else
entirely right so yeah that is what we
would want to do and I feel like that's
really that would really be it right so
what we need to do is have a thing we've
got you know we've got loaded bitmap
let's take a look at the renderer there
here's a loaded bitmap we've got loaded
bitmap and what we really need to do I
suppose is make an equivalent for audio
right and so we would need something
like loaded bitmap for audio right we
would need something like loaded sound
you know and that would probably be
something that just told us what the
sample count was right like that and it
would be you know something which yeah
which was just like how many samples and
then the the memory for the samples
right something like this I feel like
that's all we'd really need because all
of our sound samples all of our sounds
would be in the same format presumably
so there really wouldn't be much else
that we would need to do
so yeah so I feel like that would be
basically it yeah I'm trying to think if
there's anything else I also think we
may be able to do some collapsing here
of stuff there's there's there's more
stuff we'll be able to do a little bit
later but for now I think would be
something like that and so yeah so as we
do this stuff we would want to to have
that work order be something like this
right
and this guy would just be you know yeah
yeah a loaded sound star like so and
looking at it there it's it's really
there really so close I feel like maybe
we will end up collapsing these I'm
gonna leave them two separate things at
the moment but I feel like they're they
may end up being so close that we just
collapse them down into one thing I you
know it's really hard to know sometimes
before you do something how different
Tuco paths are gonna be but when they
start to look much like compression
returning to programming you know
approach you just want to look and go oh
these two things are working exactly the
same way maybe I can merge them together
and make you know less less code that's
always a good thing
so okay if we do something like this
where we have a load sound we pass it
the ID we go ahead and do this this
stuff what we would want to do now is we
would want to wait a minute that should
be there should be a sound this would be
like sound ID right sound ID do we have
that yet we've got bitmap ID there's
audio ID I don't know is it it should it
be audio it should be sound ID right
there we go sound ID so on okay so when
we load that in that would all be good
and then we just need the actual
function like this guy here which
actually does the sound loading right so
we need something that does like load
sound work right like so and what this
would do is this would you know do the
equivalent of what the bitmap thing does
it would say alright
have a sound info structure presumably
which is exactly the same as the asset
pit MapInfo kind of thing so like this
it's sound info at the moment it would
probably also just be a file name right
asset sound info sound infos like so and
we want to grab out whichever one that
is because that's the one that we would
actually use so there's our work ID
value right blah blah blah we would then
go ahead and say whatever that one is
that we're loading here the sound
we'd probably have a debug load wav file
for something like this right we would
grab out just the file name from the
info we do that and then we would well
that would be the end of it right we'd
set the sounds like this right so we'd
say something like this right so the
slots the asset slot has a loaded bitmap
in it and so at the moment this would
actually be something like this right so
whichever one it is that's what it does
so it would be something like that
that's really what we would do we don't
have that loaded sound structure yet
really but we're just going to pretend
that we do and then we'll work on
building one a little bit later so let's
just go ahead and debug this here and
that's the wrong type debug load wave
and so really all we really have here to
do is actually have a debug load wave
which is something that would be the
equivalent of debug load bitmap but for
WAV files right that's all we really
need in order to sort of get this
started in its basic form so let's go
ahead and and see we've got our our
debug load bitmap function
or at least I thought we did oh right
it's in here now we've got our debug
load bitmap function and so we want to
do now is is do you know a version of
that for wav files that's going to do
exactly the same thing so let's see if
we can just start to bang a little bit
of that out as well so we want to do
essentially the same thing here that we
were doing before if we want to make one
of these there we go we want to
basically do exactly the same thing we
want to do a debug read entire file we
want to see if we actually get anything
back if we do then we want to take the
contents and start to look at them as an
actual WAV file now WAV files are a
little bit more difficult to read than
BMP files but not by much
I'll go ahead and bring up the docs here
for it
Wow file format right and here we go
let's see if we can get a reasonable
documentation of them here let's see
let's see so this will probably do let's
see what we have here multiplayer let's
see do we want all of that pages 56 wave
update I don't know that we really want
all of this stuff this this I guess
looks like a pretty maybe we'll just use
this web page I don't know seems okay
anyway so the way that WAV files work is
there's this concept of a chunked file
format and these show up I don't know if
the first one of them I don't want to
doubt it was really the first but there
was a thing called the IFF format right
and it was it was I think Electronic
Arts made it it was by Electronic Arts
and it was on the Amiga and this is the
first one that I ever remember seeing
that worked this way I suspect there
were ones before it because
it just seems like there probably would
have been but I just don't recall any of
them and basically the way that they
work is they try to create a generic way
of encoding hierarchical data basically
so what they do is in the file now
remember exactly like a bitmap this is
just in the file there's bytes in the
file what they do is they encode like an
ID and that ID is usually in these cases
it's four bytes is the way these work
and the four bytes are mapped to actual
ASCII characters typically so they'll be
things like wav e or something will be
the actual ID of the chunk so it's not
like 0 1 2 or the IDs the IDs are
actually often for different character
values packed together so this is some
crazy big huge number if you looked at
it as a 32-bit integer because it's
actually the four bytes of wave right so
typically what they do is they have an
ID of a chunk and then they have a size
and what you typically do is the way you
write a file parser for one of these is
you look to see what the ID is and then
you look to see what the size is if you
understand the type of ID that you see
so it's one of the ones in the set that
your program understands you then parse
out you'd like you know go start
processing the bytes that are size
amount of bytes in the file that come
after that chunk if you don't understand
it you just skip that section right
because you know how big it is because
of the size and you read the next
section and that section also has an ID
and a size right now inside these you
can also have if one of the definitions
of the chunk is that it's got sub chunks
then inside them you can have more
little IDs and sizes right that have
other stuff so you can basically just
imagine this sort of hierarchical
structure that you can create with these
things it's not a particularly good way
of doing a file format I definitely
don't recommend it it's an old-school
way of doing things you can almost think
of it as like HTML and binary
better than HTML because Lisa's got
sizes and can encode binary data in a
sane way but it is just a little bit
janky to say the least anyway so if we
go ahead and start to parse this what we
would need to do is start by taking a
look at what the what the typical WAV
file has in it and again we don't have
to do anything robust here we don't
actually have to read all WAV files we
just have to read something so that we
can use it for our debugging because
we'll assume that our asset processor is
the thing that would do any of the fancy
reading and putting assets into the
format that we want so this is only our
debug loader so just like the bitmap
loader it only has to load some example
assets you know that we would use so if
we wanted to do that this is the
specification for what happens at the
beginning of the file you can see it's
little endian order so that's kind of
handy and you can see what we've got
here is we've got a four byte field that
should say R if we've got a four byte
field that says how big the chunk is and
then we've got a four byte field that
just says wave right that's what we
should see and so I'm gonna go ahead and
assume that that's true and I'm gonna
make a wave header here and you can
actually I believe this is all of the
chunks in the file will have this kind
of format right so let's see here they
have chunk ID and then they have chunk
size no I guess they're different
so I guess typically they only have ID
in size this one has IV size and ID
right if that makes sense whereas
normally that's not the case so all
right
so let's take a look at that and see
what we've got here so we've got our
wave header our wave header should have
a chunk ID right so let's just do this
as a UN 32 this is the Rif ID then we've
got a size then we've got a wave ID like
so then we've got another chunk that we
might see is this chunk right here and
so let's put in that one as well
that chunk would basically be all of
this stuff so we have a format tag
at 16 bits so we have fmt here like so
so we have a human 16 that's a w format
tag we have au int to another 16 that's
the number of channels we have the
samples per second so we have n samples
per second
oops come back we've got the data rate
average bytes per second which we don't
really care about that's just two of
those numbers multiplied together
probably block alignment and block al
I'm not sure what the actual meaning of
that is we'll have to take a look
bits per sample bits per sample so CB
size we don't actually care about size
of extension I guess but we'll see here
CD size valid bits per sample C to be
valid bits per sample DW channel mask DW
channel mass and the sub format which is
a grid is that how long has that been in
there huh well we don't care about that
but fine there's a 16 byte sub format
we'll leave it in there all right
and so then here are the different
formats I guess that that you can be PCM
is going to be the standard that's what
will read and these guys will be other
things that we won't actually be using
so we pretty much only need to look for
that that actual format okay so what we
want to do here is put in one more thing
which is the wave-like chunk if that
makes sense
and that as we know is like four and
four it's the chunk ID and the size
right
so if I go ahead and say we've got the
ID and the size like so then what I
would do
is read one of these see what it was if
it's the format chunk you know I use it
whatever okay so the chunk ID has to be
fmt so what we want to be able to do is
we want to we're gonna want to be able
to compare as we read these chunks of
the file to see what these ID codes are
and so we want to do is have a way of
making a bunch of those right so we want
to do something where we can actually
have like a wave chunk ID FMT like that
you know wave format you know riff
something like this like you know what I
mean we want to be able to do that but
we can't just do this right because
you're not actually allowed to do that
and see you can't say give me a 32-bit
value that happens to be fmt so what I
need to do is something like riff code I
need to make a kind of annoying
macro basically which would allow us to
make these in some kind of convenient
way right and so what I'm gonna do is
define one that basically just takes
these carrots like so and for each care
code it'll just put it in the correct
position now I don't know what order
they're talking about I'm gonna assume
since this little endian that the F
comes first
but we'll be able to see once we go read
the file which one's gonna be correct so
we may have to change this macro around
once we actually see it right whether
it's 24 or 0 shift up here if that makes
sense so anyway if I go ahead and and do
this then I can make go ahead
parenthesize these it's the macro just
to be extra safe there we go
and maybe I'll even be double safe I'll
cast them to you in 32 since that's what
we want this to end up being all the
time so there we go so if I make these
riff codes now oops now we actually have
a way of specifying riff codes in the
native way that they're specified which
is character strings which just makes it
a little bit easier for us to read and
define new ones potentially so there we
go
and so what we want to do here is we
would want to start parsing this guy we
would want to assume I guess generally
speaking that we we had you know a like
a wave header here right and that wave
header we would expect to see that it's
ID field right would actually contain
that rift chunk header right so we'd
want to see we'd want to see this in the
Rif ID so we would want to see in
addition the wave ID being in there and
assuming we saw both of those then we
would be good we could I guess assert
those I don't know what our convention
was in our bitmap routine did we just
assert that those things were true yeah
we did so maybe we'll just do assertions
again this is not supposed to be real
loading code this is just for our own
debugging use it will never happen on
the end-users machine so we want to
assert that those are true and then we
would start to look through the chunks
in the file now I think we don't have
any time left so I'm gonna leave it
there compiling and tomorrow we'll go
ahead and we'll actually get a wave file
loading and that will put us in good
shape for again finishing up the asset
loading but also we'll probably be able
to finish up that audio stuff as well
and that'll be good that'll get us down
again to some some nice get down to some
much less to dues because we do want to
keep like I said I'd like to start
working on game code around day 200 and
so I think we're on good track to do
that there but there's a couple things
we want to be able to cross off right I
want to I want to be done with the stuff
above this line basically I don't want
to be I don't want to be doing any of
these sorts of things there engine
purely engine work and have nothing to
do with game code I don't want to be
doing those
much past day 200 if we can avoid it
of course it's software which always
goes long so maybe we will you know
maybe we won't but the idea here is just
that this stuff I'd like to kind of get
done we did most of the rendering work
that we needed to do but we still have
to sort of big ones there that we want
to tackle the debug codes relatively
straightforward but we do need to get
fonts so there's a fair bit of work in
here right there's a fair bit of work in
here that we would want to do and so
yeah like I said I'd like to get these
guys checked off since we're within
pretty good shooting distance of getting
them done all right so let's go to the
cue and the a in case anyone has any any
questions let's take a look and also the
stream went down I noticed during you
know for some reason I don't know whose
fault that was I'm assuming it's twitch
because twitch doesn't seem to be
working at all today but I don't know if
you're getting this character sprite
couldn't you just do the following let's
see couldn't use do the following int
sprite to load equals angle plus 180
over sprites divided by 360 over sprites
mod sprites know so that there's a bunch
of things that that doesn't do right
first of all who is doing that is the
asset system doing that if the asset
system is doing that we need to start
storing additional information which is
how many sprites there are at particular
angles right but we're not doing like
right now our system has no concept of
specifically uniformly distributed
things around angles right you could
have something that has you know a very
dense set of angles in one area and then
a much larger sparser set in another
area right if you want like a boss
monster for example who only mostly
looks forwards and then so there's a
bunch of different ones of him looking
forwards but then hardly any of him
looking backwards
our current system just works now
whereas
quantizing it would not work at all
right because you wouldn't have anything
to quantize it to does that make sense
kronole dragon and i had a combined
question about the audio dassit audio
asset struct will it need a sound
loopable or loop start loop end with
loop end equals negative one meaning a
one-shot sound um so I don't really know
yet
probably but since we haven't really
built out any of the sound system stuff
we don't really know what that'll want
so probably what we'll do is we'll write
the mixer and then we can go in and back
port any stuff that the mixer actually
wanted into into our asset system plants
for implementing other audio formats
like mp3 no we definitely won't
implement mp3 because it's patented so
we're not allowed to we could implement
it may be and I think 2016 the patents
may expire but it is actually against
the law for me to implement it that
ladies and gentlemen is the wonder of
the u.s. patent system one of the worst
ideas ever software patents but what are
you gonna do so yes like I cannot show
you how to implement mp3 that's against
the law or more specifically the
instance that you were to download the
source pack that contained the code I
wrote to play the mp3 that would be
against the law I suppose all in the
stream it may not be against the law for
me to just tell you how to do it
awkward theoretically do because in some
Syrian in theory it's its patent free I
don't know that there's really a whole
lot of reason to do it because it would
take a lot of time and it would
basically just be about reducing our
download footprint a little bit which I
don't know that we care about you know
maybe we do maybe we don't it depends I
guess also on how much streaming
overhead we have in terms of disk you
know maybe it would save some bandwidth
flack is pretty useless because flack
only gets you like it doesn't even get
you like two to one so I don't know I
don't really know what the point of
flack is flack doesn't seem like it's
very useful because if you need if for
some reason you need to compress your
sounds you probably are trying to save
space right and two to one less than two
to one it's not gonna do it for you
right so you're probably looking at
something like OGG Vorbis if you if you
really need to do that but those would
be very lengthy I think to do so I don't
think I'm going to do them because they
would take up a huge amount of streams
stream time for not really very much
benefit it's just a size savings cuber
Caleb says wait how exactly is mp3
patented mp3 is covered by literally
dozens of patents if you would like to
see what they are you can use the first
hit on Google for mp3 patents and you
can see them all here are some of them
and when they expire you can also see
let's see here
whereas the patents here you go so you
can you can read about it here a bunch
of stuff and you can see right here
there's you know basically the United
States is leaves the world and being
absolutely ridiculous with software
patents and so you can see that you know
we're we're kind of messed there it
looks like so if you believe what this
part of wikipedia says in different
parts of the world it may be that the
patents elapsed in 2012 and so you know
in in your part of the world it may be
legal to make code that uses mp3 I don't
know but in the u.s. it's not so so yeah
the theory is maybe by September 2015 it
would be but maybe not because it I
think it could also be 2017 right we
don't know you know we don't really know
so
Cooper Kaela they're not patenting the
file extension they're patenting the
techniques that are used to create the
audio and to encode and decode the audio
and so if you want to parse what is in
that file you violate the patents just
by the act of parsing them because that
is what is patented right like I said I
don't agree with it I think software
patents are absolutely ridiculous and
really have no place in modern society
but unfortunately I don't make the laws
and I have to follow them and so we can
definitely not read an mp3 file as for
the person who says flack is 50% the
size of wave it's not 50% the size the
way best case it's 60% besides if I
remember correctly and that's best case
so oftentimes it is not so let's take a
look here what is black compression rate
let's see yeah so I mean I would say in
general well that's us typically so
maybe it's better than I thought I
thought that was best case meaning you
rarely saw anything that would go before
it but maybe that's not true what do we
have some kind of some kind of a
article that tries to see yeah so this
is more like what I expected to see
right so very little compression really
and so if you were trying to save you
know if you take a look at this right
let's say your your footprint you know
for your your total game is two
gigabytes or something how much of that
is audio right if the answer is out of
that two gigabytes a half gigabyte is
audio or something I don't know I mean
pick pick whatever it is a half
gigabytes audio if you take that half
gigabyte and you're saying okay I could
compress that and save 25% of it right
you're talking about a savings of
something like a hundred megabytes in a
thing that's two gigabyte just
redistributable yeah why would you
bother right you're just adding a bunch
of code to your game for really no mess
you know no significant savings right
even having the size of your audio which
this looks like this is more of a good
case instead this was the bad case I
guess this is a good case even having
the size of your audio it just isn't
that useful if you're trying to get
stuff down you need to get it down a lot
more than that right you need to be able
to get it down like you know for eight
to one something like this before you're
talking about something that's really in
the ballpark of use useful compression
that changes the the use cases that you
could actually ship this thing in right
that's just my opinion
so fifty percent is just not enough I
feel like 50 percent is not enough to to
actually care about that compression
maybe I'm being to send you there and
that's best case right a lot of times
you're not getting that so so it doesn't
seem like a very useful thing to me to
introduce all that complexity goes for
that I think if you're going to
introduce all that complexity you should
pick again something like OGG Vorbis
where you're going to get eight to one
or something like this at least and you
can tune it a little bit more so you can
actually get more than that if you want
right
and Cooper killed yes that is why Brad
doesn't patent any of their stuff is
because we didn't believe in it we
believe that it's stupid so we don't
patent it all right looks like that is
the end of the questions okay I will
wind things down I'll leave that wave
file specification up for now because
there's some other chunks we're gonna
want to get we're gonna need basically
the data chunk at least so yeah I'll
leave that up alright let's go ahead and
close this down doo doo doo
okay all right double check to see if
there's any other questions no it
doesn't look like it the stream was so I
feel like twitching is being very
twitchy today so I wonder if maybe we
probably wouldn't have enough people who
were able to actually catch the whole
stream ask questions hopefully tomorrow
things will be better and I can double
check to make sure it wasn't my isp or
something but I don't know that it was
anyway thank you everyone for joining me
for another episode of hand made here
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
with a series at home you can pre-order
the game on handmade hero dot org and it
comes with a source code so you can go
ahead and play around and experiment on
your own if you want to do that you just
use a little handy dandy pre-order
button there if you want to just support
the video series separately you can
always do that by subscribing to our
patreon we also have the forums page
where you can ask questions and look at
ports to Mac and Linux and check out
annotated episode guide that helps catch
up on old episodes we also have a tweet
bot that will tweet the schedule at you
so if you want to subscribe to that to
catch the live stream that's a really
handy way to do it check out all that
stuff hopefully there's good stuff there
that will help you out anyway thanks for
joining me we'll be back here again same
time same place 5 p.m. Pacific Daylight
Time tomorrow right here on Twitch I
hope to see you all there until then
have fun coding and I'll see you on the
Internet's