there we go hello everyone and welcome
to handmade Europe ah
handmade here oh I don't know why I kind
of got a little there was a little bit
of a like voice crack there on my
handmade here Oh normally I'm good at
doing the introduction but not today
let's try it again hello everyone
welcome to handmade Heroes show decode a
complete game live on Twitch no engines
no libraries it's just us and are we
typing fingers now yesterday we stopped
in the middle of doing something which
was kind of very clear at that point we
had had a really you know clear path
towards what we were trying to do we
just didn't have time to do all of it so
we did it in two parts we did the
runtime part first and today we're gonna
do the asset packing side of it and what
we were doing was converting our font
system over to allow it to have more
information about the fronts at runtime
than it used to so we had a bunch of ad
hoc values we put in there to get the
font system working and then what we did
is we moved those attic values into an
actual set of tables per font that the
game could load and that way it can
represent a whole variety of fonts and a
whole variety of information about those
fonts and use them at runtime now the
important thing about that is that those
tables have to come from somewhere so
although we did the code that we need on
the runtime side to actually use those
tables we do not actually have the
pipeline set up to get those tables from
the asset packing stage into the game
and there's two things we have to do for
that the first thing we have to do is
actually pull those tables out of
windows we are not currently doing that
so we have to go in the a spec or do
that writing them pull them out of
windows write them to the disk in our
asset pack file but then the second
thing we have to do is at the time when
we actually go to run the game when we
load that asset pack file we have to
pull those asset by the the font
information tables off of the asset file
pull them off of the drive off out of
the asset file and do some remapping
because remember we are allow multiple
asset files to be merged together which
means that things like bitmap IDs are
not stable they actually get moved at
load time and so because we know that
our font includes a bitmap id table in
it for example that is something that we
would then have to
make sure we remapped properly so that's
about it
it's not very complicated what we're
doing but it's a fair amount of work
it's just typing and debugging sometimes
code tasks are very heavy on the mental
processes where you're having to figure
a bunch of things out and it's tricky
and there's a lot of thinking to do
other times programming processes are
more just about some very basic
tradecraft making sure you're not doing
anything stupid but on the most part
you're just doing something very
straightforward that doesn't mean it's
necessarily going to be a cakewalk right
you can always have bugs that take you a
while to find or you just make a silly
mistake somewhere that's totally
possible but for the most part what
we're doing here is very very
straightforward nothing tricky about it
it's just a bit of attention to detail
and typing and that's all we really need
to do now today is day 171 so if you
would like to follow along at home with
what I'm doing go ahead and unpack day
170 a source code that's a source code
that I'm starting with today and so
let's go ahead and see where we left off
here if you remember correctly when last
we left we were still running but we
were running with no actual fonts
showing up on the screen because we had
converted our system to expect to load
those fonts the font information off
disk and of course it's not there so our
game is still running totally fine
there's nothing wrong with the non font
part of it but our fonts which we're
displaying up here previously are no
longer there so what we'd like to do is
go get those font tables working and
that way we can have our fonts back and
then we will also be able to do a bunch
of my stuff with them like have correct
kerning and that sort of stuff so let's
go ahead and start at the beginning
which is going to be that asset Packer
the test asset builder obviously has
some work we've got to put in some
serious work here to get this font stuff
working because if you remember we kind
of cheese it out and with good reason
because I wanted to wait of course until
we got to the point where we actually
knew what we wanted for fonts but we
could have cheese it out and what we do
here actually is we call load glyph
bitmap to load glyph bitmaps every time
we come through here and actually want
to extract a particular font character
well that's not really going to cut it
anymore
because now we actually have an official
sort of concept of a font and so that
font itself needs to sort of be
represented in the
acet table end needs to be taken care of
specifically so what I'm gonna do here
is I'm just gonna take it one step at a
time like we always do I'm gonna slowly
start adding I'm gonna like you know
slowly start adding that notion in here
until we've got things represented in a
way that makes some sense so in order to
do that the first thing that I'd like to
do is not actually really change the way
that this code works in any significant
way all I'm going to do is I'm going to
make the actual font loading work with
like multiple fonts and the concept of a
font specifically rather than sort of
this cheesy thing we did before where
you notice like we have this sort of
ridiculousness where really you could
only use one font because we had some
statics in here that stuff is all stuff
that we want would want to replace
anyway because it wouldn't work if we
wanted to pack multiple fonts so now's a
good time as I need to replace it and
that will put me into a good position to
start having those fonts be first-class
citizens in the asset file because now
there will be an actual concept of a
font in the asset Packer which there had
not been before and that's relatively
important so what I'm going to do here
is I'm going to go ahead and you know
take the the second to look at this game
assets thing you can see that we have an
asset source the asset source is the
thing that sort of tells us how to pack
something and so you can see in here we
have this first sample index this code
point thing what we want to do here is
kind of make the asset source I think
into something a little bit fancier than
it currently is right just a little bit
fancier than it currently is I like that
our very large number by the way was
4096 that's a pretty good very large
number you have to admit it's hard to
imagine a number larger than 4096
I also like the fact that we don't yeah
we didn't we didn't really have any sort
of sort of rhyme or reason for that we
just decided that was like a very large
number yeah to do Casey are there larger
numbers than 4096 do we have evidence in
the natural world of things that can
exist in quantities larger
than 4,096 and maybe just for good
measure to write on the end of this guy
we could go ahead and stick a little
note here 4096 should be enough for
anybody right just so we kind of know
that you know nobody really should ever
have more than 4096 of everything
because that's a very large number
already and I think you're just kind of
at some level being greedy if you go
above that so off we go we've got an
asset type font here now remember that's
actually totally erroneous right because
what we actually meant by asset type
font was asset font glyph right and
asset font glyph is not the same thing
as an asset type font when you see in
here how this thing is sort of working
you can see too how all of this stuff
sort of shakes out really all we were
doing is saying well in the bitmap
packing path since the font actually is
a bitmap we're just gonna have a way of
distinguishing between those two things
what we'd like to do now is something a
little bit fancier right what we'd like
to do is that the very least have the
notion of a font and a font glyph so we
could do it like this for example if you
wanted to but further than that I think
what we need to do here is say that we
have for example an asset source font
lift something like this right and maybe
a asset source it you know what we could
even we could even make this a little
bit sort of cleaning up a bunch of this
stuff a little bit more but you know
something like this right asset source
sound and I'm really just making this
sort of mirror the kind of construction
that we're doing in the asset system
normally now we're doing it in the asset
Packer since there's you know there's a
couple different types here we're just
gonna allow them to actually be a little
more explicit about the fact that they
exist in do different things right and
again I don't care super much about this
code it's just an example of an asset
Packer for people who want to write
their own asset Packer but you know that
doesn't mean we want it to be completely
crappy and we need to add a feature so
now is this good times I need to make
sure that it's relatively well cleaned
up and so if you take a look here what
I'd like to do since we've got these
assets
in here right what I'd like to do is
it's got the code working with those
first and I'd also like to introduce the
notion that there's going to be sort of
some font a font state or something like
that right there's gonna be something
like you know a loaded font or something
like this I don't know and that loaded
font what I'll do is I'll go ahead and
I'll grab all of this stuff right that
we were doing before that was kind of
gently done in here and we'll just make
that loaded font actually be sort of a
you know a real real first class citizen
that stores that data again these are
very simple code changes all I'm doing
is just a base base amount of cleanup
necessary to make the asset Packer not
awful so that we can add a feature to it
because again you know we don't really
care about this asset Packer in any
particular way but we don't want to be
so bad that it's wasting our time when
we try to add features that we need for
our testing purposes like we have right
now so okay so if I were succumbing pure
what I would say is that font glyph in
addition to the code point will actually
take a loaded font as well right and in
fact this might do that same thing so
that the asset source font would take
which font it's trying to say we want to
pack into the file in the assets or a
spa cliff would do something where it's
saying oh okay you know I got I got
which font I'm supposed to be and then
which code point you know I I'm actually
using their so that seems reasonable
nothing particularly weird about that so
we'll go ahead and continue on from
there
all right so recompiling now we should
get a bunch of compile errors because
we're doing a bunch of nonsense here
I'll go ahead and predefined that which
was not being done before we've got to
go ahead and fix that which I will do
now okay and so here when we're actually
doing our sourcing stuff now everybody
who was trying to access stuff like this
before is going to have an issue with it
obviously and so you know we're gonna
have to sort of fix this up instead of
passing a font file and a font name
neither of which make any sense at this
point and you know what what you know
what let's just go full pull we might as
well go full pull here file names gone
right that's just gone it'll come in
here and we'll have asset source
bitmap
and that will have a file name there
because now we've you know it's it's not
everything has that let's you know let's
just go ahead and and do the whole night
so now we just have a fully
discriminated union right here's the
discriminator it says which one we've
got and here's our different ones okay
alright so I'm just gonna go through and
mechanically clean those up now again
just let the compiler tell me all the
places that I probably need to fix
obviously a bitmap now the file name is
stored inside that sort of bitmap
discriminant I'm gonna go ahead and do
that here as well
oops that's the character so in this
case we don't actually need these this
is going to go away because when you add
a character asset you will only pass it
the loaded font like that and so inside
here we just have font glyph or what do
I call it just glyph yeah just with we
have glyph and the glyph code point we
need to specify and the glyph font we
need to specify but that's all right
that's all we need
so moving downwards further we've got
the sound the sound does need to store
its filename and it's sample index
nothing changes there and then in here
obviously we have to pull from the
correct places and so we will go ahead
and do that now so oops that the font
with path didn't mean do that we want
right there so there's the bitmap
loading and now we've just got
essentially that one case of the font
that's still in there and then of course
we've got the the stuff where we
actually specify out this fonts so let's
go ahead and take care of those now here
when we do load with bitmap what we want
to do now is transition load with bitmap
over to using something a little more
sane than it was using before so you can
see here here is all of our font
nonsense I want to go ahead and move
that font nonsense into something that's
just going to load a font that actually
makes some sense and it doesn't do
anything particularly unusual like our
current was doing with weird like
statics and nonsense like this so I
think what I'd like to do is something
like this in fact I don't even know why
I switch windows there that's the heat
talking probably so I want to go ahead
and do a loaded font thing I suppose
here we could if we wanted to
actually make that an embedded thing
yeah I don't see why not just like we
did with the bitmap seems like a totally
reasonable thing to do so in our loaded
font we know we need a few different
things right we know that we need this
text metric restoring I guess that was
something we were using right and again
I'm just doing this by rote nothing
Bickley weird we probably want that H
font handle right to the actual font and
you know that that may be just about it
for now I think things will probably add
a little bit more later but for now I
think that's that's roughly all we need
and so in here we'll go ahead and pass
that loaded font like so and and then we
have that code point and so when we come
in here now to me now we can start to
get rid of some of these things these
guys would be moved up into that load
font right so in here where we're
actually loading the font we would get
those out here and so inside this we can
still use that set up if we want to
because this is just about creating this
particular thing here and what we would
do is our select object call where we
select the actual font what we do is
here
we would go ahead and and select the
font that the person wanted from us we'd
select that right here right so we'd
basically store that handle and then
whichever font they were trying to
extract from we'd select that into our
device context at that time right so the
device context we can reuse for
everything but the font is the stuff
that we want to vary so that's what
we'll do okay pretty straightforward in
order to get the text metrics it looks
like getting the text metrics what do we
even used those for I don't know it
looks like getting the text metrics we
could just do that one time perhaps when
we load the font but then we would need
a DC and I don't know that we actually
want to have to bother with that so what
I might do is just do it here
where we always get that text metric for
now that's a little slower than it needs
to be potentially but I don't know that
we care so we can leave it like that and
that would be fine so really all we need
right now is that win32 font handle and
that's pretty easy to come by right so
we can just do load
this would have the font file name and
the font name like so so in here we load
that up there we go and we would store
the results of that so there we go now
we've got a way to load a font
separately and then reuse that font and
so now we can have multiple fonts which
is also good oops I don't know why put
result in there know what I'm thinking
there we go so now when we do logo fit
map when we pass the thing in we really
just want to pass in that source glyph
font and source glyph code point right
in fact it's this guy right here the
code point and that's all it needs to
actually get and then finally in here
what we need to do is actually be able
to pass those now that's a really easy
thing for us to do we don't care about
leaking font handles we're not going to
have you know hundreds of fonts so we
really don't care although we could if
we wanted to be super tidy about it we
could do that if we wanted to but what
I'm really gonna do here is just say
okay we've got our Arial or something
like this or maybe I'll just say you
know default font you know what this is
gonna be our debug font isn't it so
we'll just call it our debug font for
now I'm gonna call the font and then
after calling load font it's after
calling load font we will have a font
handle that we can use to add our
characters that we wanted right so there
we go there's the debug font and if we
want to we can like do a free font right
we could if we wanted to at the end of
this do a free font like so so if we
cared about how many of these you know
if we were gonna do millions of fonts or
something like this you know heaven help
us right we could do that we could say
okay here's the loaded font and all
that's gonna do is free that font handle
right so I don't actually remember I
think it's just destroy object
would be my guess that's the typical way
in win32 that you get rid of font but
I'm gonna go ahead and double check
usually the create call in Windows the
documentation for the create call on
MSDN will tell you what windows would
like you to free it via right and so
delete object there you go
and so delete object uh stakes anything
that comes from VDI pretty much and you
can delete it so I was close it's not
destroy sweet so yeah okay so that
should do it I think and now we've
converted to like loading fonts and so
now we can have our fonts you know be a
little more stable and we can have
multiple of them and all that other good
stuff which we're going to want to test
because we know we might want to have
multiple fonts in fact we definitely do
we want at least a thought for the game
that we might use to display text in the
game and a debug font that we use for a
debug display and those will probably
not be the same font right so we know we
want at least two and we probably want
more because we're probably going to
want different fonts for different
languages and other stuff like this okay
so if we do our load font and we've seen
while that works then our look the
bitmaps should work too and all that's
good we will have to do something with
STB where in here we would go ahead you
know well if we want to update our to
the STB path which we might do a little
later on because I did want to support
us TV so people could see how to use
that we'll do that a little bit later so
right now we've kind of broken the SDB
path right if I was to if I was to turn
a TV back on you would notice we'd have
a bunch of problems there so for now STV
we've you know we've kind of broken it
that's fine we'll we'll restore it a
little bit later okay so now that we've
done that what we need to do is start to
actually implement some of the new stuff
that we said we were going to implement
which is actually having fonts be marked
as assets that can actually be used
right
and so in here if we have begin asset
type what I'd like to do is if sort of
separate these out right so here's the
asset type for font and here's the asset
type for font glyph
right remember what that was this way
yeah
these are font and glyphs there are
things that are you know actual bitmaps
that are being used to display the font
and then these up here are actual fonts
themselves which are kind of the
centralized piece of information that
tells us all the other stuff that we
need to know about it so I want to be
able to do something like this where I
do add font asset right like so add font
asset and you know that would just be
something that takes this font and says
you know what I want to add this font to
my set of stuff okay
pretty basic nothing nothing weird going
on there right
but again just just going through the
motion so that's all good now what I
have to do is actually implement that
right and again this is just so I can
I'm doing the exact same thing I did
with all the rest of this stuff all I'm
trying to do is make it so that there is
some entry in the asset packing table so
that when it goes through everything it
will know to pack that font in so I've
got the font name and the file name for
the font in there right we come through
here we do our standard thing for
getting the font ID right like so and
then we get out the source that we
wanted we would then take an HHA asset I
guess and we would do all the same stuff
you know looking at this I feel like
this code is really probably boilerplate
e right don't you feel like I mean I
don't know about you but I kind of feel
like internal something that was kind
that was going to return us like kind of
a little package here might be in order
right something that was going to be
like this you know like that you know
struct asset because I don't think we
have a struct asset so we do something
like oh you know what we'll do added
asset like so when we do struct added
asset we would have in here the ID right
and then we would have that HHH asset
pointer
like so yeah
something more like that does that seem
reasonable and then what I wanted to do
was just have okay added asset add asset
and that would just do all of this stuff
for us so that we don't have to do the
part that's the same right that's the
same for everybody so this stuff can
just be and again this is classic
totally classic impression oriented
programming here I'm just seeing
something happening multiple times I'm
pulling it out right really really basic
stuff but it helps keep the code saying
it keeps the code smaller and it keeps
you from having lots of different places
that do the same thing where you're
likely to change one and break something
or you know who knows what right okay so
looking at this what we need is we need
the game assets pointer which is gonna
do this hmm looks like everything else
is kind of on autopilot for the most
part right this is just the index that's
all really straightforward the tags are
all the same yes a really easy really
really easy conversion the result here
is just gonna be whatever that index is
and the HHA is just gonna be the HSA
that we already had to pull out right
really really basic stuff right totally
cool and now you know again you get to
see that really nice cleanup happen so
you know we can just go ahead and say
add asset now we pass it the assets and
that's all we needed to do gets rid of
all of this code right and then we've
got that that easy access where we just
say okay the HHA pick bitmap set the
parts that are specific to our bitmap
right so that's pretty straightforward
the asset source itself looks like it's
also used here right and so what I'm
going to do is I'm going to pull that
out so it also has that
put that right in here and so there we
go
again I'm just making it really easy on
myself so there we go
and the assets to return the bitmap ID I
just need a result equals asset you know
I could even do something crazy here if
I wanted to it's not worth it though I'm
not gonna I'm not gonna all right so
something like this right
and what I can do then is I can excuse
me but that's kind of weird I don't know
why I called that supposed to be called
an ad font asset yeah I just didn't
finish
I stopped in the middle of adding that
guy so anyway that looks like it works
just fine so I'm gonna go ahead and
finish up doing the rest of these guys
that way right we've got this add asset
thing just gets rid of a ton of code
right
so there's adding a character asset
exactly the same way there we go
really really simple and there's our
bitmap ID this alt asset that ID and
again sound same thing right can clean
up all of this stuff and we only have to
keep the part that's actually specific
to what we wanted to do with that sound
right so there that is
and there's that sound ID and this just
feels good right it just feels good to
get rid of that redundant code so that
you know it's nice and tidy in one place
now and easier to debug and maintain so
let's finish it up that thought this was
the instigation for the whole thing was
the fact that I need to add this ad font
to asset so there we go we've got the
asset they're going to go ahead and get
rid of all of this it looks like we
hadn't actually done any of this yet
anyway so it looks like we'll have to
actually do it now so let's do that so
let's get our font set that stuff we got
to set this stuff and so we'll do that
in a second and finally we'll go ahead
and fill out that result struct and
so that would allow us to actually add a
font asset so that's good what we want
to do here is load up that file formats
thing so that we can actually see what
fonts themselves having it they've got a
code point count they've got a line
advance those are the two things that
they have to actually store and so
that's something that we need to know
and so when we do an ad font asset here
I think what we'd like to do is maybe
change this up just slightly maybe do
something like this no know how you guys
feel about that and then expect the font
to have those things in it right so that
makes sense and so then we just go ahead
up to here to our loaded font we'd store
these in the loaded font instead right
or you know we could also just not store
them at all we don't actually have to
store those if we don't want to that's
another option so we could just say you
know what we don't ever actually store
those anyway but we now know that we
need two things in our loaded font we
need the code point count and we need
the line advance right now at the moment
when we actually do a load font it turns
out that to get those like the line
advanced we could probably get but the
the the code point count it's just
something we're gonna have to hard code
for a moment because if you think about
it we haven't actually really done any
work to decide what what ranges of text
we actually want to support so yeah
knowing how many code points there are
is actually something that's kind of a
little bit of a different thing so I'm
just gonna assume that we actually just
passed that in like so on again and then
the line advanced is something that we
kind of want to be able to get out of
the font itself right and that was
something we probably can get from the
text metrics but again that would
require us to be able to get them out of
a device of device context that's not
really a big deal but it means that it
kind of instigates this move a little
bit so let's just go ahead and do it no
time like the present right so if we
were going to do that we would have to
do our select object
right do our select object get those
tech metrics out and now we could
actually have the text metrics which I
think give us that that size that we're
looking for right text metric TM height
see what else we got in turn a letting
external letting weight overhang Frisco
last Garris let's see the height asset
MD some of the characters there should
also be a line height in piece of line
for efficient the amount of letting
space inside the bounds set by the TM
high accent marks and other decals go in
the sphere the tire may set the Samara
the amount of extra letting space at the
application that's between rows since
this area is outside the five could
taste dough marks so I believe what we
want to do is probably team height + TM
external letting would be my guess the
documentation Inc right here but that
seems right and if we look at this let's
see what it says
internal letting external letting
baseline to baseline distance TM height
yeah so it looks to me like TM height we
then need to add TM external letting
there to that I would think at the very
least that's what it looks like to me
right okay so after get that text metric
our line advance right is going to be a
text metric TM height plus text metric
TM external letting no big deal but now
we have this problem where we kind of
need our global font device context
right this thing needs to be a little
more real and it needs to sit around all
the time waiting on our beck and call so
that we can actually make sure that it
always you know is ready to service us
let's take a look here at everywhere
that we use it global flaunt device
context and so on and so forth those are
not actually ever being used but we kind
of have them as zeroed out so I might as
well fix them so we'll do that and then
all I'm going to do is I'm just going to
pull this stuff out
and we're just gonna do this stuff at
startup right this stuff's just gonna be
done at startup and yeah and these will
become defines pretty much right
seems pretty pretty straightforward to
me right so let's suppose we did this
we've got our max width and our max
height I would rather have these do
something like max pot wit and max font
height just so now we know that those
are baked in there we can get rid of
this because we are actually doing it
and then we would have a initialized
font DC sort of a situation like so and
then we would have these guys out here
little variable right and we've got
global device context little bits right
that all seems totally fine nothing
particularly weird going on there right
so global font device context that you
don't need to make that checking anymore
we go ahead and initialize everything
global font device context and then we
also need to get those bits out right
there
so that's all fine let's see where the
bits is being used right so that's all
good and now we just need to make sure
that it's startup we call that we only
need to call it once and then our device
context would be good to go and we can
use it everywhere we want right so right
before we do anything we need to go
ahead and initialize that that's totally
doable and yeah there we go
this up here into the global section
okay so that is that and we could now
also keep that information around like
we didn't do it before because I said it
would be a little bit you know tricky to
get there now that we've had to take
that step anyway we can finish this up
by saying okay that loaded font will now
store its text metric itself right so
you know that's relatively
straightforward although I guess I now
we're starting to get into things where
it's going to be a fairly a larger
structure right and so that gets into a
thing where maybe we want to go ahead
and do it this way right so I'll just go
ahead and and make that make that
actually be something where we malloc it
right and then that's something we can
free yeah there we go
so we malloc that loaded font and now
we've got to change these guys oh that
lovely see having a dot and an arrow for
no reason
but yeah once we do that we've got all
of our stuff set up properly now for the
text metric which means that the text
metric does not have to be retrieved in
here anymore right so this is just going
to use font text metric for that piece
of information all right so let's go
ahead and clean up our compiled problems
from all these changes conversion from
long that's fine we'll just convert
these to reals that's what we want to
store the mass this is going to be max
font with and this is going to be
maximum height right actually I'll just
do a search in replace max width
Maxthon twit so go ahead and switch that
up and then do next height max font
height and done okay so in here we are
finishing up that font stuff we've got
the line advance in the code point cut
now that's all good file name is not a
member of asset source font I agree with
that wholeheartedly
in fact so let's take a look at what we
actually need to fill out there what we
actually need to fill out there is just
a pointer to the font okay when we call
load font now we need to do sort of that
code point tab we know that we're going
to have that many at the moment right so
that's really all we need to do there
temporarily speaking anyway and now this
returns a pointer it's actually kind of
nice because now it means that we don't
have to ampersand that anywhere there we
go
all right so there we go we did a bunch
of changes we're now adding fonts we
don't really write them out in any sort
of meaningful way yet so that's not
quite as useful as we might hope but
we're getting there right we're getting
there so what we need to do now is we
need to start building the actual font
tables that we're going to need right so
in here where I've got my loaded font
let's go up care to loaded font when I
come up here to loaded fonts when I
allocate this font and I know what the
code point count is what I need to do
now is I need to allocate space for
those tables right so I need to have
like my bitmap IDs like I was going to
do I want to do a malloc size of bitmap
ID
right times that code point count and
I'd also like to do that horizontal
advant hello okay
a little way from you there I also want
to do that horizontal advance the
resolve ants is going to be that sort of
squared code point count again with a
with a float in it you know so exactly
what you expect getting those two tables
sort of ready to go and so then when we
actually do the Fontan here what I would
want to do is I'd want to set that debug
font the bitmap IDs right I'd want to go
ahead and set for whatever the code
point index was I'd want to be able to
set that bitmap ID to whatever add
character asset actually returned right
it also means like get out of a tagging
business so I don't have to do that
anymore which is kind of nice I can just
go ahead and do it like that and save
that piece of information okay so it's
not what did i do there i not add to
loaded fonts whereas loaded font there
we go
loaded loaded font i never out that yeah
all right I guess I did my bad
so bitmap ID v YZ and r3 2 horizontal
advance right
pretty basic so what we need to do now
is we need to actually write this
information out in some semblance of a
useful way when we actually get to the
font we don't have to do anything in
particular for our font glyphs they can
just be treated like bitmaps like they
were being before so when we come
through this path that's totally fine
but we do need to do now is if the
source type equals asset type font we
need to actually do something here right
we need to actually do something here oh
and you know what that reminds me we
can't actually free that font I don't
know why I did that free font that
thought needs to stay around yeah I
can't be freed there I don't know what
I'm what I was thinking that phone has
to stick around cuz we're gonna we're
gonna use it so that that's the stay so
yeah so anyway when we come through here
and we've got our font oops don't know
why so it's sound there that was an
autocomplete I'm sort of mistake I'm
sure when we come through and get our
thoughts we now need a way to write
those out and you can kind of see how
exactly that that was working it works
exactly the same way as everything else
we just need to write those tables out
that the runtime is expecting to see we
know we have two tables they're very
straightforward we can even go into
handmade asset a dot H and just see
exactly what we were expecting them to
look like right we have the the
horizontal advanced table right you can
see it right here and so what I can do
is I can just come in and say okay these
are what the sizes should be right
the code point count squared like we're
doing before
again that code point count right that's
exactly what we expect our sizes to be
so all we have to do now is just F write
them we need to F write them in the
order that they're expected here they're
expected code points and then horizontal
advance so all I have to do is just do
two of these guys write exactly the same
kind of rights that we were doing first
for that that code points right size and
then for the
horizontal advance and so yeah the data
is just going to be from from the bitmap
IDs and here it's going to be from the
horizontal advance right no big deal
doing the f rights exactly the way you
would expect yeah nothing particularly
unusual going on like I always say all
pretty straightforward and so what we
need to do now is we actually need some
way of having the horizontal advance
actually to filled in obviously that's
not happening at the moment and so what
we would like to do is have an actual
way of filling in what the horizontal
bands should be and this is kind of an
annoying process I don't mind telling
you it's it's a little bit ridiculous
but off we go we just got to do it so
let's do it so in order to get the
kerning in win32 well actually you know
what I could do let's let's cheese it
first and then we'll do it correctly
maybe tomorrow right because it'd be a
little easier to choose at first so in
here if we if we actually do load font
glyph or whatever it is load with it map
right I think we had 17 minutes on the
clock if I'm not mistaken so we started
late so alright anyway so if we're in
low glyph fit map and here we are in our
font stuff here once we know the height
the abs are the width of the font let's
just stuff the width in there right
because we know what the result with is
we're just just stuff result within
there not correct value at all but
that'll emulate what we were doing
before sort of with our proportional
fonts right so yeah so we'll go ahead
and do that and what I want to do there
is say okay let's loop through all of
the code points that there are
right and for every code point that
there is we will say that if we're the
previous code point whatever the next
code point is it's going to advance by
our width right so we'll go through all
of the code points for this font right
like so we will say no matter what the
code point is there we go no matter what
the other code point is we're going to
fill in its thing in the table so
whatever our font our horizontal advance
right we're going to go ahead and say
that the other code point I believe we
have our code point whatever comes after
it it's gonna be our result with and
that's what it's going to be and that's
it now this horizontal advance table
thing I think we want to clean up a
little bit we'll talk about that
probably tomorrow but for now we're
gonna leave it hand it hand indexed like
it is okay so where is the which code
point are we actually doing oh I do an
inconsistent capitalization of that
which is unfortunate right let's see
conversion from in 32 to our 32 we could
fix that
and finally font so source font yeah
all right so now we're actually writing
everything out Chris we've done a lot of
changes so I don't even know what's
working and what's not at this point
we're just kind of in that that sort of
limbo stage but you know something just
happened we wrote out something now we
get to start the unenviable process of
actually trying to load that in and make
sense of it at all and there's something
route rather special we have to do to
make that happen now loading in the font
itself is trivial it's just all gonna
happen automatically our our load code
here that we wrote just to do the same
stuff as before totally works like
there's nothing unusual that has to
happen there it's all good so really the
the only the only part of this that's
going to be breakage II that's going to
be break II is that the code points are
indexes into the bitmap you know they're
I their bitmap IDs right and the problem
with bitmap IDs is that those bitmap IDs
get rebased when the file gets loaded
right so you know if we only had one
asset file then it wouldn't matter but
if we have 12 asset files then each
asset file as it loads has all of its
bitmap IDs offset by the total number of
bitmap IDs that there already have been
right and so that or I should say asset
IDs mm-hmm however many asset IDs there
have been right so that is an issue
right that is something that we can't
really fix without having some way of
when we after we do the load those
things have to be spun through and
corrected right so or we could correct
them on the fly is the other thing we
can do and that's not too hard either so
maybe we'll do that but either way we
need a piece of information right and so
if you take a look at at this here what
we would have to do is say okay when we
load this font in write the asset
information that we actually
have for that font needs to give us an
additional piece of information that
will tell us how far the font should
have to offset its code points right and
so then from then on whenever anyone
uses one of these loaded fonts they will
be able to do that offset properly right
so if we take a look in handmade asset
dot H I feel like we know which file
we're dealing with right if you take a
look at the we do the asset file index
the get file handle for a thing right
that get file handle for what we could
do is just say whatever the asset file
rebase mminton here might be enough I'm
not sure it probably is it because it
probably could even be perfect because
of the way that we reveille stuff mm-hmm
because the asset types are contiguous
that's the way we rewrote them to be no
I'm saying you know what I'm saying so
if we take a look at our asset structure
you can see what it's got in here it's
got the HHA right and a file index so in
addition to that information we would
need to store whatever that whatever
that we basement is so I'm just gonna do
that I'm going to do that at the for
right now let's say that we've got that
so it's just the thought bitmap ID
offset something like that and we'll see
how that goes from there but point being
so then what will happen is well just in
here we'll say bitmap ID offset right
equals whatever that the asset structure
is asset pop it map ID also
right so that'll be set to zero normally
but then when we load the things it'll
be set to something else we'll see that
in a second so what we need to do here
is just have our loaded font have that
piece of information which is the bitmap
ID offset and then whenever we're
getting these whenever we get one of
these glyphs right whenever you do get
bitmap for glyph it's just gonna
actually be offset right by whatever
that value is and that'll allow us to do
our rebasing pretty trivially right not
much not much craziness has to go on
there all right so let's see let's push
this a little further
no operator found yeah I agree with that
I agree with that how about that
does that help you apparently not
there we go so I think that's just about
everything the problem is we have not
written anything to actually set that
thing right so when we come in here and
we do sort of our all of our loading
right we come in here we're loading in
our stuff when we spin through these
things what we have to do is now inside
our assets as we spin through those
assets if the asset type is a font we
need to do that rebasing right we need
to kind of know how that rebasing would
go oh you know what I'm wrong I'm
totally wrong we can do it per file
because if you remember the way that it
works is asset types are contiguous and
they are loaded contiguously and since
all of the glyphs are the same type all
we need to know is the base value how
far that base value got shifted for that
file very clever
perhaps a little too clever
the debugging is gonna be fun getting
all this stuff working but that means
that this does not have to complicate
our asset structure it can just be a
property of the file which is much nicer
right so that's that's pretty pretty
nice so that means when we come in here
and we take a particular file index all
we have to do is you know we've got that
file when we actually see you know I
guess when we start right when we when
we initially do this I assume that when
we create one of these file guys right
like right here we can say that the
the the tag base for this guy is going
to be fit map idea I'll set zero and
then later when we come through and we
do all of our reading when we see that
we have gotten to that particular type
whatever the you know when we've gotten
to two whatever that type is like desk
type ID or whatever right
when we get to that we can just set it
so when the when the source type ID is
going to be equal to asset type
then we can sort of snap what it
actually is set to right so let's think
about this for a second
cuz we've got some things to think about
here right so in here we've got our
asset count so we know the first asset
that would be loaded for a font cliff
for this file right what we don't know
is what the previous what it thinks that
that should have been like what it
thinks we don't know the difference
between that and what it thinks right
what it thought the files were but since
in here we have first asset index I
believe it's just that right and to be
certain that's kind of a signed value
right because we it may go backwards I
don't think it really can it shouldn't
be possible to do so but just in case
right so I think that actually does do
it but like I said we're gonna have it's
gonna be quite the debug festival with
only six minutes left there's no way
we're ever gonna get this working this
will have to be for tomorrow but at
least we've got most of our stuff
straightened out so the asset doesn't
have that anything anymore
what does have in it is the file so if
we take a look at that and get file
handle four you can see that that gets
out sort of the piece of file
information that we want so what we want
to do here is grab that particular thing
so the asset file index right we want to
grab that particular thing and and you
know what I probably want to do this
right get file for like that the file
index get file for asset is that even
maybe I don't know seems reasonable
yeah yeah let's just do that
that seems better yeah all right I just
wanted to be able to put in a little
assertion there that's all that was
doing nothing particularly fancy and so
that's just going to tell me which asset
file we are so there we go
Asif I'll get file there's our final
index everything's fine everything's
dandy
there's our results for returning so
oops
and then this get file handle for
actually just becomes this file right
okay yeah now we do that and now we have
our font bitmap id offset which we
wanted that looks like I messed up let's
take a look at the file format it is
where is it asset type no I want file
format that's what I want there we go
it's just asset not asset type
we go alright so we're basically out of
time
so I'm just going to go ahead and say
that we will do the debugging for this
on the next stream because yeah there's
just just too much stuff that we did
there so both things are are you know
sort of nominally done but they're you
know not going to work is basically what
it boils down to
so we basically I'm just kind of
surprised we didn't get some kind of a
crash eNOS in there but we're more or
less there we just have to now go step
through everything clean up everything
that might be buggy and get ourselves
into a working state but that was
everything that's all the actual
implementation we need to do so now
we're just down to this the more
straightforward process of of makeup
making it work alright I will go ahead
and go to the Q and a so if you have any
questions about what we've done today
now would be the time to ask them please
prefix your questions with Q :
I'm recruiting braces give us a sec very
well I will give you 15 minutes in fact
garland abloom I try to explain to
someone that a color is just a UN 32 and
I am not sure it got across so I think
we talked about this on an episode of
handmade hero so it might be kind of a
might be kind of retreading a bit it
might be best to just go back and watch
some of the rendering stuff we talked
about but you know it's it's pretty
simple color is a very ambiguous term
right a color is just can describe a
number of different things right are you
talking about emissive color like you're
talking about something that gives off
light are you talking about reflection
right are you talking about something
that like absorbs some light and only
put some of the light back you know etc
etc so color is kind of an ambiguous
term and so you know I feel like you
want to go back and watch earlier hamon
heroes to really sort of talk about
color and get color fairly solid but
what I'll say is most of the time what
we're dealing with is sort of the
concept of modulated color which is to
say that somewhere in the game something
has an idea of an amount of light that
is occurring and we are storing what
percentage of that light gets through
right so we're talking about you know
there's a certain amount of light coming
into something right here's some red
here's some green
here's some blue or whatever right and
these are my photons they're coming in
here I've got a bunch of red photons and
a bunch of green flows so on right
they're going to hit something or do
something and then I'm gonna have less
of them left some of them are going to
get absorbed or whatever right and so
the typical case might be like a bounce
of lighting you know income some photons
some of them get absorbed into the
material here and some of them bounce
out right so typically what we're
storing is restoring sort of an idea of
a percentage color and since the human
eye responds to has you know three
different receptors red green and blue
receptors in you know in your actual eye
we tend to track those three colors we
tend to track red green and blue and so
what we tend to store is a value from 0%
to 100% for these modulated colors one
for each channel so restoring three
numbers right that represent the
percentage of light reflected light
passed through light emitted whatever we
want a percentage of some value that's
known in the engine somewhere in this in
a different way depending on the
circumstance so typically what we do is
in order to pack these down into
something small look Arlanda Bloom was
talking about is we might often take a
UN 32 which is 32 bits of information
right and what we'll do is we'll
segregate that up like so we will pack
eight bits of our 8 bits of G eight bits
of B eight bits of alpha in the case of
a sort of like a OpenGL style or on
Windows which I believe is the format
that we're using we will use sort of the
window style which makes it look like
this eight b8 g 8 r 8 a these are
reversed from what they would be right
how do we do that right 32 bits goes to
eight bits of each what do these
actually mean what's the a well first of
all
the are the G and the B are just trying
to encode this percentage so what we do
is we say that in that any particular
one of these 8-bit values a zero in
there
maps to zero percent a 255 which is the
most that it could possibly take on is a
hundred percent and anything in between
is interpreted as a smooth step between
those right so 120 for example is going
to map to 120 over to 55% that's how we
can code color values into a unit 32 the
Alpha channel which is this extra one
here is since we need to know additional
information sometimes such as how a
translucent something might be or
transparent in this case not translucent
how transparent something might be what
we often do is store another percentage
which is a percentage that says how much
you see through this particular thing
right and so that's a separate value
that's not part of the color but it's
it's important for our rendering so we
typically pack an alpha value here not
always but sometimes
robbery you added text metrics into the
struct and then decide to allocate why
and what's the benefit so the reason my
thought process there just to explain it
in a little more detail was the reason I
wanted to Alec this was just because I
was like well it's starting to get
pretty big right and so let's take a
look at how big it actually was right
text metric right is this big ol struct
right and so I don't necessarily want
people to have to store that on the
stack or pass it around or whatever I
want them to be able to Alec that once
it gets to something that's that big I
just gotten big enough that I was like
might as well allocated on the heap
right that was my thinking at some point
some gets big enough you can allocate on
heap and in this case it seems to be
reasonable because we have a bunch of
allocation we wanted to do there because
we're storing these big tables and stuff
and that just seems like the right thing
to do so we don't end up having giant
things on the stack unnecessarily
about the language having different
fonts with the supply to added packages
by other people
yeah I felt like it probably would write
my thinking that was that people might
want to add new fonts for new languages
along with new translations into the
game and so you know I there's not going
to be much text in the game I don't
think but you know there might be like
item names and stuff like that and so
what we could do is make it so those
item names are stored in the asset file
and looked up by tag and then we could
introduce a tag for language and then
people can add however many languages
they want right
let's see girl and Oh losers I'm talking
about in terms of how the GPU cares
about the color of a pixel as opposed to
a struct with float rgba which is not
really necessary for a buffer thing so
you know yes and no hmm so if you want
to talk about the GPU more specifically
so basically with GPU and a and a CPU
right they're not that different at the
end of the day they're sort of they're
getting closer all the time right and
there are still some very important
differences between the two and to
really know what all the different
important distance are you'd have to be
someone who worked at Nvidia because or
something like this because you know
they don't necessarily tell you
everything that happens on a GPU and or
CPU for that matter but point being when
these when these people are working on
graphics the important thing to
understand about graphics and the reason
that for example graphics has a
coprocessor in your machine it has a GPU
you know why isn't there a sound card in
most machines anymore right why isn't
there a card for reading the joystick
right the reason is because graphics is
sort of the most data intensive thing
the most compute data intensive thing
because it is a two-dimensional piece of
data right you have a screen and that
screen has some significant dimensions
nowadays at least 1920 by 1080 right
that's like kind of the minimum of what
gamers probably expect to see nowadays
they're not going to be super happy
about you shipping something else that's
over 2 million individual units that
have to be processed have to be solved
for every frame right and 2 million per
frame is just a lot ok that's a lot of
processing no matter what you're doing
every frame you're probably not
processing 2 million of anything else ok
and so in order to produce that 2
million of course if think if everything
goes into it there's like multiple paths
those two million there's lots of
calculations that happens on your
civilians you you tend to have over draw
so you kind of have the situation where
things get overwritten by other things
that are behind each other by Allah so
that 2 million is Chilean very expensive
things that are going on proportional to
that 2 million so what that means is you
do not have the luxury of always
representing things in the way that you
might want to and so you mentioned or
girl and Oh blue mentioned ok we have a
structure why can't I just have a float
our G be a why can't I do that and just
use that everywhere right Y in when I'm
actually talking about the frame buffer
or a texture
why don't they look like this and the
answer is they do look like that
sometimes you actually can declare it
exactly that as the format for your
frame buffer in a GPU or a texture on
the GPU you totally can nothing stops
you from doing that nowadays is it's
totally fine right the problem with it
is the size okay this structure is 4
times 32 bits right another way to think
of it would be 4 times 4 bytes right
this is 16 bytes this which is what we
were talking about right having only 8
bits for each of these is 4 times a1 or
4 bytes right not very difficult math
here so why do we care if it's 4 bytes
or 16 bytes the reason is this giant
multiplier right just the frame buffer
alone has 2 million of these elements in
it's 2 million times 16 bytes is just a
lot bigger than 2 million times 4 bytes
do we care about the size not
necessarily what we care about is the
bandwidth right so that memory the GPU
in order to operate on these things has
to go get them and pull them back
operate on them put them back out to its
memory that's on the graphics card right
it has to do that work and
to do that work it's sucking down memory
bandwidth memory bandwidth is the most
expensive thing on a graphics card it is
what gates the performance more so than
probably anything else in a lot of cases
and so what ends up happening is if you
can reduce that memory bandwidth by four
times right this number is 4x this is
this number right this is four times
this if you can have four times the
memory bandwidth that's like getting a
graphics card from several years in the
future right so if you take a look here
for example list of NVIDIA GPUs okay I'm
just gonna pull this up so you can see
you can get like a little bit of a feel
for it so here's the GeForce series
let's take the GeForce 500 series you
all remember this right not that long
ago okay
2011 so let's take a look at what the
bandwidth was on that right hmm here's
the memory bandwidth and gigabytes per
second you can see it here 14 gigabytes
per second for example on these guys 28
gigabytes per second some of these got
up to 128 gigabytes a second all the way
up to maybe like hundred ninety-two
gigabytes a second right that's the
memory bandwidth that that's quoted in
here right now let's scroll down right -
let's can we get a GeForce 900 series
there we go right now let's take a look
at at the memory bandwidth right there
it is 336 right
roughly 2x in a couple years time right
and so if you think about it's just not
it's just not growing that quickly right
you just don't have infinite bandwidth
it's not this free thing and so if you
can say I could get four times the
bandwidth right just by reducing the
space required for these things to
transmit them I'm gonna write and this
is the reasoning behind tons of things
why do we have texture compression right
it's not actually to fit more textures
on the card memory that's one positive
benefit of it
but the real win for texture compression
is it's less bandwidth it's less memory
bandwidth pulling textures on the card
so texture compression is about getting
this number down from even four bytes
it's getting it down to two bytes or one
byte right per pixel you want to keep
getting it down down further further
further right and it's all about
conserving that bandwidth it doesn't
matter how much memory you actually have
on your GPU it doesn't matter if you
have a 32 gigabyte GPU that's not really
where the footprint cost comes in yeah
there are reasons why you want to have
more memory on a card it means there's
less traffic across a PCI bus and and
all this sort of stuff there's grid good
reasons why having more memory on a
graphics card can be good but the
crucial thing to remember is that
footprint matters for things other than
just whether you fit on that GPU it
matters because the bandwidth is a very
important part of the performance of the
GPU it only has so much to spend and
it's doing all of these operations all
of them pull from memory right back out
to memory do all these sorts of things
every texture you touch every frame
buffer access you touch that is costing
you bandwidth and if you can reduce the
size of your colors that you store in
these things that immediately cuts the
bandwidth by whatever that reduction was
and that's really important so hopefully
that makes some sense
do any systems ever represent light as
an actual frequency and change that
value based on interaction with the
simulated environment yes it's less
common in real-time systems because you
usually don't care that much about it
although some people do some specific
things too so that they can get certain
effects even in real-time but where you
typically see that more as an offline
renderers for example you'll see
spectral calculus employed you know
offline renders that go for quality
right let's see here right
here we go right and and they'll they'll
do stuff like defining the spectral
characteristics of light and instead of
just doing RGB they'll actually think a
lot about what those actually are and
the reason for that is they have a bunch
of things that they will then do
correctly like for example refraction of
light through prisms and stuff like this
you know Maxwell render will do it
correctly thin film reflections like on
soap bubbles they'll do it correctly so
if you have a light that's putting out
pure red light and you shine it through
a prism and Max will render it will
scatter red if you have something that
is not a pure you know I shouldn't say
that if you have something that's like
that's a bad example if you have
something that's actually yellow
wavelength light right versus something
that's red light and green light
together when they go through the prism
they'll scatter differently right or
when they reflect off of the soap-bubble
thing they'll reflect differently right
because those are two different things
you can't see the difference if you just
look at the light but once it goes
through some kind of a participating
medium it can it'll do different things
and then you can see the results right
and so you know oily finishes that sort
of stuff that do these sort of complex
reflections recording the actual
spectral characteristics of the light
can be important all right let's take
the last questions here if you're taking
user input at some point will you worry
about blocking Unicode control
characters I don't foresee this game
ever allowing text input of any kind so
I don't think that would come up Ron
Roberts so you care about the stack
memory when would you start to really
measure it is it some gut feeling I
would never have had that idea before
not getting an actual error
I mean basically I don't like to return
or pass things by value it's less about
the stack size I don't like to return or
pass things by value if they're not you
know less than 32 bytes or something so
that's you know I only keep I keep my
structs pretty small if I'm passing them
I value right let's see what is HDR HDR
is high dynamic range basically what
that means is when you make this
approximation right if you have floats
you're good to go
it means you're you can represent any
range of numbers right because the
floating point value is exactly that
when you make this approximation to a
bit RGBA you lose the ability to have a
wide array of numbers because you have
you only have 256 different shades so
you can't represent something as bright
as the Sun and something as bright as a
candle or the reflection from a candle
for example those are so far apart that
if you tried to represent them with only
256 steps you would have no lighting
fidelity whatsoever your image would be
ridiculously banded right and so all
high dynamic range is is it's basically
figuring out a way to well one
definition high dynamic range is just
just do this everything's floating-point
everywhere would be high dynamic range
because now you can capture pretty much
any range of lighting that you want
right but what HDR often refers to a
little more specifically is the act of
finding other kinds of sort of packing
formats that allow you to get back some
of what you lost by not being in
so that you can have say for example
still a 32-bit value and it's like RGB
and an exponent or something that tells
you how to raise those are jeebies to a
power or something right
so you still try to pack like a bigger
range of values into still a smaller
space and not a mouse do you think there
will be a time when CPU and main
bandwidth is fast enough to replace GPS
entirely going back to the days of
software renderers yes I do and I hope
we see that day because I am tired of
dealing with GPUs they're just a pain in
the butt all right time for me to eat
some dinner I I don't mind saying so
let's wipe things down okay okay thank
you everyone for joining me for another
episode of hand made hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along at home
with a source code you can always
pre-order the game on hand meter or
again it comes in the source code even
just starting today starting every day
there's always going with a source code
even from day zero you can download the
source code every night after I'm done I
upload our latest changes and you can
play around with them we have a forum
site also you can go to if you want to
ask questions or get community
contributed ports to other platforms or
anted episode guide all kinds of good
stuff we have a patreon page you want
supports a video series you can
subscribe to that and we've got a tweet
bot that tweets the schedule so if
you're trying to catch it live that is
the place to go to see when it will be
live and just in case you want to know
it will be live tomorrow again 5:00 p.m.
Pacific Daylight Time hope to see you
all there when we can go ahead and do
some debugging on this guy because I
think we're pretty much done with our
font stuff
the bulk of it anyway I'd like to go
ahead and debug back get that working
and then maybe clean up a few of the
code point range things like I said just
so we can kind of look at doing other
languages but this this is maybe the
last week for Foss maybe it so I hope
see you there for that until then take
it easy everyone
have fun coding and I will see you on
the Internet