hello everyone and welcome handmade here
oh sure we could a complete game live on
stream today we have a rather unsavory
task that is well it's not going to be
pretty I'm sure I don't want to mislead
anyone it's definitely one of those days
where either we get incredibly
incredibly lucky and everything works
smoothly the first time and it's great
and it's happy or it's a much more
likely scenario we are stuck sitting
around wondering why we're not getting
the GPU to do the thing that we asked it
to do only to find out many much much
later that we specified some little
thing wrong or the GPU driver has a bug
or other fun things like that
so that's not going to be pretty but we
hope that the results of getting it all
working will be pretty which is to say
that we are trying to add a little bit
of per pixel interpolation to our
lighting today and that could be pretty
great once it once it actually is
functional all right so let's take a
look at what's going on in that code
first however we are going to as we sort
of update it we're going to make one
little change here to help folks who are
trying to compile on other machines
basically there is a we've talked about
this multiple times but shaders
unfortunately compile differently on
different GPU drivers the reason for
this is because shader compilers are
kind of haphazard in a lot of cases
depending on the vendor and there's a
bunch of things that a shader compiler
may not catch you know just errors
standard errors that you might
accidentally put in a shader that you
know if it were C++ or something the
compiler would definitely catch and tell
you no matter which compiler you are
using but on shader compilers they're
not really that strong
they're oftentimes too permissive or
just have bugs in them or anything else
so the fact that these shaders compile
and run on this particular AMD card does
not actually mean that there are no bugs
in the shader code it just means that
there's no bug that this particular
shader compiler happens to care about or
notice so people who are compiling on
more compliant shader compilers such as
the NVIDIA compiler as you can see from
this note here is talking about the gtx
1070 which is the graphics card from
nvidia or I should say graphics chip
from Nvidia not a graphics car to grab a
card of course there's many different
graphics cards that have a gtx 1070 in
them when running under nvidia shader
compiler what you can see here is that
you get a syntax error and that syntax
error is due to the fact that we
incorrectly specified the version on
that shader we were specifying I believe
150 whereas now we use shader model 330
now not all of our traders actually need
version 330
if we're going to use version 334
anything we might as well use it for
everything because as far as I know
there's no bonus having some of your
shaders to use a lower shader model the
only bonus is if all of your shaders use
the lower shading model because then you
can work on other machines lower end
machines right so that's my assumption
anyway I don't see any reason why we
shouldn't go ahead and do that so I'm
going to do that just to make it easier
for folks who are compiling on NVIDIA
card who want to follow along with the
series so again this is not a problem
we're having but it is a problem that
other people on different machine
configurations are having and so we were
going to try and fix that so here's the
situation with the current rendering and
we can kind of see that if we run our
lighting solution we produce our
our voxel lighting solution which is
what we want to now integrate into the
rendering so we'll get some lighting in
there and that's that's really what
we're going to be working on today let's
go ahead and and change those shader
models to 3:30 and see if that we can
still make all of this work properly
how do we I guess we're always showing
the voxel regardless okay so I'm going
to go ahead and do that
and just verify that everything still
runs so here's that version directive
you can see that we have version
directives here that are 130 150 130 150
and so on and I guess so the things I'm
not 100% certain about is whether shape
changing to version 150 would have fixed
everything or if you actually need 330
but I don't think there's a difference
between those two things I think that
now I'm thinking about it I think like
330 and 150 or sort of synonymous
version numbers because if I remember
correctly like one shade of 150 was the
one that came out with OpenGL 3.3 or
GLSL 3.3 rather so aren't they sort of
the same I don't know but either way in
fact you know let's see if we can get
some documentation on that
I know so I guess I guess it looks like
1.5 was actually 3.2 so I guess 3.3 is
actually the one we're using which is
one step above that now I don't know
exactly what we're using that requires
3.3 but again should be okay so I'll
just go ahead
oops and make that change for now again
what we can do later if we want to is we
can go ahead and start thinking about
after the you know rendering is
completely done and when you get closer
to shipping the game if what you want to
do is take a spin back through and see
if there's a way to reduce the version
number down right you can always do that
so during development we you know don't
really have to worry too much about what
this number is because it just means
that you know certain people wouldn't be
able to develop maybe on older hardware
but development is not really where you
want to spend your time trying to be
maximally compatible that's just not a
particularly good use of time so you
typically want to do that only when you
get more towards the end of things and
so on all right
so as far as I can tell all of the stuff
that was working before is working again
so that's realtively straight forward
I'm going to go ahead and kick that back
to Kim and friends and they can see
whether or not that helps them compile
on those other cards obviously I don't
have one of those cards in this machine
so I can't really test it but I will go
ahead and and ping it back all right
looks good why did it hey why did it
change my Y to change my dash to a I
don't want that
no turn off turn bad bad mark down no no
mm can I do anything to make it not do
that
github why why do you think I want that
I don't want that is there it escape
character for markdown
hmm well
mark can escape character
how do I escape a back tic within a code
block I feel like this would be the kind
of thing stock exchange would be good at
no no that's not what I want
oh wow
so you have to use html's ampersand
notation now that's only for this I
don't know
how do I insert a dash in markdown
seriously man I just don't even know
let's try some things randomly if I
backslash it I'm assuming that wouldn't
do anything oh wow that was lucky
all right so apparently a backslash
escapes the character who knew well
there you go
all right problem solved
surprisingly enough that should be that
I don't know that there's anything else
that we've got to do here let's take a
look at that shader layout issue one
well let's look at this one too
that's probably not really something we
should be looking at the moment
so the platform layer should be updated
to request a 3.3 context that we also
haven't done so let's just do both of
these bugs right now I don't see any
reason not to
so we're just going to have to pass when
we do open jail at ribs right now it's
three zero we're just going to have to
ask for a three three and then that
would be it
I think and I think that's everything
all right good deal
so I think that's everything that people
were having trouble with I'm not 100%
certain but we'll find out I don't know
why this is still a bug because somebody
said some stuff that doesn't probably
make any sense but they never really
followed up on it even though Martin's
tried to ask them so I don't really know
what the deal is here
all right anything else we should do on
here I don't think so
these are all just bugs we can fix with
me know what this is about at all so
we're probably not gonna use that one
anymore so probably close that one out
later but we'll leave it in there for
now all right so I think that's
everything we needed to do in order to
help maintain the code base for other
people who may be doing other things
with it I know a lot of people like Kim
for example who are commenting on those
port to other platforms as well so
there's a bunch of stuff that just they
may need or that can help them out and
we just it's good to basically have some
ways that they can continue whatever it
is they're doing without having to worry
too much so I think we're back to where
we were before and now we can focus on
the task at hand which is if you take a
look at what we did last weekend
well last Sunday specifically we
produced this handy-dandy Vox alized
version of the lighting solution that
basically tells the the I shouldn't say
tells the tell anyone anything but which
encodes the number of sample points and
those sample points have specific
lighting information recorded along with
them now when these lighting points are
recorded they are provided as voxels now
which could be looked up in say a 3d
texture or anything else now it's not
quite the same as saying that they are
literally voxels like I should be
clearer about that it's actually a voxel
lookup scheme is a is a more accurate
way to say it because effectively what
you're seeing here is not a voxel eyes
version of the lighting but rather a
series of lighting sample points which
do not have to lie on in any particular
location
and then they are simply Bend into a
voxel based on which voxel they fell
into right so that's that's the only
real part that's voxel II about it but
we need that part about it so that the
graphics card can effectively look up
where the points are where those sample
points are so what we want to do now is
we want to try and figure out and when
if they try and figure out I don't
really mean that it's necessarily
logistically hard I mean just it's you
know GPU gyrations we want to figure out
how to get these pieces of information
down on to the card so that they can be
processed right so that they can be
quickly looked up and used to
interpolate the lighting solution so
what we want to do is take this render
here which you can see is rendering
without any lighting at the moment and
we want to and has these big you know
colored blocks on the white ground
temporarily for just you know for
lighting testing purposes and we want to
take that and we want to have each of
these you know triangles being rendered
here we want them to use that lighting
solution to interpolate between the
lighting samples that are nearby to
whatever the services that's being
shaded so that's really all we're trying
to do here in order to do that we've got
to get that data down on the card so
what we're seeing here is not data
that's on the card at all this is data
that's just on the CPU and what we're
doing is we're just sending down tons
and tons of little cubes and drop
letting those cubes show us where the
lighting samples are right that's that's
the only what's going on here so not not
particularly great to say the least so
what we want to do now is start that
process and again this is just going to
be a really onerous process of trying to
deal with the GPU there's nothing
particularly interesting
about it there's no particularly tricky
aspect of it at the moment because we're
not even trying to create that lighting
on the GPU we're just trying to do that
lighting eye on the CPU and send it to
the GPU which remember is quite a bit
easier because we don't have to worry
about how we're going to create it
exactly in GPU land all right so let's
take a look at what's happening in the
render group you can see in world mode
here we've got the lighting textures
structure that we computed and you can
see that we're creating very specific
stuff here we've got two textures that
are 4096 long they are a lot linear like
there's just a one-dimensional texture
there's nothing else to it there and we
also have a lookup texture which is a
three dimensional texture that texture
to six by six by 32 these are 4096 by
one effectively or by one by one you
know that they have no other dimension
to them and so if we want to specify
these we have to be able to specify
these additional textures to the card
now in order to specify these textures
to the card we we kind of have to
introduce what's effectively a temporary
solution because remember we probably
will never actually want to do this in
the shipping version of the game and the
reason for that is that we probably
don't want to compute the lighting on
the CPU now I don't know that's 100%
true we leave we don't really know
that's the case I mean one of the things
we could do is try to write a really
fast version on the CPU that did
lighting computations and then actually
send it down that is something we could
consider doing I you know it's not the
weirdest idea in the world but it is a
pretty weird idea and not the least of
the weirdnesses of that idea is just the
fact that even if we make sure that the
CPU code is highly optimized and does
run well in a sixtieth of a second on
the CPU side we still have the problem
that the data that has to get
transferred to the card keeps going up
so now we have to transfer an 8 megabyte
texture to the card every time and while
that may not really be the end of the
world it's definitely the case that the
more bandwidth per frame transfer
bandwidth per frame you introduce into
the game
usually the worst so if we could just
send down the lighting information which
would be much much smaller and then have
the card compute everything it needs on
its own that's probably going to be more
not only faster if we can make it work
reasonably but it also it will reduce
the total bandwidth from CPU to GPU in a
nice way because so far we haven't had
much GPU CPU to GPU bandwidth
utilization so it would be nice to just
keep that generally low because it means
then we don't really have to think about
that aspect much like we're not going to
be sitting around one wondering like
what we're going to do to make sure the
card always kind of takes that stream in
nice limits ficient ly so alright here's
our lighting texture what I'm going to
do is basically just put in I think what
it would amounts to a special purpose
way to accept this data and I'm not
going to think too hard about it
specifically because as I said before
it's not really something that we're
going to use right it's not something
that's going to have to ship at the game
it's not something I'm anticipating
shipping with the game so I'm more or
less should be able here to just put in
essentially a special-purpose routine
that does nothing but transfer this data
so I'm going to go ahead and call
lighting or lighting transfer
so if we go down to the sea here if we
go down to the lighting transform
structure that we're going to need well
actually it should be right here
shouldn't it
render entry any transform then all we
really need to do here is have a way of
sending these down and I guess what we
know here is we know the layouts of
these things and they can just mostly be
implicit right we know that we're only
ever going to get this as a submission
of this stuff right here since we're
only going to get it as a submission of
these things we should be able to just
take this as is without any fuss so
where the where the push entry itself
gets pushed I will just have to have a
way of pushing one of these on and since
we don't use a union right now although
we could very easily now move to using a
union because we don't have as much
traffic going down I'm going to go ahead
and add this in so where we do a push
render entry or sorry render element
don't ask me why we called it element
here in entry they're probably just the
hazards of writing everything on stream
where it's harder to pay attention to
details such as that I this push render
element calls here will give us what we
need in order to push the lighting on so
if we want to go ahead and put one of
those in there here's all the lighting
code right what we can do is just come
up here and say alright let's let's go
ahead and have an inline call for push
lighting and if we go ahead and push a
render element of this form what you can
see here is we probably want to use the
standard
format for it which is just group in
type because we don't need to do
anything special like this one here so
I'm going to go ahead and do a push
render element for render entry lighting
transforms that render enter letting
transform will come back I believe as
something we can which is called that
best I guess so we can write too so
assuming that this person who calls us
whoever they are is going to pass us one
of the textures I guess I'll call that
source since we're copying from one to
the other I think all we really need to
do is just sort of copy the the various
elements of this in there and we're done
and that should be about it now the only
requirement is that that stays around
I'm not going to copy the actual data in
because again this is not something that
we need to think about really in that
way so all I'm going to do is say that
the destinations confirm it you know the
information from the destination here is
going to get copied directly so at that
point
[Music]
that's pretty good tell us the slow
morning undeclared identifier render
entry lighting transfer I agree with
that but shouldn't this have expanded
that type out oh dude in both places so
I just decided to use that everywhere so
it would have been fine alright so I
think that's about it
and now I guess first since this is
lighting Texel here we could also just
call this an f32 because we really don't
care about this format information just
yet
alright so now what should happen in
theory is if we were to do one of these
calls so after we compute the lighting
and we want to send it down if we take a
look at what's going to happen here when
we call this output lighting call what's
going to happen is we want to make sure
that the lighting gets sent down to the
card using this push lighting call and
what you can see here is that when we do
output texture debug back to thing that
creates all the push cubes so right now
we don't really want to do that because
we already know that that's you know the
correct thing so instead what we want to
do is push the lighting down like so
where we push down the group and the
textures or rather we push the textures
down to the group might be the better
way to say that and that will push one
of these onto our you know our render
stack
now what should happen when we do that
now is we should get an assertion in the
OpenGL code that it's received a you
know a token it doesn't recognize right
and you can see that happening here so
here's the loop of interpreting the
various things that come down the render
you know sort of the render command set
and you can see that you know it's it's
missing a case for that one that we just
added so if we want to now we can go in
and actually add something to handle
that case and again this part of it's
probably fairly simple
famous last words I suppose but we
basically just need a case that's
identical to the rest of these just
taking a different lighting transfer
taking a different final port there and
what we want to do now is we want to
actually take a look at what's in there
and send it down so you can see again
I'm just doing exactly the same thing we
were doing before
I'm peeling off the part here that we
wanted and then I'm casting to the type
that I needed to get right
so this point we have the entry and what
we need to do is we need to submit four
pieces of texture data from that you
know from that structure so we need to
submit each of these down as a texture
and so what we expect us to look at here
that look like here it's like a GL
texture update call right so we need a
GL text image kind of thing and we could
use GL text image or we could use your
took sub image I'm going to use text sub
image at the moment just because
actually you know what I should be on
Docstoc GL though for doing this because
I just want to make sure at the moment
the graphics card knows we're not trying
to allocate a texture we're just trying
to specify a new image for that texture
so if we take a look at what we've got
here we're in GL three obviously here's
that GL text sub image call and I just
want to fill this this data out with
what I've been given so there's going to
be I guess two different flavors here's
the one for the 1d textures and we've
got the DL
texture 1d coming in here and we want to
specify a couple different things first
of all there is no myth map at the
moment for the to 1d textures probably
won't be so the MIT map level is always
going to be zero the log level the X
offset is going to be zero because we're
specifying the whole texture the width
is going to be 4096 because we've sort
of hard-coded at the moment although in
the future we could sort of expand that
maybe will allow you to specify it who
knows there's a GL enum format here the
format in this case is what we're
submitting it as we do have
for the P next anyway we do have four
different values so it's a GL rgba
texture it's actually got all four
components we've got a type that type is
floating-point at the moment so it's
going to be I guess it doesn't what
there it is and like doesn't quite have
it in there but does and then the data
pointer so the again this is just a
simple way of sending down this
information to the card like so and then
we've got one more kind of ado here
which is the GL texture 3d call and
that's for a 3d one and you can see us
doing a little more complicated dance
here with tight depth format and type
are the same the level and target the
same data point same but these are now
three-dimensional so this is basically
specifying a sub volume inside the
texture we don't really want to specify
so I know my sense of the whole thanks
for just using 0 0 0 and the full width
height and depth so let's go ahead and
do that the other thing we could do here
I guess since there's not really a point
in not doing it at the moment in case
you want to play with resolutions in an
easier way what I could do here as well
is just say like data width right
something like that and then when we
come in here we could just specify this
as light data with now.i so we don't
really care right now about anything
regarding this because like I said I
don't even think this is something we'll
probably use particularly much you know
I don't know that code of this nature
will be shipping because I don't know
that we'll be doing any lighting on the
CPU it may all be based on the GPU by
that point but the point here is simply
that if you take a look at these GL
calls here we are specifying with that
width is the full width of the potential
set of data that we specified the
textures but we didn't probably use all
of that so what we could do instead is
just remember what the highest number we
used was and only transferred that much
down because we know that's how much
data we're actually going to use again I
don't really care about that even
remotely at the moment it's not the
least of which because even if we were
going to ship this code this is the
small part of the problem this 3d
texture over here is much larger than
either of these two are and so slightly
reducing the bandwidth on the 1d image
transfers is probably not going to make
a difference just based on the
disproportionate size of those things so
if I go ahead now and do the Geo textile
image 3d call I'm going to specify the
GL texture 3d because that's what we're
actually going to be using and then I'm
going to specify the rest of the things
exactly as you expect there's the level
and there's the base and now I just need
to specify the various slices here
there's the width
there's the height and there is oops the
depth of the texture and then we just
need the format and the type so the
format in this case this is just a
single u16 so the format is actually
just going to be a single value so it's
just it's just going to be like the red
channel of the texture there's there's
no other information in it and we've got
an unsigned short which is an offset
into the lighting information and so
that's pretty much all the information
we've got here right that alone is
pretty much enough to transfer all of
the lighting data down to the card the
problem now is we actually need
someplace to actually put it and what
you can see here is although we're
calling GL texture 1 B 1 B 3d we have
not found any textures so we're not
really targeting any textures here so
what we want to do here is something
like a bind texture to put a texture
into the slot that we're about to
specify and that's where we get to the
part where we actually need to allocate
the textures right we need to have some
textures that we've allocated that can
be used here so when we do a deal binds
texture we're going to need a place to
get these since these are going to
pretty much just be global textures that
just kind of sit around we can also just
assume that there are things that we got
in here right so what we can do instead
for example is just say alright let's go
ahead and make a Glu entir for the
different textures that we're going to
have lighting P next letting see letting
look up and so these will just sit here
for the moment until we have you know
some better idea of how we want to
handle them and then we can just use
those here
so this lighting PNX letting see light
and look up those are going to come off
of the global open jail because they are
detection sit around and that's really
all we need so what we want to do here
oh and I guess the other thing we need
to do is make sure that these constants
are actually specified in a place that
can be accessible so we want to go ahead
- in fact we probably if we were being
reasonable here we would probably want
to say that this stuff now kind of just
lives in the platform layer since it is
actually a render something that it has
to work with the renderer
all right so the only problem that we
have encountered here and that's
security the only problem that we've
encountered so far is the 3d textures
obviously we're introduced to OpenGL
subsequent to the initial version of
OpenGL and Windows which is very early
Microsoft decided to stop updating it
because they wanted people to use
DirectX not surprisingly so we have to
go ahead and do another cut and paste to
get ourselves this GL text sub image 3d
call so I'm going to go ahead and grab
that again nothing fancy here just the
same
oops thing we've done multiple times so
here is text sub image and here is text
image I'm going to want both of those
the reason I'm going to want both of
those is I'm going to need GL text image
3d to allocate the texture so I need to
have both of those available to me so
here we are
those the two calls that we actually
need again we have to sly loading code
as well buffers yeah and now we should
be loading bids we should be able to
call them I think I do that wrong I did
okay so now we can call those just fine
the only thing we don't have is the
identifiers for GL texture 3d so let me
just well in fact it's right there I
have I was going to search for it but I
didn't have to because it was sitting
right there and now we should be good so
what will happen now is if we actually
ran this we would get an error because
well presumably get an error because we
don't actually have a texture allocated
so we should get an error that says that
that texture handle is invalid or
something to that effect
let me see what we actually got Oh
we're in release mode so it can't
identify that variable I'm assuming it
hasn't gives any additional information
but I'm assuming that is exactly what I
said
since its omits texture beverage 1d call
presumably the error is that the well I
guess I don't know but presumably the
error is that we have an allocated the
texture data so I'm hoping anyway
because that was the one that I was
expecting if it's not that then I
suppose were we're in a little bit of a
bind
but moving along under that assumption
let's go ahead and find out what we can
do for the allocation there I'm going to
hop in to OpenGL code where we allocate
our frame buffers and such and just try
allocating those textures now every time
the settings change happens all right so
I'm just going to call delete textures
on OpenGL here three times and again
I'll just free these textures lighting T
next playing C and lighting lookup
and then I will just allocate them
[Music]
so I think that should do it in terms of
generating texture handles and then we
just have to specify the size of each of
these so a text image one D and a text
image 3 D we should now be able to
specify these so let's go ahead and
actually call that
so here's text image 1 D again the
target in this case and I guess I can
just kind of make these happen alongside
their respective folks here you'll find
texture texture in 1d alright I so so
what I just did there so now we've bound
the textures we specify the texture so
it's the fill in the parameters to these
text image calls we should be good to go
I can also unbind the textures
at the end just in case to clear
everything out so now we just need calls
that will actually put something in here
and the way we're probably going to do
this is just by specifying the size of
the texture without actually specifying
made contents and the contents will be
filled in later so this parameter will
just leave as zero which I believe we're
allowed to do to just set the size yet
you can see here that if data is a null
pointer texture memory allocated to kana
texture of with with commend onload sub
textures after that which is all we
really want to do so here we've got
target we know the target is always 1d
we got level to zero we need an internal
format the internal format has to be
floating point for the P next texture I
believe I right about that
yeah and as you can see it's a mixed
texture there it's got floating point
values and it's got u-32 and we could
choose to specify those two things
separately and in fact you know looking
at it it may have been smarter to make
to you thirty twos in the C texture and
then just VIII's for the P next texture
but it's hard to say so I'm thinking you
know it's you know what that reminds me
we didn't the before I finished finished
saying that thought for the lighting see
here this is not float
right so what we want to do here is
presumably just stick with with with
floating-point storage and have it so
that it will just correctly set it to
what it needs to set it to initiator
will just convert between the two so
let's go ahead and finish filling those
in so yeah I would say for Jill decks
for the internal format I would say we
probably want to do here it's a that's
going to be GL float right well I guess
we have to specify RGB float so let's
see here
it's gonna be RGB looks like they don't
by default to find that one but it's
okay because we actually do have it so
it's GL RGB 32f RGB a 32 F the width is
going to be that lighting data width or
the border value obviously zero we don't
have any texture border stuff happening
here the formatted sectional data is RGB
a the type of the pixel data is GL float
and then we've got at that zero in there
so same thing happens here only this
time we pretty much yeah we we pretty
much don't need to store anything fancy
this time we're just using on standard
color it's just a standard color texture
and then in buying texture that's right
in the text image 3d we've got the same
process but this time we're going to
have to do the full width height depth
call that's 2d there's 3d I so there's
the again same set of parameters we've
got the target specified already we got
the level now the internal format is
just the red Channel we've got a width
height and the depth that we know it's
the lighting lookup values like so
there's no border we've got a format
think the internal format here is still
just read am I wrong about that maybe
not
how about r8
there it is
so I think now all those are specified
properly all right so we've got that the
border now now we just need to specify
the format and the type again in here
this is a single channel so this should
just be GL read and the type in this
case is just going to be the unsigned
short now those are kind of academic
because we're not actually passing any
data but we probably want to make them
reasonable
it looks like Ari is not defined
probably because we've never sent down a
single sort of mono mono texture before
so I'm just going to go ahead and grab
that in there and add it to our
collection of extended texture formats
here
uh well actually this is an R 16 though
isn't it because I did say it's unsigned
short I'll grab the re as well alright
uh so now we want to do is just clean
that up let's see we want it to not be
r8 we need that to actually be our 16 so
now we want to see if we're getting this
transferred properly and let's go ahead
and see if that's actually true all
right so now we're able to maybe in
theory transfer the texture damn we we
don't get any errors we don't know that
that means that it's working properly we
just know that you know there isn't
obvious an error so bad that it gets
complained about so let's take a look
here and see now as far as output
lighting is concerned I'm going to go
ahead and say let's do something really
weird here I'm going to go ahead and say
let's do the push lighting at the end
when we do output lighting textures here
let me just make sure this is - I think
it's doing yeah I'm just going to do
that here well I guess I guess we can't
quite do that here I just want to send
this solution to the card so that when
it when it finishes doing output
lighting textures
[Music]
it will actually send it
so when you hit it you know you do the
lighting test you send the lighting
textures down then they will be on the
card and they'll just you know they'll
just pay on the card and so then we can
render from those textures that way we
don't have to update them every frame
just in case it turns out that that
texture update is really slow at some
point while we're testing we don't have
to worry so now you know in theory we
hit f1 we can see the solution then we
can flip back those lighting textures
should now still be on the card so we
should be able to be using them now in
the middle of the render right that's
that should be that should be working so
now the question is just well alright if
we want to actually use those in the
renderer how would we do that we've got
these extra textures there so if we take
a look in the OpenGL code at how the
shaders are working at the moment really
we're just talking about changing it so
that we have some way of sampling
lighting inside the render the basic
render right so here's the DPS program
you know I
see I attempted to add in compile Z bias
program look at this the fact that we
have version 333 supply every time I'm
tempted to just put that in the shared
code I won't do it yet but it's
something to think about anyway I so if
you take a look at what's going on here
in our compiled Z bias program what I
want to do is I want to have a way of
specifying lighting in here so you can
see that this is you know in fact all of
this stuff is kind of old so this stuff
is we don't need any of this stuff that
we were using before so for example yeah
just looking at the blend unit color
that we're outputting we don't really
need any of that anymore so all of this
stuff is it's more or less unnecessary
and we should probably get rid of it in
fact we can just get rid of it
there's really nothing we need that for
right
so all we need to do now is we need to
actually be providing these textures so
that they can be looked up into as part
of this this portion of the program and
we also need to make sure of a couple
things well we may not need to because
we may use texture calls that that make
it so that it won't happen automatically
but basically what we need is some way
of sampling from the voxels look up
texture and getting the light
information out that we need now in
order to do the first step of that we're
just going to do the same things that we
have been doing which is to specify some
samplers in here so what we want to do
there is just say like okay we've got a
sampler one be two of those in one
sampler 3d so that we can do a Teaneck
sampler B sampler and look up sampler
and in order to figure out the locations
that we should be sampling from we have
fundamentally the same problem that we
had in the actual CPU side code to
figure out where we're going to look so
we're going to need additional
information here that helps us with that
so first we're going to need the minimum
corner of our voxel lookup that's going
to tell us how the you know that's going
to give us basically the basis so we
could subtract away that minimum corner
and get a position relative to the
corner of the voxel but then the other
thing we want to be able to do is have
some way of converting once we have that
relative position
have some way of converting so that we
can figure out where in the box we are
in terms of individual units right so we
also need in this to the mid corner we
need that M cell dim and so then when we
come through here and we have the actual
position value that we're looking at I
don't know what light P is here exactly
but world P is the only thing that we
actually care about as far as this is
concerned so that when we come here to
compute the lighting what we're sexually
it's actually going to do is say like
you know Vox P equals world P minus min
corner and I guess you could save Oxman
corner and then we can also say like
voxel index effectively assuming the
voxel P times the in cell dimension
right and I guess really we're never
going to use that otherwise so might as
well just put it like that so yeah so
once we have that piece of information
we now have sort of the indexing values
for the voxel in question and we can
look up into the 3d texture at that
point to find the the correct element
right so what we want to do is we want
to find a 3d texture sampling call oops
so here you can see probably the code
that we would want to use remember this
a 3d texture is not really a texture
it's more of a lookup table right
meaning that the elements in it don't
represent anything that we can really
draw they're just indexes and those
indexes are telling us where to look in
another texture to get the information
we were looking for what that means is
we definitely don't want to invoke any
bilinear sampling and we don't really
want to use any kind of fractional
lookup into the texture we just want to
look in a specific single location and
get out the information that is
contained in the texture at that point
and so if we look at what we probably
want to get here when we do one of these
textile fetches what we want to do is we
want to take that textile fetch and
provide integer coordinates to it so we
will get back exactly the value with no
blending right and in order to do that
we need to convert me to truncate to an
eye vac now I don't know if we can
actually specify exactly what to do here
in terms of rounding versus truncating
but I assume that we could so so floor
is actually fine for our purposes in
this case right
so we can just do something like this
and I guess since we have an I've x3
here that we're going to want to use
something like that I after flooring it
we also want to convert it right so at
that point we will have a knive x3
that's the integer coordinates in the
voxel where we are and in theory at that
point we can fetch from the voxel so
again here is my 3d sampler I'm just
going to say I would like to fetch from
that sampler I would like to fetch from
this location and we don't really have
to specify a lot because we only have
one level of the texture so that's the
basic idea as one problem that we have
here and I'm not really sure to be
completely honest with you I'm not
really sure how shader model 3/3 will
allow us to get around it since we have
a texture we don't actually want it to
sample the texture in floating-point we
just want to sample the texture in
integer now thankfully for us the
integers that we're representing here
are only 16 bits wide so actually when
this red channel comes back and it has a
floating-point value in it we can't
actually just convert it to integer for
free right we can just convert it to an
int and then we have the index into the
other texture and off we go so for
example we can just say you know int
light index and then from there we can
text will fetch all the rest of our
information right and what we can do is
since we
that light I was not a valid value we
can say that while light I is zero
effectively we can now gather all of our
P next values and all our other values
for that matter so now we're just going
to do a textile fetch on each of the
other two textbook textures that we have
like P next and lighting C and all I'm
doing here is just trying to extract
that data so you can see what I'm doing
here is I'm fetching out of our texture
out of our lighting lookup I'm trying to
fetch what the first light index is that
we're going to want to use I'm going to
loop over that index and say as long as
it's still not 0 I'm going to keep going
I'm going to fetch at that point the I
guess I should do it like this the two
values from the textures that we've got
so that's the P next texture and the
lighting C texture I haven't passing
them yet although we kind of do know
exactly what we're passing for just
passing light I and LOD level 0 in both
cases so we're going to Texel fetch
those and we're going to end up with two
different values one is the light color
that one we could just use as is it
should just be the correct RGB value so
and lighten P next is going to have to
be extra
so first we're going to take the RGB to
get that light position and then we're
going to take the light eye which is
just going to be the the next one to
loop on and if it's zero we'll break out
of the loop so that's how we would fetch
our lighting that's really all there is
to it
you can see that it could be kind of
expensive if this while loop has to do
many times at the moment we don't really
have any particular need to worry about
that because we don't have a whole lot
of lighting samples done necessarily but
not to keep an eye on that as we go
forward so again taking a look at these
what we want to do here is say okay
choosing what we want to do here is say
alright we've got this lighting
information that we've we've processed
what we want to do is take the take the
light colors I suppose that come in we
just want something that will allow us
to process a little bit we can just take
the light colors that come in and just
modulate them at the moment or something
like this right sum them together who
knows it doesn't really matter i we just
need something to show if this is
working at all and so you know I'll just
go ahead and and maybe average them
together or something like this
so here we'll just do average light what
sequels like P and I guess we don't know
what the light count is so yeah there we
go
and once we have that average light we
can do surface reflect times average
light and off we go so there's a big old
nasty shader and dude theory if we got
that compiling which might take a bit
because your uniform parse error see
what's going on there sent it :
let's see can we let's get some more
data here all right vertex errors
fragment errors program airs vertex
shader with fine fragment shader was not
a lighting lookup did I not call them
that oh yeah these are totally different
names than what I said it's not good P
next fanfare seed sampler look up
sampler let's try to get those correct
that was not good either
[Music]
boolean expression expected that's a
fair statement
so not equal to zero should help you out
there in understanding what I meant
see what else you get
cannot convert from four component
vector afloat to three component vector
afloat I would never dream of asking you
to do such a thing
where is that happening
ah
well who knows why I don't understand
why sometimes the AMD driver gives you
the error message in here did that not
see what's going on there
so geo draw arrays has generated an
error probably because use program begin
didn't work properly or well I don't
really know why so anyway we currently
are a guest compiling this properly
we're not getting an error on
compilation anymore but of course we're
not actually setting any of this
information so we're not setting any of
these samplers or this the min corner or
the inverse seldom we're not setting any
of that information so we probably need
to however that I don't feel like that
would have caused the error injeel
drawer a so a little worried about that
because I can't say I know exactly why
that's causing that to happen yeah not
great but again these calls here are
just going to have to be bound one way
or the other so we might as well do the
work to do that first and then we'll try
to figure out why OpenGL is unhappy as
it often is and we'll go from there so
first of all we've got to get these
these two min corner and M seldom those
have got to get added in here
all right and then when we do open jail
a create program here and want to link
to samplers in addition to texture
sampler and depth sampler we also want
these other samplers in here right so
we're going to want and I'll just move
this down we're going to want P next
sampler see sampler and look up sampler
and so the other thing we were going to
need to do is have a place to actually
get that Vox Minh corner and Vox and
sell them so those are going to have to
get sent down along with the other
lighting information that's not really a
big deal but we're going to have to do
it and so in here we just need a place
where that can actually be specified so
inside the device program I'll just add
those in here and now we should be able
to specify those so when we do use
program here is our use program begin we
want the Z bias program which is this
and we can stop screen corner and sell
them and those now are things that are
going to have to come in
along with the lighting
so I'm just going to assume that we get
these because they're easy enough to
pass through and then in the platform
layer when we're going to go ahead and
pass them through I'm going to go ahead
and say like all right lighting textures
blocks and corner and I think that's
really all we need I can now just
specify when we do the render group when
we specify these the the push lighting I
can just pass them along so we know in
seldom and we know min corner and so the
render group here when we have that push
call we would just have them in here so
box mid corner seldom
have the wrong structure there there we
go
so I think I think that's about it
[Music]
now in theory once we run this probably
yeah so probably nothing good will
happen when we run this is probably
going to be a disaster we should at
least bind some textures to those
texture handles I would have thought we
would have just gotten black oh and we
did all right so if we actually bind
those textures now I'm not anticipating
good results probably will still just
end up with black and then we're going
to have to go through a really long
arduous process of debugging to find out
what has gone wrong because there's just
too many moving parts and of course you
have no visibility isms and of course we
have no visibility at all into what the
grabs car is doing like literally none
we can't even run a debugger on it on
this platform so where we have our use
program begin here you can kind of see
us binding the textures here where we
bind texture 0 and texture 1 those
textures are in order of what we called
them in the in the link textures call
oops sorry link samplers so you can kind
of see here we've got the texture sample
of the death sampler set up so what we
need to do here is the the PX sampler
the two sample look up sampler have to
be sort of specified in there now the
kind of crazy thing here is that I don't
know if the depth sampler slot I assume
that that will correctly just fold for
not using it because we don't use it in
the peel version but anyway when we do
use program begin to right here so what
I need to do is I need to set
these other textures so texture zero and
one are spoken for texture two three and
four are the ones that we're using now
and we're just talking about basically
binding new stuff to get to these right
so we've got opengl lighting look up in
jail play see opengl blowing @e next and
now in theory we bound our textures
right in theory now the only thing we
know is that we're not getting any
obvious errors from the GL that's it
that's the only thing we know right so
we have no idea what else is going on
here
none whatsoever uh so let's try to
figure out what else is going on here
and see if we can't maybe get some
progress I'm guessing we won't have time
to actually what we won't have time to
actually get everything working today
that'll probably have to be a job for
tomorrow but we can at least try to get
started on that so inside the OpenGL
shader let's start by trying to see if
there's anything we could draw that
would be simpler right
so the first thing I'm going to do is
say well maybe we can just do something
where we pick the brightest light color
and pick that just in case there's some
other problem with our lighting well I
don't know like what if we just picked
the first light sample something like
this so we just said okay we're going to
textile such
there's our our lookup we get an index
out of it we're going to just kind of
get rid of this notion here and we'll
just say that surface reflect is going
to equal I'm just going to overwrite the
surface reflect color with the light P
and what I'm sorry with the light C here
and I'm going to set light C to zero and
in here I'm going to set light C to be
equal to whatever the the light see that
it gets is we already have one of those
sorry
so that's all I'm going to do for
starters just again to simplify that a
little bit I'm going to keep some client
down oops
all right and now what I'm going to do
is I'm just going to try to make sure
that we're actually still drawing
reasonably I'm just going to set here as
an extended to the test make sure that
we're actually drawing I'm going to set
use light C equal to just pure red okay
so we're not actually seeing that which
means that we're never getting in here
right if I did go ahead let's set it to
green inside the loop and red outside
the loop okay so all we have to do now
is see why we're never getting an index
value that's not zero now there's
multiple reasons why we might always get
an index value of zero right for example
we might be getting an index value of 0
because our texture doesn't have any
valid data in it right we might be
submitting the data incorrectly so that
all of the data inside our lookup
sampler is actually all zeros right
that's one way another way is if there's
something wrong with this expression
such that trying to convert it to an
integer is not going to work right we're
supposed to be getting a floating-point
value out of here so in theory we should
be able to agree to an integer and have
it just be the index but maybe there's
something wrong with that that's thing
number two thing number three is we've
got the voxel position wrong so the look
up into the voxel position is going to
have to work properly here in order to
get some value that will actually have
something that's not black to begin with
because if we're always looking into a
point in the voxel that had no indices
no life inserted at that part in the
voxel
we if we never have any industries to
work with then we would be correctly
getting an index of zero out of here in
that case right meaning if the bin that
we end up looking in had no light
samples in it then we would also get a
zero out correctly here so it would be
the lookup position that was wrong not
the lookup process so I think that's
really mostly what I'm going to try and
focus on is figuring out which of those
is happening which is to say I want to
figure out whether our 3d texture lookup
works at all and then whether or not
it's going to convert properly if it
does so one way we could do this is we
could try just drawing this directly
I can't second think of a really much of
a way to do that this would be one place
where like I said it would be very nice
to be able to sort of debug the graphics
card because what we really want to do
is see a version of that look up sampler
texture using a third-party tool so we
could sort of corroborate whether or not
have been submitted properly and
unfortunately we can't do that so that
would have been the easiest way to do it
so barring that what we need to do now
is figure out some way to sort of grab
some information out of that maybe at a
known good location so maybe what we can
do is try to take this part out of the
process now the way that I can do that
is I can try to find a voxel cell that
we know has something in it and that's
not that hard to do because actually
since we control the lighting code on
the CPU side of things even though we
can't do bug the GPU side we can debug
the CPU side what that means is I should
be able to if I switch us back to debug
mode in the bill
like so if I go to the render lighting
code here oops go if I go to the render
group lighting code when it's actually
outputting these textures you can see
here it's doing the voxel truncation
thing and looking up and then packing
all the values in there what I could do
here is just take a look at what some of
these are and when I know where some of
them are going I can just force-feed
that cell address to the renderer so
that we know we're looking up in a place
that definitely has something in it so
that we can take that part out
oh you know what I forgot to ever run
this though ah um okay my bad I just
kind of forgot something
fairly obvious there yeah okay all right
that was my mistake and I admit that
that's um operator error
I had not been running the lighting so
there correctly wasn't anything in the
voxel at that point let's try that again
okay so now there actually is something
in the voxel so at least now I can
correctly say that we're not getting the
lookup to work properly so all right
that was my bad sorry about that a
little bit of a false alarm there all
right uh so the problem that we're going
to have here and I don't really know
much attention I think about how to do
this I should probably make some way of
outputting this piece of information a
little more cleanly because basically
what's the problem is here's the
optimizer has destroyed our way of being
able to actually see what these values
are
let's see your ECX
so EDX ESI
okay
so X mmm 0 XM m 1 and XM m to have our x
y&amp;z in them
let's get those sectors at please I so
we're looking at at this this and this
looks like can that be right
Oh
yeah I can't say I quite expected that
hold on one brief second just one brief
second
I need it too I want to view this as an
f32 I don't know if I can do that
I guess there is one thing I could do to
make this a little bit more expedient so
in here what I could do is force it to
place these somewhere that I can view
them
so here I've created some global
variables what I should be able to do
now is just assign to those level
variables I've made them volatile and
the reason I did that is to try and
convince the compiler that it can't get
rid of the write because if it thinks
that there might be another CPU that's
reading them at that time it can't no
the optimizer can't go oh well I'm just
writing over this value I won't bother
doing it till the end so I'm basically
just trying to keep that from from
happening there
debug color
so I guess we don't have a volatile
version here for this what I could do is
something like this though
which is if front emits let's say the
red channel it's greater than five all
right
so running the lighting here and waiting
for there to be a fairly bright light
sample to look at here what I'm going to
do is just take a look at what the debug
XY and Z values are 126 113 27 and so
what I can do now is just say well if
that's what the lighting value is going
to be then what I could do is in the
OpenGL code when we're you know doing
whatever we're doing here I can just go
ahead and enforce that lookup value
right so let's see see what happens if
we force it to that
so it looks like we're just not getting
any valid values out of that texture at
all right because in this particular
case now we have forced it to look up
into location where there definitely
should have been something but we're not
seeing anything so it's unlikely that
this part then is the problem although I
guess I don't really have a way of
independently verifying that we've got
those numbers right but that does seem
like a pretty useful simplification
there to just know all right we're not
we're not getting something out of there
okay we're not getting anything out of
there that we expect or at least it
doesn't look like it so let's go ahead
you know what else I wanted to just
check real quickly this is not related
but the world p-values how are those
getting specified here
all right so that's actually good too
because that's the raw coordinates which
is what we want as well all right so I
think we can now proceed under the
assumption at least temporarily that our
texture is not getting set up and
sampled properly for the lookup so I'm
going to go ahead and switch over to
here and take a look at that code path
one more time so here's that letting
look up okay so the r16 it's telling it
going to be submitted as a Jian side
short which I assume is irrelevant
anyway because it's not getting
submitted at this particular point but
here's the R 16 which is just saying
that there's going to be a 16-bit
integer value stored there
so again presumably we should be able to
access that here's the question if that
is stored that will probably be
converted to a 0 to 1 range is the thing
because it's not stored as a float we
could force it to be sort of the float
right like we could certify this and
force the float storage format but if
we're specifying it is that it's going
to assume that it's normalized which we
don't actually want it to do right we
don't want it to normalize so that's
that's definitely a problem we can work
around the normalization certainly if we
needed to by multiplying by 6 by 5 3 6
after we load the value out or 6 5 5 3 5
depending on how they encoded it so we
could try to get the light index out
that way but that's not really what I
want what I wanted to do is I
wanted to not mess with the value right
so ideally
ideally what we probably want here is
like eight for example 8ui right I
something that's going to leave it on
[Music]
so you slam for 2d I don't know if we
have access to that do we or don't we
because that's what we would like yes
good we do so we can use an unsigned
integer sampler type here which would be
great because then we would just get
back the integer directly and we
wouldn't have to cast so it looks like
we do have x2 that I'm going to go ahead
and use that so what I want to do here
is I want to go ahead and get and look
up sampler I want to get that used
sampler 3d in there and when we sampler
for that I'll get a you've X back which
is perfect because that's exactly what I
want so that way I can just say oh thank
you for the light information and and
off we go
so then I would use our 16 UI which is
to say it's an unsigned integer I don't
really care if it's unsigned to
completely honest with you that's not
super important I just need it to not be
floating-point that's the only real
requirement so if we go ahead and
where's my core ARB there it is if I
just grab should just grab all these
you
all right so now in theory if we get
this compiling properly we should be
able to get an integer value out which
is what I want
unsigned int
I don't know if the shader forces me to
do unsigned it in that fashion let's
find out and put the cast from int to
you end
try that one more time still doesn't
like that no my trailer come for Texas
fetch cannot convert from consulate to I
repeat vector afloat not sure where it's
complaining that exactly because I
didn't touch any of the other parts
so text will fetch dot are here
unfortunately I don't really see
anything else that I would probably need
to do there in order to get that back
I'm textile fetching I feel like that
should come back properly I guess I can
use this shorthand which is nice so if I
do you in too late I I would think that
that would work I don't understand why
it wouldn't I can then loop through that
when I do a textile fetch here this is
passing an unsigned integer maybe that's
bad maybe it only can accept an integer
in which case this maybe should be just
casted here from an unsigned integer to
an integer and then we can go from there
I don't know we could try that and see
if it's a little happier about what's
going on because again we don't really
care whether we have integers or
unsigned integers in this case we're not
using the full range
hmm so we're getting an invalid call on
this one does this card not support our
16 UI perhaps
I think that's the only thing that
changed but I'm not sure so it's just
specifying red and unsigned short which
shouldn't be a problem so presumably
this is the only thing that could be
potentially bad there right and see what
happens if I set it to eye
hmm so it definitely doesn't like that
it doesn't really want to create in our
16 UI I suppose that's not really a
problem for us we don't really care that
it's one of those we could just encode
it and use the 0 to 1 range AIDS it's
really not a big deal one way or the
other so I guess you know let me try
leaving it the way that it was since
that was something that it was ok with
and then I'll I'll forego the fancy
footwork in here and just say all right
when you get one of these back you're
going to get integer but you're going to
get a number between 0 and 1 you're
going to have to convert that to
something you can actually use to look
up and so we need a way to convert back
now if it was 1.0 exactly then we want
to be like 65535 right would be the
value that we would be and presumably
we're going to have a bias in here so we
would probably also want to just roll
that in I'll have to look up exactly
what their what their transform is so we
can undo it exactly and not have like
off-by-one errors or something like that
but that's basically what we would need
to do to convert it back right
well
that is not reassuring you know maybe
that's as good