hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show we code a complete game
live on stream we are going to play with
the lighting a bit today and see if we
can't make some progress on you know
just something that we like is I guess
all I guess to say about it we're not
trying to do anything fancy here we're
just trying to come up with something
that spreads light around the scene in a
way that we feel like makes some sense
right and that's really about it so I
don't know again if we're on the right
path we may have to substantially change
some things but we have a nice path
working right now where we can
essentially generate some lighting
information that we can then iterate on
and we can play around with what we're
storing and how and what sort of
iteration passes we're doing on it
without having to like redo everything
so we're in a reasonable spot I think to
experiment and hopefully find something
good again it's one of those things
where you never really know when you
head down if you're not if you don't
have a particular item than mine when
you head into something experimenting
you have no idea what you're going to
find when you do it however you know I
was somewhat emboldened by the fact that
our deaf peel render ended up working so
charmingly I kind of feel like you know
that maybe led me to being a little more
foolhardy than I would normally be so
we're kind of going for broke here with
the lighting and we're just playing
around with a lot more lighting than
probably ever should have been warranted
on handmade hero since this is an
educational stream and we're not trying
to you know come up with any kind of new
algorithms or anything like that but you
know sometimes you just get carried away
so anyway where we left off last time is
we have some lighting visualizations
here and we can sort of look at a couple
of those but what we essentially did was
we've got our lighting renderings so
that we have a few different planes of
information that we can look at we have
the surface reflectance color which is
this we've got the inbound lighting
we've got this right here is a term we
were analyzing and we don't
about talking about right now we have
the surface normals which we're showing
here and essentially what we're trying
to do is is iterate over these in some
way as to produce some good lighting
bounce around the scene now what we
determine and I think it's pretty
reasonable what we saw happening here is
that when we look at what was happening
in the scene
unfortunately our our scenes just tend
to have a lot of they're just just
basically a flat ground with some some
slight height differential that's really
all we do right and although on the
interiors will probably have some
dungeon wall kind of stuff we just don't
have a lot of reflectors so one of the
problems you were seeing is that if we
do a system that relies heavily on
transmission angle we're going to be in
trouble because we just don't have a
good coherent way of figuring out how
that's really going to work we would
probably have to add a synthetic ceiling
into the scene in order to sort of have
there be something that reflects light
back downwards and again that starts to
get into things that complicate the
renderer quite a bit because figuring
out where that ceiling is would
essentially require us rendering one
more layer above the layer we're
currently on and while we could try to
do something like that and while we do
get that for the layers below us because
we do have this layer on top right I'm
not sure what we can really do there
reliably you know and and maybe I'm
dismissing this out of hand I'm not sure
but I definitely feel like there's a
there's a big question mark hanging
there about what we would do in terms of
getting reflectors that would push light
back downward so I don't know that's
that's kind of one of those things where
I really don't have a good solution to
that part of me is tempted to try and
figure out a way to put in the upper
ceiling which would be basically a
skylight in the outer world and it would
be the dungeon ceiling inside sort of
the dungeon areas or whatever else
when somebody's in tourists but you know
you can see why I'm a little hesitant to
do that because I'm just not sure how to
get that in there in a reliable way I I
really just don't know and it would
complete it would add a certain level of
complexity as well because in order to
do that we would have to sort of render
one more depth peel above the current
depth peel right so I don't know but at
the same time is it that hard to do not
really since we already have a depth
keel renderer if all we wanted to do was
produce where that top level was it's
not the end of the world because what we
could do I suppose is just turn off the
front clip plane well turn it off is not
feasible but push it back right push
back the front clip plane and render
into another buffer the furthest away
depth layer that is above the depth we
have in the highest depth feel right
so we basically be taking the like in
fact what we're looking at right here
right this this scene what we're looking
at we would take the depth of everything
in this scene we would render the next
layer on top of that and we would then
take all of those and those would be you
know our downward reflectors those would
be our ceiling right so that's you know
that's what we're looking at
unfortunately I don't really know how
sane of an idea that is and that's the
problem whenever you're playing around
with new rendering techniques if you
never really know what's going to work
ahead of time you're really in a trial
and error land you can use your best
judgment but your best judgment is not
always good enough and you may end up
deciding not to go down a path that
actually would have turned out to be
fruitful and later on you'll read about
somebody who did follow it through and
arrives at a great algorithm and you're
kicking yourself for going on I could
have done something better there in
other times you'll go down a path it
just turns out to be completely useless
and you've wasted a bunch of time on it
there you know there's plenty of risk in
both directions and it's really it's
just tough right there's no other ways
saying it is a difficult situation but
that's just the the nature of the beast
so you got to just get over it and plow
forward so the question is what do we do
now well we've got two possibilities
right one is we try to push the
reflector stuff forward and the other is
we try to do something a little more
localized so one of the things that is
true about the way this lighting was
working is that if we were to turn off
the part of this that really deals with
angles which we did try the on the
screen before we have the facing
Direction turn here and if we wanted to
turn off the facing direction term so
that it doesn't attenuate based on
facing direction and when said we just
accumulate based on fall-off then one of
the things we can see right is we can
see the light does spread around in a
somewhat interesting way right and we do
have some sampling artifacts those are
due to the way that we are down sampling
which I think we can fix and that's just
you see how the light kind of shrinks
and grows that shrinking and growing of
the light is is just a an artifact of
that particular problem right of that
sort of what's what's the word looking
for that's basically just an artifact of
the degree to which the sampling lines
up on the square boundaries Advocates
downsampled right and so we can fix some
of that by improving our down sampling
so that doesn't that shrinking and
growing doesn't concern me too much we
can at least pretend for now that we can
fix it because I'm pretty sure we can
that's not the biggest problem the
biggest problem that we would have here
is the shadowing of these things but if
you just look at how this light is
playing around right you could imagine
if we go ahead and did some lighting on
this maybe we could make this work just
by itself and leave the facing Direction
stuff out of the equation for now right
it's possible so maybe add some
shadowing in here
and then use it to do our lighting and
who knows maybe that sufficient right
but we don't really know so what I'm
interested to do is I think what I'd
like to do today just as a first step is
before we go any further I'd like to go
in and add the final step of producing
an actual output image that grabs the
lighting data from the lighting
information that we have produced and
then goes ahead and renders that image
out to the screen so we can see what we
would be looking at if we use this light
propagation to produce our final image
that way we'll know whether this is
close enough or whether we need to
really worry about that basic facing
Direction information because it may be
that the normals just aren't that
interesting in our particular game and
we don't need to worry about them when
we're convicting the light around and
instead what we should do is just
transport the light around as if there
were no facing directions and then when
we're done use the facing directions to
attenuate the light only when we go to
do our final sort of gather if you will
when we when we just take it and and
look at what that actually looks like
right so I don't know there's there's
like a thought for you it may be really
stupid and crappy thought but we'll play
around with it and see how it goes so
what I'm going to do is just introduce
our final shader which in theory I think
would be the last one we have because
you know unless we decide to do some
special effects in the future we might
have some traders that do special
effects but what that is is our final
result now needs to get a little bit
more fancy what we can probably do is
not actually write a whole new shader
what we can probably do is just tack
this on to our one of our final ones so
if you take a look at how our program is
currently working what you can see is
that we do this final stretch at the end
for example right and we also do this
this peel composite step at the end so
either one of these steps could grab the
lighting information and use it so what
I might suggest
is this peel composite which kind of is
the thing that right now takes all the
def peels and smushes them together what
we could do is take that peel composite
and instead of treating it as something
that's just designed to composite the
multi sample the the multiple samples of
depth together we could have that
compute the lighting at the same time
now there's number of benefits of doing
this one is that this gives us the
freedom to actually apply the lighting
differently depending on which depth
your app if we want to do that we can
and that's kind of powerful because it
means that we can spend more processor
time the GPU to get better lighting
results to take into account the depth
of the thing that we're lighting at the
time that we actually could posit it
that seems like a positive to me the
other thing that I like about that is
that since we're already in there and we
pull in all the data we can now just
pull in the extra lighting data as well
and at that point we're not doing a
whole nother path of grabbing everything
in to go ahead and compute that lighting
we're just pulling everything in once we
do it and we just put it forth and we're
done
and so I think then that is probably the
the more preferable way to approach the
problem it's the stuff everything into
the peeled composite and do it there so
with that in mind I think what I'm going
to do is take a look at that peel
composite and just see if I can extend
it to pull in the lighting data that it
will use to produce the results right so
if you take a look at we've got here we
have these the peel sampler one two
three now one of the things that I think
probably was a little bit of a mistake
if we're being honest with ourselves is
that probably what I should have done is
use a texture array for these samplers
because if I use a texture array then
what I could have done is picked out
either have appeals go on the texture
array each each array would be a each
array element would be a separate peel
or I could have had the array be the
information about the different pieces
right like the array slices Eero could
have been the color array slice one
would have been the immittance
array slice to
would have been the normal something
like this and so that is you know
something that I think maybe we could
have done a little bit better there I'm
not going to do that now and the reason
is because introducing a new thing like
texture raise leads to the bugging I
don't really want to be doing debugging
right now I'm just trying experiment so
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
expand these out for us just to have
more samplers because I think that's a
quicker way to do the experiment later
on we can try to turn that that crank
and optimize it down a bit
figure out where we could introduce
something like a texture arrays to
reduce the number of samplers to make
things less complex for the graphics
card for graphics cards that don't deal
well with things like that Intel
integrated graphics for example I think
has a little more heavyweight stuff
associated with samplers it's not like
in Nvidia cards where it's kind of just
a pointer and you know on video cards
it's not so clear to me that there's
that much of a win to doing stuff like
switching from multiple samplers to
texture arrays there probably is a
little bit but it's a lot less drastic
whereas I think there are certain cars
where that wind can be substantial don't
take my word for it I'm not a graphics
guy at all so that may be old news but
that's just my kind of thing with my
little like inclination my gut tingles
that sounds kind of gross but there you
go anyway so what I'd like to do here is
I just like to look at what we want to
pull in so what we're going to be
getting by default in these Keele
samplers is we're going to be getting
the surface reflectance which we
definitely want the best thing we're
going to be compositing but what I'd
also like to pull in at that point it's
probably been normal because the normal
is the thing that we're going to use for
the lighting is so we probably want to
pull in the OpenGL NPL value there right
this one right here so what I'd like to
do is take these and just augment them
to pull in the NPL for each of these as
well right
so we basically have an NPL sampler for
each of the of the things we previously
only had the peel sampler for so
something like this so we've got PL n PL
PL n PL PL PL p.m. PL right so we're
pulling each of those in and the other
thing we want to pull in is that that
lighting information right so we also
have that
to think about so anyway we've got each
of these peel samplers and now we've got
to compute the lighting information for
those what we want to do here is take a
look and see okay so we've got each of
these texture samples for the peel is
now going to become something that
lights each of these basically all of
this stuff here is fine but when we do
the actual after we we pull the lighting
in we've adjusted the RGB of it we're
going to want to do the operation to
produce the lighting somehow here right
so after we've done all of this stuff
right before we start using these peel
our GPS what I'd like to do is is
augment them all so we basically want to
do like a lighting operation on our peel
where we pass you know actually I guess
that's the MPL sampler I I could I guess
just take the samples here as well like
so so that samples from everything and
now we have our peel and our NPL from
each of those when we take this these
samples what I want to do after we've
adjusted their RGB is basically modify
them using the NPL value and the
lighting value right so we're going to
pass the NPL value we're going to pass
the peel value and we're going to pass
the light so we're going to have
something that looks like this which
adjusts each of the peels lighting like
so now we don't have to do it this way
we could instead try to composite and
then do the lighting but I'm just going
to do lighting on each of them first
instead because we might as well spend
more GPU time than less at first because
we can always go in and try to optimize
things later but we don't want to do
that at the outset because we won't know
if our optimizations are causing our
lighting to have artifacts that it
wouldn't otherwise have so we'd rather
try to do it as well as possible and
just slow first and
we can optimize it by removing things
and see whether they materially affect
the quality of the lighting that's
usually a better way to go when you're
trying to velop on your technique so we
need a couple things to happen here
first thing we need to happen here is we
obviously have the the light peel that's
going to happen here I guess this the
RGB does the Alpha value the Alpha
values are not used at all in this so I
suppose we could just use the the RGB
only here like so because again the
lighting is only operating on the color
it's not going to change the Alpha of
anything at least not at the moment so
when we do our light peel we're going to
do that operation
maybe I should pass the whole thing I
don't know it's hard to say but we're
going to take in a v3 and return of III
and the NPL value itself is that packed
before and then we're going to have a
lighting sample of some kind which is
some information that we're going to
need so I'm assuming the lighting sample
is going to need a couple different
things I probably shouldn't call it
light sample we're probably going to
have a little bit something more like
light P light Direction right so as the
light the light position of the light
normal are the two things we're probably
in half come to think of the light
positions kind of already factored out
so it's probably only just going to be
the light color and the light normal
right I'm guessing that's about it so
those are the two things we're probably
going to be taking in here so we'll go
ahead and just pass those along like so
and so what we're going to have for a
light normal and the light colors are
coming in here and then what we need to
do is we need to do a mapping so we've
basically got a you know I've got to
unpack the NPL data obviously to start
and in order to do that we have to do
our unpack
the unpack of course is pretty
straightforward it's this right here
what we might want to do is standardize
on this unpack because since multiple
people are unpacking at this point it
may be better to unpack it in a sane
single way because that way if we decide
to change it in the future we don't have
to worry about it at all week if we
could just know that's being done
correctly so what we could do here is
basically say you know V two and equal
something and have that unpack happen of
course I guess now that I think about it
we've got sort of two ways but I guess
it's something like this
unpack normal to something like this I
don't know what we really want to call
this but unpack
I think unpack normal two is probably
all I'm going to really get so
completely on it that so we'll do world
nxy and unpack normal two will just be
this thing and what we can do is we can
put that in our sort of global shader
header code which is this stuff right
here and everyone can use it so we can
have a v2 which is like unpack normal -
and we can take the incoming normal like
so and what I can do here is just say
well yeah the result X or better result
here and result Y are going to be equal
to these inputs scaled like so and then
we'll return that so now we can call
that unpack normal and what we can do is
furthermore we could have an unpack
normal three if we want to actually
generate the entire normal we could say
well if we want to do an unpack normal
three we pass the v2 we can get back the
the n2 from from the unpack here by
passing it this way and then what we can
do is generate that final value right so
we can say results equals N two and then
we just have the equation again for the
renormalized part so we can
just say em 2x times n 2x minus n 2y
times n 3y and that way we can get back
a full normal if we want to as well by
calling unpack normal 3 so we have a way
of getting either of those back when we
get back this normal like I said this is
just saying this is the same equation we
had before I see if I can find it for
you so here right
remember when we kind of solved this one
right oh it's got my square root glad I
just looked at that it's the same one
here only this one is reconstructing the
normal from to regular components if
that makes sense so I guess actually we
could we could actually keep this this
function could actually sort of be made
in it's doing almost exactly the same
thing right so we could in theory have
this one be reused as well because that
unpack normal 3 is almost the same code
I don't know that I really care about
doing that right now synaptically
complicated code but point being I just
want to at least for the most part have
everything in here be systematized so I
know that it's happening in one place
and happening the same way everywhere
and there aren't multiple people
unpacking normals in lots of different
ways right
so now when we actually go to pack this
put this into you know the floating
point buffer what we gotta actually have
the n2 which is the thing that actually
holds it now so if I want to do the
unpack here now I can actually do that
rather directly and since we want to
probably unpack that once what I'll
probably do there is just say we'll get
that when we actually do the the initial
sample oh I guess that the NPL is
actually the thing that we need to
unpack nevermind so we have to do that
every time in the light feel so here is
our like reflect normal that comes out
of the MPLS XY so in this case what we
want to do is say unpack normal 3
because I want the full like real normal
so after we unpack the normal we also
have to take our two lighting values so
we have our LT 0 with
cheese comes from the Z and our lp1
which comes from the W neither of those
is really going to use but we could then
use those for specular at some point in
the future right and so once we've got
that we're ready to compute an actual
lighting equation here and what we can
do to up to produce that letting
equation is just use the lighting we
were using before the kind of poopy
lighting we were using before so let's
go ahead and grab that I saved it it's
right here
so let's go ahead and drop that in good
and we essentially want to do that right
here after we've gotten the information
out right like that so in this case we
don't anymore have any of this sort of
like to camera from camera can of stuff
that's happening and the light strength
and light distance that's all the stuff
that's now handled by the lighting
system so really what we have now is
just the the sort of the dot product to
figure out how much the light and the
and the surface are aligned with each
other
and then of course we do have the
reflects the reflection vector kind of
stuff we still do have that computation
to do for the for the specular lighting
if that makes sense
but what we can do now as well is since
we have a diffuse coefficient and a
specular coefficient that we were using
for our lighting what we can do now is
take our LP zero and our LP one and we
can actually use those now as the
diffuse light specular light for example
so like I said the reason I wanted to
get some parameters in there and
actually is have a four-wide texture
that encodes the normal plus that it so
they knew we use it for something right
and so what I figured we do is just use
it for lighting framers right now since
we have a simple Phong thing here we can
just have diffuse and specular as the
two coefficients and off we go so if we
were to say that the fuse coefficient
was the Z and the specular coefficient
was the W then we can just get rid of
these and actually do this equation as
is so we'd have the diffuse coefficient
times the cosine of the angle times the
light strength and the spectral
coefficient times the reflection angle
in the light strength so that's all you
know exactly what we would want we sum
those two together and that's the light
that we transmit now technically the
diffuse and specular should not be
separate components so my guess is what
we'll do in the future is make these two
parameters be something else probably
one of them should really be like
because because in general you can't
just reflect out an arbitrary amount of
light the amount of light total amount
of light you reflect out should be
proportional to the light you take in
and it should be somewhat less than the
light you take in right no surface
reflects 100% of the light it takes n so
in general you know you can't just
arbitrarily set a diffuse and specular
coefficient it doesn't make any sense
so in the future we may want to play
around with that a little bit but let's
not get bogged down in that just yet
once we actually have better lighting
transport going then we can worry about
fine-tuning the lighting equation of the
final gathered so anyway what we need to
do now is tune these equations that we
have before to use the information that
we probably think we'll actually have
from the light transport which is not as
straightforward as what we had in the
past so in this case we're going to have
a thing that's basically like what
direction is the light coming from at
this point like what's the overriding
direction and so when we were doing that
before we have the two light thing here
and so what we're going to have is two
light is going to be this light end now
right like so and our reflection normal
is going to be this now why we were
doing this multiple times are not
entirely sure if we want to replicate
that out so we probably want to do
something here where we take yeah like
this this looks just kind of busted what
we really want to do is the like dot
term so the reflection dot term right we
do is in your product here
let's do this so the inbound lighting
direction in our reflection direction we
want to negate that because the way this
was phrase originally was the direction
that goes out to the light source and in
this case we're probably going to end up
with a thing that says where the light
source is pointing towards us right so
we're probably gonna have to use a
negative in terms of the light normal at
this point and then we're going to have
the reflection direction that's actually
just correct we're going to adopt those
two together to see how coincident those
two are and that's the information that
we actually need for our rest in ER at
that point we're going to clamp this
because obviously we don't want to split
that here we don't want this to go
negative
you can't have negative light well you
probably could in the real world
some scientists summer probably has
figured out how to create negative
negative light but in most things we
observe there is no negative light so we
want to clamp that to zero so that we
don't contribute a negative value so
here's our cosine angle term and it'll
be used down here in the diffuse
lighting we could if we want to sort of
make this a little bit clearer by there
having the diffuse like computation
interior specular like computation so
here we go so now we've got our total
light that's the sum there so now we
have to figure out here in our specular
light we've got to figure out how to get
the two camera right so that's that's
how do we get the world P out of this
basically and that's probably something
that's going to be half - that's going
to have to be passed in here right so
this is going to be something that's
going to have to be passed to the actual
light peel itself because there's really
no way to get that information without
being outside and knowing more having
more inputs than this so we're going to
have to pass that in and so here's our
reflection vector the negative two
camera plus two times the dot I don't
know why I was typing dot set of our
inner they're the same thing but I
usually use my own terminology so then
we've got our world normal which in this
case is just the reflection
remote we've got the two camera which is
getting passed in and again we've got
that reflection normal here we've then
got our cosine reflection angle this is
the reflective exit the reflection
vector which is basically the reflection
of the of the camera out so then we take
a look at the the dot product of that
one again I don't know why we phrased it
that way so this is the the ref BEC dot
here and maybe what I'll call this is
speck inner and this diffuse inner so
that's really all we're talking about
here again we've got sort of a negative
light end maybe I should just go ahead
and say to light equals negative light N
and then I can leave these phrase
without the negative like so probably
not worth it like probably what I should
do is just a negate the inner product
because that's what's coming in and it
saves some computations but what are
going to do I'm going for cleanliness at
this point and ease of readability later
on we can talk about if we need to do
anything that the compiler can't itself
do in the shader to make things faster
all right so here's us computing the
reflection vector you can see it's
fairly straightforward we've got the
spectacular inner term now and we can
now create our vector of that and then
at the end we don't need to clamp this
because we already did that right here
we've got our power write our specular
power now this is something that we're
probably going to want to I think
there's a pal basically
for doing specular you can see it right
here so you can basically say you want
to raise this thing to this power
instead what I think we probably want to
do here is actually do something like
Coast rectangle equals pal
[Applause]
where we can take in the coast ref angle
and put in a power so in this case it
was one two three four five six seven
eight nine something like that right so
eight or nine power we can just put that
in there and the reason that we want to
do that is this is probably going to be
the way we're going to do our lighting
parameters in the future right so
probably in fact let's just do it that
way right now so let's say we have a
specular power that's going to be MP LW
and let's say that our specular
coefficient is just 1 minus the diffuse
coefficient now that's probably not
correct love to think about that so
we'll think about that a little bit more
but let's just say that this is a
diffusive ount so the specular amount is
just the inverse of actually you know
it's basically a complimentary amount
and so at that point you know we're just
sort of producing the the diffuse color
the specular color as a linear blend
basically right and we can even phrase
it that way if we wanted to add Zoeller
p-- but here's it a few slight and the
specular light coefficients together and
now the co thrift angle instead we can
put in the secular power as an actual
function which means we can have
services that get tighter or wider
reflections coming on them right
so we'll you know we'll sort of deal
with that a little bit later on so once
we have the total light we need to
compute an actual result color so the
peel cord that comes in what we're going
to do is modulate the total lighting
amount by that however we have to
remember that the total lighting value
at this point is actually not quite a
same value because we're saying that
lighting is going to kind of have a
maximum and I believe we said max light
power here I want to sort of define this
as a global variable that we can tune
however
we want and the way this is going to
work is we're going to say what the
MaxLite power is and I guess we'll call
it max light intensity maybe and so what
I want to do here is the max light
intensity is going to be something that
we're going to divide out now what this
basically is and because we haven't
gotten to this point yet and maybe in
the future we'll play around with it a
little bit I don't know but essentially
what we're doing here is like a poor
person's tone mapping right so typically
what happens in systems when you're
dealing with any kind of realistic
lighting at all which we're not really
even doing but we're just taking it
we're taking it far enough that we're
sort of stepping into this realm where
it becomes relevant what we need to do
is the total lighting value at this
point needs to be adjusted to the fact
that it was a much higher range than it
was when then the zero to one range we
actually render so at some point when
we're done we have to take these
lighting values that may be like eight
or nine nine point six might be a light
value right we have to shrink those down
to the zero to one range so we want to
do is take that total lighting amounts
and map it in some way that makes some
kind of sense now there's a lot of ways
that we could do that but we have to be
careful because if all we did is a
linear mapping what you can see if we do
a linear mapping let me try to
demonstrate the problem here note that
the web browser okay there we go um so
what we get let's see here ah go back we
go nope Milton Milton
bring me your there we go alright so gay
398 light about you mapping so what
we're going to have is in our system
we're just going to have something which
it has to map sort of these linear light
values to alpha values right so what
we're going to have is something that
takes you know our output value we know
that it is constrained between 0 and 1
because even if you have a high dynamic
range monitor you're still talking about
some range that can display where 0 is
the darkest thing can put on the screen
and 1 is the brightest thing can put on
the screen but nothing you can pass it
an arbitrarily high value to this
monitor it's never going to get any
brighter than the brightest value right
so when the deck when you finally get to
the point okay it's not back anymore
right it's all digital when you get to
the point where you're actually driving
the o LED right there's some maximum on
and maximum off signals if you can send
to adjust what the element what the
actual element is putting out so when we
talk to that monitor we're just talking
about a range of 0 to 1 where zero is
the darkest and 1 is the brightest
that's all we can do so we don't have
infinite levels of brightness like the
universe sort of does the Sun versus a
lamp in my room the difference between
these two things is so incredibly vast
and really there's not a lot of limits
on how much photons can be flowing per
unit time in a given area now in
theoretical physics I'm sure they
figured out that there is some limit
like there probably you can't have an
infinite number of photons in an
infinitely small space I'm guessing but
what do I know I'm a programmer I don't
study physics I have no idea maybe you
can but what we definitely know is our
monitors definitely can't
so our monitors are only producing
illuminate out of photon
and this is the maximum amount that they
can produce and this is when they
produce the minimum amount so what we
need to do is take our conceptually
infinite values because we can set a
floating point value to things that are
absurdly high right and so we need to
figure out a range our floating point
values and so that's in our case zero to
whatever MaxLite power is it's just an
arbitrary value right and then what we
need to do is we need to take whatever
this MaxLite power is and we need to map
it to the zero to one range in some way
that makes sense and typically what we
want to do is we don't want this to be a
straight linear mapping because our
light power is something that makes
sense only in the units of our light
simulation in the game in our case is
completely arbitrary because we're doing
purely artistic lighting but even in a
game where you were doing physically
accurate lighting it's going to be in
something like lumens or photons or
something you're going to have a number
that has nothing to do with the monitors
brightness level it's not going to be
zero to one it's going to be some other
value that doesn't relate at all to
monitor gamma or any of these other
sorts of things so what you need to do
is then take that you need to map it
into the visible range of the monitor
using something that gets you an image
that you want and so typically what you
want to do is do something that looks
maybe you know here is like the linear
mapping this mapping is not going to be
very good the reason it's not going to
be very good is because if you imagine
that lighting fall-off is nonlinear and
you're going to get these sort of very
very high values in the locus of a
bright light and then anything that
reflects that light is going to be
drastically lower you end up with a
scene where you can't see anything other
than the lights right because reflected
light is down here thanks to the inverse
square law and emitted light values are
up here right and you don't want to have
a scene where the lights are infinitely
brighter than everything else around
them that's not artistically satisfying
is not going to produce a very
interesting game that may be an accurate
representation of how much light is
somewhere if you're doing physical light
simulate you may even be right it's just
not satisfying it's why people pick
different types of film it's why CCD
sensors on cameras are adjust in certain
ways it's why we have tone mapping
in saturation and all these other sorts
of adjustments we do so you want here
some kind of what's called a response
curve and what you're doing here is
you're sort of simulating filmic
response or something else if you're
putting video camera at something or
your eyes response curve the way your
brain maps the number of photons that
hit something in your cells right those
sorts of things you want to come up with
a mapping tier that makes them sense and
typically that mapping probably looks
something like this right which is to
say that you know somewhere inside where
we expect the reflected light to largely
be we're going to have that take up most
of the 0 to 1 range and then just the
top end of it is going to account for
the rest just you know 0.92 1 is going
to like account for all the rest of that
that that area like you know from 2 to
max power or something something like
this right and so in order to do
something like that like we want a curve
that's very bowed out right so we want a
curve that's more of like a square root
curve or something like this or a
multiple square root curve to do that
mapping to kind of flatten it out now if
you're really doing this stuff seriously
right and not we're just going to hack
one in now maybe we'll do a better one
later I don't know but if you're doing
this stuff more seriously then typically
what you end up doing here is you end up
studying other plastic response curves
to construct something that's a good
approximation to one of those so for
example one thing you might do is study
the filmic response curves of classic
Kodak film stocks used to film great
movies right because there is a whole
industry that spent all of its time
trying to come up with chemical
prophecies that would produce good
looking images for cinema that's very
similar to what we want to do so taking
a look at their response curves is a
great way to figure out a curve that
will map lighting simulation that might
have something to do with the real world
into something artistically Pleasant so
what you'll do you know if you're
looking at the responses you'll take a
look at what the actual measured
physical physical response curves were
of real Kodak film stock or other kinds
of great film stock and you'll piecewise
fit polynomials to them to approximate
them just classic functional
approximation Theory nothing fancy just
basic fitting of a polynomial to some
data points kind of a thing and then
you'll use that to translate your
incoming values we're not going to do
that obviously because again like I said
that's getting a little bit out of the
scope of what we might want to do here
on handmade Hiro but just so you know
that's something you can do that's what
high-end rendering does and furthermore
it often gives the artist the ability to
tweak those curves to their liking what
we're going to do instead is just
something approximate I'm just going to
use probably a simple square root curve
that's not great we may want to do
something a little better later on but
we're going to do something like that so
I'm going to first divide by the MaxLite
power to put it in the zero to one range
and then I'm going to bump that curve up
by like gamma inge it up a bit like
square rooting it up a little bit or
something like this and we can play with
that curve all we want to produce
something more reasonable later if it's
so su stuff so here what I'm going to do
is going to take that light in and
whenever we get the light end what I'm
going to do is I'm going to take light n
divided by max light power for light
intensity rather which that fails us to
the zero to one range or at least you
know it presumably does we we will then
do a clamp 0 1 on that to produce a
value that's reasonable this should have
been a clamp here one as well I don't
know why it isn't so we're doing clamp 0
1 on that value seconds the value
between 0 and 1 and then what we want to
do again like I said is just just adjust
it a little bit here I'll put that as a
separate thing let's say we do a squirt
of the light end here and like I said we
can do that as many times as we want if
we want to bump that curve up or down if
you want to flatten the curve to do it
the other way around which I don't think
we do but if we did we could swear it
such and so forth alright so assuming
that we're doing that right and we
figure out something's good here again
this might have to be really flattened
out and what you can do you know you can
imagine this like let's say we go to
Wolfram al
or we could even just I think Google
will do this if we just say graph X
graph square root of x I think it'll
just draw it for us so you can see that
curve there if we double square root it
that's probably more what we're looking
for right like something that has a
pretty steep curve like that you know
but again probably what we really want
is is more let's make sure we're looking
at the the right range so here's the
zero to one part of this right I don't
know how to there we go
so yet you know is that is that really
what we want probably not like we
probably want this part here to be a
little more linear and not so attenuated
so I don't know but we do like this kind
of long curve here so yeah like can we
do better than this absolutely I'm just
not 100% sure what the quick and easy
way would be to do so but again we're
just going to leave that for the moment
and we will come back to that later when
we need to right when we need to sort of
make that a little bit more reasonable
right okay oops that's that's white n I
want white see I don't want to do that
to the normal image that to the color I
so we need to sample light see and light
in here those are values I'd say we need
to grab and they're both view threes and
so those will be texture samples from
the lighting information that we have
when we sample the light n we will be
getting that pretty much from the the
bezel mostly coming from different
textures let's see here
and really because we have
front-and-back admission at the moment I
suppose we technically could sample to
light values here if you wanted to I'm
not sure that we need to just yet but
it's yeah maybe we should right let's
see what the
let's think about this so when we do
light peel here we essentially have to
compute sort of to this equation twice
one for each light if that makes sense
so what we could do is just add those
two together fairly straightforwardly
actually so if we wanted to here we
could do something where we did this
where we actually took the two lights
the front and the back that the two the
two lights that we were getting and and
combined them together right
I'm going to hold off on that because we
need to keep thinking this through and I
feel like we're going to progress the
letting couple of our times over the
next few weeks so I'm going to hold off
on that just yet
because I think we've got a ways to go
and I don't want to overdo it so I'm
just going to stick with one first and
then we'll kind of start pushing that
stuff a little bit further later as we
go right so here's our light peel we
know we need to pass to camera here like
so and actually this reminds me of
something I wanted to try so let me go
ahead and compile this I wanted to know
something about these here Docs one of
the problems that we have as you've
noticed is we don't get any indentation
on these because for coder thinks
they're strings because hey guess what
they are strings I was wondering if
there might be some way to fix that
and I I just kind of had this
harebrained idea and I don't know if it
actually works so I don't know much
about the these aren't actually sweet
bustled tear ducts they're actually the
other kind of string
there's two things in people's plus
there's the here doc ones which are
actual here docs and then there's the
c++ extended string thing I don't know
why they have both exactly but they do
there maybe was a reason forward it may
just be one of those C++ things that
they messed it up the first time and
then they made another one that's
probably also messed up it's and I got
too messed up versions now there which
works but either way that's what we've
got right now and I was wondering could
you do a pound to find that contained as
a shared occupation in it or sorry not
the here doc whatever you want to call
it right like could you do something
that included that in the pound define
like so like open string or like shader
string and then it was like or I guess
even we don't even really need the name
I guess we'd do it like this
begin shader string annotator string
something like that um it's
and I don't know it looks like for kotor
has a lot of trouble with that I don't
know if this is the correct
interpretation of this maybe that the
problem is that you can't put this in a
pound defying but I would say like if
you could put it in the pound to find
then what you could do is you could use
the pound to find instead of this so
that this would still have indentation
right I was just curious if that would
be possible I don't know if it is or not
though let's let's just find out if I
can even compile it nope what I'm not
sure what exactly that practice could
undeclared in the FIR I'm assuming that
basically what happened here is that
this just gets skipped out on so I'm
assuming what happens here is that you
can't put it into a macro so oh well
right I don't think there's anything you
can do about it if you can't put into a
macro I would just have this faint
feeling I was like I wonder if there's
some way we could do something there but
it doesn't look like we can the other
thing I was thinking is could you put a
pound in clued in if it has like no bit
of the panic that would be part of the
string so you can't even import stuff
into it so unfortunately the only way
we'll ever get it is if we decide to
load these out of a file separately
essentially so ask for reps which we
could do it's not it not the end of the
world anyway so off we go we've got the
light peel competition in here
we need to sample these from somewhere
so what we need is our light sampler
like our light color in our contemporary
Lechem sampler
[Applause]
and that so the color sampler and the
normal sampler are both going to just
sample from the lighting computation
that we had and the light normal is
actually is going to be the NPL texture
for the lighting which again this one
right here with the depth so this is
really the light NP so and I guess this
is the emit sampler like so so to get
the light see out of that we have to do
an unpack of of these values right and
in order to do that again we need to do
a like sort of an extend of V extend and
again we can just make this this is
probably the part where it's good to
pull this out pops oops so light N
equals like extend or a send one will be
something like that where I can
basically pass in the X Y and get back
the version with the Z being the 1 minus
square root so if I do something like
that then that also gives me the way to
do the thing I wanted to do before which
is make all of these be things that
operate that way so here's the v2 n in
this case and basically what we're
talking about here is you don't have to
do the unpack you just do this because
the other two values are correct and so
at that point this function becomes
extends normal V of unpack normal 3 or 2
rather of n right so that way we can do
all the different versions of it
so here we do reconstruct normal for the
v3 really all we're doing when we pass
the NP there is this is just that normal
extent so this is just going to be via T
result equals extend normal Z and P XY
and then that's it so now that
computation has been pulled out which is
good now thankfully last time we did a
thing where we we took out the sort of
the sampling stuff and made it automatic
so that we don't really have to do too
much work to extend the fact that we've
got a bazillion samplers in this
particular situation here so what I want
to do inside this is I want to get my
light emits sampler and my light and
piece ampler and I also need to do these
peel and peak NPL samplers so just want
to get all of those assigned here so
it's like this sort of a thing and then
we've got a light emit sampler and the
light in P sampler and so all of those
samplers will now get linked up in
theory automatically for us which is
nice because again it was a pain in the
butt to do those all the time so it's
nice that we kind of made it automatic
and so what we need to do at that point
is we need to actually load it all up
because yeah we got them bound now but
that doesn't really help us because we
have to actually put them in here
somewhere
right so what we're going to end up with
here is we're going to end up with a
double bind if you will so we've kind of
got got this situation where we need to
do two binds for each of these so we're
going to actually bind two textures for
every peel
like so we're going to have to bind the
basic surface color 1 but then we're
also going to have to bind the end the
the NPL one right so once we read those
two things now we've got all of those
bound we still have to bind at the end
two more textures we've got to bind the
two textures from the lighting solution
so we're going to have to do something
like this
and at some point that becomes a little
bit owners so maybe we even just want
to do something like that where every
time through here we just say the heck
with it find them all right
and so yeah I don't think we actually
need to unbind these the way that we
were doing those before so I'm going to
actually get rid of those so what we
need to do here is we just need to make
sure that we're binding the light
solution here so that's going to be from
the OpenGL light buffers and so the
OpenGL light buffers we're going to take
that base level solution that we you
know quote-unquote created which we
really haven't created yet but which we
have sort of a dummy
you know crappy thing in right now and
we're just going to take the front emit
for the emission and we're going to take
the NP for the NP right and that's it
all right now we probably have a ton of
stuff to deal with error wise so let's
get started
that's not helpful but we can take a
look at the actual error here skip over
that statement let's take a look yes I
know okay under pending for a light F
that is not good there should not be an
undercard NFI are obviously light weight
F so that's the light strength there and
the light strength in this case is just
the light C all right let's recompile
that there I'll go see if there's
anything else I don't know another to
camera so in this case we have to have
two camera in here and that we haven't
determined yet so at the moment we'll
need to compute this based on the camera
and the fragment UV coordinate which we
don't actually know yet so what we'll do
here is we'll just because we need to
use the depth value at each individual
point to determine that to determine how
far away the thing is I suppose although
well I guess no we don't actually care
because this two camera is a normal
vector so actually we know just from the
UV what it actually is so that we don't
actually need the depth to compute that
so we know that it's you know the
normalized version of like the frag UV
and we just need to know the fov in
order to compute it so for right now
I'll I'll pretend that it's just the Z
vector pointing upward but we will be
able to generate that
in the future for real and we won't need
to read from the depth buffer to do it
out thing
let's see cannot convert a high GP
vector of float this is new new matching
overloaded function found for PAL okay
oh yes that's right
that Pao I think I accidentally put it
after the VM yeah this is supposed to be
on the spec in ER that was good good
let's grew up so let's see connecting
for work to float to high through so
we've got a four to three down sample
problem there I don't know where but we
will try to figure it out probably right
here
[Applause]
and so now we have to go ahead and
actually see what this does in order to
see what it does we're going to need a
way to look at the actual output of the
game but I probably want to do is have
some way of looking at the debug light
buffers as a parameter so like we can
switch between viewing the debug buffers
and not doing the debug buffers you can
see not particularly impressive here
this is not a good result say the least
that is a pure black screen but so let's
debug that first but then it would be
nice to switch between those so let's
put in something that we can use to
switch between them so here's compiled
FPL lighting the compiled FQ lighting
path
I'm sorry not compute to feel lighting
that's not actually what I want I want
the peel compiled peeled composite I so
the compiled peel composite we have to
make sure that this is actually doing
something vaguely vaguely correct in
order to do that the first thing I want
to do is figure out am I getting are all
of these samplers actually getting bound
properly because I have no idea they are
right I have no idea so the first thing
I would like to do is turn off any
computation whatsoever so let's just see
whether we're even sampling these peel
values correctly at all
so okay so that looks right so at least
we know that the peel compositing is
working just fine so it's just the other
part of our sampling that aren't working
so let's go ahead and get rid of this
and go up and work on the light peel
function I'm going to start with the
simplest possible thing just to make
sure there isn't anything too stupid
going on which is I'm just going to have
a total light set to one so I should see
the same result here that I saw before
and I do so that's all we really need to
know now we we know that we've got
problems in here so let's start working
on making those correct so first thing
I'm going to do is I'm going to go ahead
and say
that we will just light based on the the
normal and we won't try to do any other
part of the lighting equation right so
let's take the lighting coefficient out
of the equation so let's just say we
have a light C or actually you know we
can double it up
we can even say let's assume that the
light normal is just pointing straight
down and let's assume that the light is
fulbright so what we should see here is
we should see a fairly consistent image
now that doesn't have any real problems
to it right it should look roughly
correct that the same as what we had it
does right now there is a little bit of
weirdness there something that doesn't
make a whole lot sense to me
the normals for the reflection for the
peel itself should have been doing some
kind of attenuation there but they
didn't and I'm not sure why because
again eat regardless of whether we're
doing specular or diffuse we should have
had oh well you know what if we would
know but either way the reflectance
normal is going to vary in this case and
we should have seen that variance
occurring but we didn't so what I'd like
to do is let's actually try something
else first before we go any further
let's try taking the result and let's
just write out what the normal is at all
right so let's take say the NPL and
write out the NPL directly
right so here's our NPL and so this
obviously is varying which is what we
expect and which is good right so now
let's try taking the dot product and
doing something there so let's suppose
we took our to light which is just the
negative of the light end and let's
inner product that with the ref normal
that we got back from unpack normal
three and I guess the other well you
know what let's do this let's actually
do ref N and see what that looks like
maybe that functions busted parse error
what's that typo there
yeah so this is there the ref n this
does not look good
so I think we've got a problem there
here's the NPL we called unpack normal
three on the NPL the NPL should have
been more sane in that so let's take a
look at what we're getting here let's
take a look at unpack normal three and
see what the issue is
so unpack normal three calls unpack
normal to unpack normal two takes that n
in and does the unpack on it
that's the pack so this is just a
straight-up bug on my part
yeah this is the pack this is just be
pack normal - I don't know what I was
thinking this is the unpack so I'm just
stupid
it's basically what this boils down to
so let's try that one more time so in
this this right here should be the the
pack from the unpack rather it's that
code right there and where are we doing
that nxny or whoops so I think that's
all we want to do they're sort of the
nxny and there is no in in here so that
shouldn't conflict so now we actually
have the actual unpack normal - which is
what I actually wanted right
these actually pack normal - and this is
unpack novelty
[Applause]
so unpack normal - it actually does this
operation pack normal - does this our
operation so that should now be more
what we were expecting
unclear infer NPL right you are here we
go cannot go right from float to - can
picture of floats unpack normal -
also correct that quite an XY all right
there we go now we're looking much more
sane that's more what I wanted to see
all right so now our normals are looking
what we looking more like what we want
so I can take go back to taking the
lighting Craig in there let's take a
look okay so let's take a look at what
happens if we well I guess what I can do
now is let's see what we're looking at
for the actual equation now with the
light normal and the light color like
locked in so that still doesn't seem to
vary by the normal at all which is a
little weird so let's keep going let's
take the result and we'll make the
result be equal to the diffused inner
product and what we should see here is
that the you know when things are tilted
we should see when things are tilted we
should see them have a difference right
and that looks roughly correct
[Music]
at least I think it does
I'm really happy with it at least so
let's take a look at what happens here
we also I guess have to look at the
specular and remember the specular has
been raised to a power as well alright
well that answers that question so it's
the second er we probably have the
diffuse coefficient set to zero right
now because lt0 is not such anything in
particular we could reverse these and it
has the diffuse but for now let's let's
just take a look at why the specular is
sort of in the state to depend what
happens if I don't raise it to the power
if it's just the power part yeah so it's
just the power part that's that's
operating in an unusual fashion I'm not
sure why that would be the case
probably because maybe specular power is
zero in this case so we probably want
specular power as W is going to range
from zero to one so we need the specular
power to mean something else you
probably want the specular power to be
something like you know oh well you know
it's it's anything from 1 up to 16 or
something like this right or in this
case 17 let's try 16 right and in this
case 2 we sort of have a situation where
I don't even know why it would bother
with these because if you want the
surface to be diffuse you could just set
the specular power to zero and get that
oh no you could because it's still
directional again right um that's fine
all right so now I think we're at least
closing in on something
semi saying barely so here we go
so now at least we're getting you know
quote-unquote lighting from a fake light
source not any real light source so
let's go ahead and take the light color
out of out of it and see what we get
here by having the the regular light
color and we get nothing so that is less
than inspiring to say that to say the
least and I'm not sure exactly why we're
not getting anything there we're
sampling from the emission I guess
here's a question have I made sure I
actually computed those buffers yet
because I may not have ah yeah so
obviously we have to compute the light
transport that has to happen and we
weren't doing that so we can get rid of
fake seed lighting now because that's
not actually something that needs to
occur
so we can get rid of that okay I guess
it's just just that like so and compute
light transport just needs to happen
higher up the pipeline right so before
we do anything further when we're going
to do this result here we need to have
computed the lighting prior to this
operation you know I'm saying so like
right here before anything else happens
the light transport has to be handled at
that time all right
so now you can see we at least have some
of you know we have something happening
right
but it's not obviously anything that we
would want to choose yet and I guess one
of the other problems we have with this
just looking at it is the lighting
artifacts come through in like the in
the actual final image which is a little
bit of a bummer as well so I'd have to
think about how we're going to address
that that's obviously going to be
something we need to figure out but
anyway let's go ahead and finish this
off by taking the light normal as well
which I don't think is going to really
do anything but we might as well get to
the point like I said where everything
is sort of floating improperly and then
we can talk about how to start improving
this to make it look like something we
actually want so let's see here on steel
composite when we come through here I'm
not going to nerf the light normal
anymore
so will will actually have the light
normal be meaningful or at least semi
meaningful that does not look reassuring
what is wrong with our light normal
oh well part of the problem with our
light normal yeah at this point is that
the lighting calculation just doesn't do
anything interesting that the direction
the light is actually pointing so now
that I think about that that's really
not super useful either right because
really the light is always going to be
coming in from for any given pixel the
normals going to be the same because we
don't currently wait the normals when we
average them together so that's not
going to be helpful at all right so
that's that is a non that is a non
useful thing at the moment yeah so we
have to kind of nurse this if we want
anything to happen there does that make
sense
[Applause]
all right so but we did do what we
wanted to do which is to say that we
have a way of now mapping the letting
results out into the actual game render
we just don't have a way of doing it in
anything that looks nice right so our
next job is to sort of start to try and
improve what we're actually computing
for lighting in this case so what we
want to do now is have a way we can
switch to our lighting buffers so that
we can see what they're actually
computing at any given time and a in
order to do that let's go ahead and make
it so that the code at the end here
which sort of copies things to the frame
buffer let's go ahead and make that be
predicated on the debug light buffer
text index so the debug life by protect
index thing we just want there to be in
the win32 where we where we sort of have
this light buffer tech index up and down
bit I don't really know at the moment
how we're restricting that oh here we
are this is the clamp right here so what
I'd like to do there is I'd like to say
okay get the OpenGL debug light buffer
index is greater than zero then we'll go
through this path and when we go through
this path we'll clamp it to
I guess it's really honestly this one
it's the it's the debug light buffer
text index is really the what we want if
that's greater than zero then yet then
what we will do is we'll come through
here we'll clamp these and we'll say
that this goes from zero to four instead
of from zero to three and then when we
actually use the light buffer tech index
here we will just subtract one from it
so that zero now means we're not viewing
any of them so I think then at that
point what we can do
oops
so the problem here is the clamp
if the clamp we need to do the clamp
first because if it's out of range value
yeah
then we need to make sure that we don't
get into that routine but why is it
saying it's an invalid enum how do we we
shouldn't ever be able to pass anything
that we weren't passing before because
debug like buffer tech index in this
case it has to be greater than zero to
get in here to begin with so the fact
that I'm subtracting one from it should
not produce any values that it wasn't
previously producing I should think and
then at the end the GL REE buffer call
of GL or attachment zero should never
like that should always be legal so
where are we when this happens what's
what's happening here it's this one
I take it let's double check so we come
in here yes so it's actually just this
call the GL Reid buffer call so I guess
we just can't call that if we haven't
downed a frame buffer yet I don't know
I'm just I thought we already were doing
that but I guess not
so here we can switch between our
Lighting's I'm going to switch which one
is shifted and which ones not so now
shift plus and minus axis goes up the
levels of detail but here you can see
the different buffers now right so
there's like the lighting buffer and
there's the final buffer that we produce
and you can see in here like I don't
know what is happening with that that
showing through there that that's sort
of artifacting I can't quite tell
exactly what is causing that that which
is a little concerning
my guess is it's an overflow issue but I
just now I think I can't really think of
how it is an overflow issue because in
theory the peel composite is always
clamping everything so I'm not sure how
it could actually do that unless the
diffuse plus specular light equation
actually blows out to higher than it
should we could try just to see but I
don't I'm not optimistic that that has
anything to do with it yeah it doesn't
so in theory let's just verify that this
is correct because I want to make sure
so in theory if I was cannot call any of
the lighting code I should get a
correctly composited pretty image right
with no none of those artifacts and I do
I just want to make sure it's strictly
in the lighting and it looks like it is
so that's all I really need to know and
then we're okay moving forward because
the lighting has is the thing that we're
working on anyway right however I do see
some Sparkle ease like I see some
Sparkle ease in here that I don't
remember seeing much of in the past that
might just be because of the down
sampling
but anyway so as long as I know that all
this stuff is based on the the
delighting then that's okay because
that's the thing that we're working on
anyway so I don't mind too much about
that so what we need to do now is take a
look at this equation and see right with
what we want a sample in this case so a
couple things come to mind here right
when we take a look at what we're
sampling for something like the specular
coefficient the specular coefficient
really wants to sample directly from the
like the actual reflection to a certain
extent right and the degree to which
it's going to sample the width sort of
that sampling is going to be based on
the power so let's just talk about that
a little bit here in terms of what we
want to have going forwards also I don't
remember what time do will we be ending
it like 15 minutes
is that correct I want to say we'll be
ending and picking this then this thing
I have a way to tell me that you guys
have fancy stuff that you've made 31
minutes until Q&amp;A so I actually have
half an hour okay good all right so what
I was trying to say there was I so in
terms of diffuse mapping we want to
sample the whole hemisphere of incoming
light right and the only thing we really
need to do to that hemisphere is we need
to attenuate it based on the facing
angle so like you know the amount of
light we get from something here in
terms of its ability to diffuse outwards
is going to be modulated by the cosine
of the angle which diminishes is close
to zero at this point right
but we are trying to take in all of this
nonetheless so even though things out on
the very fringe contribute less light
than they would otherwise
we definitely still want a sample pretty
much everything whereas a specular we're
talking about something where we're
sampling only within a cone that's kind
of going out into that into that
learning Hemisphere so in the best of
all possible worlds what we would be
able to do is we'd be able to sample
different resolutions of stuff so what
we'd want to sample in this case is we'd
want to be able to take the direction
that we want to look in and we'd want to
be able to take a sample that was all of
the incoming light across the whole
Hemisphere and somehow modulate it right
by the cosine incidence term which you
know maybe that's pie in the sky forget
it whatever but that's what we would
want in an ideal world so when we go to
do something like this we want to take a
very average sample and the tricky part
about this the reason that it's so
annoying to try and figure out how to do
it is in at every location that we might
want to sample it we then are therefore
responsible for coming up with some
measure of how the light is flowing
through in all directions right that's
the tricky part of the problem so we end
up it yet in a situation where we are
trying to find a lighting direction at
any given point we're trying to find
like which directions the light is
coming from and how much light is coming
from each of those directions and we
don't really have like I said we haven't
really quite cracked the problem of how
we're going to do that I kind of played
around with some ways that we might do
it but we don't really have it quite yet
and and furthermore for the specular we
want to do a similar query but we want
to restrict the range so you know if you
imagined
we had a cube map
at every pixel right like magically we
just had a cube map at every pixel
somehow then what we would be doing is
for this case for the specular case we
would take the N Smith level right
whatever the int mist level of that cube
map was averaged down down down down we
would take the intimus level of that
cube map and we sample it and the N
would be based on the specular power so
the wider the specular power the further
end we would take and for the diffuse we
would take the final MIT map the one
where each of these is basically just a
solid color right and that's effectively
what we would do and I don't really
quite yet know how we're going to get to
that level of lighting simulation what I
do know is that we need to start
treating our inner light simulation we
need to start treating the direction the
light is coming from as something that
we're properly aware of because right
now we're really not quite doing that
we're just kind of averaging things
together in a haphazard way and we're
not even weighting the average by the
contribution the immittance the e
mittens at all so the first thing that I
would probably say is let's let's just
take a brief look at how that would work
I'm just going to start playing with
this again I have no plan here I'm
literally just experimenting to see
where we can go with this I don't have
any plan whatsoever so let's let's look
at the the multi grid up
so here you can see how we're doing
multi light up the way that multi light
up works is it just takes a texture
sample from each of the locations and by
Linear's them together right so this
texture call right here will take the
four neighboring textiles from whichever
sample it is and it will it'll just go
ahead and and give you back that value
right now that isn't really what we want
to do in this case right what we want to
do is something smarter here where we're
actually talking a little bit more about
how the admittance is flowing through
and so we have a couple different ways
we could do this like I was saying for
and I'm not sure which of them is really
the right way to go I kind of started
down the route of doing the sort of
imaginary occlude imaginary like disks
that reflect and shadow but I just don't
know if that's a plausible way to
continue through it especially because
we sort of don't have a very 3d scene
and we have that sealing problem where
the reflect we would need at least a
sandwich layer of things to reflect down
because otherwise we just have a ground
and no light will ever bounce around so
that it can't bounce off of anything
right so we kind of have a nasty problem
in that sense and I don't know so I feel
like we need something happier we need
something that treats the light more
like a fluid than a then real light in a
way so that it kind of just flows out
from things and we just want to kind of
stop it from flowing in areas where
there's tall stuff and let it flow in
areas where there's not or something
like this and I'm just not sure exactly
what that wants to look like but what I
would say here is
that we obviously want I think to start
having the downsample be more controlled
than this and the problem with doing
that is right now we are not really
we're not power of two at all and that's
not great
so I don't know if maybe we should try
to force to a power of two I'm not sure
how effectively we could do that right
now
let's take a look at what it would take
to do that and then see if we can do a
straight power of two down sample so we
can reliably just pick of four and and
move move down by forest although we may
need to do something a little fancier
but I'm just curious so if the texture
with and the texture height for our
light buffers were not we're not the
base on the render with the render
height in this case what would it look
like there so let's suppose that what we
did instead was say okay we're going to
take the next power of two down so we're
going to say that we we want to
basically bits can thing and take
whatever the highest bit is that set
that's with all zeros is going to be the
that's going to be the the accuracy with
which we're computing the lighting so
taking a look at that let's say we did
that we had a bit skin
maybe not so we do we have fine least
significant bits that I don't really
remember why we were using it what did
we use this for ah okay so we just
wanted to fight when we were looking at
the thing for reading in a BMP that's
that's what we were doing all right well
there you go
so what we really want to do is do the
bit the opposite of this right so you
want to do something like this
[Applause]
I'm assuming there is a bit scan back
and here I'd guess it eventually so
there we go I believe this will work
correctly testicle 31 well you know what
looks good this way
all right so assuming that we can call
this now we should be able to do what I
wanted to do which is find the power to
that's you know and the most related
here and instead of setting the light
buffer count at the outset we could just
set the light buffer count based on that
so what I could say is and in fact let's
do that first let's not do this yet
let's go ahead and take light buffer
count and make that equal to zero and
then each time through here we'll just
take right instead of doing this we'll
just assume that it's true we'll loop
through the light indices in fact we
don't really even need to do that we can
just say because light in the light
index in this case I believe is only is
there what we could do is just do a for
loop that keeps on going in each time we
do one of these we do like OpenGL light
over count plus plus so we keep going
and then down here we do in fact I could
just make this a while loop that
basically says like while text width is
greater than one and text height is
greater than one so once we collapse
down to and we probably like I said in
the end want this to be like no less
than a two by two or something right
because we probably don't want the
lighting to collapse down quite that far
I don't know but for now all right we'll
just say we'll go all the way to the one
by one so let's see if that works at the
moment again I think this would just
produce the same results we had before
so that's all good
and so then what I want to do is I want
to say all right when we do this let's
go ahead and move to just having
[Applause]
this be based on the render within the
render height and so we'll just
reconstruct whatever that power of two
would have been right so I'm just
looking and saying we're going to take
the next closest power of two I don't
remember what the actual index that's
what it is
[Applause]
and so now in theory we should be able
to make this make some sense now that
doesn't look promising to say believed
because I have no idea why we're so
squat and weird for all of our lighting
buffers but we'll find out in a second
so let's take a look at what it decided
to do for text width and text height and
why it didn't draw the whole thing I
wonder if one of our passes doesn't
really Center things properly that that
may be the case
yeah let's just let me take a quick look
at that so when we do Def feel to
lighting yes so the problem is depth
field to lighting needs to actually take
the froggy of ease now that's I think
the only thing that really needs to
happen here so instead of textile
fetching we need to actually do the
bilinear too like down sample the
results into the lighting buffer for
processing so yeah in this case we just
need frog UV out like so and then we can
take froggy be in and so then in that
case when we're taking these textile
fetches those textile fetches here would
just instead the texture samples right
so instead of the textile fetch here
here and here they'll just be texture
samples and we won't do it that way now
I believe I could make this actually be
something that was switchable
[Applause]
so here's the alternate path where each
of these is actually doing down sampling
just blending together
oh wait got a little over is up that's
the past that I'm just going to preserve
kids in case we wanted to not do that
right so this is going to be doing
regular bilinear assuming the pedaling
years turned on for these I don't
remember for those but we'll find out in
a second
either that or I'll do nearest-neighbor
sampling which is not really what we
want but we can always turn bilinear on
let's go ahead and see if that's correct
vert UV that is true we need a smooth we
need in / QV for the v2 normal yes in
yeah
so let's see here there we go so now I
think we're in better shape there
obviously so let's take a look here is
the game in its downsampled form which
is just using the closest power of 2
right so here's the power of 2 version
of the lighting and you can actually
already see that there's a little bit
less of the problem you're having for
although it's still there so as we go up
the lighting scale you can see sort of
how that plays itself out right so what
we want to do now is actually do some
more intelligent things with the normal
here so there's the normal of where the
light is coming from and these in in
this situation right and I think what we
want to do is set that normal the
lighting normal to be a little bit more
sane so that we can actually play with
that a little bit so for example I want
something where the where the lighting
actually is I'd like to set the normal
to point somewhere specific so for
example let's suppose that in the let's
see here compiled device program where
we
I'll do not think about it maybe I don't
care about that maybe it's just the flux
that matters it was just a direction
that matters so the place the light was
coming from is really all that we care
about yeah so I guess here's what I'm
sort of thinking vaguely right so
previously what we had right is we we
were taking the actual normals of all
the surfaces themselves and using that
as something that we do in our lighting
like so you know if we look here you can
see like these are the resolutions this
is the normal information and what I'm
thinking is that we might want to do
instead of that is we might want to have
the lighting be something where we're
actually just slowing out the actual
light itself and the directional values
are just based on where the light came
from not on what was there ever in the
first place so there would really be no
normals anywhere else they right it
would just be what would be in this
buffer would just be the direction the
light came from as it propagated if that
makes sense yeah so as an as lights come
together as their direction and their
color would average together right so it
would be very much like a light fluid if
that makes sense and again I'm just
trying to figure out ways that I can
make it so that this will work without
the fact without the problem that we
have which is we don't really have a 3d
enclosure we can really bounce the light
around although I guess before I go down
that route we should because we're sort
of coming to the end of the stream here
too I should also say that there's a
different thing we could consider doing
with
we could consider seeing the light pass
itself with completely separate
information which we could also do right
like we could have it so that we just
send down all the reflectors in a
separate pass because we know what they
all are right
and that would mean that that would be a
that would be a slightly different
situation right that would be one where
we'd sort of just be doing vertex to
vertex left for processing and we
wouldn't really be doing much with
respect to the incoming pixel values so
for example if you imagined us because
we're sending down you know if we're
sending down like these cubes right and
these sprites we could instead just send
down when we send these down we could
just send down the plates themselves
these these these plates that we get we
could just record the plate information
into the buffer directly meaning we
wouldn't even really treat it so much
like pixels I know this is a little bit
weird I'm sort of thinking this on the
slide but if we want to implement the
original algorithm a little more
carefully and actually try to get to
work you could imagine us saying well
okay when we have these plates coming in
here and we want to do the lighting
versus you know the the old-school way
of just to disc transmittance what we
could do is just say well if we just
recorded what all of these were we don't
have that many of them we could actually
do the algorithm a little bit more
faithfully than it used than it was
originally which is to say we just build
a vertex buffer of these things that
gets traversed
[Music]
kasing is thinking for example I'm just
going to try to throw you for instance
here so for instance I said something
like okay
into the light buffers what we're
actually going to store here is they are
literally going to be the tree of
reflectors and the reflectors are just
going to be stored as the X Y Z position
of the reflector its radius like how big
it was right and then the emit front
back and the normal so basically we have
exactly we have now but instead of
writing into that buffer instead of
writing the anything based on the pixels
that buffer just gets written with
reflector value with actual like records
of these reflectors right
and so what we would need there is we
need a spatially coherent way of
stuffing the reflectors into the buffer
but that's really it right and then when
we do that averaging up we do the
averaging just on the actual reflector
information itself that was sort of what
I wanted to do originally but we kind of
stopped short of it if we could do
something like this where it wasn't
based on the pixels anymore then we
would have the ability to still bounce
with the feeling or a skylight or
whatever else is in there like if either
emit through skylight or bounce off a
ceiling which is more what I wanted so
the tricky part about it is really just
the is really just the problem of not
having any way of placing them into a
pixel buffer in the first place so
that's why I like the original algorithm
how to do the weird like tree creation
step which you know is pretty janky
so I really wanted to avoid that if we
could and it would be nice to be able to
do it in some other way but I'm just not
sure what that other way would be if we
you know we could use a computer which
would have unordered rights but that
starts to get a little bit questionable
as well so I'm just trying to think if
there's I don't want to like totally
abandon this particular way of doing
things until I'm absolutely sure that
there isn't some clever thing we could
do here and I'm just talking about some
way of actually putting the the
reflector data in such that we wouldn't
lose any of the ones we sent down just
because they happen to be on the wrong
side of like a plane like that
and to be honest it does seem like this
could work I'm worried about the
artifact as you move through space but
it does seem like we could make that
work like if you did just double down on
it and say okay instead of using the
depth feel pass you just have one pass
where you write directly into some kind
of three-dimensional texture which is
not very deep so you know it's maybe 16
high but is fairly dense the other way
so you know it's like a 256 by 256 by 16
or something if you did write the
reflectors into that then you could
imagine down sampling that and running
the procedure on it
and what that would look like it would
literally just average them the first
time through it would just average them
in right so you just set the mode to
additive you run through and what you
write to the location is you just write
to that location in the Texel that is
the point you're looking for you you
just write the value of the reflector
that's coming in right and so if you get
more than one they averaged together in
an area
a Catalan try that I'm going to go to
the QA and here's what we're going to do
this is what I've decided because I kind
of like this experimentation right and I
feel like I want to give this a full try
so I want to like see if we can I I want
to give this a full try before I say it
needs to go so I feel like what I want
to do is just because I can't quite
figure out any way to get that feeling
in I want to try one more time to get
that to happen so so yeah I think I
might try it but this week this week I'm
going to think about this over the
course of the week and just decide
whether I want to do it or not I think
I'm leaning towards it
trickster Zorua I would like to ask me
any advice for a beginner it's most
likely asked for but I just heard about
this and while I'm interested in game
programming I never managed to learn a
language I don't have a lot of advice
for that at the moment this stream
pretty much only focuses on people who
already know how to program and wanted
to see some game programming stuff low
level game programming stuff and I don't
really have much in the way of pointers
for like when people are very first
starting so yeah I apologize for that
that is something that's pretty
important and it's I don't know that
there's a lot of really great resources
out there but you know SS Gartner is
there going to be a top level that
doesn't have a ceiling and instead would
have direct sunlight yes but again it
would have a skylight so we would still
have a ceiling there which are just
emitters that are like in a flat plane
emitting downward kind of a thing right
so so we would still have a feeling at
all times more or less
kad's 97 when you said does no library
include no standard library not quite
yet
we did reimplemented we don't use like
for example any standard library io we
don't use printf we have our own print
death not stuff so there but there is
like one or two standard library calls
we are using right now a cosine and sine
and square root because we haven't
gotten to the point on the stream where
I show how to do numerical
approximations to those functions in
Cindy but eventually yeah no library
does include the standard library we
almost don't use any of it now and
eventually we won't use any of it at all
and we don't use any other libraries
so that's the kid to do smooth edges do
you need to do the multi sampling on all
the buffers normal diffuse etc so no we
don't really need that and again we're
going to have to make a path after we
get everything working to a certain
degree to like take out any inefficiency
that there is there at the moment
because right now we're probably doing a
bunch of things we don't have to do what
I would like for the lighting is for it
to be approximate and somewhat blurry
lighting so that we don't have to have
things like multi sampling happening on
the lighting right
so that'd be my hope does my hope anyway
until it's all said and done we don't
really know
kylo possess to which I don't know to
pronounce that but any advice to working
with all loop and cost programmers not
really I you know if you're not an open
tops kind of person and you have to
program with a lot of open counts
programmers it's it it's not great it's
not a happy experience so usually I just
tell people to hang in there and find a
better place to work at some point if
you can but there's not a lot you can do
about that the dogma in the C++
programming world is really strong and
is not based on you know any kind of
solid evidence so there's not really a
lot you can do it's very hard to argue
with people who have a particular
dogmatic approach to programming this
you know not based on any data because
you know it's close to a religion in
that way it's just based on people's
beliefs and their feelings and it's hard
to argue with people about their
feelings right so it's usually better
just not to try because I you know yeah
I mean I I don't know any other way to
say other than it's very hard to argue
with someone else about their feelings
they feel like object-oriented
programming is good and so when you're
arguing with them about using it you're
effectively arguing with them it's like
telling them you know that you shouldn't
go to church on Sunday or something it's
like if you believe a bunch of things
that aren't based on any evidence you
can go to to try to look you know
whether it's true or not there's not a
lot of ways that you can really have a
constructive argument so I try to
discourage people from doing that if
possible and to just try to find
programmers to program similar to you
that you can work with eventually is
usually the best way to go just because
you know until there are really good
hard metrics in programming that you can
actually
to show people like no this is a bad
idea because you can actually measure if
it's problematic effects then really
it's always just it's always just an
emotional argument and emotional
arguments don't have any predictable
resolution you might convince somebody
or you might not and you might just piss
people off
Stephen laughs if GL have support for
fully 3d textures yeah sure
textures in OpenGL can have au of V and
W in the lookup so if you want to you
can have say a 256 by 256 by 256 texture
and when you do a Texel fetch you can
pass three parameters and fetch a Texel
or you can pass a text uvw and fetch
trilinear sample from from one as well
if you want to blend them together
Mavericks as someone who is taught and
always worked with programming how does
one enlighten themselves well I guess
what I would say is that the best way to
sort of analyze any kind of programming
is to see how much work you're doing to
get the processor to do a particular
thing right and you might say that the
global metric for programming is for any
given series of operations that the
processor ends up doing how much work
was it for the programmer to produce the
corresponding code in their language
bug-free or you know as close to
bug-free as we know how to make it right
like you know we analyze it and don't
know of any bugs in it right so for a
specific and I guess I can say for a
specific bug free set of CPU
instructions what is the code that
produces that with the least effort on
the part of the programmer right they
must in the shortest amount of time in
the problem that I have with with
object-oriented programming is I've
never found really any circumstances
where it helps with that and so a lot of
the things that people say it helps with
they usually can't actually demonstrate
that it did they think that it does I
don't deny that they feel like it helps
them but I am unable to myself reproduce
or have them show me how they were able
to actually achieve that thing and so
that's usually the first step to looking
past in grains and in grayned opinion
that object-oriented programming is
awesome or effective is going
and I produce real-world examples of how
it was more efficient to write this code
in object-oriented versus just writing
the procedural version and you may find
that when you do that you actually do
find that object-oriented program is
better and if you do you should stick
with it right I did not find that when I
did that experiment and I did it for
awhile I was never really able to find
an object-oriented paradigm that saved
time consistently across real-world
programming examples it always was
inferior to the procedural version it
involved more typing more unnecessary
structure to the program it was less
flexible because it typically involves
more constraints you end up having to do
things like having these crazy things
like friend and stuff in your language
just to enable programmers to do things
they would have ordinarily just been
able to do in the procedural version it
changes the mental focus from the
procedure which is the thing that a CPU
actually does to an object which is not
something that really exists in a
computer in any way and so on and so
forth right and so typically I guess
that's what I would say and again you
know I'm not going to argue with you to
come to a different conclusion because
like I said it to be in the priest
amount of you're here for that I don't
really like trying to force other people
to program the way that I think is
sensible to program if they want to
program in a different way than they
should program in a different way and I
also think that there's a lot of ways to
program object-oriented is one of the
few I've ever seen that I don't think is
ever useful so I don't really use it but
you know there's a lot of different ways
you can program and you it's good to be
versatile and be able to program to
think in terms of functional programming
versus
usual programming to think in terms of
metaprogramming versus direct
programming all sorts of things can help
you be an effective programmer
object-orientation is just one that I've
never found useful I just haven't been
able to find the concepts behind it to
really come together to produce
effective programs in a more efficient
way than the procedural version
Emma Krantz
could you overlay inedited grading on
top of the car geometry to make them
seem to have more depth to emulate more
of a cone shape you could do a bunch of
things if you want to go all out you
could actually have depth maps or you
know normal maps for the sprites so I
guess what I'd say is you know you've
got a lot of options there you can
definitely cheat and just map a sphere
or a cube or I'm not an active a
cylinder to get more variance to the
reflection across the surface and you
know depending on how close the geometry
of the underlying thing that got drawn
vince's that you will get a better and
worse result the full-on way to do it is
to actually have the art paths have
normal maps in it because then it's
exact in a sense but you know that
depends on whether you have access to
artists who can do that or want to spend
the time and
Cubert Caleb said wouldn't trilinear
sampling for a 2d texture imply sampling
across different myth levels if so what
p-value does the GPU use to interpolate
between the layers so first of all your
hypothesis is correct trilinear sampling
for a 2d texture does imply sampling
across different myth levels and in
terms of what the p-value is it's based
on the grid the texture gradient I that
is C so what generally happens is try to
explain this so if you imagine here is
the pixel grid then you can imagine if
I'm talking about how to pick a mid
level well if I was to say that I'm
going to talk about texels that happen
to line up so that the distance between
one texel Center let's say this is a
Texel here it happens to be off-center
but who cares the distance between one
textile sample let's say this and the
next one is exactly the same width as
the pixel grid that is rendering too
then you might say that it's one-to-one
in terms of size right and at that point
the mid level is plainly zero because
the thing that we're drawing is the same
size in pixels as the screen is in pixel
the Texel size of the pixel size are the
same so we don't need a subsample it now
let's say instead we have something that
looked more like this so now you can see
that I've got my texels are a quarter of
the size right so here's textile a
before now we have textile a is here and
here's D and C and D right well now
we're basically saying it's 2 to 1 in
both directions right because the the
width is 1/2
the width of a textile on the screen is
half a pixel so optimally what we'd like
to do there is we'd like the sample from
myth level one right because we'd like
everything that has been averaged down
by one so that now we're back to having
ABC and D merged together into another
tech so we'll call that e right which is
a plus B plus C plus D divided by four
right or some other way of computing a
nip level so that when we sample it we
are sampling properly the average of all
of these which again is important
because since we're going to take a
bilinear sample since this is off-center
our bilinear sample wants to average the
averages right so that's why we have the
myth so that we can take into account
everything that would have been in that
subsection so then you might ask
yourself well what happens in between so
what happens that the actual distance
between them is like some odd numbers so
here would have been exactly one to one
and here would have been one to two what
happens when we're in between well
that's your T value for trilinear so
however much the width is between half
and whole that's what you get so
typically the miss level if you think
about it the LOD level is actually
continuous value zero means one two one
one means one two two or however you
want to think about this right along any
dimension and what you get when you do
this is an actual continuous value you
might end up with like 0.75 or you know
0.53 or who knows what right and that's
how far in between the two MIT maps you
would be and furthermore as you go up
and up and up if it's like one point two
seven then we're part of the way in
between MIPS one and two and so on
now this also if you have an inverse
before this is also if you want to
understand anisotropic filtering you can
see why anisotropic filtering becomes
important because you don't know that
these values are the same in either
dimension right so it's
could be that my thing is very long and
skinny and so that I'm at a very high
nip level this way but a very low myth
level this way right
and so anisotropic filtering are things
that take more than one tap down the
myth chain or do other things like this
are ways of trying to reconstruct what
the value should be given that you don't
have the right set of NIT maps for every
occasion
right ideally you would have the MIPS
every permutation of MIT so if you
imagine that you had let's say a 256 by
256 texture well that's 2 to the 8th
right by 2 to the 8th so really we
should have like 8 laud levels there ok
and when we make a Miss chain that's how
many we have but what if we wanted to
sample from a Miss that was really all
the way in X still there so that it's
full width but was not that wide and why
right so we shrunk the thing down
because you know like we're shrinking it
this way but not shrinking it this way
or something or vice versa in this case
we're sinking the Y down leaving the X
wide right well if we do that we really
need am it level that didn't get shrunk
in Y in the did get shrunk I didn't get
something extra dickish shrunk and white
and we don't have that in a standard MIT
chain so if you were going to produce
all the myths you would actually need
for precomputed for sampling what you'd
actually have to do is instead of having
8 MIPS for this right you would actually
have to have 64 MIPS you'd have to have
every X level have every Y level in it
so you'd have a - 8 - 8 by 2 by 2 and a
- 8 by 2 by 3 and a 2 2 by 2 8 and a
tooth you know blah blah blah blah blah
and then you would sample based on the
gradients for both x and y into the
correct myth right
and by the way if you have a small
number of these and you wanted to do
this you could so if you wanted to do
really good down sampling you could
produce a number of MIT maps far more
than then eight four three two five
three six that are all based on giving
you fast ways to do good sampling at
arbitrary different angles and stretches
right I think I'm basically out of time
let me just double check what we have if
any more questions
what are your opinions on DRM I'm
against it
let's see I'm working on an AI to play a
game and I'm wondering if you're having
general tips for it more civically the
game is World of Warcraft
right now I'm only at basic functions to
work in an image processing pipeline
nice I don't really I'm not really an AI
program or I don't spend any time doing
much of that so I don't have much in the
way of BOTS advice I've never even
written a bot for anything it's not
something that's ever appealed to me for
some reason so alright let's wind it
down here
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for them so two hand baits here it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
with the series at home you can always
peer to the game it comes with the
source code so you can play around with
it yourself we also have a forum site
you go to to ask questions about this
what we've done with Sirius we have a
patreon page you want to support us in
the videos we have a schedule but you
can use to find out when we're going to
be live if you want to join us live and
an episode guide you can use if you want
to catch up on old episodes that may
have covered something you're interested
in there's also a great search feature
that was implemented by the community
that's really pretty darn cool so you
can quickly find the episodes you're
looking for that's about it for today I
will be back I think next week I might
take some time up coming up here I'm not
sure there may be some summer a summer
vacation on handmade here oh so I'll
keep you posted on that as it goes
definitely always look at the schedule
bot to find out but I think I'll be back
next weekend for playing around the
lighting a little bit more until then
have fun programming and I'll see you
all on the Internet take it easy
everybody