hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we code a complete game
live on stream before we start
programming today I just wanted to
update some software on this machine to
handmade programs that we use actually
Milton our drawing program and remedy
our debugger both made in response to
the series actually by programmers who
did some really great work we use both
of these on stream regularly so I'm
gonna go ahead and update our existing
copies with these copies the update to
remedy is not something we actually need
at the moment it's something that is you
know I think it has like new some new
features and some fixes I don't remember
exactly what was in - 8 - I think it
fixed some string printing stuff there
was some there was some stuff that I
actually very specifically needed at
work I remember but I I just don't
remember exactly what they were I but we
were not having any issues on the stream
with it so this is not an update to
dress anything that we were doing it's
just might as well get up-to-date so
that we don't run into any problems
Milton on the other hand is actually an
update that was made in response to
something I requested I said it would be
great if we could if I could stop
drawing lines on the screen myself for
grids and just have a thing that drops
down a grid I and that was actually made
I don't actually know the person's name
who made it I only know their Twitter
handle
excuse me but thanks here goes out to
Amin sayig I guess I assume that's their
actual name I don't really know but at
amee and SI y e GH if you go check that
out on Twitter that's the person who
actually wrote in and patched Milton for
us they made their own version that has
the tool I asked for out stream which is
a way to lay down like a regular grid
because I do that a lot and of course
drawing lines accurately is not my forte
and you want like a bunch of equally
spaced ones
for doing things like here's a pixel
array or whatever so that's pretty
awesome and we're gonna try it out we'll
just see how it works but basically in
the Milton directory I guess that was in
the root here I should probably move the
Milton directory into the apps directory
actually should start getting into that
habit there we go so this was the old
Milton and you know there is no such
tool this is the new patched version of
Milton we'll give it a shot here it is
I guess this thing here is sort of a
brush window that gives us the option of
drawing a grid you can see the G key
here so I guess if I do G I'm on grid
so it looks like it's pretty easy to
stamp down one of these
it's like here's what we were working on
so it looks like if I just set the brush
size low and then I set some maybe a
standard size here I don't know
something like that then it would be
pretty easy for us to slap down little
pixel grids and so that just I think
makes things a lot easier and it would
make my diagrams a little more clear
because you know they're usually pretty
messy and so if we just have a way to do
that so if I'm drawing let me just test
it here if I'm drawing here and then I
just hit G and then B that seems nice
right because then I can just slap one
down so thank you very much I mean for
that and I think that's probably all we
need if that makes sense I guess one
nice feature that maybe we should go in
and add since everyone else did all the
work here if we switch to grid the
opacity I assume is the same as it was
on the brush so if you go to 50% and
then you switch oh no it's not Wow
that's great well I was gonna say is we
could leave the opacity of the grid sort
of locked down at something less so that
when we stamp it down and then we switch
back to brush it's like a dim grid
because usually we don't want the grid
to be too bright probably that's great
so let's say we set it down to something
like that and then I just go like this
and then we've got a nice little dim
pixel grid then we come up here that's
great
I don't know what Lyons does all right
so it looks like we should probably take
advantage of this as well I don't know
if this was added or if this has always
been in Milton but I should probably get
used to doing L as well just looking at
that
yeah all right so we've got some nice
new tools B G and L I'll remember those
that's that's B that's G that's L let me
try it with the let me try it with the
actual pad just to make sure that that
nothing has broken there it looks a
little different like there's
it's definitely maggots okay now it
definitely looks a little weird I wonder
if this is just a version of Milton
issue 1 6 2 G 1 I like it's definitely
like not doing it's not as smooth as the
other one was
yeah it's it's not like and there's a
lot of little like laggy there
something's wrong with this do you guys
know what's up with that so I would I
would be interested to know what's going
on there because we the previous version
was fine
this one looks looks kind of a little
bit busted we could up to it we could
update the pen drivers as well I don't
want to do that on stream but maybe
maybe let's let's try to try to do that
a link here's what we'll do
because I'd like to start programming
it's been too long trying to update this
so we'll we'll take a look and see leave
that up and then hopefully we'll just
we'll see that when we go to shutdown or
something you know I'll update them
after the stream is over
seems like it you know fair idea ok
let's do this so where we left off we
kind of made a pretty cool utility which
is this is where we stopped last time we
were programming we made a cool utility
that generates sampling spheres and I
want to say it was pretty looking pretty
sweet actually when we stopped last time
and basically it just writes them into
our executable so it you know writes
them into our like it puts them as like
a array into our directly into our code
so it compiles into our executable and
you can see it's a very nice like
sampling sphere the colors on the
sampling sphere are the different frames
on which the samples will be taken and
you can see the sphere is really nicely
covered there I think and the colors are
pretty well distributed right you don't
see any patterns really to the colors
either they're very nice and well
distributed so I think we've done a good
job doing what we wanted to do
which is to make sure that we had a nice
set of samples to use and that's exactly
what we've got here so I think we are
now ready to proceed to the final stage
of the lighting process before
optimization which is getting all of the
pipeline stuff working properly so that
we're actually sampling the lighting at
instead of previously we were sampling
them on all services we just sampled
them at probe locations now and the
biggest problem that I have with the way
that we're doing things now you know
we're also gonna try and think of if
there's anything we can do to address
sort of the the one thing that feels is
still a little bit Squinkie to me which
is that if you look at how we're doing
the lighting at the moment and you go in
here to look at how actually pulled them
out on Mikey caps off if you look in
here at how we're doing the lighting
currently one of the things that you'll
notice is that the lighting itself is
very efficient to compute now I think
the way that we're doing it because we
we know we will know directly which
light sort of where the light that we
hit is supposed to be written back
because when we look at our sampling
sphere we'll know it was going in this
direction so it should be added to this
set of this should be set added to this
set of light probe information but what
kind of is what's kind of nasty is when
you have the light probe set up the way
we do where you've got six directions of
a cube it's really not particularly good
because six directions of a cube is
exactly a multiple of nothing zoondy
wise right it just doesn't it just
doesn't make for a particularly clean
way of doing things and obviously we
have another problem which is that Cindy
can't do memory accesses so we have to
downshift there but that's all
voidable so no matter what we do that's
gonna happen so it's really just the
fact that I don't love how weird the six
what like the fact that our lighting
samples are six directions they're the
faces of the cube so here's a thought I
just randomly had this thought sitting
here and it may be a terrible idea I
don't know but what if we instead just
say there were eight directions so that
instead of being six it's eight I know
this sounds a little weird but I just
thought of it randomly in my head so you
know I should also make sure this is
pinned to the taskbar oops I probably
was already confessed but so here's this
sort of weirdness
so eight wide light probes this may
already be a thing in the literature I
don't know I haven't read up on it
because I intentionally didn't want to
so we could try a crack at it ourselves
on the show but here's one thing I'm
thinking i you know intuitively just
when we were typing in the code I was
like well if I'm going to probe light
let's pretend I have a cube and we'll
have each face of the cube
you know Sam will record the light
that's incoming on each of the faces of
the cube well a cube has six faces so if
you do that you are talking about six
wide light sampling and so no matter
what your situation is if the lights
have colors or not you're talking about
taking six and multiplying it by
something and the only something that
you could multiply it by in order to
make it be aligned to four wide Cindy
lanes right wow that's really gonna bug
me those little loops there hopefully we
can fix that those four wide Cindy lanes
I the only way there's there's no real
way to ensure that other than
multiplying this by two right because if
we wanted to make sure this number was
divisible by four well 6 is 2 times 3 4
is 2 times 2 they have one common factor
which is 2 but this 3 here means that we
would have to multiply this by 3 in
order to make a common multiple right so
basically what would happen here is we'd
have to have 12 light samples in order
to make sure it was divided by both
lower 4 and I'm not even really sure
what those 12 would be it would be 2
samples per face or something right
but you can see why this it doesn't
really line up with Cindy lanes
particularly well if I wanted it to you
know it doesn't really and so I don't
know that it necessarily matters
much but I kind of think we do want it
to line up with semi lanes and the
reason is because if you think about how
these light probes work I don't really
know that you can quite do them in
parallel very well because you're going
to have to downshift to do your memory
lookup and when you do your memory
lookup you're doing a different cube for
every ray that got intersected and maybe
the answer is well then you just load
from all four of those and do the ads
for one at a time and you know thinking
about that in my head that it seems
plausible I guess but it would probably
be nicer if we didn't have to do that
because it makes the code a little bit
uglier if all the operations have to be
strided across for light probes all the
time so what I was thinking is well
another option is to observe the fact
that although a cube does have six
phases it also has 8 vertices and 8
vertices that is actually aligned to
four wide Cymbeline's it's to Cindy
lanes exactly or one AVX Lane right so
maybe that's a little more interesting
and if you think about how that would be
arranged we actually could more or less
keep a pretty simple a pretty similar
lighting scheme to what we have
if you imagined lining up the cube a
little differently so we just said okay
here's how this is gonna go you know we
have some kind of a diamond shape right
and along the other axis
we have another diamond shape right so
here's the here's two tetrahedrons that
form the faces of a cube right the ones
that we have here so if we wanted to
have the lighting still make some sense
in this organization I'm just trying to
think if there's any way to do it you
know there's I was gonna say we could
just tilt the cube and just kind of
accept a little bit of off axis nough so
suppose we have the cube so that one
vertex is pointing up in one vertex is
pointing down still then in that world
so if you assume that that was this
transversal here right then you just get
a hexagon around the other side there so
boy this is hard to imagine in in 3d
without an actual tool can we rotate the
3d cube yeah so just looking at a 3d
cube here right if you imagine the poles
being like that then what you can see is
the lighting would kind of oscillate
around like it would be up down up down
up down like that and I mean I guess
there's no real reason why we would even
have to do that in theory we could make
it a non cube so we could just make it
be like to kind of cones right and you
don't know that there'd be really any
penalty for that so another option I
guess would be to do it like this
instead of a cube
where we basically said like okay here's
moles do on the x-axis here's some fixed
points right and as we go around here we
know that we actually want to have six
points instead of four so normally as
we'd have those four axes instead what
we're going to do is divide it into six
and so we would figure you know sixty
degrees or so for each you know so
something like this
probably so would be more like there
so like same thing thing something like
this
right so we just have like a hexagon and
then up and down and you know I don't
know that there's any real reason not to
do it that way
the only reason that that maybe doesn't
make a whole lot of sense is it adds
operations in the pixel shader right
because you figure you got to actually
sample the lighting from these things
somehow right so you have to have some
way of actually asking what is the
lighting at a particular point and so
you know you would prefer to have a way
of sampling it
that was as inexpensive as as possible
and this perhaps isn't necessarily that
thing right so I guess that's you know
one reason not to do it
I don't know I'm gonna leave that for
now because I don't have a strong
opinion about it it's just something to
think about like because we control this
on both ends of the pipeline we control
the sampling of it at the head end and
then we control I'm sorry we control the
they're both sampling we control the
light propagation and so how how we
actually build these we control that and
then we also control how they're sampled
in the pixel shader and so there really
isn't a lot of issue there to you know
to us coming up with arbitrary shapes
that whatever would be the most
efficient probably the pixel shader is
the most important one for efficiency so
just making sure that that's easy to
sample that seems like you know the
right the right idea there but you know
we'll see um so I guess here's what I
want to do now moving on I just want to
get that out there so I'd like to start
sort of a bi-directional process here to
try and converge on finishing up our
lighting so now that we have we've got
our sampling spheres we've got our light
probe locations we have our ray casting
and we need to bring these all together
now to make a final lighting solution
that we then optimize and and try to
make into something we believe we could
argue is shippable right so what we need
to do there's a lot of things you have
to do I'd like to start on both sides of
the process and kind of ping-pong back
and forth on the one side of the process
we have our pixel shader and the pixel
shader is sampling the actual lighting
and we need that to be efficient and to
be able to do its lookups and blends and
all that stuff in a way that that's
reasonable so we want to work on that
and the other thing we want to work on
is getting the actual lighting solution
propagating light properly and that's
the other side and that you know we've
already done that but we're
reconfiguring it and so we have to like
debug the new parts that we put in there
and make sure that they're they're
operating properly and that we haven't
broken the ray casting and all that sort
of stuff so I'd like to ping-pong back
and forth between these today tomorrow
probably next weekend until we get
everything kind of working coherently
and then we can sort of start an
optimization pass on it to try and get
things working more cleanly now there
are some issues we have if you look at
an optimized build of the game which I
can now turn on so if I just build an o2
version here
oops there we go so if I build an o2
version here and look at the speed of
the game when I open up the profiler so
you know here's the game running as it
normally would when I open up the
profiler here and I look at our frame
timing so obsessed the memory here is
the timing cross frames and here is the
frame rate right at the moment I don't
see any real issues oops I don't know
how to at the moment I don't see any
real issues with stutter but I thought
we were using too much memory on the GPU
I still think we are not in terms of our
sprites rather than that but just
because we create too many frame buffers
for the depth feeling and we just do
stuff that isn't particularly conducive
to fast rendering so if we look at this
I was gonna say I think and it does look
like occasionally we miss I think it
does look like that to me I don't know
maybe not it's hard to say exactly
so yeah I mean I see there's definite
stutter there like there's just definite
stutter there and I assume if we took a
look at what was going on I assume that
the majority of the problem there is not
that we're doing anything particularly
difficult for the renderer on the GPU to
handle I think it's more that what we
are have not only being we got it we got
an enter in an interloping puss-puss
what are you doing Molly what's going on
do you wanna look out the window
let's see if we can distract her with
the window because otherwise she's gonna
start typing and that becomes an issue
very quickly here you go you want to
take a look out there yeah yeah watch
take a look at this okay not that didn't
work particularly well what do you want
being one of the problems is that Molly
doesn't really know how to program so
when she types on the keyboard it
doesn't really amount to much that we
can use and I don't know that she really
knows very much about lighting either
what's going on kiddo I'm gonna see if I
can get her to sit in the cat tree and
give us some reprieve just just to
finish that just to finish the lighting
code just to finish the lighting code
that's all here you go you wanna come up
trying to come up in there there you go
all right so let's hope that works look
out here look at how much there's good
stuff out there go find some birds I
know you like birds all right what's I
don't know this is this is dicey we'll
see we can do so I I do feel like we
kind of have another issue here which is
that if we want to start working on that
pixel shader I think we're just using
too much GPU memory because of all the
frame buffering and we had some things
that you know want to get fixed there so
like I said really really big spread of
things to work on right now over the
next few weekends so try and dial
stuff in and I'd like to kind of start
to get a better handle on them so one
thing that I would suggest maybe we do
today just to get started here is maybe
we say pause on the actual lighting
improvement for a few minutes let's go
take an insight profile of what we're
looking at on the screen here and let's
see if we can't optimize our actual
rendering to the point where we know
that we're not over stressing the GPU
because what I'm worried about is when
we go to put in the sampling I'm worried
that I'm gonna have all kinds of
confusion about what's going on because
we're not in a great place to begin with
because I think we're using too much GPU
memory on the frame buffer side of
things that's what I that's that's my
guess and again because it's because of
that multi sampling that we turned on
and so just to give you some perspective
on what I mean by that is if we take a
look at what's going on here remember we
do four we have four depth peels because
we use def peeling as a more advanced
rendering technique to allow us to just
splat sprites onto the screen in any
order and still get really good
anti-aliasing results around the edges
right so we have four depth field
buffers we know that those deaf people
buffers are at least 1920 by 1080 when
were when were rendering at full
resolution and they need at least for at
least four bytes per pixel but if we're
honest about it we probably want if
we're doing accumulation into those
buffers we may want more like eight
right for intermediate results like half
with float or just sixteen bits per gun
or something so it's a little worse than
that potentially right and then we have
multi sampling turned on so if we have
like really high quality anti-aliasing
or something and you look
if we did 16 samples per pixel for multi
sampling it's just nuts right the amount
of memory that it's gonna take now we
don't have to pay for those 16 samples
in terms of computing because a lot of
times there's only one thing covering
the pixel so we're not necessarily going
to be pixel shader bound on having to do
this many pixel samples but we are
storing them there's space reserved for
them either way and so what you can see
is we can very easily get up to an
extraordinarily large sort of reserve
sighs that's a gigabyte of GPU memory
right and that's just too much you know
it's that's not gonna work and again the
reason that's not going to work is it's
not just because we don't want to
require a GPU with 4 gigabytes of memory
or something not that that isn't very
common today but we just it's clear that
our game really shouldn't need that but
the other reason is not so much that
it's that even if we did decide that
like hey the heck with it you got to
have a beefy machine to run handmade
here oh my friend even if we decide to
do that the bandwidth cost of working on
that much memory is significant right so
we're slowing down our max framerate by
having so much memory have to move
through the GPU so what I would like to
do is just address that in a simple way
we don't necessarily have to go nuts
right but I'd like to see if there's a
way to address that a little bit more
constructively first now last time we
did insight we did children amorta we're
back to handmade here now so I want to
load up the handmade Hiro frame here
that's in our debug directory I think or
not it's in NVIDIA directory all right
I'm gonna cut that and put that in our
debug directory I don't know
we need to directories let's do this
here we go
okay seems fine I'll save it out that
looks right and so I'm just gonna launch
the frame profiler here and see okay
I don't know what happened there it
didn't look good so I don't know if
that's post to happen on this version
let's see if we can watch the frame
debugger so I guess we can't run it
anymore so I wonder if there's something
something bad happening here last time
we had a problem like this Nvidia
actually fixed it for us maybe we can
get them to fix it again but I'm not
sure what's broken there did I need to
assert something busted about our
project file maybe I need to close the
project file and make a new one I don't
know let's try it new project
I'm gonna say I'm gonna use the complete
path here rather than the subsidized
because Nvidia substant Drive may be the
subsidized don't work I don't know it's
hard to say so I'm gonna go in and
sometimes substituted drives don't show
up properly just because when you
subsidize its per user so if the program
switches into root or kernel mode or
somewhere you won't see those subsidized
so if we use the W Drive here you can
create problems with some utilities that
need to run with administrator access
and stuff like that so I'm just gonna
double check I'm gonna go ahead and and
make the entire path work that way just
temporarily it's not my preference but I
just want to give it the maximum chance
of working and so that's the only thing
I could think of that I can do to make
sure that that's not an issue so I'm
just doing the path to our stuff like we
would normally do W handmaids we're just
doing C work handmade because that's
where the substance drive is just making
sure that that all makes sense right so
that would be these two and I'm gonna go
ahead and save that like so and just
give it one more shot not hopeful but
yeah so I have no idea what we're doing
that's causing this problem so I guess
that I won't do that today that's what I
was gonna do but apparently apparently
insight has other ideas I don't know
what we would be doing that's so crazy a
lot of people have said we should retry
using render doc maybe today's the day
we do that because I would really like
to be able to take a look at the GP
rendering here and obviously we can do
it from the other side without that but
I don't really want to
yeah
so I don't know I'm gonna delete these
because they don't work so I don't know
Nvidia you tell me what's going on there
I have no idea if if you need something
else from me please let me know I would
like to get that working if possible
let's take a look at render doc and see
if it works any better we last time we
tried this it didn't work at all for us
it was the opposite we were able to get
insight to work render doc didn't work
so we'll just take a look and see if
it's something we can do this time and
maybe it will succeed again render doc
is the same as n cite basically it's the
same basic idea it's just a like an
open-source version that in theory works
on other platforms so on nvidia on
insight you can only use it on an nvidia
part as far as i know like i don't think
it works on anything else so let's try
render doc and see if we get anything
better but again the principles are
exactly the same so it's not
particularly difficult to adapt from one
to the other so i'm going to go ahead
and and put it over here
it's installing
okay
here it is I'm not sure what it wants
it's just take a look at the shortcut
here not sure what it wants its actual
program to be target render doc so is
this actually not running directly
interesting alright so let's take a look
if I run render doc I'm running it for
the Start menu here here's what it what
it gathers I'm fine with this on the
Hameed here much even if it wants to
gather statistics that's fine with me
render doc v1 for I don't have any idea
how to use the interface but you know it
looks pretty straightforward and similar
to any debugging utility you would you
know see the basic executable working
path command-line argument stuff it
doesn't look like I'm just looking at it
here it doesn't look like there's like a
real file menu here for saving and
loading projects it looks like maybe
this is more where that happens just
guessing based on the UI layout so I'm
gonna go ahead and try here first we'll
try actually using our our paths and if
those don't work we'll try it another
way so if I go in here and oops look at
the build directory and have it build
win32 a run win32 handmade there and
then here we do handmade data that is
all we really need these don't really
matter as far as I can tell there's
nothing there we don't need child
processes we don't watch any or anything
like that I don't I don't see anything
weird going on there so I'm gonna go
ahead and do save settings I'm going to
do the same thing that I just said I was
going to do which is put it in the debug
directory like for Nvidia and I'm going
to save the settings
as handmade Brender doc and hoped for
the best
so in launch applications I'm just gonna
hit launch now and we'll see what
happens so basically everybody crashes
but I don't actually know why uh so I
guess like you know normally I'd say
well if we crash on both are we the ones
crashing but as far as I can tell what
they're saying is they crashed not us
because presumably they know the
difference I mean it would be fairly
obvious if you launch a child process
whether it crashed are you crashed so
we're doing something I guess that's
creating this issue I don't know what
the issue is so there you have it folks
that's kind of what modern programming
is like nothing ever works even though
we're not doing anything
I mean it's handmade here oh it's a
oops
it's 32 thousand lines of code right but
you know you try to just run a thing
that just inspects the GPU usage and
that's impossible
literally impossible for a simple 32,000
line program this is not the Unreal
Engine you know this is not Red Dead
Redemption - this is just a little tiny
baby little program and that apparently
is totally out of the question
and that's just how things go these days
so that's pretty sad I guess we just
can't do that so let's go back to
handmade hero and I guess we'll just
proceed blind because you know what
that's how we used to do things anyway
you didn't used to have debugging tools
for GPUs at all when they were first
introduced kind of like when CPUs were
first introduced you didn't have
debuggers probably at least not reliable
ones so you know I guess that's where
we're at so all right I can do this
audit by hand and I guess we just will
so let's go into our graphics subsystem
here here's the OpenGL layer and I guess
what I would say is let's try and add
something that just sums up how much
memory were actually using right because
it's not that hard to imagine us keeping
track of a ballpark statistic at least
for frame buffers and textures or even
just frame buffers right it wouldn't be
that hard to actually determine what
that is because if we look through the
code here and we look for frame buffers
and we just see like what are we
actually doing with these frame buffers
the GL gen frame buffer call is gonna
occur anywhere that we're creating one
of these right so if I just search
4gl Jen frame buffers like so and I look
at what's available there you can kind
of see it's pretty obvious right that
anywhere we call this we're going to be
creating a new one of these frame
buffers and then when we call GL frame
buffer texture 2d we would be specifying
a texture on it but the GL Jen frame
buffers will tell us at least which
handles are available and if we just
track how big those frame buffers are
then we know how much we're spending on
frame buffer memory right so let's take
a look at all the places we actually do
that you can see here we've got one in
create frame buffer one in this is some
old
this is some old lighting nonsense thank
so
I don't know what this is doing while
texts with greater than one text site
why are we still doing this light
buffers we don't even use those anymore
do we
so we don't care about any of this stuff
I don't think yeah this stuff is just
old so if we take a look at these light
buffers I think this is from our very
first experiment with lighting I don't
think we're actually doing the up-down
part of that at all right let me just
take a look at where those are actually
getting used so if we look at where
they're stored light buffers twelve I'm
just curious what happens if I nuke this
entirely so I've I've eliminated it from
the actual code there I'm just looking
to see who actually uses it yes
so nobody uses it right so if we were to
literally nuke these right here we would
be fine right we don't actually use them
we actually use these other this other
information here so I'm going to go
ahead and just if zero this out oops
so we won't actually need any of this
that will not really I don't think I
have too much of a material effect
effect on our like on our usage at all
anyway but I just want to make sure that
we are eliminating things that we don't
need just to make sure we're you know
counting what we should be counting okay
so if we run and meet here oh this way
now there should be no change because
all we did is remove a vestigial remain
and so you know this would be exactly
the same it is so now if I redo that
search for geo gem frame buffers again
we have one there and then one in create
frame buffer so really the only one then
that we have is in create frame buffers
a great frame buffer right because these
two are now nerfed so this is the only
one we have which means that GL create
frame buffer if we had sort of a paired
version that was like GL delete or sorry
I'd just create frame buffer if we had
another one that was like delete frame
buffer and we just ballparked the memory
that it was probably going to use we
could keep track of that memory
accurately so if I take a look at where
we're doing like delete frame buffers
right again it looks like it actually is
paired pretty much exactly right because
there's three frame buffer so that makes
me think it would be pretty easy if we
did something like this where we passed
in the OpenGL handle to free frame
buffer here we could just add and
subtract how much memory we were
actually using so if I go to my create
frame buffer call and we sort of try to
compute how much memory were actually
using on this frame buffer we could then
just store that information you know
what I mean
so basically what I want here is we
would say all right OpenGL you know
total frame buffer memory or something
like that so it's tracked the open jail
total frame buffer memory would just add
and subtract here so we would subtract
away however much memory this frame
buffer may be like this so we would
basically add and subtract away the
amount that the frame buffer took and
then we would have a single variable
that we could inspect that would tell us
at any given time how much memory we
thought we were using it's not as good
as actually asking the GPU but at least
it's like this is the amount the GPU
would have to have right so in here what
I would do is that create frame buffer
time I would do the symmetric call which
is I'll just add in here frame buffer
GPU memory used and then all I need to
do is actually come up with that
estimate somehow so when we actually
create one of one of these results here
I just need in you know I need to make
something here which just says what's
this value gonna be so all of these have
a consequence right so once we know each
of these then at that point we would
know what the the approximate memory
usage is so first of all we know if it
has a depth buffer we have to add well I
mean we could just step through the
process exactly actually and in fact one
way to do this would be to say it
already initialized is at 0 let's just
add in every time we attach something to
the frame buffer we add add something in
so you can see when we do frame buffer
Tex image here and we have the format we
also have the filter type there filter
type I think is so I don't know where
multi sampling actually comes in here
is the only thing I guess it's the slot
yeah it's the slot it's this so the only
thing that's a little bit squeaky here
is that we don't actually know what the
multi sample requirement is here in
terms of the amount of memory so if I
look at frame buffer Tex image the thing
that's a little confusing is you can see
here if we're doing multi sampling we're
using this max multi sample count and I
don't know what that actually is going
to be but that's okay cuz I could read
it in both places so I could basically
say like look let's just take that max
multi sample count and use it now the
reason that's a little weird I wonder if
maybe what we should do is instead of
passing the slot down here we should
pass the sample count so if that sample
count is like 1 or 0 like is 1 then it's
it's a regular buffer and it just goes
through this path and if it's higher
than 1 it goes through the multi sample
path that might be more interesting
because then that way you know exactly
how many samples you're asking for and
on the callers end you know what I mean
so that seems like me me a little bit
better than what we were doing I might
do that in two phases but I think that's
a little bit better perhaps
but for the meantime or sorry in the
meantime what I'm gonna do is just
actually compute the number as it is so
the open Jill max multi sample count is
how many samples per pixel we would have
a idea here if it's float it's going to
be four times four otherwise it's just
going to be four right so if it's float
it's going to be 32 bit or whatever
right per channel whereas if it's not
gonna be eight bit per channel so that's
the like texture format part times the
sample count and then we need to know
the width and height right so all of
that put together that is going to be
our GPU memory used and we gotta add
that in here right like so now when we
get down to the depth buffer we have to
add that as well and the depth buffer we
don't actually know how big the depth
samples are but this OpenGL depth
component type here would presumably
tell us some information about it right
so you can see here 32f is just a
floating point depth buffer and so all
that would do is we just say all right
result dot chief you remember used plus
equals width times height times four and
that's probably a safe assumption so we
could do 24-bit and said and that would
be reduced I don't know maybe we do this
their bytes per sample something like
that now my assumption here again is
that the depth is gonna be recorded per
sample because otherwise you wouldn't be
able to do proper sampling and so I
think you have to multiply this by the
open Jillson another example count as
well right and you can see why this is
so bad you know what I'm saying to you
we're just using way too much frame
buffer memory here it's not good and
we're gonna need to get that down I
think that's probably our biggest
problem right now in terms of speed and
I also don't know like what our max
frame rate is but yeah at the moment I
don't think it's particularly good
probably right
we tried turning vsync off and it didn't
really work so that was a little bit of
an issue as well so anyway so this would
allow us to sum up the sizes of things
that's all the total size that there is
and then at the end we would just add in
how much that size was so this is
actually a result there so if I build
now I think I'm pretty good on those
computations all I need to do is add
these variables in where I said they
were going to be right oh and then I
need to actually make frame buffer when
we call free frame buffer we need to
pass in the OpenGL handle so like so
right
um so that's pretty much it let me go
ahead and add those values in here to
the you know the various places they
belong I'm gonna add in here total GPU
frame buffer memory I want to make this
a um M because again if we're summing up
GPU memory we don't you know we could in
theory at least during testing be using
more than two gigabytes more than four
gigabytes even if you were doing some
crazy stuff so we don't want to wrap an
integer or an unsigned integer so let's
just recorded as a 64-bit value
it's obviously not important to do so in
the normal case but you know I feel like
we should be overly cautious there so
those will be tracked as 64 just in case
even though we probably don't need it in
this particular instance because I don't
think we're getting up over four gigs
but so if we run this now and I just you
know compute that value in theory it's
computing but we don't have any way to
see it and so what I'd like to do is is
put that in here you can see we're
dumping some random rendering stuff we
don't really dump much a value here but
you can kind of see you know Oh in fact
there we go I this time we actually were
able to get vsync turned off it does
look like we get some faster frames
maybe a little bit hard to say so what
I'd like to do is be able to print that
number out right so I'm gonna go ahead
and add in something here where we're
actually doing our debug values there
I'm gonna try and print that out and if
I look at the debug values for that I
don't actually know where we've been
putting those oops at the moment
mmm-hmm why don't I see the render stuff
in here
shouldn't we see the debug datablock so
this is the data block oh because
they're all boolean's that's why so I
think if I just open this data block
inside the OpenGL renderer and put forth
the information I think that's probably
all we really need
so if we take a look inside the probably
the actual frame update call I guess
would be the don't even remember what
the frame and it's actually called it's
not end UI frame OpenGL and frame so in
OpenGL end frame here is where the
actual you know meet of the of the
rendering takes place so what we could
do here is just say look at the end of
that or something let's update that
variable so you know I could just say
all right at this point in time we've
got
OpenGL total GPU memory total GPU frame
buffer memory and in theory we could
sort of poof that forth right although I
guess now I think about it I don't know
if we actually there is a little bit of
an issue there which is I don't know
that we actually have the debug stuff
wired up in here I don't know if it
would actually work correctly because
this is a separate DLL I don't know if
we actually took the time to wire it up
for debug output that way we probably
didn't because we tried to make it stand
alone so what I might do is not quite
that then what I might do is just make
it so that the platform renderer part of
things contains it and then someone else
can print it out right so in here like
in this platform renderer header I think
I might just put it in there so it's in
the header instead of anything else so
there's just some vague like statistics
you know what I mean so in here where we
have platform renderer I'm just going to
put this in here
something like this all right so if I go
now and force it to use those instead of
like you know opengl arrow total GPU
frame buffer memory now it's gonna be
like OpenGL like header right and same
within the other place where I'm
actually using it open Jill header total
frame buffer memory so at that point
I've pretty much got it in a place where
now I can just output it with the rest
of the stuff that we're doing and so in
here we should be able to do that
because since we have the platform
available available to us we should also
be able to get the renderer information
from there right so when we look at the
platform renderer we should be I assume
we have a way of accessing that easily I
guess no I think about it I don't
actually know that that's necessarily
true we may have to make sure that that
also gets passed through I mean it
should have but I don't know that we
ever actually did that if I take a look
for platform renderer just not sure
where all that goes in so yeah if you
look here the the win32 call that
actually does this went through to in a
default renderer there you can see it
went through your hand made we're
calling it I'm not actually sure we ever
tell the application about that now
technically we don't have to
so I guess we just won't because in here
we can output the debug information just
fine which should be reasonable right so
in here where we go to do like our end
frame call that's presumably the only
place we would really need to do it
right so I'm just gonna say let's do it
that way so in here where we go into
frame display that seems like probably
the right place to put it so you know we
do an end frame and then we record these
values for next time
or maybe we do them right before the end
frame I don't know where the debug
collation actually occurs maybe we do it
before the debug collation so maybe we
do it like right here
so maybe before we collate we just stick
them in here so let's just open that
same block so much like we were doing
here we'll open this block and output
some debug values so we know the
renderer has the total frame buffer
memory years and we can also go in and
add the texture memory usage as well
ambiguous call to overloaded function Oh
probably because these are UMMS which I
don't know do we not support that in our
debug data no we do so look you know we
could easily have a size for that but at
the moment it looks like we don't right
so I guess yeah
so that's a little bit of knowing too so
we don't currently have a you mm sized
variable here like we only have a you 32
sized variable I don't really know why
we did that because you'd think we'd
want to store a you 64 as well but
that's the reason that this is you know
having trouble there I'm tempted to just
add one if I look at all the places that
are using debug u-32 you can see that
really it's just this so in theory if I
just wanted to do that right in theory
we could do something like this and just
have a value 6u 64 that gets printed out
here now I don't actually know when we
do a format string I don't know what we
made for 64-bit print out to the extent
that we did
I'll look if we've got one but even if
we didn't we can still do sort of a cast
in print or do it as a float there for
example in fact I could just make these
floats and be done with it but we'll see
so let's take a look and see did we
actually do any 64-bit print out here
did we make it easy for ourselves to do
that so it looks like X anyway pointers
print out s 64 M from memory so you can
see we actually did a memory thing here
and we actually do gigabytes this is
perfect this is exactly what we want so
what I would do is they just say look
let's do it actually as a debug type um
M here let's actually just do that so
then in the debug interface we would
have debug type um M which is our memory
type that we print out that would be
perfect for what we're doing here
because this is a memory size
specifically so that seems good and then
in here we would just need a place to
store it so value um M like that I think
that's really all we would need to do
and so in here where we have this sort
of you know a set of things that that
are you know basically just garbage
because C C and C++ are pretty terrible
at this sort of thing we
should now have a way of recording
memory sized things into the debug
stream and printing them out as memory
sizes pretty simple but probably worth
it right so here you can see this is the
disaster I was talking about we don't
know we don't know if that number is
correct so I mean I could be computing
it incorrectly but it probably is right
because remember that back of the
envelope calculation I did 1920 x 1080
let's see what that max sample count is
actually I guess I don't know what that
is is do we have that on here we don't
so let's let's forward that value out as
well at the moment because you know
that's kind of a disaster there so if we
go in here to handmade renderer I also
want to put like you know maybe likes
something like this so here's the you
the what it decided to use for a multi
sample account I'll just shove that in
there as well so then inside open gel
when we're actually it's handmade nope
render open gel when we're actually sort
of doing the change settings we can
actually look to see like okay what are
we doing with the multi sampling and so
and what is that number going to be
right so in here we can specify what
that what that number is when we use
opengl multi sampling here and we put in
the DEF appeal flags like this you can
see i can just go ahead and set the
header there to show which one we're
using so in our open jail oops header
dot used multi sample count i can just
say hey the multi sample count that
we're actually using is that max right
max multi sample count that thing and if
we don't use multi sampling then it's
just gonna be one and then when we print
this out in hand made that cpp exactly
like before oh sorry know what's in
there who's here i'll put that out here
and so a theory now we can also see what
that multi sample count is then we can
do the back of the envelope completely
computation correctly it would be nice
to verify this value but you know
without inside or something we can't
really verify it so we don't know that
it's actually correct but if it's 16
which is the highest you know possible
multi sampling then what we've got here
is exactly what I thought right we have
four depth peels at 1920 by 1080 each
one actually has four times four because
it's four bytes for a float times for
RGB a right so that's 16 right four
times nine 20 times seven eighty times
16 and then each one of those is 16
samples right so in addition to those
four we also have the depth buffer which
I guess
so the thing that I'm not sure about is
the depth buffer we wouldn't need one
per frame buffer the depth buffer would
be the same for all of them right but
I'm not sure at the moment if we're
actually smart enough to be doing that
so I'm pretty sure even that actually
goes like this right so I'm pretty sure
that that actually this gets added in
there and so it looks like
back-of-the-envelope wise we are like
using at least two point four gigs and
that's it's just absurd right it's just
totally unacceptable and so we need to
start reducing that number pretty
dramatically obviously and there's a
number of ways that we could do that
and we should we should we should start
by you know kind of addressing as much
of that as we can so if we look I guess
a couple things here there's a number of
things we could do the first one I think
is probably the most sensible and it's a
little bit tough to do but I think we
should at least try to get it working
and that is that we don't actually need
to store multi sampling after our first
pass right if that makes sense by the
way I noticed I just happened to see how
the card of my I so I was asking why
there are four channels in the Deaf
buffer there aren't this is just four
bytes for the floating-point value
that's stored right
so anyway the depth buffer I don't even
know that we would need to keep the
depth buffer like in theory we only need
to depth buffers right so in theory we
only need to store to depth buffers the
one that we're on right now and the one
that we was for the previous pass the
reason I say that is because obviously
when we're you know doing the rendering
pass we need to record our depth buffer
and we also need to look up and check
against the existing depth buffer to see
whether or not we're past it in order to
do the depth field properly but once we
compute the DEF peel we don't need we
don't need to know that anymore because
I don't think we use the depth
information when we actually do our
final composite right am I wrong about
that let's see
so here you can see a sampling it right
so we don't when we actually blend the
four def buffers for the four death
feels together we don't need the the
death buffer anymore so we really only
need two depth buffers total right so
I'm just going to come up with a a
ballpark estimate here right so let's
say we retained two floating-point depth
buffers which we could probably get away
with 16-bit
just fine but let's say we used full
float or 24-bit but full float let's say
anyway so worst case scenario full float
so we need to have two depth buffers
times 1920 by 1080 times 16 samples
times four right is what we would need
so checking out how many gigabytes that
is you can obviously see like it's it's
drastically less because you know it
would it would have the number it's
still not great so I do wonder a little
bit again about trying to think if
there's
like going down to a single one of those
would be preferable certainly you know
what I mean getting away with that would
probably the best possible scenario for
us just trying to think it through
because I think you want multi sampling
and you want a depth buffer and you want
to use the depth buffer with the multi
sampling that all seems true
now you could get away I think with just
one at that resolution because I think
once you're done with it you can map it
down you wouldn't you could just assume
that that pixel had whatever the depth
was on the largest pass so I think we
could get away with just one multi
sample depth buffer actually and that
would be what's that like 128 Meg's yeah
so 128 megabytes for the depth buffer
isn't awful at 16x multi sample which is
very good multi sampling
so let's say we do that we would then
also need one resolve depth buffer but
that would be trivial it would be like
that or something it would be like 8
megabytes no one would care because it
would be uh none multi sampled so I feel
like I feel like that would work if we
if we went that route I mean we'll see
but I feel like that would work so I
think we could get it down to 128
megabytes for a depth buffer and that
would be a savings of 4x right basically
but but that's the small potatoes
because the color buffers are really the
huge thing and a single color buffer
right now is 1920 by 1080 x 16 x 16
right uh and so a single just one color
buffer just one is half a gigabyte right
just one color buffer and so a couple
things we can do to attack that the
first one is obviously we can reduce the
number of multi sampled color buffers we
store and so again I think the answer
here is going to be draw AB depth peel
with multi sampling on but then resolve
the multi sample down first because
after we do the def peel we don't need
to keep that multi sampled stuff around
so just have one and do it and be done
that would get us down to half a
gigabyte rather than two gigabytes so
it's a good first step but half a
gigabyte is still way too large so the
next question is can we stop storing
floating-point information well
obviously we don't need float for the
Alpha Channel that's absurd
we only need an 8-bit value for the
Alpha Channel
but for the color Channel I don't know
we could certainly switch away from
float right now and it wouldn't really
do much harm but we may in the future
want to have better lighting information
recorded and so I think keeping at least
16 bits per sample would probably be
important it's hard to say you know
whether we could get away with a you
know 10 bits per gun kind of a sample
format or something or 11 bits per gun
or something like that because there are
some hybrid formats that have that sort
of thing you know maybe but if we went
down to 16 bits per gun instead that
drops us down to 256 Meg's which isn't
bad again all of these numbers become
trivially better if you just reduced a
Multi sampling count so this is only the
highest end system that would be running
a 16x multi sample right on lower end
systems we can drop the multi sample
down or turn it off entirely and the
graphics just look a little crispier but
then none of this then your memory usage
drops by 16x right and it's all nonsense
right if we just if we just got rid of
the multi sampling your 10 to 15
megabytes right so it's the multi
sampling that's really killing us but
we're trying to use it to give it give a
really high quality image and so we do
want to have that B be available now
there's another option we could think
about here and that is that multi
sampling is only necessary for objects
which themselves actually don't need to
be def field right
Multi sampling is unnecessary for our
sprites our sprites we can critically
sample properly just by using bit
mapping and they do not have geometric
edges so the only thing we're using the
only thing we're using the multi
sampling for right now is our cubes so
the question is if we wanted to say that
our cubes cannot have alpha right cubes
are solid if we just say that cubes are
solid then we can actually do something
even better than any of this which is we
can draw cubes only in like like solids
only basically with multi sampling and
then alpha things we turn the multi
sampling on in the depth feeling on I'm
sorry which are the multi sampling off
and the depth peeling on so we would not
use multi sample frame buffers for that
process that would lead to a pretty nice
way of running things which is to say we
have won a single multi sampling buffer
we render the cubes into it with depth
feeling turned off we resolve it and
then we just use that as something we
composite our alpha things with at the
end
uh I like the sound of that right
I like the sound of that and I think
that might be a good answer because
actually if you did that you could still
use cubes with alpha on them if you
wanted to and they would just go into
the other pass so you wouldn't get multi
sampling on cubes with alpha but that's
the only restriction everything else
would just work right that to me sounds
pretty compelling
I think that's what we should do that's
my argument I'm it that's what we're
going to do so here's the way we would
do this so let's suppose we took a look
at at this information right here so I
think effectively this compositor would
work exactly the same as it does now if
we went down to the multipath part of
the rendering so here's where that
happens when we first set it up so you
can see here we do like the full clear
and we begin the peals what you can see
here is we say look when we are doing
our depth feel and I don't actually know
here's on peel index so when we are
doing our def peel and we're working our
way backwards what you can see here is
that the the load so if we're peeling
right the load of the depth handle
doesn't occur if we are on the first
depth feel right so it basically says
you know when we go in here and render
where we're going to make sure that we
start loading from that depth peel and
off we go
which I guess we still sort of have to
have happen I'm just trying to figure
out how we would actually load in these
how we would get these cubes into the
system though so I guess what we do is
we just render the image as its own
depth peel as part of the depth field
process so I guess what we do is when
you get to the end so yeah okay this is
what we do so when we get to the end of
our depth peels we then render one
fullscreen quad that is the texture of
our pre render of the cubes right so we
render the cubes we have now a frame
buffer and depth buffer resolve that are
just simple 1920 by 1080 by four so very
small we render those in the pre pass we
then just composite those in when we're
doing our def peeling every time so we
just do one full screen quad to
basically like blip that in into the
depth peel so that it gets properly
sorted into that depth peel I think
that's the best way to do it
[Music]
I think that's probably the best way to
do it
I can't think of anything better than
that and it's pretty cheap right one
full screen blit on modern graphs cars
is actually fairly cheap and it's just
gonna run a simple fragment check so
basically like you know the this
fragment code here it's just going to do
this right it's just going to do that
that compare so does that work I think
it does
it seems off the complicated though
she's trying to think if there's some
simpler way to do this I can't really
think of anything simpler I mean I think
we basically have to split off the
rendering into things that require
multisample and things that don't so
here's here's a question I mean is it
smarter to just store the depth peels
depth values and then when we composite
just insert the cubes in where they
belong during the final composite and I
don't really know but you can see what
I'm getting at there hopefully when we
render these we're effectively going to
have you know five images if you will if
we just talk about the abstract content
one image is the 3d geometry which when
rendered through multi sampling without
any depth feels is just correct right
because or the solid geometry I should
say so stuff that doesn't have alpha in
it it's correct because the multi
sampling took care of the edge the
blending along the edges and so it's
just correct you know it's as good as
it's going to get so if we have that
image we then have our sprites and
things with you know that have partial
alpha so edges that are defined in the
bitmap or translucency so like or
transparency right we can kind of see
through them or see through them
partially when we do those those we are
constructing for peeled images of so
that we can blend them together at the
end and
I guess even as I'm saying that I'm
realizing why do we even need to do that
so probably we just did this for
expedience but if you think about it we
actually we actually don't need to do it
that way at all do we a depth peel can
do its blend when it's done right
because look at the compositor the
zeroeth peel which is the frontmost peel
right if once you know what that peel is
you know exactly how much alpha you have
left for the next peel
so if I'm not mistaken we really only
need to depth field buffers total no
matter how many passes you do right
because all you would need to do is just
render the first one when you render the
second one right after you're done
rendering it blend it back into the
first one using however much alpha is
left you then update the alpha channel
with the with the remaining alpha left
right and repeat the process I think
that's all there is to it
at least I'm pretty sure right so I
think actually now that we've kind of
worked this out maybe what we should do
we're kind of running out of time here
maybe what we should do tomorrow is say
let's convert our def peel render into
using only two depth fields and at that
point we would reduce our memory
footprint immediately by half which
would be a good start
and I guess I'm not sure it still seems
at that point it's not gonna be quite
small enough so you know again looking
at just trying to do the back of the
envelope here to get roughly what we
should have so if we were to take our
original equation here which looks like
this so I'm copying it back in so if we
take a look at this original equation
and we assume that there are four sets
of these and that's what was giving us
this if we drop down to two its 1.2
gigabytes which is still too high in my
opinion right so looking at where the
fat comes in you know this number I get
I said could be dropped down to eight
pretty trivially I think without a lot
of work that gets us under a gigabyte
still a little bit high and so the
question is can we reduce it further and
again I think the answer there is we can
drop it down to two a sum of two of
these by just changing the way that we
do the depth feel so instead of the
depth peel being multi sampled I think
we can we can condense the depth field
into being recording the multi samples
only for the past it's actually on and I
think that's probably fine
it may be a little loss of quality I
think that's probably fine I want to do
a quick check as the last thing we do
today so for a create frame buffer I'm
curious how many of these we actually
have so if you take a look at what we've
got here you can see that we have four
each depth feel we're creating either oh
what's this
death peel resolve buffer as well so
wait a minute are we already doing it
death perazol wait it's been a while
since we looked at this render so
actually we're doing the resolve already
so wait a minute if we're so did we just
not bother to throw away the set of
frame buffers we were using hold on if
we resolve at the end of every single
one of these then we don't need a
different one for each depth peel right
so if that's the case then like in here
right where we do the clearing each time
and we bind this buffer I guess I'm just
not sure can we just do this
I'm just gonna look at resolve
multisample so in here we say bind the
Fromm's def handle and the claret colour
handle and then we're going to begin the
screen on the two frame buffer handle
but is that
I guess what I don't quite understand
though is yeah it's in it's that's the
resolved buffer so I'm just curious if
we just do this so we're only ever using
the first one does that work
so hilariously we already had
implemented exactly what I just said we
should start with and as far as I can
tell I'm a zoom in on some overlapping
stuff here
that looks pretty darn good so I think
we can reduce our usage basically for
free right now because we already did
the work and just never bothered to
throw away these buffers probably
because we saved them just so we could
view them for debugging or something but
basically that means the depth peel
buffer here can just allocate only one
right so we would just do this
I want to say
again just going through and quickly
making this slight change
so I'm not sure if anyone uses get depth
peel read buffer looks like we do here
so in get depth peel read buffer
it looks like there's a slight issue
with this which is that if multi
samplings turned off maybe this doesn't
quite work and we might have to like do
a little bit of massaging to make that
happen so I guess I don't really know
but I think we want to do this
what with that why does that have to be
an address of that's a bit weird all
right okay so let's just try running
this so if I take a look at what's going
on now I mean I don't know that image
looks pretty high-quality to me I don't
see really much in the way of
degradation there and everything seems
to still be running correctly right so
if we take a look at our render usage
here in theory we dropped I think it was
three points something before and now
it's two right so in theory that got us
down already just just doing that if we
turn off request vsync I'm just curious
what our frame rate is probably didn't
change much but
yeah didn't really forget effective that
much but so that's pretty weird and wild
but it looks like we kind of got some of
that for free now in terms of where this
two gigabytes coming from I'd like to
kind of know roughly what that value
actually is and so I'm gonna step
through the code real quick as the last
thing we'll do today just to understand
what's going on there so I'm going to
take a break point in create frame
buffer I don't know if it's create frame
buffer cap I think it might be actually
create frame buffer lower case all right
so I want to take a look at this code
here and what I want to do is just see
how much memory it thinks it's using so
if we take a look at the result here it
should start off at zero and does we add
in one of the color buffers right and so
we would expect that I'm gonna just
double check with the width and height
all right yeah so we would expect that
to be 1920 by 1080 and we would expect
it to currently it's it's float right
I'm assuming oh this is not float
so this is our resolve buffer which is
the actual screen one so never mind that
let's just step out of here so the
OpenGL resolve buffer should be a
negligible size and let's just make sure
it is so 1920 by 1080 for why is that
that seems too large for the resolve
frame buffer so I guess I do want to
step in there sorry what's going on
there
what can I set this breakpoint oh yeah
what
did I do something I'm getting all
confused here
oh you know what I just realized I
wonder if that's what was happening we I
wonder if because we set that directory
incorrectly because we changed it from
handmade data didn't we you know what I
wonder if I've been her min the whole
time or Herbert the whole time here I
don't actually know they still shouldn't
have crashed but it's probably that's
probably what happened so in here I
think when we set this up originally the
problem was we changed our working
directory so our working directory is
this now oh man so we could totally have
profiled this ah that's that's an Al
shame so basically like I don't know why
they didn't say we crashed but I guess
it was probably just that we were I
don't know sending something down bogus
when we don't have our working directory
set up properly
we probably like called something that
they didn't like and so we crashed them
before we got to a point where where our
app would crash or something right but
but yeah okay so let's now let's see if
we can actually verify our numbers at
all here I don't really need the
performance counters at the moment thank
you
oops
okay so actually we're fine so let's go
now and see if we can get it to tell us
how much memory we're using on the GPU
so that we can corroborate that number a
little bit and we're not counting the
text remember yet so we should probably
add that in there but anyway let me go
ahead and do what I was doing step two
and then we're gonna run through insight
at least once and get that information
so if we take a look in here like I said
I wasn't sure why this was so large so
ah I see what the problem is we're using
OpenGL max multics sample count even if
multi sampling is not enabled right and
that's that's wrong so that that's the
problem right there
so we're over counting four buffers that
actually aren't being used for multi
sampling so what we want here is multi
sampled we should actually take the
sample count here
like so and that way we can say okay
let's just multiply by the sample count
and we now know that that is set
properly depending on which one they ask
for and we won't over count like the
frame buffer the regular actual like
thing we display on the screen that
won't get counted as that wanting multi
sampling right okay so now we should see
hopefully we should see this frame
buffer as a much more normal size here
we can't inspect any values and step out
there we go so now I think we're
computing these values more correctly
let's take a look at one of the ones
that does have stuff turned on so here
is a sample count of 16 probably right
and so in here when we sum these up what
we would expect to see is 1920 by 1080
times 4 I'm sorry times 16 times 16 for
the color buffer plus 1920 at 1080 times
4 times 16 for the flip for the depth
buffer something like this right and
let's see if that's at all what we
actually saw did I do that wrong
actually 20 times 10 8 times 16 times 16
plus 19 21 I've seen attempts 4 times 16
I think that's correct let me do it
speed crunch first
hmm
so I'm not sure how it got this value
and or how I'm getting the wrong value
so I guess I'll double-check my
assumptions is float so this is not
float so that's the that's the reason
this is a non float multi sampled frame
buffer what who is asking for this
I'm sorry I my death feel flags so who
is asking for this and I thought we were
asking for float did we turn off float
usage or something like this add FP of
flags of five in the renderer I would
agree that does not appear to have
floating point turned on so actually so
actually that computation is correct so
we're not using float then how are we
adding up to such a large number if
we're not using float it should be
smaller
where are the depth feel flags yeah so
it's not actually using a floating point
frame buffer interesting so how are we
getting such a large number then let's
let's keep going at this so I'm gonna
return the result here
if I look at open Jill Deppe she'll
buffer that's less than I was thinking
we're going to make four more of those
so we should how yeah it doesn't seem
like we should be getting to two
gigabytes this way it should be like one
gigabyte right because it's not using
float for anything there except maybe
the depth field
I guess the Deaf peeled buffer all right
so that's a bit odd let's take a look at
OpenGL total or sorry header and take a
look here right so there's the total
memory and it's going to go up now one
two three four and that's it
so that number just is not commensurate
with what we were seeing and I think is
there some other no I see it so if we
say 347 oh 400 divided by 1024 x 1024 x
94 my miss counting the zero is there am
I going crazy that to me looks like 340
million how is that getting three oh wow
what a typo so that is actually quite
low do we have the same typo in our
printf somehow how is so how is it
printing out such a high number or is it
not printing out such a high number
anymore but I thought it's putting out
like two megabytes or something are two
gigabytes right no okay so I guess we
just didn't recheck it after doing that
or something okay so now we've we've
drastically reduced it I didn't realize
we weren't using float so we're much
better now we've like drastically
reduced the amount of frame buffer
memory we're using because again now we
don't actually store those huge multi
sample buffers for every deaf peel for
no reason so we've reduced we've gotten
rid of that multiply by four that was
happening there so that's actually a
good yeah a good start and we were over
counting before so we weren't as bad as
we thought because we were multiplying
by 16 every time instead of only the
times what it actually was turned on so
that was drastically inflating our
number but so now now at least on this
GPU we can still do better than that but
now on this GPU I'm not worried about
that anymore we can keep going at that
level and that's totally fine so
is actually a surprise mission
accomplished in a sense and now what I'd
like to do is just take a look at what
open jail actually thinks is going on if
we can so I'm gonna I'm gonna now take
it just a quick look at that insight
that I wasn't able to do before because
we had set the value wrong just the
working directory wrong we should just
put in something that pops up a message
if the working directory is wrong
because I don't know what actually
happens when you do that in fact let's
find out should just find out at some
point all right so let's run this
through insight see what it has to say
also I think we can turn on the
profiling options as well so like if we
go in here and we try to be the launch
frame profiler I think it will tell us
that it can't access the GPU counters or
whatever so we'll see but if we turn
vsync off as well so you know let me go
in here and see about asking for vsync
off right so here's the information
about how many milliseconds per frame it
thinks we're using and there's me
hopping along and so not a horrible
render time but not great I mean we can
improve it certainly but you know let's
go ahead and and see if we can't get a
capture for live analysis on here okay
so here's the problem so this is the
thing I was talking about where we don't
have permission to access the GPU
performance counters so if I remember
correctly this is actually pretty
trivial trivial to enable though you
have to do much do you have to install
like special drivers or anything so if
you want to be able to access the the
performance profilers I believe you just
go into your settings
here we go I believe you just go into
your settings and turn on the developer
settings on the driver and they allow
you to enable these so I think for those
of you watching at home I think we can
just do something like this and get
access to those it's not like with vtune
or something where sometimes there are
some hoops to jump through but so on
here you can just go to enable developer
settings like that
and then you get additional features in
here you open this up and you can say
allow access like so hopefully you can
still see the stream let me double check
to make sure that didn't Bogart anybody
yeah okay right so now you have access
to the performance the the GPU
performance counters can be accessed by
our you know tools that we run and so
now I think maybe possibly if I relaunch
I know why it thinks it crashed there
there we go let me try running it again
and we'll see if it can actually avoid
that error message so let me launch the
profiler and I think now we're okay this
don't know where insight went it seems
to have disappeared which is not
reassuring yeah so that didn't go so
well if we're honest about it try that
one more time
[Music]
okay so work that time maybe we'd said
to restart after changing the driver
settings all right so once we're done
getting this all configured I assume we
can do a capture for live analysis and
take a look there we go
here is the readout of all of the open
gels stuff we've got right and if we
take a look at the the profiler view
here we can see that it tries to it
tries to give us some information about
who took what time and where right I'm
actually more interested just as a you
know quick look into what's going on if
there is a way to get a total amount of
GPU memory committed as a part of this
right just because like I saying it
would be nice to validate our numbers
those are just numbers we made up by
counting ourselves but it would be best
if it could tell us hey here's how much
memory we think you're using know what
this is here I stare a red flag oh it's
just that
but I don't see much like like this is I
believe just telling us how much like
throughput there was I don't think
that's telling us like how much total
we've we've added we look that we had in
there so I'm not sure you have to
forgive me for not knowing my way around
insight as well as I probably should I'm
not seeing a whole lot of information
about that like here's the API
statistics but it doesn't really it just
says how much time was spent in there
doesn't say like how much memory they
ended up allocating out here we've got
again a good layout of the time taken to
view things again not really what I was
looking for and presumably this is just
based on oops
which one of these I select right
I've seemed to have got it thoroughly
confused there okay so if I select one
of those right it's gonna show me that
the statistics for this particular call
and it's not really what I wanted to
know so I don't see sadly I don't see a
good way get totals you can see here
right there is a memory value that's on
there but it doesn't tell me like a
combined memory value that just says
like everything and you know it's
probably not the most fun thing in the
world to scroll through through these
and ask for each one you can see the DEF
peels are now only taking 8 megabytes
that was really nice I I would say I oh
no that's that's what we expect I guess
yeah
so looking at the frame buffers
themselves I guess though those are not
frame buffers those are buffers it's got
the drawables unsurprising there yeah so
I don't know here's a that's a bunch of
unrelated stuff so I can't even find I
guess there we go so these are our
actual front look at our actual drawing
buffers
there's the depth buffer
with the multi sampling right yes so I
don't actually know any way to get this
to sum them for me but it looks like it
would add up to roughly the same amount
because right you've got two buffers
here each of which are 128 megabytes
that's 256 megabytes and then you've got
like some stragglers here that
presumably as you add it up enough of
those you get up more towards the 300
megabyte range when you count the final
resolved buffer and all that stuff so I
guess seems like it correlates at least
close probably not to too far off anyway
I would say I'm seeing one less than I
expect to see because I like to see the
final resolved buffer in here I don't
see it which is weird
you know what I'm saying so I don't know
this isn't perfect view I would like
something better if we look at the
actual just regular profile view in here
we can see it I don't quite know why
there's like a bit I can't see off the
end that seems less than good I don't
know if that's just because it's docked
weirdly or something
now it seems like that's just that's
just how that's just it's just drawing
it as a tiny little thing and you have
to zoom in in order to scroll it so
that's how that's by design back over
here so actually that's not where that
went
right so you know looking at this you
can see the the time is spread sort of
exactly as we would expect I guess I
think like that's the first FPL second
FPO third death peel forth death peel
right and so each each depth peel takes
one millisecond to draw us to four
milliseconds total and then we've got
you know some some extra stuff in here
for like prepping and clearing and stuff
like that see what this is why so that
that must be submitting that so it kind
of looks like if that really is taking
all that time it looks like we could
actually save a non-trivial like not
huge but natural amount of time by
submitting the vertex buffer more
cleanly because it looks like it thinks
it has two retransform it every time
also I'm just looking at that and that's
probably an OpenGL thing right because
we didn't we didn't lock it down and say
hey look we're not touching this so I
think it has to retransmitted every time
so that we could save you know a
millisecond or something off of our time
which would not be insignificant but if
you look at it like the actual drawing
time I feel like these here just looking
at that at those at those vertex base
calls I don't I don't see any reason why
you would be paying that larger price
for those so I feel like we could go in
and get rid of a little of that fat too
in here if I look at in fact maybe it'll
tell me too if I look at where it's
actually spending the time there
so maybe I don't know maybe that's not
maybe that's not what that's telling me
I'm not sure but you know if I just look
if I just look at it it feels like it
feels like we could save time there by
just telling it look these are this is
the same thing you can pre transform it
once into temporary memory and not have
to ever run any of those shaders again I
don't know that might not really matter
again I'm not familiar with using this
profiler really so I may be just
misinterpreting what it's actually
saying but anyway you can kind of see
that there is some cruft to clean up in
there even beyond at the call if you
look at the actual call itself it looks
like you know at least in here you can
sort of see like the vertex attribute
fetching and the primitive dispatch and
stuff is totally like not implicated
right so in here you can see this this
is presumably Lucas trading unit here
this is how much texture fetch time is
going on here right you can see there's
a fair bit of that I don't know if we
can inspect specifically and say how
much time is in like a pixel shader
specifically this is the this is the
shading engine I assume she's telling us
what's going on in there right
so here is an this is like a clear I'm
in or resolve rather right wait is that
true
so vertex shader implications for wait a
minute wait a minute
so I'm interpreting this backwards then
depending on how this looks so these are
actually these drawing calls are
actually just the ones that have that
all the time I said are the resolves
there's no way of thinking one point two
seven milliseconds to do a resolve is
there well I guess it has to pull
through 128 megabytes of samples though
yikes so you we need to tell me that if
this profile is accurate this which is
drawing all of the data right there's
the 65,000 vertex shader invocations
right and and just looking at that is
that is am I to understand that was a
basically free and that no one cares and
then like this this triangle strip to
resolve the multi sampling that was the
thing that took the time
I guess what I would say is I don't know
if I believe that it seems not very
possible I mean I could construct an
argument for why that was true but it
would be a bit of a stretch so I'm kind
of thinking that doesn't make a whole
lot of sense
hmm so I don't know about that
I don't know if I believe that's
actually true so I would probably take
that with a grain of salt but who knows
if that were the case then that
basically just means that we need to
speed up the multi sample resolve that
one is what the clear I don't know I'm
not super convinced here
I don't know if I really believe those
timings I would have to get a GPU expert
to tell me if that was really possible
because I don't really know if I believe
it
it doesn't seem likely just based on
what that was showing there so maybe
that's not super useful but hey at least
we got a tree running so that's nice
alright so I think we've done what I
wanted to do which was get that memory
usage down to a sane level which turned
out to be free after we analyzed it
looks like we had already done the work
we just never actually removed the old
buffers probably for debugging reasons
we left them around so we could see them
more easily or something I don't know
why we did it but we probably just
weren't thinking about memory usage at
the time and so actually we'd already
done the work we needed and it was
pretty simple for us to just go ahead
and turn off the intermediate storage so
now we're much more sane and we're
hitting the graphics card a lot less
hard even just already so that's great
so tomorrow what I'll do is I'll put in
some some pixel shading there that tries
to sample simulate the sampling of those
light probes even though we don't really
have the data for them we'll try and
like sort of pseudo simulate what's
happening with those and then we can go
and see how much that's gonna cost us
and just get a ballpark on that so we'll
do that tomorrow until then I guess what
I'd say is sorry to have that be a
little anti-climatic I thought we would
have to actually do some work there but
turns out we were smarter than we
thought we were me it already laid the
groundwork for it so that's a good sign
anyway we'll come back tomorrow to do
that to just start the work on the pixel
shader and see how that performs or
changed the performance profile it would
be nice to see why we're taking so long
for frame and that profile that was
shown there didn't really illuminate why
that would be my suspicion would just be
because again it's a lot of memory to
chew through because
doing that really heavy over sampling
but that's something we can pretty
easily check and so if we just go in and
turn the multi sampling down or off in
fact I don't even we might even be able
to do that pretty easily I don't know if
our multi sampling button actually works
yet because we've kind of mucked around
with it but if we take a look at the
frame time we turn vsync off so it's
rendering as fast as it as it can right
if I go in there and turn multi sampling
off well that's not all right never mind
so we do need to go fix that multi
sampling Reed that was the thing that I
put them in to do so what we should
probably do tomorrow's fix that mother
Sam I read look at the difference in
time between multi sampling on and off
and just verify that the that the frame
rate increases as multi as we back off
of multi sampling if it doesn't then the
extra bandwidth extra sampling time but
mostly extra bandwidth because most time
all the sample for us probably isn't
actually taking additional samples so
the extra bandwidth there we will be
able to see that that that was actually
the case and so rather than just
assuming it's the case I'd like to go in
and actually try and verify that backing
off the multi sampling clearly produces
the improvement in rendering time that
we would expect and if it doesn't then
we're gonna go on a little bit of a hunt
to find out what's actually the problem
right so we'll do that tomorrow I hope
you couldn't see you back here for that
until then if you want found serious at
home you know which period of the game
at handmade Hero org comes with the
source code already so you can play
around with it as we work on it and yeah
until tomorrow
have fun programming and I'll see
everyone on the Internet take it easy
everybody
you