hello everybody and welcome to handmade
Hero show Rico to complete game live on
stream we so as we often do in here made
here quite intentionally often to the
chagrin of some people who just want
like the simplest possible game made as
fast as possible which is another thing
you can definitely do and I don't
begrudge people doing it
we like to solve technical problems here
or show how to attempt to solve them
anyway we don't always get a great
solution sometimes we do we're out
another one of those points where we've
done a lot of work actually Hammond here
and done a lot of things I think in kind
of some interesting ways in terms of
harmonizing 2d and 3d you know I don't
see a lot of people really trying to
make perspective rendering work with you
know 2d inserts in some of the ways that
we're trying to make it work where you
can do things like go downstairs and
have some kind of perspective bending
and you know we're trying to do some
interesting stuff there and you know
it's a tough thing to get right because
of the way that the art interacts with
the world and one of the things that we
haven't finished I think pretty much
everything is working pretty well
actually when we look at it that has to
do with that one of the things that we
haven't quite finished is figuring out
how to alter the z-buffer
in a way that allows us to insert
sprites that really we don't know the 3d
shape of in a way that makes them look
plausible right so that they don't so
that they do get occluded by things that
they should get occluded by but they
don't get occluded by other things that
they shouldn't get occluded by and we're
trying to make that happen
in what we would consider a relatively
rigorous way meaning there's some ways
you can do it which you're just about
let's hack it we'll just cheese is tons
of values and have lots of like cleanup
in there where we just tweak things
until it sort of looks right most the
time and then there's some glitches
right we're trying to say look before we
go down that road because sometimes in
game development you have to go down
that road right but before we go down
that road what we want to do is say can
we figure out a real solution to this so
that we can just do it for once and for
all
right and I thought our fogging are like
alpha fog one for example was a pretty
good way you know when we when we kind
of have our our cool way of going
downstairs and stuff now I thought we've
been kind of doing a pretty good job of
getting some of these things like really
tight and good but this one isn't and so
that's the way our last thing before we
can sort of adjust our sprites so for
example let me hop this dude down here
and and let me just take a look here so
for example right we've got that feeling
like really good you know and it feels
really tight and and all of the like you
know fading in and out looks really good
and stuff right
even our lighting is coming along we
just we don't know how to get fast
enough yet right it looks good for where
we can afford to do it but we can't
afford to do it in a big enough region
to make it make it good right but again
all this stuff seems to be working
pretty good but this is our see that
right there right that's the last thing
we really got to know how to do right
we've really got to figure out a good
way to make sure that we don't get those
kind of interpenetration artifacts right
now we're not doing anything for the Z
bias you know we put Z bias in the
shader but we really don't know what to
do with it and so our goal is to solve
that last problem okay
lighting obviously is something we need
to do more work on but that's not that
has nothing to do with 2d 3d right
that's just lighting is hard and it's
always hard for everybody always if you
want you know depending on how good you
want to be you can make it arbitrarily
hard on yourself
but from my perspective right what I
want to do is finally you know knock off
the last thing on our 2d 3d list if for
no other reason and that's what's
keeping us from like going in and
finishing all our alignment points and
having all the rest of the art in right
because we don't want to bother with
that until we know that we're you know
we're solid there and again you can see
the camera just so solid right it just
works really great now all of the fading
does exactly what it should do you can
go up and down levels even stairs it
looks great and it's easy to understand
right and so I'm really really happy
with
the aesthetics aren't going and I think
they're there right where they need to
be in most cases but we just have this
unfortunate issue where we don't know
how to do that Z and so that's what we
were brainstorming yesterday we're like
look this is the last big thing and it's
gonna really prevent us from finishing
up the artist that's you know until we
do it how do we do it and what I
suggested at the end of the last stream
was what if we did something where we
actually just put the projection into
the shader and said that the that the
final coordinate X Y Z W the W
coordinate which was previously just in
addition to Z will actually just be a Z
the the height like the the Z coordinate
of the plane the XY plane on which to
project the point to get the z-buffer
value that you should use right that was
our idea now whether or not that idea is
good is kind of another question and you
know I would like to just quickly or not
quickly but I would like to take a
little more time on the blackboard to
talk about what I mean and what the
problem actually is right again just to
try and get to a place where we've got a
little bit more rigor to it so if I may
the specific problem that we have and
this is like for our Z occlusion the
specific problem that we have is that
the place that we would like our sprites
to be sorted is not where they are
actually drawn right and so if you think
about how a Z buffer works a Z buffer
works by drawing you know into a screen
region you know
a particular Z value and then when
something else comes in you know and
wants to draw on here like you know I'm
drawing another thing on here we check
to see if it's Z value is closer to the
camera than the one that we already drew
and if it is then we'll put there if
it's not we don't right so what we're
really doing is just saying hey for
every pixel we're gonna record how close
this thing was you know and that's what
we're gonna use but the problem with
that is that if we then want to draw
things that occupy regions of space that
are nowhere near the place they wanted
to be sorted right so for example I was
drawing this the other day Friday if we
have something like this where here's a
back facing wall right and here's the
floor right when we're drawing someone
here we want them to roughly sort within
this cube so that if there was a wall
here right we would want this to occlude
them but we don't want this to right so
this wall should not block something
drawn here but this wall should now that
would be fine if we were drawing it as a
sprite card that actually stood right
there right that would be very easy for
us to do and it would just work because
that's what the Z buffer is meant to
resolve it's meant to resolve anything
that involves drawing in actual 3d with
actual 3d objects in the actual
positions they are supposed to occupy it
does it pretty well however what we have
is a different scenario when we want to
draw this thing we actually want it to
kind of come out like this right imagine
the hero body right we want it to come
and and look more like that right that's
what it should look like and then the
head should be like up here right that
means that we actually need to draw out
here as well
okay so what actually happens if we were
to do that right well the first problem
is you know okay we would have to know
to move this thing out alike along Y I
guess to however far it would take to
line up the alignment point with where
it should be right that's one thing and
then the other thing is we don't
actually want this much perspective
because too much perspective makes them
look like cards and we want them to look
more like art right so the other thing
is we have to lie it down like that and
when we lie it down like that what we
end up doing is we end up
interpenetrating for example something
that like this wall back here and
clipping into it right so our challenge
is figuring out what are we supposed to
do here right you know what can how can
we make this work in some way that
doesn't create these kind of problems
that's what we're trying to figure out
just just fundamentally speaking okay
and so there's some things we could
possibly do there are some ways that we
can address this problem and again like
I don't really know what the correct
answer is but for example one thing that
we could try doing is that has nothing
to do with Z bias if we imagine looking
at this from the side now so let's
suppose that we're just looking at this
orthographically here's our side view
right so here is the wall and here is
the floor here is the point right this
is this is P this is the entity point
and we're trying to construct something
to draw on here if this is what we would
normally draw right so that would be the
sprite card if the card were just stuck
in the world but what we actually want
to draw right doesn't have that level of
eccentricity so we really want something
that can lie flatter than that right
and we want something that can extend
further in well one thing we could do is
just say what if we just slid this thing
over this way and counter slid the other
part right back right and created a
sprite card more like crosswise right
what if we just did something like that
so rather than saying look for something
like this we're actually going to allow
it to go down below this level what if
instead of doing that we just took the
alignment point and said look we have
the camera we know what we want is
wherever the align is we want to be able
to shoot that line and hit the point
that it's supposed to align with in view
space but we're going to leave it on the
same z plane that it was right that gets
slid forward and then the one on the top
which would still be there we want to
lie down flatter so we're just gonna
slide that backwards the other way and
by the way if we want to do it we can
compensate to keep the length the same
we can also slide it down right meaning
we can sort of treat it as a rotation so
slide forward till you hit the
orientation then lie down right until
you hit the orientation I mean until you
hit the alignment point right so forward
and down you know maybe that would get
us out of the Z bias business altogether
and again I just don't know I don't know
what the right solution to this problem
is I'm not sure but what I do think is
true is we do kind of want to experiment
a little more try to find something good
and that won't involve us doing a lot of
fudge you know like I don't want a ton
of fudge in there uh now I think that's
what we want to do today and focus on a
day see how far we can get it probably
take us next weekend as well right so
what I would like to do today is I would
like to go and first I don't think we
ever really are debug camera so I think
we should go get the debug camera
working well because that's you
no the that was just on the to-do list
and we're gonna need it to verify that
we're lying down these things correctly
so let's go get our debug camera enabled
and that'll probably a significant chunk
of what we do today because we want to
make it decent and then the other thing
I want to do after we're done with that
is then play around something like this
and maybe write that routine so instead
of using alignment points in a way that
actually adjusts things in Z never
adjusting Z adjust only in Y on the
bottom and then we'll we will allow
adjusting of Z on the top to maintain
the height of things in screen space but
that's all right something along those
lines
we'll see if that works we'll see how
far that gets us maybe gets us all the
way in which case party time and we can
just go mark up all our art assets and
call it a day if that doesn't get us all
the way hopefully we will learn
something that we can then use to
determine what it is we should actually
be doing to solve this problem because
hey you know that's that's the goal of
exploratory programming either solve the
problem or learn something that new that
allows us to solve the problem later
alright so let me show you what I'm
talking about
oops here we are in handmade here oh and
if I run the game here then what happens
is you know here's me running the game
if I run the game I switch to debug
camera and I get you know kind of
garbage right and the reason for this is
the debug camera is still like nominally
involved you can see I'm actually able
to look around actually right but it's
not it's all screwed up I think it
doesn't have any displacement from the
hero and it's just it's right it's it's
just it's busted you know I mean so what
I'd like to do is just re-enable that to
the extent where we're able to easily
get around the game with the debug
camera so that when we come to a
situation like say here and we want to
see what we have chosen for our sprite
cards
we can do so easily that's what I'd like
to get working right um so let's
reacquaint ourselves with that
particular piece of code that's in the
world mode right now which is kind of
the place where we actually in a world
mode is is game mode right it's the game
where you look at the mode where you're
looking at the world as opposed to say
the opening cutscene or the title screen
we have a title screen now did you know
that it's not really a title screen yet
but it's got a little thing on it so not
just the cutscene there is actually a
little a little you know whatever you
want to call that there's a title screen
I think I might ask Anna to like do that
a little bit more completely like the
I'd like to be able to make each of
these things kind of like float
independently I don't know if she'd get
grumpy if I asked for that but it's kind
of open anyway so like what I'd like to
do here is I'd like to go ahead and find
a good way of making Ziva camera really
useful allow us to look around the world
however we want and and do you know kind
of quick analyses of it and so on so if
you take a look at the way this code
works in update and render world what
you can see here is we do look at the
input and you can see us updating the
debug camera stuff it's still so right
it's in there right but what you'll
notice is that use debug camera is not
even really predicated here and we saw
this problem before we would have these
situations where if I happen to the
mouse around without having switch to
debug in road it would actually changed
around and so one thing I would like to
do is just right off the bat I managed
to remember not wanting this to be
busted before and just we never really
fix it what I'd like to do is let's
let's predicate this right where we're
not gonna do any kind of weird stuff
with the debug mouse if you're not in
debug camera mode right so if we're not
using any bug camera it doesn't do
anything that's just better and that way
you know we can kinda and maybe I'll
even do it this way so it's till you
actually affirmatively press it doesn't
change
right and then if you have switch to
debug camera mode then you can do this
other stuff right then you can rotate
around and you can zoom in and out and
and all that good stuff
right so let's start with that so let's
say you do switch to debug camera mode
what happens then
well if you're in debug camera mode then
we have a couple different problems we
never actually fixed some of them looked
like we never really did the full debug
camera right and so one of the problems
that we had was you couldn't really move
to debug camera right mean you look up
here and we've got orbit we got pitch
and we've got dolly there's no pan right
so you can't you can't move the camera
you can only rotate the camera around
and zoom it in and out right which is
fine for most things but it would be all
it would be nice right to be able to
like move to actually take the camera
and move it around the world as well
because that's just a much you know
easier way to inspect things that we
might want inspect right so let's take a
look at that part as well and in fact
you know I can just put that on here you
can look we've got alt left and alt
middle are the ways that that's working
and so you know we need some way of the
debug camera some something that tells
us that we're going to pan and so the
thing that I think would be nice there
is just look if we just press the like
let's say we did this so basically I'm
saying here is hey if if that middle
mouse button goes down then if the alt
button is pressed then we will rotate
but if it's not pressed then we will pan
right
okay so the focus point can be moved
here and that's something that we can
you know we can work on all right so
we'll put the pan code there when we're
ready for it and we'll be good to go so
now if we come down here we can see like
near clip plane
far clip plane stuff they're predicated
on the debug camera if you look at
what's going on here I don't love that
you know I don't like the way this looks
and the reason is because it kind of
inter mixes those two pieces of code
together in a way that's a little more
than I would have liked right
so what I'd rather do is I would rather
have something that actually looks a
little bit more like the code below
where we say hey if we are in use debug
camera mode then we will set these to
something else
otherwise they just appear as they
appear above that's just a little bit
better so let's set them to what they
should be which is these things and then
if we're using a debug camera then I
will go ahead and allow them to be set
to these other things right and that way
I can again see that this is the debug
code here and this code is the actual
code that we normally use so it's more
up you know it's more direct right it's
something that you can see more clearly
and you don't have to you don't have to
sort of read these little inline ifs
which I like inline is quite a bit but
only for code that's actually always
gonna happen if it's debug code I'd
rather keep it a little bit more
separated so it's easier to see what's
going on so now when we come through
here what we're doing is using the
camera pitch in orbit regardless and
that's intentional because again we've
got that camera pit in pitch and orbit
setting that can change in the actual
game potentially and we want to set all
that stuff up normally so we're doing
all of that here as you can see and then
we set up the camera transform now if we
have a debug camera then we want to set
up our debug transform as well and
remember we set these two up there's a
reason we set them both up and the
reason that we set up two separate
camera transforms one for the game one
for debug and not just pick one and use
it is because there are things in the
game that depend on the camera transform
such as how we lie our sprite cards down
when we switch to debug camera we don't
want them following the debug
camera we want them to stay oriented to
the game camera so that we can pan
around and look at our algorithms to see
if they're working properly right so we
need to keep it's very important to have
the concept in the render of two cameras
the one that we're actually viewing the
world from which is the like real
rendering camera and the one that work
yeah I should say the game camera the
the camera that would be used in the
release mode build which may not be
where we're looking from right now but
is where all of the like camera facing
stuff all the culling code all that
stuff still needs to run off of that
camera because of that camera is the one
we're trying to like use for debugging
right now like the one that who's we're
trying to see if everything works with
and then the other one is you know the
debug camera the one that actually is
for rendering that's the one that's
actually displaying the world from right
that's the more actually looking from so
we want those two so that we can debug
things that involve the camera because
if we were always using our actual
camera we'd rotate and we'd never be
able to see how this rights are working
because they'd always turn to face us
right and so that's it's just useful to
understand why we need those two things
and we do need them all right so when we
go in to use debug camera what you can
see us doing here is using some extra
rotations that are applied to the camera
just for debug purposes and that's fine
we then also have the debug camera dolly
set here and I think the problem that
we're seeing is the debug camera dolly
it's probably set to zero at startup and
so what we're seeing is we're just we're
dollied all the way in and since
dollying is itself based off of the
distance from the camera that creates an
unrecoverable situation so what I'd like
to do is over in this window here I'd
like to jump to where we're initializing
the world here and you can see that
happening I think right in where is it
no no no there it is in here where we
set things up I would like to set that
debug dolly right
I'd like to set that to something like
let's say 10 right when I say I'd like
to what I mean is I'd like to do it
temporarily just to show you that that
was the case but there were gonna be
something else in a second but you know
just just bear with me here so there we
go here here's me building and so if I
right-click now you can see that our
debug camera is nominally restored
meaning we can now do the simple
operations we were doing before right
we'd like to go a little further than
this like I said but you know we'll get
to that in a second okay so why did I
say I want to actually do something else
there well the reason is because it's a
little jarring right I'm in here i right
click and suddenly I'm in this situation
right and what I'd rather do is just be
in this situation probably right so I'm
wondering if what I can do is say hey
with this debug camera dolly all this
stuff right would it be possible that
just when you actually switch so in here
we could say look you know if world mode
use debug camera so we know you're
turning it on right now could we set the
camera dolly now to just be whatever the
camera dolly actually is right so if
you're looking here what you can see is
we are doing something right so when we
come through here we've got the camera
orbit and the camera pitch right and
then we've got this camera P and
simulation center we're setting the
Delta there right then we do some work
to set the spans and then we come
through here and we set the camera
transform and you can see us doing right
here our cameras Z you know and our
camera 0 T these are created - as part
of our camera interpolation Delta from
sim right which is this right here is
the translation that tells us how far
away we are from from the world right
you can see us doing this subtraction
here where simulation of camera P so
that thing tells us where the camera
actually is it might be nice to
set up our debug camera to follow that
same position right to basically do that
exact thing um so we know here for
example that our camera 0t is setting us
to some displacement away from the
camera and you can see our camera
orientation multiplying our dolly that's
the part that we're you know this is the
orientation part here of the debug
camera right and this is that dolly
that's setting us away from it it might
be nice to figure out some way to again
get those two things in line right and
so if i look at what's going on here you
can see that when we take our camera
orientation here we really don't we
don't use that right i should i say this
we we don't actually take our
orientation the camera orientation and
modify this translation so this part
here we don't actually in in the actual
game rendered camera we don't do
anything to that translation so it's
just whatever the game said here's where
the camera supposed to be we just use
that right and so if we were going to
mimic the behavior of what that is here
we would need the camera dolly right to
mimic the behavior of this so the camera
orbit and the camera pitch plus the
camera dolly would have to reproduce
whatever ot actually was going to be
with delta from sim right i mean that's
what we would actually need so if you
take a look at what's going on here you
can see that we've got pretty much only
debug camera stuff happening and so i'm
gonna go ahead and say what if we just
move or well we don't even have to we
could do this
we could just record the fact that it's
supposed to happen into a boolean right
and then what we can do is right down
there where we were actually doing that
piece of code we could do the
calculation so in here where we say look
we're about to do this use debug camera
I'm gonna say look was I supposed to
reset the debug camera here if I was
maybe now what we do is we set the debug
camera orbit we set the debug camera
pitch and then we set the debug camera
dolly and we try to get those to match
right we try to get those things to
match what the camera displacement
actually was now in order to do that we
would actually need some inverse trig
and trig functions right we would need
our atan2 but you know maybe that's just
fine because at some point we would like
to use a tan too and so we'll take a
look at it right okay
so let's go back to our drawing board
here and let's just say okay here's the
situation we actually have we've got a
rotation that's not good
we've got a rotation like around a ring
and then we've got a rotation and I
should draw this better here's a plane
all right so we've got a rotation and
the rotation is going to be this kind of
a thing right it's gotta go somewhere
let's say it goes mostly around the horn
to here right then we do a rotation
upward to here right so first rotations
that way next rotations this way right
maybe I'll do a little bit smaller there
right so this is orbit and this is pitch
I believe I think that's orbit
this is pitch and then we have the
vector and we know that we have a camera
somewhere in space right so we're given
this point this is our camera point and
we want to know what is the orbit and
the pitch that would be necessary to
reproduce that the dis
since is trivial right because the
distance from this point here we're just
gonna know that's not particularly
difficult right because it's just the
length of that camera vector right so we
trivially know this right that length
that's the dolly and we trivially can
get that piece of information that
shouldn't be a problem at all what we
don't know is how to reconstruct this
vector from an orbit and a pitch right
but it shouldn't be that hard to figure
out because since the thing can only
really rotate within this right it's the
game camera so it can really only rotate
like that we effectively know that the Z
coordinate right of that vector whatever
that Z coordinate is after we normalize
it for length its Z coordinate just
tells us the pitch angle right I mean
how could it not the only way this thing
can get up into Z and not be flat in the
plane is by having this angle the angle
the pitch angle be nonzero if the pitch
angle is zero right so there's no lift
up then we're not gonna have any Z
coordinate right so pitch of zero that's
not right of zero right is Z of 0 these
are the same right and furthermore a
pitch of 1 right I'm sorry
ozzie of 1 if we saw Z of 1 would mean
that we pitched 90 degrees right right
or tau over 4 what do you how do you
draw a tau again you know I'm so not
used to drawing tau hold please
it's like a little T looking thing
there it is so it's like you kind of
have to crook the thing in the motika no
loops around I don't like how much it
looks like a regular tee but yeah it's
close enough I guess that's not a very
good time I apologize anyway so a pitch
that's gonna be 90 degrees it's gonna be
as equal to one right and so that pretty
much tells us exactly what we wanted to
know pretty much right off the bat
because it means that we can take the we
know right how cosine and sine behave so
we can immediately tell which way our
circle is working here right if the
pitch is zero meaning the angle is zero
Z is zero use cosine of zero zero no
right cosine of zero is one
he's sine of zero zero yes right so we
know that the Aysen right of whatever
the Z value is is going to give us our
pitch another way of saying that is we
know that tangent of an angle right
whatever that angle is we know the
tangent angle is equal to sine over
cosine oops so if we want to do this all
in terms of eight and two because that's
probably the only a trig function we
really want to have we can pretty easily
do that because since we know sine over
cosine is what we would feed into atan2
to get our angle well we know that Z is
the sine right
so whatever the other component of the
vector is in that plane would be the
cosine you know I'm saying so we can
trivially into our eight and two we can
trivially say look just feed the Z
coordinate in after normalization of the
vector just feed the Z coordinate in as
the sine value and whatever the whatever
is left over after removing the Z
coordinate that length so if you
subtract that off of the Z zero out the
Z coordinate of the vector that length
is the bottom part right is the cosine
so the length of the vector of the of
the remaining vector after Z is gone
that's would be the other one so we
could do it either of those two ways
either with a Nason or than 18 - that
would get us back the pitch value right
no worries and then furthermore if we
wanted to figure out the rest of it well
this vector that we would compute here
so after creating the planar version of
this of getting rid of the Z we're just
looking at a vector right that vector is
pointing in some direction hey guess
what that vector itself has an XY
coordinate if we just feed that in to an
atan - that's gonna give us how far
around the circle the orbit we went
right so again really really
straightforward here pretty much we're
done so we should be able to compute
these things directly without really too
much trouble and reproduce the exact
camera position for when we hit the
right mouse button why do we care about
doing this
we don't it's just a good way to show
you how to do those constructions we try
to do them a lot on handmade here ODEs
to drill them in right drill them and
drill them in drill them in right so you
know don't be afraid of creating
geometry don't be afraid of trying to
solve vector problems do them over and
over and over and over again and I
apologize I kind of did that one quickly
but again that's because we're on day 5
something right 5:20 you should be able
to do that if you followed handmade hero
so far but you know if you had trouble
with that we can go over it again in the
QA all right so here we are needing to
solve these so like I said we've got an
8 and 2 somewhere right here it is and
and these are our trig functions that
we're going to replace someday right
it's the only three that we have and
someday we'll just write our own
approximated versions and we'll be done
with them right but we're allowed to use
those three so this we need an eight and
two for this I need an 8 and 2 4 and the
camera dolly part is actually quite easy
like I said that one comes right away so
let's see how to
those okay so we're sending the camera
transform here and the camera transform
is just this ot so the dolly away from
the focus point should just be the
length of this vector in theory right so
we should be able to get that camera
dolly just by saying okay what's the
length of that vector that's the camera
dolly right so at that point once we
have the length of that vector we should
then be able to produce the normalized
version and I'm not going to be
efficient here so I because I don't care
but if I want to do in fact I think yeah
there we go umm so I'm gonna normalize
it like I said I already have the length
so I'm just counting on the optimizer to
do the right thing we don't care about
this is not high performance part of the
thing right here it's only getting
called once so it doesn't even matter
what we do but I now want the normalized
camera arm right so I'm gonna call this
like hogs call it cam arm right now I
want the normalized version of that
right so this is the just a vector
pointing it's a unit vector pointing in
the direction of the camera from the
focus point right at least I believe
that's what it is it might be pointing
the other direction if I'm totally wrong
about how this set camera transform
works I believe this is saying where the
camera is I could be wrong about that
looking at how we're doing it here you
can see us getting the columns of the
camera orientation matrix and passing
this down that to me very much suggests
that we are passing in the placement of
the camera I can verify that by jumping
to set camera transform and you can see
in here what we're actually doing before
we go any further let's just verify that
so camera peak here it is we set the XYZ
camera P directly so yeah it's just the
position of the camera so it is its and
so this is going from 0 out to where the
camera is so that's pretty much all
there is to it
all right so at that point we now know
this is where the camera is and we know
that we're looking at this particular
point actually no I take that back
so this is actually a little bit more
complicated than that
so yeah we do need to do a little bit
more work here I lied to you
we're not moving just off of Z we allow
the camera to kind of like go side to
side as well so it actually doesn't have
to be you know it's it's gonna be
focusing on camera Z straight down the
camera z-axis so actually what I said
was alive we do need to create a I'm not
sure what I want to call this but we
need to create a cam or like a two cam
vector right and that is going to be
based off of this but it has to only be
the camera Z part of it right now that's
pretty easy for me to do and the reason
for that is of course I can always
measure anything against another vector
that's a unit vector right I can take
this and say how far along the camera z
vector was I actually going but in order
to get the two cam back up for like the
focus point which is what I want to be
able to revolve around this actually has
to happen so I take it back
that was my bad right now I'll draw that
out for you really quickly just so you
understand what I'm talking about but
what I did is you saw me do the
construction I wanted to do the
construction around the place the camera
was looking at but actually the camera
displacement that we have isn't that
kind of displacement right the actual
displacement we have is saying here's
zero zero in the world the camera
displacement is like over here or you
know somewhere up in space like over
here and
then it's Z vector is whatever else we
want it to be so the Z vector is
actually just pointing down to here or
something so that's what it's actually
looking at it's something over here now
if I want to know what point it's
looking at well it's still looking at
the point zero zero zero in a sense just
translate it over right so if I take the
camera's z-axis and I take the inner
product of this vector with it
I will get how far along the z vector we
actually went right so all I'm doing is
removing the other components and just
saying look let's look only at those so
this is the actual displacement of the
camera in the world only off of its z
axis right only off of its z axis so
that is more useful to us and then we
can construct the thing which we
actually want in that case which I can
construct off of off of this by saying
look when we actually do this we need to
retain the displacement that we were
going to get before like we need that we
need a camera placement vector that
we're going to use and that will be
whatever the residual is here right so I
can show you what we would do with that
as well
let's do that part and this would give
us a good way to do the the panning as
well because like I said we need to do
the panning so we need something on here
that's like a camera pan and that camera
pan is something that allows us to move
the camera around which we couldn't do
before in addition to just orbiting it
and stuff like that so we want to do
here is say okay the world mode camera
pan is whatever the displacement was
that isn't part of the camera dolly so
once we have this two cam vector we know
what that is again because we just say
look whatever the total displacement was
that we have get rid of the part that's
gonna be our dolly part and just tell me
what's left that's the panning amount
right then we proceed as normal so now
we say look how long is the part that
actually goes back to the camera
great that's the camera debug dolly part
right and really you know at this part
we
could be a little bit squeakier and say
oh hey well by the way instead of
constructing it and then retaking the
length how about we just say give me the
length directly because I know it right
cuz that's what that is right there
that's the length that we have to go
along Z to get to where the camera is
right you know that was it so we can
actually get rid of that length call now
too because we can just say oh well this
is what we actually needed to do there
where we just said there's the debug
camera dolly and let me take the the
cameras you there to create the two cam
vector that means we no longer need that
vector to be normalized either because
it means that the camera Z vector is
actually our camera arm now right so
that Z vector whatever the camera Z
vector is that's the camera arm right we
don't need to normalize anything because
we've got it all now
because I think we do so now we have all
of the information that we need and we
just need to do some atan doing so like
I said in here we have one more
projection step we would like to do
which is we'd like to get the Z out of
there right so what we want to do is say
hey there's a there's a planar right
version of this it doesn't have the Z
it's just cam arm X camera and Y right
so that's the part that's that's in a
plane and Z right that doesn't lift up
and off we go right so if we know all of
those pieces of information we should be
able to do our eight and twos pretty
easily now
right so the first one we just need to
know is that length right so at the
length of the camera I don't even really
need it there's only gonna use it once
so what I can do is say look whatever
the length of the planar arm is that's
our X we know our Y for the atan2 it's
just the cameras YZ z value that gives
us whatever oops in the wrong one here
that gives us sort of the pitches and
the planar version that planar arm is
actually exactly the thing
we would take to get our orbit because
it's the thing inside right inside the
the circle so now all we have to do is
make sure these things line up with what
we were actually using you can see we
don't do any of this placement here and
we don't do any displacement here so I
think that should give us basically what
we wanted right I think and then what
you do is say okay we don't use this
anymore this is not a thing that we
actually do directly instead what we
want to do is take that pan and base
that ot off of it right so that way we
start in the place that we're saying
we're focusing on and then we do our
rotation of the dahle vector around
there right now things get a little bit
more complicated because what will
happen if you actually run this code
even if I didn't make any mistakes even
if I didn't make any math of six is we
will not get the correct result it'll be
close but it'll be mirrored and flipped
right and what's the reason for that
well the reason for that is think about
how atan2 actually works a team to work
specifically assuming that the vector
you started with was pointing along the
x-direction right and just again to like
hammer this home suppose I was to draw
the unit circle right
I take eight and two of this vector
right here's my x equals one right x
equals 1 negative 1 y negative 1 X
positive 1 Y right yes no I'm talking
about here so if I'm looking at the
circle the unit circle here if I take
the 8 into of this vector what I get I
get 0 right so 18 to you know let me
just draw it out I should say write it
out so if I take the 8 and 2 of
coordinates right this is 1 comma 0 and
why right why goes on the top XO is on
the bottom right 18 - sine over cosine y
over X right so if I take the 8 into of
this what do I get will I get 0 degrees
right I'm gonna get 0 if I take the 8
a.m. - of this what do I get
right so that's gonna be one over zero
right so what do I get in that case well
I guess besides the fact that this would
normally multiply out this would
actually divide out - nothing but that's
why we use a tan - because you never do
that actual divide right I mean that
tells you right there what I do it cuz I
wanna be able to get back to sign crease
so if we feed that into 18 - right what
am I gonna get well I'm gonna get 90
right and keep going right what's gonna
be here I'm gonna get PI gonna get 3 PI
over 4 right bah bah bah bah bah so what
you can see there is it's giving me the
answer for rotation assuming that the
vector I started rotating was a 1 0
vector right it was a vector that
started here if my vector didn't start
there that's not the answer I'm gonna
get right so let's see what we've got
here if you look at what we start with
eating that vector right that's not the
x-direction in any coordinate space
right so I could probably and I think
maybe we should just try this
I could start with one that just goes
down the x direction and then it would
probably work right but these might be
weird now so these would have to be
changed so the thing that rotates if I
started in the plane and then I rotated
and then I pitched right the way that I
would have to do that is is I'd have to
orbit four
first and then pitch second so the pitch
vector would have to actually be yeah if
I pitch first well you know what I think
that still probably works all right so I
think the only real thing we have to
change is this X rotation right so for
pointing down the x axis and we want to
pitch up then what we need to do is
rotate around the y axis right because
if the x axis needs to pitch upward the
thing that's perpendicular to it that
would pitch it upwards is the Y X we'll
rotate it around and that I'm sorry Z
will rotate it around which is what
we're doing here and Y will pitch it up
so now we're starting in the place we're
actually measuring so now now we should
have a correct construction of course
there's way too much math there you'd
never get it right the first time so we
won't but at least we now don't have any
obvious mistakes right that we can fix
ahead of time okay so what's going on
here Oh debug camera dawg this is
supposed to be an inner product I'm just
trying to write it in math notation
there like as if there was a dot
operator or something right there's an
inner product right we just want to
measure how far along Z we displace
ourselves there let's see what that is
this is supposed to be a b2 to construct
and off we go
now the other thing we could do here we
could actually say this now I think
about it
I think we support this yeah so there we
go all right uh now again I don't
actually think this is going to work
because I think we've got too much stuff
going on here
right what just happened
that's weird what did we do wrong there
was that a reload problem what was going
on there no that must have just been a
bug in our loading code or something I
didn't actually mean to kill that I
wanted to look at that bug I'm not sure
why that would fail other than like a
bitmap info just being null probably so
that probably was a bitmap that info
equals null I would have liked to have
I'm bummed that I didn't get it to look
at that all right well that's
unfortunate
all right so anyway you can see that it
is wrong right exactly like I said it
would be so now we got to go do our
homework and see what the problem is
although I I do wonder if the only
problem is just we're pointing the wrong
direction hold on let me take a look at
this construction that we ended up with
here one more time so if I go in here
and look at what we did for construction
the camera Z is pointing backwards right
so this is measuring how far back from
the place we're focusing on we would go
right so that that inner product there
is is measuring that off of the origin
so I think that should be correct we'll
have to think it through a little bit
carefully and obviously about code but
that's fine so then we have the vector
to the camera out the vector the camera
should be whatever that was times the
camera Z that should be the displacement
in Z that seems correct as well
and then the panning that we actually
want is going to be whatever is
necessary to assuming that the two cam
is actually getting reconstructed we
want the rest of it which is this right
to still be added in and that is what we
should do that is what should work right
there we then have the camera arm that's
going
be that's not right I said it was
supposed to be toucan and for some
reason it wasn't so - cam is actually
the camera arm so I'm not sure why I did
that this is actually the thing that we
want so this is that all of this is
wrong I just this was just a typo
festival I don't know why I seem to have
had such a problem with it
yeah so so this is the camera sorry this
is two camera oh no no no no I'm sorry
that's not that's not true that's not
true I I do agree with that right the
camera arm is just camera Z because we
want it normalized now right so this is
the unit vector that we are talking
about so no no I'm totally totally wrong
didn't mean to malign our code like that
that was brain fart so yes that's
correct the planar arm is the X Y
component of that so it doesn't include
the Z displacement that goes upward
right out of the plane so then we can
take a look here we say what's the debug
camera orbit well it's the cleaner are
my over the planar arm X that should
give us the spin around in there ah
that's not normalized this needs to be
no it shouldn't be normals actually cuz
atan2 will automatically take care of
that so we don't need a Norma's Asian
that's fine too
then we got debug camera pitch and
that's just the Z value is the sine part
yep that's correct and then however long
the planar arm was that's the other part
of the confess the other X component of
it that seems correct as well now see
any real issue there
yeah that all that all seems relatively
good to me
so what I'd like to do now is the bug
that and before I do I'm just gonna set
assert ourselves up for a slightly
better so something a little bit easier
to work with them what we've got here
what I'm going to do is set another
thing here that's like the camera arm
recomputation so here's us Rica you know
recreating that camera arm effectively I
mean here's actually the camera so this
is us we keep creating the two cam right
so I'm gonna go ahead and grab that part
here so we can look at this separately
so we can look at the two cam as well as
you know getting reconstruct with the
camera pan and so we should be able to
do ideally is look at these things that
come in here now debug the 0t and the oh
here so so these actually exist up here
and and that makes it less good because
i want to maybe be able to look at those
but at the same time so what i'd like to
do is just expand this out to use like a
debug version of each naming convention
wise so i can kind of do something more
like this
where we've just got you know debug
versions of them that are computed
separately and then each of these you
know can be can be recomputed right so
that looks that looks right so we can
compete debug camera oh we use that here
do grote and then we used a camera oh
and ot all throughout here so that
should let me now if I go through and do
a debug builds so let me go to the build
up bat and change that into a TV bug
build if I take the debug build and step
through it now I would like to be able
to look at where were maybe getting
these values wrong and see if we can't
do bug like I said you know I said I
wouldn't get it right the first time and
I wasn't wrong that's what other times
where you'd like to be wrong you'd like
to be like oh I guess I did get it right
not so all right so anyway inside here
here's us looking pretty standard
looking at the world the orbit should be
zero probably at this point because I
think the center of the simulation is
probably roughly where
looking at I don't really know if that's
true but let's take a look
so I right-click and we got the first
step of our solve here so let's take a
look at what these values actually are
so here is camera 0 t what oh sorry
camera Oh T can't read the difference in
the during though
and here's camera Z so as we expect
because there's no orbit the X component
of our camera Z is 0 that's exactly what
we want to see and then we have our
other components here for y&amp;z you know
it's up a little bit and it's back
because like the wide goes upwards right
so this this is what we would expect
that all looks reasonable if we look
here our X component of our camera
orientation I'm sorry our cameras
oriented translation so the this place
for the camera which by the way I don't
know why it's called that because it's
not that out here so that's a little bit
weird but doesn't matter the extra
motive that's also 0 and that's good and
you can see that it's got a displacement
that is exactly what we would probably
expect it to be so that's all fine and
so now we'd like to do is go alright
let's step through and see what we get
so the first thing we're gonna do is
we're gonna compute some of these world
mode values here since we're almost
rector's pretty big I'm just gonna get
the ones we actually want so here's a
debug camera dolly why I didn't call
this debug camera pan I don't know we
should have changed that so you know in
here this should actually not be what it
is this should be up here and it should
be called you mode camera pan but we'll
get to that a second so like yet in here
where we're doing camera pan at should
be debug camera pan in both of these
places and that was just a screw-up on
our part ok so coming back here you can
see us doing the inner pocket the debug
camera dolly so that value right here
should be somewhat close to whatever the
distance should be of this and you know
that looks reasonable you know that
looks like not a totally ridiculous idea
right and so if I was to look at what
was going on there I you know is this is
are those values actually commensurate
so it's like negative five times
negative five right which is just twenty
five plus twelve times twelve right so
it's like 169 and hey that's it's after
thirteen yeah so you know this is
exactly the value that we thought you
know the Pythagorean theorem there right
like you know this square root it is
thirteen so yeah uh so you know looking
at this I just go yeah okay that's a
pretty reasonable camera dolly amount
because that's exactly what it would
take to put us back at this camera ot so
so far so good that doesn't look like
much of a mistake that looks pretty good
so let's take a look at the two cam
vector our two cam vectors should now
basically be this and it is which is
exactly what we want right so now we
need to get that residual in the camera
pan it should basically be zero right so
we should basically have a zero
displacement because we're looking right
at the target
we're not displaced from zero zero we're
looking right at zero zero so we should
get basically nothing and that's exactly
what we get you can see the residual is
the same as here exactly respect very
very tiny number
that's all looks totally right so now
let's take that camera arm the camera
arm is just Z right so you can see it
that's what that is
and the planar arm is is just the XY I
can put into that so now we need to do
our eight and two and we need to compute
our camera orbit and camera pitch so our
first eight and two is say hey let's
take the X and the y just that planar
portion how you know what's the rotation
around of that thing let's get that in
here
all right and then we'll also compute
what that pitch upward was right and so
you can see us getting some values that
I guess for Orbitz sake seems about
right it's trying to rotate us 90
degrees this way that is exactly what we
would need to rotate to put ourselves
into negative Y facing which is exactly
where we are
pitch wise it's telling us we need to
rotate negative 1.57 that's again that's
a that's around 1/2 PI right 3.14 so
it's a little more than that which is
it's gonna be a little bit that seems a
little bit odd to me so the X Y one
seemed about right because if you were
going to try and rotate you need to
rotate the X thing down to be here but
rotating it to rotate this this part in
order to go upward around the y axis
no I guess that's right too because it
would be negative to flip it up so those
both seem relatively plausible the only
thing I would say is
is nothing that those both look good
so that's negative the debug camera
pitch this is the part of saying that
actually seems like that is going the
wrong direction I really do think so
though because if you supply the right
hand rule to the y-axis right it's gonna
pitch it down so I think I actually
didn't do the winding properly there so
although this is not the bug we're
seeing this is a different bug the
winding is wrong on our pitch and here's
why the winding is wrong so if you
imagine looking at the X Y Z and I wish
I could and I can't really show you my
hands very well on the stream but if you
imagine doing the right-hand rule
so you curl your right hand around the y
axis
well the z axis is actually the X and
the y axis of the x axis is actually the
Y right so in here when we did debug
camera pitch to me this would actually
be assuming that the the vector started
up on that like these are inverted right
it's assuming that the Z was actually
the Y but it's not right
so the winding on this is in fact wrong
and I'm not sure exactly what I want to
do there to fix that
because there's a lot of ways I could do
it right I could negate the Z for
example but if you think about how this
is starting out so this is totally fine
because it's going to rotate whatever
vector we end up with it's going to
rotate it around the Z and that's
totally exactly the same thing that
we're measuring here but this Y rotation
right this Y rotation is the first thing
that gets applied so it's going to apply
to an X it's gonna apply a Y rotation if
you look at the XY plane formed by the Y
axis it's actually Z is what is the x
axis and y is the y axis so I'm just
trying to think about how I want to
measure that part of it it's like you
know do I want to invert the winding or
do I want to keep the winding the same I
guess I want to say let's keep the
winding the same so what that means is
that the for the pitch since the z axis
is actually the X it goes on the bottom
and since the the actual length in the
how big that vector would have been when
it was on the x axis that's actually
going to be the length of the planar arm
I think this is more what we're actually
looking for here right and we do have a
problem which is the length of the
planar arm is not signed and so we would
like it to have been signed so when it
crosses over it should so if the Z right
came over the top and back around again
which we don't actually do in the game
so this is never gonna cause an actual
problem but if we were actually viewing
it from the up the back side looking
back down so we flipped over and we're
looking like that this would be the
incorrect sign right because we're just
taking the length of it we don't track
the fact that it had flipped it gone
over here
so we could try to do something more
fancy there right but I don't think we
need to but anyway so I just let's fix
that first and let's try this again all
right so there is a debug camera dolly
there's the camera pan orbit and pitch
so now let's take a look we've got the
debug camera orbit the pitch with the X
oh crap and it's again it's also it's
inverted because if it started here and
rotated down yeah so so I guess again
still not really following my own rules
so we would have to start with the
vector we had before right we would have
to start with Z pointing upwards and
then again we can make that be correct
so I guess what we had originally was
actually not so bad if this is an X
rotation that would be okay because X
would be fine
X would be rotating from the Z over to
the negative Y right and so if you just
put that in here and this was always
gonna be negative this would basically
preserve the old way we were doing it
right because we did an X rotation not a
Y rotation if I remember correctly so
that actually would be fine for the way
we were doing it and maybe I should have
done that to not change it alright so
let's see what we get here all right so
let's see with the orbit being what it
is and then this being a negative pitch
so if I have the x axis and I'm looking
at these I guess I can just choose
whether I negate this or not to whether
I want the pitch to be negative or not
since the X rotation will rotate towards
the right-hand rule wise will rotate Y
into X
then we're always going to sort of have
it yeah it's always gonna be 90 degrees
off right so the 90 degrees off would
also would have also flipped that
because we're not starting at the y-axis
either this is a bit of a mind bender I
probably should draw this out again just
to make sure we get that correct because
there's way too many things in there
that's like okay negative flips like
either one could happen uh so anyway
yeah let's see so the length of the
planar arm if that's a positive pitch
that should go yeah that's what we would
expect to see
so let's now we have to debug the rest
of it because we're still a little bit
janky here so hold on us again all right
so now if we hit the right mouse button
what do we get so we're almost right but
we're we've got our orbit wrong it looks
like and you know again that's just a
case of me failing to do this as
meticulous as I should because anything
about it to here the problem we're gonna
have is that this is producing something
after pitching that again is not in the
x-axis right so let's adjust this debug
camera orbit to assume that what we're
doing is we're starting along the z-axis
so we take the z axis and we're folding
it down so now it's pointing along
negative Y right
instead of X which means it's going to
be 90 degrees back from where it should
be right it's it's just 90 degrees it's
it's going to have to rotate an extra 90
degrees from where this would return it
was right so you'd imagine
that right would give us the actual
orbit that we wanted because we need to
do an extra 90 to get from where we
thought we were to where we actually are
right
we could also because of trigonometric
identities we could actually fix that
part too but we'll get to that in a
second all right so what have we learned
other than the fact that I need to be
more meticulous about where I'm
conceiving my atan2 is to have started
from that was relatively painless though
and now we do have it working exactly as
we want so now if I hit the right click
I'm in debug mode it puts me exactly
where we are right this is the game this
is debug mode right so we've solved for
exactly where we should be now I don't
know how we want our rotation to work
right now it works it looks like the
left-right rotation is not what I want
it to be so I want the I don't know
I thought we addressed this before but
you can see that that's going the wrong
way so I'm just gonna change the way the
input is and make it be a trackball II
kind of a thing for now I think so let's
say I do that there we go and so now if
I run it what you can see is I have a
trackball version right and I can zoom
in and off we go right I go back to the
debug let's see if I can make it work
here
look at that perfect right so we got the
math just right
my eight am too was too sloppy so we
didn't quite get it first try but
otherwise we we got the construction
basically right first try it's just we
we were too sloppy about our 18 to
origins right so there's virtual
trackball we sort of version of it right
and we can go in here so now we need to
do is we need to get our pan we get
panning in there right and so we'd like
to do for panning is we'd like to take
the world mode debug camera pan and we
like to add something to it
right and we've got two things we can
add to it we've got D Mouse px and D
Mouse py right but we don't know what we
would actually add there so you know
think about this for a second
suppose I want to add something to this
what do I add like what do I actually do
to make this work right so the naive
thing would be well I don't know like
maybe I take you know the the pan amount
that we're doing here and I just say
well you know I've got an x and y so
there's the D aspx and the D mouse P Y
and well you know just add those in
right that's kind of the amateur-hour
way to do it right and what ends up
happening if I do that is when I go into
this mode I can pan right and you know
all right it's it's kind of
counterintuitive because the axes are
not aligned the way that you would think
that they would be right so it's a
little bit weird but you might think
it's fine and so maybe you just do
something like this right you know I
invert these two again just showing you
kind of what people often do and it's
crappy you know like just to give you
some perspective so I go into debug mode
and I say all right let's let's move it
around and now it seems like it's
working pretty good right like okay
that's that's great you know now I can
kind of pan the camera around and maybe
I needed to be a little bit faster than
that or something and so maybe I can do
something about that but for the moment
it seems fine right but it's not fine
because what actually happens is when we
actually go in here and change the
orientation of the camera like let's say
here now when we go to pan it's totally
wack right because it's just using the
world coordinate space right so it's
just it's totally busted
I've actually played like bad unity
games that have stuff like this in the
that the actual player has to do
with right and stuff like this anyway
sort of a separation but anyway so the
question is what do we actually need to
use here to make us move in the space of
that the camera is looking at what how
do we do that right well we know what
the cameras XY coordinate XY axes are
because those are actually told to us in
the world mode right we actually know
what those what those are we compute
them right and store them right here
right these these get columns this is
the x axis of the camera this is the y
axis of the camera and this is the z
axis of the camera so if we want to
again and I was sort of like I didn't
know if I wanted to move this down there
or not but I you know at this point now
it's pretty clear I want those
computations so what I'm gonna do is put
that right here effectively right so I'm
gonna put that in here where we adjust
the debug stuff that'll be adjusted
right here and so what I'm going to do
is just use those things that we
actually created now I can do that
pretty easily by actually just making
these be things that we'd get out
earlier right so now we have the camera
X Y Z and then down where I actually use
them I'll just actually use camera X
camera Y camera Z but think about it so
now if I know for the cameras frame of
reference you know what it's looking at
the world through if I know what x axis
it thinks it's looking at and what Y
acts if things look at that's the screen
right so if I just multiply the X motion
here right by the cameras x-axis and I
multiply the Y and again I want to
invert this cuz I believe the mouse I'll
actually I don't know which direction
our mouse goes I'll leave it this way
because I don't really remember which
way we had the mouse coordinates come in
sorry it's down right now I've created
an X Y space that actually matches what
the camera is actually seeing and that's
step one to getting our pan to work
right so let me show you what that looks
like
right here's that pan
right and it looks like yeah so so
that's perfect right it's counter what
we want but that's actually what we
would expect and the reason for that is
this is a displacement of the camera so
it's actually the opposite displacement
it's moving the camera in that direction
right so I believe that is actually what
we expect although does that mean our Y
is flipped let me see
do we flip the Y what is that that's
Mouse clip space Mouse P so that's oh
yeah we do
there it is I'm like that doesn't really
make sense I'm like we should have found
a clip the way I should have to should
have had to have inverted the Y for that
to be correct but okay we did so that's
fine right all right so since again this
is a displacement of the camera I'm
trying to think if that makes sense or
not because it's a little weird that it
was I would have excited to move exactly
a long
nope that's correct so here's why this
is correct if we're moving if I move the
kit if I move the mouse this way the
camera should move along its x-axis
that's a negative X motion with the
mouse
we should mean negative X emotion which
is this direction right and that's
exactly what I see I happen to want the
semantics to be like grab and pull the
screen around you know so that's where
the negation comes in so we're all good
right okay so what I want to do now is I
want to say all right I'd like this to
also be proportional to the dolly
because as we're closer in I want to
move less and when we're further away I
want to move more right so what I'd like
to do is the same thing I did with zoom
speed here which is to say that pan
speed should be proportional to this and
so we'll just do pan speed times the
dolly right and just to let you know why
if I don't recompile so we do the old
version I can show you what that means
so here's me panning around right and
now if i zoom in you can see that I pan
way more when I'm in and if I'm way out
I pan almost not at all right that's
just not what we want we want a pan
proportional to what we're seeing so
that it feels more like we're moving the
thing uniformly regardless of how far a
zoomed in we are right so now if I do
this you can see it moves a lot out here
if i zoom in it moves significantly less
right proportionally still way too fast
so I think what we want to do is maybe
knock that down a bit again we can just
tune this to our own personal preference
about how fast we want the camera to pan
there's no right answer there so we can
just say all right let's say we're out
here still looks a little too fast for
my taste I'm gonna go with an 0.5 maybe
don't ask me why this was multiplied on
the other side I tend to put scalars on
the Left I don't know I didn't hear I'm
scared on the left of variables
so that seems fine
right
no concerns they're pretty happy with
that yeah so one of the things that's
weird is yeah for the picking
you'll note that picking only is
activated or the drawing anyway of the
picking is only activated when we're in
the edit mode we probably want this to
be active all the time because I'd like
to also have a thing where we can focus
on a particular part right but anyway
it's totally fine so we're in good shape
now and I can always suit back to where
I am and so now we should be able to
really use the camera for what we were
intentionally what we're going to do it
it's nothing to do it with it which is
like you know when we're in some
situation we can now right-click and
actually inspect really what's going on
in 3d much more cleanly than we were
able to do so before and so very
specifically what we want to be able to
do at this point is we'd like to be able
to now start addressing these kind of
errors like I said we've got to get this
fixed so that we can use more
effectively our sprite cards in a way
that inserts them into the environment
well and again I'm just thinking to
myself you know I would I would like to
- I would like to try that method of
doing a Y displacement and actually not
having an easy bias in there at all just
to see whether that magically ends up
giving us what we want I don't know if
it will it probably won't but that's at
least something we can try to see
whether that gets us closer to
acceptable I will say to like man I'm
really liking the look like
it's just I think we've got a little bit
more to do on our lighting and then the
this fixture strike cards it's really
looking nice
like I'm really liking the aesthetics
now and that's really important to me
again I'm an engine programmer not a
game designer don't care about the game
design it's not my thing but the
aesthetics is important right that's
part of my job as engine programmer is
to make the engine make the art look
good right nobody likes an engine
programmer who makes crappy systems that
make the art look lousy right that's no
good you need to understand how your
programming affects the aesthetics of
the things on the screen and like I
really try to like show you how to dig
into things like that all right I don't
know how much time I have I think I've
got 15 minutes maybe left so the thing
that I said about sprites figuring out
the alignment of them I figure that's
not actually that hard for us to do to
start with so let's just play around
with it a little bit and there's a
couple things that are involved with it
that are a little harder to do we can
skip those for starters but just in the
next 15 minutes I should be able to do a
little bit of that sprite adjustment
right so let's start down that path
again that's in the entity code which is
where we draw all of our sprites you can
see that happening in here so as we come
through this piece of code you can see
us grabbing a texture handle this is
just to highlight so this is not this
part is not important this is our
alignment point code so we're only
really talking about this part here and
what you can see us doing in here is
we've got this push sprite call
happening and the sprite values for
upright are coming in there
so really the sprite values for upright
is the part that we actually care
about this align P is the part that's
telling us how it's supposed to be
aligned with the point that's come
that's being input right so yeah so
let's do the hacked version first so
what you can see happening here and I'm
gonna walk you through the step by step
we're not gonna do this what I'm about
to do is not gonna be the final answer
next weekend we'll do that right now
we're just gonna play with this a little
bit to get some information about
whether it's plausible for us okay so
what you can see happening here is we
start by saying what's the up Vector of
the world and the up Vector of the world
is the z axis right what's the up Vector
of the camera and that's totally
dependent on the camera pitch right
whatever the pitch of the camera is
that's what it is
so right then we have the x and y axes
and we know that the x axis is just
gonna be the camera doesn't rotate in
our game right so the x axis is always
just the cameras X the Y axis on the
other hand is something we're gonna so
that's what sticks the card up straight
we're saying we're gonna use an
interpolation parameter that you can
specify and we're gonna use that
interpolation parameter to kind of like
fold like we're gonna sort of fold it
down a little bit right so that's again
what gives us that that lean down effect
then we compute this Z bias I don't care
about that at the moment because we're
just not using it right so what am I do
here is I'm gonna take this out for now
right and I'm pretty sure that I can I
don't think we use that anywhere
I think we're setting the Z bias to zero
right now and then you can see that's
just it's just not a problem right it's
just it's drawing the same stuff it was
before which is what we expect so that's
good so we then come down and say let's
produce the X actual X&amp;Y axis you can
see us multiplying out the dimensions
here and then you can see is producing
this baseball
we're using the alignment X to align
along the x-axis that won't cause any
abrasion this is the one that will using
the align Y to go along the the the y
axis so what I'm proposing right is that
we don't do that what I'm proposing we
do is use the world y axis right now I
don't know if we have that in the render
group I'm gonna jump over to the render
group here and just see if we got it
so we don't actually have that but
that's okay for now I'm just gonna say
look we know it's the z-axis sorry we
know it's the y axis right now so to
move the align Y along the y axis
temporarily and we'll add that in to the
to our render group if that turns out to
be what we actually use so that you can
adjust it as necessary now that Y axis
right is pointing the other direction so
the align py is telling us how like far
we would need to move to like we're
doing a subtract there this is what I'm
saying
so I'm I guess if I think about how we
would position that it means that the
minimum position we need to go backwards
along X thus far and backwards along
with that far so that's how far in it is
that means we would need to displace a
[Music]
long- Y if I'm not mistaken meaning
towards the camera to make that
adjustment right and so that should
displace things inward I would think
right and I'm not 100% sure about that
so we'll see ok so I'm gonna start
playing with this and see where we can
get again we're just just playing around
so you don't have much time with me
episode so I'm not gonna do anything too
fancy so if I go to alignment points
here and I'm gonna adjust the alignment
of like this thing so I'm gonna move
this so that it's default alignment it's
like 50/50 right
and that looks like it's moving it the
wrong direction if that makes sense
that's moving it forward which I don't
think is what I wanted now the other
problem I have is the distance of this
is also wrong because this doesn't this
world dim isn't being respected here so
I'm also gonna I'm gonna throw in the
world dim why to correct for that so I'm
gonna say that that's in here let's say
all right I don't want this head in the
way at the immediate moment so what I'm
gonna do is I'm going to turn off the
alignment point for that so I'm gonna
say look at the head out of there right
and we would go back to the game camera
so here we are in the game camera blow
that out to full screen this is our a
little dude right hopalong and looking
at where that sprite is let's see if
this alignment now makes sense right and
it sure does look like it it kind of
makes sense right so if we put it right
in the middle which is where we that's
where we would kind of expect that
sprite to stick roughly and then I
adjust the top of head part right I
adjust the top of head part to be like
right where I think that should be I'll
turn it back to bases neck and then I
adjust the hero head to have an
alignment point some default alignment
point that goes to the parent right yeah
and so then I adjust it so it's on the
head roughly and I don't know if these
sizes are what they should be you know I
don't know what the size of the head
should be really but we can play with
that stuff later so let's suppose I get
all that in there and I'm like alright
that seems about right
alright so now what happens well I'm
gonna hop along right
so it looks like we get a little bit of
a tree penetration on this hop but I
think that's actually cuz the hop is
wrong the hop should really be higher
and and like here's what's looking at
the hop the hop doesn't actually hop up
in Z like it should it's actually
hopping in Y which is wrong so the hop
is actually just wrong but that sorting
sure looks good right that sorting looks
real good
to me I don't know about how you folks
feel about it but I'm pretty psyched
about that that bodes very well I think
so I feel like if we solve some more
explicit equations about projecting
those alignment points we may just be in
the money that made us be that just made
may be just fine right now on the
hopping front yeah like that part the
hop should go up should be displacing
the entities in Y and it's not at the
moment and I don't really know why but
that's great so I think that's all good
I hadn't saved those out look we're
gonna have to go through and do all
those and then we can also attach the
bodies to the these orphans and stuff as
well and the cats and all that stuff so
that will be good I think we're in good
shape all right and again looking at
that so the reason that's clipping in
right now I think is cuz this hop is
actually wrong and the debug camera is
what told us that right the hop is
supposed to be going up and down right
but right now it's not doing that right
right the hop is going backwards hop
supposed to be going in Z Y in the hop
isn't going in Z I don't actually know
probably old-school ideas about how the
2d stuff was working is really why
that's happening so if I go and fix that
so I'm wondering if we get an
improvement here so there's some code in
here for that sort of thing you can see
this sort of nonsense here I don't
actually see quite what this is doing
what's the ATT there for entity P a so
yeah I mean that's just totally broken
right like it's it's actually it's
actually always not that right so I you
know I feel like this is what should
have been happening there probably right
and really I don't know that I like the
fact that this is actually displacing
the entity P per se because I kind of
wanted to really more displace yeah why
is that going underneath
yeah I don't really remember how this
code was supposed to work at all by the
way don't hold that against me
but that's how the hopping should
actually be working and man that's nice
and clean
that's that looks great let's see how we
do on the stairs we got that we got to
set the rest of our alignment points up
we'll do that soon I'd like to do that
so it can look cool yeah just it's great
oh man yeah this engines looking nice I
still think our import pipe is a little
borked but we're getting there right
we're gonna do all the alignment points
we'll see how it is and then we'll clean
up we'll clean up anything that's broken
and we do that
all right that's a good place to call
for today and again we're not quite done
with that that code is a little janky
right now so we're gonna want to make
that code you know tune that up a little
bit but that confirms to me that you
know overcomplicating the problem is not
necessary I think we can just use that
technique of spanning those things out
and I think it'll be good
[Music]
oh did I really okay sorry about the
label my bad I will fix that
or I'll try to fix that I'd actually
know how to fix some of that stuff is
that better hopefully maybe possibly
are we gonna switch to remedy for
handmade hero soon um so I don't know
when we will switch to it there's still
some things that aren't quite right in
it and I'm a little worried about using
it on streem because it still has some
bugs that like make the debug inspection
wrong or whatever and so I'm okay kind
of dogfooding that when I have tons of
time to work on stuff like when I'm
working eight hours a day on something
cuz I want to get it better so I'm
trying it and I find those things I just
report them unhand me here when we only
have two hours I don't know that I
really want to do that so I'm just
waiting since a little more solid
there's not many problems yet left of
that nature but there's definitely some
and so until it's like more reliable
about showing you know stepping the code
and showing the right stuff it's just
it's a little bit off and so you know so
we will but yeah
shahuri johansson says one of the
reasons i became briefly enthusiastic
about wynn debug preview is the ability
to record a trace or a running program
and then send that trace to someone else
and they can look at the exact debug
session you were looking at rather than
having to reproduce a bug spending
possibly a long period of time to me
that sounds like a silver bullet way to
reproduce a bug can you think of any
reason why we're on to conclude that the
feature is a Siller silver bullet for
reproducing bugs um I guess I don't know
what the term silver bullet means in
this case I so it does seem like a good
feature but silver bullet I don't know
the problem is that usually you have two
kinds of bugs bugs that are easy to
repro and bugs that are hard to repro
easy to repro bugs there is still some
benefit to something like this because
hey I don't have to send you like a
buildable version of the thing or you
know whatever I'll say the art assets to
reproduce it or something I can just
record the trace and maybe that works
right so there's something to be said
for that
but it's limited for hard to repro bugs
I don't know that it helps you at all
because hard to repro bugs are just hard
to get repro cases for at all so what
are the chances that you happen to turn
debug recording on when the bug happened
probably pretty low and so the problem
is unless the debug recording is always
on and just ubiquitous and just works I
don't think it's really a silver bullet
right and windy bugs recording is
definitely not an always-on kind of
feature so I would say at the moment the
closest thing to a repro Silver Bullet
is probably something more like what we
have in handmade hero where you could
just leave it on all the time if you
wanted to where it just records user
input and can play it back directly that
you could afford to leave on all the
time and if you extended that to do some
recording to try and help you make it so
that runs would be more exactly repro
able
maybe that would work but again it's
just not until like the recording is
ubiquitous always on and free I don't
think it really changes the equation
that much because the hard part about
hard to repo is that you only know you
hit one at long after it was too late to
turn on recording and I don't think this
changes it that much
does that help does that make sense so
far it seems like all the animations are
programmatically moving static sprites
is there any plan to include preset or
artistic creating animations we probably
won't you know we're pretty much a
programming stream here so you know I I
don't really want to put a lot of art
stress on the art the other thing I
guess is this game is supposed to be one
where it's easy to add new things to it
so I don't really want to set the bar
high for animation I want you to have to
draw the smallest number of things
necessary to add something new to the
game that's kind of another criteria and
so if you start having frames of
animation that just really increases the
cost for people to add like a new item
or a new enemy so I'd like to keep those
really low right that's that's really
all I could say
not but no I said they're under code for
a bit it seems the vertices indices for
the cubes and quads are generated each
frame and the CPU and put into a big VBA
which is said the stream draw is this
correct and it's yes what was the
decision to do it that way so the reason
we do it that way is because we have
it's a game with very low geometry load
right so the the number of things we
draw with Q with the cubes and the
sprites is very low that's generally
true of a 2d game it's just not that
many things and so there isn't really
much of a reason for us to spend time
managing GPU memory for no reason
because we just it's just not a
bottleneck so introducing something like
static buffers that we manage just
increases the chance that we have bugs
and work on less cards and doesn't
really do much for us because we don't
we don't spend a lot of time
transferring that stuff right textures
we do spend time transferring it so
that's why we try to keep them cached on
the card as much as possible vertices we
just don't have that problem and so
that's our current situation now we also
have the situation that we may have lots
of particles and particles are things
that we will probably try to compress
more but we still will probably have to
stream them out every frame because we
are going to move them on the CPU side
mostly so you can't really use a static
buffer for those either if you wanted to
do particle simulation on the GPU what
you can do then you could change it but
for right now I don't have any plans to
do that either because again even with a
couple you know ten thousand particles
may be on the screen we probably still
wouldn't be stressing the pipe to the
graphs card very much
once your take on ProFlowers versus
do-it-yourself in-game profiling I've
always found do it you're selling any
profiling to be better what are some
decent profiles that you know of or have
used I tried to use very sleepy it
didn't really work the multi-threading
just didn't seem to work it just gave
really ridiculous results that I knew
weren't true so I'm not sure what was up
with that I've tried to use vtune it's a
mess I haven't ever tried to lemma tree
so rad ships a thing called telemetry
that looks more sane unsurprisingly
because hey like rats would working on
it for a while so it's better but I
haven't tried it myself so I don't
really know but it looks more like the
kind of thing that I would do right like
it it records a bunch of things and then
you can kind of look at them and go show
me what a frame looked like and that
seems you know seems like something
that's more useful
so I guess we don't have any more
questions it looks like oh wait what I
think about Python you talk about the
language so I've only really ever looked
at Python like twice and it was someone
else's project uh
I guess what I would say is it looks
like yet another super janky high-level
language that is mostly only interesting
because people have written a lot of
libraries for it like it looks like
probably slightly better than PHP but
basically the exact same thing like a
janky language not particularly well
thought-out certainly not doesn't
perform well very slow but lots of
libraries so you can do things quickly
if the library does what you want right
that's about all I could tell about it
from the limited amount that I've used
it see if there's any value in keeping
the cost of registers in the
higher-level language yes absolutely if
I were designing a language you would
actually be able to essentially program
assembly language directly in it and
then scale out to like so basically you
could do register allocation yourself at
any point if you wanted to that would
totally be something I would do how do I
feel about dynamically typed languages
I feel like dynamic typing is good for
certain situations but you definitely
don't want it to the only thing you have
so if you have dynamic typing that's
fine but if you don't allow static
typing as well I probably won't like
your language because there's way too
many bugs there's lots of unnecessary
bugs in languages that don't have static
typing analysis maybe that's before but
have you looked at Pony lang no I do not
know Pony lang
the fact that your name is useless pony
seems to suggest that pony leg must not
be very good if it is useless
does the game live lettuce from files no
it generates levels itself or I should
say will generate level itself at the
moment a it only generates a few simple
things that we told it to generate but
we will be expanding on that and there
will be no level editor at all it's not
a game where you edit levels
I feel like with the number of times
people ask me like what do you think
about this random language that's very
esoteric I feel like I just start just
making up languages and answering them
right like everyone should just program
in Kronk like Gronk is obviously the
best language it has all the best things
in it like why aren't we just burning
this game and Gronk
right
it rust is I mean rust is probably a
fine language but you know it's not as
good as iron or iron ore is a way better
language also the the zinc oxide
language is very good
dihydrogen monoxide is one of my
favorite languages it's got a ton of
good stuff in it you know cuz rust has
the Baro checker which people like to
talk about but the but zinc oxide is a
way better language and the Baro checker
has a lot limitations zinc oxide has the
theft police feature the thepolice is
like way better than the Baro checker
and and similarly like like the garbage
collection features are like like goes
garbage collection is terrible
whereas zinc oxide has actually
recycling and composting has memory
composting and memory composting is like
way more powerful than garbage garbage
collection right because one of the
problems is you get in in languages like
NGO that focus on garbage collection is
that eventually there's you run out of
raw materials right so you're collecting
the garbage second guard took the
garbage putting it in into the landfill
segment and then eventually you know
either you run out of space in the
landfill segment or you end up in a
situation where you just don't have any
raw materials anymore at all right so
you know in a language like go all the
memory has to come from the memory
garden the memory gardens planted at
sort of time and after you harvest all
of the memory in the memory garden and
your garbage collector has collected all
of that used memory and thrown it away
in the landfill segment that's it right
I mean the program stops
I mean basically not not to mention all
the health problems and so one of the
things about zinc oxide which makes it
far superior or also I I don't know if
you guys would look at stop Lang stop
Lang is is kind of like go but with
compost
with memory composting right because
they recognized the fact that you know
you you have this sort of inherent
problem with garbage collection where
all of the code just just ends up in a
landfill and there's you know all of all
that memory just ends up in the landfill
after it's used and it's a really big
problem
so stop laying but also zinc oxide
because zinc oxides really like way
better right
stop lang was kind of just only internal
to fugle and you know they sort of have
it out there but it's not really where
as zinc oxide was more of like an open
language took more feedback from the
academic community we all know how good
the academic community is applying
languages very good the fact that they
never write new code Justin you know
shouldn't shouldn't be held against him
so anyway zinc oxide has that has the
memory composting so what that allows
you to do is after you use some memory
from the memory garden which obviously
you know all the memory has to go
through a memory garden at some point in
order to have the memory be nitrogen
fixated when it's initially created I
unless you're in in Pliska obviously
plis code and data are interchangeable
and you can and you know everything
everything is a blip in that language so
that's like a different kind of language
so I would I would say yeah don't don't
take that one too seriously it's just a
little bit weird but assuming that
you're using zinc oxide or stop Lang you
know that that composting feature is
really important because you know then
instead of all of the garbage collected
memory just getting thrown away all of
that you know that that nutrient rich
used memory is put into a bin right it's
put into a memory bin until it kind of
has a chance to let you know usually
what and and I know this seems weird but
this is very serious security research
was done on both stop laying and zinc
oxide and so a lot of those other
languages that you're that you're
talking about there
of those other languages they don't
appreciate the fact that there's a lot
of other malicious code normally running
on the machine there's like malware you
know viruses but those things are
actually helpful right because what
those things can do is if you just give
them your used memory then what will
happen is those malware's will actually
they will metabolize the used memory and
turn it back into remember you can use
in your actual program right
so a typical language like like stop
lang or zinc oxide that has some of
these more modern memory composting
features they'll take that used memory
after you know you use it in your actual
program to do some computations and
store some things in they'll put it into
the memory composting bin and that bin
is essentially you could think of it as
a memory sandbox right that is running
all of the malware on your machine and
it's it's allowing that composted memory
right to be metabolized by the malware
in back into usable memory and so that
is a really you know again very cutting
edge a very very very cutting edge
language feature that things like stop
lang and zinc oxide have and you know
it's one of the reasons why you know
those are really great languages I can
see why everyone always comes on the
stream and ask me what I think of them
let's see here
all right I think we'll wrap it up for
the day I think we will wrap it up for
the day
pretty please without that wind today I
don't mind telling you despite my lack
of mental grasp on the atan2 in my
imagination how I always seem to get the
basis wrong other than that we did
pretty good today all right thank you
everyone for joining me for this sort of
handmade hero it's our pleasure coding
with you as always if you want to follow
in series at home you can always go to
handmade hero Oregon pre-order the game
it comes with all the source code even
today so you can play around with it and
learn from the series hopefully I will
be back here next week to probably I
guess so I think what we want to do is
do the full version of that alignment
code that I just played around with
today so we can track that off her list
and then we can go like a Lionel our
sprite assets and have a nice like put
all that stuff in the game and that'll
give us a chance to turn the crank a few
times on the asset system and get the
bugs out I know there's still bugs in
there I guarantee you it's just we put
there's it's just really big and there's
a lot of complexity in there now I'm
sure we've got some things wrong going
on there so we need to like actually get
a really good monocle out a really good
evil genius monocle out and look at that
coating and make sure that it's just
right but that's really you know where
we're at and I'm happy about that so I
think the game will look a lot nicer
then because we'll be able to align all
the stuff make it good maybe the after
that will will ping back over to
lighting strip out some of the stuff
make a simpler version of it so we can
run it real real time on lower end
machines and also do a wider version and
then I think we're checked off man I
think we're looking great I think I
think we're ready to populate the game
of stuff hopefully right I don't know
what else we'd have to do Oh wha do
sounds right we want to do some we want
put sounds into the pack files that's
another thing we got to do so you have
some stuff left so we'll be back on that
I hope you join me for that next weekend
until then have fun prettier than anyone
have fun programming everyone I'll see
you on the Internet
use everybody