one welcome to handmade here the show
recode a complete game live on stream i
actually made a crucial error yesterday
a judgment error than i hate to correct
today it's fairly minor thankfully but i
just thought of it when I was falling
asleep last night or failing to fall
asleep last night so I'm gonna start
today with that and of course we're just
doing what we've been doing which is
cleaning up our renderer and making it
into a nice little system that can be
used more generally which i think is a
very good technique to learn if for no
other reason then even when you're
working on projects where everything is
entirely controlled by you and you don't
need anyone else to use the code
sometimes you need to compartmentalize
things for your own benefit and cleaning
up the renderer has already paid a lot
of dividends for us we've removed all
kinds of things that were problematic in
there things like we still have the
screen resolution getting passed through
and used in places where it turns out if
we just stayed in clip cornice the whole
time it eliminates entire complexities
in those systems things like that they
build up over time as you're developing
a system and figuring out how it should
work at some point you need to go
through and clean those out because
otherwise they're constantly
antagonizing you so simplifying cleaning
up changing the interface to comport
with the new way that things finally
work in the in the end these are
valuable things to learn and I like
spending time on them which is why we
are spending time on them now I'm gonna
go ahead and talk about the mistake I
made yesterday because what I did was I
said very specifically I was like well
inside the renderer if we want this to
be abstract what we could do is there's
number of things we could use a C++
virtual inheritance mechanism we could
use an enum we can use the table of
function pointers we can use we can use
organ use right and that's like well you
can kind of pick whichever one you want
I actually picked wrong and I realized
because I wasn't considering something I
realized there is a good reason to go
with one of those structures the one
that I think you should go with that
there actually is an argument of why
it's correct is you actually should go
with a table of function pointers and
the reason you should go to the table of
function pointers
is because duh why not let renderers get
loaded out of dll's right it's exactly
the kind of thing we might want to do
provide allow people to write their own
renderer dll's
that just drop into the game and then
the game can load them dynamically and
render on them right it's the perfect
excuse to do that there's no cost to us
as long as we just make platform
renderer be a func table of function
pointers at that point anyone can write
a DLL that we can use to render and we
can make a thing in the win32 layer that
loads we don't have to do that right now
but making the platform render B
callback based out of a function of
stable function lets us do that not only
does it let us do that
it lets us mix and match those DLLs like
we could even have different dll's
getting fielding different pointers by
changing which function pointers go to
which ones right why is that relevant
well for example we can have a
accelerated a one that's compiled in
release mode and one that's compiled in
debug mode right and we can call the
release mode renderer right up till the
point where we wanted to buy a frame and
then switch the function pointer that we
actually care about whichever one it is
to be the debug pointer right and step
through that code instead there's all
sorts of things we can do if we want it
so I think this is just a better idea so
I I think there's a good reason why this
is actually the wrong decision and the
right decision really looks more like
like get proc address right it's what we
actually want here so if we're gonna do
that we just need to know the things we
were using a switch statement for should
really just be part of the dispatch
table again not because I have anything
against the switch statements I actually
love switch statements I think they're
great just in this case they're not the
appropriate solution to the problem in
my opinion that's in win32 hand-made
OpenGL here
so these switch statements we really
just want to change them to callbacks
again it's pretty straightforward how we
would do
that we just need a good place to do it
right and off we go
so what I'm going to do here is take the
functions we were calling there's only
three of them I think let me just see
here yeah this is all there is so out of
each of those we may want a way to shut
down the wrath render but I don't know
that probably needs to be
platform-specific so really I think
we're talking just about these at least
at the moment okay so I'm gonna have a
render process texture cube I'm gonna
have a renderer begin frame and I'm
gonna have a renderer end frame and each
of these it's just going to be a macro
that defines the kind of function that
I'm talking about here so for example in
the case of process texture Q what we're
talking about is something that looks
like this this is what the function
prototype always will look like
similarly for begin frame we're talking
about something that looks like this
and then finally for in frame we're
talking about something that looks like
this not quite like that and that's just
a way to quickly define what these are
anytime we want again the reason I use
this defined process is because it
allows me to generate all of the things
that I want just from one line of code
so this right here can generate the type
def for me here for example is going to
be my renderer process texture cue so
this defines a type def of a pointer to
a function so I can use that right and I
can do this for each of these
blender again Frank and here is the end
framed version so each of these is now a
texture pointer I mean I've touched
that's good a function pointer inside my
renderer and we just need to call them
when we want to use them right that's
what we're gonna do in each of these
cases now if you look at what's going on
here each one of these like we've got
the the type that's here again like said
the reason I do the functions is because
now when I actually want to define the
functions themselves that are going to
get used I actually can just do that
directly I'm gonna delete these here we
do know that we need to include this in
the open jail end frame so I'm gonna put
that in here real quick
but let me go ahead and do that so if I
want to define one of these now I can
just do a winter tear open jail end
frame that's the function and I can go
ahead and make in here the calls that I
want to make like so right so inside my
win32 I can define these callbacks that
I want and how I want them again
processed textures would be the same way
just grab these out here and it doesn't
have to do anything special for the
win32 version here so we could consider
that moving in in I'm not going to just
going to leave it all in the win32 side
just in case in the future we want to do
win32 specific things in there and then
finally we just want this version in
here again very very simple you see me
do this before if you're regular to the
series very straightforward that just
goes ahead and provides those callbacks
so that the renderer knows what it's
doing right it's like these are these
are the the three ways that we interact
with the renderer we know how when threw
up in jail works now it's these three
ways right
those are now defined to be compliant
with these texture with these function
pointers which means that when we
actually do a win32 init opengl when we
come through here and do an OpenGL
initialization when we get down here and
are about to return this this is when we
want to set these function pointers so
that they can be called so we here what
we're gonna do is actually just set them
now we do our alloc here I'm gonna set
them just right off the bat so I'm gonna
set them right in here you can see the
the ones I need to set there these right
so there's the header and I'm gonna set
these individual function pointers to be
the functions that I just defined on the
win32 side so each of these is what we
want so here's the begin frame oops
here's the processed extras call and I
feel like I'm going to put that first
because it seems like the ordering is
this one this one this one so I'm just
gonna keep those and that fills out our
function table right now again this is
very similar to what would happen in a
virtual function call scenario only
we're using a slight difference so in a
virtual and I like to go over this a
couple times because people we don't do
any real C++ stuff on this stream
because I don't like it I don't think
it's very good
but it's worth understanding how it
works so the way a C++ implementation
would have worked is very similar to
what we're doing here but with a slight
difference so it a C++ implementation
would do it like this and it would do
this for you automatically do you see
the difference there so in one case we
have a renderer and in the renderer are
the function pointers themselves and
we're calling directly through those
function pointers right so we get a
pointer to a thing and we say to use the
thing it's got some pointers in it we
just jumped through those pointers great
okay that's this that's what we were
doing the Seba Swiss model is in
directed again it says hey we got a
platform renderer we're actually going
to point to the table of function
pointers so we're gonna first look
through that pointer then look through
the other pointers to do our dispatch
why did they want to do it that way
right it adds an extra indirection
that's bad right well you have to
understand C++ involved at a time when
in directed in wasn't really that big of
a deal as compared to maybe space size
amount of memory used right and you can
see why this takes a lot less space
because every object you instantiate
right in the c++ parlance only needs one
pointer it just needs a pointer to the
table whereas in our version every one
you instantiate needs all the pointers
in themselves that may be better for
cache coherency maybe I mean you don't
know until you check it right because
that table would probably be hot in the
cache a lot too right
but point being he adds more size to the
object which you might not want to do
right so it's worth noting that there
are trade-offs there C++ generates this
one for you that's what a virtual
function table is is the thing that
looks like this you never get to see it
but that's what it's doing I'm doing
something sort of similar but not quite
exactly the same and it looks like this
and again what I will do in the future
is I'll probably get proc address these
out of a DLL so that we can have
different renderers that drop into the
game as
we decide that we want them to be right
so that's all oops
that started there it must have hit the
F key accidentally so that's all that
difference is it's not particularly
different
I like these methods a lot better when I
create them myself because it gives me
more control I don't care for the way
C++ tends to do things most of time
which is why I don't use it but it's
worth understanding it's not magic right
you can make the same thing yourself a
C++ can make and if you let's see if I
supposed to make it for you you don't
have to sit around wondering what
they're doing you can actually go look
even in the debugger and see that what I
just said is what's happening right with
those with those function calls right
you can see that your struct has that
pointer in you can see that it looks
through that pointer to get the table
okay so once we have that now we just
need to make sure that we're actually
using these calls when we wish to
dispatch to the platform renderer so
when I compile we will get complaints
now I'm gonna have to pre declare the
platform render here since this it gets
passed in there but that's fine I
probably also have to do the texture cue
yes maybe I guess not
[Music]
probably the game render commands though
these are just for word declares so that
those names can be resolved there we go
and texture cue I was right I did need
it I was like won't I need the texture
cue and yes I do
there it is so now all we need to do is
make sure that that each of these things
wait how did that that is not what I
meant to do it all there that was some
that was some copypasta for me there
that was actually the allocation code
why did I do that I have no idea why I
did that that was just dumb alright well
sorry about that this is the allocation
Kurt I don't know why I put it there our
allocation code at the moment we are
coming out of a we aren't using an
actual dll yet so I'm just gonna leave
this as an internal call you can make
and in fact you can just call win32 and
it opened jail as of you can you could
almost call it directly but I don't want
you to cast it there so I'm gonna
pretend that we have sort of the DLL
loading thing going on here for the
moment and we'll get to that later
right so if we have this call here
really all we're doing is proxying this
call like so
this way all we're going to do is
practice this call here so we need to
call this something else so you know
this is just kind of arbitrary how we're
gonna do this that's how I'm gonna do it
for now so that's all we really need to
do now we just need to change our calls
into it this allocate renderer call is
really just going to be went through
opengl load renderer for now and we're
gonna change that to use of DOL and then
if I come through here and I look at its
that's passed in the wrong order there
there we go
all of these just need to call off of
the renderer right so the renderer that
we have there just we're just calling
off of the renderer so every time we
want to do whatever we're doing here we
just call off of the renderer right very
very straightforward now for a begin
frame I don't like I said I don't really
remember what we were doing for begin
frame here but I'm think we didn't
really do anything for a big in frame
I'm pretty sure it was just the a pretty
sure it was just a straight call through
right I think this is all we were doing
I don't think there was any actual other
stuff so I think this is actually what
and and all we really needed to do here
we just need to cast this to the kind of
pointer we actually have
and I think that's it so that's the only
change I wanted to make and like I said
we can live this out of DLL maybe we can
compiled as a DLL now just to prove that
point but that's really it
and so now everything just works fine
right let's go ahead and make that
change in handmade hero as well so in
here where we do this instead of
allocate renderer I'm just going to call
winter to OpenGL renderer and pass these
in like so and we can still do a lot of
things we could do with an enamel we're
just gonna do them with a file name in
the future right because what we can do
is say look whatever file name you
loaded to render out of is the renderer
you're using and that can be saved and
loaded from disk as well so we'll get
the benefits we would have gotten within
them as well so there's it running
outside of handmade hero the renderer
here's it running inside handmade here
the renderer in both cases these are
both unoptimized their debug builds at
the moment so that I think is just
better and again like I said the reason
that I think that's better is because it
allows us to load the renderer out of a
dll and not have to worry about like
letting other if other people want to
provide new renderers they just can this
is kind of fun I feel like like let's
suppose someone just wants to make a ray
tracer for handmade hero they just can
right they can just replace a dll they
don't have to touch the game code at all
right they can just drop in a new dll
and it would work so I'm kind of curious
right if let's say we want to do that
let's say we actually want to just make
it be part of the DLL we already know
that we can build dll's pretty easily
right we have a way to do those things
and we do them for the game right so if
we wanted to
as far as renderer was concerned right
we can have a thing here that's like you
know renderers and we can build in here
the renderers that we want to build so
if we want to I don't need to include
Ayaka at the moment
so if I want to build one of these I can
and I can make a file that will allow me
to do that and yeah I'm gonna go ahead
and and try so you can see here we pass
some stuff I don't need to specify the
PDB in this stuff we may want to do that
at some point but you can see here we
build in some exports what I want to do
is define those exports to be very
specific calls alright so if I now want
to break this out into a DLL in win32
hand-made open jail which is the code
that we're talking about specifically if
we look at what those have to be what we
can see here is like win32 init open
jail and so forth I'm sorry with you and
frame begin frame and process texture
cue right these are the functions that
we actually want to be generic across
renderers I can change them to be like
this well okay you know I just realized
even that I don't need those don't need
to be exported because we actually just
need the initialization be exported so
if we take a look at what actually
happened here it's really only the the
load call right because since we load
the pointers into the thing we provide
we don't need to export those functions
because no one's gonna bind against them
so if we just export the load then on
load you will call it you'll get back
the struck that's got the functions in
it you need your done right so what I'm
gonna have it be here is just platform
load renderer that call needs to take
some information with it I'm gonna call
it win32 load renderer I think because
since its platform specific it's gonna
need information from the app that's
window specific right that is important
so it's not a platform agnostic load
call because it needs you to pay it
needs to be called from the win32 layer
and you would need another shim so you
need like mac OpenGL or whatever if you
wanted to do this on Mac right
it needs to have match specific startup
code in it okay so that's how that would
work so if I just go ahead and say look
we're gonna export this function okay
that's going to come out this dll right
it's going to come out then what I can
do is build the DLL of this by saying
win32 handmade OpenGL complete compile
this for me that can now be its own
compilation unit right so I'm going to
try that just to see what we can do if
we make it alright so the first thing we
have to do is change a little bit about
the way we do our our compilation here
all of this stuff that we used to call
like that we use to include we don't
need to include anymore so their OpenGL
side of things like all this stuff
actually doesn't need to be here anymore
handmade OpenGL renderer opengl those
things are actually not necessary
anymore
outside of the OpenGL render itself
those are going to be baked in here now
we still need all this stuff because
these things are themselves used inside
the renderer but we don't need to
include any OpenGL specific things in
here right so now let's go ahead and
build let's see what we've got here so
now we just need our platform includes
like things that we rely on from Windows
itself that's just this stuff there we
go
and similarly now inside here we don't
need to include OpenGL anymore because
we're not going to include the OpenGL
renderer right none of this has to know
that opengl exists at all
we never have to talk about OpenGL if we
don't want to right okay so now let's
see what kind of problems we get here
we're getting some read some kind of
problem with a redefinition I don't know
why who is doing that what's happening
here
oops somebody is doing some kind of a
pound include that I don't like I'm not
sure you
don't see why that would have happened
actually twins to accidentally include
the same thing twice number let's take a
look
C++ doesn't compilers don't generally
have the best error reporting for things
like this some I think LLVM has
considerably better error reporting so
yeah but let me just double check what's
going on we don't care what any of these
or these or those or those or those so
we're really just talking about and sign
a made types so this looks I know this
looks pretty reasonable what's the how
did we get multiple defensible for
buffer struct type redefinition where
did it so we're including we're
including handmade types twice I'm just
not sure how I did that because I didn't
think I did but I obviously did oh
there's the couple right there a file
should not include itself just in case
you were wondering all right let's see
what else we got opened Jill debug
callback undeclared event so this GL
debug callback pound define that looks
like that wasn't done yet that's
probably because it's all in here so
some of these definitions should we
should probably move down so I'm
guessing that we just want to do this
here to make sure these are all already
accounted for let me just double check
that yeah there we go
um so win32 load renderer is the only
thing in here that we're actually
exporting so that's the function we want
to export what you can see here is even
though I clearly have it defined you can
see that it can't find this symbol why
not well the reason that it can't find
it is because this thing isn't
unfortunately exported in any it isn't
set up to be named that on
what's heard before I'm compiled
now what do I mean by that well if you
pay attention to all of handmade hero
you already know what happens here but
this is kind of stretching it it goes
way back so for those of you who don't
remember when you compile C++ code
mangles all the names what that means is
hey C++ allows overloaded functions it
means two functions with different
parameters but the same name are
distinguishable in order to support that
in the old days since names were
typically used to bind functions to
their call points what they did is they
just made up new names that included
what the parameters were in the name so
you could still use the old linkage
system for it that means that win32 load
renderer doesn't come out being called
win32 load renderer it comes out being
called some really ridiculous long
mangled name instead what we have to do
if we want to tell it to not mangle the
name so that we can find that and export
it is just call it X turn see once we
call it extra and see it knows that that
name will stay the same and we should be
able to do it of course as I say this it
turns out that it actually did not find
the name so I take it back don't take my
word for it I will have to find out why
it decided not to that's okay so okay I
guess not let me look at that build
again I assumed that it would do that
for me apparently it wouldn't do that
for me so you know oh well such as life
so my assumption was that hey if we're
compiling went through to handmade
OpenGL and I just marked this as extra
and C win32 load renderer
will come out as a function that is
named what it is named but unfortunately
as you can see in here that's not
actually what happened so forcing it to
export this it didn't actually want to
export it woe is me now I'm not sure why
it didn't because I feel like once I do
an extra and see on that it should have
done it for me
so now I just want to know well why are
you having trouble finding that function
I specifically said that this should be
fine right and so I just want to know at
this point what did I screw up I
obviously screwed something up and I'm
just forgetting something important that
I was supposed to do but the question is
how do I figure it out so the first
thing I want to do is just look to see
hey if this went through handmade open
Jill that obj right which is the thing
that got created what I could pile this
file can you just tell me what you
thought was in here so that I know what
the names were right like can you give
me some information um so what I'm gonna
do is try writing a thing called dump in
it's part of the visual studio utilities
I'm just gonna ask it can you just tell
me what can you tell me about this obj
file you compiled what's in it right
what are what you know what do you
actually have it in there maybe I'll do
all of us to see ok maybe not quite that
all yeah the fact that exports didn't
tell me anything
suggests that I've got issues right but
that's kind of beside the point um let's
see here yeah I mean if exports doesn't
show anything I think I'm kind of dead
in the water so that's obviously the
problems that we've got let's take a
look at those symbols there
Oh duh oh man
so maybe the long pre stream threw me
for a loop you'll notice I still was
saying that it's an internal which is
which means static right to us which
means it's not gonna export it so I
don't know what I was thinking there
that is all it is yeah so when you say
something like that and you say that
when you say that something's file scope
only it's not going to appear in the
import table right so we have to remove
that because even though I said extra
and see it won't mangle the name what
I'm curious about is if I get rid of
that is it smart enough to override the
name I think it is yeah that's what I
thought so when I first put that extra
in see in there I was like I shouldn't
have had to do that because usually at
least my recollection and they changed
these things all the time so you know
taken with a grain of salt when you
specify something to export it usually
turns off the name mangling for you on
that automatically usually right so I
was weirded out with the fact I had to
do it I forgot that this static will
over like that takes precedence
this isn't strong enough to override
that don't ask me why probably just
because this is - the linker and this is
- the compiler so it never actually gets
this function far enough to do this I
suspect so I think if I want to do this
I think I'm actually okay I'm not sure
though meaning just get rid of the
internal and you're fine let's double
check so oops
I don't need symbols there sorry I just
need exports let me see if I can get
that to show up well that didn't
actually show up so I'm not sure I'm not
sure if it's okay or not I'm not sure if
it's okay or not so let me finish the
rest of this linking and then we'll see
what will toggle it either way so what
you'll notice is we can't finish
compiling because we have a bunch of
undefined symbols those undefined
symbols are all linker issues their
libraries that we need that we don't
have now I don't know where we defined
these but they're basically all in here
and we're gonna at least need the open G
32 and the GDI 32 stuff so I'm gonna go
ahead and put those on here let me just
go ahead and see where we've got there
and then it yeah yeah
so handmade went so witty to him in open
Jill I don't know where these are coming
in though destroy window create window
register class I don't understand why
those would be involved in winter to him
it made OpenGL though so I want to just
look and see why why are those getting
called right just so I can double check
like that they should be so yeah I'm not
sure yes so we had to create a dummy
window in order to test for these things
first
okay so that's fine I just wanted to
make sure those should be there there's
nothing wrong with doing that so I'll
leave that in there but that means we do
need to link with the user 32 which is
where the standard window functions come
from right so that's all good so that
allows us to build our tol there we go
and now we're done we you know we've
we've got a dll built and it should be
ready to go I'm gonna check those
exports again so it's weird to me that
that doesn't have that in there because
it looks like it does here yeah okay so
as you can see my fears about the
mangled name though we're still correct
so it looks like you still end up do
with do end up with a bunch of name
mangling whether that's actually
prompted dll you don't know that because
you can see here it knows that the name
is a short name I assume that's the one
that it puts in the dll's import table
but who knows let's run depends on it to
find out so again this is something that
will allow us to look at our DLL and see
what it actually is exporting like what
it actually directly says and that's
just a way to know whether we did that
correctly
not so um I was actually the right
director there so here's that one
through to your handmade OpenGL DLL and
if we look at that after incredibly a
long time of it walking tons of things
because kernel now depends on eight
million things in blah blah blah there
we go we should be able to see what we
actually depend on and here they are
these are the four things to depend on
that's what we want those are things we
expect so let's see what we export
here's what we export you can see that
even though the name itself
we didn't extern see it right so you can
see here we didn't extra and see it the
fact that we told it we wanted an export
it did use the comfortable name for us
right so that's exactly what we wanted
to happen so we don't need the extra and
see it understands that name mangling
isn't appropriate for being in the dll
so when we named it that in the export
it puts it in there correctly so now
we've got a dll that we can just use you
know we can just call that so that means
if we wanted to take our went through to
render test now what we could do is say
okay let's go ahead and just get rid of
any notion that the win32 OpenGL
renderer is built into here right let's
get rid of that and instead let's call
this as a function call so let's do it
right here
here's the load library call right and
for those of you that don't remember
we're just going to pass a name of a
library to load dynamic one flower to
load windows we'll load it we can then
get function pointers out of it by name
so if you go familiarize yourself with
this function if you don't know what it
is right this is it right here all you
have to do is just pass a file name to
it that's it right that's all you have
to do so what I want to do is I want to
call load library and again remember we
were we want this to work in unicode or
otherwise so we're gonna use this text
macro to wrap it this is just in case
people compiled unicode verses ascii we
want it to work in either one i believe
you have to use load library a or w if
you want to call specific one so we're
just gonna let it call the default one
for however the person's compiling and
we're gonna pass in and through to
handmade opengl dot dll as a string
that's just it makes it easier for the
person to understand what's going on
right they don't they know that we're
just wrapping the string with whatever
kind of you know whether it's supposed
to be a utf-16 or UTF well we're asking
write or ANSI so i'm gonna go ahead and
do the the load library here the load
library is going to return me this
module and that module handle is
literally just a handle to the loaded
code right it's just a way of
identifying two windows what code I'm
talking about um
and so here's the render DLL at that
point what I want to do is just get the
function pointer for loading this for
loading the renderer out right and so in
order to do that what I want to do is
again up here I kind of want to define
the way that win32 stuff gets loaded the
problem with doing it in here is this is
not this is a platform nastic file so
what I want to do is I want to have in
the code base I want to have a win
through to handmade renderer H this is a
thing where win32 specific stuff will
live it's very short file unfortunately
but we need to have that
accessible basically to the system in
this way because we need a place to
define the window specific call right so
what I want to do there is just say okay
to load though zooming to load those in
we need something cure that will that
will load the render and you know I can
also take advantage of the fact that
we've got this win through through
handmade renderer bit here I can make
that actually be something that you link
in which has the win32 code necessary to
loads the the render as well so I could
like wrap this up in there actually that
might be a good way to do it but we'll
kind of get to that as we go so what I
want to do here is just say all right
there's a win32 load render recall again
this is exactly the same way as I was
doing my other function callbacks and so
inside here where we've got this win
through to load renderer I want that to
be a function prototype because every
dll that's up on win32 that supports
rendering that anyone want to make wants
to conform to this so what we're gonna
do is the exact same thing we did before
we're gonna supply the name here as part
of the macro and then we're just going
to go ahead and define this so here's
our type def for a function pointer to
one of these loaders this is going to be
win through to the renderer the call
that's the type def and then here we're
just going to use that okay so that's it
that's all we need it and now we know
that this is the the function pointer
that we're trying to load we also can
make it so that this name itself is
actually a specific name that we always
know so we could even do it like this
right again these are just there so when
people make these they just do that and
they know that they're gonna define the
right thing and they don't have to think
about it ever again
right so you just do that and you know
that it's defined properly for you and
if we change what's getting passed here
everyone can just recompile and run okay
you know I'm saying so if we do that
right then in here what we can do as
well is just have actually we can have
this be something that just is built
into the the H file so we could say like
hey winter to load renderer you know
load to load render DLL and this would
just take this thing right so whatever
you pass through to this whatever like t
care you know string you get here this
is the file name we can just make that
be something in here that loads the
renderer dll in and then does it get
proc address on that renderer dll using
the winter to load renderer name and
make sure that all of that stuff is
specified properly I don't think you can
get proc to address wide Kara stars so I
think that's literally just like I think
there's no get podcast yeah I think it's
just get proc address I can't quite
remember though so we'll double check
that later but anyway so if we load this
out of the DLL there's our you know
retrieving our function pointer that
means that the user of this can
literally just do this right they can
get their their renderer loader out here
by calling this function and then they
can call it whenever they want right
okay alright so let's see here what's
the problem there it's not what I wanted
just want win32 renderer there it is
um so here's the definition of that
function but Windows DC should have been
defined there so what's the problem
oh the problem is this isn't including
it that's all okay so that probably
should be down here after everything is
defined okay and there we go so that
also has to get included here like so
but otherwise I think we're fine okay
so this is pretty straightforward now
it's basically exactly the same thing we
were doing before it just comes out of a
dll now right so now if we look at what
this code does what we should be able to
do is if we go to the render test now
remember the render test is now being
built with no open jail code in it
whatsoever it doesn't even need to link
to open jail in fact let's go ahead and
make that true just so we can
double-check right so here's a render a
testbed it's passed common linker flags
so common liquor flags here includes all
of these sausage gentlemen right so
OpenGL 32 is included in there so I'm
just gonna get rid of that so OpenGL 32
is no longer included in there right so
we we no longer require OpenGL to even
start we will start up with no OpenGL
bound at all ok so now if we loop
through here and we take a look at what
happens let's set a breakpoint when we
enter our renderer thread right here and
if I step through here what you can see
is when we do win through to load
renderer I'm gonna come through here I'm
here's my file name and through the
availab shell I'm gonna try to load it I
load it successfully I'm gonna try and
get the address of this procedure I did
get it and so now we can call it right
we can call in here and call in it up in
jail so now this is running entirely in
an external DLL right and we can make as
many versions of that dll's we want
which render through different things so
right now literally if you want to go
make a d3 D version you can just do that
drop it in place and you
run on d3d right so we are now not we
have no coupling to open jail whatsoever
in that testbed which is great right so
that's a nice way to keep that flexible
now if we come back here and look we
note that we do have you know we
probably want to as you know maybe put
up an error message or something here
right like if we try to load this
maybe we just exit process if we can't
do it
maybe we even push up put up a message
box right and so for example if I was to
say you know here we go
so it's window text caption type type in
this case is a fatal error so we just
want this because there's really nothing
else we can do
and then we probably want Ike on
exclamation or well I can't stop or icon
error maybe I kind of error let's say
okay so if we look at the call to this
we want the window handle there which we
have we want our to text things to here
to be okay
so now if we fail to actually get this
it's just exit process with an error
code there whatever I don't care
um so now if we fail to actually find
that that renderer we just can't start
right if we don't have a renderer we
can't start so here's us finding the
render if I now go in and without
recompiling to generate a new one if I
just delete right I just get rid of our
renderer DLL which is this thing right
here then we should find that it pops up
a dialog box right and just says hey we
ain't going nowhere fast my friends
right um so this is pretty great right
now we're we're good to go we can just
treat this render as something that's
externally usable anyone can do it and
you don't really have to think about it
too hard right we can also go one step
further and figure well okay if this is
the stuff that someone has to do to get
started and win32 well why not just make
it completely trivial for them why not
just do this
right so we can just say win32 load
default under it or initialize default
render or something like that doesn't
take anything that well no actually
it'll take this it'll do all this for
you including popping up the message box
if it's not there and then it'll return
the renderer to you in this case so that
wraps all of that up really cleanly and
you can just say hey do everything
please I don't want to think about it
so that's just a again a really simple
utility function so now you know anyone
can just call it it'll check to see if
it's there it'll fail catastrophically
if it's not an off you would go right so
that's just again just really basic
nothing particularly exciting going on
there right very very simple so if we
wanted that to work in handmade hero as
well again nothing really particularly
odd has to happen first of all we got to
make sure that we don't include any of
this stuff so now like these things like
win32 open jail and so on like that
stuff just shouldn't be in here
right none of that stuff should be
included in there it should just be
missing and yeah we don't want so I
don't know where all these things are
defined we don't want that right we
really we don't need these either
because those would now be outside in
fact all of this stuff I don't even know
if Cindy is necessary they're probably
not
so I'm pretty sure that's it right and
so all we would need to do now is have
went through your handmade renderer
included here and then we're good to go
so at the point where we were doing went
through to load OpenGL renderer here we
can just call that utility function that
same one that we had here which is went
through to in it right and we would pass
the window there so then when we run the
you know this is using that DLL when we
run handmade hero it now uses the exact
same DLL like they're literally calling
the exact same DLL whether you're
running outside or inside right so I
didn't think of that yesterday otherwise
that's the way I would have done it I
don't know why I didn't think of it a
renderer is an obvious thing to just
stick in a DLL now anyone who wants to
screw around with handmade hero and
implement completely different renderers
you can go do a crazy optimized cool
renderer you could do a ray tracer you
could do anything you want you can now
just put that into the renderer and be
done with it right I wouldn't recommend
doing that quite yet because we're still
working on make some of the API stuff
here but that's what's going on right so
now we've made that clean split and I
think that's pretty great because now
when we have the final version we'll be
good to go okay um so now what I'd like
to do is just focus on cleaning up some
of these other API is here um so let's
pop back over to our renderer test which
is this um so looking at the renderer
tests like I said I'd like to clean up
some of the camera stuff here and I'd
like to clean up some of the sprite push
stuff those are the two things that we
really have left to clean up there and
then I feel like we're mostly down to
just making the header files pretty may
be breaking down the code into making it
clear like what you would and wouldn't
use in various circumstances and so on
like so just like kind of general text
cleanup that's not really about the code
it's just about how it's organized in
files so that it's easier to carve off
or things like that
so we we got maybe a little bit to do
there but mostly we're good alright so
if you take a look at all this stuff for
the camera information just you can look
at this stuff we're doing with camera
and I feel like we can wrap a lot of
that stuff up into some some basic
functions that people can use in the
math library again this is just for the
sake of people who don't want to see
really think too hard about this stuff
if we look at get standard camera params
one of the things that you note here is
just that that's actually defined in the
renderer even though I'm not sure that
the renderer necessarily cares that much
about things like camera params so if we
look at the camera params themselves
it's just focal length now so I think
what we want to actually do is change
the way that we're thinking about camera
params to be sort of their own thing and
then when you do rendering you can pass
like whole like more complex things down
to functions as necessary right so the
first thing I want to do is sort of get
rid of anywhere that talks about camera
params that's directly in the renderer
so for example well actually you know
what I don't think we do which is good
so the renderer doesn't really care
about these right so what I was thinking
is we could just make a thing like
handmade camera that's just got a bunch
of camera utility stuff in it and that's
like optional if you want to use it
right so I'm gonna go ahead and make a
handmade camera oops
eh and what I'm gonna do here is just
grab the stuff I'm gonna just go to
Lemongrab here the camera params out and
put him in here okay now when I compile
I'm gonna get I don't include this
anywhere so I'm gonna get some problems
in the places where we don't have those
camera prams right so I'm going to grab
again just Lemongrab in here the the
code that relates to this and putting it
in the handmade camera stuff
there we go alright and so now everyone
who uses those is kind of at a
disadvantage because hey it's gone right
oops
but that's okay anyone who wants to use
it can use it and they can just include
that handmade camera dot cpp right and
handmade camera dot H so now anyone who
wants those utilities can use them but
that's where they come from then what I
want to do is make sure in anywhere we
use them now we can expand on kind of
the what a camera pram actually is and
what it can do for you is sort of what I
want to push on there right if that
makes sense so let's go ahead and just
put that in here again that doesn't
really matter too much where we put
these because it's kind of arbitrary
we're just putting them all in here
right maybe I'll just make sure they're
underneath the wherever the renderer
went just yeah all right okay so now if
I come back over to win32 render test
and I look at what we're doing in here
with the with the camera stuff you can
see all of this information that I've
got in terms of setting up a camera view
for looking at a character on the screen
and what I like to do is just move that
over so that it all gets initialized
automatically I and you don't really
have to do a lot to think about it right
and all this stuff we can start to have
happen automatically as well right so
let's go ahead and do that
let's just go ahead and do that so
here's my camera routines and what I
want to do is I want to start by pulling
out some of this information here right
so what you could see is when this stuff
happens you can see that we're not
really using this yet the first place
that we start to use it is down here and
we do this like camera ot+ camera offset
right and we passed a bunch of stuff the
camera oh information here you can see
all the stuff that we're doing um all of
that I want to start making more like I
want this to be more encapsulate able to
people who don't know what they're doing
they can just use something here right
they can just use something that does
this automatically for you
so at the very least I want to do
something like this and I'll be honest I
don't understand why this camera Oh
can't just have the tea baked into it
right so to actually just to even do it
slightly differently than that let's not
even do this yet let's just fix this so
that we are good to go so if I take this
camera out here and I just translate it
right so instead you know when we're
doing here I can say like get
translation out of it or whatever let me
let me look at translate here so you can
see this translate called
I'm just gonna go ahead and say you know
camera matrix and what I'm gonna do is
I'm going to translate the matrix that
comes back by this by the camera dolly
amount right so that's how much I'm
going to translate that by and you can
see I also add this camera offset in
which is this thing here so I really
just want to add the camera offset to
right
so that's really what I'm trying to do
and then in so when we come down through
here more I think that pretty much just
gives us what we want right am I wrong
about that let me just double check oh
wait no no no I'm not quite right we do
use it to multiply first right we use it
to multiply here however I mean just to
be clear if we were to make a
translation matrix to begin with that
would have just worked so I know this is
a little bit confusing these operators
will operate on this if it was on the
right side here right so we could have
just said this right that is actually
the same thing so what we really want to
be able to do is do a translation but it
looks like we don't have a thing for
building a translation matrix here no
worries
that's about the easiest matrix you
could ever build right I'll just call
that T here's the matrix for building
if this is the identity matrix here
right we know that when we actually do
our translation here that we're going to
be multiplying we're multiplying column
vectors by row vectors right that's how
we've structured our matrices to work so
we know the W component of one is gonna
multiplying these values so if we want
to translate something all we have to do
is put our translation in that final
column and that's where in the matrix
translation will occur right if we then
put this back here like I said flowing
through the matrix this will
automatically do that transform because
as these rotations come catenate on they
will rotate the translation that exists
in the matrix as they're doing their
multiplication so this camera M just
basically builds everything we wanted
and so here we can just say that right
and that just recreates exactly what we
already had you know everything should
work well that's the wrong program that
just recreates everything we already had
and as you can see it's just doing that
operation right nothing particularly
special going on there
okay um again we can continue this
process if we want you notice this is a
translation that happens in this order
remember we again we've done all over
this in handmade hero all before but
I'll just keep saying it for people who
you know well it helps to say things
multiple times right so matrix
concatenation because of the way we're
using our matrices which is to say that
the columns of our matrix are the object
axes right not the rows the columns it's
our choice how we wish to organize our
matrices it's our choice how we set up
that math we chose to go with the
traditional math formulation not the
traditional graphics formulation where
the objects made are actually rows
that's a whole nother situation but we
went the math style because of that when
we actually concatenate transforms
together it means that you can think of
reading the transforms from the right to
the left so the first thing that happens
is we translate by camera dolly the next
thing that happens is we rotate by the
camera pitch around the x axis that's
this twist and then the final thing we
do is we rotate around the z-axis by the
camera orbit right so the order goes
from right to left that's because when
matrices are multiplied together in that
order
right you are I can't really give this
entire equation you should go back to
him here's when I explained how matrix
may tradition works but because we are
doing it in that order and that is how
we have structured our matrices we are
constantly doing the reinterpretation
from right to left so this matrix is
reinterpreted in the coordinate system
of this matrix which means that this one
is the one that is applied conceptually
first and then it is reinterpreted here
and then reinterpreted here right and
again we have lots of information on
that so if I want this camera offset to
be applied and I want to get rid of that
in here I can just do this right I can
just put it here
and again that series of matrix
concatenations will just give me exactly
what I want um what is the problem
syntax error semicolon I deleted one too
many and again I can just build that all
up with one matrix operation so this is
the complete one for dolly pet with an
asset at the end plus an offset at the
beginning right and then the sort of the
orbit cam in there as a separate issue
right now if we wanted to we could also
add shake in there so if we wanted to
give it a bit of a way to shake this way
we also could I don't know that we need
to do that at the moment but you can see
why I want to pull that out because then
that way we can get it more into a way
of just getting the camera matrix here
out directly this way so we can say you
can see me starting down how the road to
where I want to be in terms of of an API
here for the camera right so I want to
make a call
that's like build camera matrix right
they kind of want to wait to say that
this is the matrix that says what the
camera itself is in the world
not the camera transfer matrix so those
are two different things right the
matrix that moves things into the
cameras space for viewing is actually
the inverse matrix of the one that tells
you where the camera is in the world
right those are opposite operations so
I'm not sure if the best name for that
is but that you know is kind of a
separate issue so if I just implement
this directly where you pass the orbit
the pitch the dolly and the offset
I now have a function that gets rid of
some of that math for someone who again
might not be knowledgeable enough about
3d math to know what was going on there
and might be confused but this is
probably easier for them to understand
because it's gonna do the math for them
right
so hopefully that cleans up fat a little
bit and just makes it easier to make
that call but we still have a lot of
stuff going on here and again we could
make this much simpler by sort of
continuing to reduce the degree to which
you need to interact with these things
ought to set up the camera so again
refining the API a little bit further
the question is what else can we do
and like how can we do more with fog
settings and so on like how can we start
to roll all that stuff up into one you
know what I mean and so what I would
like to do here is say well what if get
standard camera params is maybe
something again that now could sort of
come out here and we can have this
camera params that sort of rolls up a
bunch of this stuff maybe what I can do
is just call this camera and and not
camera params cuz it's just not really
necessary we don't have an actual camera
object thing in our game so we don't
need to worry about that conflicting so
what we could do is just roll all this
stuff up here and actually make this be
something that gets specified more
directly so let's suppose we just took
all of this stuff that we've got in line
here put it all in to this
and set all of these things based on
that information so then when you get
one of these standard camera frames you
actually get a whole lot more than than
that right oops and where's that focal
length oh it's right there
there we go right so this gets that
automatically and now when we come down
here we can sort of start to work with
this as a as like a bucket that has all
these things in it so then we can make a
version of this that just works with
camera params directly and you'll notice
I'm not gonna get rid of this one
because maybe we still want to be able
to call this one so all I'm gonna do is
say hey if you call this on here it's
just a utility to avoid you having to
think about where those things come from
so you're just funking through to the
existing API call again this is about
granularity here this is about giving
you those options of calling something
at a higher level or calling it at a
lower level if you find that that's
better right now camera offsets didn't
get put in here so it needs to so we
actually want our camera
probably to look more like this right
and then we need this to actually have
all these things in it so there's the
pitch the orbit the dolly the focal
length your clip playing our clip plane
just like the transform parameters and
then the offset oops
don't ask me what that just did all
right okay so once we have all that now
again we can we can just continue to
simplify these things really nicely
which I will which I will do
and so now right we still want to be
able to do these things and we can write
we can still just set these things
anytime we want we can also just now
simplify this call because it's just
that and then we can imagine again what
you can see where we're going with this
we'll be able to simplify this call as
well to be something that you can use
without having to think about what it's
doing right so let's keep going there we
go
so now you can see again the same exact
results but now the person who made this
app if they weren't us and don't know 3d
math it's getting simpler right it's
getting simpler and simpler and simpler
for them and that's good right that's
what we want so let's keep it even
let's just keep pushing that as far as
we can push it so set camera transform
I'm gonna change the name of this to use
camera or view from camera right and
that's gonna be a utility it's gonna
take a render group and it's gonna take
a camera and it's gonna do this work for
you so now you can just make this
semantic call hey I would like to view
from this camera please you don't have
to know anything it'll do all of this
work for you and now it's just semantic
begin a group of things here's where I
want to view them from I push my scene
on all the stuff I want to draw end and
that's the end of the frame right
very very very straightforward right
um so how do we do that well first of
all we know we need that camera matrix
well that's okay that just goes right in
here then we do all of this stuff off of
the camera that we have and it's as
simple as that
now note this is kind of exactly like
what I talk about when I sort of use the
phrase compression oriented programming
right well I forgot we haven't really
talked about the fog stuff so we'll talk
about the fog stuff a little bit later
um we just took what we saw as how the
API was being used and we make we reduce
the complexity of what's getting called
by making utility functions that do the
normal things we don't remove the
ability to do them at the lower levels
because that's good that gives us the
granularity if the user of this renderer
wants to get more and more specific they
can they don't have to use our camera
and that's crucial don't force them to
use something when we don't need to
force them provide the option right
provide the option okay um so now again
here is this same exact thing running
but again the API so much easy
for someone who doesn't know what's
going on look at how simple that is now
view from camera push simple scene and
render group right so so so simple okay
again just thinking it easier and easier
and easier and increasing that
accessibility and reducing the
likelihood of making those errors while
still at the same time retaining all the
power right anyone can still now go in
here and do all of the same meticulous
calls set their own camera transforms
from their oma to all of that stuff
could still work so we have eliminated
no capabilities and we have introduced
the power at all all we've done is
provide utilities that allow people to
not care if they don't want to care
right um so now let's see about bringing
this even like even further like I
saying um so so let's call it can't
standard camera here all that stuff
looks fine so now what I'd like to do is
just focus on the fact that we never
implemented the fog okay so let's extend
our renderer which we like I said we
never did that renderer group stuff we
needed to to make the fog work render a
dusty tepee so I'm looking for actually
here you can see the way we're passing
the stuff in note the way that we
specify whether we want fog or not so
there's all this stuff Alpha clip
distance we have these settings the
person can't accept access them right
they can't get they can't get to it and
we need them to be able to to get there
right um so there's a couple things this
ortho called here I when we pass in the
flags right we're not passing any flags
here so
i we don't have to worry about
orthographic I don't think the fog value
here why that wasn't a flag I have no
idea
it so obviously should be a flag but
what you can see is regardless of
whether it's a flag or not we need
direction start and end those need to be
set right and the same thing is true of
the clipping the Alpha clip we need to
set these things and if we don't set
them then then this stuff won't work
right so let's go ahead and try to make
this a little bit better than it is
right now because right now it's super
crappy let's do an Alpha clip and a fog
let's remove the parameter for fog
something like this and then we can pass
those values in here all these ones that
we actually want now the fact that you
could just set them in the setup it's
kind of hard to say whether we should
just do that I don't really know what I
think about that
but basically like if we imagine passing
all these things in here you know I
don't have a strong opinion about it one
way or the other I guess is what I'm
trying to say
so you can see it's a pretty huge set of
features we would have to pass here
right and it doesn't look great right it
doesn't look great so the question would
become you know can we do something more
same here right can we do something bid
would work better than what then what
we're doing here
and I'm I'm not sure serious here's my
proposal right it's not a good one
something like this
and do something like this it's pretty
easy to do that and I don't love it but
you can see that it's pretty
straightforward right
you would just put these in here and the
Alpha clip ones in here and so that's
pretty basic and then you'd pass them if
you wanted them and you wouldn't if you
wouldn't right so if you then look at
you know the what I would actually
define for these sort of default values
right
the default flog grams in this case we
just got directions start distance and
end distance the default Fogg params is
just all zeros actually if you look at
it right so that one doesn't require
anything that's just good to go and then
the default alpha clip is always phrased
as being off of the near clip plane it
looks like so I'm guessing what we can
do is actually define these as like this
right and the default values are these
negative 100 and negative 99
and then the other values are these
right these are the default ones for a
clip start and end I'm not really sure
why they're this way in I'm not sure why
we don't just start at the near clip
plane but I'm sure we had a reason
famous last words
so yes so then if you want to set up fog
specifically you set it up this way if
you don't you set it up the other way
okay so then in here when you pass these
in for your fog params and your Alpha
clip ramps when you come in here you
actually always do assign them right and
you pass in these so that way
when these get passed in you know you
set them how up however you want to set
them and you pass them in this pointer
like I said don't love it but can't
think of anything better seems about
right
and yeah I mean we could have like a set
call that we use in some other way I
don't know but that seems pretty good to
me
and this is supposed to be what and so I
think that's okay you know
so I'm just gonna try that I'm gonna see
how that goes so yeah if we go ahead and
look a little bit further down the road
there sorry I'm just gonna take a look
at what we would need to do to make that
stuff work
[Music]
don't know why did that that's the exact
opposite alright so there we go
okay so sip camera transform we're now
down to just like looking at where these
actually get called and what the
problems are when we actually call them
and so that's good so now let's go
through here we don't need to call past
that anymore
and we should work okay now if we just
pass those defaults right so let's go
ahead and run and verify that we
actually do so that's good right now
let's try to put in some alpha clipping
or some fog just to make it clear that
it works at all because we don't know if
it does right so I'm gonna go in here to
where these were set up I'm gonna first
loft these I'd like these to be
available you know up here so that when
we're actually talking about render
groups it's clear so there's a render
setup here it is
these are kind of like part of this and
we could actually include those in here
if we wanted to in the future right I
don't know that we necessarily want to
what we could um so if I go ahead and
hmm and we compile here oops
instead of having this fog equals false
nonsense now I can just do a fog params
in I can do a fog params and the fog
params I can set the direction again I
want like based on the camera Z so I'm
gonna again follow sort of what's base
you know what we're looking at here so
I'm going to want the camera Z and
remember I could actually pull this out
ahead of time because it's this
there we go and so here I can just say
the negative camera Z Direction is the
direction I want the fog to go the start
distance is going to be whatever and the
end distance is going to be whatever so
what are the distances we actually
realistically want for the fog well I
don't know let's set 4 and 20 because
that's just some distances I don't know
let's not forget we actually have to
build our camera matrix first before we
can get stuff out of it and so now we
should be able to start to play with
those values to see some fog eventually
assuming fog still works I don't
remember if there's other stuff that we
have to do to make sure that the fog
works so I'm not seeing any yet it
should be based on distance from the
camera I need to make sure that we
actually well I think that should have
done it but I'm not sure it's not to see
if we're really getting oh we didn't
pass it got to start by passing it first
all right so passing the fog down so
there we go and that's great because now
our fog is actually quite obviously
there let's stiffen it up a bit so
here's a more dramatic fog we'll start
it at 8 ended at 10 so it's like a very
dense fog at the end that we oh my god
that's it very interesting that outline
we have to look and see what's going on
there our fog stuff is a little bit
chewy there it looks like what what
distance should we start at that that's
interesting so I think our fog doesn't
properly handle the doesn't properly
handle either the Alpha values or the
multi sampling and I'm not sure which so
it's something that'll be good to fix
I'm not sure what ya value we should use
here okay there we go
so you can see we've got some kind of
bugs with the outlining there again I'm
not sure if that's depth pilla related
or exactly who's responsible for that
but but that's what we wanted right
and similarly it's kind of a weird
weirdly shaped fog - I feel like yes I
feel like we've got some work to do
I feel like our fogs a little bit wonky
but I can I he's on camera Z so I'm not
sure but anyway it's basically just the
specification is what we care about now
we have to work on our shaders obviously
we know that so that's not a huge deal
but if we want to go ahead and set the
direction to be different maybe we set
it to the world Y or the world Z rather
so it's actually an upward fog so maybe
the fog starts kind of at a low distance
as measured along Z so you know the
start of it would be somewhere around
like one let's say and it would end
somewhere around negative one
five Direction is measured relative to
the camera though so that makes it a
little bit harder to do this we don't
have a way to do world space fog at the
moment which we probably should add but
if that's the case then it has to be
much lower
so the fog start distance would have to
be if measured upward so we want to
actually measure downwards from the
camera and it would be what like that
not sure
so there's one that gets stiffer as you
go down right and again looks like
everything you probably accept we just
we have those edging artifacts on our
fog there so we'll have to figure out
what we're doing wrong and fix those but
that's you know kind of for a different
different day and you can see the fog
has completely obscured the ground here
which is exactly what I wanted to see
happen right um so that's good
I'm pretty happy with all that so what I
want to do now is make sure that that
stuff can be set in the actual camera
values you know itself so what I want to
do here is say you know fog direction um
fog start log end and one of the things
that would be nice there is if the fog
was actually based on a point not on the
camera and you could just pass the point
so I feel like we kind of wanted to do
here we want to basically say here's the
point to measure the fog from and then
here's the direction because we can
always pass the camera but you know what
if we don't want to pass the camera what
if we want some other point to be the
fog basis right it's just so good think
about okay so what we want to do is say
okay we're gonna make some fog params
here maybe I'll just do it this way
leave that to do in there
and then so once we get to here I can
just say hey past past the fog there so
now if I want to set these as default
values I can just say maybe there's a
little bit of fog by default I don't
know exactly what that fog value should
be but again we'll just use sort of the
stuff that we were playing around before
and just call that good um so fog
direction in this case I guess one
problem is since it's based on the
camera
the fog direction in this case I guess
we kind of have to hard-code that into
the camera one way or the other you'd
have to have that setting for it
um and so I guess that sort of suggests
why this maybe is it would just be you
know because we for most purposes here
we want that to be you know based on
some direction that has nothing to do
that has to do with the cameras location
probably right and I don't know maybe it
me it really wants to be more world
oriented we'll see eventually as we play
around that a little bit more
and so here all we're going to do is
only have the fog start and the fog and
and we'll go from there so assuming that
that's right fog start fog ends and
negative camera Z which i think is
correct then let's just set these to
something that makes some sense here
that's a little bit too much
and that's a little bit too little
there we go so now we've got the fog in
there by default and that you know is
just a you know parameter that anyone
can play with as they wish so that's
fine and now let's just put the Alpha
clip in there as well okay so if we have
the start and end points of our clipping
alpha again those are based on the NIR
clip plane so we'll just set those to
the two values we have here we probably
won't see anything happen at the moment
but we can try to construct some ways
that we would
again just putting these in here
okay so clip out the start and clip
alpha end just going here and now we
have everything initialized via that
camera params itself and alpha clip is
now engaged as well so if we actually
wanted alpha clip itself to be something
that we saw happen in the render test we
just need to move the camera closer so
in theory if we just change the camera
dolly so like here we change dolly to
like you know one instead of ten so
we're right up in it
we should start clip well that might
just clip everything away we probably
need to go back a little bit more than
that so let's try three and then we can
try to get that clip working um so you
can see the clip working unfortunately
it's a little bit hard because
everything's brown here but you can see
the clip working just nicely there so
we're totally fine let's move back a
little bit Wow so we have to move back
quite a bit how much what is our camera
dolly default - oh it's 20 okay I
thought it was only ten all right so
let's move close enough that we start
clipping through some of these things
let's try eight meters displacement
there
and you see you can get really nice
alpha clipping I mean you can almost not
even see that that's what's happening
it's so smooth so that's really nice
obscuring those objects right so you can
see through it so that's really good um
so that's working just fine so I think
all that's good now
and if we wanted to we could also extend
out the clip out a bit further there
okay um so that's everything there I
think we're almost out of time I'm gonna
go clean up the Hameed here a side of
things so that it's still cooling but
that's good I'm happy with where this is
at now because now you just call that
and you're kind of off to the races
here's the camera this camera code is
really just now here too you know kind
of do both rotation and offsetting and I
mean that is something the user has to
do the way that they want to do it so I
think all this is really straightforward
now I may be hard to have a simpler API
than this right the sum total is call
this function call this function call
this function if you want to write then
download your textures start a frame
make as many groups as you want say
where they're viewed from put the
sprites in that you want finish and then
render everything when you're done
pretty straightforward
and so about the only question I have is
can we get rid of the render groups and
we'll have to see are those necessary
because they might
I mean it is very possible that we could
just get rid of the render group so we
may be able to make one more simplifying
we may be able to make one more
simplifying step we don't have any time
left doing
what time did we actually start
anybody now
help me out here stream
oh all right 1:30 p.m. okay okay so I
actually have 15 minutes is that correct
all right if I actually have 15 minutes
[Music]
15 minutes may not be quite the amount
of time that I would need to do
something like this so I'm hesitant to
do it but if we consider the render
group and its reason for being I would
say we really don't need it anymore
[Music]
basically this stuff can just be stuck
on to the render commands and I mean if
we look
if you kind of look at what's happening
there it really all we really need is
just the clear command like this if we
just undid a little the change we didn't
how to begin DUP he'll end up peel
that's really all you would need and you
really don't need even that you can
assume that everything is through the
def heels and you could just have one
called it's like stop depth peeling now
right
so I do think it's probably worth noting
that you don't really need this thing
whether that means you should get rid of
it or not hard to say but we probably
could right I'm gonna pop back to
handmade hero just clean that up this is
the focal length here
not sure where else we've gots yeah um
so that's really the entirety of the
porting so here is this running on the
renderer here here's this running on the
renderer inside the game and if we now
want to return now what is true though
is we now no longer have like any of our
fog effects or any of those things
happening in the game proper so to
return those to operational I'm just
gonna put to do in here when we're ready
add alpha clip and fog back in here
right now we're not I mean I guess you
know what we got the time now just do it
right just do it why not
here's what they were set to you before
right
prom solved so literally just setting
the values exactly what they used to be
set to in both the Fogg case and the
Alpha clip case and now we can just
adjust those as necessary out here to
whatever we want and when we actually
set the game camera up I can just
eventually we should actually have we
want to set these values to things that
we actually care about more so there's
that but yeah
but otherwise you know six of one
half-dozen any other so uh oops I
deleted the wrong values not very bright
not very bright today am i it's 80/20 so
that's all we really need to do there
and we're you know good to go at that
point so that should be the same as what
we're using but before I think we had
decided those really weren't the good
values anymore because we kind of
changed the perspective a little but at
least they're still working correctly
now right so that's all good I think
that's all I want to do I don't think
there's anything else really that we
should do today I'm pretty happy with
how these are and so the only thing that
I have left to get to not sure if we
want to remove render groups or not
that's kind of hard to say maybe they
should stick in here but this all looks
really nice right now and I can maybe
comment this a little bit
so we'll ask blombo AKA windows to tell
us what the size of our window is we
then use to figure out how to fit a
sixteen by nine drawing region in there
remember or this is not necessary if you
don't want a fixed aspect ratio you can
just use the whole thing so you can just
pass the entire thing if you want to I'm
not sure so I can't really remember if
we correct for that properly or not
let's just see I guess we've never
really tested I don't remember so right
now when we run
oops go to the render test there so
right now when we run right we always
maintain a 16 by 9 aspect ratio so you
can see we get the black bars in there
right but if you didn't want that so
suppose you just always wanted to draw a
region to be the entire thing you could
just pass this and that will fill the
entire thing I don't think that works if
you don't pass like you'll just stretch
at that point I think
note that just works I guess
so we actually reallocate the buffers
and everything I guess I couldn't
remember if we actually did that but I
guess we do
so that actually reallocates all the
buffers and everything for compositing
and everything every time so you can
really just do that if you want to happy
birthday right so that's fine
there we go so here I'm just commenting
the code we already know all this is so
sorry to bore you with this but I
figured we might as well put in here
because this is the example app right
normally I don't put many comments in my
code because I feel like they tend to
get out of date but this is the sample
app so it's kind of what we would expect
to have this documentation so people can
read it this is just a thing that is you
know want to tell people that or call on
processed texture queue here we don't
only need to this app doesn't stream
textures but if it did right
okay
make sense so I feel like we've got that
API down pretty darn good right I think
anyone could use this most of these
calls aren't even for the API they're
just windows nonsense or calls that
initialize our test scene right so
really we're talking one call here one
call here one clock here one call here
here here here here here here
right each of them does something very
specific seems good to me all right
let's go to Q&amp;A
Jonathan Blow asks how can I program a
really good Windows Update system like
Windows has that makes sure you update
all the time especially if you are not
home or are watching a movie right now
that is a very good question John so
here's the thing a lot of programmers
who are inexperienced and aren't as good
as the programmers who work at windows
might think that one of the things the
computer should do is like take
direction from the person using it so
for example if that person says don't
update unless I tell you to then that is
what the computer should do that's
old-school programming that is not
cutting edge and as Microsoft knows
cutting edge involves artificial
intelligence and deep learning and one
of the things that your code needs to
deep learn is to completely ignore what
the user is doing or wants right so the
AI has learned that the best thing you
do is just to do whatever it wants
regardless of what the user wants and
rebooting your machine and installing
updates whenever it wants is you know is
what it learned it's deeper he just
learned deeper and more than you have as
a human so I don't think you should
argue with that you know basically what
you're saying is that your puny little
human brain that doesn't really know
anything and doesn't have all kinds of
flops and things knows better when to
install updates then Windows does and
that's just hubris right that's human
hubris that you were bringing to the
table you're thinking crazy thoughts
like I paid two or three thousand
dollars for this machine and I had to
pay $200
for this copy of an operating system
that's crappier than the one that I had
20 years ago and you're thinking that
that gives you some kind of right to
determine when your machine should do
stuff right or you're thinking
absolutely ridiculous things like if you
pay $2,000 for a computer it should be
able to do computations for you at the
time that you want it to rather than
when it wants to all of those things are
false and Microsoft has figured out the
true interest of those questions which
is that when you pay $200 for an
operating system it should literally not
care at all what you want to do who you
are or if you you know had something
important that you need to do that time
that's not important that's not deep
it's not learning that's not
artificially intelligent I can't say
anything other than that's like 1990s
thinking it's just obviously wrong off
topic you mentioned in the pre stream
fetching the cache misses do you mind
explaining how it's done fetching the
cache misses can you be more specific
what what do you charge of fetching
cache misses do you mean texture cache
misses sino cron why do you want to
remove the render group what is the
alternative my following is a bit spotty
so I'm sorry if this is obvious from
watching pure streams I just want to
make sure that we don't have an
extraneous step so if really the person
doesn't really need an extra struct in
there and they could have just used the
render command structure and use just a
bracketing call that's probably better
and I think that's where we're at I
don't think you can really use render
groups for anything at the time render
commands is really where everything's
going so it's sort of like a vestige
will remain and so I feel like it should
probably just be removed what is your
opinion of the Vulcan API is it overkill
to use it for a little indie game or is
it worth the thousands of setup code
lines hmm so
my opinion on vulcan is first of all I
don't think it's a very good API I don't
think it was designed well I honestly
don't think almost any thought was put
into the design of the API from an
actual like is this a good API
standpoint and I say that because I
actually tried to help on the side of
the API and got literally nowhere trying
to convince people to think about the
sort of things that I literally was just
talking about on here I think it was
primarily designed just to be the
quickest thing they could get out the
door that was a version of mantle that
was cross vendor that's what I think I
think it shows I think it's a really bad
API I don't like any part of the design
so I'll just pull stop it's a lousy API
that said so are most API hice right so
you know OpenGL a sense of problems with
it direct3d has tons of problems with it
metal has tons of problems with it
whatever you know do people spend a lot
of time figuring out whether these api's
are well-designed No so that's not a
reason not to use it it's just an
observation that I don't think there's
any value to the Vulcan API as an API I
don't think it's good right so you
wouldn't use it because it's a good API
but you might still want to use it
because it's the most effective thing to
talk to the hardware so that's I think
the question you need to ask is it the
most effective thing for you to talk to
Hardware in the current landscape my
answer is no I don't think it is on
Windows you should use direct3d it's the
native API and the reason why you might
use OpenGL like we do is for
cross-platform it used to be that it ran
on Windows Mac and Linux so for an
educational stream like this even though
it's less well supported on Windows it's
still a useful thing to use for
educational purposes right it's easier
for people to follow along on Mac etc
that landscape hasn't fortunately
changed Mac has decided they will no
longer support open jail
so the hand-made hero of five
years from now if it was getting started
at that time wouldn't have that option
there is no cross-platform API anymore
right
there's only metal on Mac and everything
else that you might call is actually on
top of metal so you've pretty much got
to use it otherwise you're just adding a
ton of cruft right you might as well
just use a good API that sits on top of
metal you wouldn't use Vulcan because
it's a bad API that sits on top of metal
right so it really is looking like a
world where in the future what you will
do is you'll program D 3d on Windows and
metal on Mac so I don't see any reason
for Vulcan is not useful from what I can
see it doesn't really have a reason to
exist anymore maybe it will become the
crappy API you use to replace OpenGL ES
on Android right and that's something it
could do or maybe it will become the
Linux default API I don't know but but
yeah it doesn't serve much of a purpose
at this point I mean memory cache misses
[Music]
okay so memory cache misses that's a
very broad topic I hate to keep asking
to be more specific but what kind of
memory cache misses are you interested
in hearing about like what prompted you
to ask about memory cache misses disturb
was there something specific or you just
mean in general what is the memory cache
miss you he what steps are you going to
do to optimize the render so primarily
the main thing we we need to do is we
need to coalesce our textures into
texture arrays so they can be switched
quickly that's our number one thing the
number two thing is to finalize our
lighting and make a simpler lighting and
make it so we do less lighting ops
the shader as well so those are the two
things that need to happen before the
renderer would be like a shipping thing
that that you'd be like okay you know
this is okay
accidental rebel I'm making das games
for fun do you have experience making
games during the Dussehra a little bit
but I was still during the Dussehra I
was still in high school I I didn't
actually make it into the industry until
after dusk games had kind of ended and
so as far as as far as ever working
professionally on one no but I have done
das you know mode X programming in DOS
as a hobby when I was little
ah okay okay okay now we've got it
sorry I'll rephrase it is there a
function that tells you how many L 1 l 2
etcetera cache misses happened since for
example the last time you call the
function yes the problem if I recall and
I don't think this ever got fixed so
somebody jump in and correct me if I'm
wrong here because it may be that they
fixed it eventually the problem is that
you can't do it without a device driver
so there are they're built into the CPU
they're called performance counters they
can tell you those things you can't
access them without ring zero assistance
I believe so for example in handmade
hero we have a built-in profiler right
like if we let's say we build in in
optimized mode and I run the game oops
here's the game if I run the game you
can see in this profile we got all this
information saying like how many cycles
we spent in different things right
we're getting that from the call our
DTSC read time stamp counter which is a
cpu performance register that you use to
figure out how many roughly instructions
it has issued right not instructions how
many cycles it has issued it's it's a
whole ball of wax to say what that
number actually means but it's related
to how many instructions got issued in a
certain sense although you can issue
multiple instructions on a cycle and
they're not really measuring cycles
because of speed step and bla bla bla
bla bla so are DTSC hard to explain
exactly what it's measuring and it
depends on the chip but it's effectively
a performance counter that tells you
about how many cycles elapsed since the
last time you called it there exists
similar performance counters set up
things you can do where you can ask the
chip to count things like l2 cache mates
is much like you can ask it how to count
cycles retired to the best of my
knowledge you can't call them without a
device driver so what people often do is
you can install something you don't have
to write the device driver yourself you
can install someone else's device driver
that will access this information for
you so for example Intel ships a program
called vtune that does this you probably
have heard of it's got device drivers
that will get that information for you
there's probably others I just don't
know what they all are when you actually
care about this most is usually on
things like Playstation and stuff like
that
and there that you just get access to
them they are provided as part of the
default system software there for
obvious reasons right because everyone
wants to use it on the PC I don't know
[Music]
you know Windows 10 or the windows
performance counters might allow you to
get those I've never tried to get them
that way you might be able to get it out
through that but yeah so the answer to
your question though broadly speaking is
yes you absolutely can get that data no
unfortunately it's not as simple as just
issuing an AR DTSC like we do but you
can do it you just have to go a like
slightly more a roundabout way after
ending up with the render apart which do
you think is the next Mac recep Mohamad
hero going through in like decorating
the world right like putting in like
grass and changing like walls depending
on what rooms are in and stuff like that
do you ever see Linux as a consumer
machine not really I could see something
like the steam like let's say steam
valve got serious about steam box and
shipped like a dedicated steam box like
this is the steam box not multi-vendor
like we actually just packaged it I
could see that working
a dedicated known hardware configuration
with a specifically optimized version of
Linux that targets only that hardware
and it's optimized to run it and runs it
reliably with a custom UI on top like
big picture or something could work and
Martin's mentions that on Linux that you
can get those l1 l2 cache things with
the perf utility yeah I don't know
anything about that I'll take your word
for it it's the kind of thing I would
have expected to be able to get on Linux
so that's cool that they avoid it I said
that they provide it I just don't know
of anything similar on Windows I mean I
shouldn't say that I don't know of any
way to get it on Windows without
installing the device drivers of some
kind right and you know there's multiple
ways of getting that device driver but
as far as I know you have to do that
it's cool that Linux doesn't force you
to do that right
alright let's wrap it up
close these things down here
there yeah all right thank you everyone
for joining me for the epicenter
handmade hero it sort of pleasure
coating with you as always if you want
to follow on the series at home you
could always prepare to the game on hand
made here at org and it comes with a
source code so you can follow along and
try experiments yourself maybe you want
to try optimizing the renderer to use
texture rays before I do you've got the
option to do it right a couple of things
to note we have a watch page on the hand
meter a page that allows you to watch
the series it's got a window that'll
show this three months live and show the
schedule when it's not so you know when
it will be live it's also got the
episode guide on there so you can catch
up on past series it's pretty cool you
can just type in anything you want to
search for it'll search for all the
episodes and you can jump right to the
part of the episode where I talked about
it it's a pretty awesome feature
and of course we have the hand made fund
if you want to contribute to that which
is what supports work that people do
like that like that watch pages episode
guide which wouldn't be possible without
it also obviously if you just want to
check out what we're doing it hit at
Mali rocket you can always join our
mailing list here and you got the little
hand made here ahead you can click on
which brings you to all of our other
pages my blog as well and and all that
kind of good stuff so check that out
when you get a chance that's about it I
will be back fry well I don't know if
they'll be back next week I may have to
take next weekend off in fact it's
highly likely I think that I will have
to for other reasons so check the
schedule page we'll see when I'll be
back maybe the week after that or in
three weeks time we'll see so there
might be a brief little mini
back-to-school vacation but until then
whenever it is it'll be a couple weeks
from now at most hopefully everyone can
find some interesting program to do in
the meantime and until then I will see
everyone on the Internet so take it easy
everybody