hello everybody and welcome to handmade
here are the short we code a complete
game live on stream we are doing some
lighting today just catch people up to
where we are because obviously lettings
pretty complex topic so we've got a
bunch of things that we need to be
working on and that we need to get right
so just a real quick overview of where
we're at and what we need to do this
weekend if we take a look at where we
just do a quick recompile just so you
can see the fresh build so there's our
compile here's the run you can kind of
see where we left off
this is debug mode by the way so we're
still in the kind of slow version of it
although our debug builds not that slow
right now because since we're not
running the lighting transport so we did
a lighting test and the way that we did
it is we put a purple light at the top
and a yellow light on the bottom not
running light transport so we're just
hard stuffing those values as if that
light was ubiquitous everywhere and then
we tested our reflector function to make
sure that it actually worked and it does
appear to so as you you know move around
you can see you hitting basically the
mirror surface there and that all
appeared to work right so we believe our
pixel sampler is that's our pixel shader
is sampling from the volumes the way
because we also tested a number of other
aspects of the volumes we believe it's
sampling properly what that means is we
can now start moving towards the full
sampling of it and in order to do that
what I'd like to do this weekend
is get us to the point we're still not
doing any lighting transport because we
we have that code so it won't take us
too long to like sort of rehabilitate
that and start to work with it to get
the actual looking transport working
because if you remember we already had
that working in a different version of
the lighting pipeline but in this new
lighting pipeline we have it turned off
because we're just working on the pixel
shading okay so what I'd like to do this
weekend is start stuff
simulated lighting values that actually
sort of relate to things we might
actually find right so when I'm hopping
around in here what I'd like to do is
let's say we take the location of the
player for example and we stuff lighting
values into our light probes you can see
all the light probes are being drawn
there right there those little hovering
cubes suppose we stuff lighting values
into those cubes right that represents
something like a local light source
emanating from the player and then what
I'd like to do is verify that we can get
our pixel shader working well to sort of
sample the lighting that results from
that and the idea behind this is before
we switch over to working on the light
transport I want to verify that if we
stuff predictable lighting values into
our system that sort of relate to the
kinds of lighting values we hope to get
out of our light transport assuming it's
good do we get acceptable results in the
actual game because if we don't we need
to keep working on that pixel shader
because obviously no matter how good our
light transport is if the pixel shader
that samples the result of the light
transport sucks then the lighting sucks
so we have to do we have to make sure
that we get that part correct right and
so what I'd like to do first is yes
stuff those values and then verify that
we get reasonable results out then after
we've got that totally settled which
maybe if we're really lucky we'll be
done by the end of the weekend so we can
just check that off and then we move on
so if we're lucky we get that done by
the end of the weekend and then we just
move on to the final phase of lighting
which is working on getting the light
transport to run fast enough through the
system so that it can be still at 60
frames a second and so on right and
there's lots of things we can do to try
and make that happen
including like subsampling like which
light sources I'm sorry which light
probes get updated each frame and we can
restrict
light probes that were sampling - only
the ones in the view and all sorts of
things that we can play around with
there as well as just straight-up
optimizing that path there's a bunch of
stuff we can probably do to fix that
part as well
so looking at the system as a whole
that's going to be sort of the final
phase of lighting and so what we're
trying to this weekend is set ourselves
up for going into that part of that part
of the process right and so you know
let's let's get started on that it's
pretty clear what we want to do so let's
kind of move forwards on that all right
so the first thing I want to do is just
play around that pixel shader a little
bit because before we try to stuff more
interesting lighting values in there I
want to still play with directional
lighting as we have in there right now
where we're stuffing in like yellow
light and a purple light into it
specifically I want to go ahead and take
a look at that lighting which is right
in here you can see the lighting
equation that we're computing right here
and if you look at what this lighting
equation is doing it's pretty straight
forward right and I can break it out a
little bit more just to kind of give you
a to give you a better idea of what's
actually happening right and there's a
couple different things that we want to
be able to do here but yeah like that
and you know what I think I want to see
there's also a bug in this lighting
equation that we didn't really look at
and I could be wrong about that but I
you know we'll just take it as we go so
a couple of things here and I'll explain
the bug that I think is in here as I
break it out if we take a look at what
the components of our light equation are
right now which is like I said was just
a basic one we threw in there a very
simple reflection which is not that what
we really want so that's why I want to
kind of beef it up a little bit and get
it a little more interesting before we
move on to stuffing other values in
we've got a couple different terms here
so the first thing we have is a term
that's telling us what the incident
light versus the outgoing direction to
the I yeah
right and that's sort of a specular
bounce term so that's like a reflection
coefficient right and you can see that
reflection coefficient it's right here
and so this coefficient here ref see
it's taking the inner product of the
light normal and a sample normal right
so that's the direction that goes to the
light and the direction that goes to the
sample and so if we're sample meaning
like the so the direction that goes to
the light which is the incoming in the
direction that the light's coming into
this surface and then the sample
direction is like the I direction right
so where it's where we're looking at it
from or whoever wants the sample this
doesn't have to be the camera we happen
to be calling the cam right now but you
could sample it letting in any direction
you wanted so those two as they become
coincident so if they're pointing in
exactly the same direction then we get
the maximum contribution from this light
source right and as they separate we get
less does that make sense
and so that's what we kind of want to
see there now it's worth noting that
this part of the equation again like I
said we haven't really worked this
through yet so I think we also have some
kind of buggy parts here or at least
nominally HR problems as well and so we
kind of want to now take the time since
we just did this at the end of the last
dream we want to now take the time to
start a like work this to get all the
bugs out of it make sure we're sampling
it properly and and at least try to
verify it as well as we can so if you
take a look at what happens in the main
part of this machine or you can see a
sampling all of our actual lighting
incoming lighting values and then we
specify what the actual parameters are
from what the actual directions of those
incoming lights are which we happen to
know because they're just the the
cardinal directions right that's how
we're storing our lighting in our light
probes and so when we look at what
happens what we pass in is the direction
to the light and then the reflection
vector right and so really when you look
at this this is not an accurate name for
this thing it's not the sample direction
really what it is is it's the outgoing
direction right it's the it's the bounce
and so what we really want to do is call
this the reflec
to normal because that's really what it
is and if and so I named it like
basically what the I direction would be
but that's not what we're passing and so
the first bug would have been a bug if
it had actually been what we'd named it
that would have been wrong the inner
product between the light direction and
the reflection direction that's correct
meaning this inner product is the thing
we want to commute compute but the inner
product of the light outgoing direction
and the eye direction that's not what we
wanted to know right that would not have
been correct so again not really a bug
in terms of what the code did definitely
a bug in terms of how he named it so we
want to get rid of that okay now we do
clamp this inner product and that's
important right so this clamp is very
important the reason the clamp is very
important is because if we get something
that actually comes out more than 90
degrees away we don't want any
reflection there right and so what we
kind of need to make sure can't ever
happen and I think we currently have the
problem of this happening honestly is
that we don't ever want this to produce
a situation where you can get light
transmitted sort of through a surface
because this is not supposed to simulate
any this lighting equation is not about
subsurface scattering right if this is a
basic reflectance function and we want
to make sure that we're actually doing
that computation if we wanted subsurface
scattering or transmission through
services that's all fine and we can try
to implement some of that but we don't
want to accidentally implement something
like that because if we accidentally
implement it it's not going to be
correct right it's gonna be some kind of
weird lighting function that doesn't
really properly do transmission in the
way it should I last one more time does
anyone know if Milton's been fixed
someone please message me and tell me if
Milton's been fixed cuz I'd really like
to fix our Milton at some point here
anyway
so the part that I want to say we have
is a bug right now or at least it's you
know it's a bad lighting function at the
moment because it doesn't have something
that we want if we take a look at what
this is doing and I'll draw the diagram
again from from last week we have a
surface so this is our surface here and
this is the surface normal we know that
we're looking at this thing from some
direction so our eye is over here this
is the camera so maybe I'll call it the
camera because that's probably a better
name for it's what we call it we don't
call the eye so our cameras over here
we're filming from this direction we're
looking at this particular surface this
is our reflection vector right so this
is our reflection I think we called this
ref n in the shader just then right and
in fact if you look here yeah we don't
actually pass in a surface normal into
this routine yet we will be doing that
but we don't do it yet so we only have
the ref N and then we have the light
normal and we don't know where that life
light normal is right now we just know
like hey the light normal is coming from
some direction right so we've got a
normal that's going out to the light
source here and we want to make sure
that's pointing outward from you know
it's the direction the light - the light
source not the direction that the light
is incoming and so if we take a look at
that we just want to make sure that that
says it light West is negative one
that's pointing in the west direction so
that seems consistent so I think this is
correct right all right so the bug that
I was talking about is if you take a
look at what's happening here we've got
our light normal and are reflected
normal and what we're doing here is
we're saying well as long as these
things are within 90 degrees of each
other right we're going to get some
light now why is that the case well it's
the case because the only thing that's
attenuating the incoming light in that
direction is the inner product between
the reflection vector and the light
vector these are these two vectors right
here right one of them came from the
camera bounce that's our r FN and one of
them is just the ink incident light
wherever the light is coming from right
and that could be anything that we want
it to be for sampling this equation but
it happens to be
the the six cardinal directions because
our light probes are storing you know
their their little cubes or light probes
are and they're storing the incoming
light that that is found by looking in
each of these directions right so we
have no idea the services oriented eclis
orient in any way in space we have an
incoming light direction that incoming
light direction is going to be based on
one of these kernel directions we don't
know how the service is oriented we have
a camera we don't know where the camera
is and we know that it's going to
produce this reflection vector that you
know bounces off the surface goes in
that direction we're taking a dot
product between these two what do we
know about the dot product well we know
what the dot product is if we took that
reflection vector here and we drew a
perpendicular plane right and then we
take whatever we're sampling like light
n right what we know is as long as this
angle is 90 degrees or less so as long
as it doesn't go behind this plane we
will get some contribution as it goes
behind this plane the dot product
becomes negative right and it will
become negative one in fact here so it's
negative something here right and it's
negative one over here becomes negative
as it passes through and ends up at
negative one comes back around to
positive as it passes through that plane
again what that means is that the clamp
will prevent us from viewing anything
any light from back here so if the light
Direction is this way and the reflection
vectors that way we won't see anything
right but if the light vector was this
way in the reflection vector that way we
will see it why is this important well
if this is the surface like we drew
before and this is a very plausible
situation we could have constructed if
the cameras here then that means that
anything remember anything that's on
this side of this side of this plane
will give us light including this entire
region but this region is behind the
surface right we can't even see the
surface from here so if our reflection
vector is pointing this way and our
light vector was pointing that way we
would see the light coming from behind
the surface which is wrong
so unless I'm mistaken and I mean again
you know I do these streams with no
preparations so I'm just working through
the math on the stream exactly as you
see me doing it but unless I'm wrong
about that constructing it with the
diagram thus makes it look like to me
that there is an additional bug here and
the bug here is that we aren't
accounting for the fact that we have a
surface normal and the surface normal
has to be pointing in the same direction
in order to get this light contribution
right in other words if we have a light
that's coming from behind the surface we
shouldn't see anything now arguably we
never see surfaces that are facing away
from us we backface call those away and
so we don't really needed to do any work
to prevent us from having the situation
where the reflection normal itself is
cut is is behind the normal why because
you can't actually construct that I
can't view the surface from behind the
surface normal so I won't have a
reflection vector that's behind it
because the reflection vector and the
and the camera vector are on the same
side of the surface normal by definition
by construction they will always be that
way
so don't need to worry about that but
the light not true the light could come
from anywhere and so what I want to do
is I want to take another coefficient
here and this is like our side in this
coefficient and what I want to do is I
want to say like there's a light
Direction coefficient and what that is
going to be is that's going to be a
clamp zero to one of the inner product
of the light direction and the surface
direction right and so what that means
is I need another normal in here when I
when I pass that when I when I ask for
this get radiance I need to know what
the surface normal itself is and we know
what that is right because we had to use
it for a reflectance function it's just
this right here so I'm going to go ahead
and say this is what the surface normal
is like that but honestly because we
don't sample multiple surfaces what I
can do here is say look we know it's a
global we know it doesn't change it's
just for whatever the surface were on so
we can just put it in like that and call
it a day right
and that keeps our function simpler its
function signature simpler if we were
going to sample multiple surfaces inside
this shader which might happen if you
were doing some kind of weird shader
we're not gonna probably need it but if
you were doing something weird you might
want to make that prayer parametric
because you might want to sample
different kinds for us we're always
sampling the same thing
so why over complicate things it's
always gonna be that world normal okay
so this is a directional coefficient
that basically says all right when the
light bounces off the surface I expect
this to tell me whether or not there's a
self shadowing going on there whether or
not basically the light is coming from
behind the surface and shouldn't be
transmitted now we're gonna need this
for other purposes as well because we
this is only a specular equation right
now and we have an encounter for diffuse
lighting diffuse lighting of course is
letting that hits a surface and goes in
all directions we're just right now only
to make specular lighting that hits a
surface and bounces off in one direction
right and so we need to kind of like
improve that part of it anyway so we're
gonna need that term but we probably
don't want to do the light DC here we
probably don't want this right and the
reason for that is this is not just a 1
or a 0 this is actually a smoothly
varying function that goes from 0 to 1
and what I want to do is I only care if
it is positive at all if it is that I
probably don't want another cosine term
attenuating my inbound light because we
don't have any real reason to do that we
know that there's I think well you know
I could be wrong about this but I'm
fairly certain that we don't want
another cosine attenuation that's based
on the incidence of the light we only
want one cosine attenuation and that's
based on the difference between the two
angles I think now let me just draw that
out for you and it may be that we're
wrong about this this is a physically
based lighting question which honestly
is not something I study that often and
so I could be wrong but let me give you
just the basic breakdown so again what
happens and we've talked about this on
other lighting things before is if you
have the surface normal here
and you're talking about a light
situation like this where you've got
some direction to the light source
there's the light some reflected vector
here and you want to talk about how much
light is going to bounce basically back
at the viewer so we're talking about
this bounce right here so what we try to
simulate is the fact that on the surface
itself you have to imagine a patch of
light and you've got sort of inbound
light rays coming at the surface and
bouncing off of it right if they're
hitting the surface directly this way
then whatever the size of the thing is
like so what we're simulating
essentially like a infinitesimal like
patch right of because you know we're
doing this point by point we're
simulating it at an intentional patch
we're basically saying there's some
shaft of light that's coming down
hitting the surface and the side saying
the surface is some infinitesimal size
right this shaft if we were to rotate it
right we're still talking about how many
light rays fit into that same size patch
that goes in here but what we're looking
for now is this right this is the amount
of light that can hit that patch from
the side right and when we get all the
way to here that is really tiny so as it
starts to fall to the side the the width
even no matter what the size of so even
though this is like in this is
infinitesimal very small even though
this patch is just like if effectively
like an integral sized patch right so
we're just talking about the you know a
generic sized patch that we would
integrate over the entire surface to
calculate the lighting or whatever so
there's no real size to this thing but
it still has a dimension right what we
know is that no matter what the size of
the surface we were asking about whether
it's infinitesimally small for
integration or whether it was actually a
real patch of surface that was you know
a meter wide or something what we know
is as the light comes from a steeper
angle
the amount of light that could hit it
the sort of the the bandwidth the the
the pipe size right the cross section of
the tube of light coming down onto it
just gets smaller and smaller and
smaller until eventually if there's
nothing at you get as you get to like
the perfectly glancing angle right and
so that's where our cosine theta term
comes in right and what I don't
understand because I've never really
gotten the explanation like that part I
understand fairly well what I've never
really quite gotten the full answer on I
don't understand the explanation very
well is how you know whether you need to
do that for the outbound miss right so
if that comes in here that's how much
light this surface has to give off but
then you have an equivalent question
which is like well if I'm viewing the
surface from the side then that limits
the amount of light I could let out in
that direction too doesn't it right and
so what I'm not entirely clear on is why
we seem to mostly talk about a single
cosine incident there and whether or not
it really should be a cosine squared
sort of a situation I mean it's not a
cosine squared because it's two
different angles but it just seems to me
that it's a little bit weird I don't
quite get why we have that sort of
differing dichotic like I don't really
quite grasp the explanation this
physical explanation makes some
intuitive sense to me lightly meaning I
get where they're coming from when they
say well as you imagine it coming from
the side there's less room for the light
to hit in so assuming a uniform field of
light coming in as you get down to an
incident a glancing angle you're going
to get less and less of that light
collected I just am not clear about the
irradiated part of that so when we then
go to radiative outwards shouldn't the
same thing be true meaning I can only
send out a smaller part of light if I'm
looking at on the side right and maybe
you know you know let me just check
let's see if we can find one
because that's basically what you want
to know with lighting right like you
want to know these terms how they do the
fall-off but the point is we need to
know whether we want to account for that
extra cosine in there or not and what we
would do two different equations
depending on the circumstance so if I go
over to it something physically for any
like let's see a specular lighting
equation let me see if we've got
anything that seems reasonable I don't
have any idea which of these things
would be actually useful yeah I really
just don't know but we can try to see
what they end up with in their equation
right okay so this is our exact diagram
which helps right you can see the light
incident here you can see the I guess
the what is the V point in view right
that's the light reflection unit vector
though which okay so this is not quite
exactly our equation there phrasing it
opposite they're doing a light bounce
like that which in weird we did the view
bounce and the reason for that is
because well I guess you know I guess
there's no real penalty for us doing
that if we were to do a view bounce we
so you know I'm just thinking about it
it seems really less efficient right
because we've got six incoming light
sources that we're trying to simulate
here and only one viewer so I think we
did it the more efficient way for us so
we can ignore that though like it's the
same equation either way you can bounce
the light or you can bounce the viewer
and you can you it would wouldn't change
really right so I think we're okay there
but I don't think that's a good decision
for us but we can
we'll use what they suggest so this
right here is the end L so that's the
that lighting is telling us how much
light can hit the surface right and that
was the part I was saying about before
like that tells us how much is there so
we do actually want that amount right
and then we have the reflectivity out
they are doing and they are doing an r
dot V as well so it looks to me know
they use it a some though right so it
looks to me like they just use the
diffuse by itself and the specular by
itself and they don't so there is only
one cosine fall-off there right
I mean that that appears to be that
appears to me what happened again that's
farm lighting which isn't necessarily
physically based though so let me take a
look here
and unfortunately we're probably not
going to get a pretty good we're
probably not going to get a great
explanation there but we can see
I'm just looking for a diagram that
would say I would just discuss that part
because I don't feel like yeah so I
don't know we'll have to take it offline
but that's my only question is like I I
can convince myself a lot of these times
when I read these things I just have to
kind of convince myself that I believe
it because light is a pretty tricky
thing and I don't you know you can't
really see it at the kinds of scales
that we're talking about here so it's
like I'm like yeah all right I believe
this explanation of like if we imagined
a particular size any size and you want
to talk about how much gain if the
service I'd get that but then I don't
understand like why you wouldn't care on
the like outbound side and I don't know
there's a lot of stuff that it just
doesn't make good sense to me sometimes
and it's hard for me to really like wrap
my head around like why it's true in one
case but not true in the other case and
so I would feel better if we double
checked our letting stuff with a
physically by I don't do much lighting
work and so I would feel better if we
had some verification there but we can
do that later because again we just need
this to be roughly correct and we can
finish the rest of our lighting system
and then we could come back to this part
and try to make it more in line with
what we want as we go but anyway so if
we have a reflection the direction we
want to say if we want to see what
lights coming from that direction we've
got this light DC that's going to be
important for our diffuse term like I
said before but we also kind of need it
to make sure that we don't allow mixing
in of this light in the case where this
is zero so what we would like to do is
effectively have a thing where we say if
light DC equals zero then ref C equals
zero right and this is just a quick like
sort of conditional move kind of a thing
we're basically saying look if we can't
see the light from here because the
surface itself would have blocked it
then what we want to do is make sure
that we knock out 100% of the light now
really we can make this be a
or specific like we don't have to be
that cagey because what we know is that
if we can't see the light from here
we shouldn't even have bothered really
computing this in the first place
and so what we might want to do instead
is say well actually why don't we just
say if the light DC is greater than zero
do the equation otherwise don't do any
of it right so what we may want to do is
say like look the result starts out at
zero we will compute this thing in the
case where we actually know we can see
it but otherwise we just won't compute
it at all right and so that I think is
probably what we want because in the
case where we're talking about lights
that can't be seen probably most of the
pixels in the warp will not be able to
see it and will be able to fast track
that part of the computation right and
so what you can see now as well is I
think we're kind of now getting a more
correct
I think lighting I think the reason we
were seeing so much light before that I
think we probably shouldn't have seen is
is because we weren't sort of knocking
those services out however I do think we
still got I don't think that's quite
right because when I'm looking at it
here I expect to see some yellow bounce
there and I'm not seeing it so this may
be incorrect here if the world normal
and the light well no you know what I
guess that's not incorrect now I think
about it that's correct because this
surface that I was looking at there this
surface is directly perpendicular to the
light source the light source is coming
from straight bottom right and so you
can't see it if if you've got a surface
that's that that's that flat to it
that's actually true so the problem that
I think we would have there is it's not
immediately clear to me that that's the
right answer the only reason is because
we're kind of simulating these light
probes as cubes right
and so I don't know that we want to take
out all of the light that's coming from
below us because it's a probe right and
so I feel like we kind of want more of
that light in there and just to talk
about what I'm just to draw out what I'm
talking about they're just a little more
clearly so if you imagine what we're
doing here
I think what we saw there was actually
correcting that we had a wall this is
the normal to the wall we're talking
about a light that's incoming from this
direction right so the outbound lighting
direction we're looking or the direction
to the light source is completely
perpendicular to the wall so based on
cosine fall-off we should not be able to
see it right
it simply shouldn't be possible to see
that light source at all because none of
that light can bounce off a perfectly
vertical surface the problem is this is
a light probe it represents all of the
light coming from an entire cube right
so like this it's gonna represent all of
the light coming from a cube by putting
it down in here and so we kind of end up
in a circumstance where that's not very
useful because it could easily have seen
light from that direction all through
here would have hit that bottom part of
the cube right and so when we look in a
direction and we want to know what's off
in this direction doing that seems bad
and while we want to prevent it from
looking over here we don't really want
to prevent it from looking anywhere in
here right and that is exactly what we
would be doing by taking the dot product
of this normal with this normal you know
what I'm saying to you so I think it's a
little harder then we would like and I
think what we want to do here is talk
about spreads a little bit so meaning
what we'd rather do is say all right the
amount of light you could see from here
is actually you know it's it's sort of
trying to ask
a wider field of view and it's
specifically the direction of the light
source we're sort of talking about a 45
degree angle right that you can see out
of that you know like a it's a it's a 90
degree frustum right 45 in either
direction so we kind of want there to be
an actual ability to see this half right
of that lighting source by going this
way and we might want to account for the
fact that it falls off to half right and
there is such a thing as falling off to
zero if you manage to get all the way
back here on it but we kind of need an
equation that represents that fall off a
little bit better right it needs to be
able to account for a wedge of light
coming in and sort of taking that into
account right and I'm not really sure
the best way to do that but I do think
we want to do it
at least a little bit so when we're
doing this here where we're doing the
light and the world normal and we do a
clamp zero to one I think what we want
to do here is we want to potentially
bias this by some amount you know some
some amount of bias upward so that you
know we can count light that's coming
from a wider cone
I feel like again we're gonna want to
work the equations out more carefully
but I think we want something more like
that where we're allowing light to come
from a wider
I didn't mean hit the escape game let's
try that again
I'd like that our logo is lit so I feel
like we do want something more like this
and so do you see how that's now getting
that contribution in there which i think
is more what we want so I think this is
a better approximation it may be that
that's a little too much right and so
it's hard to say but that that would be
the full 45 because if you look right
and we asked the question well what is
the cosine of 45 degrees
it's 0.7 Oh blah blah blah blah blah
right and so if we wanted to talk about
exactly 45 degrees spread we should
probably be adding like 0.7 ish right
and if we wanted maybe a little bit less
than a 45 degree spread we could drop
that down right but so this value should
probably be more like that honestly
although actually it's the other way
round so it's probably this it's the
inverse right of that it's the it's the
it's the amount you would get if you
were 45 degrees off
trying to see how let me let me draw
this out because I I was about to say
something very hand wavy there and I
want to make sure that it's not totally
bogus so we're talking about a situation
right where we've got here is our
surface normal and we're talking about a
light perhaps that is directly incident
sorry directly parallel to the surface
it looks like that and what we're seeing
is that well you know what we would
really like to do is say that this
surface looked more like this
so actually we want zero to be when you
get all the way to when the dot product
right gets all the way to this 90
degrees plus this 45 degrees right so
it's the 90 degrees plus 45 degrees of
the dot product that's what we actually
want to see there right now we know that
when we do this just bear with me as I
draw the diagram we know that when we do
this the inner product will go to zero
here right because the inner product
gives us the cosine of the angle between
the vectors so if we take 90 degrees
plus 45 degrees it's not this it's this
right and so if we look at what that
cosine is going to be we would say
what's the cosine of 45 plus 90 degrees
right and so when we take the cosine of
45 plus 9 degrees we're expecting that
value here this one here to be negative
seven right so that's when it should go
to zero if we were to make it the full
45 degrees right it should go to sorry
negative point seven right so when it
goes to negative point seven if we
really wanted that to be the end of the
fall off so the end of the fall off goes
goes there
and so we swing completely around here
then yeah when we do our cosine theta we
would expect us to get point seven and
we'd so we would bump the entire thing
up by the point seven so my point three
thing was wrong we would bump the entire
thing up by the point seven and that
would give us you know as if we were
getting the entire range right that's
one thing however what we want to be
doing here is treating this as if we are
still talking about cosine fall-off I
think right so what we really want to do
is map this range more consistently
right so when we take these two vectors
we would really if we could we'd want to
compress this down a little bit more so
rather than talking about simply jacking
it up what we may want to do is talk
about shifting it and scaling it so
scaling it back down because remember
that would make our cosine go now
between the zero clamp which is it can
go all the way to now negative 0.3 we're
clamping that out right so it's going to
go from zero to one point seven so we
may also want to multiply by one over
one point seven right to rescale back
those values so I would guess it would
be something like 1 over one point seven
times the inner product plus 0.7 right
again not really sure this is a valid
way of doing this but it at least gives
us something that approximates and
inbound light for these kind of weird
samples we're doing and I'm gonna call
that good enough for now we can also we
can always kind of work on our letting
equations later once we feel like we've
got the rest of the system under control
right but so now we're sampling from
those light sources I think a little bit
more sanely and off we go
okay so now let's work on the diffuse
lighting component of this because we're
not doing we only have that one
reflection not only that but this is not
really a spectra lighting equation
because normally you'd raise the
specular light to a power as well so we
haven't done that yet but we also
haven't included any diffuse lighting so
to include some diffuse lighting in here
as well what we need to do is actually
use our light DC to figure out how much
light should probably be emanating from
the surface in the first place
and in order to do that what we would
like to do is use this incident dot
product to determine how much light just
goes in an arbitrary direction right so
incoming light and then we bounce it out
at a particular at basically the rate
commensurate with that that inner
product of the surface normal and the
incoming light so in order to do that
what we want to do is in addition to
this equation right we would like to
have a sort of a light DC term here
that's going to multiply this as well
right the light V RGB we want that part
as well and that's the diffuse component
what we can do probably is just add
these two things together right that's
how much light would be coming in from
the direct specular and then how much
light would be coming in from the light
DC right I'm gonna break it into two
parts only because we probably want to
spec there power if I want to play the
specular separately so what I'm gonna do
is I'm going to get in here a basically
a light like an inbound light so this is
a inbound like or an irradiance value
right that's just coming from the lights
art or or
maybe I'll call this sure light just
just the light turn by itself or unpack
the light basically we're sort of
reconstructing what the light incoming
light color is that something like that
and so then what I want to do is I want
to have that in both sides right so I
want the light color times the diffuse
amount and then I want the light color
plus they're reflected amount right and
so we're counting both of these now it
may not make a lot of sense to count
both of these because again we want sup
there's a certain amount this surface
whatever the service is transmits a
certain amount of diffuse light and a
certain amount of secular light or might
have an actual like lighting equation
that it uses like a brdf or something to
determine how much diffuse light how
much specular light comes out at any
particular point and so on because you
know lightning is lighting and it's
complicated so what we want to do is
probably mix these using some sort of a
surface characteristic some surfaces
will be very specular some will be very
diffuse things like that and we would
like some way of talking about that
particular piece of information what did
I do wrong here that is what I did wrong
here
all right off we go and so this is now
what we would expect more to see with
again the diffuse and the reflected
lighting and what you can see is there's
a lot less angular dependence so as I
get like really incident where the light
sampling is right off the bounce I see
more of that specular coming in but as I
come down I don't get as much specular
right and so that's what we would expect
to see and that's all fine
if I now change to just one light so
let's go back to our lighting where we
output sort of fake lighting information
if I go into the fake lighting
information and I just stuff it with
something else so instead of what we
were stuffing it with which is like two
directional lights one from the top one
from the bottom you can see that
happening here if I took out one of the
lights and now we're just talking purely
about an inbound light coming from above
us and I want to look at what that looks
like what I can do is see how that
diffuse lighting holds up now right
because now you can see that like things
that really don't get much specular
bounce right still get some light when
we have something coming from the top
and that's what we would expect right
these are really brightly reflecting
because they happen to point right there
and they get brighter as we get incident
on them right because that's because
that's the specular contribution coming
in right and similarly like well it's
hard to kind of see them because it's
hard because we've got we don't have any
that extend really that far downward but
as I get incident on these right they're
dimmer there they're gonna be brighter
here but that's just again like the
diffuse helps keep services from seeming
like they're kind of doing mirror
lighting which is you know not what most
of our services are going to be doing so
this is what we would expect here and I
think that makes all good sense if we
wanted to control the specular versus
diffuse as almost
like a slider right then what we would
need here is some information about the
material which at the moment we don't
really have right we don't know anything
about the material that we're sampling
here and that's something that we just
haven't really addressed in handmade
here oh we don't have any information
about what materials were sampling we
don't really know anything about them
we could have a non per pixel material
and we could have a an object per pixel
material specified fairly cheaply that
would just go into our it would
basically go into our pipeline where the
color where this where the color term
goes in per vertex that'd be a pretty
few place to put it if we wanted it per
pixel we're in a bit of a bind the
reason we can't get away with anything
free there is because normally what you
would do for most situations in 3d
rendering is if you want to have stuff
like material parameters per pixel you
can use stuff like the Alpha Channel of
the texture of a four-wide texture so
you have RGB and then you're like
parameter for reflectance we don't
really have that luxury because we have
sprites everywhere so we use our alpha
for saying how transparent is the pixel
at this point we still could do
something there we could split our pixel
definition because it's arguable that we
don't really need 256 levels of
transparency transmitted in the textures
so we could say that our textures could
have actual information in them about
reflectance by seeing that maybe we take
the 8 bits and we split it into 4 bits
and 4 bits 16 bits of alpha 16 I'm sorry
60% 16 levels of alpha 16 levels of
specularity that's not a bad idea
I like that idea we could totally do
something like that but at the moment
we're not really stuff to do it anyway
because we don't have an input for that
at some point we could actually have a
way to paint specular Maps you would
import those into the games so it's
something to think about but what I want
to do is say let's pretend
that we can get something like that and
what we'll do now is just make it a
constant so right now what we'll do is
we'll say like specularity or something
right and this is just a random respect
spec mix right suspect coefficient or
something like that and what we'll do is
we'll say that there's a well I guess
we'll call it Specter Mexican we'll say
all right let's say that services are
half and half and then in that case what
we end up with is our spec coefficient
is the spec mix and the diffuse
coefficient is going to be 1 minus the
spec mix right and so in here what we'd
say is well this is going to be the
diffuse amount this is going to be the
spec amount and off we go
oops so you see how that goes there
right and that's just saying so now we
can make our surface completely specular
or completely non specular based on an
input value and in the future maybe we
try and find a way to get that input
value from someplace interesting so that
it will vary as whereas right now it'll
be constant everywhere and so if we look
and by the way I guess there's no reason
for me not to be compiling in release
notes so that our startup time is a
little bit better there right I mean we
could just do that
and so if we take a look now at what's
happening so here we've got a 50/50 mix
which basically should just be what we
had before which is as we get sort of
things get brighter as we get sort of
within them what we can do is say let's
crank up the specular so this is a
perfectly specular one so this should be
back to just pure bouncy lighting no
diffuse and let's just verify that
that's what happens right so now I
should see like everything should be
angular ly dependent right you can kind
of see that now this is perfectly
angular dependent now and you can see
it's getting brighter these bounces as I
get close to incident right so that's
what I would expect
let's go pure diffuse so I should see no
change from view angle viewing angle
produces nothing so now this should be
just pure diffuse no changes and that
seems to be right and so then we can
just pick you know what we're gonna do
and you know I don't know what we want
our services to be specular wise but I'm
just going to leave it at 0.5 as the mix
for now and we'll just call it a day
we'll revisit these when we want to
actually do some any kind of lighting
effects like services that are supposed
to be shiny or something like that
we don't really set up to do specular
very well because we aren't capturing
enough information with our light probes
I don't think like you know we don't
really have the notion that those light
probes the light probes don't store an
actual image off in the direction they
just store a single color and you know
if if we were gonna be a little more
hardcore on our lighting we would store
car more of an image the problem is that
just increases your purpose will cost
just goes up and up and up and I don't
know that we want to go into that
territory
so if here we've got effectively our
irradiance sampling now working we now
pretty much have actual lighting working
with our light probes for the most part
right and so we should be able to do
some stuff where we like I don't know
like actually put some fake lighting
values in there and then when we look at
the scene we should see something
resembling some real lighting in there
right
and so if we look at what we're doing
now and we just change to that half that
half an F if we just said all right
there's an upward lighting we're gonna
make it just be straight up straight up
white light and coming and we go ahead
and and look at what that looks like we
should just see a flat lit scene like
this but hey it already looks a little
bit interesting because there's at least
some notion of directionality so you can
see that the light is kind of coming
from the top down a little bit there
right but we're not getting any bounce
it's not really very good right there's
no real lighting happening here and so
what we want to do now is start moving
towards the real lighting and that's
gonna require the lugging transport but
first let's stuff some money values in
here that are based on location
so we can watch and see whether our
light probes actually are being picked
up correctly across sources and more
importantly since I kind of think they
are because we did some testing with
that let's see if we can verify that our
light probes themselves actually are
what's remaining for oh that our light
voxel is not producing artifacts so when
we stuff these light values in that'll
change over the surface over the voxel
that we don't see like weird bands or
something in there that would indicate a
bug or having thought through the
problem incorrectly somewhere so if I go
into our place we're stuffing our
lighting voxels here I need to do a
couple things first of all we need to
turn back on the repeated transmission
of the lighting voxel which is something
that we had turned off for testing
purposes I believe it's off and so if we
want these things to move around we're
gonna have to put that in there so this
only twice nonsense where we're sending
this down we need to get rid of that now
what I might do here is actually just if
zero it out right actually I'm just
gonna nuke it for now
um and so what we have here is every
frame we will retransmit all of our
lighting voxels so that they can be
updated and this is a sort of source
sticking point because we don't really
know how much that's costing us in terms
of frame rate but it wasn't good when
the voxel was big the Vox was pretty
small now so maybe it's fine
but either or you know it is what it is
right and so now let's try stuffing some
real values down there that move
according to some kind of a debug piece
of information all right so the first
thing I'm gonna do here not gonna be
very interesting I'm gonna do a light P
and this is just a light position value
and all I'm going to do is I'm gonna
take the distance from the light P based
on the location of the vaak based on the
location where the voxel is relative to
everything else right and so what I need
to know here and you can kind of see
when we do or is that here we go so when
we do our lighting computation we've got
our render group here and if you look at
the render group itself I believe inside
that render group we've got the light
bounds and I think we also specify in
the setup function so in this last set
up that also tells us the voxel
information so if we look at render
setup here you can see that there's a
voxel mid corner and a voxel in total
dim and those are pieces of information
that we might want here to produce the
information about how the box should be
shaded so if I want to figure out what's
going on in here we know that these
values like we want the we've got this
light index voxel Jim we've got this M
total dim going on in here which is
being specified you know why did we have
this no no no talking about that
um there's simplifications we should
probably make here but anyway if we want
to do our in photo dim right what we can
do is we can take our voxel and we can
we can do
one of two things I'm gonna do it the
way that makes the most sense based on
sort of the where voxel setup and the
way we're transferring your values but
what we want to do is figure out for
every point here like where is this
point in voxel space in theory right
like where should it be and so if we
think about where this point is where
its location is right so this is our
voxel center P right we know that we've
got essentially a x y and z value that
is supposedly where this thing is right
and those are just values that go from
zero to Vox dim so they don't represent
world space so the first thing we want
to do is say well we can either map this
out to world space or we can map or we
can map the light into voxel space and
I'm gonna map the light into voxel space
just because that Maps a little bit
better to what we're doing in the actual
pixel shader so what I would want to do
here is say well the voxel centre P is
roughly something like this right it's
halfway between the two grid locations
presumably that's how we're sampling it
I have to think about whether that's
actually true with the way that we're
with the way that opengl is actually
sampling it but I think that is true
because open Jill I think uses pics
looks as Texel centers for sampling not
Texel corners even if you're sampling a
voxel so the voxel center should be
there and we need to change that to a UV
coordinate so then we've got like the
Vox UV W and that's going to be the Vox
in total Jim right so that's the or
sorry the Vox in Vox Tim times that Vox
Center P right so that's a Hadamard kind
of product there that's we're
multiplying each component and we get
back a UV W so we need that value as
well and this is that in Vox dim right
and that's going to be 1.0
over Vox Tim ad infinitum because
actually this voxel is the same in all
directions we don't know that that's
gonna be true forever but for right now
it is so this is what our scaling factor
would be right our inbox theme is going
to be that we take the Hadamard product
that puts us into uvw space and so then
what we need to do is just say well
where's the light how far are we from
the light source so we have a light uvw
like where is the light in UVW space
right and you know that's gonna be
something that would go up here so you
have to find the light uvw face we'll do
that later but for right now what we
need to do is say well what's the
distance between these two things right
so let's take the the light distance the
light distance is going to be the length
of the Vox uvw the light UV w- luxury
that's the distance between the light
source and our position right that's the
light distance that will be 0 if we're
right on top of it it will be the you
know 1 plus 1 plus 1 square rooted
square root of 3 if we're all the way on
the corner right so that's the maximum
distance that we could be away I think
if if the lights on one corner and we're
in the other corner so we want to make
there be some kind of fall off here so
what I want to do is I want to say our
light coefficient here is going to be
getting less bright as it gets further
away for no particular reason I'm just
saying we're gonna be less bright as we
get further away from whatever the light
location is and so I want to do one
minus the light distance but the light
distance here again I want to do a clamp
zero to one on this because I want it to
range cleanly between those I want to do
one minus whatever the distance away
from the light source is
and you know maybe that's just fine but
then we we may also want there to be
some kind of a coefficient on this for
the light radius so like there's a light
you know radius coefficient in here that
we can play with so that's that's like
how you know it's basically one over the
light radius and UV space or something
right and so this is what we would want
to compute we would end up with a
lighting value here and so what I want
to do then is I want to make this value
which is the brightness right
I want like light brightness or a light
base alpha something like that
I want this value here to basically be
computed now so that we can make the
intensity of the light be what we start
with and that way when we put a light in
here it will be based on this actual
distance from the light source if that
makes sense right now there's other
things we're gonna want to do here so
we're gonna want more information so I'm
gonna make a light direction as well
and that's gonna be this value and I'm
gonna normalize or zero that probably in
here and again where this routine is
gonna get really slow so we're gonna end
up with some issues here but you know
that's just something have to deal with
cuz it this is only for debugging anyway
so anyway as we do this sort of normal
to the light source there we're gonna
end up with some more information I'm
gonna call this light just to be clear
so as we compute these values here now
we've got more information for the light
source and what I want to do is pack
that into this light base a right so all
I want to do there is say well it's
already clamped from 1 to 0 so really
all we're talking about here it's taking
that light coefficient value which is
basically intensity of the light source
I want to multiply it by 255 which is
the maximum value that could be and then
I want to convert that to you 32 and
then I want to shift it up into the
Alpha Channel right and that's all I'm
doing
so that's how I'm going to create my
light base a unfortunately in order to
do that I need to like UVW here which is
the location of the light source
relative to the voxel for now let's just
call that zero so it's it's always gonna
be the corner of the voxel actually you
know what I take that back let's make it
the center of the voxel for now right so
your distance from the center of the
voxel is what's going to determine your
lighting and we'll start with that right
light RC is I don't know point five as
well all right all right so we're gonna
have to make those values of you real
things but now basically what we want to
do is see if we can get this stuff
working now this looks super crappy so
obviously I screwed something up not
sure what yet but we'll find out in a
second
looking at the Vox UVW there that seems
like so one thing is true that this
light this light see maybe yeah I mean I
feel like maybe we may want this to be
higher than that and the fall-off is
probably not gradual enough the
interesting thing about the light see is
this is the maximum intensity light so
we really don't want this light to be
maximum intensity is the other problem
if the max light intensity is is 10 and
we want this lights intensity to
something else we want that to be kind
of reflected unattended in here
so we've won a light intensity value
that's probably not the full intensity
so we probably want like max light
intensity to something like you know
this is only a tenth of the maximum
lighting intensity or something it's all
I'm thinking right so let's see if that
produces anything a little bit more
interesting there but probably not yeah
so we've got some weird bugs here it
looks like we're stuffing really bright
values in here always which is a little
weird so let's try and figure out what I
screwed up there we've got the vox
center peak here we're taking the
Hadamard product to figure out where the
voxel is and UVW space we take a
difference between that in the center of
the voxel basically we look at how long
it is to get there and we normalize that
afterwards we don't actually use this we
look at the light coefficient by saying
well alright the fall-off should be
however far away we are for the light as
that increases we should end up getting
something where at zero we have a full
bright and as we get up to like whatever
light our C is implying we are this
should probably you know maybe we need
to make the fall-off be faster
no I'm just wondering why we don't see
any fall-off but maybe that's because I
I was being too generous with it I'm not
sure but we'll see there we go all right
so I just had to fall off too far right
so here's what our lighting would look
like as we go and you can see the voxel
itself represented there right
and since our voxel is not stable right
now it moves with the actual character
quite a bit but you can see so the
character hops up and down that's
because of our Z range that's something
we want to fix anyway so I'm not worried
about that hopping at all because that's
a separate thing and you can see the
hard edges of the voxel right now
because we have interpolation turned off
so as we sort of look at that lighting
it actually looks like what we want
which is just a purely distance based
light it's what we expect to see so that
looks nice but we don't want those hard
edges let's go ahead and turn on the
interpolation on the voxel just to see
and make sure that that looks ok because
now that we've seen the actual like
voxel size we don't really need to see
it anymore I mean maybe we want to turn
that on occasionally just to you know
debug something but at the moment I
think we don't we certainly don't need
that so if we do sir chips for nearest
we should see that and here here's our
voxels
there's the nearest sampling so if I
tell it no I would like you to do linear
please
now when we run we should see something
that hopefully approximates decent
lighting and and you know it's not
perfect I do see kind of at the edges I
do see a little bit of sort of banding
I'm not sure what I think of that
exactly just looking at kind of like
these parts maybe there's a little kind
of Fox elite banding like like you see
that kind of right there
so I don't know if we're gonna have to
work on that a little bit you know maybe
we will maybe we won't because you can
see now you kind of see that stair step
pattern there and I'll be honest I don't
really know exactly where that's coming
from though
I'm not sure yeah exactly where that's
coming from so it's hard for me to say
whether that's something that gets fixed
with lighting sampling or whether that's
a inherent limitation of the way we're
doing the light box lusatian right but
you can definitely see some
objectionable miss to the way that
that's being sampled and that's I think
just kind of a property unfortunately of
the of the trilinear interpolation on
the on the voxel I'm assuming but I
guess I don't really know right so if we
were to make this fall-off the you know
what I really want to do is make it lock
to the to the to the player so let's
let's finish what I was going to do
which is to actually map a real light
location in there so that we can talk
about the location of the viewer and
like have a debug like kind of a thing
so when we come through here if we
mapped the location of the of the light
source in here what we want to do is say
if there was a light P so let's say the
light p value was some thing that we're
gonna pass in what I want to do is have
a way of computing the light UV W value
which I believe all we would need to do
there is if we take the render group and
say where's club group if we were to
look at what we used for the lighting
setup there what I should be able to do
is just take that pair of parameters
that we're using inside to map and say
well we know that the voxel mid-corner
is what we need to subtract away from a
position to base it around the voxel and
then we know that the in total dim
is what we use to map something into the
scale of the voxel that should produce a
UVW value for where the light source is
in voxel space assuming that we had one
right which at the moment unfortunately
we don't so we do need some way of
getting that which we'll take a look at
in a second oops forgot to change that
to a comma so now as long as we have a
way of passing in a debug light which
we'll do in a second here we should be
able to now actually make this based off
of the player's position and what you
can see right now is it's just based off
of zero zero zero in world space which
doesn't really give us anything we
didn't get before but you can really see
you see those kind of objectionable like
blending just it just doesn't look very
good right you get that kind of rippling
there right and I don't love that like
so I don't know what we're gonna have to
do about that but that seems bad right
so we'll see anyway so moving on uh if I
want to go ahead and have this be locked
to the player which I kind of do so we
can sort of see how that sampling works
what I want to do is have some way of
sending down where the player actually
is and in the world group like I mean
sorry in the world mode we do know where
the player is right because what we're
doing when we actually do stuff like
tracking the movement for the entities
where's that code it's right here
so when we do this you can see we know
like what the camera entity is and so in
here where we say world D but light P
like we know where the debug light is
supposed to be it's right there
right so all we really need to do is
when we do the N Lenny computation what
we could do is say well you know the
test lighting debug light equals you
know the southern T bug light got here
and so inside the lighting stuff we can
just for free have this idea that
there's a debug light kind of smut
sitting around on us here like that and
then we should be good to go because we
already tracked a debug light position
for you know for fun and profit before
and so what we can do is have another
one here so the lighting system itself
now has its own debug like that you can
stuff with whatever value you wants and
when we turn on this debug mode here
that's what we should get right so now
as the player moves around right the
light should move with them and you can
see that sort of you know that radius
around them occurring right and so I
guess the thing yeah like I was sort of
saying before the thing that I don't
care for here is I just don't like
what's happening with I think this is
this light sampling just isn't good
enough because I don't like the way
we're getting those those hardline
artifacts where the lighting sort of
falls to zero and that mean you know
what what that kind of means to me as
well is it's like it also means that
that that artifact is sort of present
everywhere right like you know you're
getting you're getting that pretty much
wherever you go so anywhere in the world
where where you actually see lighting
happening at all you're gonna be having
this artifact it's just it's it's just a
lot harder to perceive when the values
are close together but
the values get a little further apart
you get that stiff banding right now
maybe the argument is well you should
never really have values that far apart
because the lighting is supposed to be
fairly continuous but I don't know that
that's a very good reason to have it
look the way that it does I think we
want to be able to have it sample the
lighting well in any case right and so I
think I want to at least want to try to
get to get that a little better and what
I would assume is that like you know the
the the reason we tried this was because
it's a lot simpler to blend the light
probes this way but there were like you
know there are other ways that we could
have done the light probes right and
it's a lot simpler to blend the probes
this way than it is to blend them the
other way so I you know rather than then
using a voxel lookup into a light probe
array and then blending the light probes
sort of that way which was much harder
in this particular case what we decided
to do was just use the voxel use a 3d
texture to sort of look up the lighting
but unfortunately you know it just it
looks pretty bad there now I guess the
other thing I don't really know is is
that an artifact to of kind of maybe
more how we chose to sample this you
know like for example suppose you wanted
a less hard fall-off curve you know I'm
saying it to you so you know if we you
know if we take a look at that how do we
get this thing there's this good site
Decimus we were using
there we go so if we wanted to look at
like what we're getting for fall off
there right we're getting like within
one radius we're getting like an
x-squared plus y-squared fall I don't
know if this thing can do that but well
it doesn't really matter that much I
guess the point is like let's suppose we
just looked at the fall-off along a
diagonal and so we said it was basically
the square root of x squared plus x
squared right
and really you know what we want to do
is look at it like this but this would
be a 3d and I don't know that this thing
can do that so I'm just going to go
ahead and assume that you know we're
just through x squared plus x squared
right so the square root of x squared
plus x squared that's going to be the
fall-off equation for our particular
light which right it was one minus and
so we had some coefficient in here which
we can use to sort of change the angle
of this right like if it was that it
would take longer if it was that then
it's steeper but basically it's linear
right and so what we could do if we
wanted to is if we want to smooth this
out we can look at this function and
this interface sucks now is it always
this bad I just want to put this whole
thing into the square root so we can see
there's that would be a steeper fall-off
all I was trying to do is illustrate the
difference between these two things and
this would be a smoother fall-off right
so I don't know like we could say well
how bad is it if we assume that the
lighting isn't as harsh you know it
doesn't fall off as harshly
so with this clamp 0 to 1 maybe what I
do is say well ok like yeah we've got
light see x equals whatever the light
intensity actually is but before we do
that we want to smooth the fall-off
curve so we just say like well you know
square that right and so if we square
that term we just get you know in theory
a smoother fall-off curve and how bad is
that right and the answer is you know
it's true it's not as bad right but it's
still pretty bad I would say you know
any you know we can we can sit there ad
infinitum making this less and less
harsh I think but I don't think we're
ever really gonna get away from from
that artifact right so here's in fact
that wasn't really looks worse honestly
right
because it cursed weaker right
so I think we've learned what we want to
learn from this we can also try it March
or fall off but I'm assuming that it's
gonna be bad as well wait oh you know
what we don't call it square it we call
it square I'm assuming Harsha fall off
will be just as bad as the as the really
unhorse fell off right that not work
sometimes yes I agree
um so I think yeah I think we want to do
some more thinking about this right yeah
you can see like there's looking at how
hard how much blockiness you get at the
edges of that one right and we can take
the light intensity down to see what it
would look like more reasonably because
like that I like intensity it's too high
right now but it's still you know you're
gonna get that really hard fall off
there and it happens pretty much in
either case right so I think there's no
way around it I think we're gonna have
to do something better right I think
this is just not good enough and
and that's kind of unfortunate to say
the least but I think that's basically
where we're at so yeah
all right so how much time we got here
we've got about 15 minutes left I guess
what I would want to try and we're gonna
have to think about this a bit so the
next thing that maybe makes sense to
drive is to say what if we actually just
compute like just lighting distances so
we actually think about for the voxel
UVW we say where are these lighting
probes
where are the Centers of these probes
and let's like actually try to shoot
light towards them so that we blend
radially instead of try linearly right
like that's my first thought my second
thought is well you know since this
stuff is being sampled as like more of a
you know that's what I'm saying actually
true
so the thing that I'm thinking about in
my head is just like well you know we've
got light sources and those light
sources are not have there's no direct
illumination pass and handmade here oh
right so we only have the indirect
illumination and that was really all we
were planning on really doing so we're
not doing like shadow maps or anything
like that and projecting lights as
specific lights we just have like a
lighting sort of convection phase and
that's it and so you know I mean one
thing that I guess you could say is the
situation specifically that we're
talking about here where you get like
fall-off of the light you know based on
the distance from the light source it's
not really ever gonna happen so I guess
it's possible I mean it's it's I don't
know for sure but I guess it's possible
that you would never really have
something like this happen anyway so
maybe it's the wrong thing to say let's
get rid of it altogether you know right
away because you know I don't know maybe
maybe we don't actually need to get rid
of it
maybe it's fine and maybe if you're
talking about lighting that has it's
always got you know sort of the the
first pass with the probe distribution
already having smooth the light out
around so that you know things are
generally lit things next to each other
are pretty similarly lit you know maybe
you just don't ever have that particular
problem and I don't know right so it's
really hard for me to guess
it's it's pretty difficult for me to
make a specific guess about that
so it's hard to say you know on the one
hand I'm like should I just go in then
should I you know
should we go forward with this light
sampling and then you know do it after
the fact I don't know maybe we should
because maybe it's putting the cart
before the horse to try to improve the
light sampling and maybe we should see
so let's do one more thing before we end
for the day we've got the light normal
here let's use the light normal to
decide who we stuff right so we have our
you know up down or south east west
just to put some different lighting
directions in there and mix it up a
little bit and so what I'd like to do
here is say all right let's take a look
at which one of these components is
Maxwell or maybe we'll just say we'll
use the light and itself to determine
who gets what light where right and so
we'll say okay there's going to be a a
light stuff value here I might go ahead
and make a little utility function for
this well you know we could use an RGB
AIPAC 4 by 8 here I guess it's a BGR
pack technically so I could use this so
we basically just we call this on each
one so instead of doing it this way we
would do this
and then what we would do is we just all
we would do is have actual like values
here so we'd pass in a v4 right and the
v4 would would have the alpha or the
intensity for each channel so this is
the west intensity or the the west alpha
I guess you would say and then the light
color right so this would just be you
know that for now but we could obviously
change the light color if we wanted to
so we'll do something like this I think
and then we just need to actually
compute those alpha values and we'll
compute them based on the lighting
direction there right so here we have
south north found and and then all we
need to do is actually produce those
light values ourselves and you know get
them in there so we don't need this
anymore we'll let the PAC work
generically so looking at what we've got
here we can see we've got a light this
is the direction to the light from the
place in the voxel which is what we want
to use for packing so what we want here
is to produce values for each of these
and this is how much of the light is
coming in from that direction right and
so what we'd like to do is we'd like to
basically you know maybe use the dot
product here to say like how close are
we to that this is not exactly right
because we're trying to conserve the
amount of light so we want all of this
to sum to one in a sense and so you know
it's it's something that we want to kind
of do a 1-norm on probably after the
fact to make sure that we don't add
light to the system so it's more we
gotta be a little bit flexible here so
we'll try to further that in a second
but anyway so if we take these values
here and first compute them as plant
zero to one you know light and and we
don't actually have to do because we
know that these are all cardinal
directions what we can do is just take
the dot product manually we know that
the westward facing one is going to be
whatever the X parameter is negated
because you're multiplying it by
negative one right same thing here this
is just you know each one of these we
can just pre evaluate the dot product
right so we know each of these is going
to be the light the normalized light
value basically like with with these
with these pre dot products computed and
then what we need to do is say well
that's how much does contribute each one
but this is not going to sum to one
right and so we then need to do is make
sure we don't distribute too much light
into the system so at that point we
would just sum them all
and then we just need to do the inverse
of that right to like fill it in so we
would need to say West a you know divide
equals total a write each of these piece
south north down and then we know that
we're not like making too much light
because we won normalized it right and
I'm not gonna guard for 0 there although
it probably should I guess I should cuz
this can and technically be 0 so maybe
I'll do this right and then this is just
a multiply and that's just if you happen
to be standing like right on the light
source you don't know which direction
it's coming from right well and actually
so that's a safe ratio of 1 technically
right because if you're standing right
on the light source you should get it
equally from all directions not not get
it at all so I think that's actually it
should be that um ok wow that went
poorly so what a nice grip there anyone
know we're competing the light normal we
assign it to each of those say for sure
why don't we multiplied by the inverse
to 1 normalize we then do beat your pack
that looks good doesn't it
is this just rusted I wonder if my pack
is broken
yeah it is apparently all right so my
BGR I packed 4x8 is there something
we're oh yeah gets me every time
so these are two fives so this is
actually this
[Music]
there we go
all right so taking away the Fulbright
up a nonsense there the other thing we
need here is this is not respecting this
in total a is a little bit wrong because
we have a light intensity value so we
want it to sum to the total light
intensity right or rather the total
light seek contribution level right I
should say so what we want to do is say
this is the total light contribution
we're going to spread it out this way so
we want to say don't normalize to 1
normalize to whatever the total amount
of incoming light should have been at
that point and we'll do it like that
right and that's just a radial fall-off
curve right so here is our you know
directional version of this so now we
actually have the light coming from
different directions and you can see
that it actually is as well because if
you look at what happens say on the wall
here right you can see that you get like
curvature coming in so the surfaces
themselves are not uniformly lit they it
depends on what direction you're facing
right so that does seem to be working
and we see exactly what we would expect
to see there like darkening in that
corner right because again it can't when
it's pointing in the different
directions there it's it's gonna fade
out that earlier right so we do see that
I think that's what that should look
like
it just looks fairly right to me so that
all seems pretty good let's take a look
at what happens when we just go into
something that's a little bit more
vertically stacked
you
so here you can kind of see and I don't
know if those normals are correct or not
on the sprites in fact I kind of wish
we'd turn those off because I should
probably go severa phi that the normals
are correct is what I should do that's
sort of a separate issue but it's hard
to really gauge whether that's working
properly
but it sure seems like it is and the
only thing that I think isn't quite
working properly it's I don't think
these sort of the I don't think the
sprites themselves have their normal set
the way that they should be so I do
think we want to take a look at that and
if I remember correctly there's some
kind of nonsense happening I there with
normals that I don't really remember
what it is
but like if you go look at the entity
output stuff it's I feel like there are
some nonsense going on in here so if we
look at the way that we're spamming
these values down
[Music]
there's a cover end value here and like
looking at this it's kind of nonsense
right I'm not sure exactly what we want
that value to be but it's probably not
that right
we'd have to think about if it's
probably something more like this you
know I'm saying say so we'll have to
think about that and whether or not that
normals coming through correctly and we
probably want that normal to vary as
well so we probably want that normal to
actually be like something that
something that changes over the surface
of the sprite as well so let me just
take a quick look though and you know
for ground cover it almost seems like it
wants to be lit more with the actual
ground that's on so I wonder too if
maybe that's not the right thing for
cover sprites cover only actual up
rights rights that are you know not just
ground cover maybe don't want that
because then you would get the lighting
that you get for the ground which seems
like that what you want so that though
the ground cover appears to be lit the
same way that the surface underneath it
is right and then you should see them
getting sort of more uniformly lit right
and maybe that's what we want
I don't really know kind of hard to say
I also do wonder what happens with like
a sprite like that looks like that gets
lit pretty correctly there but as we get
behind that guy it should they should be
darker yeah which is exactly what we
want so yeah I mean it looks like our
lighting sampling is working pretty good
I just don't love those those edge
artifacts let's go ahead and go to the
QA you know we're not horrible
I could see shipping this because you
know people have shipped a lot worse but
I do think spending a little bit of time
maybe not now maybe we should just leave
it this way and go do our light
transport and then come back to it but I
do think
there's better things we could be doing
there and so I don't know right but yeah
so I think we'll you know will I think
my good inclination if I had to fight to
say is I think we should do is this is
good enough for now
we should ping pong over to the light
transport the light transport working
ping pong back to the sampling and then
improve the sampling based on what we
see as a result of the light transport
stuff right I think that might be more
what we want to do
so do we have any questions we don't
have any questions apparently could you
give a sort of brief handle excavation
how the lighting works and/or someone -
people ask questions on that could you
draw a quick diagram giving it overview
of the stages and lighting solution sure
we don't really have any questions so
that seems pretty easy let me actually
let me feel that these in opposite order
though because so much of my name I'm so
asked are the cube artifacts result of
the view vector reflection instead of
the light vector reflections so it is
worth noting that we don't really know
what those artifacts are exactly I think
they're just would happen any time
you're doing that trilinear though but
let's double check right so if we do
compile Z biased program in here and we
look at how the lighting is working
right what we could do is say well you
know what just get rid of the specular
so that way all we're doing is pure
diffuse so you know goodbye specular
it's gone and now like what does our
light sample look like when it's only
sampling diffuse lighting right so if
we're only sampling diffuse lighting
this is what we get and to me that looks
the same right so I don't see any that
the artifacts look like they look to me
right they looked like they looked
before so I'm assuming that our specular
reflection equation doesn't really have
anything new with the artifacts it's
just the trilinear interpolation in the
voxel that sucks right and I can
understand why that would be because
what effectively is happening is we
don't blend the light probes and then
take some aggregate light and sample the
aggregate lighting what we do is we
blend directly what we think the
incoming light from that direction is on
the voxel so I have to play
where it goes from something to zero
there is just a hard trilinear edge
there right so it's not gonna give you
radial fall off like you would expect
for the diffuse lighting and the only
way I think to really get that radial
fall-off is to be using the distance to
the voxel as part of it right now maybe
the answer is we should be doing that so
that it's a radial fall-off but in order
to do the radial fall-off um you can't
use the trilinear anymore right
I mean another answer is like an another
question the first thing that came to
mind was sort of like what if we just
sampled the light from all of these
cubed maps based on normal I don't know
so I really don't know
but let me go in let me go draw the
diagram anyway because that was the the
question that was asked so the lighting
stages are pretty straightforward
actually there's not that much stuff to
it it's just that because there's like
the need to persist over frames and you
know optimization concerns and all this
it gets over complicated which is why
lighting Yowies is bad
I mean lighting should take like five
seconds to implement it's just a ray
tracer right and then the lighting is
perfect
the problem is that's way too slow right
and so everything is about all these
like hacky approximations that we're
doing to try and and not have to do that
right so anyway the stages are pretty
basic so
so basically this is it startup and this
is it runtime so during startup the
first thing you do is lie probe
distribution and what that effectively
does is it says well you know we
generated some stuff like I don't know
here's a room and there's a doorway and
then there's another room over here or
something right and so whatever the heck
we generated we need to distribute light
probes so we put them in the environment
wherever we think we might want them
right and it's just a hacky random thing
we can spew them out wherever we want it
doesn't really matter so we have light
probe distribution and that distributes
light probes through the system right
those light probes are actual entities
so they go into the entity system and
the reason for that is because we're
just using the fact that we have a nice
robust enemy system with caching and all
kinds of stuff that allows us to have
like billions of entities if we want to
so it's nice and free to just throw the
light probes in there and in there go
right then at runtime what we have is
the thing that's basically like a light
table so light probe table of a certain
fixed size right and so this is like n
long whereas this is like arbitrary
right so the number of light probes the
number of probes is like you know
basically infinite it doesn't make with
in machine storage we don't care how
many light probes the world generator
generated it doesn't matter at actual
runtime some number of these light
probes right we have a light probe table
so step two in the process and the first
step that happens at runtime because
this one happened when we created the
world is like probe index assignment
right can somebody please tell me if
Milton's been fixed by the way it's so
bad to draw on now it like totally broke
and I don't know why it broke because it
was good before I'm not sure
they broke it but somebody broke it and
I'm not sure what the deal is with that
anyway so probe index assignment just
basically says look some subset of the
million probes or whatever that we put
in the world some subset are actually
useful right now and what we're doing is
as we move around the world we're sort
of taking some subset so maybe we say
like you know these probes right here we
don't need anymore right so this is like
you know removal and then some new
probes came in so then there's like
insertion and we like use those spots
that we pulled stuff out of and we stick
new light probes in there so we have a
light probe table that is basically just
a way of maintaining a small number of
light probes that'll actually go into
the lighting system and that can be
indexed by the hardware as necessary
right and what we're doing with this is
we're storing the light so we can have
what's called hysteresis I'm not gonna
try to draw that with the new Milton you
spell that
hysteresis there we go um so we're
trying to get some hysteresis in there
which is basically to say that look our
lighting is gonna be very noisy we know
it's gonna be noisy because we can't
afford to really do like computation we
are not on like an RT X 2080 or
something here and even if we were most
people who do that still use hysteresis
so we kind of need to smooth these
values over time so what we're gonna do
is we're going to take this grid this
array of light probe table and we're
keeping it so this is like persistent
frame-to-frame right so we want this to
persist frame-to-frame
and so what we do is you'll see that we
get up here we're keeping this so it has
a value from the previous frame and
that's what the lighting was at each
probe on on last frame right so then
what we do is we say okay we assign
probe indices so people who need a mixes
get them people who are old and have
fallen out of the view frustum or
whatever get their indices removed then
we do step three right
which is like light injection and all
this is is if we have actual light
sources actual light sources those get
you know rendered directly in so we need
and we haven't done this yet for the new
system we did it for the old system
haven't done it for the new system so
actual light sources get specified by
entity output right so somewhere we're
gonna have to like you know we've got
the the thing that could say push light
that push light records the fact that
someone's actually emitting light in an
area not just bouncing it around right
we don't do this yet so we were doing it
with the old system and the new system
we haven't done it yet and we'll get to
that at some point once everything else
is we're
with debug lights and so on okay then
step four is you know light transmission
and so what happens here is we say all
right let's take all the light probes
that are actually in the view so we've
got you know some light probes here
let's just see you know cast rays out
from these light probes and see what
they hit some those values up to produce
what's basically like a you know new
light probe set right and then we smooth
it right so here we say you know
smoothing this is the like word I can't
spell hysteresis right so what we do is
we take the new light that we have and
we multiply that right times some small
coefficient like 0.05 or something right
and we add it to almost entirely the old
one so this is the old one that we had
way back here right and what that does
is that allows us to average over you
know 100 frames or something let's say
we made it like 60 frames but it's any
number we choose so one second worth of
gameplay and basically what we're doing
there is we're trading off
responsiveness so lights will lag in
their effect on the world by about half
a second on average because half of it
will take a full second to respond
completely to the light so the time the
user actually sees like a prominent
effect from the light would be like half
a second or something in so you're
trading that for noise because if we
just drew the light directly whatever we
calculate on that frame it would be very
flickering
because we're not casting enough rays to
actually capture the complete lighting
environment so what we do is we take the
average over several frames so that we
actually have way more light rays that
we're actually using on any given frame
because we're using the ones from last
frame and the frame before that
the frame for that a frame from that and
frame from that right and that's the
entire light pipeline really after this
all happens we do have the part that
happens on the GPU right and what we're
doing there is the part you just saw we
have some voxels oops
and what we're imagining and don't do
yet is right here there is a voxel
ization step of the light probes and the
reason that we don't really know exactly
what this looks like is because right
now we're not sure if it's the right way
to sample this is why I was saying well
I'm not sure if this looks good enough
right but what we would say is well we
have this array of light probes we will
voxel I as the light probes we will send
the voxels down to the GPU and then the
pixel shader right we'll sample them
right so we sample the voxels and it's
it's up to us how we choose to encode
them right now that wheat we tried doing
is six times the voxels where we put
each direction of each probe into a
separate voxel so we basically would say
like okay we voxel eyes the directions
of of lighting in the probe into one
voxel per direction so X have six voxels
we try linearly sample each voxel to get
the average incoming light from that
direction right and that's what we use
so-called a view says responding to why
there's not two cosine terms two things
the beardy f is defined to the
derivative of the outgoing radians
respect to the Iranians so whatever
extra terms you think you need are
already folded into the brdf okay so
basically if we were to use an actual
lighting brdf it's already got that
accounted so that's fine and that makes
sense also remember that the next bounce
of light will have another cosine so the
other cosine is accounted for does that
clear it up or am i misunderstanding so
it doesn't clear up for the eye because
the eye doesn't have that cosine term in
there so I guess I'm not sure about that
last part but yeah if the brdf already
has whatever a random transmission is
going to happen baked in then sure
that's fine but we're not actually doing
that here so I'm not sure whether that
accounts for when you're not using a
brdf right hard to say and zero L PBM
says regarding Milton aren't using an
unofficial version that as the grid
chilla patched in if so made me switch
back to the visual version yes I am
using the unofficial version but
according to the person who made this
unofficial version the official version
also has it the reason we didn't have it
before
was cuz I was using an old official
version so apparently what happened is
somewhere along the line between the old
version we were using and the newest
official version they broke it
supposedly so I was hoping someone would
fix the official version to not be
broken anymore and then we could have
the grid tool and reasonable sampling if
not I can try to roll back to whenever
the Milton is that doesn't have this
problem
all right looks like we're all done I'm
gonna go ahead and wrap it up
okay thank you in for joining me for
this soda handmade hero spit pleasure
coating with you as always if you would
like to follow along the series at home
you can raise peer to the game at
handmade hero org and it comes with a
source code so if you'd like to play
around with it you can do your own
experimentation at home also now might
be a good time to do said playing around
because you have all day today and
possibly quite some time if I choose to
work on the light distribution function
stuff tomorrow to figure out what might
be some better ways of doing light
probes sampling that don't have the
artifacts that we were seeing with our
trilinear filtering there that would be
a fun thing to play around it's a very
well constrained problem you can think
about it you can play around with how
we're doing hammer here and see if you
can find a better way to do it there's
also lots of research in this topic you
can go look up papers on light probes
and how they work and how people use
them and so maybe get some ideas of how
to implement something closer to a full
fledged thing I don't know but point
being is a lot of work you could do
there so it might be a good time play
around with that if you're looking for
something to do for practice that's
about it for today I'll be back to her
tomorrow same time same place for some
more work on the lighting it's looking
like we're getting there I like where
we're going with it but you know there's
still a lot of work left to do so we're
going to be doing that work until we get
it just right that's it for today hope
see you back here tomorrow till then
have fun programming everyone and I will
see you on the Internet take it easy
everybody