hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero the show where we code a complete
game live on stream today we're going to
be fussing with lighting seeing what we
can do we're trying to sort of push
forwards into getting some lighting into
the game we're just not sure what that
lighting is going to be like because
lighting is very difficult to do
correctly and in our case it's
impossible to do correctly because I
don't even have 3d models because we are
a 2-d game but we are trying to play
around lighting to see what we can do
that will produce an interesting or
useful effect for us one of the things
that we have been doing is writing
shaders lately and one of the things
that that one thing that kind of
confounds us I'm going to load up the
code base series you can see what I'm
talking about is that I didn't really
make any system for loading the shaders
from disk largely because I don't like
shipping extra files of the game so to
be honest I I kind of like them being
embedded in the executable and so if we
were going to do something like loadable
shaders I would probably do it honestly
I probably do it through the hot code
reloading system which is probably
something we should do eventually anyway
since the hots of reloading system kind
of handles this case as well we just
didn't happen to put the renderer in the
hot loaded section we should right but
all that aside one of the things that's
been confounding us since we haven't
really had a much of a need to hot load
the shaders at the moment because the
game boots very quickly so it's not
really that big of a deal but one of the
problems we've been having is because we
just put them in as strings in our
executable is the indentations all
messed up because once we open something
as a string we end up in a position
where the fork odor went looks at what
we've given it thinks that we are
talking about just a giant group of
characters and it's misha's all the
indentation out of our shader
which makes it hard to read simple ones
like this aren't so bad but you know
when you get into ones that are a little
more complicated which we have a couple
now that are somewhat complicated you
know you look at something like this and
it's just it's hard to read it's just
it's difficult to read some of the
slightly more complicated shaders now I
was like well I wish we could fix that
but I can't think of a way how to fix it
I tried a little bit but I couldn't do
it
Martin who many of you already know he
answers all the questions on handmade
Network like all the questions he seems
to know everything figured out a fix for
this that may work so let's try it what
he suggested was since we're using an
arbitrary string opener here apparently
the rules of C++ 11 are that if we open
a string with a one of these sort of
like what's the word I'm looking for
with one of these like arbitrary
modifiers that arbitrary modifier is
allowed to include a closing quote
apparently so we can in theory do this
and then at the end of it we can do that
right so the question was if we did that
would for coder no longer think it was a
long string unfortunately it looks like
here for coder is too smart for us it
looks like poor coder knows about that
string syntax and so as a result here it
looks like there's no way to turn it off
so because like you can see I've got the
closing quote here but unfortunately all
of this remains a string according to
for coder so yeah it looks like for
coder it's just a bit too smart it
understands how to do open and close
strings like that so that's too bad
I guess one thing that would be really
cool for coder did is like if you could
say in here like that as the string
opening closer or something like this
you know like something that would tell
it to indent the string in a normal
fashion like that and so for coder would
know you know if you made a thing like
that to allow indentation inside it
because it was supposed to be C code for
something similar to C code that could
be indented that way correctly so that
would be cool
let me see
of us who see for some reason for coder
has a maximum length here is that is
that also part of C meaning is this not
considered one of those strings anymore
because that would do it oh man for
coder cut for cluttered I know dude nope
so I guess that's just part of C as well
so you can't have longer sequences for
coders just telling you that and parsing
that properly so yeah I don't think
there's any real way around it yeah I
don't think there's any way around it
unfortunately so there you go thank you
Martins for trying that was a really
good idea
unfortunately for cutters a little too
smart for its own good
in this case and so basically we will
just have to ask Allen I think we'll
just have to ask Alan to fix it for us I
don't think there's anything we can do
at this point we've tried pretty much
everything we can think of alright
anyway let's go back to a game
programming here and specifically render
rendering programming now where we last
left off we sort of have the ability to
take a look at several buffers that we
were storing with information in them
regarding the lighting and one of the
weird things that we sort of have here
right look you can see what's going on
here we felt like our subsampled
lighting buffer here and we've got our
normals here and we've got the emission
current emission blur thing happening
here and blah blah blah excusing so one
of the things that I had been doing is
we were sort of playing around with the
lighting in this setup that we've got
here and it occurred to me as we were
doing this and I thought about it this
week I think I kind of realized that
we've been taking a slightly inaccurate
approach or rather a slightly
unproductive approach here and what I
realized was continuing what I realized
was we are sort of making things a lot
harder on ourselves here because what
we're doing is we're trying to develop
the lighting algorithm in like the most
unfavorable circumstances possible we're
trying to develop a new algorithm
because we don't really have any
existing algorithm we're implementing
directly we're trying to implement a new
algorithm in like the GPU directly and
we don't even have the ability to debug
this GPU we can't use like a GPU
debugger on it because it doesn't work
with a GPU that's old and so it occurred
to me it's like how are we ever going to
do how are we ever going to figure it
out right it's like the most
unfavourable way to possibly develop
something we can't even see really
what's going on it's laborious to store
information because we have to create
like new textures to put the data in and
all this other stuff it's just really
inconvenient and bad and so what I
realized is why don't we not
that way instead of doing that why don't
we just write the lighting on the CPU
side right like what if we just wrote
the lighting on the on the CPU side
finished it and then poured you to the
GPU right it seems like a pretty easy
approach to me that would be a lot more
fruitful because what we could do is
like for example if we want to do this
thing with reflectors like I was trying
we can just create a struct for the
reflectors create as many reflectors as
we want run the lighting on the CPU side
and then download the results of the GPU
and draw the lit scene with that and
that way we can even draw those
reflectors so we can actually like send
down reflectors as geometry to see what
their current status is and all that
other sorts of things right so it seems
to me like maybe that's a smarter way to
go because if we did that then we
wouldn't have to worry about all the GPU
side stuff that is endemic in trying to
implement a complex algorithm using
nothing but pixel and fragment shaders
I'm a vertex and fragment shaders
because then it's more like just writing
like a compute shaders a secured out
what we want to do then we can translate
it right down to something that the card
could do so that's that's my thought and
so I was thinking of trying that this
weekend that way we can sort of get out
of the business of trying to do this on
the hardware side of things which to me
seems very difficult all right so I what
I was kind of thinking about there is
just literally trying to do some of the
stuff with the reflectors I like on the
seaside right so inside the insides of
render group right we've got this thing
called render entry textured quads and
render entry textured cloth just outputs
all of the basically Subsidy everything
in our game
it outputs a series of quadrilaterals
each quadrilateral is you know either
going to be a sprite or the side of one
of our like structural cubes that we use
to make up the ground for the look of
the game and if we want to we can easily
grab one of these textured quad elements
and we can loop over all of the quads on
the CPU side so what I was thinking we
could do is just take all of those quads
and generate reflectors for each one on
the CPU side compute lighting between
the reflectors and then render those
reflectors to see what the lighting
actually is right and furthermore we
have a way of doing this in a really
convenient fashion because we can hijack
all of the textures and colors in the
quads at any point in the pipeline what
I can do is just insert effectively a I
could I can sort of insert a piece of
code that just hijacks that does the
lighting and outputs the lighting
directly to the quads and I think that
will pretty much solve our problem for
it I think in terms of development so
let's just take a look at this and see
so here in the appeal composite program
you can see that we've zeroed out the
lighting so there is no lighting going
on anymore and that's why when you run
the game at the moment you can see that
we sort of have a unlit world but
otherwise it's rendering as we normally
would expect it to render now if I want
to insert that hijacking what I can do
is say okay inside world mode there
should be a time when we actually push
the the rendering out here you can see
at the end depth field state of things
for example so what I want to do is is
basically hijack the render group here
so I'm just going to insert a thing
called lighting test skin to render
group what I want to do here is I want
to create something inside the render
group at the end that's a dummy function
well it doesn't have to be in line so
after we have pushed this render element
to end the death field we now know that
right behind our current render element
is the one of these on you know on the
render sack is going to be one of these
texture quad sets so what I can do is
like and now I know that I can just loop
through the in you know the the render
stack looking for these right now
and do lighting on them so what I can do
is grab out of the render group right
because the render group itself
Janee because the render group itself at
least I believe maybe that's not in here
so that's going to actually be here the
rendered group has a current quads one
Oh in fact I suppose we could just do it
that way maybe I want to do this before
then maybe I want to do it on current
quads so maybe I want to say this
so what I want to do here is say let's
do that right before we push in that
case so let's put it here that way the
quads will be correct as written so what
I'm going to do here is I'm going to go
into those textured quads and let's see
here so I don't know I don't know what
the easiest way to get the pointers to
things is going to be I think yeah so
basically we just have quad count in
vertex or a offset so basically what I'm
going to have to do here is it's going
to have to grab out the pointers to
where the information is for the
textured quad but that's not a big deal
right we've done this before but you can
see here on push glob this is how we
were writing to it in the first place
you can see how we get the vertex array
there and you can see how we get the
quad bitmap so I can just kind of come
down here and do that so what I could do
is this I can say here's the quad
bitmaps for vertex array offset and that
should give me pointers into the render
buffers at for the vertices and the
bitmaps in question
[Applause]
so this is really all we need I think so
once I have that I can loop through all
of the quads that there are or I can say
quad index you know goes up to the quad
count and inside this loop I can access
the vertices and the bitmaps what I want
to do is basically nuke out the bitmaps
so what I can do here is say like
bitmaps quad index equals that white
bitmap so now there will be no sprites
there will just be flat
pure white textures right and if I want
to here I can say I can pull that
commands app we're going to need it
they get so grouped commands is that
right yes and let's take a look here
so lighting test which I can't put a
loaded bitmap it's a double star there
we go
and so now all I need to do is call this
before ending the death peel which is
what I was doing that and it should go
through and be able to access all this
information so just to start testing it
like I said this will nuke everything
and just produce white right well not
white whatever the color is of the thing
and you can see that's exactly what it
did right so here's all of our here's
all of our sprites all of our you know
quote-unquote reflectors and and this is
exactly what I wanted right so that's
good and similarly if I want to I can
edit the vertices so I can do something
like
Virts plus equals four I could do this
even so now I know that on every quad
that sort of lined up if you will now if
I want to edit the quad or access the
quad which is exactly what I want to do
I can pull out each individual vertex of
the quad the same way that I did it when
I was pushing them on so I can know
where each of these quads is by again
just doing this sort of a process so if
I want to I can take the textured vertex
pointer here and say all right let's say
that I've got each of these separately
so let's say I do something like this so
I can access each one of the vertices of
this constituent quad through a
convenient named v-0 v1 v2 v3 and
similarly if I go look you know I've got
this struct about the the vertex there
textured vertex and you can see we've
got a position in normal a UV and a
color now we don't really care about the
UV but we do care about the other three
values what I can do here is demonstrate
as well that these are editable by
changing everything to white so now we
should get a completely whitewashed
screen
every day so there's our our completely
edited version all right so that gives
us our sort of information that we
wanted for our lighting test here we now
know an easy way to sort of get into the
CPU all of the information about all of
the reflectors in the scene and where
they are what their color is what their
normal is etc and furthermore we can now
output a lighting solution that we can
look at and debug quickly by just
changing the vertex colors of these
sprite geometry to reflect whatever the
lighting system says right so let's go
ahead and do that let's start down that
path
I need some tissues here allergy ish all
right so the question is how do we want
to create some space for this here not
probably super difficult because we can
just create a dummy buffer that's
however big we needed to be and let that
do its thing so for example we know how
many quads are going to be here because
you know again this is not really
something that we're going to be using
long term so I'm just going to create a
dummy buffer that we can use to do
whatever we want to do and so if I go
take a look in that lighting test
function let me just go ahead and set a
breakpoint there rather than trying to
get to it in the bugger if we actually
just look to see what is going to be
jump through here I
2220 182 commitment so you know if we
created a buffer of 4096 things that's
more things than were ever
going to have during our testing here so
if I want to I can just create a little
thing called you know reflector maybe
I'll call it a lighting element I don't
know who knows but this lighting
elements is going to be something we can
play with and like I said for right now
let's stick with the thing we were doing
before which is let's just say it's got
a position it's got a direction it's got
a color and it has a radius so how you
know big the thing was that and so in
this case we've got sort of these two
notions of color like we typically do
which is always a little bit confusing
right there's there's two kinds of color
there's immediate color like I am
shining color out and there's reflected
color and they're different things so
I'll put those two in here again and
I'll do the front and back like we had
so this is now just what we were
building inside the GPU I'm just
building it outside the GPU now and
again this is because I want a way of
looking at this that doesn't involve so
much laborious work just to try things
because I feel like we're never going to
converge on a solution if we have to try
them in an environment that that's so
slow as what we were working with we did
a bunch of work to get it to the point
where we can do you know a bunch of
stuff with it but just trying to figure
out what the right things to store is
and the right ways to process them just
seemed way too difficult without be able
to debug or draw or do anything really
interesting and so I think this is just
a lot more effective as a way of getting
to a solution and then we just move it
to the GPU and we're done
and you know that part's not so
difficult that point because we're only
trying to do one thing all right
so if you imagine here that we sort of
just have a set of these reflectors that
are going to be generated based on
on the sprites and the quads that we see
I really should not be scratching my eye
like this just you know don't do this at
home folks that's a bad idea you may
have allergies like I do but don't
scratch your eye it only damages the eye
actually I don't know we know that I
think it's currently hypothesized that
it damages the eye anyway moving on I so
what I can do here is have basically
tulips woman extracts into the lighting
elements and one that pushes back into
the lighting elements so what I'll do is
I'll just create a global array first
that's like you know the roots sort of
set of elements and what I'll do is
using make two passes through this is
going to stay sort of as a thing that
[Applause]
copy lighting out and copy lighting in
so first we'll go through and do an
extraction we don't need the bitmaps to
do the extraction we just need the
vertices so we'll ignore the bitmaps for
now and the way that we'll do the
extraction here is well basically we'll
take sort of a span so we'll assume V 0
V 1 V 2 we'll assume that V 0 to V 2 is
the span across the sprite again this is
just approximate for now we can work on
better ones later we but we just need
the basics for now which is to say for
any quadrilateral you know I could
approximate what it's doing by saying
all right if I was to take this then if
I want something that as big as the you
know I can either inscribe something
here or I can you know sort of make it
bigger as big as the whole thing I'm in
a error on the side
making it bigger for now so what I was
thinking is this basically taking V 0 to
V 2 right if we assume that it looks
roughly like this just taking this fan
and saying the midpoint will be the
center and the distance out to one of
the sides or rather the whole thing will
be the diameter of this set of one of
the sides will be the radius right so
when I do this I've got the vertices
coming in here I only need two of them
and what I can do is say V 0 P V 2 P if
I subtract these two from each other 3 V
4 3 3 actually she's talking to you
before I think they're four-dimensional
because they've got that Z bias built in
that would give me the span now I think
about it that Z bias is actually
something we want to take into account
as well we probably want things to be
reflected as if they are standing up the
way that that we faked them to be yes so
maybe we want to do it this way so maybe
we want to create V 0 p as V 0 X Y Z and
then we want V 0 P Z 2 plus equal V 0 W
[Applause]
something like this that's true all true
my friends there we go I cannot convert
again so let's see okay so this right
here would give us the stand so now if I
want to create a lighting element let's
just go ahead and pretend that I have
one here so here's my element and that's
just going to line up with the quads
exactly so as I spin through all these
elements I'm going to add the quad index
here and get the elements out so then
what I'll say is my elements position is
going to be the fan vector here what I
want to do is take my v0p
and add half of span right because that
walks me up to that midpoint which is
the location that I wanted so I can take
that element P and I can go up half the
span and get the location center it
there once I've got that element P what
I can do is I can create the normal from
it by just looking at any one of these
normals so I believe all I have to do
there just grab one of them because
these are all flat so just grabbing one
and have to average them or anything I
can just assume that they all have the
same normal because that's basically how
we've been doing it so far that changed
in the future I need to use something a
little more complicated the emission
part I don't really have any way of
setting any of the emissions at the
moment so we'll go ahead and eliminate
those and then what I'm going to do here
is just look at the reflect
color that reflected color is just going
to be the color of one of the vertices
doesn't matter which one at the moment
cuz again I we don't really vary the
color across the vertices just yet
so we don't worry too much about that
but what I need to do is up convert it
here so I was hoping we had one of these
like an RGB unpack but I don't know if
we do let's the RGB unpack four by eight
so that is going to pull out those are
GPS exactly we want so I'll I'll pull
that out there and that'll give ya the
red the green the blue and the Alpha
correctly so that's what we wanted and
then the radius in this case is going to
be half the span length right so if we
take the length of that span that will
give us the radius well give us the
diameter and then we divide by two and
that will give us the radius and again
that's just a simple construction based
on this we take this fan vector v2 minus
V zero we walk halfway in the middle to
get here and then the radius of course
is just going to be this this is the
diameter so we take the length of that
bat span vector divide it by two and we
get what we wanted all right so just get
ready create a dummy emission there I
don't know why we set this as a v4 it's
not and honestly it's not really a rest
that the recipe is not relevant either
because we're not going to remember
alpha at the moment maybe in the future
we'll take advantage of alpha that would
be like translucency right so yeah maybe
we'll put that in here maybe we'll say
transparency in case we do want it I I'm
going to put this up here and then I'm
going to grab that out from it that way
if we do change their mind about how
that's averaged or anything else we can
change in a central location all right
so let's see here C is not a member of
textured vertex what is it called it's
just called color so that's us getting
our lighting in so now if I run it we
shouldn't see any difference
it's just copying it into that array not
actually modifying at all then we do
copy lighting out you can see here that
we've got our our test stuff running
what I want to do here is have some way
of viewing what we actually created here
because again we could have a bug in
this copy lighting in that would create
reflectors that don't accurately reflect
the world so what I'd rather do rather
than leave everything unadulterated I
would rather go ahead and reconstruct
now the four vertices from our original
lighting data that we created so that
way we can be sure of what we're
actually getting right so let me do here
is recreate these four vertices from the
lighting data so let's take a look here
here is the lighting element which we've
pulled out for this particular quad I'm
going to copy the lighting element data
back into the quad okay so the first
thing we can do is we can say that you
know it's got this the it's got that
reflected color value what's interested
about this what's this thing about this
is like we need some place at this point
to put the lighting so I guess you know
we've got the front emit see the front
emit see is what the light
actually is so I guess for now what we
would say is maybe we'll do like you
know no Casey compute lighting so maybe
in here we actually go through all of
our lighting elements and just copy the
front in the the ref see reflected color
into the front emit see right so this is
as if we were pretending we were doing
some kind of lighting that we're not
really doing right all right so now what
we do our copy lighting out we know that
all of the colors are going to be
whatever the emit color is so those are
all going to be set this way and so
we've got a front emit here that's just
going to be our pack RGB we do have a
pack don't we go to unpack RGB pack
that's what we want so here we'll pack
the front emit from the lighting element
[Applause]
and pack it back in
what is it was a front submit see yeah
and so what we need to reconstruct here
is stuff like the normal in the position
and the UVs we didn't touch so we don't
need to reconstruct those and because
those aren't relevant to lighting so
really what we need to do is use the
element P and the element end here now
the vertices can all take on the element
the normal in this case although one
thing I point out is the normal if we're
computing the lighting we won't be able
to see whether the normal is right or
wrong in any particular way we would
have to draw it so it's really sort of
irrelevant to copy in here so I think
I'll probably skip it although well you
I won't skip it because we can look at
like a normal map in the renderer right
to see if it's roughly correct so maybe
I'll leave it for now
sorry so if you have the the vertex
normals here again they're just copying
out whatever the lighting element had in
it like so and so we've got the colors
here we've got the normal here and all
we really need to do that's any work at
all really is we've got to come up with
the positions so we need to come up with
our three different positions obviously
each of them I'm sorry at 40 positions
each of them is going to be based off
element T which is sort of the center of
this lighting element and we knew we
have a radius so what we can do here is
essentially take our our sprite and the
normal to that and we can go ahead and
blow out you know make it sort of a
diamond shape or something roughly that
size whatever the size that normal is
right so we need two things we need an X
and the y axis in this case and then
when we do V 0 V 1 V 2 V 3 we can sort
of create those by you know doing
something smart here so for example we
can do a plus X or rather let's start
with a minus X now sorts life will start
with a plus X and again what I'm trying
to do here is just draw something out so
let's suppose that we've got the element
P is here right we know that we have a
radius and we know that we have a normal
so what I know about this if I want to
recreate something that sort of shows an
approximate space-filling here with a
quad you know is I'm just going to be
drawing something that looks like this
right inside the the circle what I can
do is say
right I know the radius part which is
how far it is out here so all I really
need to know is what are the x and y
axes of this circle because if I knew
what those were I could just draw a plus
x axis plus y axis minus x axis minus y
axis and get the corners of my sprite
now the reason I can't do that is
because the normal just tells me the
other axis that tells me like the z axis
effectively right if I were to look at
this on a plane sitting in a plane where
I'm saying here's my Y axis here's my x
axis and I'm trying to draw something in
that plane the normal is this right the
normal is the z axis it's the axis we
don't want to draw along so how do I
produce these other two axes well in
this case I can use again the
cross-product to produce some of these
for me since I know that all of the
vectors x and y that I might want and
remember I don't care which I have I
don't just as a circle I don't care what
axes you give me give me any active
doesn't matter as long as they're both
perpendicular to n well we notice the
cross-product like we talked about
before it gives us vectors perpendicular
to other vectors so if we want to if we
just had some other vector we could
cross it with N and we would know that
the result would be perpendicular to n
right we know that that's true so I just
need some other vector if I had any
other vector at all it doesn't matter
what it is I would get one that would be
in this plane and it turns out I could
do this relatively easily right why is
my area so it turns out I can do this
rather easily because actually any since
any vector will do I can just find a
vector that is not pointing too close to
the direction of N cross it and get a
new vector right we'll just call that a
and I know that whatever that vector is
that vector is going to be perpendicular
to n right
that's that's just the definition of the
cross product so once I have a vector
that's perpendicular to to end in that
way I can then say let's just call that
vector the x-axis right so I can say any
vector cross n I could call that the
x-axis I just have to normalize it right
then once I have the x-axis well I know
that if I take the x-axis
cross the z-axis I'll get the negative
y-axis right so negative x cross n is
going to equal to the y-axis right so in
theory if I just do enough cross
products here I will get the thing I
eventually wanted right I could just
keep crossing these vectors until I
generate an active system that's one I
can use right it's pretty
straightforward concept it's just a
little tricky to wrap your head around
when you think about why you can sort of
magically take one vector and turn it
into a full coordinate system just by
repeatedly crossing it over and over and
over again right
but hey that's just how that works
so yes so we should be able to do
something like take a fictitious vector
whatever it is and like I said so we
just need a way of figuring out what
that is so if we have our normal what we
want to avoid like we could just pick
any arbitrary vector we could just say
it's always the z-axis right and then
when we cross it you know I don't know
where the you know maybe the z-axis is
going this direction relative the normal
or something we'd cross it we'd get a
vector out in the plane we'd call that X
we then cross it to get Y and then we'd
be done or whatever right however the
problem with this idea is that what if
the vector that we're trying to start
with the N vector is very close to this
to begin with right if that's the case
then the cross product will degenerate
because since the cross product is
proportional to the sign between the
angles if the angle comes down to zero
the sine goes to zero which means that
we degenerate and lose the ability to
take the cross product at all we get a
zero vector back so what we actually
need to do is take a look at in and see
perhaps whether or not it has a high Z
value right for example what we could do
is say well let's say if the Z value is
higher than point eight in here then
we'll use the y-axis otherwise we'll use
the z axis or maybe we'll just scan for
whichever the lowest one is and we'll
use that one right so what we can do
with there with that is just say look
all right let's take a look at which one
of these would be the best so let's say
that we have if n dot X is less than n
dot Y then if m dot B is less than n dot
X
[Applause]
and in this case we have why so you see
all I'm doing here is just creating a
thing that figures out which one of
these is minimum and so what I'll do is
I'll say min elements and what we'll do
is say alright if n X is less than n Y
then we know that n Y cannot be the
maximum authorized the minimum element
so then we just have to go well is it n
Z if it is then the minimum element is
the second element is the otherwise it's
X right and the same thing would hold
true here either but the only difference
is the minimum element yes the minimum
element would become one instead because
it's Y is the minimum now not X since
we've determined that Y is actually less
right so if we do this we can then say
all right let's take our our base vector
here which is all zeros will then set
the minimum element of whichever one the
normal has a de minimum we'll set that
to one so we're basically picking the
like Cardinal basis that happens to most
be be as far away in terms of magnitude
and I'm sorry in terms of direction from
the normal and then we just start
crossing so first we to get our x-axis
right in this case we want to cross it
doesn't matter which direction we cross
them really because again we don't have
any other definition of this coordinate
system other than it's got to not be and
it's going to not have any component in
N so what I can do is alright let's
cross it first we'll cross the base with
the normal that'll give us our x-axis
then we'll cross the x axis with the
normal again and like I said that's
actually give us some negative why it
doesn't really matter again because for
our purposes we don't care but we just
want to be wound properly so we want to
negate that so that it's going to be the
positive lot and again that's just so
we'll produce a proper winding to them
so once we have these two we basically
want to normalize and we want to
multiply by the radius right whatever
that radius is going to be or we could
do that here right but we might as well
do it bake them into the x and y axis so
we take the element radius and we put
those in here then we've again just got
a pretty straightforward process to
create the diamond and off we go
got to grab that end from somewhere and
oh and these are VIII's so actually we
just want to do yeah so we probably
don't want to change the Z bias in this
case which makes it a little bit tricky
because we factored the Z bias in
already
so the Z bias value is going to be kind
of erroneous which is unfortunate but
that's just the way it is I guess in
this case
[Applause]
so I think what I would like to do here
is just zero out the Z bias so we're
just looking at the actual reflectors
themselves
[Applause]
alright not great not a very auspicious
start for being honest about it but that
basically what we're looking at here
right so let's take a look here let's
first just get rid of the positional
part of things all right so we've got
first a problem with color which is sort
of separate from the positional
debugging the positional creation so in
order to compute the lighting here where
we create the front emit see and take
the ref see for some reason we're not
properly passing through the color which
is odd right because what should be
happening here is right we get the
elements from the clawed index here and
each time we should be passing you know
taking whatever that color when we
unpack the color of the first vertex
which should always be proper something
you know fairly bright we're taking the
RGB of that and we're putting that into
the the reference color we're then
copying the reference color into the
front emit color for each individual
element right we loop over them all and
this is just pretending we actually did
some lighting we didn't we're just
taking the reflected color and
pretending that that's what you actually
see coming off of the surface however
that right that should basically
reconstruct whatever the reflected color
was or this thing that we unpacked from
from vertex zero so then when we go to
copy it back in here where we do our
front emit 32 we set the colors for each
of those two
that when we go to packet we're taking
the front emit color which again we
should have taken and copied vertex
zeros information into their right here
is where that should have happened so
coming back around we should end up with
this being pretty much correct I'm not
sure what's going on there so let's go
ahead and not do that because there are
the actual colors so we're doing
something wrong in terms of the copying
that out so let's first take the element
front emit see and verify that the fact
that we're not setting the front emit
see properly so suppose I set that to
white everything should be white what
does the same terms going to go into
function and ooh whoops okay that's the
mistake I forgot about the fact that
these are actually functions that we use
yeah that's not great I admit that
that's not not my best idea if we're
honest about that not my best idea let
me go ahead and plate replace v-0 with
virzi row here
and then I'll replace V 2 with invert 2
if only the compiler knew what I meant
and not what I said
wouldn't that mean wonders what like the
artificially attentive intelligent
compiler I can't do that days all right
[Applause]
so I'm just verifying here that it's ok
so that's what I want to see so it's not
that it's actually this pack that's
problematic here or the transparency
value right so something about what
we're doing here is bogus or or in here
or whatever else right so that's good
because I was trying I was like I don't
see how this is possibly messing up so
that's actually quite nice that it's not
messing up potentially it's actually
something different happening here so
let me just go ahead and take a look at
what's happening there in the debugger
to see what got messed up oh you know
what I know what it is RGB pack is
assumes they're qg5
yeah
yep yep so you can see here these are
just for packing color values that are
non-normalized we don't have a pack
unpack that the fix is that I don't
think yeah so we don't really have one
of those so basically what happens here
is when we unpack these colors right
here this unpack is not going to divide
the colors by 255 so we need to
basically do you know this so that we
will get back proper zero to one colors
and then when we go to pack them again
we need to do the opposite of that
because they're not going to be based
off the two to five properly furthermore
here the transparency is not going to be
correct either so we could say like to
do casey remove the premultiplied alpha
dice here if we want to start handling
transparency in the reflections as well
so yeah so right here what's going to
happen is during the front emit this RGB
pack again this is going to pack down
things that expect to be in the two to
five range so it would need to multiply
that out again in order to get the 0 to
255 values now since they're clamped
no they're rounded so that's fine that's
probably fine for our purposes at least
at the moment
all right uh getting a little closer but
still not there yet so when we let me go
ahead and again take the front omit C
out of the equation there and yeah
perfect
so looks like this is correct now but it
looks like this one isn't so when we
unpack the color should be dry 35 I so I
assume that that's correct
please double check that yeah so these
would these would come out 0 to 255 for
sure so I feel like that's correct
let me again take a quick look at that
code I want to be what I'm getting there
all right so what I'm gonna do is I'm
gonna look at vero here and I'm gonna
look at the color see the color there
and then I'm going to look at what the
elements reflected color is computed to
be um and that looks roughly correct
right and actually won't stop it anymore
you see a lot of those are quite
reasonable they're exactly what we
respect to see so all that looks pretty
reasonable to me let's go through here
and see what starts happening when we
set these front emission colors I'm
going to go ahead and look at the
elements array ah typo there we go and
now I think we should be good to go all
right
all right so now we need to actually get
the rest of this working with our
positional information so the next step
is to fix of that right so you can see
we don't have our position stuff coming
in correctly here so let's step through
this and see what we've got and try to
make make this part reasonable so I'm
going to go ahead and step in here just
to see what sort of values we are ending
up with just to get a hint of what work
what we're looking at
so it looks like that's another type
though I'm not very awake this morning
am i there's a lot of typos in here try
that one more time that's not looking
great so these should not be zeroed out
so what's going on with that my base
vector and my normal this looks like I
did this totally wrong here so let's
figure out what's going on here so we've
got our normal vector our normal vector
is 0 negative 1 ah
that's that's my problem I forgot these
need to be absolute valued right because
they could still be negative which is
which is not at all what we want so I
actually need the magnitude of each of
these so yeah so what I want to do there
is I want to have a way of saying
[Applause]
probably something like this and that
way I will know definitively which one
is the minimum magnitude not minimum
value because those aren't the same
right
okay if so then this can still use the
the vertex end in that case and I think
we're all good and now we'll see how
we're doing on values all right so those
are looking nice that looks like roughly
what I would expect let's see how we're
doing here all right so close but no
cigar so I guess I don't remember which
way we decided to make our quads go I
think it's probably a case that we have
them let's take a look at push quad here
yes so with three zero to one so
basically the way that we've got it here
is assuming that it's a laund quad but
that this is a tri stripped basically
right it's how we're outputting them so
in order to output those correctly what
we need to do is we need to do it in
that order right we need to do three
zero you know or yeah three zero to 1
instead of 0 1 2 3 so if we want to do
it that way that's not such a big deal
right like here's three here's 0 2
there's one
so that's the actual order then I guess
that it would expect to be shown in and
there's our little diamond reflectors
and and they're looking pretty accurate
to me I guess it's a little hard to say
in some of these but let's go ahead and
send the camera around and see what we
think
so here's the world ostensibly I don't
know what those giant pink ones are I
think those might be the bounding boxes
which we'll probably have to make sure
we remove from this
so it looks like we're not quite correct
here though because like for example if
you take a look at these cubes now
actually know what that does look
correct because the cubes are not square
so that part's alright so that does look
roughly correct to me these giant pink
reflectors are a problem and we kind of
need to make sure that those aren't in
there when we're doing the lighting
testing right the problem with those is
you know where those are coming from let
me just copy
let me just a nerf out the the copy out
so we can see what that is so if you
take a look here I let me zoom out you
can see that there's that pink sort of
band that just shows like the simulation
region bounds it's a debug it's a piece
of debug information and the same is
true of the yellow square there so in
both cases those are going to be long
thin rectangles that makes it appear
like they have an extremely large you
know radius but the radius isn't
actually that large right it's like we
wouldn't really want to represent it by
a giant reflector like that so it's
unclear exactly how we would handle that
case we don't really have to because
it's debug but you know you can see that
that's a little bit of a of an issue one
thing that we could do here is we could
set up a little bit of a guard for that
we could say all right let's grab
vertex one out as well and compute it we
could do say all right let's take a look
at those two so there's a check span
here where we take both of these so we
get that span out let's put the color
stuff in a different location so when
we're computing the position and the
radius here we could do is say alright
let's look at this check whatever that
check is and say that whatever the side
length is as opposed to the diagonal
maybe we just say that you know you
can't be more than twice the side length
or something like this so we would know
you know going from zero to one is one
side of the quadrilateral going from
zero to three would be the other one
maybe we take those two and average them
or something like that in fact that
seems like four take whichever the
smaller of the two is as the reflector
or something like that that seems like a
better plan maybe to avoid the large the
eccentricity I could do that let's let's
maybe let's try that so what this would
be here is I've got you know two
different versions of the span and what
I can do there should say look whatever
the to find the center I'll just go
halfway on each of them is that is good
I don't know if that is good is having
the other one so maybe actually still do
all of them can't hurt us goes again
we're not super trying to be efficient
here we're just trying to play with the
problems that make sense so yeah I can
do spam to zero for it but then maybe
when we actually compute the radius what
we'll say is we'll take whichever one is
the minimum of the two sides so we'll
look at 33 zero and one zero as the two
sides of the quadrilateral emanating
from the base vertex and we'll take
whichever one is the lesser of the two
gotta put in the copy
oops so here we go now we're not using
that span to zero for anything other
than the policemen of the centre and you
can kind of see what that amounts to so
you know there's the trees and the
ground and and and and all that right
now for some reason we're still getting
large and then why we'd be getting such
large comparisons there because at least
in theory I feel like
half of the side lengths if we're taking
the smallest side length
there should be no way for the thing to
be there should be no way for it to be
that long you know I'm saying to you
there shouldn't be it you shouldn't be
able to produce some producing something
so long as that at least not if this
radius is to be believed this this
should never be something quite so huge
is that I mean that thing looks like you
know 20 meters or something like this in
the world which is way more than it
should be so we if we're looking for the
minimum of those two of the the three to
zero and the zero to one I don't see how
oh this is this is me being stupid again
it's because the winding order of these
vertices is not that order
remember they yeah they go 0 1 2 3 so
they're in yeah they're in exactly the
wrong order so they would have to go 0 1
3 2 is actually how they would be wound
if we actually wanted to put them in
correct winding order I don't know how
much of a difference that would make but
yeah there we go so that fixes it and so
then you just get these little tiny
reflectors into the debug thing which is
what I would actually want all right
yeah that whole winding thing is
annoying and that's just because of the
way we sort of hacked the the output of
those but
alright so there's some interesting
things about this that you can sort of
see already which is that you know if
you imagine these things were actually
discs which they're not at the moment
but you can kind of see how that's not
the greatest approximation for what's
happening in terms of bouncing the light
legging around because whenever you have
looked long and skinny things you sort
of end up with that problem of not
really having sufficient coverage right
but you'd want a bigger lighting element
there now you know maybe we can
eventually expand our notion of how
these things work to be more about quads
and less about about this but at the
moment since we were kind of taking a
look at basing what we were doing a
little bit off of the old disc lighting
transfer stuff for now it makes some
sense for us to do it as disks just to
see if we can get that working a little
bit better but again yeah I don't know
how how plausible that's really going to
be and we could always make them a
little bit larger in terms of reflectors
how big they should be again I don't
know stretch it all right I don't know
how much time we got here we end in what
25 minutes I guess
like this yeah so from here now what I'd
like to do is I would like to figure out
one of these ones we can use as an
emitter and the test emitter so let's
randomly try to pick the hero I don't
know that we are going to be able to do
that
[Music]
I think how we do that we specifying a
lighting as sort of a constant position
we don't really have a way of doing that
here what I guess what I could do is add
a synthetic lighting element onto the
end of the lighting element array so one
way of doing that would be to say
alright suppose there's an element count
and the element count is actually going
to be the the quad count but it's going
to be the quad count plus one and then
what we'll do from there is we'll say
that they'll be a synthetic element that
will use it'll have that lighting
information in it so we've got the the
current quads right we've got the sort
of the sort of last setup information
and the render setup has the debug light
in it this debug light key right here so
what we could do is use that debug light
P to create a synthetic one of these
that's just our light source and we can
move the light source around so what we
can do there is say yeah like all of
these we're not going to do this
emission thing anymore when I run this
right you can see that we we don't have
any of these lit at all and so then what
we could do is we could say that there's
less pathetic light source in here I
guess maybe I don't even have to do it
that way I could just use the people at
white P temporarily as some kind of an
approximation oh you know what I'll do
here's what I'll do I'll take the
distance to it so I'll say all right
your front emit is zero however will
basically say that if the distance
between you
[Applause]
like what's your position right so the
this elements position - the debug light
P if the length of that is less than you
know one meter then you're going to be
lit and so all we have to do there is
use that render setup to get some kind
of a debug light P in there so I believe
all we have to do is is just a last set
up P but like P I think that's all there
is to it so now in theory we should be
able to tweak that somehow - to figure
out how to light some things up while
keeping other things unlit there we go
so now we sort of are proceeding those
emitters right those those particular
lighting elements that we have are now
lit right they are artificially pushing
light out into the world so let's
suppose we've got these these things
here and now we're just going to be
stupid we're just going to be just dumb
and stupid so if we wanted to do a basic
lighting calculation to prove that this
was working at all again we can go ahead
and do sort of our our basic lighting
let's turn this into an N squared loop
because why not
[Applause]
so I'm going to have two of these here
and then I'm going to and N squared
propagation of the light which is going
to be a disaster right but that's okay I
don't mind it being a disaster at all
again I'm just playing around with this
and we can also limit the number of
Stefan or like reduce the amount of
stuff that's in the scene to take it
down from 2008 it into maybe the hundred
range in fact I could do that right now
maybe I will and so what we're going to
do here to say like alright I've got a
source and destination I'm just going to
compute the lighting transfer between
them so I'm going to say something like
okay so you know the the thing we were
doing before where we were trying to do
the light transport here here we go so
let's see so you know we've got a thing
that's the direction to the light well
we know how to get to the light source
so that would just be the source of
position minus the destination position
that's going to go to the light source
we've got the reflection normal in this
case is just going to be our our normal
right so the destiny gives the
destination is normal the diffuse
coefficient of specular coefficient we
don't know yet so let's just assume that
these services are fully diffused at the
moment and the specular power is just
going to be some other things
here I will take the diffuse inner good
we have pal
[Applause]
we don't have pal yet that's a little
bit of a problem but all right so the
diffuse center product is just going to
be exactly what this says it's going to
be right so all of this stuff is pretty
much exactly what you expect the light
color in this case is just a desk front
of it yeah and I think that's basically
it and so whatever the result is here
that we're going to get in this case we
have the reflected color times the total
incoming light is going to be the result
so we'll just take whatever the
destinations front of it is and we'll
add the results so this is just a
cumulating light into it right
just in next source index now this is
not a good loop because it's going to
over Kitts going to propagate white you
know yeah we'll talk about that in
second there's there's issues there so
in this case we just got a hat AMARG
product and same is true here but it
seems unhappy why are you unhappy with
that we've got diffuse color oh because
actually you wanted to do that
and so the vector to the camera that's
not something we have actually
determined so we need in our debug setup
I guess we do have a camera position so
we should be able to do something like a
camera P equals group left set up camera
P we have that yes so when it needs to
camera we should be able to say where
the camera is real to this to camera is
just going to be camera three - desk P
right so again this is just a complete
this is completely crappy and it'll be
extremely slow or it won't stop at all
some reason I don't know what was going
on there
[Music]
that should be okay they're right why
are you going so slowly
did I miss a
well that's incredibly slow that's much
slower than I would have expected
actually
where's my exercise let's see so you
have 2182 2182 to be fair that is four
million elements it has to do and
there's a lot of instructions here so I
guess it's not that surprising so what
I'd like to do is I'd like to cut that
down to a very small number just so we
can play with it a little bit better and
so in order to do that what I'm going to
do in world mode is going to take the
particles out and then I'm going to when
we create our world here I'm going to
also say when we do screening index I'm
going to only have one and I'm going to
see what we can get that number down to
so it's still quite high
[Applause]
I would like to know why we're still
getting so many things so I would let's
just I'm just going to go ahead you see
what I can see here I so here's all of
the stuff we're sending down now the
room is much too large I guess is one of
the things I don't know if maybe I can
reduce the size of this room somewhat
when we do as standard room room radius
X and room radius Y I guess I could
force the room radius X to be smaller
but that still seems like yeah I guess
we could make it even smaller still if I
wanted to I could say something like
this and there's like a pretty tiny one
now I don't know like I said how many of
these things we're drawing now it still
seems like an awful lot of quads 500 of
them like where are they all is that
really right I mean one two three four
five six seven eight nine ten eleven
well I guess I could say there's you
know there's at least six for each of
those yes I suppose there's just a lot
if you've got six for every cube so M
square is still going to be pretty rough
on this guy I admit that but we'll see
what we can do
so there it's like you know barely
running but it is running and we could
if we wanted to also potentially look at
if the optimizer can make that loop run
faster because since all the times when
we've spent in that loop now yeah there
it goes
I don't know why I'm getting that
flickering there are there multiple
quads stacked on top of each other but
anyway so if we take a look at this here
this is probably cheating because it
probably figured out that this loop can
go away and that's probably why it's
fast so let's take that away and make it
actually do the work and see what it's
like if it's optimized well that's not
too bad actually
all right all right so let's try to get
this working here too something that
does some kind of light transport so
what was it doing it does source P yeah
the light color is from whatever is that
now this is wrong we go show that one
more time all right well that is
interesting to say the least in this
case we're going to have to clamp when
we push this information down otherwise
we're going to get all kinds of weird
stuff like that so we do need that
clamping to come back into play here so
when we do this summation what we would
need is back when we do our copy out and
we do our pack we need to take our front
emit here and we need to to clamp each
of the components from zero to one
because after we've done the lighting
sort of transmission we got to clamp it
down so we're going to do something like
that we need to say okay so clamp zero
to one
whatever the elements front emit see is
its
and that'll produce the front submit
that we can then pass through here that
should be properly clamped so we won't
get those weird like color wrapping
artifacts where you go over one and wrap
back around to zero which is what was
creating that flickering right so ya
still have some weirdness here there I
don't know why we're getting some of the
things I'm seeing there so like I said
this looks a little bit weird and the
reason that this loops a little bit
weird is because when it computes the
lighting it's going through all of the
sources which include sources from
Baha'i like ones that have already had
the light transferred so we might want
to say something like well this yeah not
sure exactly how we would say that we
could use a different accumulator so for
example we could do something like we
could accumulate into the back admit C
and then use the back in it C or
something like this
or for now just to make things easier on
ourselves I guess the other thing I
could do is just use a separate light
accumulator so basically in here we
would say here's the lighting element
there's an accumulated you know light
field here and what we do is we just
summon that so when we initialize these
originally assumed that no lighting has
been accumulated we accumulate the light
like this so that we can distinguish it
um to me why is the why is my little
head thing dawn my little I don't know
why if this is where my head is here I
don't know where the little head thing
went I think Windows Windows just always
seems to be very bad at keeping on top
Windows actually on top unfortunately
but anyway point being Zen and here I'll
just use the EQ MC and that way it's not
doing the problem I was worried about is
that as we were propagating the light
around let later people as they loop
over the source would pick up that
lighting yeah and there you can see that
that sort of helped out that problem a
little bit but it still seems wrong
still seem somewhat incorrect I'm not
sure what we're look at seeing there so
here's the rest of the computations
let's just take a quick look
yeah so a couple things about this so
one this still has the angular element
to it which we sort of were saying was
probably problematic however still
should be okay
so if we take a look at what's going on
here we say all right we've got the
destination one that we're going to be
signing into and we've got the source
one that we're going to be coming from
we grab the light color from the source
we grab the direction to the light by
subtracting these two do we need to
normalize that that's the problem yeah
this is assuming if this is normalized
where's the distance to the light so it
looks like we kind of got rid of a lot
of important stuff in here all right so
let's fix that so we've got two light to
light distance
[Applause]
so let's restore the way this
computation was working before so let's
take a look at the light distance we'll
look to see if it's greater than zero
and then assuming it is will normalize
and continue right I guess - camera is
the same way here so once we have the
camera information and the lighting
information normalized then we're in
better shape however you notice we don't
seem to have letting fall-off in here
anywhere for I guess because we were
just hacking around with it before so we
need that to be in here as well and it's
currently not it was just angular
fall-off was the only thing that we were
computing which is totally wrong and at
least now that's normalized which is I
guess good but again still a little bit
funky so let's see what we got here so
we have the two light here the light
distance to light is then normalized by
multiplying by one over the distance
which is good we've got the reflected
normal which is this one we compute the
inner product of the light and they're
reflected normal that seems good as well
no issues there
yeah that all seems good it just needs a
distance baseball so then we've got the
reflection vector that all seems good
the inner product of specular that seems
good as well yeah so that all seems good
and the specular isn't contributing it
all right now should be zero so that
should be fine
so that all looks good so yeah I'm not
sure why I still don't understand what
I'm looking at there don't that doesn't
look right to me
like if you look at what's happening
here you can kind of see that well I
guess you know that's probably just the
angular fall-off I guess I could believe
that since we have no distance fall-off
at the moment I guess I could maybe sort
of believe that but not really but
anyway so if that's the if that's the
the angular fall-off term even if I
convince myself that the bats correct
which I'm not really sure it is let's go
ahead and put the distance term in there
as well which is just going to be like
so that's just going to be again inverse
square law so that would be one over the
light distance squared and in here where
we're actually sort of summing up all
the rest of these things we just put in
the distance fall-off there
so now at least we're getting that
distance fall-off but I just I feel like
maybe there's a little bit too much of
an angular like the amount of angular
flickering we're getting there is seems
a little odd to me it just doesn't make
a whole lot of sense
I mean it does seem basically correct
angular wise meaning you know the stuff
that's down here is getting no light and
the stuff that's up here is getting
light and that makes a little bit of
sense I guess on the other hand part of
it doesn't really make a whole lot of
sense because well I guess we're not
using the light the other lights facing
direction so I guess that part is okay
you know I could convince myself that
that was roughly right all right so you
can kind of see that this is sort of
working a little bit right so yeah so
that's like all right so there's a
little bit of light transfer tapping
there I think the agiza crazy crowd
along tomorrow I'd like to go through
them and actually start to try to type
it tighten this down a little bit but
the other thing we can do here is we
could say well we could also do this in
as a multi pass operation now and see
what happens if we just let the light
bounce a little bit by doing a loop
again since we're already very slow and
this is a problem this is not great but
you know we're again we're just playing
around so let's suppose I allow this to
do three loops and what I did here was I
just said like all right just propagate
the light out and each time you
propagate the light out assume that you
then take the emission and you take
however much light you see late and now
you're going to shine that light back
out right
so again just a lot of really weird
flipping there so I think we've got some
bugs that we could probably fix without
too much trouble
but again we're getting there and this
is a much saner way for us to do
experimentation here because at least
with this system I can see everything
and we can play with stuff quickly and
we can do whatever we want and then that
way we don't waste time with a bunch of
GPU nonsense when we don't really know
exactly what we want so yeah I think
that that definitely helped pull I would
say so again I'm just not sure I feel
like we're getting some odd behavior
here and if I take the distance fall-off
out of the mix right and we just look at
one one sort of pass here let me also
drop the iteration number down
look I just don't understand why the
lateral moves are creating so much
flickering it's like it's passing
through some sort of the
it just doesn't seem like the amount of
motion should be able to create such a
difference in terms of the angle change
between so many different things there
so when I look at this I just think
we've got a bug in here that you know
maybe I shouldn't be looking for right
now because we should wait for tomorrow
to look for it but otherwise you know
that's my thinking on anyway and again
you know there's not a whole lot
happening here like basically it just
takes the inner product of the vector
from the light the vector from the the
place we're trying to compute lighting
to a light source and then the normal of
the surface that's the only thing we're
taking here we then do the product of
the diffusive which we've removed the
diffuse coefficient which is just one so
those are non terms so it's just the
cosine of the angle times the light the
incoming light color right that's all
we're doing and so somehow that cosine
angle term is really getting pretty
jacked in terms of its fluctuation and I
just don't know where that's coming from
now it's possible I guess that something
else is kicking in here but in theory
the specular coefficient since it's zero
shouldn't should nuke out anything else
that we're getting here and so we should
just be looking at really nothing other
than just add a few Center product that
should be smoothly varying like it
shouldn't be that drastic but maybe it
is so yeah I guess that's that's all
there is to that so let's go to the Q&amp;A
here
yeah I can't enable the or overlay it
died the problem with that is that for
some reason Windows just sometimes
removes it like as far as I can tell
nothing is happening weird in C tray it
just removes my overlay I do not know
why just windows being Windows I guess I
should try and figure that out it
happens every so often
so is it gone I mean did it get is it
actually totally gone it's crazy how
many windows are open
so what are the styles of this window
pop-up visible clips siblings so you can
see this is a topmost window that's
visible there's a top most visible
window it's coordinates are exactly the
bottom corner of the screen right where
is it like where is it anyone so we want
to tell me where it is I have no idea
but it sure does appear to be there
yeah I don't know
Martin's mosaic uh says sorry the trick
didn't work it works the editor I use
yeah the thing is I suppose for coders a
little too smart
is it like it actually parsed the C++ as
C++ as grammar says to which is in in
most cases I guess is what you want in
this case it was too smart for us right
because we wanted to we were hoping it
would be dumber about about the string
but hey Martin says there is an option
to try to use old non raw string
literals caressed our shader equals
stringify parentheses right multi-line
code here close parentheses where
signifies the macro with pound
preprocessor thing compiler will smoosh
multi-line code into one line string and
you'll lose line numbers and error
messages but they don't you musn't
stream anyway hmm that's interesting
I've never tried that does that work so
basically what you're suggesting is to
do something like this
[Applause]
is this what you mean Martin's so we
would just say because I would assume
that that's not going to really work
because also you can't close you
wouldn't be able to really close
parenthesis in there would you I feel
like I guess the other problem is - I
feel like that doesn't work because for
coders again - smart it knows that
brackets wouldn't couldn't be done in
here that way I think maybe no maybe
it's not so yeah that that I guess would
work but but what about having quotes in
there I guess is my only question like
that probably works
but I'm a little nervous about if
there's quotes now maybe we don't use
quotes ever in the shaders so maybe it's
fine
in fact I guess they probably wouldn't
so that is maybe that's the best maybe
that's the best option so let's see so
we're as if that doesn't indent properly
I think that's a sore crater bug maybe
it's already been fixed but for some
reason if you block indent something
like that the first time through when I
did it here it wouldn't indent but then
it obviously can't invent it because if
I go through and reinvent it again it it
worked so I know what's going on there
exactly
um so there's shader code down we go
doesn't look like it understood the
ending of this though looks like that's
a bug in the indent or right because it
thinks it thinks that that is there for
some reason it can't handle what's
happening here in fact it seems even
more confused I guess maybe because of
its the second one in it indented it
further this time so I think we just
need to ask Allen because even this
doesn't really seem to work right
the cryptic mind I do think that it does
get addressed a little further down I
think we get rid of the sleep because it
was too unpredictable on different
platforms exactly as you discovered did
the black overlay disappear during the
stream or during QA during the stream I
think but I'm not sure from the code if
target active you could always check the
video when I posted I suppose we'll see
if the countdown has finished and
whatnot then there's not active anymore
all right well anyway I'm going to wind
it down here yeah we should try and
figure out if we can get Alan to maybe
put something in here that would work
I'm going to back that change out for
now because it looks like none of those
options work and we can just ask him
like what like what we should do like
what's the right solution there because
it's nice to be able to embed code from
you know into a C file will be nice it
there is some way to make that
indentation work okay right Martin says
you could do caressed our shader gloss
shader code parentheses return pound
include shader H return close
parentheses and then put code in the new
shader at H file maybe then indentation
will be fine afterwards we put Martin's
how would that work because it wouldn't
that take the pound include and string
eyes it
Martin says new that will work
interesting I didn't know that you could
do that that's a that's an interesting
trick Martin's is saying that you could
actually if you do like what I had
before if you do that he was saying you
could actually do this which is crazy
because I just assumed that the string
eyes would take precedence over the
pounding food but I guess the pound
include comes first if that's the case
then the pound include would would allow
us to just put it in a separate file and
that's probably fine I would assume so
that might be a reasonable thing to do
because that would also put the shaders
in separate files I'm not sure I'm
necessarily psyched about having quite
so many files as that would require but
I'm not adverse to it like so we've got
a bunch of files that seems okay
furthermore if we wanted to be weird
about it in theory we could actually
just glom all the shader code into one
file as different functions and then
just have our actual code here just call
whichever function it actually wants for
that particular shader or something
weird like that but that probably would
create some problems for the compiler
all right I'm going to close it down but
that's an interesting trick Martin's I
didn't know you could do that that seems
like it would work all right thank you
everyone for joining me for another
episode of handmade carrots and a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you'd like to follow along with us at
home you can always pre-order the game
on hand made here or to come to the
source code so you could follow along
you can also go to our forums if you
have questions you want to ask our
patreon page transport the video series
our schedule bot if you want to know
when we're going to be live and our
episode guide if you would like to catch
up on
past episodes that's about it for today
I'll be back tomorrow where we can start
playing around with that lighting
transport in CPU sides and see if we
can't figure out something interesting
until then have fun programming and I'll
see you on the Internet
take use everybody