yeah there we go hello everyone and
welcome to handmade hero the show where
we code a complete game from scratch
live on Twitch we don't use any engines
or any libraries we code everything
ourselves here and that's our goal this
is an educational program what we're
trying to do is basically show how every
single part of a game works and so each
day we take an hour to code something
and it's some new part of our game some
new aspect of our game so that we can
kind of see the entire process and again
I do it all without really any
preparation so that you can see how I
would actually approach it warts and all
in a real professional environment right
I don't go write the code first and then
just type it in here I actually go
through the whole mental process of how
do I figure out what to code how do I do
plug it when I make mistakes all that
kind of stuff that's what we do and
that's been going pretty well so I'm
pretty happy with it and and we've got
plenty of stuff that we've got to do so
let's go ahead and get started if you
have pre-ordered the game on handmade
hero org obviously you get full access
to the source code here since we there
is no game yet there's just source code
so you can go ahead and download that
source code anytime you want you'll get
a link in your email if you have done
that
today is day 69 so you want to download
roll the source zip will have day 68
source code in it you want to start with
day 68 source code because that's what
I'm starting with today so if you're
trying to follow along with that today's
video that's the one you're gonna start
with if you want to code along with me
at home so if I remember correctly we
were right at the point yesterday where
we wanted to start talking about doing a
sort of more collision response code
more handling of collisions and so what
we had yesterday is we had just gotten
to the point where when two entities
sort of collide on the screen we know
that they do that right and then we have
we want to respond to that in some way
and we're about to deal with sort of all
of the complexities that come with that
collision response now one of the things
that we haven't addressed yet and that
was kind of where we left it was we
don't really know what to do
with things we don't really have a
strategy for dealing with when things
hit other things but should just pass
through them right so for example if I
had this little test I could fire this
little rock sprite out from my guy as a
little testing that we were doing and it
hits me and it gets stuck on the edge of
me right I've got a little bounding box
and when it hits the edge of that
bounding box it gets stuck on me and
that stops it from going forwards
anymore because it just keeps hitting me
and hitting me and hitting me and
hitting me and hitting me which is kind
of what our collision Tector supposed to
do it's not supposed to let things go
through bounding boxes right that's what
we coded it to do but in this case we
basically need some way of making that
work right we need some way of getting
the code smart enough to know that
sometimes we want things to pass through
things and sometimes we don't and maybe
we even want something as complicated as
whether or not something can pass
through something else is dependent on
which two things collided right you
could imagine that certain entities can
pass through magical doors and others
can't let's say right so we may have a
situation with collision detection where
even just the notion of what can pass
through what is entirely a gameplay
decision that involves a bunch of logic
right and that's the kind of thing that
we we want to take a look at today right
how do we enable that how do we make
that clean how do we make it so it's not
all janky and hacky again our collision
detector isn't a final collision
detector so there's plenty of problems
with just a collision detector because
we haven't really written a full one yet
but ignoring those problems with that
I'm just talking about the logic of what
happens we want that to be nice and
clean so that the logic is generally
flawless so if the collision detector
itself when we actually make the
bulletproof version of that it's not
hamstrung by the fact that there's all
this kind of weird not really that
reliable way that things do or don't
collide and you know we end up having
all these bugs and the shipping thing
where it's like people report Oh
I tried to fire the thing and it
disappeared halfway through because of
some you know like weird like collision
II bug sorts of stuff so we want to make
that code work in sort of a nice way
that's that's not going to cause us
problems and that we can add things to
when we need to and and it's not this
huge deal to add them right so basically
the first thing I want to take a look at
and I think we've got our important in
here yeah so need our closure table here
so the first thing that I want to take a
look at I'll delete this to do because
it's basically what we're doing today is
we sort of started on this handle
collision path and what we do is we have
a collision thing here and we've got the
stops on collision thing right and we
were sort of saying like okay the the
flag that says whether an entity
collides is telling us whether or not
when an entity hits something whether it
stops or not and so the first thing I'd
like to do today is let's go ahead and
change that concept right and say
whether or not something stops on
collision let's just make that a factor
that gets computed in the collision so
basically we don't even have to change
the rule right now we could make it so
that essentially we'd get sort of a
thing in handle collision right we can
make it so that we we sort of do it the
same thing in here and so it's still
based on that flag but I just want to
make it so that it could be procedural
if we wanted to so stops on collision is
now going to be something right that
gets done in this particular call so
something you know like this I'm not
saying this is actually how we should
necessarily do it but something that
looks like this where when a collision
gets handled whether or not the
collision handling code said so is what
will determine whether we stopped the
thing from going in the direction it was
going right so that's step one of the
process right and that's a pretty easy
step to do the other part of the step is
taking a look at sort of the bug we
already have now and that we actually
talked about solving this way back and
we started this and we kind of decided
to go off on a tangent cuz I wanted to
fix a bunch of things with how we did
things so we did the sim
and stuff we inserted that in there
because it was the next logical thing to
do well way back when I talked about the
concept that we kind of want to have a
more robust way of thinking about when
entities hit each other and just to
refresh your memory for people who
didn't basically have that sort of down
necessarily let's go ahead and make a
little space here where are we in our in
our whiteboard is there day 68 let's go
over here oh I guess I kind of need to
zoom out I wish how is there a way to
look remember what the current zoom
level is I don't actually know I guess
not
so here's our whiteboard let's go let's
go find a location oops let's go find a
location that would be fine for this day
so I'll just I'll just zoom in over here
right for day 69 say it's right here I
guess this is probably is that probably
how big things were before I don't
actually know so let's go over here I
need some way of remembering the zoom
level is that a thing is that this 100%
okay so I guess I just want that to be a
hundred percent is that what that does
no that's a pasady so I don't know is
there is there even a zoom I don't
actually know if there's even a thing
that that says what the zoom should be
I'm not sure I I really don't know
erasers presets that's just all brush
stuff view yeah I don't know if somebody
happens to know write it on the forums
or tell me in the Q&amp;A if there's any in
this thing if there's any way to like
save the zoom level that would be kind
of nice anyway here on day 69 let's go
ahead and talk about what I was saying
for us so what I was saying before is
the approach I'm gonna take first to
this problem is all right so I've got
mr. hero here and he throws a sword at
you know and then there's a monster
right here who's you know basically like
mad or whatever and the swords gonna go
it's gonna hit the mon-star right so
this is a monster and this is a hero and
this is a sword and so what happens is
our collision routines all there you
know all their job is
to basically take some representation of
each of these things and tell us when
they hit right it's supposed to
basically say okay if this is traveling
in this line then I know that at this
particular time when the sword gets to
here it's gonna hit this Monstar and
when the sword starts out if the sword
started out here it's it's touching the
hero right so what I want to do is be
able to write logic that basically says
when a hero throws a sword I don't care
if it hits the hero don't consider that
a problem right so I want to be able to
say things like okay hero versus sword
you know ignore that don't even think of
that as a collision don't you think
that's a possible collision when this
hero throws this sword now
I don't want to say necessarily all
heroes I want to say this hero right so
it's specific it's not necessarily a
type it's not about the fact that he was
a hero it's the fact that he's the guy
who threw the sword if the Monstar threw
the sword it'd be the monster that I
don't care about right so this is a
specific object this is an entity I want
to say and this is not all swords if
there's another sword that's coming at
the hero I want to know if they hit so I
want to know this sword right I want to
say this hero versus this sword don't do
that that's just a logical that's what
my brain wants to say similarly when
this monster gets hit with this sword I
then probably want to say alright if
this sword at that point is done meaning
if the sword is like a one use thing it
hits a monster and then it disappears or
whatever right it shows some damage
effect and the sword stops goes away
goes back to the hero essentially so
they could throw it again whatever
that's fine we don't to do anything
because on that collision the sword goes
away there's no more logic involved but
if the sword is to continue through the
monster so it's a piercing it has like a
piercing property or something so it
hits the monster it does damage to the
monster and if there's another mon-star
if there's mon-star to over here right
and maybe this is a really evil monster
maybe this is let's say that this is
actually a super evil monster so it's a
it's like a mimic it's a it's a thing
that pretends to be other things and
then attacks you or whatever right and
and what was the name of that oh right
it's a it's the super fish monster right
it pretends to be something else and
then it attacks you when you least
expect it
so there's another monster over here and
we want the sword to go through it and
hit this guy so once it hits this dude
every frame thereafter our collision
detector would keep reporting that hit
right if we didn't do something about it
and that would be problematic for our
collision code cuz every frame would
think it hit the monster it would think
to do whatever supposed to do and hit
the monster and if that's like subtract
the hit point it's gonna take off as
many hit points as frames it as it goes
through the monster there's all these
problems right so we have issues there
so the other thing that we want to do is
once it hits a monster we won't want to
say like you know on hit Monstar versus
sword right and against this Monstar
versus this sword right ignore so that's
another thing that we want to do and so
essentially what I'd like to do here is
I'd like to try and again I've never
actually written code this way before
it's not something I've actually done so
I'm kind of interested to see how it
works and I often clients will be doing
stuff like that in the stream so that
you can see how I work through new
problems not just problems in the same
way that I've done them in some other
way in some other case so the thing that
I was thinking about to try first for
this and I explained it on a previous
stream is let's just make this explicit
let's just go ahead and actually just
write code that does exactly this so in
our collision response routines and
anywhere whe else what we want like when
you throw a sword you can literally just
add rules to the system that tell you
this and the collisions vector will obey
them so when a hero throws the sword we
add a rule that says this here on this
sword can't collide right let's just do
it and then we'll see how that actually
goes right that's my theory and I don't
know how well that'll work but it seems
like it seems like a good way to start
because usually if you can make code
explicit
if you can make it do things the way
that you want to state them directly
that is usually the most versatile most
easy understand most easy to debug way
because then there's not all these weird
implicit rules that you've basically
tuned you know code that you've sort of
crafted to do essentially what we just
wrote but in an indirect way so I'm
going to try that and that's going to be
the topic of today's stream all right so
let's take a look how are we gonna do
that
what I want to do is basically do that
right here okay so we already have
essentially one implicit rule we already
did sort of one part of this which was
saying that when I test an entity I
don't want to test the entity against
itself meaning an e cannot self collide
so what we did there is we said all
right when we loop through for any given
entity right here we are in our move
entity routine removing this entity
it's called enemy when entity moves we
loop through the other entities that we
want to test called test entity and
right now we don't have a facial
partition that's why we say expansion
here we want it we're looping over all
the entities in the same region and
later we probably only want to do the
ones that are close to you but that's
not a that's an optimization that has
nothing to do with the logic that's just
optimization so what we do is we then
say if the entity is not equal to the
one we're testing us if there are
different entities then we'll do the
test but if they're the same entity
don't do the test and that was sort of
one of these rules essentially that's
universal for all entities we don't want
them to collide against themselves
because that's a meaningless statement
right obviously an entity always is
colliding with itself so if you had
something you wanted to do on that
condition you just put it in its update
call because if you know it's always
gonna happen you don't have to test for
it right and so given that placement
what we really want to do is we want to
upgrade this to basically say should
these empties collide so we want a
should collide call right which takes
two entities and figures out whether
those two entities should collide with
each other if it were if it returns true
we'll assume that we actually do want to
do that test if it returns false we'll
assume that it wouldn't and what we can
also do is roll this test in
right so basically the collision
detector now will be completely dumb as
far as any is concerned it will just
call out to some kind of grand notion a
predicate function basically that's just
there to know whether two things should
collide and in that way anywhere else in
the code that we want to know whether
two entities could collide or not if we
have logic that that you know needs to
know these sorts of things it can just
call that same function then we know
everyone's always asking the same
question they give to entities they can
get back a yes-or-no answer whether or
not the two things will collide right
and so that's what we want to do there
now we have one other sort of yep and I
guess we have one other thing that that
doesn't address which is you know
whether things stopped on the motion or
not but that's the job of the collision
response routine so we're breaking into
two pieces there's whether or not we
want to register the fact that they
collided and then there's what do we
want to do on it and what we want to do
on it is handled down here so this is
strictly telling us whether an event
could occur when these two things touch
and that event could be about physically
colliding with the things but it could
also be that they're just passing
through but we want to note it right so
that's what we're gonna do here so if we
take a look at what this should be we
already know potentially one of the
things that it should do right oops so
if I take this out here and say yeah
should collide sim entity a Simmons TP
right then what I could do is just start
by saying well we know one thing which
is this right so let's go ahead and move
that out there like so okay all right so
basically we know that if two things are
going to do colliding right then this
this collides flag I don't know how much
we want to deal with that anymore but we
know at the very least both of these
things should not nothing neither of
them should be non spatial entities
right in other words both entities have
to be spatial in order for the tooth for
the things to collide and that gets us
out of that business essentially of
testing this now we could still do this
here as sort of a special case if we
wanted to where we basically
are quickly getting out of this routine
so we could say right here note you know
this is just an optimization to avoid
entering the loop in the case where the
test entity is non-spatial right this is
just an early out but we really don't
need it anymore
meaning we could get rid of that and the
code would still function properly but
we may just want to do a little pre
checking there to see right so anyway
we've got this test we can basically say
if either of these two things are
non-spatial then we know that we
wouldn't have to do this but if either
of them are then then we need to
actually do the check all right so we've
got our result here we assume that they
don't need to return true assuming that
they're both facial and then we return
that right and so that would be one way
of us testing that and again that should
just kind of work and do the same thing
that we were doing before okay we still
have our stops on collision thing so
that would be this right but yeah on the
stops on collision front
we don't really quite know how exactly
we haven't talked about how we want to
deal with this yet but we could say that
basically it's not really about the
entity flag anymore we could say that
stops on collision is just whether you
know the I guess we'll do the a type
equals entity oops and made H and made H
there we go things that stop on
collision are basically the hero right I
guess and let's see here get if this is
not the way we want to do this I don't
even know why I'm typing this in right
now I just kind of wanted to go do the
other thing so let's see the the
familiar and the Monstar all right
familiar and the Monstar right those are
the things that stop on collision and we
did this kind of sorting thing I don't
even you know what I'm not even gonna
I'm not gonna do that yet that's not
even the way we want to write it
it's not I'm gonna do that we're just
going to return false for now and then
the next thing we'll do is we'll come in
here and do that so to do real stops on
collision cuz that's gonna be a property
identity property comparison thing so I
don't want to pretend that that would be
something useful all right okay
and so what we need to do now is
actually kind of build these things out
and make something logical about go on
there right so mm-hmm
let's tackle this one piece at a time
what we do know is we want to have a way
to write these but these rules that I
talked about in the whiteboard we want
to write that into the should collide
function so basically what we want to do
here is say you know in this section we
wanted to do that'll basically do look
in a rules table to see if we should
collide right and that'll be that and
then the other thing that we want to do
is probably we want it we want to sort
of formalize this this handle collision
thing here so we can make the stops on
collision think I'm a little more
logical so on handle collision I'm
trying to think of whether I just want
to return that boolean whether a boolean
is sufficient or whether I want to
return a package of information that
says what should happen
hmm I guess for now since I don't know
I'll just leave it with the boolean but
in the future maybe we want to return a
little more information there I'm not
sure
and so I'll also move this to do for
stairs up here because really that will
be something that happens in the handle
collision when we actually handle stairs
and stuff so I think this will be fine
but what I would like to do is the
sorting stuff I'm gonna get rid of the
sorting stuff in here I'm gonna move the
sorting stuff that basically was about
doing the dispatch I'm gonna say that
handle collision actually just takes the
things directly right and and we'll deal
with that kind of up here if it wants to
sort them it can sort them and so handle
pollution will just pass the two
entities into it like so what are they
they're entity
and hid and so basically yeah there we
go
basically this is the setup that I think
that I want to use to go ahead and write
the code so the way the code works is
when we are moving in entity at least at
the moment we go through some number of
iterations trying to move them to the
new location that they should go we have
a movement cap which we implemented
yesterday so I can only go a certain
distance if they've got a moving cap on
but that's separate issue so what we do
is we go through all the entities and we
say if these two entities should collide
then we actually test to see if they
could collide and we set the the
collision time based on that then we
come out here if we actually did collide
with someone we handled that collision
and if that collision handling code
decided that we should actually go ahead
and stop the thing where it was we will
update the Delta to not allow them to
move in that direction anymore and then
we continue our iteration right so very
very straightforward and so now
basically all of our stuff is broken
into these two sort of routines I'm
going to put them the opposite order
because this is how they actually are
logically or organized we essentially
have one function that needs to
determine whether checking should occur
at all and then we have another function
which basically says ok what do we do
when two things actually do collide
right so let's start with the should
collide anytime two things are spatial
we're basically saying they can collide
and so then the other thing that we're
going to do here is basically look for
any rules because I think that's all we
have right now it's basically like two
things should collide if if both of them
are spatial I can't think of anything
right now that we have that doesn't
actually at least have events that
happen on collision because the sword is
something that passes through things but
we want to do stuff on it so everything
in our game so far collides and so all
we really need at this point is the
table and so I'm going to do a very
simple version of the table first but
we're probably gonna want to do a more
complicated version of the table
in a little bit
something that's a little bit smarter
than this it's gonna be like a really
stupid version of this table right but
I'm just just to get it working so that
we don't have to think about it too much
because we probably want to organize it
to be fast and this this ain't gonna be
that so all right so basically what
we've got here is we're gonna have a
little collision rule so we'll do it
basically say there's a collision rule
here and we'll call this a pairwise
collision roll I guess and so what this
will be is this will this will
essentially say we've got you know in
and the index storage index a and
storage index B like these two guys
right and we're basically saying that
they should or shouldn't collide it's
what I would say right and so for now I
guess we'll just or a rule should
collide and so what we want to do is
basically look this up and I'm gonna do
the dumbest like I said dumbest possible
thing will have this pairwise collision
rule I'm just gonna sort of store
I might even store just a linked list of
these things I'm trying to think of what
I want to actually do here because I
think what I probably want to do
eventually is have a hash table and I
want to probably hash on on storage
index a yeah I mean that's probably what
I want to do so you know we're probably
want to do something like this right
something like this and then there's
just this is just like like a hash in
here that Jacek says we've got a
pairwise collision rule and you know
we've got some hash table of said rules
right and so we've got collision rule
hash right and that's going to be
something right so that seems fine and I
guess I don't even really care how big
this is it doesn't even really matter I
don't know we're not really doing
anything particularly intelligent here
so we'll just do the same thing we did
before
it must be power to right like so and
I'm just gonna store those things in
there so what we'll do is anytime that
we want to know about this pairwise
collision rule thing we're just going to
go ahead and say let's go ahead and look
in that table so this is gonna have to
know about our game state right so this
is
game stake here game state and it's
gonna go ahead and look in that table
and say okay well we'll do the same
sorting that we did here right we'll
basically do the same kind of sorting
technique we want to look up in the hash
table based on a stable index for when
two things are gonna collide with each
other so since they're stored on storage
index what we'll do is we'll just say if
the storage index will sort them so that
a is always the one with the lower
storage index right so we know we're
always looking up and if you don't if
you've never done that kind of thing
before it's a pretty standard scheme
right I have two things I've got a and B
right
I want to hash I want to look up
something on both of them
so I basically want to do a query which
says you know or a map right which
basically Maps you know a B to a single
boolean value right and the problem with
this is if I just wrote it like this
then map a B would not return the same
thing as map BA right those would be two
distinct entries if I was just doing
them you know kind of as whichever one
came first and since nobody knows which
of these like you know if we just kind
of took well whatever the routine
happens to pass is the first one of the
second one
we'd have two entries one for when they
were passed in this order and when when
they were passed in this order so we
want to do is make sure we always pass
them in a stable order and the easiest
way to do that is just to compare some
known value in them and swap them around
so that we know they always get passed
no matter who passes them in the same
order and so that's what I'm doing here
I'm just basically saying okay let's
swap them so they're always in the same
order and then I'll look up in the hash
table to see whether there's an entry
for these two guys right hopefully that
makes some reasonable sense so we're
gonna do should collide we swap the
things first so that we know that
they're always in the right order and
then what we do is we take a look into
the table and we could actually say
perhaps even that the table is
authoritative for now which is if
there's an entry in the table then you
use that otherwise you don't right and
so we'll just say for now we'll do a
found
actually I guess we could do it actually
just we'll do it this way where we do it
afterwards so we'll go ahead and say all
right let's take a look in that
collision rule hash will basically say
we have a hash function here where we
basically say you know we have a hash
bucket right for this guy and I've
already gone over hash tables so I won't
belabor that point again we're doing
exactly the same thing we did before
we'll just take the storage index and
this entity we won't even bother trying
to do any kind of hashing on it yet
we'll put in the Hat the thing that I
always love although we may never do it
with better hash function it's in every
code base and no one ever actually us to
do it because hash tables are so darn
fast compared to everything else in your
code oftentimes you never bother going
to write a better hash function but you
know it's there and then we go ahead and
we'll say whatever that size of the hash
table is a collision rule hash we'll go
ahead and and and that with with the
value so that produces that mask for a
hash table there right that basically
wraps us into the hash table so we go
ahead and we get that rule out we've got
our pairwise collision rule like so and
we basically want to loop through that
in fact I guess I could do this with a
for loop here so we start here we keep
going really cool to a little next in
hash right next in hash and in the case
where whatever the rule is storage index
a equals a storage index all right so if
I find a match just looking for that
match I find a match that has both a and
B in it then I just assume that the
result is whatever the rule said right
so the rule just straight-up overrides
whatever I might have computed in
whatever this logic ends up to be right
so to do property based logic it was
here so basically like we probably want
to make this more complicated than it is
right now eventually doing things with
enemies to determine whether they should
collide based on some properties of the
two entities but for right now we don't
have that we don't have any really rules
we want to implement so but they will go
there eventually
so assuming that we you know we already
set that to something then what we do is
we'd go ahead and check in our hash
table look through the hash table right
grab out the first one that's in that
whatever bucket we should be in hashing
off of a go through each of those rules
and when we find one that matches we
just override it and in the case where
we find a rule that overrides me to stop
right okay
so we kind of have there's there's a
nasty thing here in fact I'm kind of
glad we started down this road actually
because this is gonna kind of be an
interesting programming problem because
there's a thing that I haven't actually
considered here when I started writing
this but actually is going to make this
a more interesting data structure than
just something that we've done before
right we actually technically have a
problem in terms of who we want to look
up on because when we add these rules to
the system right we kind of want also to
be able to pull them out based on the
entity as well right we want to be able
to say when the sword when this sword is
done you know comes out of existence you
know it doesn't really come out of
existence but when it goes back to the
player we can get rid of all of those
collision rules that were on that sword
right and so we kinda have to think
about how exactly we want that pull that
sort of removal to work and so there's a
couple different ways that we could do
it obviously but it's kind of a tricky
problem like I'm not sure what the most
efficient way to handle that would be
one way is to thread it again
so we basically can pull things out by
an entity thread so in addition to being
linked by hash you're also linked by
entity but I'm trying to think if
there's if there's clever or cleverer
ways of doing that and I'm not entirely
sure so for now we'll just start with
that well finish getting this working
but then
let's think about whether we want to
kind of upgrade sort of how we're
storing that because we want it to sort
of be able to do both things and we'll
see I'll so if you don't know exactly
I'm talking about it's okay we'll get to
it in a second here so there's our
should collide right that basically
tells us what should be going on there
and so you know we we now have a trivial
way of avoiding two things from from
colliding with each other in that
particular case right and so I think
that actually should be mostly what we
would need to get started with this
collision rule hash episodes a member of
game state and state let's see here
storage index a absurdity story index
and then our should collide takes the
game state now so of course this guy
doesn't have that so this actually takes
a game state well there we go which
means we have to pass it here like so so
there we go and now we're in theory
actually checking this stuff properly oh
well but of course I can't just randomly
change my memory layout we don't support
hot loading on memory layout changes at
the moment so yeah so now what we want
to do is we should be able to add a rule
that would allow us to stop having that
weird bug where we kind of get stuck in
there and we could also make it so
familiars can pass to do the hero now
pretty easily by making it so that
familiars can pass through the hero but
not other stuff that would also be
something that we could add pretty
trivial like this familiar can go
through this hero and so on
right so let's see how we can actually
add that let's see how we can do that
with our pairwise collision rule stuff
so now what we need is we need a way to
add that so we've got our should collide
right sim region we've got our should
collide call we also need a way to
basically say you know add collision
rule something like this where we can
basically pass in this and say should
collide and now that collision rule will
you know get added to the to the list
it's the exact same thing like we're
just going to grab the hash bucket out
we're gonna look to see basically which
one there is and unfortunately I guess I
don't know if I want to share this code
or not it's such a small piece of code
but
maybe you know we kind of want to share
that we'll see how it goes
what I want to do here is say all right
when we add that collision rule I'll at
least do the due diligence and assume
that you know that could already be in
there and that you're just trying to
override an existing collision rule so
that I won't keep adding new rules I'll
look to see first if that rule is there
and and I guess I need to do this as
well to make sure that switch happens
I'd like to pull that code out I don't
like the fact that that's duplicated so
you probably want to get a little we
probably want to collapse this to do
collapse this with should collide and so
we're have to think about exactly how
that's gonna go but anyway when we have
the a and the B's will do the same sort
there will look them up again and
basically what we'll do is we'll see
whether or not we found it so we'll do
pairwise collision rule found equals
zero when we get here we'll do found
equals rules because we found it and
then if if we do not find one we will go
ahead and add one so we'll basically say
that you know whatever is in the hash
bucket right now we just need to do that
chaining we're doing this this next in
hash thing right
we're basically to go ahead and chain
that on there so what we'll do is we'll
say if we haven't found one then we're
just going to make a new one so we need
to do one of our our pushes here right
we need to do a push and then we'll will
basically get a new one out and then
what we do is we say whatever was
previously in the hash at that location
we push that down we the new entry that
we're gonna put into the location here
is going to become the prime the first
one and we'll point to whatever one was
in there before right I'm doing that
standard thing where basically we've
done exactly this sort of thing before
right I have a table of pointers here
right here's my this is my my hash right
each one of these is 0 at the start when
we go to add something into it we take
whatever the pointer was that was there
we're going to put a new pointer into
its place we're gonna make a new thing
right we're gonna put a new pointer into
its place and point to whatever the
first thing was now if there already was
something there then when we put the
when we set the pointer equal to some
new thing we need to make sure that this
guy gets saved so we make the next
pointer of the thing we insert point to
whatever was there before right
so we're basically inserting it the
heavy always insert in between at the
head of the hash table in between you
know we basically insert right at the
beginning so that everything that was
there before I just kind of gets pushed
down right pretty simple so the next
thing in the hash is going to be
whatever was the first thing in the hash
before and then whatever the the head
pointer of the thing points now to us
right so we overwrite whatever was the
thing that was there before the pointer
to it we overwrite it with a pointer to
ourselves right so all we really need
now is to actually go grab that arena
again we can use the World Arena for
this because this is sort of a permanent
thing that stays around these rules are
important to the gameplay so we've got
our World Arena we can push into the
World Arena something that is the size
of a pairwise collision rule and now
we've got a new one right like so I
believe that's all we need to do for
that push what is it called
I don't remember I never remember what
we called that it's called push struct
yes
push struct yeah so we do our push truck
to get the new one and then assuming
that we at this point we now want to
assert that we definitely have one right
although we could actually do an if
found here to allow out of memory
scenarios which you know like I said we
haven't really gotten to how we're
handling memory policy yet so it's not
that big of a deal we'll look at all our
push trucks later and decide how we want
to handle it cuz there won't be that
many of them and so basically assuming
that we found it we said it should
collide equal to the should collide and
we set its a and B equal to our a and B
as well so this is storage index a and
this is storage index B and so storage
and that's a oops in storage index B
so I think that's all we need to do
really to add a collision rule and so
let's go ahead and check that out inside
our handmade CBP when we actually create
the hero right so when we do add player
like so what we could do is say all
right when we add a player let's go
ahead and say that because I think don't
we add a sword when do we add the sword
there we go we add the sword so we add
the sword let's go ahead and add a
collision rule that basically says that
whatever our sword was oh you know what
I just realized too
this should actually probably not be we
don't want to have to have these in the
sim group like we want these to just we
actually want this to just be storage
index a and storage index B because we
want to be able to call this outside of
of stimulation we want to be able to
call it at any time so really we don't
want this we just want we just want to
work this way right so we have storage
index B Storage index a and then we have
our temp the equals storage index a
storage index a equals storage index B
and then storage index B equals 10 right
so we swap those around so then these
become this way instead right that way
we just don't have entities anymore and
that's nicer because now we can call it
from anywhere so basically we have at
that point we have our soared low index
and our our hero low index as well
entity low index like that and we passed
that game stayed in there and then we
say that those two things should not
collide right and in theory that might
work but who knows we'll find out
so I still am colliding properly of
course our collision detector is awful
at this point we should really probably
go in and just fix that collision thing
so people can't get stuck in things but
yeah so we got a bunch of work to do to
fix that sort of stuff we'll look at
that in a second but basically now we
should get into a situation where yeah
that thing does not collide anymore
of course it does collide with the tree
which creates a problem for us
because now the thing can't get past the
tree which is not what we wanted but
that's a separate issue all right so
let's get let's go fix that problem
in fact I guess we can fix it probably
without actually doing anything here
all right that's that was pretty funny
so when two things should collide we
could also say that basically inside our
hand a collision if if any of them is a
sword then we don't want stop on
collision to happen so actually now that
I think about it what's going on here oh
I see
so I got I guess I see what sort of the
problem is right when two things hit
each other we don't actually have a way
of saying okay we want this thing to go
through so when stops on collision is
not true at that point we essentially
have a rule that we want to obey which
says these two things you know this
should pass through right this thing
should pass through the thing that it
just hit if that makes sense
okay so we can do that we've got issues
to deal with now at this point but you
know let's let's just go ahead and
follow this through to its logical
conclusion so we'll add a collision real
cure we'll say all right we've got the
game state the game state is going to
say from now on these two enemies can
hate each other so entity storage index
and hit entity storage index just can't
can't collide right and so we'll just
say that that's true right and there hey
look our sword goes right through stuff
now now of course we're not sorting yet
so it doesn't draw on top of them or
anything like that
but now it works but we've got a slight
problem here which is that we're kind of
again this is the part that I was
talking about before we have this
problem where we don't really want to
keep accruing these collision rules
right because as we do this we'll just
add more and more collision rules as the
sword goes through more and more things
more and more different entities right
will end up in a situation where we just
fill up our entire memory well
maybe not because memory is huge these
days but just in terms of thinking about
it from a more efficiency standpoint we
don't really just want to add collision
rules so that we eventually have a rule
for everything that the sword has
touched ever and gone through and all
that sort of stuff so what I'd like to
do is I'd like to be able to remove I
threw that I was going so fast that it
actually end up going backwards which is
pretty funny that's pretty funny it's
gonna take that guy a while to disappear
because of how slow he's actually moving
come on go I want to throw another one
there we go
so what we want to do is have some kind
of a same policy where we basically say
things that are doing this sort of
behavior should have some time when
their collision rules get cleaned up so
as we add things when you know when they
go through we won't just accrue them
forever that seems like a better idea
right than doing it this way
that's just my assumption so yeah so now
everybody can go through everything
because everyone has that false and
we're just accruing collision rules like
crazy and I want something to stop that
that makes sense
however one thing we also can do let's
go ahead and exit there one thing that
we can do first is we can make this
handle collision call actually do stops
on collision in a slightly more
meaningful way we could do it where it
basically says okay you know if the a
type equals and the type sword then then
stops on collision is false false
otherwise stops um collision equals true
so basically everything but swords have
to stop and we'll talk about you know
we'll figure out what's gonna happen to
other stuff later but now at this point
in theory I should still stop right
which I do but my sword won't stop when
it goes through things which it doesn't
and so that's good and everyone's happy
about that okay so I think we're in good
shape now and of course our Monstar also
sort of works to some degree but of
course we get that collision rule thing
happening I don't know why did our that
was pretty interesting why did our sword
disappear the first time oh because it
does this if we we have a rule in there
for
make any non-spatial but we yeah we want
to actually women you hit a monster we
wanted to say that it does stop at that
point because that is how we were
actually doing it so that we wouldn't
had that rule right that makes some
sense yeah of course we don't actually
want it to do that what we want to do is
leave it spatial and have it just go
through so we want to actually do that
but I just thought it would be
interesting to see what would happen
there so now we should be able to file
the sword through the guy and you'll
notice that even though oh and so yeah
there we go this is an even more serious
manifestation of the problem I was
talking about which is like once we've
said that the sword can pass through the
guy it can pass through forever so you
can never hit him again with the same
sword right so that's another reason why
we need to clean them up it's not just
efficiency right it's an actual rule
that we don't want we want to say that
that rule only exists for when the sword
is essentially in flight right and when
the sword stops we want to reset its
collision rules to be no and so that's
the next thing to think about right as
part of this system how do we want to
handle that so if we want to have this
sort of flexibility where we can stab
these collision rules we also need the
ability to pull them off because
essentially when that when we did that
processing here when we were basically
saying okay you know the sword becomes
non-spatial right we've got the
simulation for the sword we say make
entity non-spatial when that happens we
want to clear out all of its collision
rules and then when you throw it we want
to put them into effect right so when we
throw it you add flesh and rules to it
and they give crews amount of time and
then when it comes back we want them to
go away right so we want to do something
like clear collision rules for right we
want to do something like this game
state entity storage index and then when
we do our add collision rule for the
sword we actually want that to be when
we throw it right so when we do our
Artie sword
and we go ahead and we actually throw
that sword we want to do it here when we
make the thing spatial we want to add
the collision rule that basically says
okay you know the entity
that's that's thrilling the sword and
the sword itself those two things should
never collide with each other right so
that's what we actually want to do but
clear collision rules for is kind of a
nasty problem right and yeah and we
should try to think about that so we've
got our add collision rule and we've got
our clear collision rules for if these
by the way should probably go they don't
really belong here they're not about sim
regions at all
so basically I want to do this sort of
thing storage index like so so I'm gonna
go ahead and pull these out at
collisional for like so I'm gonna go
ahead and pull these out to here right
and this is the sort of thing where
double indexing is kind of nice right if
you imagine you have a more sort of
built out system so you're thinking of
things more in terms of a database and
you've got systems that you use for this
sort of stuff already that you've
written this is the kind of query that's
much easier to do and we're having to
write it ourselves that's just part of
the writing everything from scratch you
have to write everything once but it's
something that's worth pointing out
right that querying on one or another
thing it's something that like systems
oftentimes will make easy like a
database makes that very easy but other
kinds of structures often make it kind
of hard C++ style coding in general
often makes it hard and I'm not talking
about auditory impaired anything like
that but just the way people tend to
write things and see where you kind of
have the index as primary it stores the
things they typically don't tend to have
being able to look up on two different
things
that's tends to be kind of a harder
thing to write whereas if you're used to
using say my sequel or something like
this it's an easy thing right you can
just say I want an index on both of
these things so just worth kind of like
noting that this is one of those double
index and kind of problems because what
we'd like to be able to do here is say
well I don't actually care which of
these two the sword was the sword was I
want to remove all of them right I'd
like to remove them all and so I there's
a couple ways we could approach this
one is we could have an opinion about
the sorts of people who have these rules
and just always do the hash on the
proper one another is we basically do
the hash in both directions I guess so
we would first hashed on it as if it was
a and then hash on it as if it was B
which seems like a pretty easy thing to
do in other words well no I guess you
can't really do that either so this is
always hashed on a and we don't know
what a actually is we don't know like
say that this was always be in the rule
we don't know what it's a actually was
so there's no way for us to do that so
yeah we would have to literally go
through the whole hash table if we
wanted to remove the collision rules for
something which maybe isn't a big deal
but it could be very expensive right
depending on how many things are in that
hash table I don't know if we want to do
that or not
we can do it pretty trivially here you
know we could do it in a very expensive
way the very expensive way is just this
way right so we would basically say okay
we have a hash index right a hash bucket
the hash bucket equals zero the hash
bucket is less than whatever the size of
the collision rule hash is and then for
each one of those buckets we then check
all of the entries in the bucket this
would be searching the entire hash table
and every time we find something that
actually has this storage
index in it we have to remove it right
and so the way that we would do that is
we would essentially do something like
this right we'd say if if either of the
two things right if the the storage
index a or the storage index B if either
of them equals a storage index we're
looking for then we need to remove it
otherwise we don't need to remove it
right and so the way that that would
work is we actually want to be able to
set the pointer properly to skip this
particular one and of course like I
always do
this will probably be a free store
situation so we basically have first
free collision rule here right so
anytime we get rid of one we just
give it back so the next time someone
actually uses it in a hash it'll get
used right so we have this collision
rule we'll say all right you know we'll
go ahead and we'll look for it the sort
of tricky way to do this here would
basically say instead of walking by
pointer I'll walk by pointer to pointer
so I start by saying all right I'm gonna
look to see what that first one is in
the hash bucket
I will then say all right I'll walk as
long as it's the thing that it's
pointing to is not no and so then I look
to see if the one that I'm looking at
right if the this one happens to be the
one that I'm that I want right and I'll
say that my pair wise decision rule next
rule right whatever that is left I guess
I don't even need to do that right so
then what I do is I say okay I'm gonna
walk these guys mm-hmm I'm gonna see if
I actually got got one that matches what
I need to do is patch the pointer so
that the pointer who was pointing to
this now points is the thing that's
after it which removes it from the list
right so I need to basically say that
the pointer that was pointing to the
rule that I'm looking at right now I
want to make that guy actually point to
whoever was next in the hash right so
basically the way that I'm removing
these guys is I'm saying well okay you
know I've got pointers
I've got like a linked list like so
right and what I want to do is each one
of these guys actually has the pointer
in there right this is the the hash
table let's say this is a link and so on
so what I'm doing is I'm looking at this
pointer I'm saying if the thing that I
point to matches that I want to set this
pointer to point to whoever the next
person in the link was to skip this guy
so that I can remove him from the list
right so basically saying like okay you
know as a pointer right this pointer
will now point to whatever was next in
the hash table so there we go so that's
how that would remove it from the list
and then of course I also want to put it
on the free Storace or the first free
collision rule so basically like what
I'll do is I'll just store it
I'll say pairwise collision rule removed
rule equals whatever was the thing we
removed now it's basically been removed
and then I can say all right
my removed rule next in hash equals
whatever that first free was whatever
was on the free list before it's exactly
the same way we did it free list
previously and then the removed rule
mm-hmm sorry then the the head pointer
just points to removed rule so that puts
things on the free list and then we can
also use the things on the free list so
now instead of doing this push struct
what we would do is basically do
actually I guess I could do it right
here you can just say if not found then
found goes push direct so and we can say
this is going to be first free collision
rule like so I guess I can do this put
this way so we grab the first thing off
the free list if there actually was
something on the free list and that's
fine and we'll basically just set the
free list to point to the next thing
that was there otherwise we'll go ahead
and make a new one and then when we free
them we free them right and so we just
use again a very simple scheme and off
you go nothing particularly interesting
going on there
what is this complaining about identify
are not found ah yes because we don't
actually we need to actually make these
things be available to other people so
I'll go ahead and put them in here oh
boy
look so and stay with clear collision
rules for you go other people might want
to call these there we go oops
interval we haven't written any interval
code yet internal so that'll add things
back to the free list in that case we
haven't quite finished this loop yet
though so clear collision rules for we
go through them we remove ones that
matched and in this case we have done
everything I think that we needed to do
probably the left step through it I just
make sure again
this on stream while I'm talking is a
little bit daunting and on the brain but
in the case where we where we didn't
match we want to make it equal to the
next in hash right we want to take the
address of that so that we're we can
advance the point forward right so that
would would do our hash bucket this I'm
pretty sure that's probably most of what
we need to do so let's go ahead and step
through that and see how that worked
just so we can kind of see but again
this is not particularly good I guess I
should also put in that to do so to do
need to make a better data structure
that allows removal of collision rules
without searching the entire table right
because that's not really the way we
would like things to go if we could help
it alright so there's our our stuff
let's go ahead and get things started
here why am i okay so we haven't
actually added any collision rules yet
so let's go ahead and shoot that sort
out so here we go on our ad right we
want to do our swap because we always
want our storage entity our storage
indices to be in the right order so we
always want a to be lower than the-- so
that's what it did which is good we're
gonna grab out that collision rule hash
bucket and just take a look at it there
was nothing else because this is the
first rule we've ever added if it hasn't
been found
we're gonna try and grab the first one
the first free one
we couldn't obviously get one because
there's nothing in there yet and so what
we do instead is we grab a new rule off
of our arena basic is use a little bit
of our of our storage space and then we
go ahead and set the pointer to whatever
was in the free of this before and we
set the pointer to be the hash
Buckethead pointer to be us right
assuming that we actually found it which
of course would always happen in a case
where we didn't run out of memory or
something
we then initialize it so now we've got a
nice rule set up and we're done right so
that's all we had to do there and then
presumably the same thing will happen
again
hopefully we'll get a similar situation
where the storage index now this this is
gonna store off a different guy so this
will still not find anybody again there
is no free nobody on the free store yet
cuz we haven't eliminated anybody so off
we go adding another collision rule this
time this time it is okay so I think
that's the sword right and probably some
wall that's hitting or something like
that so we want it that's good now we
can actually see it look for a rule I
think oh no I guess not so I guess we
always I guess it was 92 zeros or a 4
that was added before I was the hero
yeah too bad alright so there we go
at least I think that's true which I
guess we should probably double check I
wasn't quite paying attention which all
the rules we should have checked to make
sure that that was going in the right
hash bucket there I would have liked to
have gotten that ok so then when we do
our clear collision rules for
essentially almost all of these are not
going to hit right so what we want to do
is we want to kind of find when we
actually get inside this loop at some
point right so here's where we actually
had a hash bucket that actually had
something in it which is what we want to
see so what's our hash bucket which one
are we looking at we're looking at hash
bucket 41 and so we have collision rule
hash and we've got hash bucket so here's
that first hash bucket and as you can
see there isn't anything next so what we
should see is this guy should get
returned to the free list and it should
then write a null pointer in there so
we've got first free collision rule so
there's nothing in there right now what
we want to see is we want to see this
guy move over to here and the rest of it
get cleaned up so it should match it
does match we go ahead and say pairwise
collision rule removed rule equals rule
so basically that rule is just the rule
that we're looking at right which is
fine we then say the pointer whatever
the pointer was that we're putting which
is this one right here right we want
that to now point to the next one which
was this so this should now become a
null right and it does so that's nice
and now we want to make sure that our
removed rural stores whoever was in here
which would also be no so that's not
gonna do anything exactly but then we
want to push this guy in the free list
which we did right and so now he's on
the free list so it just moved him out
of the hash table into the free list
and that's the end of that right so now
let's make sure that that works when
there's something already on the free
list which is what's gonna happen here
right we're gonna go ahead and remove
that one guy again and now we want to
see our first Creek collision rule right
what we should now see is when this guy
gets pushed on here it should be chained
right so there should be the other guy
should be on here and there he is right
and so those guys chained together and
off we go so that looks good but what
we'd like to do is also double check
that our free list removal is working so
when when things want to come off that
free list if that works as well so now
we should do is we can see the opposite
happened we should pull somebody off
this list so found is going to be this
guy right here so assuming that we found
him what we want to do is advance that
pointer that first free collision rule
equals the next in hash so this could
move up right and it did and so that's
what we wanted so that's good there
looks like anyway and so off we go and
so let's see how if there's any bugs in
that I don't know there might be ooh
that was weird what just happened there
I didn't like that at all there was a oh
that was probably the stuck key but okay
but so we have a bug here what's our bug
push rect draw hit points hit point max
oh yeah okay well I guess we when we do
our if we shoot the the guy enough times
to actually make his hit points go to
two negative we never actually really
wrote any of this code but we just sort
of did a hit point max you're not ever
supposed to actually do this but I
should probably just double check since
the code exists now let's let's make it
not do something ridiculous that's going
to cause assertions so there we go so I
think now we should be in a case where
we can hit the monster multiple times
and we can now so that's good but it's
not a great data structure we didn't do
a fabulous job there that's something
that we should go ahead and and think
about improving when we do our final
engine components I feel like that would
be a good idea
so hey guess what we're pretty much
right on time I said I would go about 20
22 minutes later then we then we said
we're gonna do because I took a bunch of
after getting telling a story that had
nothing to do with programming and so
now would probably be a good time for us
to start the Q&amp;A and we'll still do
about 15 minutes QA I feel like to get
some Q&amp;A in here just because we told a
story at the beginning of the show
doesn't mean that there shouldn't be any
Q&amp;A so if you could I will go ahead and
start the Q&amp;A like so and if you could
please prefix your questions with Q : so
I can see them that'd be great and if
you could leave stuff that's off topic
ask those during the pre stream we
always talk about off stomach steps just
come like 15 minutes before a scheduled
start time and we can talk about
whatever but for during this Q&amp;A please
try to keep the questions to stuff that
are about the programming we did today
or the program that we've done on a
previous day and future looking stuff or
just questions about general things try
to move those to the pre stream so yeah
let's see what stops us from programming
a game that directly boots into BIOS
hooks up to hardware as low as possible
basically so basically the thing that
that prevents that is the fact that we
all have different computers right so
this is why I keep saying that one of
our big things in the future is to port
to unknown platform where we can
actually do exactly what you just said
that's why I said probably it'll be the
Raspberry Pi or something but I don't
know I'm actually in the process of
trying to get stuff like that figured
out talking to people and sort of figure
out what platforms we can use for that
and because that is what we'd like to do
eventually we'd like to go ahead and
pick a platform so that all of us can go
ahead anyone who wants to palette can go
by that platform help me be like a
relatively low-cost homebrew kind of
platform everyone can buy that platform
and then we will actually do that that
exactly that way the reason that we're
not doing that currently is because it's
almost impossible now everyone's
machines are totally different do you
have you have UEFI BIOS or not what kind
of graphics card is in there how does it
get initialized like you know all of
these sorts of things are just dos was
DOS we could have done it if was in the
dass days now in in the modern days it
would just be so much overhead of trying
to get everyone on the same page and
writing all things just to get like USB
keyboard input right would take us
forever so I didn't want to go that
route off the bat but that is what we
want to do eventually and so after we
are finished with the game porting it to
a platform where we can boot directly
into the BIOS is wrecked directly from
by us into our game is absolutely
something that we will do and so I
haven't decided exactly what platform
that's gonna be we'll probably take a
little bit of a wait-and-see approach
because you have a long time before the
game will be done but by the time the
game is sort of wrapping up I will have
a very specific answer for if you want
to do handmade fully handmade hero where
we'll go ahead and drop down that extra
level I will have some kind of
announcement before then about like
here's the platform that we're gonna be
doing if you want to do it by this
platform and get ready right
let's see do I ever use function
pointers so occasionally there's times
when function pointers are useful in
this particular case you know the
problem with function pointers is they
can't persist they're not stable right
function pointers change every time you
recompile your program so I tend to
prefer switch statements because the
thing that you're switching on persists
like you could write it to disk and it
works you can stream it over a network
and it works even if the to binary is
were compiled differently whereas if you
use a function pointer it's always
unstable so the only time you can really
use function pointers is by building a
table first and then using an index into
the table you know what I mean so
because most things you want to do in
games have to be saved you know saved
games are very important Network
communication is important stability
across builds is important function
pointers tend to get used less
frequently because of that because if
you use them you then have to introduce
a layer that's does it stabilizes them
often times and so usually it's just
more efficient to not to just use that
layer directly whatever the enum is that
you were using that would have allowed
you to serialize those function pointers
properly you can just not do that just
switch off the enum and it's way more
efficient right and so it's not so much
that I don't like function pointers I
like them just fine it's that there's
these downsides of function pointers for
the types of code that we're writing
that make it so that I rarely that
they're rarely a win but that doesn't
mean if they wouldn't be a win in other
scenarios that didn't have those kind of
constraints
should the throne Indy have the players
Direction speed added to its throne
speed and distance so you cannot catch
your own throws well right now we do ad
that is what's going on right now if I
understand you correctly we have right
like if you take a look in here when we
have D sword so the sword has whatever
your speed is plus whatever the speed of
the sword should be that's how it works
currently but that's a game design thing
we haven't we don't even know that
there's gonna be swords in this game
right so that's not really something
we're thinking about right now that was
just how we happen to do it cuz someone
was asking about it and so we showed how
to do it but yeah that's not really
something that we're thinking about I
mean it's not even a sword right now
it's a rock technically we're calling it
a sword because that was what we were
thinking of conceptually but yes so we
don't actually know if that's gonna
something that's in the game right we
haven't decided those sorts of things on
the stream yet so I don't really want to
talk too much about how to make that
work well because we don't even know in
order to know what should happen with
something like throwing a projectile you
need to have an understanding of the
game design and we haven't progressed to
that point yet right
could you explain again why you should
order the entities before processing the
properties yeah so well we haven't quite
gotten to where that's useful yet but
basically we may not have to actually do
that animal collision we'll find out but
basically the reason we want to do that
is if we end up doing a dispatch table
for them then we want to be able to
dispatch based on a stable ordering of
them right so let's say that we had this
was that upper triangular thing right
let's say that we wanted to make a
routine right called like sword hits
Monstar right and that does a thing
where you basically have a pointer to a
sword right and a pointer to the Monstar
we don't want to also have to write
Monstar hits sword right so really all
we're gonna do eventually and we haven't
actually done it so you can ignore it's
not even you can even just wait it's not
even something we've actually done yet
this is meaningless stuff at the moment
basically all we're trying to do is say
we just want to write one of them so
what we should do is pick a universal
ordering for our stuff like sword always
comes before Monstar or whatever so that
we know we only ever write sword hits
monster and we never write monster hits
sword because if a sword in a monster
collide it's always sort hit Monstar
that's the only thing the sort is there
for it's so that we don't have to think
about things in both directions we know
that we just only have one which is when
this hits that and we know that if we
have the opposite we would flip them so
that we'd still call this hits that
instead of that hits this that's all
isn't there a potential bug and move
entity if an entity happens to spend the
whole distance limit which gets set to
0-0 and then considered as unlimited in
the next frame so no I don't believe so
because the way that that's designed to
work is that if your entity has some
kind of a movement limit
you're supposed to be processing that in
your update call so you're supposed to
do something when distance limit hits
zero right now if we decide that we
don't like that then you know we could
we could change that rule to be when you
hit zero you can no longer move at all
but we have to actually find an anywhere
that is actually important right and so
the reason we don't have that bug is
basically because the entity types if
you're so with the movement limit you're
supposed to respond to having the
distance limit run out and if you don't
respond to it then it seems as sane a
default to me as anything else that now
you can move right that's totally fine
too because what was the limit there for
you know you have to have some kind of
idea it presumably was there because
something happens when you stop and so
you should have an event there and if
some reason you forgot to put the event
there then allowing it to move again
doesn't seem any stupider than leaving
it where it was but yeah so I feel like
that's fine and it avoids introducing
some other constant value that's like a
crazy value that's meant to indicate
that you don't move but if we find that
we don't like that we can certainly
change it right it's trivial for us to
make a constant value here there's just
some special thing that's like unlimited
can the discarded next pointers in the
hash function become a memory problem I
don't I don't know exactly what you mean
but basically we're based the the memory
if you if you want to think about
temporarily what the memory implications
of a hash plus free list are they have a
really nice they have really nice
behavior so basically what happens is
you have if you look if you think about
how your memory gets used right you have
a fixed amount of memory for the hash
size so there's the hash memory right
right so we'll call that we'll call that
H right and then we have the memory for
the links right like so and that's
basically like the size of the links
times L so that's proportionate to L
which is a variable right times the size
of the links so basically the the hash
to do this scheme you basically have the
hash times the number of links times the
size for links this is your memory usage
right that's your memory usage for the
hash table plus the free list to store
these things what happens is the maximum
amount of Link's you can ever have in a
system at a time so whatever the
gameplay ends up making this maximum B
that's the maximum this will ever be
right because it can never be more than
that because every time one of these is
freed it goes to the free list so once
you once you've hit your maximum
scenario once you have a scenario where
the most number of rules are in play as
possible so L max h plus the maximum L
that are in play at any time times s
that's the total footprint you will
never use more than that that will get
allocated for you dynamically as you
push out and then it will just stay
reserved from then on right because
every time something gets freed it goes
on the free list when it gets used it
comes back in so you never thrash
remember you never fragment you're
always perfectly utilizing the memory
that you have and it grows to the total
maximum usage in any gameplay scenario
and stops so even I like these even in
dynamic memory allocation
so even if we decide at the end of this
game that we don't care about a fixed
memory footprint and we just want to
allow the game to grow to however much
memory it wants
I still like these schemes because it
means that they grow to the total size
they need to be and stay there which is
nice I like that and they never fragment
I have two game play requests a
non-euclidean room and a monster that
spans multiple rooms vertically are
those things possible
a monster that spans multiple rooms
vertically is trivial because we don't
think about rooms in terms of how any of
the gameplay code works a room is
strictly a camera concept at the moment
so a monster that spans multiple rooms
vertically is easy or horizontally or
any other way you want a non-euclidean
room is definitely something that we
don't support right now in any
particular way oh wait do we
so yes we could support a non-euclidean
room the way we would support a
non-euclidean room is by mapping tile
chunks by by changing the mapping of
tile chunks to not be in order so we
could do a non-euclidean room I will add
that to my reminders text file to show
how to do that I don't necessarily want
to make design decisions around that
because I don't think it's particularly
important for gameplay but I will write
it down so if at some point it becomes a
good time to maybe say let's do a little
bit of a non-euclidean thing here we
could probably do something like that
the thing that we couldn't do very
easily is a non-euclidean room that
wasn't an even number of tile chunks
wide I think that would be hard but yeah
I think we could do it the other way I
think I don't know I have to think about
that so I wrote it down I don't really
want to make design decisions based on
that because that's not a big part of
this game and it would be something that
would have affect other things that we
could do it definitely something that
would introduce a bunch of trade-offs so
I'd rather not make a bunch of decisions
based on that but I'll write it down and
if it turns out that something we could
handle in the future that wouldn't
jeopardize a bunch of other stuff we
could take a look at it
our render is reusable sure I mean
that's what a graphics card is it's a
giant reusable renderer so yeah
vendors are definitely reusable it
depends to what degree you needed to
take advantage of certain aspects of the
game that they were rendering to get
performance that's really the thing that
determines how reusable they are but
sure renders are often reusable
so I think I think that is all of the
questions I don't see anymore so it
looks pretty good yeah all right well I
guess that's the end of today's episode
let's go ahead and wrap things up here
so we've actually done this that's
that's done these are done we did some
to do's there so we basically you know
we've got stuff straightened out here
but of course we I guess technically we
kind of accomplished everything that we
want to accomplish it's just we don't
have a very efficient way of dealing
with with clearing those collision rules
for like the sword so that's a little
bit of an issue and I don't know so it's
something we you know we've done our
first pass maybe we need to think about
it more maybe we'll let it go for a
while like I said and we'll sort of see
how things shape up as we sort of do
more stuff with collisions and more
gameplay maybe that will inform our
decisions it'll let us know do we care
about this performance-wise do we even
want these collision rules maybe we
handle it in a different way in the
future because you know the game design
sort of dictates that way but it looks
like we did the thing we wanted to do
which was give ourselves an easy system
where we can just add and remove
collision rules that's not a big deal
and so we've done that and that's good
and I'm happy about that so we'll be
back here tomorrow and I'm trying to
think what's the next thing on our list
of things to do I think probably what we
should do is allow the monster to die if
you if you heard it and then maybe we'll
rights a little bit of AI pathfinding
code for the monster maybe it's time to
add some path finding where he can find
his way around because that's a big if
and then we should probably start moving
on to animation because we've we've
pretty much done a fair bit of specking
on this sort of stuff I feel like we're
getting into the part where we would
start writing things for real like you
know start fixing the collision detector
to be like fully featured and all that
stuff and we're kind of pushing up on
that like real code boundary and again
we're just trying to make sure
everything expect for us before we
actually take that plunge
make something fully featured so I think
maybe you know we should move on and and
get a little bit more done in each arena
and then start coming back a lot of
things down because we're getting pretty
far in in a lot of I'm a lot of backsies
so that's good but it also means that we
want to make sure that we don't neglect
anything first you want to get
everything sort of fleshed out before we
really commit to doing something first
for real so anyway thank you very much
for joining me it's a pleasure coding
with you as always here on some morning
handmade hero action I will be back here
tomorrow same time 9:00 a.m. Pacific
Standard Time tomorrow so if you would
like to come back for some more
programming I think maybe what we'll do
is start that pathfinding Monstar
behavior stuff that seems like a good
place to go next because we haven't
really just you know worked on how we're
gonna do pathfinding which is gonna be
an issue cuz we basically we don't have
grids anymore we've got just a free
freeform world so we need to kind of
think about that and figure out how
we're gonna deal with it and I don't
know so that's something we have to dive
into so that's cool come back tomorrow
we'll take a look at that if you would
like to follow along at home with a
source code you could do that by
pre-ordering the game on handmade hero
org and that'll get you a link in your
email which allows you to download the
source code every every day after I
finish I upload it if you would like to
support the video series we do have a
patreon you can subscribe to as well on
here we also have a news and forum site
you can go to that has a bunch of great
resources on it it's got ports to Mac
and Linux that community members have
done also port to iOS now and to Android
so people who are looking to sort of run
on other platforms that's a great place
to go it also has a discussion forum and
an episode guide that has like time
marked indices that you can go to and
use it's a pretty handy thing to go to
how their command checking it out and
also there's a tweet bot that tweets the
schedule so if you want to check that
out go to the tweets that's an easy
thing to subscribe to that allows you to
know kind of when the stream is is gonna
be every week so you can if you want to
catch a live one you kind of know when
your options are so that's it thanks for
joining me hopefully I see a tear
tomorrow morning have a great rest of
your Thursday and I'll see you guys
later