all right hello everyone and welcome to
handmade here are the share we code a
complete game live on stream today I
wanted to kind of shift gears a little
bit because I think we've come to the
point lighting wise where we kind of
need to get more involved in the
geometry production side of things and
so you know I try on handmade hero to
break things up in sort of like to to
break things up into blocks where it's
like if we're doing lighting we try do
lighting for a couple weeks in a row
rather than bouncing back and forth
between you know different parts of the
engine that's not necessarily how I
would normally do stuff sometimes it is
and it does mirror the process a little
bit if I'm working on new lighting
algorithm obviously going to spend a lot
of hours working on a new lighting
algorithm and doing tests and so forth
but often times I'm bouncing around
through parts of the engine modifying
what needs to get modified next and
whatever and I would imagine like you
know I can't speak for other people
necessarily but I would imagine that
folks like John for example who's
streaming I know a lot of people watch
to watch this show I I feel like
typically speaking maybe not as much
when he's working on compiler stuff and
whatever but typically speaking when he
does a game because he's a game designer
and he does a lot of engine programming
I feel like it's probably even more
right like he probably bounces around
even more does you know totally kind of
random walks through the codebase where
he'll be like oh I want to work on this
gameplay thing I was thinking about and
oh but it needs this engine thing so
I'll do a little bit of that and then
I'll come back to the gameplay and I'll
see if that works and all that that
reminds me that this thing was broken
and right and so I feel like it is true
that generally speaking when you're
working on a project most of the time if
you're on a small team and you're
responsible for a lot of different
pieces you're gonna be bouncing around a
lot and so that's sort of where we're at
now I think and so we're gonna start for
the next few weeks we're probably
bouncing around quite a bit the goal is
to eventually get to the point where we
sort of have an idea of how our
world creation lighting movement all
work together and so we've put in a lot
of pieces for that individually but we
haven't really kind of taken the step of
like ok game make this an actual game
now that we're confident everything's
working together and so that's what I'm
gonna start trying to do today and this
is just gonna require us to go through
all sorts of parts of the code and clean
up lots of stuff and tune it to be what
we want and remove parts that turned out
to not be useful and all these are the
things so I do apologize for that making
a little bit harder to follow but
realistically speaking that's just how
programming actually works and in fact
it's a very common way that you might be
programming on a game and you know I try
to maybe make it a little less likely on
handmade hero simply because of the fact
that it's you know hard to keep track of
things if you're watching the series at
home but yeah so the first thing I want
to do is I'd like to take a minute to go
in and make the movement code and minute
I might mean multiple episodes I'd like
to go in and start to like lock down the
movement code a little bit and I'd like
to basically make it so it's easy for me
to move around my character and the
character right now doesn't have to be
anything in particular it can literally
just be that light source or whatever
but I want to feel like I think it
should feel in the game if that makes
sense and I'd like to be able to move
around pretty cleanly and have the
camera fall pretty cleanly and then I'd
like to start getting the lighting to
follow cleanly and the lighting points
to be aligned right with the cube based
geometry so that's like the first big
push and it's gonna take several weeks
to get there several because we only do
like what four hours a week of
programming so that's not very much
programming so if I like it take several
weeks to get there and but that's what
we kind of need to do because at this
point we we've got a lot of systems in
place and really the only way to finish
them is just to actually do the fly
stuff that we want there and see what
the requirements are and so that whole
set of things will do and then we will
have to do one more big thing after that
which is finalized sort of the way in
which the world building code works
right now the world building code is
completely standard we've literally
never spent any time on it on the series
we just spam stuff in there as we're
trying to test and we've never done
anything even remotely serious in that
branch of the code it's just a dumping
ground for whatever tests we're trying
to do at the moment we just spam
something in there that creates it but
basically after we get all of that stuff
working which is quite a considerable
push through the codebase to the way we
want it then we need to update that
world building code to be ready to
actually go do real-world building and
the reason that we need to have
something nice in place there is because
we have to be able to do stuff like
conveniently place entities in the world
and know whether things are connected to
other things and you know do reasonable
sort of accessing of the world to
produce what we want and we can't really
have anything in that system that's not
going to be efficient because as the
world gets generated fairly large
anything that was like N squared or
anything like that is going to
immediately roll over and die
so we'll you know it will sort of give
us a chance to sort of proof all of
those pieces so that's what we're doing
again just to recap want to get it so I
can move through the world nicely and so
we can explore rooms then I want to
build some reasonable rooms that have
lighting points distributed across them
how I want them lit then we're gonna
roll into the lighting system get it
working correctly for that which will
require modifying how we pass things
down the pipeline like finalizing all
that stuff and then I want to go ahead
and do world build-out so we can
actually like place fairly large numbers
of things throughout the world in a
a little pattern and not have it be
cumbersome to do so so like good tools
for just slamming down rooms and walls
and whatever else we want so that we
kind of can see how that what that part
of the code needs to support because we
don't really know right until you start
generating something that you actually
want it's pretty hard to know what that
code has to support right okay so let's
see here I'm gonna go ahead and just
like I said get started on on this kind
of semi randomly I'm just gonna do sort
of walks through the code and get
whatever I feel like I need to have
working at any particular time working
again
what I will do temporarily is I think
I'm going to go ahead and and re-enable
we had like a little stand in player
there and let me see yeah we just turned
off like a lot of the stuff that was on
the hero so I'll turn that back on and
we can take a look at at how that's
working at the moment okay so you know
the hero is is still in there right and
he can still kind of move around but I
think like I've talked about before I
have a much more solid idea now about
how I want the hero to move around
through the world and what's supposed to
happen there and so I kind of want to
clean that up a little bit and and make
it feel more like I want to feel and one
of the things about that too like you
can kind of see is you know we don't
really have a lot of understanding here
yeah well there's just a lot of stuff
that we haven't really talked about or
haven't really like addressed and I want
to also make sure that we have like I'm
gonna try and add some more levels of
room here
- because again I kind of want to look
at the entire picture so I'm gonna go
ahead and add some more rooms in here
let me see here so it actually looks
like we've added quite a few rooms but I
guess right I mean we're we're adding
quite a few rooms here is that our the
room just above us I guess all the rooms
are above us is what actually is going
on so does that mean that if I came over
here and tried to jump on to this thing
I don't know if we actually can but does
that mean I can kind of come up here
yeah okay so I guess our lighting is
actually holding up okay - even in the
face of like kind of a bigger set of
geometry that has to deal with but again
like
okay so yeah so that seems fairly
reasonable right like and so I guess
we've got a bunch of room stacked on top
of each other now which is pretty easy
to test with we do have a few
weirdnesses here with just the height of
things I think we decided that this was
roughly how high we wanted things to be
so maybe that's fine I don't know we'll
have to take a look at that later too
it's a little hard to see how stairways
work here so that's you know maybe
something we need to take a look at but
anyway so what I want to do here is just
make the movement code a little bit more
solid in terms of what I can expect from
it
so originally the way that I was
thinking that the the hero would move
like way back when we first wrote this
code was I kind of assumed that what I
would want is sort of maybe a continuous
sort of motion for the hero and you can
kind of see that that's what we have at
the moment like there's basically like
you you know you move the head of the
hero around and and the body just kind
of follows after it and while I'm you
you know while I well I'm okay with the
feel of that what I sort of was thinking
when I started sort of closed in on some
of the design things that I was like
well how do we want to actually do this
I I was thinking that I might just want
a more tapi feel for moving around
because as I've been sort of like into
the more block tile-based sort of
aesthetic I just I feel like you might
just want to click to move to the next
square so like if I just tap you know
like that I just want to move from
square to square to square and have it
be fairly precise now obviously I'm not
sure if there may be some downsides to
that like I don't know if maybe that
becomes too sort of onerous as you're
sort of moving around like maybe it's
just too clicky and I I don't know if
there's a lot of precedent I can look to
for games of
nature because usually you don't click
to move square to square so I am a
little bit nervous about it but I do
kind of feel like it would just be nice
and so like one of the things that I'm
thinking in in my head anyway right it's
like I would be interested in sort of
when you're when you're doing sort of
fighting style things to like think
about moving like quickly like I can
click like aw and know that I'll be
exactly on this square so like aw click
for attack and it would go like here
here and then punch that way right and
just the precision of that I'm just
interested in that feel right again I am
NOT a game designer so I am not
pretending that these are good ideas I'm
just saying what I'm gonna implement and
so I think I would like to go that route
if for no other reason than I think that
it's not done that often and so I think
it might be just kind of nice to have
something that feels that way to play
and if it turns out to not be a great
idea well handmade here as an
educational series it's not supposed to
be a great lead assigned game or
anything so I'm okay with that so I
think that's how I would like that to go
and so then at that point I like when we
forgot we did that little camera thing
where you can look down if you're if
you're if you go next to an edge so I
would like to sort of get get that stuff
working a little bit more and just kind
of have a nice sort of snappy feel to it
and so then the head and the body will
actually not move separately if that
makes sense so it will only really be
the body that moves and the thing that I
want to do on top of that is basically
like if you will will get there I guess
when we get there but the idea is you
click wants to move to one Square and so
just clicking will move you but if you
hold it down I was thinking that will be
dodged so basically if you hold down the
button you'll just lean to the side and
you won't
to the next square I know this sounds
kind of weird but I'll I'll show you
what I mean so that's the movement that
I want and so I'm just gonna go ahead
and put that in and kind of get it
feeling the way that I think it should
feel and then we can move around the
world kind of cleanly and we can start
to build worlds and I'll see how they
feel to move around and then we can put
the letting points in and get to the
point where we're pretty happy with
construction right
in general alright and maybe I'll let
this thing pick there was kind of I
think this will generate arbitrary stuff
I'm not mistaken right yeah so this
these rooms are too big and they don't I
forgot we have a bunch of stuff so this
will this is yeah I mean this is long
overdue because if you look here we
don't zoom the camera out far enough to
see this whole room and that was the
thing we had in there but then when we
did some of the other camera stuff we'd
never really re-enabled that stuff right
so yeah this'll this'll this will be
good alright so first things first just
gonna look at the movement stuff and
then we're gonna look at the camera
stuff then we're gonna look at the
lighting stuff and yeah then we look at
the world building stuff just one one
thing after another until you get there
so inside our entities if you remember
the way that we were doing this and you
can see this when we did oops I've typed
correctly you can see them better when
we did add player there were a couple of
different entities that were sort of
involving the player right the body the
head and the glove now we don't have to
undo that we can still keep this
basically the same way and you know
maybe we want to because maybe there are
some weird spells you can do that like
detach the body from the head I think I
mentioned that before so these can be
different
that's not
the end of the world but regardless of
whether or not we merge those into one
entity or leave them as actual separate
entities where you know they're each
kind of different one of the things that
I want to do was to make it so that the
the movement always is coherent for the
body in the head so I don't want it to
be that the head moves and the body
tries to keep up with it I want it so
that the movement decides what's
happening and then both are tracked with
it directly now I believe we have a
specific update call for these for these
two right here and where is it's in
brain right yeah so you can see here
we've got this brain here oh right and
here's that code right there which is
kind of huge at this point so I might go
ahead and pull it out I don't know why
these remarks is in line because I can't
imagine the compiler would care one way
or the other whether there's a jump in
there but you know who knows so I'm just
gonna put this out here
and I'll just call them do it now when
we compile this you can see here we've
got a bunch of stuff that we are then
gonna have to pass into it and this is
just basic gonna tell us what those
things are right the compiles going to
tell us when I cut and paste that code
out what the stuff from the previous one
was that it depends on so you can kind
of see here we've got the the brain part
here that was getting passed in right
here that we're gonna need we're gonna
need that DT as well so I'm gonna go
ahead and put those in here you can see
that it's looking at the input layer
oops
where'd that go there it is here so
we're gonna need that as well I don't
know that we need the entropy at all for
this guy but maybe we do and the
gamestate
so looks like we use most things here
that that we pass in yeah and that's
just to make it a little easier for me
to see what's in there cuz it's a lot of
code at this point alright
so taking a look at this code we have a
bunch of stuff going on here and you can
see that we've got analog control versus
digital control and you can see here
that we put into this hero controller
which is sort of a thing that stores
what's going on with any individual
person who's controlling a hero cuz I
don't know if you guys remember this but
and in fact I don't know this might
still work for all I know probably
doesn't because I don't think we've
really made any way for them to get in
here but if if somebody is using a
controller okay so it does work so if
someone's using another controller they
can just join the game right so it's you
know I don't know that there's gonna be
any support in the design for co-op but
we allow you to do it so I'm just
holding you can see I'm holding a Xbox
controller here I'm Xbox one controller
and so you know if if you happen to grab
something that has an analog stick we
kind of want that to work as well and so
we want to allow both types of control
to do the thing that I'm talking about
which is you know sort of the hop from
room to room
sorry hop from square to square as well
as dodge behavior
whatever so let's go ahead and and
figure that out we'll start with the
digital version and we'll go to the
analog version after that now one way we
could do this is to keep going the way
we were going which is to say that we
just set a DDP value which is basically
saying curious the acceleration we're
using whatever the the control stick
says and then if it's digital we're just
stuffing it with whatever we've got here
and that's a pretty reasonable way to do
it I just don't know if we want to be
more specific than that
I don't know if we need to yeah I'm just
not 100% sure how we want to make that
work so for the moment I guess I would
say let's leave it this way and we'll
kind of just we'll see if we need to
push up into that code and change and
and give that code more control later
because that's mostly that's something I
really don't know until I actually write
the code below whether it's sufficient
to just look at a DDP value right and
again DDP is just I'm just using that I
typically use P for position DP as
velocity of DDP is acceleration
it's just position first derivative of
position second derivative of position
right so PD DP DP and DDP mostly because
you can't write Prime right I can't do
it I can't do like P P Prime and P
double Prime
those are not you know things you can do
and see so DP and DDP or another way to
write that okay so if you take a look at
what's going on here you can see we've
got the hero spawning code and that was
the thing that allowed the hero to come
into play before so when I hit start on
controller this is what executed so we
don't really need to worry about that
now obviously eventually we'll have to
do something
Mart here I don't even know Fergus for
multiple players I have no idea right so
that's like way down the line this is
for handling the sort of swipe glove
thing which we haven't really worked on
yet but that's you know when we want to
start doing attacks so we don't really
care about any of that either
so once we actually want to start
working with this stuff what I want to
do here is differentiate between the two
cases and see so what okay so is this
the one place we used eight and two by
the way yeah it is basically oops so one
of the interesting things about this is
we were we were looking at replace to
see runtime library and so Andrew
Bromage pseudonym 73 sorry and uber
homage I said that wrong I look I love
the pronunciation of his name it's like
homage basically anyway Andrew Bromwich
was looking at how to replace the sine
and cosine stuff and he showed us on
stream some ways to do that which we
should do at some point soon but then he
was like I don't know about a tan -
because you don't really use it and I
was like yeah you're right we don't
really use it we are only doing the
facing direction of stuff here with it
which we could easily have done in a
different way
we could just look at which of these
parameters was greater effectively and
just use that so we should probably get
rid of that atan2 entirely it's really
not necessary so that's something to be
thought about at a different time anyway
so what I want to do here is I want to
differentiate between the case where
we're moving just ahead so basically if
we're doing a head and no body or a body
and a head which are the only cases I
think that we will support so in this
case
here we want to basically say like if we
have a head and a body right then we're
gonna do some extra stuff and in fact I
don't know yeah I'm not sure exactly how
I want this code to work so we gotta
yeah I'm gonna have to kind of take this
one step at time but just looking
through it here I think I probably want
to simplify this down a bit because it's
just like until we actually know that we
need to ever do it separately we
shouldn't really have to worry about
that so at the moment I think I'll just
mainly collapse most of this and then
we'll worry about what happens without
it later so what I'm going to do here is
and I don't want that to acceleration
vector what I want to do here is
basically remove all of this and just
say look if we don't have a head in the
body that's something for some other
gameplay stuff down the line that I'm
not really interested in thinking about
right now so this stuff will just kind
of happen and yeah for no glove maybe
that's fine maybe I'll try to isolate
the glove stuff a little bit here but
otherwise I think we're good and I think
for the glove I can pretty much keep
that at the end where we can just do
something like this and so we'll still
allow you to be gloveless for the time
being
but we'll leave it so that we really
don't execute any of this code unless
you have a head and a body so looking at
this input code here does the body get
referenced in here anywhere it doesn't
so one thing I might do the head is all
that that gets referenced here you can
see that happening I might just move
that stuff down so it's a little easier
to see that's really not supposed to be
happening other than in here right and
similarly the glove part we could also
move to right here so now I know that
like nobody is doing anything with those
things so I'm not sure what this was
exactly
it's trying to stop the attack from
happening if the glove was already
moving right like you can't do another
attack if the glove is still in the
middle of an attack is what that was
meant to do and yes so I don't know I
guess what I would say is maybe I'm ok
with that for now I could move this out
and actually put that here
and we'll leave that for now ok so this
will not change anything that we did
right we're still just kind of moving
the old way and everything is the same
now what you can see here is the way
this was was working is when you do a
head motion the head was just getting
accelerated along and then it would look
to see if the body needed to go towards
where the head was by looking at
wherever the closest traversal was to
where the head was currently floating I
don't really want to do that anymore
what I want to do instead is when you
are in the middle of moat so let me draw
this out so you can see what I'm talking
about
ok get some milk and go in here
sounds like some kind of a dance series
at the Modern Art Center body motion by
Casey Mira Tori so what I want to do
here is say all right the body is gonna
be standing on a square and there's a
square next to it if you tap I want you
to hop to the next square
if you hold I want you to just lean and
stop right and so we have these two
conflicting ideas right tap versus hold
and the thing with tap versus hold is we
don't know which has happened until a
certain amount of time has passed so
right if you imagine here is time and
what we get here is at a certain moment
in time the user presses let's say the D
key right so this is the D key goes down
well is it a tapper is it a hold if
later the D key goes back up when we
look at this amount of time we can then
definitively say tap or hold right and
we can pick some threshold here like oh
you know a hundred milliseconds is a tap
a hundred and one milliseconds is a hold
right we can pick some threshold that's
whatever we think is the right feel so
we need to wait we need basically a
timer that says how long we have between
these right but what we definitely don't
want to do and what unfortunately games
affect player unknowns battlegrounds has
exactly this bug we don't want to wait a
hundred milliseconds to start taking
action for the user because in an action
game we want to take action as soon as
the user does something so if the user
is trying to tap to move to the next
square if they want to move to the next
square right now right but we don't know
whether they're trying to move the next
square or dodge so
what I want to do is I want to basically
have the first let's say hundred
milliseconds which is one tenth of a
second right I want that to respond
immediately and I want it to be
ambiguous as to which is happening and
then if you let go of the key within the
hundred millisecond window then your
character will hop
so he'll kind of like move to the side a
little as you write when you push to
give you instant feedback that it is
happening and then you let go he'll hop
right you hold down and he'll just
crouch into it and so again you you
really want to make sure that you
immediately give the player some control
effect right away otherwise the controls
feel laggy and unresponsive and that
that is not a good action game feel
right this is not a competitive game so
where it's not like it's making handmade
hero not eSports ready and to not
respond or something
it does make pub G not eSports ready in
my opinion but that's separate thing but
what it does mean is that the feel you
know the feel of the action game is
important because whether or not a
player is having a good time has a lot
to do with how the controls feel so we
don't want to be in a position where
we're not giving them any feedback that
they actually started doing the action
they're trying to do and so all we need
to do is start an action in that
direction and then when they either
release or don't release the key and we
definitively know which one they've done
we'll commit to this to this particular
animation that shows them the activity
that they actually were trying to do so
what I want to do here is in the sort of
in the code I want to have that timing
occur and I want to manage that timing
based on how you're pressing the keys
right
all right I so I'm gonna start by
nerfing out a lot of this code actually
and then I'm gonna slowly sort of put it
back in as we go so for example if I
take all of this out I should no longer
be able to move right ASD if do nothing
but attack does cuz the glove codes
still in there
right so that's the only thing that's in
there so now let's start by looking at
just straightforward button button
pushes and what I'm going to do is I'm
going to assume when the user presses
the button that they are always going to
jump so I'm gonna implement the jump to
next square code first with no timer and
then I'm going to implement the code for
lean with no timer and then I'm gonna
integrate the two and tune the timer
until I think it feels okay right
because we know we need both things and
so I'm going to write both things so I
can see how they look and then I'm gonna
merge them together rather than trying
to Murray write them both at the same
time which I think would just lead to
more confusion so the first thing we
need to do is say all right look if
there is a DDP going on here because you
can see we've got sort of this this
notion of the DDP that you can see up
here right and so I need to figure out
something that tells me whether or not
we think we're doing an actual motion or
not and so I think I'm just going to use
like how lengthy is this how much
movement is am I actually getting like
haha what's the distance that I'm
actually moving the stick and I'm gonna
look at that to determine whether or not
I think I've issued instruction to jump
and the reason I'm doing that is because
I need some plausible thing in my head
that will tell me and in fact you can
see it right down here there's there's a
version of this code happening for the
old way of doing it basically I need
understanding at least to a certain
degree that tells me whether or not the
user has committed to a move at all and
if we're playing on a controller that's
like an Xbox controller the distance
that they move the stick may need to be
a certain amount before we ever want to
consider it because a little bit of
motion maybe we'll let them the head
dodge move with that little bit of
motion right but the hop is never going
to want that so the hop is only ever
gonna happen if you've moved enough in a
particular direction so the first I'm
going to do is effectively do this part
right here where we're doing like a
length squared so I definitely do want
this part of the code to come back up
and say all right here's the DVP that's
happening I'm gonna take a look at that
length I'm going to go ahead and see
what I want to do with that length here
and so you can see what's happening
where I've got the DDP length greater
than 1.0 and then I do some stuff with
it and bah bah bah bah bah right you can
see what's happening here right so what
I want to do is I want to produce a
normalize DDP from this and so I want a
DDP normal and what that's gonna do is
that's gonna start out as nothing and
I'm also gonna have like a hop requested
flag let's say and so I'm going to look
at this and say I've got a DDP that DDP
is pushing a certain direction I don't
know how long it is so I'm gonna take
the length of it first I'm going to look
to see if that length exceeds a certain
hop threshold if it does I'm going to
normalize it right and so looking at
this this code was meant to sort of this
code was meant to prevent acceleration
past a certain amount I don't care about
that anymore right that's not really
what I'm looking at here at all what I'm
looking at here is whether or not you've
pushed far enough to request a hop and
to produce a normal so this codes going
to change a little and maybe we'll do
something like this similar later I
don't know but it's not that important
right now for what we
actually want to do so what I'm gonna do
here is say okay you know
and in fact honestly maybe this is the
right code temporarily so we do want to
do this in in this case but I also want
to do it for the normal in the other
case as well might be the right way to
say it right so basically what I want to
do is say look if this CDP length is
greater than some really low threshold
then I want to do one thing and then I
want to do another thing in another case
right so something like this so if the
DVP length is greater than any small
amount at all and maybe you know who
knows how small it is but quite small
then what I want to do is produce this
value so maybe like the normalize
coefficient is going to be one over the
square root of whatever this length is
right and then what I want to do is say
well the GDP normal is always gonna get
well it's not quite that it's that way
the DTP normal is always going to be a
normalized version of the direction
we're going or zero if there wasn't one
right and then if the DVP length is
above a certain amount then I'm going to
also normalize the DDP so that it can't
get longer than one hopefully that makes
some sense okay so that's all I wanted
to do there and then for my hop
requested actually this becomes fairly
simple that's just get the DDP length
like the amount they're pushing the
stick is greater than some amount that I
think indicates that we're definitely
trying to move to another square I don't
know how much that should be let's say
that it's 0.5 for now but obviously
these are all tunable okay so that gives
me like an entire sort of I'm not sure
how to say this
that gives me sort of an entire set of
information about what the
trol stick and or keyboard are trying to
do it this time and now what I want to
do is I want to show that in some way
that I can relate to pretty easily so
what I'm going to do here is actually
peg the location of the head I'm just
gonna literally put it at whatever that
thing was I'm gonna put it at that
offset to the body right so you can seen
here
there's ways that we're saying where the
head should be and you can see a bunch
of that information here right so you
can see for example let's see where
we've got head P settings P equals so
we've got a spring on the head and I
don't remember how high off the ground
we chose to make the head I literally
have no idea the head distance max is du
DT bomb but okay that's the floor
displace times head Delta XY y-axis head
Delta X Y also don't care about that
that's the 2d stuff where's the Z
love that no you anyway
so uh yeah I'm not sure exactly how we
pegged it here let me decrypt this code
for a second so you can see that all of
this stuff is moving the body and the
head I mean the head has to want to be a
certain distance off the ground right I
mean that's and so I think that was just
how we were doing it but I want to look
at what that was because I don't really
know what we decided that to be right
and so let's see here this is just
transactional occupy stuff against
substrates reversible the timer is up no
push recenter duty PCBs closest to a DP
e that's the spring right and some drag
[Music]
you know what I guess we just leave the
heads point on the ground that's a
little unfortunate but I guess that's
because our heads bright is offset
poorly honestly we should probably fix
that
before going much further I mean the
good news there is well we just set it
with the body's direct position and then
we move it and that's that so anyway if
we want to do that that's pretty easy
right
so all we have to do is then say okay
you know the head P equals the body P
plus the whatever the actual GDP here
the value is that we're looking for so
I'm just gonna set the heads position to
literally be whatever the body's fishin
was and then I'm going to take that
offset and you know however you're
pushing the stick basically and move the
head directly there right no animation
yet so I don't know if you can see this
but right and so if I start this other
guy with the analog stick you can see
that well you can't see me moving the
stick but you can sort of imagine how
I'm gonna stick you can see that like as
I move around the stick the head just
moves exactly as I as well as you would
expect it to right and that's just me
verifying the fat code is working
properly and also verifying that
commercial joysticks have really crappy
pots in them but yeah mmm so anyway
looking at that that is exactly what I
wanted so I know that that's working
relatively well now and so what I want
to do now is look and see when we
request the hop I want to look to see
where I could hop to in the
and if that is unoccupied I'm gonna move
the body there right and I'm not going
to do any animation for that yet
well I guess you know what since we've
already got a thing in there that does
the animation I guess I'll leave it in
there because I suppose there's no
reason not to leave it in there but yeah
there we go so in this case we'll take a
look the body movement mode equals
movement planted we could just we could
make this a little simpler by saying
look don't bother looking for the
closest traversable if you're not you
know we only really need to look if we
could move right now so let's go ahead
and and actually and actually look for
the close traversal first so we'll get
the close traversable to wherever the
place we wanna look is so call that hop
target P if we found one then what we'll
do is we'll say look if this is a place
that we can go then we will try to go
there and if we can then we will set our
our movement request to be that we want
to hop from this Square to that square
right and so all I need to do here is
say look if if the hair is a hop
requested and what I could do is say
look let's roll this into there so you
know there's only a hop requested if we
could request the hop meaning we're not
already in the middle of a hop and we're
gonna want to now a little bit we'll
talk about that later but we don't
actually probably want you to have to
finish your previous hop before
requesting an S top so you know I'll
make a note of that that's again this is
I've said many times not a game designer
so I am NOT trying to tell you anything
game design really need I'm just trying
to tell you game implementation related
the feel of controls is important and
the player doesn't want to have to wait
till the full height of the hop has
completed before notching over to get
the next one
necessarily so if they're just about to
land
the knotch left again like they top left
they mile hop look again you want to let
them have a little bit of leeway there
now you don't want them to have all the
leeway because you want them to have the
ability to change their mind so if they
click left twice in the middle of this
hop and then like by the time they land
there's like a monster there and they
really shouldn't do that you don't want
to remember that hop and force them to
hop right so they need you need to
basically pick what feels right when
you're playing it in terms of what's
good for forgiveness but not something
that feels very laggy right it's got to
be that that nice middle ground between
the two of those and so that's just
something that you need to make sure
that you've polished when you're when
you get the code right so anyway in here
we've got the hop requested code if
we're going to request the hop then what
we're going to need to do is is build a
hop target and the hot target is going
to be wherever the body is plus the
Delta so we've got this DDP normal which
is telling us that direction and that
direction needs to be moved out by a
certain amount so I don't know how far
we want to move that out but it's
probably something like two units to
look there for traversable and we'll see
how we want to do that exactly right and
yeah there's a couple of the things in
here that we need to talk about but
roughly speaking that's what we want to
do okay
so you can actually see that this is
sort of working now right and I can
actually hop exactly how I wanted to hop
and the hop takes a little too long but
one of the things about this game that I
don't know yet is whether hop speed will
be so yeah well there's a lot of things
so first of all I don't know whether
you'll be allowed to hop diagonally but
I suspect the answer is no so I probably
have to get rid of that because with the
analog stick you can and so I'll
probably have to yet make that not
happen you're only really supposed to be
going on Cardinals in this game so that
actually feels very good right now
actually it feels so much better than
the old way it's kind of a little bit
frightening to think about what a small
change can different what a small change
that's it how much difference a small
change can make in terms of whether you
want to actually play something or not
we got to fix that camera it doesn't
understand big rooms for some reason now
and that's like yeah yes so anyway sorry
I'm being distracted by the fact that
it's kind of fun to hop around now
anyway so there's a couple things that I
don't know about so just playing with
this and I really want to emphasize that
every step of the way that I'm not a
game designer so please don't take my
advice on anything game design related I
will say that repeatedly every time
we're working on anything that's game
design related so I'm just calling
it like I see it here as a player of
games and that is that and and I'm
harkening back to something that a good
game designer said which is John blow he
often says that like the important thing
to do is you have to like experience
things and follow them right rather than
back then you you can't always be going
towards a goal that you've predetermined
you have to be willing to follow what
feels right in an experience and he
could say it better than I could because
it's his idea not mine but one of the
things that I'm just noticing here is
like I wanted you to be able to do that
kind of dodge by just holding down the
button but it feels nice to hop like it
feels nice to be able to hop by holding
down the button and so that's making me
reconsider what I was going to say about
about holding to dodge it's a problem
because I wanted you to be able to dodge
without moving but maybe the game just
needs to not do that I mean maybe the
dodge is like left and then you come
back you go like that right I don't know
so that's that's a problem because yeah
I feel like now I want to be able to
hold down the button and go so I'm not
sure how you would dodge
we move this guy so yeah I'm not sure
how you would dodge at that point
so if you're on a controller I think it
would be pretty easy which is to say you
just have a clutch I suppose like I like
maybe like the trigger for example you
just hold it down and then you'd let the
head dodge on the keyboard maybe you'd
hold the spacebar oh god what did I just
do
I detached my head my head is now a
snake that's jumping around I don't want
to know what happened there so the
keyboard is a little bit of an issue
there
you know shift in space I suppose you
could have either of those to do that
[Music]
I mean that isn't my first choice cuz I
really don't like games that proliferate
the number of buttons you know I mean
like I don't know if you guys have
played a triple a game recently but if
you go play something that's like you
know even to take a game I thought was
pretty decent like I mentioned horizon
zero dawn in terms of really great
graphics the other day I thought they
did a beautiful job with them you know
there's like this orgy of controls that
happens and like every last thing on a
controller is mapped and like it's
you're in the middle of a battle and
like you're pushing like this button and
that button down as well like the actual
push button version of these is
happening both bumpers and both triggers
are in play the d-pad and then you know
and you're just it's nuts right and like
I can usually manage it because I've
been playing games all my life and I get
used to it and it's okay but still kind
of annoying but then like you know your
hand like controller to someone who just
wants to play a game
who easily could have played like Super
Mario Brothers because it's like a d-pad
and two buttons and like forget it right
I mean it's nuts how many things if you
haven't played a recent game that you do
and and so I don't want to end up in any
kind of scenario where there's all these
buttons but given the fact that I can't
think of any other way to do it
I could see allowing one clutch button
for dodge because it just seems like
it's gonna feel better and I think it'd
be pretty easy because I could make I
could make basically anything anything
on the you know left or right trigger or
bumper all of those on this thing could
all be the clutch so anything that you
hit was fine you didn't have to be
specific about it I don't know so it's
that's a tough decision again that's
really the kind of thing
that I think is more appropriate for a
game designer to be worrying about and
not me but in this circumstance I
suppose there's not a lot I can really
do about that so I've got to have
something so I'm just gonna go ahead and
say for now I will introduce a clutch
key it's not my first choice but that's
just because I get not because I think
things are wrong with it in the abstract
but just because it proliferates the
number of buttons and I was kind of like
hoping this game would be a game where
you just have a d-pad for movement and
then any button you hit punches in that
direction so it's extremely simple and
anyone can understand it and they don't
have to be some kind of like you know
dude who has their picture on a face of
monster you know their face on a monster
energy drink carton to be able to like
play this game right and so I'm gonna go
ahead and say that it's okay to have the
clutch button in there and I'll expose
that through the platform layer but I
don't really want to go nuts with that
so I'm really gonna try to make this be
the last thing that we have here so
looking at this we've got sort of the
up-down left-right up-down left-right
for the for the game here but we got the
shoulders the shoulder buttons there and
then we've got this button state so I
don't really know it looks like the sort
of triggers are not mapped right
so I think that would have to be mapped
in here right so if we've got a stick
average so I'm just gonna clean these up
to our new types so you've got stick
average I think I'm gonna have to say
clutch average and just point out this
like eg triggers or spacebar yeah I I
claim that this is okay because yeah
like my not a game designer get out of
jail free card allows me to just kind of
say I'm just doing what feels right here
and I don't pretend to speak for people
who know what they're doing in terms of
making design decisions that is not the
point of handmade Hiro and I do not want
to argue with anyone about it so please
take that argument somewhere else about
whether it's appropriate to be using
these buttons or not because I don't
want to hear it and don't care but in
this particular case I just feel like
that's what I want to do and since it is
programming I feel free to do it because
this is a programming stream so in here
we've got how the d-pad is coming out
and you can see here that I'm going to
switch over here because it's code
that's kind of going behind my head too
much and it's making it hard for me to
see it as well so I'm just going over
here you can see that we've got the the
controller being read out and we beat
out here digital buttons for things like
the X input d-pad and the X input
buttons but we're not really looking
anywhere for anything else right like
we're not looking for those trigger
buttons I don't think anywhere else so
if you take a look at the X input
gamepad stuff here what we should see in
there I think we've got that in here
somewhere
and put pink that we have that anywhere
no so that's probably something in the X
input Docs that we did not just cut and
paste in yeah so we're actually opening
up that text input stuff that's no big
deal I'll just open up that Docs and
what I want to do is I want to read out
those triggers and they're simple this
will take 10 seconds it's not a
complicated thing to tube it's exactly
like the analog sticks they're just
values that we read out of that struct
so I'm gonna go ahead in here and say
include X input dot H again using my
magical search feature here let's here
include and then so all I'm gonna do is
just say look tell me where X input
gamepad is using like the Browse info
here so you can see here here's the
example gamepad you can see the
thumbsticks
are here and those we are looking at and
you can see that those are signed values
so those are actually shorts so that's
because you know the x position goes
negative positive so they just decided
to represent it that way the triggers
can only go down right they can't go up
from their rest position so they chose
to represent those as purely unsigned
values those are unsigned values that
just go from 0 to 255 at maximum push so
we know we got V left trigger and B
right trigger and I'm just gonna verify
the B left trigger and right trigger
don't get you yeah and they don't right
I so we're not using those currently as
I suspected so I am going to go ahead
and just use that now for that purpose
and you can see here we've got the stick
average stuff process stick value we've
got a dead zone in there and that's the
dead zone for
that's the deadzone that's prescribed or
[Music]
do we not read the right thumbstick I
guess we don't read the right thumbstick
all right well um we've got a dead zone
that's prescribed there by the ex input
system that we're kind of lazily
applying there and I don't know whether
we want round or not and there's a bunch
of stuff that we might want to do there
but it's not really probably going to
matter a whole lot for this game so it's
not really worth worrying about point
being what we want to do here is we want
to take the stick average stuff here we
want to go ahead and take those those be
left trigger and be right trigger values
again these are bytes and what I'm gonna
do is since I don't care which one
you're holding down and I want you to
just use whichever one you feel more
comfortable because you know they're not
gonna do different things it's the
clutch button is whichever one you want
what I want to do is I want to make it
so that whichever one you're pushing if
you push it down far enough it works
right so what that means is I don't want
to add them together right because if I
add them together then pushing either
down just a little bit might result in a
clutch and that's not what supposed to
happen
right what I want to do is make it so
that if either one is pushed down far
enough so what I want to do is look at
that whichever one's pushed down the
furthest look at that one and if that
one's pushed down far enough then you're
good to go
so what I want to do is take a look at
the pad here and I want to say like
let's start with the left trigger and
then I'll say okay if being right
trigger was actually greater than that
then we'll take that one instead right
so I just I just take whichever ones
bigger and off we go so then from there
I'll say all right on the new controller
we now have
the clutch average it's not really
clutch average it's clutch max so
because that's what makes more sense in
this case so I'm gonna I'm gonna change
the name of that just to be a little
little clearer here right so the clutch
mass max in this case is just gonna be
whatever that maximum trigger value was
and then I'm gonna just divide that out
by the maximum that it could be which is
to 255 right so that lets me know like a
range of what's pushed and we'll decide
you know maybe if it's greater than
halfway its clutch maybe it's only a
quarter of the way I don't know how far
we want to go but that's all it's gonna
do so we don't need a dead zone on it
because the whole control itself is a
dead zone we're just gonna tune that to
be however far we want to be so we don't
need us best dead zone there because the
actual control further down the line is
gonna apply that dead zone for us in a
sense okay now if we have this clutch
max value being set for these guys we're
also gonna need the clutch max value set
for the control for the keyboard so we
need because we need a way of having
that happen as well so we've got a
spacebar a situation here so I'm gonna
take a look at where that happens so you
can see VK space here and that's
controlling the start key so we're gonna
have to change that so I want VK enter
to now be the start button and we need
VK space to be something else so hitting
return will start because the spacebar
it's not gonna be clutch and I mean to
be honest we could use the clutch for
this purpose as well so that's kind of
neither here nor there but for the
moment I'm just gonna say that that's
that's mapping
so VK space will now do processing on
the will do pressing on whether or not
the clutch is gonna be there
and what I don't quite remember in this
case is is there anything else yeah I
don't know if there's anything else I
really want to set there so what I want
to do here is if we can look at the
wintery to process keyboard message bit
here you can see this like this half
winter view prosecutor message this half
transition state stuff we don't actually
care about that very much so what we
really want to do is just cold set the
keyboard controller so that the clutch
max value is just whether it's down or
not so if it's down on any given frame
it's at full clutch if it's up if it's
not down it's at no clutch at all and
off we go right
is it DK return oops that's not handmade
hero
right so in theory now we're good to go
on that and you know in in theory there
is the clutch value now so if I am like
hopping around now what I want to do is
make it so that the clutch value would
switch me to dodging so I'm gonna go
ahead and do that I'm gonna go in here
and take a look at inside the brain code
the hop requested stuff basically what
I'm saying is if you have the clutch
down you cannot request a hop okay
that's just right it's just not gonna
happen uh so what I want to do is say
all right hop requested has yet another
thing on here which is that I you know
the the level of down miss of the clutch
will control that so that's where I'm
looking for dodging maybe so dodging
will be false and by default you're not
dodging if we did get input here then
what we're going to do is we will look
to see at the end if whatever the
controller is doing here patroller yeah
whatever the controller is doing here if
I take a look at clutch max if that's
greater than whatever I don't know what
it is
then dodging is going to become true and
so then when we get down here we can
just use well we know we'll set that to
something intelligent up there
eventually and so from here we can just
say look if you're not dodging then we
can do the stuff we were doing before
otherwise you're gonna stay in one place
and now I can test to see whether that's
actually working if we flip back to the
game running here so here I'm walking
around and so when I push down the
clutch you can see now I am just dodging
right
okay uh so
so I think that's all fine and let me
just test the keyboard version of that
as well just to make sure the spacebar
parts working so if I'm hopping around
here and I push the space bar that
totally didn't work oh right of course
that's not going to work because I
actually need to record whether I don't
remember what happens to that keyboard
state over time so how does that persist
or not persist
so yeah you can see here how the
keyboard processing works
actually wait that's not keyboard
processing that's mouse processing why
is that called keyboard processing what
why did we call this keyboard processing
this is mouse button processing right I
mean look at it there's no keyboard
processing yeah
that's why comments suck they're always
wrong so anyway if we take a look in the
actual processing for the keyboard code
because this is Mouse position but
that's mouse button right what I
actually want to do here is is figure
out how those keyboard controllers work
so you can see this is the part that is
problematic for us we want this keyboard
stuff to work properly as well so the
for every keyboard controller
that we have here yeah you can see we
want the state to persist and I think
that's what's doing it for the other
buttons so what we want to do in this
case is we want to say like alright the
new keyboard controller clutch max
equals the old keyboard controller
clutch max because we just assume that
if we haven't gotten another message
then that's what it is
right so we need to persist that value
forward
don't ask me why our gloves stayed there
probably because we don't move the glove
now or something so here's what I will
say if it's a little concerning about
this is it doesn't feel that good to
dodge on the keyboard it feels actually
pretty good on the controller I like it
on the controller
[Music]
and you know maybe that's okay cuz you
know this is a game that probably is
meant to be played on the controller but
you know maybe there's a better way to
do dodge on the keyboard I'm gonna leave
that maybe to figure out a little bit
later yeah that just feels awesome this
game feels really nice with the
controller now
um I just I really just don't know what
to make of it on the keyboard side of
things cuz I kind of had this idea about
how it would work and it's definitely
not gonna work that way now you know
maybe I just give the you the option of
doing you know I'm sort of playing with
it here and like I could see maybe using
the right shift key as a clutch as well
you know maybe if I just give you enough
keys like left and right shift and space
bar are all like clutches maybe there's
always one that kind of feels ok to hit
[Music]
so I really don't know you know I'll go
ahead and throw those in there because
maybe it's the right thing to do but I
don't really know so I'm just gonna go
ahead and do that because I feel like
spacebar just it doesn't quite feel
right to hold down the spacebar while
you're doing the dodge and you know the
other thing you could do is maybe maybe
one another way to think about dodging
would be like if you just like spam if
you hold down like the the punch key or
something I know III don't have a I
don't have an idea for it I really don't
but while we're in here I'll just I'll
go ahead and and throw shift on there as
well so if you get an up-or-down message
from either of those now probably what I
should do is use the state of the
keyboard you know like if we if you
Union some keys together in this way
then what we probably want to do here is
actually check for those check for those
keys here
like this so basically if I get a
message for space or shift what I want
to avoid is if you push down the shift
key then push down the spacebar then let
go of the shift key but don't let go of
the spacebar that should probably still
be dodging right so I don't want to
assume that the last up message we get
means it's up if we haven't received up
messages from everybody else yet right
so what I want to do is I want to
essentially do something that looks a
little bit like this so we say look if
space or shift either of those two is
down then the clutch is down right and
that way it's not gonna like take which
ever one comes up first as meaning it's
up so now if I hit shift it's down right
clutch is still down in holding space I
let go of shift I'm still in clutch I
let go of space I'm in clutch I'm out of
flat rather right and so we'll just use
that for now and that seems fine so I'm
just going to call that good for now if
you don't like it call a game designer
that's their job not mine and I'm not
responsible for those kinds of decisions
now what I want to do now is allow the
dodging and the hopping to work a little
bit more fluidly we don't have to do the
thing that I said at the beginning which
is to look to see whether or not whether
or not a timer has elapsed because now
we're saying look there's a button for
it period right and so what I want to do
now is just kind of make the feel a
little bit more fluid you'll notice that
right now we just move the head and the
body doesn't lean so I can put that in
there and I also put a little bit of
crouch down on the clutch so there's a
couple things I just kind of want to do
there
kind of like rounded out a little bit
this turned out to be easier than if I
was gonna be so it looks like it'll all
base to be done today I mean I got I
don't know 10 20 minutes left or
something so yeah we kind of did what I
was planning I thought it might take a
couple days of programming to get it to
where I wanted but it's pretty much
there so again come up say sube we come
on down here and you can see all this
code that's in the if zero what I want
to do is just take a look at the the
code for the leanin direct direction
right and kind of get that bit in there
so when we look at this here you can see
that there was sort of a a head distance
thing that was getting created here like
how far the head was away and there's
like a bob delta and all this stuff and
a floor displacement and all this sort
of nonsense and so what I need to kind
of do is look at how that stuff was
working and just put this back in there
now it looks to me like this might be
somewhat isolated like I don't know if I
can just rename a like this code for
example and pretty much be done I'm not
quite sure I'm gonna look and see what I
don't remember much of what this stuff
is doing so we'll see yeah so so
basically the code that kind of
stretched him out along the way and and
did the dodging and so on that's just
still in there right
and so what I kind of need to do now is
probably like figure out a way to
indicate that you can't go diagonally I
mean another thing I could do just not
let you go diagonally and not feel the
need to indicate it at all but that's
another story but basically yeah this is
all I wanted and we don't really I think
when I I got to put some new art in
there
this is the old art that's not really
drawn at the right perspective so I'm
not too worried about the weird look of
that I just want to make sure that it's
stretching properly and it looks like it
is the moment right so I think that's
all good
so I think that's all I wanted to do
with that part of the code so I don't
know the rest of this stuff here so all
of this can just go like I don't care
about any of this
[Music]
let's just eliminate dead code here so I
don't care about any of these things I
don't know what the recenter timer is
anymore and I don't think we care about
it so I'm going to delete that as well
in fact let's just let's just get rid of
that wholesale so that's just not in
there anymore
all right and so we've got this other
code still in there the head DDP the
head doesn't get a DDP any more that's
just not a thing so I don't care about
any of this the movement mode
[Music]
is already handled above I think I don't
want any of that the bob parts so that
might be something I kind of want to do
so let me just look
I'm not sure what body DP ever actually
does so let's take it one step at a time
I'm going to leave this out for a moment
and then I'll get rid of em anything in
there that I don't like yep that's all
good and so the body DP part I don't
think matters the this part here we were
adjusting the DDT Bob value of the body
based on some head distance stuff and
I'm not sure what that really needed to
do so yeah I don't think we need that
but let's see what happens with it in
the first place it's just some micro
control stuff for like adjusting the
bounce I think
so it's fine I mean we can leave it in
there
getting some weird lighting effects on
that I wonder if we have some bugs there
or if that's just because when this gets
far enough away they're sort of hitting
an aggregate light value that that is
not properly shadowed right like our
aggregate light volume stuff is probably
a little bit bad you know but
occasionally I see some lighting
happening here that probably shouldn't
be happening
not sure how concerned I should be about
it but anyway so that seems fine anyway
so I think that's all fine what I do
want to do here is look at the DDT Bob
stuff I I want that squishiness for the
Dodge I want that to maybe be a little
bit related to Klutch max so yeah like
I'm gonna take a look inside the env
stuff for the movement mode and just
look at how this is working
sooo it looks like I could just hold set
the t-bob value if I wanted to
[Music]
what I want is when you hold down the
clutch button I want him to kind of
compress relative to that that push and
I'm just not sure if I want to like dig
into that code much right now or not but
like the t-bob value I'm just gonna like
see like just play around tell it so
let's say I just cold set the t-bob
value just straight up and I set that to
be whatever the clutch max is so maybe
like in here we have you know when we
get the controller out I will just say
okay the clutch level equals the
controller clutch max just in general
and okay so t-bob going up it actually
makes that go up and the head doesn't
actually go up or down based on that
value but I could probably displace them
a little bit
so I guess what I would say is let's
suppose I did the head is the body P
plus a deep GDP plus some nominal value
I don't know what it is
that's a Z displacement and the Z
displacement is going to be times the
clutch level right I and specifically
probably the inverse of the clutch level
so the further the harder you press on
the clutch the further the head will go
down
yeah that's that's more what I'm looking
for there and then I'll set the t-bob
value to kind of mirror that so you know
and in fact I can do it in watch here
which just like says all right you know
if you want something that counter
varies with the clutch you can have that
and so here you can see me setting the
thing to the Bob value I'm gonna set it
to the inverse clutch level I'm at that
as well and I don't really want to get
rid of the bobbing feel for the body so
I want to not quite override it like
that I'm just doing that at first right
so you can see this way we have you can
have like visual confirmation of the
clutch going down just because otherwise
I mean it's just kind of like you're hey
it's down I think right so having visual
confirmation of the clutch going down so
you can dodge more confidently is all
I'm looking for there right and you can
see we've lost the springiness now and
that's because of this line over Mt Bob
so what I want to do here is say like
that there's like a concept of whatever
the clutch Fat Bob value is right and I
want the key Bob value to say like don't
whatever that value is I want you to
make sure that you aren't going to go
above it if you're dodging I guess
I mean really what I want to do is set
this as a target in this case and not in
the other cases so I think I probably
want to like as we kind of do a little
bit more with the animation floors there
so it's probably not quite what you
really want in this case but what I'm
gonna do is say all right we set a
clutch Bob target if we're dodging then
you know maybe it sets it if we're not
maybe we don't maybe that's what I'll do
for now but we may want some fancier
yeah so we're gonna want something
fancier than that and I guess we'll see
what happens when we when we put some
art in there we may want do some other
stuff right
so what I the only other thing I think I
need to do now is I want to prevent you
from being to go diagonally because I
don't think you're supposed to be able
to go diagonally in this game ever
it's supposed to be Cardinal movement
only so what I'd like to do there is
kind of snap you to one or the other so
when we talk about the movement there
you can see we've got the hop requested
part this DDP normal I guess I need to
kind of do another yet one more step on
there and maybe the DDP normal value
should just need this in general but I'm
gonna just introduce another value which
is like like a D target value that'll be
two times it'll be this value to start
with but it's gonna threshold its two
values so basically it'll say like if
the absolute value of D target X is
greater than the absolute value of D
target Y so basically just looking at
whichever component is greater right
then all zero the other one so whichever
one's greater gets the preference and
that's the direction you go and that'll
just prevent you from moving on a
diagonal so you know I can still use the
analog stick like I'm using here but if
I try to go diagonally it just goes in
whatever direction you go you sort of
are mostly pushing in if that makes
sense and then the player will just know
they can't go diagonally so you know no
harm no foul right
now whether I don't know if I want the
head to reflect the fact that you can't
or not we can cross that bridge later
but for now hey that's fine all right so
that's good I'm happy with that let's go
ahead and go to Q&amp;A I think we're almost
done
two minutes left if anyone has any
questions
hmm in Subodh is doing some good stuff
there feller on for the win failfish are
you planning on having a jump command no
everything this character does jumps so
in some sense there are only jump
commands a Celeron was just you know how
nowadays they have like Core i5 and core
i7 and stuff like that
Celeron was just a previous sort of
version of that kind of branding where
there were slower or perhaps more
power-efficient or whatever but it
wasn't the high performance version
that's all Celeron was if I remember
correctly so they were basically like
you know what a maybe an i3 or an i5 is
today is what a Celeron it's just
branding it was just a way of creating a
more readily consumer identifiable name
for the difference between a Pentium and
a seller on or would you know like those
kinds of things Intel's not very good at
that they tend to not name things very
understandable for the average person
and so I don't ask me why they don't try
harder on stuff like that but you know
it's just how it is
there were some questions around b3 2 X
versus B 32 at some point B 32 X is just
saying that I don't care how big this
value is I just am storing a boolean in
it yes it's like yes or no it's a true
or false value but I don't care how much
space it takes so use whatever the most
convenient thing is for the processor be
32 on the other hand says use exactly 32
bits to store this boolean period even
if the processor would rather store it
as 64 bits or something else right how
about a dive and slide command I want as
few of commands as possible so it was
just gonna be dodging move ideally so
hopefully no but I you know I don't put
any control remapping interface
probably not we will probably do some
support for other keyboards because not
everyone has like WASD in the same place
but I know you're viewing comments but I
often see you asked myself what was all
that about when looking at old code
wouldn't be beneficial to comment now
yourself no because it's wrong that's
it's the same problem always comments
are old widow
I would totally use comments if I
compiler check them to see if they
actually were accurate but they it
doesn't so commenting old code is
usually worse because the comments are
probably also wrong which means now it
will mislead you into thinking it does
something else so I try to just always
reread the code and figure out what it
did shut up 4 6 7 what is the reason of
pure C I think see both pluses OOP and
procedural coverage much better so I
don't like it I don't think it's a good
language that's why I don't use it if
you like it then well no one's stopping
you if you don't care how much space of
bool is why not use b8x
the reason for that is just because
sometimes they move in between so for
example a lot of times I'll do some
comparison of two 32-bit file
and then put that into Brule and I want
that to stay 32-bits so the processor
would keep it clean through right so
typically I try to make everything b32
it's kind of like as if you were simply
programming it you want all of your
lanes to be the same so typically I try
to keep it as the same Lane size always
throughout so if I was using you eights
I'd probably use a v8 right
we eventually make these input commands
event-driven what do you mean by
event-driven I'm not sure I understand
the question
I'm in here what do you think are the
disadvantage of samosas compared to see
isn't see basically subsets useless yeah
so you know I've talked about this many
many many many many times before so go
look at the episode guide if you want to
hear more about it but generally
speaking yes see is more or less a
subset of C++ and I actually use C++
like these are this is actually
compiling as C++ so I'm not compiling a
C I just don't like the features that
C++ added because they're crappy so it's
it's not that I don't compile my code to
see much less I do some people don't
some people actually compile their code
to see so you know that's a different
thing I actually still use C++ per se
meaning it is a C++ file compiled with a
C++ compiler I just don't use most C++
features because I don't like them I
don't think they're effective if that
makes sense
like if I wrote the book effective C++
it would just be empty right there'd be
one page in it that says you see and
that would be it right so it's it's
mostly that right it's it's mostly just
about what I think is good in the
language and what I don't use features
that I don't think are good and I don't
think the features that C++ added to see
we're good I think they were all pretty
lousy which is not to say that I that
there aren't miles worth of features of
that I would add to see it's just simple
stuff didn't add any of them right
there's so many features I would add to
C and C bus plus added like none of them
so that's why I don't use it
they added things in the vicinity of
what I want like you know they they
added metaprogramming like stuff with
templates they just did it all wrong and
so I would actually rather have no meta
programming than their meta programming
right and you know they I like dispatch
tables but they added them as
inheritance based vitae
which I don't like so I don't use them
right so you know C++ is kind of CMOS
this is an example of a language that
every time there was something I would
have added they added the wrong version
of it such that I would just prefer not
to use it but there were good versions
of all the things they added they just
didn't add those they added crappy ones
and so I don't use it long boolean
something I thought of of course it is a
gameplay thing type to you you could
have the Dodge double as an attack or
have it push enemies away in the
direction of the Dodge it's not a bad
idea we'll have to see how it progresses
I'll keep it in mind since you
interviewed Pat Wyatt in 2015 handmade
Khan have you ever thought about copying
the Guild Wars fo z axis configuration
so do I know what that is I don't know
if I know what the guild war is foes the
axis configuration is so I mean the
answer to answer the question literally
no I have not thought about copying it
because I don't think I know what that
is what is that
what is happening with C++ templates
that shouldn't be
isn't it just generating code based on
the temp remembers yeah so I mean to be
specific about C++ templates
the problem with C++ templates is that
the way that meta programming it needs
to work is it has to work across
elements so basically in order for a
meta programming system to have any
important level of power it has to be
able to do things like look at the call
graph it has to be able to do things
like introspection and C++ added like
literally the most useless part of meta
programming which is passing a type as
at compile time right and it's just
really benign and like ineffectual it's
like it's it's like the least useful
thing you can do in meta programming and
then they tried to like build everything
on top of it for some reason it's
laughable how bad it is like even really
basic stuff like like injection and
stuff you can't even do right so like
you know a really typical thing you'd
want to be able to do with meta
programming to say hey I want to insert
a linked list linkage like a next at a
previous into an existing type and like
you can't even come close to doing that
C++ there they're like years away from
even thinking about how to do that right
and that's like meta programming 101
right so I don't know I mean I think it
was just it was written by people who'd
never done Megha Mehta part name before
it's what I think in fact I kind of know
that's true um maybe to a certain extent
so but you know what what do you think
about nd component systems as the engine
architecture how would you implement
this if you don't use inheritance sorry
if it's off topic well so the problem
with that is I'm not sure what you mean
by entity component systems because
different people mean different things
from my experience when they say that
but I guess I would just ask why do you
think you need inheritance to make an
empathy component system can't you just
have an enum that says what the type is
like I mean what why do you think that
inheritance would be something that's
required ever really but just even
especially in that case I recently
learned about imperfect shadowed maps I
wonder if that could be a substitute for
Ray casting in the current lighting
system at least on the GPU so not really
because remember we don't have
individual light sources everything in
the game can be an emitter if it wants
to be so shadow maps don't really work I
don't remember which one in perfect
shadow maps are so I apologize if they
somehow allow everything in the world to
be an emitter but I assume they don't
because I assume they still take some
shadow maps if I remember correctly I
could be wrong about that
any other questions
400 viewers that does seem like a pretty
high number for your average Sunday
the flame 937 even if you don't do
Network for the game but you do some
lecture about it probably not because I
am NOT a network game programmer so you
know I mean I know how to do basic
networking stuff because I've made
things that you know do land-based
networking for various reasons like
tools and stuff like that but generally
speaking I don't do that sort of stuff
for a living right so on a handmade hero
I try to stick with things I'm at least
fairly comfortable with and I certainly
would never give a lecture on stuff like
you know I'm here we do some stuff that
are not my job like lighting isn't
something I typically do right so you
know I'm not an expert on it but we need
to do something for the game so I did it
right and it's probably not the best you
know if you went and asked you know
somebody to do I don't know like like
let's say you ask someone from the the
ed tech team to do the lighting or
something right they the or maybe like
an Nvidia research guide to do the
lighting or something right they would
do a better job on the algorithm than I
would cuz that's what they spend all
their time doing right but I'm okay with
you know it's important to be versatile
as a programmer so I'm okay with showing
how to do stuff that maybe isn't my
strong suit but just so you have some
familiarity with kind of just how it
goes
networking I've literally never done any
network game programming on any
significant scale like anything that had
to really be played on the internet I've
never worked on that side and I so I
wouldn't even really know what to tell
you it's something that you at least
need some experience having done
real-world stuff to really know what to
program and so you know if there was a
reason to show you how to duel and
networking we could do that but there
really isn't
cuz nobody does that there's no such
thing as land only games anymore games
are either couch co-op meaning they just
run on one machine or they play over the
Internet and land parties are just too
rare for a game to be only land party
based right so no I'm probably never
gonna cover that and the reason is just
because it's really something you need
to have done in order to say anything
about it sending packets back and forth
takes like 10 seconds anyone can do it
that's not the hard part like getting
through mats and figuring out what to do
about you know packet loss and rate
limiting and replay attacks and blah
blah blah blah blah like all that stuff
you just you kind of need to have some
experience having done and so I really
have nothing to say about it it's
something you don't have to learn
somewhere else what are your current
thoughts on jei I don't have any yet I
am really happy that it's happening and
I hope it becomes popular even if it's
only slightly better than C and C++ it's
still very welcome and so you know I
hope it does well I hope it becomes a
viable option to ship your games on I
would love to not have to care about all
the ridiculous decisions of C++
standards committee makes all the time
right and so having something nice to
turn to that was a viable alternative
would be fantastic
so don't have much thoughts other than I
hope it works out with the capabilities
of mobile games exponentially increasing
what are the decision factors that
result in games being ported to mobile
well I mean most of the that's really a
business question you know and so you'd
be better off asking a person who does
game business stuff but generally
speaking if you just look at it
objectively the problem with mobile is
the market right so there's zero price
support on games in the mobile space so
it doesn't make a lot of sense to ship a
call
there that's just not something you get
rewarded for on Steam if you ship a
quality game you can still often times
have someone pay $15 for it that's
really important that's that's a very
important thing on an iPhone no one will
pay $15 for anything ever under any
circumstances it just doesn't happen
right a lot of times you have to slow
your game for like $2.99 or just free
right and that's just Apple and androids
fault for not curating their store well
for not promoting high-priced games well
that like that's just strictly a failure
of those companies to curate their
market space to be fair that's not what
they care about they just care that you
use their phones and look at their ads
and stuff like that so they're doing
probably the right thing from their
perspective it's just not the right
thing from a person who wants to sell
games on their platform and so what I
think is much more germane to the
decision has nothing to do with whether
the phone can run a game what half has
to do is can your game support ad or
micro transaction based economies
because that's the only way you're
probably gonna succeed over there once
in a great while you might be able to
make a game that some people buy in an
iPad for $9.99 maybe but most of the
time what you're looking to do is to
make games for that platform that are
designed to make money in other ways
like you know farmville kinds of stuff
right and so I think that's really what
ends up happening and one of the reasons
I think that a lot of people don't port
their PC games over there has nothing to
do with the fact that they couldn't port
them over they probably could they just
still think they make any money cuz the
store over there is a joke right it's
like a sort of race to the bottom low
pricing manipulate your users into
spending money other ways kind of thing
or show ads all over it and they just
don't want to do that necessarily right
uh it's a shame I wish they had made a
thriving marketplace for gamers on
mobile I wish they had done that they
didn't do it so now it's just a lot less
likely that people will poor quality
games to mobile if they don't see a way
to kind of have some other market there
you know it's not to say you can't do it
there are some examples but it's just
rare
a lot of people you know just don't
think it's gonna be worth their time
because if they're if they're not gonna
make enough money off of it if they
don't do something like shove ads in
there or make microtransactions be a
thing right and they may not want to do
those things or their game just might
not that may ruin their game right those
things might ruin the game for them
right what are your thoughts on rust I
don't really have any I haven't looked
at it much what was it C was missing
that makes you compile using C++ not
much honestly when I started using C++ C
didn't even have stuff like declare
anywhere and I do think like declare
anywhere is a good idea I also like
function overloading because I like to
be able to have the same name take two
different sets of parameters so that
people can just still use the same name
to call it there's a couple things like
that that I think are worth changing and
so I guess what I would say is in the
most modern versions of C probably have
the things I would want and I probably
could compile and see robably I'm not
sure but like there's enough stuff in
the base level C++ stuff operator
overloading for vector types like that
sort of thing is useful so I'll do like
having those features pretty much
everything else I don't like
s TV doesn't do hinting is there another
lib that supports small text I don't
know OpenType or free free type whatever
the that giant packages OpenType free
type open free type free open type free
type open up probably does hinting I
don't know get a higher res screen and
call it a day all right time to wrap it
up and stretch as well
okay free type free type there we go
yeah free type probably does that I
don't know how many types of enemies
enemies are you planning on having I
don't know how long have you been coding
since I was seven so so that would be
what 3 plus 31 so 30 34 years I guess
kind of off topic question but here it
goes I've been in the game tooshi
working with studios but now I decided
to make an independent game of my own
and I kind of wanted to make a
Kickstarter do you have any
recommendation that I do not I've never
done a Kickstarter so I do not know all
right I'm gonna wrap it up for today
thank you everyone for joining me for
the upside of handmade Hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along the
series at home you can always pre-order
the game on handmade hero dot org and it
comes with all of the source code that I
update every night so that you can play
around with it and do your own
experimentation we will be back here
next weekend to start working on the
boom creation stuff because like I said
I want him now the movement stuff
wrapped up quicker than I thought like
that's basically all I really wanted for
my movement stuff to be solid like that
for now and I want to just build out
some nice room areas that we can explore
through so I can tighten up the camera
code and the lighting code because those
are going to take a while to sort of
settle in and like I said we got a bunch
of stuff I want do with how we're gonna
place letting computation points and
then we got to make the lighting effect
the entities properly so there's just a
lot of bookkeeping that's gonna go on
there and in order to do it right I feel
like we need to have some real like
level geometry stuff that's plausible in
there that then I and have it so that I
can actually have the code that like
places walls actually put lighting
points intelligently throughout those
and so on so that's what we're gonna
continue pushing towards next weekend so
up see everyone back here for that until
then have fun programming and I'll see
everyone on the internet take it easy
everybody