alright hello everyone and welcome to
hand made here oh sure we code a
complete game live on stream you may
have noticed we've got a Kickstarter
going right now for those of you
interested in comics you might want to
check it out Anna and I I'm working on
it for the past year or so and there's a
print edition up now so there's a banner
on the handmade hero page so if you
visit the handmade hero page is pretty
easy to find we're gonna jump right into
the coding today we have a bunch of work
we can do now we set ourselves up to do
some optimization of our rendering pass
well specifically the lighting the ray
casting in our rendering pass and we
actually set ourselves up to call the
entire path actually so one of the
interesting things is we can now also
work in isolated fashion on optimizing
the texture processing if we want to so
that's all pretty good stuff so we now
have this HH light prof and if we
actually run that you can see if we go
to the handmade directory and we have
like a debug dump here that we dumped of
all of our lighting data which i think
is included right now I don't know if
it's a go to the get up asking lease
included in the it's probably including
the github but it's presumably included
in the zip files that you download from
send owl or you can take those dumps
yourself using the source code depending
on how you're doing it but once you get
those dumps we can actually run our HH
Lite prof executable it will load those
dumps it will do a Texel match to see to
what extent were agreeing with our
previous results so for example if we
look at this number and it's relatively
low we're in fairly good shape and then
it will tell us how long it took to do
things and you can see here how many
seconds elapsed total and basically what
this is doing is it's just taking the
thing that handmade hero does for
lighting every frame and it just runs at
a ton of time so it runs it for you know
seven seconds and it just keeps running
it running it running it running it and
the reason for that is just because it
runs so fast normally because you know
anything that has to run at 30 frames a
second or 60 frames a second is probably
already down to the to the point even
before we
mine's at hardcore where it's you know
it's running fast enough that it's hard
to time because the variants that you're
going to get in there is a little bit
too much so we're just running it lots
of times so that we can kind of smooth
that variance out a little bit and get
somewhat consistent run times out of it
so we can see how our changes actually
affect things so what I'd like to do is
I'd like to take a look today a little
bit more at just reducing the amount of
computation that we're actually doing
here there's a couple of different
things that we can do that we haven't
really looked at yet and so if we look
at how our lighting solutions actually
working we can actually go to the the
raycast
and and see this right now we did the
work already of splitting it into two
types of loops you can see those loops
operating here and there's a whole bunch
of stuff that's not immediately clear
out of it I hope that most people
watched last week because it's gonna be
kind of hard for me to explain what's
going on here if you haven't seen it all
but what I can try to do to bring you up
to speed a little bit is there's two
signs of the loop in the Ray caster and
one side of the loop which is actually
represented by the first part here is
actually the part that does the Ray
casting against our actual like volumes
we hit so this is actually the part that
does all of the Ray casting that can
actually produce results right but then
we have another side of the branch
that's here which is basically the thing
that does all of the Ray casting against
things which categorize space so this
right here is something that categorizes
you know it looks to see which parts of
various structures you're actually going
down right and so this allows us to take
our spatial hierarchy and pass it and
figure out which parts of the spatial
hierarchy need to be examined and which
ones don't and so it's not really
producing actual ray intersections what
it's doing is testing to see whether the
Ray hits a particular region so that we
know whether we need to look at the
things inside that region and that's
recursive right it doesn't actually use
functions to recurse it actually just
keeps a little stack but it's still
doing it recursively in the sense that
it looks at something and then goes
oh if I hit that I'm gonna put more
things on to my stack to process right
so that's the way this is actually
working and what's interesting about
that is it means that we have two
specific two totally different right
specific ways that we're doing our
testing and they don't necessarily have
much to do with each other so if we go
look at something like the lighting box
structure what you can see is that if
you take a look at this here we have
this lighting pack which has this
information in it right and then we have
this stuff which has the P the radius
and the ref color and what we know at
least at the moment is that it's unclear
to us that we ever actually care about
like what we're actually storing here
the Box P and radius what you can see is
that more or less all the time we
actually use that we expand it to box
min and box max and the only time we
ever actually use the p and radius is to
store those to be used finally at the
end when we actually know what our hit
is and so we could trivially reconstruct
those things by just actually storing
min and Max and so the first thing we
may want to do just to get rid of this
cruft like this stuff that's happening
here to get rid of this cruft what we
might want to do is just let's just take
the simple step of saying we're just not
going to do that anymore we're gonna
store box min in box Max and that's it
and also while we're at it let's take a
look at how this thing is working ref
color here also is the kind of thing
that we could look at and say you know
what that's too big
we could easily eliminate some of that
by stuffing that into the lighting box
pack as a u-32 or something like this
right that's just the color value that's
like RGB and like a scaler or something
like that
so it turns out that like this could
also be optimized away in some way that
would make a lot of sense too so there's
other things here that we could do but
for the time being I think the first
change I'd like to make is just get rid
of extraneous computation because as
we're like working through this there's
really no sense in having extraneous
computation and we know that both sides
of our branch are doing this extraneous
computation so it's not like this is
going to be something that we will like
if we decide to separate these two
branches out into completely different
routine
are completely different passes it
doesn't really matter because both sides
want this change so doesn't seem like
there's any downside to it to me right
so what I'm gonna do here is say let's
pretend there's a box min and box max
here where we just say okay we're gonna
go ahead and take this to do and take it
seriously so instead of the radius we're
just gonna get rid of that right and
we're gonna do everywhere that we were
previously filling these out we're just
gonna take the P and radius and do
exactly this so we're gonna say look the
box min is gonna be the P minus radius
right and we're gonna say that the Box
max is going to be the P plus the radius
and that's what we're actually gonna
store so when the person actually gives
us to us we're gonna store it that way
now you may ask a question and it's a
perfectly legitimate question why does
it matter where we do this like if we're
gonna have to do this expansion anyway
like don't we have to back propagate
this to the people actually calling us
or anything like that to order to do the
savings the answer is no because
remember every single ray we trace has
to do this to every box it encounters
whereas this only happens when you
create the box itself so when we
actually push the occluders on each
frame so this happens once per box per
frame this happens once per box per Ray
per frame and since we know we have
thousands tens of thousands but actually
hundreds of thousands of Ray's there's
an extra multiplier of a thousand or ten
thousand or a hundred thousand on here
depending on how many times this box
gets hit so the difference in multiplier
here is massive so doing it once here
versus doing it thousands or tens of
thousand times here that's the savings
I'm looking for right
it's like it just seems obvious to me
that we just want to get rid of that
crust now it may not have much effect
because it could be that this isn't the
slow part but again one of the things
you have to do when you're optimizing
since there's so many variables involved
is just don't do anything obviously
stupid get it out of your way so you
just have to think about it anymore and
this is a clear thing we can just get
out of our way right so what I'm gonna
do now is just get rid of that so that
we're clear about that and then from
then on now here we can just go all
right every time we were doing this we
can just always use those other values
so instead of
Center hack half dim I can do min/max
and just you know create the rectangle
out of that pretty easily here
same thing here recommend max you know
what this actually looks like it's just
using these since we don't need the
extents value here at all it looks like
we probably don't even need to do that
but you know okay whatever you know it's
it's fine so inside the box min box max
stuff here we'll just do it like this
and then we just need to update our
actual lighting routines to use these
right so you can see those happening
there and you can see us doing a some of
the work with it in our actual tree
construction so this again is gonna be
something we're gonna have to work with
as well so let's go ahead and do the
first the easy part first which is this
routine here so in here we've got the
box P in the box radius and we don't
actually want this anymore so we're
literally just gonna load up the we're
gonna change what this is to just saying
look we're gonna load these directly out
of there to corresponding members there
and we're not going to construct them
anymore so if we just do this we should
find that now we don't have any need for
those other than the place where we
store them for use later and so in here
where we actually store them where we've
got the hitbox Center and that sort of
stuff we're actually gonna do here is
say look hit hit box min and hit box max
so we're gonna store the min and Max so
again exactly the same code but we're
just changing it so that now it doesn't
use those values okay so now all we have
to do is hit box min bucks max now all
we have to do is at the end where we
actually use these anywhere that we
actually needed the radius so in places
where we actually needed to use that we
can reconstruct it now eventually we
probably want to do this it's possible
like I think it's it's it's likely we
could actually make this work by instead
of using the position and the radius by
using something else but in this
particular case I don't really care
about that because since this this part
of the code is so rare like this happens
only after you've done all the loops up
here only one time it's pretty free for
us to do
any calculations we want to do here
because it happens so infrequently
compared to everything else so I don't
really care about this right now so I'm
not gonna spend much time on it I'm just
gonna recompute the hit center although
wait does it even need that so it looks
like it only needs the radius so if it
only needs the hitbox radius then that's
fine so all we have to do for that is
we're just gonna do a multiplication
here and what we need to do is subtract
the two and then take half of it right
so we have the Box max minus the Box min
that gives us the diameter and then
multiplying that by a half will give us
the radius so we can just recompute that
right sorry its hitbox min hitbox max um
so it's pretty trivial oh there it is
hitbox Center I'm like I thought we
needed that you know it was like we
should have needed that so to do the
hitbox Center again pretty pretty
straightforward it's the same thing and
again I'm not thinking about these at
all I don't care about how fast this
part runs because I just don't think
it's gonna be particularly relevant to
us um so then it just leaves us I think
with just this one routine that was made
to work on other kinds of bounding boxes
and I think so it's just the spatial
partition stuff that's necessary I think
yeah so basically we're just looking at
two things split box and then the stuff
that calls split box right now it looks
like this one's actually pretty
straightforward it looks like in this
case we can just use some different
calls and we'll just it'll just work so
this routine looks like it's pretty
straightforward to park out to port in
this case we're just doing a rect min
max here is all we actually need so
there's our box min
there's our box Max and and this is much
like what was it in the letting
computation where were we actually
looking at this before let me let me
just do a quick search air box or rect
min max yeah okay so in get lightly for
P you can see was the other place we
were doing those rectum and maxes right
so in through here
but that's about it so yeah in here we
can just do recommend Max and this is
just to build up the total bounds of the
lighting so again it doesn't really
matter
we're just unioning these two things
together in here we are pulling those
out as a peon or radius but we could
just pull them out as a minute and max
instead so that should be relatively
straightforward as well we can just do
like you know get min get max kind of a
thing which is just a direct access so
it's literally just this I believe
am I right about that
sorry weird look at this function there
we go
yeah and so it's again really really
simple we don't actually use this root
lightbox stuff anymore and so we're
probably gonna pull that out but I've
been leaving it in just in case we
decide we want to try some light
shooting approximations where we where
we are some biasing towards lighting in
the future I don't know if we want to do
that we probably don't but I just wanted
to keep that in there in case we find we
want to try it again so yeah it looks
like our errors are now isolated
entirely to the split box routine and
since now we're only looking at this lit
box routine we can concentrate on what
actually needs to happen here now some
of the porting is exact the same sort of
stuff we're doing before so box min box
max here again just really simple min
maxing here right so instead of getting
the center in the P out we just do it
this way so when we do the bouncy bounce
B we're really just you know producing
those mins and maxes directly so this
again if anything this is actually just
more efficient than it used to be
because now we're always using mins and
maxes instead of using center radiuses
which didn't really ever were ever
really what we wanted in any of these
routines as far as I can tell right and
now we're literally just down to a
couple things which is the inner product
with the actual center of the box looks
like the only thing that will be less
efficient in here again recked min max
is quicker so we can just do that and
that again just uses the Box min box max
right so I think that's basically it and
all we're left with now is the fact that
look we're trying to classify the
Centers of these things you can see us
doing that here and so we just need a
way to compute box P and really that's
just getting the center right so all
this is right here is just look box P in
our case and we don't really even need
to do this we can just do it here we can
just say look this parent this thing
here we've got a box min and a box max
right we've got a box min in a box max
and we just want to take the middle
right so that's that's it we're just
getting the center of that thing right
and the same would be true here so
instead of parent box it's just box but
in theory that's all we need right at
that point we've gotten rid of anywhere
and it depends if we introduce any bugs
there but that's really all we needed to
do so we can see probably pretty easy ly
if we got any errors by just looking at
what the what the actual errors you can
see I must have had an error there
because oh no we have to recapture now
actually no I think about it because
we've changed the storage format so
we're gonna have to recapture our dump
which is unfortunate but that's just how
it's gonna be we can't actually see to
what extent that helped us well you know
we could though now that I think about
it we could do that so here's one way we
can still use the same dump when we load
this thing in so when we actually do our
debug load so in light prof when we load
in this information for the debug load
here so this stuff right here what we
can do is we can quickly do a debug pass
that just updates those those pieces of
information so in here where we do right
before we call internal lightning core
right we can do a quick sweep over all
of the boxes in the system
and we can change them so we can just
say alright we've got a box index the
box index is gonna go up to whatever the
box count is right so we just go through
all of the boxes and we take each
lighting box and we transform it right
so we can say okay for whatever box were
on we take box min and box max and we
compute values for those and all we have
to do is recognize that box min the
value be loaded in is actually gonna be
the p value right so all we have to do
is say look here's the trick if this was
that you know this was the old p value
right in fact I can just do it this way
and this was the old R value right is
that clear
hopefully that's clear so then we can
just say okay the old P minus the old R
that's gonna be the radius and the old P
plus the old R that's going to be the
the new max right and so now we should
be able to debug this without actually
having to take a new capture right and
if we look at what happened there you
can see now we actually get the same
results right we actually get the exact
same results and what's nice is as an
added bonus we actually got faster right
so here's the old speed that we used to
be running at 7.15 seconds for the test
run now it's down to 6.7 seconds and all
we did was change the data storage
format right that's it we didn't do
anything else I'm gonna put it to do
around this because once we do a new
capture we don't want to do this anymore
right so we only want to do this while
we're while we're using old captures so
we don't want to do this once we do new
captures
um so that's fine right all right so
again really great a cheap optimization
for us there all we were doing is
removing cruft right we we worked
backwards going look we optimized this
routine at least somewhat and we can see
that we never really care about the
position and radius in the inner loops
of this thing so we don't really want
that to be primal right we want
something else to be primal which is the
Box Manan box max so let's just do that
and then in the cases where we think we
might want the radius in the center we
can just regenerate them because that's
only happening at times that aren't
performance critical right so it's just
shifting the data storage format so that
we're not doing spurious computations in
in sort of more specific scenarios here
that are expensive right so there's a
lot of other things we could choose to
do here and they start to get kind of
Squinkie particularly fast but there's
one thing that I do want to know there's
a couple of things that we've tried so
we took a look at this routine before
and one of the things we were looking at
is whether branchless whether making
this routine work branchless lee was a
win or not and one of the things I
realized was because our trees are
effectively binary trees they split the
world in half each time this loop is not
really a loop right every time we look
like the way to look at it is this is
not only a perfectly for this branch is
not only perfectly predictable it
happens every other time but it's also
not really a loop meaning we're just
loading two things right and one of the
really stupid things about this is we
don't actually need to do two tests we
could just do one test and know what
we're pushing on because all we really
need to know is does this particular Ray
cross both regions that this is split in
two or just one right or neither right
there's there's basically three cases it
crosses one it crosses two it crosses
zero or zero one and two right
and so we have a lot of issues that we
want to start thinking about now in
order to speed this part up and this is
the part right here that does the work
that we actually care about and trying
to go how to explain all the issues here
so we have three main points we now have
to start looking at and pushing on point
one how do we actually want to store our
tree right because what we did before is
we just stored it in the lighting box
structure we already had and we don't
really know a if we want that meaning do
we want to do it that way or not do we
want to store some other struct that's
separate - what does this tree want to
look like if it's a KD tree like right
now it's a KD tree that's what it is
we're not actually storing it as a KD
tree we're storing it as if it could be
an NRI tree an NRI AAB tree basically if
we're gonna do a KD tree if we're gonna
decide right now KD tree is what we're
doing and we're gonna go forward with
that we should just make something
that's purpose-built for KD trees and
doesn't have a whole bunch of extra crap
in it right so there's that and then
finally do we actually want these in the
same loop or not because there's two
different ways we could do this the way
that we're doing right now is
oscillatory so we basically we go down
sort of depth first and we process some
hits then we pop up process some more
hits and so on right so it's a depth
first walk of this tree but we don't
have to do that we could do more of a
breadth-first thing where we do all of
the calling first build some kind of a
list where we use where we go through
that list right and we could do
something like that and right now I
don't know which of those two things we
actually want to do
so I think what I need to start doing
now is investigating how is this
actually what's the most efficient way
to actually use what we have here right
so what's the most efficient way to
stream these pieces of information out
right that's what I actually want to
know and so I'm gonna try I think I'm
gonna try constructing what we have
right now so without touching really
anything else I want to see what happens
if I change the way that we're
structuring these loops right and I just
I just want to get a feel for whether or
not we can make a market improvement by
for example separating these into two
different loops that are unrelated to
each other okay so that's all that's all
we're doing and the way I'm gonna do
that is I'm gonna essentially keep more
or less what we have here and I'm just
gonna maybe if zero out one of my hmm so
it's gonna be kind of tough to test
unfortunately
because we're gonna have to make some
decisions even just to test it and
that's unfortunate but I just want to
see what it what the difference is if we
just change it into two loops and so
what would happen is as we do our loop
here we would just have a thing that
allows us to do a a see move on to a
totally separate stack so right that's
all we're talking about here so
basically what I want to do is in the
lighting work structure is basically
there would be a scratch array that can
be used for streaming so that you can
basically yeah I mean well here I'll
show you so I'm gonna go ahead and go to
the lighting work structure and in here
what we're gonna do is say in addition
to all this other garbage that's in here
we're gonna take a little bit more off
the big pad so we're gonna subtract
another 8 from that and get down to 2
give us like space for another pointer
right so we're gonna have big pad is is
not really a big pad anymore it's more
of a small pad and in here we're just
gonna have a lighting stack thing that
we push on right so we already know we
can represent all of this by just having
a lighting box pack so what we're gonna
do here is gonna say look there's a
lighting box pack and the lighting box
pack is like the scratch space right
it's just a scratch array that we're
gonna use for whatever stack random crap
we need here and we're gonna assume that
whoever is running this thing is gonna
allocate enough space here so that we
know that we won't run out right and
that may be a lot of memory actually but
doesn't matter as long as we don't touch
it
right so what we're gonna do there is
just say ok so during the course of the
of the allocation of work units so you
know when we're actually creating the
the work units we're gonna want to
assign them to some memory right so in
here where we go through and
zero-out destruct what we're gonna want
to do is stop this zeroing so we don't
want to do this we want to be able to
leave in certain values that are going
to persist so if you look like diffuse
Atlas and speck Atlas work Index entropy
these are things that actually need to
get set
solution does not right so solution
doesn't need to be set that can be set
outside and so can the scratch space
somewhere yeah so the stuff that
actually wants to be zeroed is like
total casts initiated total partitions
tested total partition leaves used and
total leaves tested and we may change
those stats in the future as well
according to our needs right and so what
we want to do here is we want to set
these up somewhere else right and we
want to go ahead and like you know
initialize all the things we might
initialize here and so we're gonna need
to initialize the solution in the
scratch space the scratch base is going
to be something that we may lock out
that's basically like lighting packed
box pack structures and it's just gonna
be like the size of a lighting box pack
structure times some number right and so
what we want to do is before we get
started on anything else you know when
we're in our actual page light Prof and
we'll have to back port this into
hand-made here as well if we end up
keeping it if we don't then we don't
have to then what we're gonna do is when
we do our when we do our setup here so
when we malloc this nonsense here right
what we're gonna want to do is go
through the like a lock work count
basically which is you know we set it to
this we're going to go through the a
lock work count and for each of these
lighting work structures we're just
going to go ahead and
set these values now we want to know
like what's the maximum you know max box
or the max work stack depth right like
how many of these are gonna be and we're
just gonna say look it's possible that
every box gets pushed on I mean sure
right I don't care so we're just gonna
say look for every one of our work
distribution units we're just gonna say
that we have a max work staff depth
right now the problem with this is it's
not quite exactly what we want because
there's more of these than there are
threads so what we really want is one
per thread and the problem is we don't
really have a way to express that at the
moment right so this is not the best
possible thing we can do I'm just gonna
put it to do here on that and the
problem is that we don't really have
that concept in our system at the moment
I don't think now I could be wrong about
that because I think we actually do have
in fact maybe this is all a waste of
time what I'm doing maybe we actually
already did this and if we did
oops but let me just see where is our
actual thread work stuff
so yeah we didn't really do it right as
far as I can tell because when we call
through to these things or maybe wheat
well here's the type def yeah so we
passed like a work queue but we don't
actually pass any other information
right and that's kind of a mess up you
know that's kind of not what we really
want and inside like whatever the the
queue entry point is so like for
whatever our actual work queues are we
probably shouldn't have done that when
we look inside like win32 handmade and
we go down to like whatever the like you
know so if you look here we've got our
curry thread and we you know we have our
do worker work nonsense here right
so in our win32 make queue where we say
like we're gonna make one of these
thread procs and we look at the thread
prop you can see here what it does is it
calls this win32 do next work entry you
can see that sort of doing a call here
and it does the callback on the queue
what we really should have done is given
this this whenever you call someone back
using the callback you should have given
them an arena is what should have
happened so you know there should have
been something look like that on the
thread there should have been an arena
and so that's just a screw-up and I mean
one of the things you have to remember
is handmade hero was started and a lot
of this stuff was done like several
years ago and I've done a lot more
multi-threaded programming since then
and so you know if it was today this
system would look a lot different
because I have a lot more experience and
I would not have done some of the things
that I did so you know this is just like
experience talking right I can tell you
you definitely want that if you're
serious about multi-threading and
handmade hero we're not that serious
about mother threading we do it to do
some of the heavy lifting work but we
don't really multi thread that much we
don't really need to but you know if you
are you need there to be a scratch arena
for each thread because you want threads
to not talk to each other about memory
management every time a thread has a
pass to do memory management in a way
that another thread can see you're just
locking up your threads and it's bad
right so we're gonna leave this like
this for now just because we don't have
per thread Arenas we should and so
that's something you can think about
separately anyway in here we're gonna
create this scratch base and the scratch
base now can be used I'm gonna call the
HH light prof just to prove that nothing
changed but we kind of knew that because
we haven't actually put this change into
place yet so if we now go up to see in
our ray caster if we start to actually
use that information then the first
thing I could do for example is this box
tack information here I could for
example or should be able to just do
something like this where I just say all
right
instead of au 64 right I could do this
where I say the scratch what is this
called again
scratch base I should be able to use
that scratch space here where I just do
a cast of the u32 and the box tack is
now and let me see if I ever take any
thing weird about that box stack I don't
so now we should be able to run this
without crashing and it should work
properly and basically all that's doing
is using that scratch space right and
I'm gonna undo that change almost
immediately because I don't actually
want to use that scratch space that's
not the goal I just wanted to make sure
I had some scratch space there so this
box stack is probably fine to use
exactly as we were so the only thing I'm
doing here is I'm gonna say oh hey by
the way we're also gonna have another
one of these doodads here where we say
alright there's like a different u32
stack here that we're gonna use also I
assume we see to you sir at this no I'm
gonna start that the lighting box pack
here is the same size as you 32 because
that's just what we're doing right
that's required anyway so in the you 32
start here what I want to do is I want
to load up that you know that works
truck we have the scratch space and I
want to call this like some other things
so this is instead of the regular box
that we were doing this is our like leaf
count right and this is our like leaf
stack I don't know right or leaves and
so what we're gonna do is we're just
gonna stream our leaves out into the
scratch space that's that's all we're
doing so we're gonna pull this routine
out right we're gonna say look this is
not gonna happen anymore okay and so
instead of oops
and so instead of doing what we were
doing there we're gonna do something
different right now because I can run
these two in line I'm actually going to
do that so what I'm gonna do instead is
I'm gonna say all right since we have
the ability to run both of these I'm
actually gonna do and if zero here and
literally take like this entire thing
and copy it just so I can flip between
them pretty easily if I want to right
and again I wish compilers made this
sort of thing easier they don't like
programming in general kind of sucks
because stuff where you want to do a/b
testing is so poorly supported pretty
much everywhere it's just annoying but
you know what do you do so what we're
gonna do here is we're gonna get rid of
this loop right so this one's going away
and instead we're just gonna have just
this one and then we're gonna have a
totally secondary pass that happens
completely separately right i and so you
can see what I'm going for here so what
we're gonna do is we're going to break
up these two loops the first loop here
is going to loop over the stack like it
normally would so this is working
exactly as you would expect it to work
right so nothing nothing weird happening
there right whereas this one is going to
do streaming so it's going to just like
loop over the leaves if that makes sense
and there's some things that are a
little bit confusing about this which is
that I don't know when we exactly want
that to happen like I don't I don't know
to what extent we want things pushed on
in like a sane order and in in to what
extent we don't right I think what we
probably will want to do long term is
when we actually sort these boxes in the
actual startup routine we probably just
want them
they're already sorted so that you don't
have to do this indirect reference if
that makes sense
but it doesn't matter anyway
so what I want to do here is I want to
loop over the leaf stack here reading
out each leaf and running over each of
the leaves in turn so in here we're just
gonna say look what's our leaf index
what's our leaf count and then for each
of those
[Music]
I'm gonna grab out the pack and this is
just going to come from our what did I
call it leaves so we're just loading
these out right and I guess this is
called entry so we're just gonna load
these out and process them in order that
they come so now we don't have that test
in there we do have this kind of
annoying test which is we don't know how
many of these they're gonna be each time
and so the thing I'm not sure about is
do we want to unpack these here or do we
want to unpack these here and I don't
actually know right that's just who
knows I have no idea so then if we come
up into here what we need to do is we
need to go ahead and take a look at the
this part of the routine we're pushing
things on and what we need to do here is
we need this to be predicated so this
part here we're and we're not actually
using that part we're using the top part
here so we're choosing this part right
and so in this part of the routine what
we need to do is we actually need to do
an if on this and we need to do like a
switch on it right so we want to take
what we're gonna pack right and we can
grab that this way
so you want to take what we're gonna
pack and we're gonna pack it into one of
two places so either we're gonna pack it
into here and we can dispense with this
because we know these C mobs are not
actually being done but you know oh well
so what we need to do is we need to take
that test where we say look is this
going to be a leaf or is it not going to
be a leaf right so we basically want to
say all right is this box is this is
this thing a leaf container or isn't it
if it's a leaf container we actually
want these the other way around if it's
a leaf container we need to go ahead and
push it on to our leaves um and if it's
not then we don't right oops and so all
we're doing is breaking these loops into
two passes that's all I did and
hopefully I didn't screw it up right and
it looks like I did like that's wrong so
I've got some issue here that I gotta go
address so the timing is going to be
meaningless because we've got an error
so let me just see if I can correct
whatever mistake we made there and let
me take a look at it so if the box we're
about to pack is a leaf container we
push it on to our leaves right like so
and if the box is not then we push it on
to the stack that we're using at the
moment right
and then we loop and then we continue
looping right so this this thing keeps
going at that point right and that's
while the depth is is valid when we get
through here we go through the leaves
one by one so this should go through all
the leaves we load each one of the Leafs
well we're loading actually the thing
right above the leaves we go over each
of the children and we produce the
values for it
to be honest I guess I'm not sure what I
screwed up there that seem sane hmm
so what did I mess up
while depth greater than zero so this
should not have changed like it's still
accessing the box stack exactly the way
you would expect it's weird that I wrote
those two different ways should probably
not do that let's try to be a little
more consistent so in theory this should
just run exactly the same way as it was
before I mean I don't see any reason why
that would be different right
[Music]
the leaf count gets incremented and we
pack into the leaves array as we go and
that seems just like what you would
expect right we didn't touch this branch
gosh
yeah I don't really know what we did
wrong there I mean it seems pretty
straightforward and you know I can
eliminate this code out of this branch
for now because we don't we can always
cut and paste it from above if we want
to try it so it's not like we're gonna
lose that right but I mean that's the
that's the whole routine right so
becoming here we yeah we we just go
through the box stack we push on the
leaves for every time we would have
every time we would have put one of
those on our own stack we don't do that
and then in the leaf index run case we
just run through all the ones that we
have yeah what hmm what did I mess up
there that's a puzzler cuz the total
error should be eight and it's thirteen
and the max Texel error got high like
it's just wrong so you can see that it's
not actually doing what it should be
doing but why I'm assuming nothing else
got touched because I'm assuming if I
re-enable the old case I should get
right back to the valid version right
and I do so it's only the difference
between these two cases if entry is
light leaf container and is leaf
container
oh wait wait wait wait wait wait hold on
a second am I doing this right
so I load an entry well no I I know I
think I am because it was going to test
this before to determine which one of
the loops to do so in theory this should
have worked right because as long as it
was a leaf container before now this
should properly pull out it's children
I'm under stuff do this yeah I don't I
don't there's a subtlety here I'm not
appreciating where I've done something
stupid but I'm not sure what the stupid
thing relates to it doesn't look
Oh duh to state the obvious I need to
actually check to see whether I need to
push if I don't need to push I don't do
these things so yeah I was only checking
the should push in this case so I guess
that's yeah that's the obvious error I
was pushing all of those on all the time
of course I guess that means technically
I wasn't producing an error so much as I
just wasn't using the early-out
conditions that we allow so yeah so that
was definitely wrong let's see if
anything else is wrong here so that's
still not right which doesn't look like
it right because that compiled correctly
and we still have the air oh no no
that's right is it
no no so that's that's still wrong
because that's our max error protects
all right normally and we're getting a
different max error protects 'l now so
we still have something wrong so we do
should push we look to see whether we
need to push if we do need to push we
check to see whether it's a leaf or not
and we push it on to the correct stack
right leaf containers go here non leaf
containers go on to our box stack and in
either case we're just pushing on the
information that we need hmm again
totally puzzled though I have no idea
even I don't really even understand of
why that can possibly be wrong
I guess I would like to assert this
potentially like every time we pull one
of these off let me just go ahead and do
an assert here because that obviously
should be true but I just I mean let's
make sure it is yep so we're only
getting leaves in our leaf loop and so
the only thing that I guess could be
wrong there is where we're not
descending down some boxes we should or
we are descending down some boxes we
shouldn't I guess so in the original
routine when we pulled one off right we
just needed to know which of these two
we were doing seems straightforward
enough we then are doing the exact same
loop like this is identical right oh
sorry this is identical
yeah I mean that all just seems fine
right we do it should push and if we
should push we push on to one of the two
stacks otherwise we don't right and then
we didn't even touch this routine this
version up here right that's just
exactly the same we didn't even modify
it at all its operating 100% the same so
how did that change and like I don't
feel like photos like floating point
error is implicated here because you can
see that the maximum error protects all
is like very different it's ten times
higher and while you know it's it's
never obviously true that you I mean
could it be possible sure but is it
likely no right it's much more likely
that there's a bug in these two so let
me go ahead and see what happens I guess
when we look at the decision list
between these two like I mean let's I
guess try to look to see what is
actually happening in terms of the
leaves that are tested and why we're
getting certain sets of these tested in
one and not the other right I mean I
don't know what else to do unless chat
already found it
did Chad already see it no doesn't look
like anyone did it's a bummer you're
supposed to find these typos for me the
wild depth loop doesn't wrap the second
loop yeah but it's not supposed to write
this this the point of this is that this
wild depth loop produces a second count
which is leaf count and then this runs
through it in one pass so it's not
supposed to be wrapped this is supposed
to generate all of the leaves you know
I'm saying but but it doesn't and so I
don't know how is that able to produce a
totally different thing let's take a
look at let's just stream out I mean
right so let's just stream out what
boxes were testing
I can't quite do that in here can I so
here's what I'm gonna do I'm gonna add
some macros because everyone loves
macros and what I'm gonna do is I'm just
gonna stream out which boxes we were
testing in each case so I'm just gonna
have a thing called like record leaf box
and I'm gonna pass the box and then I'm
gonna have a record partition box and
pass it there so in both cases I'm gonna
just record and I'm gonna do this in the
secondary side as well so same thing
here and I'm gonna record the leaves and
I'm going to Accord the partitions in
both cases now what I do at the top is
I'm just going to say look if nobody has
defined these things then we just don't
do them right so basically like normally
you can pile it those things just
disappear because they don't do nothing
however instead in the HH Lite prof what
we can do is before we do anything else
we can go up here and say look let's
define the macros in this case to be
like an F printf or something yeah i'm
santi to like leaf box out
and petition box out see I'm doing here
and so I'm just gonna stream out those
box indices so this way we'll just print
out all of the box indices into files
that we can then diff and see what the
heck is going on here so all we need to
do is create actual file handles for
those so like you know no this is gonna
work I think it will so like right here
and I guess I can actually do this so
now we will actually compile in sort of
a debug sync that can just send all this
crap out and what I'll do is at the
outset like when we actually start I'll
just open up like you know some of these
where we're just like yeah leaf box out
equals F open actually guess these are
not binary some files so this is going
to be like a leaf box traversal dot text
and partition box traversal dot text
and then we just have a nice quick and
dirty way to make those work and I can
even predicate these I can just say look
if like this thing is defined go nuts
right
oops there so now when we run this thing
we should get a dump file like of those
outputs so they've been streamed out and
there's just gigantic huge files like
they're gonna be massive right of just
like thousands and thousands of
traversal integers and I guess the leaf
box ones well in theory this actually in
theory this should actually produce the
exact same results I think in both cases
I also now that I think about it
we only want them from one run so I
probably also want to do this I only
want that first one
all right so there's our two text files
like I said they're just giant lists of
integers that's the order of the boxes
that were tested and now we can see like
is it just totally weird or is it
roughly the same and there's just a few
differences so what I'm going to do is
that one if you remember so if we go to
the Ray caster it's in here
you can see that that was the new way so
like if we rename those files like these
two here this is like new and if I do it
again with this IFFT in now I've got the
old ones so oops and in theory we could
use I think we use meld for this
normally I think that's the difficulty
we decided to use on stream um so in
theory like I should be able to compare
those files and see like how similar
they are right like this is just to give
me some idea of what the heck is
happening in there cuz I have no idea
oops that was not in the file I wanted
it all so let's start with the league
with the partitions because that's
actually the part that I'm most
interested to see so old partition box
traversal and then new partition box
traversal compare so here's a comparison
right I don't actually know how to use
meld I use beyond compare normally so I
mean that seems to be suggesting they're
exactly the same is that with that
saying
but they're not
you
what's what's going on here so does this
utility work like what I've wanted if
these do can you tell me the difference
between them actually it looks like it
just Scrolls them wrong man all right I
should probably just install beyond
compare here because this is pretty
crappy
and it's hung all right so yeah I guess
this is what we're gonna do I use beyond
compare at work it's inexpensive and
since this doesn't work let's just go
ahead and and say look you can afford it
get a real comparison utility I guess so
here's the download let's see on Windows
so let me well I guess I don't care if
it gets installed on this machine
normally at work I just use zip files
because I like to put them into source
code control but this should be fine
all right so let's try this in beyond
compare and see if they fare any better
so in beyond compare I'm gonna say look
this is the left side this is the right
side
give me a comparison and here we go so
you can see that these are actually
different in terms of the order anyway
and it does look like they're actually
legitimately different like that
wouldn't matter cuz that's just an order
difference there but it's then it starts
to get to the to the point where I don't
know about that part right but more
importantly I'm not sure I know why
there would be that order difference
right so the fact that those are there I
don't actually know I don't actually
know why that would be so I think we
definitely have an issue here
furthermore well you know what let me go
let me check the partitions first that's
that's actually I guess what I wanted to
do so let's check the partitions first
and I'll refrain from comment until we
actually do that but yeah
point being looks bad all right so
here's just a big old chunk and it
really does look like we're traversing a
bunch of extra boxes so like I see a
bunch of differences on this side and I
don't see it on this other side so it's
like we're pushing boxes on that we
shouldn't be in the partition traversal
so why is that so what we're basically
saying is that when we switch this to
zero and we come through cure this this
we're pushing things on that we
previously weren't now what's weird
about that right I mean you're less I'm
missing something what's weird about
that is if anything this thing should
push less I mean if there was a bug in
this it would push less things on right
so it's weird that like what we're
actually doing is we're pushing more
things on how are we doing that
like somehow sort of fairly soon to
write on box so we we push on 2:29 is
that in here anywhere so we visit to
wavelet so this thing visits to 29 twice
right did you see that there's one
there's two
what the heck oh well okay but it's per
ray so that's yeah sorry I was freaking
out there since it's per ray that's fine
I should probably put in like a marker
for each time so that we can look at
that more carefully because like yeah we
if we only look at one ray then we would
expect to see a partition only visited
one time but since we're looking at many
rays that's you're going to traverse
those route boxes a lot of times all
right so
so how did we mess that up
so let's put one more assertion in here
let's assert that we never accidentally
process a non-leaf in the partition
container right in the partition loop
I'm assuming the answer is that won't
happen but I just want to see and we can
also actually turn this off for now
because we don't need to record it at
the moment so I guess I need a separate
switch for these as well so I'll make it
a thing called record break a stack put
that in here and now I think we're good
alright so if we're gonna record the
raycast stack then we do if we're not
then we don't and again no assertions so
really strange this is like curiouser
and curiouser I feel like I feel like
we've hit a stumper here so um somehow
we are pushing too many things on the
box stack even though we never
accidentally process something that's
not a leaf nor do we accidentally leaf
process something that we never process
um that is a leaf in the wrong time or
is not a leaf at the wrong time
far as I can tell anyway
how many boxes are there let's start
with that
so in here mm-hmm Jimmy
when we load and we print out like when
we print out that summary so like here
could we just say how many boxes do we
take in and how many boxes do we put
forth so basically before we build this
base partition we would print this
so we're inputting 1488 and are
outputting 2550
so I guess what I would say is I am now
thoroughly confused I have absolutely no
idea what's going on so what that would
imply to me right so like if we look at
this how the heck are we getting the
numbers that we're getting like okay so
let's just go up to the top how do I go
to the beginning this file
all right so here's line zero of the
photo or not but these files are just
too big like no I guess diff utility is
just can't handle large files or
something like I'm having a hard time
viewing this file at all tell you what
maybe what we should do is make it so
that if we're actually doing a profile
run where we're doing the dumps
maybe we just only do like one of these
so that we can make these smaller so we
can see them better I mean I don't know
what else to say so like maybe what we
do just to make this tractable because
even beyond compare so having trouble
with it so maybe what we do is in the
raycast er we basically say like look
previously we were doing like tons of
ray casting right we go through all
these work orders and all this stuff
maybe in the Ray caster now we just say
look stop dumping after the first time
or something right so something like
that where we say look this is the end
or it's like oh okay
like if it's the end then we stop so we
just say look there's a switch
so there's a stack time switch these are
actually enclosed in if-statements right
and so when the raycast ends we just say
like stop that stop dumping and then the
raycast end in the lighting code we can
just be so we just we record a single
ray cast and that way the file isn't
huge right because we only really care
about one probably as long as it's
different as long as it has a difference
in it then we're fine so we can probably
just do it that way and that way we can
not have this utility failure problem
right alright so we'll just say look at
that point we've cast array so it's over
so like don't worry about it
and then up here we can just say you
know it's defined nothing all right one
more time so now if I rerun this I
should be able to go like okay first
let's actually let's see which one we're
on I don't remember all right so this is
the new way right that'll dump the new
way oops
no one well
all right so that'll dump the new way
hopefully so now we should have like
smaller files so we didn't get any
so that ray didn't hit anything is the
answer
apparently all right well let me just
let's take this case just to see right
so there's the new one and let me now
make it do the old one
so those operated exactly the same so
the answer is we do have to get to Jimmy
we do have to get to something so maybe
I'll do it this way
right will basically say like look if
the stack dumps which is at a certain
level like hey we'll do
16 Ray casts and then we'll stop no I'm
saying to you so let's try this one more
time and again this is just to try to
get the data down so we can actually
look at it in utilities without them
freaking out alright so there we run we
did we compile so this is the old way
here's the leaf boxes here's the
partition boxes right which again I
don't understand what's going on because
we shouldn't I didn't think partition
boxes could ever actually be below the
box count so something's weird already
like I need to go look at how this stuff
works because I obviously don't
understand right I mean 25:48 is the
root box right which makes perfect sense
but these are the input boxes so 1488
anything anything above 1488 is a
partition box anything below 1488 is a
leaf box
these are partition boxes coming from
the old way of doing things
what are those obviously the wrong kind
of box right doing on there again 1488
is the minimum that
that's a that's actually a leaf like
what is the leaf doing on on there so
like that's just wrong it's yes it's not
a leaf container but it's an actual leaf
so how was it not processed as just a
one of the iterator things we got issues
and by the way assuming that this is
correct it's actually good these are
good issues because if there were bugs
in the original routine of the traversal
that we didn't know about they could be
causing artificial slowness that we can
get rid of right this could mean that we
have optimization fat in there that's
just due to bugs which would be
fantastic so let's hope that's actually
the case it might not be but let's hope
all right
so I make sure I'm dumping these right
it looks like I am um so let's uh you
know what I don't even want to do a
comparison yet I want to know what the
heck is going on here with this so let's
find out in split box is something how
is this working so when we call split
box right we go through and we say if
the number of things that are if the
source count right is more than four
boxes then we're gonna split the thing
we look to see if we can split the thing
and assuming that we could right so
assuming that like we actually found a
plane that splits them then we split
them right and if we split them into two
then we yeah we record whether or not we
split them or not so if we split meaning
the things that we got input in we split
we say alright whatever the box is that
we came in with it's gonna become a leaf
container or not
based on that so either it becomes a
leaf container because it didn't split
so it's you know its contents are are
things you test against or it clears the
leaf container flag if the things in it
are therefore if it therefore is
containing actual splits right actual
split partitions right
and I guess the thing here is I guess
maybe it's the indirection table that's
confusing me and I wonder if this
indirection table should even be here
so I kind of want to say that this
indirection table just shouldn't even be
here so let's get because that's
probably what I'm seeing so the reason
that we're seeing these are is probably
cuz these are not the actual boxes
they're box indices and you know since
we're doing such heavy ray casting on
these things having that indirection is
just stupid it's just an extra read into
a table for no reason I feel like we
should just get rid of that so let's
pause for one second before we try to
debug this any further and say all right
stop the recording that's not gonna
happen run the old routine right make
sure it's working right there's our old
Texel error we expected right six point
six seconds let's just pull out that
entire thing so let's say that in the
lighting now we're not gonna have you 16
indices here I also don't know what the
heck the scratch AB&amp;C stuff is actually
for is that really necessary how is this
working
so what is that what does that work so
it gets past a source on a desk and
they're like scratch buffers and it goes
through those and tries to partition
them into two lists right so that all
seems fine actually
so I guess just looking at this right
so looking at this I feel like it
wouldn't be that hard for us to
rearrange this to just work directly so
ad box storage is the thing that we're
thinking about right and it's this thing
and all we would really need to do here
is say let's move ad box storage so
instead of ever a box references would
just not exist anymore right and if I
remember correctly like ad box reference
if you look the only times we do that is
just to come Jimmy is literally only in
the case where we're doing it here so
this could just copy the boxes right of
each of the children it could just say
like let's copy those and so we only
have two cases we have one case where we
know we added the Box storage is here
and we could obviously add them
symmetrically like there those are now
in a row so we know we have two children
and they go right one after each other
right like right we could say look we
know those are contiguous you know I'm
saying so we know that these two that
these two children would be contiguous
and we know that if we didn't actually
split then we can just copy the boxes to
make those contiguous right so we could
just add box storage as we go so here in
this one where we say it is a leaf
container we can just add box storage
for each child right so like this
so in here when we go like let's go
through the sources to this particular
box what we want to do is like get that
box and just add the box storage for
that box into our set and then all the
boxes would just be continuous right we
we wouldn't need indirect referencing
for anything because all the references
would be correct if that makes sense to
me
and off we would go so another way to
look at this would be like look the
actually split case which is here we
could actually just change this to a
look if you didn't actually split and
then this comes up here so we'd say
alright in this case we set everything
right so in the case up here where we
say like if we actually split the thing
we're gonna leave and we're not gonna do
anything else this stuff now becomes
like determinative right so the child
count here like is 2 we don't set these
because you know it's continuous right
so then the first child index in this
case because this isn't like an output
box at this point right
wait nope it's not even quite that I can
just leave it like this now I think
about it so during this what we would do
is we'd actually add a new one for the
parent box right entirely so it's a
little complicated to do it because just
in order to make this routine still work
the same way that it was before but to
stream them out directly it's a little
bit more work once you've added the
children you know that the children are
added in order so now you should be able
to add the parent and that parent should
be basically in order as well right so
yeah so I think that's fine yeah I think
that's fine
the only thing I'm not sure about is the
fact that as you're walking the tree you
use different indices so in here when
you're getting these things out this
source said oh but it's not because it
comes from here yeah all right so I
think we're fine so I think that I think
we can actually just basically leave
this as is and the only difference here
is that instead of this like the first
child index bit here the way that that
works has to change slightly so when we
do child box a child box B and the add
box references
this part needs to change and instead
what has to happen is we just have a
first child index on a child count here
so we need those to get set so let's
just set them where they actually happen
so in here we'll just say look this is
going to be two right so we're just
gonna set this like the parent box here
we're gonna set and then we need the
first child right the parent box packed
first child index that's just going to
be this child box
at right so that's all we're doing here
you know I'm saying to you so that's all
we need to set in that case this case
doesn't need to happen at all right this
doesn't need to happen either so then
all we need to do is when we are a leaf
container all we need to do is just set
these things up right and the way that
we need to do that is we need to do ad
box storage for all of the boxes in our
set right so we need to do like four ad
box storage we would do like box count
equals one or whatever right and then in
here we would say look let's make sure
we can fix fit that many in and then you
can add as many as you want at a time so
then what we would do is say well the
child count is just the source count
right we know it's a leaf container the
first child index is the ad box storage
of however many of these things we
actually have which is that and then we
just need to copy them so we need to do
like child index zero you know and these
are 16s I guess seanix is less than the
child count hmm and for each of these we
copy it in so whatever the solution box
is child index like so right that's
gonna be copied from the source box so
you know it's this actually I guess it's
it's this way might be the right way to
do it so we say look here's our sources
and each one of those needs to be copied
into like one of the parent boxes
oops as a bit of a miss click there
there we go so now that streams out um
where we say Jimmy we now have a compact
list where we just say look we're gonna
stream these out in order so now there's
no box references ever so the box
reference concept would go away meaning
this right here would would go away I
believe and the get box concept would
also go away I think so I'm going to try
that real quick and just see if I can
make that work mm-hmm so in here where
we do lightbox index again forget box
this would no longer use ref I mean the
other way we could do it I suppose is
get box could just work without the box
table so we could just do this right we
could also assert that like solution
that like box index is less than
solution last gap right so what else so
in this case when we add the root box
here again we're not adding references
anymore we just add storage like this
right I'm not sure we actually need to
do anything else here's the child count
equaling a source count you can only
have you 16 of those I mean we can
assert the source count is less than you
know you 16 max but it's not going to be
8 max sorry
because we already said it had to be
less than four look we don't have a u8
max somehow yeah we don't know no biggie
we've got one now all right and so now
we have to see whether that works at all
I mean it might be a total disaster
and we'll see so yeah still looks buggy
there right like that's not quite right
so what did we mess up wrong to me what
did we mess up there let's take a quick
look so when we're actually pushing
these on and now we're just calling get
box I guess in let me just make sure all
the places we're calling it makes sense
so getting the route light box should be
fine
getting the child indices here that
should be fine
same here on the same here
yep so all those are what you expect the
ref see there should be fine yep yep so
all of that should be fine so let me see
so our split box must be slightly wrong
somehow hmm
so we passed the sources down here how
do we pass those
because I'm not sure how this dest bit
works here so you can see that what we
do is we loop through and we write out
the refs into destination arrays right
yes so we pull out each box and so I
would assume that if we actually made it
down to here where you know if we
actually split we remove the leaf
container whereas if we didn't actually
split we store it the child count is
going to be the source count that we
were given the first child index hmm
we're gonna add that many boxes right
however many we had make sure that is
right
nope that's wrong so this is actually
that and we have to do the increment
after right that was just a screw-up
there so because the result is going to
be what at the Box hat was that plus
equals was not like that would give you
the wrong results so let me try that one
more time okay so now we're back to the
correct Texel error so that's a good
sign and what we can see here is we
saved some time again right so before we
were running it like six six I believe
pretty routinely and you know we we
managed to drop down again like you can
look up back at our our starting runs as
we were working through those we got
down to six six right but we never had
anything as low as a six four so
removing that table helps us to write so
now that we've removed that table we
don't have those in directed box arrays
so now our lighting structure is also
more straightforward so we can for
example remove the ref count the box
table all of that stuff can go away now
since we flat load this thing we can't
just nerf them yet but we can say like
hey all of this now can be removed right
so that entire box table and all of the
box references would would be removed
and furthermore I can nerf them
explicitly here so that I can check to
see if anyone's actually doing anything
with them and get rid of it
so this debug dump now is irrelevant it
doesn't have to happen anymore this box
ref count here can go away it doesn't
need to be there anymore
this check is not relevant because we
don't need box references
all right so that stuff can go away and
we can simplify our lives by just doing
a recapture there and off we go
so our 6.4 is now like hey we're
actually like a full second faster on
our on our test yet and we haven't even
really started to optimize this thing
like all we're really doing here is just
the basic work of getting us into
position to optimize like we haven't
really even looked at our performance
counter numbers we just got it working
with vtune but we didn't actually do
anything yet so I mean this is great
like this is good progress if that's
being made we're just de crusting the
routine all right so now we want to go
back to what I was doing before where I
say like look now we should be able to
see those values and they should be
clearer what's happening so now let's
actually take the dump let's actually
take a dump
uh-huh and and see what's going on so if
I build now with the old way of doing
things I should be able to score some
traversals here that let me see what's
happening so there's a run here's the
old way and now we should see
exclusively high numbers and we do right
so that's easier now because I can
verify that there's no leaves in there
which I was just nervous about that so
this is the old leaf traversal here's
the old partition traversal now let's go
ahead and do another run where we do the
new traversal and let's see what that
looks like because again this is broken
we think right and you can see that the
max Texel error jumped up like
dramatically and we don't know why
something's busted so now let's take a
look here's the new leaf box traversal
the new partition box traversal and
let's go ahead and diff those so here's
the old one here's the new one
and there's a very small difference so
it's interesting in that looking at
these you can see that that the the
routine behaves fairly similar to what
you would expect except for one minor
difference now this is good because
again it helps us to if there's only a
small number juices we can start to
isolate in those differences I do want
to do one difference one thing that's a
little bit odd here so I'm gonna say
source I want to know who caused the
Edition to happen so like what I'd like
to see here is when we go and record a
partition box and I don't know there's
really any way to do it actually
so maybe not it'd be nice to record who
pushed it you know I'm saying to you so
maybe what we could do here is say hey
when someone pushes someone on will
record that too so like
we'll send the should push will say who
got pushed and we'll go from there so we
know that we want to push down this Fox
pack right so basically what we could
say is like here's the box pack that got
pushed and here's who pushed it so we
know the source index right because we
would have just written that out so we
can do a record partition push here and
the same would be true in our other case
we can do that here as well right so we
could just dupes actually we can just do
this and that way we have yet another
piece of information so record partition
push in this case has two things one is
the should push and the other is the
pack and this can just do like look if
stack them switch and should push then F
print F petition box out and we'll just
do a loops just do a little push line
here
so that's the pact up first child index
and I guess we'll do it like this that
seemed good let's see how that does
so inside raycast like I'm going to go
ahead and try taking the old one now and
again just do another recapture here so
here's the old way of doing things
and so in the partition box traversal
here well why didn't that push anything
seems like that should have pushed
something right like we're in this
branch oh whoops
that's in the wrong place there we go
try that one more time there we go so
now we can see like who was doing what
here and I'll be honest it looks a
little weird like what is happening with
that oscillation I guess those are
multiple ray casts so those rays didn't
cast so nevermind you know what let's
add that too because I'm tired of
getting confused about that part of it
so let's just put a blank line in there
so we can see when the raycast actually
ends so there we have each ray so like
here's an example of array like 1498
pushed 92 through 94 then it did 91 that
didn't push anything then it went to 92
right so now we can see the stack
traversal a little more clearly and
again that's the that's the old way and
now let's go ahead and see what happens
with the new way so I'm gonna go ahead
and swap in the the broken way or at
least we think it's broken
maybe it's actually one that's working
properly on the other ones broken we
don't know
so here's the new one and now if I take
a look at these two so here's the old
one and here's the new one
whoops I just want new leaf box
traversal there we go a new partition
box there we go
so if I look at this now I should be
able to see like where the push went
wrong so what looks like it happened is
on box 1638 for some reason this thought
it needed to push the children of that
box but this didn't hmm right so
I just the only thing I'm not sure about
though is
well no this I mean yeah so this should
record both top types of push so if you
were supposed to push in either case it
records the push whether it was a
weather was leaf boxes or not and so you
can see here like 1639 and 1638 both
pushed and then those pushes even pushed
right like there was actual results of
those that went down so we now know a
specific person we could look at like we
can look at 1638 explicitly if we want
to and see why that happened the same
would be true of 1844 it looks like so
something is happening with those that
it's like causing a push and we don't
know why like why would those why are
those getting a push and the end only
those right fortunately this is pretty
easy to look at I guess so I mean it's
just
16:38 I mean something like that and I'm
guessing that like I mean I guess I
could just do this so that would stop me
in remedy right there
and I can see you know what what's
happening I guess and the same would be
true in here so I can just do the same
thing just right before the should push
you know I can put that that breakpoint
in there I guess I can do this even
further down right and I'm gonna go
ahead and compile in debug mode here and
verify that I mean I would like to just
be able to not have to do this in
release so I'm gonna verify that the
same thing happens on both I don't know
that it will because there could be
problems with that so let me just first
verify that this is true so in I'm in
the case where the old way happens I'm
gonna take a look and say all right
don't quite do that yet
run a trace and make sure the trace is
the same so there's the trace mmm here's
the the old partition box traversal and
then here's the that same one
compared with itself they're exactly the
same
so in debug mode I should be able to
just reproduce this just fine so if I
now do this and run it under remedy like
so I should stop on the one we actually
care about right so here's source index
so if I actually clear this out and just
look their source index 1638 and what we
want to know now is like alright so
we're assuming that any like these these
numbers are wrong or right these are the
correct ones I should say and they're
what's wrong in the other one so any
inside should push so all of these are
false right nothing actually hit the box
that we're looking at so if we look at
the actual box structure here
so I just thought of something I want to
check sorry to derail that train of
thought so when we push on to the other
stack we should check to make sure that
the leaf count isn't larger than the
total size we have right so like in
because that could we could just be
overwriting that memory maybe that's all
it is right so if you look in here where
we actually create these oh this is
garbage right we don't know that that's
well no it's not because if that's the
total number of boxes there are we
couldn't actually push more more than
that good way but you see why we could
have a problem there right so
so I think we do kind of want to at
least validate that right so I'm not
sure exactly the best way to do that
because the box count itself has been
modified at that point so it's harder to
have some way to record that but I can
just do this
oops so if I save the global max work
stack depth here just for debugging
purposes right then I can do an
assertion here that it doesn't get over
pushed right so for example in this case
here where we push onto the leaf count I
can just do an assert that like the leaf
count is less than the global max works
tap depth here right and off we should
go now
I will admit oh but I didn't file a case
so now if I turn this off I should get
yeah I should get an error in the non
light perf build that that's undefined
and that's fine and now when I run this
beautiful okay so the problem is we were
actually somehow generating too many box
pushes what the hey man so I wouldn't
have thought that was possible since
each one of those can have at most one
child I'm sorry at least one child or
they wouldn't get pushed so how the heck
are we pushing more than the total
number of leaves worth of partitions
am I missing something there oh wait no
nevermind
that was the T bug break never mind
never mind
everyone calm down I was gonna say that
that was surprising me alright so I'm
going to nerf this real quick we're not
gonna do the debug break cuz it's gonna
say that shouldn't have been the case
but let's see maybe it still is so I
want to see whether I ever hit that
assertion right this assertion right
here and doesn't look like we do and in
fact I can probably verify that like
here so I come down here and you look at
leaf count right um you can see like the
number of leaves that we get is like
super low right it's just not that high
so I don't know what the maximum leaf
can't would be but it's not gonna be
that big I don't think and so we don't
actually ever hit that assertion
okay good good cuz I was like you
shouldn't ever be able to hit that
assertion it should be completely
impossible to do so alright so we're not
over writing that I don't think although
it's possible that we allocated two
little memory for it somehow otherwise
in this sort of hacked routine here
where we do the stacks stack space we
malloc the max worked ah and we did so I
think that was it right or no we didn't
why do I keep thinking I keep miss
reading that as the work count so nope
totally fine that our Kate's as many as
we wanted that's what we would expect so
yeah I don't know so let's go back to
what we're doing before I just want to
check that and make sure nothing was
weird there so we'll pull out that
assertion
and this I'll go grab the global maximum
stacked up there we go
and now we can put these back in so
let's just take a look now at 1638 Bock
1638 in both cases so we can see why
like one thinks we should push and one
thinks we shouldn't push because I have
no idea why so we'll look at this case
first and we'll just like we'll just
dump like we'll just like manually
inspect the box and see if there's
anything weird about that box right so
here we go
unbox 1638 we can look here it's like
negative thirty seven negative nine zero
negative twenty eight zero six zero five
right I mean I don't know we could try
to copy these values I don't know if
there's any way to dump the watch window
I don't know if George is watching but a
way to like dump the watch window would
be pretty great like I know save watch
window to file or something like that I
don't you know I'm saying um so what I'd
like to do is say look we know that all
of this came out zero in our reference
case so we're not gonna push this thing
on the stack we know that the box looks
like this and so we should in theory
have exactly the same results right and
the pack well we don't care because that
doesn't even matter what the pack is
because we never push it so we just want
to know that these are the same and so
like that's not really what I want so I
really just want to know this stuff
right and I guess I could just put it in
a little like temp area somewhere like I
don't know like notepad plus plus right
here we go and then here's box max and
that's just so I can see if the boxes
look any different which hopefully they
wouldn't but you know what if they do
and then similarly I can also look to
see like the other only other thing is
like the Ray origin and stuff right
and the invar ad right like this stuff
and those should should not change at
all like those know if someone's like
mucking with those then we have a
problem right um so right so the Ray
origin should be duplicated because it's
multiple rays coming from out of the
same origin and then the raid erection
should be well you know so I mean it's I
guess we'll copy that in as well I don't
know I don't really think that's gonna
change but I suppose we should just
double-check it didn't I mean it
couldn't because if these two changed
then everything downstream would change
so I really don't know what's up so we
got the Box we've computed these
ah yes okay so I really don't need to go
any further I know what's going on here
so we will actually produce different
results and the reason that will produce
different results here is that the team
acts values well although you know what
I guess I'm not sure why we produce
different answers but what's happening
here is we aren't actually testing
things in the boxes as we visit them and
so the result is that we will test more
boxes because we push more leaves on to
the stack so I guess we really yeah so I
guess now that I drilled down to that
that does sort of answer my question
which is that it seems like you don't
want to stream this because as you go
down you want to test the things in the
closest box first always and if you hit
something there you don't want to test
the other side you don't ever want to go
down it alright so I think I don't
actually want to even drill down any
further then so that answers my question
streaming is not happening because we
need to actually early out right so that
is over goodbye you're gone so actually
what we want to focus on here is doing
this sidedness in the correct way too
early out so so I think that's really
what we want so what we want to do
tomorrow now I know what we're doing
since we're doing Katie tree probably so
we haven't really talked about not doing
that if we're gonna go forth Katie what
you want to do is test the nearside of
the Katie tree first if there's a hit
we just don't test the farside so that's
what we need to actually do right so we
need to keep those bounds right so we do
want to do depth-first we want to walk
down all the way down test the closest
things
and only start testing further things
out when they don't hit so that's we're
doing tomorrow that's what we're doing
I've declared it I've declared it that's
what we're doing okay so before I'm not
going to actually stop today
oops I got to get rid of those debug
breaks so before we stop today I want to
go create I want to go back out the
scratch buffer change since that doesn't
need to be there anymore because we're
not going to use it right so so that's
just gone so let's go ahead and test
this here's the debug mode I'm gonna I'm
gonna flip it to release mode in a
second here you know what let's just
stop that and I want to go into lighting
and just say like alright so let's just
get rid of this that's gone goodbye and
the internal lighting core this can now
do the work solution set again so this
doesn't have to happen and I think we're
good now all right so let's run the
lighting core
looks about right let's run the actual
version looks about right seems fine to
me let me just see what our profile
looks like so yeah I mean that looks
looks like what we would expect
yeah so that looks fine
I'm gonna do a brief QA
want to let you know we have a is memory
equal oh so we do where is it memory is
equal so we do have that hmm
so I just couldn't find it I guess when
I tried before so this doesn't have to
do that it could just do like memory is
equal right and you can just pass it to
buffers looks like I don't have exactly
what I want though because I need one
that takes the counts so I guess we'll
leave it like that for now off topic my
nose relays bla post oh thank you I
probably forgot to set it I manually
enter the date on those because um you
know it gets generated and then pushed
let me let me remind myself to fix that
I'll push a change today
all right
why is it this software companies
increasingly seem to not care about
performance so the reason is that I mean
there's the reason that it happened but
I don't know if that's really what you
want to know the reason is because they
can write so previously what would
happen is nobody would have used a piece
of software if it took so long to type
characters that like you know like if
you program software the way you program
it today and you know the Machine you
had was a Commodore 64 no one could use
that piece of software so no one it
wouldn't have existed that company
couldn't have sold software right but
you know more or less what happened
today in today's world is like users
don't really demand much performance
they demand only very passing
performance so that's the end of it if
your users don't demand good performance
then companies can keep selling bad
performance and so I don't really know
how to say it any other way than that
it's because companies can stay in
business who ship poor performing
software that's it if users stopped
accepting low performance then you would
get high performance right
you have to look at software as the
software you have is the software that
can exist right so companies just
generate software and unless you are
actively weeding out companies that
generate bad software you just have bad
software so at some level it's just like
look maybe someday people will start to
demand performance and maybe that
happens because some companies start
shipping high performance stuff and then
people gravitate towards that like oh
why would I wait you know 30 seconds for
my freaking Facebook page to load when I
can just use this other service that's
instant and then you get that service
right but until then you just won't it's
not going to happen
to the git repo for any of your code so
not really no I don't use git or github
the handmade hero source code is
available if you preorder the game so
like if you go to if you preorder the
game here it comes with the source code
that you can look at there is a github a
private github that you can get access
to if you've pre-ordered but it's
unsupported so like when you pre-order
the game it will give you this screen
which basically tells you you get
absolutely no support for the github so
the only thing I actually guarantee you
get is the downloadable source code
which is like it's just you just click
it's like zip file right but they're
technically is a github I just don't
support it people wanted it so it's
there it gets automatically updated so
the github for this source code is
actually there right but it's private
cuz this is not public domain software
right this is like a commercial thing
right
about my question before the stream
started I am looking for a doubly linked
list structure and usually that's done
through a structure with the first and
last entry pointers and those have a
structure with a next pre Vande value
pointers let's call this entry structure
in order to add an item to the end of
the list you need to create a new entry
structure set the pre-fire to the
previous last entry and update the last
entry structure in order to have the
next point to the new last item is there
any other service that does without this
prerequisite again I just I'm sorry if
I'm misunderstanding you but I have no
idea what you're asking a doubly-linked
list is just a link tiss that has next
in previous pointers III don't know what
you mean by prerequisite obviously you
have to update the next and previous
pointers when you insert something
because they have to point to the new
thing so what is it that you're trying
to avoid if I insert an item so if I
insert item B after item a I have to go
change is previous pointer to point to B
and furthermore assuming that you know
you're keeping a doubly linked list then
if you have a and C that are in the list
and I insert B between them a zest
pointer has to point to B and C's
previous pointer has to point to B so
you have to update those two pointers
and I'm not sure what you're asking for
like how could you not update them your
you would not have a properly linked
list if you didn't update those two
pointers on insertion right
are there any scalability usability
issues when using enums versus something
like a hash table for indexing assets
well enums are more scalable than hash
tables so do you mean just usability
like like enums would be compact and
perfect so they scale perfectly whereas
a hash table actually cost you something
it cost you the amount of time it takes
to hash something right
so enumerate in your assets with a
globally unique set of indices is like
the fastest possible thing usability
wise yeah there are some issues which is
to say that you have to have a way of
allocating those enums and you don't
want to leave like gaps in the enums
otherwise you waste memory in the table
so you do have a usability issue there
ok I want to say that the witness is
John here I don't think naysayers here
but if John's here you can answer this
question I don't really I I didn't look
particularly hard at how the witness did
their enum allocation by wanna almost
say the witness didn't even compact its
enum list before shipping like it was
something John was going to do and then
didn't even have to do cuz it just
didn't matter it was just wasted some
memory but no one cared right so so yeah
but he would be a better person you know
well if he's streaming right now we're
just gonna go raid him after this anyway
so you should ask John that question
because he actually ships games on the
enum method not the hash table method so
he can probably tell you exactly what
you want to know from experience rather
than hypothesis
do you know if some sane way of learning
a bit of dx11 other than trial and error
while discovering information I
understand there's got to be a dx11
tutorial somewhere how would you
recommend writing assembly directly for
a function to the compiler refuses to
optimize it the way you want usually
what you have to do is one of two things
either you just have to make a NASM file
so you just write the function in NASM
or you just fuss with the c and try to
get the compiler to eventually do the
azzam you want which sometimes works
often it works if you happen to be using
compiler that isn't Visual Studio so if
you're using clang or GCC those
compilers actually have some inline
assembler facilities so you may be able
to just put some inline assembler in
there and that can help tremendously but
Visual Studio doesn't support that
because you know you've seen how fast
Visual Studio runs are you surprised
that they don't allow inline assembly I
imagine the people working a buddy list
of you don't even know
assembly at this point how important is
it in game development and in general to
be concerned with microarchitecture
level optimizations and using metrics
from seed before it's just critical I
would say I would say that basically if
you don't understand microarchitecture
you probably shouldn't be an engine
programmer at some level maybe if you're
just on an architecture side I mean just
period you should just know that stuff
how many lines of code are there in the
HH project like 50,000 or something it's
like less than 50,000 I think sorry not
even 15,000 maybe Adam don't we have
clock on here somewhere
so 34,000 total lines and that counts
everything I think so
including like the rake at not the
nothing ray Kassar including like the
art asset processing like whatever
everything involved if you do another
programming discussion with John do you
think it would be valuable to do
discussion about entity systems I mean
no like John is set a million times
entity systems are stupid like it's a
waste of everyone's time
and I don't know why people harp on them
right they're just it's not a thing
vs 19 is support for x86 but not excess
for assembly why is it one bit on the
other oh um so I don't actually know the
internal reasons reason I know you're
asking let me summarize this people
don't know so Visual Studio doesn't
support inline assembly but it used to
so it uses of writing line assembly and
why does it not anymore
well the answer is because when they
went from x86 the x86 compiler to the
x64 compiler that's where they lost the
support so if you switch back to the
32-bit compiler you can actually have
inline assembly back but when you're
doing in on modern 64-bit build you
can't do it I don't know why I think
it's because they didn't want to do the
work I think it's just pure laziness
they didn't want to have the code paths
necessary to ensure that user assembly
could be inserted into the back end and
work so derp I meant like what you guys
sitter is a good approach yeah the the
point is if you're thinking about entity
code as a system then you should stop
doing that that part of the code is the
structure of your game it should not be
systematized it depends on the game and
it should be like
written in the way that makes the most
sense for you to express the behavior of
the game which is not which is
inherently not systematize Abul unless
your game is very generic
alright looks like that's it for cues
did we ever hear back from Mario Manzano
about the doubly linked list because I
still don't feel like I actually
understand the question but I don't know
if maybe that's just because I am
thinking he's asking or I guess I don't
know if it's Mahdi as is male or female
but they are asking a question about
about like updating pointers in a doubly
linked list or whether they're asking
about some other thing and he's just
mentioning the pointers or whatever I
don't quite understand and so I just
want to make sure is there an actual
thought to that question that clarifies
it at all or what cuz I still that when
I did not answer but it's because I
don't understand it so I don't know if
we could get a clarification in there
[Music]
oh I think you're saying you think they
wanted to know if there something that
acts like a doubly-linked list that
isn't actually a doubly-linked list so
just like something that's easy to
remove things from I guess
all right well I'm gonna wrap it up they
can get back to me with a more specific
question if they have one later but all
right thank you everyone for joining me
for another episode of hand made here
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you want to follow along with
the series at home you can always
pre-order the game on hand made here org
it comes with a source code so that you
can follow along with it we also have a
Kickstarter going right now for our
comic be sure to check that out if you
like comics it's pretty easy to find the
banner should be on our pages at the top
you must click through there and it is
here it is funded too so if you back it
you will be getting a comic from Anna
and I when the Kickstarter closes we
will be be sending it off to the
printers so that's about it for today
I'll be back here tomorrow when now that
I'm pretty sure I know what's going on
in our loop in terms of what I want it
to do we can go ahead and do that I'm
gonna go rage on stream now I don't know
what he's doing over there but we're
gonna go find out so for those of you
want to stay tuned
I will not actually end the stream I
will go raid now so see folks tomorrow
and let's go rage on wait what the heck
I'm not seeing I'm not seeing anything
on here though