start recording hello everybody and
welcome to handmade hero show Rico to
complete game live on stream I really do
not know exactly what we are going to do
today I often say that I don't know what
we're going to do on the stream and I
mean it a lot of times you're at a point
on the stream where you're like okay
there's a number of things we could be
doing especially when you're you know in
the middle of a system that sort of got
multiple multiple axes along which it
could be improved sometimes it's hard to
know exactly what you should be doing so
yesterday we implemented some basic
debug you I handling and so I assume
that the best thing today would be to go
ahead and push that a little bit further
but I don't know yet so I'm just going
to dive right into the code take a look
at where we are and see what I think is
the best thing to sort of get the debug
stuff up to a point where I'm happy with
it and again like I said what I would
like to do is I'd like to be able to
sort of start to pull the debug system
together you I wise into something that
seems like it's relatively usable to us
that you know we will be able to do the
sorts of stuff that we want to do with
it and we have a bunch of things that we
might want to do with it now we've got
some variables we can tweak we've got a
profile that you know in a log we can
inspect things like that and so I'd like
to have some kind of a way of sort of
starting to pull those together so I
think that's what I'm going to try to do
like I said I don't know exactly how I
want to do that yet i'm just going to go
in there and see what the most logical
steps are to take and we'll work from
there so today is day 1 97 that means if
you'd like to follow along at home you
want to take a 106 is source code and
unpack it into a directory that is what
I am starting with now and so if you
want to follow along with me at home
that is what you should be starting with
as well here is the state of the code as
we left it and you know I think most of
the things we're working that we did
there we we sort of have this this V for
that has not been implemented so we have
not done any of the vector types or
things like that but we did add
adjustment for four scalar values right
we got that working so the debug camera
for example can be adjusted as
as necessary and all of our bull values
can also be adjusted as well you can
kind of see us playing with that there
so at this point like I said what I want
to do is kind of now that we sort of
have a little bit of this in place I
want to start to focus on getting the
debug system like sort of bringing it to
closure we've got all these like various
pieces in there I'd like to sort of try
to figure out how I can get these all
working together into a system that will
allow me to leverage what we've written
and also kind of continue on with with
with adding other things that we may
want so if late as leader and the
product if we come across something and
we're like you know what there's there's
probably this new debug thing that we
would really like to have that would
really help us out based on what we're
doing there'll be some clear way of
adding that into the system as it stands
so that's what I would like to do you
know that's that's how I would like
things to end up so this is kind of
interesting here actually using the room
based camera it's pretty funny actually
as I kind of go through it that's that's
pretty amusing I forgot that we have the
ability to switch between room based
camera and scrolling yeah Oh games
they're so wacky and weird all right so
anyway what I'm going to go ahead and do
now is I'm going to go ahead and start
playing around that and the first thing
that I'm going to try is I want to see
what I can do about starting to merge
this debug view with the ability to view
say those those what's what's my called
there the the profile the log profile
stuff I'm going to see if I can start a
kind of smoosh those two things together
so that we have a unified way of
interacting with them you know and so
one way that that I might try to do that
is is by putting them underneath you
know one of these things so that I can
like open up a profile and have it here
but so that I don't have to have it you
know it's something that kind of comes
and goes based on based on the hierarchy
right and like i said i don't know that
i don't know exactly where this will
lead but we're about to find out
and remember i also want to do a thing
where we could tear variables off to put
another thing in there so you know
that's a thing that i would like to do
at some point and we'll sort of we'll
see as we go how that goes alright so
here is a compilation directory there
okay so here is our debug stuff at the
moment the way that we're doing this we
don't have any way of putting something
like the profile group in there but you
know we've got these debug variable
types and I it seems pretty clear to me
that we should be able to go ahead and
add a debug hierarchy kind of concept in
here it seems like it should be pretty
straightforward right I should think
that I would be able to do something
like you know debug variable type I what
did I call the counter I think or
something like that I should think I
could do that and if we take a look at
how we've defined these things or rather
how we're drawing these things we should
be able to do something by just you know
taking a look at how I was drawing the
grass before and just start by putting
that into this system right like if I
look here we've got this sort of Steve
again thing here right if I if I look at
this I've kind of got I've kind of got a
thing that already draws them and the
way that the thing draws is it's
basically got these regions and it's got
its got two things right it's got
regions which are time spans and it's
sort of any given region is in something
called a lane you know and each lane is
like a cpu I'm sorry each lane is like a
thread right so you know I'm not sure
exactly what the the faintest way to
create something like this would be but
what it occurs to me when I kind of look
at it is that like you know I kind of I
would kind of like to potentially view
that stuff in multiple ways like I feel
like I would like to be able to make it
so that there isn't necessarily a hard
and fast rule about what is in the
hierarchy if you look at how we
out here you know when I create these
debug variables there's sort of a hard
and fast rule with that's in there so
when I have a debug group it expects to
have this kind of thing like a first
child last child sort of a situation
right and so what I would rather do is
I'd rather have probably some way of
saying well some things that are you
know in this hierarchy I kind of like to
be able to say well they don't
necessarily have permanent storage like
these guys do you know there you know
there may be things that are kind of
transient like we kind of have here
where we've got you know something where
there's just these regions and you know
maybe a you know depending on what I've
toggle the regions will show up in as a
series of lanes that can be expanded and
maybe a different way to toggle them
would be show up as a series of function
so we're gonna expand it you know
something like that and so as I go
through this i'm going to try to think
about whether there's a good way i could
make it so that i wouldn't have to worry
about the fact that you know i don't
want to have to sort of create all this
stuff at the outset right i'd like to
have some way of doing a more immediate
mode you i sort of thing for that right
and i think i've got a fairly good idea
how i might be able to do that okay so
if i take a look at when I write these
things out I'm thinking that what i
could do here is instead of counter what
I might do instead is make something
that's more like the top-level iterator
so instead what I'm going to try to do
is I'm going to say that like okay I've
got these debug variables in there and
they kind of say like what which kind of
variable they're looking at or whatever
but then I have another thing which is
like like debug variable type and it's
going to be you know a Elaine you know
maybe a lane list or something like a
list of lanes and then maybe I have
another debug variable type which is
like a you know some kind of parentage
concept so got the lane list in there
and then maybe I have a you know a
different thing which is like from a
particular function what was underneath
this function or something like that and
I guess you know maybe that's getting
ahead of myself you know counter
functionless counter laying this like
that so maybe I'll just start with one
and we'll see where we go from there so
if i wanted to do something like that
then what i can do is when we do the
create variables right after we do debug
create variables we can also do
something where we take those variables
and we you know create some some
additional you know we kind of a pen due
to the group that we started with right
so i could do something like where we do
that add variable thing where is that
guy handmade debug variables yeah so
where we do this thing where we do like
a debug add variable right I could just
at the end of this guy post penned
something to do that so let's do like
profile by lane or something like that
or profile by thread you know something
like this in fact that's really what I
probably should call it how let's call
this a counter thread list so I'm going
to add one of these guys and I gotta add
it to one of these contexts here and so
what I'm thinking is I kind of want you
know the variable add stuff to maybe not
do everything itself so maybe what I
want to do here right is I want to be
the guy who initializes this context
this kind of makes more sense too
because then it doesn't write to this
thing so I kind of like that better just
in general to be honest it's kind of
like all right I can pull that out I can
make it so that I create the context out
here and then I called debug variables
and I pass the the context into it do I
actually need state in here at all then
I don't so you just pass in the context
and then once you know you add stuff to
the context I can also myself add a
bunch of things to the context you know
what I'm saying so that seems kind of
nice so if i do debug add variable to
add something to the context you know
what i want to do sort
the direct one here I suppose where I do
context I profile by thread so that's
that's good so if i do that that will
give me back a debug variable this is
the thread thread list and I don't know
that we actually need any variables for
that because I think that's just freely
determinants deterministic as it is so I
don't know that there's anything else to
do for that so I'm just going to start
with that as a very basic thing and that
would add it to here and i think that
should in theory just work right oops I
gotta get rid of that at sign at context
comes context so again i'm just all I'm
doing here is just saying like let's try
to stuff these two things together and
we'll sort of see what shakes out of it
right and we'll see what we can do let's
see here at debug state and debug create
variables does not need to debug state
there we go so I think if i read this
i'm guessing oops drug debug menu do I
not set that anymore I thought I did oh
I I did not that's my bad i deleted one
of the lines there that i wanted to keep
I want the the debug state route group
of the hierarchy there whatever it was I
wanted to make sure that I still set it
so yeah so here's the root group now I'm
setting it correctly and so if i run
this i think i should be okay yeah so
when we create a debug when we do debug
variable to text obviously there is no
way to convert this guy and i'm assuming
that this is something that when i do
right hand made config as well i will
have to watch out for because when we do
right hand made config it's going to try
to turn that debug variable into text
right and i don't actually want to do
that or rather I don't want to ever save
these guys so you
I would I think well yeah maybe or do i
wanna i want them to show up there do I
not want them to show up there I don't
think they need to show up there so
anyway in right hand make it fig there's
some stuff that we don't want to do so
when we go through variables will
probably do something like just to test
whether or not a variable wants to be
printed so if you know should be written
we'll just check to see if this bar
should be written and we'll just have
sort of the notion but this thing and
what i can do is i can also put this
with the variables themselves so we can
just kind of see I'm sorry with the
where's that guy yeah with the variables
themselves so we can kind of say what we
want to have happen here right this is
just kind of like a predicate that says
for any given variable type do we want
to save this guy or do we not want to
say this guy like does this guy have to
be processed or not right and so really
what that's going to do be at the moment
is very simple which would just be okay
whatever the counter thread list is if
that's the type then we don't save it if
it's is the type we do save it but we
probably kind of add that in right we
kind of we presumably like make more
stuff there eventually so we're drawing
the menu now we have to think about this
a little bit more too so what we'll do
what we do here is we do debug variable
to text and you know for debug variable
the text now we've got so this notion
that there are functions there are
people who might want to do more
complicated you I like their own UI but
that's really easy again since we can
just do whatever we want we don't have
any weird like kind of crazy heart like
like object oriented class hierarchy
anything to deal with we can just do
whatever we want
so we can just say like okay when we do
this text nonsense right we can take the
the sort of the concept of the bounds
right we could we could sort of
formalize this a little bit more we
could take the concept of the bounds and
then when we I think we should probably
roll this up like this right we should
probably do something like that so what
we would do here is we basically find
out if there's any sort of cool
rendering that we want to be able to do
and then you know for the text case we
would produce the bounds by doing this
sort of action right so we knit we're
just having exactly the same thing that
we had before but now it passes through
and sets the bounds but we can now and
this is just for anybody who we don't
know how to do we'll just say hey if we
don't know how to do something with you
then go ahead and try to convert you to
text but if we have some kind of special
rendering that we want to do we can just
do it right so in here where we've got
the counter thread list and we want to
do some kind of rendering to it we need
to be able to produce the bounds and we
need to be able to you know draw it so
that's actually both relatively you know
those are both relatively simple right
because all we have to do there is take
a look at that drawing code that we had
which we do have around here somewhere
right let's see it's around here
somewhere p people's here it is right so
you can kind of see what's going on here
we've got our we've got our profile
drawing code and if i take this profile
drawing code and i just do exactly the
same stuff that we were doing for right
then I should be able to just insert
that profile into our little hierarchy
pretty easily right
so I'm just going to go ahead and pull
this out this entire thing out like so
do-do-do-do do-do-do-do there we go and
I'm just going to stick it right about
here and this is just going to be you
know I don't know Colonel Boyd raw
profile in or something like this you
know okay and what I'm going to do is
I'm just going to say well you know the
profiler just draws in whatever box we
tell it to so what I'm going to do is
I'm going to prescribe what the bounce
actually would be right and so here is
like sort of how the bounts are
constructed for the other one but I
don't really want to do that instead
what I want to do is just kind of use
the concept that like okay this is where
it would have started certainly so
that's all good although that's on the
baseline so we'll probably want to
offset it but at the moment that's
totally fine so this is the left corner
this is the you know the the top for now
but like I said we're gonna have to
offset I think that's actually the
baseline if i remember correctly i can't
remember but i think that's the baseline
so we may want to drop it down by the
baseline by the descender height so what
we want to do here is say like okay this
is the min corner right and the max
corner is going to be whatever the right
edge of the screen is which I don't know
whatever I don't actually know what that
is at the moment because I don't think
we ever define a right edge yeah so I'll
just go ahead and define one here so
we'll have a right edge like that so you
know it'll go over to the right edge and
we'll just do however big we want these
guys to be right and I don't know how
big it you know one of these graphs
should be we probably want to have some
kind of parameter that says how big they
are and so that'll probably something
that we you know we actually stick in a
parameter somewhere but for now let's
just say it's 100 pixels tall I don't
know why it just is that's how big it is
it's 100 pixels tall
all right okay so we've got our min
corner we've got our max corner here and
so if I want to make a rectangle I could
do that pretty easily I don't need any
of this stuff all I'd have to do now is
do a recommender max corner and then I
can just say like okay draw the profile
in and I would need to pass it you know
whatever it needs probably the debug
state would be my guess and then just
whatever the bounds are there's the
rectangle and so now I just have to make
this function be able to do whatever the
debug state you know stuff is that it
needs to do and then I need the bounds
right so the profile wreck just comes in
here now and then I can get rid of the
concept of it being in here at all
because now that stuff's in the UI in a
nice kind of clean way and so I can get
rid of all this stuff because I know
that I won't be getting called for any
other reason it wasn't weren't trying to
show it wouldn't get called i assume is
there an orthographic call somewhere
else yeah it starts right there so we
don't need that orthographic call either
at least I don't think so yeah there's
no reason to have that so we're all good
we've got the profile wrecked and we can
yeah we can go from there so at the
moment I'm not going to bother with this
although well you know what I could just
do it why not there's a profile wrecked
so here we go everything else should
work roughly the same let me go ahead
and look where that profile wrecked is
used profile wrecked there we go profile
wrecked you know profile wrecked profile
wrecked and off we go got to add that
right edge
okay debug should be written that is
true that should take the type of the
variable rectangle is actually rectangle
to I believe render group is probably
debug state render group ha and mouse p
so we need to do hit detection in here
which is totally fine as well Rob
profile in with the mouse be in there
but we're going to have to make that
stuff work with what we're doing so I'm
going to I'm going to get rid of that
hot record bit because we're going to
have to make this work with the rest of
the UI or even decide what that's going
to do you I wise because we don't really
know at this point alright so right edge
in this case is off of the debug state
there we go we've got our texts p what
is that for that is not supposed to be
there at all yeah that is part of this
guy and not necessary so that should
just go in there and this should
actually be so this since it's going
line advance I assume that at why should
actually be adjusted probably as part of
this but maybe it should just be part of
the bounds to it advance the way that it
does you know because you can see I feel
like when you get the text size and you
just go I may I don't know I mean can
you you can see why maybe the at why
should just be something that happens
out here based on the bounds so I don't
really love this but I'm gonna leave it
like this for a second but I do feel
like that's not great you know I feel
like we probably want something more
like this in fact you know what I'm just
going to do it this way for now so when
this guy does debug get text size what I
might do is say something like make sure
it's a certain size to to avoid like you
know
things being stacked differently or
something like that but but you know I'm
really just not going to care about that
stuff I'd rather have something that was
that was very reliable and does the same
thing every time for every path through
here especially in debug code so i think
what I'd rather do is say you know
forget all this stuff instead what I'm
going to do is I'm just going to say
after we draw something you know where
wherever at the at y is and we're going
to advance to the next thing what I'm
going to do is take whatever the bounds
are and I'm going to get the minimum of
that and the Y parameter of that is like
the next is like the lowest part now
that I would be advancing to you know
what I mean and so like here where we do
that hierarchy uip thing we start at the
Y or whatever you can kind of see what
I'm about changing sort of the idea of
what our why is because we want things
now that are not always text instead of
advancing like baseline wise I want it
to actually be like the upper left
corner of like the rectangles that we're
drawing of the rectangular things that
we're drawing so what I'm going to do is
I'm going to look at that uip thing
right you can see that it does the this
thing what uses at why you can see what
we did is we took Oh point 5 to type
that's the top of the screen then we
offset it by the font scale times that
starting base line y so what I'm gonna
do is going to remove that right that's
gone now and then what I'm going to do
is when we draw the text before we draw
the text I'm going to consider that
offset this offset right here to be
baked into the text drawing so that way
we give the text the upper left corner
and then it will offset down to where
the baseline is that way things that
want to draw rectangular lee don't have
to be like Oh where's the baseline
enough they don't have to think about
fonts at all which I like better so I
think that's a little more more nice so
we're going to have get min we're going
to get the minimum bounding box and what
we're going to do is we're going to
subtract away a spacing y value and the
spacing y value is just how many pixels
we want to leave between things so I
don't know you know that maybe we leave
four pixels between things I don't know
however many we want let's see get why
you know we could also do
some kind of a font scaling sort of
situation but anyway dot y must have a
class structure Union what is what is
this left of dot why what does get min
return early does it not return a does
not return the vector get min it's
getting in corner very well okay so
let's see what's going on here that does
not seem very good our rectangle is not
good what is wrong with our what is
wrong with rectangle why is rectangle
broken why so I've got my at X in my
here and then I get whatever the ah
that's that's why right so we need to
remember the min corner which is before
we offset this thing right that's
actually the sort of the left corner
there of our of our thing and then where
we draw the text is offset by the
baseline right so where we draw the text
oops there we go where we actually draw
the text is what's going to be offset by
the baseline like so that's more what
we're looking for so yeah so debug text
out that is where we're actually going
to draw the text out and let's see here
text be undeclared identifier yeah we
don't actually care about that um and we
use that there we go alright so let's
try that out ah
yeah I say mean court everything ok so
that is not that is not good that is bad
that is a bad thing that has happened
here and i am not sure what I did to
deserve that to be honest I feel like
that was correct but apparently it
wasn't so okay we have our min corner
that is the right location we then want
to do a yeah we then want to do a offset
to get ourselves to the baseline which
we do here and we should draw the text
we then take whatever the bounds
actually were that we ought that we
produced for whichever one of these you
know whichever case we were actually
working with when we produce the actual
bounds we then say whatever the lowest
point wasn't there that's what we want
our new top to be and we're going to
advance we're going to leave a little
bit of space in there so that seems it
right to me but I mousey forgetting
something at well for obvious reasons it
you know the fact that it's all
scrunched up it's not it's not how it
should go to say the very least so when
I get back this I feel like that should
be correct it offsets it by the min
corner and so I feel like that ah right
so I feel like part of the problem is
this is the top corner so that's
actually the max right that's actually
the max corner so I think that because
right we're saying we're at the upper
the very upper part so when I do here
like this this same thing here when I do
MIT min corner max corner this is that
standard thing where I always say I
think going down from the top of the
screen even though that's not the
correct case the min corner would
actually be the low point and the max
corner would be the high point right
look you can see there so I did the same
thing in this one and so the max corner
is actually going to be
or you can't even say max corner because
I don't know what the max corner is
going to be but point being I just know
that I've got sort of my my my left
point if you will which is this real
value and I've got my top point which is
this value and then when we get back
this rectangle and put put it in the
bounds what I need to do is say okay
that is essentially you know that's the
width and height of it right but now I
have to offset it by by a specific value
that's going to be constructed from
these guys so I want to offset it I want
to offset it by the the left PX that's
correct because I need to move it over
so that it starts there but in terms of
why I don't want to move it all the way
up I want to move it all the way up but
I want to move minus its width and I
guess that's why I sort of had
instinctively started to do it this way
I kind of have to be able to access
bounds itself to know what it is so
whatever like the height of the bounds
actually is however tall the thing is
i'm placing i need to offset it by at
what by the top less that amount so that
it will actually line up properly that
makes sense then when we draw we would
draw at these at these values like we
like we thought before so I think that
should be roughly correct I think it may
not be it's a good question
my mind that's kind of cool-looking by
the way all right all right so not quite
there yet but getting there slowly but
surely working my way out of thinking
from top down from the top of the screen
down okay so
do you think uh yeah yeah so debug text
out at that part is not really
particularly prob odorous or interesting
i don't think it's really just these
guys that are that are yeah that are in
the mix so when i create one of these
guys with the get text size when i go to
offset it I'm offsetting it by the left
PX and i'm moving it up to where i think
it should be in the screen based on
wherever the at y is right and then I
just remove however much height it was
so that puts it back you know that
aligns its top edge with the top P Y
value and that seems just about that
seems correct to me and if I look at
what's happening here when I do debug
text out I think that's correct because
I've starting at the left VX which is
where I think I should be and I'm
starting at the top you why but I'm
offsetting by whatever the baseline is
which is again what I think should
probably happen at least that seems like
what should happen and then I draw the
text once we have those bounds up that's
the problem I did not save my offset
bounds okay so it's still a little wonky
though right it still looks a little bit
weird and I'm not sure what's going on
there that's that doesn't seem quite
right and I'm not getting the
highlighting that I would have expected
to get so I'm still I'm thinking that
the bounds must still be a little bit
weird right although I didn't actually
look to see when i set the item color
okay that's the problem so i also need
to set my item color before i draw
things right that's obviously got to
have to happen so let's see so all right
so we're in much better shape now
however when i open this guy I'm kind of
getting my code is getting stuck here
what is the what is the oddity here and
make it fig ah
man it's it's been a sloppy day today
it's been a sloppy day today so things
that should not get written obviously
all we really want to prevent them from
doing is that we don't want to stop them
from iterating otherwise we'll go into
it go into an infinite loop where we
just loop on VAR all day even though VAR
is not changing all right so we're
getting a little better here and we can
sort of we still have a little bit of a
weird positioning thing you can see what
sort of happening there I believe that's
because we're taking into account again
the rectangles it depends whether you
have a descender how big your rectangle
is so that was the thing I sing before
we might want to sort of change a little
bit but you can also see now that we
have done the the first part of what we
wanted to actually do which is to
include one of these profiles in line
with our actual with the rest of our
actual stuff and so if I wanted to make
that expandable or collapsible all I
would have to do now is actually make a
group for it to live inside right so
that it can be expanded and collapsed
that you know because right now it
doesn't have any way of doing that so
when I add that thread list what i can
do is inside hamidou you know variables
stuff we have this ability to kind of
open groups and close them so what I can
do in here is just a look all right
let's go ahead and get a group around
that guy like so and this will just be
like profile or something I don't know
and you know I probably just called it
this by thread I suppose so if I've got
this wrapping the thread then I should
be able to when I open up the profile
you can see that now I've got that stuff
by thread there and you know I can
interact with it some degree I don't
think we want to yeah we're going to
have to think about exactly again how to
make this the UI for this thing a little
bit better but now we can at least kind
of open and close it along with
everything else we do have to do one
more thing which is that if we want we
probably want to fix those sort of guys
who are doing debug text line outs at
the bottom there because they're they're
not lined up properly and that's just
because when we actually sort of
print this stuff out where we do the
draw you know the menu draw stuff what I
want to make sure is that here right
we're sort of taking that at why I feel
like it's not quite it must I don't know
if that's because i'm setting the bounds
room on the min corner or something like
that but you can see that like
afterwards when we take this stuff oh I
know why it's because the debug text
line stuff does not include this offset
right it does not include the offset
doesn't use that top corner and so when
we do like debug text line text out at
the automatic stuff here where we're
using debug state at why that really has
to be again adjusted by the baseline
value if we want it to actually work
right if we want to be like Oh everybody
using sort of the min corner right but
then it's all good right then everybody
lines up properly and so on so i think
that seems pretty reasonable at least so
far right that all seems pretty
reasonable and hey now we can sort of
let's am I doing here now we can sort of
get that that profile in line and just
open it when we want it and so on right
and that's all pretty easy so yeah the
next step here is just to start making
this a little bit more sensible so I
feel like probably we'd want to clean up
a little bit of this stuff and then we'd
also want to start to think about how we
would actually make this UI thing usable
and you know you could imagine if I had
more than one of those so probably what
you want to do too would be something
like a you know when we begin the group
when our group debug group where where
is group must be here somewhere well
thread list
so this thing here where we do begin
variable group and very little group
really we probably want two of them
because we want we might want multiple
things in here so be right this probably
doesn't have a name because it's just a
big block of stuff and again you could
imagine in a second we'd probably have
you know by function or something in
here and have another way you know we'll
have another one of these that we could
do but for it for the moment i'll just
do both of them and this would be
function list like so so you know again
pretty basic stuff it's just now we have
ways of opening a profile views in here
so that it's kind of all looped into the
thing and now it's sort of annoying
because like you know we compile we
still have this kind of annoying compile
thing it was fun while it lasted but
again it just seems like a to owners to
kind of really have that be our model is
that we have to compile over time
because msvc just is not fast enough for
that but we can fix that as a separate
thing we do later so when we have
something like this you know the other
thing that you know you could imagine
wanting to do is like maybe we want to
be able to like resize how big these
profiles are or something like that so
if we wanted to change the size of one
of these profile views then it's pretty
easy because we already have a place
that we store extra stuff associated
with the the debug variable group you
know so any one of these debug variables
where we have stuff we can it's free for
us to just add a thing which is like oh
this is a debug like profile or
something thing you know debug profile
settings I don't know so this is like
profile and that comes to have some
stuff in it and I don't know what it
would want to have in it but you know
it's got the bug profile settings and in
it there's you know maybe something in
like dimensions so it has like you know
within a height to it that maybe you
could drag out and so if we did that
then we could allow that to be something
that's edited by
the user so that when we actually do a
draw a profile in instead of the profile
wreck that we do they're coming from us
just making an assumption about what the
max corner of the thing would be instead
what we could do is say like oh okay the
min corner of this thing is actually
going to be whatever the top is is minus
the dimension right so we've got the
profile settings there we're going to
minus the dimension x and then the I'm
sorry I didn't mention why and then in
the the max corner we're going to do
like okay whatever the the whatever the
left edge was the min corner we're just
going to take that and we're going to
move it over right so we're going to say
whatever the min corner x is plus
whatever the dimension x was something
like that right and so if we do that now
when we do one of those things where we
add the thread list sort of thing we go
oh threadless profile dimension equals V
2 I don't know it's like it's going to
be a 1024 why that's going to be hundred
tall or something like this right that's
like time big that one's going to be and
this one will be a different size right
this one will be like 200 tall it's like
this is taller we don't know why it just
is and so then when I open these you can
see that now they're like they're
different sizes right and we never did
put in anything that tries to clip these
guys that's something that we should
probably do eventually the renderer can
already clip them we just don't actually
say anything about it but anyway we can
see what size are supposed to be and so
if we wanted to we could probably put in
as well like a little handle here that
we use to like resize where stuff is or
something like that wouldn't wouldn't be
too hard right so like maybe we want to
make it so you can easily resize that
you want to be able to like have a
little handle there that you could grab
on and move back and forth and so if I
did that what I would have to do is when
I'm drawing these things when i do my
draw profile in right right after i do
that i could add a thing that was like
some kind of a little you know like a
little handle or something like that
like a little like a little grabbable
widget right so if I want to do
something like maybe do a push wrecked
and take wherever the max corner is I
guess it really wouldn't be the max
corner I guess it would be like a sort
of the size point or something like that
and the size point would be the min
corners or the max corners X and the min
corners why so it would be like the
lower because that's where people
usually think of sizing from the like
the lower right corner you know getting
that way so you know if we had run those
sighs Keys and we want to do a push
wrecked here here at it oops let's try
that one more time push wrecked there it
is so if I want to do a push back there
what i could do is say let's do a
wrecked centre-half dim and push in the
size P and how big do we want this to be
I don't know something like to buy two
or maybe it's bigger maybe it's 4 by 4
i'm not sure i don't really care at the
moment how big it is at all but there it
is so once that does this little thing
you can see now that we've got like a
little handle that we could drag here
right we've got a little a little piece
that we could manipulate like a
manipulator that we could do and so
again what we'd like to do is we'd like
to have some way of expanding the UI to
have the notion that that what I am
dragging at any particular time may not
just be on a value it may be something
else right and so again we already have
this concept sort of baked in there to
the UI oops no there we go to the UI
which is I've got and I don't really
know even remember what the functions
are these days like I said I brain so
addled most the time I have so much work
to do I like do work all day and then I
come home I'm just like I don't even
remember
we're doing on handmade hero but then I
see the code now I'm like oh right okay
so debug begin interact as a way of us
sort of saying what are we actually
interacting with here right and so the
problem that we would have is right now
our model is to just store a debug
variable and that's the only thing that
we know about we only know that we're
interacting with you bug variable but a
debug variable might have lots of
different handles to it now there's two
ways that we can go about sort of making
this a little bit different and you know
I don't know which one of them would be
the best way to do it there's there's
sort of like two different branch to go
around one is that we could just
introduce a synthetic debug variable
that's something like oh this is you
know I'm dragging this v2 it's a
synthetic debug variable that's a v2
that's the dimensions of this box and
then you still always have everything as
just a v2 but the other way to do it is
to sort of expand the notion of what I
am pointing at to be different things
right because since we already know that
we've got like different debug
interactions that might happen what we
can do instead is change this concept
where we do the begin interact to be
instead of it picking what the
interaction is going to be based on the
thing that it sees it's just going to
pick the interaction based on what the
person who like place the things there
says it was probably going to be right
now I know that sounds a little bit
strange but just bear with me for a
second so here's our interaction types
right so let's say that what I did is I
said okay there's a debug interaction
and inside here right I have whatever
the hot variable and the next top
variable and that sort of stuff is right
well let's suppose I also have something
like debug interaction hot interaction
hot interaction what that is is this a
thing that says when I was mousing over
something if it's some kind of a special
purpose manipulator it may want to say
hey I know that normally you would do
thing x by looking at the variable and
picking something but I want you to do a
different thing and I'm going to tell
you what that thing is right so we hear
what we would say
is ok check to see if whatever the hot
interaction is is valid if it is we just
assume that that's what you're going to
do right that's the thing to do so when
we do like next hot here or whatever and
we do that stuff let's go ahead and do
that so when we clear this stuff out
we'll just say well when we're about to
do a sweep right the next hot
interaction is going to be cleared to
debug interaction then and then when we
process next hot which we process like
they're here we will do oops a hot
interaction next hot interaction there
we can and hopefully you can kind of see
where this is going I assume that you
can so if I want to I can just say debug
interaction like sighs sighs resize
profile for now I don't want to get too
far ahead here so how to say okay look
we're going to do a thing where we can
resize the profile and so what happens
is when we're interacting with this
thing you know we'll go in here and
we'll say yeah like where is where is
this where are you where are you
we had you in a second sighs p there we
are we just take whatever the rectangle
was this is the size box reproduce the
size box we're going to draw it and what
we can do is we can say oh well okay you
know like we were doing down here when
we do is in rectangle what we might want
to do is say okay we make we we may want
to set the next hot thing to be equal to
yeah I'm thinking about this I feel like
we kind of want the hit testing to be a
little more specific so i think you know
we want to do something like that right
so what I want to say is I want us to
size box first so if it's in the
rectangle of the size box I want to do
one thing if it's if it's not going to
do another right and so what I'll do
here is debug state next taught
interaction zero but in this case I'll
do next site interaction equals resize
profile you know I'm saying and I can do
the same thing that I was doing before
so for example in here I can actually do
a thing where I say like okay when I
push this wrecked on I can do a test to
see whether the currently hot
interaction is my interaction right I
could say is the current interaction
that would be hot is that resize profile
and am i hot right like you know and I
could also do something like this is hot
and that
and if it is again I can do the yellow
thing and if not I can do the white
thing you know so testing whether
something is hot we already do it's what
we do right here so instead of making
that be just a test for the color what
we would do is we just say okay that's
actually now the test that we just save
and then the item color is just you know
I'm going to see are we hot or are we
not hot right and now we know the item
color right so yeah and we could also
say in here you know we could do things
like if it's hot in and the interaction
is not you know we could do something
like this as well debug stay hot
interaction equals zero something like
this let's a bunch of things we can do
I'm just putting some new stuff out
there and you know normally we'd
probably collapse these things up down a
bit but like I said one thing in time
right okay so once we get that in theory
we should be able to see a little
something happening here right which is
that when I mouse over this it turns
yellow so now you can see that i'm
actually highlighting a particular piece
of this guy but of course when I
actually interact with it nothing
actually happens and the reason for that
is because we haven't actually written
anything right to actually do the
interaction but it's not particularly
hard to write that interaction right if
i want to write that interaction when we
are doing our mousing around you know in
here i can just say oh well if you know
if the interaction type is to resize the
profile then i can just say well okay
you know whatever the group sorry
whatever the the profile dimensions are
i'm just going to go ahead and add to
them whatever the d mouse is right and
that'll change the dimensions but what i
would also like to do when I you know
when i change the dimensions I want to
make sure
that I don't go below a certain value so
I'll also do something like you're well
okay you know if the profile Dimension X
is less than you know some minimum you
know I won't let it get less than like
10 by 10 or something right all right
don't really know exactly what I want to
say there but something like that I
could do you know this like third
dimension x equals min you know
something like that you know I'm Sam so
again really really simple nothing
particularly tricky here I don't
remember what our min function is in
this particular thing but I'm pretty
sure we have one minimum somewhere
anyone platform minimum in do we have
them in and actually know if we have a
min minimum apparently we do we'll just
say that we do uh so you know now if I
open this right uh oh dear well that
didn't go quite as I'd planned how did
that change in the way that it just did
d mashpee should not be particularly
large am I wrong about that oh that's
why yeah if you want to clamp something
you don't want to use minimum you want
to use maximum yeah and it looks like
our mouse is upside down as well right
from the screen coordinates which which
is a little janky so what did i do there
to deserve that if the mouse is changing
it should have increased oh so I must
negate the Y value right when I actually
subtract so when I do my
I size boxer you know it I start at the
top and i subtract the dimension down
which means that you if you move up if
you moves in positive Y the thing should
actually get smaller which is crazy but
that's just how that goes right so it's
really this kind of a thing you know I'm
saying so that's you know again a really
simple way to just kind of make that in
there so now you know okay we want we
want to make it so that we can have some
profile graphs and that's all good you
know it's fine it's fun whatever we can
size those guys and you saw how easy
that was for me to add right just based
on the way that it that it goes now you
don't usually want to actually do
resizing this way you want to actually
use the Delta from point A Delta from
point method the reason I say that is
because like you can see what happens
here if because I'm just adding the
Delta once you clamp the mouse is now
wrong you know I'm saying so you know if
you want to be a little more swanky
about it what you actually do is like
record what the down click point was and
whatever but for debug you I don't know
that we care about that hopefully
everyone understands that's not you know
something that we're trying to do for
any kind of fancy you I but you can kind
of see like again it's really easy for
us to add that in there and that's what
we want we want it to be easy to add
that now we can make it even easier to
add stuff like that by starting to
compress out some of that code that's
kind of like a little bit janky in there
now that I just kind of like put it in
and you know kind of wrote it in place
but there's a bunch of things we can do
to make that even easier as well and
maybe we'll take a look at some of those
tomorrow but for now I think we're
getting towards the end of the time
limit because I think I started around
ten if that makes sense but we're
getting pretty close to some to some
good stuff here right and hopefully you
know you can see where where this sort
of thing is going right and yeah there's
there's a
there's this couple things I'm not sure
about yet like I'm not sure how we're
going to draw this the profile you I but
at least it's kind of all in one system
now and that's kind of good and I think
that we could also do a pretty easy
thing here where we kind of we could
compress all this stuff into a pretty
clean thing where we just have you know
profile and debug kind of things so we
could we could it you could imagine
doing something like this right let's go
grab a group so in here if I were to do
something like this we're at the start
of the context I just go like debugging
or something like this and then close it
here you know now I've kind of got this
this notion of a root group up there
where it's out of our way and it doesn't
come into being until we start to like
you know grab stuff from it you know
what I mean so that's kind of nice too
so yeah all right I'm going to go ahead
and go to the QA let's take a look if
anyone has any questions about what I
was doing feel free to to put a queue
coal in front of them and ask me
Panik 00 do you think this way of
structuring UI code to be used to build
a full application or is it just useful
for the bug you is what extra things do
you think you'd need to add to make it
useful for a full app UI um well so the
I guess what I would say is I can draw
you a visual diagram it's going to be
amusing here is what I would say
so essentially I would say yes this way
of structuring the code does totally
work for doing a full app but the
problem is it's not like you like we're
just at the beginning of the stuff that
you would implement for that so even
you'll see me do probably one or two
compressions on this before we're done
but there's a lot more sort of
compressions you go through like you
will like the first thing you do and
we'll do this later right is you take
this stuff now hopefully you can see it
start to grow do you see how we have
debug interaction debug variable for the
hot interaction and the hot variable
we're interacting with but then we have
this next Hut interaction next not that
there's a concept there which is like
the memento it's like the thing the
interaction cookie if you will that
stores the information that's necessary
to understand what will start happening
if the user should click down at this
point right and that becomes a more
complicated data structure that is not
just ad hoc like this okay then you've
got other stuff like the interactions of
cells have state there's like a bunch of
stuff that will happen along the way and
you know we're going to stop with the
debug system we're going to stop like
here this is this is where we will stop
and there's all this other stuff that
happens in between so nothing I'm I'm
doing now is stuff that you wouldn't do
on the way to doing the full app version
but there's just a lot of stuff that
happens along the way and so that's
that's how i would say it
let's see Connor rents were you nervous
the first time you streamed handmade
hero no I I was not really for whatever
reason I feel like it's a lot like you
can see me but I can't see you right and
I feel like one of the things that's
true about the nervousness of public
speaking is the actual physical like you
seeing a large group of people that you
are communicating with makes people
nervous you know and if you keep you
can't see that there's a large group of
people like I mean I you know I to see a
number if I can't see all those actual
people there's it I don't think it
elicits the same kind of response that
that actually publicly speaking to that
many people would elicit you know and so
I feel like I feel like it's pretty hard
to get to get really nervous about
streaming something because it doesn't
evoke the kind of response that like you
know you know we've had streams where
they've been like three thousand people
on or something when it was on the front
page of twitch if you actually got up in
front of 3,000 people that's kind of
crazy like to see that many people
that's a huge number of people and I
think that would have an effect on
someone I don't know if it I don't
affect on me personally but it would
generally have an effect I would think
but if you just are streaming to 3,000
people well it's no different than
streaming to one person as far as the
actual sensory input that you get on the
stream I just see one webcam no matter
how many people there are out there and
so I just it just doesn't have an effect
you're just like I'm just programmer on
computer you know the big giant head to
what do you think about GCC and it's dbg
I do not like debugging generally on
those systems gdb is just not a very
good heads up debugger it's a good you
know it does the features you need for
the most part but just the the console
the heads up of it it just doesn't let
you debug that as the as efficiently as
you need to
so you know it's finding a pinch but
it's just not a good everyday to bugger
and so you know as a thing that you use
like you know typically my interacts
with GDB I try to keep to just like i'm
porting somewhere and so I don't care
how efficient to the bugging is because
I've already written like ninety-nine
percent of the code and I'm just doing
the port or whatever in that it's fine
but yeah do you ever get your IRS be
fixed to show names again no hex chat
still never doesn't show me needs to be
fair I haven't tried like I didn't
actually try to get it working but no it
did not spontaneously start working
Archer awful have you considered working
at valve what is your opinion of them
and their structure um well I mean I did
interview at valve long long ago and
like in 1998 I think but I did not
decide to work there I decided to go
work at gas powered games i thought the
game they were making was more
interesting I don't really like
first-person shooters that much the last
time I liked a first-person shooter it
was doom so I didn't really like the
idea of working on half life which is
what they were working on at the time it
was right at the very end of the project
I think and so I I have never really
considered working there after that for
again pretty much the same reasons I
mean you know talking about their
structure or other things like that
there's plenty of things to like or not
like about valve structure just like
there's plenty of things to like and not
like about any company that you might go
to work for and so to some degree it's
more about like what are the what you
know what would I be working on and am i
interested in doing that thing and for
to a large extent you know valve just
isn't doing the things that I would
necessarily be interested in doing if
that makes sense but you know
like I said if you're going to go work
somewhere of the places you could work
you know Brad game tools is probably my
favorite place but you know valve you
know they pay very well right and
there's a lot of people there who I like
I have a lot of friends who work at
valve and so you know I it wouldn't it
would not bother me if you'd like you
have to go work at valve that that would
not be I wouldn't be like oh my god
that's going to be off for anything I
feel like that seems totally reasonable
i don't i don't think it would be my
first choice because i just i don't get
excited about perhaps working on you
know you know i mean at whatever it is
that that would be like dota or
something right I just I just don't like
that sort of thing very much and it
would be hard for me to really get super
motivated about that so I don't know I
mean maybe you know working on the VR
system sounds like fun they got some
digits and really good stuff there so
that might be interesting and and you
know the other thing would be like maybe
work on steam for a while there's a
bunch of things about seem you know that
maybe it would be interesting to change
or something I don't know but hopefully
that's a good enough answer
crow activities what will the game look
like in 25 episodes it shouldn't look
really any different from now because I
we just have we still have a few engine
things to finish up so I'm really just
assuming that like we'll probably do
like the art changeover to start like
putting actual stuff in it like you know
let's say 2 50 to 40 I don't know I mean
it depends it's hard to say I don't try
to pick those things because I don't
like to rush things you know the point
is to be educational here and if the
main point is people want to like just
make a game doesn't really interest me
very much right like you know that's if
you're just trying to make a game
quickly then and you don't really care
about like the quality or in how to
program the system's it you know then
you know go grab game maker and drop
some sprites in or whatever right so so
I don't want to rush things when I say
that like maybe we'll be there this
that's just an estimate based on where
we are and like like I said 200 episodes
was like kind of my my feel at the very
start I was like it'd probably take
about 20 episodes through the engine
stuff and you know where we could have
blitzed it to do that we could have not
done this debug code much and just
focused on finishing the lighting and
the Z stuff and and probably hit that
but I don't want to do that I I want
things to take as long as they take and
I want to be able to spend time showing
people how to do stuff even if that
thing is not one hundred percent
necessary I want to be able to do things
that aren't my percent necessary ins
show here's how you make a little you I
if you need one so that people know
their trucks will you be using profiling
tools like jeepers fi hot spots in the
code or rely on your own debug system
only I think we will probably we have
pretty good profiling now so I don't
know that we will really need something
like gpf we do use I ACA though to dump
our assembly we've used that on the
stream before and we would use that
again
to take a look at the instruction counts
for sure yeah yeah
and again yet to on the on the time
thing the thing to remember is 197 is
197 hours so like you know figure round
that up to 200 hours 200 hours if you're
sued you're working like even like you
know even 20 hours a week which is like
half time programmer right that's 10
weeks it's a pittance of time right so
you know it sounds like a lot because
it's a it said sounds like a day but
it's not a date it's an hour it's hardly
any time at all right and so I feel like
if you look at how much stuff we've done
into it ours its kind of staggering I'm
like I feel like if anything we went
pretty fast and you know if I wasn't
worried about the fact that I don't want
to spend like seven years of my life
streaming this program I would ago I
would have actually probably go like
let's go slower right because I could
spend more time talking about individual
things or you know explore more options
for things and show people stuff so it's
generally the case I think we've
actually made pretty fast time and I
really don't want to go any faster and I
know that some people just don't care
and they're impatient about stuff too
and they just want to like see some
particular thing that they care about
but all I can say is really like that's
not going to happen like it's it's never
going to be rushed one way or the other
and like I said if anything I feel like
it went pretty fast because at the end
of the day we just haven't spent that
many hours on it have you met Michael a
brush or carmack in person yes i have
met both of them in person
I mean you know I've I've met Carmack a
few times at conventions and meetings
and stuff like this Michael a brash you
know we worked you know work two offices
down from me for three years four years
something like that so I mean I know
Mikey brush very well
so we all good here
I guess we don't got no more questions
so I'm going to close this down Odin six
or seven are you going to see the
Martian um I don't know I have not read
the book and I don't know Anna Anna I
read the book and she was going to the
movie she said it was a really good book
I don't know if I should maybe when she
goes to movie i'll ask her if i should
read the book first or something or if I
should just go see it icarus you talked
about products you like to program we
are seeing a bunch of space games now
after being without decent ones for a
while are you interested in space games
at all um I guess I am interested in
space games at all but you know I'd have
to think about it I want a real joystick
like in the old days we used to have
that nice proportional flight stick I if
I was going to play a space game I would
want like a really good joystick for it
and I would want the game to be like
good like the old x-wing game was I
don't like these stupid like I didn't
like Wing Commander I don't like the
model of just like some people randomly
flying around sort of shooting at each
other just kind of flying in loops all
the time and not doing anything
interesting I like the idea of like
having a lot more sort of intelligence
in the game and like situational
awareness and stuff and managing things
like you know like the x-wing games had
like you know this content that you
manage your shield and your power and
your other stuff you're you're firing
pattern and stuff if I was going to play
a game again I would want it to be like
really high quality space game I don't I
wouldn't just play some random stupid
space game where you just kind of street
at stuff a little bit and it's boring so
so it depends and I have not bothered to
order a joystick and I have not actually
gone and looked to see if any of these
new space games are
going to have that kind of quality to
them like I don't know if eval curry has
that I don't know if you elite dangerous
has that I did play enemy Starfighter
but it was really early still and it
just didn't didn't seem to have a lot of
that stuff yet in terms of the feel and
and I have so you have an IV also not
played limit theory but that it looks
like it's still pretty early as well I
did play kerbal space program a kerbal
space program kind of felt to me like
the physics engine wasn't good enough
for what they were trying to do like
you'd build these things but it seemed
kind of arbitrary it was like like a bad
spring-mass model or something it just I
don't know it just didn't work and so I
felt like if you're going to do kerbal
space program right it should have like
a awesome physics engine like it should
have a physics engine so good that you
can test it like NASA rocket on it and
it'll be correct so I q 144 when is the
next Casey drink and game night ah um
you know I I don't really know about
that it prop you know maybe in two to
three weeks something like that those
are pretty infrequent those tend to be
pretty good frequent so
Graham 70 star citizen yeah I did not
mention star citizen because I have
never looked a star citizen it sounded
to me like that thing was kind of an
epic disaster where they just took a ton
of money but don't necessarily have like
this sort of they don't necessarily have
the kind of a structure or like teams in
place that can execute the kind of thing
that they're talking about which is
massive and so I'm really nervous about
star citizen I kind of feel like that
may be one of those things where like a
hundred million dollars goes into a
giant hole somewhere is never seen again
but you know I don't know so so I don't
know what's going to happen with star
citizen that's that's going to be
interesting to see I hope that it
doesn't happen because I don't want I
don't really like when people get burned
by crowdfunding because then you know it
makes them may be less likely to crown
fun things in the future and there's
been a lot of stuff that's been
crowdfunded that's you know I'm really
happy with craft fun and I want people
keep doing that and so they've taken so
much money and you know they weren't
even like a studio to begin with right
and so you know you end up here with
like 80 million dollars or something and
you're supposed to build this gigantic
game and like i don't know i mean like i
said i hope i hope it i hope it goes
okay at least passably i hope it doesn't
crash and burn in a spectacular fashion
because I think that would be pretty bad
you know for maybe it would kind of ruin
it would kind of take away some goodwill
from the crowd funding because so it's
so high visibility so so hopefully you
know it doesn't it doesn't go too wrong
you know cuz elite dangerous went really
well it seems like right like they took
money for that craft find they got a
reasonable amount they it seems like
they shipped the game you know in a
reasonable amount of time and it's you
know it seems like it's what they said
they would deliver you know I don't know
if it's like the best game ever anything
or if it's what people exactly want to
but you know they delivered right so so
yeah
correct tivities how did you end up
working on the witness and what does it
like to get jobs as a freelancer I
probably don't really know that I answer
the second question but so in terms of
how you end up working on the witness
that was just like John's a good friend
of mine and I knew that they might need
some help so it was really just a like
you know it was it was like a friend
thing I don't really know what much
about what it's like to get jobs as a
freelancer because again I've really
only mostly worked for just my friends
and and you know I if you just if you
don't just already know places who would
want you to do work for them I don't
know what you would do I'm not really
sure start your pancakes if star citizen
does end up delivering do you think it
has a potential to change the current
publisher triple a model or do you think
it will be a one-shot regardless of a
success uh well I mean like anything
else I'm not sure that even the people
who did it would be able to reproduce it
but you know I don't think it has that
much of a of an impact on the publisher
triple a model because it's really no
different than the publisher triple a
model at some level right the current
publisher triple a model is about
charging a lot of money for a game like
sixty dollars and then up selling you on
a bunch of stuff right like in game
stuff or pre-order bonuses special
editions season passes as exactly what
star citizen does right so I mean what
would chain nothing would change like
the triple a model is exactly like star
citizen at some level and the only
difference is publishers don't have to
get the money up front because they have
the money so there's no real need for
them to do so but yeah so so i don't i
don't think it would change things too
much but i don't know you know
all right I'm gonna wind down where
where my page at there it is thank you
everyone for joining me for an enough
sort of handmade here at San
undercoating with you as always if you
would like to follow along at home you
can always pre-order the game and it
comes with the source code and you can
play around that source code at home
experiment and learn from the source
code in your own time you can do that on
handmade hero dorg we also have a forum
site you can go to where you can ask
questions you have a patreon page you
can subscribe to to support the video
series we have a tweet but the tweets
scheduled at you if you want to catch
the video series live and we also have
if you type handmade con org into your
browser we have a convention happening
December fifth you can buy tickets right
here I will say that the tickets sold a
lot faster than I thought they were
going to sell and we've already sold
more tickets than the number of tickets
that I thought that I was hoping we
would get so yeah I am a little bit
nervous that we may have too small of a
space I was thinking there was no way we
would fill 275 seats but that is looking
like maybe that was not such a safe bet
because I haven't even announced the
speakers yet and pretty much all of the
speakers are much bigger names than I am
in the industry so I am a little nervous
about what will happen but yes that's
just bet it's better to be have too much
of just into little interest and so
we'll just leave it at that and what
popcorn wait there is a limit oh yeah so
there that when I in here where you look
at the thing where I'm talking about 275
275 is the total number of people we
could fit in the room like that's it so
after 275 there's no i mean because
right like i had to have to rent a space
i picked you know a space that i thought
would be big enough and you know it's
expensive to rent places so
I just picked a place that would be
reasonably inexpensive and nice but that
means it only fits two hundred
twenty-five people I felt that was
pretty safe because you know how many
people are going to travel to this but
it looks like maybe I don't know what
will happen so we'll see but yeah I
guess what I would say is maybe if you
know you really want to go to handmade
con and you haven't bought a ticket yet
you probably want to buy tickets soon
I'm nervous what's going to happen when
I post the speaker list yeah I don't
know what's gonna happen point being
there's a con it's going to be pretty
awesome it's probably going to be really
ridiculously awesome actually I'm really
looking forward to it so if you're
interested in that definitely sign up
for that and yeah and then i'll see you
in december but until then like i said
i'll be back here tomorrow 5 p.m.
pacific daylight time doing some more
programming kind of like the way that
debug UI stuff is starting to shape up I
think there's a lot of fun things we can
do with it I want to get the profiles
working and I want to clean up some of
that stuff so we've got several days you
know i i'd like to do tomorrow and then
probably like next week i'd like to
spend just doing debug UI stuff and kind
of just getting all that stuff into a
nice clean package for us to use and so
we'll be doing that so again 5 p.m.
pacific daylight time tomorrow until
then p SF on programming on your own and
i will see you guys on the internet take
it easy everyone