hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode a complete-game live on
stream we're gonna start the stream
today with a question we got because
it's actually very germane to what we're
doing
here on day 437 the question was I was
watching the previous stream came from
the trap I was watching for your stream
about getting better noise stamping and
wondering why you need any randomness if
you obtain a pretty and evenly well
covered sampling Hemisphere I think
that's a great question I think I kind
of mentioned the answer when we were
talking about letting before but we
didn't really harp on it and it is
important I think to harp on it simply
because it is a important thing to
understand about sampling and so let's
talk about it okay so what we need to
talk about is under sampling
specifically and the consequences of
under sampling because that's all we're
dealing them that's the whole thing
we're dealing with here right our
problem is that we have a system that we
know we could get perfect results from
if we just threw a ton of samples at it
right and we saw that happen when I turn
on the accumulation version and we just
let you know 60 frames or something
accumulate we end up with a nice pretty
stable lighting solution right so we
pretty much know for sure that there's
no problem with the algorithm if it was
off line our problem is with running the
algorithm on too few of samples right
having it have to produce a lighting
result without being able to sample as
much as it wants to that's all we're
doing right so the question that the
person had on chat is well why can't we
just not use random samples right why
can't we just say like alright you know
if I'm sampling here and I just sample
out in a few equally spaced directions
and I know that that won't have any
noise because you know it's not changing
the sampling directions isn't that
sufficient can't we just stop there
right and the problem with this is
because it's and and again the reason I
wanted to kind of open talking about it
is because it's critical to understand
what the functions domain is that you're
sampling and what will happen if you
undercover certain parts of that domain
as a result alright so let's look at
this lighting for our hemisphere is
talking about sampling a function that
looks like this effectively right we
have a hemisphere
and that hemisphere for the surface we
could parameterize with two angles right
we could look at it as like how far
around the hemisphere you're going you
know and then how far up let's say
really anything we want
it doesn't matter there's just two
degrees of freedom doesn't matter how we
parameterize it but there's two degrees
of freedom to create a hemisphere right
and we could talk they could be anything
that could be X&amp;Y and then you just
normalize Z right or something right so
it doesn't matter what you put here I
don't care just any two parameters that
get us so that if we did the whole range
of them right like in this case like 0
to 2 pi and 0 to PI over 2 right because
you can only lift it up that high right
if we just do something there I don't
care what it is as if you densely
sampled it you would get the right
answer and then we have time right now
why do I include time in here well I
include time in here because this
function changes over time there's you
know a light and that light doesn't stay
here necessarily that light may move
over here over the course of a second
let's say and so as it moves we would
expect the the lighting answers to
change right they're not going to be the
same all right so let's suppose we hold
T constant so our game is not moving
it's just a static steam in the case
where it is just a static scene
what happens to our domain sampling
right we're sampling the hemisphere I'm
gonna look from top down because just
easier to talk about it we don't need
the extra dimension really so we can
even just think about one of these
dimensions at this point which is theta
right so as I'm sampling what I'm doing
is I'm looking out into the world and
I'm seeing the sorts of things that I
hid out here and sometimes because of
the sampling density I will miss things
entirely right they just I just won't
hit them make sense
now normally if we were doing rate
racing for reals in an offline renderer
we would be rate racing from way more
points than we're rate racing from right
now right now we're only rate racing
from like like for example one little
point here at the centre of this big
reflector right or maybe for points one
in each corner or something right but
normally in a ray tracer we'd be tracing
from lots of individual little points
right and so the question of if we were
to take randomness out of the system
right because randomness means that
every time we sample we will get
slightly different answers if we're
under sampled right because sometimes
we'll hit things like sometimes we'll
randomly hit this and sometimes we
randomly won't that leads to noise in
the answer that we see right so as these
vectors jitter around sometimes they hit
brighter things sometimes they get
darker things that's the source of the
noise so what the person on the chats
proposing is like why don't we just not
do that so the first answer is because
okay
something not relevant to our game let's
say this or just an offline ray tracer
what would happen is the noise that you
now no longer see in terms of the
changing brightness of a particular
point goes into noise across points so
this point and this point and this point
will all hit differently right so some
of them will be brighter and some of
them will be darker and you'll end up
with noise there right so what the
temporal noise attempts to do is smooth
that noise out by giving everyone a
little bit of flicker so that over time
they still look like they're all roughly
the same amount of lighting right so by
locking it in what you're effectively
saying is well now I'm gonna have stark
lighting changes especially if we said
we're gonna use the same hemisphere for
every point then you would see like you
know dark dark dark bright bright bright
dark dark dark as you've moved across it
would be like these little bands right
to be really bad okay but so maybe you
don't care about that because that's not
what we're doing right so that's fine so
now let's talk about
releasing this constant right instead of
willing T constant let's talk about what
happens when a light moves through the
scene
well now what happens is you get really
bad behavior because as this light moves
through the scene that noise that was
previously distributed amongst pixels in
the offline case is now distributed over
frames in our case instead of having a
little bit of flicker but generally the
right lighting amount what we have is a
stable lighting that appears to be dark
as the light moves across this ray it
becomes bright all of a sudden and then
as it moves away it becomes dark again
right so what you've done is you've
pushed a flicker that was happening
across frames that was just gentle and
consistent but reflective of the actual
lighting into a perfectly solid very
dark color that then gets very bright
all of a sudden and then very dark again
right and so what I'm trying to impress
upon you is that when you are under
sampled if you do not want to have
randomness in your initial sample you're
still going to get the noise coming out
somewhere else the question is where is
it going to come out and at least for my
taste
actually if I have to pick between those
two in the end I'd rather have the
flicker especially cuz this is a night
time game most of our light sources are
going to be kind of flickery anyway I
would almost say the flicker that's more
accurate in you know on average is
actually better than perfectly stable
but highly erroneous result all the time
and so that's really how to think about
Monte Carlo if you take randomness out
of a sampling problem that really does
have a very complex domain you're going
to push the noise somewhere the question
is where do you push it and all the way
you could literally summarize all of the
techniques involved in Monte Carlo
sampling they are all about only one
thing and that is pushing the noise to
the least objectionable play
that is all that all of them are about
because there is no way to get rid of
noise in a Monte Carlo problem that
you're under sampling period the noise
is there the question is how do you push
the noise to the place that causes the
lease objection all visual artifacts all
right hopefully that clarifies things a
little bit I and yeah and that explains
a little bit more about why you it's not
as simple as just saying well you know
we know that it's stable if we don't
introduce any noise so how about we just
don't introduce any noise it's like well
that noise we're introducing is actually
pushing noise that we don't want out of
the place that it previously was and it
is important to push it out of that
place so we're moving the noise from one
place to another I think to a place that
we actually would prefer it to be in
this case but again those are decisions
you're free to make like I said the
important thing to understand is you're
not getting rid of the noise you're
moving the noise always so you have to
just think about are you moving it to
the best place that it could go right so
anyway and like I said you know just
looking at the way the lighting is
working at the moment I also do think
like that flicker is not really
objectionable to me if you imagine this
light source is supposed to be a candle
or a fire or a torch right it actually
looks just fine and so since this game
does take place at nighttime I would be
inclined to leave that noise in so that
we don't get some of the more
objectionable artifacts in other cases
as well right so that's probably the way
I would summarize what's going on at the
moment hopefully that makes some sense
if it doesn't I apologize
but yeah but there you go so at the end
of the last stream time I was talking
about how to introduce blue noise onto
the sphere and you can see we made a
sphere here that's a blue noise based
sphere and the questions that sort of we
were working on was just how exactly we
would allow this sphere
to have its points very so that we could
sample neighborhoods around these points
more efficiently right and the other
thing that we needed to figure out is
how we were going to ask cast coherent
Rea bundles this coincidentally is also
a problem that we would have if we went
with the spiral based sampling speech
schemes same problem we just need some
algorithm on the back end to figure out
how we cluster these into bundles that
will probably hit similar geometry
because the more disparate the bumble
the bumble that's good
I like that array bumble I guess so
if you put rays together that are
coherent maybe that's a ray bundle but
incoherent maybe that's a ray bumble
anyone any takers whatever anyway so
putting those together into a coherent
ray bundle so that's for example these
four are picked to send together because
they go out in similar directions as
opposed to say picking this one that one
that one in that one which would all go
in completely different directions and
never need to do any of the same
geometry tests those will have
significant effects on our performance
because we're not doing any kind of ray
re-up we don't once a ray has terminated
we don't really have a good way to re
stream it in so all of our rays go
through all of the checks that all of
the Rays need to do in the bundle and
that means that the closer they are to
hitting the same stuff the better right
so that's you know that's where we're at
so given that yeah I don't know if I
just want to cluster things on this or
what
we could do some kind of K clusters on
this to produce some clusters of four
I'm not sure what else we might want to
do there the other interesting thing
about this is you know if you imagine
tessellating this sphere and producing
your analyst inside if that's another
way to go anyway
I don't remember I'm gonna take a look
here I don't remember if we saved our we
did so we've got you know a couple of
different things here in terms of sphere
creation right we have a couple
different ways in which the sphere is
getting created
so one thing we might want to do here
too is pull those out into you know
routine for generating this for just for
our own testing purposes really where we
can kind of say like okay let's you know
have some different routines we can
switch between well we're testing and
obviously we'll only weld one in when we
find the one that we definitely want to
use but you know for testing we may want
to be able to be a little more flexible
and switch between different
tessellations of the spheres that we can
actually use here right so I think the
first thing we do is just get that into
place so that we can do some testing
with them and that'll basically be
something you know in here that we can
use to generate our sphere and play
around with it from there
so if you take a look at the way this
was working we've got this like points
buffer here and what I'd like to do is
just go ahead and make that you know
sort of an array out here we can we can
play with separately and I'll put a
little sample point count out here as
well although actually I guess we always
need to produce 64 of them so maybe you
know that can just be something that
happens only inside the routine I
suppose that's that should be fine um
and so then what I can do is I can kind
of make ways of creating these routine
ways of switching between which routine
we want to produce the sample points so
for example here where
I've got all this stuff I can grab this
out like so and then make one routine
for the spiral and one routine for the
blue noise so here we go on
you know generate spiral samples or
something like this and generate song
samples Poisson obviously being another
way of referring to blue noise or a
pull-on rather as a pattern that happens
to exhibit blue noise might be a better
way to say that so here is our spiral
sample this is the spiral sample version
we had here oops that the wrong place
there we go so if I take a look at what
happens here what I can do is make it so
that we pass in the random series here
and that way as it goes we should be
able to know
okay I'll do it this way
so as we do the sampling from the series
this will make it so it doesn't affect
anything else just uses that as the
starting point and that should do
everything else correctly except when we
go to do the push cube here what I'm
going to do instead is just retire the
point so in the destination and what I
want to do here is go ahead and
hard-code this so what I want to do here
is I just want to say okay as this goes
through we're going to take 64 samples
we're gonna write them into dest
so the index is just gonna tell us where
to put this thing we're not gonna do
that and so the rest of this routine is
fine as it is it just goes ahead and
writes us in there we don't need the sub
indexing at the moment of that
and this so there is our spiral without
any noise just the basic spiral that
gets put in there and then here is our
plus on version which of course means
fish in French just kidding this
person's name
although plus song is also fish in
French doesn't matter
point being I as we go through here we
will just replace it and right to the
destination array exactly as we were
writing to the one outside but this time
you know we let it pass it in there and
yeah I think that's really all we need
to do so those are our two ways of
generating samples and then when we
generate those samples now down here
where we're going to draw them what I
can do is
when we take the normal here instead of
doing any of this stuff to it what I'm
going to do instead is just say all
right let's take the sample points that
we recorded or saying we will record in
our solution and just draw whatever
those were then what we can do is when
you actually initialize the lighting we
can not that I know where we do that
anymore but there it is so when we
initialize the lighting we can
initialize the lighting with one of
these two doesn't matter which one but
for example if I want spiral samples now
I just say okay Ron should do the spiral
samples into my sample points buffer and
that'll be bad you have to replace the
point count with the fixed point count
[Music]
and we should be good to go
area and let's take a look so we should
hopefully if that was correct we should
now have the spiral sample in there
right there is our spiral sample which
again is quite nice and if we want to we
can switch that to our our blue noise
sample and I can make I could make a key
that would switch between these as well
so you know if I go into world mode here
you know we could bind the f9 keys to
generate these
so this way if we wanted to test like
say the difference between these two or
something like that run time you know I
can or should in theory be able to did
not work very well did it I should be
able to do that fairly trivially where
is my seems like this is having some
trouble inserting due to the cosine
measurement um the other thing too I
wonder here is if we should try to make
this a more efficient generator but
that's kind of a separate issue I
suppose so if we take a look at this
here the maximum cosine it has to be
higher than that so we would like this
value to be larger yes because the
higher I'm sorry ought to be smaller
right because the smaller this value is
the better for us I think
because the closer it would be to one so
I think if we make this value lower
we're in better shape right yeah so
there we go so the other nice thing
about this is since it uses a random
series that is updating every time it
also means we can generate as many of
these as we want right now our spiral
sample at the moment is not randomized
so it's pretty hard for us to tell about
that distribution because we don't
really have any Renison there where it's
the blue noise one you can see we have a
lot of random sampling options there
right because it'll always produce a
random sampling there I'm not sure
exactly what we want to do with the
spiral per say in terms of generating
random samples from it we haven't looked
too hard at how that function works so
it's kind of hard to say anyway
regardless of any of that once these
things are generated we could now
actually try using them for our sampling
just by feeding them directly in now
unfortunately we don't have any like I
said clustering of these that's kind of
the hard part now is to figure out how
we want a cluster for arrays together on
any given one of them right because
neither of these two emits a
straightforward way of figuring out
which ones should be attached right
which ones
[Music]
which ones we should be looking at so
for example let's just go ahead and I'll
show you kind of what this what this
implies if we take a look at how we're
drawing these here where we do the push
cube right if we were to do that again
here where instead of drawing cubes we
actually just drew a line between the
two points that's there I'll show you
what I mean so let's suppose we take the
previous point and this point and we
connect the two of them with a line so I
do push line segment and I say you know
I'm going to go from P plus normal a to
P plus normal B and then you know we
just have some color flow line like so
then what we could do is we can see if
we were to just group them in groups of
four you can sort of see what would
happen with our pairing right so looks
like I've got something room slightly
wrong there what did I do wrong there oh
I don't need to offset these
sorry about that they're just they're
offset from just that constant they were
being offset from each other um so if we
take a look at this series right of
points you can kind of see that you know
the way the spiral algorithm puts them
in place is kind of nuts right it just
it just goes like in this really
unfortunate kind of bounce pattern it
makes it so that we really just don't
know from one to the next well what we
do know is they won't be coherent right
so it's kind of hard for us to make a
lot of assumptions about that now maybe
we could do something where we just
reverse engineer this pattern enough so
that we can sort of say well we know
that the first four points will all be
kind of pointing upward so that's fine
and then after that you know we know
it's like okay well take every endpoint
maybe you know it's a little hard to say
so I'm not really sure about that one
the blue noise one is no better because
it's gonna be completely random or
should be based on the way we generated
it like you can see here right it's just
kind of connected all over the place
so again no real rhyme or reason to it
now we could have generated this in a
more coherent pattern what we would have
done is started with a point and
branched out from that point but even so
again it could still form kind of
relatively long chains that wouldn't be
the closest clusters together so you
know again I'm not really sure there's a
lot to do here the spiral pattern
definitely gives us the most plausible
way we could it's the one we'd be most
likely to figure out a rote algorithm
for certainly more so than the blue
noise the blue noise definitely you know
the blue noise would definitely be
harder because there is no sort of
yes correlation there so I'm not sure
exactly what we want to do we could take
a look at the the other one there
whether we want to use some like you
know other kind of sampling patterns
there are like let's see know if there's
any other interesting points for
hemisphere sang but like something that
has a specific let me see if this has
some diagrams in it here's like a Halton
sequence was the one that I was thinking
of unfortunately I don't it doesn't seem
like they actually they don't have a
diagram of it here yeah come on people
here we go these are hammer Selena
halting parts that those are related
though I don't remember they're they're
more mostly the same right mr. year
again mostly results but not oh there we
go
so here's Halton points and here's
Hamersley points these are the diagrams
I think that we want here right so here
we go this is I guess random for
comparison and here are various p-values
for the sequence which I mean that looks
really nice right
[Music]
here are Halton points with different
bases on this right so I'm not sure what
they were using for bases right because
these are 2d planes so it's kind of hard
to say how they were mapping them on
exactly right that's the thing is
because Halton amorously points are 2d
tilings of points and I'm not sure
see here they've they're talking about
basically how they're gonna put them on
to a hemisphere right
so my question is it's not directly
answered here but I assume that the
answer is yes the reason I mentioned
these points sets more specifically is
just because if you look at how these
point sequences work they're made to
sort of progressively refine as you go
further into them which made me think
that you would maybe be able to more
easily figure out how to bundle rays
together with them right let me see
so for example here you go red is 1
through 10
blue is 11 through 100 and green is 100
through 256 now don't ask me why they're
split in that way I guess but you can
kind of see how they scatter fairly
regularly like amongst the sets so you
don't get for example a lot of red
points next to each other which is the
important part here so you know my
thinking there was perhaps you could
come up with something a little bit more
a little bit more regular for sampling
the sphere and getting randomness around
a particular point so I don't know so it
may be that we want to investigate you
know some other series as well that
would be a little bit easier to make it
go you can see what the algorithm is
here it's not you know particularly
complicated right
and the other problem is it's kind of a
recurrence relation here so you kind of
have to keep running state as you go
which I don't know how problematic that
would be for us probably not really yeah
I don't necessarily know that we care
too much about that anyway but again
it's a little bit it's a little bit iffy
so I'm not sure if we want to go one of
those routes if we had infinite time I
think the best thing to do would be to
implement lots of different syriza's on
the sphere and take a look at which ones
were easiest to control given what we
have at the moment I guess what I would
say my first inclination is to take a
brief look and see if the spiral version
is possible to glean a little bit more
structure from how it is being generated
such that we could more easily generate
points next to each other or know which
of these points were next to each other
and then furthermore to jitter them to a
certain degree right or whether that is
not going to be possible and then
furthermore to yeah to make sure that
that can be done over time so my first
inclination is to take a look at that I
would like to maybe have some idea of
the ordering of these points a little
bit so I think what I would like to do
is introduce a color sequence that
allows me to more clearly see visually
what's going on with the points I'm
going to turn off the lines for now
because I don't necessarily need that
what I would like to see instead is a
sequence so I manage juices a structured
sequence of colors here so that I can
see pretty clearly what's going on so
what I'm going to say is I'm going to
start with red
go to green go to blue then I'm gonna go
to yellow cyan and white black one two
three four five six seven I and oh sorry
I forgot one magenta
white and black maybe we'll start with
black and with like so they'll get a
black red green blue yellow cyan magenta
white and that way I can sort of see the
colors as they go so here where I would
be drawing cube this whole thing there
we go here where I would be drawing cube
instead of always using white I'm going
to use a color from the table so what
I'm going to do is going to say give me
the color from the color table that's
whatever is indicated by the point index
and just wrap you know so this will
because we have eight this will give us
eight sets of of eight permutations of
this color table basically so now we can
at least see a little bit about a little
bit about how these colors go I realized
I forgot the trailing one there and
hopefully this will just let me see a
little bit more about what the pattern
looks like because at the moment right
obviously don't really know and so
here's the spiral and so if we take a
look at this pattern here you can see
that we start with black on the top
right so and we can almost see you know
you can really actually see the way
these things curve down now that I look
at it right so every eight points
kind of produces almost like a try strip
pattern right coming down here which to
me is actually very interesting I I
could probably make interesting use of
this to a certain extent so let's take a
look at the black spiral for example so
the black spiral starts up at the top
here to move this down a little bit
lower
so this the this black spiral starts
here and as it comes down you know the
initial point is probably gonna be a
special point so you know point zero is
a little degenerate and I'm not sure
exactly how we would process it but one
thing you know let's ignore that one for
a moment if we ignore that top one then
what you can see here is that the black
and blue so that's here and here so the
zero and three entries form a nice sort
of tessellation there that you could do
you know you can make quads essentially
between those if you had wanted to right
so I guess you know the one way to look
at this would be let's do it this way
so if we wanted to we could even sort of
draw that out right we could draw that
pattern pretty directly so let me
actually do that just so you can see
what I mean so how many of these are
there 1 1 2 well you know 1 2 3 so one
problem that you do get though if I look
at this right is it kind of becomes too
eccentric as it goes so there's really
no fill down here 1 2 3 4 5 and then you
got these two here so it does seem like
maybe okay so maybe that's barking up
slightly the wrong tree there right so I
may not be ill I was gonna think I was
gonna say that maybe that would be a
pretty easy way to create regions that
could be sampled in regularly but not so
much as it turns out because of the way
those are not gonna quite line up as
they strip down the sphere there's a
little too much triangularity to it now
there's anything wrong with that but
just makes it not as attractive as what
I thought it might be
so I want to take a look too let's let's
look at a couple other things now that
I've got that so it's pretty easy to see
when we generate our spiral samples here
I if I twiddle this value here so the
3.0 that's that's the value we know that
we want to at least be something above
two right because we don't want the full
sphere if it was just zero then I mean
if it was just one we would get the
whole sphere two gives us a hemisphere
because we're only going to go half way
down so then the question is well what
happens if we do less than that you know
kind of scrunches up right which is sort
of one way of keeping us from sampling
direct you know directions that are way
non-contributory that said however we're
free to kind of pick anything in there
so I'm wondering what happens as we vary
that value a little bit so what I'm
gonna do here is I'm just gonna say
let's have a sphere amount here it's
gonna be two point O plus random
unilateral let's say 2.0
so now every time i generate i'll get
some coverage of the sphere that's a
little bit different right so you can
kind of see that you know i basically
get the exact same points they just
jitter vertically that you know pretty
well right I would say it's not awful it
does produce different amounts of
clumping towards the top of course which
is not really what I want to have happen
but it does at least jitter that
direction okay and then similarly if I
wanted to I believe that just offsetting
the theta would probably spin it as well
right so if I said that I locked my
sphere amount in as sweep right now if I
take my theta offset and I do a random
unilateral up to say 2 pi well I don't
remember how this affects the series
either but I'm interested to see
keep wanting to do that and so if we
take a look at that so that's not what I
wanted and you know what that's because
I did this originally I think as well
theta is the wrong place to do that so
really what we want it's it's a row
offset here let's fix that so that
should spin us around
so that's better in terms of spinning
right so now if I combine the two of
these together you know in theory this
should give me something that generally
covers the sphere okay
hard to say really right but it's at
least not awful right and if you take a
look at you know one of the appealing
things about this obviously is that it's
pretty cheap to compute as well right
there's not a lot of math in here so we
could actually compute this for every
sample set probably and we'd probably be
okay however obviously there's a little
bit of an issue here which is that we
still have to do the one thing that I
was talking about before which is decide
from the randomness we actually need to
figure out how to cast points together
right so points that will end up being
somewhat close to each other so going
back to the colorist to see if I can do
much with that you know if we were to
cast say you know points 0 1 2 &amp; 3
together those would certainly be
reasonable then the next one here is
this next point here we would want to
cast that effectively with with it
probably with the red we'd probably want
to cast those four together right so we
probably then want to do a fairly weird
like
in pattern in terms of what gets cast
together it'd be like what is that point
number five for so it'd be like point
number four then point number nine for
and then nine and then the next two
would be like the eight offset from that
so I'm gonna try something here which is
again kind of dumb that's fine I'm
literally going to manually make the
sequence as my first thing
why am I gonna mail image videos well
because it's easy for us to go read the
sequence off now that we can see it and
so when I'm hoping is that if I manually
construct the sequence the series of
numbers that emerges will be something
that doesn't have to be manually
constructed right that will be clearer
and then we can see whether it actually
holds true across multiple jittering x'
as well which we don't know if it will
but we hope that it will based on how we
did that right so okay so let's take a
look here if we use our get current
quads loop if we use this this loop here
what I'm going to do I don't know why
we're still doing this placement because
we don't actually use it
here we go so what I want to do here is
have a point sequence that we're gonna
use instead
so here what I'll do is say you know
before oops
we were doing it like this right we just
pick out the color and the normal like
so now we're going to do it slightly
differently when we push the key bond
here what we're going to do is we're
going to use the color as the color
table point index mod array count clar
table as before this time it's going to
be point index divided by four because
we're going to take four points at a
time to put them into clusters because
that's what we have to raycast
right and then what we're going to do is
we're going to take the normal out of
our cluster table and so here we go with
cluster table and inside the cluster
table we will just put the points that
we want in there so you know if we did
nothing
Tydeus a little bit more efficiently
this way and compiled so in this case we
should get exactly the same thing we
were getting before only now when we
actually draw them we should get a well
you know we could get exactly the same
thing if we just do this right and so
now what we're gonna do is we're gonna
actually try to get those clusters to
come out so that we get things next to
each other by manually inserting these
samples so now I'm going to delete all
this so everything is just going to be
point zero so we're just gonna see well
effectively nothing we're just going to
see the top point so now let's try and
work out what the cluster should be
based on what we said we saw there so
here's like all the points with their
sequences intact so what we're sort of
saying is like well the first cluster
you know if we wanted to sort of send a
series of rays at the top that was good
I guess I would say maybe this set
together makes some sense I don't know
how you guys feel about that but that'd
be 0 1 3 5
one three six so if I switch back now
and look at that there's my cluster my
first cluster why is that black though
shouldn't be oh yes black is correct
never mind so let's take a look at
cluster number two so if I wanted to
send another cluster down now going down
the spiral it would it's just
pinks and reds from here on out right
now
I don't know those actually look a
little more coherent so maybe not you
know maybe not if we're sending those
down together as the first tranche you
know maybe the next truck should be
these guys right here
so the first two yellows the first green
and the first white you know so yellow
is four so the first two yellows would
be 4 and then 4 plus 8 right so 12 the
first green in the first white first
white is 7 and the first green is 2 so
putting these in order not that we
really necessarily want them to because
but just because that may make them
slightly easier to see at first
so there's another one another set and
again there's looks those look pretty
coherent and you know the other good
thing about them is they look coherent
no matter which randomization of the
spiral I'm using so that's also sort of
encouraging to a certain extent
oh so that's good as well all right
let's take a look at another one and
again I'm just going to do several of
these and see if I can see any pattern
emerging north some way that I could
make force the pattern to emerge maybe
by changing a little bit of how I sign
it or who knows what right okay so
you know what I think might also be good
because as we get higher it's gonna be a
little harder to see I might do this so
this way I can see both at the same time
and what I'll do here is I'll just say
I'll push the cluster table version out
slightly further right so now you can
kind of see which ones of these are
already taken and furthermore I could
make that easier to see by maybe pushing
a line segment instead so what I could
do here is say like okay
so now you can see the raycast clusters
coming out as little lines but you can
still see the points there involves that
way we don't have to guess about which
points go with what right so yeah so you
know looking at that it's like alright
can we make another bundle that would
make sense here you know you can see the
problem with the triangularity is still
there it's just hey you know oh well
because as you pick ones you're always
going to be in situations where you get
some that aren't really great but here
we go let's do some more so the next two
Reds the next two Pink's would be fine
as a cluster right so the next two Reds
we've already used one so the next two
Reds would be 1 plus 8 and 1 plus 16
right and the Pink's we've already used
1 pink if you were to use 6 so the next
two Pink's would be again 6 plus 8 and 6
plus 16 right 6 plus 16
so yeah so something like that right and
there they are
and so at that point it seems like you
then want to kind of switch a little bit
it looks like you know then the next set
of points probably wants to be blues
maybe it's really hard to say cuz if you
cast again you get really eccentric
there I don't know if there's a way
around it right but you could sort of do
something janky there and so like if I
took if I took these guys together for
example that would be the next two
purples and these two blues here the
problem is then what do you do down here
right because you're starting to get
down to it there's and you're gonna
paint yourself into a corner so again
it's really hard to know how you would
really get these guys together
I guess one man I just say I wonder if
there's some virtue to skipping point-0
you know I'm saying - skipping the top
point because if you skip the top point
maybe that gives you a better alignment
going forward I'm not sure
but it could be that you know you can
get you could get a little bit closer
that way I'm not sure that's a good
question hmm
or if you did it like slightly offset
like offset by 0.5 or something like
that as you go down you know do you get
something a little bit easier to
tessellate because that's what we're
effectively trying to do right
so I guess I really just don't have an
opinion about that
so I'm a little bit tempted at this
point just because I'm seeing how hard
this is gonna be to keep these coherent
I'm also a little bit tempted to ask
what would happen if we just were doing
a straight forward polar sphere so
because we you know the spiral version
requires us to use sines and cosines
anyways so we've already you know if we
were going to go that route it's not
like sines and cosines are a big deal
because we're already doing them so the
question would be like okay if we were
going to do a straight up one that was
just that long right
what would that look like so if we take
a look at what that would look like I
would want to divide into rings the
sphere and I'd want to take certain
samples around the Rings right so in
order to take certain samples around the
ring is what we're gonna basically say
is like okay
and I guess technically these might be
considered more like cylindrical samples
I don't know how you want to say that
but if you imagine taking the height so
how many if we said how many slices
around the ring do we want I don't know
maybe we want 16 something like that
then you know my height in this case is
going to be something proportional to
the slice amount so maybe 1.0 - the
slice over the slice count right
something like this and then of course I
just want to take my I just want to take
wherever I am on the disc and I probably
want you know this to actually be sliced
plus one in this case but I want to
think wherever I am on the disc and I
want to go out in my sine cosine fashion
right so I've got my sign I've got my
cosine so now I want to place things
around my slice and again I'm just gonna
do this
wrote at first and then we're going to
tune it so we know we want 4 spokes
around each slice we don't actually want
to do that eventually we're gonna want
to send a little bit more sophisticated
but for now let's do it this way and
then I'll say ok for each of the spokes
you know whatever my theta is for the
spoke is just going to be whatever its
focus divided by the spoken and so then
in here I can figure out what my x and y
are don't ask me why this is still here
and so what I can do here is just say
all right I've got my theta like so and
I know that I'm just going to be
assigning as I go up my height right of
the slice is effectively telling me what
my well let me just draw it for you
because I can't really explain this in a
good way with that pointing to a diagram
so if I look at a hemisphere right as I
go up effectively if I assume that I'm
going to be on like a particular height
then what that height effectively tells
me is it tells me you know looking at my
right triangle that I would construct
here it tells me what like sine theta is
for this angle right and so if I wanted
to know what this had to be it would
just be the cosine theta of that right
or put another way Pythagorean theorem
lies I know this is 1 and I know this is
the value that I'm giving you is H so I
know that H squared plus whatever the
thing is that I'm looking for right I
know that H squared plus R squared has
to equal 1 well 1 squared which is still
1 right so I know that if I just solve
for how far that had to go out I would
know that it's going to be the square
root of 1 minus the H squared right and
I know I don't want it to be negative so
I know it's always positive here right
so I know I could always figure out what
that value should be which means I don't
really need a sine or cosine for that so
I know my radius in this case is always
going to be equal to like the square
root of 1 minus the square of the height
and furthermore that's just you know
that's only persuade that's not going to
change right so I know in this case I
know what my Z is and in fact I could
just call it my Z instead of my height
right so I know what my Z
is and then I know what my X and my Y
are because my X and my Y in this case
are just going to be equal to the circle
right the radius that I want to go out
times the sine and cosine for the sweep
around so at that point I pretty much
just have my normal and I can just say
like okay whatever the point I'm
recording is just going to be that XY
and Z and then I'm done right so this
could just be called point count well I
guess I don't know what that is because
we don't have that structure here so
generate polar samples it's just another
thing we could do here and I can make it
in world mode I can make that be
something that we look at
so now in addition to spiral sample blue
toy sample we also have whatever this
sample is right okay so actually and I
think we did that pretty much correctly
the first time except for we forgot our
tau term so we're not doing the whole
circle but other than that right because
this is just going to range from what
from zero to one and we needed to range
from zero to two pi so there we go uh so
here you can see yes sort of covering
the hemisphere a little bit right but
not a lot because we've got way too many
slices versus spokes in this case so
what I want to do here and I guess you
know we could just reverse the numbering
here or something or do eight and eight
or something like this but what we want
to do hopefully you can see is we need
to change the slice count sort of
proportional to where we are in the
sphere right because as we get closer to
the top we don't need nearly as many as
when we're down at the bottom when maybe
we maybe we might want more right it's
hard to say so you know if we put this
out the other way then you can see we've
got good sampling kind of around the
base but as we get up towards the top we
we would like more here but we don't
have enough slices for it and if we kept
the slices going they would get way too
dense so what we can do instead is say
something like oh okay maybe the spoke
count is proportional to the slice count
so you know maybe the slice count can be
something higher but the Emmis boat
count adjusts as it goes up so we've got
you know some number of slices that go
in here and then as we adjust the spoke
count what we'll say is like okay you
know maybe the
vote count is starts out at four and
goes up to 16 as we go right so let's
just take a look so we can tune this
ourselves and then we can make them we
can make an expression for it once we
have something that we've hand tuned to
what we want right so in here with spoke
count we're just going to say it's the
smoke table indexed by the slice amount
and so let's say we did something that
was like we know we've got eight of
these so you know if we did something
like this all right so let's see we did
something like I don't know how we doing
here that's 16 plus 16 plus 24 right
oops
I've been admonished to never use
calculator on the screen there we go so
6 yeah 16 plus 16 to 24 right so we have
a little bit more to distribute there so
you know maybe we do something like that
so now we have 4 plus 4 plus 8 well 2
times 4 plus 4 times 8 plus is that
that's 2 times 12 right so you know I
mean I'm just I'm winging it right I
don't have any particular opinion about
why this would be good or not I'm just
trying to come up with something that
seems plausible maybe right you know
maybe plausible
and that slice wants to be able to get a
little higher so I also think you know
and since we're doing the spoke thing
here you know also so this 1.0 - slice
+1 I think maybe what we want to do is
actually sort of put this inside here
and say it's probably more like slice
point 0.1 or something right so it's
more like that so we do get a couple up
at the top you know and then furthermore
you can see how these are sort of
distributed down as they go you want to
kind of be less at you know you want I
think this slice value also kind of
wants to be more proportional right it
wants to kind of go itself as a you know
as a cosign or something it wants to be
counter balanced so it will sort of
progress at a different rate than that I
don't know what the best waiting for
that would be I'll try I'll try like
changing that to you know maybe a square
root first just to see if that helps
we'll try a square in a square root just
to see what those look like
so that does shrink up towards the top
but not really the way that I wanted
that too
so if we do something like pi32 that's
gonna be one hemisphere we actually only
want half of that so if we were going to
use like a sign to move it down just
take a look at what that looks like
oh that's too tight you something stupid
there let me um oh I did do something
stupid
I put the slice coming I said I'm just
going to take this out there we go so
I'm gonna go ahead and take just this
raw value says slice over slice count
I'm gonna take that ratio out just so I
can get it in here clean more cleanly
there we go and we're probably gonna
want to like I said offset this angle a
little bit inside here because we're
gonna generate points right on top of
each other there so here is us right
generating four points on top of each
other there I'm gonna go ahead and look
at this first
that's still just that weights the
opposite way that I want it to so it
looks like what we really want here is a
cosine weighting of these points right
there we go and that's much better
again so progressing a little bit
further on this so the interesting about
the coastline - that's kind of nice
there is that the ratio when the ratio
collapses so if you look at where this
is going to go it's not going to go from
0 to 1 it's going to go to 0 - not quite
1 so Z will not quite go to 0 but it
will the cosine term will hit 1 exactly
right so what I can do here again was
like think I do want to bias it slightly
just to get it out of to get that angle
out slightly I'm not sure how much we
want it to be biased there but do want
it a little bit right so you can see our
first set being right there yeah and we
don't I don't really know again how far
out we want that to be biased there you
go
probably not quite that much so now just
looking at it it looks to me like maybe
we still have like too dense of a
sampling in terms of already and not
enough here like we got much bigger
holes there so I think what that tells
me is the slice count probably wants to
be reduced so I'm going to reduce the
slice count to 6 which means that we're
going to remove like some of these here
right so we're gonna remove two of these
which means we could afford to
distribute these points a little bit
more right hard to say exactly how we
should distribute them obviously and
that first one probably def you know
only does want to be 4 to be fair
just to be a little bit easier for me to
work with there we go so if you've only
got six we can maybe start to make these
ones a little higher there's something I
might want to do there again with the
sampling hard to say we've got four more
there so I might I might say like that
and that's looking awesome honestly I
feel like that's pretty good right and
so you know the interesting part about
this then is just how do we line these
up for casting purposes and the reason
that I kind of liked this tiling is
because I feel like it's a little bit
easier maybe to work with as far as
alignment is concerned certainly the
first four points just get cast together
that's not that tough
so the question more is like you know
the question is mostly just like what do
we want to do with rows that where the
row breaks happens so from 8 to 12 from
12 to 16 you know and down here at the
end like I was saying I don't know that
you know it would really help if we
always had pairs so you know maybe one
thing we could say is maybe you could do
something like this
and trying to think of how to get rid of
that there so you know that's that would
be pretty easy to do the problem with it
again is you get some bigger holes in
here now one of the things that I
probably should do though is we don't
really want to be sampling that ring
that ring is it's too much right
and so we almost want to make sure we
constrict our hemisphere to not really
quite go that far right so we want to be
sampling a little bit more like that so
let's keep it like that because I think
that informs our our layout a little bit
better as well so all right let's let's
keep pushing on that a little bit here
let's try to get that top part cleaned
out more so let's suppose that we reduce
the slice count further because you can
see we're still a little too tight here
so maybe we reduce the slice count to
five so we have something more like this
here
right and again that admits are really
simple covering almost everywhere except
that last you know that last pairing
which isn't quite great and you know I
guess one thing we could do if we swap
those two I don't know it doesn't
I'm still not sure quite how I feel
about that
because again it's really tough to kind
of decide how you group these points
together and there's some further
complexities there like this is really
very well structured so you know we've
got the best chance here of figuring out
how to bundle them together but still
difficult right and part of the reason
for that is when you think about how
we're going to have to introduce jitter
in here well we know that you make the
jitter is proportional to this ratio
right because we know that the this
ratio is going in steps and I mean here
I'll just play to you this way so if I
introduce a random unilateral jitter
here it's pretty easy to see how we get
the vertical jitter to cover right and
we probably want to do that for every
spoke as well so that this thing
probably wants to live down here
which is a little more computation but
that's okay right
so you probably want something that goes
like that I mean I don't know maybe you
don't because maybe you want to maintain
more regularity so maybe you want to
make sure that the jitter can't actually
produce points that close together in
which case you would sort of want to
jitter them maybe more as a group I
don't know that's a hard that's a really
hard call and I'm not sure about it one
way or the other because again
yeah like the more that you do the more
that you do that the harder it is to
know right yeah so again just really
difficult to say and you know the last
point I just made is a really important
one to the fact that it's like you want
to jitter these points but once you
start jittering them then you have to
decide how are you going to maintain an
even sampling despite the jitter that as
well kind of then you know makes me
think again do we even want to do that
right we've looked at several of these
and I'm not sure any of them really do
necessarily exactly what we want like
the spiral probably does I mean for the
most part the spiral always maintains
the even sequencing right so the spiral
is really the only one that I know of
would do that this one I don't know
would really do that because again it
you know it's gonna want if it's really
gonna be sarcastic over the frame it's
gonna want to jitter the points
vertically this way and there's gonna
you know so the spiral is the only
procedural one you know the blue noise
obviously will always do it but the
spiral is only procedural one that would
probably generate an even spacing every
time but that would still be coverage
based now we'd have to test it to make
sure it really does end up being
coverage based but you know there you go
so
it seems like the only two options I can
really think of at this point based on
this experimentation that seemed viable
to me are either figure out some way to
actually cluster the spiral procedurally
which I don't immediately see but you
know if we grind on it we may find one
or the other option is take the just
precompute these pre compute a bunch of
permutations of them and use those
permutations and we could perhaps rotate
the permutations as well for extra
permutations because it's we know that
if we wrote if we spin the sphere this
way we don't change its distribution at
all it's still the same distribution so
for example blue noise or spiral if we
generated a bunch of different ones of
those clustered them proceed you know
actually using a routine that just
looked for the clusters so we don't have
to have a procedural way to do it if we
did that and then just picked random
picked a random series out of our batch
and randomly rotated it maybe that's
just better and then we could literally
use blue noise at that point so we could
actually have something that was truly
blue noise not the spiral sample which
is not really blue noise right so I
don't know
but I'm kind of leaning towards that
that to me seems like the same is the
way to go
and I think the bonus of that method is
also that it doesn't really matter how
we come up with those distributions
either so it kind of has the nice point
of like alright if you want a spiral or
you want blue noise or you want
something really difficult to compute it
doesn't really matter because we can
just compute pre compute a bunch of them
and just pull one out because that gets
us out of the business of caring how
long it takes to produce the
distribution which some of them like the
spiral don't take very long but others
like blue noise might take very long
even if it's optimized it may still be a
little bit too expensive right so I
think that's what I like best honestly
I think that's what I like best so I
think that's what I'm gonna try it's not
super hard the only thing we have to
write that we haven't written is the
clustering algorithm and the only thing
the clustering algorithm really needs to
do although it is hard but we doesn't
need to be perfect it just needs to make
sure that every four point pet set tends
to be fairly correlated and maybe if one
of them is wrong it's alright but you
know generally we don't want like lots
of wrongness there right so yeah I mean
that's just gonna be there's a sample
point array and we've got you know some
number of them I don't know how many of
them we actually want to do but you know
let's say we took 16 of them or
something and then you rotated them that
seems like a very large number of
permutations right furthermore these
sample points if we get down to it we
don't really need to store 3-3 whole
floating point values we can just store
two floating point values because the Z
value is always positive and it's always
the square root of the two other values
my each other right like we know that x
squared plus y squared plus Z squared
always has to be equal to one so we
don't really have to store that value so
again in terms of like if we just want
to make sure we're always minimizing the
amount of like bandwidth that's
necessary to use precomputed sample
points here not only is that true but
also we maybe don't even really need
that much precision so we could also
decide to just store it as some more
compact representation as well so for
example we could sort them a 16-bit
values instead of 32-bit values we know
their range is always between 0 &amp; 1 so
it's not like we even need
floating-point for that we can just use
literally 64 I'm sorry 65 thousand
divisions of the 0 to 1 range and
probably be fine with that as well
so I feel like we've got a lot of
options here so I'm fairly comfortable
with this as as an option
so I think that's okay and furthermore
we can we can make sure that these
sample points are lined up nicely for
however we want to load them so if we
just go briefly back to where we're
actually sampling these and you can see
here where we're picking our random
bilaterals and so on right so the way
that that has to work at the moment is
it's picking up the the Delta there so
it wants to to load in it wants to load
it in forward time right so we can also
you know kind of pre make make this a
little bit sort of nicer on us by saying
that you know we actually just want 16
of these and we want them to be pre
packed in the load format so you know
that is also another way that we can get
a benefit here right so let's go ahead
and try making our algorithm work this
way just temporarily and the way that I
think we can do this is just by saying
look if we know that this is a rollable
value then we can automatically make a
mask for it so in here where we go
through casting our rain radius out of
the sample points here what we can do is
sort of say well alright don't you know
don't do this anymore
instead just load these out of the
sample point array and the array index
mask in this case is just 15 right but
we'll play with that a little bit more
just get rid of that so in here then we
just have to load out sample for the X
from there and I think we're pretty much
done and in fact this garbage doesn't
have to happen anymore either out think
right because these would already be
ready to go so I think that's pretty
much it and so if we just now initialize
those with useful values then I think
we'd probably be good obviously we need
to know which one of these were using
here and that one could be based on the
sample point index for example as we
step through so maybe this is a sample
pattern mask as well and so as we step
through those we would get different
samples out and so what we can try first
of all is just now when we ended our
lighting in here what we could do is
just make our lighting code do this to
start with and this will replicate our
existing lighting to a certain
approximation using the tables instead
so we can just you know double-check
that
actually didn't really need to do that
today because I'm going to put this
inside another for a look inside so here
we have our pattern index and that's
gonna be proportional to however many
there are in the pattern array and then
there's the bundle index and the bundle
index is going to be proportional to
however many there are and like say one
of these and then we're going to produce
those random ones and then in here in
instead of just using it we're just
going to do a reassignment back to the
sample points and so then in when these
are stuffed here after we're done with
that I think all we really need here is
a way to get our series out so what I'll
do here is say that the random series
series equals solution series and that
should be the end of it okay uh so I'm
gonna not do the drawing for a second
here because that's sort of a another
part of the problem
what are we complaining about sample
point and okay so this one sample point
n is just saying what direction the
sample point had to go here that's a
good point so we are gonna have to
rotate these to align with a sample
point though this is this is a good
point so we do need a little bit more
code there it's not going to be quite as
dropping as I was about to say there but
that's okay so the sample point in in
this case though if we want to produce
patterns that are just basic patterns
then what we're really looking to do
here is that
sample point in is just the normal we
want these to all be pointing along and
of course we know what that actually is
in this case we know because we want it
to just always be pointing upward right
so really in this case when we're
looking at the the less than or equal to
mask we only really need to look at the
Z and that's you know so we don't we
don't need this inner product anymore
all we really need to do is say well we
want to we want to basically pick
between the positive and the negative
versions of these based on whether or
not the Z was going the right way
and that's all we needed right there so
that that's all that's doing and that's
that's fine right so let's go ahead and
nerf this out temporarily but I'm gonna
put it in I'm gonna put it back in
I spun nerf it out for a quick moment
there because yeah we're gonna have to
have fuss with it a little bit more
alright
and so our lighting is gonna be a little
bit broken when I first run this the
reason for that like I said is because
it's not aligning with the normals so it
will sort of do lighting but it will be
gathering like backwards and doing other
kind of odd stuff right and so first we
have to correct that part of it in here
where I grabbed out those sample points
here so once we have that we know that
the sample point normal which is this
thing here we know that we need these
things to be aligned along that sample
point normal and so in order to
why did I bother masking this this is
done we know there's exactly that many
yeah I yeah that's just that was stupid
anyway um so looking at this we know
that once we have one of these
we now need this to be oriented along
the sample point normal right and if we
look at the sample point I believe we
sort of have this nice factor here that
the x axis and the y axis are known to
us which is pretty important actually
because that's the only way that we
could trivially construct things that we
know face out that hemisphere so
generally speaking when we do this
sample here and we have the sample for X
that's aligned in like the reference
coordinate frame where Z up is 1 of 0 0
1 and then our X and y axes are 1 0 0
and 0 1 0 respectively and so if we want
to transform this what we need to do is
effectively create an equation here that
reinterprets it along those lines so we
kind of need something that's going to
look like this
that reinterprets these as they should
be along the various directions so this
is the sample point in here and we need
the sample point x and y here whoa what
that was like so and so in here where we
do x and y that's just these axes and i
think that's really all we need to do to
make sure that they point in the correct
direction
so yeah you know not necessarily a huge
deal but but something we definitely
need to do we don't know if that's
actually correct yet so we would need
more we need to actually test and draw
these things to make sure that we're
doing this properly but that's basically
what we need to do right we need to
basically take the samples that we've
baked in there and we need them to to be
reinterpreted
along these these axes let me make it's
not sample point X&amp;Y it's the x-axis and
y-axis which is different so I'm just
want to make that a little clearer there
so as we pull each one of these out
again the sample point index this is
just giving us which sample point array
we actually want to look into and the
rate index is just 0 to 16 that which
were the valve sorry 0 to 15 the values
in there that we're actually that we've
actually stored and that should be
usable right that should be giving us
something similar it looks a little off
to me so again I think we didn't quite
we don't quite have the transformation
exact yet that's my guess anyway but
it's pretty close so tomorrow what we'll
do is we'll draw it and then we'll also
actually generate ones that have good
distributions and we will be able to
then verify what we want I'll take a
quick look now just to make sure there's
no obvious bugs but then you know we'll
tackle the rest of the debugging and the
improvement itself tomorrow so looking
at this here
I mean really the other thing about this
here is we'd we'd rather just have this
be completely randomized it's alright
but
it's it looks fairly reasonable to me
though so I don't see anything else
around with it so I'm gonna go ahead and
go to Q&amp;A today and we will take care of
the debugging of it tomorrow
while I'm waiting for questions I
noticed as Sylvan said by the way I
mentioned this on Twitter but the
easiest way to compute a cosign
distribution is to start with a 2d disk
distribution for X Y then compute Z by
projecting to a sphere that seems pretty
good I guess what I would say is what we
could do let's assume that this idea of
pre-computing the points is a good idea
one thing we could do is generate a
bunch of blue noise disks and then
project the Z so that they end up being
cosine weighted you know that seems
pretty compelling to me I guess you know
I would I think that's a good thing to
try assuming that this this precomputed
version is a good way to go
then we could pre compute like 16 blue
noise disks and project them up using
the square root do you have some
resources for researching different game
system architectures in C I'd like to
focus on the data layout I do not really
I mean obviously there's the game
architecture book by what's it called
key game programming game game engine
gaming engine architecture I think by
Jason Gregory and he's doing a third
edition I think of that now as well
okay maybe yeah there it is yes third
edition so when is that coming out I
don't know when that's coming out
actually yeah I don't know I don't know
what to say necessarily about that but
that's kind of a I would say one of the
basic rest for it
a lot of these things unfortunately most
most books that kind of talk about these
sorts of architectures things the coasts
date my having learned how to make
engines so I don't know what's in them
cuz I don't read a lot of game
architecture books now for obvious
reasons I already kind of know most of
the things I like to do so when I want
to look something up I tend to be more
pigeonhole so if I was gonna look up
something in a game of cartridge why I'd
be looking at a specific section I
wouldn't really be reading the whole
book typically anyways so one of the
problems is ie I I don't have a lot of I
can't let go back to when I was learning
and go oh here's the books I liked
because there really weren't any good
ones at that time there may be good ones
now and I just don't know what they are
but that one I you know Jason Gregory
obviously has a lot of experience with
these sorts of things so I would be
pretty surprised if the book didn't have
good information in it I guess one way
to put it
Jeff Lander as well obviously I don't
think I know the third author I know the
I think I know that who was there was a
third author I don't I know two of them
and I don't know the third I don't think
yes so so Matt witting I don't know who
that is
although I guess it looks like Jeff
Lander just wrote the foreword so maybe
it's all Jason but Jeff Lander is also a
very good programmer most people don't
know who
I think probably but he's very good and
he's been around a long time and done a
lot of really good work so you know
apparently he didn't write the book so
doesn't matter but the foreword is
probably also good
let's see blackburn 1911 what should i
do every day to become a good programmer
well i guess i would say that
programming a lot and exploring new
ideas is really the most important stuff
right like i feel like the two main
ingredients to being good programmer are
programming a like a lot so you know at
least six hours a day every day your
whole life right you can take weekends
off if you want is step number one and
number two is always be looking for new
things like don't assume that the way
you did something last time or the way
someone told you to do it is a good way
explore new options and think critically
about how you can improve things and
that process takes a long time but
that's the only really way to get good
right it's the same as getting good at
anything else you know how do you get
how do you become a concert pianist it's
like well you play piano every day and
you constantly try to think of new ways
to interpret a piece of music that sound
better or more interesting right I mean
you know it's it's just a lot of hard
work and most people who are bad
programmers unless somehow they were
born with brains that literally just
can't be good at programming one of
those two things isn't true either they
don't program enough or they don't try
hard enough when they're programming to
do new things or look at things
differently because it really is an
active process like you don't just sit
down and do it it's an active process of
going I want to make an improvement here
I want to get better at doing this thing
so I'm going to try something new and
see how it works because that's the only
way you get better is by trying
something new and seeing which one's
work and sometimes they don't work you
see done a hand meet here all the time
we try something new it doesn't work
right that's the cost of finding a good
way is having to have gone down bad ways
and recognize that they didn't work and
then
start over that's just that's just how
new things happen otherwise you're just
kind of a monkey right typing in stuff
the same as everyone else and that
doesn't really isn't really worth a
whole lot unless you just I mean if you
just want a job that's fine but if
you're trying to really be good that's
not good enough well effect do you use
templates in the code no we don't use
templates
I'm programming my first game in 2d is
an intake assignment for my next
education the game uses an entity
component system but now I'm stuck
because I want different entities to
have different animations for different
situations but don't know how to
implement that my question is how do I
go about that without writing different
sprite components for every different
env type all sorts of information is
welcome so I guess what what I would try
to encourage you to do here because this
is for educational purposes is I would
encourage you to take a step back and
think about whether the structure that
you've been posed or that your
assignment more perhaps has imposed on
the question you're asking right and
this again is one of the really big
problems I have with object-oriented
programming as well but it's not really
a problem with object-oriented
programming per se it's just that it's
particularly pernicious in that type of
programming but it extends to all types
of programming if you let it
and it's always bad and that is thinking
about the answer to a question in terms
of artificial constraints you have put
on the solution because either someone
told you they were good ideas or because
you thought they were good ideas and
it's always important to re-examine
those so let's take your question apart
more specifically and look at what you
asked you said I'm stuck because I want
different entities to have different
animations for different situations but
I don't know how to implement that okay
but you absolutely do know how to
implement that because it's trivial
right so more specifically what you
don't know what you actually don't know
is how to implement different animations
for different situations in terms of
this structure you've imposed on your
code somewhat artificially right because
if all you want to do is have different
animations for different situations we
all know how to do that right whatever
you've got
you could just have a thing in here
that's like alright ennum my different
situations situation one situation to
situation 3 right and then you've got
something that's like play animation
let's put in here right so we all know
many ways in code to just sit down and
type in something that has different
responses based on some parameter that
we just set on an entity like hey this
entity I'm just throwing a thing in here
that says it plays this animation for
this circumstance right you just
literally put that in and so the
question that you are actually asking
here is in some weird construct that
I've created where I pre said I'm not
gonna do that thing that is very
straightforward and obvious how do I do
it well the answer should be rethink how
you're doing it if it's not obvious how
to make a special case in your system
there's something wrong with the system
and that system should be augmented to
include an easy way to add a special
case or it should be thrown out because
it's just bad and again that's the
problem I have with a lot of auditory
systems is they they make it so that the
obvious way to type something in is like
round upon or bad or just straight-up
impossible because they've made this
ridiculous collection of objects and
concepts that are impenetrable to
actually writing what's supposed to
happen writing what's supposed to happen
explicitly is not bad it's in fact
optimal and the goal of any system
should be to make it as easy as possible
for the programmer to say explicitly
what they wanted and every additional
step you add to
system that forces the programmer to do
something other than the obvious
hard-coded correct answer he's actually
bad not good what a system is supposed
to do is make it easy for the programmer
to put in special cases and to apply
cases to as many useful ways as possible
so if they have a thing that's like a
anything that sort of acts like a sheep
should play the Sheep animation when you
know chased by a wolf the goal is to
make it as easy as possible to write
that down it is not supposed to be to
prevent the programmer from saying
explicit things and as soon as you get
yourself into a system into a system
where you don't even know how to say
explicit things anymore that system is
bad . so it's important to understand
these pieces so I don't know exactly
what your system looks like right now
there's two situations you may be
encountering one is that you've ended up
with a system that is simply too
unwieldy and it should be torn apart a
little bit and made simpler right and
made more flexible the other is that you
just don't understand the system that
you've built well enough and this
happens to everybody it happens
literally to everyone all the time which
is when you first start building a
system no matter how good you are you
have no experience with that system so
you don't really know how to use it yet
it may be that you're a situation where
your system actually could express this
very easily but you just don't
understand how and so you need to look
at that a little bit too and so you need
to figure out which one of those cases
you're in if you're in the case where
you just needed to like sit down think
about a little bit more and the system
actually expresses this cleanly great if
not you need to back up and you need to
say how did I paint myself in this
corner
var said he played with the spiral and
had problems with the angular fall-off I
can yep I could see that that's why I
kind of like the idea of precomputing
[Music]
the the distributions more but we'll see
3d gamer first time we're here from what
I saw it looks like organizational wise
a lot of things are bundled together in
your code how do you handle organizing a
lot of code in general is it a c c++
thing to have so many things together
I'm just kind of used to having small
pieces of code um no that's not only a C
C++ thing there's lots of C++ code
programmers who break things down into
incredibly tiny parts that's just how
they like to do things in my opinion I
think that's usually bad the reason is
because the more interrelated code is
the easier it is to play with it you can
just quickly like rewrite parts of it
and do whatever so I tend to postpone
breaking things apart too much later in
the process than most people now that
doesn't mean that I actually leave them
all bundled together forever because I
usually don't so eventually when I get
to the part where I'm totally sure I
know exactly how something works and I
want to kind of put my stamp of finish
this on it I will then tend to break it
apart a little bit more into pieces
possibly if I want to do some testing
possibly if I want to do some
optimization because sometimes you need
to do that and so on but I think
typically there's a lot of fetishism
around breaking code into small pieces
and I don't really approve of that if
you don't have a reason to break code
into a smaller piece you typically
shouldn't because it just makes it
harder for someone who's coming to the
code to edit it and read it to know
what's going on because now they have to
look across many many small pieces of
code to figure out what's happening
rather than just stepping through the
code in series and seeing exactly what
it does and furthermore it creates
artificial divisions in the code that
don't actually exist that then crimp
create problems when you're trying to
modify it so typically I think code
should be broken into pieces that are as
small as necessary but no small
and I think it's important to remember
that but no smaller part because a lot
of people just break things into small
pieces of code for no reason I don't
think that's done really good case I
just want to say thank you for
everything I started watcher you in 2014
when I graduated University you taught
me more than all my teachers there I
loved game development and love
programming all because of you well that
is very kind thing to say
I very much appreciate that and I hope
that you continue to love programming
and it continues to be something that
you you find interesting and enjoyable
throughout your life did I find a answer
to my questions in my blog post the
particular bog blog posting question
I'll bring it up here is all registered
names still useful no I haven't this is
a blog post it's just about hardware
it's not an educational blog post it's
just a question that I posed to hardware
designers and the question was simply do
you think that register names are still
the best way to communicate a program
from a compiler to a cpu in light of the
fact that nowadays hardware doesn't
really use registers in the same way
that it used to it used to be that
registered names really were registers
so it was the CPU was literally getting
exactly what it should do from the
instruction stream and registers names I
think make a ton of sense there nowadays
what the what the instruction stream is
telling the processor is actually not
that because the processor typically has
lots of versions of any given register
in-flight at a given time either in a
hyper threading context the registers
are wide across threads in a an out of
order processor there they're often
referring to different things at
different times so the same register
name is actually referring to different
states throughout differ
parts of the microp retirement and all
these sorts of things so this was really
just a question like our register names
still useful or is there some other
naming scheme we should be using I know
like the mill CPU proposed one I didn't
think it was a particularly interesting
proposal I think there's other proposals
that might be more useful I gave an
example of one which was like a
stack-based register naming scheme I
don't think just using memory directly
makes sense and the reason for that is
because memory names are too long
they're sick up to 64 bits long and
that's simply not a concise way of
producing an instruction stream because
instruction streams need to be compact
in order to avoid too much cache
decoding and so on so I asked that
question here in this post I have not
received any real answers from hardware
designers yet probably because they
don't read my blog because why would
they there's nothing in it about
hardware but I still wanted to post it
anyway if I ever do get any answers I
will be sure to let you know fort 99 you
mentioned not using templates to use any
code generation or meta programming at
all I do in our actual code base at Mali
rocket I do not use any meta programming
on stream on handmade hero only because
I wanted to restrict this to kind of C
C++ programming for this particular
stream meta programming is a whole
nother thing that you do it's a
completely different discipline largely
unrelated to anything we're doing on the
stream so I didn't really want to take
on that topic here every time I am
designing the data layout of a game
system I get very happy inside is this
normal or should I see a psychiatrist
also I absolutely love the sections
about the entity system in game design
decisions I don't know if it's normal or
not but it's probably good anything that
makes you happy on the inside while
programming is good
sneaky Bob how much more optimized do
you think you'll be able to get this
lighting code once you've sorted out
this bundling I don't know depends
whether we do a GPU version or not and
we got to look at it a little bit more
but right now we just want to smooth out
our sampling a little bit and that's not
really optimization that's just getting
a little bit higher quality from the
same optimization I'm a programmer a
three years experience what would you
recommend for someone with my experience
level to do to improve as a developer
I've been trying to learn new things
outside of work while avoiding breaking
the non-compete part of my contract
yeah I would say that taking up side
projects that you just use purely for
your own educational purposes and
experimentation are actually very good
things to do it depends on what you're
interested in learning but you know if
you wanna learn graphics write a ray
tracer for example would be a good idea
things like that but it really depends
what you want to learn a pick pick a top
you know pick a side project which
aligns well with your goals do you wanna
learn more math do you want to learn
more programming structure architecture
do you want to learn more sound
programming do you want to learn more
rasterization do you want to learn more
physics you know make the project fit
the main thrust of what you want to get
better at just your own personal
preference what you want get better at
right now that's what I would say do I
still use my Amiga well use my Amiga may
be a strong term I don't really use it
for any real purpose do I still fire it
up occasionally to marvel at how much
better it is then this piece of garbage
Windows 10
CPUs sitting in a system sitting in
front of me absolutely but really I just
get depressed because I realized that
you know thanks to Microsoft
we've spent 30 years getting absolutely
nowhere even though the hardware we have
is absolutely amazing
any good resources about game
development that is surely not language
or platform specific I don't know
couldn't couldn't say for sure sorry
alright and with that we have come to
the end of the questions so I will go
ahead and close things down probably
should get rid of this here before I do
so we don't check in that code to the
github in a second here
everyone would pull the changes from
today and be like what is this thank you
everyone for joining me for the set of
hand made here it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always I think we've
pretty much settled into how we want to
do our sampling so tomorrow we will try
to improve that by actually implementing
some of those like maybe putting putting
our blue noise scheme in there or
whatever and then seeing how that does
when we put it into actual practice in
the game so hopefully you'll join me for
that tomorrow same time same place
until then if you do want to play around
with the source code you can always peer
to the game on handmade hero or it comes
with the source code so you can play
around that yourself and do your own
experimentation maybe you can find some
good ways to do letting sampling in the
meantime that will be interesting that's
about it for today I'll see you back
here tomorrow till then have fun
programming and I'll see everyone on the
Internet take it easy everybody