okay hello everyone and welcome to
handmade hero the show where we code a
complete game live on twitch you know
one thing that I pretty much always say
at the beginning of the stream is that
we don't use any engines and we don't
use any libraries and that is true and
the reason that we do that is because
you know honestly mm-hmm I always say
that it so we can see the entire you
know the entire pipeline of a game and
all that's right Stefan honestly like
there's a hidden part there too which is
just like I always get grumpy about the
way other people do things you know I
think there's like a control-freak
aspect of that as well where it's like
it's not just that I think it's a good
idea and educational to go through and
do it entirely yourself at one point but
also that like I would spend all my time
complaining about how they chose to do
something you know what I mean you ever
get in that situation where you're like
using something and you're just like you
know what this is just done totally
wrong like I don't agree with any of
this and I don't see that's the
experience I have most the time I try to
use that stuff so so you know I'm doing
this one for educational purposes but
honestly even if I wasn't I still
wouldn't be using an engine or libraries
because frankly they're garbage
alright so that said I would like to go
ahead and introduce to you day 90 if you
are trying to follow at home and you've
pre-ordered the game on handmade hero
org you can download the source code
that from the link you got in your email
and what you want to do there is you
want to unzip date 89 source code
because that is what we are starting
with right now so unzip that and you'll
be able to follow along exactly with me
so let's take a look here where we're at
where we have what we have come to and
honestly you know since its kind of a
little bit of a sleepy day today I'm
gonna start off with something that I
mean you for a long time I'm just gonna
do it it's complete busy work but I want
to do it anyway which is I realized that
I named these a little bit wrong
compared to my code base that I normally
use
and it drives me insane when I switched
between them so I put them as capital
letters when we did it here the X Y and
the X Y Z and stuff which is what I
would normally do
however if you have ever looked at HLSL
or GLSL the shading languages that you
are required to write stuff in when you
are using OpenGL direct3d etc they use
lowercase accessors for their vectors
and I like to make my code so that it
can compile both ways so that you know
you can have expressions that compile in
a shader or in your code and so what I
did with my source code the way that I
write it you know at my day job
basically right is I use the lowercase 1
so that I can use so that I don't have
to do any translation between them right
and so every time I switch between the
handmade hero code at night and the code
that I work on during the day I always
end up in this situation where I'm like
ah because I typed the wrong things and
it drives me bonkers so I want to just
kind of unify these two here so that I
can stop having that that painful
process occurred basically so that's it
that's all I really wanted to do was
this and so it's again it's just
annoying I just have to kind of go
through and change what people were
accessing those by so it's gonna be a
little bit of Drudge work but you know I
really wanted to do it because every
time I was like aah and so I'm gonna try
and get us back to there before we get
any further down the oops that's not
right before we go any further down the
the rathole of using a different one so
it's gonna take a while I apologize
there is really nothing to describe I'm
literally just changing these from
uppercase to lowercase which is
extremely boring but that's just what
you got to do sometimes oops
I wonder if I can do something like dot
X equals dot X and have that be mostly
right most of the time looks like it so
that's good that looks good so let's do
that that'll save us a bunch of time
wasn't sure how likely that would be to
work but it looks like it does so that's
good so let's do dot y equals dot y
there we go
also that'll also save us from making
typos potentially hopefully I just take
a little bit of attention here kind of
crazy when you think about how much code
you end up writing we look through here
and you know 90 hours of code I guess
we've done well maybe a little bit more
than that but mmm you know 90 hours of
code and there's just so much stuff in
here even though we're just you know
we're only maybe a sixth of the way
through working on this stuff my head
keeps obscuring that last replacement
all right so that's one file down so dot
XY becomes dot XY as well there we go
and let's see dot Z Z Y dot y all right
okay next file dot X becomes that X that
that's pretty good
and why comes that why
it's one of those things where I do feel
like I kind of have to watch each
individual one even though probably I
don't have to yeah you never do now are
are I wonder if I can just do a thing
where I Wow yeah I won't do that I was
gonna say what if I could do a thing
that'll automatically do all of them for
me
Emacs has ways of doing that but I'm not
I don't have enough Emacs foo to to bust
that out and B's and A's alright let's
see how we're doing
hmm all right and dot Z as well yeah
that was mistake
oh it's a sleepy day here yeah I did not
get much sleep last night and then you
know I was I was doing a bunch of coding
all day long and then it's like you know
I think my brain might just be tired my
brain might just be a little bit tired
sometimes it happens let's see see see
you know I liked it better in the old
days when it didn't do this see
Declaration of thing because jumping in
like that makes it hard to just quickly
go through where all the errors are I
don't know if you can turn that off I've
never looked I should but just kind of
spontaneously turned on and I don't know
how you get it get rid of it
all right so let's do Dex Dex yeah a lot
of those and why last file I think this
is the big one right here people and
we'll see if I made any critical
replacement errors all right what do you
think do you think it worked
do you think it worked let's find out
okay
yay
looks pretty good nothing particularly
suspicious going on so we'll call it
good all right okay so now we can get
started with other things I just I
really wanted to do that I kept being
like you know I gotta do that sometime
and since you know I'm a low energy day
you kind of want to go like okay what
could I do that's not going to take a
huge amount of mental energy something
that like needs to get done that's just
kind of that that sort of thing all
right so let's take a look here we were
working on our render group structure
when we last were handmade hearing and
we sort of introduced this notion of
multiple things like we had the rec time
goals and the bitmaps and clears we
never implemented clear though and so
what I want to do is I want to go ahead
and implement clear so I'm gonna take
the the place where we were actually
calling before we draw a rectangle to
clear the screen right like this is that
that rectangle clear call right right
there so what I want to do is I want to
turn that into an actual clear operation
so I want to do like a render drip clear
where I just say okay you know what
clear the screen clear it to this color
right here that's what I want you to
clear it to rgba and then we'll make it
so that that actually does that clear
operation so in here when we actually
get one of these clears what we're gonna
do is do the sort of the draw rectangle
call that we were doing before because
we don't really need to implement an
actual clear yet
and we'll actually make sure that it
does exactly what we wanted to do now we
don't actually pack a in here at all a
has to be 0 for now so what I'm gonna do
is I'm going to actually go ahead and
make it so that there is an A for the
draw rectangle call in terms of what you
actually want to pack in there it just
defaults to 1 let's say but that way if
you want to you can clear the buffer to
have an A in it even though that's not
going to actually do any alpha blending
if that makes sense so I think I'll just
allow it to do that like so you know
what I'm saying
so it'll produce that packed color like
that so if I do that then what I should
be able to do is just pass that as a V
for right that that V for from the clear
call so this entry right here right will
have that color that we passed so this
will just be color are you I could do it
in lowercase now that's very good
so we'll do our G loops RGB and a there
so that way we can set the clear and
when we do that clear when we do the
actual call we now have to you know
anything that we want to do render wise
has to kind of go through that buffer
push right and so when we have this here
we're going to make
in line Boyd clear like so and it's
really just gonna do the exact same
thing that you know everything else so
far has been doing it's going to push on
mm-hmm one of these render elements
that's the that's the actual clear right
and and then it's gonna set whatever
values are specific to that thing right
so this in this case we've just got a
color and this is what we pass here and
so that's really I think all we'll need
to do for a clear I don't think there's
anything else that would be particularly
relevant at least not yet so up here we
now just need something for that it
looks like we've already got it so
that's good so we'll put in color there
which is a little bit different from how
we have it set up but we'll take a look
and make sure that that's all all kind
of kosher
we need the buffer to be changed to
whatever the output target is right so
that's what that is and that's good and
then we okay yeah need to change it here
as well so if you get the width and
height of that buffer we want to clear
so once we've done that we can now sort
of lean on that clear call and that
doesn't really do that much compared to
what we would have been doing in
software but in hardware and probably
eventually in software as well we'll be
able to do a faster operation there then
drawing something we'll be able to you
know most renderers and all hardware has
an accelerated way of clearing things
because it knows that you know it's
doing this sort of block operation
instead of having to figure out where
something is it knows it can just do the
whole active buffer at once right so we
should now have that working of course
we can't really tell but we could see we
can still see the purple flashes so we
can kind of assume it's working although
it's not a super great test what we
could do is of course stop drawing our
our ground patches for example and make
sure that we're actually seeing
something back there so what I can do is
I can go in here and say alright you
know this this thing here that goes
through and draws these ground buffers
you know I could just make that stop
right I think that would probably do it
oh why do you do this to me why
concessional press why is that even in
our build that's going away I hate that
wording it's like why are you even
telling me that I know whether I wanted
it to be constant or not it's not your
job so yeah so that's clearly clearing
it to that beautiful beautiful pink it's
really you know when people say their
favorite color is pink that's the pink
they're thinking of is that pink right
there it's this it's this sort of lush
magenta favorite of artists everywhere I
think it was Leonardo da Vinci who said
that you know if he could that the
perfect painting would be nothing but a
canvas of pure magenta he also listed
the the HTML pound color for it FF 0 0
FF so what you want to do now or rather
what I want to do now is go okay what's
what's the final set of things that we
haven't moved over into the render and I
think out of those I remember there was
an outline call as well and that's not
going through our renderer yet just
trying to think if there's anything else
that ever gets drawn right that that we
don't that we don't do and you know what
else here this is interesting so the
other thing that we haven't addressed is
the ground chunk that's calling the
bitmap routines directly not the
renderer and so I think we'll probably
we will more than likely want to port
that as well so maybe that's what we'll
do next as well but I'm pretty sure
we've still got the outline calls which
have not so this yeah these two guys
right here so push rect outline and draw
a rectangle outline so both of those I
think maybe we want to make those happen
we want to put those into the render as
more of a
you know as more of a specific concept
basically so I don't rally really
remember how this was working I feel
like you don't see these I feel like
these don't show up
normally anyway because they were behind
the ground chunks so one thing I could
do is say okay like after this filling
happens here oh no I guess they would
show up after because these get pushed
on first all right so that's fine
so when those get pushed then what I
would do here is I would say I want to
be able to have the rectangle outline
get pushed on as well
and one thing that I'm not sure about
yet I don't think we probably want this
but the the phrase push doesn't really
probably need to be on here anymore
either right we can probably get rid of
that anomic nature in a second but I'll
leave it for now so we'll just call this
push rect outline for now and we will go
ahead and port it
the two to what needs to happen for us
to actually draw here all right so if we
want to push the rect outline here let's
take a look at how this is being done so
screen P that looks like it's actually
something in screen space do we actually
care about any of this though how is
this stuff working that's strictly
something that's being used for
rendering right so let's move that down
here so we can see what sort of stuff
we're using for rendering some way
screen dim screen dim is also only used
for rendering so really that's those two
what about r LP r LP is actually used
okay
so really this is what we're doing for
rendering here and we're we're
differencing off the center of the
screen which is really not necessary
because the renderer will do that part
for us and the meters to pixels
conversion it will do for us as well
so I think most of this stuff we can
actually just use the standard things
that were happening kind of
automatically to make most of this stuff
happen so I think we can get rid of most
of this we can just say okay you know
what the v2 for this is actually just
going to be rel PX r l py so it's going
to be that that's
that's where the the rect outline starts
I guess and you know to be honest I
guess I don't know yeah it looks like
that's the center right of it so so
that's fine and if that's the center I
got a C so this does min and Max is what
it was doing before right right it was
doing - the screened-in + the screen to
him and here it just does the dim so we
can just do without doing meters to
pixels we can just do that world chunk
dim in meters basically so now we know
that that as well so I think we more or
less could just do something like this
and kind of be done with it entirely if
that makes sense not have to do any of
that fussing there don't quote me on
that we'll see is it not push rect
outline it's push rect outline right did
I miss something Oh doesn't take for
arguments that's probably true it
doesn't take for arguments that is
because we need to put in offset Z like
so mmm dim and color color is a v4 so
let's make sure all right so let's see
if that gets us any outlines oh my I
guess we forgot to update our push
rectangle call yeah these are still
pushed piece calls we want these to be
pushed rect calls not push be skulls so
let's go ahead and change those because
I guess we haven't ever called push rect
outline since we did the port to the
renderer so it's still a bit a bit janky
what does it need let's see push rect
takes the group the offset the offset Z
the dimension so it doesn't take the
alignment that goes away takes the
dimension and that looks like it
so there's our tiles always good to be
able to see those skin let's also add
back in the other thing that was I think
we had one here that would show the
spaces that were defined so let's make
sure we can push those on as well I
assume that we can I don't actually know
why we wouldn't be able to so don't
think we change anything there they are
so those are just empty spaces that were
defined in the game so that's good
all right so everything seems like it's
flowing through properly now so I think
that maybe all of the calls to draw
anything that that we had had outside of
Phil Gramm chunk right do we see no we
don't so I think that's probably all we
really need to do for that now one thing
we do want to do like I said here is I
think we want everything going to the
renderer so I think we want fill ground
chunk to probably be able to go through
the renderer relatively easily and that
means it's gonna need it's gonna need
access to some kind of renderer that it
can use so what I'm gonna do is I'm
going to pass it the renderer as well
and allow it to do its own kind of
rendering for now we'll see what happens
with that but that seems like it should
be pretty straightforward so what I want
to do is say all right that kind of
happens up here where we do these ground
buffers you can kind of see where we
were we right here we do them the render
group is already something that we have
at the time so what we can do probably
pretty easily is allow the we could
probably have the ground buffers just
work directly through sort of that we
could probably have them work directly
through that render group before we
really get started now
we'll probably want it like I said do
these on a separate thread eventually so
they would be using a different render
group but for now we really don't need
to use a separate render group although
you know no they think about it I guess
we just could that doesn't really even
doesn't really even matter so you know
we could just do this right um
ground render group this it's so easy to
do right we could do something like this
where we just say all right let's do
that render group right here where we
have like ground memory right and then
we'll just release it when we're done so
we'll just do and temporary memory down
here right before you and temporary
memory ground memory so I think that
would just work right I don't think
there's really anything fancy that has
to go on there and so then what we could
do is say let's just go ahead and and
and sort of let this fill ground chunk
stuff let's let that actually use yeah
let's let that actually use our render
group now I don't actually know I got a
go make sure that the ground chunk will
actually work like I don't I don't
actually think there's anything special
that it has that it needs right it
wasn't doing anything yeah it doesn't do
anything that we can't do through the
render it's just drawing some bitmaps so
yeah I think we can literally just go
ahead and do it so when we do feel
ground chuck what we do is we go ahead
and take that render that render group
right and in fact I suppose we could
even instead of doing it there we could
even just do it in here right we could
just do it right there so that whenever
we want to refill one of these ground
chunks we just do it like this and then
it sort of can just build its little
queue and that would also let us
leverage the sorting that we're gonna do
which will be kind of cool because then
we don't have to make two separate loops
like we don't need two separate loops or
like we have we could just use one push
call and have them both get sorted so
that's kind of nice so let's let's go
ahead and and see if we can make that
happen as well that seems like a good
idea all right so if we if we make this
happen with the render group oops we're
gonna need that transient arena but we
have it so that's fine and it doesn't
look like there's anything else in
particular fancy that has to happen so
it would literally just be making sure
that we at the end of it render
everything out to whatever that target
buffer is so if this is the buffer that
we're trying to target we would just
make sure that we sort of push
everything out at the very end right so
if we do this now we should presumably
get well we'll get nothing although we
could say that we you know we would we
would we could put a clear in here and
verify things were actually happening
like if I say clear render group v4 and
put in maybe a nice yellow you know a
nice tasteful yellow I should say let's
go ahead and do that we should see all
our ground chunks be yellow now like so
and the reason for that is because again
this is still just calling the
drawbitmap directly so all of these draw
bitmap calls are actually happening on
the destination buffer immediately when
they get called but then at the end we
say render group to output and it starts
interpreting the command it's the only
command as is clear so it goes and
clears the buffer right but I just want
to do that to make sure that like it was
actually going through the pipeline
properly and it looks like it is so then
when we get here we can just do change
this to a push bitmap call right and
then we just have to change it to use
that renders syntax okay so when we do
that what we want to do here is say oops
push bitmap we want to do here is just
pass the same stuff the stamp right the
offset is just that pxpy I believe we
still we have some stuff here that makes
this a little bit trickier
this is being done in pixels at the
moment and so this this is kind of
interesting this may be a little bit of
an impetus for us though to go in and
support
soul positioning which isn't
particularly hard for us to do and so
maybe now it would be a good time for
start thinking about that so how would
we do that well we can actually cheese
it right now basically in a pretty
simple way like let's say we just want
this to be pixels so we want to push
that bitmap on and you know previously
we're calling this right and we just
want to literally have it you know do
exactly that draw so we don't want
anything other than that we don't want
to see offset right we where's that
bitmap called there we go we don't have
any alignment or anything that we needed
to do we've already done that although
we could start passing that along and
and so we're just gonna let it do its
thing now if I do that right if I change
our to push bitmap calls to do that
exact thing then the problem is now
those oops well the problem is I
obviously have not finished what I was
doing what is the problem too loaded
bitmap to render group oh yeah sorry if
I do that now P right is in pixels but
the renderer only works on things in
meters and they always converts them up
to meters to pixels right so if I do
this you can notice that like okay so
there is some splatting going on there
but it's not at all right because only a
couple things will still fall within the
rectangle cuz everything else will have
been generated way outside where the
actual rectangle we were trying to fill
was so as say is we can choose that
pretty easily and it sort of sets up us
up for doing the next step that I wanted
to take with cleaning up our renderer
and that is there's a meters to pixels
that's specified right
and instead of specifying the actual
meters to pixels I can just specify
nothing right I can just say you know
what it's one don't don't actually do
any multiplication just leave the values
the way they were and if I do that then
the stuff is actually in pixels right
because if I pass in pixels values and I
multiply
by one point oh I get pixel values right
and so hey that's an easy way to change
the scale that everything is operating
in in the renderer right and you know
you can kind of see this a little more
concisely right if I if I open up the
code here and I just kind of you know
edit it while we watch let me go ahead
and kind of pull that out there
so if I edit this code while we watch we
can kind of see hmm let me move over
here so we have a little more space to
see it you know this is basically you
know it's just a scale right you can see
that if I scale as that number gets
higher then the sort of the separation
between these things gets bigger because
the placement of each of these elements
is getting multiplied by a higher and
higher value similarly I can like sort
of condense them down right into
something that's very smush face or not
as the case may be
oh there it goes I don't know why that
wasn't reloading let's try that again oh
it's just taking a long time when I do a
0.1 for reasons that are not immediately
clear to me but anyway you can see right
oh I know why because a lot more stuff
falls within the actual rectangle when
you do that so anyway you can kind of
see what happens right with with that
scale value and so all our meters to
pixel value was was something that was
kind of taking a small number which is
meters relative to the number of pixels
on the screen right because a meter in
our world is pretty pretty large here
and a pixels pretty tiny it's taking a
small number and blowing it out to a
larger one but we can just not do that
right and so what I want to kind of
introduce with that since we haven't
ever formally really talked about this
now it's probably a good time to talk
about it what I'd like to start talking
about is just the concept sort of of
coordinate systems and of Basie's and
that sort of stuff because we want to
start actually having a real notion of
those in our renderer so that we can you
know do more powerful things with it and
so that we have less stuff that confuses
us like negating Y and multiplying by
this and all that
it'd be nice you know just sort of get
things more towards something that's a
little more reasonable and so what I'd
like to do is just go ahead and talk
about that on the blackboard for a
minute
so that everyone kind of gets what the
idea is so all right so here we come
with day ninety there is day ninety so
what I want to describe now and this
will probably take the rest I think
probably of the session I think that'd
be my suspicion but because it's
probably a fairly in-depth topic but
we'll do our best so what I want to
introduce here and I think we kind of
talked about it a little bit but not in
the cloud just not not so much in the
context of rendering but what I want to
talk about is that concept of a basis
right or another way to think about it
is an axis right these are similar
things because typically we see these a
lot like we'll draw things right you
know like this and then we'll say like
oh this is the x axis and this is the y
axis right and we don't think a huge
amount about what they mean if you
haven't done it spent a lot of time
doing graphics programming you're not
thinking about these much other than
like oh they're just some lines and some
graph paper or there's some stuff on the
screen that's sort of is you know one
goes up one goes to the side or whatever
right but these are actually fairly
important to think about as first-class
citizens and it's important to sort of
think about you know what I what I would
say is how we measure things right and
the place where we talked about this was
before was with the dot product and if
you remember I said that with the dot
product what you could do is you can
measure a point along some unit vector
so if you have like a vector right I've
got some vector V and I know that V is
unit length right it's a unit length
vector then whatever the point is that
I'm trying to measure P if I take P if I
do the dot product of P dot V right that
actually gives me how far along V I
traveled to get to the place where
perpendicularly like a
right angle P would have been projected
onto it right and so what that really is
is that's a thing that generates
coordinates off of axes right if this
was the x-axis then I would be asking
what P's coordinate was on the x axis
right if this was the y axis I'd be
asking what its y-coordinate was right
and so we talked about this if you don't
remember that I highly recommend going
back and watching the dot product
episode the dot product is incredibly
important but that's you know that's
like how we measure things okay and axes
are the basis of that axes tend to have
when we use them in games they tend to
have two properties okay
the properties that they have are one
unit length right and the reason that
they have unit length is because that
allows you to use coordinates in a
logical fashion right you can basically
say okay I know that I can dot things
onto these axes and I'll get a
coordinate on it that is actually the
distance I would move you know in
whatever space I'm in it's the distance
I would move along this axis to get to
that perpendicular point right whereas
if the axis is scaled right so if the x
axis or you know or or oh sorry I should
say if this V was not unit length if it
was say length two right then P
transpose V remember length of P length
of V cosine of the angle between them
that's the formula for the dot product
right if this is scaled so this was two
or something then this value is note no
longer allows us to do our sort of
length of P times one cosine of theta
which is what produces this this
projection here right it produces this
value again cosine theta
there's our theta right so if this is an
extra value in here we're multiplying
that coordinate by the length of V which
we don't want to do it produces a result
that's not very usable for us right
so unit length density 1 and orthogonal
or I should probably say well I'll say
orthogonal sometimes it's hard because
because that gets or overloaded with
orthonormal which kind of wraps in the
unit length part of things but what our
thuggin all means in this case what I'm
trying to convey with it is the fact
that the basis vectors tend to be at
right angles to each other right and the
reason that they tend to be at right
angles to each other is because of a
property called linear independence and
this goes way back this goes so far back
in my math education when I was reading
like introduction to linear algebra
indeed my handwriting so bad I can't
tell where in the word word I stopped so
this is something that pseudonym 73 will
hopefully clean up for anyone in the
chat or maybe on the forums or some
other person who does math for a living
because like I said it's way back in my
math education but basically what linear
independence means it for the purposes
of our discussion is that when we are
talking about coordinate systems the
reason we like them to be at right
angles to each other is because the
coordinates along those axes axes do not
interfere with each other right so if
you think about it let's say I've got
two axis systems one looks like this
with a right angle between them right
here's my X here's my Y okay but then I
introduced two other axis systems and
they look like this they've got
something in here some theta and theta
is not equal to 90 degrees it's it's
some other angle right and so this will
call this like U and V or something now
when I look at these axis systems what
you will notice is that if I want to
locate a point you know in this
you know what now that I'm thinking
about it this is really the wrong term I
should not have introduced that because
linear independence really it's really
just orthogonality because the thing I'm
about to describe has nothing to do with
linear independence linear independence
is a thing where you have matrices
whether or not they end up collapsing on
each other so you know what forget I
even said that if you do want if you
want to know what that is
do a student I'm 73 to explain it on the
forums because I just realized I don't
really even need to talk about that so
yeah
let's pretend I never said that for now
that'll come up some other time maybe
maybe later I'm really just really only
talking about our thought analogy here
and linear independence really isn't an
issue because these would still these
would still create a linearly
independent basis if you wanted to if
you made a matrix out of them I'm pretty
sure but anyway so ignore all that my
bad again sometimes my explanations not
fabulous let's get back to the important
part
so if I want to locate a point here
right point P versus a point here what
you can see about these two systems is
essentially that when I map this P
coordinate on to these two coordinate in
onto these two axes you'll note that
motion along the y axis does not change
the motion along the x axis at all right
so if I want to find P I can literally
can I can consider the two the locations
of it on the two axes completely
independently of each other right I do
not need to know where it is on one axis
to think about where it is on the other
so basically I can do a dot product here
and I can do a dot product here and I'm
done those are the two coordinates that
I'm talking about and there's nothing
else that needs to happen but if you
think about what happens here it's quite
a bit different actually right if I
wanted to find P here well I could
easily see where it was along V right it
might be right there okay so that's
pretty easy and if I wanted to I could
also see where it was along U right
there it is right that's where it is
along U perpendicularly speaking right
but what you'll notice is when I
go up along this axis right when I go up
along the U axis I'm actually also
moving the point along V do you see what
I mean
because if I said that this was you know
let's say that this is five units up
right or something like that that's five
for some reason who knows why it just is
if I mean if I went five units up here I
don't just get five units higher in
space I also get five units along I also
get some amount of of that five units in
V and in fact I get the amount that's
proportional to that angle that's that
cosine again right so I actually move
cosine theta right times however much
that motion is in V I move that along
I'm sorry along you in V as well and
that just creates a much more
complicated scenario that you constantly
have to work think through right
whenever you're doing things whereas in
this one when they're orthogonal you end
up in a nice pure scenario where you can
always consider each axis completely
independently and you don't have to
worry about the interaction between the
two and so that's what the orthogonality
gives you that you want it just makes
life a lot simpler it's not that you
couldn't do things in this system
because each point can still be uniquely
located using this system right I can
still say oh well you know what if I
wanted to get here what I would do is
I'd first move up this far right along P
which is not the dot product of it on
you and then I would move this far along
V right you know I can still get there
just fine and it's still unique there is
still no other way to produce P so it's
not like it creates some ambiguity about
what the coordinates are there's only
one set of coordinates still and that's
why I said this was the wrong term to
introduce right and in fact I could
probably I'll try to save maybe I'll
maybe I'm only making things work but
worse but I'll try to save pseudonym 73
from having an aneurysm here by just
briefly saying what this is or at least
what I think it is and so
then you know maybe this is only gonna
make it worse for him to try and
untangle it later but you know I'm a
game programmer I'm not a mathematician
but you can imagine coordinate systems
were even that wasn't true and that's
where the linear independence things
come comes in that I was sort of saying
I thought I was gonna have to introduce
but I realized to talk about thing I
want to talk about it really have to you
could imagine making coordinate systems
where there are multiple ways to
describe you know where a point actually
is so let's say I create a coordinate
system that looked like this so I have a
2d plane and I'm using U V you know and
s to say where a point is right and so
if I have a point here at some point you
will realize that because I have three
vectors and there's only really two
degrees of freedom in a plane right I
could get there via multiple pass I can
trade off between say the s and the V
how far I go on either one and still get
you know I could go this far up s and
then this far in you or I could go this
far in V and this far on you right
because these basis vectors s U and V
they don't they are not linearly
independent they have they collapse I
put this
they do not uniquely span this
two-dimensional plane that I'm talking
about
they are redundant right and because of
that redundant it means that if I want
to talk about a point P I can't assign
it a single unique coordinate and say
anyone who ever wants to talk about this
point in space given this basis has to
use this value
there's many values I could assign to it
there's infinitely many in fact right so
that would just be crazy and like I said
I don't really need to talk about that
for talking about why I need to but I'll
just briefly mention it and if you get
into more linear algebra right what
happens is you imagine matrices with
these things in them and it's whether or
not that matrix ends up having whether
it's you know singular and stuff like
this you could so this there's there's
linear algebra afoot here
right but getting back to just the more
intuitive stuff you can see why these
are important properties right for what
we wanted to we want to have unit length
we want to have them be orthogonal and
you might grab a little bit from this
and just say and we want them to be
minimal right in some sense right we
want them to uniquely span the space but
no more so if we have a 2d plane we want
to basis basis right we want X and y we
don't want some other basis jumping in
here making things more confusing for us
so we typically want you know the same
as the number of dimensions we want the
unit length we want them to be
orthogonal to each other and the same
thing happens in 3d when we extend it
out here's our X right here's our Y
here's our Z when we extend it out we
want the exact same thing to be true we
want all of these guys to be unit length
right want them all to be unit length we
want them all to be orthogonal so
there's a right angle between each and
every one of them and that goes for
every single pair right and you can
imagine writing this in terms of that
dot product again because if you
remember the dot product I spoke about
this before cosine theta
well if theta is 90 degrees right what's
the cosine of 90 degrees right remember
your circle here's the circle right this
is this is our unit circle right and as
we go around that unit circle cosine is
the x-coordinate sine is the
y-coordinate right so here is 90 degrees
right here's our 90 degrees right here
when we're here what's our x-coordinate
it's zero right so cosine of 90 is 0
which means that the dot product and if
it's zero everything else goes away
which means the dot product of any two
vectors whose angle between them is 90
degrees in space the dot product is zero
so we can define this cordas requirement
for our coordinate systems similarly by
seeing we also know not only do we know
that all their lengths are one we also
know that if you take any pair of them
and you dot them together you will get
nothing right
and that's what we like to see right
that's what we want to see so that's
kind of how we define basis vectors okay
now moving up from basis vectors a lot
of times you know it depends how you
want to describe a basis vector I
actually use it then to start talking
about any sort of coordinate system like
that that I introduced which may be
stretching the term basis a little bit
thin but it's still I think probably
technically correct because that's like
what we would create for our actual
screen coordinates or our actual world
space coordinates would be would be
obeying this but what we probably and
and this part were probably never gonna
change this is gonna be true all the
time
you're very rarely are we gonna do
anything that messes with that but this
part right here we may change right and
so that's where basis vectors get a
little more interesting so when I let's
talk about how to represent thing in
base vectors then we'll talk about that
scale let's see how much time I got got
seven minutes so what I want to say here
is these basis vectors are ways in which
we can both measure things and encode
things right so if I take a basis like
the screen space basis right it's a way
of encoding points so I'm encoding
points by saying I'm going to record
where they are right I'm going to record
where they are by what they're
measurement is along axes so if I want
to record P I record P by saying what is
its exposition what is its Y position
right I want to know what its
measurement is and with that measurement
I can reconstruct what it is but the
interesting thing about that is that
process right can be made more explicit
and when you make that more explicit you
can do more powerful things with bases
so for example we are used to using
these relatively directly we are used to
singing oh okay we just have some
function like you saw us with the pixels
we do something like okay we've got
pixels right and we look at the pixels
that were at like Y times
stride you know plus X equals some value
right equals the color right you saw us
doing a bunch of drawing things where we
were doing this this is that we were
drawing things implicit in that is this
understanding that this layout this this
grid of pixels that were outputting to
the screen implicit in that is that
we've just we moved by rows when Y
changes and we move by columns when X
changes that was just we just baked that
in there and that's what x and y meant
right but if we want to get to more
powerful rendering what we want to be
able to do is we want to be able to
rotate things we want to be able to
scale things right and so in order to do
that we want to start thinking about
this these bases more explicitly and
thinking about screen space versus a
sort of object space or world space all
these sorts of things more explicitly so
we already have one of those right we
already have one of them happening
already and that is meters to pixels
right you saw this happen this is a
basis change all right we baked that in
but that's a basis change what we were
saying literally the whole time we never
mentioned it because we haven't really
gotten to the point where we want to dig
into it but now's the time what we were
saying there was okay we have oh and you
know what negate why those are the two
things these are all basis changes
that's what they are we were saying this
is what our world X and our world Y axes
are and we are describing points in
world space right that is what we were
doing maybe I should be a little more
consistent there X world wide world
right
there we go ex-world oh wow that's not
x/y world x world yeah a little bit
better my handwriting is atrocious
right that's what we're doing we're
specifying these in world space we were
saying that one unit along X or one unit
along Y or something was a meter right I
think it's what we said so these are in
meters one unit is a meter that was its
units this is our world space basis
that's what it was and everything's
described in it but when we render this
is completely unrelated to how we were
rendering right this is a totally
different basis what we did is we
changed the basis we changed the basis
to screen space and first of all I
should draw that the other way because
what we actually did was negate Y right
so on our screen space basis you can
actually think of Y as going down
because that was what its direction was
it was left handed right so here's our Y
in screen space and here's our X in
screen space right so we needed to
change the basis of this thing if that
makes sense and it's hard to say I
should clarify a few things but I'll get
to it when we get to it so when we
wanted these when we wanted to actually
draw things we did two things first of
all one unit is now like is this is this
high and it's a pixel right so that's
one on these and they have different
pixels ranked and so to go from this
basis to this basis right we had to
basically do these two operations we had
to negate the direction that Y went
always and we had to change the scale of
our of our coordinates because they were
much larger the core
would become much larger when we went to
pixels when we were going for meters and
so what we were effectively doing is we
were applying a scale right we were
applying a scale to our bases we were we
were scaling and the scaling that we
were using is we were using meters to
pixels whatever that was
we'll just call that I guess m4 now we
were using the scale M on the x axis and
negative M on the y axis right because
we were flipping that y-coordinate right
it was flipping it around because that's
just how we wanted our stuff to go we
wanted it so that if it was moving
upwards in sort of the notion of space
upwards here goes down the y axis it
gets less whereas upwards here it gets
greater right and so you can think about
this as taking those coordinates right
in fact I can sort of let me take a few
more minutes here and just show you one
more thing because this is something we
probably want to pick up on tomorrow but
if you take a look at this right what
happens here is how would we have known
like how could we describe what we were
doing we did it by intuition we negated
Y because we needed things to go the
right direction in screen space and we
had meters to pixels cuz we knew that's
how big we wanted stuff to be but how
would we actually talk about what really
happened there right and the answer is
you can actually do what I was saying
before in terms of measuring things I
can actually measure this basis in this
space right if I want to right that's
something that I could do and I can also
measure this basis in this space right I
can I can figure out where these things
were right and so that is almost exactly
that's really exactly what we were sort
of doing you'd have to think about a
good way to say this let's pretend we
had some third universal basis right
there's some third universal basis
that's magical
we don't know exactly what it is right
but we have some some universal basis
the magical God basis right so this is X
Universal and this is y Universal okay
and we imagine that we have both of
these bases described in the same space
right well what would it look like
well our pixel basis right would be here
let's say right here's our pixel basis
let's just we're just making this up
here's our pixel basis right so this is
going to be what did we call it do we
call it screen yeah as we call it so
here's our screen x-axis and here's our
screen y-axis right and you know if I
wanted to pick the unit on them let's
say it's there right so that's one along
those axes in fact I could just draw
them that way to begin with that's
probably the easier thing to do let's
just draw it so that it's unit length so
that's that's one unit in that direction
right so there's X screen there's y
screen so that's my that's my screen
space basis now I've got this other
basis right that's meter that this is
the sort of world space and world space
is not only totally different size it's
also somewhere else entirely and the
y-axis goes in a different direction
right all of that stuff is true so I've
got something that looks like this
there's my world space basis here's my x
world space here's my Y world space
right so these are my two bases this is
what I'm drawing to the screen how I'm
figuring out where the pixels are this
is my world space and this is just some
synthetic axis that's some universal in
which they are both it which it is
possible to represent both of them right
so if I now want to ask the question how
do I move a point from world space into
screen space right how do I know what
this value is in this basis right I can
actually do that somewhat directly right
I can actually say
what I want to have happen there what I
first would do is I would transform it
into this other space this universal
space right I would first say okay I
know where the origin of my world space
is in this space right it's going to be
you know the world space point the world
space origin I don't know what you want
to call this world space origin origin
of the world in you right I know I start
there I know I go whatever the
coordinates of this point are but why do
I keep mixing up my x and y axes that's
crazy
I really really want to call those X and
I do not know why pun intended
guess it's just that kind of sleepy day
alright so here's my Y axis y axis x
axis x axis try it again okay
sorry back to the back to the point I
can imagine starting here going as far
as its coordinate tell because remember
this has a coordinate right a B or
whatever right so I would just go a
along this axis and then I would go B
along this axis and I'd beat it right
and now I would want to know well where
is it
you know where is it in this coordinate
system so then what I want to do is
measure where it is in this one right so
the first step that I would do if this
was a and B this really that's let's say
that's really what that was right the
full equation is I started oh W in this
space right I then add a times whatever
that that x axis is plus B times
whatever that Y axis is for the
worldspace basis and now I am at PW
that's where I am in this space in the U
space this is the universal in fact I
should say P Universal right in the
universal space that's where I am now if
I want to measure that right I can just
say well I know how to figure out where
it is on one of these axis it's just a
dot product right that's all that is so
if I want to figure out what P is in s
face I could start by measuring it along
these I could do that with dot product
but this is at a different place it's
not coincident the the origin of that
coordinate system right is not in the
same place so the first thing I have to
do is make it relative to this
coordinate and I do that by subtracting
wherever this guy is again in that new
space right so what I would say is okay
I've got that screen space origin right
origin screen space what I do first is
I'd subtract that right so I'd say okay
P of U minus that origin that is the the
sort of the the local version of that PW
but now I also need to know you know
what its measurement would be along the
these axes right and I could do that by
taking that that dot product right I can
just say okay you know I need to I need
to figure out where they are along this
I'm way too over time here yeah uh what
should I do
kind of want to get to wanted to get to
the end of this well I'll give you a
little preview of what we're gonna do
and then we'll pick up on this diagram
tomorrow and then we'll go implement it
in the render let's say that's what
we're going to do so all right pretend I
didn't quite right this math yet we'll
write this math tomorrow and we will go
and implement it in the renderer what I
was going to say simply was just wait we
need to measure it and then we will
figure out where it is in this other
space once we have done that we will be
able to see that you really don't
actually ever need this external
coordinate system you just need the
relationship between these it just the
the math boils down to the relationship
between the axes and their origins so we
end up just doing the relative
Corrections to move things one is we
translate the origin right so we add to
the point whatever the difference in
origin is right or rather weeks a recent
track depending how you wanna think of
it and then we change the scale like we
had to to account for the difference in
axis sizes and then we have one more
thing to do which we haven't actually
done yet because we haven't supported it
at all which is rotation because these
axes could be anywhere right and that's
that dot product piece and the same
would would be true here right so what
we'll see is we'll see that collapse
down and we'll see that really what we
were doing with negate Y meters to
pixels right is just this operation so
if we want to we can introduce a more
Powell for more powerful version of that
that supports the rotation and arbitrary
of scaling that we're gonna want for the
render but I think if I went now I'd be
totally out of time so maybe we'll pick
up here tomorrow so that we can we can
actually have plenty of time to the
that's it all right so I will go to the
Q&amp;A for now all right
so is that relatively what's that was
that beginning to make sense if I it had
another let's say 20 minutes to go
through did you kind of see where I was
going even though we kind of got cut off
before I could get there
mr. fourth-dimension would you represent
the origin of coordinate systems in a
universal coordinate system so yes so so
basically what I was you you don't
actually have to ever represent it in a
universal scoring system you just have
to kind of introduce that so that you
can think about them being in some space
but what we actually do in in the game
is we don't ever actually need that
Universal coordinate system because what
we think about is we just think about
where the camera is relative to the to
the origin of the world so what we
typically do in the game right and
you've seen me do this a bunch is we
have some world space right so here's
our world space right and there is a
zero zero there's a zero zero in world
space it's like where we started making
like that first room right like here's
the first room you know that we made I
think that's how it lines up I don't
remember exactly where the actual world
space is but you know there's the world
space right and what we do is we say
well there's a camera and the camera is
here and the screen is there right and
the screen is its own space its origin
is actually up here right like that and
we never really explicitly form any kind
of a notion of some universal coordinate
system for these two things right we
never really think of it that way all we
do is just go oh well we know that if
the cameras here and here's where that
corner is then to translate from world
space we have to just move things so
that they're relative to that so we
subtract this point from everything to
put everything as if world space
coincided with the screen right so the
is just like an ocean to help you put
them somewhere but you never actually
need it right it's not required for
anything it's just a thought experiment
the other way you could think of it is
just always pick one to use so always
use world space and then just think
about these other things that's being
represented directly in world space so
I'm just gonna say that the screen is
here in world space and that's sort of
how we do it by intuition when we were
writing it that's sort of what we were
thinking of right here's where the
camera is in world space right and
that's fine because we only need at the
end of the day like I said it all boils
down to just a relative thing anyway
after you plug through this it's all
relative so it doesn't you don't really
care who's represented in what space as
long as you can get from one to the
other you're fine
why oh actually probably there's a
couple questions that I want to answer
that one but a few Stream ago you said
you preferred to call functions through
a macro and then forgot to explain why
oh well we haven't gotten there yet I
know which one you're thinking of I
think I know which one you're thinking
of are you thinking of this one that age
which size are you thinking of this guy
it's not that I didn't forget to explain
why it's that I I was intentionally
saying wait till later it's coming it's
good that way it will happen eventually
why is the familiar moving left to right
or did I miss something I think that's
probably just bugs in our like we will
clean that up in the render I think
that's just a bug in that that stupid zi
fudge thing I act in there that was just
we were playing around I suspect that's
probably just a messed up thing in our
in our zi fudge so as we're doing the
renderer I think that will get cleaned
up why our computer coordinates upside
down
I believe I mean I guess I don't want to
say that I know definitively why they're
upside down but I mean here's why I
always think of them as why I think
they're upside down it's because you
know in the old days the way that things
worked was you had a cathode ray tube
and the cathode ray tube is basically
it's got like this vo this is before
LCDs right you don't see these around
anymore almost no one makes them but old
arcade cabinets would have them in there
for example so here's your TV set right
yeah that you're watching right here's
like the dude drooling with big eyeballs
sitting on some kind of a chair right he
is watching the television now
the cathode ray tube the way that that
works is there's like this screen right
this glass screen and it's coated with
phosphorous right so basically there's
like these this this sort of glass this
this piece of glass that's coated with
phosphorous and what the phosphorous is
is its little RG and be like phosphorus
coatings that when they are hit when
they are excited when they when they get
hit by you know when they're basically
given some sort of electromagnetic
charge there they give off call you know
color there's an r1 on g1 and a b1 and
so this cathode ray tube what it does is
it's it's basically I don't even really
know how they work I believe it's
magnetic
basically what it can do is it can kind
of shoot that beam of energy at one of
these at a time but it's just a beam and
so what it would do is it would shoot it
and it would just scan it would go
across right and and so the magnets
would just be set to like to aim this
thing across almost like you know like a
sprinkler system or a laser Floyd or
something it would scan across lighting
up the phosphorous and they would
modulate the intensity of that beam to
change how bright each of the things was
on the screen right and really I
shouldn't have introduced RGB yet
because in the old days it was actually
black and white so really there just be
just some phosphorous but they
eventually did our GMP it would then
when it got to the end it would it would
trace back and come here right and it
wouldn't actually shoot any energy in
that phase because I didn't want to
lighten up anything there and then it
would start again lighting up the next
row and for reasons that I do not know
you would have to ask an old TV
engineering kind of guy they always
started in the upper left scan to the
right jumped back and then started in
the left again and scan to the right and
down right and that's how it worked
so when computer graphics came along it
was not connecting to an LCD it was
connecting to one of these right so what
you had to do was you had to drive the
signal of what intensity you wanted to
send out the cathode ray tube for each
point now the easiest way to do that is
to just have memory in the computer
right the memory in the computer says
what the intensity should be what that
means is the memory right is getting
read out in that order as you go so the
easiest thing to do was just to say like
oh okay I'm pointing the first value in
this memory is going to be that first
pixel right so it just kind of is
natural to say well okay in that case
what we the way we store things is we
store this pixel first then this pixel
second this pixel third right and we get
to the end we star the next one which
means that if I was talking about a
pointer to that thing Y will always be
talking about going up to as I go up in
Y I'm going down where it would be on
the screen right and as I go up in X I'm
going you know from left to right and so
you know I feel like and I can't say for
sure but I feel like really that's why
it started that way if CRTs had gone the
other direction I feel like we would
have had that that wouldn't have been
the notion right so I don't know that's
just my desk I don't know if you're sure
but that's my guess
how important is it to know how to make
a game engine versus simply using one
and if you were used to use DirectX
libraries how much would the code differ
uh well DirectX is really more of a
hardware interface kind of a thing so
the code for our stuff wouldn't differ
much at all the only thing is that we're
doing we're doing a little bit software
rendering stuff that'd be the only part
that that wouldn't be there but you'll
see me use like OpenGL or something
later on I'll show be showing how to do
that and then you'll be able to you'll
be able to see exactly that difference
you'll be able to see the difference
between the OpenGL path and the software
rendering path you'll be able to look at
those directly so we'll be covering that
but in terms of how important it is to
know how to make a game engine versus
simply using one the answer is it
depends how much you how much you care
about quality be how much you care about
differentiation and see how much you
care about exploring new things right so
let's start with quality one I think
that people who don't know how to build
a game engine when they go to use a game
engine often produce lower quality
results and the reason for that is
because they don't know everything
that's going on and they don't super
understand how the game engine works so
they aren't able to drive the quality
level to where it should be when they
use an engine because they really just
don't have the depth of understanding
about the engines doing to be able to
handle situations that they want to be
able to handle properly and I see this a
lot in games when I'll play them you
know like I'll play a game that was
written in unity or something and
there's a bunch of stuff that's busted
and I know that it isn't unity that's
busted I mean you could argue whether
it's unity is busted or not but I know
that I could have gone and fixed unity
that that problem in unity let's say
because it wasn't a thing that unity
forced you to do it was just how they
were choosing hues it but they didn't
know any better right because they
didn't understand how unity works at a
deeper level and they didn't understand
what they would have to do to fix the
problem right and so I feel like if you
care about quality as a game developer
you really kind of have to know a lot
about how
work because you're never going to
actually be able to get high-quality
results out of an engine without knowing
a lot of that stuff and some people
disagree with that and oftentimes the
games that they point to I think are
local um in a number of areas that
doesn't mean the games bad the game
might be fantastic in fact there you
know are games that are absolutely
fantastic that are written in like you
know flash or whatever with very little
knowledge of how things work the game
might be great but there's tons of stuff
that was low quality in there simply
because it couldn't go to that level so
quality and how good a game is aren't
related it's sort of like saying you
know how do you like this TV show and
talking about whether it was in whether
the camera work was really good right
there's quality there's lots of quality
axes and some of them have nothing to do
with how much you know about engines
line but some of them have a lot to do
with it right and so I feel like if you
care about quality a lot and you want to
know you want to be sure that you can
always do whatever you need to do to
make sure that your game whatever it is
doesn't have any of those rough spots
because you can go in and fix them and
do what you need to do I think that's
one of really compelling reason to know
engine stuff it doesn't mean you
shouldn't use an engine it may be that
it's a very good decision to go use an
engine you should use unity you should
use Unreal 4 or whatever like that may
be true for the game that you're making
you might really want to use them
because it'll save you a ton of time and
it does the things you need to do but
you want to still know how it worked you
want to be able to modify it well you
want to be able to understand why it is
breaking when it is breaking or why it
is slow when it is slow and fix it
that's really important for achieving a
high quality result in games and so
that's the first thing and you have to
decide how important that is to you you
may not care about that you may be like
low quality is fine I'm all about this
other aspects of game design and I don't
care about the quality if it if it looks
lousy or if it's slow or stuttery or
there's a loading screen that's 30
minutes long I don't care about that
it's not what I'm about that's cool too
but I'm just pointing it out that if you
about those things and you want to do
all those things efficiently engines are
not firemen forget these days
unfortunately there's actually just a
lot of stuff you have to know to be able
to use them effectively there they're a
complicated tool that requires a lot of
knowledge to use effectively and so
understanding how an engine works is
part of gaining that knowledge okay so
think to again sort of depending on
different differentiation so if you know
how to write a game engine even if you
choose to use an engine because you can
write one you have the ability to mod
that engine to do things nobody else can
do right or rather no other person who
doesn't know how to make a game engine
could do so it's very easy to
differentiate yourself in your game if
you have those skills because you can do
things that other people who all they
can do you know all they know how to do
is like click check boxes or whatever
could never do right they're never gonna
be able to do a bunch of things that you
can do if you knew how an engine worked
right that's pretty straightforward
self-explanatory so if you don't care
about that if you're like no I just make
games where you come just walk around a
3d space and that's what you know unreal
and unity do so we're good then you know
you're probably fine but if you have
specific things you might want to do
that involve a little more deeper stuff
maybe like advanced time manipulation
things or stuff like that right people
who can do that they can make that game
and you can't because you just did
there's no options for that in unity
you're unreal
that doesn't have that particular way
that you wanted to warp time or have it
do something right so up that's it right
you're you can't do it and they can and
then the third reason is a different in
addition to the differentiation is
exploring things that people haven't
done before right so there's tons of
things that the Unreal Engine 4 and
unity can't do they are a set of things
that we have not even conceived of yet
potentially and then there's a set of
them that we have conceived of in that
just they just don't do right if your
game wants to be in one of those spaces
you can't use those engines or you can't
use those engines without heavily
modifying them and if you don't
understand how to make
you can't do that so again you can't
really ever make those games and so in
some sense you could think of it as if
you don't know how to make a game engine
you will only ever be somebody who can
make games in the small space of games
that we currently have carved out by
those engines everything else you will
have to wait for other people to make
for you and you will have to hope that
they license whatever they make because
you can never get out to that space
because the engines don't do it right so
taken together I just feel like if you
are a game developer it's incredibly
limiting to not know how to make an
engine especially in this day and age
when games haven't really defined all
that they could be like we don't know
every possible way a game can be like
we're still coming up with new ways that
games can be we're coming up with new
genres even like you know there's a lot
of progress in terms of defining what a
game is not being able to be a part of
that because you just don't know how is
very very limiting and it doesn't mean
that you can't still make good games
that are interesting in the known space
of games but it does mean that you're
not on the frontier and personally I
feel like if the frontier is a way
better place to be than just kind of
with everyone else in in the known space
so hopefully that's a pretty complete
answer
no more questions ask me no more
questions I will tell you no more lies
as they say all right well if there's no
more questions there's no more handmade
here oh all right well thank you
everyone for joining me for another
episode of handmade hero where we almost
got through Basie's well we will try to
do that tomorrow so that we can have our
sort of rotation and scaling in there
now of course we'll have to actually
start working on the rendering to do
rotation scaling as well so that'll be a
whole nother issue but just in terms of
getting our stuff defined more cleanly
we kind of have to work through this
stuff so hopefully that will go smoothly
tomorrow and I can do a little more
whiteboard diagramming that we can
implement it and that will set us up for
for kind of some nice I feel like by
Friday I'd like to have it so that the
specification of stuff is a little
cleaner and it's not so weird about like
when things are getting negated and
meters to pixels and that sort of stuff
so that's what I would like to do and
that's what we'll continue doing
tomorrow so anyway thank you very much
for joining me it's a pleasure coding
with you as always if you would like to
follow along at home you can always peer
to the game on handmade hero org you can
use the little pee order button it comes
with the source code so you'll be able
to download it every night and follow
along and just play around the stuff
that we've been playing around with
which is fun and hopefully educational
as well we also have forums we can ask
questions you go to that site there's
also things like ports to Mac and Linux
there's even a BitTorrent now where you
can download high-res versions of the
videos so that you can watch them
without using YouTube that's kind of
Handy there's stuff in there go check it
out it's cool we have a patreon if you
want to support the video series you
could subscribe to that we have a tweet
bot that tweets the schedule if you want
to know when we're gonna be live so
that's pretty handy and of course we
have an episode archive you can get to
the YouTube one here and there's also an
episode archives it's annotated out in
the forum so check that out as well so
yes I hope that you have I thought hope
that you will have a lovely April Fool's
Day tomorrow I know that the internet
will be rife with April Fool wings so
hopefully that'll be good and hopefully
no one plays a prank on you I know that
I'm certainly hoping to and play a prank
on me
and so we will see hopefully we will all
sort of come away unscathed from the
from the from the sort of the tomfoolery
if you will the Tom April April
tomfoolery so thanks very much for
watching and I'll see you tomorrow