hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we code a complete game
live on stream we almost didn't make it
today the we moved we did an office move
and can't stop moving who was the moving
company I would not recommend this
moving company they destroyed the
handmade hero desk it's one of those
like desks that has a height adjustable
height on it and they like I probably
tried to ram it through a door without
realizing that it has a control on it
and it just like shattered like the
control board was fractured out of the
rubber housing and like one of the
capacitors or I guess my circuit board
knowledge is not very good but like the
the actual there was like a coiled wire
and like what looked like a capacitor
cap or something which just split in
half and all the wire could come out so
it was it was pretty bad so I was super
depressed and I'm like oh man what am I
gonna do cuz that desk like it's pretty
old all the desks at my rocket were from
the old days and they took a long time
to get and they're pretty expensive and
so I was like oh this is terrible but
then like you know John blow recently he
had spent some time in Seattle and he
had actually gotten a desk one of these
desks it was a Jarvis desk it was from a
company called fully and it was a pretty
cool desk and it had high just - like Oh
where'd you get this desk and did it
take a long time to get it cuz I'm still
thinking in the old days and he's like
now he's ordered online it shows up but
I'm like oh that's awesome
so I'd had that in my head and I like
idly mention this I'm like well I don't
know this desk is probably toast and I
there's no way I'm gonna be able to
repay the circuit board I don't know
anything about hardware so I'm just like
I'm probably you know probably screwed
we're not gonna be able string handmade
here for like weeks but man it's like
well let me just try it let me see if I
can get one from that company and she
actually went online and she ordered
this desk and it showed up in two days
so like clearly the process has gotten
the
lot better people must use these kind of
desks a lot more now than they used to
so basically this this stream is
definitely happening thanks to Anna and
to John as well for having proved that
you can get these desks nowadays in a
recent amount of time hold on one second
I gotta get my tissues too I don't know
where they went
all right so yes so basically the the
evil moving company tried to thwart the
stream but they were not able to thanks
to the heroics of of john and anna
indirectly and so now we are able to
resume programming as we as we would
have which is very good all right so in
theory everything is working now I
checked on the Blackmagic capture card
took us a little while during the pre
stream to get it set up properly back
again you kind of got to do a little
dance but it looks like it's capturing
at 1080p 60 again which means everything
should be working okay
and I should be able to just start as if
nothing had happened and maybe possibly
who knows could be we'll find out in a
second everything it'll just be fine so
we'll see I'll try to keep an eye on the
streaming - this is the first time using
the Internet here so we don't really
know how that's gonna go but so far I
don't see any dropped frames so
hopefully everything yeah hopefully
everything will be okay let's get
started so if you remember where we were
we had kind of done some exploration of
the camera I never I couldn't really
find a good way to get the camera really
working in a way that I wanted to with a
specified control curve like where we
actually just specified a cubic for it
so what we ended up doing was just
falling back to what I said we would
fall back to if we couldn't which is a
proportional derivative controller and
those are pretty
good but there's some problems with
proportional derivative controller which
is that the sometimes will do some some
stuff that you don't necessarily want
and you have to tune it to potentially
tune the parameters to be set
appropriately to avoid things like
overshoot or framerate dependent stuff
like that but if you look at how its
behaving now you can kind of see the
cameras pretty nice even so with the
proportional derivative controller right
you know we go ahead and bring that up
to full screen you can see that's doing
roughly what we wanted to do which is
that you know it it smoothly transitions
between different camera modes and
doesn't produce a lot of unwanted
artifacts so for example when I'm
hopping around in this scene you can see
that the camera is allowed to roam
freely across the vertical extent of
this particular room and you can also
kind of see that it doesn't do that
horizontally and that's by design right
we specified that explicitly we have
different kinds of rooms there that do
that and you can also see here a sort of
ease of transition like when we come in
here it's not tracking any motion of the
player it's just a static right it's not
doing anything to track where the player
is it just focused on the scene directly
and so that it transitions between those
modes nice and seamlessly and that all
feels pretty good and if I go into again
this is another vertical track room if I
go into a room that tracks both
directions so I believe this garden area
outside here
that's a double track room so it I think
it tracks horizontal and vertical maybe
not it looks like it doesn't track
horizontal I don't know if we have any
rooms that are big enough for that we
probably should have some we'll have to
set those up later but anyway it seems
to be tracking pretty pretty well
through there and all that all seems to
be pretty good so really what we have
now is we can just choose to say look
that's good enough for our purposes
let's go ahead and double down on the
proportional derivative controller and
just look at some of the other things
that we need the camera to do and maybe
clean them up so for example if you look
at this you probably can't quite feel it
on the
on the stream necessarily depending on
how you're watching this because again
the stream you know isn't a perfect
replication of what the players act
going to see it goes through an MPEG
encoder and decoder and there's some
loss there and you know who knows the
frame rates not 60 I think I stream it
like 30 so you guys don't quite see the
full 60 frames a second feed and you
don't really need to write we're not
this isn't an action gaming stream it's
a development stream so that's fine but
the point is simply that if you look at
what's going on native so what I can see
on a 60 frames a second display and I
think we are running at 60 frames a
second here let me see where's our
profile counter stuff here so yeah we
are running at 60 frames a second locked
more or less right now and so when you
look at it at 60 frames a second what
you can see is that when the character
hops along it's actually following the
character up and down with a certain
amount of that hop and so it's
constantly trying to get the exact
player location for the axes we tell it
to so if we tell it to do just why or
just X it's not gonna look at the other
axis it's not gonna try to track that
axis but it is gonna track the one that
we told it to and it's gonna track the
entirety of the editing motion so if
there's some enemy motion that involves
like hopping it's you're gonna get that
wobbling of the camera now you don't see
as much wobble in the camera as you do
in the character like the characters
doing a hop and the cameras only doing a
little bit of a damped motion that's
because the proportional derivative
controller again it's proportional to
how far off of correct it is at any
given time and so that's why you're not
seeing as bad of a wobble but it is
there and so one of the things that we
want to do I think here is make it so
that we don't generally we don't
consider small displacements of the
player to be essential for the camera to
track we only consider like large
displacements of the player you know
so I think generally what I would say is
there needs to kind of be some sort of
an understanding there about what is and
isn't supposed to be tracked by the
camera system other than that I think
the only thing we really need to do the
camera system is bulletproof it a little
bit against large frame time Delta's so
we want to probably cap the speeds at
which the camera might consider changes
and the other thing I think we want to
do is we would like to make it so that
we have a debug camera again because we
don't currently have a debug camera
right now we actually don't we don't
have any way to look at anything other
than the actual game camera if I switch
remember we've got we slide the right
mouse button will switch we have nothing
now we have no debug camera support
since we modified the camera so those
are some things that we want to get done
I think we could try to shoot for all of
them today because they're not that
complicated
really but some of them are a little
tweaky and weird so I think that's what
we should focus on today and then I
think after that we can maybe move on to
something non camera related you'll
notice do we get some interesting things
here we've got an invalid code path here
that looks like again we're having some
kind of a of an entity count overflow
and one of the things that's interesting
about that is the entity count appears
to be set to 4096 even though I upped it
to 81 92 because we know we've got porn
movies now um that max enemy count you
know in the future we might be able to
say more specifically that we don't want
a max entity count at all we could
actually say look we'll just handle as
many entities as as can fit in memory or
whatever there are gonna be hard bounce
on it because obviously there's you know
there's issues with respect to how
that's gonna work is this is it just me
or is this text a lot smaller than it
normally is would you guys say I feel
like this text is really pretty tiny do
you think that's because we didn't
reboot as far as
scaling is concerned or something like
that do you want to do a quick reboot
let's do a quick reboot let me see here
restart
let me restart and get the this
you
all right I just want to make sure that
we're not and we can also poops let's
see here okay yeah see that's I think
the scaling was wrong because we hadn't
rebooted that's that's what I think we
know it's normally I would have a higher
res monitor and a higher a smaller font
so I could have probably used that but I
think this is what it normally is on
stream just to make sure that everyone
can see it okay so is that I think for
those of you who are used to watching
the series does that look more like what
it should look like because I feel like
what was happening there was it was it
was getting an incorrect scaling factor
apply that I just want to make sure but
that that looks more like what I spent
because usually on hammy hero the font
is much much bigger than it would
normally be look like that it would
normally be when if you were actually
programming because of the limitations
of streaming you know and the motion
compression and and all of that but that
that looks like the right size to me so
I'm gonna say that that's about right
unless anyone has any objections so
let's see yeah okay so let's let's
recalibrate here also I should restart
the timer there we go
what was today five of four type of five
maybe let's find out sorry for the delay
this always happens when you change when
your setup changes at all because
everything's so darn finicky let's take
a look here
yeah 505 good yeah say 505 what is
YouTube beta have for the last video
that was updated yeah 504 okay good so
everything's back to normal now and let
me just set this to start what do we
start at 115 I think is when we started
this session oops
alright 505 everything's good alright so
back to our program what I was trying to
say before was just that we want to kind
of go in there and change from that
stuff up so I'm just trying to get
everything yeah just trying to as we go
through and make sure that there's
nothing particularly weird in going on
here I'm gonna change the contrast on
this monitor a little bit too there we
go all right all right looking good so
let's see if we take a look inside the
entity code I was about to say why is it
using 4096 sorry sim region rather
because I don't really know why it was
doing that and you could see in here we
kind of just have some constants for how
many of each of these things were gonna
have I'm gonna say that the entity hash
here just looking at how this was going
it looks like that I don't know why we
have this working this way that was fine
actually
the way that that works so this is
actually what controls how many we have
and it gets pushed on dynamically so we
can actually change the number of these
that we have at any given time pretty
easily right and we don't really have to
worry too much about that but looking
you know we may want the hash tables to
be a bit bigger so there's no hunting
through them that's the only reason I
was saying you know maybe so maybe this
does make sense because you don't really
want there to be a lot of collisions in
the hash you want there to be some empty
space in it so that you're not all
everyone stepping on top of each other
but again that's all stuff we can tune
little bit later so I'm gonna again
focus on the camera today then because
I'd like to get that into a stable place
where we don't really have to think
about it much till maybe much further
into the development process and the
other thing that we do have that we
might want to create and I could do one
of those now is when we interact with a
character like let's say here if we end
up interacting with one of these orphans
or whatever because we're gonna go
through and create some of that stuff
and we're gonna do a bunch of gameplay
related stuff soon and so we kind of
have to start thinking about how all
that stuff's gonna play out I want to be
able to have it too so that if there's
an interaction
maybe it's oom Zin on the interaction a
little bit too and we added support for
that there's sort of this notion of
camera special camera regions involved
and you can see inside the entity struct
there's like different things here where
you kind of get like the camera
behaviors for entities are you know
there's they're sort of like this notion
of special camera information that
happens and inside the entity code I'm
sorry inside the sim region code where
we do the update camera for entity
movement one of the things you can see
here is when it goes through and looks
at sort of what kind of stuff is being
what kind of enclosures the user is on
right what's kind of enclosures the
player is on you can see here that
there's a notion of a special camera in
addition to an inn room so you can kind
of see that like to where when we go
through the entities and look at which
ones we overlap with you can see that
there's room entities that we could
overlap with and those room entities are
things that we will then use but in
addition to that we also have this
notion that different other kinds of
entities that we might be interested in
can also have camera behaviors
associated with them and those camera
behaviors can be things that we maybe
like like that say to zoom in or
whatever so we may want to you know
create one of those where we so we can
test to make sure that that's working
properly and so we can see whether or
not
sorts of things still work because we
would like those sorts of things to work
so I want to put in one of those and if
you look you can see the special camera
there's like some stuff here where we
say like oh you know there there's an
inspect and stuff like that
then possibly an offset and so those can
set these target Z's to different values
and they would have been set to you can
see it normally sets one here right and
we've got other things here that we're
doing that set those up one of these you
can see is the new target P gets set to
the simulation center and we do some
things here to change that right you can
see the camera erna stuff we want to
make sure this code flows correctly it
probably doesn't flow correct anymore we
want to make sure that's correct so
let's go ahead and just read through
that and make sure that's going properly
and then we'll go create one of these
entities and make sure that works too
that way we can sort of verify like all
the camera code and kind of hammer on
that a little bit more today just make
sure that's working right so you can see
in here once we know which room were in
we're gonna say that there's a volume of
that room and here it is right
the you know the collision volume part
of this and we've got this notion of the
simulation center which is what we're
going to simulate around that just gets
set to the center of the room and that's
fine right so then in here we sort of
set the new target P the simulation
center but you know if you look at kind
of what happens there it's a little
nonsensical really to be honest so yeah
you can it's a little bit dumb but it's
fine so if you see what's going on here
what we say is look let's default to
setting it to the simulation center and
then later we'll do some stuff with the
camera arm and stuff like that right I
don't really think that's how we want to
necessarily do this I think what we want
to do instead is say look the simulation
center is always something that we're
gonna set so you can see us doing this
here right we're gonna set the
simulation center and that's
non-negotiable
because the simulation center always
takes place around the room rooms are
sort of our fundamental semantic concept
in handmade hyrum and so we want the
player to also be kind of under the
expectation that the game generally is
aware of what room you're in and there's
things that happen based on the room
you're in right so you know if you're
inside a cursed room and you can't use a
certain magical
or something like that the player
understands that and the game
understands that and so we generally
want the concept of the simulation to
just be about the room and that's just
how like so this is all just you know a
given and it's not gonna matter whether
we're focusing on a particular part of a
room or not that that part is sort of
non-negotiable so then we get to the
part where were like okay we've got
where do we want to actually look at
with the camera because remember we can
simulate a round of the room but maybe
we're focusing on one part of the room
so those are not necessary the same
thing so we start out by saying well
let's pretend that we are gonna focus on
the center of the room which is the
simulation center and let's pretend that
we're gonna focus on the target offset Z
and that's all gonna be fine or whatever
right and so that's what we're gonna do
here right and let's let's sort of feed
for it from there the other thing I want
to do is take a look at how the special
camera stuff is working here when we
look at the camera behavior okay so one
of the things we also see here is that
you know the special camera information
so special camera can be related to the
room or it can be related to an entity
so if you look at what happens here room
always gets set by whatever the room is
that you're in but the test entity may
have camera behavior and that camera
behavior can get specified whether
you're in the room or not now this means
that there's some stuff that we have to
do here that we want to make sure we do
correctly and right now we're not really
doing it correctly so what you can see
is you can see us setting the special
camera and we're sending the special
camera based on whether or not we had a
room with a special camera or any other
entity with a key special camera that's
not really what we want to do because
the room itself may overlap the entity
as well as a special part of the room
may overlap nd so we don't want the room
to override a special camera if there is
one we only want to use the special
camera information from the room if
there isn't another special camera
information
that we see elsewhere right so what we
want to do here is is almost like an
else clause right I think so we want to
do some stuff here that that we want to
kind of move this stuff we want to move
how this logics being done and we want
to make sure that the room won't
override another special camera so the
easiest way to do this probably is to
say look if there's testimony camera
behavior on here then when we go into
this loop and we see you know we're
gonna do some stuff to see if this
passes if it does pass we want to do a
check in here to say look if this is a
room right so if you know test entity
equals in room or maybe better way to
say it would be if it doesn't equal in
room right so this is some more specific
region of the room we're specifying if
it's not equal to in room then okay we
can apply this camera logic just fine
right however if it is the in room then
we only want to do it we only want to
override it if this thing doesn't have
if there wasn't already a special camera
so if there wasn't a special camera
we'll take it otherwise it it better not
be the room now we may want to make this
even more specific than that you could
imagine circumstances where we actually
have many different camera regions
overlapping and we wanted to merge their
behaviors together I'd rather wait till
we actually have that situation because
I don't have any way to test that right
now and so I don't really want
necessarily write code that tries to
figure out what you mean if you have
overlapping camera regions you know did
you want to apply both of them or only
one of them you know what were you
trying to do and so I'm not really going
to get into that right now but I would
like to make it so that it works for the
for the region inside room case
regardless of which order the entities
come in so we're gonna do that like this
all right so once we get into the
special camera information here and you
can see us specifying that stuff here
what I do want to do is then make sure
that this works properly so if you look
here we can update the target axes which
is something that we've already tested
when the room that self is setting that
value but then we also have a thing when
there if there's an offset you can see
us saying here like okay what are we
gonna do there and what you can see is
we're taking the X Y and we're changing
the camera offset using that X Y I don't
like that what I would rather do is I
would rather have that offset for the
camera actually be based more on the
location of the entity itself which
right now it wouldn't be right so right
now that camera offset X Y would be
relative and I don't really want it to
be relative if that makes sense so
looking in here and there's a couple of
the ways we can write that we could
write it as an offset relative to the
player as well so I don't know how we
want to do that but do you think um
there's a lot of ways you could do this
and I think the right way is to say
let's make it relative to that to the
actual entity the actual enclosure that
you've specified for the camera behavior
so when you create the entity that's
like got the bounds that says when
you're inside these boundaries use this
special camera let's make it relative to
that so in order to do that we don't
want to do simulation center here right
what we want to do is take the test
entity's actual location in X Y which it
has and then we want to add the camera
offset X Y so in other words you can
still create an offset if you want but
we're gonna start at least in the middle
of that thing because that's probably
where you wanted it generally speaking
and if you want to move it one or the
other you can do that but will you know
that that sort of an additional thing so
we want a cold set that and make that
just work and whether or not we want the
Z to be based off that based off of that
I couldn't really tell you that's
something we're gonna have to think
about a little bit more but I suspect we
once and after that it's pretty hard to
say I don't know yeah I don't know so
the target offset Z should definitely be
this Z cuz that's the one that says kind
of how far you want the camera way what
I'm debating is saying okay the new
target P Z rather than being the
simulation center that might want to be
this so you know I think maybe another
way to write this right would be to say
let's maybe just say this so look we're
gonna target whatever this test entity
is that's where where the center is now
and then we're gonna take the offset in
X Y and we're just gonna apply that on
to the XY as it is placement if you
wanted to shift it around most of time
they'll be set to zero and then we'll
use that Z for the target offset and
that's just saying how far you want the
camera to be pulled back then when we
come through here we've either set the
new target P up to be focusing on that
candy or we've set it up to be focusing
on the room center one of the other
that's you know totally fine either way
and then what we'll do is we'll say okay
now we've got and remember if this was
the room then it'll just do it should in
theory just do exactly the same thing
although maybe not so no but but you
wouldn't have this flag set four rooms
either so that's fine so it's probably
all good so I think all that makes sense
I think all that would be fine
and and then when we get down here you'd
still create the camera arm which is off
of whatever the angle the cameras being
set at at the time so I think this all
works correctly and there and it should
just flow through here and be done in
line with everything else so that means
now we have to actually create one of
these like we've got to put a thing into
the world somewhere that we can use as a
test and we probably want to make some
way of actually seeing as well so we
might want to have some entity bounds in
there or something or like some way to
visualize camera bounds
I don't know we'll see so probably to do
something like that just to make sure we
even have one because we don't really
know otherwise what those would be so
anyway test entity is the wrong thing
it's special camera I don't know why I
said test entity that's what I wanted so
I think that's all good and now we just
need to make one of them so when we're
inside the the generation code we need
to put one of those entities in there so
that we know like what that square
actually means and so how to do that is
probably a little confusing just trying
to think about how this would go exactly
so inside room Jen and we've also done
it we're gonna have to look inside
worlds in here we have these notions of
placement options right and an option is
saying look here's a room that this
thing can be placed in you know what I
mean and so if you remember how this was
going inside world Jen we did stuff like
oh well there's different rooms that
different orphans can be in or just
orphans in general and we have a table
called like look here's where orphans
can go and here's where our cats can go
and we haven't really you know looked at
this in too much detail but that's sort
of what's going to go go on here and so
when we've got this Jen option orphan
when when we're inside the room Jen or I
guess I should say when we're inside the
the place cat or place orphan thing you
can see us iterating over the options
here and then we say like oh here's the
room and then you can see in here we'll
just say like oh we're gonna place one
of these entities in this room and
that's really all that happens the room
gencode then just kind of has to stick
one of these things in there
and you can see you know where it
actually does this where's the placement
stuff here it is so you can see here it
says I want to create one of these
entities that you told me to place here
and I'm gonna tag it up and then move on
to the next one you can see in here that
each one just takes up one of the spaces
on which you can
stand right so what we would need to do
here is create when you know when we're
placing down a footprint for one of
these things we kind of want to now say
look we've got to be able to place
things that have a footprint of like two
things right or you know three things or
whatever and we're gonna have to do a
lot more we're gonna have to do like a
lot more stuff to make sure that our
random generation makes sense for
example if you look inside the game here
we're gonna have to do things like make
sure exits aren't blocked and things
like that right so when we look at
what's actually going on in there we
have to have some way of making sure
that we don't place things in ways that
make rooms impossible to play or things
like this so we're gonna need more of
that later but for now we can probably
start by just doing a little bit of work
to make something that allows us to do
sort of quick and dirty placement of
things in a way that makes a little bit
more sense than what we have right now
so for example what I could do here is
say well when we're actually going in
here and doing like the generate room
call for example let's reintroduce the
notion that we had before which is that
we could have a like a a grid that we
keep track of locally that lets us know
where we've placed things and where we
haven't placed things so that we can get
it better a quicker way of like looking
up where what we've done and how we
might want things to happen right and so
if we go ahead and do that let's say I
create a thing that's like a struct here
which is like a room grid right and
inside the room grid we know we're gonna
have a like an X dimension and a Y
dimension so we're gonna have like X
count Y count and then we're gonna have
a like gen room you know tile or
something like that
[Music]
and this will let us create little local
grids of the area that we can look at
and do things with so we can see like
okay let's create a local tile set for
this thing this will allow us to quickly
do things like look where we want to
place things and search in them so that
we don't have to keep doing what we're
doing here so you can see the way I
wrote this code cuz we just kind of
hacked it in there because we wanted
stuff to work and we weren't working on
this code yet we do things like
basically saying okay loop over the grid
once so we are effectively looping over
the grid and just choose one thing to do
for every spot on the grid that avoids
us ever having to store what we did
right it doesn't make you know any any
difference really and so we we you know
it's one way to quickly write this
routine but now that we want to really
generate things that are actually
playable and more interesting we'd much
rather have a way of doing multiple
passes on that right so we can place
things search asked questions like can I
get from here to here and if not that's
a problem right things like that we
really want to be able to specify this
more specifically and so you know maybe
we just for now have a b32 that says is
this slot open right like can you place
something on it is it reversible and
like it can either be set to true or
false if it is or isn't right and so
that's more like what we want to do here
and then we can kind of get you know
more--
into it a little bit later we can this
can become a very complicated structure
that's tons of information about the
tile as we sort of go further on and and
and you know make a little bit more
specificity about that so in here we're
gonna want a way to initialize these and
then ask questions so what do they do is
I'm gonna fall back to snuffleupagus
oriented programming because I think
that'll work pretty well here where we
basically just say look let's pretend we
already had a library or a system in
place that does what we want to do let's
make calls as if it could just do those
things and then we'll go implement that
library basically right it's like
pretend you add the library
you wanted use it and then go implement
that library that helps us understand
what we actually want to create here and
so what I'm gonna do first is I'm gonna
pull out this code and we're not gonna
do it this way anymore so before we were
doing a bunch of ifs here and then we're
placing these entities what I'm gonna do
is I'm gonna make that happen in a
separate pass so that like I said we can
look for areas where there's places next
to each other that are accessible and so
on right and so what I want to do is go
ahead and have like a for loop here
where we loop over all of the entities
that are available and so rather than
setting this thing because you can see
here we got this notion of a pending
entity when we come into this routine we
have already in the pipe we say here's
this room here's all the entities that
the world generator said this is what we
want in this room so what we're gonna do
is we're just gonna look at that list
and here's that list right we have the
room specification well it's not through
fuzzification
that's a different thing we have the
room's placement list this is the first
entity let's just go over all of those
entities now and place each one of them
according to the rules of placement for
that entity right so that makes this a
lot clearer - now we can stop doing
these things as well so these have more
to do with finding particular cells in
the grid that are useful for this value
right useful for this placement that
we're trying to do and that's really
more what we're going for so here we're
gonna place the entity into a location
and then we're gonna apply the tags that
is exactly the same as it was going to
be before and so all we're gonna do now
is we're really just trying to look this
up right we're trying to get where this
pending entity should be placed on like
which entity it's standing on like the
floor right
like that right and so what we want is
we want a way to say look get us some
some information about what floor tile
we're standing on so that we can so that
we can work with that
right now right off the bat remember I
said you know the reason that we want to
start looking at this in more detail is
sometimes we want to place things that
take up more than one tile so I don't
really want it to look like this right
and this is the snuffleupagus or a
deprotonated pot we're gonna we're
looking at the usage code first which is
a great place to start here because
it'll help us understand what we
actually need if I type this right which
is what I might normally type you know I
place I send the room grid down I say
hey right find a place to put this
entity in in the grid well the problem
with that is you can see right away I'm
only gonna get back one entity but I
just said I may want to entities I may
want to place two different things down
into this area and so that doesn't
really help me right I needed more than
that I needed more I needed to have
something here that was gonna tell me
stuff like how do I get entity with
another thing next to it either
vertically or laterally or something
like this right so I think what I want
to do here is have a way of saying
what's gonna come back is going to be
more complicated than this right and so
I don't actually know offhand exactly
how I want to do this but it would is
probably something like this right
give me back this thing where I say fine
place to put entity and it's gonna take
the grid and I'm gonna say something
like I want you know a place to put an
entity with a place underneath it that's
like traversable or whatever right and
so the query will come back with some
information here probably something like
men
well you know what I think we already
have and I constantly this this Jen
volume is exactly what we want so you
know this would tell us the region in
which that would go and you know I might
I don't know but I maybe could just do
this right it's hard to say I'm gonna
leave it like this for now and the
reason I'm going to leave it like that
is because I think we're gonna probably
want Jimmy I think we're probably gonna
want other information about what
happened and you'll see that in a second
so let's suppose we have one of these
queries when we ask I'm gonna ask for
different kinds of things and maybe we
get back something like this so this way
I can say look you know find one of
these and if you didn't find one I need
to take a days of action or whatever
right something like that uh so right
now I could do something like this where
I say assert that the thing that we got
back worked right and maybe I could just
use is valid here there could be like a
thing that says does the actual volume
exist but again I just think I might
want more information to ride on this
thing like for example maybe these
things you know when I when I specify
that region I might want to say and I'm
gonna place in any in one of them but
not in the other things like that and I
would need to know which one is the
place in so you know I just think
there's gonna probably be more
information coming back from that so
let's say I you know issue this query I
get this thing back and so then I may
want to do placement that that works
across you know multiple things so when
I'm doing one of these pending entities
here what I want to do in the world Jen
is say well when I have one of those
pending entities and I think those are
specified in here aren't
I'm not seeing it the gin room
Chen entity okay so I guess we put it in
here so yeah you can actually see this
working in here so there's the genitive
II next and then there's just the the
creator and here's the tags right so
when replacing one of these entities
what I wanted to do there was say well
we also want to have potentially a way
of saying that this entity has other
entities that need to be placed next to
it or things like that right because
when you place one of these like let's
say you're gonna place one of these
orphans or maybe there's other things
like you're gonna place like a a sign
that the player can read well when they
hop next to the sign there's like a
square next to the sign that you
actually hop on but that is the thing
that says you can read the sign from
there you know there's stuff like that
and while you know while there's other
ways we could implement that there's
ways we could go oh we'll look to see if
the player is standing next to a sign
implement that way I don't know that I
want it that way because for example I
may want you to hop on two different
squares to say things like yes or no or
pick this or that and you know it's it's
more logical to make the squares
themselves hold that information I think
so it's just it's it's a tricky
situation and I don't know which one
will end up using in the actual game but
I want to support that because I want to
try that and if it turns out that we
don't use it we can always delete the
code later so again you know I I don't
really know which one I want and that's
the point I'm gonna explore and I will
settle on one when I'm done but I don't
want to pick a priority because that's a
sure way of creating something that you
know is maybe suboptimal you haven't
tried all the things so you don't know
that you've done the right
one so in here what I want to say is
we've got a creator for this entity here
and I want to like daisy chain these
together so in addition to saying like
the next one I want to say like there's
a child entity basically like so you're
gonna create this entity but then we're
also going to like daisy-chain it to
this other entity that's gonna come back
right and I again don't actually know
exactly how I might want that to work it
may be that this Creator function wants
to do that in a different way and these
tags are really more that will get read
out in a way that it's hard to say how
we're gonna do this but we'll see so if
there's a child situation then what
we'll do is we'll we'll assume for now
that what we're gonna do is place those
two things next to each other right
we're just gonna assume that and what I
also want to do is inside the box math
here we've got these sort of directional
pieces of directional information so I
also kind of want to say well okay if
you were going to place a child right so
you know essentially like this how is
the child like related to you so if i if
i had the place you here you know where
do i have to place the child you know
going from where you are to like where
they are or something you know what I
mean and that way I could say like okay
I want you to place a dude here I want
the child to go you know here or
whatever furthermore I can be even more
Squinkie about that and actually say
like that this is a mask right so you
know you you see how we do it here where
we have these box masks here we could
say that there's you know placement
rules that just say this is how you
place the entity you can you know the
the square could be to the left or it
could be to the right or you know north
south east west whatever so we can have
a flag 30 to here where we basically say
this is a box surface mask that says the
directions like a loud child Direction
something like that or maybe just child
directions so that's where this child
could be placed relative to me and we
just assume that we chased that whole
thing down when we do the creation
making sure that it's legal the whole
way furthermore while we're in here we
can also say whether or not this thing
would take up a square meaning when we
actually place it down does it actually
need to stand on this thing or doesn't
it right and so there's kind of another
piece of information here which is a gen
entity flag which can say something like
you know gen entity occupier or
something like this and we can sack
other flags in there but basically what
these are saying oh and we already have
this Flags those are probably not the
same lags though I guess I got ahead of
myself before an entity just take a look
at what we're setting those at Flags
equals okay
well you know what I have no idea who's
using this so we're just gonna do this
and find out because I don't know who's
doing the flags so literally no one is
using those flags like there is no one
who's actually like doing anything with
those flags first I can tell let me
double-check that again no so so no one
actually uses the flags at the moment
which means I must have just put them in
there somewhat provisionally I guess so
I'm gonna add them now right so these
are the JEM flags these are the flags
that are because you know we could add
there's enemy flags as well you know
what I mean and so you know maybe those
get set some other time but in here
we're talking about does
this thing go on an occupier look does
this thing actually occupy a spot or
doesn't it right and you know if it does
occupy a spot then we know that when
it's placed down no one can move through
that square which is going to be
important for us when we're reasoning
about where we can and can't place
things so things that occupy a square
they can't block doorways they can't
create like a solid bifurcation of the
room such that no one could get from one
side to the other there's a lot of stuff
like that
where it's like okay you know we need to
know when we play something what's it
gonna do so when we have this gem flag
in here that says whether it's going to
be an occupier then when we're actually
generating the room we can actually look
here and see if we need to place it or
not so in other words the traversable
reference that the thing gets placed
upon will not get set to anything if
this thing is actually not going to
occupy that Square it will simply get
the position like the the it will get a
position that says this is where the
thing goes in the world but it won't
actually get a standing reference
because it doesn't actually sit on the
square in that way right so for example
if there's just the invisible cage like
for the special camera you know that
that would be sufficient for example so
there's a couple of the things we need
to be able to do here but but you know
that's that's thing one so if the Jen
Flags
say that this thing is an occupier then
you know it's gonna act by it I may
switch the meaning of this since most
things that place on squares will occupy
them I'm thinking that what we probably
want to do is like is not occupier so we
probably want to do something more like
this where we just say okay you know
does this thing occupy or not and you
know we could do it this way because
that way people don't have to set that
flag most of the time and we'll just
reverse the meaning of it when we
we pick it right and that's just an easy
way to make clear to zero work which I
like better zero should generally be the
default and the more unusual
circumstance should be the one where you
actually set something so in the
occupier case we'll set this up the
p-value for this we need to get from
somewhere that may come out of the query
itself as well and so that might be
another C there's another good reason
why that should be happening there
so again other other important reasons
why we want that to happen
ensue I'm trying to think of other stuff
that I need to do here where we have
that grid query oops
Jen that would have a hmm I guess it's
just a P like a literal is it does it
take a world position I don't remember
which one this actually takes
so inside entity Jen when you actually
call one of the entity placements
functions like search cat here like
where we place the cat there it is so
what do you actually expect this thing
to be Jen create entity right like what
is that actually it takes a world
position right so I guess it would be
that right I don't actually know why it
takes a real position that might be
something we want to change cuz when you
look at when you look at how that dupes
where it has to happen here and we call
place entity isn't this gonna get
circular yeah I mean it this this just
goes kind of all around its rude all
kinds of gyrations it doesn't really
make any sense
this should probably just be a this
should probably just be a
straightforward positional location it
would be simpler and you can see here
when I say this is just garbage I'm not
kidding it really is just garbage right
because you can see here the entity P
just doesn't affect so really you know
this this place entity call doesn't need
to do the
right it could be just saying hey this
is where this thing is supposed to go
right it goes there
none of that has to happen you know what
I mean
and so normally when you're talking
about a placement in the I think that
just works and we don't need any of this
other stuff that you know that NADP
placement can just occur so I think
that's all we really want to do there
and I think I'm gonna leave it leave it
at that but going back here to the gem
tracker so this would just be a v3 P
that was coming in here and when you
call in to this function
these don't normally use the real
position if they got a standing on value
there so this but this world position
will will become a v3 instead which is
relative to whatever the the room
generation is going to be and so when we
call in here and we say let's place this
thing that will be the query P not a
world position but the actual v3
position of the entity if that makes
sense I'm going to comment this out for
a quick second oops
know what happened there sorry about
that
I accidentally reinvented everything so
what I want to do now is I want to go
ahead and push forward through to
figuring out how this code would
actually work with something that has to
place in multiple locations like I said
we can sort of make that notion work
that says like the child has to go here
or whatever there are some sort of
issues though that are a little bit more
difficult to address that we sort of
want to figure out how to do when we
place a an entity and then we call the
creation routine for that entity one of
the problems we're going to have is we
find a volume and we kind of want to
fill that volume and it's gonna want to
use that volume to figure out how it's
going to place its various things in it
so in a sense too I think looking at
this I think it may
make more sense to say actually you know
as opposed to doing the standing on
stuff here and so on I wonder if when we
place this thing actually what we want
to do is pass more like the room query
itself so like here's like where you
know this is the placement query that
the and that the that was done to figure
out where you were supposed to go and so
that you can see the entire region and
furthermore when you actually get called
you probably need your whole chain of
what all these entities were that you
were placing down you know what I'm
saying so this part is a little bit more
complicated and confusing to me because
again I'm not really sure exactly how
this wants to go and another way to look
at it would be maybe the Creator call
you know it's possible that this part
really doesn't specify an additional
Creator call or maybe it does I don't
know
so we'll kinda have to see how we want
to structure that code it's tricky right
but you know I'm just gonna continue on
from where we are here so in terms of
the traversable reference you know when
we get that back it's like in this case
we may want to say well okay the
traversal reference is something that
maybe is going to happen more inside
that query as well right so this part
here where we're saying you know we're
on this floor ID and that sort of stuff
you know this part may also be something
that has to get handled in a more
specific way again not sure just saying
we're gonna figure it out as we go so
when the query comes back maybe it has
all of this different stuff in it so
that when you get this placement corey
you actually get all of this stuff here
and this is the standing on piece and so
when you're actually called to do that
generation then what we're going to do
is inside the room gem call right we're
going to actually pass you the query
that we use to find out where you should
go and you're gonna have to take it from
there you know what I mean
so that seems you know relatively
reasonable to me
[Music]
I think that all makes reasonable sense
and like looking at how these things are
gonna get tagged it looks like this also
is sort of a cascading process so hmm
the main thing I'm not sure about is is
how this actually unwinds for people who
get you know multiple parts of the query
so let's push a little bit further on
this because I'm again I want to make
sure that this works relatively well but
I can see a lot of issues that are
probably gonna happen with it here's
what I'm gonna say let's suppose that
what we do is we run through the sub
entities here so we look at the like
root entities in series right and these
are the things that are on the main
chain so each entity kind of goes goes
through that goes through this process
right for each root entity we find a
place to put it probably like this and
then we assert that we can actually find
it we maybe don't actually do this we'll
see what we do about that a little bit
later then in here we go
through a place entity or you know
source entity call and that just starts
with the rune attiny and goes through to
each child something like that because
we're gonna go to the child but I guess
we want to go okay so that's not quite
right we do the root entity but then we
do the children of the root entity as
separate calls so it's more like this we
start at the root entity and we say that
like the next entity you know I don't
like to look at that loop either so I
would almost argue that it should look
more like this I would argue that we're
really talking about two things we're
talking about groups of enemies and
those go together like this but they
don't have tags because a group of
entities can't really have tags although
you could make something that applies
multiple tags to multiple entities then
you have entities and those have next
pointers creators and things like this
right
in here we have first entity right this
is actually what we're talking about
here if that makes sense and this entity
group like I said I'm not sure exactly
how that wants to be specified in terms
of the footprint that it actually needs
this may be a bad way to to phrase it so
it may be that we want to do something
else here but we'll see
well well again we're just gonna play
around it and see what happens
but this is really the structure we have
I didn't like the previous structure we
had so this makes a lot more sense
so I mean here you're actually gonna be
saying look we're gonna go through the
groups of entities that have to be
placed together because they sort of
have you know inferred they sort of have
to be placed in ways that they can
cluster together so they're not they
can't be placed free of each other and
so we go through those groups and we say
look the room has a first entity group
and then we go through as many of those
as the room has right I think I'm just
going to model the problem correctly I
don't really want to string it together
in some other way so then we say okay
like let's find a place to put this
entity group and here's the entity group
we assert at the moment that we found
one in the future we may have to handle
not being able to find one and do some
kind of fancier footwork there but what
we can then do is say alright now we
loop through the entities of this group
so now we say okay we have like a
pending entity and that comes from the
entity groups first entity and then we
just go through each of those in series
like so and this is much now much
cleaner so you can see that that now
looks correct so then we place the
entity from the pending entity like we
did before this part will have to be
worked out a little bit exactly how
that's supposed to go because again I'm
not exactly sure and so we'll figure
that out in a second but that's roughly
what we need to do there and then as we
go through those entities we can apply
the tags to them as we were applying
those tags before and all of that should
just work you know totally
fine that makes sense so what I want to
do now is just say well forget all the
rest of the stuff we just want to get
this working in a basic you know
rudimentary fashion so let's try to
implement this just for the case we
already had and then we'll try to
implement it for the more complicated
case of having two things next to each
other right so let's go ahead and switch
back now to the room case so in the room
Jen code will actually guess it's in the
world Jen code where we set things up
originally we have in here this notion
of identity it's really gonna generate
any group now and we're gonna have first
in the group so let's just deal with the
code that had the group entities
together first and we'll fix that and
then we'll go from there if that makes
sense we also want the room tile query
stuff I don't really know what we're
gonna be calling here I think maybe what
I'll do is I'll switch it back
temporarily to what we were talking
about before so just to just to again
get it working in a rudimentary fashion
and then we'll look you can kind of go
from there so this is a what a
traversable reference so we'll just get
that working temporarily and then we'll
kind of push forward through the
different ways in which that's gonna go
by will ping-pong over to the other side
of the implementation where we're
actually creating entity will see what
we want there and then we can figure out
how we want to wire them up together
because that's gonna give us a very good
idea of how those two pieces should look
once we've seen both sides so here's our
first entity stuff that we're gonna
place an Indian room we got this sort of
first entity whatever nonsense right so
if we're just placing an ear in a room
by itself so we essentially are saying
we're just putting an end in this room
that means it sort of needs to have a
self creating group if that makes sense
so because we're just placing one so
that's totally fine we just say here's
the group this is like a single group
right and so all we need to do is just
say like add entity group to this room
this is the room in question and then
after we add that then we add the we
place the entity in a particular group
right place Kennedy and instead of a
room we just say like gin entity group
so it's saying put it into this group
and in order to do that it just looks
like this it's the same exact code it
just now it's on the it's on the group
instead right so now we just start
chaining them on to the end of this
group instead if you call place entity
with into a room it will just add the
group for you automatically and write
this code it's trivial code right all it
does allocate that structure and return
and so this then we'll just thunk
through the place entity like so all
right
police entity in this case just daisy
chains on so all of that stuff should be
fine
when we place the entity group here what
that's going to do is just use the
temporary memory that's that's set up in
ghent entity to make sure that it can
access one of these or get you know
storage temporary storage space for one
of these but that's about it so all its
gonna do is do a push direct write and
it's gonna do that on the gent a memory
like so I and it's just gonna push on
room for one of those it's then going to
set it up I and Link it in I don't think
there's any actual information in there
so there isn't right it's just the next
pointer in a first and a so right now we
don't have any actual information there
in the future we probably will put some
information in there we just don't know
what it's gonna be
offhand so anyway you know it's next
pointer it's basically this exact same
code so we just say okay the rims first
entity group is us and the rooms first
entity group then will point to us right
so our next pointer just points to
whatever was on the chain before so
again it's just simply a linked list
pushing it on there so that's pretty
trivial right nothing fancy going on
there I and in terms of this code now we
just need to actually implement
something that finds an empty spot in
this grid and so now we get to the part
we actually care about which is the grid
implementation so let's start there
again this is going to be pretty
straightforward so when we come through
here we have the notion of temporary
memory that we're using here which you
know inside this temporary memory you
will all get unwound so we can pretty
trivially just take this right after
trying to say it's a little more cleanly
we have a giant set of scratch memory
that we can just use while we're
building the world and this grid is a
totally temporary structure so we know
that we can push this grid on trivially
by just using the temporary memory that
we have here so all I'm gonna do is just
say alright we're gonna create a room
grid like so so I'll push that struck
down here where we say all right let's
push the the dejenne remember it on we
know how big the room is right because
we actually have this information we
have like min tile X min to Y and I
guess technically we've got Z as well
right so we have the X count the Y count
in the Z count those all exist and since
we have this V this gen v3 thing where
we've got the dim and everything feels
like we should probably use it as well
so
maybe we can just do this and so in here
we can just say look the dimensions of
the grid are exactly the dimensions that
we had to begin with and then the tiles
is just going to be an array that can
store all that right
so we'll say look allocate in the temp
memory something that actually just
gives us this dimension all played out
right so give us a solid volume filled
with that much stuff and clear it so we
can use it and by the way each one of
them should be one of these so we this
is how much room we want to store in
there right
so that would allocate the tiles for us
and then as we sort of march on through
here what we can do is say the tile that
work that's in question here is just you
know whatever tile comes from you can
see what's going on here these are tiles
in the real world but we just want the
tiles relative to the grid so we're just
gonna say X and X Y and X right our Z
index is always gonna be 0 for now I
think we don't seem to set up a Z index
for whatever reason I'm just trying to
look here to see it looks like we just
we just don't use Z at the moment and so
when we come through here to do our
placement I it looks like it looks like
we just used this floor tile Z so the
floor tile Z is just always the Minzy
which is always 0 so you know in a sense
it's that this makes sense or I should
say it's that right
so really the tile in question is this
tile right it's it's this and another
way I could do that is to say to the Z
index is 0 and that again is just the
relative to the grid so X Y Z and that
would return the tile to us ok now we
don't have to care how we index this
thing it's entirely at artists
because we made the array and we can
index it however we want so all we
really have to do is make sure that
everything is in bounds and assuming
that everything is in bounds and I don't
know if we have do we have a in array
bounds so really all we need to do here
is assert that all of these things are
in bounds because we want to catch any
errors that we may be making here that
might otherwise be a little bit hard to
catch don't ask me why that's a greater
than I man
so really we just want to make sure that
all these things end up flowing properly
okay so in here we sort of have this
notion okay there's a gen room grid it
here's the grid the dimensions of the
grid are specified by the stem for
ammeter so off the go and maybe I'll
just pull that out so here's the the
dimension of the grid which I pull out
then I assert that you know the things
within range and then I just try to
figure out okay well if that's the tile
that you wanted then all I need to do is
to take the tiles and offset them by you
know these so we have the Z index the Y
index the X index these will be
multiplied by their respective values so
you know this is a standard dimensional
writing that we always do so for example
the Z index here for every Z index it
will go by the X and the y and for every
Y index it will go by the X right so X
is primal Y a secondary Z is is tertiary
right again doesn't matter how you
choose to index these at all it may
affect things like you know how fast the
caches or how well loops can be
constructed or things like that there
are reasons to care about them in
performance situations we're not in one
of those situations yet so literally as
long as you map an X Y and a Z to
uniques one of the tiles you could have
done this any way you wanted you could
have had X be tertiary and z be primal
here you could have done all sorts of
things as long as you map them some way
I just chose to map them with X
things that are neighboring in X go
sequentially things that are neighboring
in
why go by X pans and things that are
neighboring and C go by XY plates
basically right and you can see that in
the map here so there's me getting a
tile out of the room so when I get one
of these tiles now I can fill it in with
information as necessary so now is the
part we can start to fill out this
struct with what we might actually store
here so it seems pretty clear what I
would want to store here at the moment I
add all this stuff in there and really
what I need to know is okay did not you
know did I add a traversable right did I
put something in there can it be stepped
on and all that sort of stuff right I
need to know that information so what I
want to know when I go to place this
entity I want to know all that stuff so
for example I want to know the
structural entity the floor right this
thing I want to know that so the tile
structural entity should be this entity
I probably also want to know if it's
open or closed right
and so the open or closed status of this
thing it's gonna be related to this
thing I said before and again this now
we can actually start to make this part
of the routine a lot cleaner because as
we're gonna be able to use things on a
grid we don't need quite so many things
happening all on top of each other we
can do things that maybe will operate in
passes on the grid that will just clean
up the code and make it easier for us to
work with it doesn't really change its
correctness but it will add power and
and ease of use to it for us which is
going to be important because this is
gonna be these routines are gonna be
central to the game design process and
I'm not a game designer so I don't want
to speak to this aspect of it but just
what I can tell you from having observed
and spoken with great game designers I
can tell you that having the code in
that's involved in design be flexible is
is critical but you can't you really
don't want pieces of the design facing
code to be brittle or confusing that
will limit the amount of iteration you
can do and it limits the amount of sort
of experimentation that will go on
just because the designer is being
hamstrung and forced in directions they
don't want to go by what is hard and
what is easy in the codebase and so
again that'll be something we'll talk
about more later as we go to start
iterating on design things you'll see me
I'll say that multiple times I won't
have a lot of advice for you on the
design side of things but I will mention
things like that where I'm like trust me
on this one from having work with great
designers before don't deliver them code
that is hard to work with in the that
they have to tweak right so that is just
something that you'll get you'll hear me
say multiple times as we go so now you
can see me filling out these tiles at
this point that means that when we issue
one of these clear queries we can start
to do stuff that will actually work here
if I wanted to re-enable this this code
here where we get one of these
traversable references that thing goes
through here what I can do is this on
floor entity now I can look that up I
can look up into the grid who we
actually found so I can say here and you
know we can even put that back in there
in the query of some percent but I
probably don't want it because you can
get back a volume and you may want to
look at all the tiles in the volume and
do stuff with them so when I get back a
found here what I want to do is for each
of the entities in question I would like
to then go through and figure out which
of these things we were doing like who
were we placing on if that makes sense
and there's a lot of kind of subtlety
here that I'll go into in a second but
basically what I want to do is say well
look let's see whether or not this
thing's an occupier and if it is we'll
pass down the reference what I could say
is since we don't need to do a standing
on transaction I don't know that we
really need this so the occupier flag is
really gonna be more for the query I
think we can always prepare this anyway
so we just need to say look whatever the
structural entity is that you are
standing on that's the thing that it
would be and we don't really need to go
into more detail than that at the moment
anyway
so we'd really just be talking about
let's get one of those tiles we know
which tile we're going to get because
we're going to essentially start right
at a tile position that top position is
the the query that comes back is going
to give us a P that P is the top
position oh sorry that's not true it's
the gen volume min so we know that that
minimum value is where we would be
starting placing things just just for
the moment against twice a week and I
gotta work this in phases because we got
to figure out how that stuff's gonna
look a little bit later on um so we're
gonna sort of take that that volume in
piece there and move that little bit
forwards then what we're gonna say is
this standing on thing doesn't need to
actually need to happen that can come
out here so here we create the reference
what we can do is say look the tile oops
the structural entity for that tile is
what's your gonna be standing on we can
make this predicated on whether there is
anything to stand on there which makes a
little more sense but normally there
would be then it gets placed and added
and it's done right now this should work
for single entity placement but of
course we want to get to multiple
interview placement so we'll do that in
a minute here but what we need to do
here is like a to do
that's like update the tile P because we
need to kind of move through the volume
so we kind of need that to work a little
bit better as we go forwards all right
so let's take a look at where we're at
this needs to take the grid which is
good we've got the grid so that's fine
pending entity here that's not important
anymore cuz that was just a check to see
we were making sure we have into place
we're placing the separate loop now so
that's not part of whether it's open
open is now a separate thing it's just
saying would we be able to play
something on here if we had some of the
place the check doesn't need to include
whether there something to place in the
first place because that will only this
loop will only iterate over things we do
have to place we haven't even to this
function yet so we will about in a
second the get tile function here just
needs to actually take the tile P and
and what I really want to do here is
actually have an ability to call this
directly with a tile P that comes as a
gen b3 because that's just going to be a
little bit easier to work with and so I
probably want this to look something
more like this most of the time and so
what I can do here is just say you know
let's thunk through and this is just a
literal funk right it doesn't do
anything else that's it alright so
that's that's that we're down to just
this and this function actually is
really easy for us to implement if we
don't want to take into account let me
move over here so my head's not in the
way if we don't want to take into
account the sort of harder next-level
stuff that we want to actually do with
it it's pretty trivial because what I
can do here is just say well alright you
know if this is the genuine grid here's
that entity group that I want to place
if all I need to do is find a place and
I'm just going to say a priori that
we're gonna just find one empty square
to place this thing on again not doing
the stuff I actually need to do what I
can do is just set this stuff up here a
little bit more straightforward just
going to go through and set the stuff up
where we just set the min and the max
equal to the same location which is the
XYZ that we found that was open so it's
basically going to look like this and
once we find that it's open we'll also
set it to closed so don't place anything
else here right now we may want to do
this somewhere else
I don't know how exactly one do that
we'll probably play around that a little
bit later but you know we'll see
so here's our found results where we're
gonna say that we found a location the P
location in this case I think we want to
do a we want to probably assert here
that there's a structural tile because
if the thing is open it means there's
something to stand on so we kind of need
that to be structural at that point and
so then what I would do is I would say
like get sim space reversible for this
this one let me just see how that's
happening in in at each end so that
takes a traversable reference actually
if that makes sense I think that's what
we want the P placement to be is
wherever that traversable is I think
that's my story and I'm sticking to it
and so you know I think this is actually
we probably want to create this thing
like this probably so we probably want
to do something like that so we create
one of these first we create the P from
that we set the location here and so I
think that's mostly all we really needed
to do so again we're gonna search in the
worst way possible and we'll work our
way up from there
so we're literally just going to take an
X and these can actually be you thirty
twos because you all because they can be
although I
I'll leave them as necessary - for now
all right
so if we just go through here like so I
can search throughout all of these cells
and again this will be slower and we
will probably have to think about how we
might want to do this faster in the
future but it's you know it's relatively
tricky stuff to do good spatial
placement queries it gets a little
complicated so don't feel bad all we
really want to do here is say all right
there's a tile let's get the towel we
could step the top pointer more directly
I'm not going to do that right now
because again that's an optimization
that's an optimization I don't really
need to do right now and I'm not so that
I'm not going to and we don't want to do
that because it complicates matters and
leads to potential bugs and so until we
actually look at how we want to optimize
things I don't want to do anything there
that could be introducing error
erroneous or errors in the sort of in
the errors and how things are working if
that makes sense so entity traversable
point is actually probably not what I
want I want that I assume yeah and so
now let's debug just this part of the
code and then like I said let's ping
pong into making this do the more
complicated thing that makes sense
what is our dim Z here oh that's a
little bit of a failure to update there
it's gonna say that doesn't seem bright
all right so let's take a look at what's
going on now there's us looking for the
grid we're getting back a statement that
it wasn't actually found correctly and
so it's unable to place like one of its
things in there so that doesn't really
make a lot of sense because we should
always be able to play stuff because
we're just looking for tiles that are
marked as open
and and then we should set the result to
true oh I also needed to do this so I
lied about that that would actually have
gone through and filled them all up so
things that had two entities in them
wouldn't have worked all right so let's
see if we placed our entities properly
it looks like we did right there they
are and so there are people getting
place now and so now we can try to
upgrade that to placing things more
intelligently in there so that we get
two things next to each other the way
that we wanted so the critical part here
is you can see once I get into here and
I would want to do a tile open like I'd
want to occupy this tile right what I
need to be able to do now is search
through the entities that are involved
in this entity group and see whether or
not they could be placed down in the
location specified so if there's only
one entity it would just work if there's
more than one entity it would have to
look to see whether the neighboring
squares in the directions that are
listed would actually be plausible or
not in terms of being able to place
entities there right so we'd have to see
whether they were open nearby if that
makes sense
so yeah in terms of doing that process
and also another thing we I wanted to
look at here what are we doing for Jen
top so we get the query P and we send
that down so yeah you know like so
looking at this for example when we're
placing these when we're placing these
entities I'm just trying to think
through how they would actually go in we
don't probably need that query P there
because this would get that for us so I
kind of feel like that's just an own
yeah I'm not really sure how we want to
do this but I do think maybe that
doesn't really happen I think this is
probably more aware that should go out
here so when we actually create this we
would make a v3 this sort of thing I'm
Sam and that would get passed down and I
think that flows a little bit more
correctly there and we do have the
problem of if we don't have a location
for this thing so you know it's probably
more like this and what we want to do
here is initialize this value to
something that would be sensible in the
case where we have absolutely no idea of
what is actually going here here what I
mean and that's a little bit more tricky
so for now I'm just gonna clear but I'm
gonna remind us here right you know what
I'm gonna do I'm gonna do even one
better than that I'm just gonna say look
we didn't implement this yet that way in
the case where we actually placed
something in a non structural way like
this code will just fault and we'll come
clean it up because this needs to get
better yeah that's not going to be
sufficient to actually get us through to
a final piece of code so we know we're
gonna be back there alright so what I
want to do now is think about the dual
entity placement case and so I want to
create this notion of a you know a text
box or whatever if you will a place
where we can put like bubble balloons or
something so you know if you're on this
square you can hop on the square and it
will
like you know line of dialogues that
kind of thing like I want to talk to
this player or something like that just
I don't know if that makes sense
so what I want to do is I want to find
some way of getting that worked in here
and like I said we need some way now
placing two entities this is a little
harder than it seems and the reason for
that is because as you'll see when I go
to place the camera entity it's gonna
want to encompass both the other the
person you're talking to and the square
you would stand on when you're talking
to them I think maybe it won't but at
the very least it would need to well I
don't know let's let's just do it and
we'll see what happens all right so
let's suppose we did this stupidest
possible thing first here is a fine
place to put entity group call loops
over the x and y of this thing right and
what I want to do here is I want to do
effectively a search to find what else
is nearby to the various people here
right so I want to do a thing that's
like returns the success or failure
criteria and I want to do like a
recursive open tile search and what I'm
going to do is I'm going to take the
first entity of the tile group and I'm
going to conduct the search from there
so I'm effectively gonna say okay I know
that the location I'm at is this gen v3
here so I in fact I can actually just do
this right
right so I want to say hey if I pass a
tile P down and I pass this grid down so
I say like you know recursive open tile
search do you know work your magic and I
want you to return me true if you can
place this and false if you can't then
what would happen here is we'd say well
if you know recursive open tile search
and you know really even this I could do
even more succinctly probably this way
where we actually call into this thing
first right so if if the thing works out
oh my then you know we do this otherwise
we don't etcetera etcetera up something
like this
and so now instead of just assuming that
we can place on an open tile we're
actually going to call through to this
function and we're gonna give it in
addition to the location to start at I'm
also gonna give it the first entity okay
and so this will actually be the entity
that we're trying to place and we'll go
from there so here's that call will now
get called off the tile P there and this
you know will happen however happens
we'll see in a second so let's suppose
we were gonna make the call structured
like that so the reason I want this to
be recursive is because when we look
back at how we've spent set up the
entity groups we have this notion that
there's a next pointer and the next
pointer off of an entity group is going
to have to say where the next person
could have been placed right so here are
the allowed directions for next so what
we want to do is say if we were going to
place an entity here on this tile
who do we have to place next and when we
go to place that next entity where are
the locations that we could place them
okay you can see why this is relatively
complicated but again we're just going
to brute force it for now so what we're
gonna say is when we go to do this
search we're gonna say all right if we
found an open tile that we can place our
cells on right then what we're going to
do is say if our next entity like
whatever the next entity would had been
if the next entity could have been
placed as well into the next tile P then
we're good right and we can break out of
this and we can finish the the placement
otherwise we can't make sense I and we
also want to make sure we put on here we
need to put an additional thing on
probably that looks like this I'll talk
a little bit that in a second so why
don't we do is I'll call this
recursively and a path entity in
question right we're gonna look up where
it was supposed to be placed if it could
have been placed there oh and the other
thing we want to do is to terminate this
we want to make sure that the entity
actually can be placed at all
it's something like this we assume you
can't place the entity but you know in
here we actually would do this and so
what we're doing now is saying look I
assume you can't place the entity go in
find the tile if it's open we're
starting a structural for now because we
don't really know what we would do in
the cases where it wasn't but we'd
probably eventually have to do something
there once we know more about that now
say assume this tile was occupied keep
trying to place future entities if they
all play successfully all the way down
the recursive chain when we get here
we'll say okay we succeeded and will
break out otherwise we would end up here
and we'll set this the tile that we
marked as closed back to open because we
didn't actually use it right and we'll
keep going
if there was no entity to place that
meant we hit the end of the enemy
placement change
so therefore the result is true because
we know by the you know we know we've
gotten all the way down to all the
previous entities we replaceable and so
now we're down to nothing and we just
say ok that means it worked right so the
only other thing we have to do now is
figure out how to update this next tile
P right because we're not doing that so
we need some way of saying what would
the next tile P be given that the first
tile P that we started with was here and
that we have a flag that says which
directions we can go here
well we know we have some number of
directions we can go from a tile right
and we just don't know which ones we can
use but we can pretty easily find out
all we have to do and in fact I guess I
could even just do it this way right so
when we break out of the loop here well
setting this back I guess we can't
because the way that that breaks out of
the loop makes it so we can't do it we
don't want this to happen in there so
the way that we'd want to do this right
is we want to go through all of the box
directions that we have and for each box
direction we want to check to see
whether it can go there or not right and
so this is you know something like this
so we would say okay during the x equals
zero durand x's
lesson counts for each direction index
we will say if and remember we have sort
of a useful routine sir that help us
with this so we can sort of say look
what's the mask for this so we can just
say you know whatever this direction
index is here for whatever this one is
if we're allowed to go that direction so
effectively we would say look if our if
our child what do we want to call this
here I can't remember what I called it
allowed directions for next so if the
allowed directions that our next pointer
like when we move to the next one
if those allowed directions are valid
right for this if it would allow this
direction to to be one of the place
directions then we will actually update
it for that direction and try to
continue placement if it isn't then we
just don't right because we can't even
do we can't even try right because we're
not allowed to look in that direction
not to see whether that's okay or not
and so then here what we would want to
do is say okay you know we just look to
see here if we've got one that gives us
back the Delta it doesn't look like we
do actually at least not in here so we
would want something in the gen so in
the in the gen math which is this right
here
we would want to be able to get a
directional vector based on one of those
so we'd want to have a thing here that
was like gen v3 get direction and this
would take a box surface index of
direction
and I might do it like this you can't
iterate through enums for some stupid
reason in C++ as as is always the case
in C++ so if I do that right that tells
me that I can go that direction and then
what I would do is say well for the next
tile P what I want to do is figure out
what that direction actually is so
that's this I would pass the derp index
there and it would just add to whatever
my top he was right and I don't know
that we have and we don't actually have
an operator plus so I would throw an
operator plus in there as well right
so I would need to do that and in order
to do that you can see the way that
we've got this set up here where the
it's like set up in this sort of the
axis index and then the positive or
negative so it's sort of like saying
here's here's which axis we're talking
about and here's whether or not that
axis is positive or negative so we don't
really need to be so specific about
what's going on we can actually just say
give us the parameters for this surface
index which is that right that will tell
us the axis index so if we just
initialize the result to zero we can say
whichever one of these we're on then if
it's positive or negative is all we need
to know it's either gonna be this for
this right on that axis or I should say
this for this because it's scalar right
so then I can just say all right if it's
positive it's one otherwise it's
negative one and that's it so that gives
us the direction we would step to pretty
easily and what I need to do now in here
is just say well alright once I get in
next top P I probably want to check to
make sure it's in bounds to get that
tile back now what I think I want to do
is maybe something I don't know why
there's not an internal on there Oh God
the flash of death what I probably want
to do here when I call that get tile
function is I want to have one that
actually checks the bounds and so if you
look at what goes on here you know maybe
the better way to look at this right I
use that there's a test tile or a like
check tile not sure how to phrase it but
basically I want something that will
return zero when it's out of bounds you
know what I mean so maybe you know what
I could argue that that should just be
always what happens so you know maybe
this just looks like this because a lot
of times you're gonna do a fetch and you
just want to say is there a tile there
you know I don't know because I'm like
procedurally doing some stuff you know
what I mean and so you may actually want
to do something more like this you know
what I mean so there were we get to do a
get tile in here we would do an
assertion because it has to always be
true but in other parts of the code we
would not do that we would say okay it's
not always going to be accurate or sorry
there's not always gonna be a tile there
and that's actually fine so when I do
this call again working all the way
through now what I would do is I'd say
look let's go ahead and get a genuine
tile there's the tile I would use a get
tile for next tile P if the tile is
valid then we do this otherwise we don't
and that handles the case where we were
looking over the edge somewhere in sort
of the placement scheme
and off we would go right okay so the
last thing we want to do here is we
really don't want to do most of this
stuff in the case where the entity
actually doesn't exist so if the child
doesn't exist we want to just consider
it done and so looking at this it's not
quite as nice as I would like it to be
if that makes sense
and so I probably need to do this a
little bit more carefully that way and
so what I would do here is probably say
something like alright let's suppose
when you call into this with an entity
maybe what it does is it says when it
gets down here we will set the tile in
question this is actually the next tile
right so maybe what we'll do here is say
oh well maybe we passed the tile in
there
hard to say or well you know what we
could do - we could actually also pass
in the Delta like this that would
probably work - so what we would do
there is we just say okay yeah the tile
comes by saying it's this plus D tau P D
tau P comes from here right we don't
ever do this that doesn't happen and we
set the tile open or closed stuff a
little bit more specifically so we do
this like so and probably what we would
do in here is say that we look and if
this never returns false then we assume
the result was true
something like this that's not quite and
I love that either we need we want to
make this the simplest we can so we're
doing the least amount of work it seems
like maybe we need this to always pass
an enemy so we want to do this check
maybe inside so we maybe want to do
something like this so we would say yeah
in the case to see if this flows a
little better so in here would say
here's the tile P I guess the detail P
could even be rolled into there I
suppose it's fine we don't actually need
to do that there right that's fine so if
we'd say okay look up that tile if it's
open then we go ahead and close it
we then see if there's nothing else to
place we assume them then we're good to
go like go ahead and exit out like
unwind the stack and you're done if if
we do have another entity to place then
let's step through each of these and we
won't assume the results true we'll
assume we have to place it so we'll test
each one to see if we can we will look
for where it should have been placed and
then we'll actually you know recall the
recursive function to keep that going
that seems good so I think that's all
fine we can if we want to be a little
prophylactic here and just say look if
there's nothing to place then we're just
not going to return we're gonna return
false because that's just a bad thing
so we'll just nullify that out right so
that seems fine the I guess the other
way we could do this is allow that so
maybe in here we could do something like
look if the entity group first entity
doesn't exist then just don't try to
place it what does the
assume that the answer is true right
right that seems good enough to me
although I can't imagine what you'd even
be calling it for at that point so that
kind of seems busted I'm just going to
go ahead and say let's let that fault
because why are you calling the function
who what exactly you think you're going
to place that point so I think that's
all we really need there and I think
that gives us what we want when we
actually go now to unwind this and we've
found everything we want to probably now
set this allowed direction here to be
the one we actually used so we probably
want to set the mask so like we'd do
this so now we know that that's the
direction it's actually going in maybe
we don't quite want to do that maybe you
want this and then what we could do is
say well you know when we loop through
these we then want to know where did we
actually place the thing and so in here
we could just say well here's the
direction I actually used then we can
finally answer this question down here
right where is it when we actually need
to go to update tile P we can just do
that because we can say well tau P
[Music]
equals tile P plus def direction and
it's whatever direction we actually used
so the place entity Direction used
something like that and so I think
that's roughly what we would need let me
just go through these one by one that's
actually that
that's all fine what else we got the
plus we need to implement and the Plus
me with us so we knew that we had to do
that and so that's the only other thing
we've got there and so that's just the
operator for these two so that's
basically just an operator plus between
these two which is pretty easy to
implement right it's just this here's
the result so that just says look just
add them the way you would you know
normally next Direction used is not a
member of place entity is that really
true next direction used oh you're right
sorry I didn't mean place entity I meant
pending entity because we're actually
talking about the placement instructions
not the result sooo anyway now we should
be able to place double double with
things and so for example in theory if I
wanted to place the cat so that it was
below the like below the orphan for
example I should theoretically be able
to do that we're pretty much out of time
for this stream so I don't want to go
too long we ended up doing a bunch of
good generator work stuff that I wanted
to do so that was good
but we won't really have time to get to
the camera part that I wanted to do but
we'll do that tomorrow so but I would
like to just test to see if this is
working or so that we know whether we've
got debugging to do or not and so on so
in here if I wanted to actually put a
little bit more specificity in here
kuden excuse me
when we do this place whorfin call what
you can see here is it's placing you
know this a Danity call right when I
create one of those I'm interested to
potentially add it to the group
that's getting constructed here and so I
could choose to place an orphan and the
cat right and so I'm interested to see
what would happen if I did that so if I
was to do say this and I just said all
right we're we're gonna do like the
orphan placement thing here I'm gonna
create also a cat so there's gonna be
like a child entity here you and I'm
saying how would I do that there's gonna
be cats on cats on cats you know what
I'm saying just lots and lots and lots
of cats so if I wanted to create lots
and lots of cats how would I do that
let's let's just take a look if I want
to string it on to this I would
basically say like you know a pen or
something I guess actually it's here
right
so I basically say add it to this one
maybe I don't know if I love that syntax
exactly we may want to play with that a
little bit but it'd be something like
this and then I would have to give it
some information about in fact I think
I'd prefer it like this which means I
should probably flip the way it's doing
here as well meaning I think rooms
should probably come first but anyway in
here I would need to give it that mask
so inside the mask stuff here I would
need to say like what directions it can
be placed and so maybe I say like look
it's gotta be it's always got to be to
the south so if you place an orphan you
gotta place a child to the south makes
and so what I need is a call that will
enforce that rule and so that's pretty
simple all it's basically saying here is
look I'm appending to this the group
that this child's in and so I should be
able to just string it to the end of
that with with really I don't think
there's really much more to it than that
so here's the parent here's the child
here's the mask and so all we be saying
here is all right the parent next equals
the child child next equals the parent
next that sort of thing so we just kind
of like lump it on there I'd have to
assert that this doesn't already have a
chain so we may want to do this a little
bit differently in the future we'll see
but really that's all we're talking
about and then we would need to set that
allowed directions for next needs to be
this this direction mask you know what I
mean but I think that's it I don't think
there's very much else to do there it's
stup not super complicated so it should
be pretty pretty simple to build this
change chains now whether or not they
work that's a that's another question
oops that was supposed to be a knot
okay
so oh yes so I was supposed to check to
see whether that tile was valid because
again remember that's gonna look
off-the-grid potentially so I said I
needed to do that and then I didn't do
it so unsurprisingly
it didn't work so when we're searching
here this is actually supposed to be
that meaning if there is a tile there
and the tile is open then we can proceed
and off we go so it looks like it didn't
find anything for a placement here which
means that it's it since it should be
able to find something I think that
means we screwed up right I'm not sure
how we screwed up exactly so we're gonna
kind of have to step through there and
see but I don't think there should have
been any cases that it couldn't resolve
because all we're doing is placing like
two entities in two rooms with tons of
empty tiles so in theory this should
have worked just fine and yeah I don't
know what would have been what did I end
up passing here Bach's mass
so being able to place that to the South
should have been fine and so something
in here is is just not correct this is
wrong so that could actually be part of
the problem
so yeah in fact it's almost certainly a
problem so when we set open equal to
false we need to then check to see
whether or not we've actually placed so
if we haven't placed the thing then the
tile open should set back to true right
if we if we were not able to place it if
that makes sense
so I think that's probably fine so let's
see if we got what we wanted it looks
like we did so you can see there's
ghosts cats
well not ghosts cats but Hannah's being
placed to the south of each one let's
try briefly switching it to north just
to make sure that that worked and then I
think we're done for the day
I'll take brief Q&amp;A so here's north
and so this should have flipped yeah it
did
um so that's great I think that's all I
really wanted and that's good we can use
that for lots of things so I'm pretty
happy with that and so we will go from
there
all right let's go to a brief Q&amp;A just
to see if anyone has any questions about
what we did there again that was just
we ended up poops it's not what I wanted
to type you want to type it in here
you okay oops that's cute yes that won't
help
come on Q eh okay so there we go
if anyone has any questions I will be
happy to answer them and so again the
reason I want to get that done is
because I'd like to put in squares you
can hop on and that are related to the
orphans and then they can pop up some
dialog and stuff like that and so I just
wanted that that to work and the camera
will you know will just be a good way to
test that out and it will also let us
make sure that our camera code is
working properly which I also want to do
any questions
haven't done much on tumf yes its
pending a rewrite in Odin okay seems
like you had it all working why would
you want to rewrite it in a different
language could you make an elevator in
the game sure I don't think I will
because I don't tend to like elevator as
much so I don't know that we would have
an elevator we might have some things
that that move around like inside a room
that are going around like this that you
would jump on they'd move but I wrestled
deBeer hey case you have topic is it
beneficial performance-wise you switch
statements instead of if-else blocks as
far as I can understand from disassembly
using the switch statement allows that
to compute where to jump to directly
without invoking comp instruction for
each case is that correct if the answer
is it it's actually kind of complicated
the it depends very heavily on the
optimizer technically speaking there's
really no reason that the optimizer
can't just take a series of if-else
blocks and turn them into a switch
statement if they tend to test
sequential values the question is just
whether it does or not furthermore a lot
of compilers actually don't optimize
switch statements into jumps unless
there's more than a certain number of
switches so the I hate to sound like a
broken record but as I often say with
performance things unless you test it
you don't know every time like pretty
much every time you're gonna if you care
about that which one it does you're just
gonna have to look and see because you
know it it will it will basically it be
entirely dependent on what the optimizer
chooses to do and you'll probably get
different results between different
compilers
so
off-topic but I watched her 30 million
lines of code and was wondering whether
you think that Intel and other hardware
manufacture be more likely to adopt an
ice ax as a response to consumer
unfriendly policies from Microsoft if
they're scared of the consumer PC market
collapsing um
I don't know because the decision-making
process inside companies like Intel or
AMD it's very opaque to me and I don't
really you know you have to understand
that large corporations like that aren't
it's not just like I'm like I'm sitting
around and I say something and it
happens right it's like there's a lot of
meetings there's shareholder meetings
there's boards of directors there's all
these sorts of things and so large-scale
strategic decisions aren't things that
don't that just happen because someone
thinks it's a good idea they have a lot
of buy-in and there's a lot of social
and political implications of them
inside the company and so I have no idea
would be my answer in terms of arguments
I have made it's definitely one I make
often I'm like look why do you want to
rely on Microsoft to deliver you the
platform you need to succeed why not
just deliver that platform yourself
right why not just make an Intel chip
that just runs
why do you what Windows does nothing
it's it's almost completely useless it's
you know Intel already ships things that
have like Linux built into them for
example like the Knights landing what
they call it the Xeon Phi right just you
know why don't you want to just ship
apart it just works you know why who
needs it
you know it's it's not good why not
start shipping something that runs out
of the box and see if people adopt it
worst cases they don't you have billions
and billions and billions of dollars it
would be a small investment to make and
it seems like really good security and
really good insurance and why not and
again it's just an argument there's just
an argument I'm making I but but I don't
know you know I don't know what sorts of
things resonate with them and what sorts
don't
to be completely honest with you I think
in their mind we're the small part of
the wheel of cheese because their
highest margins stuff is server stuff
that all runs Linux anyway none of its
gonna run Windows and they know that
going forwards right and the other part
is they they really want to be in like
phones and stuff right they they're
trying to produce low-power chips now
right they're not thinking desktop so I
don't while I think it is important to
their business and they should care
because there is money there and they're
making that money right now and that
money could go away and that should be
scary I think sometimes companies are
both more focused on their new markets
and they forget to consolidate their
gains sometimes and keep hold of them I
mean it's how Microsoft lost a lot of
its market right now a lot of how a lot
of the market for Windows went away is
they failed to see the threats to that
market and that's why there's huge
segments of the market now that run on
things like iPad like iOS you know or
whatever and Linux for service
or all the rooms going to be generated
yes
have you played in any of the souls
games what do you think of them I don't
know if I asked this question before I
have not played them now
is the game granny containing both 2d
and 3d assets not really there are 3d
cubes but no other shapes probably don't
quote me on that maybe we'll add another
shape someday but we only allow
structural cube tiles basically and then
everything else is a spray so it's 2d
assets only really even though there is
some 3d in it regarding until shipping
their own platform that just runs how
would that look would there be a
minimalistic OS boot once you power on
the machine sorry if this is obvious but
I don't quite get it
yeah I mean one way to look at it would
be if you take a look at the actual
hardware spec so if there's USB there's
nvme and there's the GPU that they're
shipping that together comprises
basically a complete operating system
API without actually having much else in
there there's a little bit you might
want to do for task management but you
could also just leave that up the people
writing the software for it right this
is a hypervisor part and so what what
I'm sort of suggesting is just write a
minimal write a 50,000 line program that
is just a bare-bones operating system
that runs your chip write publish source
code and let's go from there you know we
can solve these problems but there's
such a huge buy-in cost when nobody will
commit to an actual Hardware interface
that it's just never gonna happen I mean
you can even bake that stuff into the
BIOS firmware and that's not my favorite
answer but like suppose you did that
just even that then we would at least be
back to the dass days where you could
write something that boots directly from
startup and basically just uses BIOS
calls no
right for the most part so it's really
just I'm just saying look give us
something you know
I because I feel like we I feel like we
could have a good chance of making
something reasonable if we just could
take the ridiculously huge driver space
we currently have to deal with and
shrink it down to just unknown set that
people would agreed to support going
forward I think we could do some good
work that's all so I don't even it
doesn't even need to be settled it just
needs like like work with us right like
work with people like us who want to do
this low-level stuff let's see if we can
work something out right is all I'm even
saying so we don't even we don't even
need to agree on the specifics yet just
let's let's get together let's have some
streams where we talk about it you know
let's just let's just go take a baby
steps right because I don't care exactly
what form it takes I have my opinions
about what I'd like to see but you know
I don't have to get my way
I just want to see something I want to
see something happen that gets us off of
these big monolithic unwieldy
problematic unreliable breaks all the
time
spies on you blah blah blah blah blah
like listing every all these things that
happen right
favorite cheese oh I can't pick sorry
there's a lot of really good cheese's
out there
so that's basically it any more office
moving drama in sans cher has the reason
to move and talked about oh well we we
just had there was a better cheaper
opportunity so we took it there wasn't
really any more drama though it was just
the movers were terrible i was really it
alright looks like we're out of time I'm
gonna wrap it up thank you for joining
me for another sort of handmade here
it's what a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to following
series at home you can always peer to
the game on handmade hero or come to the
source code so you can play around with
it and follow the series
it also comes the source code for all
the previous days so if you want to look
at a particular day you can always jump
back there and play around with
something from a particular time period
as well that's about it for today I will
be back here tomorrow to then do the
camera stuff because we decided we
wanted to put in some entity stuff today
so we did that but I still want to do
the camera code stuff that I talked
about the beginning of the stream so we
will give that a shot tomorrow and we'll
use the entity code we created to place
some special camera markers that we can
then test to make sure that the camera
code actually respects them and does
them properly and then we'll sort of
start tweaking the camera code a little
bit more I mentioned some things we want
to do to it so I'd like to do that and
kind of get that to a point where I'm
happy with the camera code so see back
here for that same time same place
although we won't be delayed we're
delayed by an hour today hopefully
tomorrow will be smooth because hey it
looks like the streams working good so
hopefully everything's fine hope to see
you back here for that till then have
fun programming everybody and I'll see
you on the Internet
take it easy