hello everyone and welcome to handmade
here are the show recode a complete game
live on stream what times it's 507 so
we'll go to about 607 I think is what we
will do today on handmade hero we are
going to implement some entity browsing
stuff that I wanted to do yesterday but
we well how can I say it we we hit a
quote-unquote bug in the in the
rendering stuff that took us like
seriously like 40 minutes to figure out
and in the end it turned out it was not
a bug it turned out it was like actually
the way the render was supposed to work
and I had forgotten
so that was yeah that was that was just
a little bit of a little bit of a old
neurons you know but I mean the good
news is meeting that to fix the bug
because it wasn't there and so that
takes a little bit effort oh my I
suppose always good point being here on
day 205 we are going to go ahead and try
to actually now implement the thing that
I said we're gonna implement yesterday
now that we have the bug the bug gone if
you would like to follow along at home
you can always pre-order the game on
Hammacher org it comes with the source
code so if you would like to follow
along with what I'm about to do you can
unpack day 204 's source code into a
directory and follow right along with me
if you so desire my friend so let's see
here like I you know like I said when we
ended we had it working fine the thing
that I had that the part that we thought
was broken so obviously it wasn't so
broken after all although there were
some things that we would have liked to
have cleaned up as well but anyway point
being what we were trying to do as you
can sort of see here we got this debug
thing what we were trying to do is we
want to be able to like pick one of
these entities you got a little
dismembered tourists over here and our
floating head and we've got the hero and
we've got these trees and stuff like
that we have our little yellow floating
obelisk thing and all of those things
are actually entities that have
properties and stuff on them and I just
wanted a way to kind of like
what the properties were right pretty
pretty basic thing we might want to do
to support our game and so if we want to
do something like that I was like well
I'd like to just be able to pick them
with the mouse so that I can just
quickly like you know I don't have to
think I can just move the mouse and hope
you know move it over some entity and
click or whatever and that would just
give me
you knows make it really free and easy
to inspect those things and so what we
wanted to do was first of all figure out
a way to check whether the mouse was
intersecting an entity and as I said in
order to do that since the game goes
through a projection of 3d projection we
have to basically take the mouse and
unprojected back into that world and so
we did that like I said on yesterday's
dream we did that and so now you can
kind of see as I move the mouse around
we've got this cursor that's like
matching the location and so that's a
start
that's what I was trying to do the rest
of it should actually be pretty easy
from there that actually should have
been easy as well and would have been
easy had we not had our little amusing
run-in with previous render decisions so
anyway what we want to do now is open
this back up to the way that it was
working before and sort of get back to
get back to doing something to doing
something reasonable here so we've got
this thing where we do this push rect
outline and so if I restore this code
like I said if I take the IFS out of it
and have it run over all the entities we
should be able to get back to a position
where I'm sorry to get back to a
situation where we're outlining all of
the entities themselves right and so
let's just undo so that we were kind of
playing around this code trying to
figure out what had gone wrong and so I
kind of got to undo some of those
changes here here we have a push rect
outline call right where we're trying to
to draw the outline stuff and remember
we had done this thing where we check
the offset peeing the scale and we reset
them we're not going to want to do that
anymore right so we're gonna want to
leave the render group with what it was
previously so that we can get all of
those outlines back to to lining up with
the oh and you know what
I got a I got a not change it anywhere
right you can against all of this stuff
would would change that that offset so
if I get rid of all of those touching
the the render state we can now kind of
see that we've got all of the entities
have their little sort of their bounding
air their collision rectangle basically
is being drawn on them right and so
that's the first thing that we wanted to
do before we had done it yesterday so we
know that that's fine and so now what we
have to do is kind of figure out how to
get the like I said the mouse into
something that's a little bit more
reasonable and again now we know that
the Z itself is not getting used at all
that's a that's kind of an amusing thing
the Z offset doesn't actually do
anything so if I want to actually do any
debug viewing here I have to kind of
think a little bit outside the box of
how we're going to do it which is one of
the reasons I was saying I feel like we
kind of want to make the renderer work
in maybe some way that's a little bit
more logical than how we're doing it I
guess it makes some sense I understand
why we did it the way we did it but it
does make certain things kind of a
little bit difficult when you consider
the ramifications of it but anyway you
know we've got the mouse here a
transforming Demeter's mouse and we've
got the unprojected that's happening
like i said that that sort of brings it
back into the real world there and what
we need to do now is we need to start
unprojected the mouse into the
effectively into the plane of the of the
thing that we're actually working with
right and we've kind of forgot this
nasty this nasty part of it where when
we do that on projection right we sort
of have this problem where distance
above target is not actually being taken
into account during that on projection
right so we don't actually know since
the the Z values in the world
we don't actually necessarily get back a
real Z value in the world when we do
that on project because of that distance
above target and that was sort of the
thing that I was saying was a little bit
strange right that was that was part of
it that was a little bit weird and if we
go back over to the code in
render group code right where we do that
unprojected
that the wait look sort of the reason we
were doing it this way is all we were
using it for was to figure out at a
certain distance from the camera how big
would the camera balance be and that's
totally reasonable that we were doing it
that way at the time but it creates some
problems for us in the in the long run
to have it that way because other things
we won't want to do are not exactly
reversed transforms right they're not
exactly going to be reversed in that way
and so now we have a sort of a
fundamental question here which is to
say that we need some way of we probably
want to do something that's going to
take those into account but we still
want some way of calling this old code
we could test this old code and make it
work with the new thing but I think I'm
gonna do just like I'm gonna do
something here just just to just to
shunt it where we call um project old
and I'm gonna make it unprotect here to
get that we could get working which
would which would literally do the exact
reversal of the transform right and so I
kind of want to make you know I want to
kind of get this thing into shape so
that we know that we could just push
something through it and it would
actually unprojected properly right that
seems like a little bit more of a good
idea to me that's more that's more what
I would like to see happen although you
know the other thing that that's
important to remember here too is we've
got kind of a wonky situation which is
we've pushed we sort of have this offset
P and the scale that are being used for
for everything in the world when we send
them down and it's kind of a little bit
odd to with that because it's like you
know do we want a way to do unprojected
that don't take those into account and a
way to do on projections that do take
them into account right and and other
stuff like this so it is also still a
little bit bizarre but point being what
I'm gonna do for now is I'm just gonna
like I'm just going to put this part I'm
gonna keep this part a little bit off
what I'm gonna keep this part off for a
second and then I'm gonna implement this
function right okay so this is
unprojected at the moment
oops and I'm gonna do it this way and
then we're gonna sort of work this until
it's out to something that I would
consider a little more reasonable a
little less janky so there's us doing
the projection the projection ton
projected the mouse right and it's
locked to the mouse which is what we
would expect and so now what we want to
do is we want to start getting this
stuff back you know we kind of want to
get this stuff a little bit more want to
get the stuff baked in so I want to do
this completely unproductive thing and
what I want to do in complete on project
will we'll make this via not implemented
for the moment but what I want to do and
complete on project is I want to take
care of all this stuff so you can see
here we've got the meters to pixels
transform that should actually be
happening in here right so when we do
this on project and we'll just call this
right this is the actual thing that I
wanted for unprojected
so when we do this on project we'll just
say you know I've got a sort of a screen
space point right a screen space point
and that's like good to be in pixels
right and and I guess you know the thing
I could do too is like pixels XY and our
32 you know Z like this is Z meters
because we never really transform meters
we never transform the Z into meters or
we never think of the Z as being in any
other space when we do that transform so
it might make sense to leave those out
and document them this way so that you
can clearly see what we're talking about
right in there and so if I do something
like that then assuming we're not in
orthographic transfer mode the first
thing I'm gonna do is I'm gonna take
whatever that that pixels XY is right
I'm going to subtract the screen Center
from it and because that would be what
we would be doing with the pixels XY I'm
gonna subtract that screen Center from
it and then I'm going to multiply it by
the meters to pixels transform right
the inverse of it so that I can get it
out of pixels and intimate errs then
what I'm gonna do is I'm going to use
the distance from Target I'm gonna
subtract the PZ right so I'm gonna do
essentially this the Z meters thing here
right I'm gonna go ahead and do that do
the reverse of that so that you no
longer before remember we were doing
this kind of crazy thing where we would
change the the offsets and stuff in here
right we would do this render group
transfrom just above target - local Z we
do that nonsense we're not gonna do that
anymore right so we're passing that
result down we do that subtraction we
divide by the focal length and then we
multiply that that basically gives us
whatever that the scaling factor would
be to put the the temporary thing that
we computed into the correct space and
now my goal here right is to sort of fix
this and make this now so that this
actually works properly we can always
just call it so at the end of this no
matter what we always are gonna do sort
of the transform and scale thing I'm
gonna take a quick look up at render
group and see what I don't really
remember what would happen with scale if
we even used it exactly you can see in
here right there's a transform and we
have transform scale but but transform
scale doesn't do anything so we never
actually use that in our projection so
for now I think we should probably just
not do anything with it now you can kind
of see what happens here right when we
come out with a 2d value which is what
we get here we're then gonna take
whatever that 2d value is we're gonna
assume that it's at this distance right
because that's we know that it's
actually at that distance that's the
distance they're telling us the point is
in the from the camera right and so the
actual P the actual you know position
for that guy
is actually going to be if the v3 which
is going to be and I and this should not
be in here right this is like
unprojected or something something like
that
when we compute that unprojected XY we
then know that the unprojected XY if we
just staple that Z on to it right that's
the distance from the camera and so in
here right we should be able to you know
determine that that actually would have
been the z
came in and I think that's correct right
because you can see distance to P Z this
is Z with P Z distance above target
minus P Z right and so whatever the
actual Z is that you tell us is actually
just gonna pass straight through I
believe because we don't we don't
transform like Z doesn't get modified in
any way so if you tell me this is how
far it was away from the camera that's
just how it far what the way it was from
the camera like . so i think that's
really all there is to it but at the end
so at the beginning of this function
right we added the offset whatever the
offset for the transform was and so at
the end of this when we have to subtract
that offset if we want to fully undo the
transform that was happening with the
you know with the get rendering entity
basis right and so that's that's all
that's happening there so then if i
return that result again we have to kind
of go through this step do this to make
sure we're doing everything just so but
that should give us the fully
unprotected thing no matter like
basically what the circumstance was in
terms of how it was was being handled
okay so that means in you know whatever
the actual pixel value of the thing is
now i shouldn't actually have to do any
of this stuff like i shouldn't have to
do meters Mouse right so i should be
able to just pass the mouse p now
there's a little bit of a weirdness here
which is that the mouse key comes in it
doesn't come in in pixels actually which
is a little bit strange and so I feel
like that may be like our output
coordinate system and our input
coordinate system maybe should be the
same so if you look at like Mouse X
Mouse why we do this global back buffer
width thing right we do we do this stuff
here and I do kind of think that maybe
that's not the way we should do it right
it may be that the better way to do it
would be to specify the X in pixels
right and then specify the mouse Y as
being something you can shoot me and in
fact you know what I could do to here
save this just for one one second stick
that in there
just for future reference I will talk
about that in a second
so the mouse X would just be like in
pixels right it'd be there's the PX and
the mouse Y would be in pixels as well
so it would be like whatever the back
buffer height is - that that Mouse py
right because it still we still want it
going in the right direction because
that's the way the pixel values are
going right and and so yeah off you go
so that's that's kind of the idea right
that's what we're trying to accomplish
there and in this case if you imagine
the way this works we want to be able to
get to zero and you can never be on that
last pixel so I think technically we're
looking at something more like this
right where you can only ever get to
like height minus one as moving the
mouse because there's only height pixels
and the first one zero so that would be
a more correct way of you know of
stating it yeah I'm saying
so anyway oops I know I just did that
that was not what I wanted to talk about
yet so anyway when we do this on
projection now we're passing things and
pick subordinates so now we can really
read we can actually legitimately just
undo the transform for reals which is
nice and so yes so now we just have to
actually debug that and make sure the
fat works properly and again we kind of
have to do we still have to do this
nonsense because and in fact now this is
a v3 so we should be able to do
literally this where we just pass them
at the world feedback as the thing we're
doing is the transform and it should
just work right so that's the thing that
we want to work now that's the thing
that we want to behave properly I gotta
get the transform out of the group here
so this is actually let's see render
transform
and let's take a look here okay and what
is the problem transform offset P and
results
what is transform offset P render
transform offset P do we just not have a
- equals I guess we don't that's a bit
weird if we really did we really never
type in a - equals well fancy that so we
did a plus equals for everybody but no
minus equals and that seems kind of dumb
to be honest so I feel like that's just
something we should rectify right seems
reasonable
alright and that should probably go
below this thing as it will tell me
since I can't reference heaven forfend
you should be able to call something
that was below you in the file you know
how would you ever implement that
feature okay so let's see when we do
unprotect old now we want to change this
to doing regular unprotect and that's
good we want the offset P to be the
world mouse here and now we want to do
the full transform randomness we've got
our unpredicted XY potential initialize
local variable used you are correct we
don't actually do it here I'll do I
guess I'll do a little thing just for
you it kind of stubs it out there just
to make sure but off we go okay so now
we have to do our only goal now is to
basically get our little get that that
little blue square back right that's all
we're trying to do and so I'm gonna go
ahead and step through here and see how
we're doing alright so the first things
first our mouse be
should be in pixels now and that does
look pixel II right so it shouldn't be
negative when it's up in the quadrant
right like if I'm if I'm up here this
would have been negative X before it
should just be always positive right
like we should never get negative values
for the most part in there and it's not
so that's good so here we go with our
unprojected come in here to our
unprojected the graphic transform so
let's take a look at what comes in
there's the X Y there's the Z and meters
that's what what I want I've got the
transform screen Center here screen
Center and that's exactly what I would
expect so let's go ahead and do our
transform where we transfer the pixels X
Y basically into meters so let's see
what that got that is oh well that
should be a device and it's not so
that's you know that's one of those
things that you probably don't want to
do alright let's take a look at where
that's at
alright still got nothing on the screen
though so we've still got a ways to go
let's go back in there and see about our
meters that is much more like it that's
a certainly much more reasonable value
to have and so now we take this as a
target so this is basically just going
to be evaluate to 1 right well negative
1 and then we've got the the transform
focal length so it's gonna be like you
know negative some small value right so
what's the unprojected see here
unprojected y so that's where it is or
believes it to be in meters which is a
totally reasonable value and the the
transform offset P should actually be 0
at this point so it should not actually
be relevant and it isn't ok so that's
what we wanted there and now we set the
offset P to be equal to the the world
mouse that this is the actual location
right and so let's go ahead in here now
I guess now I think about it
well well let's actually go into push
rect and actually see I'm gonna say I
think we have might have one slight
thing wrong there but that's kind of a
separation ooh no I did not want to step
into the security stack check but thank
you all right and so we're gonna go
ahead and compute the P here
so essentially yeah like know nothing
other than base they are dimensional
offset so that's all totally fine
and exactly what you would expect
although I do note well we'll talk about
that a second I'll go in to get render
an entity basis and now we can kind of
see what what our original P is right
there's the value that we're looking to
get and our transform offset P well
we've got it right there there it is
right and so what we should have is a
p-value that's mostly made up of that
right thus we made up of that value yeah
although although I am a little curious
I do have one slight confusing thing to
say there which is that
this is a little weird how we did this
quick me if I'm wrong but if you look at
how we were doing this here when we do
our offset right in our dimensions when
we pass those in it is a little bit
strange that this offset is not well all
right you know what I'm gonna I'm gonna
table that let's say it's a little bit
strange the way we do it because one of
these would be scaled and the other one
wouldn't be it it's it's not worth I
guess I don't know it's not worth
fussing over anyway
so when we come through here the office
of Z is this thing that's never gets
used we get deleted that because we
decided we didn't want Z offsets to to
matter at all so that's why I'm sorry
just as above target is 9 like we
thought it was going to be so the
distance to PZ negative 1 so that's
basically so that's our problem there
right you can see what's going to happen
the new your clip plane check is going
to force that out so we're messing up
this Z the Z computation that we that we
sort of back compute and I suspect
although I am not really 100% sure I
suspect that that is because we were
just a little sloppy when we quickly
kind of did that routine so let's take a
look at get render entity basis P ok so
yes so the Z value in this case is
literally just going to be like look the
Z that that you actually specify that
you put that you pass in right that's
going to if that's supposed to be the
distance from the target if I supposed
to be the distance from the camera then
I guess I guess that would literally
just
like I'm trying to think of of what this
the meaning is here I want to make sure
we get the meaning correct so that if
it's actually this routine that should
be modified in that the other one so I
just want to kind of go and and actually
specify this a little bit more directly
right so the way that we've got this set
up at the moment we're sort of saying
that we have a camera that's looking
down on things right and we specified
distance to target right this is
distance to target that makes sense
so then we've got Z the the actual value
that's getting passed in is here that's
that's the point we're trying to draw at
right and that is like that value is how
far off of the target plane you are
right because I mean look at the way
that that's being interpreted right so
if P Z is positive right that means
you're coming up and if P Z is negative
that means you're coming down because
you can see I'm taking distance of our
target and I'm moving Z distance away
from that right so if you tell me that
you are that your Z value that you're
passing in is like 10 for the
unprojected was if what we're trying to
say is it's tansy and screen-space like
you're 10 away this way in screen space
that's how far you were you know that
we're not inverting that at all by the
way that we did our unprojected the
question is what do we want this Z to me
because we're passing in a Z but what do
we want it to mean do we wanted me to
mean a world Spacey or do we want to
mean a screen space Z right and it feels
kind of like we don't want to do any
inversion at all on that right it feels
kind of like since we're always
specifying Z there's no there's no
actual world space Z in that sense
there's only a camera relative Z
relative to the targets not the camera
that Z just gets passed through directly
right so like this value yeah that value
would just get passed through directly I
think I mean isn't that what we want it
to be I don't know it's hard to say I
feel like that's the right thing because
if we're talking about Oh where's the
mouse well the mouse is on the sort of
on the plane right on that target plane
we'd pass in that Z value we pass them
to Z valve zero right and we'd want it
to be here so I feel like what this is
this is like Z meters from Target plane
or something like that that's what that
actually means and so yeah when we do
the result presumably that just gets
added in there and like it would just be
something like you know something like
zero so yeah so I feel like that's what
we want and so we can't have a distance
of 10 like that's what we were asking it
we were asking it to tell us where the
thing was this is a 10 it will solve it
but then it will immediately clip
against the plane so the fact that we
were passing 10 men that would never
actually work like this local Z of 10
will never work so like three could work
and we should be able to get that
working just fine but 10 is never going
to write and so hey yeah that that was
the only problem there right because
there you can see it it's locked on so
that's a more sane unprotect map to me
because at least now all you do is you
actually are you're actually
unproductive pixels for reals it's still
not great there's still some janki's in
there again this is because of the two
and a half D nature of things and since
this is the first time I've ever done 2
and 1/2 T normally I'm full 3d I'm not
used to thinking of I'm not used to
knowing what the right way to like wrap
everything up is and so I suspect after
handmade hero or sometime in the middle
of a meteor in fact we may have develop
a strong opinion about how these
parameters should be specified that
minimizes the chance
that you make a stupid mistake like we
did yesterday for example but yeah so
now that that's actually known and
that's correct I feel like we should be
able to maybe get a little harder quark
here and say okay so now if we wanted to
unprotect the same if we want to do a
full-on project which is what we're
doing here
we shouldn't have to pass anything other
than just like okay if the mouse P were
at the plane of this entity which we
don't need to add any of this because
it's just whatever the volume offset is
because the the transforms already set
to that so if we just did that right
where we just like that's the offset the
total differential offset right if we do
that on project and then we do yeah we
do that on project we should be able to
get back whatever the correct local
coordinate is I think right and you know
I probably spoke a little too soon I
probably should still leave this in
there so we can debug this code with a
single entity right like just do and the
index equals 10 like we did before
just so we can just see it happen once
right so we just do this on project now
we say where is the mouse you know if it
were out this plane we then go ahead and
push a rectangle that shows the local
mass P relative relatively speaking and
in order to do that again we have to the
problem with this and this is the kind
of thing that I'm saying it I feel like
we need some way in the renderer to do
this a little smarter but we want to be
able to render this and we need to be
able to render it at a particular offset
there fortunately we now we can just say
it could be at zero because we're going
to render it in the same coordinate
system that we're already in and we just
want just to use that local offset that
we computed so in theory that would
probably be fine let's see if it
actually is fine here we go and I guess
when we unprojected
yeah I think that's probably
I think that's probably reasonable I
wonder when we do our unprojected let's
think one let's let's let's think one
more thing about our unprojected just
want to see if this works but I want to
do I want to do one more thing with the
unprojected I was just thinking of so
let's do that a second here alright so
let's see so there's our unprojected
thing and it's a little bit off you can
see that the scale is is a little bit
off it's not quite right for the mouse
but it's pretty close and we're pretty
close to being correct for that back
projection so we're close but not quite
so let's try this is the part that I
think is gonna be a little bit wonky and
why I said we should talk about this a
little more so I think probably what we
would like to have happen right is we
would like to be able to render directly
with that unprojected think of what to
do here how to do this exactly
well so here's one thing I will do first
I'm just gonna see
so suppose we specify as the as the
unproductive suppose we specified just
nothing
so we're it's not going to be if we were
to just specify nothing this is the part
I wanted to check out so yeah yeah so
this is the part that's a little weird
if we were to if we're gonna use the Z
meters from Target plane as a direct
pass-through then we also have this
other kind of nasty problem which is
that the math doesn't exactly work out
correctly on like the math doesn't
actually work out correctly to reverse
it because everything with the XY does
happen in reverse order like it should
but since this is not the actual value
that would have come out of the
projection for this got for the you know
the entities let's say then we don't
actually know like what we would we
don't actually get in the Z value here
that should actually be used for this
part now we know what it is right we
know what it actually is but I just
wonder if maybe we shouldn't sort of
again think about changing that meaning
to make it a little bit more consistent
like just to say oh you know I want
these to be much you know more logically
invertible and so if you were to say
pixels XY and like some kind of a notion
of a screen space Z but you often would
have an in a real 3d set scenario
because you do a full 3d transform so
you know what the Z is relative to the
camera and then in here you know when
you want to talk about doing the
unprotect you would talk about doing
unprotected with a screen space z
coordinate so you'd have to figure out
how far the entity was like from the
camera or whatever in order to do that
now it's it just seems a little unwieldy
so I just don't know it's like it's more
convenient to do it this other way but
it's not invertible it just feels a
little janky right I don't know I'm
really torn about that I'm really torn
about that but point being when you pass
in Z meters from Target plane right then
that's Z meters from Target plane like
if you look in we look back here at the
get render entity basis P thing so when
we divide by PZ it's like what's PZ made
up well it's made of this transform
offset P thing right and so essentially
when we do this this reversal here this
distance above target minus Z meters
from plane thing right we're emulating
what we're we're you know reversing what
happened with this distance to PZ we're
emulating what happened here right and
in emulating what happened here we're
sort of we're sort of redoing the same
computation excuse me
so what that means is that if we
actually do if we if we had some offset
in the offset P right that was different
from the value that we were passing here
right you can you can imagine like you
know like this right so I pass in this
volume offset P and now that offset P is
is actually not necessarily the correct
value it's really the correct value
would actually be whatever the whatever
the entity's actual offset was right
it's actually going to be whatever this
thing was that's what actually would
have been doing the transform here what
I mean so in some sense it's like oh
really you could avoid the way we've got
this effect you could avoid passing the
Z altogether because we know that
actually the Z is just this that's the
only Z that we ever use right and so
that's actually like that's sort of I'm
trans days like that's a more correct
thing if you actually looked at the
function we wrote it's actually that
that is actually what it is and so I
don't know you know I don't know what to
say about that
I really don't I think it's just kind of
ugly and I'm really feeling like we
probably need to fix this I probably
won't fix it immediately but it's
definitely on my list so hey and you can
see now that we're working properly
right because we are now correctly doing
that in that inversion so when we move
over an entity we can highlight it and
that's all well and good I'm just really
not feeling good about that way we're
doing transforms and I wonder if maybe
it's like maybe we need to do like a
real transform there maybe we need to
start taking it a little bit more
seriously and not letting the math be
quite so lacks right I don't know what I
just I just did something bad what did I
do
I need to delete that and that and that
and so now we should see those around
all the entities and hopefully we can
pick any entity we want like so we don't
really need to draw these rectangles
this rectangle anymore that's really
just a testing rectangle so what kind of
get rid of that and then we've just are
left with something that can kind of go
around highlighting an entity as
necessary now what I would like to do -
and you can see it we could highlight
these entities like so what I'd like to
do too is actually do something to make
sure that as we move up like is in RZ
that these all still work and if they're
very precise which they do appear to be
right and as you can see we can also see
if we're over multiplying Z at a time
which we are right so that's all good
let's keep going with that let's try
moving upwards and over there with lots
of these guys let's these entities
around yeah so that all that all feels
pretty good to me that all feels fine
okay so that whoa all right I guess the
Wacom tablet decided to take its own
life they took a whipper off the table
there all right so that's really that's
the long and short of it I'm not super
happy with that and I feel like we
should put on our to-do list here I
don't know that it matters super matters
when we do it but I kind of feel like we
should do something like real
projections with solid concept of
project unprojected
it's not you know I mean if it has to be
the way it is then maybe just at least
document it thoroughly if it's like this
is what two and a half D is gonna mean
and that's we just do it that way that's
fine with me it's not the end of the
world but I just think it's like it
needs to be a little more more rigorous
so that's that's all she wrote in this
particular case what we could do is
something like oh you know actually
let's just only push that rect outline
in the case where we're actually
highlighting the guy right that seems
like a little bit more sane so we'll do
something like this
and that way it's like okay you know the
game is normally doing its gamey thing
and then you can kind of move around and
like highlight these entities right
whatever their collision volumes are
okay so now what I'd like to do hmm it's
like to have a way of displaying the
entities and so if we take a look at
just you know we've never really
implemented anything particularly fancy
for our entities but what I would like
to do is I'd like to go through here and
I'd like to make a really easy way for
us to essentially dump out an enemy
right so if I want to display this
entity when I come over these volumes
here you know what I'll do is I'll say
oh okay
entity is or maybe you know I'll do
another kind of one of those hot entity
things and so I could do something like
debug hot
element or something like that I would
do something like this
I'd say debug hot element and I'd say
the debug element is going to be one of
these entity things the entity is going
to be whichever this one was that we
were on right whatever it is here it's
just this guy right and then later I
would I would sort of pick it up and I'd
draw it a little bit further down the
line now I guess there is a little bit
you know there's a little bit of a
problem with that if this entity which
this entity is right the way our sim
region stuff works is the simulation
only exists for the time when it's
stimulating so if I wanted to output the
stuff here I kind of don't want to defer
the actual capture of that state so I
might do something more like this I
might say something more like begin hot
element right and hot element sort of a
thing I might do something a little bit
more like that and I might say that you
know like okay this this is a hot
element it's the Senate II thing and I
want to dump all this
I want to dump like everything from it
right I want to dump like all the stuff
that there is and so like I want to dump
like what kind of type it is right
something like that so I want to do
debug you know debug value property or
something something like this debug
value I want to say okay I've got the
end of these storage index right I got
the updatable I've got the flags type
all this stuff so I just want the whole
thing and again this is why I say like I
like medipartner myself because see is
like well it's C++ is just a I mean it's
it's an ancient language right
and as I harp on the C++ standard Kamiya
all the time like no one should ever
have to type this code I mean it's just
absurd that you have to type this code
it's absurd that in the Year 2015 you
would ever type this code but in 30
years of development the C++ Ange
community still has not added
introspection so every programmer who's
ever written anything has typed this
exact code doesn't they're not concerned
about this they're fine with it
they're like that's totes cool man and
you know we'll get to it when we get to
it so anyway we've got our stuff here
right we've got our entity reference
there well that's probably well okay
that's fine we've got these guys well
damn and our walkable height and that's
just again we don't really have anything
going out these entities but it just
like it's what we kind of had done for
tests code inside you know pretend it
was a real entity and that we want to
dump it this is what we would do right
and for those hip points right - we've
got a four I loop here so we've kind of
got a like hip point index that we could
loop over and we could say like the hit
point index has to be less than the hit
point max like so and whoops and then we
would dump we dump each value there -
right so we do like debug entity hit
point point index like that and this
would probably be something like debug
begin array or something like this as
well and this is like debug end array or
something not totally sure kind of a
thing ish thing that exists in the world
yeah
so something like that right
something like that and you know if we
were super motivated fancy-pants people
we could even maybe have something like
a thing that printed out a raise
manually like that automatically but
let's not let's not bother with that for
now
so if we imagine that we had the perfect
debug system I feel like that's like in
C again without C with C or C++ without
augmenting it with a meta programming
system there's nothing you can do for
this because it doesn't have
introspection so you're always stuck
doing something like this or something
equally similar somewhere so but this is
a pretty straightforward thing right so
that's what I want that's what I want to
have happen and with that is I think you
know maybe tomorrow we got a weird like
stream Athan thing happy tomorrow maybe
tomorrow we'll we'll implement that what
I will do here I will just stub it out
for now and then I want to go over and
do one more thing that we kind of have
to do for our unprojected stuff so all
right so if I go to handmade debug
probably maybe handmade platform I guess
it's in here technically right so if I
come in here to handmade platform we've
got all our debug code is in here right
and so I'm just gonna come in and I'm
gonna define these guys right so I'm
just gonna do a pound to fine of each of
these things for now I'm just gonna like
stub it out and it's it's not gonna do
anything at all let's see we've got this
right and we got that already exists
there's this guy and this guy so now all
that stuff will just compile out right
it won't do anything so it'll just be
sitting there and so when we actually go
to activate it you know we'll be able to
see it right so that's all good so we're
still highlighting now and those calls
are in there but they don't do anything
what we want to do tomorrow's make them
do something now the other thing that I
wanted to do is now you'll notice well
you should be able to should see that
our old debug stuff doesn't work anymore
right like we can't actually click on
that and of course the reason for that
is because we changed the mouse input we
totally changed how the mouse input
worked right and that's actually ok and
it's actually a good thing because if
you look at the way we do the mouse be
here right we do this mouse piece stuff
and we create the mouse piece so let's
see mmm else P equals right so there's
where we create our mouse B and C that's
really that's really the place where
it's created the other things are just
pass throughs so we create our mouse be
here all we did was take the mouse bian
to start using it but that's not really
the reality of the situation because the
reality situation is the thing with all
of our drawing right is happening in
this orthographic projection this one
that we set up here we could have set
that up to be anything and so this would
have been wrong a long time ago actually
even before we change the screen center
stuff because we weren't actually taking
the account what we said if we had set
it to be a broad ass more stretched out
projection just we could have all the
drawing would have worked fine with the
mouse we've been wrong so what we
actually want here right is we want our
mouse speed to actually be a nun project
right what we want to do is we want to
do this so that we can unprojected
right whatever the the mouse is by
whatever the current transform is right
like this that's what we actually want
and so if we run that we're gonna get an
assertion because we set it up here
because we didn't implement this but we
should just go ahead and implant it now
and that way everything's actually
running through a nice uniform path as
well so no matter whether you're some
orthographic debug stuff overlaid on top
of things or you're some projection case
you still just call and project to put
the mouse back into the world that you
are rendering in whether that's an
orthographic screen space or a
perspective world space it's kind of
this that's nice it just keeps it more
consistent and correct okay so if we
take a look at what's going on here
what we need to do is just figure out
what the transfer actually is again for
orthographic views and so I'm gonna take
a look at what we actually do and it
looks like that that's I guess we just
cut and paste it in here right so that's
that's what we do and you can kind of
see that it's the same sort of thing
it's exactly what we were doing before
right so and meters to pixel just
happened to be defined to one in this
case right that was the one that we were
passing in when we didn't remember this
in debug do you remember this one right
here that's why that didn't do anything
that's why this worked right that's why
this mouse X Mouse why announce that
that's why that work so yeah
so now we just have the opportunity to
do it right and that just means
multiplying by the inverse of meters to
pixels right and in doing that
that's subtract first right so we
basically just reverse we're just
solving the equation right so we just do
the the reverse and that gets us our
unprojected X Y and and that should be
that should be all there is to it
actually
right and so now I've got my my picking
back right and so I can do all this
stuff and so that's pretty good right
but you'll note that we do have some
other things and this is why I said I
kind of wanted to do the hot and any
stuff in there this there's more stuff
that we're gonna want to do we're
probably going to want to make it so
that when you're over a debug menu right
you don't like pick enemies underneath
it and stuff like that and again this is
all part of you can see how it's slowly
building up into a coherent system for
UI for doing the debug stuff it's just
inherently very complicated and takes a
while but you know once you do it you
did it right and and it's kind of just
nice to have around alright so I'm going
to go ahead and go to the Q&amp;A so if you
have any questions about what we do I
will try to answer them now please
prefix them with Q :
so they'll be able to see them
not much in the way of questions
mr. fourth dimension I'm a little
unclear about what pressure is keeping
you from doing the Z math exactly like
you would do in 3d so I can try to sort
of explain the problems that I have with
it and so normally what happens right is
in 3d you're gonna have some kind of a
situation where all of the points right
like in your world whatever they are
that form whatever things they form you
know you've kind of got this this like
view and they all kind of symmetrically
project along you know on to some some
monitor plane right and so the way that
you handle Z is like really clean
because it's just it's just a transform
it's a straight transform and the XY z--
and z0 handle done hundred percent the
same and it's it's fine
but we have kind of a weird situation in
2d where things don't work that way
right and the reason they don't work
that way is because if you imagine for
example a dude standing somewhere right
here's the head here's the body right
the body is here the head is here let's
say when those two things get projected
then what's going to happen is depending
on how close you are to the camera and
depending on how you are laterally right
you can imagine like let's let's draw it
this way so let's say we're looking down
so this is this is us here sitting right
here's the monitor here's the world and
like here's the dude's head right so
there's the head and and the body like
they're right on top of each other
right so what happens and I guess even
this is not quite the diagram I need
because we're looking down on something
that's standing up right it's it's kind
of weird
I really wish I should probably just
install blender on this machine that's
why I can show it all right
fully concrete case and I'm sorry for
the diagrams I just don't know how to
draw them well enough in 2d like I don't
have those kind of sketching skills I'm
afraid so here's a here's a box right
and here is a head a floating head the
floating head of the familiar and the
floating head of the familiar is behind
the box here's its shadow and it's
moving this way right and it's going to
move it's going to move straight across
the box it's not gonna hit the box right
so in 3d we know that the head is like a
certain Z above the plane right and we
know that the box is a certain Z above
the plane well in that case it's zero
and we know that the box has a bounding
box that's some certain height right and
we know that this Z that's floating plus
the the diameter of the head right I'm
sorry plus the radius of the head but
it's bounding box we know that the
height and that don't intersect so that
all works just fine in our system and
it's fine right but if we were to draw
that remember we have a camera that's
looking straight down onto the screen
that's just what we're doing right and
we can pick you know we could pick how
that was if we wanted to we could have
it be look at more of an angle right but
but at some point we've got something
between you know like 45 degrees and 90
degrees that's where the camera is okay
now if we were to actually just
interpret all this stuff 100% 3d what we
would see when we looked when we did
this projection so we are here we're
looking down here's the monitor here's
the view for us - here's the guy we
would see for handmade hero the top of
the hero's head and his cloak would be
like a circle like this you would just
see hair right and it'd be even weirder
because since yangshin drew it side on
here's the guy right we'd actually see
his head like looking up at us and his
cape from the side would be stacked
right on top of them and it's just
totally wrong right so instead obviously
what we need to do is
make sure that when we draw him we
actually consider the Z values for him
to actually be sort of Y values for him
because he is a standing up right entity
whatever that means right and so what
that means is that we now have two
conceptualizations of what Z actually is
it is actually a Z value off the ground
for purposes of collision protection but
then it is also an offset in Y if you
are part of a model so this guy's
position in Z is actually handled just
like everything else in the real world
but his offset in Z is not the like
different parts of the body offset Z
have to be interpreted directly in 2d
without ever going through any other
kind of transform other than just the
scaling necessary to make him shrink or
grow and what that leads to is a
two-part transform where the basis point
of the guy which is XYZ gets transformed
for reals right real Z it gets
transformed for reals but the for lack
of ever trim the attachment or the
alignment points of bitmaps they get
faked and that was the problem we ran
into on Tuesday why we thought we had a
bug was because I had forgotten that we
had to do this nonsense right to make
the 2d stuff work out properly and so I
was like passing a Z expecting you to
actually do something but it doesn't do
them because that's the offset slot we
were passing things in and it's only the
transform the base transform slot that
actually has a real Z in it so mr. Firth
I mentioned does that clear it up at all
for you or not really
party wind bill where are you going to
draw the levels for entity properties
our sorry let labels you corrected your
thing uh we're going to put them into
that debug hierarchy Icarus did you
decide which awesome thing to do for
tomorrow stream not really and I'm not
really sure I was I was thinking about
it whether we should bother I think I
was thinking I should just do what I was
gonna do so I think I might just do this
because I think it's more important to
stay on I'm focused so I think I'm
probably actually just gonna do what we
were gonna do anyway what do you find is
a good game design
I just want food s that's a pretty big
topic it probably one that's better for
a pre stream that's not really about
programming jerry johansson curious your
decision to design your own game engine
has more to do with you furthering your
own skill level or do you have a reason
to not trust the middleware solutions
that you have seen in the past well so I
can't tell you for example that you know
for handmade hero I don't know how many
things we would be doing in it that
would that you couldn't do in a
middleware thing obviously there's some
stuff we do like the loop live coding
aside that that are cool features that
middleware doesn't have right now so
there's definitely that and there's also
sort of the agility with which you can
program in a code base like handmade
hero that's like just simply not
possible in something like you know in
something like unity right look unity
doesn't even have the concept that the
whole game streams in right you have to
have like weird look level packages and
all this like so there's there's
actually a lot of reasons why middleware
is actually not very good but you know
on the whole if you were gonna sit down
and make handmade here on your goals to
make it as fast as possible you know
it's probably true that you could make
it quicker in something that was already
all built you know game maker or unity
right right and maybe you can't do all
the things that we do but you could do
most of them and maybe
yes a bunch of things are annoying and
take you longer but they but because you
save time not having to write like this
other stuff maybe you come out ahead I
don't know right and I don't really
pretend to know that particular thing
because I'm not really in the business
of cranking out very simple games
quickly right I don't I don't do that
and I don't have a strong opinion about
how you should do that but what I can
tell you is that if you actually care
about making something fairly new that
pushes some boundaries you can forget
you know using an engine usually because
they just it ends up being more trouble
than it's worth you know maybe it's
worth it if you're doing some very if
most of the stuff you're doing happens
to be like exactly what Unreal Engine
does and you just need some other small
changes that could be a big time saver
you know but like for example what we're
doing at Melly rocket right now is like
not I I can't even think of a single
piece of it that I've built so far
that's in either engine like neither of
them have any of it so it's not even a
choice with like the stuff I'm working
on professionally it's it's not even
like I I would only be strictly losing
time I'd be paying money to lose time
right if I use one them there so that's
you know hopefully that give you some
perspective and one of the reasons that
I'm doing handmade here alright there's
a couple different reasons but one of
the reasons is to encourage people who
are interested in this kind of code to
do it and to show how easy it actually
is because like I said you know a lot of
times you know we're all it's only an
hour at night that's not a very big
investment and we've gone through tons
and tons of features already on handmade
hero and and you know we just haven't
spent very much actual physical time and
so you know part of its to show how easy
it is to do some of these things but the
other part of it is to say like hey yeah
you know if you are the kind of person
who enjoys the sort of stuff I hope you
will consider making some new things you
know and that could be like a whole new
engine Pratt potentially with does some
really interesting things that people
don't do in ways they don't do them or
it might just be
opponents for existing engines right
like maybe you're gonna go make a unity
plug-in that does a bunch of really cool
stuff that unity can't do or maybe
you're gonna go you know mod the Unreal
Engine to do a bunch of tough the unis
can't do and so even you know even if
your mindset is let's use an engine I
think it's really valuable to have done
a bunch of this stuff because it means
now you know how everything works out
there and you can go do the stuff right
SIA Chisholm says did you play Warcraft
3 at all or any of the mods I need some
help replicating some of the movement
mechanics from one of the games and
nobody understands me when I describe it
willing to pay PayPal to whoever can
code it I am sorry to say that no I I
did not play worker 3 I played I played
Warcraft 1 and 2 to completion but I
never played Warcraft 3 I think I had
burned out on realtime strategy games by
then because I played like all of
command &amp; Conquer all of World of
Warcraft
I mean I'm sorry all of Warcraft I love
Warcraft 2 and I think I even played
like all of Total Annihilation and I
just at some point I was like okay and
Starcraft the original Starcraft and so
by the time we got to work our three I
think I was just I was like I'm done
okay just don't wanna play this anymore
and so you know it was probably one of
the better Warcraft but I just
yeah I'm spent would it work to render
it in full 3d and rotate all the sprites
by 40 to 5 degrees or whatever the
camera angle is taking um you know it
might I mean I don't know like I said
I'm a full 3d guy usually and actually
the project that we're working on a
trolley rocket does have some too nice
there's it's not that there's to the
illustrative stuff in it obviously but
it's not this this way it's not the like
weird like two and a half D thing so I
don't it's definitely not something that
I have an opinion about because I just
haven't played around with it and so you
know I I just don't know
I mean maybe something like that would
work it seems like it would be a little
tricky to get right I feel like you'd
have to have the camera at 45 and then
spend the sprite by 45 and then it would
look right cuz if you if you only if the
camera was top-down and then the sprites
were bent 45 that would still that would
compress them right they would they
would even if was orthographic I would
compress them in a bad way which you
don't really want so I think you'd have
to have the camera at 45 and then the
sprite at 45 or something like that like
the camera at 80 and the sprite to 20
times I had 10 you'd have to add up to
90 somehow right the sprites would
always have to be at a right angle to
the camera I think that's just my guess
anyway
aren't even well I understand the
artists run in the 3/4 view is the
camera at an angle or top down the
camera is like top-down right now so
we're basically like emulating Zelda or
Zelda dungeon is like the goal right so
you know if you look at something like
this right this is this is you know what
we were starting with us as far as an
idea anyway
right which is to say that it's very
clear that the camera is pointing
directly down but the sprites just for
attractiveness purposes are pointing
like at you and nobody knows why his
works right I don't pretend to know why
that works but it does and so since
people are ok with it
you know since they they seem to be okay
with that style that's what we're doing
and like I said I don't pretend to be a
game designer I don't claim to know if
that's like the smartest way to design
your game or anything like that that's
just you know handmade hero it's a
programming stream and we need a game to
program and so that is I I liked this
game a lot the original Zelda was one of
my favorites I really think it's a great
game and and I think you know like I've
mentioned Binding of Isaac before is
like an update of it you know and all of
the dungeon part of it and I think it
worked out fabulously again and so I
feel like there's something reasonable
about this sort of methodology I mean if
you look at Binding of Isaac right the
if they did the exact same thing right
down to like the number of squares in it
and it's exactly the same everything's
like top down except sometimes they
decide you know the sprites are this way
and like some rocks or that way and some
rocks aren't right some rocks are top
down some rocks are sideways that's just
something that like players brains
except they don't have a problem with it
and so you know that's that's just what
I decided we would do again because
original Zelda was a was a favorite of
mine and and I am I really like binding
of issac too so I just feel like that's
it's reasonable
the 3d Zelda games do the 3d angle for
2d yeah I so I don't super love that
look to be honest it's a little weird to
me because it's skews well I don't know
I wouldn't be like adverse to it but I
feel like it's just a little bit I feel
like if I was gonna do that I'd go all
the way I don't I don't know that I
would I would just make it 3d at that
point I'm not sure what the bonus is of
if you're gonna actually construct the
geometry like that why can't you just do
it in regular old 3d and that's a little
weird it's a little bit weird
so Gary Johansson so I'm making a full
3d RTS that uses a mouse with a joystick
built-in so you can adjust where you are
looking with the joystick it's to use
the mouse's mouse from your section do
you think that that's an untenable idea
for a product what Gary what how do I
have anything useful to say about that
at all I'm a programmer that's not
really a programming question I have no
idea I feel like most of the time it's
hard to get people to buy peripherals so
I guess what I'd say did you ever end up
playing the mother series that's still
in your to do yes it's on my to do I
would like to play the mother series
it's been on my to do for a long time
actually and I haven't been able to do
it but I would like to at some point
when I have some time which probably
will be never but if I ever have some
time you know I would I would totally do
that already windmill I kind of jumped
over 100 episodes so I don't understand
what the issue was with the debug
selector was the issue with the hitbox
depth only or also the position well it
was it was actually just that we didn't
quite understand the fact that the Z
wasn't reproductive so everything was
actually working just fine but the
problem was when we went to draw it the
Z we were passing was just getting
thrown out which is what it was supposed
to do but it it's obviously a little
deceptive right so
all righty I think we are we are good I
want to see a type user list
we go do we know why the usual list
doesn't work anymore he used to work
just fine so it yet anyway I think we're
all good I think I've answered all the
questions that are actually questions
tomorrow is a little bit weird
tomorrow's a little wonky it's like a
two-hour stream and it's like at night
it's like at 8:00 p.m. so yeah so that's
a that's the thing but I guess what I
would say is I also don't know
should we if I tried when I originally
set the stream to stream it on hitbox as
well and you know I don't know how to I
couldn't get it working to stream to
both services at the same time you were
supposed to be able to do that on using
this like server thing you know but I
never got it working and so what I was
wondering is like I don't know since
since Twitter ban John I guess of
Twitter since twitch banned John I feel
like maybe we should try again to
support hitbox so people who you know
want to go watch it on there might be
good act binary sent sent restreamed IO
so what is restream that IO is that just
a thing that would like broadcast it to
multiple services for you I don't know
I'll check that out
and swag kiddie 69 the reason John got
mad was he was playing a video on
YouTube and like playing a video on
YouTube I guess that's like content
that's you know copyrighted and so I
don't actually know like how that works
but I guess technically that is a
copyright violation because YouTube has
a license to play it but but twitch
doesn't do you know what I mean and so
you know I don't I don't really know I
don't really know I mean it is a
copyright violation right you can't play
a movie on a stream but you know in in
in all fairness I feel like it probably
was something where you know to be how
much did he play was it illegal excerpt
sighs you know I have no idea
and it's probably likely that it really
wasn't much of a copyright violation at
the end of the day certainly shouldn't
have resulted in a ban but yeah so
anyway so I was thinking of trying to
support hitbox just to have more people
in the mix there I could also try to
support YouTube streaming so yeah if you
have opinions about that send them to me
or post them on the forums and we could
check it out all right um
anyway anyway let's wrap it up I'm gonna
go hop over on my crutches and hop over
on some crutches I am I'm gonna go hop
over some crutches and try to have some
dinner
anyway thank you very much for joining
me for another episode of hand made
heroes don't slide recording with you as
always tomorrow we have the dev stream a
thon thing I don't really know very much
about it it's a thing that someone was
putting together of just like dev
streams that are going back-to-back so
if you're interested in that check it
out and and like I said we'll be in in
the timeslot I think from eight o'clock
to ten o'clock so will be an 8 p.m. to
10 p.m. will
do a 2-hour stream so maybe an hour and
a half plus a half-hour of questions or
maybe we'll save questions for Monday or
I don't know what we'll do but we'll
figure it out so that's happening
tomorrow hope see you here for that and
you know maybe we'll do a cool look a
cool entity debug view things since
that's where we've kind of ended today
that would be pretty cool to get working
so anyway that's we're doing tomorrow in
the meantime if you want to play around
the source code you can always do so you
can play around with the source code on
by pre-ordering the game it comes with
source code I uploaded every night after
we're done so you notice to play with
the latest one just fool around with it
see what's going on we also have patreon
page you want supports a video series
always much appreciated we have a forum
site you can go to to ask questions and
watch episodes old episodes annotated by
the community
and there's also a tweet bot that you
can go to to find out what the schedule
is now we also have a convention that
it's coming up till handmade con it's
coming up in December and I just wanted
to mention it one more time because the
speaker list is now essentially
finalized it will be announced on Monday
it is pretty much the best speaker list
that I've ever seen on anything ever for
programming it's like literally kind of
like exactly the five people that I want
to interview on programming for games
and so I'm expecting that probably when
I announce the speaker list on Monday I
don't know if it will be a sellout but
I'm suspecting that probably the tickets
will go pretty fast at that point so if
there's anybody who's like a hardcore
handmade hero viewer who's on the stream
right now and was on the fence about
whether you want to go please try to
make up your mind this weekend because I
do not have any I literally do not have
a way to sell any more tickets than 275
that is the number of people that will
fit and like 15 of them or so will be
reserved for you know the speakers and
and help people who are helping and so
like there's I think there's a total of
250 second ticket 250 tickets to sell so
again like if you
really want to go to it and you're sure
that you are gonna go if you can decide
by Sunday and buy a ticket just I can
only apologize in advance i I just don't
I don't know if it how long those
tickets to last after next week but you
there's plenty of them left right now so
it shouldn't be a problem for anyone who
wants to buy one this weekend that's
about it so check that out that's again
that's just handmade con org if you want
to go to it alright that's it for today
I will be back here tomorrow so hope to
see you all here at 8:00 well I'll be on
early so you know I guess see you here
at 7:30 or something like that if you
want to warm up ahead of time before a
stream until then have fun programming
I'll see you guys on the Internet and
and yeah take it easy