hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here a sure weave code a complete game
live on stream we are kind of add a
little bit of crossroads today let me go
ahead and run the game for you so I can
explain what our situation is well John
blissfully plays manifold garden we have
to deal with our own sort of garden of
troubles here so basically if you look
at where we are with lighting which is
what we're sort of grappling with at the
moment here is a fresh builds and here's
the game running so what we sort of did
is stuff the lighting with just a
generic sphere right now and you can see
that we have two sort of things that we
now want to move on to we have lighting
sampling in there and it's pretty good
like I'm not horrified by it but it's
not great and the reason I say that is
because you can see the voxel ization
artifacts that you get from just
straight trilinear sampling of your
light which is what's happening here so
you can see in the interior it's harder
to see and that's because the I think
there's it's less it's less obvious
because it's more subtle it's still
there right it's still there I can see
the artifact now that I know that I'm
looking for it I could see it in the
interior right but where you can really
see it is anywhere there's a harsher
light transition so you can see here
where we've got the fall-off of the
light and you can kind of see how that's
you know just around those edges you can
see those really ugly blocky sort of
traditional bilinear artifacts you'd see
there try linear in this case but you're
more familiar with them and and I'm more
fillet them as bilinear artifacts as we
see them much more often in that context
trilinear cute you know voxel sampling
is not a thing that we do that often by
comparison to bilinear which is you know
done everywhere so what we can see here
is that our sampling isn't awful it does
work but it's not great and so one thing
that we probably have to keep on our
radar if we don't do it right now is to
make this better like we're gonna need a
better
scheme I think unless we just want to
accept it that hey it's an indie game so
it's maybe not as awesome as it could be
if we had a dedicated graphics team who
will solve this problem right but that's
usually a poor excuse so we may want to
go try and improve it ourselves however
that said what we can say about it is
there's really only one specific
artifact that we're seeing right now and
we kind of know what it is so it's
entirely possible that we could just
accept that artifact temporarily and
move on to the actual lugging transport
part get that working since that's a
separate part of the puzzle and then
from there we move on to trying to fix
the sampling all of that is certainly
possible
I just don't know again because I'm not
sure I just don't know how important
that that particular part of it is so my
guess is we should just move on to the
light sampling for now I'm sorry love
like simply we should move on to the
light transport for now since we have to
go to bring that code up to speed so I
think we kind of want to do that and
then from there we can go ahead and
decide assess afterwards what we want to
do to try and improve the sampling of
the light information we do have from
there right and we can see that even
with the artifacts it at least still is
pretty cool the way we can sample these
lights and so once we get some actual
transport in there where we're gonna
have some more interesting things
happening like shadowing and stuff like
that so that you know you wouldn't see
light kind of in this corridor and stuff
like that it seems like it would be
probably a pretty cool aesthetic as well
and you know we'd have a number of
different lighting environments as well
obviously this one just has a light
hovering above the character but you
know we'd want lots of things like you
know our lamps and specifically to be on
and shining light and things like that
so I mean I think it would create a nice
lighting environment and so the question
will just be how bad is the sampling and
is there anything we can do that doesn't
tank the frame rate that would that
would be usable right so that's where
we're at and with that in mind I want
to just make a judgment call here and
say let's do the lighting sampling and
the the reason I want to go that route
too is because one of the things about
the lighting sampling that's worth
that's worth noting is the light
sampling itself we're gonna want to work
on that algorithm for a little while and
as we work on that algorithm we may also
discover some things about the way we're
working with lights that change or
inform how we might sample it so it's
possible that by ping-ponging back and
forth between these two sides of the
problem maybe we'll gain insight into
the other side while working on one of
the suck like you know side a the
sampling maybe we'll gain insight into
the sampling side while working on the
transport side and maybe we'll gain from
the transport side Lorcan sample size so
ping-ponging back and forth between them
maybe makes some sense as opposed to
trying to get one perfect and then
moving to the other one because for all
we know they may be a little bit more
intimately connected because again the
transport side does have to itself
sample lighting the sampling side has to
reconstruct lighting which is what comes
from the transport and so that interplay
there is you know it's a process of
gaining that understanding that we're
trying to do here and so what we want to
kind of work towards is getting both of
those problems solved together as
opposed to them being completely it's
not like they're these disparate
problems that that bear no relationship
to each other right um and so if I go
ahead and pop over to the lighting
transport side of things and we start to
think about well what are we going to do
to make this stuff work right well you
can see what we've got here is a
beginning and lighting computation call
and basically all that happens is the
begin learning computation enables the
lighting what I probably want to do when
we end is disable the lighting but I
don't know that we actually have such a
thing at the moment is that how does
that actually work
we should probably should probably have
it turned off you can see the enable
lighting here I don't know there's a
disabled letting so that definitely
should probably do it's not important
right now but you know
something to think about um but
basically as you can see here all begin
Lenny combination does is say look start
tracking lighting through the system
that's that's all it does and so when
you go to render you say begin lighting
before you put down all the scene stuff
and then the idea is afterwards when you
call in lighting computation after that
eventually we'll have a thing where we
don't do any lighting on anything after
it that's so that you can avoid doing
lighting on things like the title screen
like stamped the thing the stamping of
the title screen or the the debug hood
or whatever right so we don't always
want lighting most of the time we are
lighting but sometimes we don't want to
and that's the important part there so
moving on from fact we have begin
landing computation and then we have end
lighting computation at end lighting
computations actually does all the work
because only by the time we've gotten to
the end of where we want to do our
letting combination do we have all the
information in between these two calls
the exterior code has done all of the
specification where are the light
sources where are the looters that's
basically what needs to be happening
right and so as we move through this set
of stuff what you can see here is we
have this old sample table we were
working on all of this stuff we kind of
replaced because what we did is we made
a generator that generates well
distributed samples fears you can see
that here at some point and that point
is probably going to be very shortly you
can see that there's a table of zeros
here you may be wondering what that is
and the answer is eventually what we're
going to be doing is saying how to
weight these samples when the calf raise
how to weight these samples into which
sides of the spheres and so on and we
don't actually know if that's something
we want to do yet so what we may want to
do is just say each individual ray just
goes to one side
you know whichever side it left through
so there would be no blending right and
so eventually we may say look the way
this actually works is actually just an
int you know it looks like
this right uh and so we don't really
know exactly what we want to do there
but we're going to work that out now but
the important part is we already figured
out how to do a well distributed
sampling on the sphere and that is
actually you can see it hovering right
here right we debug through it just to
make sure it has good coverage you can
see we have a really nicely distributed
set of points there again not white
noise this is blue noise here or at
least blue noise adjacent and so we have
you know the first step of that problem
sort of sorted but there's more to it
left there's more to come basically and
so we'll be taking a look at that as we
go so inside and lighting computation
now let's just go through really quickly
what we're gonna be trying to accomplish
here so what you can see in in letting
computation this sample table stuff
we're not going to need anymore because
I believe this stuff is just kind of a
holdover from when we were kind of you
know screwing around with how we're
gonna do this lighting so the sample
table stuff which is here right I don't
actually think we want that anymore
right these things are I don't I don't
even know what this stuff what were we
doing here let's take a look I think
this stuff is just just garbage now yes
you can see this this stuff is just we
don't we don't need this anymore it's
not it's not actually being used it can
go away right that was I think that was
before we you know we had gone down the
samplings fare route so I think we're
good yeah that's all clean so when you
take a look at an lighting computation
there's some debug code in here but then
basically the first thing that happens
is what you would expect this code is
test code in there to see what happens
if you accumulate the lighting over time
we've probably want to re-enable that
testing as well because it's a good way
to test to see that the light transport
is unbiased which we probably want to be
at least to a certain extent what you
can see here is we've if zeroed out the
part that actually does any work and
that's because we aren't we weren't
actually doing the lighting transfer
anymore but then what we did is we
have the code at the back end that's
going to be responsible for outputting
the actual information about what the
graphics card needs to sample and if you
take a look
we've just have a ton of code stuck in
here that's mostly all for debugging
right here this right here is the thing
that stuff's our voxel with fake values
this stuff's our voxel with that orb
that you saw there so that's based on
the code that's producing this fake
light this is not light transport it's
just a sphere of light that we you know
basically a distance fall-off light just
stuffed in there that's why it doesn't
do any shadowing and it's not doing any
transport just stuffing the light into
the voxel directly and so what we want
to do now is start to move this function
towards something that's actually going
to produce some kind of lighting we can
use and so the first thing I would like
to do is take one step forward and
that's probably what we'll do today the
step I'd like to take is figuring out
how we're going to go from light probes
to voxels right because right now what
we're actually doing like I just said
we've got this thing at the end here
right now we're actually doing is
directly stuffing light into voxels
right
these voxels themselves are the things
that are actually storing the light here
the light probes are not right so we're
not touching light probe information
we're not even building like probe
information all we're doing the entirety
of the process is literally just us
doing these doing these voxel stuffs
directly into the lookup structure that
the GPU actually uses for lighting and
whether or not we want to do that long
term we don't know but what we do know
is that the very least if we want to
actually have light probes that we place
throughout the world where we think they
make the most sense we're going to have
to start with those and then move to
voxels and if in the end we choose to
remove the voxels and have the GPU work
with the light probes directly that's
fine but we still need to take the step
of at least having the light probes be
the thing that that is persistent right
so I'd like to start with
that step and furthermore we probably
also want to start to think about how
we're doing actual lights so right now
we don't really have any idea of what a
light is we may want to have lights be a
first class citizen no particular limit
on them just a way of saying this is a
light because right now what happens is
we actually do warrant to the renderer
that there is a light here is a call but
the light instead is just a cube right
but I think that's a bad idea because
since we are saying that the game will
announce where the lights are even if
there's a hundred of them it's going to
tell us where they are specifically it's
not gonna bury that information into
some kind of hard to detect scenario
since it is gonna tell us where the
lights are and generally speaking that
is what we want anyway like we know
what's supposed to light up in the game
and what's not we probably want to then
take that light information and give it
to the renderer so that it can bias the
sampling towards hitting light sources
right not biased in the sense of
creating a biased renderer but biased in
the sense that when it does importance
based sampling it can know that it
should try to aim for light sources
write the word bias is difficult because
there's a very specific definition of
bias when it comes to talking about the
output of a renderer that doesn't imply
so for example let's suppose that we
know that our renderer will go out of
its way to try to see if it can hit
light sources when it does its ray casts
rather than using a perfectly even
distribution of outgoing Ray's you would
obviously call that biased sampling
right I mean that's a you know
intuitively that's a phrase you would
use to describe it because it is biased
towards trying to hit a light source
right it obviously is
not a uniform distribution it's not even
a cosine weighted distribution it's very
specifically a distribution weighted
towards trying to get the light source
right however there are plenty of
examples of sampling schemes people have
constructed pretty much all the ones
used in production as far as I know that
are biased in exactly that kind of way
the trick is as long as you create the
correct probability model on the back
end biasing your sampling doesn't mean
your rendering ends up being biased and
what bias means in a renderer means over
time as you a verge of sub subsequent
rays biased or unbiased biased means you
will converge to the wrong answer
unbiased means you will converge to the
right answer
so a biased renderer if you run it
forever and just keep accumulating
results a biased renderer will converge
towards an erroneous answer usually
infinitely brighter infinitely dark I
would assume but I guess that's not a
story true whereas an unbiased ansel
answer will return the correct answer if
you ran it infinitely long that's the
actual difference between the two and so
the crucial thing you need to know is
when you are biasing the sampling you
need to know that your biasing the
sampling and you need to account for
that in how you combine those samples
but that's really all there is to that
and hopefully that makes some sense
anyway so we probably want this
information to come through and that's
something that we should look at now as
well so those are the things that I want
to do start getting the light probes
involved directly in here get them
through to the voxels and we probably
also want to start tracking those light
sources so that we understand where the
light sources are supposed to be when it
comes to lighting time at the very least
we're going to need that because we know
they have to inject light into the
system whereas nothing else does and so
if we don't understand where a light
source is we're not gonna be able to put
light in the system at all and
everything will just be dark so here we
are in the end lighting computation as
we move through here the first thing
we're going to want to do is probably
ignore these guys
but continue to keep them out because
what we want to do is just build the
light prep set and then out out put it
the spatial partition is not for the
probes the spatial partition is going to
be for the boxes I believe so let me see
here is that correct yeah the spatial
partition is just for doing the ray
casting so that's just taking the base
of the occluders and building a
hierarchy so that they can be ray casted
more quickly so we're basically looking
at sort of the part that comes below
here now as we're looking towards this
these boxes here where we're looking at
these box store directions and
accumulation a lot of stuff we really
don't want this stuff anymore so more
what we need to look at here is how
we're going to combine the light probe
arrays so I'm going to go ahead and move
this down because this is basically you
know a non-issue for us now
so I'm going to go ahead and move this
down and kind of get it out of our way
because this is not really relevant
anymore and will eventually go away but
we may want to look at how we were doing
our averaging over time there so we'll
you know we'll leave it there just in
case we want it for reference later so
we don't have to go dig it out of github
or something here we've got how we were
drawing some of our sample points here
we don't really need that at the moment
either but it's again it's some debug
stuff for drawing so I'm gonna move that
out of the way as well let's get this
down here and this is what we're
currently doing to draw our sampling
sphere again not super concerned about
that at the moment so we're gonna move
that down here to I'm just gonna leave
all this code down here just so I can
see this function this is all kind of
unrelated stuff at the moment and so
here yeah we have you know so we're just
looking at this as well
none of this stuff we care about either
so all this stuff can can pretty much go
know what this nonsense is I don't think
I care about any of this stuff yeah I
don't care about any other stuff I'm
gonna get rid of the cluster table stuff
as well
and what's the start point nonsense now
okay so again just cleaning this stuff
up here you can see us drawing our debug
lines we want to keep that in there
because we're probably gonna need those
debug lines as we try to debug this
whatever the new code is you're right so
you want that in there this stuff here
we don't care about this was the old way
we were doing things so that goes away
as well and so I think we want to start
with all of that code out of the way and
probably so probably that's really all
we want and so we look here and we say
all right we've got the accumulation
stuff going on and that should in theory
be not really doing anything anyway
because accumulating is not going to be
turned on at this particular moment as
we're starting this but we do want to
maintain that we probably ought to get
that working again eventually to check
our results and so we want the debug
line output to be there and so then here
is the part that outputs a sort of our
test light at the moment that's all good
and so now we want to do is put in the
part that actually works with the
lighting probes if we look at our game
render commands what we can see here is
we've got a light probe count and a max
light probe count a light probe position
right all this sort of stuff and what
this tells us is effectively what we
this is effectively an array that tells
us what are all of the light probes that
the game thinks are currently in like
the active set right so this right here
is our light probe position table it's
where the light probes are this right
here is our light probe irradiance table
it's what we thought the light probes
were last frame and again all that is is
the incoming light at each of the six
faces of the cube right so however many
of these we actually used in this case
that they're coming through here and
those are the lighting values that we
remember for them some of those lighting
values will be full black they will just
be zero zero zero
those will be light probes that have not
actually received an illumination yet
either because they are new or because
there's no light near them at the moment
others of them will have a residual
light value in it that is whatever their
lighting value was last frame and since
we smooth our values over time as I
talked about yesterday those values will
sort of be used to heavily weight the
results so that we only update the
results by a little bit on each frame
right so that's kind of where we're
starting and the light probe irradiance
is a bit piggy right now because we're
just using v3 s for it eventually I
think we want to encode the lighting in
there because we don't want to spend the
extra bandwidth reading and writing that
every frame so I think we're gonna want
to sort of composite that down a little
bit but otherwise I think this is
basically where we're at and we kind of
you know we'll have to see how it does
so if we now go and we take a sort of a
survey of this the lighting solution
itself
kind of needs to work with these light
probes you can see here we've got the
light probe counter right here and what
I can do is I can just make sure that
that's always the right size and then we
can work with these the light probes
themselves our position in a color if we
assume that we're just always gonna be
working with this we maybe can just use
these directly I mean it certainly seems
plausible so we may be able to do is
just say look we don't really care about
this it's not relevant we don't need a
separate version we'll just work with
the one that we've got here and we don't
really need to know anything about these
light probes other than their irradiance
in their position for the most part
right now there's one other piece of
information we may need because one of
the things that we don't necessarily
know is how many samples we added to
each light probe on this time for you
but one thing we could do and maybe
should do is just assume that we like
if we just assume that any light that's
actually active on this frame gets the
same a uniform set of samples so one
sample to each face of its cube if we
just assume that then I think we don't
need to track weights so we either send
out 6 12 or 18 rays per probe right and
we send one out of each of the faces of
the cube if we assume that we maintain
that sampling pattern then we wouldn't
need to track a weighting value we would
know that every ray that comes in is
always waited the Zak same way right in
other words the input values can be pre
that can be adjusted ahead of time to
account for what we're adding in and
then that would just be the end of it
right I think that pretty much just
works and so basically you would sweep
over the light probe irradiance table
and you would knock it down by 0.95
first and then you would just multiply
your rays by 0.25 for to raise or 0.125
for you know 24 rays or you know however
many it is and you would just build the
the temporal smoothing directly into it
and so again that just removes a step
that seems like a perfectly reasonable
thing to guarantee because I don't think
six arrays six rays at a time is a
totally reasonable stepping increment I
think so we'll just like say that that's
true right and if we find that we really
need things to be allowing two fours
then we can just switch to octagonal
sampling which maybe is something we
want to do anyway because eights are
better than sixes right they line up
better with machine words and ALU sizes
and so maybe we just start sampling the
vertices of cubes in the future right
and if we start sampling the vertices of
cubes then it's a cos you know you think
about there's no real reason you have to
go up the center of a cube right I mean
it's there I don't know anyway so that's
all that's all I'm saying
not complicated just just that's just
saying what I'm saying nothing nothing
weird all right so if we assume that all
that's true and we have our light from
radiant sense here and we're doing
whatever we're doing and we come in here
and we say we not gonna do weights we're
just gonna make these things operate in
place then if I go to the lighting
system then what I expect to see here is
basically this accumulation value right
the accumulation the way we were doing
the equation before I think what we want
to kind of say here is that the blend
the blending coefficients are just gonna
be like specific to whether you've got
permanent accumulation on or off if you
look at the accumulation see here
probably what we want to do is just
think about the two values we're
actually using and pass those down so we
probably want something like this we
want a preservation factor right so
preservation see like irradiance
preservation see and then we want a new
or irradiance acquisition my stone that
right
yes you can tell I don't work for
Silicon Valley firm otherwise I would
know how to spell acquisition better
than any other word
so irradiance preservation C and
irradiance acquisition C these are the
two values that we're going to be using
to blend things together and so we can
set these to whatever we want and you
can see we were sort of already doing a
little bit of that here and so what we
want to do is assume that our irradiance
preservation value is going to be
something like you know let's say we
want to blend it over one sixtieth of a
second that's all right let's say we
want to blend it over 60 frames so it's
one second on a 60 FPS machine right if
we want to do that kind of plan than
what we would say is well our
acquisition amount is going to be one
sixtieth of a second right and our our
preservation count is going to be the
opposite of that right so what we would
also know here is that generally
speaking we could say that our
preservation amount is just going to be
the sort of complement of whatever the
the acquisition around to so we preserve
whatever we don't acquire and so that's
just another way of saying look we've
got some of that we're gonna keep or
some of that we're gonna add in we'll
start and just make those two values and
I'll note them here waiting for new rays
waiting for old irradiance right so then
when we have our should accumulate here
I don't know that we really want should
accumulate to even be there because I
think we're sort of having this either
way so I think if we have solution
accumulating on all we really need to do
here is say it's to set these values
right so if we're trying to accumulate
and our accumulation count is less than
the amount that we wanted to do right
then what we do is we just set it so our
irradiance acquisition C is going to be
1 over whatever this total acquisition
can
is supposed to be and then our acute
irradiance preservation see right is
just going to be one and so we keep
whatever the old value is and week so
it's not a moving average we keep
whatever the old amount that we put in
there is and we're just adding every
time right to do a smooth accumulation
gap on the other hand we're done then we
just say oh well actually our
acquisition see and in fact I suppose
this can stay our preservation C is
always one our radiance acquisition is
either right a amount to contribute or
if we're done accumulating we just set
it to zero so this is if we want take a
long-term average over 5000 frames to
see what the result is just to see what
whether the lighting converges to
something stable right and so that's all
we'd have to do there because now now we
don't need this extra baggage when we do
compute light propagation we can just
say look the preservation will already
have been factored in so it's really
just acquisition for you now right and
off you go now the problem that we will
have here is that the way that we're
doing our acquisition and our
preservation we probably want to factor
this in in the reverse order so we may
want to do this a little bit more
Squinkie in the future the reason I say
that is because the simplest way to do
this is now once we have this
information what we would do is loop
over all of the light probes and knock
them down by the preservation
coefficient right so what we'd want to
do is say all right for each probe index
here as we loop over the light probe
count that we have so this is going to
be in the you know commands here but I'm
gonna actually just make that be a local
variable
and I'm gonna grab these other things
out of here so here we've got our our
light preposition air light Berber
radiance so probe pee I'm gonna do probe
count probe that's probe probe pee and
our light probe irradiance and this will
be our probe I or something right and so
these will just pull these out into
local variables so that they're easier
to see and type and I'll take the probe
position here and I'll take the light
print irradiance here and so what I'd
like to do is I'd like to go ahead and
make this knock down the irradiance of
each of the lights in question right so
I'd like to say you know probe I
oops like zero x equals irradiance
preservation C and off we go right so I
just want to knock those down by
whatever the preservation value is and
when I was trying to see before when I
say you know and I'll put it to do here
so we probably don't actually want to do
this here it's going to be slower
I would imagine to take the light probes
and multiply them first by the
preservation coefficient then do the
light transport and then come back loop
over the light probes again to voxel
eyes them what we would rather do is
multiply by the irradiance preservation
coefficient when we actually do the
voxel ization right but the problem is
we have the irradiance acquisition value
at you know baked in there
and so what we probably want to do is
take the irradiance preservation
coefficient multiplied in the inverse of
that to the irradiance acquisition so
that we can just add in to the
unadulterated values first and then do
this to the accumulated values right
because remember we should presumably be
able to figure out how we would do that
waiting now maybe we can't because
things don't always distribute over sums
the way we would like in fact I guess we
could figure out whether we can right
now but there probably is some way to do
it is all I'm trying to say without
creating a separate buffer let's take a
look
so let's assume that we want to
accumulate these probe values and so
what we have here is we have a
preservation value right and we want to
add an accumulation value and that's
going to equal our new probe value right
and so this is the the equation that
we're trying to create and we know that
we don't want to just add these two
together we want the these contributions
to be weighted in a particular way and
so our goal here is we really what we
want is not this equation we want the
new probe value to be some kind of a
weighting value so effectively we want
and we know that that's it's a it's
balanced I guess right we we pretty much
know that what we actually want is you
know T times P plus 1 minus T times a we
we do want like a linear blend in here
where we're saying we're going to keep
you know 0.95 of this thing and so we
want to add point 5 of this other thing
right every step of the way
so we know that we want something like
this but the problem is rather than
having each of these values what we
actually want to know is is it possible
to produce the value TP plus 1 minus T
times a is it possible to produce this
value right by instead computing a
different form an equation of a
different form which is just some other
value right like with let's say we have
a U and V values or something right some
other value u that we're going to
multiply these things by can we multiply
at the end by U and instead compute P
plus V times a right and so is it
possible to get this result out of this
equation when we can control U and V but
not P an a right so we only get to set
those two values these are whatever they
are right that's the question and so you
know I guess I would say looking at the
way that this multiplies out what you
see is TP plus 1 minus T a equals u P
plus UV a right that's the distribution
there and if we look at what these
values end up being it looks to me like
we would need u to be equal to T right
it would seem and we would need u times
V to be equal to 1 minus T right and so
looking at that equation I don't you
know my maths as the British would say
is pretty weak but looking at that
equation that suggests to me that if u v
is focus opposed to be equal to 1 minus
T and I know you has to equal T then
that means that T times V equals 1 minus
T right and so solving for V I would get
1 minus T over T right and so if I
didn't screw that up it means that we
could set our values thus so that we
produce a U and V value that can be used
in this way right which allows us to
multiply by one thing after the fact
while simultaneously just summing using
this value right so I think you know I I
would argue not strenuously because like
I said I'm not really a maths person but
I would argue that that's a reasonable
approach because the math seems to back
up that there's really no reason I would
have to do it the other way so I would
think that if we started out with an
irradiance acquisition in a Radian
preservation see here that's the rates
that we want to do it if I wanted and
call it something else which is the
irradiance blend factor right and this
is effectively our T value in here we're
basically saying this is how much
preservation we want in a sense right
would be what that is so maybe I
actually start with irradiance
preservation see as the thing we want to
do and I'm gonna set that to sorry
fifty-nine sixtieths right if that's the
preservation factor then what we would
end up with is irradiance Glenview and
irradiance blend v looking at these
equations here the outermost
preservation value is going to have to
be equal to that right so this this is
straightly carried through this one is
one minus that value over the value
right so here we have and in fact i
guess i could write it this way i'm
going to actually call this the t
irradiance preservation right
makes sense so that just is my way of
avoiding this problem entirely and so if
we want to change how this is phrased
here all I have to do is say okay since
we're gonna multiply at the end by
something that's something is just one I
don't ever want you to change it and the
acquisition value that we actually were
using before that's the amount we
multiply in again not going to be set
that same way so you know when doing
long term accumulation for testing we
turn off the linear blend and instead
just set the coefficients for long time
right so I think this very very simple
set of things allows us to do everything
we want to do and this part here now can
just be ignored right basically we don't
have to care we can just at the end when
we want to go through and do something
with their light switch you know we do
want to do you know here somewhere after
we do our computations once we want to
actually Vox lies these things or
whatever gonna do with them we can do
that blend value here
and that way when we load them into the
cache for vocalization or whatever we're
gonna do to actually output them the
graphics card at the same time we can do
that blending that way we're not doing
the blending as part of some you know
some separate paths just waste time
pulling them into the cache and then out
of the cache again or whatever else
right because we know where you need
those values to come into registers for
other purposes in a minute so we might
as well just do the multiplication when
they're already there and hot so that I
think is pretty straightforward now all
we need to do is decide okay yeah how
are these things getting lined up and
blended in and Voxx lized once we have
these light probes and the answer to
that question I think in this case is
just well if we're looping over each
light probe it's pretty cheap for us to
voxel eyes it given the fact that we
already not cheap but we already know
how to do it because we wrote the voxel
ization code to do this like add probe
to spatial index stuff right so you can
kind of see here where we're you know
putting these these probe pieces of
probe information into the voxel you can
sort of see how we're doing that here
and again that spatial index is
something that I toyed with actually
just sending down the spatial index and
the reason we didn't do that is because
we were looking at how expensive it
would be to blend these probes together
and it's you know it's pretty expensive
per pixel to do that sort of stuff I
feel like but it's always tempting to
underestimate how fast GPUs are they're
kind of incredibly fast and the fact
that right now sampling from all of
those voxels is apparently just a
non-issue for the GPU it's really
bizarre like how fast it is when you
think about it and just looking at you
know the fact that it's sampling from
six voxels and try linearly
interpolating all six voxels like right
now right is kind of ridiculous so you
know when we think about that kind of
going forwards right
it's kind of interesting what's going on
there Hoss again oh right that's the
edge of the lighting voxel right there
ha ha ha so at the edge of the lighting
voxel which you normally can't see if
you don't go the debug camera it just
it's a clamped edge so it just continues
to be lit for the rest of the place
continues to be lit man just like my
Friday nights um so anyway I think the
idea here is just that we really don't
know what we want to do here it's again
it's an experience with just how fast
GPUs can be in some of these
circumstances because maybe we just want
to keep what we were doing with our
spatial our probe spatial indexing I you
know I really I really just don't know
it's it's really hard to say so um I
think I'm gonna say let's just use the
spatial index that we have first we're
gonna use the spatial index to fill the
voxel and then when the time comes to
start looking at the sampling again
we'll figure out whether really what we
should be doing is just transmitting the
index voxel down and letting the GPU
deal with it right because based on
those sampling artifacts I was seeing
I'm thinking that we probably do want to
do that because there's a lot of reasons
why we would want to do that so you know
we'll we'll cross we'll burn that bridge
when we come to it so if we now go to
how this was working you can see this
add probe to spatial indexed stuff what
was that well that was the thing we
wrote where we have a light Pro spatial
index in here we can put in all of the
light probes and where they actually are
right and so if I was to call are the
already existing thing that that does
this right the ad preparation on this
and I don't actually know if we ever
called it we don't right so if we want
to do this I want to do ad probe the
spatial index right if I want to do
what I can do is here where we loop over
all of these I want to add them in the
spatial index here now what you might be
saying to me you might be saying KC and
you'd be using that because it's my
first name obviously um it'd be weird if
you said you know Brian or something cuz
that's not me but if you were talking to
me and use my first name and said well
KC you just said we don't want to make a
pre pass over these things which is not
really what I said remember I don't want
to pull the irradiance into the cache
this is pulling the positions into the
cache which is a separate array and it's
a separate array for a reason it's
because that way it doesn't pull the
irradiance into the cache if I don't
actually want to look at the irradiance
so when we add these probes the spatial
index we're only pulling in just their
location because that's the only thing
we actually need so here what I can do
is I can say add this probe to spatial
index the the spatial index here is
called the spatial index I think just
spatial probe index sorry so I want to
do a dupes ad probe - spatial index I
want to add it like that you can see
that we've got which index we're talking
about so it's this one that's actually
you 16 here because we don't allow more
than 6 5 5 3 6 probes at the moment we
didn't have a probe min P and a probe
max P like I said we need to add that P
in here on something hmm
in an old sign so what we want to do
here is say okay we've got this probe I
feel like this probably should have
passed the probe position in here I
don't feel like the probe mimpi probe
machspeed thing makes sense because in
the event when you need to do a
tiebreaker you needed to load the
p-value in anyway so I feel like this is
kind of stupid and wrong so I feel like
what we actually want here is a probe P
like like this value right these should
have been derived at the at the head end
you know I'm saying so like I feel like
these two values so I think what we want
is probe P minus radius and probe P plus
radius again I'm saying to you is what
we actually want and so I feel like this
should be passed down like that because
we're gonna have to look this thing up
to compute those values anyway and then
this thing just goes ahead and grabs it
again for no reason right and so I think
what we want to do is say this probe we
should never actually have to query
right so like this value here right you
can see that this probe was only ever
used to get that and so I don't think we
want that we need to look up probes in
this case to see which one is best and
if we really didn't want to bite that
which maybe sometimes we would we might
find that that's too expensive in and of
itself actually and so if it turns out
that that's actually not not going to
work for us then what we could do as
well is just say look inside here we'll
store one extra f30 tube so basically in
sight you know right like you can
imagine going into the spatial index and
instead of just a you sixteen there's
also like a right and we would just look
to see like okay in this cell what was
the most missing I don't know which of
those is worse I suspect that doing it
the way we're doing it's probably okay
at the moment so we're gonna leave it
with that but you get the idea
so now if I look up one of these spatial
probes so I go ahead and grab group I'm
sorry it's actually probed why do I call
it probe B from P so if I say probe P of
light probe index that gives me
well in fact I guess I don't even need
to do it there stir it right in line
each probes radius needs to fill the
voxel to a certain extent and it's hard
to know how big we want that to
necessarily pee but if we look at how
we're you know talking about these
values at the moment if I look at add
probe to spatial index we can see here
is the get center of call actually
produces a world space center so you
know if we look here you can see us
actually adding the cell dimension in
this is producing like the center of
this voxel right like where it at where
we actually think the voxel actually is
if that makes sense and so when we
actually do this ad prep of spatial
index presumably the probe radius is
actually in world space and so we would
just say like how big do we actually
want it to be and at the moment we don't
really know we can tune this value and
it's just how much coverage it's
expensive because as the bigger we make
it the the costlier it is to to build
the voxel in the first place because
each probe has to fill that many voxels
so it is an expensive operation to do
but the bigger it is the better the
lighting in a sense because it adds sort
of a fill region around each of the
light probes that will contain lighting
even if there was no probe in that
particular voxel square right so I don't
know what that needs to be set to at the
moment I'm going to use a one meter
probe radius in all directions at the
moment and so that's what we're actually
gonna look at there but who knows right
this is all kind of pretty
seat-of-the-pants and we're gonna have
to sort of deal with all of the
consequences
as we go right alright so moving forward
yeah we're going to have to correct a
bunch of stuff cuz we removed that light
prim strut because we're just kind of
working with them directly out of the
gate here I also think that maybe the
spatial probe in next thing doesn't I
feel like that could just be welded
directly into the like solution I don't
know why we actually made it a separate
thing that was probably unnecessary but
you know we'll see so when we do our add
probe to spatial index that should sort
of put that into our voxel now when we
go later on again this now doesn't
really have to be done in that way and
the reason on that to be done in that
way is when we go to output our voxel
now if we want to what we could do is
say well why don't we just actually like
get rid of all this nonsense completely
right and go and in here let's just pull
out the light probe that actually
belongs in this thing right so what we
could do is say all right we've got you
know like crevo rants values that we
want to deal with here we want to do the
ear blend you thing but then after that
what we want to do is just you know pack
them up right so these values here would
just be kind of copied verbatim directly
into here I think uh well you know I I
lied that's not true so we do have the
problem of having to encode these things
so really we are going to need a
slightly different algorithm for that so
I guess what I will do here is I'll do
this slightly differently I'll save it
in here what we want to do is we want to
do a light pack right
because that's what actually wants to
happen here like so here's our
irradiance packing that we wants to do
and here's the values we actually want
to keep
so we need to generate an irradiance
connect function and that irradiance
packs function needs to somehow figure
out how it's going to represent light
values in that way right and so what
that will look like is something like
this we get in the light intensity value
this value is something between zero and
like the max light intensity right I
mean could be anything really so it's
not zero to one if it was we just call
this and be done basically so what we
need to do is produce a value where we
slide the magnitude into the Alpha and
everything else is sort of everything
else is is just treated as the color
balance right the proportion of the
colors so if we want to do that you know
the fastest thing probably to do in this
particular circumstance right is to just
say well you know we could even
Euclidean norm these things like we
could do just a squared
you know without square rooting we could
just do a squared version and then
square root we could use a one norm for
them we could just use the maximum value
I guess I would probably go with maximum
value just offhand so I think what I
would probably do is say you know
whatever the max value is
so I want the element maximum which I
don't think we actually have so anyway I
want the maximum value here so I'm gonna
assume it's X and then I'm gonna say
look if the maximum value is less than
light why we take it actually I guess I
could write it this way I mean that's
actually what we want right and so I
think I don't have a triplicate version
of that so I'll just you know sort of do
the Korean version so producing the max
value there if the maximum value you
know the result here will be zero if the
maximum value is greater than zero then
we can actually do the PAC otherwise we
can't and it's just going to remain zero
it has no intensity it has no intensity
so we look through here and we say all
right if the if there is a max intensity
then we can do the pack the pack is
going to be whatever the incoming value
was X Y Z these are the color balance
values and then that maximum value it
would be going in here we need to
balance these out right so we need to
encode these in a way that actually
works with the encoding which is
supposed to put the magnitude in here so
what that means is the maximum value has
to come out we kind of need the in max V
right so the end of max V is going to be
1 over the maximum value we need these
guys to sort of represent that
max V right and furthermore we also sort
of need this max the value now to be
encoded between two between two ferns
right as it were
we need that max V value to be relative
to max light intensity so this value
here we need that to sort of be we need
this to be bounded in that in that space
because it's going to be reinterpreted
in that space so the max value that
comes out can't be you know it can't be
higher than this and the number from 0
to 1 that we encode is going to be
reinterpreted as part of this so we need
the max value to basically be like
divided by the max and tensity
and we need it to be clamped right so we
kind of need in here you know this you
know alpha value so we need this alpha
value here we need this thing to be
reinterpreted in terms of what
percentage of the max light intensity it
is and then we also need that value to
be clamped because it can't go out of
the range of an 8-bit value right again
a lot of dancing around here that we
have to do but that's just you know the
nature of trying to pack HDR values and
we can do a much better job of this in
Cindy certainly so when it comes time to
optimize this stuff assuming this shows
up on the profile this and if this part
is slow right you know off we would go
so anyway let's go ahead and yeah
all right so I think what we want to do
here is not sure which order I want to
take these things and uh so I think let
me just finish what I was doing here
before we go any further though so we we
have a probe in NextEra we need to use
to look up which light source we're
actually talking about and what I may do
is actually grab that out first right
and so here we have each of the light
values in question
and I think now that's basically what I
need right so I need to look up the
probe index which we haven't actually
pulled out of the voxel but we will we
need the irradiance pack each of these
values and before we do we want to let
multiply them by the bun coefficient so
they reduce down right then we're just
gonna stuff them as you can see right
into here and so I think that's pretty
much all there is to that getting the
light probe value out since we have you
know the x y&amp;z here if we look up that
spatial index let me just see where
we're at here so get corner light index
I'm not really sure we have to go check
to see I don't even understand what get
corner light index is supposed to do
here
like I'm not sure why that's called get
corner light index I think that was
probably because we were thinking about
this in terms of like
yeah I mean it looks sort of like what
we were doing there is saying so let me
let me take a look here so when we do
and probe spatial index I'm not sure why
we're calling it get corner light I
don't quite understand because if you
look at what's actually happening it's
just figuring out what the closest one
is to the cell center so it's not the
corner light index it's the center light
index right and so then when you say
like when you say get probe lighting for
and you know hear you say cell P you
know this is all totally fine the
problem is that when you looked it up in
the first place and you wanted to know
right like so get probe lighting for for
example right when you map this into the
grid you didn't actually want it to give
you the grid cell you were in you wanted
it to give you which probe was the one
that is less than your spatial partition
position in each direction which cubes
Center is the next one down right so I
do feel like we have sort of a
fundamental stupidity happening here
this probably has to get fixed
and so I will fix it but it looks like
we've written this a little bit bogus ly
which is probably because we just kind
of wrote it to get one in there and we
didn't think it through as good as we
probably should have right so you know
I'm not gonna harsh on us too much but
it's not great so in here what we really
you know
really not calling this is not really
corner light I think that's just dumb
that that's what that that is but so
we're gonna say get corner light index
this is going to be you 16 that's like
you know probed index pointer here we're
gonna get that actually I guess I could
just do this and so we pass here the
solution s probe spatial index or
whatever it was called and then we need
the actual cell coordinates and those
coordinates we know are bounded right so
we know that we're not going to get
anything out of bouncer because we're
only iterating over voxels that actually
exist so in this case rank we go through
and we we are sending out basically the
values based on what we find in the box
any particular location and that's based
on the whatever yeah like whatever it is
the the voxel ization of the probes to
begin with tells us is there that's what
we send out for our actual irradiance
right and so I think that's sufficient
the only thing now is we wouldn't
actually get any light even if all of
that worked correctly because none of
these probes has any irradiance in them
and so one thing we knew would need to
do at some point is actually assign some
irradiance to these probes and again
that's actually something we can sort of
crib now from from this previous voxel
stuffing what we can do is we could do
the same thing with our light probes so
here where we actually kick the probes
down we can put in some debug code here
that actually stuffs the irradiance of
those light probes sort of based on the
same stuff right if you want to so we
can just kind of say like hey this light
PE right like maybe we go
and so we have this this debug light key
here we're gonna grab that out and and
when we come through here we can say
well let's find out where ever this
light probe actually is which is you
know something like this and so if we
actually know where this is then we can
use the exact same like debug light
situation here
we can compute this same light situation
and sort of use that to stuff the values
of our of our light probe instead right
so if I was to take like this let's say
and stuff that in here then this becomes
debug code we can use to stuff the light
probe irradiance values as well looking
at them here we could say well the light
preparation svali in this case is going
to be you know wherever the light
position was which is this - whatever
our world space position is which is
that the distance is still the same the
N value is still also the same right
know why that is written twice but that
was just bad code before so we take the
you know this is the direction to the
light source we normalize it because
we're going to use it in a second
we do the light coloration here we do
need that light our C value but we can
again move those things up here so these
two values we can share between the two
sets of debug code just like we share
the light value right and so we can
compute all of the lighting information
this way and then all we have to do is
when we come down here we can just stuff
whatever these values are here right
into our actual irradiance table
so for the light irradiance here we
would just a light probe a radiance
that's our irradiance table and each of
these just tells us how much light there
should be so in this case we have each
direction we've got a you know the west
east south north down up and now we just
need some idea of like what the light
color actually is which should be fine
because and that's something we can also
set up here so that gives us a way of
stuffing our light irradiance values at
the outset and we can stuff the light
I'm sorry the light probe irradiance
values we can stuff the light probe
irradiance values first then we've
oxidize them later and now we can see
whether that pipeline is working
properly because if it is working
properly we should get some sort of a
lighting sort of a crappy spherical
lighting thing like we had before just
stuffed in there right and so this way
we can sort of debug that process as
well now building spatial index for
these things I believe like I don't know
when we actually if we if we ever tried
this or not I don't think we did and so
if you look at like the spatial index
stuff one of the things about it is I
don't think anyone ever initializes it
right so we kind of have to actually set
this stuff now right if we want to use
this thing we're
have to actually set it to something so
when we come through here we're gonna
set each of these values and the light
index as well has to kind of be
allocated or you know pointed to
something or something right so when we
do init lighting that has to happen and
you know looking through here it
obviously doesn't so you know one thing
we have to do here is say all right the
light in next year that has to be pushed
on there and we need you know to know
what the what the voxel size is actually
going to be and I believe that's
something that's just hard coded at the
moment to what its maximum actually is
so you look up here you can see what it
is so we need the like the cubed version
of that
right so the light lookup Fox will dim
that's gonna have to happen three times
or three you know it's cubed that's how
much we need for our storage there and
then when we come through to the end
letting computation we need this stuff
to be set up right like someone has to
set it up that that voxel ization and
the first thing we would need to do is
actually clear it as well so we would
need to do a zero array and we would
need to clear out the size we expect to
use and then we would also need to set
all of those other values that that we
care about so all of this stuff here we
would need to update now the total cell
counts I don't know who's actually using
that but I'm assuming that we could set
that as well so no one's using it at the
moment but we could it probably is handy
anyway
so the total cell count here is always
just this and so we kind of know that
that you know it's something we can lean
on there so when we want to clear this
array we can just say like hey it's this
many right but we also then every frame
we could you know we don't know if
someone has adjusted this stuff so we
also need to set all of the values that
have to do with the voxel ization we
need those values to be set in here
right so all of this stuff has to get
set before we can use the voxel
effectively because otherwise it won't
line up with what we're doing anyway and
so we need like we had down here where
we've got sort of this information
that's coming through from in set up you
know that stuff kind of has to be
captured as well just grab this stuff
here in fact this stuff could should be
kind of put up to the top and then down
here
so the in voxel dim and the voxel Minh
corner right those come through this up
so the the Fox Ulm in corner hoops comes
in here and then you know we need to
know the seldom in the inverse seldom
for our purposes and at the moment right
those are not things that we actually
know oh I guess they are no they're not
no no it's the dim power - that comes in
here right so we don't actually know
that so what we actually want to do here
is start to talk about like you know we
want to be able to compute these values
efficiently is the thing and what you
can see from some of these is it's kind
of hard to do that and some based on
what we actually know in some of these
cases because we're providing only the
minimal amount of information it's also
kind of scattered around a little bit
and so we end up in a situation where
like we're probably not doing this as
efficiently as we could be either way
but we'll you know get there as we go so
if we take a look at what we know the
inverse voxel dimension is well the
inverse voxel dimension the inverse box
of dimension here yeah that in fact that
doesn't even matter I don't even know
why we're looking at this value this is
not this is not relevant to us put that
back down here because we don't actually
want that there we go
so the imp total dim is really the thing
that that tells us the piece of
information we wanted but it doesn't
really tell it to us in the way we want
so if we take a look at how big a cell
is well right we know what the dimension
is and we know what the inverse of the
total dimension is so the inverse like
of a cell for example and the inverse of
the total dimension are related by to
each other by the dimension
unfortunately for dimple two is
something we don't actually know because
we only have the Vox Tim coming in and
in order to figure out what power of two
it is we would have to bit scan it which
seems bad which makes me think we maybe
want to specify the voxel size as a
power of two because it is something
that you do want to know and we know
that we can never really use a non power
of two you know in terms of the way the
graphics card is going to work we're
always going to want to send down
anything that's voxel we're gonna want
that to be a power of two for sure right
and also for the facility of working
with it on the CPU we probably also want
each dimension to be a power of two they
don't really have to all be the same but
they do all want to be a power of two
probably and so it's probably the case
that we you know looking at how this
this is shaking out I think that also
something we probably would want to fix
right but again moving forward with what
we have as we have it and maybe I'll
ping-pong back to the old way of doing
the test and and replay around with how
we're specifying some of these things
but for the moment just to you know play
with it here I'm gonna actually just
derive these values directly instead and
so what am I do here is when we did
enable lighting and we have light bounds
right you can see in here when we record
those light bounds right into the render
group I'm assuming
don't we have cuz in here I thought we
had to set I thought we had to set the M
seldom am I wrong about that so sorry
that's not that what I'm thinking of
what I actually mean is the voxel in
total done
somebody has to set that right I mean
it's getting set in the actual thing to
set light bounds that's what it is so
inside set light bounds here right when
you send these two things down I'm not
really convinced that right like this
seems to be sort of a little bit of the
issue so when we have that set light
bounds call I think that's kind of the
part that's a little bit sticky here and
so if you take a look at when this is
getting pushed on at the beginning I
feel like that's sort of more the thing
that we wanted to look at in the world
mode where it actually occurs so if I
look at set alight bounds if you look at
where that's actually happening you
could see that like begin lighting
computation is the thing that happens
right before it and so what I might say
is like maybe that is actually the way
this should work is instead of you know
this is maybe the wrong way to look at
it maybe what we actually want is this
call here
should actually be occurring in here so
like you know the lighting is enabled or
whatever and we are then gonna set the
light bounds or you know we could do
them in the opposite order or whatever
it has to happen right who knows but
that way inside begin letting
computation we can store more
information about what the heck we're
trying to do here so when we pass this
in you know we just pass light bounds
directly and this thing can store all of
the stuff that it wants to know about
the light bounds without having to like
sit around trying to reverse engineer
what the heck it was from inverted
versions of itself and everything else
right so if we were to switch to doing
it that way then this is kind of nice
because then inside begin lighting
computation what we can actually do is
set up all of this stuff in there right
so this can just happen in here we know
what the mid corner is because it's just
the light bounds men right we know what
the seldom is because it's this
dimension here divided by the number of
cells in each direction right so the
cell dimension is just the light dim you
know it's a Hadamard quotient right but
we'll deal with that in a second and the
intervals in V seldom is just 1.0
divided by and I get rid of that it's
just 1.0 divided by 2 seldom
right and so really that gives us a nice
way of pushing all of that information
down cleanly because now we're just
sending down one bounding value at the
start and then all of these sort of like
values that we're gonna need that are
dependent on that value just all get
computed in one place the problem that
we have is this dim pow2 bit because at
the moment we do know how big the voxel
actually is we just don't know what it's
actual power of two is and that makes it
a little bit harder right so when we
want to actually compute the seldom
that's not so bad because there we just
need the arbitrary let count and that we
do have right so we can do a Hadamard
quotient here do we have a had a marked
ocean don't all right so I guess we'll
have to do ahead of our product I'm not
gonna go right ahead of our quotient
just for this of the light dim and the
in cell count right and so we know some
of these things right like this right
here is the inverse cell count I mean
that's what that is so we know we can
actually create these things as
necessary the Box dim here is specified
as a part of the command structure
always so we know what that is going to
be and this is the inverse box um so I'm
going to call this box count here or a
cell count and inverse cell count right
so then when we come through here we can
say all right we know that the cell
dimension is going to be the height of
our product of whatever the total
lighting bound dim is right and the
inverse cell count because that will
divide it out we then know that the
inverse cell dimensions is what's the
opposite of this right so it's one over
that value and so the only thing we're
left with is this value here which we
don't know and this wants to be you know
set we kind of know vaguely what it is
right we know that
the cell counts and we could sort of
just do it this way where we say look at
the moment we kind of know what it is
it's just going to be whatever that cell
county is the power of two right and I
don't know if we actually have any
functions that do that scan yeah so we
do kind of know like we can find these
out right it's pretty easy for us to see
what they are so if we assumed it was a
power of two first then it's actually
not very hard for us to find out what
that power of two is yeah so I mean I
guess we could just stuff that the other
thing we could do here is just change
the way we're defining this right so
inside the render if we look up here and
we say I think this is just a saner way
to do it so this way we would say look
you know it's it's gonna be specified as
a power of two as well and so cure you
can just kind of get that information
out and maybe we hard code those a
little bit more maybe we make them
looser I don't know but you know at the
moment we'll do that and then we'll
maybe pass that down as something here
that we needed this code desperately
needs to be cleaned up I don't want to
start cleaning it up until we actually
know that we've got it the way we want
it because there I'm just like burning
time so in here now we can get all of
the information we need for our voxel
and it can least be set up properly it
can be cleared and then in here we can
voxel ice into it which we want and off
we go now it kind of doesn't make much
sense to do this clear to be completely
honest so I think what we'd probably
rather do is when we come up here and we
do the initial allocation right we know
that it will be cleared then so I think
what I'd rather do is when we process it
here I think this is probably the time
to
where it so what I think we should do is
say let's grab the probe pointer like so
and this can be made much faster because
right now we're doing a blind lookup
here whereas what we could be doing is
just stepping linearly through the
voxels so I could just increment this
pointer every time and be done you know
what I mean and in fact you know that
might be the smarter way to do it just
to start with so you we could do instead
is just say yeah forget about it let's
just assume that what we actually wanted
to do was take like a pointer here and
say let's start at the initial indexing
of this thing so we've got the solution
light probe index light index and we're
just gonna step it so each time we know
that the probe index is just the probe
in next pointer dereference trite so we
don't really have to do any work to get
that we don't have to caulk it corner
light index we don't even have to build
a cell cord or we're gonna do is just
look it up and then when we're done with
it right so now that we know what the
probe index actually is we can just go
ahead and clear it as well right so we
that way we are reading and clearing it
at the same time we don't need a
separate loop at the head end to like
deal with that right so we read and
clear and pack all in kind of one go and
I think that's probably better than the
alternative because we're not doing
separate passes for no reason all right
so now we we more or less know when we
do light probe calls we kind of need to
change these to be just passing the
information we actually have rather than
these false sort of probe pieces of
information which were which are gone
now
so if we look at how we wrote this code
let's sort of take it step by step and
and sort of replace it so in here where
we look we can see all of the sort of
the red nastiness here what we need to
do here is is get the light probe
position separately so we kind of have a
light probe P right that's going to be
coming this way actually and you know
these are probably things that we can
just have pointers I want to see these
can just be off of the solution as well
I think we probably want to do it
roughly like that and then you know we
know that the origin is just gonna be
looked up like this and then at some
point we're going to need ok so here's
like the sampling and whatever and at
some point we're going to need them
still not actually seeing it at some
point we're going to need the actual
compositing values you can see that
happening here but we really don't need
a position anymore after that so this
can just be a light proba radiance value
that comes back from this call right and
then I think we're pretty much done yeah
so I think we can just modify that code
to be pretty straightforward when we
call this we're really just asking for
the irradiance and so I think that
solves that problem the solution itself
needs to have the pointers to the actual
rays we care about here so we're gonna
need like you know the light probe P
here
and we're going to need the irradiance
as well and this is just to avoid having
to pass them down they are in the render
group so they're easy to come by but we
just don't want to have to pass those
around because we know that everybody
who's operating lighting solution is
going to have to have them right get
learning from probe again that is I
think just this and now we actually have
to change those things to work with
those so when we do this is actually
probe irradiance right in both cases and
light in this case just needs to be
replaced there instead of color and I
guess I don't really know like in terms
of the way that these are working does
anyone ever care about the position and
the answer seems to be no so I think
that pretty much all of these want to
work on like almost everybody wants to
work on just the probe irradiance
but but for this one right here which
needs the actual position right this
this one is the only one that actually
needs that position now I don't think it
makes any sense to actually call get
probe here but I mean maybe we will it
just it seems like kind of stupid but
you know whatever
so when we're actually calling that get
probe call here what we really want to
know is just what the existing probe P
is right so we really just want that is
all that we actually need and so here
what we want to know is just well we've
got the existing index all we really
want to know is like all right
you know what's its position and that's
just you know a pretty trivial thing to
implement so I think everybody else just
wants the irradiance value so I think
everybody else can just work right by
just replacing it with this for now and
again this code probably needs to be
like improved quite a bit
it's not great at the moment and so will
you know but that's the nature of code
it goes through some bad stapes before
it gets to a good state and that's just
how you have to program if you want to
program well if you try to make sure
that you start off with a good state you
will just always have either no code or
bad code all right so I think we're
mostly good this is this and this is
that what else we got here in the error
list same thing I think yeah
and this is again just alright this is
just a change of name there but I think
otherwise we're good what else you got
and
[Music]
so this needs a variable type obviously
I guess that needs to be casted to an
f32 because it's expressed as a double
at the moment the light prep index total
cell count here
spatial probe index alright sorry yeah
this just a lot of bookkeeping
[Music]
all right so the total cell count here
this push array needs which arena which
is easy enough the light bounds let me
call set light bounds this is just
called group not render group here we
don't have the commands readily
available so we really need that and
then this Vox dim here is supposed to be
cell count I changed the name of that
and didn't update it right
is there something what is it
complaining about here oh yes this is
backwards all right and so now I think
we've got those sorted out what else you
got for me an end lighting computation
we've got issues here it doesn't like
that : can't blame it I'm sure why there
is a column there the light probe count
here
we don't set a lot of these values so
we're gonna have to go make sure these
are set to we're just gonna have to go
through this and clean it up a little
bit and clamp oh one of the light RC
times the light dist
what is it complaining about oh there's
a previous value of it
sorry um I'm gonna call that light color
at the moment
oops so we can make that work
and then I don't know if we defined a v4
that's a v3 version we did so that
should work as well um so actually yeah
these this I was a little premature on
remember this actually store is full
values these aren't these don't have to
be packed or split in any way they're
not HDR values they can just be
arbitrary floats so it's actually just
the light color times the brightness in
that in that direction and we're done
let's see what else we got here that's
spatial probe index we don't need any of
this stuff turned on and then I think
we're compiling yep
and so the only other thing I want to do
here before we end for the day is we
just we didn't initialize these values
so they're not going to work right and
so what we want to do when we first
begin the lighting computation or really
we can do this at any time but so maybe
we do it here because we could do all of
them here what we want to do is make
sure we set all this crap right so all
of this stuff here that we're just kind
of duplicating because we want it to be
centrally indexable by anyone who just
gets a pointer to the lighting like
because we have multiple threads who
then come and have to look at this stuff
what we want to do here is say all right
like let's actually set all these values
so the light probe count needs to be
equal to the actual number of light
probes that got recorded right and the
light crimpy needs to be
said as well and the light provenience
needs to be set as well
kids get those wired up and then I think
you know we're fine and so this is gonna
be you know super buggy and crashing and
weird cuz we just kind of barter thing
up so I probably won't a bucket today I
think what I'd like to do is you know
next weekend we'll start playing around
fit try to smush that code down into
something more reasonable
well actually I take that back
I might debug just this because this is
probably pretty easy for me to debug
but smack the code down a little bit you
know kind of smooth it out a little bit
and then start to actually work on
getting the light transport up and
running because this is all this is
going to do now is just actually have
the light probes flow through properly
but that's all it will do right um so I
just want to take a quick look at that
well I'm still thinking about it
add probe to spatial index is here and
you could see it looping over the
indices in question the map into grid
the one thing I have question is is this
actually clamped yeah so this is not
clamped so you know that's why we're
getting that error this is just kind of
stupid right you want these things to be
clamped so that they yeah I mean this is
this is just kind of dumb so what you
want to do here for a map into grid and
you know if we look let me just take a
look at who's calling at the moment yeah
so what you probably want here is map
into grid is is something that probably
wants to be more of a like rejection
based thing probably but for the moment
I guess I won't do that and we'll kind
of think about it a little bit
differently but what we'll say is you
know when we do map into grid I will
then take the resulting UVW indices that
come in here which is probably not the
best name for those we'll take those
indices and we'll we'll floor them out
right so we'll say like or we'll
document will clamp them right - we have
a clamp for integers so like this right
so each of these values what we'll do is
we'll clamp them and we'll say that we
want them to clamp out between the dim
values here right so when we have the
spatial index dim power - nonsense here
right we're just gonna say look you
can't you can't go outside those bounds
now the clamp itself doesn't really do
quite exactly what we want because you
can see will allow the max value to
exist and we actually want the max value
to be out of bounds because there is no
cell there that's like the outer bound
of it right so we're actually clamping
to 1 minus that value and that's what we
actually want to return okay so yeah
like I said I wasn't gonna really do bug
it but I'm probably gonna bug a couple
things cuz that's obviously stupid right
so we're gonna fix that and we might fix
a couple if there's any other obviously
stupid things going on but we'll leave
the actual making of the code nice tall
till the next weekend
well what is this complaining about Oh
woops UVW is not sorry not what I wanted
to do I was trying to clamp the cell
coordinates not the location what's
interesting about the UVW is I mean in
some sense I feel like this probably
wants to actually be allowed to be
completely bogus like in other words it
probably wants to be computed afterward
but I don't know like maybe you want it
to always be zero to one anyway
that's really hard to say so I'm not
sure what that should be if you place it
up here yeah there's just you know I
don't know so I feel like maybe we want
it to always be more bounded I'm gonna
put two do on it so yeah you know what
do we want to do there I'm not sure we
could also clamp that value and then it
would always be correct I don't know we
want to do with that but you know we'll
see okay so actually not as bad as I was
expecting it's actually doing something
at the moment but yeah obviously totally
wrong but I'm gonna leave it there
because we'll go ahead and actually try
to work these out more directly in next
weekend when will actually start to work
on the light transport part we'll get
the light probe stuff cleaner and then
we will try to you know figure out how
we want to start doing the light
transport stuff we've got it sketched in
there like it's actually got some code
in there that sort of does it but that's
gonna have to start improving alright
let's go to quick QA
room why does the hand meet here I shall
not have the game development and
programming tags so it sometimes does
and sometimes doesn't is the answer
Roman basically the wait which chose to
implement their system because you know
that they are web programmers I guess is
that rather than allowing you to set
what your tags are going to be in some
kind of a like groups and then when you
start streaming you say which one it is
which is exactly what you would normally
do they just clear your tags every time
every time you broadcast they clear your
tags so the reason that we are not
labeled as game development programming
is because I got tired of every time
before I stream having to pick all of
our tags again right so I don't I just
got sick of it it was too rage-inducing
because every stream its exact same tags
we always do the same thing we do game
development and programming every stream
every time and I don't really want to
have to go set up our tags every time
Oh for debug techs no we haven't put in
a separate pipe for non lit rendering
yet
do you have any examples of good written
software open-source that you would
recommend someone to study or that you
yourself have studied in the past I
couldn't say for sure so I don't know I
don't spend a lot of time reading source
code I read mostly technical papers and
I just take people's word for it when I
read like here's how we it worked right
I don't usually go read their code but
you know I guess what I would say is I
would be shocked if say the doom and
quake source code wasn't really good
source code like I would be shocked if
it turned out that the doom source code
or the quake source code wasn't really
good I bet it is I just don't think you
can make doom and quake in that era
without the code being good I just don't
think it happens right so I would say
probably all right that's where I would
look first I didn't read them myself but
I you know I I would be pretty surprised
to find that that wasn't good source
code
where's the puss she is outside the room
that I am streaming from that is why the
puss is like I usually close the door if
the puss is already out there because
that way there's not as much noise
coming from outside but you know I don't
think this color scheme has a name I
made up this color scheme this is a new
one
so I made it up and balanced it out I
think I've done a future revision in the
clara scheme as well it's a little bit
different that's on my new editor but
it's pretty similar
alt overflow how can we improve the web
just burn it down man like the get rid
of all of it
start over and make things be
peer-to-peer again like just you know if
if Microsoft had actually known how to
make an operating system that could talk
to other that we're too computers could
talk to each other we wouldn't need any
garbage anyway so you know as far as I'm
concerned we're living in 1970 right now
and everyone has a terminal connected to
a mainframe and it sucks because it
always sucks it's never going to be good
ever in the history of mankind 3,000
years from now it will still suck to
connect to a mainframe for all the
reasons that it sucks latency that is
insurmountable but in like you can could
not it's insurmountable you can't you
can't nothing you can do about it right
it's the speed of light until someone
breaks the speed of light you're screwed
right the latency is bad the politics of
it are bad it centralizes the control of
things into a handful of people the the
ownership is bad it prevents you from
being able to actually like have your
own computing environment and control
how it works
we're in 1970 again somebody needs to be
Microsoft someone needs to be the
Microsoft of 1980 right and you need to
do that you need to be that in 2020 and
it's get rid of it get rid of it
does anyone connect to a VAX anymore no
and that's what we need we need someone
in 20 years to look back and go oh
that's weird like you mean to tell me
everyone there were these giant rooms
filled with computers and everyone like
called over what's essentially like a
phone line to them or something
that's absurd right we'd three let's say
the same thing about cloud computers
like there's a giant datacenter with
lots of computers in it you didn't just
have it at your house like what
and like you mean to tell me that you
used the like Internet backbone instead
of talking between you and the person
you're trying to talk to you like talk
to some giant corporation first you like
read all your messages
what and you'd be like you need that to
sound as stupid today as putting an
acoustic cup or mode em on your vt100
and calling evacs sounds to us today but
that's what you did in 1970 1975
someone had mentioned it a stream
perhaps you needed 1.0 - herb blend you
but I had one - herb lend you why would
that matter not sure why that would ever
matter in that circumstance so maybe you
guys are saying something I'm not
understanding but like you're talking
about this line of code right I thought
we're talking about or is there
something else
is DirectX dependent on the C runtime
can be used without it so I I'm not
really a DirectX expert because I don't
spend a lot of time programming it but
my assumption is that the reason that
there's some confusion about this is
because people don't differentiate
between direct X the hardware API and
direct X the library so if you're
talking about DirectX the like library
with all of the like tools and crap in
it and like the matrix routines or stuff
I mean I remember there being like a
bunch of stuff marked X that is almost
certainly dependent on the C runtime and
probably can't be used without it right
but DirectX the hardware API if you just
want to like get proc address or and and
you know get pointers to the comics that
implement DirectX or something that
should just work right you shouldn't
need anything you don't even need an
import library for that all you need to
know is the layout of the virtual table
so you need the H files and and you
could even cut and paste all the
definitions and you need to actually
query where those V tables are which I
think you could probably just you do
with get proc address I think now you
need to hard-code the grids and your app
as well I mean but that's what happens
anyway like that's in the H file it's
gonna hard code the grids that you query
for but I again not something I really
do but you should be able to do that
stuff so you shouldn't need to link with
the real DirectX library that might pull
in the C runtime lever and all that
garbage
so okay god I gotta answer some
questions about this line because I'm
not sure why this is causing so much
confusion so let me just walk through it
so key irradiance preservation is a
number that is between 0 &amp; 1 and you can
see that here right so herb lend you is
by default it's between 0 &amp; 1 it's it's
gonna be well I mean here is the actual
value I don't want to try and do that in
my head but you know it's it's this and
so if you think about what 1 minus herb
lend you is going to compute it's just
going to compute like 0.02 right it's
not quite that because you have this 3
repeating but you know it's within the
ballpark that's what 1 minus for a blend
view is going to do now in terms of what
happens with this expression this is a
floating point value and this is an
integer so it's going to convert this
integer to a floating point value now it
is true that you do need to watch out
for that sometimes if this is a variable
or something but in fact if it was a
variable I would have gotten a warning
so if for example I had done something
that couldn't see so like for example
let's suppose that I took solution debug
line count which is an integer and I put
it here it would have issued a warning I
believe and the warning is just that it
can't necessarily do that conversion I
think all right that's a little bit
weird so I'll be honest I'm not sure why
it didn't issue a warning I would have
wanted it to but it didn't did we turn
it off we may have turned it off
let's find out I really should REM these
in here so we know which ones they are
just for quick reference but let's take
a look
name the struct Union unreferenced
formal parameter local variable
removed function conditional expression
constant so I guess I'm not sure why
it's not warning us about conversion
there because it should be it can't it
can't represent an arbitrary you 32 and
I'm not sure why unless I'm missing one
of the warning disables I'm not sure why
it isn't warning because my recollection
is normally it does when it and I don't
really need it to because most the time
I'm okay with that but my assumption
there would be that that it's not really
a problem per se so let me just check
and you know the other thing I'm
thinking is I wonder if it's is it
because so it's because it's never used
it may just never actually be producing
this value the other thing I was
thinking so I also kind of wonder if
like we need to use it
yeah I got nothing I don't know why it
doesn't issue value an error there
because I would have assumed that we
would get an error on on that and I
don't know why we're not normally if you
do an in to float conversion implicitly
it will give you some warning at least
that was my recollection so you know I
mean I'm assuming unless unless I'm just
going crazy here at the very least you
know like that ain't gonna work
right you would think you'd tell us hey
I'm worried about this right yeah float
to you 32x and that's when it knows it
can do properly right it's looking at
the value 1.0 and it knows it can do it
so that's a little bit odd looking at
floats in here you know debug light P
maybe so if I said debug like P X equals
you know some value here then I'm
assuming that it wouldn't issue a value
if it it wouldn't issue an error if it
knows it can place the value in there
safely now I don't think it would be
able to put all values in there safely
because I don't think for example if I
was to do s 32 maximum it shouldn't be
able to represent that and I would hope
that it would give me an error maybe I'm
wrong
yeah that's really strange because I'm
pretty sure that there would be no way
for it to actually do this operation
right this operation doesn't work and I
don't I would have expected us to have
turned it off in here and that's why
it's not happening
but that doesn't seem to be the case is
there some other - WD that we're doing
that I missed yeah I mean I don't know
that's really strange to me I guess it's
all I would say because like for example
if we look at what actually happens here
I mean let's just do it right so let me
go ahead and set this to minus OD right
and let's go ahead and run the code to
that point and I'll just kind of show
you what I'm trying to say here so if we
were to set a breakpoint
where we were going to run that that
particular piece of code where we do
this assignment here right so if we look
at what we expect to find here I guess I
should probably also put s for you max
market that's well I can't probably look
at that in the butter yeah so if I was
to also have the value here and you know
now I can just do it directly so we'll
do it this way test Val equals s what
say you 32 max right and test float
equals test Val I can also do it the
final way and say you know round-trip
equals new 32 test float right so if we
watch what happens here and we just look
at the you know the process of shuffling
these things around
hey look I finally got the warrant so
now I got the warning that was the
warning I was talking about so let me
see how smart it is
yeah so I'm just really confused I don't
quite get I don't quite get it how it's
- yeah all right
so just to be clear this is what I would
expect if it sees a value if the
compiler sees a value it knows it can
convert to a float exactly I would
expect it to just accept that value and
that's what I assume it's doing here if
you use a value that it doesn't know
which in this case right
it maybe does or doesn't it depends on
how much analysis is going to do is it
going to look and see that test val is
set to five or not and the answer
appears to be not right because it looks
in it things I can't do this even though
this was possible right so it is
assuming that's an analysis problem so
it's going like oh I convert it I can
convert a constant to an f32 and I know
it's fine
but I can't just convert some random u3
to it and I didn't go to look to see
that that would actually work so you
know what I'm saying so this is what I
would have expected but what I don't
understand is why I can't put do that
same thing here so integral conversion
side it looks like this is not an error
or something yeah so somehow when it
does the integral promotion right it
doesn't think that either of these two
is a problem like no matter what it
decided to do here if it decided to
convert them both to integers or it gets
decided to convert them both to floats
there's a problem right in either case
it should have been giving you the same
warning it was giving me here because
all I did was the exact same operation
right here's test values as a float
here's test values as a float again
right so I don't really know and
furthermore I'm assuming I can provoke
the air nope so literally it just
doesn't think casting test value an f32
is
problem right up into the point where
you actually assign it I guess I am no
idea like I I can't even hazard a guess
as to why that's the case
good luck right so I have no idea what's
going on there I really couldn't tell
you I'm happy to write it this way if it
makes you feel more comfortable but
either way one should have been fine and
it's just moving that to an integer from
integer to a float which is fine but
let's talk about this part here so if I
force it to do this conversion and you
can see that it's complaining about it
which makes perfect sense if I force it
to do the conversion like so I just want
to show you why this is relevant in in
some way so when we actually go and look
at what happens here what you can see in
this particular case right if I inspect
the actual values that we get like you
know it that the CPU is actually going
to use if I look at each of these things
I don't know yeah there we go
well actually let me do this
so if we were to look at these actual
values what you can do is you can see
what they actually each gets set to and
what you can see here is the actual
mantissa of this thing is gonna be you
know right here and it's gonna be set
it's 24 bits right so I think usually
and so it's gonna be set in such a way
that we can actually directly encode
this value without any loss right so for
0 a at the head end of my float is going
to perfectly transpose to right so the
power of the thing the remainder of a
power of 2 is going to be like 1 because
the actual the actual power of 2 that
I'm trying to raise this thing to
presumably is 2 like right because I
want to write it here there we go
so I want to write this as something
that is raised to a power and then I
want to encode it as 1 point something
right so what I have to do is I first
have to figure out how would I represent
5 as something raised to a power right
and it's a little hard to read this way
because this is like I don't know
exactly how this is choosing to write
this out if that is already in power of
2 in binary form or hexadecimal form I
guess it might be
although I don't know I mean bear with
me here Romney was right this out I'm
not sure what I've never actually tried
this feature in remedy so I don't
actually know what it's doing but if I
have an integer right and I want to
represent five and I'm gonna put it into
a thing I know that I've got like a 1 a
2 and a 4 you know and some other things
that I can use to represent it so I'm
looking for values here that can add to
that right so I know I want to set the 1
and I want to set the 4 because 1 plus 4
equals 5 and I don't want to set the 2
so this is what I end up in with my
integer so the encoding for an integer
is 1 0 1 in binary and in fact I don't
know I might be able to get that to be
shown in remedy I guess not III guess
they don't I don't know if it has a
binary specifier but that's what this
would look like if we actually looked at
it in binary right so then if I want to
look at what the float encoding is gonna
be well the floating coding is the same
as like when you look at scientific
notation for a number I'm gonna have
something like you know 5e 3 or
something you know like the you know 12
times 10 to the 3rd or whatever right
it's this kind of notation but in you
know in human form we always use tens as
our base in floating-point form we use
twos as our base right so what we want
to do is represent this number as one
point something right times two to the
something you know I'm saying that's
what we're actually trying to represent
this as and the one point something is
binary right this is it's not one point
you know 2 3 4 whatever it's 1.01 101
right it's a binary floating-point
number not a decimal floating point
number right so if we look at what 5 has
to be in this particular circumstance
right then what we need to do is create
a number that will be like one point
blah that when we raise it to some power
of 2 it will slide it over
into the correct position right so this
is the number we actually wanted we want
101 point nothing right that's what
we're looking for in binary because we
just said that that's what it was so we
would expect to see in the mantissa 1.01
nothing times 2 to the power that will
slide this in the correct direction
right so we want this to go 1 2 over
right we want this 2 to the 2 right and
furthermore that 2 value as you might
expect that to value is encoded as in a
special way in that upper 8 bits right
the first bit is the sign bit and then
the other 7 or encoding is like what is
it's like 127 is 0 so you know or
something like this I don't remember the
exact encoding off the top of my head
right and so if you actually look at
what the value is that we got here right
if you correct here if you look at the
actual value that we got what we would
see is well a right is again I wish I
could show some binary because a is just
the accessible encoding of 10 right like
it's you know it's just you know because
we've consolidated XS but you can't see
what it is we go like 0 1 2 3 provides
any 9 10
right so the a is just the accessible
encoding of 10 and so I assume what's
going on here is that the the
floating-point value as we see it if you
look at how many zeros there are there's
1 2 3 4 5 and then the a right so this
is actually the part of the mantissa
starts at that 10 it's going to be 1 0
and that's totally wrong why I said that
10 value that's encoded there is encoded
in binary right so that 10 is going to
be the 8 plus the 2
which are set such that we get the 1:01
I believe although well that's not
actually true because the one is
implicit so actually that's not true
either I should continue drawing this
out I hate having to do this kind of
stuff stuff I'm horrible at all right
anyway let's let's continues through
because if it confuses me it probably
confuses plenty of people so anyway what
I was trying to say there is like okay
so we got the a value there right and
the a value as we know in binary right
that that equals ten in our language
right but we need to encode that into
binary so if you look at binary like I
just said before we've got one two four
eight and some things we don't need
anymore to make ten all we need to do to
make it a ten value here is we just need
a 2 and an 8 right we don't need the 1
in the 4 for anything because wouldn't
really help us at all right so we know
we've got that value which happens to be
exactly what we want right we've got a 1
0 1 and furthermore I guess we have it
in the position that we would want now
the thing that I don't super understand
is why like this gets into the like I
only pop into floating-point encodings
when I absolutely have to and so my
knowledge them is just super rusty and
bad but the thing I don't understand is
why we didn't only need to encode the 0
1 I'm not sure why we need to encode
this at all because to my mind it seems
like the mantissa is always expected to
be 1 and we just need this and then we
slide it up the 1 shouldn't have had to
have been encoded so I'm not sure why
we're seeing that and honestly it just
confuses me so we should probably look
at the floating-point encoding thing and
look at why because it doesn't make
sense
I don't quite get it right I don't quite
get why that would be the case like just
just being honest
I don't understand
yeah so I don't I don't quite get it I
don't know why it looks like that it's a
little confusing to me because I would
have thought that it would have been
coded the other way I simply floating
point in coding
[Music]
all right so if we look at single
precision floats there's eight bits of
exponent exactly like we said and 24
bits of the significand
let me take a quick look here
oh so that's a bad part of my remember
there so that explains part of it right
away actually so I was thinking that the
sign bit counted against the exponent it
doesn't the exponents eight bits of it's
eight bits of exponent after the sign
bit so there's nine bits taken up so
that actually is is probably where that
extra one is coming from right so if we
look the at maybe I'm wrong about that
too but we'll just see in a second so if
we look at what this value actually says
it is here address of test float like a
memory window here this yeah so if we
just look at the address of test float
there what you can see is it's like zero
four zero a zero zero zero zero right
although I guess it maybe is the other
way round because I'm assuming this is
going in byte order so it'd be zero zero
zero zero a zero four zero right so if
we encode what that or if we decode
rather what that value actually
represents there and I go back to my
little drawing board here right so if
we're looking at what 0 0 0 0 a 0 4 0 if
we look at what this actually decodes to
in binary right like each of these and I
probably should write these a little
further apart
right so if we look at what these
actually decode to well zero zero and
hexadecimal right each one of these is
four bits so this is just like binary
all zeros right same thing here so we
know this entire part of the binary
number is zero and how many bits do we
have here well this is 8 and this is 8
so the bottom 16 we know are zeros so
now we're looking at this part we know
we start with four zeros right and then
we have a witch like we said if we look
at what the bits actually are of like
one two four eight right then we know
that a wants to encode 10 and so we want
to encode a 0 here a 1 here of 0 here
and a 1 here so we're looking at that
value then we have four more zeros then
we have a 4 so that's just the third one
is set so we have a 0 a 0 a 1 and a 0
and this is the binary number we're
actually looking at now if we look at
where our exponent actually sits right
what I said is we have 24 bits of
mantissa but the first one is 1 that
means we only have 23 bits so I should
have known even when I said that that I
was wrong about the sign bit but either
way right so this is 16 bits and we have
23 total bits of significant to make a
24 bit mantissa with one assumed in the
upper place where would we be well
there's 4 more to get to 20 and then 23
3 more so it's 7 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 exactly
as I thought would be the answer right
so the one happens to be in the right
place in just this number 5 which was
what was screwing with us
but actually the 1 is implicit
we're not encoding it that's part of the
exponent which is here right so here is
that 5 encoded it's an implicit 1
followed by a 0 and a 1 and nothing else
right all the rest of this would have
been actual data that we could have used
to store actual information
but all the floating-point number is
it's the integer you wanted slid down
with a one at the head right so if you
want to encode integer as a floating
point value what's the highest bit
that's set you slide it down till that
one is gonna go into the implicit slot
which means well get rid of it and all
the rest of the bits just go into the
significant right they go in here okay
we get the implicit one that would have
gone here that means we can use this for
our exponent now what's our exponent
well it's the encoding of how far we had
to slide the number down we know we had
to slide it two places down right so we
want to encode the exponent of positive
two but lo and behold when we get down
here what we find and remember the sign
bit is also in here so this guy right
here that's the sign so obviously it's
zero because you know it's it's not
negative right
I believe that becomes set to one when
it's negative so obviously what we need
to do here is encode that to what the
problem is this is encoded the exponents
encoded in a super weird way because
they don't want to actually have to you
know I guess process it the way we might
normally think about it
I only know why they chose some of the
things you can go read about the history
by Triple E floating point
standardization is pretty interesting
actually but what you can see here is
they range from negative 126 to 127
right and it says here that negative 127
all zeros and 128 all ones are reserved
for special numbers but that means that
we start it's a it's a biased value it
doesn't it's not two's complement right
it's a biased value instead so zero
means negative 127 right not zero so
unlike two's complement we're actually
just shifting the range over and then it
just goes so what that means is that if
negative 127 is zero and we want to
encode two we need to add 127 and we're
gonna end up with what like 129 right
it's the value we actually need this
stuff in here makes sense and so how
would we encode 129 right what would we
actually do to encode
twenty-nine well again remember your
binary I want to encode 129 I have eight
bits to do it well 1 2 4 8 16 32 64 128
how do i encode 129 well thankfully
that's a little bit like shooting fish
in a barrel because it turns out that
128 is right there
so one added to 128 produces my 129 I
don't really have to go very far through
the list right so I know these will all
be zeros and this will be a 1 and this
will be a 1 and hey lo and behold what's
sitting right here exactly that value
right so that's how the actual encoding
process works but what that means if you
look at just literally that little
digression that we had there which I'm
really glad we did because again like I
say those I'm really rusty at some of
those sorts of things and they fall out
of my brain so it it helps me to go over
them it helps me as much as it helps you
because now I remember it more solidly
and maybe I won't forget it again for
another 5 years or something all right
so anyway what we know is that this
value has to be something reasonable
right I can't just shove any old value
in here and expect it to work because if
I make a value that's high enough that
it can't represent that number if it's
enough bits to represent the number
right then it won't work so let's see
what actually happens here when I write
5 and I set the breakpoint here what I
will see is when we go through what
happens to this number my round trip
value will be the same as that value
that I put in so when I look at the test
Val and I look at Boop's test Val and I
look at the round trip I get 5 in both
cases and that's because floating point
can represent the number 5
exactly right not an issue however ok if
I was to put in another number I might
not get that result now you might be
thinking well I just need to make one
big enough right so what if I just did
one that required 26 bits to represent
right surely that won't work and then
when it rounds just afloat it'll break
but action
not true and what you can see here is
when I actually run it that I shouldn't
unless I'm gonna be totally embarrassed
here and it's not correct but I should
get the same number back right and I do
the reason for this is because remember
we have this arbitrary exponent so
actually even though it takes 26 bits to
represent this number normally since I
have an exponent and there's only one
bit set right when I go to do this it
just encodes the entire number into the
exponent it just says oh it's the
exponents 20 what did I say the
exponents 26 right so all it has to do
is encode 26 here nothing here and it's
done right so that was very very simple
it actually isn't hard represent that
how do I break it all I've got to do is
just stick those bits far enough apart
so this is the real weakness of
floating-point values compared to
integers in this case integers can store
a number where there's a bit set 31
places away from another bit set right a
floating point value can only store a
number where there's a bit set and then
there's 23 places to the next bit set
right so if I spread out my bits by 26
places as I have here or 25 places you
might say or 24 depending on really
comes inside the outside right there's a
fence posting nominate your problem
there right but let's suppose I just
spread it out by some number of bits
clearly larger than the 23 that I could
use then when I do it now I'm in a bit
of trouble and what will happen is that
I won't get garbage right but I'll lose
the bits on the end so that bit that I
word in there right you see it it got
lopped off it can't remember what
happened down there right and so that's
the real weakness of floating point
values and so when you have implicit
conversions that go between float and
integer if you're going from the
direction integer to float you have to
worry about numbers that are spread
apart by more
and the significant the number of bits
right those numbers will get truncated
and that's the problem if you're going
from floating-point to integer then you
have to worry about where the actual
decimal point is because those were are
the bits that will get truncated right
if that makes sense and then the other
thing of course you have to worry about
is that the exponents really high
because the exponents really high then
the you know the that that number there
it needs to put it in like the 78th bit
but that isn't doesn't exist in
interested right so again hopefully that
gives you some appreciation for what's
going on here and why I don't think it
would be any problem to just put a 1
here because when that converts to
floating-point it's exact and there
isn't a difference really between
running and one and a 1.0 F in this
particular case I don't think why the
compiler is choosing to output the
warnings that it's outputting I don't
really know that seemed a little bit
weird to me and so I really couldn't
tell you why it shows the warnings it
did hopefully that helps let's go again
[Music]
hopefully that's that's enough of a
digression to there and for asking what
debugger it is it's remedy it's it's
this debugger it's 20 bucks it's you
know for all intents and purposes these
days for me it's it's has all the
features I actually need there's some
features that vigil studio has that it
doesn't have so but it's it basically
meets my needs and it is way better to
use in Visual Studio all of the crap
about Visual Studio is gone and you know
even just basic stuff like you know if
you come in here and you look at like
the light like this light probe in next
thing right so one thing that you'll
notice happens in Visual Studio these
days it's just absolutely drives me
insane
it's like when you actually run the
program the watch window doesn't update
for like a few seconds half the time
here you can just whale on the f5 key
and look like the number goes up like
that's actually usable I can just watch
if I wanted to get to one I could stop
on the one I want it you know it's just
like it's actually usable again it's one
executable no installer you just put it
on your machine and run it it saves your
window layout doesn't all get all
screwed up all the time it's nice and
fast it boots instantly you don't have
to wait with there's no splash screen
and so for me it's just like
for 20 bucks it's like the best 20 bucks
you'll ever spend if you debug programs
yes once in a while if you need some
specific feature like downloading stuff
from Microsoft symbol server or
something you might have to switch back
to visual studio debugger at that day
but for everything else you can pretty
much just use this and and I really
haven't had much problems with it and
new features are coming so someday maybe
I won't even have to add that caveat
it'll just be good enough that there's
no reason to ever switch to visual
studio because honestly visual studio is
not that good of a debugger it's not
windbg it has a small subset of the
features of windbg right so have you
tried clion if the bugger is awesome
somehow I doubt that
but no I haven't what's cly on so like
here's what I'll say I can pretty much
guarantee you this debugger isn't
awesome like the chances that this is
awesome seem so low to me but maybe it
is I don't know I don't know how to like
see is there like a survey to actually
like
man I guess I can search for certain
things and see
so I'm assuming I mean can you see the
assembly at the same time that you can
see the
the regular source
I mean unless I'm mistaken isn't this
saying that you can't even look at the
disassembly of your own code wonder if I
I feel like I tried this on Linux one
time did this actually ever get
implemented I mean yeah like okay so and
what about like the register view what
does that look like doesn't even have
one
I mean okay so just to be clear like I
could try it sometime
on stream just as an entertainment
exercise I suppose but like if you can't
step through assembly language as part
of your daily process automatically in
your own code with source highlighted at
the same time and you can't have a
register window then this is not a
serious debugger right this is I mean I
wouldn't even start trying it if it
can't do those things and my assumption
I think I tried this because I remember
trying a bunch of debuggers on Linux
trying to find one that was any good I
think I tried that one and I remember it
being so slow as to be almost like
unusable anyway so I'm guessing that
like no I'm guessing this debugger is so
far from awesome that it would not even
be it would not even get the a in
awesome let alone defining final E
I mean it definitely would not be a
replacement for remedy if it can't even
show like assembly language as I'm
debugging right cuz that's like critical
I don't want my assembly view to be only
when it can't find the source code
because assembly is critical to see all
the time like I look at it every couple
days right sometimes all day I'm looking
at just the assembly all right let's go
ahead and wind dance the long stream
today thank you everyone for joining me
for this on a handmade here at sometimes
our coding with you is always if you
would like to follow the series at home
you can always peer to the game on
handmade here org comes the source code
so you can play around with it I
you got all week to put the lighting in
actually if you want to start playing
around we just started the probe stuff I
love you back here next weekend probably
I think hopefully I'm assuming I'll be
back here next week to work on getting
that letting stuff implemented fully
until then have fun programming everyone
and I'll see you on the Internet take it
easy everybody