hello everyone welcome to handmade here
on the show recode complete game live on
stream yesterday we well we pretty much
finished are making our texture download
synchronous so that the opengl driver
would be happier about them and we had
one bug we kind of ended the stream we
didn't have time to go debug it we
finished typing it all in be note I'd
like it on the light rail today home
from climbing I think I may have thought
of what the bug was actually just popped
into my head for some reason so yeah
this might not take very long if I'm
right but if I'm wrong then we got to go
to bucket so I don't know which is going
to be maybe this will be quick maybe
it'll be not so quick day 33 26 so if
you want to follow along at home day 325
source code is the source code to be
reckoned with today here is mr. gamey
pants poo and if you remember where we
were yesterday I we had this sort of
call doubt the bottom of win32 handmade
where we were doing our you know our
stuff and what we did is we need to
begin ticket mutex and we grabbed out
the whole list of of texture operations
that were as waiting and I I do believe
i'm correct even just looking at the
code here i think i'm totally right
about with the bug was and then we had
our end ticket mutex we then took a look
to see if there were have been any
texture ups in there if there were we
went ahead and put the process them and
then put them on the free list so that
they could be reused and what we found
was and you know this is what why i
think my brain clued in to what the bug
was assuming am right and i think i am
what we found was a bunch of our
textures loaded but some of them did not
load right you can kind of see some of
those are just blank white textures so
the question is what happened there and
at the end of last dream i had said
something like well it looks like at
some point we stopped loading textures
but I don't think that's a anything to
it the ticket mutex because the ticket
mutex looks pretty solid well what I
forgot was we have a last pointer as
well I decided to retire texture ops in
series if i remember correctly and so
that texture q just make sure i'm not
crazy but that texture q i believe has a
first and yeah so you can see here we've
got a first and the last and we are only
resetting the first so all of our future
attempts to load textures were getting
stuck after a link that was already on
the free list right so just going to
keep sticking things on the free list
which is not going to get them loaded so
I believe that is really the only bug
that we had potentially if I'm right
like I said don't know if I am but yeah
that's just the way it is and the other
thing that I point out is when we get
this first out here we could get the
last out and then OpenGL manage textures
would not have to return us the last
because we already have the last so
really you know maybe it's a slightly
cleaner thing to do to say oh you know
don't don't bother keeping this you
don't need to because we know what the
last stop was so you're fine just let's
go ahead and get it here right so we get
the first text sharp get the last text
wrap and assuming there is a first text
wrap we then go ahead and do all our
stuff we can also show there's a last
one because because first when there has
to be a lasting right and off we go so
hey there you go that was the bug so
that's good news and now in theory or
texture downloads are all synchronous so
we should not be having the problems on
nvidia cards and stuff like that that we
were having before or occasionally with
a TI at least that's the theory now i
don't know how good these sex or
downloads are
and so I was interested to see in in the
in this cutscene here I'm interested to
know if we can maybe get some some
profiling I don't remember I guess we
didn't have there it is oh dear my
goodness why are we so slow with the why
are we so slow with frame profiling on
does anyone know that's that's crazy ha
look at that if we're in threads mode we
go very very fast if we're in frames
mode we go extremely slowly let's pause
right there and see what what's going on
if I pause there and look at the clocks
display oh it's our sprite craft sorting
yeah you know we need to just turn
sorting off for the debug display I feel
like we just need to tell it to don't
bother sorting because it's just a waste
of everyone's time and energy with all
these little guys here you know what I
mean they don't need to be sorted for
any particular reason and that builds
fright graph just ends up being very
very costly but what I suppose I could
do for the time being because we know
that our builds right craft code is very
debug code limited I could do this as
well but maybe I should go in while
we're at it since we don't have to do
the other debugging we were going to do
today maybe I should go in and and make
it so that that stuff doesn't get sorted
it's crazy how much different that speed
is there but anyway all right so you
know here's our here's our frame layout
and you can kind of see what most of the
time being spent is here in fact you can
kind of see in here we're spending most
of our time
doing that there most of the time is
that frame display
I just want to see what happens at the
changeover point if it's a problem frame
timewise
it does not appear to be so it appears
that the synchronous texture downloads
Oh nope there it is right there so we do
have one bad frame right you can see it
opengl render commands 72.6 milliseconds
how can we can't see that frame like how
come it doesn't I feel like this display
is bad like this is I need to fix this
display at some point because I want to
be able to see those single frame
hitches and I can't see them right now
so that that frame is not it's not doing
its job right
yes you can kind of see
hmm so I don't know what the best thing
to do there is I'm thinking maybe you
know that's a good argument for trying
to do some stuff with the pixel buffer
objects or something i'm not sure but
you can see what i'm worried about their
right we get this like frame hitch at
the time when the textures have to
download this is why i would have
preferred them to be downloading
asynchronously because I was worried
about what was going to happen there i'm
not sure what that's necessarily from
right and so what I'd like to do is I'd
like to get rid of that if i can because
everything else is nice and smooth but
that transition point is you know is not
and i think we're still giving the game
plenty of time to understand that stuff
so I mean the driver plant I understand
so I feel like maybe it's worth trying
to do the pixel buffer objects just to
see if we can reduce that transfer time
because yeah maybe you know having the
additional copy is a really big problem
for it or who knows exactly what's going
on there so it might be nice if we could
allocate those in you know in GPU space
or something like that so that we
wouldn't have that problem yeah
I don't know I don't know whether we
should do that now whether we should
wait till later for that it's really
hard to say but yeah so hopefully you
can see why I don't love that you know
it's it's difficult to see it happen but
it's definitely happening right like
it's it's not something we can really
perceive because it happens at the flip
so you don't see the hiccup happen per
se but it looks like it's definitely
there at least according to our timings
so unless there's something else that's
going on there I'm assuming that that's
a pretty clear indication of badness I
should probably just make a little
indicator to that just tells us when we
have a bad frame so we know like maybe
it'll just puts up a little thing that's
like hey there was a bad frame two
frames ago or something like that you
know a frame it's like an outlier in
terms of how long the frame took
something like this so there's certainly
stuff we could do there that would be
nice but anyway that is that is what
that is and the bug is the bug is gone
so this was our asynchronous texture
downloads being reliable so I'm gonna
say asynchronous texture downloads are
now synchronous but we get hiccups which
makes me grumpy so yeah I don't know
like I said when we want to dress up i
think we probably are going to want to
address at some point i'm not going to
probably not going to be super happy
with that it might be fine for in game
downloads right like when we're just
hopping around here and we because the
detectors are so small you know that i
could see that being okay you know those
download hits you maybe can just be
slipped into the frame without a problem
but i don't know
the those cutscene one's definitely
can't because they're just downloading
at UM texture that doesn't look like the
card is doing those as as promptly as
they could do them or maybe it just
needs more lead time I know but since
it's hitting on exactly that one frame I
think that suggests to me that the
driver is like waiting till we actually
do the GL text image to D and then it's
doing it right then right well no it has
to wait till the GL text image to D
obviously but it's not necessarily
overlapping it at that point or
something or just the the copy to to GPU
viewable memory maybe that's all of it
and if that was the case that's great
because that means that pixel buffer
objects would fix it but if not then
yeah then then not okay so let's see
here let me let me do what we were going
to do though and and sort of fix these
here I'm going to take a look at our
to-do list and put some things in here
frame view not showing bad frames
disabled sorting uh yeah I think that
should do it editing system what to do
about your graphics for entities my
purse extremes region the LA real
projections with solid console project
I'm project I think we kind of did a lot
of these but that's okay so I think the
only thing I wanted to put on here was
pixel buffer objects for texture
downloads all right yeah all right so
let's take a look at the clearing
compatibility situation void start to
Glu nth and vice versus would fixed
according to this so i guess this part
here is not a problem so it looks like
we're mostly talking about like the
printf and the function macros that are
the problem here and
yeah I don't know about the function
macro one but the sm printf s being not
supported and being something that
should be replaced that is something
that we could probably do pretty easily
I don't know how to get to this didn't
look like it oh maybe here let's see
that let's see some finis functions so
it looks like it's using v SN printf on
other functions so you know I guess we
have a couple different things we could
do here but I think since I don't really
want to use the c runtime library long
term I think probably what we would want
to do is be able to just do our own
printf or something you know just take a
look at what we're doing printf lies and
maybe try to replace it with with
something else so I'm going to take a
look and I'm just going to see
everywhere in the code where do we use a
printf or an S printf or things like
that so in the debug stuff what is it n
printf so it's SN printf s and so yeah
it looks like basically that's you know
the win32 code i I don't know why the
win32 code is using that to be honest
with you I don't even know what this is
handle debug cycle counters I that's not
something that we even use anymore get
let's get rid of that entirely um debug
draw vertical this is the sound debug
okay let's just let's get rid of all
this stuff I don't really want any of
this stuff in here anymore okay because
we want to put that in a regular debug
system
okay so let's try that again I'm going
to search for SN printf s and now we've
just got here test the play cursor right
cursor rid of those and stares another
SN printf again with that right cursor
in there what is this guy hammy internal
all right all right uh so yeah so now I
think we're just left with stuff in the
debug system and I guess we just have a
lot of s and printf esas through here
because we're just printing out various
values and so all of those are the same
then we've got ones that are kind of
yeah just used throughout and so I'm
assuming we know what we use here we
have % s % f % d % u sfu de
I think it's behind my head all right so
sfu d
and that's really it
so we would basically just need a printf
that handles SF you and d right that's
what we would need to do so we could if
we wanted to implement one of those and
and see how far we get right it probably
would be fine so strictly out of
curiosity if I eliminate these what
happens and you can see I've got a tu
TOI and SN printf s are basically the
the two things that actually get used
there so let's just assume that we get
rid of those and let's go ahead and try
to replicate them a toi is a lot easier
obviously then then anything else is
going to be I don't know where that hei
actually is oh dear
why does it say if pipe count equals one
and there's nothing there is that what's
supposed to be there tebow personname if
the pipe cap is one it does nothing if
the pipe count is that correct did I
accidentally delete what was there no
that's the way it's been isn't that a
little weird I'm curious to know I feel
like isn't this the sort of thing that
the github should be able to do for us I
you know I mean can can it can it look
back at handmade debug dot cpp and tell
me why we have a blank line there for no
reason apparently right here can it do
anything like that am I asking too much
is that am I just my way out of line
here
yeah not feeling great about it like hey
this is the line can you tell me I think
about the line please I guess not yeah
alright so I'm not going to try and
learn to use github because I really
want to learn to use github but point
being that's a little weird but whatevs
anyway we've got some functions that we
have to replace now a toi we actually
already wrote if i remember correctly
because inside our handmade open jail we
had to check for the version number and
so we have this sort of situation here
where when you know we wanted to do
essentially a toi it's this thing right
here so what i could do is like it
basically making a 2 I in here that's
like a like a shared version of a 2 i
right that's like s32 from a skeezy or
whatever right or maybe just from Z
sitting right and so you pass in your a
little at there and it does exactly what
it does and then it returns the result
so opengl parse number we can actually
make that just be a generic function now
and then in this place where we were
doing a 2 I I can just do so2 from Z and
get the line number back so I think that
one's fine the sm print deaths are going
to be a little bit more sort of involved
the reason for that is that while it
probably won't be too hard to do a
crappy numerical output thing for % d
you and obviously % s is trivial % f is
like rocket science trying to print a
floating point number if I remember
correctly really recently there was like
a new way of doing it that wasn't
heinous and maybe I'll try to dig up
that paper so we can use it but like
doing a % f print is like insane or was
insane and I'm hoping I'm crossing my
fingers that they simplify now but like
printing a floating point number is an
epic disaster I just we'll get to that
when we get to it but just trust me for
now real bad roll roll bad so let's
pretend we're going to have one of these
here and we'll just have a you know you
know a format string function or
whatever and we'll have like the sort of
death size dest format string and you
know proportional whatever something
like that and then we can also have a
separate version a format string list or
something which is the one will probably
actually call and I'll talk a little bit
about how these guys work I think this
is like it VAR d list or something like
this I don't remember how these guys go
but anyway so we'd want to call format
string with death scythe dest format and
the dot in place of our SN printf and so
yeah like
this gets a little bit into the vagaries
of the C and C++ default calling
convention and i'll go ahead and sort of
give you a little bit of a sort of a
light sort of introduction into how
these guys work well you know what let
me actually do it this way because I
think this might be a little more
interesting to see but i'll give you a
little background on it and then we'll
get that part of it going and then we'll
see how far we can get in reading the
format string so uh where's my wintered
there it is this is my like little EE
project that I made for searching for
things yes prepare the solution keep on
preparing that solution good job so if I
want to do a VA start here and I want to
go to the definition of the okay the
package server has stopped working well
that seems bad all right so anyway these
guys VA start VAR GA end which will be
using and you'll see those those are
defined to go to this these sort of
interim ackles which I believe get
redefined yet again in here but anyway
here's the actual macros themselves and
you can kind of see what they're doing
so this doesn't really have to be a
mystery I'll cut and paste these guys
out so you can sort of see what's
happening here but hopefully it'll it'll
make a little more sense as I walk
through it because it's actually it's
not that mystical and it's kind of
interesting to see how this stuff ends
up working anyway that address of I'd
like to get as well where are you go to
definition there you are scrap that out
copy and actually you know what since I
hate C++ let's actually use the non C++
way
there we go uh so let's talk about this
what we have to do here before I dive
into it and let me give you a little bit
of a background on what's going on here
with variable argument list stuff so as
you know here on day 3 26 oops 306 as
you know variable are twists normally
when we call a function and we've talked
about this a bunch of times we'll see a
function signature and it looks
something like int foo you know int X
right and then we've got some stuff in
here and this stuff uses X right and so
we've talked about this before where we
sort of imagine because we you know this
the sea specification doesn't really
necessarily say very much about how the
stack is supposed to be allocated or
moved around or any of that sort of
stuff necessarily but we do know a few
things but what we know abstractly in
terms of what's happening is just that
there is such a thing as the program
stack which is a bunch of memory that is
used and as you enter functions things
get pushed onto the stack and as you
exit function they get pushed off and i
believe the stack grows Down Goes
negatively on x64 if I remember
correctly so you know as you push stuff
on you're going down you know lower down
the stack as opposed to up right in our
memory arenas we push on to them so our
addresses get higher I believe the
program goes down don't quote me on that
it's one of those things I never
remember which way because I don't
program in a semi language if you very
much simulator which you would remember
since you'd be doing it all the time
anyway so what ends up happening when
you call a function right is the
parameter for the function assuming that
it fits in a register will just stay in
the register right so you know
if it can if it can pass the values to
foo in a register than it will but you
can imagine having stuff that's too big
for registers like maybe this passes a
whole struct like there's a struct bar
or something that needs to get past it's
got a ton of stuff in it you know you
could imagine there being stuff that you
can't fit and of course when you can't
fit something then it needs to be pushed
on to the stack and so what ends up
happening is you know you push on say
this bar here that happened that goes on
there and if there was another Barbie
you know that would go on there as well
you just kind of go on there when this
function executes its going to use these
locations where those things were pushed
to do work on a and B and whatever and
then when it's done it's going to pop
the stack back to hear right so you
basically have this this proud and
execution is every time you call into
something the stack is growing and then
every time you return from something to
stack shrinks right and that's how you
know those calls sort of work so what
happens in a variable argument list
function is actually very simple what
happens is we have a function like int
foo in X but then instead of specifying
what comes after the in X we just know
that there's some more functions right
I'm sorry some more parameters so what
happens is at the call site to foo these
extra parameters just get pushed on to
the stack just like ABCD whatever they
just get pushed on right then when the
function returns they will get cleaned
up usually by the caller since the
caller knows how many pushed on it will
actually do the fix-up to pop them off
in at least in the old days I don't
really know the x64 ABI works I haven't
looked at it in detail myself so i'm not
sure but somebody who knows how many
things got pushed on will make sure that
it moves the stack pointer back to where
it should be right and so when you
actually do this sitting on the stack or
these are is all this data that gap
pushed on based on how many parameters
you specified like with a printf you
know you passed by the format string and
then you put as many things on the end
as you want well
each one of those gets pushed on the
stack but now the question is how does
the actual function get them off of the
stack right because we know that
typically we just refer to things by
name and the compiler is silently every
time we talk about X or a or b in that
function foo it just knows where the
offset is in the stack but since it
there is no function signature here we
just know there's a bunch of random
arguments that nobody knows what they
are we can't refer to them by name and
the compiler doesn't know where they are
it just knows Dave some sequence of them
stuffed on the stack so that's where the
macros for VA you know start VA and etc
there are these macros that the C
library provides which basically involve
taking the address of the parameters
here which I believe are then required
like in a ver arms function I believe
the compiler is then required not to
pass the final named argument in a
register I think it's required to pass
it on the stack so that it knows where
it is I think that's my recollection but
basically what these macros do is they
use the address of the last named
variable to know where the next name
variable is going to be and then you
just say exactly like we do with like
our raw memory stuff you just say what
you think it should be and it will
advance by that much right so if I think
there's going to be an integer there it
will advance the integer and it's just
hopes I'm right and so that's where like
the format string of printf comes in for
example that format string of printf is
just a string that printf purses and
when it sees something like % d it knows
to advance one integers worth of space
on the stack and pull that off as an
integer right so all these very large
things are doing is they're walking the
stack like regular memory just like we
do and they're using the format string
to figure out how big and of what type
the thing on the stack in that location
is right so it's very very similar to
what we do with our push truck stuff
right only this case it's using a stray
and it's parsing the string so we just
need to do exactly that and off we go
now you can see here right exactly how
these work they work exactly like I just
said the ver argh start part of things
you can see it takes the address of
whatever the function the whatever the
variable is that you give it and the
variable you give it has to be the last
one right so it has to be this one right
here because like I said it's going to
look after it and then it adds however
big that thing is because it needs to
skip over it now you'll notice it
doesn't use size' but it rather uses in
size of and what does in size of do well
in size of rounds the size of that thing
up to the nearest integer boundary right
this is plus you can see it doing it
here it's rounding up right to the size
of the nearest ensure the reason for
that is because that's the speck of vert
ards the sea spec says ver arms are
passed in size chunks that are integer
with right so even if you're only going
to pass one bite it still uses an inch
worth of space on the stack for it I
don't know why it's SPECT that way it
just is right and to be honest I think
that's not compiler specific I think
that might actually just literally be in
the sea spec that it is incised I just I
just think that's true but don't quote
me on that maybe it is compressor but I
think that's just actually do it
specified so that's it right and you can
see how you when you do see our TV are
great so see start it's like getting the
address to the first one VA argh is
pulling off one argument and you pass
what the type is and you can see it
looks just like our push struct right
we're going to cast to that type and
we're going to in here say advanced by
however big that type has to be and and
like take wherever the stack is we're
going to move it that far we're going to
advance and we're going to return
wherever we were before because that's
you know that's where the thing actually
was so this is just shorthand for like
hey I need to advance this pointer for
words
by the size and thank consumed but hey
the user wants to get back where i was
before so I'm just going to subtract
that out you know to give them the right
return by VA n doesn't really do
anything it's it's really just I think
some kind of a tidy-up thing in case it
needed to reserve something for I mean
maybe some compiler implementations need
to do something that would have to free
something here or something like that I
don't know so you're supposed to call VA
n but it doesn't do anything not on msvc
anyway and I don't think on llvm either
but on some compiler somewhere it might
or maybe I'm like a different platform
all right so anyway if we go ahead and
do these guys we don't actually need to
keep these here we can use like VA start
VA or NVA end and I guess what I also
want to point is I'm doing this in two
parts and the reason for that is I would
like to be able to call format string
with a ver args function or from
somebody who who themselves was a ver
artists function and already got the
list right so really the VA start VA end
are going to be here and they're going
to sort of create the list right this is
our our list like so so these guys their
wives did that okay these guys create
the list and then just we'll just call a
function
return the result and then this format
string list right here is the guy who
will do all the work he has the arglist
so he's going to pull off the things in
the yard list as he understands what
they should do right okay so what we
want to do now is we want to you know
loop over these characters and I'm going
to consume different numbers of them so
you know honestly I'll probably just do
this be that way so what we're going to
do here is we're going to take a look at
what the what the value tells us right
and in this case I think I might not
really need a switch yet right probably
what I want to do first is just say you
know if at equals percent then I know
that I have to do some sort of parsing
right and if it doesn't then I know I'm
just retiring a regular character so I
want to just try to get this started in
a very basic way so what I'm going to do
first is I'm going to try and just make
something that just rights to the buffer
and it strips out just these the
percents right so it's not going to do
any conversions yet so what I want to do
for this is I'm going to add the utility
thing here that's like a you know format
desk or something like that and format
desk is going to have a size and a desk
pointer something like that so that i
can say like format dust dust and you
know maybe something like this
and that's just so I can keep track of
how much space i have and where I am in
the destination because that just makes
it a lot easier for me right then when
I'm done it's pretty easy to see how
much space i actually used because all i
have to do is say well wherever i ended
up minus wherever i started is how much
i used right so that's that's pretty
basic now what I would like to do in all
cases also is say you know assuming that
the destination you know if desk dot
size assuming that there is any
destination at all I want to make sure
that if I run out of space I always null
terminate so what I want to do is at the
end of everything i want to say if there
is sized remaining right then i want a
desk and then maybe i'll make that a
gnat if their size remaining then I want
to know terminate if there isn't any
space remaining then I want to that's
not what I wanted if there isn't any
space remaining then I'm going to
overwrite whatever the the final
character was with a zero because I
never want to not have a null terminator
at the end so yeah if there is space
remaining we'll just null terminate if
there isn't space remaining we overwrite
the last character with an L and we know
that we can always override the previous
character because we know we always have
at least some size to begin with so
there's no way we can ever have a fault
there by going before the buffer so when
are we coming here I'm just going to go
ahead and say okay you know i'm going to
output a care here so i'll just say like
out care dest
whatever the character actually is and
this will just be a really simple
function again not we're not going for
speed here certainly but all this does
is say okay if nest sighs this size is
minus dust at this plus equals value
right so all I'm doing there is just
putting characters into the output
buffer so that's really all I wanted to
do at first and i'd like to go ahead and
get that stuff working before we try to
do any of the vert argh stuff and then
inside here while we're looping through
at I you know actually I guess I could
write this a little more succinctly like
so and did here i'm just going to
advance it without doing anything so now
we can get rid of all this stuff that
was just there for example just to let
you know what's going on and so now we
should need what is it varargs dot h
think yeah there we go too many actual
parameters for macro VA arc okay
VA start i should say definition go to
definition but but but that's how many
they're supposed to be which is to write
am i missing something
I must be missing something well let's
look here our pointer previous / am hmm
how many parameters did you think there
should be
oh you know what I just realized I
included the run function varargs is the
old one standard args is the new one
that's probably why it's probably a
different macro all right so now all we
have to do and by the way when we
finally get rid of the CRT as well we're
going to have to copy and paste
essentially those there are macros
ourselves because you have to have them
right so that has to be / compiler
eventually but we'll only need those we
won't need the whole printf right
because we're implementing the printf
ourselves anyway so SN printf is now our
format string call and we can get rid of
this weird dance we had to do where we
had to pass sighs twice which I don't
really understand why right but that's
what it actually should look at look
like now you mean conversion from size t
to you 32 I'm going to go ahead and say
we'll let format string just to make it
easier on ourselves will let format
string take a full size there there's no
real reason for us not to so we could
just let it take memory size stuff and
that's fine let's see from institute for
to you 32 wait didn't finish yeah areas
so yeah so now i just kind of have to go
through here and i'm going to switch the
other one so my head's not behind it but
i'm just going to loop through these
guys and change them to format string so
there's format string and sort of get
rid of all this ugliness it's like much
nicer this way too because now we don't
have these weird SN printf nonsense
things that it wanted us to do which is
nice
yeah you know what's interesting is we
could also make this more systemic if we
wanted to the app the whole app plus
thing we could actually just make that
be our own sort of string out thing
because we already have that desk one
right that I made for the actual printf
function itself so we could actually if
we wanted to be mr. reusing pants we
could actually just just repurpose that
for this as well we can kind of see
what's happening here we could totally
do that so maybe that's a cool idea as
well right a lot of times you can just
sort of see stuff like that you know you
can just sort of see like oh okay you
know I see what this this function is
doing it's just concatenating a bunch of
things together and that's sort of what
I needed to do inside the other function
as well to prevent me from writing off
the end of the string potentially and so
maybe I just make a little thing a
little cursor like thing that I can just
use to stream out strings and maybe
that's really cool you know who knows
maybe it's not I don't know I really
don't
sorry this is a bit boring now coming up
over my my own typing area that's not
polite mr. notice let's not polite it
all again nothing happening here really
than me just like rearranging getting
rid of the cruft that was in there from
using SN printf which is have a stupid
function I don't even really know what
the point of it is i'm not sure what the
emphasis was for it taking two sizes
alright what else we got almost there
again like sometimes it wanted two sizes
and sometimes it wanted one size
depending on like the type of the thing
we're passing or something even weirder
than that i remember it was just super
strange
okay so I think now we actually have
everything ready the actual size of this
guy I guess we'll return in um in this
case is just going to be you know
wherever we started versus wherever we
ended up right so this is where the last
right was this is where we do you think
this is where we began so that's really
all we should have to return there does
not have an overloaded operator right
you are sir let's see format string list
death sighs desta net format arglist
initializing conversion you move to you
32 where is the conversion ah there it
is okay
so in theory we now have jump back to
handmade we now have our own printf
happening but well first of all we have
a bug obviously but we've got no actual
formatting happening right now what's
the problem here my appt pointer is no
how did my at pointer become no let's
find out
so here's the desk Destin it is null
death scythe blue
what did I do so I guess it's okay to
pass null here or something what
happened there buffer at plus equals
format string how did that end up
getting destroyed I wonder well let's
find out if I can
alright so we've got our at their hope
don't care about that
looks like cases got a typo so we start
with the format string we loop through
the format string till we get to a zero
we know terminate which seems reasonable
and then the result that we return is
wherever we ended up my ass where we
started all right let's take a look at
that in action and so what am i passing
here and minus at at loop in there just
size is 256 dust is there so we've got
des a 26 deaths in it is what you expect
we're just going to increment at four
words we're going to do a an output of
that wherever this value is assuming
that there is sized left we're going to
subtract it and then we're going to
write to wherever this guy was pointing
whatever that value is right
and that seems reasonable
aah yeah there's a nice type of for you
well it's been a slow night there we go
and so I think hopefully that's all for
our are typos I think we should now be
printing things out just without any
without any actual formatting right so
all of our stuff is just essentially the
format strings and that's it but off we
go so that's a reasonable scaffold for
it and basically what we have to do now
is implement the actual formatting in
here which like I said is not too hard
for everything except for f % f is just
a real real bad if that makes sense so
I'll go ahead and go to the QA and we'll
see what everyone's queues and azar
pseudonym 73 printing floating-point
numbers a faster always correct method
this does look like the paper i was
thinking of yes this in fact definitely
does yeah so you know maybe we have to
read through this i have not implemented
myself maybe we have to read this and
implement it because we don't really
have if there's no easy way to print a
float and have it be right there's an
easy way to print a float and really
sloppily but
a canoe kills short recap of what we've
done today oh we just started replacing
SN printf and the reason for that is
just so that we won't be relying on as
much of the sea runtime library where
it's slowly kind of getting at the city
one time every so we'll be able to
compile on Linux easier as well this
Isaac blame in github lets you see the
change history okay I remember seeing a
blame button but i'll look for one
popcorn says what does negative 1 in
desktop 80 negative 1 do well remember
bracket syntax in C is just the same as
pointer arithmetic essentially so all
that means is it goes back one element
of whatever desk at is pointing at so
since death that is putting it
characters it goes back one element so
it's the it's pointing to the element
before the one that that's actually
pointing at you can stick any number in
here you want 17 negative 50 whatever
and it will basically move by that
number times the size of whatever the
pointer is pointing to and then that is
the thing you'll be addressing
I want to start getting into this series
is there a way to easily compile run
this code on Mac OS X so I don't
maintain a Mac a sport because I've said
many times we're not going to port till
the end of the series but because it's
just a lot of work involved in
maintaining a port if you're sort of
showing how to bring the platform layers
up and you're changing how things work
and so on so I don't want to do that
till we finished everything and are just
doing a pork basically but other people
have so if you've pre-ordered the game
and so and you have access to the
private github there's people who have
put mac up like sdl ports and stuff up
on there that you can look at there's
also a some ones that aren't up to date
some older ones like handmade penguin
that are up to date for that are sdl
ports but yeah so people other people
have made mac US exports but that's not
something that that i will be doing
until much later on the series
no more questions
all right i am going to wrap it up then
alright thanks everyone for joining me
for that sort of handmade here it's been
a pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along the
series at home you can always po2 the
game on handmade here it comes the
source code so you can play around with
it we also have a forum site and go
through when asked questions a patreon
page philosopher at the video series a
schedule bot that tweets the schedule at
you and an episode guide featuring past
episodes you can take a look at if you
are trying to catch up with old parts of
this series that's about it for today
and this is the last episode of the week
I will be back here next week for the
last few episodes before I am going to
have to be gone on vacation for a little
while so until then oh how long is right
because breaks going to be a while at
least a couple weeks until I'm back so
there'll be a bit of a break but yeah
there'll be there'll be some streams
next week so that's I'll be back here
before before break that's about it I
hope to see you guys next week for the
last few strings for a break until then
have fun programming I'll see you guys
on the internet take these everyone