hello everyone and welcome handmade hero
show Rico to complete-game live on
stream we are going to put our cap heads
on our cap bodies today which is a very
important thing to do we pretty much did
all the work for it and editing it and
we even have like a fairly reasonable
editor now that draws it and so what we
want to do now is just actually
implement the skeletal snapping stuff
inside the entity system this is not
particularly difficult but it is
something that we kind of to think
through a little bit and oops it's not
what I wanted
and prj file and we have to work on
scaling a little bit as well so we want
to have a more coherent way of tracking
scaling through the pipeline if you
don't really do right now and so that's
another thing that we'd like to make
sure we have correct let me show you
what we're where we're at right now so
if we want to right we can click on
different people like for example this
cat here and it actually when we click
it shows us all of the possible things
that were under the cursor at that point
in depth order so for example if we
click on the cat it is true that there's
two pieces of the cat right there's the
head and the body and it's not clear
which one of them we were trying to edit
because they kind of like stamp on top
of each other and so we implemented this
nice little interface here so we can
actually pick which one we wanted to
actually interact with and similarly we
can get like the ground tile under the
cat if we want to so it really makes it
easier to edit there what we do here
when we get alignment points in this
case let me just make this bigger here
case right we can add them and we can
like adjust them and so on right like
this we can add new ones and so what
we'd like to be able to do is we'd like
to be able to actually you know go on to
this what we want to do is go on to like
the body here we want to add an
alignment point like that right and then
we want to switch back to the head and
set like it's alignment point like that
and then we want those two things to
snap together so that like basically the
green point here will snap to the red
point here which is like the base point
for this
for this element right and so that's all
we really need to implement they're
pretty basic then from there we want to
move on to dealing with these scaling
values and what these things are is
their relative scales that allow us to
say when two things snap together how
they should scale on top of each other
and so for example if you know you want
this if you wanted cat bodies to have
small cat heads for some reason you
could say you know everything that snaps
on to this is half height or something
right you know what I mean
and that's just a way of us giving
ourselves some giving our sense of
flexibility of how we refer to different
elements of our world and we need to
think that through a little bit because
if we don't pick it carefully we'll end
up doing a lot more work than we have to
do what's the point of that well the
point of that is suppose we want hats in
the game which players can wear we want
casts to be able to wear them - well cat
heads are smaller than human heads right
so there's multiple ways that we can
look at that we could say that
everything in the world has a uniform
scale and then cat heads are themselves
set to be smaller or cat bodies are set
to be smaller so basically everything is
a uniform size like all animals are
uniform size right and then we shrink
them down to be the size that they are
so that anything gets put on them is
naturally shrunken down right another
way to do it is to say that everything
is its actual size at scale 1.0 so cats
are just naturally smaller and then when
you snap a hat on them the attach point
for hats on cats is set to be half the
size you know of right the the scaling
value on the attach point is set to half
so that only when you put a hat on a cat
does it get the 50% scaling and it's not
the whole cat that scaled down 50% from
a size that's you know larger than a
normal cat you can see why there's
complexity there and there isn't a right
or wrong
but there is a way that will minimize
work and so in some sense that becomes
the right way for us because what we're
looking for is to minimize the amount of
busy work we have to do setting like
special parameters to make sure that
things that go on cats are scaled
properly versus things that go on humans
versus things that go on monsters versus
things that fall on the ground you would
like as much as possible to set as few
of information points as possible it
just saves you work and so we do have a
right answer for us even though there's
no it's not objectively right but
subjectively from the standpoint of
someone who doesn't want to do extra
specification there it sure seems like
there's a good argument to be made for
that that answer which eliminates them
the majority of the work so we'll be
gunning for that but who knows we'll get
there we'll certainly try to figure out
what it is and we'll you know start with
what we think is our best guess and
we'll see hopefully we're right so now
if we go back let's take a quick look
here at our like is this looks like this
is like off-center a little bit was that
off-center a little bit maybe it wasn't
it was just a trick of the eye I can't
quite tell no I guess it wasn't no so
anyway um looking at this code what we
need to do is right now we don't
actually have any idea in most of these
cases we don't really know where what
the transforms are for our various for
the various pieces that we're working
with here right and so just to give you
some perspective on what's going on each
of those points like alignment points
their relative to the object in question
right so if I say that I have an
alignment point and it's defined with a
certain set of parameters those
parameters are interpreted inside the
shape of the thing that they're defined
on so if I talk about the cat body and I
talk about the location of alignment
point on the cat body it is assumed that
that alignment point right will move and
scale and
form along with the cat body this
creates a problem for us actually
because what happens is we cannot store
you know there could be up to 12 we have
a limit right now and you know we could
even increase this limit so this is just
what we randomly picked but we could
have picked anything we have some number
of alignment points right now you can
have up to 12 of them when we process
each individual piece in an articulated
body like that cat where it's got two
pieces when we process say the body
piece what we find is that there are 12
alignment points up to 12 alignment
points that could be defined on that cat
we don't want to have to transform all
12 alignment points and store all 12
alignment points so that when we go to
process the next thing if we see that
it's supposed to connect to one of them
we can go grab what it is right because
imagine later we find twelves not enough
we go to 16 we go to 32 that number is a
flexible number we're multiplying the
amount of work we have to do on each
piece by that number
because now we have to store and compute
all those points so what we'd rather do
is compute those points on demand right
because only one or two other things is
gonna really be snapping to that at any
given time and so what we want to do is
only compute those points that actually
have something attached to them going
forward in order to do that we need to
delay the computation which means we
need to reach back right to previous
pieces and say where would this
alignment point have been how do we
compute at the time right so what we
need to store is the basis in which we
would interpret those alignment points
which are two axes the X and the y axes
and a base at like a origin point right
one way we can store them is em four by
fours we don't actually need an EM four
by four we could just do three three
element vectors so it's really
more like this right or we could say
which may be more intuitive and so we
just need to store these values as we go
through the pieces into a temporary
array which can then be used to look
them up and once we can look those up we
can reinterpret any attachment point in
that space and then provide the
alignment information that we need now
fortunately for us we kind of already
know what those are if we go looking
inside the asset renderer part of things
here what you can see is we have a lot
of stuff that's used for pushing
information on and you can see the
computations happening here so inside
this push bitmap call here that's you
know the upright one for example this
one right here where we're doing all of
this work you can see that what we
really want to start to do is extract
that work outside so we want to turn
these into utilities that then get
passed down and we kind of knew that to
begin with when we abstracted the
renderer you notice we shoved this stuff
into asset rendering why it's because
it's all handmade hero specific it's not
stuff you would use outside of handmade
hero because it's all very special
purpose to how handmade here has chosen
to represent its world its axes its idea
of what sprites do and how they are
formed it's not really specific to the
renderer per se because the renderer
doesn't actually care you could put any
old quads through the renderer the
renderer is just thinking about things
in terms of textured quads that it will
then do per pixel sorting on an output
right so you know our our understanding
here is is really mostly about this
whole file being stuff the tomato stew
probably wants to be broken up into
utility routines and for this very
reason because a lot of the information
that's computed inside here in the
process of running the spry
is actually information we need for
other reasons and furthermore our pickin
procedure right so like if you look at
how we're doing our ray intersects box
that right now is and and also when we
render it like here you can notice that
that's really imprecise right now right
so right now like this when I'm picking
is perfectly accurate right not only
does it highlight exactly the cube but
it also picks perfectly so even like one
pixel over and you get the right answer
because that was 100% accurate right the
reason for that is we have an exact 3d
shape so we could be exact here we don't
have any idea what's going on and so we
had to just pick a general region and
not only did we have to pick a general
region but we didn't even know they're
really the sizes of these things because
we just know we don't even know what
their actual dimensions were the reason
for that is because we're a lot of that
was happening in here and we couldn't
see it so as we move it out we can also
tighten those bounds because we'll have
actual information about exactly what we
rendered for our quad which would give
us the ability to specify a box more
succinctly will it be perfect no because
it's still a bitmap that's getting drawn
in there and we don't want to do per
pixel testing for any particular reason
here it's not worth it for our purposes
but week certainly can be better than we
were right now but we intentionally
didn't do that when we when we were just
writing the basic routine for the very
reason that we didn't have easy access
to the values now we'll be able to get
those values as well which is nicer
right so that's where we're at right now
what we want to do here is say alright
when we're doing our push bit madness
let's figure out how we could sort of
split this information off and have more
like a more coherent way of pushing this
information for example we could have
all of this computation be something
that computes its information into a
struct and then you could just use that
struct to call a more explicit function
and that way you don't have to worry
about who gets access to this stuff you
could just call it and then anyone who
wants to use it could use it without it
being
to do just something that's passed
forward into the push quad right so
that's what we want to do here so moving
through here if we look at just trying
to find some basics of what we probably
want to do our get bitmap dim call right
this sort of stuff again this all could
sort of be disaggregated at this point
and you know maybe it should be if we
look at how all of this stuff is getting
used I'm gonna pop over to the renderer
you know and oops not that I'm gonna pop
over to the renderer here and if you
look at our if you look at our push
breitkopf you can see that this is
probably all the information that you
really needed to push the sprite on
right and furthermore you know push quad
would have done it you know what I mean
so you know you could imagine us just
call like computing this stuff and then
just having a push quad that actually
you know puts this information into the
into the render into the render state
right and so just thinking it through
you know I can kind of see where all
this is headed right like eventually
like like let's just look at how this is
working right you can see how expensive
and unnecessary a lot of this stuff is
so we say like get current quads and we
give it a number that we want to pass
but you know really what we want to
probably do is we probably just want to
do a thing where we open a quad set and
we just keep pushing quads on it and and
then every time we would overflow it
just adds more and in amortized lots
work we could write directly into that
area and so just thinking it through I
see where this is headed like it's very
clear where the architecture wants to go
whether we want to get there today or
not is another question
but I can definitely see where it wants
to go and so if I go to the push quad
call here you know here's that push quad
call you can see that really what we
want to do in this case is we want to
probably separate these things out we
want to probably special separate
special texture from non special texture
and what we would like to do is all of
this stuff right where we're pushing
these quads on can really be rolled back
out into the actual direct calls so in
here where we're looping all the pieces
this stuff could be filled out right in
line so as we push those quads on each
of these things that does a quad push
could just do that right and so much
work would be saved right so much work
would be saved there because in a lot of
these cases all look a lot more stuff is
known than it then needed like a lot of
stuff that's getting done every time
when it goes to do the reservation this
call right here could be amortized
dramatically right and so I this can get
a lot better and I'll just go ahead and
so we kind of know that that's coming
and so what I think I'd like to do is
you know take ours the steps that we're
taking I think we want to take them in
that direction you know what I mean
so I don't know do we have a hand made
asset rendering H right now we don't and
I don't do that we necessarily want one
either because we could just say that
that properties things probably should
live in the renderer and so what I want
to do here is say look let's temporarily
let let's like try to make this a little
more thoughtful about the way that we're
actually making this flow and let's look
inside the renderer at how that push
quad call wants to actually work like
what does it actually write into the
stream you know what I mean and so if
you look at what it's writing into the
stream it needs to get and you can even
see this here like there's some there's
some stuff that happens here that this
probably really shouldn't be happening
inside push quad this right here right
that should probably be happening
outside as well the inverse UV part
should really probably not be happening
here you know what I mean because that
information is more is better handled
outside you know what I mean like you
know you you don't really need to be
doing this inversion and tight side here
all the time because the person outside
if they actually cared could have done
it themselves there's a lot of reasons
why you probably don't want to in here
we could push that out so you know just
looking at how the push quad thing works
you can see in here it's pretty basic
the way that it pushes this stuff in I'd
like to just make it so that we fill
these things out as part of some utility
thing and then we can redirect those
utilities that fill them out to be
things that fill out the stream directly
when we get the render into that
position okay so what I want to do here
is say all right let's pretend
that what we actually have so you know
in in the in the render itself I'm gonna
basically define like an output type
here and I'll just call it and you know
I we could make another we could make
another place for this stuff to live
like handmade geometry or handmade like
rendered geometry or something like this
where you know the render itself doesn't
really care if you use this stuff it
just it's gonna be utility functions
that help you make the geometry that
you're trying to make you know and so
inside handmade render geometry th we
could put these functions that we want
you know whatever they are and here you
know right quad or something you know
whatever it is I'm not sure we'll talk
about that in a second but we can put
those in here so we know like they don't
they're not wedded to the render in any
way like you could use the render
without using these if you wanted to but
they are available for you to use to
make it easier right and so it's just
sort of like a utility library for that
kind of rendering and then when we look
you know this basically this exact
process that's happening all of this can
sort of be wrapped up into a routine and
so inside you know this system we could
say well we know we've got these
vertices right textured vertices and we
know that we we want to write those to a
particular location perhaps right so
we've got like a vertex a pointer to
where we're going to write the vertex is
right and then we've got indices that
we're going to write out here right and
those are you six that's a you 16
pointer right there it is and so we can
define like a an output system here and
furthermore we could almost we could
even sort of bacon the notion that
there's requesting happening there but
this is basically just an output stream
right so this is like I don't know a
quat output or I don't know what we want
to call this this is like geometry
output right and so what we could do is
just have one of these and we can just
write quads to it and we will have
different ways of producing that those
quad writes but you don't have to call
through tons of functions and do
anything you can get your pointers first
and then just do your stream out right
so if we wanted to write a quad then you
can see like okay so one way is to just
write the quad direct and that's you
would pass the all of the information
right and then it would output this
pattern you know what I mean so if we
want to light index I think and texture
index art there's only one of them and
then the other things there's four of
them you know what I mean so when we
look at what push quad gives us if we
wanted to do a right quad function what
we would have is we have for each of
these we've got the UVs I don't know
yeah we've got the UVs
and we've got the color right and those
are you thirty twos the emissions don't
I don't know why the emission is in
there cuz that's not I'm not sure what
that's doing there if the emission
probably doesn't still need to be passed
at all anyway so that's a little bit
weird and so in here we just need the
light index and the texture index right
so those those two things light index
and texture index are the only two
things we would actually need there you
know what I mean and so the base level
of writing one of these looks like this
because that's what actually goes into
one of them and it can be done with none
of these with none of these things
being checked or done right and we can
build up from there so that everyone can
just stream out directly and this can
even be welded in place as necessary so
that it doesn't even need to call a
function if it turns out that it's just
better not to bother calling a function
so you know that's another sort of good
reason why I might want that to happen
so I'm just gonna imagine that I have
one of these I'm just kind of sort of
push from there so I'm just gonna like
set this stuff in here right there we go
now in here we I guess that I look at it
we also we didn't specify a normal for
some reason but we do want normals right
so this is actually we need we need the
point the normal the UV and the color
that's being specified per vertex always
and then we just have a light index of
texture index which is per quod as they
go out right and so inside here this
actually has to look like that and then
in here it would just write those out so
actually why am I even bothering that we
don't care what that is so I can just do
this
so if you pass a geometry out it will
get these it'll just push those out
right and then you know this stuff we
don't care about because that's again
gonna be something that happens a little
bit outside that although you know we
could do this rebasing here because that
is something that probably maybe wants
to happen possibly so we may we may want
to do that I don't know if we do if we
don't let's say that we do and so this
base index here that is just something
that it's expected to know and so this
right here will just be the base index
and it will get written out right that
seems plausible it seems plausible to me
and then we know exactly how much to
advance at any given time right oops so
we can just kind of make that always
work so you know if we wanted to do a
stream out here and like I said we don't
need to switch to this right away but
just to give us an idea of what is
supposed to be coming out here it would
look something like that
right and so when we actually go to we
want all of our stuff to funnel down to
something that can stream out in that
fashion
and we don't really need you know we
don't we want to stop thinking of these
things as we want to stop thinking these
things is having to all call down
themselves we want to be able to get
that information kind of back in some
kind of sensible way so that we can
compute these values perhaps like you
know using different utilities depending
on the circumstance and then pass them
down too right quad as necessary so the
other way to look at the
would be you know maybe we want this to
to take actual textured vertices that it
just copies or maybe we want the you
know these things to be specified more
succinctly I don't know but we want to
look at stuff that's gonna produce that
kind of a value right so moving forward
from that if I go into asset rendering
and I see what has to be computed here
in order to get down to that push bitmap
call right you can see all of this stuff
happening here I want to start looking
at what these are and getting those into
some kind of a I want these to be things
that can be used outside of this push
bitmap call so I want to maybe introduce
some other structure that can produce
this information similarly like to this
here for example so I think what we want
is like a more complete version of this
so instead of used bitmap dim that maybe
is not going to be the thing anymore
maybe we've got like a sprite parameter
is sort of a thing like this something
like that or sprite values and this
would let us compute the basic values we
need for the sprite in a number of
different ways depending on what we were
trying to do with it right and so
looking through here at the kinds of
ways that we want to be able to set this
up I want to split this in two different
ways of of having that happen I guess if
that makes sense
so let's take a look at how I might do
that because like I said there's just a
tremendous amount getting computed here
and I want to simplify down how much of
that has to happen and how control the
book can be so you know we've got two
basic ways that we want to render
sprites one is flat and the other is
upright and those have very different
ways that they might compute things and
if you look at the difference between
them then really what we have is is sort
of two ways of computing our x and
y-axes
or that's right and the Z bias is the
other thing that gets computed
potentially differently right and so
when we go to produce these and we
produce the V force we tack on that Z
bias in a particular way right you can
see that here so we might say we might
say that our sprite values look
something like this you know well you
know that and then a Z bias this is what
these things are computing here right
that's what's going on when we compute
these values and you know there's
there's a couple different ways we could
describe that and those ways would
affect how we would then output it but
you know if we imagine that these are
computed independent of if we imagine
these are computed independent of the
alignment first and then the alignments
interpreted in terms of them then that
gives us a pretty good way of having
like two calls one that's like produce
sprite values from an upright sprite and
one's produce sprite values from a non
upright sprite and one's produce sprite
values from a camera facing sprite and
ones for not you know so we can add a
lot of different functions that all
produce the same intermediate data
structure and then we just have
something that takes that data structure
and blows it out into one of the right
you know quad writes you know what I
mean
so disentangling this and making it part
of a coherent way of computing it is a
good thing I think as far as as things
go right so I think we want to kind of
push in that direction so you know what
I would want to do is say
you know something like this and then
we'd get those back so you would pass in
to this routine some idea of what you
were trying to do you know not in 3d
necessarily and it would kind of give
you back what was happening in 3d and
then you could also produce those
alignment values so for example you know
then we could have a way of if you had
one of these things you could say well a
line point for and you could say you
know or get P compute P maybe P from a
line P or something like that so if you
pass in like the basis of the sprite
values that you're trying to compute
with you're saying I'm computing with
these sprite values here's my line
percentage that I'm want you to
interpret in this space give me back
what it actually is that gives us kind
of a nice way of computing that
furthermore it allows us inside
something like handmade entity instead
of making this be some weird custom
thing here we can have like piece values
or piece sprites or whatever right and
then that way we know that will just be
storing the actual things the renderer
you know utilities use and we can always
ask for the P from line P using the
correct value in that way and so that
looks very compelling to me - I think
that would be a nice way to do that so I
think that all sounds pretty good and
yeah like well I the only them a little
unsure about is just like as we move
forward with how we're doing our
animation I don't know to what extent we
really want the axes to be passed in two
dimensions anymore so that like edges
are the
inputs this function I guess I'm a
little concerned about but that that's
fine because the inputs to it we can
make multiple versions of these in
experiment with different inputs and
that sort of stuff anyway so that
becomes a little bit easier as we go as
well so that's probably not such a bad
thing either way so looking at how this
is working here let's start trying to
make these routines make sense to us and
see what we can do about how they
actually get computed right so if I want
to do sprite values for flat or sprite
values for upright right if we're doing
either of these sprite values for
upright is the one we actually need at
the moment
so let's think about how we would break
that down and then P from a line P is
the other sort of half of that so let's
say that I was going to go through it
lets also split these into the order
that they probably are meaningful which
is that way I will just say that that's
kind of our this is our more fundamental
element here that will eventually be the
way we do things and then these are
things that just produce information
that's used in that process so if we go
ahead here like so here I can say well
you know I know that's this part right
here I know this stuff is happening any
time I interpret an alignment point and
I know this stuff is happening any time
I do the sprite value so this actually
splits in half depending on how these
two things are going to pan out in here
where we're doing the push bit map call
again looking at these sorts of things
they sort of split a little bit
depending on what we're trying to do but
generally speaking you know we'd be
doing something like this here and
now probably not a whole lot else right
yeah so we'll kind of play with that as
we go so in terms of producing one of
these alignment points we want to point
in three dimensions that's where we need
to put something based on an alignment a
piece of alignment information that's
given that wants to be interpreted in
terms of a particular set of sprite
values then what we want to do here is
sort of use the values themselves to
compute what's going on so what we're
going to need inside these values we
know that these sizes are now baked into
the actual values so in terms of how
this shakes out it's really you know in
terms of going along the that where that
point is getting that point from the
alignment P is really just going to be
about using these x axis and so these
are like scaled right I mean we could
call this scaled x axis scaled y axis
you know what I mean just to be clear
about what it was and so in here we
would say well whatever the scaled x
axis is that's how far you know you
would go I guess I should just do that
and then obviously I have a scaled y
axis and adding to those we just have
the base P that we need to start with
so that would give us an alignment point
in world space and we could also say
like world P from the line P you know
what I mean and that would give us that
gives us back where in in space that
thing actually is you know what I mean
so once we know like one of those points
we also have another thing that we would
want to do which is when we are figuring
out where one of these things is we then
also need to be able to compute what the
sprites actual rectangle would be from
there right so there's a couple
confusing things about this right this
only works if the alignment point thing
like these are based on percentages
which maybe was stupid like I don't know
like that could be dumb depends on how
you want to think about it but probably
not so when we compute one of these
sprang values for up right you know and
it computes what's going on here this
hasn't been offset by any particular
dimension you know what I mean so we
could roll we could do this one of two
ways we can either set the sprite values
based on just no dimension whatsoever
and then we just have like the center
point basically or rather we have like
the point where things would be aligned
to plus the axes and then at some point
we shift it and we met like we make a
second call that's like shift for this
you know dimension right and yeah I'm
not sure which way makes the most sense
there I want to say that we probably
just want to make it I mean I I want to
say we probably want to do this so you
always actually just produce the fully
scaled rectangle here and you just
interpret it out of that I want to say
that I don't know that could be wrong
certainly
but you know I I can only extrapolate so
far into the future and guess what's
going to happen so when you pass bright
values for up right what you would be
doing here is you would also you'd be
giving it also in alignment P which is
to say what is the alignment P for you
know your alignment purposes and you
would be going backwards by those
percentages along your computed axes
right so if we look at what's gonna
happen there you would say all right
I've got a dimension for an upright
sprite I've got a base point which is
whatever I'm aligning around so that
came from like some others right or the
world and then so when I actually go
through here now I need to compute that
entire thing so the size here is
actually the dim right and the min P in
this case is going to go backwards along
those axes so we would say the base P
minus the align P times the dim is
actually what we're doing so we would
call that I don't know what like a line
offset or something like that and that
would just be whatever the dimensions of
this thing are times that alignment P
that we're using to align it right we
would first compute what those are and
then when we want to compute our minimum
P it's just going to be that offset now
once we computed that min P this primo
color here is probably not gonna whoops
not gonna stay around um once we do that
we now have to sort of say well what's
that where's that dimension coming from
are we actually gonna do these things
and again I think that wants to be
something that's that's a separate step
and you can see me sort of separating
out all these steps that's intentional
I'm trying to disaggregate all these
routines because one of things that
happens and you could you saw this
happen on a rent
a bunch and so what I'm doing now is I'm
trying to get more systemic and clean
that part of a code up now that we see
what's happening right we ended up with
a proliferation of rendering calls
because the people who are calling it
have different needs and if you have
several different steps that your
renderer calls do then you're gonna end
up if everyone needs different
combinations of those steps you're gonna
end up with a nasty N squared problem
where you know if there's step ABCDE and
F and each one of them can be done two
ways you now have two to the fifth
different render calls you need to make
or like parameters that's like bool yes
to do this don't do that right and so
what I'm trying to do is extract those
steps out into something that each
person who calls it can just call the
ones they need in the way they need and
have that cascade into the final result
in a way that makes it so that we don't
have to have different render calls for
all the combinations you just write
whichever combination you wanted into
the call site right so I mean here what
I want to do is make a different call
that's called something like to mention
sprite Jim from world height like that
so we would pass the height and then
here we would like compute what it
should be so what we'll do is we'll say
give me the render texture and all
compute that for you so again you can
see breaking that apart really helpful
here because now only people who want to
do certain things have to call these
certain pieces right so that part is now
a separate pass that'll just do the
right thing in that case
so once we have this right dim from real
tight stuff working that way then we
know we can just pass in the dim here
which is effectively the world dim so
it's supposed to be or I should say
something like that right hopefully that
makes some sense and so all of that
stuff should now just be okay
now we don't actually have the we
probably need an additional value here
right which is going to be the when we
want to apply those alignment point
scales so those are gonna have to thread
through here but I'm leaving those out
for now because I'm gonna push those
through in a separate pass and if we
need to break things up further at that
point we will okay
so let's keep pushing here we know
that's correct we're ignoring this for
now because we don't actually need to do
it in fact let me just get rid of it
because we'll add it when and if we need
it so we're really just gonna be talking
about these these pieces here right so
inside the sprite values thing that's
going to give us our minimum prz bias
and stuff here we're computing this way
when we're saying 0.25 times the height
one thing that's a little annoying about
that is it means we have to know what
the height is and so being able to pass
those yeah I mean well I also don't
really know is that really what we want
to do because that's a little confusing
in and of itself
let's let's table that for one second
while we think about this some more so
looking at how we're doing things here
like let's ignore the Z bias because
it's a different thing right so let's
just say okay the Z bias is something
that we're gonna have to compute a
little later on here's how we were
computing this value I want to say we
also had a different way of computing it
so here's a different way that we were
computing it for a sprite fit for facing
sprites totally different right and you
can see how it's it's using the world my
like so again like this this may be what
we really want more so this was the one
we developed for the renderer standalone
and I think it's probably just better
right than this stuff because we tuned
it more and it works for even if the
camera was to rotate which our old way
did not so we probably just want this
right we probably just want to do just
what this does that's my assumption
anyway so let's just grab that because
it's better and hey we even have the we
even have a Z bias computation that just
works directly off of the world dim as
well so that's kind of nice too so
problems with this because I could see
some
I don't think that's actually what we
want what we want to do here is we want
to see how when we set the Z bias we
really just want to see how tall this
thing's gonna end up being and I feel
like that almost wants to just be a
function of the actual axes like plus
the Z buys yeah I feel like the Z bias
really just needs to be computed in a
way that takes into account because the
sprite could look rotate around you know
and if it rotates around you don't want
the bottom points to have the Z bias
value is applied to them right you want
the top points to have that and so in
terms of biasing the Z to be different
than what it would normally be I feel
like in that case you really need to
actually be measuring where these things
are relative to the base of the sprite
and it's that measurement that you would
like to be doing for each of the
vertices really I mean I really think
that's I think that's kind of how it has
to work
I mean I hate to overcomplicate it but I
mean I really do think that's how that
has to work and figuring out where that
Z bias would be is kind of like has to
be taken into account you know and so
for in some sense I what guess what I'm
saying is I think it's really that where
when you compute what these are you say
for whatever you're for whatever you
wanted your Z biases to be they're all
actually their real parameters that
actually get G op geometry of their own
and they get multiplied out and applied
and I mean you could do something
different there you could instead
specify a measurement point pass that to
the vertex shader and let the vertex
shader use the measurement from the
measuring point to the point in question
to produce a Z biased value but that
doesn't seem to be the smartest thing if
I'm honest about it you know so I don't
know that I think that's a particularly
good idea it's probably not so what I'm
going to assume is that if we're placing
something on the base point then the Z
values the Z bias that we want to have
on that base point that's going to be
like the
I'm gonna have to do this on the
blackboard cuz like I'm having trouble
even explaining to myself the
complications of how the Z bias would
have to work in order to do it right so
just want to like explain it to myself
and also to to you so if you look at
what we're talking about here you know
here's a square and we place a sprite
card on to the square right in the naive
case that we were doing before we just
said well you know the Z bias down here
will be zero and the Z bias up here will
be like 0.25 times the height right and
so that just gave you a way of saying
well you know since our perspective
tends to be fairly top-down you know
like it's it's really like that and so
this sort of stuff the walls are pretty
steep here when we actually put a sprite
in there this part here would normally
clip through the wall and we don't want
it to so we want it to show up higher
right
so the naive case that works just fine
but then I guess what I'm saying is
suppose this thing we're spinning
so suppose we were just rotating it
around and we would end up with a sprite
that maybe looked like this and now the
Z bias is actually going sort of the
wrong way right the Z bias is going this
way which is sideways when really what
it should be is going up and furthermore
this shouldn't be zero on Z bias this
should actually be the higher value this
should be zero right but this should be
full right this should be the high value
here this would get a high value it
shouldn't this should still get zero
probably or close to it maybe just a
little bit right and this one should be
the full value so in terms of biasing to
Z right you can kind of see why I'm
concerned about that what we really want
to do is have some some measurement
about you know where the Z values are
supposed to be set bias wives now it
gets worse than that that's not even the
illness of it so the other problem that
we have is when you look at what's going
to happen when one of these things is
sitting on a position right so let's
suppose we take like what one of these
things looks like let's say the cat body
so let's say that's a cat body and so we
think about what the cat eye looks like
in 3d it's sitting on a point so even
though we see a sprite that just is like
this bitmap like that we imagine that
the point that it's sitting on is like
back here so then when you look at like
what the square actually is that it's
sitting on it's like it's that right
that is what would snap to the center
that means there's actually a little bit
of sprite that extends below the point
and the crucial thing for us is we don't
want that right to clip down into this
surface so we actually want to set the Z
value of this to be in front of whatever
this thing is makes sense so we don't
want it to clip down into the bottom
piece and so that's really complicated
you know what I mean
that's really pretty darn complicated
and it's so complicated in fact that I
think you might even say that it's
technically impossible if I may the
reason for that is that if you think
about what this means
if the sprite is supposed to be placed
here but this comes out to here you
don't have the information necessary to
know what would happen if there was
another sprite placed here because
without actual Z depth information for
the sprite you can't tell where it would
actually be you don't know who's in
front of whose so really like unless you
had a depth buffer or purse right
that actually described the fatness of
the cat all bets are off right it's not
actually going to you're not actually
going to be able to compute the right
value so the best we can do it's I think
it's impossible to do something correct
here the best we can do is just do
something that will be artistically
correct for what we most of the time
want right and that's going to be we
want this thing to appear below the
square on which it is placed and so if
we assume that that was going to look
like this or whatever then we just want
to shift it backwards by however much
that alignment is we want to shift it
into a z plane that would allow it to
look like it was essentially sitting
that much further forward probably you
know what I mean so the Z values of this
sprite as it goes wants to do two things
yeah I mean I guess you just want to set
the Z bias to be whatever that Z value
would have been for the point that's
like over here you know what I mean I
think that's really all you want so
another way to say that would be yeah
like it's really kind of tricky if you
were to take the plane on which the
sprite is is sitting and thankfully we
can rigidly define that plane right it's
the XY plane so it's the plane with Z as
the normal that is always what things
are sitting on in our world because
gravity goes one direction one direction
the band so Z in this case is always the
the measure it always does point up and
so if something was sitting on one of
these and then we want to shift it down
due to alignment so that it actually
appears to be there right like that then
the question is what would the Z value
have to be at this point what is the
actual point here that we would want to
transform for Z purposes in order to
determine what the Z bar for values
should be for this point given that we
know we're going down that much on the
screen axis right so effectively what
that is is it's a projection back right
it's a it's a back projection from
wherever the bottom point is back
through intersecting with the the XY
plane rooted at that point right another
way to say that would be since we know
we're rooted at this point anyway and
the aligned values going there we know
that we have at whatever the root point
is we know that we have the the downward
vector whatever that downward vector is
going to be we know that we have just
that vector if we go down there and then
project it onto the XY plane rooted
about
that's what the z-value would want to be
to prevent that interpenetration right
well to prevent the z-buffer from
clipping it away um so yeah like that's
pretty nasty if you think about it
that's a pretty nasty computation to
want to be doing
I don't know if I'm overthinking that or
not but I don't see a lot of other ways
you would do it I think the way that
people normally handle this is they
don't really I mean most games just
don't handle 3d really most 2d sprite
games they just kind of throw them in
there and cross their fingers and then
let the artists or the map the further
you get towards oblique you know and
they'll just always draw these on top of
whatever the square is and you can't do
things like hopping down stairs and
stuff like that a lot of times in these
games because it just doesn't work so
you know to get that right I guess what
I would say is you know if you wanted to
do the figuring out of how much the Z
bias should be then it's gonna just be a
ratio between that vector and you you
know cuz like let's say we know what
this point is right because we've done
we've figured out what that that vector
is so you know suppose that vector is
just V or something right then we know
that the camera you know we can create
sort of the triangle there if we looked
at this from the side so if this was our
vector V then if we looked at it from
the side
we should probably draw it like this
then we know that if this is the camera
point that we're looking at and this
here is a plane right this is the XY
plane there's the z axis so we know that
there's some depth that it's going to
inter penetrate the plane by and what we
want to do is we want to know what this
Z value would be right so there's a
camera coordinate system here makes
sense
and what's going to happen is if you
look at what the Z values are going to
be for these things we're essentially
saying that well there's a point here
and it's Z value is going to be you know
Z zero here and what we would like to do
is we would like it to warrant represent
itself as having this Z value right and
therefore the amount that we want to
change the Z by is the difference in
these two values so we want that number
and we want to set that so that when we
actually produce the Z it you know we
get that difference included you know
what I mean
to figure out where that point is
looking at this set of triangles here we
it really is a projection because we
don't really know any of these
we don't really know any of these by
rote we have to solve the projection in
order to get what that point is or you
know we have to project something before
we could do there's no shorthand I don't
think that would be like some shortcut
where you could just save the values so
in terms of this V here right when we're
looking from the camera if we want to
take and figure out what this point
would be from the V we need to know that
camera the this vector as well so yeah
yeah I can't say I see any shortcut so I
mean really what its gonna be is it's
just yeah it'd be like whatever the that
point is - the camera right so
effectively you're gonna have to have
some camera vector here you know we
could just call whatever that whatever
that is we could just call that the like
the C vector or something right so if we
assume if we were to draw the diagram
somewhat like this so like here is the
vector to the camera and this is the
origin right and then this is our our V
vector then what we want to do is we
want to find the intersection of of that
right so we've kind of got V minus C and
we could call that like I don't know
whatever yeah let's call that u I guess
you know what it's called a so we're
just looking to find where that vector
intersects the intersects the xy-plane
right and furthermore I guess we only
really need to know that dotted onto the
cameras Z vector itself so it's a little
bit confusing as to whether that will
make the problem easier to compute in
the end but effectively what we're
saying here is well alright if we want
to know when this thing intersects the
XY plane then really what we want to
know is when Z would equal zero right so
what we're trying to say is like look T
a I want to solve
t a
I want that right I want to say at what
point would when I multiply this vector
and well okay so it's stated a little
bit wrong there it's really you know C
plus T times a equals zero not sure if I
could have said that easier probably so
if I just multiply that out instead
forget the Z for a second right if I
want to say C plus ta if I want to
simplify that down right well C plus ta
also I could expand so I can just say C
plus T and we know a is V minus C right
so really to create that construction
I'm just saying T V minus T C which is
equivalent to saying if i reorganize
these terms here it's really just the
blend in a sense right it's saying tv-
right now moving this over here here and
I mean so it's really like TV plus you
know 1 minus TC which is exactly what
you'd expect right you're going between
those two so you could write that
without combining the variables and
maybe that's easier you know I don't
know hard to say
maybe it's not but but there you go so
if you were to write it that way where
you saying like we're between those two
things do I hit it so if I want to say
that that I only care about the Z value
equaling zero right so it's that so if I
want to solve that equation I would say
okay you know TVs
z + c z- Tsz right so it's that i would
group my T terms together I guess so I
guess I really I guess you really do
want it in that forum anyway right you
just want to actually have it in the cz
plus T V minus cz form because that's
the easiest to solve so you're
essentially saying cz whatever that
happens to be equals T V minus C Z so
you would divide those you'd say that
right so that's what the T value would
be so that's when these things would
intersect right so that doesn't change
the fact that still what I want to know
is the actual Z value going this way
right so I want to know what I
effectively want to know what the inner
product of that is with the camera Z
vector right so if you think about that
once you have this value what you're
really saying is well if I knew that
that value is you know whatever the sort
of output value is there this vector
inner product did with this vector so
this a whatever that value is there
inner product did with the cameras z
axis negative Z X in this case it would
be that times this right
I mean it's not great you know it's not
fabulous but that's like roughly what we
would need it to be so I'm trying to
think if there's some other way that you
could
so here's a thought so in the Z bias
program which is this so if you look at
what's happening here one of the things
we could we could change this function
quite a bit and we could possibly just
use the fact that it's gonna do a
projection anyway we could just roll
that into the vertex shader so that
actually when we specify our Z biases
those Z biases are used in a way that
produces the correct result because
projection we can do the projection of
them twice right so what you can see
here is we don't actually do that oh we
do right we do so you can see us we
transfer them both of these two we
transfer them both of these things right
and so if you look at how this is
working what we're doing is we're trance
we're pretending the Z value so we're
pretending the height value here is
different the world height value it's
different maybe that's dumb maybe what
we should be doing is pretty is setting
the Ziva bias relative to some other
thing that's a easier way to set it like
for example what if we just said well
this is actually the construction that
will happen inside the actual vertex
shader so for example what if we said
that what you actually do to compute the
Z is you move that way along the XY
plane and then it does the projection
and that's what it uses for the Z
because then we could potentially just
use that information more clearly or for
example maybe inside the vertex shader
we do this construction inside the
tech shader so that people when they
send it down just send down what they
actually wanted to do projection wise so
what would be if we had to bake that
down to a single scalar like you know
what would the scaler be
and I guess what I'm thinking is and I
kind of like the way this is starting to
come together in my head what if we just
said Z bias is not really Z bias it's
actually a you actually set two things
you set the bias vector this is a global
so you set that to say for example in
our case we always want it to be
whatever we want it to be this right and
then the Z bias value is just something
that we use to slide we say how far
along this vector you want to go to
produce the location the actual ending
location of the point for z computation
purposes
that's a good start and the only thing
that I'm not sure about there it's the
only thing that I'm really not sure
about there is how that should how that
should interact with everything else
another way to think about it would be
maybe we don't actually want our
alignment points to work that that way
maybe we want our alignment points to
actually move things out in why you know
what I mean yeah this is tricky I do
think we're doing the Z bias worse than
we could be but the other thing I'm
thinking is like maybe we just want you
know when we actually have something
here maybe what we want to do is say
look you're always gonna draw this thing
aligned with the ground so it starts on
the ground and you're just gonna move it
forward by the alignment amount that it
should be rather than moving it downward
in Y to make the align work so we will
align in projection space and we will we
will align the points in projection
space but we will use a motion along the
Y plane to produce that alignment so
that we're actually moving the sprite
forward on the tile proportional to how
it was supposed to be aligned
man 2d stuff in 3d just just sucks folks
always do a platformer you don't have
any of these problems or you
orthographic anything orthographic
really if we just set to orthographic
we'd be done so yeah I don't really know
that's a really tough call I'm not sure
what the right answer is to it
I think it's sort of defies the right
answer as much as I can think about it
so I would say the Z bias there is
definitely something that we're gonna
have to work on I'm gonna leave it until
we actually go and draw these and then
we'll have to think about how we want to
set it up but I do worry that we maybe
should not be placing the points where
they actually are and we should be
sliding them forward to a line to do Y
alignment because if we don't slide them
forward I'm concerned that that will end
up always making things interpenetrate
into the ground and no amount of
creative Z biasing is really going to
help solve that problem I think you just
need to slide them forward so that they
are sitting just a little bit ahead of
where they should be that's my thinking
anyway
so we'll have to see how it goes let's
see what would happen if we were going
to do that so if I've got one of these
here where I'm saying here's what the
sprite values for upright are gonna be
and I produced the alignment offset here
that's still correct in a sense probably
but again when we look at this min P
here line offset it's really a question
of what we would be doing with it
so you know we we've got an aligned us
that X and we've gotten a line offset Y
and you know we would be subtracting
these two things away from the like we
would be subtracting these based on our
axes so you know we would have an x axis
and a
axis that we're moving along for the
sprite and the question is should this
really actually not be the sprite why
access should this actually be some
other axis should that actually be like
an axis like a ground why that would
move it forward and towards the viewer
and I have no idea if I'm honest
looking at this we need the render group
here so we need the render group here
and from the render group we can get the
various camera parameters that we need
you can see us doing some interesting
what is what does T camera up set to
there so this I guess lets you say how
much upness you want so it's like a
blend between the two we're just saying
how much do you want to flip between
them right how much do you want to blend
between the worlds up Vector and the
cameras up Vector makes sense and then
the Z bias was just computed as the
difference between those like right so
it was going to use the dimension that
you pass in for that
[Music]
so looking at these these allow us to
rotate things around so that when we
pass in these bright values we can give
it some rotation we do want those
and so effectively what that's doing
right is that's just like that's just
allowing us to rotate this right inside
that reference that camera reference
frame so that seems reasonable I guess
and the only thing I really just don't
understand is how that was in like that
seems like the interplay of that and
Xevious is just totally wrong so you
know if you look at how this was working
here I mean this it's just this is all
flying construction it's just when it
comes to the Z bias it's just wrong
because this min this min X min Y it
assumes that the y axis and the x axis
are going in it seems that the y axis is
going upward and the x axis is not it's
going sideways but that could be totally
wrong as you rotate this thing around
it's like increasingly more wrong so
again I say it's really just that that Z
bias is just totally incorrect and so
trying to figure out what that should be
is really going to be challenging and
there may be ways that we can figure out
some way of of minimizing the degree to
which that occurs but mover least we
would want a dot product our stuff here
and try to set the Z bias per point to
something that at least is coherent so
that higher points in Z get higher Z
values but I feel like we want anything
better than that
and you know I feel like maybe we can
and and I think we're just gonna have to
tweak with it
3d is always so much easier it's amusing
but honestly like you know I would have
thought because I don't really do 2d
program very much not in this kind
anyway I would always have thought that
3d would be more complicated than 2d but
actually 3d is very uncomplicated
because you are always able to actually
compute the thing you want and so you
never really have to hack it like you
can always just say well you know I want
this thing placed here and I place it
there right so like if you just do the
full solution you end up with a correct
value in 2d you never will what you'll
never actually have a correct result and
it's very frustrating because it means
you have to constantly be like well I
don't know let's make up something here
because we don't have a way of actually
producing a valid answer actually you
know what
doing like that so I'm gonna regress to
just saying that for now because I'm
just not sure what should go on in there
so I'm gonna leave it this way and just
be unhappy with it for a little while
and then we'll we'll still compute that
Z bias the way that it was getting
computer inside the renderer but just
that's not gonna work
like just be advised right this is wrong
and so really since those are always
plainer values we should be able to UM
with something good in the vertex shader
that'll always compute them it's it's
really that interpenetration bottom part
that that concerns me the most that's
the thing that really seems confusing
and I can't say I can think of a
particularly good way to solve that you
know you heard my thoughts on it there
it definitely seems troublesome to me
and so I don't really know we're gonna
have to do some experimentation to get
that right and we'll be able to do that
now because we'll be putting stuff in
the game we will be able to see to what
extent we can make it look okay but it's
definitely an issue definitely an issue
so I think that's all we really need
here because that computes those values
that we're talking about and I think
this would give us what we wanted let me
go ahead and compile these so we can get
the errors out of them
did I call this put it next to the
renderer there
so textured vertex not sure why that's
missing shouldn't the renderer have been
included by now oh no it's down there I
want this underneath the renderer so I
want because it's always gonna be
dependent on that there we go so that's
fine all of this looks like it compiled
pretty cleanly actually so I think we're
good to go on that let's go ahead and
put our put this actual stuff to work to
the extent that we can so what I want to
do in here now is when we're going
through all of this trouble now every
time we come to a place where we would
actually be rendering something like
here when we do one of these get bitmap
dims I'm gonna start by just actually
calling the renderer John French and I'm
gonna say that we're gonna get the
sprite values here right so I'm going to
say look I want my sprite values I'm
gonna pass you the render group to use
and then I'm gonna pass all this
nonsense here like all of this stuff
right that's where that should be
and I'm gonna pass the dimensions where
is the is this this is it right in a
sense world radius you know I and well
actually I guess I made a utility
function for that now I think about it
it's this
so if I knew that I'm passing a
particular height here which is
represented by this sort of weird
convention we have of specifying the
piece dimension dot Y right it means I
can now specify the texture handle get
back the world dim that cleans up this
code path as well because now that's
actually accurate we don't actually know
what our line P is we're just going to
temporary one but that's fine we know
our x axis and our y axis those are
actually specified right we have them
here they are and the t camera up we're
not going to mess with right so that
will actually give us our sprite values
that we actually want you know what I
mean
entirely now we could get rid of the
bitmap dim stuff and stop using this
push I'm not going to bother I'm just
gonna let that happen there for the time
being so I can inspect it I'm gonna
store that back to our array so here in
piece rights when I'm we're actually
able to retire one of these I'm gonna
say okay why don't you put that you know
whatever the piece index that we're
working on here right that I'm gonna say
move that over here so I can see more
I'm gonna say look whatever that piece
index is here it is now so now we can
remember what that is and so from now on
I would actually have a way of getting
alignments so I can connect my sprites
up because when I actually go now to
pass in this this base point here I can
actually add in an offset computed from
some previous parent here what I mean
okay so the first thing I want to do is
just get this working the same as it was
working before so if I run this I'm
really I'm rendering to the same thing
so I'm seeing the same thing as I was
seeing before right so the first thing I
want to do there is say well let's
suppose that now we actually we're going
to render with the sprite information
instead so instead of calling push
bitmap here and push
map in this case is doing like all of
this other garbage right instead of
calling push bitmap let's try and call
something that's actually more direct
like you know inside the renderer let's
stop calling that stuff and start
calling this stuff or something right if
that makes sense
so let's suppose I was going to call
push right and in here
you know we looks like well they just
love a size baked in there so I don't
really need it to be doing that do we
have one that doesn't bake a size in we
need just a bear like push call that's
just like push one of these things on
that just specifies everything right
I'm gonna have to add one because we
really don't have one
uh who uses push right so I'm gonna go
ahead and say let's just stop that
because if you look at what happens here
there's no reason that it needs to be
the unit access for any particular
reason so I'm going to call these scales
and then we're gonna do it this way
right and that would allow us to always
have one call there that we can use
where we're actually passing in the
directly computed stuff so instead of
this we would actually just say like
okay
no I mean
and so that push Brett call would need
the color in there as well
so we're going to assume maybe that gets
shifted this way and then we're good to
go
right
what is the bounds there so we need the
maximum I'm assuming
also let's just make sure that's right
call how does it do it moves backwards
on the axis let's also not do that can
make the calling code do that
oops not that this one let's not let's
not do that I would vote for making that
be something that happens in in the
actual call and similarly we could have
a version and push right that does that
for you
but again like I want to kind of pull
that out a little bit more specifically
so I'm gonna say that this is actually
novice entropy that's the min P and that
doesn't that just doesn't get computed
right and so here you know we can do
that work and we can add that in if we
find we actually need that call but I
don't think we're gonna
all right
oh right I do have to do okay
sooo yeah again that's just used in the
debug system so that's not really
something that I care about either I
mean in the editor so again like we
couldn't make a utility function for
that if we want to preserve that old
would just be it would be calling push
right this way would be utility function
but again I don't really want that to be
probably a thing we'll see that doesn't
look quite right does it now there we go
[Music]
that looks good
so one thing I don't know Oh one thing I
don't know is how are those bounds how
are we specifying those bounds I think
you know what we probably need to do
like we needed to do this that's what I
should have been doing because we don't
know we don't really want max X right we
want whatever the difference between the
min of the max is we probably I probably
accidentally deleted a call to that as I
was moving those around and I can yeah I
didn't mean to do that so let's try that
there we go so that all looks fine
and so now I can finally actually just
call that inside on a day in order to do
that what I need to do here is when we
call push bitmap and with bitmap Tim and
all that nonsense here I'm just gonna
say like let's get rid of that and in
here instead let's just call push right
because now I should have the
information to call that myself and so
in here what I can say is yeah here's
the render group here's the texture at
issue the min P we computed it's in here
the scale taxis are also here the color
value we know and the mini V and Max UV
I think never get changed so I think
we're just looking at that
these would all be off of the sprites
position so yeah all of this stuff
that's happening here
that's just like off of us right now but
we'll be changing that code in a second
anyway all right can't say it was a
resounding success if I'm honest about
it but that's what we need to work on so
now we're actually you know we're using
this sprite values for up right here
we're actually using that and we are
producing the actual placement for our
rendering and you can see how we're
producing the rectangle for it we're
starting at the min we're going by the
scaled Y and scaled X right we're
producing those so what we really need
to do now is just go into the geometry
stuff and figure out why we've got bugs
in here we can start by looking at this
function this is just taking the texture
and the height and producing the width
and the height value and that you know
looks pretty straightforward so I can't
say there's any particular reason to
suspect that we're getting issues there
but we can obviously step in and
double-check them too so we're probably
getting problems here inside render
group right so we're passing in the base
P and that base position is the ground P
plus whatever the offset from the
animation stuff is plus the piece offset
but that seems good that's where we
would start right then we have the world
dimensions which is the thing that we
computed right here so that was coming
from here and we believe that to be
correct as well then we've got the align
percentage which again we're getting
from the bitmap itself which is probably
just like you know point five point five
and then we have our two at our two axes
that we start with and we're not changed
the t camera so in order to produce our
alignment amount and I guess I should
move that down here
it's really probably where it goes so
here's how we're producing this stuff
we're basically saying all right we've
got whatever the up Vector is for the
world and whatever the up Vector is for
the camera we're gonna blend between
those to produce our final like actual
up vector and this basically tells us
how flat we want to be and we may need
to pass something very different there
because we may be flatter in this case
then in our renderer test where we were
actually doing this stuff so that's
worth noting but anyway and the Z bias
we can probably ignore for a moment cuz
we saw the cats were at a completely
wrong place so we're really working on a
more fundamental issue right now than
the Z bias so we can ignore the Z bias
for the time being also I don't know if
push right even has Z bias it probably
should right so we should probably pass
in here like what the Z bias is because
it actually needs to get placed in here
probably right
no I'm saying to you that's not gonna
cut it eventually so you know I take it
back
because again that's part of what we're
gonna have to fix so we can kind of
ignore the Z bias for now I think
because until it's exactly the right
place and just sorting wrong we don't
have any reason to focus our attentions
there so once we produce these what
we're gonna say is alright now we've
sort of got an idea about how big this
thing should be XY is how big it should
be Y wise and what we're gonna do is
we're gonna produce our to scale axes
here by multiplying those scale values
by our interpretation of the x and y
axes here's the x axis interpreted along
this sort of camera card centric axis
system
that looks correct to me so III don't
see a lot of problem with that honestly
we're then gonna say look all right we
need to oh well that would do it so this
is not that's not right
so we can we can start by fixing that so
the align P is really all we need here
that that's a big problem we don't want
to account for the world dimension twice
that was not good let's see what this
looks like now all right so that's much
more reasonable and in fact it's much
better than what we had before as well
because you can see that it's actually
stacked in the world a little bit more
properly and actually you can see that's
writing direct it's stuck right on the
place where it's supposed to be - you
know what I mean and so what you can see
here even just right off the bat we're
actually looking at the problem I was
talking about - so do you see how you
know we would probably want this to sort
in front of there but we actually do
want it to be placed there because it
should be placed somewhat down from its
actual like standing location so we need
like that overlap there is exactly the
part I was talking about there to figure
out how we want to solve that to work in
3d properly now just looking at our
perspective here you know we would want
it to be shifted more the only thing I
don't know is honestly I wonder if our
default camera is maybe like I think
that might be a little bit too steep for
our default camera as well
it's really hard to say but I kind of
feel like maybe you know if I'm honest
about it I probably want the camera
sorry it's on the wrong file there I
probably want the camera when I'm
setting up that camera transform I
actually want to rotate it in a
different like more downward than it
normally would be so you know looking at
how this gets set up here when we're not
using the debug camera here's the world
mode camera pitch that's normally set up
and I think those get overridden right
like if you want to use the debug camera
yeah you can see it using debug camera
pitch and stuff like that
so if we're using the normal one this
value here actually controls that pitch
so you know if I was to make it pitch
down more that might actually be more
accurate to what we wanted to do so
let's say that we were gonna have a more
oblique pitch so something that's a
little bit more side on there so you
know that might be a little bit too much
or maybe it's not you know maybe that's
actually good I don't really know
it's hard to say not sure why that cause
why is that causing a problem with
interpolation that's interesting take a
look at that later so I don't know if we
want to be a little bit more side on you
know then we were
because again that would help us with
our with keeping our art sorting
properly and you know it's difficult to
say I don't really know what we want to
do there that that might be a little bit
much you know but something like that
you know
it's always kind of a struggle to figure
out like what we want
uh-hum those focal lengths to be and how
much eccentricity we want there you know
what I mean
I need to make a little thing where I
can play with the camera values and dial
us into exactly what I want we should
probably do that sometime soon
especially if we're working on like the
snapping stuff now right but just
thinking about how far the camera should
be above the world again it's just like
we need to at some point lock that stuff
in and you know now that we're gonna be
putting art in the game we kind of need
to get that exactly right we can't
really afford to have that be wrong
anymore where is the camera code for
that simulation right so the way that we
were doing this for camera offset Z's
you know I don't really remember how
that was working but I think it was
something to do with yeah like how the
room the rooms themselves can set how
far off you want you know how far up you
want them to be
so that camera offset Z for the in-room
I want to take a look at that so when
we're actually setting this right get
camera offset Z for dim you can see how
great you can see we kind of played
around with what we wanted them to be
and it's not great right but yeah so you
know
so probably okay I also might want to
make our build our build is slower than
I would like it to be right now
so you look at all the stuff that it has
to build in this case I just get rid of
couple of these it's probably a good
thing I don't know that it really speeds
up to build all that much but it's at
least more minimal now so you know if we
were to do that more as our perspective
and assume think I fixed whatever
weirdness is happening with the camera
there it's pretty bizarre but we never
really finished a camera code we still
don't really know what we want to do
with it exactly but assuming we have
something like that as as the
perspective you know that seems pretty
reasonable and it would keep us from
having too bad of a situations with
sorting - too rough from a sorting
situation we might have to do something
where like we make blocks invisible at
the edge of the room though which is
kind of annoying and again I don't
really know if there's I don't think
there's really any other solution for
that I mean we could tip slightly more
up so you know maybe maybe just a little
hair more would be the best possible
option
mm I don't know you know maybe just just
a little tiny bit more so maybe that
because then you can always see the
bottom square but you never get anything
that tilts you can never see the front
side of things either right so like I
don't know who knows maybe maybe not
we'll see this stuff would have to be
extended obviously
because the fog values would be wrong at
that point I think
you can see our lighting region is wrong
too so yeah we got we have some we have
some bugs in that in the camera
projection somewhere because it should
be correctly getting that region it's
not all right well anyway so probably
opens a bunch of stuff that we should be
working on we should probably get the
camera stuff right but now that we have
that part of the snapping working we
should be able to actually snap these
sprites together as well and so if we
look at something you know
like the cat if I want to do the
snapping on the sprite for the cat there
I should be able to actually make that
work so if we were to add snapping
values to the cat I need a way to move
the debug camera maybe maybe next stream
should be debug right if I want to add
the snapping values and where they
should go I should now be able to to
make that happen properly so I think
that's the next thing that we should do
so let me just do that real quick since
it's really easy assuming here when we
get those values back when we store them
here we're no longer using this code so
that can go away and we push the sprite
on using the values that we have there
what that means is if we wanted to snap
here we would just look up the value
that we were trying to snap to and be
done with it right and it's a little bit
slow because we need to find the correct
one so that's a little bit onerous but
other than that it's not that bad
so let me show you what I mean by that
so in here what we would do is say well
okay we've got a piece and we know that
the piece so we look at this right here
we've got one of these and we know that
we've got this information so we know
we've got a parent index that we can use
here to look back to to see you know
which parent which thing it should be
attached to and obviously the first one
doesn't have that if that makes sense
so it doesn't really need to be done on
piece index zero but all anyone else
would want to do that we can also do
some things there where we could use an
offset if we wanted to say that zero was
just initialized with the world and so
could just reference itself we could do
some tricks there if we wanted to so
we'll see how we want to do that but
these here this snapping basically tells
us take this alignment on us and use
that alignment on the parent so to start
with when we do this snapping what we
can do is initially take what our child
alignment is and use that instead of
just getting the first thing so you know
in here we were doing a thing where we
said get first aligned right we were
saying that instead of that we could say
instead of getting first aligned let's
get the actual alignment point so here
we could say like child aligned and HHA
aligned point parent aligned and we
could actually try to start fetching
these now so off of our bit map info
where we have aligned points we're going
to get which we're going to get this one
so what we want to do is like find a
line
so hopefully that makes some sense there
like you can see we would basically you
know we'd get this out so if we got that
out what we would then do is we'd say
let's get the alignment for the child
align whichever one that is you know
find that and then here we would you
know do the same thing so if we have
some way of finding those alignment
points we'd get them back once we have
them then we know that this align P is
just let get P percent of the child
aligned that's where we're aligning this
thing right and then we have some parent
alignment basis point so we would say
you know what is this value here like
the entity ground P thing that all of
this computation here is actually and it
kind of thing if it includes the piece
offset
yes so so that's kind of a little
complicated just in terms of how it's
supposed to work but you know you could
think of it this way we'd say here
there's like like an initial p-value
that comes in here which is that and if
we are not piece 0 then that initial P
is actually going to be found in a
different way so rather than using that
basis there we're going to do something
different
so in here where we want to do this we
now need to find out what the parent you
know whatever the parent piece is so
this we want to look up what it's bright
transform was let's just say hey
whatever you know we know our parent got
processed before us because we had force
that ordering so whatever the the
transform was for our parent we need to
now ask using those renderer utilities
that we created we need to ask where in
the world we would be if we were lined
up we were using that alignment off of
this right value right so we're saying
whatever the parent aligned P percent is
here whatever that should be interpret
that on this on this frame of reference
which is what our parent was use that
and then we will then align to that
using our point whatever that is it's
pretty complicated right but I mean
that's that's the long and short of it
right we want to fix this code also now
to use this this code as well so
for example this world P from align P is
what we would actually use to draw these
points so rather than using this here
where we're actually calling this part
forward this would actually be also
worlds P from the line P and we would
pass our sprite values and whatever the
alignment point was that P percent this
makes sense and then that goes away so
now we are both like looking those up
and drawing them up this is sorry this
is bitmap piece and let's see here
that's just a bug typo and so that's all
of the snapping code actually and so we
just need some way of actually doing
that find a line if that makes sense
let's go ahead and change that there
have like Speight
that needs to be an address other than
that I think we're good yeah so all we
really need here is inside our access
Oris for when we're actually using these
what we want to do is have a find align
function that takes the information
necessary to find one of these and basis
says look for this bitmap find me the
align point that is of that type and
give it back so we'd start with an align
point maybe that had nothing we look
through them all and if we found one we
would return it you know what I mean so
in here we would say all right we've got
point index we go through however many
there are in the bitmaps and if we find
one we use it
so we would effectively do a like get
type here right now when we do this
we're really saying is we want to be
able to do a to parent here as well so
this is honestly more of a like complete
type here and so you know I think we
want to say it that way and so you'd
you'd want to smush down the two-parent
part where you call find a line so here
when we call find a line we would say
here's the parent alignment who's
traveling this one is supposed to be a
two-parent
don't ask me why I'm passing it that way
right so think that's correct
semester what that's doing there all
right so now we should perhaps I guess I
don't know in theory we should be able
to debug this and these things should
now snap together right and it's a
little bit squirrely there but that's
basically what we're trying to do so if
we can find these alignment points here
oh and also this parent align is wrong
because that bitmap info is actually
that has to be the parents bitmap info
right so we need to reach back into that
particular piece so it's really this and
we can do it this way so we need to be
able to grab the bitmap info in each
case here I guess I could also say look
just give me the bitmap like that so
that way we can just say well whenever
we get the bitmap info
whatever that actually is from there
we'll store it so in this case we'd say
bitmap infos and and place it in there
and that way we could also know when
we're referring to something that
doesn't actually exist because it would
be a zero so in this case what we could
do is say all right like get rid of this
and just say if parent bitmap info is
valid then we can look at the parent it
met the parent bitmap infos alignment
point like that and then we can always
write our own back in here so whatever
we find for ours will put in there does
that make sense
so we have an H it's a bitmap
our parent oops bitmap info we said it's
a zero normally and then we you know we
go through it like so so normally what
we do is we look up in that array we say
whatever our parent was supposed to be
we get their bitmap info out of it we
then say all right if we found one of
those then we can do an alignment point
lookup to see what the parent alignment
point was and assuming we got that we'll
take whatever the piece is and we will
use the percentage for our prepare
alignment to align us with that then
we'll write ourselves back into right
now notice we do that second why would a
second that way we don't need a special
case the first piece anymore because
when it goes to look up into the array
it will just find zero in the slot that
its parent is which is itself and it
won't try to offset it at all okay so
now we need to bug that because that's
gonna give us yeah like any bugs we have
will send things flying off into the
middle of nowhere which is not what we
want so now we have to just debug that
but I think that's roughly correct
meaning that will now give us all of our
snapping what we don't know here is like
looking at this stuff so you know you
can see here the way to stuff flows
through computing things like this you
want a way of making only the initial
basis piece get to get these offsets so
we we kind of need to rework how this
code flows through so that's kind of a
you know that's kind of an issue there
and so that stuff needs to get improved
to say the least
because we're going to end up with
compounded stuff in there unfortunately
but if we look at how this is being used
we still should be able to get our
initial sprite to be placed in the right
location the fact that it's not is a bad
sign so we should probably fix that
looking at the child line and accessing
that P percent there we should be able
to say that the default alignment is
always going to be that that's zero line
value and so I do think so I do think
what we may need to do is set the
initial like all of our initial stuff
should be set to actually use none there
although we could make default
not sure I want to do that so in here
like you know for example if I was
feeling saucy I might say that you can
just set that if it's not yeah hmm I
really don't know I really don't know
how to do that so just to give you a
little perspective on what's happening
there so when we put these pieces in
place so you know when we do the ad cap
which is obviously our most important
function so we connect this stuff and I
guess I want to say something like like
this like you know I want to be able to
say that this initial piece is connected
to the world like that
and so when we would do that instead of
like this stuff we would always just say
like the parent piece in this case is
zero and the aligned type is none oh
well actually that's a smarter way to do
it isn't it now that I think about it if
the parent aligned type is none then you
are connecting to the world that seems a
little easier so maybe what we could do
instead here of any of that stuff is we
could just say hey in this case well you
know but we're still gonna have to do
that because we're still gonna have to
set this yeah so no we still need this
this has to happen regardless I think so
in this case we just say yeah we're
connecting this child in this child type
so when we go ahead and set that up we
set the parent piece of zero and the
aligned type to none
so it's actually this and then the child
the line type is the align type or tug
nut so it's basically saying connect
this piece but to the world so it
doesn't get an actual parent that makes
sense so then inside here when we're
actually drawing this that makes more
sense now because effectively what we're
saying it's like we are gonna look for
the alignment type in this case and I
think when we look here at the you know
this child type that we're passing in
that has to get ordered with two parent
right because it's looking for the
default to the parent side of things I
think so in this case we have to specify
that Ord together and I think we want to
specify it here too right like it should
be there because you're looking for that
one in one case and the other one in the
other case right and so I feel like we
would just want to do this probably
right so yeah so I think what this
actually boils down to is we would say
okay if the bitmap piece parent a line
type is valid then we do this if it's
not then we don't do this right so we
wouldn't even look up even if we were
not on the zero with one we would not do
that I think that's right but don't
quote me on that
what's the problem here
Connect peace to world that is not you
why is it complaining his child not a
bitmap or something child is a bitmap
what's the other assertion you could
have there Oh like I guess the safe
truncate to u8 okay so I guess maybe
there's our reason that's not part of
the u8 so these actually have to not B
ANDed with that I'm okay with that so
that does mean here like you would have
to do this which is fine
okay so let's step through and debug
that real quick I want to take a look at
that and then we can wrap it up for the
day so I just want to get that initial
piece working there
so let's set a breakpoint in the entity
system there and let's just stop in here
somewhere so when we come through here I
just want to look and see what like the
bitmap piece is set to for example so
this one's entirely cleared and so I
want to make sure that that actually
works when that's actually the case so
let's go into child align and it's
looking for a type of of what just to
parent right 0 and to parent it
shouldn't find one and that's not our
cat so I really want to look at the cat
let's see if we can find the cat here
this looks like our cat so now let's
look through here it should find one it
does so what's the result there so
here's our encoding we create the
initial P we know that the parent a line
type is not involved so this should just
align us to the world in general we
write these pieces back let's see what
the align P is the align P is exactly
what we think it should be which is 0.5
0.5 within epsilon there we go for the
world dimensions we look and see what
those are those are reasonable
dimensions we go in here to say we
passed the initial P in the world dim
right and our align our alignment and
our axes that looks like that should be
giving us the right answer to be honest
with you so I'm not sure what's going
wrong there like why we aren't seeing
the cat in the location that we think we
should be that's a little bit confusing
to me so let's go into push bright and
just see what's going on there so I can
see if there's some values
like weird and like super strange or
something so there's our min P in our
scaled y-axis it's scaled x-axis scaled
y-axis I mean that looks totally
reasonable right I don't see anything
weird going on there and yeah I mean
that looks totally fine for our cat so
let's see if the cats actually showing
up correctly then maybe it is all right
so our cat actually is showing up
correctly our player isn't but that's
fine because the players a different
kind of object that's completely messed
up so we could fix oh I guess we were
right and we could fix the player now if
we want to we really need something that
sets the debug camera location I should
probably add something like that right
like whatever the in fact how do we set
that where is the camera location set so
there it is so camera offset
it's actually something we could just
overwrite so we really should add
something like that I'm not gonna do
that quite yet but that's probably
something we need to do sooner rather
than later I guess I don't need to be in
the debug for this let's hop in here and
in here and we can select our kitten
so much I gotta fix in the cui
we just the camera is just so screwed
like it's beyond messed up and we're
gonna have to fix that soon because
there's no way to even look at entities
in the game right now we don't really
even have the ability to move the debug
camera it's complete garbage so we'll
have to have to fix that
but anyway so there's like right there's
one of those there's our cat right not
that we can see it but if we could so if
we set the alignment point of look where
the cat should be you know we can we can
now place the cat properly on the tile
which is kind of nice right and then in
theory now if we add a child alignment
point where the head is which I just did
and I set that to base of neck then you
can see if I set the alignment point of
of this then the cat is now assembled
properly right and you can see it like
kind of always gets assembled properly
there so now if I flip out of debug mode
our cat is always assembled properly now
you can see why the Z bias and our Z
position is going to be important right
we need that head to sort in front of
the body for example right but even in
fully 3d now it's always pegged properly
to the location and so now I think we
have full snapping working right that's
all just correct and so we really just
need to now work on our actual like we
got to go fix our camera and our other
end our figure out how we're gonna do
that Z bias right and that has to be
offset a little but other than that like
we're in pretty good shape because I
think that's really all there is to it
right that that sort of concludes our
editing of alignment points because they
just kind of work now know what I mean
all right so that's good we got done but
I wanted to get done today and we can
save for the next stream maybe we'll go
fix the camera and then we can once we
fix the camera then we can we can also
figure out maybe in that process like
how we're gonna deal with with properly
biasing z-values because that really is
a bit of a that's that's gonna be a real
trick and so will you know we'll have to
kind of work on that as we go
all right no questions we'll be done
early
do you know anything about the state of
the series bitwise we haven't heard
anything from pair in the last two
months no I don't know anything about
the state of it I have not been
following it
why not render with the projection
matrix plus W M matrices to position
sorry I'm not sure I understand the
question
I'm not sure what that question means
exactly
these weight free multi-threading as
difficult as lock free multi-threading
[Music]
so yeah like I guess I would say that
there really only is weight free
multi-threading lock free
multi-threading is sort of a the phrase
lock free multi-threading is really more
a statement about the tools that you're
using to implement your multi-threading
algorithm and not really a statement
about the correctness of the
multi-threaded program weight free
multi-threading is more of I mean like
when I hear that phrase I'm thinking
about the correctness of the
multi-threaded programming weight free
means that all threads can always make
forward progress and they'll never end
up in a situation where they like
literally can't I mean you know like if
I hear weight free I'm thinking I'm
thinking like this right
so when I hear weight free what I'm
thinking is that you actually designed
the algorithm properly to not have any
even abstract race condition because
technically if you were to use a real
blocking lock like let's suppose I have
two threads and they both need to do
something with a resource and I have a
blocking lock that I take and all it
does is it says whoever the first person
after the lock is gets it and then the
other person just can't use it until
it's released if I have two threads who
are both using that lock then
technically right technically I could
end up in a situation where one thread
never does any work because every time
it goes to take the lock it finds that
the other thread has it I mean
technically that's true right even
though in practice you know that will
never happen probabilistically it's
technically possible for a scheduling
the worst possible scheduler to go ahead
and create a situation where it does
occur right if I only allow thread B to
execute while thread a holds the lock
that B needs it will never get it wait
free synchronization is usually a
statement about the fact that that is
not technically possible I
I would say right meaning everyone
always is able to do something so they
issue an atomic operation that is going
to do something and then they can
continue to do work right
I don't know uh this stuff is
complicated if you try to read and
actually understand this paper which is
the seminal paper in the field right
it's pretty tough and you get stuff that
it can actually tell you like look this
thing is not technically possible right
it's like look if this is your
implementation paradigm and this is the
kind of consensus you want to come
through come to it's like not possible
to do so right and so it's pretty tough
you know it's pretty tough I believe
this is where the concept of compare
exchange is established as the only real
thing you can use to create consensus
numbers higher than you know one or two
or something or higher than one I don't
remember what it's it's a pretty good
paper in terms of telling you like look
this is what processors actually need to
implement because if actually all we
have is these old things that we were
using we're never gonna get anywhere
it's pretty good that way so when I hear
weight free I'm thinking this I'm
thinking something that has to do with a
proof about a consensus number and an
implementation virgin you know what I
mean that's what I'm thinking whereas if
I hear lock-free I'm thinking like you
don't have like things that look like a
critical section which doesn't really
mean anything to me I mean I understand
what you're trying to tell me maybe like
you're trying to tell me look I didn't
use this particular type of
implementation technique but I don't
know much more than that probably does
that make sense
okay clarification on the the matrix
question why not renders rights with
projection matrix we're setting its
rotation facing towards the camera we do
that is what we're doing currently we
didn't like completely having it face
the camera you can go back to the
archives you want to watch me doing
experimentation there
we don't want it completely facing the
camera so we blend between the two
different ways it would be in the
environment one where it's straight up
and down and one where it's completely
flat and we blend between those and we
actually specify that parameter here so
this value is the difference between
those two things and so if you look if
you want to actually see that more in
practice so if we kind of go back to the
cat we were looking at before right so
if I come in this room and we're looking
at this cat here right the headless cat
let me let me actually reconnect the cat
we got to add the save and load now we
have a good reason to do that because
now we can now we can actually use the
values we kind of have a reason to do so
but let me you actually put that on
there
so anyway if you're looking at the cat
you know you can kind of see how the
sprite sits in the environment right
it's kind of it's not straight up and
down but it's not it's not directly
head-on to the camera and if you set it
head-on to the camera or or or
completely straight up and down you can
see the difference between those two
things by setting these values so let's
say I set that value to 1.0 and
recompile the program that's what it
would look like if the sprite was 100%
facing the camera right and so that's
what that if I rotate around here so you
can see what it looks like from a debug
camera angle right it's very flat it's
very flat against the ground which is
what you'd expect because the camera is
looking pretty pretty straight down
right if I set that to zero now it'll be
what it actually would be if it was a
card in the environment right and so you
can see how that looks here right it's
very flat up and down sorry we don't
draw the back faces so I can't show it
there but you can see right what I'm
what I'm looking at there and so it's
kind of an open question like what we
actually want that value to be and we
can tune it when we finish how we want
our art to look but I kind of wanted
somewhere in between and you know maybe
it should be a little more towards the
back or maybe a little bit more towards
a front Leamy that's about good but I do
like get to be some what I like it to
move perspective a little bit I don't
want it completely non perspective
because it just feels a bit wrong to me
I don't like the way it feels when it's
not at least a little bit if it doesn't
shift a little bit side to side and so
you know what that ratio what the
perfect balance is is hard to say but it
gives it a little more depth that
integrates a little bit better and
that's really why you know that's why I
I want those values to look like they do
can you explain again briefly how you
might want to solve the problem
straights are penetrating the ground no
I can't because I don't know what the
solution is yet right so what I was
saying is that that's something I'm
gonna have to look into and figure out
how I want to do it there's a couple of
different ways we can do it one is by
adjusting where the sprites actually are
in the world and another is adjusting
what we use as the Z values for the
actual pixels to fake where they are and
we don't really know which one of those
is gonna be it might be combination of
the two right it might be both of those
things it might be neither so I don't
really have an explanation of it yet
because I'm not sure how I want to solve
it have you read communicating
sequential processes by Tony Hoare no I
haven't we my posting that
multi-threading paper in the chat I'm
guessing somebody already did did anyone
do it let me just hear how to type in
just
I might have spelled that slightly wrong
but that's that's really all you are
looking for right are you planning on a
line camera rotation the final game no
not really
you could reface after certain angle so
it still gives you some of what you want
no I I don't really like the look of
games that rotate when they have sprite
art so I probably won't allow you to
rotate the camera pitching the camera
perhaps but just not not orbit right so
we may pitch the camera a little bit we
may we may like like let that happen but
we probably wouldn't let orbit ever
happen because I think it just breaks
the illusion a little bit too much syrup
I probably would draw the line there
all right looks good let's close it up
thank you everyone for joining me for
episode of hand made here it's been a
pressure coding with you as always on
the spec special let me see if I can say
it right this time
Krampus Laos stream leading up to of
course I think - in two days the running
of the Krampus will be coming up we
pretty much did what I want to do today
so that was good took a little extra
time but we're in good shape so I think
we want to do is next dream which will
happen - surprise time but probably in
the not-too-distant future I'd like to
go in and clean up the camera and I'd
like to add the saving and loading of
those attachment points and then I think
we want to get down and dirty with the Z
bias stuff there to figure out how we
really want to render those because now
we've got the ability to render our
sprites correctly I think we really want
to push forward and try to get our
graphics cleaned up there so that
everything looks good so bad I think
would be the next situation sizes also
like so we just I think now we've got
everything in place we want to do some
polish passes get everything just so so
that our art looks good and we can
populate the world with confidence that
when we put something in we're putting
it in the right way so that's what we'll
be up to next time as always if you want
to following the series you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero or
it comes with a source code so you can
play around with it that's easy enough
to do
and so yeah until the next surprise
Krampus laugh stream I'll see everyone
on the Internet take it easy everybody