there we go hello everyone and welcome
to handmade Hero the only show in the
known universe where we show how to code
a game live on the air from scratch
every single line explained even when we
have no idea what's going on and we're
confused we will still explain every
line and then we'll just correct
ourselves later when we realize we've
made a horrible horrible mistake that is
my promise to you here on handmade hero
no engines no libraries just good
old-fashioned quote unquote engineering
because my understanding is that
engineering technically is a more
defined term and like software engineers
shouldn't really shouldn't use it
because really they're just programmers
but either way whatever you want to call
it it's pretty awesome and we're about
to do some more of it so I highly
recommend sticking around for precisely
that kind of awesome now if you are one
of those sorts of people who has
pre-ordered the game on handmade hair
org you should have gotten a link in
your email where you can download the
source code so if you would like to
follow along at home this is day 53
unzip day 52 source code and you will be
where I am so when that big zip that has
tons of little zip files one for every
day funds at 52 and you'll be right
where I am
and that may lead you to ask the
question which is where actually am I
and that's a very good question
where I am is we just started doing sort
of some reworking of how we want it to
structure the game so that we could
start doing things in a in a more
logical fashion where basically things
around the player that we are simulating
that are on-screen and and sort of
nearby are getting mapped into sort of
an active set that we process and that
we're going to do all the collision
detection on and all the gameplay logic
on and then things that aren't are
getting mapped out into a lower
frequency update space where they can
still have stuff happen to them but it
just may not be stuff that's happening
at as high a frequency so we can support
very large numbers of entities in the
world all with autonomous behaviors
even if there's like hundreds of
thousands of them and still have it work
okay without making the framerate
intolerable
but one of the things I said that I
wanted to do and that was change all the
collision detection over to working on
entities instead of working on the tile
map and so now we no longer have tile
map collisions with our walls right you
can see that we just straight up you
know go kind of off these things oh dear
what have I done what have I done indeed
it looks like we're drawing a bitmap in
in an illegal way
well I correct me if I'm wrong but
anytime we have a bug we should fix the
bug so hold pretend I didn't say any of
the things that I just said and let's
let's find out what happened here
because that is way more important at
the moment I don't like having bugs in
the code if I I really strongly dislike
having bugs in the code at any time
really so anytime I get a repro I like
to look into it so let's take a look at
what happened here presumably we were
half some valid things but we ended up
drawing them to or from invalid
locations presumably so taking a look at
this here we do in fact in fact let me
let me check to see what our source row
pointer is even here source row so
source row is wrong in general where are
we on run why 180 and what is our max
why is 181 so this is the last row of
the bitmap and it looks like we are
basically fetching off the end of our
bitmap for some bad reason and I'm not
sure exactly what that reason actually
is so let's try and figure that out so
let's see we've got a buffer here that
we are trying to draw to I guess that's
not the problem at the moment and we
have a bitmap that we're loading from it
has a height of 217 and so it looks like
this must be our offset code that is
busted am i right about this
plus source offset X soft source at Y so
essentially the way we were doing this
is we backed ourselves up right so
here's our bitmap pixel splinter we
backed ourselves up to just before the
the last the the last row because the
bitmaps the as we were loading them were
inverted they were flipped so basically
the bitmaps in BMP format are stored
from the bottom up and so what we had to
do was start at that top row because we
were doing our blitz from the top down
so we basically go ahead and back up to
that point by saying bitmap height minus
1 so that seems reasonable there and
then we're pre-incrementing our pixels
to that right then we've got a source
offset X in this case there isn't one
what's the source offset why it's 37 so
if the source offset is 37 37 plus where
we were at where were we at there plus
180 right well that that does seem to
indicate a problem here so what have we
done wrong what have we done wrong here
so what we did is we said when we are
off the screen so we can see what the
value is that we passed in right we
passed in real X we rounded that down so
that would have been
oops I didn't want real X I want to real
Y so that's where we were trying to draw
when we round that guy I assume that we
got 37 Y so we got 37 rounded it up so
we ended up with 37 so we came in here
and we said well the 37 is less than 0
so what we need to do is we need to set
our min Y actually equal to 0 and we
need to offset where we are drawing so
that we don't Oh hmm this is very very
interesting people this is particularly
interesting so what is the bitmap height
right the bitmap height is 2
17 so if we were actually adding real
why this is this is this is particularly
odd so let's find out what's going on
here if we were actually adding this
right we would be going we would be
going from 37 to 181 right those are the
rows that should actually be involved
here although 181 should be the row at
which we would stop right so that is
we're not gonna fill row 181 yeah so
then if we find that we are actually I
should say that for negative 37 right so
then if we find that we've actually Wow
is this actually because this straddles
the positive and negative line and it
happens to be exactly 0.5 so it rounded
in a different direction each time is
that actually what occurred check check
that logic right so basically if it's if
it was doing even odd rounding right
which says that if the number is even
you round one way in if it's odd you
round the other way right I wonder if it
rounded this one up and rounded that one
down I guess that's not even it it's
just if you round towards infinity in
either direction that would Wow all
right so I guess I guess that means that
this we can't really do this anymore we
do actually have to go ahead and use the
width and height after the in after we
do our rounding to make sure that we
don't ever have that
happen it's kind of a little unfortunate
I guess the way the real renderer would
work wouldn't have to worry about this
hmm that's that's crazy
but I believe that's actually true so
I'm gonna go ahead and see if we could
repro that I need my editor here I'm
gonna go ahead and see if I can repo
that let's see here
so Winston oops it's not don't need any
win32 there so in drawbitmap
I'm just gonna flat out say that when we
go ahead and draw this bitmap I'm gonna
set it so that real Y is is negative
thirty-six point five just to see what
happens just to see and let's find out
hey look we immediately get a crash so
that's good that's a good thing right
and of course what I need to do now is
turn off that other draw bit Matt call
so I only get one draw a bitmap call so
there we go let's get back let's see so
first things first we compute min Y and
Max Y right and let's see what real X
plus bitmap wit is here oops
plus a bitmap hiked there we go so yeah
this is this is this is exactly what
what one might expect so when we compute
this right that is exactly what's
happening so we're getting real Y in
here and it's exactly 0.5 is where the
value happened to end up so it rounded
min Y down but it ran round admire
because it was positive after the
addition right so the negative rounded
towards negative infinity I assume and
this one round toward to positive
infinity it's either that or it's even
odd Ronny I don't know what the rounding
mode is right now set on the processor
so it actually expanded the size of the
blip by one more pixel than should have
been legal right
so I guess and I this is a little wonky
but I guess we will have to do this the
other way we will have to do it this way
so that we avoid that possibility which
I didn't really want to have to do
before because I wanted to talk about
you know I was I was thinking it'd be
better when we talk to rendering work to
talk about the things in actual float
space but that's okay so I think this is
actually what we need to do to make sure
that we don't ever have that problem so
that we essentially only do the rounding
once and then whatever happens happens
so there we go
all right well that was pretty cool
quite a way to start the stream but at
least we've got it now so there we go
alright so back to what I was saying
what we have not done yet with our new
system is actually put anything in place
for the wall entities and that sort of
stuff so basically what I wanted to do
was stop having the tile map be checked
at all for really anything and to start
just checking for entities so I want to
make it so that he can't walk through
these little white tiles that we've got
here I want to make it so that you can't
walk through those but basically in
order to do that I have to add them to
the actual entity list right and so what
we need to do is we need to actually
formalize now how we are bringing things
into and out of that set right and the
other thing that we need to have an idea
for is how we're gonna actually manage
these entity sets because one of the
things that's true is I don't actually
know if I it's it's kind of hard to say
at this point I don't actually know
whether I want a low entity for every
single thing that could be in the tile
map like trees and stuff or I should say
a dormant entity I don't know if that's
a particularly good way to store all
that stuff it might be just a waste of
storage I don't know it's kind of hard
to say and we might want to compress
those in other ways but the other thing
that's kind of hard for me to think
about right now and this is why I'm not
and I don't want to take any steps
towards it just yet is I don't know how
crazy you want to go with modifiable
scenes as well like if we have a thing
where we wanted you to be able to burn
down trees or break through walls then
it is kind of true that the more
destructible that the environment is the
more of those things might want to
actually be stored as entities so it's a
little bit hard to say without getting
further down the game design path to
know really how much of each individual
thing we're doing so for now I guess the
first thing to do is say alright let's
just start by simplifying our world
state a little bit here let's just say
that instead of doing that many screens
we're just going to do just the one
screen right so the only thing we're
going to do is just this screen so this
is it so since we only have one screen
being generated now which is just this
one it'd be safe we won't have too many
entities to worry about so we can try
just just dealing with the ones that we
see on the screen here making those into
entities and seeing what we get right so
let's go ahead and do that what I want
to do here is say okay we we have sort
of this concept here of the camera
moving right this is the concept of the
camera moving and what we haven't really
done yet is is formalize what happens
when the camera moves and that camera
having to sort of bring with it you know
get rid of any stuff that is now off
camera right and bring in any stuff that
has now come on camera so I'm going to
do is try to break that off now into a
separate function so that we kind of
have unknown place where this sort of
stuff actually happens right and so what
I want to do is take this stuff
basically
well that stuff's fine but it's it's
this stuff right here like this entity
offset for frame and this this stuff
where we actually move the camera here I
want to sort of pull that out so what
I'm going to do is I'm going to go ahead
and make a function here right and that
function is going to be something
actually not gonna be inclined internal
function and that's going to be a set
camera or something like this right and
set camera is going to take a game state
and that game state it's gonna take that
and it's also going to take what you
wanted to set the camera to be so
basically they'll be a tile map position
that is where you want the camera to be
a new camera P right so that's what I
want to do and so now instead of doing
this math directly what I want to do is
do it this way say there's going to be a
new camera P and then everything here
just operates on the new camera P okay
so we do this like so and then we say
new camera P right this is actually
going to go ahead and go up here so and
we're gonna have to deal with the entity
offset for frame in a more special way
as well which you may actually just do
in there for now but eventually we'll
probably try to roll it into a different
iteration so what we want to do now is
when we finish this we'll just call set
camera and in fact you know what I could
do for now actually to just to keep it a
little more straightforward I could do
it this way just for now so that we can
keep the same data flow that we had
before so we're not changing too many
things at once okay so we could do that
and we could say all right entity offset
for frame we go ahead and do that set
camera we past the game state and we
pass that new location that we want to
go to and so that should see tile map
that should be able to be ported pretty
directly so we have our D camera P is
just whatever the camera P was so we've
got in fact what is our what is our
actual camera P here there it is
canapé so we've got our game state
camera P and then we've got well
actually it's this way there we go and
then we've got our new camera P that's
basically what's going on here after we
do that difference
our gamestate camera P should be set to
the new camera P like so and then we
have then at the offset that we've
computed so that's just doing the same
thing that we were doing before
hopefully that'll still work just fine
when I walk off screen and then walk
back on screen yes we're moving camera
properly and so now what needs to happen
is whenever we do this move we now need
to do two things first we need to go
through all of our high-end entities
right so all of the entities that are in
the hiset and we need to remove them
right so we need to basically say well
not remove those that are too far away
right so we know where the camera is
right and we know what the end of the
offset for frame is so I guess when we
this this is exactly you know what this
is gonna happen immediately essentially
so I guess I didn't really need to do
that that's fine I guess that one one
little bit of testing yeah so get rid of
that so what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna
go ahead and and do it right here
eventually we may try to roll this in to
to another loop so we don't have to loop
over the highway rip and entities
multiple times but for now we'll do it
this way so we basically have our entity
index here right and we're gonna go over
all of those entities so this is the
array count of the high entities and
we're gonna look at them and say okay
let's go ahead and and get whatever
entity we're on and see index I should
mention you know this isn't normally the
way I'd do it by the way I've been doing
it this way for the sake of people who
watch because it's usually the way that
things are normally done I wonder if I
should just do it the way nobody good I
actually normally do it this way I don't
know what people think about that that's
how I usually when I'm not doing it for
the benefit of other people that's how I
usually actually write my array
accessors because then you don't have to
take the address of something
because this is essentially a
dereference er right that dereferences
the pointer and gets what it's pointing
to but I still want a pointer so I feel
like that's a little bit better maybe
we'll leave that for now what do you
know
all right so when we do this we're gonna
take the high end of the right and that
high entity we are going to go ahead and
take its P and we're gonna add the
entity offset for frame right and then
we're gonna check to see if that P is
inside or outside of basically are valid
rectangular region right and this is the
kind of thing that we probably will
start doing a lot of and so I kind of
feel like I may want to introduce
something here for example this is just
you know mm-hmm a convenient sort of
thing you could imagine wanting to do
something like is in rectangle right or
something like that where you basically
say here is the min here is the max you
know and here is the test value and
similarly what I almost would like to do
as well is just say that there's a
rectangle to write structure something
like that and it's got its min and it's
max right and we can test we can test it
that way why do I like to bundle them
like that so the reason that I like to
bundle my rectangle sometimes that way
is because rectangles oftentimes want to
be constructed in lots of different ways
if you do it this way it becomes very
hard to do right because let's say I do
is in rectangle and I want to test
inside a rectangle and I've got like the
center and the dimensions of the
rectangle right well then I've got to
first construct the min and the max here
right or have a function that constructs
them and then I gotta pass them into the
max right and it's just kind of annoying
whereas if I take a rectangle to here
like so then what I can do is I can
actually just
a bunch of functions that are like you
know wrecked min/max
you know these little just little inline
bundling functions that create
rectangles in different ways so rectum
max rect Center dim is another one that
I often do which is basically like you
know constructs a rectangle in in a
slightly different way so here's like
rectangle - this way looks like this
right gets just directly setting them in
the max of the rectangle but this
rectangle on the other hand does the min
is the center - the dim right and the
max is the center plus the dim so this
is basically like stores half width and
half height right like so on and I
should probably say that rec center half
dim just so you know that that's what
that is because we could do it the other
way but then we have to multiply by it
by 0.5 as well right and so you could
imagine lots of these like another one
would be rectangle min min dim right
would be another one that's very common
and so this one would actually be the
min sets the min and the max is the the
min plus the dim so that's like if I
want to do the corner and so that allows
me to do stuff like now when I call this
if I wanted to I can just do rec center
half dim here and I just pass it and
then I pass the thing that I'm trying to
do and it allows me to just have a lot
of different notations for stuff that
takes rectangles does that make sense
so that's just kind of you know that's
one of those things that I just know I
like from experience I there was no way
for me to know that just from looking at
the code I was doing they're just
something that I was thinking of it I
was like well if we're gonna do
rectangle it's probably good time for me
to talk about how I like to do that so
just something to think about there you
go in this case I don't think it'll be
particularly important for that I was
just sort of a thing a side and a side I
don't think will actually have to use
that here but that is how I typically
like to do it so I thought I'd do it
that way all right so anyway when I want
to do my inside rect
test right I've got my result here and
my result is going to be equal to
whether or not this guy is inside or
outside and here I remember the other
day gharlane abloom was asking about
whether I thought that inclusive
rectangles were okay because that's the
way like unity did it or whatever and I
think I said like just whatever you
write your code to expect and so for our
purposes here I feel like if I had to
guess I would say maybe we shouldn't do
them though I don't know I'm leaning
towards keeping our other rectangle
convention where the max is not the very
max is not included because it allows
you to but abut two rectangles so that
they're perfectly touching but that's so
something that's right on the edge only
falls into one or the other so for now
I'm not gonna do that but again like I
don't think unity is necessarily wrong
for doing it that way I just I just
don't know I just I just feel like maybe
we should try it this way and if it
turns out to be bad then we will switch
but for now I think that's probably the
way that I would prefer to do it okay so
obviously the test to see whether
something's in a rectangle is basically
just testing the four conditions the
four boundaries of the rectangle right
whatever my test thing was basically I
have to say that I want the test to be
greater than or equal to the min right
so both the Y on both the Y I want to be
greater than or equal to that min and
then the same is true for the max only
instead of less than or equal to I'm
just going to do less than so that we
don't include that final coordinate it's
just not quite in there not quite in
there yet right and so that would be a
point in a rectangle test right so it
tests this against this so that's you
know just a simple thing so I'm gonna go
ahead and do that here and again I just
kind of spam those out there we may have
all kinds of bugs in there we're not at
the point where we're testing things
rigorously or anything like that here
again this is just exploratory engine
code so you can see how things work so I
don't
care too much about that we'll debug it
as we as necessary so let's go ahead and
say so what we have here is our camera
inbounds or something right and the
camera inbounds is going to be a
rectangle centered about the origin so
it's a rec center half dim kind of a
situation certainly right and it's the
center is just going to be the origin
and because the definition of our local
coordinate system that we're doing
everything in is that the center point
where the cameras looking is at the
origin right and all of our high entity
positions are relative to that so then
it's just how big in meters is the
actual span of the area that I want to
cover and so we know we've got the tile
side in meters right and so the real
question is just how many tiles do I
want to have in that working set right
that's really all we have to decide here
and so we're gonna have another v2 it's
gonna be multiplied by this tile sided
meters and it's just gonna be how many
tiles we want in the working set so you
know let's say we did some we're just
totally you know this is just going to
be to do I am totally picking these
numbers randomly right I just figure
well we said we were 17 across so maybe
the dim and you know what I'm gonna make
another one here which is correct root
rec center dim so I can actually also do
one that just automatically does does
that x by half for me so Center 0.5 F
Jim again again just making it easy on
myself so I'm going to go ahead and do
recta rec center dim so I'm gonna say
that I want it to be 17 times 3 which is
just three screens worth that way and I
don't know what we said nine or
something times three up and down right
that's that's gonna be the camera in
bounce and oops it's no good
yeah so when I say this I'm just say say
that is all I guess I'll call it camera
bounce that is the camera bounce so from
then on I could check against those
camera bonds and say if this guy is in
the rectangle then it's okay that he's
here
but if he's outside the rectangle then
he's not allowed to be a high entity
anymore and he should become dormant so
I'll just do change entity residence at
that point right and I'll change the
entity residence for this entity index
right yeah game state where is my game
state changed it to the index so that's
probably gonna take the game state and
it's gonna take the fact that he can now
become low or dormant I don't really
know which one we want to do yet like I
said I guess I guess low is probably
what he becomes at that point all right
so that does the first part of the thing
that I need what is my problem here you
entity residents our whips it's the
other way around yeah camera doesn't
return to value so that goes that goes
ahead and demotes people but then we
have another thing we have to do which
is now we also have to take anyone who
should have come into being and you know
that is within there and those people
should come into the high empty set
right so as that camera moves to
encompass them they should come in there
right and so that's it to do because we
don't really have the knowledge to do
that yet and that's the thing that we
should start working on move entities
into hiset here and then the other thing
we want to do now is say all right let's
go ahead and move in any tiles that we
now have to sort of do the fake since we
don't really have it worked out quite
yet exactly how it would work we have to
move in the entities that should be
there for those tiles that are sort of
in the in the tile map and I guess now
now that I'm thinking about this
I don't know that I really want to go
ahead just yet and actually change the
tile map to be storing entities directly
but that's kind of where this is going
eventually right like what we want to do
eventually is the tile map just
basically now instead of being a tile
map that's that's that's locked where we
just have States of tiles I just want to
have those entities right in there where
the entities are sort of positioned so
that it creates whatever the map
actually is and I'm just trying to think
of how I would do that what's the
easiest steps to get to that point
whether I want to leave the tile map as
a tile map for now and generate entities
as we pull them in or whether I kind of
want them to be out there I think I
think I'm just gonna go for the gust oh
I feel like at this point I'm I'm happy
with the way these things are going and
I kind of want to just keep going in
that direction
so yeah well I forgot we had a jump in
the QA last night or levitate really
because there's no jump implies that I
couldn't keep doing it but he's more
like a hot-air-balloon essentially at
this point he's under the influence of
gravity but anytime we want to we can
always just make him float up by holding
down the up arrow so it's only if you
tap the up arrow that it's actually jump
in any real sense of the word
so anyway what I wanted to talk about
here was just say all right so maybe I
actually want to go ahead and start
doing that work for the tile map system
moving moving entities in and out of
that and what that would basically mean
is that you know those dormant entities
would actually be sort of stored if you
will in the tile map basically so in one
way or another the tile map is actually
sort of a compendium it's sort of a
thing that lets us pull out the entities
less so than something where we actually
pull out tiles from it right and that's
a pretty major change but again yet well
so what I want to do is do that
basically so that I could make it so
that all of these individual things were
tied
so there is one thing I can do to make
that transition a little easier what I
could do is just slam in some entities
that are basically walls that are that
are there right so let's try that let's
try that first because that's relatively
simple to do
so what's relatively simple to do there
is when we're actually creating these
things right when we're setting the tile
map value I could just flat-out add an
entity now that is whatever this thing
is right that that is at its location
and has that width and height right so
let's let's just do that we know what
the tile position is because it's the
ABS tile XY and Z which we've got right
and so I'm gonna add I'm gonna add so
that there's basically a little handmade
hero guy a little one of him all around
the whole outside right so let's go
ahead and do that so we've got
initialized an initialized player right
which which works this way I don't know
why we didn't do a dent atif or that
this maybe should have been an ad player
call what do you guys think about that
do you think it should be an ad player
call for now because we do at we do it
this way we just doing the ad right here
anyway so I kind of feel like we could
have just done it this way for now right
enemy and x equals ad player something
like that what do you think about that
seems reasonable to me
initialize player right so we just
facially have internal you went 30 to
add layer I don't know why I cut and
paste it that way that's dumb results or
I should say entity index equals entity
so and I guess what I don't know though
is does this guy have to no he doesn't
so
I don't think there's empty index yeah
yeah alright Adam D function does not
take yes that's true no second player
must return to value returned entity
index so there we go we change it to add
player and we run it and we can add a
player so that's good and now let's go
ahead and add another one of these that
adds a wall so let's do add wall for now
and what we want to do there is take a
tile map I guess we want to do ABS tile
X abs tight Y AB style Z so now since I
don't know what else really to set there
so we'll just do ABS X ABS Y ABS tiles Z
the offset can be nothing we are zeroing
these are we not though I feel like
additively already zeroes them yes it
does so I feel like there's really no
reason for that to be done I don't know
why we're doing it out there and then
the height is gonna be that game state
world tile map tile side and meters
right because that's how big our hmm
oops that's how big our tiles are
supposed to be on a side and it does
collide that's true and we don't really
care what its residence is I guess at
the moment that'll be a test to see if
it gets brought into the hiset when it
does and we would not want to follow the
camera so that's basically the entirety
of our ad wall code oh whoops
of course I accidentally and it hits the
wrong one but that's okay that's what
happens on the stream sometimes people
yeah you know it does alright so let's
go ahead and fix that they're freaked
out I don't even want to know what kind
of cut and paste mistakes I just
introduced there alright so in theory we
have now added
some walls oh well we haven't yet
because we didn't actually call it but
in theory we have written a function
that lets us add some walls and so let's
go ahead and do that so let's do add
wall and we will take the gamestate and
this stuff
right there it is and we'll see what
happens I don't know what happened Oh oh
my well you know that's that was a
mistake
and I admit that I realized that in
retrospect we should only add it when
there actually is a wall we did not do
that so you know my bad I'm sorry about
that
that was a mistake so let's go ahead and
say that let's pretend that didn't
happen pretend that we didn't just fill
the screens with with dudes and we'll go
ahead and try something else here so
we'll say okay which tile value do we
actually want we want tile value too so
only if the tile value actually equals
to will we use behind my head there okay
so there we go now I don't know why that
only happens oh I dunno why it only
happens nevermind and that's way too
much for our poor little really crappy
blit code to handle because especially
because we're not even trimming this guy
down so it's like bleeding and tire
extra you know a huge area around him as
well but that's correct now at the very
least and so in theory I can't go
through this either so that's all good
so what I'll probably do is change it so
that those walls will get drawn as just
little squares and then I'll stop
drawing the tile map but you'll notice
that it didn't actually add any of the
walls into the high entity set until we
actually did a set camera call and
that's because right we was waiting
until we had a camera following entity
to actually do that so it's until the
player joined it never called our set
camera call which is the thing that
brings things into the hiset so what we
wanted to do there right is we wanted to
go ahead and say
although now that I think about it we've
had to implement that yet either so
that's a little wonky right that is
bizarre
mmm that I'm gonna go ahead and step
into his I don't understand why that
just happened now that I think about it
now that I think about it because that
should not have worked that just
straight-up should not have worked why
did that work because we had implemented
that yet
I didn't actually write the code okay
Wow all right so uh all right I know how
it works now that was bizarre
okay okay Wow all right okay do I even
know it I don't know if I really know
how it worked
yeah I guess I maybe do so when we're
we're doing it here I think I would have
expected to see those entities right but
they didn't have their hi there they
hadn't actually been mapped into into
that space yet because it didn't have it
didn't have any those guys didn't have
any entity residents whatsoever right so
I guess what must have happened is when
we finally go and make the set camera
call it moves it must just be because
we're finally calling change residents
it just so happens that since they were
all non-existent well but yeah none of
them even pass so how is it tell me how
it is possible that any of these guys
are getting drunk what is going on here
that's just quite the that's quite the
oddity because I would have expected it
not to draw any of these right and it
doesn't draw them
okay I now know what's going on yeah
that was that was bizarre that was like
I guess that's our system being a little
bit too clever so because I wrote it so
that whenever you see what's happening
now finally because I wrote it that
whenever you ask for a thing at high
resolution it does the mapping correctly
and all that stuff as soon as the
collision detector we wrote the
collision detector so that we're just
like well for right now we'll just check
all the entities we wrote the collision
detector to check all the entities so
the collision detector actually is the
thing that goes through and makes all of
those guys come back up - hi oh that's
hilarious all right so it's actually
this call right here that's doing it so
that's pretty funny well I guess the
system's nice and resilient that's good
but that was not what I expected that
was not what I was trying to do at all
not what I was trying to do it all so
yeah okay that's fine let's go ahead and
do something a little more
straightforward here though so we can
kind of get get back to what we were
doing that was crazy I I didn't realize
I forgot kind of that I had made a
system that would always do the hi
movement correctly if you just asked for
one who wasn't already in the hiset I
don't know that I really want that to
happen I think I may want that to not be
the way it works but I forgot that I've
added that and so it was like hey poof
as soon as someone needs to know
magically everyone's map properly
surprised okay so let's go ahead and say
that inside our entity struck structure
here let's go ahead and make a entity
type as well for now right so we'll just
say entity type and inside there I'm
just gonna do there's a well will do
here oh and then we'll do wall and
that's really all we've got right now
so I'm gonna say that we've got to type
in here to type oops that's not our
entry structure though they're like so
and now I'm gonna say that whenever we
add the entity like this you're gonna
pass and add entity type that you want
that entity to be and then I'm just
gonna set it to that so we now know so
we can at least tell the difference
between a wall oops that's not right so
now we can tell the difference between a
wall and a player which of course is
something we would want to do so for the
wall we will set wall and for the player
we will set hero that and then that null
entity oh I guess that's a good thing
too we can also have a null entity right
so then when we actually draw the
entities we can just do a simple draw
rectangle call so what we'll do here is
we'll say okay if this entity if the
dormant entity type equals entity type
player or hero rather we'll do the hero
draw otherwise we'll do well I guess for
anything else that happens to exist
we'll do the draw rectangle call and so
that is gonna be in here okay and let's
think about this so how is this doing
it's doing the ground point meters two
pixels high and deep thing but the Blasi
player left top and entity with height
so I that might still be correct what I
want to do is stop drawing the tile map
entirely right so that goes away
and then we can just see what happens
here
so that looks right those are our tiles
right and in theory if I was to change
it so that we were going to disallow so
let's say we do two screens and we were
going to disallow disallow up-and-down
movement right so I'm just gonna say
that the random choice when it does this
it's going to always do one of the first
two so we're not gonna allow that up and
down we're not gonna allow the
stairwells anywhere Oh
conditional expression is constant
really I had no idea how could it
possibly be constant compiler thank you
for warning me you'd think of that it
would be smart enough to not warn you if
you put a 1 in there as opposed to
something evaluated to a constant but
that is not how compilers are written
ladies gentlemen well thanks for that
warning I guess I'll have to do this the
old-fashioned way
what are you smart enough to do that no
personally not all right so we'll just
do we'll just do this I guess yeah thank
you mister compiler for making my life
harder something that Microsoft to
science whole teams of people to do as
far as I know so if we do two screens
now in theory you can walk through here
and that's good but we only have two
screens again so all of those are
entities now and they appear to be
working correctly
so that's good of course there's so a
bunch of yellow blobs and we still
should be able to collide with things
even though they're on the other screen
right we're still treating them so I
still have to go through the wall to the
hole right that makes sense so that's
kind of cool and the other thing that in
theory should work as well is if we
wanted to do you know
smooth scrolling I feel like we could do
it at is at whatever granularity we
wanted right so that kept camera call I
think should probably work just fine if
we if we just always you know if we had
a much shorter tolerance so you know if
we if we did something that caused us to
be off alignment so for example if we
were doing something where it was just
like you know one or something in either
direction I don't know it's gonna work
quite right because of the hysteresis
and stuff but let's just see so if I do
it this way yeah so we can actually just
change the camera at whatever frequency
we want and it's all good so that's fine
as you can see that's all good and yeah
no real issues so that's good and I
think that's basically everything that I
wanted to do with that test all right
yeah we could actually do smooth going
to write up I don't really want that so
I'm not gonna actually bother but it's
good to know that that's just a good
test to run the make sure that
everything still works so we've got
about 10 minutes left so now I think
what I'd like to do is sort of
concentrate a little bit more on what we
were actually trying to do here with the
set camera moving stuff in so what we
want to do now is say move anything in
that sit have been in right and so again
the sort of the lousy way to do that is
to come through here and say go through
all of like the dormant entities right
and move them to high
so we basically say okay let's see what
the dormant entities are dormant and
dormant empties
and we will say that well I I just love
typing doormat I typed that so many
times if that's not reason enough to
call them dormant I don't know what is
because justing doormat all the time
it's funny and basically what we'll do
here is say that we'll move stuff into
the hiset and as I'm doing this by the
way I'm starting to be kind of convinced
that I probably only want to and not
three so there just be a high and a low
and there'd be no dormant I think it's
just gonna get too complicated with
three but just calling out my gut my gut
feeling
my feels as I feels them so when we're
doing this what we're gonna do now is
check because we're going to make this a
more intelligent query in the future
because this one's going to have to be
more spatial what I'd like to do here is
just test against the tile locations of
these guys so essentially this dormant
guy he's got the ABS tile X so basically
I say if it's ABS tile Z equals hours
right equals our new camera P AB style Z
that means he's on the same plane as us
so that's good and if the dormant P AB
style X is greater than equal to the min
tile X which will have to compute all
right blah blah blah so you know
something like this I guess I can do
this as a maximum X so if I do this
check and basically say when I loop over
the dormant entities if they are inside
the rectangular region tile map wise
then we're going to move them into high
right min tile Y min tile oops
maxed out x max hat Y and what I can do
here is just say that essentially these
are actually going to be computed off
the same stuff that this is right
essentially what I have here is
Tyl spandex and a tile span why this is
our towel spandex right
and this is our towel span Y which is
how big that camera view actually is not
the actual usable camera but sort of the
apron that Cole area that we want to
calculate and so the min tile X is just
going to be the negative of that right
and the positive there and right tile
right like so on yeah
so I think that is and it's it's half of
this right so it's it's a half it's a
half size I believe that's correct with
who should be brought in
she should be brought into the system so
now what are you complaining about
you know - oh yeah sorry about that
my bad I admit that I admit that so this
is going to be camera bounds sorry a new
camera P ABS tile X - because this is
based off of where the camera actually
is obviously plus plus so that's
actually what I wanted now again we're
we're you know we're there's a little
bit of a bug here that really doesn't
affect us much but remember we're not
supposed to be wrapping and we will be
wrapping here because we haven't moved
the world to the center yet so there's a
little bit of a bug here but I don't
think it affects us yet so we don't
really have to worry too much about it
you just got to put those hands in there
there we go and so now I think we would
be correct yes oh there we go well of
course I don't actually know yet because
I have to call that set camera call at
the start of the game as well so what we
want to do we want to do that set camera
somewhere where you can force it to
actually do the entity change
so what we want to do there is say
basically when we start the game really
when we do this camera P what we'd want
to do is actually you know make the
camera P be set this way right so we'd
want to do is say a tiled map position
camera new camera P right and we'd want
to we'd want to set the new camera P AB
style X and AB style Y and then we just
want to we want to set it that way so
that we set the we set the camera
exactly that way now I don't know why
it's being set there though so I feel
like all of this stuff should actually
happen at the very end so that
everything gets moved in properly what
did I do badly they're missing initially
yes it is miss exact : so that should
actually get things initialized properly
now it's startup I would think but it
still didn't why is that so let's take a
look at what happened there I think I've
typed too much code oops that's the
wrong set camera call there we go that's
the one we actually want so let's take a
look at what happens here we come
through there are no entities in the
high set at the moment well oh well I
guess there are so of course what I
should do here as well although this is
going to change pretty soon as well I
should do this as well let's see if game
state into your residents the index
equals high so we should only actually
check the people who are at high alright
so go and and this is going to be for
the people who are dormant and I believe
should be remember to actually set would
be the other thing
did we remember to actually set the wall
to dormant or not yes we did okay so
that's good all right but we're still
not working properly so we got a we got
a debug this here we've got about a
minute left before the QA because the
timer is still running one minute ahead
I gotta remember to fix that so we come
through here and and we shouldn't have
any entities in hi right so those should
all get skipped right we should come
down here and we should compute these so
I wonder if this is our wrapping yeah
nevermind you know I said the wrapping
wouldn't bite us and it totally did
right it totally did that's too bad
I'm alright so we do have the problem
that we're on the edge of the world so I
think we're gonna have to solve that get
that wrapping thing straightened out so
let's go ahead and and say that we'll do
that first thing tomorrow where we'll go
ahead and and actually address the
wrapping problem because you know we've
kind of done what we wanted to do in
terms of splitting things up a little
bit and the next step is to get these
things rolling through a nice having not
having totally duplicate arrays for
everything and storing the guys more
sensibly in the tile map anyway so that
kind of dovetail nicely they're just
going okay let's go into the tile map
and actually make it will actually make
it store them sparsely so that we can
start in the middle of the world instead
of all the way at the end like so so
yeah so let's say that what we'll do
tomorrow that'll be our thing and so
this will be our to-do to concentrate on
on tomorrow all right so let's go ahead
and and and start the QA then so if you
could let's see CD I gotta set up my
little thing here if you could please
prefix your questions with Q :
so that I can see them and please keep
the questions to stuff that we have done
today or that
we'll do that we did on a previous one
if you want to ask stuff about like
stuff we're going to do or if you want
to ask stuff about just totally off
topic questions those are totally fine
but ask them during the pre stream so
come about 15 minutes before the stream
starts on any given day and I'll answer
I answer all kinds of crazy questions
then
all right sort of the signs of them they
may well be someone's asking if some of
the signs are wrong in the mint I'll
xiii put those in quite quickly yes they
are but of course the wrapping we have a
wrapping problem whether those are right
or wrong so unfortunately I don't think
that's gonna help us here these are
these are all kinds of messed up
actually so this is if we actually want
to do this let's let's fix that so we've
got mint i'll xmax tuile X min tau Y max
tau Y AB style X ABS top X tau Y okay so
the min is the absolute minus the half
span this should be twice the half span
of Y so these are all wise men men AB
star y yeah there we go
all right but again I think we're still
we're still not gonna yeah it still
isn't gonna work because just because of
the wrapping problem so but yes good
catch that was wrong we just you know
what does internal modifier which is
applied to the set camera function I
mean what is the difference between non
static and static function so basically
it may seem a little bit like voodoo and
it is I guess a little bit like voodoo
because of the unity build but I can
explain that
so internal is just a pound to find that
I pound to find two static so it's the
same as saying static which obviously
you already knew because you put that
into the question so the question is why
am i defining these functions as static
and the answer is because any function
that is not defined as static can be
linked by the linker to other compiled
modules right that's that's what static
being static means that when I compile a
particular what's called a compilation
unit which is oftentimes one CPP file
but the way we're doing it it's lots of
secret files cuz i you know concatenate
them together during the compile right
static says do not put this function in
the table of functions that are actually
in this compiled module don't export it
no one else could call it only the
people inside this same module can call
it compilation unit is the correct term
so the reason I do that is because since
I know that we're just one big bill
we're just one big unit II build right
we you any bill is the term for when you
put all of your CPP files you just pound
include them all into one translation
unit right and you just go sorry when I
said complex me I met translation unit
before too many terms so basically if
you have a system where you're compiling
lots of different CPP's they compile the
CPP is compiled to OBJ's well you know
what I'll just draw it might as well
draw it so this is the typical set up in
C for C++ or whatever right the typical
setup is you have a dot H file or
sometimes a dot h PP file depends on how
people do it and a dot CPP file right
and these define like you know a class
or something right so the definition of
the class goes in here and the class
contents go in here
right and then you have tons of these
right so you've got like 500 of these
pairs right and you compile them right
you call the compiler to translate each
CPP file over into a dot obj file right
and the obj file is basically assembly
language but it's not really it still
has a bunch of sort of markup in it
because what's gonna happen is for all
500 these you're then going to get 500
obj files right and those all have to go
and this this is the compiler that's
doing the step right those then have to
go with the linker here's the linker
gathers up all the obj files and that
makes it into an executable right and so
the question is at this stage when the
linker takes these OBJ's and builds them
into an executable
how does it know how to resolve cross
cpp function calls so if i have two
CPP's Fuu dot CPP and Bar dot CPP which
are both part of this build and they're
both becoming obj files right so
actually I'll be more success
excuse me I'll be more specific they
become food obj when they get compiled
in bar obj right I've done the compile
here and let's say bar calls a function
inside foo what that means is that foo
had to have that function defined in one
of its H file somewhere bar had to
include that H file and then when they
became obj files the compiler had to put
something in to these to sort of leave
the name dangling so let's say the
function was called blah right it had to
put a thing in here which basically said
you know this calls blah
and had to put a thing in here that said
here's where blah is and then the linker
is responsible for making these things
line up it's a put its roster for taking
the call to blah and patching it so it
actually calls the location of where
blah is when it assembles these OBJ's
into a big executable so food out obj
goes somewhere in here right into the
executable Wow so here is the food obj
but it's not really the obj it's like a
condensed version right it's it's
compiled down and bar dot obj goes
somewhere in here right and it finds the
call to blah and it patches it to just
point directly into wherever food obj
actually is so that the name blah is not
still sticking around hopefully all that
makes some sense now what happens when
you call something static is that let's
the compiler know it doesn't have to
record what the name of it was because
nobody else can call it so what that
means is your obj files get smaller and
your link time goes down because now
it's not looking at this giant table of
8,000 10,000 20,000 strings that are all
the functions in your program so you
always want to put static on anything
that you can because if you don't call
it outside of its translation unit the
static will will reduce that compile
time overhead and again this is all
total crufty nonsense right crufty
nonsense that it's because c and c++ has
such a broken compilation model that you
even have to care about this because you
should never be thinking about this it's
it's dumb but that's just the way it
goes yeah hopefully that makes some
sense
why do we consider a wall and entity so
the reason that we consider a wall empty
is for two reasons and to be clear we
don't consider a wall in envy I am
considering considering well identity
this is again exploratory code so I'm
seeing how I like it there are two
reasons I consider a wall identity
reason number one is because I would
like to have a uniform way in which I
process things so I basically like to
have it so that everything that's in the
high entity list there's basically just
one big thing which is sort of like here
is a uniform way you can look at all of
the things that have collision info
because that's gonna be something that
we have to deal with and spatially sort
and whatever right the second reason
that I want walls to be entities is
because I would like you to be able to
do stuff to walls potentially I'd like
to be able to potentially damage them
I'd like you to be able to potentially
imbue them with properties for example
if something that has a magical property
hits a wall that wall should now have
that magical property so I I want to
probably have the flexibility to have
walls be active rather than just sitting
there and so those are the two reasons
that I'm sort of considering it now that
doesn't mean that that's what we'll do
in the end it's just what I'm
considering now well tile chunk in town
that structures go away and walls will
be stored only as entities no the tile
chunk and tile map will stay but I'm
what I'm leaning towards is they will
become the things that hold dormant
entities we have to do some cool screen
shakes and some whip pan transitions
between screens noted and we will do we
will do exactly that will there be a
doormat enemy there will be now let me
open up the reminders file
let's see reminders doormat entity don't
know what he'll do but we'll definitely
have one okay can we have some old man
that transforms you into a dog and says
you're the dog now man that's that's a
lot of work but okay into a dog and says
you're the dog now man alright I will
take care of that just for you garland
Oh bloom uh so that looks like it for
questions I don't see any more am I
wrong about that
I will wait a little bit just to see if
there's any other questions otherwise we
can all go home early I see nothing all
right cool well that is it for tonight
then we are in we are in pretty good
shape I think so this should be pretty
straightforward
like I said we're kind of getting close
to the point where we're like I'm
thinking maybe next week will be time to
do some gamey stuff as well just maybe
making some hit points and that sort of
stuff
oh thank you
Thank You mo Zuko that is that is a very
good idea he reminded me that there was
a collision thing that we wanted to do
that we were talking about in the forums
that was wrong and I said I'd like to
fix it on streem so we should fix that
there was a calculation bug in the
collision detector er we've player that
makes him be able to move a little
further than he should
so let's yeah let's fix this that's a
great idea thank you very much
thank you very much for reminding me
because now we've got some time it's a
great time to fix it so here was the
problem I'll tell you what I thought I
was doing but I didn't actually type
this in
so hey guess what it's not what I was
doing so here's mr. wall right and
here's a dude who's trying to step
through the wall what we were doing is
we were finding the point of collision
right and then we were taking this
vector and we were clipping off the part
of it that ran against the wall
so what I was thinking in my head I was
I was like oh okay that means we'll be
generating that vector right and so the
next time we try to do a move we should
try to move the whole distance of that
vector because we've already taken care
of the fact that there's less distance
now to go right but that's not what I
actually typed in what I actually did
was I took this vector and clipped it so
now it's that long and then I applied it
here so really there's an extra amount
that he can go there that he shouldn't
have been able to go so in my head I was
thinking I was doing that but actually
that's not what I did right and you can
see what I typed it in here right I
clipped player Delta which is this whole
distance not just the distance from here
to here which is actually what I was
trying to clip right hopefully that
makes some sense and so yeah I think if
I'm not mistaken I think you could
probably do this and at the risk of
making now a bug on top of a bug I'm
gonna try doing something a little
different I think you might be able to
just get rid of T remaining altogether
so basically like I think you might be
able to do it this way so you just get
rid of T remaining and instead what you
do you know there's there's player Delta
right player Delta and instead of
actually clipping player Delta what we
do is we take wherever player Delta
would have put us so new player P right
is where we
be and so player Delta is essentially
equal to whatever wherever the player is
player Delta once we know where the
player would have liked to have gone
right so basically we say at the start
of this what we're gonna do this
iteration we just say target position or
a desired position is just wherever the
player was right so old player P or I
should say wherever he is now so
whatever we update what do we update we
update entity hi P right so we say
wherever the player is plus whatever
we're trying to do that's where he wants
to be we'll do the update and then
instead of updating player Delta this
way right
we'll say player Delta now equals
desired position minus the current
entity position I think that is is
actually correct right because that's
doing what I thought I was doing in my
head
so we'll see so I believe that's
actually more correct now but yeah we'll
see
so that just gets rid of that T
remaining thing which was kind of
annoying and I didn't really like it
and so now we don't really have to worry
about the T remaining so much and so
what I'm doing now right because I'm
just going okay so we have here two here
right this is player Delta right this is
player Delta that span when we hit
something I then compute this as player
Delta right because this we have a
desired location I then compute this
vector I clip it and then I try to move
by that and that'll work if I hit the
wall again right it'll keep doing that
so I think that's more correct and again
you guys can take a look at it now
and see if you agree with me and we can
take a look at offline iostream so I
think that is more
correct and it won't do the wrong
calculation for the case where he hit
just that one frame where he hits the
wall it would be wrong right
what do you think of message buses and
what is your favorite implementation of
one I'm sorry I don't think I really
know what you mean by message bus if you
want to post on the forums a link to one
I can take a look at it though are you
planning on having any game screens that
pan the camera I wasn't really planning
on it but I want to make sure we support
it if that makes sense so like we may
use it in some places I don't know but
either way I want to make sure that the
game works without it because there are
people who wanted to learn how to do
free scrolling stuff so we're going to
do we're going to make sure that we
allow that sort of thing as well
all right I think we're basically done
this I don't think this question is
particularly on topic but have you ever
played path of exile or heard of it they
have this desync problem that they claim
is unfixable because they handle stuff
server-side just wondering if you've
heard of that game it's or torus bugs so
what I would say is that obviously
nothing is unfixable really so that's a
bit odd but no I'm sorry I haven't heard
of that so I can't really speak about
bugs that they may or may not have sorry
about that
all right looks like we are basically
done basically done so let me see if
there's any other off topics to answer
here are using a stylus and creature or
a mouse
stylists most the time but sometimes I
use the mouse if I don't want to grab
the stylus so as I use the mouse as well
depends on which is easier all right
just forcing a game to a certain refresh
rate introduced lag uh it depends what
you mean by lag I would I would highly
recommend going back and watching one of
the earlier videos where I draw the
frame-by-frame diagrams and talk about
where things get displayed on the screen
and so on monitors most monitors
nowadays have a fixed refresh rate
anyway so you kinda have to sync to that
if you want to have a image that gets
displayed properly now you know there's
I talked to yeah I guess I say is I go
back and go back and watch those and go
back and watch those I've talked a lot
about that and it'd probably be
retreading it here if I answered it
again let's see all right well I'm gonna
call it for now
cuz you seem to be mostly off-topic
questions so but if you do want to do
off-topic shot I do enjoy a good
off-topic chat and we do so for about 15
minutes before the stream every time so
definitely don't don't forget you're off
topic questions I would be happy to
answer them
I just like to to do those and
non-record in part of the Q&amp;A because
sometimes they get silly and you know
and we're goofing around and so I just
try to keep that for the free stream so
come back tomorrow we'll be here at same
time same place 8 p.m. Pacific Standard
Time right here on twitch so come back
tomorrow if you want to do about 15
minutes before 8 p.m.
let's say Pacific Standard Time if you
want to do off-topic chat because we
always do off talk chat and it's usually
a lot of fun so hope to see you there
anyway thank you for joining me for
another episode of hand made here it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to get a copy
the source code to play around with that
home you can pre-order the game and it
comes with a source code so if you
preorder here on handmade hero org you'd
get a copy of source code and you can
play around with it just like I'm doing
try your own stuff out see and try to
learn along with the stream if you're
interested in low-level programming that
sort of stuff
and and if you do and you want to ask
questions about it you can go to our
news and forum site which has a bunch of
stuff for example it's got an episode
guide for catching up with old episodes
got the schedule of the week posted
every week on Monday I've got a coding
resource
page which basically lists all sorts of
people who have contributed like ports
to Mac or Linux or guides about how to
do certain things and there's been a lot
of people have done some really cool
stuff there I highly recommend checking
it out especially if you're trying to
follow along on a Mac or on Linux it
could make your life a lot easier and
then it also about for if you can you
can post questions on if you have
questions I answer questions on there so
do other people who are experienced
programmers so it's a great place to go
talk about the series so however been
checking it out if you're traveling from
Sirius it's a great place and of course
we also have a patreon if you would like
to subscribe to support the video series
you can do so right there that's about
it until tomorrow again hope see
everyone here 8:00 p.m. start time
tomorrow come fifty minutes early if you
want to be in the pre stream off-topic
chat and we will do some more entity
coding it's starting to get exciting now
I'm starting to get starting get pretty
excited about this yeah yeah still got
one more big thing the render is gonna
be a big thing we gotta get through but
we're starting to get we're starting to
get to some of the really cool stuff but
the render is gonna be a lot of fun - I
think people really enjoy it so we'll
see all right thanks everyone and I will
see you tomorrow