hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show recode a complete game
live on stream yesterday we added some I
don't even want to say we added some
lighting I basically just showed the
rudimentary first step I did a bunch of
stuff on the blackboard so you can
understand kind of various lighting
principles and we implemented the very
first step in putting some lighting into
the engine in just a few minutes all we
did basically was do a radial fall-off
to show how to light things and you know
amusingly enough so today it's a 390 so
if you're finally at home used a 389
source code but amusingly enough it's
surprising it is always surprising how
good fake things look at first when even
if you just get them a little bit
correct it's funny and I think in games
you know the people who play games are
so used to approximations and artistic
interpretations of things at this point
that getting things like the lighting
equation photorealistic or correct is
not even remotely required for people to
appreciate the effect and so here is an
example of like the dumbest possible
thing it's literally just a radial
fall-off there is no lighting at all in
terms of surface calculations or
anything but you can see that even just
putting in a radial fall-off function
already gives a fairly convincing
lighting effect it's like you know even
just that one little thing you can
already kind of see why it adds
something to a game to have some
lighting in there and so that's what we
did now at the end of the stream we
threw in normals normals are the ability
in the vertex stream to specify the
direction that surfaces are facing so
you know a flat surface saying what
direction that flat surface is facing
for example so the canoes in
calculations and what we're going to do
today is just play around that a little
bit to see if we can make this lighting
a little bit more accurate by adding the
idea that the directionality of the
surface off of which the light is
bouncing will determine some of the
lighting and we
talked about why this was yesterday
because of course lighting is a
directional function and have to do with
the SIRT the micro structure of the
surface it's bouncing off will determine
how the light bounces so knowing the
direction the service is facing is
important since surfaces bounce light
differently in different directions
depending on their micro facet geometry
so now that we did that work yesterday
what we would like to do here is have a
way of taking into account those normals
and what you can see from what we did on
the stream yesterday is in the render
group when we do our push quad function
and again everything in our game comes
through this push quad function at the
end because everything in our game is
quads our cubes are made up of quads our
sprites our quads just have an image
flapped on them so everything comes in
this function and all this function
really does right you can see here is it
just generates four virtus pieces of
information for the vert as vertex
records basically that are streamed
after the graphics cards this is just
writing to memory and that memory is
going to get picked up by the graphics
card that's all we do okay so if you
take a look at what happens in here you
can see that we're now specifying
normals and those normals we we
basically generate them by taking a look
at the quad and saying whatever this
direction the quad is facing we generate
vectors that point in that direction now
you may ask a very reasonable question
which is why do we need to specify those
at all because shouldn't the graphics
are just be able to know if we specify a
triangle it knows the triangle is a flat
triangle it knows which direction is
facing the answer is because most of the
time in computer graphics when we are
generating triangles to try to
approximate three-dimensional objects
that we want to draw they aren't always
supposed to be flat right a lot of times
you may be generating triangles that are
supposed to comprise say a person's face
or a round ball or you know a
cylindrical shape a post a lamppost for
example these things are supposed to
not b-flat and so what we do there is we
say that the normals are specified
separately from the triangles the
triangles are used to fill the shape in
on the screen and we try to make the
triangles dense enough that you can't
really see the hard edges very much but
the lighting would be very obviously
faceted if we just drew each triangle as
flat because as it curves around the
curved surface each of those flat
triangles is going to reflect the light
very obviously differently and you see
hard lines so the reason we always
specify normals per vertex or most of
the time specify normals per vertex is
specifically because we often want to
specify normals that are smooth across
the vertices so that it's takes the
lighting to be continuous right and it
can make things that are comprised that
a flat shape like triangles seem round
because as the interpolation of the
normal goes across the surface you end
up with something that approximates a
more smooth blending equation for us on
handmade hero fortunately we don't
actually have that situation at all yet
we don't have to care so we are actually
just specifying the same normal for
times and we could be doing something
more efficient there if we really cared
on modern hardware you can do a lot of
stuff like specifying the normals in a
separate vertex stream that only get
specified once for every N vertices in
this case it would be 6 3 3 for each
quad you know 3 vertices for triangle
but actually I guess no these are
indexed so we would only specify 1 / 4
because these are actually indexed so
nevermind I so anyway that's the idea
there and we are specifying these
normals we're specifying them by taking
the cross product of the edges of our
quad and we're pointing all the normals
out in that direction to give us flat
surfaces which is what we want now we
don't have any way of knowing right now
whether those are correct because we're
not throwing them we probably should try
to draw them but we're not going to
right now we're just going to cross our
fingers at the moment and see where we
get with that what I'm going to do is
I'm going to pop over to the OpenGL code
and I'm going to take a look at the
shader that we have here which is
who's this one so what you can see here
is that we don't even take the normal in
yet even though we're specifying it and
of course we want to so what I'm going
to do is I'm going to start taking in
that vertex normal by specifying here
what it'll do is remember yesterday at
the end of the stream we specified a
vertex and array now we're actually
going to give that amount point so that
when the program code says hey is there
ever an array if so I'd like such high
it will actually find something to
specify we're going to pass that normal
through directly because we don't really
have anything else we need to do with it
so I'm just going to say we're going to
pass a world pose and a world normal I
might change those to world P in world n
because I don't really like delivering
the point so let's just do it this way
there's the world po-faced position and
the world space normal and then when I
go through and look at world post here
we'll just go ahead and make that a
little bit more straightforward vacuum
is going replace pose oops
replace photography there we go
okay so in theory now that should allow
us to get normal into our code of course
we're not using it yet so when I run it
we should basically get if I de bug any
things we have under the world pose oops
forgot to fix that in the vertex shader
here we go
we should just get the same results
you're getting for so no change here and
the only difference now is that in the
fragment shader we have access to the
normal so we can do something with the
normal if we want to do something with
the normal now there's another thing
that I kinda have to do here that'll
temporarily make our graphics be a
little bit worse and that is that the
color of our cubes needs to change a
little bit so if you remember correctly
the way that we were doing our cubes in
the render group we actually specify the
colors differently per side of the cube
you can actually see in push cube here
we were generating these colors
Ct CD right you can see those top color
bought colors dbcc all that stuff
okay expensive ice here and that was to
give our it a little bit of a sort of
gradient to make it feel like it was
getting lit a little bit in a fake way
right for the moment I want to stop
doing that and I want to go back to just
sort of overriding everybody with that
same color that's being sent down and so
what's going to happen there you can see
that now we're just getting lighting on
the cubes and there's not any there's no
differentiation between the various
surfaces of the cubes right they're
completely arbitrary
all of them are specified with the exact
same color so all we're getting is those
two fixed lights that I'm just playing
with right now that are always centered
at zero zero and you can see that it's
lighting everything exactly the same way
right there's no difference there
whatsoever um so that's a thing we got
to start with because we don't want that
fighting with our lighting yet that
doesn't mean we won't play with that a
little bit more in the future
potentially but for right now we don't
want to touch it so then we go ahead and
we say all right here's our program our
lighting program and I'm going to turn
off one of the lights for now I'm just
going to use one light like so and this
is going to be the light that's in the
middle so there's that light and I'm
just going to now start editing this
lighting equation to use those normals
that are coming through now one of the
things about the normals that come
through that's a little confusing and I
want to mention it here because it's
going to look like I don't need to do it
but I actually would have in other
circumstances is that this is and
actually I got a launched Milton I
forgot it rebooted this machine because
Windows wasn't finding the network of
course where could the network possibly
be so let me go ahead and launch Milton
up here and
a little day 90 normal interpolation so
the normal interpolation here on day 3
90s I want to talk about is just so if I
were to take up a triangle right and I
want you to think about the case where
for example like I talked about before
where there's a cylinder for example so
here's like my cylinder and let's say
that I was sort of drawing triangles on
the surface of this cylinder so you know
they look kind of like that well if you
take any given part of this here where
two of these triangles sort of meet up
right like this section here you've got
topology that looks something like this
right and what we know is this is
actually on a curved surface so the
normals for these things are going to
bend right each normal is going to be
pointy a different direction such that a
given triangle will have normals that
are pointing actually in different
directions right it's that one would be
the same if this one group the cylinder
there you go
right what that means is over the
surface of a triangle normals typically
will interpolate and if I took this and
laid it on its side so you could see
here's a triangle laying flat and I've
got one normal pointing this way and
I've got one normal pointing that way
let's say right like here and here not
to these two what you would notice is
that these two normals and I'm not
drawing these particularly well here I
should probably draw them to scale we
know that they're unit length so
actually it would be something more like
this right now the way we want to you
know if each of these is a unit length
the way we want these to work is we want
them to work kind of like this where
each time we interpolate the normal we
get a new unit length normal right we
want the length of our normal to equal
one at all times the reason we want to
do that because we're going to be taking
dot products with it and doing other
things where we don't want its length to
affect our computation so we want it to
be length one unfortunately what's going
to happen remember is
when we pass these down it's just like
everything else like fragment color and
that sort of stuff whenever we have a
vertex shader that outputs something to
the fragment shader that something is
linearly interpolated across the surface
now it's not strictly linear
interpolation because remember we get
perspective correction in there so it's
actually not really linear interpolate
it but it's linearly interpolated in
world space right it's just not linearly
interpolating the screen face because
it's pressure but if you put that out to
the side right now because all we're
talking about the moment is
interpolation in world space that we
actually care about and so that will be
happening linearly just like the
stepping along the triangle happens
linearly for all intents and purposes
you're never going to get something that
lies off of the line off of the triangle
right it's going to everything would be
on that triangle the same ends up being
true for normals so the normals will
also be interpolated in a line and what
that means is let's take a very
exaggerated case here's a two you know
one an edge of the triangle let's say we
had a normal pointing that way and a
normal pointing that way if you look at
what's happening here in between those
two we should get a normal that looks
like that we're actually going to get is
a normal that points yes in that
direction but that's much shorter right
it could be you know half the length
that it should be so instead of a length
of one instead of the length of the
normally glowing one the length of this
normals going to equal like point five
or something right so not only that but
we're not getting spherical
interpolation here so we're not getting
you know we're not getting that so as a
result when you interpolate linearly
across this you're also going to get a
difference in acceleration of the normal
so instead of a smooth rotation through
here it's actually going to have more at
the points than it does in the middle
it's going to get faster in the middle
meaning the the interpolation that are
one's going to change more dramatically
but at the end simply because a line is
getting projected out to an arc and
that's what happens in the line gets
projected out to an arc right you can
see this yourself just by drawing it if
you draw it like this so let's say I
have
it and I take an even number of steps
along it like so right so here these are
roughly equivalent steps if I then look
at what happens if I were to actually
take the real Ark here right if I extend
those outward look at what happens well
you know this is a really bad dry ground
I got it I got a little bit better than
that okay I'm gonna try really hard to
draw a really good diagram here heaven
help me this is the worst circle ever
okay
so this part looks sort of circular
let's say there we go so let's say we
were going to take and use this as our
interpolation right so here's the
halfway mark here's the halfway mark
there let me see if I can do this
all right so I'll try my best to make
this work here I need like a ruler tool
or something
oops
so I didn't do as good as I would have
hoped but it's still good enough right
so hopefully you can see the difference
in speed that's happening there right
the distance between these two for
example is much less than this is
between these two and so that's what's
going to happen when you linearly
interpolate what is meant to be a
spherical quantity you're going to get
the angular interpolation is going to
get much more quick in the middle of
your things and much slower towards the
end right and so normally what you have
to do with normals normally yes too is
normals is you have to renormalize them
in the fragment shader or come up with
some other encoding scheme that's going
to interpolate properly right you have a
lot of different ways you could approach
it but you know the simplest one would
just be lets renormalize an illustrator
when you do that what you're spectively
doing is doing this projection outwards
to the speed the speed is wrong but
everything else is fine so all the rest
Cal goes right it's just the
interpolation is a little bit more wonky
than it should be right but for our
cases we have a much better situation we
only have cubes right and sprites
variables flat which means that for each
primitive we never round anything
we're always drawing a flat face on
something so our normals are always
playing the same direction which means
not only do we not to worry about that
speed problem because we're not
interpolating between anything they're
just constant right but we also don't
have to renormalize because the length
will stay one because they're not
actually bending at all and technically
if we wanted to instead of this being
smooth out we could probably actually
have this just be flat out but I don't
want to push my luck and start using
lots of different qualifiers because who
knows anyway so I'm not going to have to
do any of those things that I just said
but I want you to be aware of them
because if you're doing your own stuff
here and you want to make a curve privat
--iv or if we ever have to make a curve
primitive on handmade Hiro will have to
be aware of it all right so here's our
light distance fall-off here is the
amount of light that we have here now
what I want to do is I want to break up
this equation a little bit so the
distance equation right we all know what
the distance equation is
in this case it's the P - I guess we
should say the P of the surface - the P
of the light rank we're taking the
length of that that's the distance but
the problem with this equation right is
this produces a scalar that just tells
us how far away from the light we are
but we need more information for that
now we also need to know what direction
the light is shining on us because we
want to start to talk about these
surfaces and now we have the surface
normal because we specified that and we
know what point on the surface we're
talking about but now we need to know
some things right we need to know where
the viewer is right we need to know
where the viewer is and we need to know
where the light is because we want to
start constructing a reflection equation
here that will tell us how light is
supposed to bounce off of the surface so
we've got this we don't have this we
don't have this and we need to start
getting them now we did produce
essentially this because this equation
right here taking the length of PS minus
TL well what's PS minus PL well this is
PS and this is PL right so if we did PS
minus PL we would get this vector which
is the inbound lighting vector which is
exact what we want we want an outbound
lighting vector we can just switch these
two terms and do PL minus PS and get
that vector so whatever vector we want
we can get it pretty easily and that's
great right so without doing any more
work if I literally just pull out this
equation into two steps excuse me so
here's my vector that goes to the light
I can just say light P - royalty right
and now I can normalize this essentially
for free because I know I have to take
the light distance so I can say you know
length and you'll forgive me for never
remembering what the GLSL intrinsics are
GLSL reference card there you go just
lengths so if we take the length of that
to produce our like distance we then
know that we can normalize the vector to
the light by just saying I want to take
two light and I want to divide it equals
it by whatever that light
distance is right so this produces a
normalized to light vector we know we
have a world end vector so now we at
least know we at least know this and
this right so even with just that if we
assume a perfectly diffused surface we
could go ahead and dot product these two
together to emulate a fall-off of the
light as it approaches a steeper angle
to the surface right all right so let's
take a look at that so right now we're
doing this let's just rerun this here to
make sure that we're still computing the
fall-off properly right because we
haven't changed anything the fall-off
juice will be right and it does look
right so that's good but now we want to
do is take that two light vector and I
want to do the dot product of the two
light vector with that surface normal
right so now we're going to be producing
basically remember how many times we
talk about the dot product in the past
well it's coming back if it always comes
back right so now we've got essentially
this two lights vector we call that L
we've got n with dot product with L
right that's what we're producing here
now what what does that give us right
we've got in we got L what does that
give us well everyone everyone who's
left handmade hero had better be saying
it out loud right now it is the length
of n the length of L times the cosine of
the angle between them the angle between
them is right here right and anyone who
didn't just say that who has been
watching the series I'm going to
personally come over there and slap you
about the face a little bit just a
little bit not enough to leave any kind
of bruises okay so the M length of n
length of L cosine theta is what we're
going to get out of that now what do we
already say well this and this have
already been normalized right life of n
is one length of L is one so neither of
these two things is going to contribute
to this equation at all so all this will
compute is the cosine of the angle
between them right so this is the cosine
of the angle to our light source right
here and that is exactly what we would
need
to simulate the inbound lighting
equation right meaning if all we wanted
to do was pretend that all this surface
did was radiate light in every direction
whenever light hits it from any angle so
a completely diffuse perfect chalk
surface well remember what happens is
that when light comes in it comes in you
know as as light hitting the surface
when light hits the surface the angle to
the light at which it hits the surface
right here is the angle which it hits
the surface the cosine of that is going
to be oops I wrote that in the wrong way
there we go
here's the address better and in fact
you know what this has always been
confusing to me for letting Cuevas so I
might work this out right now just to
satisfy my own self let's just let's
just do this out the whole way because
I'm interested to do it so first of all
we have in inbound light right and the
inbound light is coming in at the
surface and we can assume that when it
strikes the surface if it's striking it
for a particular direction the cosine
rule should still apply right so here is
the inbound light and this triangle here
right this is the lighting direction
there's theta right and the right angle
the triangle is right there yeah so
here's the hypotenuse right there and
this right here is the amount of light
that's striking the surface in that
sense so it's reading the light out on
the surface proportional to basically
inverse of that cosine right so this
right here is the cosine of theta or I
should say H cosine theta so if we
assume this is just a unit size right we
would just have cosine theta is the
spreading function of this light so all
the light that comes in falls on cosine
Thetas worth of surface or so I should
say cosine cosine theta
worth of light falls on a unit length
surface right so 1/2 the cosine of theta
if you will right equals you know
surface light over incident light if
that makes sense this is the parts that
I've never really quite understood about
letting poisons I don't do a lot of work
with them so I just wanted to sort of
write out the equations for my own
amusement to see if they line up
intuitively or if you have to go make a
special leap right now for the viewing
direction you also get another situation
right where this exact same thing
happens so whatever angle I'm viewing at
and this is cosine Phi this is like a
different there's going to be a
different angle right the viewing
direction so this is the light up here
this is a viewer coming in here right so
the viewer on the other hand is is
viewing one units worth right of ups and
now to put this one units worth of the
surface is going to go out on cosine
Thetas worth of space right so if you
think about how much light you're
actually getting out on this shaft you
should be getting up more of the light
if that makes sense
if you I don't know if this makes any
time right so really just I shouldn't
say fate I shouldn't say cosine Phi
right so it's another angle that's the
viewing angle there right so the amount
of light that comes out that you're
seeing that coming off of the surface in
this case I feel like the amount of
light coming off of the surface should
be proportional to the inverse of that
because again you're going to end up
with a situation of 1 over cosine C
right this is the surface again and this
is the the width of the band right this
is the view that makes
but so if I had to do something
completely ridiculous here and just say
I want to take you know the incident
light that comes in right I want to
multiply that by the ratio of infinite
light to surface light right I want to
multiply that by the ratio of surface
I'm sorry of view light to surface light
and in so doing transform infinite light
into outbound light right what would
that equation look like it would be like
incidence times right surface over
incident which is one over cosine theta
times view over surface which is cosine
5 times 5 over 1 equals my viewing
amount right because the view like
transmission and so looking at this I
would say naively not looking at any
graphics textbooks and having no idea
what I'm talking about right I'm I'm
literally just pretending I have two
surfaces and I'm just seeing what would
happen if I just write the map out no
preconceived notion here whatsoever then
I would get incident light x cosine Phi
over cosine theta equals the viewing
amount right that that's what I would
naively expect to see in my lighting
equation and what are these two things
well that's basically saying that I have
whatever my light strength is right this
is my light strength you know so my
light strength times the cosine of the
view angle over the cosine of the light
angle equals the viewed light strength
uh so yeah there you go that is that is
the naive persons wrote out the what
should happen to the amount of light
that gets like bounced off a surface if
you just tried to write it out as if you
literally have like bags of photons
coming down a beam and you wanted to
know what the proportional transfer to
that thing was right and so I don't know
if that holds a lot of water I don't
know if that's at all correct physics
wise but that's just what I would assume
and looking at that you know let's see
what that actually does so if we assume
for example that the light comes down at
disco sine theta right as that as that
same light band got you know steeper if
that makes sense you're shining quite a
bit less light on it so as this goes
down you get less light and the same
would be true of the other way around i
well know so as the viewer gets deeper
down you're seeing more of the surface
as a result so the opposite true of the
viewer meaning as the viewer gets higher
up you're seeing more of the unit area
of the thing right so I don't know that
that squares with what I expect from the
standard textbook lighting equations but
it seems like an interesting like I'm
not sure where the logic is flawed there
so it seems like that's roughly what I
would expect to have happen now that I
think about it right I mean I can't say
I know why that's wrong
yeah I would be interested to check I
would be interested to check this
against the physical lighting transfer
equations I don't know that we have
those in a particularly convenient form
that we can go look at because I would
like to see a real explanation of this
like I'd like to see what the actual
physical behavior is there worked out
because I feel like this seems
reasonable but I don't think I've ever
seen it written that way before so I'm
assuming it must not really be out works
but that seems relatively saying to me I
don't know anyway so we'll leave that as
an exercise for a little bit later
because we will have to check some
reference material to when we get into
maybe some other lighting stuff but for
now I'm fine with it we can go ahead and
implement this and it'll just be
interesting at least to see what the
deal is so cosine Phi cosine theta on
the difference between those two and so
we already know how to implement one of
those which is the cosine theta portion
of that and so that would be 1 over
cosine theta would be the incident light
right which is to say that if the light
is directly down so if that angle and I
guess to be clear here we need to talk
about how we're measuring these angles
exactly but I'm measuring the angle on
the inside right now
so that 90 degrees right and this is a
little bit confusing so yeah how does
this work when cosine goes to 0 we want
cosine to go to 0 at this here so we
want this to be cosine of zero we want
this to be cosine of 1 right which is
exactly what I guess we would get in
this case because cosine if you think
about it right it starts at at 1 if it's
pointing in this direction and goes to 0
point when you get here so what we kind
of need to do is measure the other way
around
but that's exactly what our dot product
will actually do right dot product in
with the normal of the surface is
actually going to measure it in this
direction right so I think that's
exactly what we want to do anyway as far
as I can tell yeah so basically as this
angle goes down to zero this this will
clamp up to zero as well and it would be
increasing the as this kind of comes up
to 1 this would be 1 over 1 right I
would think and then it goes to 0 to get
it gets much higher what's weird about
that and which doesn't seem to make much
sense and maybe this is why I've messed
the map up here a little bit is we can't
if we have a divisor there but it feels
like we should have to have a divisor
there because again one of these two
things have to be a divisor
I would think since I don't see how they
could both be on the same side of it is
that that makes it so that these values
get very high eventually right which
doesn't make much sense like we want
these to be on top they make a lot more
sense right because if this is on top
and we have a very well-behaved equation
when this is on bottom we don't but I
don't see a lot of ways like I try to
think of exactly how we get around that
maybe I need to link these up in a
slightly different way right maybe I
can't string them in this particular
fashion like for example if this was
cosine theta cosine Phi that is always
well behaved and it doesn't have weird
behavior like get it making this term
get very large as the as the view angle
decreases which is what would happen
here which doesn't really make any sense
right so just thinking about it I must
be thinking about that wrong in the way
that these things get related meaning
there must be some way to relate these
in a way that isn't talking about the
ratio of incoming versus outgoing in
that sense
[Music]
but I'm not sure exactly again what it
would be because it does seem like
that's still how you would think of it
right let me just do this one more time
and see if I can make a little bit
better sense of it
again I want to I always wanted to
understand this and I've never really
spent any time looking at it
rendering people have to do this all the
time so you know presumably they would
know how to do the right diagram here
for it for thinking about like micro
shaft of light but let's measure this
and let's measure it correctly the way
that we're going to measure it which is
like this so there's data there right
because we're going to be doing that as
the way to get our cosine so we kind of
want to measure it from the top down
does that make sense okay so if we were
to assume something like this where we
are pointing directly at the normal
right then a unit area a unit amount of
our light falls on a unit area and that
makes sense because the cosine of theta
in that case is the cosine of 0 which
equals 1 right and that means that 100%
of the light that hits the surface is
eligible for use right rather you know a
single amount of area is going to
reflect the complete amount of light
right that those photons all in you know
whatever unit width of light is are
going to hit the surface right now as we
move over here we're going to end up
looking more like this right and now for
the same amount of incident light there
it's going to fall on I guess I kind of
see how this is more logical so if this
remains the same
this got bigger right meaning as that
rotation goes down if we kept the same
size here right so we're that's probably
where I messed up in my thinking so
let's say we're talking about the same
unit area always here right like so now
if I slant this over to the side like
this right as I go further to the side
that the size of that light gets smaller
and smaller right the the sort of that
gets smaller and smaller because before
it was equal to the whole size here same
size of the surface but as it gets more
and more incident it gets equal to a
much lower amount right it gets equal to
a triangle that looks more like that
right whereas this is theta out here
right and if that's theta out here okay
if this is Zeta out here then I assume I
can do what I need to know is what's
this in here so that's actually this
right here this angle is going to be 90
minus theta right and we would want the
cosine of 90 minus theta there I assume
right because this this value is not
really super relevant to us is it I mean
I can't see why it would be because it
doesn't really have anything to do with
the shape of the light it's this one
over here so it's the cosine of the
theta on the inside there and that yeah
that really does seem to be like it
would be the wrong way around
what's interesting about that is
that's a sign if gonna which again
doesn't comport with what I would assume
to have happen with the lighting here
right so that's a little bit weird to me
if I want to know how much light source
was seen by this unit area the amount of
light source I'd see is going to be the
sine of theta I would think not the
cosine and furthermore it's actually the
negative sign right so that's peculiar
so that's a little bit closer to what I
would have expected but again it's a
little bit weird so I don't understand
quite yet again how to draw that diagram
in a way that makes good sense to me I
do see that my mistake before was not I
need to think about a unit area on the
surface like a fixed area on the surface
and thinking about right the difference
between that and that and you can see
that this that same size of the surface
in terms of how much of the light area
it can see it can see much less because
here is the window of the view that this
unit area gets on the light source right
it's the same size as the surface area
so that's the 100% case 100 percent
transmission or 1 under separate
reception of of the light from that
surface but at the angle right we're
only going to see that much and that
makes really good sense to me and if
this were the angle we were measuring
which is the angle from the her from the
surface out to the light source right
then it would make reasonable sense
because that is the value we're trying
to measure right and isn't that how we
would have to have measured it right
because but then against thinking about
it it actually works properly if it's
cosine theta because if this angle here
is zero cosine will be one if this angle
is 90 oh so am I miss thinking that
here's the right triangle that we're
trying to make and that's usually right
oh no no no I just got it turned around
so okay we're all good no need for panic
if I actually turn this around right
this is cosine theta and that's sine
theta right so okay just the fact we've
dodged screams' upside down and me being
a little bit slow today that was the
problem so that does make good sense
then because cosine of this angle would
give us this and we don't want that
right we actually want the sine of that
angle but hey it turns out we're
measuring this angle so that's
absolutely perfect because since we're
measuring this angle this would be that
triangle right it's that triangle right
there and that is the cosine of that
angle right so that's pretty nice
actually okay
so that to me seems right so I would say
that the amount of light
so the amount of incident light is going
to be proportional to the cosine of the
angle right and I'm happy with that but
now let's ask the question what happens
on transmission right so now I want to
know okay
now I've got a viewer and if viewer is
going to look at this thing and it seems
to me that the same thing should happen
right so if I'm talking about this much
area that I'm viewing well if I'm
viewing it straight on then I should be
collecting all of that I should be
seeing all of that light that's getting
well I guess hmm so this depends on how
we look at it so the light that comes in
how much you can see is the light source
how much you can see of the eye point is
a tougher question right because the
this stuff is getting evenly now but I
think that's probably true right if you
assume that every point on this surface
right is radiating equally in all
directions then in theory as long as you
have all of the light points in there it
shouldn't really matter what the width
is that you're viewing I don't think so
it doesn't seem like the viewing angle
would change it at all meaning the angle
is the view in this case doesn't seem
like it would apply so it seems like you
only have the cosine theta term on the
incident light because the incident
light is how much of the light source
you can actually see where you're
talking about the viewer
well the viewer I don't know that it
would necessarily have that same effect
because the viewer is collecting
whatever gets thrown at them and I guess
the collector size is changing in some
sense there that's a really hard one to
think through I'm not really sure how to
think about that one from first
principles very well but
yeah I so I don't really know so in some
sense I could see you multiplying by
cosine fee because the same thing is
true here is a size the the area on
which you're sending that out to the
viewer is going to be smaller but at the
same time I think maybe there's an
argument that you wouldn't do that
because if this is actually uniform
distribution function which is what
we're starting with here because we're
only talking we're not yet talking about
the surfaces the surface properties
we're assuming that the surface radiates
light in all Direction uniformly it's
perfectly diffuse because we could talk
about later making it not the views
right so if we think about that I'm just
trying to gauge at that point if it's
radiating equal in all directions as
long as you're collecting everything
from there from the same size it doesn't
seem to matter that it's coming back in
a smaller area no matter what the area
is the total brightness is still the
same coming back now I could see an
argument being made that you would
collect more because the same area on
the collector is collecting more here
than here right because let's say you
took the same sized area that much well
when it's looking straight down the same
sized area back is looking at a lot less
light than from the side which is
collecting more light so it almost feels
like it's an inverted scenario like the
near the smaller it gets the brighter it
should get because a smaller amount of
looking at it is going to collect more
light right so this is a bit of a
puzzler I feel like this one really
wants to be researched I feel like we
should go read a physical rendering
explanation of the reflection the
differential reflections calculations
here to get this right because I'm not
sure I could really say I feel like
that's a little bit above my paygrade
in terms of rendering tech to say what
should happen there but it feels like
there
is sort of a need to compensate for that
and I feel like going back to thinking
about photons bouncing around you know
when we talk about the surface area a
differential surface area you know
photons coming out of the light source
well this band is going to collect a lot
more photons than that band is so it
makes a lot of sense to say that the
amount of light incident on the same
amount of area on a surface is going to
be proportional with the cosine theta -
the light source and the reason for that
is just going to be that the cosine
theta to the light source tells you how
many wide the photon collecting band was
for the same surface element right but
for viewing we're talking about the fact
that we're sort of viewing this whole
surface right so we're talking about
pixels that are collecting the light
that's bouncing back at us here right
and so when we talk about collecting
from the surface it seems like what
should be happening is that as you get
more oblique to the surface it should be
looking brighter to you right I mean
I guess what I would say about that is
I mean I'll be honest with you just for
again I wanted to work with that from
first principles rather than looking at
somebody's explanation of it because I
just wanted to like have that experience
I've never done it right I and I'll be
honest with you just looking at it from
first principles it just really feels
like there's going to have to be an
inverse relationship there and again I'm
probably just wrong about that because
I'm probably my intuition is probably
missing something but here's my
explanation for why I would think that's
the case let's take a weird scenario
where we're just saying here's some
surface right and we've pre said how
much light is emanating from this
surface right and we're saying it's
uniformly scattering in all directions
so the same amount of light is getting
scattered in any direction you happen to
choose to look at this thing right well
if I was to put my collector directly
above it and the collector is this size
then I am going to get all of this
surfaces light that it has to contribute
in that direction right I'm missing all
the light that's going in the other
directions I'm going to have this much
you know that big of a band worth the
whole surface is worth is going to fall
on my entire collector right so however
much is falling on a particular part of
this collector let's say however much
this light is that it shines off in one
direction if that's L then I'm going to
get whatever the width of this thing is
I'm going to get L over W right as the
amount of light per unit area on my
collector right again really just being
dumb being a dumb non graphics
programmer that's just what I would
think right and then if I take the same
collector and I move it over here right
so now you know the collector looks like
this right well if I take a look at what
part of this I could see it's actually
the same amount of light right is
falling on a much smaller part now
remember this is supposed to reflect
evenly in
all directions so I seeing the same
amount of surface and it should be
reflecting the same amount of light out
in all directions so in theory right
shouldn't this now be you know maybe
that's half the width or something
shouldn't this be L over width over 2 or
2l over with so shouldn't this thing now
appear to be brighter than it appeared
before it seems like a dumb result so
I'm guessing the answer must be no
that's stupid and here is why but the
here's why part I don't know what that
here's why part is and I guess one way
to think about it is these not
collimated light so really you know
you're getting a cone of light and it's
going to fall on the whole thing right
and in both circumstances it's going to
fall on the whole thing and maybe that's
the answer is that since it's uniformly
radiating out and not collimated like
that that you always will pick up from
any point on here you're always going to
pick up that much of the light that's
coming out right from any point on here
so it's always uniform because no matter
how big of the light source you are each
infinitesimally on there is always
projecting out towards someplace on here
and you're always going to that integral
will always work out to be the same
that's the best I can do to convince
myself that there wouldn't be a term in
there so I'm going to stick with just a
cosine for now since I'm relatively
convinced that that's the correct term
for the incident light I would like to
look at the viewer operations I might
take a gander this week in between
episodes to take a look at a physics
rendering text to see what their
explanation is because I'm assuming that
they have a good way of explaining why
there presumably isn't a angular term to
the reflection again prior
- calculating any kind of surface
property right obviously service
properties introduced angular
coefficients but we're not talking about
service properties yet we're talking
about if you factor the surface out and
you're only talking about the angle the
direction of the light and the viewer
right so anyway once we have this dot
product of the light to the world like
that at that point we know since we're
going to light and we have the world
number those four affections one of the
things that we're going to have here is
this can be negative right so if this is
my surface and the light is over here
right it's coming from behind then when
we compute the angle to the light and we
dot pack these together we're going to
get a negative value right this is going
to be negative something you know like
negative point six or something right so
what we need to do here is after we take
that cosine we need to clamp it because
once the light gets behind the surface
it can't shine on the surface anymore
unless this surface was transmitted so
light coming from behind it passes
through so it's got translucent we
shouldn't see it right so what we want
to do here is we want to use a clamp and
there is a good clamping here
OpenGL provides that by default so
here's our clamp right because they
clamp this value to emit into max and
that's all we need to do so we can say
cosine angle equals clamp of the cosine
angle between zero and one and so if we
clamp it between zero and one now we
know that if we get behind the light
source it won't contribute so now all we
need to do is take what we were
previously computing to be the light
strength based on fall-off and now we
just use the cosine of the angle to
determine what the angular reflection
should be of that light now if we've
actually specified our normals correctly
oh man that doesn't look like we
specified our normal schedule looks like
our nerville's are coming through as
zero um if we actually specify our
normals correctly we would have gotten a
good result there I suspect but at the
moment it looks like our normals aren't
and so what you can see here is
we did do two lights so this is
direction from the world to the light
right and here's the distance we
normalize based on that distance so that
should produce a unit length light
vector there we can also praise this
this way which is a little bit better it
shouldn't change result at all but it's
just a little bit better way of saying
it in terms of normalization there so
basically what happens is we multiply
the vector by one over the like this and
so we don't divide each component we
multiply each one case multiply is
faster we then take the cosine of the
angle between them by dot product in the
pink the two light and the world oh you
know what though no actually that's
that's fine and then we take the cosine
of angle and we claim that between zero
and one right and I believe I put those
parameters in correct order right it's X
min max right yeah so X min Max and so
after that we should end up with the
correct value for cosine angle but we're
obviously not getting a good result from
it Jimmy and so the question is why not
my first suspicion is that our normals
are not coming in as correct values
right so what I'm interested to see here
is if I was to go ahead and say that
everything points up directly up so
world n is zero zero one I just want to
see what happens there okay so it's the
rest of our equation that's busted it
looks like so let me go ahead and debug
why that is so let's say I set cosine
angle here it's cosine angle if I
overwrite it with one we should be in a
situation where we get our lighting back
right yeah so that's what we would
expect and that is what we got
so now let's say well if we take our
cosine angle
prior to clamping just to make sure the
clamp isn't the problem if we tear
across thing I'll probably clamping and
set it to be 10.5 or rather even if I
just said it
I should get full lighting again it
should just pasture as one it does so
that's good so then I've got our job
practice of a to light with the world
end so let me set both the world end so
now we're assuming that the light if I
wanted to actually make these both would
be so now we're assuming that the light
and the world normal are both pointing
straight up so we should get one here as
well and we show the same lighting and
so now what I'm going to do is I'm going
to knock out the normal part of that to
see what happens if we just set the to
light and so if I knock out the world in
part I get zero if I knock out the to
light part I get oh not quite zero but a
very odd sort of behavior there one
thing that's true is our light probably
needs to be up above us a little bit
more so let me go ahead and make the
light be a little bit higher up it might
just be in geometry at the moment there
we go okay okay
[Applause]
okay
so now if I go ahead and and see what
happens let me restore world normals to
be pointing directly upwards so if I
make world normals point directly upward
we do collect light right and we get
some fall-off of the light distance so
we may have to up the light strength a
little bit here just to still because I
put the light up a bit higher so I'm
just going to make the light a bit
stronger so there you can kind of see us
lighting one thing that's a little weird
about that is I'm not really sure why
the light amount changes so much based
on the height because the height
difference shouldn't have been that
great for these things I wouldn't have
expected it to quite be so dramatic
in terms of like the distance should
have been smoother there I would have
thought it doesn't make a lot of sense
to me
to be completely honest I think we've
got think we've got other problems to
say the least so a couple things here
first of all yeah I was seeing in this
situation a lot of color changes based
on the distance to the I mean based on
the viewing angle which I don't know I
mean there could be fog effects involved
there but I wasn't expecting to see that
I guess that might be fog I don't know
but like see how these are getting
darker as I get a bleak to them and I
don't really feel like that should be
happening right that doesn't that should
not be occurring out thing and
with the radial fall-off you wouldn't
expect the small height difference to
make such a pronounced difference but
it's not out of the question I suppose
that it would but anyway let's take a
look at what happens if I need both of
these so the two light and the other one
or both is saying do I still get that
you can still see that even if those are
even if we're just using the distance
fall-off so let's let's see here if all
we're doing is distance fall-off so
cosine angle is always going to be 1 in
this case in theory even in that case we
get some interesting effects there so
let's say let's let's just clamp total
light to 1 so now there's no lighting at
all right
it's just flat what happens if I do that
same behavior that I was doing does do I
get darker here so you can see I get I
don't get darker so something weird is
happening because if I'm setting the
cosine this light distance itself
appears to be changing based on
something that it shouldn't be changing
based on right because this light P
world P is supposed to be just passed
straight through it's not supposed to
have any relationship to the transform
of the camera at all right it should not
be it should not be related in any way
to the transform
so let's take a look at this shader one
more time so here we go we take our
vertex right and we produce the proper
homogeneous coordinate version of the
vertex because remember the restore the
Z bias in the W coordinate we pull the Z
bias out and we set the set it to one in
the W coordinate we then create a Z
vertex which is our vertex that's just
our vertex biased up by the Z amount
that we want to buy so we're pretending
it's in a higher place than it is right
we then transform both the vertex that
we started with and this vertex that
we've artificially bumped up with the
bias we transfer in both of those and
that will transform them by the camera
transform to view them where we're going
to view them by we then go ahead and
take the modified Z as being our we do
basically the transform that we would
have done to produce a correct V value
for our result right for our you know
synthetic result we're going to pass
through but then we take just whatever
the Z vertex was what we were initially
fashion with its artificial Z value
there right we take that and we pass
that directly reader so that should not
none of this work should affect that
it's just got to be bias added to it and
that's it and by the way the cubes which
you were seeing the weird sort of
artifacts on those are not even in don't
even have a Z bias so those are just 0
all right we then pass that through to
world P which is supposed to be
interpolated and presumably is being
interpolated properly we set a fixed
location in world space for the lights
which is just the center of world space
0 0 4 right and then we take our
[Applause]
we take our light and we just look at
what the distance was from where we are
in the world that sort of what should be
a normally interpolating value in world
space linearly interpolated value in
world space and we take whatever the
light location was and we subtract them
so yeah I don't know if there's anything
particularly strange doing it that way
I mean I can't think of anything strange
that would be going on there why the
distance to the light source would be
changing based on the view angle there
I really can't so let's go back and just
verify that that really is happening
though so if cosine angle equals one so
basically we're just using light
strength over light distance times like
distance so the squared light distance
if that's all we're doing then what I
was deserving before
it just seems like that's getting darker
as I rotate upwards is it possible that
that's just an optical illusion I guess
that's just because they're getting
closer to other parts of the I guess I
could just be an optical illusion let's
see if it is that could be one of those
optical illusions so here I'm going to
do shift printscreen and I'm going to
open up there's game and then I'm
going to go ahead and do that rotation
downwards and I'm going to do another
ship print screen and then I'm going to
paste that is the new layer then I'm
going to crop it
and I'm going to put these next to each
other and I'm going to look at the
values of them
all right so here is like the edge of
this cube the corner of this cube here
and it's 38 60 39 right all right it's
just an optical illusion I guess wow
that's crazy right oh I is in color they
don't really work all right so maybe
that's correct
I'm willing to give it the benefit of
the doubt for now so that's time man
that's weird all right so let's get back
to debugging now I can not I can you
know not freak out that there's
something wrong there so really we just
have to figure out what's wrong with our
cosine computation here because it's
obviously not working quite correctly so
the world normals it would be nice to
verify what direction those were
pointing in as well but for now let's
just get back to the start so if I'm
going to fix both of those normals to 20
upwards I'll get the same result if I
switch the world normal but not the the
one that goes to the light source right
what does that give me
so that appears to give me some actual
lighting correctly but the calculation
of making the light go to the light
source seems to I'm sorry the the
calculation of fixing that the normal
seems to be the to be good if I do that
if I instead fix neither of them so if I
don't fix the world normal then I get
black so it suggests to me that my world
normals are just not coming through
correctly right so I'm wondering if
invert up I never pass the fruit so of
course there's zero
so now I'm actually passing it to the
fragment shader rather than leaving it
set to zero okay so there we go so now
our light source is reflecting more
correctly right and hopefully you can
see from that that now we get a lot more
of a sense of lighting too as well and
correctly is the wrong word here I don't
actually mean to say it's correct
we're just probably more correct we
haven't done testing so who knows but
here you can kind of see if I look at it
right the light source is directly above
I get almost no lighting on those
surfaces because they're totally oblique
to the light but I get plenty of
lighting on these other services over
here right so that's a more reasonable
direct lighting calculation it's not the
lighting calculation we're going to
actually want to use and the reason for
that is because the main bit light we'll
talk about that a little bit but we're
starting to get more of a definition
here to the surface right um now let's
talk a little bit just for a second here
I want to sort of add the ability to
test this out more this is not what
we're going to want to do at the end of
the day so I don't want to make it sound
like this was accident was going to stay
in here but temporarily speaking I would
like the ability to move the light
around as well right
and we're going to want to do something
a little bit more fancy for moving the
light around in the future so this is
not a good example of how we would be
doing that going forwards but if I come
in here and where's my my render group
whereas my settings here so here's my
render setup if temporarily speaking I
just did like a v3 debug light P where
you could set the location that the
light was coming from for example if I
wanted to add something like that I
certainly could right and what I would
need to do there is go into the OpenGL
stuff and take a look at where we set
say for example fog color and so
something in here we would just add
another one at the end but we're just
going to use just very temporarily
debug light P and that is something that
again is just now where we have this
light P here I'm going to I'm going to
pull that out and say that the uniform
[Applause]
okay and so I'm just going to say that
we've got a debug light P in there and
that's for our Z bias program that's
something's going to show up here and
then whenever we use that uniform
that's re whenever we use that program
we can just cut it like so what is the
problem connect avert cost GL float
start I don't know why this isn't
wrapping anymore though it's wrapping it
the wrong size I guess cannot convert
argument three from v3 okay that you can
now so now we have to do is actually set
that in the render group so in the
render group when we pass the sound set
camera transform we're gonna need a way
to control these things better but keep
the light P do this and so now we run
the game you know we should get the same
results with the light is kind of in the
center of the world now what we want to
do is put that somewhere reasonable so
when we pop over to world mode where it
sets like the near clip plane and stuff
like that we can also set that divided
by T and so in here where we set that
[Applause]
and hey guess what if you want to set
that you've got to actually set it to
something as it turns out where should
that get set probably just right here so
yeah if you take a look at what's
happening now we're back to the original
and now we can move the light around
anywhere that we want to move the light
around I'm going to probably just attach
it to the hero for now I guess and so we
know where the hero is standing in a in
a sense I think probably maybe do I I
don't really remember to what extent we
actually know that
once we do the simulation we do so
here's the camera entity here so if
there's a camera entity I guess we can
just say like hey whatever the camera
entity
whatever the camera entities position is
that's all we really wanted to know
right so we want to set the the light
position to that so I'll just go ahead
and put one in here and we'll just
specify it that way
[Applause]
and we're probably going to want to bias
it up a little bit from that because
that'll be just where the person
standing I assume why am I not seeing
that move
[Applause]
Oh camera entity is not what I guess I
mean uh now that is what I mean
so camera entities should be correct
there I got to see oh right Comex that's
problem there we go and so what we
probably want to do here is also bias
this up so that it's kind of hovering
above maybe that's a little bit too much
that's probably not where the hero's
head would be that's probably more where
the heroes head to be alright so there
we go
so now it's basically like the light is
just on the hero's head as the hero
moves around and you can kind of see
that light falling on the services more
correctly now than it was before and you
can actually see a lot of definition in
those services - right like like I said
before even just basic lighting that's
not very good yet if it obeys some of
the basic criteria for lighting produces
relatively nice results right so that
seems pretty good so far now there is
some weirdness there doesn't make a lot
of sense to me I asked to think about
that so that is wrong we're going to
think about why that's happening like
those trees should be basically black I
think because they should be pointing
more away from the light than they are
and I guess maybe the thing is the light
kind of now up high enough over them but
it's not so I could maybe convince
myself that that was correct and I guess
when you look at it like that you can
see why and I don't know if that means
we want to bias the lighting calculation
using the Z bias in a different way as
well to maybe make that a little bit
different but you can kind of see that
that's you know giving us some of that
first step to reasonable lighting that
we would want right now one of the
things that you'll note here is that
this is giving us lighting from only one
light source and we want to get lighting
for more light sources than one
and we also need some other at in order
for our lighting to be reasonably we're
going to need a little bit more sort of
I don't want to say realism but softness
to the lighting so I want to talk a
little bit about that in a second here
now that we've now that we've sort of
established basic lighting and I've
gotten that to the point where I'm
relatively happy with it right like this
is this is all you can really expect
from trivial you know trivial lighting
that doesn't do anything beyond the
standard diffuse lighting equation so
let's talk a little bit about just what
we need out of our lighting going
forwards because this is probably the
two things that we'll try to get over
the next week or two so that our
lighting so the two things that we
really want out of here is one and you
know what I guess I'll I'll say that we
could get three things even one of them
I don't know if we actually want slash
care about but we'll talk about them
anyway so one is we want more lights so
the way that we've done the lighting
right now our equations are good so you
know we can throw more light at it but
we're going to have this loop over all
the lights that there are so we probably
could get away with you know doing eight
lights this way or something like that
and it wouldn't be a problem but if we
wanted to scale up to like you know a
hundred lights or 200 lights
it wouldn't work because looping over
200 lights per pixel over for depth
appeals is not going to be happening
right that's that ain't that's not going
to cut it so what we want to do there is
think about ways we might get more
lights into our system there's a lot of
ways you can do that but we got to kind
of think about how we would want to
handle situations where we would have
lots of lights right
so the second thing we really want is we
want to have life that isn't just direct
because all we're simulating right now
is a particular light source shines
directly on an object and we see it now
as you can see from the results of that
it looks pretty convincing for something
like you know a flashlight because
something that's a very bright light
source in a very dark area that doesn't
have questions to that what I really
mean to say is a very dim light source
in a very dark area doesn't bounce a lot
of secondary light around so it kind of
looks reasonable when you look at
something like a flashlight effect this
is more reasonable so you can see what
our lighting looks like is exactly what
our lighting is zero bounce lighting so
it's kind of the equivalent of shining a
flashlight which is a very dim light
right compared to the Sun or something
very dim in a dark room and so you just
see these very harsh lighting effects
and that's good for that particular
situation but if you want a softer look
more like a fun light where there's a
lot of bounce light around so even
things that are incomplete shadows still
have a lot of illumination to them from
the surroundings things that's what the
surrounding we're not getting that so
that was what we want out of number two
is some way to get some ambient lighting
in there right some lighting that's just
about light that bounces around the
environment and lights things up instead
of having to come directly from a light
source that were computing and number
three would be surface variability okay
so service variability is just a way of
saying we would like some way to know
what a particular surfaces reflectance
properties actually are and then we'd
like to treat the light that bounces off
that surface differently right now
we haven't talked very much about
reflective functions but we mentioned a
little bit of it right a very diffuse
reflector is one that takes light from
any angle and scatters it to any angle
it's like a chalky wall paint or
something where there isn't a lot of
reflection in it directly you don't see
whole shapes or images reflected in it
not much gloss you just see light that
is the general amount of light that's
hitting it is what you see very diffuse
very chalky all the way to the other end
of the spectrum is like a mirror
something that literally scatters light
only out the direction it comes in so
like it comes in and it goes out the
exact opposite bounce like a ball
bouncing off the surface right and it
doesn't scatter hardly at all so when
you look at a mirror you don't see any
indication of how much light in general
is falling on that part of the surface
instead you only see the light that was
incoming from a very specific direction
and that's what makes it a mirror right
and so you know getting some surface
variability in there is what allows you
to communicate to the player that
surfaces are different types of
materials so for example if you wants me
to look wet or like water that's a very
highly reflective surface you want
something to look choppy like a wall or
a piece of stone that's not very
reflective that is more toward to
diffuse side so being able to vary
surfaces a little bit can add a lot of
visual interest to the game I don't know
that we want that too much in Hammond
here or need it too much in a material
but it's just worth noting and so we'll
talk about trying to upgrade to do some
of those things next week but for the
time being we could actually augment
what we're doing right now to take a
little bit that into account let's take
a look for example in our shader right
let's say that in our shader we wanted
to start taking into account the viewing
direction right so where the viewer was
well we should know where the viewer was
generally speaking because our transform
tells us where the viewer is right our
transfer my believe I think should tell
us where the viewer is
I mean it might be something we would
kind of have to reconstruct so it might
be better to just pass it down because
well here you can see I mean we already
know what the answer is here so I'll
just show it to you but so then we do
set camera transform right here is like
our equations for the camera so we say
oh here's the do rotation X rotation we
take you know how we're viewing the
world we take the camera translation and
we produce like this as I guess the
debug right version of that and in order
to produce the cameras final position we
just say rotate it by whatever that
rotation is and place it out there right
but then I think I'm not very much
mistaken when we do such camera
transform and you take in that camera
position I think don't we do yet so when
we actually specify the projection
matrix right we have to multiply the we
have to multiply the camera position
happening we have to multiply the camera
position by the rotation itself right to
sort of produce what will be the correct
effect after things are rotated and so
if we wanted to recover that out we
would have to invert the transform to
get it back so what we really need in
this case is for our camera to still
preserve that piece of information so
when we do render setup and we pass down
that camera P I think what we want to do
is just provide that to the vertex
shader or the row any shader really that
wants it we would want to still set that
up right no and it looks like we do
right so there's that camera key so
we're getting that camera P directly and
that is really all we will need
so in here we don't use it in the
fragment shader yet we only use it I
guess in the vertex shader right here
but if we want to use it we can also
access it so it's already being
specified we can access it in here as
well so we can just get the canopy and
the light P that means producing this
vector that we want which is to camera
is just as simple as what we were doing
before right there's the camera distance
[Applause]
which is what we want there and we can
normalize that one as well and then we
can have the Coast cam angle is dot two
camera little N and now we know the
angle to the camera as well as the angle
to the as well as the angle to the light
source now what we may want to do here
is then create sort of we can do a bunch
of different things here right one of
the things we can do here is we can now
start to make our reflectance be based
on the angle so if we wanted to create a
mirror surface what we basically be
saying is we want the angle to the
camera and the angle to the light source
to be at 90 degrees to each other right
so what I could actually do here is say
something like okay this is like the
cosine of the camera and the light right
so I could say take the camera take the
light do the dot product there let's
clamp that and now we could say well in
addition to modulating this with the
incidence of the light we could say that
well now what we're going to do actually
is pretend this as a mirror we could use
this entirely instead right so we said
say we could say whatever is that angle
is between these two that's what it's
going to be now
you know let me do this completely
different way so that's not going to
give us quite this is going to make it a
little bit too hard for us to do it so
let me do it slightly differently let's
see I just want to do the reflection
right so what I want to do is I want to
say well we've got our diffuse light and
that's here so let's put the name these
cues like so this is the light strength
this is this is the diffuse mount right
times this cosine angle so you could
think of this as saying a diffuse
coefficient right so let's say the
diffuse coefficient right now is one
point now and so that's any of us the
lighting that we already have then what
we want to do is we want to produce
another thing here which is going to be
our specular coefficient right it's
going to be the reflect that light that
comes out in a mirror style again this
is a really basic way to do lighting but
let's say we have a specular light
amount here so we do specular C times
you know whatever this thing is
something times the light strength and
what I probably want to do is like make
a term here for this and these may be
different things right we may want
different colors for these for example
in the future and so on as well but for
right now we want something there and we
want that to multiply the light strength
as well and then what we'll do is we'll
sum up our life so the amount of light
we get here plus the amount of light we
get here and really if you think about
it these should not
these should always have to sum to one
if this is a realistic surface so we
could say that this is a half diffuse
half specular surface right because we
can't reflect out more light than we
took in so whatever the light strength
is coming in we should expect to have
that same amount at maximum bounce back
right and we can come up with you know
basically coming up with real
reflectance functions is about tuning
these things to be more
realistic curves and so on but well
again move on from that we're going to
do a basic little reflection here so
what I need to do do here is like a
cosine reflected angle function and so
what I want to do is say okay we've got
the camera we've got our our diffuse
light amount so then what I want to do
is I want to take another thing here
which is going to be like the the coast
reflected angle which is going to be the
dot product of the light with the
reflection which is the you know reflect
vector reflection vector we'll talk
about what that is in a second so what I
need here is some kind of reflection
vector this is going to give me that
that thing that I I want and I'm going
to clamp it again just like I did that
will give me the amount of specular
light contribution okay so what's a
reflection vector well a reflection
vector what I want to do what I'm trying
to set up here is I've got I've got my
two light vector right it goes out this
way I've got my viewing direction right
and what I want to do and I guess what I
should say is you know the viewing
direction looks like that right what I
want to do is come up with if this was
coming in at this angle and and maybe
you notice that I can emphasize the
difference between the two maybe let's
say instead let's say this is the way
I'm viewing it what I want to do is
reflect that vector out like so so I
would get where where am I looking if
this were a perfect mirror what should
it reflect if it was a perfect mirror
and then I can dot these two together to
see how close I am to my mirror
reflection then that will give me how
much of that mirror contribution I
should get right the specular light
amount okay so if I wanted to do that
how do I produce the reflection vector
well I know I've got this vector which
is the vector to the camera so let's say
I negated that vector to the camera I
would get the vector I wanted
essentially but it would be pointing
down the ball it would be pointing you
know essentially the
wrong direction it's pointing downward
and I want to be pointing upward right
so how do I reflect that about this line
well it just so happens that because I
have the surface normal I'm in a really
good position to compute exactly how to
do that because the dot product of the
normal with that vector right so n dot C
is going to give me exactly the amount
that I wanted now if this looks familiar
to you it should we did this for physics
for bouncing right we computed this
reflection for bouncing our particles
and I don't remember if we'd also I
think we may have done it for bouncing
when we are moving objects around so I
know that my and my n transpose C here
will give me how far along the normal I
am right and that's going to be a
negative value because I'm under you
know I'm basically under the normal if
you will so if I want to then move
myself back up to where I would be what
I can do is just subtract two of that
right to move myself up to pointing back
as a reflected amount the first end
transpose C moves me to the horizon to
the equivalent line so that gets rid of
any vertical displacement and the next
one gives me back that same vertical
displacement in the opposite direction
right now remember in transpose C is
only if this were the C vector but I
actually computed the C vector going
this way
so it's really n transpose negative C
which is negative n transpose C which
means this negative cancels out which
means it's actually two ncc right if
that makes sense
which is a little bit weird to say the
least but anyway so let's work that out
exactly so we can actually do it okay
so here's our camera that's to camera
and it supposedly unit length right here
is our normal normal vector and what we
want to do here is pretend we have
negative C there's our negative C we
want to know where on the N vector we
are right so in order to do that we do n
transpose negative C and the negative to
distribute there because it's a linear
operator so that should be negative n
transpose C right so that's negative and
transpose C which is negative n
transpose C is that that distance right
there right so now if we take negative C
and we now want to bring negative C up
to here right and then up to where it
should be in order to produce the
reflected vector I need to add this
twice right so I need to add to it well
I need to add this to it twice and this
is going in the wrong direction right so
I really need to subtract it if that
makes sense in order to in order to get
going the right direction so I need to
subtract 2 times negative n transpose C
like so in order to get my new you know
reflected vector right so I start with
negative C I subtract 2 times that and I
need a direction because remember this
is vector math so I can't take a vector
and and this is a scalar right so what
direction am I going along well I'm
going along n right so this is this far
along can so again start at negative C
figure out how far along in I am under
the surface and then I just
subtract twice that along end to put me
back over the surface and there's my
reflection back there and there's a lot
of negatives in there so really I could
just say this is negative see this
negative comes out so it's really just
plus two n transpose C N and that's all
there is to it I think so in theory we
should be able to compute this the
reflection vector here so we've got
negative C and that is our Q camera
function we have plus two times the dot
product of the world normal and the
camera like so and that's times to the
normal that should give us the
reflection vector that reflection vector
gives us what we want to dot product
with in order to determine how much
we're looking directly at the light and
yet in theory that's the correct letting
computation for a more specular surface
now it's hard to tell whether we did
that correctly obviously but what we
should see now and that course I and I
am seeing it is we should be able to see
I don't know if you can see this but as
I sort of look down I get the light
source there's a highlight on the light
source right which kind of comes at me
right you can see that right it didn't
use to and what we can see that's a
little bit weird here right is this is
feel a very glossy diffuse reflection
the reason for that is that the
reflected angle that we compute remember
we're going to be adding some of that
specular contribution based on a very
wide angle because when we're right on
the cosine will be one but even as we
spread out and start to look at wider
angles the cosine fall-off is not
particularly sharp right it still falls
off cosine angle so we're going to
collect a lot there so if we want a
tighter more mirror-like surface we can
choose to start up making that curve be
more than cosine fall-off so for example
once we produce cosine reflected angle
we could choose to square that and we
could choose the square that a couple
times as we wanted to really crank down
the sort of the tension of that
highlight and what you can see if we do
that is once we make that happen you can
see our specular highlight gets much
tighter right and what you can see too
is that you know this again gets into
the non-physical aspect of our lighting
this is a conservative way of making
sure the two things don't sum together
but what we could do what we end up
doing there is killing a lot more light
than we should so what we really want to
do there is actually figure out how to
make that a more fair distribution at
the moment what we could say is let's
make this particular very bright and
very tight just totally fake right not
correct lighting but it just accentuates
it so you can see it right so here's a
pretty hoops here's a pretty high
specular power right and now you can see
that we've got that that shine on the
light there and so you can see as it
goes right we're getting that sort of as
I'm moving the hair around you see that
very clear specular highlight moving
with them and as the viewing Langille
angle change as soon as that specular
highlight again power wise you can crank
it as high as you want oh yeah I'm just
squaring squaring squaring right so
there's a very tight specular highlight
you can see again we're not putting any
shadows so you still get a specular
highlight down there right and so on and
that's just again just a really simple
very very simple this is basically like
kind of crappy Phong shading now right
do you ever heard of that which is
basically just saying we have one
specular term we have one diffuse term
the specular term is raised to some
power and you know tweak as you wish
right but you can already see how that
kind of gives you more of a sense the
the surface has some shadowing is to it
and if we were to kill the disputes
light more so let's say we were to take
this diffuse light down to a very low
level you can start to see how it starts
to sort of look more mirror-like now
again the only thing we're reflecting is
the light though so that's why it
doesn't look like a real mirror because
we're not reflecting all of this other
light that's bouncing upstairs again
that's the thing with direct light we're
only reflecting literally the light so
now we've got a three mirror like
surface here in terms of how the light
behaves and again the further you crank
that power the more you will see that
happen right so if I just continue to
crank that power more and more that
highlight would get tighten and tighten
and tighten into what's more like a
direct reflection of the light source
you can see there right um
alright so I think that's a good place
to end for today now that we've got the
basics of like a Phong a you know kind
of crappy Phong lighting in there
that's it that's that's all I'm gonna do
today so so next week we'll look a
little bit more
the problem you could not find when you
thought about dividing by cosine Phi is
that the only reason diffused surfaces
can exist this best use just was trying
to answer the questions I posed on the
stream can exist the surface roughness
which invalidates the assumption that
you will collect photons from the entire
surface roughness blocks some photons
one trick is to check your model a
photon must have the same probability of
going one way as the opposite way all
formulas were diffused light our
approximations and all diffuse surfaces
are different in order to render a
physically correct diffuse surface you'd
have to measure a four-dimensional data
set of light distribution reflectance
depending on two angles of incidence ya
which would be like the whole brdf for
that surface or something I'm not sure
that still just answers my question in
terms of like I mean I still would like
to see it written out a little more
clearly as to how the light is bouncing
around just just to see a diagram you
know you're a sniper GLSL has a reflect
function yeah I don't tend to use the
GLSL reflect function though I always
write their flex lecture myself and the
reason for that is just because I may
want to modify things in it I find if
that's a little bit too much kind of
like how you know sometimes I use the
normalize function there but most the
time I write to normalize myself as well
because I need to do something in
between mts mocks should you normalize
the world end in the fragment shader I
don't believe so as I discussed on the
stream earlier because all our services
are flat there shouldn't be any
situation where our world normals are
not normal because they're not actually
be interpolate 'add because that makes
sense
be a 6ix says ever done website dev work
well I did the our website Mali rocket
if that's what you mean
uplink coder can you take a quick shot
at reducing the banding no we can't
really do that quickly that is something
that is just about introducing differing
because there is no actual banding in
color space there are actually colors
that are exactly next to each other so
the fact that you can see banding is
just because the monitored resolution is
only a bit color right so to get rid of
the banding what we have to do there is
we have to introduce a dither step which
is not going to be quick I don't think
we have to just at the end when it goes
to convert 16-bit color which we are now
storing to 8-bit color ill dither uplink
coder also I opened an issue where the
game crashes when you go backwards after
starting the game backwards
did you did you put that in here and a
are you talking about this one yeah that
I mean we can that's like in the game
entity code which we have not really
done anything with so there's that stuff
is all totally placeholder right that
reminds me this needs to get finished I
should just do this one this was a
someone wanted to change for their
compiling individual studio 2017 and I
tried to fix it for him but I messed up
this thing they were asking for they
were asking for getting rid of make it
resource I think in both places so I
believe that's what they wanted so we've
removed make it resource in both so that
was just saying they wanted for
compiling individuals through 2017
let's see
tt b JM would ACR turn mapping be worth
implementing i yeah it's usually worth
implementing I don't know that we might
be getting a little far from the scope
of handmade hero if we start doing HG
our enduring though so I don't know that
I really want to go down that route but
usually yet is worth worth it
so that's the kid is but mapping a
future you're looking into implementing
so bump mapping is really an art problem
not an engine problem it's it's trivial
to implement in the engine so in here
where you get the world normal all you
really have to do is instead of just
using the world normal you load the
normal out of a texture that's it so
there ain't a lot to it
so really the problem is that the
sprites have to have normal maps and in
order to have them have normal maps you
have to have some art profits that's
going to produce those like either they
have to be painted with like bump you
know like sort of diffuse maps by your
artist or they have to be post processed
with a tool like sprite lamp or
something and I don't really know if I
want to go down that road either but
there isn't a lot to it like you don't
have to do a lot of work to add it there
is a modicum of work because you you
depending on how you want to do it you
may want to send down more than just the
worldspace normal so right now we're
sending down world n but if you think
about it world n is not enough to
specify the facing direction of a
surface because it doesn't specify the
tilt so you if you depending what kind
of lighting effects you want to do you
may want to send down a full
three-dimensional access system or a
quaternion that can that you then
convert to one if you want to say vertex
bandwidth um so there's a debt because
slightly more work has to be done to
pass down a full reference frame instead
of just a world
normal and the other thing you have to
do is every texture now have to have
about Matt right or a normal map
preferably a normal map a higher quality
than both map
jazzy 23 says sim Dion CPUs are pretty
cool however it sounds painful to make
use of the newest and the best
instructions while remaining compatible
with old CPUs I don't see programs being
compiled separately for different SSE
capabilities I assume program will just
crash
if the cpu encounters a non support
instruction would you dispatch at
runtime for a different code path to
flex we use supports any instructions of
some dumb yes so that's not really the
problem the problem is actually somewhat
amusing if you want to optimize your
game for newer instruction sets like
avx-512 or a VX fix to whatever rather
than at sassy 2 or something that's
universe supportive sp2 sp3 this isn't
that hard to do you just pick a few the
few functions that you probably because
you got to hand optimize that anyway
right because you've got to go make use
of intrinsics usually if you're going to
get any good performance on affinity
most of the time or use a you know an
automatic thing like Intel IPC or
something sweet you've done some work to
isolate what it is you're actually going
to compile via that path and once you do
that it's not that hard to just have one
or two versions of that function that
you just set the pointer to it start up
by checking the CPU capabilities and
then setting the function pointer right
so it's not it's not very hard it's kind
of exact like we do with OpenGL where we
check extensions and then set the
extension that's about all you've got to
do right so that part's not particularly
hard here's the real problem and why
we're not doing it on handmade here and
why probably no one really ever does it
unless I get paid by Intel or AMD to do
it and that is because you're optimizing
the case you don't need to optimize
right because if you think about what
happens is your worst performing cpu is
going to be the one that doesn't have
that instruction set so if the game runs
on SSE to on an older CPU at all then
it's going to run great on an avx-512
supporting cpu it's going to run
gangbusters on that so you have no need
to optimize it with avx-512 because it's
already way faster than your minimum
spec computer that doesn't have avx-512
so paradoxically you end up never really
caring about something like avx-512
until it's actually available on lots of
CPUs on your minimum spec because then
you can use it on the minimum spec to
make that minimum spec perform as well
as your high spec machine which doesn't
really need you to do it right but when
avx-512 or something is only available
on your high spec machine forget it you
can't use worthless you can't use it for
anything the only way you can possibly
use it is if you have some isolated
effect that can be turned off on the
lower end CPU right so typically what
actually happens in practice is that you
don't ever need to do two versions of
the code one for the ADAC 512 and one
for s3 2 typically you only do the
avx-512 version you check the CPU bit
and if it doesn't support evic 512 you
turn that feature off so you're never
even going to called you're not going to
call an SSE 2 version of it it's over
write that feature is not there whatever
that feature was realistic Defamation
physics of blobby whatever is this off
it's gone forget it's not there right
and so basically you know you you really
don't have the use case that I at least
that I can think of of I'm trying to run
the exact same thing on something that
has avx-512 and saying that doesn't and
I need to optimize the a the X 512 part
I just I can't even think of a way that
would happen you always have to have
some additional thing you're turning on
and and I mean maybe if it's just going
to pure quantity like how many particles
am i doing with this thing then maybe
that's why you optimized 512 because
then the higher machine can have 10
times as many particles or something but
but you know you can see why I'm sort of
saying
it's rare that you're running literally
exactly the same thing in both cases and
have to optimize the avx-512 one because
typically that ship just doesn't need
any optimization it can run exactly the
same thing the sse2 version and it's way
faster already because it's a more
modern cpu with more optimizations and
possibly higher clock sometimes who
knows more cores certainly
and just yet what you just said about
what if you have a deal with Intel to
benchmark higher on the newest hardware
like I said that's the case that why
remember I said if you have a deal with
Intel or AMD or some like that that's
that what I mean and that's fine right
that's a totally that's a totally
worthwhile thing because optimizing for
new instruction sets is usually pretty
fun programmers oftentimes enjoy doing
it so if you can get a hardware company
to subsidize the cost for you then that
just lets you add a high-end feature to
your game that will only work on the X
512 let's say and everybody wins
you've got to do some fancy feature that
you couldn't have justified otherwise
because you know you're not going to
sell more copies of the game to the
10,000 people who have a B X 512 like
they're not going to not buy the game
just because it didn't have an avi X 512
feature but now if Intel's willing to
subsidize that development cost you know
if they're willing to pay you 50 grand
or something then you know that that's
worth it because now you can add a
feature to your game they paid for it
your players get the benefit of it if
they happen to have a big size 12 and
you got to do a fun programming thing so
you know everyone wins in that scenario
but that doesn't happen very often
you know not that many people have deals
with Intel to optimize stuff on their
latest hardware or add features that can
only be exposed by having you know more
cores more instructions whatever but if
you do then that's that's a scenario
where you do that right Jim 0.o says any
plans to create different types of
lighting as in room X is with like a
summer's day while room Y is contrasted
in dark like a film noir or would you
have all the sudden the art assets maybe
yeah no I do think we will change the
lighting the lights per area for sure
some areas will like be lit mostly by
you know point lights like we've got now
and others will have like a Sun or a
moon lighting kind of a thing I think so
I do suspect we'll do a little bit of
that I don't think we'll get too crazy
but you know we're going to do a little
bit of that over the next
weeks all right let's go ahead and close
things down here okay all right thank
you everybody for joining me for another
episode of handmade hereis and a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along series at
home you can always clear to the game on
handmade hero Oregon it comes with a
source code so you can play around with
it we also have a forum site you can go
to blast questions a patreon page you
can go to if you want support the video
series I'll schedule about the steps
we're going to be live and an episode
guide that lets you know what happened
in the past so you can find out what we
already covered that's about it for this
week I'll be back next week but we'll do
a little bit more work with the lighting
trying to put a little bit more advanced
stuff in there than what we've got right
now until then thank you for joining me
a have fun programming and I'll see you
on the Internet take it easy everybody