hello everybody and welcome to handmade
Hero show record a complete game live on
stream I think if I'm not mistaken we
verified sort of last weekend that we'd
finished up our apron stuff and we added
some nice code to the world generator to
just make it easier to place entities
correctly and use essentially a tile
grid for creating stuff when we want it
to do that obviously our engine doesn't
really require tiles at all our engine
is completely free for him but the sort
of the play of the game is supposed to
be fairly tile based a lot of the time
and while we may relax those constraints
for certain circumstances we want the
ability to think about things in terms
of tiles in order to create sort of the
zelda-esque or binding of issac as kind
of feel of a lot of the rooms and
dungeons where you're supposed to kind
of have this understanding of of tiles
and so and in really honestly our game
is even more that way because we're sort
of like which tile you're standing on is
actually really important to our game
and so it's it's even more than those
two games important that the player
understands the tile nature of most
rooms and again we can relax those in
the future we may want to kind of make
it so that there's different fixed
locations that are not really in our
grid but you still like stand on
specific points because the game is more
about standing on specific points than
it is about tiles in other words it's
about being able to know that there are
certain exact numbers of locations in
the room you can stand and which one
you're on that's important but that they
are in a grid is not important to the
gameplay it's just the easiest way for
us to create most of the things that the
player experience is because it's
something players can understand very
easily and visually process very quickly
if you provide some kind of chaotic set
of points the player can stand on then
one of the big problems that you have
is moot choosing which point you're
moving to from any given point becomes
perhaps a little bit more exercise in
frustration where it's like you were
trying to move to one and you actually
move to another that sort of thing
whereas a grid all joysticks are set up
to be pretty clean to press if you only
have to choose one of four directions
you know a d-pad will do that really
nicely even an analog stick usually
works quite nicely for doing that sort
of thing and so I'm an obviously the
arrow keys WASD and stuff are perfect
for that as well
so it you know most of the time we want
to stick to things that kind of look
like a grid or at least can be processed
like a grid and so we were able to get
all of that stuff working I believe we
are you know clear now to do sort of the
next whatever the next sort of larger
thing is that we want to do and so what
I want to do today is talk about sort of
the next sweep through the game because
we want to start making some bigger
changes here and we'll just sort of talk
about those are I mentioned them briefly
last weekend sort of what the options
are but we're gonna have to pick a big
thing to do today and go from there um
so if you take a look at the current
state of the game you can see the stuff
that we added last last week is these
aprons as we pull out here you can see
how we've sort of created an external
area around where the player is this
looks smaller than here it's actually
not if that's just because it's not
paged in so if you see as I move the
viewable region over you can see that it
paged in more of it so it's always at
the moment in eight wide apron that we
just sort of hard-coded to that number
but we can change that number we don't
really know exactly what we want it to
be so we can just always adjust it as
necessary but anyway that apron now
exists everywhere in the world that
rooms don't on the top floor which is at
least something we wanted and we could
add them to any other floor it's pretty
free for them the way the system works
and so we kind of now have the ability
to control all of that and that's good
so now that we have that taken care of
that sort of ability to add stuff
externally I want to
tackle the rest of the world solidity
issues that we have right and so the to
world solidity issues that we have at
the moment that I'd like to to tackle
are first of all we've got the lighting
we have to finish the lighting that's
going to be a major undertaking that'll
take several weeks because that's got to
go from being kind of like a okay little
system we worked out to being something
that's industrial-strength like right
now you can see it only operates on a
very small area that's largely just due
to performance issues we haven't
addressed how we're gonna make it more
efficient right and so we have to take
that system and make it something that
can just run on the whole visible area
all the time and be nice and fast and we
have to produce more usable results
right now we really are only tracing
panels and the consequence of that is we
don't really have any way to sample the
lighting for our sprites it would be
pretty easy for us to run sprites
through a lighting pass but right now we
can't do so because we just don't have
information available for that right and
so we need to deal with the lighting and
the other thing I would like to do again
for world solidity purposes is I would
like to go ahead and get ground cover in
there so when you look outside when we
go into the forest areas or into those
aprons one thing you can see is there's
nothing on those tiles the idea was that
we would have sort of grasses and stuff
in areas that are supposed to be
external like these we would not simply
have a tile that was you know a green
wash we actually wanted to have some
little like you know flowers and grass
fronds and stuff like that that we would
sort of stack in there and so that it
would make it a little you know more
clear what was you know just to give it
more character right and so that's the
other thing that we want to do and the
thing about these two world solidity
things I think once we have that there's
maybe one more thing we would want to do
which is to start putting you know trees
and stuff out into the
apron which is pretty simple we already
have the ability of this place tree so
it'd just be a matter of running some
kind of a simple process to scatter them
around out here in fact you know we
could just do that right now and have
that be done so maybe we'll do that but
point being ground cover is a major
thing and lighting is a major thing both
of which we have to address and then
once we've got that done I feel like at
that point we have sort of gotten to the
to the level where it's fairly flush
right it's it's like I don't think
there's anything else we need in terms
of world solidity it would feel like
you're playing a game and not like a
prototype right and that's really where
I'd like to be on that so you know
getting to the point where when you just
look at things they're solid and again
like I said a lot we've got a lot of
that right most of the things in here
look like they're solid now I like the
camera motion looks solid and the sort
of the way that we're focusing on things
makes it look like it's a world there's
not obvious empty parts anymore all the
stuff looks stable and clean there's no
crispy edges or anything so I feel like
we've done a good job look with the
world solidity and so it's really just
the lighting ground cover the two things
that I think remain so I'm gonna go add
the trees today I think that's probably
the easiest thing to do but then I think
we want to start on on those two issues
and I'm actually as opposed to tackling
them separately I think they actually
are sort of part of one single update in
a weird way and the reason that I say
that is right now we haven't really done
the work in our entity systems to
properly deal with dynamic versus
persistent state or I should say
transient versus persistent state what I
mean by that is that even right now the
lighting information that's cached
from frame to frame that lighting
information is cached forever so for
example if you look at what happens if i
zoom out here and I move around you see
how the lighting region follows me right
that lighting region is computing
lighting for all of the entities that
are inside that that sort of rectangular
it's actually a right rectangular prism
it extends downward as well so it's
actually not flat but you get the idea
so what's happening with the lighting
when it's getting computed there is that
that area is storing lighting
information into those entities it's
actually cache from frame to frame and
that's necessary for mmm-hmm
for pretty much any advanced lighting
algorithm you need to store results from
frame to frame because if you don't
store results from frame to frame you
end up in a situation where you can't
smooth out the noise inherent in
something as complicated as lighting
sampling and so we need to store that
information but right now it's literally
stored forever so as I leave it's
getting stored like these entities out
here are still storing that lighting
information for no real reason because
we could just start recomputing it as we
get closer to them so we at the very
least these things out here that got
paged out like the entities aren't even
in the simulation region anymore even
those entities are storing the lighting
information so at the very least we only
really want lighting information for
things in the simulation region but
probably we only need it for things in
the visual reason or at least a like a
small apron around the visible region
wherever we want our lighting startup to
be right and so if you think about how
this interacts with ground cover what's
gonna happen with ground cover is sort
of the same thing I really don't want to
store the information about how all the
grass is placed on each individual
entity forever because I only really
need to know it when I can see it right
when I'm in here I need to know the
grass placement for every entity that's
on the screen but as soon as I move up
right
and I and this room fades out of you I
don't need to know where the grass is on
it anymore
right I can recompute that once I come
back here as long as I have a way to
regenerate this sequence of grass
placement for any given tile I can just
recompute it when it comes into view so
again the same exact thing is going on
we sort of have this idea that there's
probably information we want to use and
store in fact it may be information we
even want to store on the graphics card
right we may want that information to be
persistent in a way that the graphics
card is actually able to just retain all
of the point information that's relevant
to it right so that we don't have to
send it down every frame so even that
piece of information is another good
such a good example of why this
information needs to be managed more
carefully and so when I'm getting at
this extremely long-winded explanation
is that what we need to attack both
problems is a new understanding of
entity state that gets persisted during
its lifetime on the screen or nearby and
then that gets thrown away in the case
where we are sort of paging it out and
so our world system gives us a very
convenient way to do this our world
system itself understands this concept
very well it has a it already has the
ability to look up things by chunk and
these are stored in chunks and those
chunks get unpacked into the simulation
region already right that's something
that we already do and so all we would
really need to be doing in this case is
we just need some way of having that
world system store complete data so all
the lighting information all the ground
cover information gets pushed into the
world system but instead of the world
system treating that it for me
as permanent and writing it back into
the world chunks where the information
is stored for the entire length of the
game what we can do instead is hold it
in a effectively like a level 2 cache if
you will that then if you ask for it
again you'll get it back but if you
constantly are pushing information into
there right and when you pull it out we
mark it as being like recently used when
you eventually try to push in too much
more than the total storage that we've
allocated for that level 2 cache we just
purge whatever the least recently used
thing what was and reuse that space for
the new information right and so putting
it into a cache in this way would allow
us to do exactly what we want
only store this information for things
that are actually being used in the
visual set or that have been recently
used in the visual set and purge those
things that aren't we can also tie this
system to GPU information updates such
that if we would like we can actually
store things or rather allocate space on
the GPU for things like lighting
information and grass information based
on whether or not the thing is in the l2
cache of the world right the w2 cache so
that's really what we're looking to do
here and so that's why I say these two
updates are really kind of closely
coupled because they both need
effectively the same sort of thing and I
think we can sort of kill two birds with
one stone at least in terms of the
structural implications of what we need
to do and the fact that the lighting
will require sort of a different set of
work that has more to do with improving
the algorithm we're using doesn't really
change the fact that it can still
benefit from this idea that certain
pieces of information are stored in sort
of a second level of cache inside the
world
so let's start out just for a warm-up
let's start out with it something easier
let's go into the the world generation
system and just add those trees you know
as we're sort of doing this generate
apron I'm just gonna do a really stupid
version where we place a tree down there
you can see in here we've got a
situation where we add one of these
trees I'm going to pull that out just
because you know there's no reason to
write the same code twice I'm just gonna
go ahead and say place tree or you know
maybe like add tree or something we're
not really placing it we already know
where it is
and so if we look here when we get into
this place here is the information that
we're doing and what I want to do is
this add obstacle here where we're
actually placing a thing I don't know I
have to go look and make sure that the
add optical call doesn't do anything
else but we probably don't quite want
this in both cases we probably want one
thing that will add an obstacle in one
case and another when we're just placing
a generic tree can probably do some kind
of a generic identity call so we're
gonna look at that in a second and we'll
see but basically what we're gonna do is
have this add tree call do something
here right and it'll do all this so to
start with we can probably do something
where add obstacle would work and again
maybe maybe we just really need these in
here so you know maybe this is add tree
tags or something like that and all you
have to do is send this down right so
you could say like okay here's the world
generator and here's the entity and then
later on we can customize this function
by having parameters that we send down
so that these things aren't random
anymore they're you know actually geared
towards whatever's in that area so let's
go ahead and do this procedure if we
want to add a tree in this code where
we're sort of iterating over these tiles
what I can do is say alright you know if
some condition is true that's a random
pick for now but maybe it would be more
interesting later we're gonna add the
tree tags to some kind of a tree here in
order to create an entity I could just
make one like so I don't know that
there's anything I have to really do to
it other than make sure that it's placed
in the right location so that's pretty
straightforward as well I don't really
remember what the ground point rules are
for this so we'll take a look in a
second for those but we should actually
have in fact get Minzy Center P we
really just need to get max Z Center P
here probably I don't really remember
again exactly how this code wants to
work but I think that's just the bottom
point of the tile and so what we want to
do here is just move that up so in fact
if we look at how this is actually
working let me set this collision volume
here this volume where we do this get
volume from Minzy and we pass the height
right that gives us the exact offset I
believe right so if this volume is
relative to this location then we should
be able to add this location to the
maximum point of the volume and get the
place where you would stand right I mean
that I believe that's true anyway so if
we sort of said here there was like a
ground P and I said something like in
fact like well I guess I don't see any
obvious way to do this using this
because this thing doesn't know how big
that tile wants to be but if I was to
say get max
corner like so where we get the maximum
for this volume and you know I could
even say get Minzy center P so this
actually we we could make an equivalent
to this which is just that and that
would actually give us exactly what we
want right so all we have to do now just
say whatever the the location is of this
thing we know that we made it relative
so let's just use the get maxius entropy
for this volume and then we're done
right and so if we're gonna place the
entity on that ground P we should be
able to just you know do it like this
again I don't know if that's the right
placement because I guess we haven't
really done much work on figuring out
how to create entity placement points
but I believe that our convention so far
has been to take the point that's on the
ground where the entity is and treat
that as the entity location so I'm gonna
keep that for now alright and so what
I'll do here is I'll just place a tree
on everything for starters and we'll go
from there
I think this is all we really actually
need to do to make this work I don't
know why I call that entity instead of
tree I think that's probably all we need
to do because again these entities don't
do anything they're just an inanimate
object so I don't think we need to call
anything else for them and we'll see
although the fact that I've seen no
trees is not a good sign since they were
supposed to be trees everywhere and now
there isn't
what happened what did I do wrong
um oh I I know what I did wrong
I did it I literally did exactly what
wait why isn't why isn't that call found
where's that add obstacle call I
literally said I was gonna look at it
and I didn't
what is add why is add obstacle not
something that's been marked as a
function what's going on there oh it's
just one of these Jannetty callbacks
that's why all right so what happens
here is we didn't add any pieces of
scenery to it and so we kind of do need
a thing that does this part of the call
so adding the tree is sort of an actual
thing we do need to do here right and
this occupying part where we passed you
know it gets the standing on bit I
assumed he could just passion all for
that if we wanted to so I feel like
that's probably fine now
unfortunately like I said I don't know
that we really want to though because we
don't really need the colliding flag it
doesn't need to participate in
collisions at all although you know I
mean maybe we could argue that it should
I don't really know but so if we
actually look in here let's just say
that this add piece call and I'll you
know we want all of this stuff yes he
see this placement wouldn't work because
this is just a standing on port would
work all right so I'm gonna I'm gonna
basically pull the common part of this
out which is like we've got that add
obstacle I'm gonna have like an add
inanimate and we're just gonna have this
stuff here that would normally be there
this doesn't need to be there this
doesn't need to be here but these do
something like that and so when you do
an ad in animates and I do want to
return this as well
it'll do just this part similarly we
could in fact this part here would work
as well so we could have it so that you
say add an animate and you say where you
want it to be I don't know that we need
anything else from there other than the
regions so I think it's just this right
and so if we were to do this call all we
would have to do is say hey when you
actually do one of these call add
inanimate first with the sim region and
the location you wanted the thing to be
and of course we do know that the
location where you wanted the thing to
be it's this right so we'll do that and
then this extra stuff here that you
wanted to do well you can do that as
well
for the adding the obstacle part but at
least now we've got the ability to do an
add inanimate that you know is a
callback for that right and so let's go
ahead and say that that's correct we may
want to make this a create entity call
as well and chain create entity to take
something else besides those but you
know for now I'm not gonna actually do
that so now we can actually call this
and I think that will solve the problem
we having where we didn't assign a neat
image to it so there were trees
everywhere but we couldn't see them so
what we'd like to do now is just say
yeah let's fix that right so make this
we want all this thing to create the
tree set it up add the tags etc
everything should be good
rediff finished a formal perimeter P let
me go back to that code so the problem
there is that when we are saying you
know this part right here I guess it
gets past a p-value as well I'm gonna
look for the gen create entity spec I
just want to see what that looks like so
it looks like it's the it's got a
traversable reference here and a p-value
that's being passed what's interesting
is I don't know that that p-value is
ever getting used so it's a little bit
odd like if you look at what's going on
here you can see the p-value gets used
in one case but the standing on gets
used in other cases that seems a little
janky to me and I would imagine that we
really need this to be we probably
really we need that to be more robust
than that just just looking at it so you
know my assumption is probably what
should happen is like when we do these
things instead of them getting the
instead of calling this code we should
probably just add the p-value directly
in here in other words we should
probably do something like this
you'll have to forgive me for skipping
through these I just wanted to take a
look so yeah you can see here how we're
kind of doing that yeah so what we want
here you can see that there's there's
sort of two general flavors for how this
is called one is I want to place a nosey
on this point the other is I want to
place an entity kind of what's where I'm
looking for I want to place it on to
something that's supposed to be standing
on like this right so you get the you
get this call and you only need one or
the other right in fact you can see in
this case it's kind of doing it the
wrong way it's using the MV P equals P
what it shouldn't be because it's
supposed to get a standing on instead
you know and so on so I think we want to
kind of solidify that part and so what
I'd like to do is I'd like to introduce
two ways of calling sort of these
functions right and so if you're using
like the the Jenna T thing you've got
this gen entity creator bit here so what
I want to do is something maybe like
this we've got one version which it's
gonna look like this that's going to be
like you know Gen entity at P and then
we're gonna have another one that's like
Gen entity at traversable and so you can
have two ways of calling it and
depending on which way you call it
you'll get a different way of doing
things right so in here we'll call the
creator function for whatever it is that
we're doing will pass the sim region so
you need to tell us that and then in
this case you'll pass the P and in this
case you'll pass the traversable
reference right
and in either case once use my head out
of the way in either case we will call
that function but in one case we'll use
the p-value directly and in the other
case we will use the p-value indirectly
make sense and in both cases we'll
return the result but in one case such
as this one we also have a little bit of
additional work we need to do there all
right so hopefully this makes sense what
I'm talking about
it's just basically allowing you to use
this in either way so the occupying part
needs to come in here and the get some
space reversible part needs to come in
here but then I think we're good to go
right looks like we call this standing
on and so I think that's all correct
looks good to me and so now this stuff
doesn't need to happen anymore so entity
P can just be the p-value what we could
also do is actually looking at these I
feel like it's just wasted code anyway
and so one might argue that that can
even be abstracted out more or rather
pulled out to a higher level right so if
I literally get rid of the even the
entity P part in its entirely this
entirety right that just looks like this
and so that code can now be used in two
different ways depending on what's going
on and the functions that actually
implement this no longer have to concern
themselves with what their location is
so when we look at something like add
obstacle this goes away right this goes
away that goes away
all of this stuff just gets simplified
right
what else we got alright again just
deleting the code that's no longer
necessary I think all this stuff is fine
that's result not entity probably should
have called it entity don't know I
didn't and I think that's it right and
so now people just need to call the
appropriate one whichever one it is that
you actually wanted and then you can go
from there right so in here we're we're
calling add obstacle or here where we're
calling pending entity creator instead
of doing that right what we're going to
do is we're going to call Jen entity
oops entity at traversable and we're
gonna pass the grid region we're gonna
pass the Creator function and we're
gonna pass that ground reference point
right this is not necessary anymore
because it's already automatically found
for us so that's good and now we're
gonna do the same thing in anywhere else
that we see it so here's our add
obstacle call and again add obstacle now
we're just going to use add obstacle as
as a creator function so rather than
calling it directly we're gonna pass it
again so this is Jen entity at
traversable we again pass that grid
region the add obstacle call and the
reference point on the ground same would
be true here
and off we go so now we have the
flexibility of having functions that are
you know passed to us but that we can
call in multiple ways and so now when
we're in our tree code here this finally
leaves us at a point where we're in good
shape what we can do is say look instead
of calling something like and add an
animate here we'll actually make this be
a gen entity at peak all will pass the
grid region and then we'll have that
inanimate here and we'll pass the ground
P as it stands that allows us to go up
here take that AB inanimate call turn it
into one of these and oops
and now we're good to go also why is the
gen Cree entity call Jim create antique
fall these should be marked internal
there's no they're not supposed to get
exported so that's that's just a
oversight there when we were creating
that code okay so I think now we've got
a situation where everything is flowing
a little bit more nicely through that
line of code and again yet gives us the
ability to call it two different ways
which which we want if we run it now we
should have a forest of trees quote
unquote which is just garbage right now
or it's just randomly picking but there
you go
right and so those areas are completely
filled with trees now just to make sure
you know we're in the realm of
reasonable here this is going to want to
be some distribution function at some
point and so we should be able to do
something like a random choice here and
we look at the the series that we're
using here we want to take that random
choice you know one in every third tile
I don't know is a tree let's say and so
that would just make it so that it's
clear that we're actually placing them
kind of randomly yeah again not a good
distribution function for trees but at
least it proves to us that it's working
and does what we want it to do
right and I think that's pretty good
let's also sort of have a maybe if we
wanted to do our tree tags a little bit
differently here so inside the tree tags
you can see here we're doing sort of
random unilateralis for these things
where we've got different kind of treaty
taxing unit for now since we don't want
it to look so ridiculous maybe we would
like to just say look let's let's keep
dark energy and fall and stuff out of it
in fact I guess you know I could do this
a little bit differently and say maybe
these are gonna be set to zero for now
right
and so you know maybe that just looks a
little bit more consistent for us at the
moment and so off we go and you know
mostly what that highlights to which is
good is just that well and you know what
else we could do now that we're at it
too
I feel like we could also look to see if
there was anything close to it and not
put trees there that would be an
interesting thing to try as well so for
example in here where we say like okay
we're gonna generate the apron so we're
looking to see whether or not
overlapping entities exist in this but
you know in this particular area here
where we do a get total volume what we
could do instead is just say you know
what let's do that same thing here I
guess for the tree well of course it
would find other things so we'd have to
be more Civic I'm just thinking like
where do where do we want what if we
wanted to do things that are like always
gonna be a little bit further away from
the room so we don't place trees like
right next to rooms or something like
that
yeah I'm not gonna do that yet because
I'm gonna say like once I start thinking
that I'm like it kind of gets into
things that we want to do a little bit
later with distribution so i'ma leave it
like this anyway what I was gonna say is
what you can really notice here too is
again for the world from the standpoint
of world solidity you can see why it's
so important to light the sprites right
we're not letting our sprites right now
and as a result this area out here
should be dark but it's very obviously
not like only the ground tiles are being
dark darkened whereas the actual trees
are completely bright and so that really
breaks any of the illusion there of the
trees also we have the trees sort of
poking through poking through the walls
here which actually I don't know that I
really want to fix because I I don't
think we should ever put trees in look
trees are supposed to be kind of overly
large and so I think we want to solve
that mostly with world Jen we don't want
trees that are placed next to walls
because they kind of occupy more than
their tile that's just how the trees
sort of work you can see they extend
kind of out too big so I I would say
that that's really a bug that has to be
solved more with world placement and not
with and not with changing the way the Z
stuff works so yeah I think we're all
good there we should be we should be
fine going forward I'm gonna go ahead
and take the add tree tags and do what I
said I wanted to do which is sort of
unify those two code paths as well so in
here I'm just gonna say let's take the
tree tags
and this way those will both be going
through the same path that will mean
that now we only have like the wintry
trees Oh Grod that's good
what's a Grod I feel like a Grodd is
something that we should know what it is
all right so now we should have just
those trees and let's see if we do
oops
probably ran it too soon huh
so we're still getting some of those
some of these what's going on there I
thought I changed it to oh no I didn't
ha ha okay so now I think we're good to
go and to move on to the next part of
our next part of our adventure here
right so we should now only have the
wintery trees because everyone's going
through that add tags call and so it
shouldn't be picking any fall trees
anymore or dead trees or dark trees
whatever they're called uh so just
looking at at what's going on here also
what is what's going on what is what's
happening right there there's like a
tree that's like placed sort of
underground or something do you see that
what what's happening there why are we
getting a second tree placed sort of
that's a bit of a puzzler and I don't
unfortunately I don't think we really
have much of a way to figure out where
that's coming from
hmm so that's yeah that's kind of one of
those things room like I don't really
know we don't have a real way of picking
where that we almost need better debug
information to figure out where that's
coming from so we don't really know who
would be responsible for drawing that
what's what's more interesting is it
seems to be that that occurs on every
bottom-left tile so you can see like
it's at the it's like we're adding one
tree at the root location of every room
I don't know every room but many rooms
in fact let's go see if that's true so
it's like there's one tree being placed
at zero zero zero right so who is
placing one tree at zero zero zero
and to be fair it might not be one tree
it could be lots of trees being placed
at zero zero zero right
so I'm going to start by doing something
pretty basic I'm going to get rid of
this piece of code and see whether or
not it gets rid of the errant tree
placement just so I know who is placing
it because there's only a few places we
call an any generation so we should be
able to see okay so first thing we know
is it ain't VAT code right because there
they are so we know it's not this code
I'm also gonna do a little thing that I
like to do sometimes which is just like
make sure that I can find this again
there we go uh so now what I want to do
is go find out you know is it
who else is calling something that could
be placing those trees in in a bad way
right and so let's suppose that it's
this call let's just ice that out and so
again one by one I'm going to remove
calls that can create entities until I
know who is responsible so it's still
there so it's somebody who's not
creating a tree at all it's somebody
who's just creating something right so
again let's take a look and see if we
can brought in the set of things being
removed again just removing some
entities from the mix
and so it looks like if we're not doing
light well no no no right so we're still
creating something at the sort of base
of the room so let's keep going
so now I think we have removed any hint
of the problem
so I'm sis what I'm suspecting is maybe
there was actually just a bug in this
general code bath that now like because
for example if I go to Gen entity at
traversable now I'm assuming that if I
make this a is anyone calling it now
yeah so I'm assuming this just generally
has a bug
oh and in fact I'm looking right at it
so that's it
we were just accidentally left a
secondary call in there right oops so
let's go ahead and remove these I think
that's all there was just a little typo
there no biggie
and now I think we're good
yeah so that was all there was I think I
don't think there's any other problems
with that okay
all right so now we want to get started
on the next process which again is just
to give us the ability to sort of have a
secondary level of storage where we know
that there are some things that are
there for visual continuity and
efficiency which either its information
we cannot regenerate in any predictable
way that would be something like the
lighting where it's not like a function
we just call and we get back the
lighting it's actually a stochastic
process that we hope converges to a
reasonable result so it's something like
that that we literally cannot just
recreate so we want to store it because
it needs to be averaged over time or
we're summing up the ground cover maybe
it's something that actually could be
recreated at any time directly but it's
just too expensive to do so meaning and
in certain some states those are both
kind of the same because you could argue
that the lighting is recreate able we
just run the algorithm long enough and
it converges to the lighting and so that
you know answers the question right
there but assuming that we're going to
treat it as just these things are too
expensive so we need to cache them at
least a little bit those pieces of
information need a place to live but
they don't want to live forever and so
the first thing that I guess what I'll
do to start us off is let's go ahead and
put a basic ground cover system in there
let's get it working with permanent
storage and then we'll have we have both
the lighting and the ground cover are
both in there we'll see how inefficient
it is because it could be it should be
quite inefficient and in fact with
ground cover will be even more
inefficient we probably don't want to
send it down every frame because not
changing every frame so it will
basically give us a good layout to see
how we want to start moving forward with
that secondary level of
in the world system alright so how this
would work right in the fully most worse
and most expensive way to do it is again
we've got this sort of super bloated
energy struct that we haven't really
cared about much and now we're going to
start caring about it a little bit more
and you can see here how we've got this
lighting point state nonsenses in here
and you can see here like we've got sort
of you know to do already talking about
the secondary level cashing so what we
want to do here is have the notion that
there's ground cover as well right it's
part of the process and just looking at
that what we need to do for ground cover
is pretty straightforward if we said
that there is some kind of ground cover
here we just need two pieces of
information we need like a location for
the ground cover and we need like what
we're gonna draw right so we need to
know at least that information but if
we're honest we probably need a little
bit more right we probably want to do
some kind of a color variant here right
so maybe we want a color that we would
multiply in you know like a tint
basically so that we could vary the
colors a little bit as necessary and
then we probably also want one more
thing which is we may want a scale so we
may want to like you know sort of change
the size of some of the grasses just
again probably not cute but maybe
between like point nine and point you
want and you know 0.9 and 1.1 which is
not quite a uniform on either side but
you get the idea so that we can kind of
have a a nice you know clean way of very
you know varying the the bitmaps a
little bit even if they're the same
bitmap they can get sort of played but
so thinking that through this is
basically the information we want for
splatting down those those ground covers
and
when we put those in there we kind of
need a known way of doing fins on them
but we can since the ground cover
shouldn't be very high we can probably
just use a known method of fitting them
which will not require the extensive
calculation that we currently do to
place sprites properly so that they
don't intersect the ground plane we
should be able to literally just put
grass in there in a pretty
straightforward fashion that's that's
not particularly interesting to anybody
so if we're gonna do that we really just
need this piece of information right and
off we go now one thing that's true
about this is there's not a lot of
reason that it has to be attached to an
entity so this ground cover could be
kind of arbitrary but I think there is
an argument even though it creates a
little bit of inefficiency for us I
think there is an argument to be made
that these things should be attached to
entities the reason that I think there's
an argument to be made there is because
if these things are attached to entities
they can be manipulated when necessary
so for example if the ground cover were
not attached to an entity at all then we
would get in a situation where if
something was supposed to happen like
something supposed to catch on fire or
an entity was supposed to go away or was
supposed to like raise or lower the
ground cover wouldn't move with it right
and so I feel like we do need our ground
cover to at least be related to the
entity somehow if not stored with it but
I think it probably needs to be stored
with it in order to work properly right
and so if we take the ground cover and
me say all right there's going to be an
array of ground cover that exists in
here right we would have something like
this and you can already see why this is
going to start being a problem this is a
lot of information and if we were to put
as many of these in as we probably want
which is probably a fair
right that just really bloats out the
entity structure even more and so now an
enemy structure is just huge and even
just the time we spend copying that
around is now going to be probably an
issue so I don't know if we'll see a
speed hit here you know computers are so
darn fast that you know it's kind of
nuts that we don't see an immediate kind
of obvious speed hit from that but you
know it probably still is at least a
little bit well you know I'm gonna be
honest you can kind of look at the
profile you can see it really just
doesn't matter computers man Intel and
AMD really ships some amazing stuff you
got to hand it to him we do our best to
ruin it here in the world of software
but it's just kind of nuts when you look
at how flat this profile is it's like if
we just when we improve our lighting our
frame time goes down to basically
nothing right
even though it's so piggy right it's
it's horrible and there's so much we
could do to improve it it's kind of nuts
how amazing CPUs are they just eat it
for breakfast you know and it's just
it's kind of crazy how how good they are
at that it's really you gotta hand it to
them they they do such amazing work
anyway so if we take a look at something
like a pute light propagation here which
is just taking up all of our time and
again you know we can sort of see that
here's like a huge chunk all of our time
is getting spent doing that we would
reduce our frame rate by gosh what
probably 2/3 so you know if we look at
this here this this is what's sort of
unfortunate this is a little bit
misleading because this is going to get
counted because of how many threads are
doing it and so when you look at this
it's not 87% of the frame time probably
it's more like 66% of the frame time or
something and you kind of got a look at
this to see what would because you're
not saying how much CPU time was spent
doing it you're asking how much CPU time
how much frame time would be saved and
so the CPU time is uneven these things
are not paralyzed that are happening in
here right and so even if we free up all
the CPU time it wouldn't get used by the
other threads that are that are sitting
around idle right and so that's just you
know a reality of having to look at the
profile with a more careful eye but you
get the idea
all right so looking in here at this
entity you can sort of see how that
floats things out and it doesn't really
cause a time problem for us but you know
we could also see whether up to what
extent it creates a space problem for us
one thing that we don't have right now
like when I run the game right we can't
see how much space is taken up by our
world database but I feel like we could
and so like if we looked inside handmade
world that's CBP when this actually gets
run in here we've got some information
we could use right in fact if you look
we've got a memory reading here that
tells us what we're using for world
storage right and so what we could do if
we wanted to is we could take this this
world arena and just say how much memory
it's actually using so if I look at you
know the memory arena and we I don't
know do we have a function that just
says how much space is getting used
so we don't actually have we don't
actually have a immediate call that
gives us the total amount used but it
would be pretty easy to find right
because you could use the the current
block information for that and I think
that would give you what you want so let
me see here
so this debug platform memory stats
right we can get that information
[Music]
and we probably just should print that
out that the only thing is you know
that's just for the total memory use and
so actually you know it doesn't really
tell us what we want we want to know how
much is allocated to our worlds arena so
I think what we really want is something
that would tell us that information
right and so like when we run when we
bring up like the profile or whatever
you can look here and you can see like
how much memory is being used in how
many blocks right and so you can kind of
see that like we've got all right it's
using half a gigabyte of memory right
now but of course a lot of what's being
used for that half of a gigabyte there
is in the debug information in fact this
may only be the debug information right
that's all of our just recording
everything that happened on every frame
and that's why it stops getting used I
don't so I don't know whether that's
actually the whole game or just a debug
information but point being it really
just doesn't tell us any information
right none of our debug views here have
anything like this right and so what
we'd like to do is get sort of something
that would tell us more specifically
what is going on with our memory there
so that we could have an idea of how
much space we're saving right or using
for any particular for any particular
arena and you know if you looked at that
sort of you know in here we could sort
of have those arenas labeled as well
might be another kind of nice thing
about that so that the arena's
themselves could maybe update the debug
system periodically
with what the actual size is and I don't
know you know how we necessarily would
want to do that but I do think that
would be relatively straightforward for
example yeah I mean if each time through
we just said like hey or even if we just
had our memory arena's iterative Bowl in
some
of global way that would probably work
um I'm not sure I just don't know if I
really want to do that right now
it's something we should probably put on
the horizon though let's just take a
look take a quick look so in here where
we've got sort of these editor these
various editor calls right and then
we've got sort of our debug system and
this whole thing didn't really come
together as well as you know we would
have liked cuz just takes a long time to
build these systems and we never really
zeroed in on it so it's still a little
bit sprawling and a little bit kind of
hacky you can see here like we've kind
of got this two-phase kind of thing
where we've got our debug stuff in fact
there's a memory a dev mode memory right
there that doesn't actually do anything
at the moment
and in fact do we ever actually oops
we actually have an f8 key that maps to
a dev mode memory but we don't actually
do anything and you can see here like we
call this so it just doesn't do anything
when you actually push the f8 key right
so I'm not sure exactly how that was
supposed to work in the grand scheme of
things but let's take a look at maybe
where does dev mode rendering actually
get set
so I assume that this column needs to
get called and just isn't getting called
at the moment so like that
and so I guess you can see that we sort
of had a a sort of loose plan in place
here where we were gonna say look let's
go ahead and have these memory arenas do
something useful here and we just never
actually did anything right so it may be
the case that we can put these into we
can press these into service somehow for
example I don't know if I can really
know how this works but maybe we can do
something like this where in the world
system you know when we come through
here and we create one of these worlds
maybe we can announce that to the system
I'm not really sure again to what extent
this would actually work but you can see
that it just I guess it just uses
whatever that parent arena is here so
when we do a create world in that case
pretty much just happens right there
looks like so in here where we call this
with the mode arena we want that mode
arena to be captured because that's the
one that would show us what's going on
and you can see in here that the mode
arena itself is just you know game state
mode arena and so in theory we should be
able to I guess I don't need to put
in its own area I guess that could
actually happen here as well so we could
just do something like you know oh like
there it is so never mind I guess we do
have that we don't have the asset arena
here but that could also I suppose be
placed in there as well because it's
just assets a arena right so we could
put so that asset arena I actually don't
know if that's what that's called
but I believe that's a separate arena
that we use only for this particular
purpose so
[Music]
it's called non restored memory and now
the question would be if we take a look
at these arenas inside the debug system
like what can we print out that would be
useful right at the moment I really only
care about one thing which is I would
like for these arenas here to have some
kind of a total space right and so like
going into the debug system like just
looking for where that gets actually
used so we've got this straw arena
occupancy stuff and again don't really
know like what our plan was here what we
were doing
and so you know
it looks to me to like this part
yeah it doesn't really make a lot of
sense so it looks like we're basically
looking at things that were tracked to
the arena but I don't think these
actually ever get stored do they I mean
maybe they do but did we like did we
actually put a debug marker in here for
when we push a size on here cuz I sure
don't see one right so I feel like that
probably doesn't actually do anything
but yet we had something in here so I'm
not sure what this was doing to go back
to our own video archive and see so I
guess what this was doing previously is
it looks like it was just accessing the
actual directory no structure and then
drawing some kind of a rectangle just
show how much was used or something like
this right so ideally what you would
have here is not that right you would
have something that sort of said
who is responsible for allocating each
block right and so
and so there's a couple different ways
we can do that and I'm not really sure
which one we want to do but
[Music]
yeah but I think at least from my
perspective I think this is kind of
going at it a little bit the wrong way
right so what you want to do here is
every time you do an allocation you want
to record like who did the allocation so
you can see who's using the memory right
and so in a sense I would say that
really these should just be things that
are underneath the arena and we just
print out those sizes and we could do
them as a graph if we want to but we
probably just want to know those sizes I
like there's something to be said for
showing the allocation pattern but that
allocation pattern would definitely be
something that's a little bit harder to
track it certainly requires more
bookkeeping to do so so I don't know the
other thing that's a little bit janky
here is if you look at how this is
working when you do draw arena occupancy
you're gonna need to know like like in
this case we're actually getting the
arena itself and while that might work I
don't know how well it works
it wouldn't work like over time right so
we're not storing that information sort
of persistently which maybe is okay
but again it's just one of those things
where it's like I think that if I had to
criticize the approach to how I was
doing the debug system is it's just too
generic and I think it doesn't really
accomplish much as a result because it's
just very very arbitrary and generic it
doesn't have like the tools that you
actually need for doing specific kinds
of debug viewing and so I think just too
much time was wasted on that sort of
stuff and that you can kind of see that
fragility coming through because it
should be pretty easy right if you had
just purpose-built a little thing that
tracks the allocations that's not very
hard thing to accomplish but because it
everything tries to go through like a
uniform event system that doesn't really
know what the heck it's doing there's
not a lot of ways you can really there's
not a lot of ways you can really deal
with memory allocations because those
are things that aren't viewing an event
you're viewing the state of the
allocator at any given time which cannot
be recreated only from events unless you
have all the events from the very
beginning of time and ran through them
all so you kind of need a list of the
results of the events right and yeah you
know I just don't necessarily see that
being something that's easy to do here
so I think what I would want to do is I
would want to build something that's a
little more purpose-built and allows us
to show the actual loves to keep the
actual set of allocations that we had
right and so if you look at how the
memory arena works at the moment what
you can see is that for every memory
arena you've got one of these current
blocks here right and the current block
is the thing that that platform memory
block that platform memory block is the
thing that we actually use to
push things on so like we've got the
flags the size the base they used we use
this use parameter to kind of like move
things along as we go and so it seems to
me like what we probably want here is
something where we could do like just
imagine for a moment what you kind of
want to do is say look whenever we do a
push size call right we have the
information that we actually need to do
what we want to do in that push size
call so if you look at everywhere that
we were doing any kind of push calls so
like for example all of our main ones
here I don't know what optional clear
parameter is because we have an optional
clear parameter which says don't clear
so is that I don't think that to do is
Val anymore um if you look at these it's
pretty easy for us to say at least in
these when we do pushes in here it would
be pretty easy to say look the push size
call is gonna do a thing where if we're
in sort of our handmade internal version
we're gonna take a file and line number
in there right so we're gonna say here's
the file here's the line number and if
we're in handmade internal where we're
saying this is an internal builds that's
just going to pass down right and so I
would assume the easiest way to deal
with that is to go well and I suppose
now to think about it I suppose we could
do it at the end which might make things
a little easier
excuse me well I guess it would
um so when we're doing these here right
we can sort of have two sets like so and
essentially what we're gonna do here is
just pass the file online and so when
you come in here and you get a file name
and a line number now you know you can
actually do and you actually don't ask
me why put those in the opposite order I
don't have a reason now we have to make
sure that everyone who calls push sighs
actually obeys that rule so you can see
in here there's some people who call
that directly those are the other calls
inside the memory system looks like for
the most part which will fix this stuff
will if zero out for now and so looking
at these Jimmy what we need to do here
is make sure that these also do that
exact same thing so we want push string
Z to actually call push string Z like
this right
so effectively push string Z there's a
macro that would just take the file in
line from whoever was calling it and
make that work like so and again same
thing so this is actually that and this
is something that would get up here in
the you know just just like the rest of
them that would that would use sort of
an internal function to do the work that
it's going to do however when it's not
an internal node it won't pass those
it's just a pass-through and that's it
okay so now push strings II can just
have a pass-through file and line number
so exactly the same way as it was doing
here and again this is just all horrible
it's horrible because C++ is a horrible
language and designed by by simpletons
right and so you know we've got to do
all this garbage for no real reason it's
just a waste of our time but that's just
how it goes what we can do here is we
could make this be something that's a
little bit cleaner so we could make this
like internal memory pass-through right
and then what you could do is say look
each one of those starts with that so
then we do like you know internal memory
pass-through is this nonsense right
otherwise it's nothing that way when you
come through in each case we don't have
to write the routine every to have those
pastures every time maybe this so this
way we can say like look everything has
to start with that garbage and then
everything has to pass that garbage
right and that way it's not you know
[Music]
it's not something that has to have so
many pound ifs through the whole thing
it can just be one sort of sort of thing
that's determined by this central system
and then everyone can use it it's still
not great but it's you know better than
nothing I guess is the way I would put
it and they used to find them - nothing
in the non internal build version right
so I think that's probably good enough
and here you know we can use the same
thing for the push size function itself
right to get rid of that and off we go
so again it's not fabulous but it's the
best we're going to be able to do
all right so if we put this in here and
say that we want to do all of these the
same way because really we sort of do
like we want these to all have that same
tracking so that we know what came from
where we so we probably want like all of
these to have that information just
looking at it right and so if we were
gonna do that it's again pretty
straightforward
all of these get one of these which
again is not the worst thing in the
world now that I've done that pound two
fine
so all of those get one of these and
then all of these get the pass version
right and these push copy calls they
need the ability to take those
parameters themselves in this case here
where we do a push buffer I guess this
wants to clear so I I guess we're
literally doing this so you know this
was defaulting to clear why this doesn't
take a parameter I don't know because
you would think that you would want to
um like this in fact I'm really not sure
why these all don't take that but the
idea would be you know this this should
always have the params there so that you
could override the ones where you when
you call push buffer like what did you
want to do right and and I really don't
know so if you look at push string Z
versus push string here I'm gonna have
to go out and a limb and say I don't
understand why we have both of these
functions am I missing something
well I guess that one needs to be
null-terminated and this one doesn't
that's about it right yeah I don't
really see much else um so we probably
want these two again also be macros in
that same way if that makes sense so
that they can do when they do their push
copy you know we can do something more
like this and so that would really be
the only thing there nothing else really
needs to happen there and the rest of
these work properly so these guys are
under squared and then we need push you
know both of them push buffer and push
string sort of both need to have and and
I sorry and also pushing they'll
terminate those all need to be Mack Road
right now in order to make push copy
work properly we actually need to sort
of versions of that we need one that
that puts the file and line number in
for you and one that doesn't now the one
that doesn't do that should you know we
should be able to reuse the same one by
just having this take the file in line
number so basically like you know this
would be file and line like that and it
would actually do it like this and then
this push copy would just be a call to
the existing push copy that went like
that
right and so we'd only have one actual
push copy and the other one would be
this so if we looked at that and we
wanted to sort of make this work this
way we would just say okay in the
version that's not internal when we do
the push copy we still have both things
but now they just don't actually do that
file online pass-through anymore you
know I'm saying for the rest of these
it's literally just a thunk so you know
that in the same way that we had our
push strings II do this and do nothing
in the other case we would do the same
thing for our other functions so we'd
have a push string do the same thing
we'd have a push buffer which does the
same thing and we'd have a push and nil
terminate which does the same thing so
all of those are just you know
straightforward wrappers and then here
we would have the exact same set of
straightforward wrappers so we would
have push string push buffer and push
and mill terminate and those would
literally just sunk through to their
underscored version without actually
changing the parameters and again that's
strictly a concession for allowing that
stuff to flow through unadulterated in
the other case so now we kind of got to
fix all this stuff looking at how for
example push copy here is working not
enough primary function like macro okay
so we've got to actually go make sure
all this stuff is correct that's
supposed to pass the filename in line
number to push copy which is supposed to
do
but it looks like it's hmm excuse me
it looks like it's the right number of
things because there'd be the file name
the line number so I messed up something
there but I'm not really sure what
because it's supposed to take 1 2 3 4 5
parameters and we're passing 1 2 3 4 5
parameters which seems like exactly what
we want you know so I'm not sure why
it's thinking that's bad because it sort
of seems correct but obviously it
doesn't think so
so why doesn't it think so
not enough arguments
it also thinks there's a missing this
isn't a return right yeah so yeah what
is the problem here that this is
complaining about because I don't really
see I don't really see any issues with
that I'm gonna just double check so
something about internal memory pass is
not working right because I replaced it
with two things here and it didn't
generate an error of course file online
shouldn't necessarily work in there so
what just happened I'm very confused
right now like why didn't that give me
an error
but obviously internal memory passes is
an issue here internal memory pram is
apparently not
but I don't again don't know why so I'm
at a bit of a loss there and I would
like to see what it's pre processing
that - so I could know what's what it
thinks is wrong one thing I could do as
well is just make sure that these are
getting used let me just go ahead and
put some errors in there yeah so that's
getting used and that's getting used so
it is as far as I can tell actually
doing you know putting into things there
and yet let's see if this is true hello
five if I actually replace these with
something else I'm wondering if there
was a some other bug and and that there
just doesn't seem to be so I really just
don't understand
I really just don't understand what's
going on there I wonder if this is a
problem that placing that inside its own
macro expansion is creating a problem
where it's actually using that per that
as a parameter instead of expanding it I
guess is what's happening there so I
suppose there's a smarter way I could do
this right I could always have these
take the file name and line number
because it works for anything where I'm
calling an actual function but if I'm
not calling an actual function you get
the problem is there a way I could make
push copy you know not be that and if I
look at it it does look that way because
if you take a look at what happens
inside a push copy it looks like it just
kind of works to a certain extent right
so maybe if I just make push copy into
its own function instead of doing it the
way I was doing it maybe that's
sufficient so like for example we can
leave it like that and then here we can
just create a push copy and that way I
wouldn't be in that zone of macro
expansion death I'm not sure we'll find
out so if we actually had a push copy
and we did it like this
and I went ahead and grabbed the same
like I said same sort of procedure here
where you're just sort of telling it you
know what you wanted to do then in
theory you know this could just work so
we do the push copy and you do this in
you know this piece of information here
what's also nice about that is you could
get back a pointer to it if you wanted
to so like there'd be a result now which
there wasn't before which is kind of
nice so I feel like maybe that's just
better all around and it also solves a
problem that we were having with that
with that call in general right and so
yeah I like that a lot more and then
that way now we don't have this function
at all like it's just the macro and
furthermore I guess that means we can do
this right and so it means that all of
these are now just doing that one
stripping or adding activity which seems
what way better right so I think that's
I think that's more solid and I'm gonna
leave it at that okay so let's take a
look here so in order to make these work
we now need those to be actual
parameters that should be pretty easy
because the size is just a memory index
or um M as we call it now and this is
just a void star that's like where you
wanted to copy from so that should all
be handled pretty easily all right so
let's take a look at what we've got now
Oh push buffer this used to actually be
a call I guess which I don't know that
we want it to be because that's sort of
a different situation where did we do
here when we call push buffer it cultic
which is one of these and this is yeah
so this is like we do push render
element
let's call that push render buffer and
then we'll call this push render buffer
all right so in theory we have hopefully
broken nothing and everything works just
fine now
and in theory the only difference for
the code and again I do need to test one
other thing when we actually change
handmade internal to zero we need to
process bugs there right and just see
what's going on it looks like we've got
some other ones in line variables
require at least but it's not an inline
variable so this must be like a debug ID
is skillets you know what I don't think
it's called a debug ID anymore it's
called a dev ID anyway just want to make
sure that the non internal build still
works looks like some weird
so I'm not sure what's going on here not
a member of game assets see decoration
of game assets ah so you know what
though that is true so all of this stuff
we really don't all of this stuff where
we you know parse incoming files really
not supposed to run anymore right so
basically this entire file is an if
handmade internal alright because we're
not supposed to have any of that stuff
so I guess what I would say is that kind
of needs to happen it's what okay I
wonder what the bug is well we we almost
never have a for coded crash that's a
weird one so let's go ahead and go to
handmade hero again let me just see
where that ended up with where we were
at it may have actually saved the
changes there we go alright so looking
at handmade internal here what is this
this is just placing things where it
doesn't find a structural part I may
change that to an invalid code path for
now see where we're at
so debug UI hood I guess that must be
something that we forgot to define in
both cases I'll take a look at see so
here is debug UI HUD and I'm gonna go
ahead and guess that we just forgot to
put it in here again these are just
making it so that we can compile out all
of our sort of development code there so
here's an on internal builds not sure
what this is complaining about
so somehow in this case we don't have a
font ID right meaning that's came back
as an on thing right alright now I guess
it didn't so what's the problem here
you can't write to the UI font info but
why not hmm
so I'm not sure exactly what that's
actually complaining about here because
in theory this looks like valid memory
and so you should be able to write to
this pointer just fine it's not writing
through the pointer right it's gonna
overwrite the pointer so I'm not sure
what that's actually complaining about
it looks more like an assertion I wonder
if it's an assertion that's actually
somewhere else maybe an inline code it
could be because of the get font info
call maybe this this font ID value isn't
quite right or something let's take a
look at that so it's probably this I
would assume I don't actually know so if
we look at the defines for assert here
handmade slow is actually the thing that
determines it so the asserts are all
compiled in and since there's a right
directly to D word 0 that pretty much
lets you know that that pretty much
tells us that that this is the assertion
and it's probably the assertion that's
saying that the thing that you received
wasn't a font but I have no idea how
that could actually be possible or why
it would change between the handmade
internal version in the non internal
version so that's a little bit confusing
right like in other words I'm not sure
if there's some other and bug we
introduced there let's just double check
to see what happens in internal mode
so internal node works oops
port does it I didn't actually define it
to zero there but I guess maybe having
nothing in it is the same I don't know
there's internal mode
there's non internal mode and here's the
debug build and so I'm correct that it's
asserting that the type of this asset is
not a font and if we look at the HHA you
can see that it gave back basically a
like I didn't find it right it's saying
like it couldn't it could not find the
one that that's being discussed here and
the question is like why couldn't find
it you know what I mean and I have no
idea why and so what I think we need to
do there is we need to take a look and
see whether or not that oops
whether or not there's something that we
were doing that that needs to happen
right in internal that is causing a
problem for us right and there could be
so
[Music]
I can't say I necessarily see why that
would be the case because the asset
loading still seems to be relatively the
same but you know something's obviously
different we just don't know what again
nothing particularly compelling in most
of these they're pretty much what you
would expect
you know I don't I don't see anything
it's it's mostly just you know exactly
what you would think
hmm so what's going on there why is it
having so much trouble with that I would
kind of like to know I realized we're
sort of off on a tangent here but the
game should be able to run in both modes
and the fact that it can't is a bad sign
so we've got some lurking bug there that
we need to take care of if I go ahead
and say handmade internal one and that
does work and handmade internal zero
doesn't work and the place where we're
stopping is in get font info because
when we got the font we couldn't find it
the question is what happened there so I
will say one thing which is that let me
run that one more time so if we go
backwards here and we get the we do the
like font ID equals get best matched
font from right I should be able to
watch this fail when we go through the
asset system you know and just see
what's what's wrong why I can't find it
and I'm guessing it's because there's no
types yeah so it's like the first asset
of type for this type ID is not like
loaded properly and so I'm wondering
like who is responsible for that being
messed up and again that sort of code we
is scheduled for the chopping block but
it shouldn't be different between these
two paths so I would like to know what's
going on there probably the set asset
type got buried inside an internal block
accidentally so looking here let's just
suppose a priority that was the case
this would be where we would expect that
yep oh wait no that's right there so
this is where this is happening
is there something in here that we
actually needed to have happen that's
not happening I wonder
so seeing is how it just uses global
asset index presumably as long as global
asset index is correct it should be okay
right
and so when we come through here where
do we set that and how it's really all
we kind of need to know so you can see
us just incrementing the asset counter
here we get the global asset index that
way that really shouldn't be dependent
on this block
hmm
is there some part about us writing the
tags out wrong that like this is
correcting four or something because
again I don't see it like just looking
at what's happening here there really
isn't a lot of reason to suspect that
code of doing anything really relevant
so I guess I don't have any other ideas
so I think what I'm gonna do is I'll
just loosely step through this source
path and I'm gonna step through it once
the correct way and once the incorrect
way and just see if I can spot anything
obvious that it's doing differently so
in the asset system I'm just gonna set a
break point when we enter this part of
the code and I'm just gonna see what's
going on so we're gonna come through
here we're gonna get the file asset
counts out of this file it says one
hundred and sixty nine of them for a
good measure I might as well look at
what the file is I don't know if there's
any okay yeah so the file stem is intro
cutscene and so if we're doing that we
just want to know like okay intro
cutscene has 169 things in it so we
start reading them like so when they
come we loop through each asset the
first global asset index for that case
is one what we would expect we're gonna
do some nonsense here that I don't feel
like should be doing anything but maybe
is somehow we're gonna look at the type
ID and we're gonna search the tags in
this file well actually that we loaded
in right to see whether we can find one
that's the basic category we're then
going to set the asset type of that
index to that which will start to string
it together and that's really it so
that's exactly what we would have
expected to have happen if I go ahead
and just jump here to where the fonts
actually are coming from it would have
been bass game I believe and they get
found properly
let me do that one more time
so here's bass game right
it's got foreign to Sony and assets in
it let's see just real quick
what is the global asset index and in
this case it's 170 and we're doing the
rebasing here off of the file tag bass
does file tag base need to be no I don't
think so
so there was no type ID for that one
whatever it was that came in there a lot
of things there's no type ID which seems
bad but I think those are actually ok
technically because they're fonts
there's the font
and it's 275 so all right let's do a
recompile here I'm gonna set handy
internal zero and just see if I can spot
a difference if not we'll save it for
tomorrow here is our file asset count
and our first file it looks the same
which is good that's what we want to see
we can sort of do a spot check here you
know come through get the first global
asset index of one verify that it also
creates a plate type and it does then we
go in to set asset type right and that
all seems fine so no real worries there
let's go ahead and run again oops
deny not set a breakpoint oh so we
didn't load our other file so the
problem is actually that we just aren't
loading the files
how did that happen
let's try this again so run to here
first file in char cutscene looking up
the header
that does not look correct
although it could actually be correct so
we've got at a count of 227 asset count
of 170
right okay so somehow we're not even
looping over the correct number although
actually no that's not true because it's
zero is not counted so we're just not
we're just not correctly adding the
number of files somehow so something's
weird here
we got a step back for a second
so when we come through here we're doing
this nonsense right and for every file
in the file group we're creating one
source file so this is the issue I guess
in its entirety so hold on let's see why
here is me initializing two source files
and yet somehow that only results in two
total files interesting so what's going
on there in its source HHA
oh my god seriously seriously so where
did we set that did you see that so the
reason is because we put in space for
extra files but this is wrong that's
lame I feel like maybe the sets a mini
owl of shame sort of so the problem
there was just that you know we we were
maybe a little bit too that should have
just crashed or giving us a hard error
but instead we kind of handle the error
by saying oh well I guess we're loading
a file that's too many files so we just
won't load it and not mention it which
is not great right but I think that's
our only problem right was just that we
didn't you know we had left room for a
null file and then we didn't actually do
anything with it so there's the internal
builds or the non internal build running
we should be able to kick it back to
regular optimized release build and not
have a problem now I would assume
yeah so that was a waste of time but hey
at least we now know the internal build
works so what I'd like to do tomorrow
then and you can see now none of the
debug stuff really works either you can
see that like you know we can you can
use the editor which uh probably we
should get rid of at some point but like
none of the profile or any of that stuff
it's cuz that's all compiled out should
probably compile up the editor too um
alright so let's save everything for
tomorrow I'd like to go ahead and
visualize that memory tomorrow now that
we have the ability to record it coming
through and this seems pretty clean so
now I'm happy to turn this back on I
assume we can also turn slow off yeah
that's all good all right so I think
we're good let's go ahead and set this
back to normal state and we'll do brief
Q&amp;A
let's see any questions that what we
were doing
on top of questions please
why do you delete the PD B's before each
build have you found the compiler having
issues or leaving junk if you just let
the copilot uh so the reason that the
build has to delete the PD B's is
because we create a new PDB every time
so in a normal build environment where
you don't use live code reloading you
would normally just generate a PDB to a
file that is the same file every time
you build so you don't get a problem
with pdbs like stacking up and getting
an infinite number of PD B's in your
build directory right but because we use
live code reloading and Visual Studio in
fact probably most buggers don't read
the PDB and then unlock it you end up
with a situation where you cannot
replace the existing PDB file because
the game is running so what we had to do
really early on in handmade hero because
we support hot code reloading like
without closing the game the code will
reload when you make changes we had to
create random names for our PDB files so
instead of running a PDB to the same
name every time we pick a random number
and write the PDB did that right then we
link that random PDB with a random name
for the DLL to create a new DLL that
isn't going to clash you know with our
existing one right and so we do this
kind of fancy dance to allowed hop to
allow hot code reloading to work but
really they're just deficiencies of the
coding environment it's because Visual
Studio is crappy would be another way to
say it yet another way to say it is to
say that's because Windows is crappy
because their system doesn't support
inode like file manipulation like for
example Linux does so as a result the
default way you interact with files
unless you go through extraordinary
lengths and use volume Shadow Copy
Service and all this other garbage
can't do stuff like replace this file
even though someone's using it and make
the next person who goes to use it get
the new file like doesn't work right and
so yeah you just fundamentally find
yourself in a position where you have to
work around those things and that's why
we delete the PDP's is because otherwise
they would just stack up forever because
we're creating a new one completely new
name every time
in that system do you have to transfer
all push functions into macros I'm not
sure what you mean by in that system but
generally speaking if you want to push
things onto memory and track what file
and line number they are you do have to
do that right lucid Frost what are some
better alternatives to things like if
desks that a language could provide well
in our case it's fairly obvious right if
you were designing a language and had a
clue
you would just include the ability for
someone to say get me the file and line
number of the person who called me done
so all functions to allocating memory to
become macros if you want to keep track
of where the memory is allocated yes
correct
how much more stable has Remedy gotten
since you started using it on streem
were there any particularly big issues
that caused you trouble that have been
fixed in that time yeah actually there's
been tons of revisions to remedy that
made it more stable since we started
what I would say is use I mean you see
me usually at every day on stream now
have you seen any issues
I just don't run into them anymore it
seems very stable I really haven't had
any issues there's some features I'd
like to see obviously but you know I
said as a replacement for Visual Studio
now it's just fine
do you think unit using do you think
using tests would have made it easier to
find the code paths that were broken
with this refactor refactor what
refactor first of all we have not
refactored anything I don't really like
that name either because it doesn't
refer to anything and specifically write
it just as a term that means programming
but I I'm not sure what tests we would
have had in this case right I mean first
of all no code did break with the
changes we made all the code worked
exactly correctly the thing that
actually was wrong was just a thing that
with handmade internal setting to zero
we had not tested that code paved path
in forever so there was just a one bug
with asset loading that we introduced
long ago like many many weeks ago right
and would when it tests have fixed that
no I mean we found it quite quickly
actually so even I can't even think of a
test that would have caught that error
that could have been written in less
than the 15 minutes it took to find it
right so I guess one way to say it would
be no test would have been a complete
waste of time is that why you put all
push functions in the same file I know I
think I put them all stepfather's
because they all have to do with memory
probably I don't think I put them in
there because I was thinking ahead I
just put them there because that's where
they go right
the calls that have to do with putting
memory into an arena should kind of all
be in one file so that I can just see
what puts mime around and Reena here it
is right if you didn't do code reloading
say for release would you still have the
platform XC and a separate gala for the
game code no I don't think there's be
any reason to do that you could still do
it just because there's no real reason
why you couldn't like you don't
necessarily get any benefits from
welding the code together in any
particular way because those boundaries
are pretty low frequency so you don't
really need to take advantage of any
kind of like linker
zatia nor something like that that would
happen there but there's certainly no
reason not to do it and for really all
intents versus maybe we will have a way
to build just a single X Z version just
for fun I mean we might do that you know
so I guess I don't know but what I would
say is it's purely an arbitrary
distinction that's there in our case for
no reason other than to support the code
reloading so we don't need we don't need
separate dll's for any particular reason
the renderer on the other hand we have
as a separate DLL for for a good reason
and the reason for that is we may want
to allow people to replace the renderer
dll without replacing anything else in
the game if someone just wanted to
someday cook up a like ray tracing
renderer for handmade hero it'd be great
if they could just post a dll that's
like hey here's a ray trace renderer go
nuts and it just drops in and works
right so having the renderer be
extendable in that way where you can
just sort of drop in a new renderer and
make it work
the chloral location is a many to one
mapping which is why languages generally
don't do it you could but it means
complications for the runtime code
generation uh nope it really doesn't
right and the reason that I say that is
because if you look at what I just did
that is what the compiler had to do so
anything I can just do by making a macro
is something the compiler could have
just done so it really doesn't write
it's like that is not a complication
that is owners if your compiler is any
good at all it's really basic it's just
saying I in fact a template is the same
way right C++ compilers for word you
have to deal with templates which
essentially say generate a different
version of this code path based on what
the declare the declaration
of the person doing this thing does it
the call site and they've got that so I
know they could do it they just choose
to not support features like that
because they don't know what they're
doing right they they basically almost
all complicated languages actually do
the work of doing things like this and
then are so short-sighted in the way
they design things that they don't
actually allow you to use them in useful
ways in fact you could argue that the
entire design is C++ has been one giant
exercise in making massive complexity in
the compiler that actually yields you
know practical benefit to the programmer
it's kind of remarkable actually how
complex the C++ compiler is for how
literally it offers you alright we're
done with questions
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for the episode our hand made here at
so the pleasure coating with you as
always
if you would like to follow along the
series you can always do so at handmade
hero org if you pre-order the source
code that's alright if you preorder the
game you can get the source code any day
you want I updated after we stream and
so you can follow along at home and play
around with it for example some of the
things that we talked about if you want
to try and beat me to it you've got all
day today to go try to put some memory
visualisation into the system maybe you
should give it a shot it's good practice
to always try to do something that I say
I'm going to do before I do it because
then you can see what it feels like to
try and have to do it without already
having seen someone do it in a
particular way
and who knows you may come up with
something better than what I'm gonna
come up with which is even which is even
more cool right so that's about it for
today I'll be back here for tomorrow
we'll be at the normal time tomorrow
which is a noon today was an early one
at 10:00 we'll be at neural time
tomorrow so see everyone back there for
that when we'll put the memory
visualization in and then we can move on
to working on the ground cover stuff I
just want to have the memory verse laced
in there so I can demonstrate the
difference when I change things like
those enemies trucks how much memory is
being used and so on that's kind of hard
to get a feel for that right now it's
just something that we'd like to be able
to look at that's it for today I hope
see everyone back here tomorrow till
then have fun programming I'll see
everyone the internet take it easy
everybody