like so alright hello everyone and
welcome to handmade Hero the show where
we code a complete game live on Twitch
no engines no libraries our goal is to
show the complete set of things that
happen when a game runs right down to
how pixels are rendered even without a
GPU we did our own renderer we've done
all our own stuff and today we're
actually starting because it seemed like
a good time to get this in there we're
sort of doing a quick run through things
to sort of pull stuff together a little
bit I wanted to start getting sound in
there and sound is again one of those
things like graphics and where a lot of
people just use a library or something
and don't think too much about it but
again I'm hand made here our point is to
be educational to show everything
involved so that people understand
exactly how all of these things work and
sound is actually one of those things
that's worth understanding because
there's a lot of stuff you can do when
you understand it that you might not be
able to do if you just kind of use a
library and don't really know what's
going on so what we'd like to do now is
get a little bit further into that so to
that end I have updated the witness ask
them sources the witness I'm talking
about the witness a lot in the pre
stream I'm I've got witness on the brain
we've updated the handmade hero our
asset pack and you can see there's now a
test3 directory in there so it's just
it's got all the test directories but
before there was just test in test2 and
now there's a test3 I'm going to go
ahead and copy that test three out into
here so that now we've got it and really
there's nothing particularly interesting
about this it's just a bunch of wav
files that I had which I had made myself
so I know that they are not copyrighted
by anything so they can be included in
here for free and freely copied which is
what I wanted so here they are and what
I what I wanted to do today was I wanted
to get us loading WAV files so that we
could have something to play back so
that we could a finish up our asset
loading system because our asset loading
system is dealing with bitmaps now but
it's not doing with WAV files so we kind
of needed to push that out a little
further but in order to have it deal
with WAV files we are going to need to
you have it some idea of what you wave
files even our look we got to implement
that because we didn't have that yet and
then also we're gonna want to make our
own sound mixer and stuff and so we kind
of need as a first step to any of that
the ability to just load some kind of
wave data in to work with and so what I
chose for that is WAV files just because
they're easy to produce just about
anywhere and they are fairly
straightforward to work with so they're
not quite as easy to read as being piece
but they're pretty easy and so I'm gonna
go ahead and show you how that worked we
got started a little bit yesterday and
by the way it's day 138 so if you've
pre-ordered the source code at home you
want to unpack day 137 source code
that's what I'm working with now
but anyway so if I go in here to our
asset loader and I take a look at the
load wave right there it is somebody was
saying that I did a miss type in here I
don't remember which one it was they
were saying that I was as I was making
the the header I got one of the things
wrong perhaps in the format chunk I
think but I'm not sure which one it was
valid bits for samples so it's two - two
- two - two - yes so block a line is two
and I had it as four so thank you for
catching that saves a little bit of
debugging work here but yeah so what we
did yesterday is we just kind of started
with the basis we really didn't do
anything all we did was start to copy in
the the sort of structure of a wave file
in here and so I'm gonna go ahead and
kind of pull this stuff up a little bit
into the same location as we define our
bitmap stuff so that it can be inside
the same pragma pack there because again
we want to make sure that these are
pragma pack 1 so if the compiler doesn't
insert any additional spacing so for
example if you take a look in here right
these you in 16 they would actually get
padded out probably to thirty twos at
some point well in this case they
probably wouldn't because they're packed
okay so actually to be honest this this
probably wouldn't changed but just in
case I want to make sure that it
wouldn't so I'm gonna go ahead and put
that in the private pack so
compiler doesn't fuss around with it at
all so anyway what I'd like to do now is
I'd like to go ahead and find a way to
test this stuff and so what I'm going to
do is I'm just going to insert so that
we can start testing and not have to
worry about running the game and doing
anything in particular
in right when we actually do our update
and render call right at the beginning
of that I'm just going to make it do a
debug load wave right there right so I'm
just gonna have it do a loaded sound
like so and I'm gonna have it load some
sound out of here
say bloop zero zero or something like
this so bloop zero zero that Wow and
that way I can set a breakpoint and have
it just kind of you know start right out
at the code that we're trying to test so
that we can you know be more efficient
about the testing since presumably we're
gonna have to debug some stuff and test
some stuff right so what I'd like to do
is I'd like to go ahead and step in to
break that to step into that our well
looks like I named I think debug load
wave my bad
let's try that again build I wonder if
that should actually be the name debug
load sound what did I actually call the
other one what did I call debug load BMP
was it BMP it is BMP all right so debug
load wave is correct debug load lab so
as I run this let's just make sure we
get the whole file first we do and let's
take a look at that header and see if
we're actually getting something that we
think makes some sense so here is our
display here that size parameter looks
in theoretically correct and let's take
a look and see if the Rif ID makes sense
right what's our know what that's why is
it inserting two of those that's really
annoying when did it start doing that
did you see that when I hit one of those
it inserts two of them that's awful whoo
who thought that was a good idea I don't
know what that is but I wish it would
stop anyway you can see we have our iff
here
and these are the character codes and
hey there they are 42 49 46 46 so it
looks like it does go in little-endian
order like we surmise that it would so
our macro is probably fine too and then
we've got that wave ID there I believe
that's just what is it W a V I don't
think it's e I don't think it's e it
might just be wave I forget what we said
that it actually was in the actual
loader here I don't know it is WAV e so
yeah so 5741 5645 and so that is exactly
what we would expected the header to
have so that all looks good so our
assertion should work they do so now we
have to do is actually get down to the
business of parsing the actual file
obviously which is something that we
want to be able to do so I'm gonna jump
over here to that that function and I'm
just gonna stop start implementing it
now like I was saying on the other
stream essentially what happens here is
you've you've got these chunks in the
file and those chunks say how big they
are and so what we want to be able to do
is we want to be able to have like
convenient perhaps a little cursor that
we can kind of move around that will
just help us with the bookkeeping of
reading through the file so what I'm
gonna do is I'm gonna have something
like a RIF iterator and remember these
are with file format is the file format
that we're talking about and what I want
to do there is I want to have a pointer
to some bits which is just where we
currently are in the file and then I
also want to have something that I guess
that lets me know what my current RIF
chunk actually is and you can see that
we've got these these sort of wave chunk
things here so I kind of want to have
whatever the current chunk is as well if
that makes sense
so let's start off with that I'm gonna
go ahead and say once we parse that
I'm gonna say that we have our riff
iterator and tears are our riff or I
definitely let's call it hitter right
and the inner is going to assume that I
guess we could do parse chunk at
something like that and when I do parse
chunk at I'm going to say I want you to
start at header plus 1 which is just
whatever's right after the header and
and I want you to assume that that is
the chunk that we're gonna start working
on ok so again what I'm doing here is
just making a little utility that I hope
will be useful in making it easy to read
this this thing right so I'd have
something like that in fact you know
I'll just go ahead and and read they
used to do the usage code first like I
normally say so if we do this something
like this I'd probably want to write a
for loop say you know parse the chunk
there and then I'd want to do something
like is valid you know and then I'd want
to do I guess just get to the next chunk
write it or equals the next chunk
something like that something that just
moves through those chunks like so and
so this would just be each chunk would
kind of be a thing right then we could
switch on whatever the chunk actually
had is it's tight right so I could do
something like like this switch on get
type and then I could have the different
types in here that I wanted to check
right so if I had something like a
format chunk I could get that and I
think let's just take a quick scan
through the file format here and see
what the other chunks are that we need
mmm a fact chunk I don't think we care
about because we're not going to read
compress for your files we're just
reading regular WAV files at the moment
the data chunk looks like what we want
for the sample data which we want which
we definitely want to be able to read
right so let's go ahead and and and get
that that's dat a lowercase so that
would be in here
Eata and so we'd have that one and what
else we have here
PCM data is is inside here WAV format
the cheque size pad bytes so that these
are just examples these are not
additional chunks yeah so I think that
may be it that really may be all there
is that we actually care about so all we
have to read is we have to read a format
chunk which will tell us what we're
looking at and then a data chunk which
will actually have the the actual sound
information in it and so I think that's
really all we would need to do so maybe
we'll just go ahead and get that going
here so if we have that then what I want
to do here is say get me the actual data
for this this format shop as one of
these right so I could do something like
WAV format FM t equals get you know get
chunk data and I'll just say that I want
a WAV format out of that iterator like
so and then when I have the data chunk
here same thing although I guess the
data chunk itself doesn't really have
anything in it other than just the bits
right and so what I want to do there is
is probably something like this data or
sample data equals get chunk data like
so write something like this yeah yeah
so we'll go a little bit further with
this in a second but that looks like
roughly what I want and so then we'd
save the sample data out here right so
there's our sample data ok so let's take
a look at what's going on there so for
our first chunk out what we want to do
is create one of these little riff
iterators right that we can use and what
it's going to do is assume that it's
pointing
at an actual one of you know at
something useful here like so wait chunk
and that's really all it needs to do for
now and then we can return that result
and I guess there's one of the things
that I do need to do which is it needs
to know when it would be out of space if
that makes sense so it also would need
and here are some it would need to use
the size of this thing to know you know
when it runs out of room if that makes
sense so we'll take a look at that in a
second as well so then we've got a next
chunk which is something that would
advance one chunk forward so here's riff
iterator next chunk likes em off there's
our input iterator and so what I want to
do there is I want to say okay the app
pointer at this point now is going to
advance by whatever the chunk size was
right it's gonna go ahead and move
forward by that now what I don't know is
if the size includes the header it looks
like it doesn't to me it looks like the
size is like how much is is like after
right is after the header part we see if
anyone says that specifically I don't
know if they do or not but like for
example it says chunk size is 16
potentially and so if the chunk size was
16 that means you could only have 8 that
means that would be the biggest it could
possibly be at 16 because if you had
here's 8 and here is 8 I get actually
it's it's less than that you would only
you would only have that much right so I
think the chunk size is only is
non-inclusive of that wave chunk header
so what I want to do here is say that
we're gonna advance and this is just a
kind of guess but that seems like dead
reckoning what what that would be so I
want to go ahead and do it that way
right something like that
I think that looks good I'll put in a
stop parameter there so we do parse
chunk out I'm gonna do something like
this right so now we have two pointers
one that's where we're at one where we
want to stop then we can go ahead and do
our next chunk stuff and then I'll just
do a thing here where the is valid on
the iterator right to know whether or
not the iterator is valid or not
what did I do I forgot some kind of
something here Mighty Max is not
indenting why is it indenting their
compiler tell me there it is let's see
oops sighs oh yeah so in here in my is
valid right all I'm gonna do is I'm
going to take this riff iterator and I'm
just gonna see whether or not the app is
underneath is lower than the stopping
point right so the result is just gonna
be if the inner at is less than the
inner stop and if it is then we're all
good
if it's not then well we're not so good
right so that'll let us either iterate
through these guys and that means that
when I do parse chunk at I also have to
do you know something like say you know
something like this where I'm gonna go
ahead and say whatever the the data was
where I was starting we're gonna go
however big the header says after that
right and I again I don't know if that's
inclusive or not so in other words I
don't know whether it should be header
plus 1 or just header here + Enter sighs
that's something that I couldn't quite
see in the docs but we'll be able to
figure it out when we actually step
through it and then we'll be fine all
right so then we've got a little thing
here and I guess now that I look at it
because we only use one of these I was
gonna do a little type safety thing here
but we really don't need to because it
turns out that we really don't ever call
this in any particular way so anyway
what we want to do here is just say that
get chunk data is something that gives
back whatever the contents of the chunk
was right oops again with that annoying
insert there so what I want to do is say
if
you asked me on an iterator what the
chunk data is also I suppose these
should all be in line they're tiny
little they're really just utilities
they don't do anything so they should
probably be inlined completely so get
chunk data is going to go ahead and
return that app pointer
plus the just a header part right so
it's going to be whatever is after the
header is presumably the actual data
that the chunk contains right that's the
specification all right so get type is
going to give us back some kind of a um
32 that says what the type is now the
wave chunk itself I don't remember how
this actually worked let's take a look
here it looks like the wave chunk has an
ID in a size so what we want to do there
is we want to return that ID right so we
want to be able to say that the result
here is the iterator chunk ID right and
then we can return that and that should
tell us what it is all right so let's
take a look at how we did in terms of
our first pass and and shake try to
shake the bugs out a little bit here so
we go ahead and read that in and then
we're gonna we're going to start to
parse this file so we we produce an
iterator here and let's see what the
iterator says it's got a chunk the chunk
ID is is this right here I don't
actually know what our various chunk IDs
actually are but I suppose you know what
I could do is something like this I
could just do a Cara star and I could do
chunk
ID like oops Peter chunk ID right
there we go and so if we take a look at
this that will show us what the ID
actually is right and of course it's
where we're at as well so I guess I
could have just used that now that I
think about it points to the first thing
but this is a little more specific so at
least we know so the first one there is
that format chunk so presumably we want
to go ahead and go into this branch we
actually do get that format chunk out so
let's see if we can view it of course we
can't because visual studio you know in
their relentless upgrading to make
things slower and less useful made it so
that when you get to the closing brace
of something you can't actually view any
of its variables which is fantastic
I think everyone deserves a big round of
applause for that good job guys let's go
ahead and insert something so they can
actually read it there we go so now
we're here in fmt let's see what
everything says so here is our oops I
did not mean to do that
here is our spec for this wave 48
kilohertz which is our audio sample rate
we have two channels so it's stereo
which actually I didn't know it was I
didn't mean to make a stereo wave I
guess it is a stereo wave we've got a
format tag here which is gonna tell us
which format it is hopefully that's PCM
because that's the only thing that we're
planning on reading but I believe I I
didn't compress any of these I'll
double-check here there was they had
them listed somewhere so yeah that's PCM
which is good
I believe that stands for pulse code
modulation which is the standard
uncompressed audio file format we could
talk about that in a second but what
else what else do we have here
block Ally we don't care about just
saying it's aligned to four bytes which
is fine
we've got bits per sample at 16 which is
what we want and then we've just got
some some other stuff that we really
just don't care about it all I don't
think most of this stuff just shouldn't
shouldn't matter too much to us I don't
know what CV size actually develops for
sample I don't know if we care about
that stuff very much but anyway so the
format chunk looks good let's go through
here move to the next chunk we have
another format chunk that doesn't seem
right
what did I do wrong I did something
wrong unless we have to format chunks
which just does not seem right yeah that
seems busted what happened oh I know
what happened I know what happened well
and you know what we can fix this we
should probably fix this right this this
chunk thing here is a redundant pointer
and of course I didn't update it when I
actually went to move so I wonder if we
should just get rid of that right just
get rid of that entirely since at is the
chunk header you know it we should
probably just do something like this
where we are just constantly looking at
it this way since that's you know the
majority of what we actually needed to
do right that seems like a good idea to
me so I'm gonna I'm gonna go ahead and
say that for now and that will prevent
us from doing something stupid like we
did so there we go all right so let's go
to the next type the next one's the data
chunk which is where we get the sound
samples from theirs it looks like
there's some others in there but just
one other one and we didn't read it it
was not a type we understood and that's
fine maybe let's go through there and
just see what the type actually was just
for our own edification there's the data
chunk and so now in here let's take a
look and see what that that chunk
actually is at it looks like zero so
that's a little bit odd I wonder why
we're at a zero chunk does that mean
that we oh we're mmm well we're four
bytes from the end is there some kind of
a specification that says that the file
ends with zeros or something like this I
wonder
I wonder I just want to make sure we
don't have a bug right if that's what's
supposed to be there then that's totally
fine but just just don't want to I just
don't want to have any kind of a an
error there let's see if I'll format
right there are three variants of the
chunk right the obsolete formats blah
blah blah this doesn't really tell us
much about that I suppose we could take
a look at one of these things well or
maybe not take a look at this I guess
let's see what's supposed to happen we
got a big old document going on here
resource interchange file format yeah
yeah let's see I registered chunk types
basic notation escape sequences blah
blah blah blah blah storage strings we
don't care about any of this stuff
country code structural overview the C
talked chunk we don't care about this
stuff at all we just want to know really
I just want to know what the end of the
file should look like right I just want
to kind of know if they've got anything
that says specifically what should
happen they're basically in a closed
chunk a for CCS representative that's
right yes I understand that
yep I get that a reform is a chunk with
a RIF chunk ID term also refers to a
file format that files with framework
that's all good let's see seek a size
firm type
yeah listen man attracts listen I was
possibly a required order for the chunks
defining you're registering them we
don't care about that yeah so I don't
see anything here that really talks
about that the other part of it which is
unfortunate because I guess I don't know
hmm
Hey look they said in Electronic Arts
iff file which is what I was mentioning
before let's see a counter part a little
bit label yeah star this ticket is a
word aligned with respect to the start
of the riff file if the chunk size is an
odd number of bytes a pad byte with a
zero value is written after ck data so
we're not really obeying that which is
not good right so we probably should do
that
but that wouldn't really explain what
we're seeing either that's like not
sufficient right but you can see there
we're not actually obeying that
basically what it's saying is if the
chunk size right if the chunk size would
have been odd there then we have to you
know Pat it out so you know something
like you know size equals chunk size
like so and then we need to do if sighs
you know I guess and one we rounded up
right or we could we could even do it
something like this right just to round
that size out and then we go ahead and
advance by that instead that would be
how we would be that that element of the
specification but again that doesn't
really answer our question at least it
doesn't answer my question
which is just why we were seeing what we
were seeing there I suppose
what it could be is if the header
if I'm not correctly interpreting what
that header size includes so what I what
I might do here's here's what I might
propose is happening so this chunk size
here in the Rif thing right
it does say 4 + n so maybe what they
mean is this is not included and we we
were including it right and so if we
wanted to if that was the assumption
that that would make sense that's
probably what happened right so what we
would want to do there is say okay the
actual size of this thing in terms of
stopping is going to be the header size
minus 4 because we need to take out that
that wave part that we skipped right
that seems like maybe maybe the smarter
way to go about it so let's see let's
see now if that makes things a little
cleaner so we'll jump in here there's
our format chunk there's our data chunk
and there's no other chunks so hey we
don't even have to deal with we don't
even have to really skip any chunks
because it turns out that I saved these
out of a program called goldwave it
turns out that we don't actually have
any other chunks other than the ones we
specifically wanted okay so when we load
this in here what I want to do is I want
to now remember the actual salient data
the the data that we actually wanted to
get right and so what I'm going to do is
I'm going to try to find specifically
what what the data is that we're looking
for
I want to assert any of the stuff that
you know we're just expecting these to
be the correct format obviously so
something like the WM Dobie before I tag
we want to assert it's PCM right we want
the the channel count we want the
channel count to either be 1 or 2 we
want the samples to per second to always
be our preferred samples for a second
and then we also want
I guess the we don't care about the
block aligned I guess
think about it bits per sample left to
look at see maybe we do we want the bits
per sample to always be 16 right and I
don't know what channel mask actually
means speak your position math I don't
think we care about that
now we don't care about sub format so
what is any block a line data block size
in bytes like what does that mean
is there some documentation for what M
block a line actually means here we go
the first part of the format chunk
reduce noise PCM data after boosting day
at the format chunk in the header
declares the number of bits per sample
we got that the original documentation
specified that the number of bits per
sample to be rounded up to the next
multiple of 8 bits this rounded values a
container size this information is
redundant in the container for each
sample can also be determined from the
block size divided by the number of
channels ok this redundancy has been
appropriated to define new formats for
example Cool Edit use the four which
declares the sample size of 24 bits the
other looking at size of 4 bytes
determine from the block size and of our
channels with this combination huh ok
well alright so I guess in block a line
divided by a number of channels tells us
how many bits per sample it actually is
is the idea or how many bytes per sample
I should say so I guess we want to
basically say that that that end block
aligned has to be either 2 or 4 right
we basically want it to be however many
channels there are we want and block the
line to be the number of channels times
2 because we're saying it's got to be 16
bit right so we essentially want to to
guarantee that we have 16 bits per
channel because that's the only thing
that we're going to support so we
distort that we have all of those things
to be true
right and then really the only
information that I think we need here is
the number of channels so I'm gonna have
a channel count out here right and I'm
gonna set that to 0 and here I'm going
to say the channel count equals and
channels like so I don't know that we
care about any of these other things
then
I don't think we need to know anything
else we just need that channel count
because we're only supporting everything
else this way then when we do the wave
chunk ID data there what I'm going to do
is I'm going to I'm going to go ahead
and and grab out the actual wave data so
the sample data I think just is just
straight ahead in the actual I don't
think the PCM does it actually does the
PCM form and actually have anything else
in it I don't think it does
I think the PCM format literally is just
a size and then the data yeah so so this
is literally the data that we actually
want and so there's our sampled data and
so then we actually have everything that
we need at the end of that to know and
so what I'm going to do is I'm going to
say assert right that the channel count
and the sample data are both valid so we
have an actual valid file and now I want
to actually make that loaded sound thing
right I wanted to make the load sound
actually work so let's go ahead in here
and say all right we've got loaded sound
where is that what we're returning our
result there it is we've got our result
we need to know what the sample count is
and we need to know where the memory is
the memory is just the sample data right
but I may want to do something with this
first
[Music]
in fact I strongly suggest that I am I
think what I would rather do is
something like this let's just say that
our samples or you know 16-bit samples
or something like that this is the way
it's working well you know what now to
say they're voids and what I want to do
is I want to introduce the concept that
the loaded sound can have one or two
channels so I'm gonna say that we have a
channel counting here as well as a
sample count and so you can you can
actually have a stereo or announcer or
mono sound I think we might just go
ahead and support both of those for now
like because music will probably want to
come in stereo and sound effects will
probably want to come in mono at the end
of the day mm-hmm and that would also
let us extend it to like Dolby fot you
know if we wanted to have more channels
in there it's obvious how it would
happen
rather than just having no I you know no
plan for what we would do to solve that
problem right so what I want to do here
is I want to actually set this stuff up
correctly then because we're gonna have
to do a sort of a tedious whistling
operation I guess the other thing I'd
like to know is how do I determine the
sample count - any weird rounding that
they may have done does this stuff
saying here how that would work in some
way bits per sample or do am I just
supposed to divide to figure it out like
does the format chunk CB size size the
extension that doesn't help us valid
bits block size data rates sampling
rates so you know it looks to me like we
just have to divide to figure out what
that sample - it is so it looks to me
like the sample count right is going to
be the channel count whatever the
channel count actually is right it's
going to be the channel count times size
of unit 16 like so right I guess we
should probably also use that up here
that's what the sample counts going to
be it's going to be the channel count
size that you're in steam divided by
however big the sample data was right so
we need to also keep that sample data
size in there right so I'm gonna go
ahead and get that get chunk data size
as well like that and in here when we do
get chunk data I'm just gonna do another
one here which is get chunk size
actually I guess that would be this good
chunk size and that is not inclusive of
the header correct because we were yet
it's not inclusive of the header so
that's good all right so what we want to
do here is we want to go ahead and say
that we've got that that chunk size
coming back so we can get it let's see
get chunk data size I guess is what I
said J design so if we get chunk data
size now we have the sample data size as
well sample data size and now we can
actually go ahead and do this
computation and figure out what our
sample count is we then are going to
need
to create arrays for our sample data and
if we only have one channel right
so if our channel count equals one we
don't have very much work to do if our
channel count equals two we do invalid
channel count and WAV file right so if
the channel count is one this is really
easy right results channel count equals
channel count always good the samples
are going to point to reasonable things
here right the samples are going to
point to the sample data in one case and
0 and the other right because all the
samples are in an order just the way we
would want them to be stored but if it's
if the sample count equals 2 I'm sorry
the channel count equals 2 they're going
to be interleaved like left right left
right left right left right but we don't
actually want that probably when we're
dealing with them we want to be able to
deal with each channel individually so
what I'd rather do is unintel so in
order to do that that's I don't know
that there's a lot of ways to interleave
to unintel I have to think about that
gosh can you do a none interleave in
place hmmm so let me talk about exactly
what has to happen here I don't know
that I have I don't think I have
anything clever up my sleeve for this
maybe somebody else out there does but I
don't so here we are at day 138 and
here's the problem that we're talking
about what we would like to have is we
would like to have two pointers right
this is channel 0 this is channel 1
samples and what I'd like to see right I
would like to see
my sample is looking like this left zero
left 1 left 2 left three left four and
then you know the same thing over here
right zero right one right two right
three right four
right that's what I would like to see
and so the problem is right now what we
actually have is something that looks
like this doo doo doo doo we've got some
that looks like L 0 R 0 L 1 R 1 l 2 and
so on right now the problem is this L 0
and L 1 right if I wanted to D
interleave just the left channel it
wouldn't be very difficult because all I
do you just go through and you know copy
this L 1 into here and then I'd copy
this L 2 back into here right that's not
particularly difficult but if I want to
like Unsworth all these things in place
I'm not sure how I would actually do
that like okay you know I would I guess
swap those two and then move this I
don't I don't know how you would do that
probably would take more than one pass
over the buffer I don't know it just
seems ugly like how am I going to do
that in place because what I want to do
is sort it all so basically you know at
the end this buffer basically is at the
end of this buffer right so I can just
point to here for my for my second
channel so I kind of need to migrate all
the ours out there while migrating the L
once in while compacting the L ones in
and I don't really see
[Music]
a smart way to do that right if if I
swap if I do the swaps that's just gonna
do weird stuff I would think I don't
know maybe it doesn't so let's see what
actually happens I'm just gonna see what
happens here because I don't super
understand it let's say this is the
buffer right and let's say I've got L 0
R 0 L 1 R 1 L 2 R 2 L 3 R 3 L 4 R for
like this
so what we're at what would happen if
all I did was just winning a straight-up
swapped right so I come in here and I
swap these two right so now I have L 1 R
0 right then I come here and I need to
swap these two so I would have L 2 and
our zeroes out here right then I would
come here and I would swap this one with
this one
so this would become L 3 right and this
would become R 1 like so then I would
come to here and I would swap what's
this this is l2 so so it's already been
swapped with r0 and it needs to have l3
actually in it right so it needs to swap
with the one before it if that makes
sense
so this one wait no this says l2 l3 this
one is R 0 and R 0 needs to swap with l4
right it's already placed the rest of
them right so we need to stop with l4 so
here's our 0 r 0 goes out there l4 comes
in here right l4 so what does this end
up looking like at the end of the day
it's R 2 R 1 R 3 R 0 R for right which
is pretty random and what is there some
kind of magic to that ordering that
would allow me to then on the Swizzle it
you'd have to swap this here right so
this would go here this would go here
that would stay where it was and that
would stay where it was so you have to
swap 0 &amp; 2
I'm sorry you have to swap is that right
are two needs to go here are three needs
to go here so it's like a ring swap
right are two would go here are three
would go here and are zero would come
back to the beginning so yeah I mean
gosh that doesn't seem very
straightforward the initial swaps going
through here seem okay like that's that
would just work I guess you'd just step
through and you just grab and you'd swap
into place whatever was there beforehand
you'd just keep doing the swapping but
just sorting out those are samples at
the end I'm not sure if there's a
straightforward way to do it
can anyone think of one it'd be
interesting to see a longer series here
right it'd be interesting to see a
longer series of what this looks like
maybe we should just write it and see
because maybe that's maybe that's
interesting right maybe I'll do exactly
that so yeah so if we were to do it this
way I'm also gonna I guess say that the
sample data is gonna be you in 16 since
that's what we're working on right so
sample data at 16 okay so in here we've
got the the right stuff that's all good
for getting that sample data and and
then in here what we need we need to do
is we'd say the sample data plus and
then we'd have half the total size right
so something like this those would be
the two buffers and what we would then
have to do is we'd have to go through
and do this this Schwing like I say so
we have to do something that basically
step through all the samples so
have our sample index right we want to
step through the sample count and for
each one of these guys right we want to
take basically that that sample data
right the sample data at the current
sample index right and so we're trying
to put ELLs in place right so we have l0
l1 l2 l3 and so on right so the location
of the one that we want this is the one
we want so this is the source right the
location of the one we want is actually
going to be at sample data times 2 right
because it's it's going by twos in in
the buffer like it's l0 are zero
we didn't want then l1 we want right so
grabbing that out we then want to put
that into the current location right
like so but first we need to save out
our information into that location right
so we're doing the swap like this makes
sense so yeah so that would do that that
would do this the swap and that would
put our left channel in you know into
the proper format right but it wouldn't
actually do anything else what is this
saying sample index or boots set to be
115 okay so if I if I do that right now
when I load any kind of WAV file that's
it's doubled it should unsociable the
left channel properly but the right
channel is going to be total garbage
right so what I want to do is I just
want to take a look at what the right
channel actually ends up being right and
I guess for now I said I was going to
leave it as a void but I might change it
to a unit 16 just just for a second so
we can view it a little more easily so
what I'm going to do is I'm actually
going to spam in beforehand
I'm gonna spam in actually the like
specific a specific set of values if
that makes sense so what I'm going to do
is I'm going to say the sample data
right sample index is going to be equal
to the sample index always so on so
basically it's like I'm just writing in
0 0 1 1 two 2 three 3 four 4 five 5 six
6 so we can analyze it after and see
what we end up getting because I don't
actually know right I've never thought
about this problem before pretty much
ever all right
it just kind of interested me what can I
say
so let's take a look at that result
right here is our samples 0 which is un
16s right and I'm gonna just take a look
at the first 32 and you can see that
those are correct which is what we would
have expected right so the question is
what happens with that second channel
and I don't know
so there's oh well that's not
particularly useful why are they all
zeroes did we mess something up I feel
like what I feel like I messed something
up there that should not have been the
case right how did that happen
so we go through the sample sample data
sample data plus sample data size over -
ah that is the problem this should this
is actually just should just be the
sample count right like so yeah my bad
my bad
all right let's try that one more time
so yeah quite the interesting spread
there so there again is after we do our
Swizzle there is the you know the left
channel and here is the right channel I
don't know what you make of that that's
just crazy so it's 97 98 99 it's very
interesting that so those go up in order
these also go up in order and then these
don't seem to have oh every other one
that's like this and half of that so man
I mean just look at that just looking at
that I don't know it seems like figuring
out what the right way to do that Swiss
emplace would actually be fairly
complicated I mean if you just look at
look at how that's going right it's just
so bizarre
seven
yeah so I don't know so there's probably
like I'm guessing there is a smart way
to do this I just don't know what it is
so maybe we're just going to go ahead
and say that will bite some additional
memory or something like this or we
could just even just only load the left
the left channel for now something like
this you know we could just always say
that we only load one of the channels
right so we could just say to do Casey
load right channels and we could just
say result channel count equals one
right so I guess to be completely honest
with you I don't really know where we
left things at the moment in terms of
sound playing we have game output sound
the moment is still being called and I
guess we actually are outputting
something here which is I guess this T
sign we don't actually have I could make
that though let's see game state T sign
game state T sign does that ever get
incremented + tab 32 wave period game
city sign 1032 all right so I guess we
would just put this back in right for
testing purposes I don't know what else
to do at the moment so I'm gonna go and
put that in just so we can see if our
sound output is still working first with
the sound what's with a sine wave before
we do anything else so here's our T sine
and I'll go ahead and
run that and see if we have any sound we
do all right so that's all good so if we
want to play an actual sound wave now
that's you know if we were gonna do game
output sound for something else I guess
what I could do is just say well let's
say we've got a loaded sound here called
test sound all right and I'm gonna go
into to the place where we loaded the
sound their load Wow and I'm gonna say
that game state test sound equals that
sound so when we come in here and was
that so I had that at the beginning so
that was actually loading the sound
every frame and apparently that was fine
that's kind of crazy anyway so I'm gonna
put that in here when we actually do
this this is just you know to test the
debug loading that'll go ahead and load
it into test sound and then what we can
do if we want to is we can have this
game app that sound thing actually do
something a little more useful
potentially I don't actually know why I
have a separate function called game
output sound but yeah whatever so if we
actually get rid of this I'm just gonna
say that that's not getting called
anymore if I actually just come in here
and put put this in here I'm gonna go
ahead and say we we're gonna output to
the sound buffer like so and the sample
value that we're gonna output is just
going to come from that debug sound that
we loaded right so I'm going to say that
the game state test sound what do we
call it samples I think we're gonna say
the samples zero that first channel I'm
going to grab the the sample index of
that and put it into the buffer now of
course we want the sound to continue
playing over time so I need some notion
of the global sample index right so I
want to do something like you and 32
sample index or test sample index like
this so what I want to do is say okay
you know it's actually going to be the
game state plus wherever we were in the
same
plus the sample index then at the end
we'll go ahead and advance that by
however many samples we actually retired
like so and then all I want to do in
here is say oh you know I I never want
you to play more than whatever the
sample count was obviously right so
whatever it's sample count was only only
play that many right so let's take a
look what did i do there game state test
sample index right mod test sound sample
counts missing you're right I am there
we go
or maybe not what did I do game state Oh
sample value that's what I wanted and so
that was actually correct sample out
whoops did I did I not copy the thing
that actually does figure that where
we're writing in the buffer sample out
there it is okay okay so let's see that
does not sound particularly good I'll
give you that
so let me actually go through and step
through here so this is going to be our
sample index or our test sound sample is
index it's going to be this guy right
like so and then our sample value I
guess the Q&amp;A doesn't quite begin now so
I wasn't quite ready yet let's go ahead
and save that I just want to go ahead
and step into this guy
okay
so let's see what we've got here what's
our test sound sample index it's zero
what's our sample value also zero so
we're gonna output Pat come through
again what's our test sample index right
and so on do we ever have any sample
values here before yeah that's good oh I
don't know why that's that's kind of not
what I meant to do it all there these
are supposed to be in 16s not UN 16s
yeah sound value is encoded as signed so
I don't know why I did that that's
probably half the battle right there but
let me just make sure this part works as
well what's the sample count supposedly
1066 so there's that that goes up so
that looks relatively correct actually
but I did not mean to make those the
human 16s that that was a mistake again
just guess it's been a while since I've
coded sound I just didn't think of it
for some reason so yes so you meant 16s
that was unintentional all of these
places that are using UN 16s they should
have been in 16s because that's actually
the way we're encoding that sound to be
sure so yeah that is more what we're
looking for all right
but I still haven't gotten anywhere
it just sounds like clicking to me right
and let's actually verify which one are
we loading again and actually remember
we're loading like bloop zero zero I
think so let's just see what that's
supposed to sound like let's see can we
hear that here we go
of course VLC also seems to have an
audio bug where it's clicking but you
can hear the at least the bloop part let
me try it with a different player that
maybe won't be quite so bad at actually
playing it okay
so let's figure out what we've done
wrong here we can go a little bit into
the QA I think won't hurt anything might
as well just get this up to a reasonable
state before we break so that tomorrow
we can start by talking about sound
because we'll actually have stuff loaded
and we can you know go over a little bit
more okay so here we go with the samples
right it's stereo out so we're writing
these guys and that's all fine and I
were just writing the same thing to the
left channel and the right channel
should be fine we're grabbing out of
test sound the out of the first sample
channel which is what we were expected
we're grabbing them in order and we're
just looping the buffer right so it
should just you know give us the sound
repeated over and over and over again
right so that looks you know that looks
relatively sane to me like I don't see
much in the way of nonsense going on
there so I want to go like double check
the loading code first as the first
thing we do because I'm a little I'm a
little more concerned about that at the
moment than I am about the playback code
but you know that that's just my that's
just my guess that's just my hunch if
you will so okay so if we come in here
what I want to do is I want to take a
look at that sample data I just want to
see what it kind of looks like right
so I'm just looking at what those
samples are so that fat looks like
plausible sound data to me right like I
could I could believe that
was plausible sound data to some degree
that that seems that that seems with
within reason anyway right
let's take a look at it a little further
down the road right so that again seems
seems pretty plausible you can kind of
see well that does oscillate rather
quickly but yeah yeah I mean it could be
true it is just rather quickly
offsetting so these are packed together
right so these are stereo samples so
these are samples that follow each other
negative 21 negative 11 negative 24
forty to sixty four writes negative 60
they just they seem a little odd to me
and I'm wondering they seem just a
little bit odd let me go back and
double-check that we did not miss
something about the format let's take a
look at what the PCM data actually says
here let's see non PCM data we want PCM
data channel interleaved M byte samples
right and bits per sample eight times M
so I feel like that we are interpreting
it correctly are we not I guess there's
that Swizzle miss to it I wonder if any
of these are not dual channel so we
would know whether or not we would have
we would have a we could test whether
it's just our Swizzle code that's wrong
right but yeah but this is before we
fizzled it so let's double check and
make sure that the Swizzle is operating
as we would expect I mean I think we
checked it pretty well with the zero one
two three four thing Oh
that's what it is we just never removed
the test code hahaha that's great yeah
well you know if you write a bunch of
garbage into the thing as part of the
test code don't be too surprised when it
doesn't sound like a sound when when you
oh that's funny that's that's funny okay
so we're still a little messed up there
but but but now we're loading and
playing the sound correctly I think
we're not hitting our frame rate so I
suppose I suspect if we if we go ahead
and build that's something that hits
frame right now will probably be fine
although we also have to we have to now
make sure we sink to the proper frame
rate instead of doing 60 Hertz so let's
take a look let's go let's go back to
that first of all and and and reset it
yeah so anyway let's see we've got
monitor refresh rate is 60 Hertz right
refresh rate so we want to go ahead and
set this guy in here really for now so
that should be better okay now we can go
to the Q&amp;A although maybe we'll change
it to playing piano music so that we
don't drive everyone completely nuts
with that sound I think I threw in
something from the ad-lib library in
here where is it data test three music
underscore test music underscore test
all right so so let's let's try that
there we go
okay so now it'll just kind of play
something that's that's a little more
innocuous and that'll be fine all right
okay so now we can actually go to the QA
oops I double Q&amp;A there and and that's
good because now we're in a good
position for tomorrow I can just talk
about sound we've got some sound loading
so I can talk about it and we can
introduce like how we'll do the mixing
and that sort of stuff so that that's
good I glad we got to that point today
so yeah
robot Java Dino says you could try on
interleaving the channels in place like
this and he he sent a link address let
me take a look and see what that link
address actually is let's see
[Music]
swap Arzu are too thin swap oh so you're
saying like inside outside swap so go
from the go from the beginning and the
end inside does that work
did you actually see if that worked
maybe it does does that work for long
sequences I guess it's the only thing I
don't know sudonym 73 I feel like that I
don't know if that works for long
sequences robot rocket now that's my
only concern
soon as ac3 says probably the second
easiest way to do interleave is multi
pass swap R 0 R 1 R 0 l1 r2 l3 l4 l5
then do the same with two sample blocks
for sample blocks etc easiest way is to
D interleaved directly into mix output
buffer yeah we don't really want to do
that because we can just do the the D
interleave at construction time so our
art pack will just have the D entry
leave already done why do you need to
unintel Eve the sound when you play it
you still have to read both left and
right values the reason is because we
don't process the values the same way
and we're going to want to be wide we're
going to want to be Cindy
abner Cumbre people are asking about the
benefits of extra and see what issues
does it address well it addresses a
bunch of things and a partial list of
them would be first of all it prevents
the names from getting mangled so you
know normally when you link it mangles
the names for C++ so that you can have
operator overloading work properly with
linkers that don't know about it right
and that it goes for dynamic linkage too
so if you do a DLL export right like we
have a DLL exported thing right our
entry point to our game is exported as
part of the DLL in order to do that
export the name would have been mangled
in the DLL import table if we had enough
extra and seat it right so there's that
the next thing is it implies a calling
convention so on 64-bit X 60 X 64 on
Windows there is only one column
convention really it's standard call and
there's ways to maybe force other things
like with compiler stuff but in general
as standard calls used everywhere that's
not true on 32-bit on 32-bit there's
multiple Kallang conventions
there's Pascal and there c style and so
on and extra and C lets you know that
it's a C deckle which is this Pacific
call calling convention as well right
it's the calling convention that allows
VAR args if that makes sense
so you know there's there's a bunch of
things like that that happened and so
when you're trying to do
interoperability stuff that's when you
have to use extra and see if you're just
compiling within your own code and you
don't need to like if then linking is
not an issue typically extra and C is
not really necessary like there aren't a
lot of uses for it when you're just
talking about your own code then it just
typically doesn't matter
constantinople Casey can you please
explain chunk size plus one and negative
one
yes so let me show you what it does
because it's pretty easy to understand
if you if you see it Tappin rather than
me just sort of staying talking at you
why it happened so if you take a look at
this code okay if you switch to
compiling in a build where that code is
not completely inlined
and then look at this function so what
happens here right is you have a chunk
size and that size is some value now if
you consider what this looks like in
binary right you can imagine that I've
got my bits right here's the one bit the
two bit the for a bit the 8 bit the
16-bit 32-bit and so on right if this
bit is set the number is odd right
because all of these other values are
even and a sum any sum of even numbers
is going to be even right so no matter
what the rest of the bits are it doesn't
matter all I need to know is this bit
will tell me if it's odd or not right
and what the spec said when we were
reading the spec is it said that chunk
sizes are always padded if they are odd
so if the chunk size was say 15 it would
actually insert one blank byte at the
end of the chunk before the next chunk
to make sure that it rounds out to an
even number of bytes so what I wanted to
do was I wanted to make sure that this
bite was was clear I wanted to do that
rounding so if I had 15 I want it to
round to 16 right so one way I could do
that is I could just clear this bit I
could and the bit and knock it out right
and what would I hand it with well I
would end it with not one because not
one
is all the other bits set but not this
one so if I ended them I would know I
would clear this one right and that
would get rid of the bottom bit but the
problem is now my size is too small
right if I have 15 right that would take
me to 14 so yes I made the number even
but I've made it too small it needs to
be rounded up not rounded down so the
easiest way to make sure that you do the
rounding up is to first add one to the
number right because if there was
already a one in here then adding one to
the number right will cause it to carry
and round up to the next value if it was
15 it will round up to 16 right and
clear the bit for you automatically
right if on the other hand this bit was
already 0 so it was already 16 adding 1
will merely bring it to the next odd
number so then I can and and clear out
the bit knowing that if the bit was set
was one that I added so a number plus
one right andddd oops ANDed with
negative one is just the same alignment
pattern that we've been using all along
but for for aligning two even numbers
like remember we did stuff like plus 15
and not 15 to align to 16 byte
boundaries so it's just that same
pattern again and you can see it work
here right let's say in fact let me let
me just make it a little even more
explicit so I can when I walk through it
it's really clear right let's go so
let's go ahead and do first the first
step and then the second step right
let's do it like that
and so if I go in here now and I step
into it right you can see what happens
so the chunk size is 16 we first add 1
to it to make it 17 and then we clear
out the bottom bit which brings it back
to 16 right now if instead of doing that
right if instead the size had actually
been 17 right okay now what you can see
happen is when I add 1
to it I rounded up to 18 the bottom bits
already cleared so this function this
step will have no effect right so
whether it was even or odd he always
does the proper up rounding when you
write it that way and so that is just a
general pattern for doing rounding to a
power of two any even power of two
because of the way binary works you can
do rounding to Indian power of two by
just adding one you could think of it
this way it's really adding the thing
you want to align to minus one so just
enough that you would bump it to the
next one if you were anywhere in that
range and then clearing all that
clearing all the other bits right so
it's really that it's really like the
number you want to align to minus 1 and
then ANDed with not the number you want
align to minus 1 and so that works with
any with any power too
popcorn Oh 9o x9e
why did they put in that order and not
just bunch it up so he's saying why are
they interleaved and not flat the reason
is probably because that's the way sound
cards used to take the data usually I
think that's how it used to be sort of
sent down the stream nowadays it doesn't
make any sense to do it that way because
really and I think we'll probably see
this later I would expect but all of
your processing happens on a variable
number of channels usually so you don't
want to have interleaving or you end up
having to do a ton of extra work usually
that you don't want to actually have to
do in order to support more flexible
like my two channel output or five
channel output or whatever right but
yeah so nowadays doesn't make as much
sense but
now our moto if you think of your
implement or leave data as an N by 2
matrix then transposition can be viewed
as interleaving here is an in-place way
to do it let's see for each length
greater than one cycle see of the
permutation pick a starting address S&amp;C
let d equal the data at s let X go to
preserve s in the cycle while X is not
equal to s move data from X a successor
of s let x equals predecessor risk move
data from D to testers I'm gonna have to
read that that looks like I'm gonna have
to read a little more carefully RPG
Ignace I just wanna stop it and say
thank you so much what you're doing here
putting all this effort in time to
teaching us all this stuff is highly
appreciated sometimes seeing stuff like
this may feel normal and we don't stop
to think about how much time effort
energy teaching stuff like this takes so
I just wanted to thank you once again
and say that everything you do is like
they show you thank you you are very
welcome
it's wonderful to know that you were
enjoying it that makes doing it totally
worthwhile so thank you very much yeah
you know what I don't see any more
questions right now so I want to go and
address a bug that somebody had posted
on the forums since we have a second in
the asset loader I think I when I was
cut and pasting I made a mistake
when I was doing stuff you can see in
here when we use the arena we make a sub
arena for our game assets and we don't
grab any of these out of there and you
know actually I don't know that that's
really a bug in any particular way but
you know we could consider making
everything go you know including these
arrays go in there I just I just don't
know if we want to do that
not so now that I look at it I think I
think that's probably what we meant to
do to be honest with you because this is
structural information and this is the
data information so I don't know I don't
know that we want to do what you were
suggesting actually sorry so that may
not actually be a bug I think that's
actually just probably what was supposed
to happen if that makes sense
why do you want to change the PCM data
in place instead of compacting it to
just the information you need in
allocating extra space well we it was
really more of a curiosity question
because the answer is we won't be doing
that at runtime anyway because the asset
processor will already have put it into
channel order for us so it's really
doesn't matter that's why I didn't
really care and I was like forget it
we'll just load just one channel it's
fine because the asset processor will
actually be the thing that takes care of
that for us so it was more of a
curiosity I was like mmm how would you
do this interleave and the answer
appears to be that you can do it but you
have to be a little more clever about it
than something simple like what I was
doing
that make sense all right running out of
questions it seems it does seem so it
does seem so all right okay folks let's
wrap it up let's wrap it up
or not there we go okay thank you very
much for joining me for another episode
of hand made here at some pleasure
coating with you as always we got our
sound loading working today which is
pretty cool and so I think tomorrow what
we'll do is you know we we will make a
decision about whether to go and do our
sound mixing code or whether we want to
go back and do the load asset stuff
whether we have enough information for
that right now to do the load asset
stuff instead now I don't know which one
of those will be so probably what we'll
do tomorrow is a little black board work
we'll think about which one we want to
do next and what makes sense whether we
have enough information do the load
asset stuff or whether we should do the
mixer first we'll make a judgement call
them we'll start in on one of those so I
hope to see you back here for that 5
p.m. Pacific Daylight Time right here on
Twitch it'll be good to see you all
until then if you want to follow along
at home with a source code and play
around with it yourself you can always
go to hand mate here at work and free
order the game it comes with a source
code you can download it every night
after I'm done I upload it if you want
to support the video series also we do
have a patreon page you can pledge to
it's very much appreciated we also have
a forum you can go to ask questions if
you have questions that outside the QA
it also has ports to Mac and Linux if
you need help running on a different
platform you can look there for
community members have contributed
information now how do that it also has
the anti episode guide maintained by the
community that's really pretty cool for
catching up on old episodes and we also
have a tweet bot which will tweet the
schedule at you so if you want to know
when the series is gonna be live and you
want to catch it that's the place to
check out for that so that's everything
I hope to see you back here tomorrow
until then take it easy everyone and
have fun coding