hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here on the show Rico to complete game
live on twitch no engine no libraries we
take care of absolutely everything here
it's it's the full shebang it's like
it's like from that time when the
universe was entirely collapsed into a
little tiny point and then it suddenly
exploded into being that is really what
you're witnessing here on handmade hero
now yesterday we saw something very
unusual happen it has never really
happened before on handmade hero and I
don't have an explanation for it
we covered lighting yesterday I just did
a brief introduction to lighting and not
really even talking very much about any
specific things but just kind of giving
the broad overview of how light works
and how you have to sort of start
thinking about it in terms of
programming graphics and somehow during
the QA we had literally dozens of
completely on topic very specific
lighting questions normally we you know
we do get some on topic specific
questions but a lot of times the
questions are just floods of off-topic
questions or things like this something
about lighting is obviously magical and
people are interested in it so I am
delighted to see that I do not know why
it is but I feel like we might as well
just run with that since we have to
implement some lighting so today I'd
like to build on what we talked about
yesterday I'd like to take a little bit
of time on the blackboard to explain to
you how normal map lighting works and
I'd like to go write it in our engine so
that we can see how it actually gets
coated because it's really not actually
that complicated at the end of the day
you can obviously go nuts with any
lighting thing by keeping trying to get
more and more accurate or more and more
fancy but just to get the basics of
normal map lighting in is actually
pretty straightforward so we should be
able to show how to do that in
relatively small amount of time so that
said I just remind everyone if you have
pre-ordered the game on handmade hero
org and you want to follow along with
today it's day 97 so unzip day 76 is
source code from the pre-order pack
there and that will put
right where I am today so we really
didn't do anything yesterday we were
only talking about lighting and
hopefully everyone is sort of on the
same page at least to a basic extent
with how lighting works and what I'd
like to talk about today is how we're
going to implement normal map lighting
what a normal map actually is in you
know sort of at the lowest level and how
we actually gonna do computations on it
all right and I'll try to keep this
hopefully if I'm if I'm concise here I
can keep this to thirty minutes so that
we'll have 30 minutes to actually code
it because it will take a while for us
to just get you know the flow proper
there's there's some structural code
that has to happen all right so we're on
day 97 yes we are so here we go this is
normal maps a very simple explanation of
how we're going to do the lighting here
all right so what I talked about
yesterday was I talked a lot about how
you have surfaces in the world and you
have light sources and the light sources
shine light on the surface and then if
you want to talk about what the light
does when it hits a particular point in
the surface you need to know the
direction that that light was coming
from and you also need to know the
direction that you are trying to observe
the light from okay and what I was sort
of working through yesterday when I when
I talked about all of these sorts of
effects of lighting and all that sort of
thing was I was saying well you know the
the way that a surface looks how it
appears like what kind of a surface does
it look shiny does it look dull does it
look wet does it look choppy and all
these sorts of things has to do with the
shape that the lighting ends up taking
when you look at for any given angle
that comes in
what sort of the brightnesses are that
are reflected out in all the other
directions right and what's implicit in
all of that and why normal maps are such
an important thing in graphics or even I
should say just the normal the concept
of a normal is so important in graphics
that the map part is just how we are
assigning them in a particular case with
the normal the reason that's so
important is all of that discussion that
whole discussion yesterday was all
assuming an implicit thing that
never mentioned because we're gonna get
to it today which is that you know the
orientation of the surface okay that
bounce that happens again just like I
think I used the description of a ball
bouncing off a wall you can only really
compute those brightness probabilities
those those ways that the brightest are
propagated if you actually know the
angle that the surface is at relative to
these things because again that function
that says you know how bright like if
this is the brightest that the surface
reflects from this angle if that's the
brightest and it gets duller here and
very dull here right that function that
we're trying to simulate is all based
around this this normal here this angle
of the light right and measuring that
angle requires that I know the
orientation of the surface if the
surface was bent another way this would
be a different angle and the lighting
intensities would change because we
would be talking about a different
incidents to the surface right and so
the reason the normal is so important is
because the lighting equation again
we're talking about little points that
we're evaluating that here that sort of
represent little infinitesimal areas
that we're simulating in some sense or
you might start thinking of them as like
texels or pixels on the screen some area
that you're simulating we're baking the
surfaces orientation down into a single
direction at that point which tells us
how we're going to compute that bounce
right and that direction is the normal
and it's called a normal of course
because it is unit length right it's a
it's normalized right right it is a
normalized vector so that normal the
length of that normal is always one and
it points in whatever direction you
might say it's tangent to the surface at
that point so if I have a surface in the
world
like this and I want to talk about what
the normal is at a particular point
we're talking about as if there was a
plane that just sort of barely touched
it escalated at that point what would be
the that you know sort of the vector
that points out perpendicular to that
plane right and so like over here the
norm
would be pointing in this direction over
here the normal way pointing this
direction and you can kind of you know
what this is intuitively it's just a
vector that points directly straight out
of the surface at that point that is the
normal that we are talking about okay so
what we want to be able to do is we want
to be able to compute lighting based on
this normal and what we're going to do
with our normal Maps is we're going to
do something very straightforward we're
going to have essentially some notion
right we need we need to have sort of
two things if you will we need to have
one a description of the surface right
description of the surface that will
tell us how we want to treat the light
that bounces around this normal right
and then - we need some equation in
terms of the inputs that we have which
is the normal to the surface the view
direction right and the light direction
we equation in these terms that will
take the description of this surface and
output a light value right you know some
some light value which would be in our
case maybe an RGB that's sort of what
the color should be at this point right
and there's some other stuff that's
baked in here in addition description we
would might also say maybe we say
there's actually three things - we might
want to say that there's a description
of the light right because we're
probably going to want to assume that
lights have different sorts of things in
there okay so that's pretty
straightforward right so that's what we
need to determine and so the first part
or I should say the the easiest part of
this the first thing we're going to do
is in that equation the normal rank that
is where the normal map thing comes in
right we have a sprite we don't actually
have surfaces right we have no such
thing as that we have a sprite that
somebody drew right they drew the tree
in there right yangshin drew a tree and
so there's no description of this
services anywhere in here so what we
need to have in addition to that if we
want to ever compute this thing you know
if we if we want to compute this whole
set here this equation we need to know
what that normal is and so what we're
going to do is introduce this concept of
a normal map and what the normal map is
is it's something that sort of mirrors
the sprite exactly but at every pixel
instead of RGB we have the normal right
so in here it's going to encode again
this normal is a vector right yet points
in the direction out of the surface it
has a length of 1 which means that it is
you know something where it's got an x
squared or Y squared is Z squared right
and the square root of them equals 1
right it's a it's a normalized thing now
what we know from that right is that we
would only have to encode two of those
values because we could always
reconstruct the third one right because
if we square both sides of this you end
up with one equals x squared plus y
squared plus Z squared right which means
that if we wanted to solve for one of
these let's say we don't want to store
what the x squared term is for example
or we don't want to score store what the
Z squared term is something like that we
can just solve for one of them so one
minus x squared right if I move the
extra the other side plus y square I'm
sorry equals y squared plus Z squared
right and I can move the one over and
and the gate right so I can have x
squared equals y squared plus Z squared
oh sorry I said I wouldn't gate equals
negative Y squared negative Z squared
plus one right I can then square root
both sides and end up with the actual
equation negative y squared negative Z
squared plus one under the radical and
if I haven't done any math mistakes
there which is pretty common but you can
point out assuming that you didn't make
any math mistakes when solving these
equations you would end up with an
equation for whichever variable you
wanted in terms of the other ones right
because this constraint that they have
to sum to one in that way that basically
tells you that you only have two real
degrees of freedom here so if we want to
at first we'll probably store all three
but it's worth noting that if we want to
we don't actually have to do that
so first we'll start all three but we'll
keep an eye on the fact that really
that's wasteful and if we have spare
cycles in there that we can fit it in
certainly on the GPU we would probably
have them we can reduce that but you
know it depends it's always a trade-off
whether you want to do this extra math
here to sort of reconstruct it right so
the normal map every Texel in the normal
map is going to store the x y&amp;z of the
value and we'll probably use the same
encoding what 0 to 255 equals 0 to 1
right so the same encoding that we were
using for our for everything else
for our RGB values we'll just use that
to encode with the normal list and that
means that when we are drawing a sprite
at all times we always can get in
addition to the RGB value we can also
get what that normal was so this is
actually really pretty easy except for
the fact that there's an asset load on
it it means that you know someone's got
to produce these normal map set to get
them from somewhere that's a separate
issue though for actually doing
computations we know we can just pull
them out of the normal map okay so the
rest of this stuff is where things get a
little more complicated for us because
again it's unclear exactly what we want
to do to describe all of these
additional things now what we would like
to do probably is be able to simulate a
little bit of different surface types
right we'd like to be able to have some
things that are shiny and some things
that are dull probably right that might
add some nice visual interest of things
you know we don't know but it's just
something to think about right and so
you know if we were to to sort of
conceptualize what's going to happen
here when we are drawing these and we're
going to draw something so we're taking
the the - the sum of these guys here and
we're producing what we're going to do
for our lighting you know maybe we're
drawing the upper part of this here and
so we know you know the normal map of
that says that it points off in this
direction so we have the color the
incoming color of the sprite we have
that that directional vector and the
question is what can we do with that
directional vector that will give us the
most bang for the buck in 2d since we
know that we can't really do much in the
way of realistic lighting since we don't
have a 3d description of the scene and
what I was sort of suggesting
the the yesterday was maybe we could
produce some sort of synthetic things
that we could look up into using these
these values to sort of cast against a
fake version of the world that we
construct which would allow us to
produce lighting values at those points
and so the first thing that I kind of
want to say is you know I guess this is
taken care of right description of the
surface is the normal that's really all
we're going to do there well that's not
entirely true we still have to talk
about what the parameters of this are
the surface are going to be so let's say
temporarily for this that all we're
really going to do is for our surfaces
the only real thing that we're going to
say is like how glassy they are right
how shiny this thing is right like how
we'll sort of have some concept of how
dull how shiny it is
so maybe we'll start off by saying our
description the surface is going to be
like a zero to one value right
where zero is is totally dull and this
is like very reflective right so this is
super shiny and we'll try to make that
be something that we can control okay
the description of the light is really
the part now that we end up with having
the problem which is well we could just
have some lights floating in the world
but I want to kind of do something or
try to do something that's a little
fancier than that and so I just try to
think about what can I do that would be
something that that would allow me to do
interesting stuff there right so let's
think about this suppose we had maybe
let's say we were looking at a value
that was pointing down towards the
ground we could imagine looking at our
ground chunks to see what the color was
down there right - to say what that what
you know would be seen by you know what
light would be sort of hitting the
bottoms of the tree right and similarly
up here at the top when things are
pointing upward we might imagine that a
sky texture just some sky thing maybe
that we have or a ceiling
case of indoors might be sort of where
the light was coming from there right
and then stuff pointing sideways right
stuff that's pointing sort of directly
sideways is sort of looking at more
stuff that's in the actual plane of the
you know of the game at that at that
area right that's the sort of stuff
that's around it it's actually sort of
reflecting out around there which
suggests to me that maybe you know could
we do something with some sort of a
three plate scheme right could we do
something where we have our ground which
we already know that we had to produce
so we've got that we could look up into
it right could we do something where
we've got our ground we've got a sky and
then something we do here right and so
what I'd like to suggest at first is
maybe we just ignore the something
ignore the stuff that's lateral because
that's going to be hard and we'll focus
on two of the three plates right so
we'll have a above and we'll have a
below right and we'll just use the above
and the below as our things that we look
up to get the lighting now again none of
this is stuff that I'm saying
definitively this is literally me
hypothesizing what we might do to
produce some sort of a useful lighting
contribution for our game okay
so what I propose is we will take our
normal values here right and one of the
parameters of our normal value right if
we've got XY and Z well one of the
values and it depends on how we choose
to encode it but let's say that when
we're encoding you know whether things
point you know up or down right let's
say that's encoded as a Z value or
something well that means the Z value
would essentially give us a blend
between the above and below things to
sample right meaning as we cross from
pointing upwards to pointing downwards
we would want to change which one we
were sampling between and furthermore if
we imagine the three plate version
we'll we'll sort of talk about it being
there for now
we'll say we have a top a middle and a
bottom let's say right if we just assume
that this is just a uniform lighting for
now right then we might say if you're at
one point o in your you know in this
encoding here and you know what I just
realized
for these values I think this I I
misspoke here we probably don't want to
use the same encoding because we want to
be able to do positive and negative
values right so really we probably want
to say you know let's say we store X's
and Y's here right we probably want to
say that 0 to 255 max from negative 1 to
1 right so yeah I think I misspoke there
a little bit we probably want that so we
probably want something although it
doesn't really matter at the end of the
day as long as we know how we're
conceptualizing it but still so yeah so
we might say that you know if it was
negative 1 point out that value we would
be sampling directly downward and if it
was 1.0 we reflect sampling directly
upward and as we move between those two
we are effectively sort of you know
sampling different we're sort of
sampling less of the top more of the
bottom more of the middle whatever and
so this would be right at 0.5 would be
right in the mid plane and so this would
be like a linear blend between top and
mid that a linear blend between mid and
bottom that sort of thing right so one
of our parameters would control which of
these three things we were blending
between and then the other two
parameters would control where we were
sampling in these right and so if you
imagine these as being sort of a I
should I put it if you imagine these as
being sort of a a picture that we're
sort of casting against right we're sort
of we're sort of looking in a direction
to see what we see so if you imagine the
top it's like some sky thing that we're
looking at then what we would do is we'd
say well okay here's where we are in the
world because we know where we're
drawing the pixel and here's like the
erection were casting so let's solve for
where that cast would hit this you know
thing that we're sampling and we'll grab
the color value out of that you know out
of it there does that make sense and so
that's what we would use our other two
parameters of the normal for for solving
that you know that cast equation right
we would do that cast for top for middle
and for bottom
well middle we don't know what to do
with yet because that's not so easy so
pretend I didn't say that we don't know
what we're gonna do here work on that
but for top and bottom we can do that
pretty straightforwardly we can compute
those cast values and once we do that we
can then produce the final result right
and in this case we'd never really blend
top and bottom together because you know
middle zoe's in there and and and
obviously there's no contribution of
from the bottom if you think about this
from a sideways view here's the top
here's the bottom then obviously when
you've got that vector as it starts to
point upwards right as that value gets
as this parameter gets to zero point
five it literally never hits the bottom
anymore right before it was kind of
casting out right and it would always
hit the bottom at some point there right
but it's some but once you get two point
five it'll literally never hit the
bottom and the same is true of top right
once you get to 0.5 on that parameter
there's no no matter what the other two
parameters are you're always just
casting directly in that plane so you'll
never hit the top right and so there's
really no overlap there's no it never a
plane between top and bottom only
between top and middle and middle and
bottom let's say depending on how we
choose to make all this work and I don't
really know exactly how we're going to
like I said it's all a hack at some
level because we can't compute the real
thing but the question is can we produce
a hack that gives us something that we
want right so I feel like that's an
interesting way of making a description
for the light for now and so the other
thing that we'll say is well if we want
to describe the surface and we have that
that zero to one value I would propose
that the way that we use that zero to
one shininess value could be similar to
what I was talking about yesterday with
blurring things if you think about
how the light effects something that's
very shiny what's basically happening
there is you're looking up actual you
know the actual reflection you're trying
to reproduce the actual thing that's
there very accurately in the shiniest so
you almost in a shiny object you almost
see the exact picture of what the light
is that's coming in right you see like
an outline of a window with the Sun
coming through it or whatever on you
know on this reflective thing whereas if
it's dull you just see a vague amount of
light and the color of the light right
it's just kind of a wash so again what
we could do here is take these planes
and just blur them right now if we were
to blur them every time we did a look up
it would be fantastically expensive
because you know you'd have to blur this
big area to see what the total incoming
light was for a really dull object but
what we can do is when we produce our
top and our bottom bitmaps we can just
successively blur the whole image just
one time right so we just take the top
and we blur it down and we decide how
much how many levels of blurriness we
want right so we have a top like I said
maybe we do a 256 by 256 top thing and
then we just kind of have a 128 by 128 a
64 by 64 right just down sampling by two
each time tilt down to some level that
we think is the right level right so we
essentially have you know five or six of
these something like that maybe four or
whatever and then we use that that
parameter that's zero to one to decide
first of all which two we're going to do
so maybe you know let's say we did four
of them so if it's zero we're sampling
out of the 32 by 32 from zero to you
know 0.33 right we'd be sampling out of
the in between these two we'd grab one
from here and one from here and blend
between them or something like this and
then from zero you know from there to
six six same thing and then 21.0 right
so we'd pick two and we'd like blend
between them or something like that
right and that seems like a relatively
easy you know way to make that work and
we could even say if we wanted to to
keep things easier for our software
renderer since nothing is animatedly
changing from blurry to smooth presume
we don't probably actually need to ever
do this amount of blending we could just
say that the surface description is just
going to be a literally a pic of which
one of these you're going into right so
it's just like you know two bits or
something which says which of these four
you look into right zero zero looks into
this one zero one looks into that one
one zero looks into this one and one one
looks into that one right so we could
really just force this to be a discrete
process if we want to and probably be
totally fine with that so I don't know
this may all be an awful idea it may
totally not work but like I said try to
come up with approximated lighting for
2d games is all about experimenting to
find out what will work so I think this
is sort of the scheme that we'll try to
go with for now and so let's move off of
the whiteboard
I'm sorry blackboard for the moment and
since we've got a good 35 minutes let's
try to get some of this implemented all
right so first things first what we need
to do is we need to introduce the
concept of a normal map to our pipeline
because we do not have that yet and so
when this thing says we've got a texture
here what we want to do is in addition
to the texture have a normal map right
so that it can have a pointer to
whatever that normal map is going to be
and we need to pass that all the way
through the system so when you push the
coordinate thing on here right you're
gonna have a thing where you pass the
normal map and the normal map is going
to get stored and pulled out by the
renderer later when it calls that fancy
the draw triangle slowly thing and one
of the things that probably we should
have done here I don't actually know why
I didn't we could just pass the entry
directly this thing that seems like a
pretty reasonable idea well maybe new I
guess we've gone this far without doing
that I won't bother it for now because
we're probably gonna change a little bit
of that stuff anyway so in draw
rectangles slowly we're just going to
assume that we've got that normal map
now right loaded bitmap normal map like
so we're gonna see when we've got that
normal map and we're going to have in
here the opportunity to basically just
reuse all of the work that we did
sample our normal map right now
technically we would want to bilinear
blend the normal map as well and so you
can kind of see the sort of problems
that that introduces because sort of
I'll show you what we're talking about
here if I have a normal map right and in
that normal map I'm pulling from like
right here I presumably want to do the
same thing I was doing before where I
figure out what the normals are here
here here and here and I grab out
exactly the right one from there right
the problem with that is remember
normals have to be normal right that's
kind of just obvious you know when I say
it's probably not something that's very
strange to you but it's true right
normals have to be normal
and if normals are going to be normal
then I can't just I can't just lurk to
normals together because they won't be
normal after I'm done right let's
imagine that I'm here right and I've got
this normal in fact I'll draw this for
you actually try to draw this relatively
precisely right suppose that I have you
know a normal pointing here and a normal
pointing here well a linear blend is
going to give me a motion along that
line right so if I were to linear blend
fifty percent between these two normals
I would end up with this vector and what
you'll notice is it's very stumpy it
should be out here if it was normal
length it should be that tall but
instead it's much shorter than that what
does that mean well it means that
whatever we were going to do with it
would be wrong because we don't actually
we're not actually accounting for that
difference in in if we baked in the fact
that it was normal to our equations we
wouldn't be able to handle that right so
this is something to be aware of we
don't have to fix it quite yet because
we have to see maybe it's it's
relatively free to bake it into our
equations to see what we can do to to
fix that or something like this maybe
we'll have to take into that account
anyway so we don't have to panic yet but
it's worth noting that like lerp four
colors works a lot better than lerp for
normals because generally when you lurk
normals you have to do that you have to
handle that Reed
zatia right you have to you have to
project them back out onto the sphere
and that kind of gets back a little bit
to this thing that I was talking about
before that's why you typically don't
mind doing this kind of thing because
since you would have to basically
renormalize anyway what you can do is
just lurk to values and then renormalize
to get the third since you were going to
have to do that anyway if you decided to
store just the X and the y so it kind of
all works out in in some sense if you
think about it that way all right so
moving on from there let's go ahead and
do our sampling here one thing we might
want to do is turn this into something
that we can reuse because we see this
happening a lot what what we would like
to do is just do like you know sample
from a texture well is a sample from
texture first let's get a little more
simpler but like this is unpack you know
a thirty to unpack 4x8 something like
that you know something that basically
takes a pointer and does this unpack so
we don't have to keep saying it over and
over and over again so I can say textile
pointer a right like so and have it do
that unpack so I'm going to go ahead and
have that be an inline function here
that we can call from multiple places so
that's an inline that's gonna be unpack
4x8 it's going to take the the value and
we'll call that the packed value right
and it's just going to produce that
result exact same way that we were doing
okay so off we go pack pack pack pack
packed like so and then we return that
right and that's just a nice way to get
that unpacking done so that we don't
have to keep writing that code over and
over and over and over again which is
obviously pretty annoying so in here now
we can replace all of these so that's an
unpack this is an unpacked 4x8 of Texel
point Gorby this is an unpack 4x8 of
Texel pointer
mmm see and finally textile pointer
whoops
unpack textile pointer tee and I believe
we already handled the color a stuff
here right because we're we're doing
that right there
so we unpack the texels mm-hmm gonna be
just fine and so if we want to do this
we could we could do sorry my throat's a
little sticky we can do this exact same
thing for the normal map so if we want
to we can change Texel to normal and off
you go and similarly we can just go
ahead and unpack those here so here we
go textile normal and the weird part
though if you take a look at this is the
unpack here is a little bit strange
because if we're reading 32-bit values
out of here we actually end up with more
values than we actually need right we
end up with four values and what exactly
are we going to do with four values we
only need three at most potentially only
two so what's that fourth value so
typically what we often do in graphics
in this scenario since as you might
imagine this sort of thing comes up
fairly frequently what we'll often do is
take the description of the surface and
bake that into the normal map as well
right so if we have a four-channel map
here we might store x and y and then
we'll also store you know even if we're
storing Z we still got that final
component let's say we'll store in that
in what would be the Alpha Channel we
can actually store say what we want the
glossiness of the surface to be right so
we could have that fourth component
could be how glossy the surface is at
that point now whether or not we candle
that being super smooth or not who knows
but that allows us to paint a single
sprite that has both reflective and non
reflective portions to it right and so
that can be kind of nice alright so if
we've got this here and we want to
produce these what we can do is say
alright we've got the Texel
the Texel got lurked here and that's the
lerp but we can also go ahead and
produce the same lerp for the normals
and then we just have to decide if we
want to do something with that later
that's going to be you know a little bit
fancier than just a lerp like
renormalizing or something fat but
there's our normal and after that we've
essentially got the normal to play with
in our pipeline
so here's the Hadamard product that we
were doing to cut to use the incoming
color to color the surface we can now do
some more work here where we use the
normal to you know to do some kind of a
lighting lookup right so in order to do
that we have to introduce yet more you
know you get more bitmaps in here right
if we want to be able to compute
lighting like I was sort of saying we're
going to have to start introducing a few
more bitmaps in here now loaded bitmap
might be the wrong thing for this
because like I was saying we kind of
want there to be a range of them
potentially where they've been blurred
or something like that so really if we
if we you know want to do this right
what we're going to have to introduce is
some kind of a structured system that
has multiple bitmaps in one place right
it's got to have multiple blurryness
levels right and so you might imagine
something like let's say we had you know
loaded bitmap here and we have logs
levels of detail let's say and we'll
have some number of those so there's
like eight of them or something or you
know maybe four of them I like we said
four originally it was how many there
were and this is going to be like our
our concept of like that that sort of
that top that bottom that sort of blur
those blur levels right and so this is
going to be we'll call this an
environment map for now because that's
sort of what it is it's a map that says
what the environment looks like and so
we'll kind of pass that in here and
we'll say alright there's an environment
map really we could do some other stuff
here but you know we'll say we'll say
out at the top we'll say what the the
sort of the the base width and height
are which are sort of saying
how you know how or I guess I kind of
said they would even be square right
because I think that's what I said out
here I think I said you know we do like
a 256 by 256 kind of a thing where was
that yeah something like this I don't
know if we want to support rectangular
ones I mean the screens rectangular so
that seems like that might be a smart
thing to do but at the same time when
we're looking up into things that may be
that having those powers of 2 is gonna
make it easier on us to do some certain
like some wrapping and clamping
operations on them so what we could do I
don't know let's let's just say for the
moment that these have to be powers of 2
but will allow them to be rectangular
potentially so we'll say X POW 2 and y
power to something like that right and
so that way we can encode essentially
the fact that these are going to be a
power of 2 width and height right
in fact I guess I could say wit POW 2
and height pad 2 right and so I could
say note KC love level 0 is 2 to the
width power 2 by 2 to the height power
of 2 right and then it just goes down
from there all right so assuming that we
want to do that then we could do in here
we could pass our environment map so
we'd say our top environment map our
bottom environment map and our middle
environment map like so so we would have
from these and in just in case you can't
already tell this is why I saying things
are going to get incredibly slow right
because you can see all these things
without any optimizations this is going
to be incredibly expensive even with
optimizations it's going to certainly be
cost costly to say the least but off we
go so we've got our top middle and our
bottom we need to then do that sampling
so what we would want to do here is we
want to take our normal and we want to
figure out what we were going to sample
on right so we've got the concept of our
normals Z right and our normals Z I
guess we could we could say is going to
tell
whether we're pointing you know up or
down that sort of a thing right
so whatever the normal we'll call that
you know we could almost call that
something it's slightly different since
we're not gonna really we don't know
exactly how we want unquote encode our
normal so yet let's call it something
different let's just say we've got our
our M map RN map T like the thing that
tells us the blend of our environment
map so right now we'll just go ahead and
pick that off of the Z of the normal
right if that makes sense so we'll pick
that off the Z of the normal and we will
go ahead and use that to figure out
we're gonna blend between so it's pretty
straightforward if at this point we
could say that if the the TN map was
less than 0.5 or if the TN map is
greater than 0.5 right we've got the two
cases we have one where it's actually
exactly equal and that's a little bit
janky because again we we sort of had
this problem of not being able to
compute what would actually happen when
you're when you sort of kick up off of
there and furthermore I guess when I
think about it if I think about it a
little more holistically here where is
that diagram you know really at some
point we might want to say that we
switch that with that it's probably
something considerably less than than
0.5 at the point which is switches you
know it might be more like 0.25 or
something that we might want only things
that point fairly downward to have that
so it might be something more like if
it's less than 0.5 you know and if it's
greater than 0.5 then we cast into then
we cast into the top and the bottom you
know something like that and in the
middle we are only looking at that that
other map or something like that and I
don't know like I said it's really hard
to say this is all just very happy to
see how things go so if we do TM map
less than 0.25 then we're going to do
that reflection into we're going to
we're going to do a look up into the top
map
bring that down here right so let's go
ahead and put these on here so let's see
this is not 0.25 0.75 there we go
alright so if we are over 0.75 on the M
map we're gonna say that we're you know
are sort of our are call this our farm
app maybe equals top otherwise our floor
map farm at people's bottom and in
either case we're going to use the
middle map so then we say whatever our
farm app you know I guess our blend
ratio is so like our key farm app our
tea farm app we're going to assume is 0
and then we'll say ok if we are in one
of these our tea farm app if 0.25 is
that breaking point what we want to do
is say whatever the end map value is
over 0.25 that is going to give us our
blend ratio right so normalize TM map as
it goes from point 2 5 to 0 is going to
make our key farm app which is the
amount we want to you know blend in the
the farm Apps contribution go up to 1
right and we can do the exact same thing
in the case of the 0.75 what we'd want
to do there is say all right from 0.75
up to 1.0 that will sort of make tea
farm at blend in from there right so in
that case I guess the way we want to do
that is say now we've got 1.0 half minus
TM map right which kind of turns that
into the range of 0 to 0.25 and we would
divide again by the 0.25 to normalize it
back up to 1 so that should give us
roughly what that blend amount would be
in either case and tea farm app again
off to check those I kind of just did
that in my head right there and again
just to make it clear what's happening
there I'm just producing a value tea
farm app that says how much we should
grab from the tea from that farm app
versus the middle map when we eventually
ever have that sort of other map that we
happen to find yet all right so once we
know that what we can do is sample from
the middle map and from the farm app
right we can get a color value so like
we'd have middle map color equals you
know sample from middle something like
this I'm just typing this in and then we
have our farm map color equals sample
from whatever the farm map was right
assuming that it was going to be greater
if tea farm map has to be greater than
zero here
well sample from that right and then we
would blend between them so you know we
almost might say result color or light
color right sample from whatever that
middle map is which we always want
sample from since I always I assume we
always want to sample from it we'll have
to see about that
but then assuming that we actually have
some contribution from the farm app we
take a look at what that color is and
then the light color would be equal to
the blend between the color that that we
got from the middle map and the color
that we got from the four map so again
just total hack coat you're just to say
hey let's let's put something in here
which does that blend between them and
so really the only thing we have to work
out at this point is that sample from
how do we sample from one of these
environment maps how do we how do we go
about figuring out given and normal and
some kind of idea of how what the
surface should be how do we actually do
that sampling right so we know what we
would need to pass right we need to pass
that surface description value which in
this case is just going to be like the
the fourth parameter right of our normal
we know we have to pass the normal
itself which is the XYZ right and then
we need to know the map that we're
actually going to sample from but we
need one more thing which is we need
where in the screen we are so that we
can kind of know roughly where we're
casting the
we're doing this this check from right
so we also need to know essentially this
value that we were using for our pixel P
right where we were in screen space
right and so we don't really have a
normalized version of that which is what
we would kind of want here so we're also
going to have to produce some normalized
version of our location in screen space
right which we know of course what the
sort of the width width max and the and
the height max are so we do actually
know what that would be we've just never
computed it right so we need to produce
something cure which is like you know
screen space screen space UV might be a
good name for it like where we are in
screen space normalized and that's just
the x over that with Max and the Y over
the height max right if that makes sense
and we can make that a little bit more
efficient - by just saying well we can
pre-compute what those are you know what
I mean oops there we go in with Max so
we know over a real with Max and in
height Max there's one point over height
max like so and so if we have those
values mm-hmm we can actually just do in
height max times the Y and in with max
times the X and that'll just tell us
where we are in screen space normalized
right so there we go
so that gives us our screen space UV so
that would allow this the sample from
function here that we're talking about
that would allow that to know kind of
where we are so we're sampling from here
we're sampling in this direction we're
sampling with this surface description
this is this amount of glossiness and
we're sampling you know this environment
map and so if we you know call this
sample environment map
like so we could go ahead and actually
write this and see what it does now for
right now what we could do is we can say
and you know another thing that we could
do here too as well as we could say if
there's a normal map right if there's a
normal map we don't have to do any of
this right and later we could have two
versions of this sort of shader if you
will that you know evaluate those
options so assuming that we've got that
we can write that sample environment
we'll end up with the light color and
then what we can do for now just to sort
of simplify things is again we can do
that Hadamard product we can take our
Texel and pre light it by just
multiplying it by that light
contribution right so we're basically
saying okay whatever the Texel was we're
assuming the Texel was that color at
maximum brightness essentially and now
we are going to modulate it by however
much light we're actually receiving from
the environment right that shouldn't say
maximum brightness basically that Texel
tells us how much light get reflects
essentially and so we're gonna multiply
that by the incoming light color to
figure out how much light actually got
reflected right now there's some other
things there that are you know we
haven't really talked about too much
about how you compute lighting equations
per se and part of that's because again
we're not really doing fully real
lighting so it's unclear how much we
really care since we're kind of doing a
total hack to compute the incoming
lighting it's not clear how much
accuracy we really want in terms of how
we process what that comes in we
probably want to do something that's a
lot more hackish which is just tune it
until it looks okay because there's
really no point in trying to do accurate
computations on completely fabricated
values right but basically what we've
got here is sort of the you know the
basics of it and so what I'd like to do
is just say all right for now we're
gonna take this sample environment map
thing where we've got our screen space
UV our normal our surface reflectance or
our let's call this our our glossiness
maybe
our mirror nests oh I know it could say
roughness and then just like zero is
it's perfectly reflective and one is
super rough
let's call let's do that and then we
have an environment map which is the map
to sample and for now what we're gonna
do is say you know what let's just
return the normal so the light the light
color is the normal so we're not
actually going to actually compute
anything here we'll literally just just
pretend the result was whatever the
normal is again just so we can start by
getting things working okay this is a
typo so let's fix that right there and
that is also type up our farm app is
environment map star flower map equals
zero there we go
in fact we could also I suppose do this
is just gif farm app like soups so then
we've got oh so we didn't do XYZ in our
math I guess I guess we only did RGB it
looks like that's actually true so what
we want to do is we want to change this
guy right here essentially to to have
the same look as this we want this X Y Z
X Y Z so we can get a little more
expressive there all right T for color
that's true T to do it's actually T farm
map yeah and lerp doesn't work with
VIII's that's totally fine we can fix
that we can certainly just copy that guy
there put him in here so v3 now has
alert and I guess Hadamard also does
some well okay so this is a little bit I
guess we might want to do this manually
because really we don't want we only
want to do the RGB we don't want to
touch the Alpha value here right because
we're not really affecting that alpha
we're not reflecting that that
brightness at all so we really I think
we want that all right
so finally we need to send this guy our
environment maps and so that would
require again this entry to sort of be
expanded to have all of these things
like I said there's a lot of plumbing
involved in this you'll find in general
this is actually we don't need this
anymore either you will find this is
generally actually true that when you
get into more complicated rendering
stuff typically the hard part oftentimes
isn't writing the equations it's the
plumbing it's making sure that
everything can move through the system
well and that there's always the stuff
that you need in the right places ends
up actually taking a lot of time there
just tends to be a lot of stuff that has
to all get lined up which buffers go
where and this is even worse on GPUs
because you've got stuff that you got to
manage on the you know moving to and
from the card and all that stuff there's
just a tremendous amount of bookkeeping
we have it actually pretty good right
now because we aren't involving the GPU
in this so we kind of have the luxury of
just you know being very direct but it
definitely it becomes an issue it
definitely becomes an issue all right so
there's our tough middle bottom scheme
like so and finally when we are passing
this along what we want to do here is
just passed zeros for everything and
that should give us our our tree oh you
know what I forgot to do forgot to add
those down here as well this would
probably there's easier ways to write
what I'm writing here I probably should
have just exposed the since it's just
debug code I probably should have just
exposed this where it just returns the
render coordinate system I should stop
having it set the values but whatever we
we've come this far and we'll just keep
going so top middle bottom
and then we'll just say top sound middle
bottom okay and that should just about
do it I think and we can get rid of this
points thing here it's not necessary
anymore and so now we should still cuz I
made everything just be Iftars tree
should be intact and it is so the next
thing we have to do is actually generate
a normal map that we can start to play
with right and so in order to do that we
need something that we can generate some
predictable set of normals from like I
said this would normally something where
we'd load them but we don't have them
yet so let's do something that'll just
generate a normal map for our tree
directly using some kind of a very
simple algorithm and so what I'm gonna
do is make something here which is you
know literally going to be just a thing
that I guess it's sort of like make
empty bitmap right it's going to be like
make fake or make a sphere normal map
right and all I'm going to do is I'm
going to do exactly this right in fact I
can even call this function in fact you
know what I could do is just say you
know what assume you've got one from
somewhere so we'll take a loaded bitmap
shooting we'll take a loaded bitmap
pointer and we'll just say that whatever
happens here you're gonna write in a
basically a spherical normal app so what
I'm gonna do is I'm going to say that
okay this normal map that we're going to
create right is just going to literally
be like a sphere you know it's just
gonna be like this sort of thing and so
you know when you look at it the normals
here will all point in these directions
off right the normal here will be
pointing directly up at you over here it
will be pointing slightly that way right
so it's just gonna be as if you were
looking down on a dome right that's all
I want to do so if I was going to do
that right
what I would do is I'm going to loop
over both x and y very straightforwardly
so here's my X like so and here's my Y
and for each pixel in here I'm going to
generate a normal based on that x and y
and again that's going to be based off
of sort of the U and V if you will of
this of this bitmap like where I am in
it so if I wanted to I could make this
the in width here right like so does
that same thing we're computing before
and the in flight and this is just to
give us some normalized values that we
know range from 0 to 1 across the bitmap
all right so there's our invite same
thing so if I want to produce sort of
the bitmap UV at that point it's going
to be that in width times whatever the X
is and the in height times whatever the
Y is okay and that bitmap UV is what
will allow me to create a normal at that
point so I could say that the normal at
that point
you name the normal at that point is
just going to be the normalized version
right of of this guy right if I first
was to say let's have it range from
negative 1 to 1 right so you know all
the way on the left side it's pointing
out and all the way on the right side
it's pointing right so we'll just kind
of do that we'll say all right whatever
the X is of this guy it's going to be
and this was that equation that I used
back when we were doing the splats I
think where I was sort of creating a
bilinear value out of a linear value
right I'm just going to multiply it by 2
so instead of going from 0 to 1 it's now
going from 0 to 2 and then I'm going to
subtract 1 so now it's going from
negative 1 to 1
right so my normal is just that in both
cases and
and the other guy right so I've got my
ex and I've got my why I'm trying to
think now do I actually need to think
about what the other value what the Z
value actually would be yeah because I I
also need right this is not quite gonna
do it for me
this is not quite gonna do it because
this is just gonna give me the flat
values in the plane hmm all right I
gotta think this through a little bit
more because of this this means I'll
have to what I was kind of hoping is
that we'd have some values in here I
guess I actually have to think about the
actual sphere itself right
I actually I have to actually produce
this the the actual sphere so I can
think about what the three values would
actually be at that point I fig I don't
maybe I'm missing the like cheap way to
get that but I don't think so
mmm yeah I don't I don't think so
I'm pretty sure so I guess what I would
say is well you know we could do there
actually is a pretty cheap way
I guess I could just say you know what
the Z value is just going to be those
two combined right in other words the
closer you are to the center of this
thing the more the whatever that's going
to determine what the the actual Z
pointing value is as well or something
like that right that would be pretty
straightforward so I could do something
where I said you know start with that
and then say normal about the equals
normal dot X plus normal dot y will do
the absolute value here this is probably
a bad idea we should probably actually
do this correctly so I'm just gonna
throw this in for now and maybe maybe
tomorrow stream will be how do we
generate a good simple simple thing
there
but anyway then I'll normalize that
normal right which I you know will give
me back the actual normal value and then
we'll have the color that we want to
write in will actually just be the
normal and then our surface our surface
values so our roughness value and
there's that roughness value so we can
do that pretty easily and unfortunately
we're pretty much out of time
so I guess I could quickly slam in this
thing here in terms of actually writing
to the bitmap we could grab the code
from from render group that says draw a
rectangle so we could go ahead and do
this row equals buffer memory write row
plus equals pitch on each line and then
for each one of these we just do pixel
and then the start pixel equals that
packing so you know that's the other
thing too this guy right here we could
certainly make this stuff be we should
probably pull this stuff out as well we
do this sort of thing enough we should
we should go ahead and make this B and
you know something more reasonable but
anyway so if this becomes our color
value again the thing that we would have
to do here once we have our normal we'd
have to translate these back into the
right spaces 0 to 255 and and we'll have
to unpack them correctly as well so I'll
just quickly do a thing that that sort
of gets us a little closer there and
we'll save most of the rest of the stuff
that we're going to do for next time so
here is our color value like so our
roughness value has to be multiplied by
255 these values are ranging from
negative 1 to 1 so they're actually
going to be 255 times whatever the value
is we have to you know basically put it
up into the range of 0 to 1 so this is
going to be negative 1 to 1 we have to
change its range there
sense to me
similarly the normal Z we kind of know
that that's always going to be pointing
upwards so that one actually I can just
be directly treated as a smaller value I
suppose since we know that it's it's
never going to actually be negative and
then this guy similarly has to be
handled the exact same way as the normal
X okay there we go
I didn't mean buffer I meant bitmap and
what is the question here Oh signed
unsigned mismatch sorry about that
if you really want those to be signed
they can certainly be signed I thought
we had a normalized function in our
handmade math dot age do we not have one
normalize I guess we don't we certainly
done the normalization operation before
but I guess it's true we don't we don't
have one normalize of course is very
simple right
normalized just takes in a vector and
divides it by its own Mike do we have
oh do we have normalizer zero anywhere
no wow we have we've never inflicted a
normalized it's weird that we've gotten
this far doing that but pretty simple
right it's just a vector divided by its
length and I thought we had sort of
talked about that so I wonder if we just
yeah yeah that's pretty weird pretty
weird all right well anyway very simple
oops
it's length not its length squared so
that's about it and like I said we're
out of time so I will go ahead and wrap
things up I guess this doesn't do yeah
divide operator so we'll just go ahead
and do it that way
and this is bitmap I think we're back to
compiling and again we have set
ourselves up to do in our laps
and we've got most of the stuff in there
but we have it quite gotten all the way
so we'll have to spend tomorrow actually
doing some more stuff with the normal
maps this is not quite right so I'll
just what to do in here actually
generate sphere here we'll just say that
and then we can you know we can play
with that tomorrow so I'll go ahead and
go to the Q &amp; A and we can field any
questions that there might be I don't
start that now and yeah I think we made
pretty good progress like I said there's
a lot of bookkeeping and so tomorrow
we'll be sure that plenty of time to
start playing with the normal and
getting the actual environment Maps and
the sampling of that sort of stuff we
should have cleaned out but there's a
lot of bit a lot of stuff there that we
actually have to do if that makes sense
your 2d art already seems to have some
shading will that just represent ambient
lighting when mixed with this dynamic
lighting you're trying to do yes that's
correct
you know we can't really there's really
no way with a 2d game it's just not
possible to really do all of the
lighting in code
you know because you just don't have
nearly the fidelity you would need to to
really do that effectively I don't think
and so what we'll try to aim for with
all of our art assets is they should
look like they are sort of ambiently lit
to some degree in a sort of basic way
and then we will sort of apply lighting
on top of that which is you know not the
way you would do it if you were going to
compute all of the lighting because
lighting is normally an additive process
and this is gonna be more of a
subtractive process right but you know
what can you do it makes fear a normal
map should y less than bitmap whitby
while it yes yes that that should be
thank you typo there
how far do you think you can increase
the capabilities of an engine like this
before you start to suffer from
performance constraints due to using
only the CPU well I guess I mean sort of
the answer that is we don't really care
because we're not shipping the CPU
version as the version that players will
play we're just writing the CPU version
for educational purposes so if we
actually had to ship the CPU version
like for some reason we were trying to
ship into a market where GPUs didn't
exist which I don't even know where that
would because all machines have them now
but if you were trying to do that um
yeah we might get away with this I mean
we'd have to really spend a lot of time
optimizing it but we might be able to do
this at some of this dynamic lighting
you know like I said we got what we
probably would have to spend a lot more
time optimizing it than we will because
we'll just optimize it a little to kind
of show how you would do it and get it
running like okay right and you know if
it's too slow if it's only 15 frames a
second and it's running at 320 by 240 or
something that's okay because we just
wanted to show how to do it but you know
if you actually wanted to actually run
this at a reasonable resolution
reasonable frame rate yeah I mean
obviously doing dynamic lighting is
expensive and you might be able to you
you might be better off picking a
simpler scheme for lighting as well but
I don't want to do that because like I
said we don't have to we don't have to
care how fast our CPU version is it's
it's it's for educational purposes don't
you need to srgb to linear one the
normals or use the normals instead of
the Texel in the lerp so we we kind of
endeavor to that so when we do the lerp
here when we unpack these and lerp
basically oh that's good some reason
Texel did not get replaced there there
we go when we do this right we
we could decode these from two zero to
one first but we could just leave them
this way because we don't actually know
what we're going to do with them in
sample environment math so the answer is
we definitely don't want to use srgb to
d5 to linear because normals are not
encoded in srgb right they're not a
perceptual brightness value so normals
will be encoded exactly linearly what we
do with them in terms of unpacking we
could divide them in fact no I think
this is correct
because we don't want to bother
multiplying these guys to make them not
in the range to make them zero to one
until after the lerp because that way we
can just do the multiply on the
resulting value and save a bunch of
computations the only reason we had to
do these here is because we wanted to do
the lerp in light linear space so does
that make sense so we really don't want
to decode these guys into the zero to
one range until after we composite them
I believe
sudonym service II says normal Z equals
square root of 1.0 - normal squared -
normal y squared I was thinking that but
does that actually do the right thing is
that actually gonna produce trick III
want to believe that's true so let's
just say that it's true and then we'll
see if it's true
sudonym 73 is our resident math expert
anyway so let's just assume that he's
thought about it and it's gonna be
correct and what he was suggesting is
well if instead of normalizing the
normal you actually just let the final
component B what the normalization would
be that will produce the sphere shape
does that make sense and so he's
basically saying well just take the X
and the y in fact it's just the length
right of this vector just take that and
let that be your you know your your
final value right whatever the whatever
the yeah whatever the the the squared
length of a although I guess you're
saying that we actually would have to
solve it inside the radical so I guess
you're saying we would have to do this
right
meaning the thing that I showed right
here this guy he's suggesting just
actually compute that so basically you
do again 1 minus X words y squared or Y
squared Z squared right like so right or
I guess I could also write it like this
that's how you wrote it in the Q&amp;A so
that's doing this actual equation and I
guess that does that produce the sphere
shape maybe it does I don't know let's
let's assume that it does for now and
we'll we'll just keep going
is your lighting look up a similar
technique to Matt Capps used in other
software I have no idea I don't know
what Matt Capps actually are what
benefits do you see from using the extra
time it takes to create your own engine
from scratch is it worth it in your
opinion we answer that on yesterday's
Q&amp;A so you can take a look at
yesterday's Q&amp;A if you want to see the
answer to that ah students turning 3 the
catch is that it's going to take the
square root of a negative number if
you're outside the sphere well you know
that's okay because what we could do
there is just clamp it right we could
say you know clamp this or or or take
the minimum right I'm sorry the maximum
of like of this you know what I'm saying
like the or I should say the minimum
just don't let it get above one right so
the minimum of that right that seems
fair
cuz we don't care what's outside is
we're just this is just a simple test so
that's totally fine and I guess we've
got a little bit of time left here and
there aren't any other questions so we
could just try running this we could
just try running the mixer a normal map
to see what it does although I guess
I'll save that for next the next time
that's for people who aren't watching
the q and A's
any other questions before we move move
on yeah right
well it looks like we have come to the
end of the questions so we'll pick back
up at with makes for a normal map
tomorrow again we've done most of the
plumbing stuff so hopefully we'll be
able to kind of go through and like
actually fix a typos that have got in
there and also just kind of go through
and and play with it and see what they
what the normal Maps look like and then
try to get them actually sampling into
our into our environment Maps so that we
can see you know something can I go like
all right how does this work is this
something that we can use is it actually
valuable and play with it a little bit
and that probably what we do next week
is just trying to play around those
environment Maps see if we can get them
to do something useful and maybe letting
that inform us a little bit because like
I said we don't really know we're gonna
do with that middle plane which is kind
of the thing that's a little more a
little more difficult because it's the
active area it's the area where you know
like things are you know if a fireball
is flying by that kind of stuff
and so I don't really know what we're
gonna do about that but you know we will
we'll tackle it the way you know you
tackle hacky things like this we'll just
do experiments make our best guess as to
what to try and and move on from there
so I think that's good let's see
and yeah looks like everyone so we never
had a question so I will wrap it up let
me go ahead and save the mischief file
always important and I will close that
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for another episode of handmade hero
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
at home the source code you can do so by
going to handmade hero or Arg and
pre-ordering the game it comes with the
source code during its whole development
so if you want to follow along that's an
easy way to do so you can also subscribe
to our patreon if you want to support
the video series it's always much
appreciated we also have a forum site
you can go to to ask questions and that
has community dun ports to Mac and Linux
stuff like that and we have a tweet bot
that you can go use to see what schedule
is so if you want to catch a live stream
get tweets to schedule at you every day
and it's easy it makes it easy to know
when the stream is going to be so that's
about it
thanks for joining me and we'll be back
here same time same place tomorrow 5:00
p.m. on Twitch where we will play around
those normal Maps and see how they work
so thanks for joining me and I'll talk
to you tomorrow