okay hello everyone and welcome to
handmade Hero show recode complete-game
live on twitch new libraries no engines
just us and good old-fashioned C code
and a little bit of C++ code now and
again as well as the need arises we are
here on day one one one for those of you
who are you know adept at binary you
will note that is seven right or
whatever it is I hope you enjoy that
that little translation but we are not
in binary here this is actually day 111
and so if you wanted to follow along at
home and you pre-ordered the game on
handmade hero org you should unpack day
110 because that is the source code that
I am starting with now before we
actually do anything today we had thing
in the freestream where me blow was was
asking us to fix something in the code
for so he could use it in one of his
ports and so we will go ahead and do
that right now
essentially what happened was when we
introduced these here I didn't give
unique names to these values like
ignored zero here they're not used but
we need to give them unique names so
that they don't conflict with the other
ones up here and if we do that I think
it'll allow it to go through his
compiler properly I'm not a hundred
percent certain why our compiler didn't
complain about it because technically
although these two would have shadowed
each other the this one should have
complained because when you used ignored
zero I guess it wouldn't know which one
it was but I guess the Microsoft
compiler may be only complains if you
actually use them that it doesn't know
which one you're referring to and I
guess that doesn't happen on like maybe
LLVM or something goes wait a minute I
don't know what's going on here so again
that doesn't really affect anything for
us but it's just something to do to make
it a little bit easier for anyone who's
porting who's running on Linux or
something like that just trying to keep
it easier for them to maintain the same
codebase so there you go me bloat should
be all good now let's go ahead
and and see what about what we're doing
I believe what I said that we were going
to do today was to take a look at our
ground chunk stuff I also wanted to
before we start I wanted to go ahead and
make this debug camera even be a little
further out because I'd like to be able
to see the entirety of the pink region
as well there so let me go ahead and and
go into render group if you remember
yesterday we introduced the concept that
we could have it you know one camera
that's what the game thinks the camera
is and then another camera that's what
we actually render from so that if we
want to we can see sort of a bird's eye
view of what the game is doing with all
of like you know with with everything
that that implies right
and so if you you know if you take a
look at at this scene right the actual
screen is the yellow area that's what
would actually have been rendered if we
were using the regular camera but then
you can kind of see that there's you
know you can kind of see what else is
going on like this stuff just got paged
in because it came within the purple
region and so on so what I want to do
here is I want to just kind of take a
quick look and I wanted to see about
that whole paging situation to see if
things are actually paging in and out
roughly where we we think they should be
and to be honest it looks ok you know I
guess we can when we when we go in to do
some finally work on some of that stuff
we can double check to make sure that it
is actually correct but it actually
looks pretty good it looks like our sim
region is actually paging things in
where it needs to be and stuff like that
and so I'd say that's that's you know it
doesn't really were an immediate
attention but I do want to kind of check
some of that stuff out perhaps a little
bit later so anyway yeah it's kind of
nice to be able to see all that stuff
working properly and you know what we
could also probably up our tree count we
reduce the number of trees in the world
just to make it so that it was gonna be
less stress on the renderer but since
we're getting pretty close to where
we're gonna optimize that we can
probably reintroduce it to make it
not that big of a not that big of a
problem so let me go ahead and change
that that tree part there because we
want to start making the game very slow
so that we feel the so that we kind of
feel good about ourselves when we go to
optimize that we're like look at what a
good job we did so that's you know
that's always fun anyway
let's go ahead and take a look at the
place where we had had dropped out some
of the trees you can see we kind of did
a weird sort of thing here so let's just
get rid of that see ABB's tiles e oops
that's the stairwell
I bet it's this one why if it should be
door it should be door why does it do if
should be door and then do tile mod X
mod - I know shouldn't it be should be
wall that's that's confusing I don't
understand I understand that very odd
but anyway I think this is just nonsense
in our world creation code which you
know is just there to kind of be be
weird all right so anyway there's all
the there's all the trees in a ring like
they should be again and if we go up now
we can kind of see it now what I'd like
to do today like I said it's kind of
take a look at those ground chunks
because well we got a couple things we
might want to do one is to look at the
ground chunks what another is to look at
the the collision stuff but basically
we've got a Z situation that we still
haven't resolved which is that we we
both we said we wanted to move to Z
layers and we sort of did a little bit
of work of moving to Z layers like we do
fading in and fading out based on the Z
distance and and other things like this
but at the moment we don't really
properly handle I guess maybe I should
zoom us back in here let's go ahead and
let's go ahead and use the regular size
of things so if I go ahead and and
actually walk up here right oops here we
go you can kind of see that we've got a
bunch of things that we're not really
handling yet for starters we've got a
problem where we don't have any ground
right we did our we did that ground
chunk work so we actually have a system
that can compose ground chunks for us
but we don't actually have any way of
using them right now because when we
actually did the ground chunk the system
that actually calls the ground chunk
Composer it only ever actually worked on
one single plane and so if we have
multiple depth flames like this we need
to actually start thinking about that
and introducing something that will
actually work when used in that
environment that's if we set ourselves
up to do that basically it was it's not
like we didn't plan for it but we never
actually implemented it and so we want
to do is we want to go do that and I
think that's probably the first thing
that we'll tackle today the other thing
that we want faculty day is we don't
really process the ground properly I'm
sorry I shouldn't say the other thing
around tackle today the other thing we
want to tackle if we have time but you
know maybe we won't so it'll actually go
to next week the other thing is we need
to start actually thinking of these Z
layers as actual layers because right
now we're it's still very ad-hoc we sort
of said we were gonna have this concept
of layers and we now need the renderer
to kind of understand those layers as
well because it's doing things like
fading in them in and out and stuff like
that but we never actually and oh and
we've got our light mapping system and
so on which also wants to think of
things in terms of layers but we really
just don't have any conception of those
layers in the actual code itself outside
of the rendering system and so we need
to do is start actually thinking about
that more specifically so that we can
have you know have data in the right
place and understand it the correct way
in the code so that when we need to
start talking about things like you know
this is this layer that's that layer we
actually have some idea of what entities
that actually entails this is kind of
fun I like walking around this world
already and going up and down the
stairwells alright anyway that's
basically what we're doing as soon as I
stop as soon as I can stop myself from
walking your hand
uh yeah it's it's one of those things
what can you do when you're a programmer
if you like programming you end up
liking when things are sort of working
when things start working all right but
I really want to see some ground in
there so that's my motivation to stop
walking around here and actually go fix
that so let's talk about ground for a
second alright so we already did a bunch
of stuff with the ground we've got you
know a system here that does the ground
compositing right we've got fill ground
chunk that's here but the problem with
that is we have not actually done any
thinking about how to like fill those
and when to fill those in that sort of
thing right we saw a system that would
work just for one plane but we didn't go
any further than that so we've got a you
know we've got our ground chunks here
ground buffers right like so and those
ground buffers they know where they are
in the world right so you can see that
it actually you know each ground buffer
knows where it is the only thing that
that's preventing us from being able to
use ground buffers at multiple Heights
is our thing that actually goes and and
says when we need to fill these ground
buffers needs to start thinking about
the heights properly right it needs to
think about what the height should
actually be and if I remember a text
blog tell you the truth I don't actually
remember but I don't actually think we
really did much with those those Z
chunks I guess well you know what no I
take it back
it looks like we actually did even do
that part properly like we are actually
technically looping over the Z chunks
and then doing
mmm Ground creation here looks like it
well I stand corrected it looks like we
are actually filling Z chunks there or
at least we have we are set up to do so
so the camera bounds in meters it looks
like really the only thing we would have
to do there is when we actually render
them I suppose when we actually were
rendering them I don't know that we I
don't know that we actually yeah so I
don't know that we actually did anything
when we actually rendered them so let's
take a look here with ground buffer to
practice camera P bitmap with height
gosh I don't know I'm gonna go ahead and
re-enable this we've got some stuff that
we're gonna have to fix but it's kind of
weird like it looks like we did a lot
more work than I thought we did almost
everything here looks like it's actually
somewhat correct actually I mean there's
some maybe some things to fix that but
that's very surprising all right well
what are you gonna do it's correct it's
correct all right so we had to do an
alignment thing here where we were we
now use alignment percentage not aligned
right for the bitmaps and that's
actually nice because that means we can
actually fix this stuff to just be we
know we always want to be halfway in
both directions right that's just what
we want we want to be centered so now we
know that the align percentage is always
the same thing we don't really have to
compute it based on the bitmap distance
or anything like that so that's pretty
good we no longer have the Z offset
thing in here that we were testing with
the camera so that's all good and so
yeah I don't know if there's anything
else we need to do there we'll find out
in a second push bitmap does not take
three arguments that's probably true
what we probably have to do here is now
think about we've got that whole meters
to pixel situation that we wanted to fix
with these ground chunks again and so
what we have to do is decide on a scale
right I believe if I'm not mistaken just
guiding on a scale like yeah so we have
to have an actual scale for our ground
chunks because right now we don't
actually have one right
what is that why is what's happening
there oh wow
okay so one other thing that we did not
think about here is that our basis our
basis for drawing the the sim bounds
here was never cleared and this is
something that we're gonna have to start
looking at in the renderer so I want to
show you what I saw a bit made me think
of this
so you notice now that as I move around
I'm basically getting that's the screen
rectangle right which is that the screen
rect on which is that yellow thing is is
switching where it is right and what I
realized is that we have a system in
here where we basically say what the
basis is for all of them are rendering
once it gets set in here it's sticky
right so once we set the basis here that
means that when we do stuff later on
it's gonna that basis is going to
actually be kept right and so what we
need to do is we need to when we go to
start doing our push rect outlines here
we need to change the basis back to be
whatever the default whatever the
default actually is right which I assume
is just all zeros right oops it's not
what I wanted at all so basis I think we
just got this here if I want no offset
and that's something we want to clean up
that's not a good API at the moment
right that's just we're kind of again
working through the render kind of
slowly so but I just wanted something
that would work so there we go now we've
got that back in there but obviously my
grand junction not showing up and we
have a bunch of things that we didn't do
yet with ground chunks as well which is
first of all we have that the fill
ground chunk routine we did not update
this when we did a bunch of work on the
on the rendering right we we didn't
really do anything in here so I don't
know what we need to fix we may have to
fix some stuff in here to see what act
has to get improved to work with the new
bitmap rendering stuff and we're also
gonna have to make sure that the way we
actually draw the ground buffers
still right and like I said the scale is
wrong at the moment as well so I'm gonna
start with something really simple I'm
basically going to get rid of everything
that's in here because I just want to
get this back to a reasonable working
order so all I'm gonna do first is I'm
just gonna do that clear to purple right
I want to do that clear to purple and
that way I can see as soon as we
actually have these guys rendering it
all we'll see some obvious purple right
and then I want to go ahead and what is
this request background buffers this is
just some old vestigial code that we
never used so what I'd like to do here
is just go ahead and figure out you know
I'm gonna enable this temporarily as
well which is I want to be able to see
where those ground where those
grandmother's are so what I want to do
now is go ahead and try and get this
stuff back into good working order right
with the new rendering stuff so here we
go over our ground buffers and for each
brown buffer assuming that it's valid we
will go ahead and try to render it right
I don't actually know why we were
pushing rect outlines in here that's
kind of make a whole lesson to me yeah
I'm gonna actually move this up here I
think so what I'd like to do instead is
when we do this push bitmap call I'd
like to push a rect outline optionally
on top of that push bitmap call right
and what I want to do is I want to make
it basically outline whatever the bitmap
outlined right and so I believe there's
not much that I would have to do for
that right I'm pretty sure I can just do
a pretty straightforward rectangle
outline here and I don't actually know
what the dimensions gonna be this thing
yet but I want to actually see there we
go I want to actually see all of the
places where we are currently rendering
stuff so there is
there's all the places where we're
currently supposedly rendering ground
chunks now what's interesting is as I
move away from here you can see that
it's never actually updating where those
ground chunks are which seems really bad
so that's obviously the first thing that
we probably want to fix so let's figure
out why that's happening so again this
is the renderer and this is the ground
chunk rendering right this is ground
chunk rendering and this is constant
updating right so when we do the ground
jump chunk updating I'm not sure it
looks like we don't actually use the
chunk stuff much we're doing this here
we have our super inefficient thing that
goes through for every chunk that we
look at we go through all of the ground
buffers right we take a look to see if
we have a furthest buffer it looks like
what is this actually doing if they're
in the same chunk so if it's already got
one I guess is what it's doing this
thing it's already got a ground buffer
for this place then we do nothing
otherwise if it's valid we see how far
away it is and then possibly get the the
furthest buffer there and then we'll do
that fill ground trunk ah so I probably
accidentally nerfed the one thing that
we actually needed I put that if zero a
little bit too far down you can see that
that ground buffer key that's the update
so hopefully that will go ahead and fix
that update and it does so you can
actually see now those ground chunks
getting kind of updated as we as we move
around and they look like they're
actually working pretty well right you
can kind of see it I'm thinking about
all those ground chunks as we move
around now again a lot of this stuff is
kind of janky at the moment cuz we
haven't done much with it but at least
it looks like it's picking the locations
that I would expect it to pick and so
that all seems pretty pretty reasonable
to me nothing particularly weird
right so what I want to do now is go
ahead and see why we're not actually
getting any if we actually turn on the
compositing why we're not getting
anything in the actual bitmap so let's
take a look at that code now right just
to make sure and some of this stuff so I
guess when we have these stamps and
stuff I don't know if they've got any
kind of alignment stuff working with
them this stuff maybe this looks also I
mean just looking at this I think I can
see what the problem is all of this
stuff was still being done in pixel
space right which may be you know I
don't know we might want to support that
still we wouldn't want to support having
the renderer be you know in a mode that
can support pixel space but I suspect
that we might as well do the same thing
for the ground chunks as we're doing for
everything else which is to make it
resolution independent right because at
the end of the day we're just slotting a
bunch of stuff in there anyway so it
seems to me like we would want to go
ahead and make it work
resolution independent so what that
would mean is instead of looking at
things like the width and the height now
we can just sort of consider these
ground chunks to have some kind of a
uniform size however big we want that
size to be and then we just flat stuff
into it right it's pretty
straightforward so what I'd like to do
is just go ahead and say all right for
ground buffers we're just gonna say that
there's a particular size in meters of
those grande buffers we do here and I
guess you know what we could even do is
let's make them line up with the chunks
since they're supposed to line up with
the chunks we know how big a chunk is
right if we go ahead and look at
handmade worlds we know in Hanalei well
we've got that chunk dim in meters so
what I'd like to do is say that whatever
that that world state is there that's
that's what we're going to use right so
the size and meters of a ground chunk is
just going to be whatever that chunk dim
meters is so the first thing I do for
that is I want to go ahead and get those
outline
drawing in the right place so when we go
ahead and we do this work here for the
ground trunks I'm gonna say that we want
them to be based on that that that chunk
size right and so you know we could also
make the alignment of these VIP masts be
based off of their corner I guess no the
center is correct because chunks are
based around their center so we want to
keep the same thing right we want to
base these two bases line up with our
world rep for now that's what I was
thinking we should do and and that's
what I'm going to stick with so whatever
we want that chunk Tim to be it would
have to go in here right whatever the
scale is and so that that chunk diamond
meters right is just going to be world
chunked in meters X the x and y scale
should be the same because this is a
square because that should be fine and
I'm gonna go ahead and maybe say that
this is the the ground side and meters
or something like that right and we'll
just grab that right out of there okay
so there's that ground side and meters
and here is that ground side and meters
again and now I'm hoping anyway that
everything yeah and it looks like it is
everything actually forms a coherent
grid so you know it's it's essentially
covering a complete coverage of all of
the area that might have some ground in
it now I would say really that looks
about right to me nothing funny going on
there as far as I can tell
so yeah I would I would basically say
that that looks totally what I would
exactly yeah that looks exactly what I
would want it to look like so I don't
think we've got any problems there I
think that's all good next step is just
to fill those in with something and
again like I said I think the reason
that we're having a problem here is
because this is still Owen pixels which
is not what we want now we've got a
problem here which is that in terms of
when we
get our render group in terms of what
we're actually sending down in term for
the the sort of width and the height of
the thing that we're rendering to the
reason that that's a little bit wonky is
because you know that's basically just
something that's that's computing our
perspective that's all those are doing
and we don't really want to change what
that is
pretty much ever right we don't want our
ground chunks to differ depending on a
resolution or anything like that right
so I'm not really sure what we want that
to be but I think what we'd probably
want to do is I think we'd actually want
to use whatever the the actual buffer is
there we'll have to think of this
through I'm gonna I want to get these
working but then we may have to think
about this a little harder because again
we're still kind of working with that
render group and it may imply that we've
got some other work that we are going to
need to do there right yeah I mean I
guess the way to think about this is we
really want to put this render group
into an orthogonal projection mode is
what we want to do because we really
don't want a perspective projection here
at all and so that might be the way to
think of it what we want to do is just
pass standard and normalized coordinates
into the thing and we want those to it
to work and so yeah I feel like we may
have to extent extender sorry expand our
render group a little bit we don't have
to do it right away we can kind of hack
this into working but I think that's
actually what needs to happen and so
we'll do that and we'll put that on the
list
we'll put that on the list so what we
want to do here is something more like
this to do KC need to be able to set an
orthographic orthographic display mode
here and that's what we'll do
so what we want to do for our ground
chunks in terms of width and height now
is we want to again use that game state
we want to use the world we want to use
whatever that chunk gamin meters is
right so we've got our chunked in meters
we want to just use that for what the
width and the height are of this thing
because they should be and essentially
you know relative coordinates and
they're going to be relative to the
center so we really want to do something
like half height and half width probably
because that's what we'd use for
everything and so then when we do this
let's see here V to Center it goes trunk
offset ah
well okay I take it back you do actually
want this we don't want to pre-compute
it that way we'll do it like that and
that looks about right so we're
producing the center there for the
bitmap Center I feel like the bitmap
Center we shouldn't have to deal with
anymore because our alignment code
should take care of that so what we want
to do here is in our alignment code when
we actually go in here what did we set
it to you by default right top down line
x and y so and we do debug load BMP so
we do these debug load B and peas here
right I think what I want to do is make
it so that by default when we load
something instead of the default being
that it's I want the default to actually
produce even alignment right so I think
what I want to do is suggest this right
I want to make it so that if you call
debug load with an align X another line
Y then it will actually do that but I
also want to have some way for you to
actually just say I want the default
alignment right I want I want it to
align to like the center or something
like that
I'm not sure what the best way to do
that is I guess one way I could do it
although we might want negative
alignment so I don't know I'm trying to
think what I want to do here is
something like you know
I don't know I want really to functions
so what I want to do here is I want to
break these out right I want to do
something where I've got it's another
one here which when you just do this
it basically over - oh well I guess
that's pretty easy you know what I'll
just do that
here we go I don't know why I'm
different so long that that's been a
long day all right
so if we do this here where we actually
load we just have like a thunk call
basically which does the the load by
calling the existing function right like
so and then just takes the result and
sets that result a line percentage to be
equal to that you know 0.5 point 5 then
it looks like that's just you know
that's just all we would really need
right so we now have another way to
debug load bitmap and oops we just
passed zeroes for that because we don't
care what it is right so I believe that
would actually give us what we wanted
which is of course not know what's going
on right now there we go okay
I believe that's what we wanted so
everything will load properly and yeah I
think everything looks I don't see any
bugs from switching to that load bitmap
all right and so now let's go ahead and
finish what I was saying so that gets us
out of the business of having to deal
with these bitmap centers right the
bitmap centers go away and so that's
good no more bitmap centers which is
which is another good thing so you don't
have to think about anymore so we do
these random choices really all we need
now is a random bilateral that we can
use to to you know basically position
this thing inside the chunk and so I
think what I'm gonna do is say that
we've got like this is this will be the
half dim and I'll just do it like this
right I'll produce that half dim here
and so really all we have to do is say
oK we've got a random bilateral in this
case now random bilateral random
bilateral and I'm just gonna do that's
just going to be
always made with the Hadamard product
Hadamard product of the half dim and a
random vector right and so what that's
gonna do is give us some random thing
from from the center out to the edge
right and then we just go ahead and use
that Center plus offset in fact we don't
really need to we could make this a lot
simpler in fact and just do this so and
that would be that right so I think
that's really all we need there same
thing would be true over here right in
fact I think it's exactly the same thing
there's really nothing else that was all
exactly the same yeah so let's go ahead
and try that out now and let's see if
that produces anything more usable for
us in terms of ground chunks
still nothing that's disappointing I was
thinking we would see something there
but that's okay we'll go ahead and we'll
take a look at what we're actually
seeing now the fact that the frame rates
going so slowly implies to me that we
are properly drawing those ground chunks
now it's just they're not filled with
anything right so what is going on what
did I mess up and you know now that I
think about it we did it clear so even
if we weren't bleeding anything we
should have seen it so I'm still i'm
making some fundamental error here when
we're actually drawing these things and
so off to go see why that is because
technically I forgot my thing that I
wanted to do technically once we do this
right if we just do that clear we should
at that point we should see the pink we
should see that debug that that hideous
pink right so I'm wondering why we're
not seeing that and let's take a look so
we're not seeing it we do a push bitmap
here right we're doing it with ground
side and meters zero zero the bitmap
itself
we are getting from ground buffer bitmap
see what's happening there yeah I mean
right it doesn't it seems like we should
be seeing something there and I'm not
sure why we aren't and that is kind of
troubling so something is weird there
because the same exact drawing command
that follows right after it does show up
and so the bitmap I'm gonna go ahead and
just verify something just to make sure
that we know that the bitmap is what's
wrong right I'm gonna go ahead and say
that the game state there's a tree right
let's push that instead of the bitmap
and so now we should see you like trees
everywhere right and as you can see we
do see trees everywhere and they are
scaled what looks like appropriately
even so so we're drawing in the correct
place but for some reason our bitmap is
not even filled with the debug purple
and I have no idea why that would be
right so fill ground chunk I'm gonna go
ahead and step into that and see what's
happening in there just go ahead and say
fill ground chunk when I walk around
here oh my what what just happened why
did it why didn't ever call fill ground
chuck okay are we never calling fill
ground chunk I mean I did set a
breakpoint did I not fill ground chunk I
don't know what these guys are doing
here
so we never call photograph chunk all
right well that would explain why
there's nothing in the bitmap at the
risk of stating the overwhelmingly
obvious right so all right I guess let's
take a look at why we're not ever
filling any ground chunks ever which
doesn't even make any sense to me
because if we're not filling them how is
it drawing them up here it's just that's
nonsensical I don't understand
all right oh I know what's wrong we're
still building in the Oh to build ladies
and gentlemen mm-hmm the visual studio
debugger apparently is too dumb to set a
breakpoint at the inlined point of a
function oh well all right
let's try that again here we go so we
come in here and what's what buffer are
we filling here let's take a quick look
so all looks pretty reasonable that
looks like a buffer 256 by 256 buffer
and there's some memory we've got a line
percentage is not set to anything at the
moment so here we go we're going to
clear that right which pushes one of
these guys on there puts the entry color
on there now we're going to go render
the group output we're going to loop
through here we're gonna encounter that
clear and then we're going to do a
rectangle draw call into into the buffer
in theory so let's take a look at the
output target target the output target
is the buffer that we thought it should
be width over height that is our problem
we did not initialize our bitmap with
over height to anything did you see that
that is that is our problem so when we
do fill ground chunk
we should probably I don't know who
wants to be responsible for this stuff
I'm not sure let's take a look here but
that so that a line percentage when we
do that we probably want to in here
basically say all right the buffer is a
line percentage of that and the width
over height make sure that they're even
so that way it's set properly so I
suspect that that was the problem so
we're just always thinking that the
bitmap had no dimension at all right
at least I'm assuming that's what was
happening not actually sure that all
right that's a little bit better so hold
on a second and now we have to actually
do some work in here right and I guess
sorry pink I don't know why I was
thinking pink this is actually yellow
right that we're clearing it too but
yeah
beside point so off we go and let me go
ahead and set our - OH - back here so we
run a little faster all right so now
we're going to be incredibly slow
because at the moment our ground chunk
actual building is super super slow but
alright so now we're at least back into
some semblance of reasonableness here
and of course all of that bleeding is
just super expensive for our yeah for
our renderer so we're probably not gonna
be able to use this hardly at all right
I mean you can see look at that frame
rate because it's over drawing all of
that stuff look at how painful that is
it can't hardly do it now remember we're
not sorting anything here so we've kind
of got this situation where different
ground chunks at different heights are
just doing arbitrary stuff but at least
now we can see okay we are filling them
in properly everything seems to be
kosher
now we need to adjust that scale because
at the moment we're you know we're still
using that perspective transform in
there which means that when we actually
go to fill the ground chunk everything
is kind of tiny and far away that we
splat in there so if we wanted to we
could fix that by just making the stamps
much bigger right but that's not
probably how we want to handle that
eventually I'm just gonna go ahead and
do that so you can kind of see what I
mean like so that's all yeah that's all
I'm talking about with that so let's let
that go ahead and do it's a little
splatting again it's gonna be
excruciatingly ly slow
and Jimmy alright dude to do again what
we're waiting for here is the
excruciating ly slow process of doing
like tons and tons and tons and tons and
tons and tons of splats into those
bitmaps right and it's producing 60
foreground chunks each of them has a
thousand twenty fourth blocks I don't
even know how my splats that hasn't it
little grand chunk let's see fill ground
chunk where's it a hundred and fifty so
swing 150 times a 64 it just takes
forever to fill all those guys in or
wait it's not even I don't even remember
how many how many actually were there
for those ground just grab buffers
around buffer count oops sixty-four yeah
alright excuse me
now if we can ever get back there so
there now what's kind of interesting
that looks like I made it much too large
all right let's try that one more time
I guess 5.0 was much too large see here
fill ground chunk and let's take that
down to two or something like this and
then of course I guess the other thing
we need to do is this thing right here
is not actually this is I'm gonna put
the to do in here basically to do once
we switch to orthographic stop
multiplying this basically we're not
covering a wide enough region right so
we need to do something like this to
make sure that we actually do cover it
because again we're actually doing
perspective transform into our actual
ground buffers which
makes no sense whatsoever but that's
just the way the render is set up at the
moment and so what we have to do is make
sure that we're actually covering the
whole thing in order for to get them big
enough so we'll see if that's actually
it's not quite there yet it needs to be
a little further out and also this you
know what I think I did it backwards I
think if they actually were too big
originally these guys are like way too
big I guess because they should be like
a half a meter and then these things
should be like 2 meters that you splat
on the backing plates I guess something
like that and that's kind of confusing
but yeah all right so we're getting
there slowly but surely and I guess
there really isn't that much to do here
do you think yeah I think what would
help I love to say it because I don't
actually want to have to do this but I
think what would help here is if the
they were actually if they were actually
layered properly right because I can't
tell which layer I'm looking at and it
makes it hard for me to tell what the
right sizes are for things right I also
don't understand why we're getting so
much yellow throat showing through I
guess it's because the backing parts are
still not quite big enough they should
be more like 3 metres wide I guess or
something like this but yeah and so
let's go ahead and sit here so I think
we may actually have to do one level of
sorting like I said didn't really want
to have to deal with that at this point
but yeah whatever is the next logical
thing to do is the next logical thing to
do yeah so let's make those a little
bigger here and these were a little too
tiny as well I feel like
so that's good I think producing those
ground chunks seems okay and if I'm
gonna sort these so here's one thing I
could do at the moment when I when I
render them right
I could only I could just only render
ones you know and gram buffer peasy you
know is within some region of zero right
it's like greater than or equal to 1.0 F
right and oops
negative one point away and grab buffer
P is less than one point here oops I
wanted that in world space so I actually
want the Delta if Delta Z and Delta Z so
if it's not if it's far from the camera
I'm not gonna draw it right and so I
just wanted to see if I could make that
do something reasonable right let's take
a look
oh how long it takes we really need to
optimize the renderer I'm not one for
slow turnaround times they always drive
me they drive me batty all right so
there's one layer if I'm not sure why
we're still we're not filling in over
here I wonder thoughts cuz we are we've
overflowed the number that we have to
use that couldn't either because now
we're doing so many depth layers there
but yeah so let's see if I come into the
game eventually hello it doesn't seem to
want me to do yeah it's crazy how slow
that is now it's gonna feel really good
to optimize this so I guess I mean
here's what I would say about this so I
feel like it wouldn't be it really
wouldn't be that onerous for us to
optimize some of this stuff it wouldn't
be inappropriate for us to optimize some
of this stuff right now because although
we haven't had a chance to finish what
we want to do for lighting the stuff
like the ground buffer compositing
ground buffer compositing we could
easily go ahead and do the optimization
for right because that's going to use a
bitmap lit that doesn't actually have
any lighting on it to produce those
tiles so I feel like because that's
causing such a problem we could optimize
the ground buffer build and then we
could call that that version the blip
that doesn't actually do anything that
doesn't actually do any lighting we
could call the blip that us do any
lighting for drawing the ground buffers
as well until we get the lighting
finalized and then we write the
optimized version of that
because there's nothing we're really
gonna be able to do when it's going too
slowly and we know we can speed this up
dramatically right from where it is so I
think that might just be the thing we do
next I don't know because hey we've got
a thing that's totally not usable right
now at speed so it would feel really
good to optimize it and usually that
seems to me to be the best time to do it
right because we're gonna be excited
about it and it's gonna be cool
so I would say maybe that's what we're
leave it I would say maybe that's what
we do next week next week we'll be like
our optimize the renderer pass and we'll
go ahead and do one optimized pixel fill
routine it'll be the unlit pixel fill
flit routine and we'll just do one there
because we can even do one to throw away
right we can do one that just you know
that we use temporarily because we'll
learn some stuff from optimizing that
that will guide us in our optimizations
for other stuff so that seems to be a
good idea to me that's what I think
we'll probably want to do that seems
that seems good alright so I'll leave it
there for now I think that's really all
I want to do it looks like those
actually layer in properly as well so
yeah we're pretty good we're in pretty
good shape
really what we're gonna have to do is
just go ahead and do one optimization
pass just so we can have a good renderer
feel so that things run fast enough
right but yeah I think that's about it
all right I'm pretty happy with that and
I've been wanting to do the optimization
stuff in the renderer for a while so it
gives me a good excuse it's like well we
can't really do anything if it's gonna
run that slowly you know other than just
turning stuff off and so I feel like
maybe now's a good time just go ahead
and do that and so what we could do you
know in there is essentially we've got
our draw rectangle slowly we can
basically make a draw a rectangle slowly
version that doesn't do lighting right
because since we don't really know how
we want to do the lighting yet you do a
draw a rectangle slowly that doesn't do
the lighting and that's optimized so
it'll actually do it'll just do this
exact same thing here but it'll be
optimized you know it'll be Cindy
optimized so we can go through and and
have all that work
that seems that seems reasonable to me
all right
so that's what we'll do we'll go to the
QA let's see here
so if you have a question go put Q colon
in front of it sorry seven there are 15
minutes left of the stream since you
went over in the pre stream there are
but do we really want a starch
optimization right now I don't know
that's a good question right I'm not
sure if that's a good idea or not I
don't think I want to I think I want to
stop it and then on Monday will you know
will do the beginning of the
optimization stuff and what we could do
is maybe take an extra 50 minutes that
day or something like that right no
stream tomorrow right that is correct no
stream tomorrow grumpy giant 56 how are
you going to handle the ground chunks on
the further layers would disappear while
still on screen well you need to expand
the visibility range based on layer
distance so I'm not sure what we want to
do about that but I think my my gut says
that what we'll want to do is
essentially have what amounts to like a
fog concept like a fog of war basically
because we that would apply not just to
ground chunks but to everything so if we
do the perspective foreshortening which
looks kind of cool so I feel like we
want to keep it if we do the perspective
foreshortening I feel like we just want
to introduce some art like an artistic
conceit to the style of the game
basically which is that you know only a
certain range is visible and it fogs out
to black or something there because
otherwise you could see just really far
and I mean maybe that's fine I mean
performance wise we may be fine we may
be able to handle it just fine
especially on the GPU path right but I
don't know if it has negative
implications for gameplay where like you
shouldn't be able to see all this stuff
that's you know that's around there
right so I don't know I think that's
going to have to be a gameplay call at
the end of the day and for now what
we'll do is we'll just let it be
but if we
turns out the gameplay it's fine well
then we will just expand we will just
expand the query region to be basically
like a you know like a pyramid or a
frustum as they might call it but if not
then we'll leave it as a rectangle
some elements in the ground are being
repeated now for some reason
what does repeated now meme in this case
some elements in the ground are being
repeated now yes all right can you be
more specific about what that means I'm
not sure what that means so I can't
really
corpse Lulu I'm afraid of using sorting
and stuff when making games because I'm
afraid that if I get too many items it
will slow down or shall I not worry
about that well you should worry about
it obviously but you should worry about
to the extent where you figure out how
many items you're likely to have and
then you figure out whether or not you
can sort that many right if you're
talking about having a thousand items
then you can definitely sort that many
if you're talking about having a hundred
million items then no you probably can't
right and so the question is not whether
you can sort stuff in a game the
question is how much stuff you can sort
in a game and you need to have some idea
of what the maximum bound is of the
number of items that you might be
working with right and so that's really
but that's true of everything right
that's true of any algorithm that isn't
Oh n you need to have some conception of
how it's going to scale up I mean even
onu have to have some idea of how it's
going to scale right to ha you could
always pick a number of items that will
break whatever the algorithm is that
you're using if it if it has to iterate
over things
I think it'd be really cool to see far
down for example floors made of ice or
glass yeah I agree with that
that would be kind of cool if you're in
a nice area in fact I'm gonna add that
to the thing since we've got it that
does sound like it would be pretty cool
so let me open up the reminders file
okay um
yeah I like that I like that a lot
well the memory footprint keep getting
bigger there's so much for a pixelated
being stored right now is this a concern
at all
will we be compressing data to save RAM
I imagine not but it still feels like
we're using too much memory for just a
2-d game correct me if I correct me if
and because I'm wrong so here's the
thing in terms of memory footprint this
is the way I look at it right the thing
you don't want to do is use memory for
no benefit right so like let's say
you're you know the Facebook front-end
for iPhone right and you just eat all of
the memory but you're not actually doing
anything it's just a stupid picture you
need to scroll or whatever that makes me
super grumpy because I'm like okay
you're making the performance of this
thing chuggy and it's weird and the
paging slow and it's crashing because
it's using too much memory and all this
other stuff and you didn't actually do
anything right you just you displayed
something really trivial and that makes
me very angry right but I am not angry
at all and in fact I am glad if a
program uses all of the memory in the
machine to do something cool right and
so what I would say is when this when
we're done with this game what we would
like to have happen is we would like to
take however much memories in the
machine and use all of it for something
cool right we would like to have a
plausible argument why every single
thing is you is being used for a cool
reason right and so if a you know if a
gamer bought a 16 megabyte obsessively
gigabyte of RAM machine right what we
want to do is use that 16 gigabytes of
RAM to give them game right and so it
doesn't matter that the games 2d I still
want to find as many things as I can use
the end users computer to give them
something cool if we're just wasting the
memory that's not so good but if we're
actually doing something interesting
then that's good
and so to me stuff like generating the
ground chunks is a great use of memory
because it means that now the user has
unique textures everywhere for their
whole world and that was a good use of
their system resources and so if a 2-d
game normally can't use
a 4 gigabyte graphics card or something
well here's a way we can start to try
and use some of that and it produces a
good effect right so the goal is never
to use the least amount of memory
there's really no benefit to that
because the memory in the machine is the
memory in the machine what you want to
do is use all of the memory but you want
to use it for something good you just
don't want to waste it you want to have
a reason why each part of its being used
and an argument of why using that extra
200 6 Meg's or whatever in here or in
another 50 Meg's there or whatever is
actually giving the user something good
or the ground chunks stored in some data
structure or are they recalculating each
frame at the moment they are not really
stored in a data structure but they're
not rejected every frame they're just in
an array and so what I wanted to do and
we talked about this briefly but we
haven't gotten there yet is they'll
probably end up being stored in the
world structure that's what I suspect
we're kind of going that direction you
can see that we almost already did that
it's right here right so eventually I
think that's what we'll probably do we
haven't quite gotten there yet there was
a horizontal repetition of some splats
but not all of them
I'm so I'm sorry I still don't really
know what that means
do you think you are roughly 1/5 of the
way through completing the game at this
point
yes I do
well we're not quite one fifth wheel of
a little bit more to go
timewise to one fifth but yeah I think
we're about one fifth we'll see when we
get to day 200 that's where I was
expecting to kind of stop working on
engine stuff
so are we halfway through the engine
right now yet probably that that sounds
about right
so seems correct to me
all right so repetition of horizontal
flats see if we can zoom this in a
little repetition of horizontal splats
so I don't I mean what you might be
seeing is just the fact that we don't
have very many flats in there and we're
not doing anything intelligent with them
so there's they tend to form similar
shape sometimes because of the low
number like that and that but they're
actually different right like you can
see that these things are actually not
the same but I don't know if that's what
you're thinking but yeah they're not
exactly they're they're actually
different right
when all Ram even on the GPU is used
when the game is put into the background
switching a short time to their
application all the memory has to be
swapped in and out right even to the GPU
or what strategy is used to prevent
swapping in and out of big memory chunks
so not all of it gets wok just however
much the application needs but yet it
gets swapped in and out and the answer
is you don't do anything to prevent that
right that's if the user wants to switch
to an application in the middle of
playing game then they get whatever they
get right as far as I'm concerned that
means they didn't care about how the
game experience was if you're in the
middle of switching to you know
Microsoft Excel or something then I
don't care about your performance right
like performance is only for someone
who's willing to run the game dedicated
and give it all the resources in their
machine and if they choose to give it
less resources than that then they're
gonna have a worse experience right and
that's fine and that's our decision and
that's also you know why I tend to think
like I like this sort of I would prefer
it if there was a more rigid boundary
there like I don't really like the fact
that Windows does multitasking on games
and stuff I would prefer that you
basically said okay we're gonna run this
game now and it gets all the resources
and if you want to switch out to
something else then it will essentially
pause the game and do sort of a very
significant swap out event where you
don't expect it to sort of half keep
running in the background and stuff like
that I would rather it be a little more
console like in that way but yeah
are we rotating and scaling the slaps on
the ground chunks to get the maximum
variability not yet we will do it
scaling rotation on the other hand we
can't quite do I don't think because the
the things kind of have a perspective
baked into them so I don't know how much
rotation we can do but we can scale them
in the future when we do the thing I
noticed the hero's head would clip
through the trees on occasion and then
it would fix itself what's causing that
that is actually
the same things I've talked about with
the sorting with the ground layers we
don't sort anything right now we're just
drawing everything to the screen in the
order in which we process it and so what
you were seeing there is just whatever
happened to be drawn first it's actually
the same reason why like say this tree
appears behind this one even though
logically it should be in front so what
we need to do to change that is we will
actually end up sorting stuff as it
comes out and will render it in the
correct order and that will fix the that
will fix both of those problems
alright looks like that's about it go
ahead and close this down here yeah okay
thanks everyone for joining me for
another episode of hand made here oh
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always I think we have gotten to the
point where it's time for us to do some
render optimizations so I think that's
what we're gonna do next week we are off
tomorrow there is no stream tomorrow on
Friday well spend a bit of a short week
but we should be back for a full week
next week Monday through Friday so I
hope you will join us for that it'll
should be fun when we start talking
about optimization topics so I'll try to
do a little bit of an introduction to
how to time code and then we'll talk a
little bit about how to do Sindhi
optimizations and that sort of stuff so
we'll start covering that stuff next
week and we'll get into some of the how
to you know basically figure out what's
actually taking the time and make a plan
about how we're going to solve it so I
think that should be a lot of fun I hope
you join me for that in the meantime if
you would like to play around with the
source code you can always get a copy of
it by going to hand-made here at Oregon
pre-ordering the game it comes with a
source code and you can play around with
that and and have fun learning from it
and all that sort of stuff if you want
to support the video series we do have a
patreon page you can pledge to we very
much appreciate that we also have a
forum site we can go to check out the
anti episode guide you can post
questions on the forums there and you
can also get ports to Mac and Linux
stuff like that and then there's also a
Twitter feed which tweets the schedule
at you so if you want to catch the
stream live that's the easiest way to
stay up to date on that so definitely
check that out if you've got to get a
chance so again there's no stream
tomorrow so I will see you guys on
Monday 5 p.m. Pacific Standard Time back
here on Twitch until then I hope
everyone has a wonderful weekend and I
will see you later