hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero show where we code a complete game
live on stream uh we are gonna probably
try to put some interesting
room designs into handmade hero today
i'm guessing
uh we were sort of like uh
last time wasn't last weekend because
obs pooped out on us last weekend
and we had to try and fix it hopefully
it'll stay working today we don't know
uh it worked for the pre-stream it might
work for the regular stream we'll see
so what we're gonna do today is probably
go in there and
use what we were doing uh two weekends
ago
when last we were able to program and
we're just gonna go ahead and and see if
we can put some interesting uh
room design in now that we have uh sort
of
ways of calling stuff that looks at the
entire
uh scene and you know like i said
mostly what we were doing that time was
we were just sort of re
trying to think of how i would call what
i would describe it as
we had sort of tried to make the system
a little bit too abstract at first
uh largely because we just didn't know
what we were doing i mean we didn't have
a plan for it we're just kind of putting
stuff in there
and i think we want it pretty hand coded
we don't want a lot of generic systems
in there just like doing stuff
because the game design side of things
is always very touchy and you want to
make a lot of little
like tweaks and so the goal is i'm just
trying to reorganize that code
so that in as so much as possible
i'm able to really like
hand code how things are decided you
know what i mean
um so we're trying to make a
scaffold like we're trying to make it so
that as much as possible
we don't have to think too hard about
where to put stuff in the code
so that we can make sort of arbitrary
uh game design tweaky stuff
that uh that creates the rooms
and probably we want to do this at all
levels so
again it's tough to give you a little
like
broader outline of what's going on um i
can even you know what we can even do
this now if
obs is still working let's let's find
out so just to give you
a slight outline of the idea
uh what we have right now is we
we want to start putting in like you
know gameplay stuff
because we're kind of out of engine
stuff to do and in order to put gameplay
stuff in there
we need ways of generating interesting
environments
from code because the idea is this
game's supposed to be sort of like a
binding of isaac
kind of feel to it in that you don't
explore
one specific world you like it generates
something for you each time
and when we do this it's it's important
that we
give ourselves the maximum amount of
flexibility
when programming the thing that
generates the world
because that's what the user is going to
be playing right they're going to be
interacting with this world
and so if we just kind of throw some
random numbers in there
and cross our fingers it's going to feel
exactly like that's what we did when
they play the game it's just gonna feel
like they're playing a bunch of random
numbers and it's not gonna be very
satisfying
so we need ways of hand coding
a lot of stuff like when we're like oh
it would be nice if when we put one of
these in the room there was a
sometimes this happened because that
makes an interesting gameplay thing
that's just human intuition and we need
to be able to like dump that
in to the generator easily so that we're
not struggling all the time to make
those things happen
at the same time it's a fairly
complicated problem because one of the
things that you get
with random generation is it's you've
got all these things happening at
different levels you've got
randomly placed rooms with randomly
placed goals and randomly placed
environments that randomly connect to
each other with random enemies
there's so much stuff in there that it
can be hard to organize that code
in such a way that allows all of it to
actually be smart about how it's doing
what it's doing
and so it's gonna be a little while i
think of
us just you know trying uh uh
architecturally trying things to get it
down to what is
what works well and is simple but that
also still
like actually allows us to generate what
we need to generate
uh in a convenient way so that's really
what we're doing
um and so we're just trying to feel out
where that is and
we previously on handmade hero didn't
really care about how things were
generated because we weren't trying to
do gameplay we were just doing engine
stuff and so it doesn't really matter
what we generate just as long as
generating anything
we can work on like the renderer or
whatever right
but now that we're actually trying to
say let's let's try to make the game
work in a way that's like fun to play or
that there's interesting things for the
player to do
in this world that's when we now need to
start saying look
the generation code is where all this
stuff is going to happen
every time we add something in the
gameplay code we're going to need to
back that up with it generating
you know interesting things happening in
the generator to expose that gameplay
we don't want that to be a pain in the
butt we need that to be nice and fluid
and so that's what we have to start
working on much like how we're starting
to work on the entity system
these two things are the gameplay part
right envy system and generation
are what determine the gameplay and so
we need to just refine these
uh to the point where it's very easy for
us to make
the changes uh that we need to make and
to make sure that the code operates in a
way
that allows us to express things cleanly
so that we're not struggling all the
time and cleanly is probably the wrong
word
succinctly so that we don't have to
constantly do all these like
larger systemic changes to make stuff
happen so that's what we're doing
um and we're going to give that a shot
right now some of that a shot right now
so if you take a look at how
we sort of left things you can see that
we just put like a little temporary door
it's just a stone graphic in there we
don't have a door graphic right now
um and when you hop on like a thing it
moves the door down or whatever
um and we have some stuff we wanted to
do gameplay wise
with the with the the pressure plates we
had some stuff we wanted to fix
we could fix those now too because
that's pretty straightforward but
mainly the thing we want to do is now
start putting
in pressure plate patterns into the room
and we kind of need rooms to um
we need to like work on that room
generation code so it's easy for us to
do things like
put down enemies
pressure plates and obstacles in a way
that works together
right and that's why i keep saying like
we need to make it more
hand coded in a way um because we just
don't currently have
any way of of expressing that stuff with
the way that we did
uh the generation code before right we
just don't have a way
we were just dumping things in and then
they randomly got placed
and that's really not going to cut it so
we're we we're trying to figure out ways
of making that be more
logical right that be more flexible
okay um so if we take a look at
the the energy generator code you can
see like the first change that we made
to try
and make oh how do we get this purple
that's a new four quarter thing we've
got like a bright purple for casey
is that like uh you know to let it let
me know it's me
um i don't even know
oh we look at this purple what's going
on with this crazy purple
ryan what's going on this crazy purple
that is some crazy purple right there
um anyway
i'm probably going to change that color
at some point
that is nuts um so we made one of the
first changes we wanted to make which is
you can see here that
now what happens is entities are not
generated individually they're generated
as part of patterns
and patterns are laid down inside their
own hand-coded routines
the reason i did this was again so that
i could hand code
crazy rules like whatever i want i
didn't have to make them fit some system
i could just have whatever crazy rule i
want and that
would uh be how you know it would be
laid out
so this is the first step in doing that
and now you can kind of see like all
right so the tile switch pattern for
example
we need to start making some tools that
allow me to lay these tiles out
easily right some way that i can make
the tile switch pattern
be intelligent and what you can see here
for example
is this tries to put uh four tiles down
right at the moment um
and it tries to put four tiles down but
so you know what i also noticed you know
i need to like have this male up there
so that i can do it uh my types aren't
highlighting anymore either
did you notice that like it used to be
that the types
would highlight um
but they don't anymore and i'm not sure
why um it might be because we haven't
actually set the correct thing but i
just wanna
if you'll excuse me for a moment i'm
just
just want to why don't types highlight
is this a setting and what
is this garish purple okay so i'll look
at those
those are probably actually pretty easy
answers
um i can probably figure them out myself
they're probably just settings
but uh i just want to note all of the
things that i noticed so that i can fine
tune it
all right so if we go ahead
and continue forward if we if we march
forward
um what i want to do is say all right
let's
try to make this grid thing um
let's try to make this pattern generator
actually generate patterns
uh that i care about right
so one way to do this there there's a
couple different things i might want to
do and i'm just going to kind of
mention them out loud so if you take a
look in here we've got this gen entity
pattern
this probably wants some parameters so
that when you put a pattern in a room
you can
you can specify stuff and things like
this
i don't really know exactly how i want
to do this but one thing i can pretty
much say
is you know we probably want something
in here that's like a difficulty
right um where we can just spam stuff
out there and say look when we call a
particular generator
we're going to want things in the room
to be coordinated in terms of how
difficult they are
so for example a really hard room might
generate
lots of patterns with high difficulty so
the enemy pattern
the tile switch pattern and the obstacle
pattern may all
be like hard lots of tiles with hard
restrictions
enemies with lots of hit points that do
a lot of damage these sorts of things
right
and similarly in other parts we may want
like a high difficulty tile pattern with
a low difficulty enemy
or low difficulty everything in
introductory areas right
so one thing that we probably want to do
is just carry a difficulty idea
idea along with the patterns so that
every
pattern generator can be tuned to be
able to generate things
reasonably and so like in here for
example
maybe when we look and we say like
random between like this
maybe in the tile switch pattern thing
we've got some ideas about how these
patterns
might go
um and there's probably going to be like
a lot of stuff in here
at first i'm just gonna say let's just
do
some simple patterns that have like you
know that generate some some pretty
simple sort of
directional things and uh
there's there's a couple things that we
probably want to add here which is
because
tiles are so important we probably also
want easy ways to test to see whether
there are tiles in places or not
right um and so that's something we
probably should add as well
like the grid should know so that as we
put things in the grid it knows like oh
here's where the tiles were or something
right
so we probably want that to happen as
well
all right so first things first i'm just
gonna do
uh some some simple setup stuff here
uh where maybe we break things down
into difficulty like i'm gonna say
like if the difficulty is uh
and maybe we'll just call the difficulty
d just because we're going to use it
everywhere
so if i say like all right the pattern i
get
called with the pattern right yeah so if
the pattern difficulty
is less than like you know 25 if it's
less than
75 uh and then otherwise this is like
the hardest or whatever right
um then what i might do is say let's
take the tile counts and we'll put the
tile counts
um in as like some kind of a you know
of a thing that gets set on each of
these paths
right so um and i'll initialize it to
zero because
why not i don't really need to but i
might as well
so in here if you know if it's less you
know maybe there's only like four tiles
or whatever in a simple case um
you know just something really really
basic or maybe maybe there's only like
very few so sometimes there's only one i
don't know
so we could look in here and say we're
going to take the entropy here
the grid itself so if we look at the
edit grid
[Music]
um
interesting product
i wonder what product means
i don't know um i'm not sure
this is pretty confusing so like i typed
in edit grid
right um and it looks like it
shows me everything in the file
edit grid for some reason and i have no
idea
why that would happen like none of these
things are edit grid
um maybe what it's saying is here's the
things that use
edit grid uh
but but it doesn't seem to because like
this doesn't use edit grid
at all
right so i feel like that's
really weird and i don't like that at
all um
i don't want it to find files at all
so let me let me add this it's gonna be
this thing of like making a bigger
bigger email
um why does
project search find file names
um maybe i called the wrong thing i
don't know
oh um
let me ask ryan it looks like ryan's
here
so i can ask ryan ryan and see
uh what what he has to say i don't know
if there's an answer there might be
we'll find out
um but but who knows
uh all right so anyway um i don't really
care because i don't really need it that
that badly
uh but again these are things i don't
wanna keep having these problems so i
just wanna get it to a good state and
leave it
so i'm hoping we can just you know iron
some of those out
so in the edit grid you can see that in
here the series
it comes in with the you know with the
grid
so i think i can just do something like
this where i just pull the series out
now
it's hard to say because it might be
that what i should do
is actually have the random like
random maybe should just be right on the
grid so that i don't even have to pull
it out
um but i don't know right
uh so so who knows
anyway so assuming we have the series in
here what i'm gonna do is say look
there's gonna be between
maybe one and four um tiles
in in those cases there's going to be
like between
four and 12 tiles in this case
uh and you know there's going to be
between um
maybe like 8 and 16 tiles in this case i
don't know
and we don't care i'm just trying to
like get some stuff set up that sort of
starts to look like something i could
imagine doing in
in-game programming in in game play
programming right
um and so when we do the tile counts
here
then what we need to do is figure out
what kind of patterns are going to be
and also like what kind of tiles they're
going to be
um because we want to have a couple
different tile
like types and so there's like a tile
there'd be like a tile rule
you know what i'm saying so there'd be
tiles that are like
you have to stand on this tile for a
certain number of seconds
potentially in order to trigger it right
um
so i feel like there's going to be a
couple things like that that we want to
set as well and those would get set in
here we just don't quite have that yet
so once we know how many tiles there are
then we have to kind of figure out what
kind of tile pattern we want to do
and the tile pattern i guess would be
like
um how it how it snakes through we can
have tile patterns like the tiles don't
have to be connected
but it probably is more fun to see them
connected a lot of the time
so we probably want to actually have
a specific idea of what kind of pattern
we're talking about
um
like
we probably want to choose like are we
doing a snake-like pattern
or a line-like pattern we probably want
these to be like hand-coded i guess is
what i'm saying we don't want them to be
random we want to say like
here's one that's like a one that goes
in directions and makes
turns right and here's one that you know
um that just randomly scatters
i don't know uh i don't have a concrete
idea but i just think we want there to
be
like we want there to be
discrete types of patterns and that the
player recognizes those patterns
specifically um
you know what i'm saying so like
and and to the point where this is
probably gonna be the sort of thing that
that even has its own like associated
nonsense right like it's probably gonna
have like
um
uh
something like this and and maybe we
even have you know like a
uh
a tracker
so we create one of these and we'd like
push you know
ones on there right and so i would
almost do like
okay we've got a tile pattern
um and we start making the tile pattern
by using different things and maybe we
have like a you know tile pattern
type and the tile pattern type
uh let's say there's just like line
um
[Music]
snake and scatter
i don't know so like scatter would just
kind of put them
[Music]
around line will just go in one straight
direction and snake will like bend
you know occasionally or something like
that
uh and so what we do here is say
you know what actually we can even make
this be like
uh
part of it so we do tile pattern pattern
right
and then in here we do pattern max tile
count
not moss stuck we do max tile count
to set it right and in here
we just go ahead and pick
the max tile count out of the series and
then in here we just do like
while pattern tile count is less than
pattern
max tile count you know pick
right um so we'd create this and this
way we can have functions that do
picking based on this sort of thing and
we can also do checking
you know what i mean
all right um
so the way that i would approach this is
i would say like
i would say uh for our tile pattern
thing here um
so i think what i want and again this is
all just me making stuff
up i'm not a game designer so please
just always take this stuff with a grain
of salt
i'm just doing the code that comes to
mind
based on having played games that's it
right so you know if you actually want
to know how to do
the process of deciding how to make this
stuff work
you really want to watch like john blows
stream not my stream
this is me just randomly saying
i'm going to place some patterns on the
floor
but i'm probably not doing it in a very
good way because there's probably
ways that if you did a lot of game
design code very well like john does
then you probably know how to do this
stuff right
um so i would i would highly recommend
not following
my logic of how i'm deciding what to do
here
you know i still feel like the way i
write code is good
if you can somehow separate that from
what i'm what i'm deciding to write
but you know please try to make that
separation your head as much as possible
because
the decision-making process here will be
poor right
uh so so you have to keep that in mind
because you know
you you want to take game design process
advice from an expert game designer
not an engine programmer engine
programmers don't know how to do game
design
so you know it's not it's not the right
person to listen to
so please keep that in the back of your
head this entire time
okay so anyway in here i just want to do
like a
a simple thing that's like uh
tile already exists or something
and so if you pass a tile pattern it'll
tell you if this particular
tile pattern has uh
this tile in it right so
at this particular position you know
what i'm saying and again i don't care
about this code right now so i'm
literally just going to write the
stupidest possible thing
i'm going to loop through all of the
tile indexes
in in the pattern and i'm just going to
see
if we've already placed one there we'll
reject it right
and that'll be that um i noticed four
coders indentations
is still broken also so that's another
one i should probably put in there
um it's weird it actually seems to is it
actually lining it up with that
uh i doubt that's true
no so it's just it's just a it's a
hard-coded four tabs in
for some reason it it looks like it's
correctly picking the hanging indent
but it's adding the actual tab stop
after the hanging indent for no reason
so so that's one
so uh um
ryan may may check the stream we'll see
uh let me let me go ahead and also
load in apps4coder bindings
so if we look at j
it's behind my head right now but if we
look at
the jump command
um
you can see like f4 search for
definition project wide
right um
if we search for edit grid
you can see that it just gives us like
every function that's in editgrid.h
or dot cpp even though all we really
wanted to know
is we really just wanted to jump to edit
grid
right um
so let me type this in f4
search for definition
project wide
right
and we don't know we don't really know
what's going on with that um
it's it's super weird uh
but you know i don't know what it's
doing it's doing something
anyway uh so i'm just going to look
through these and see
if the tile match
uh if the if the position that you're
going to put
um i'll call this i for index if the
tile that you're going to put in here
matches um then off you go
otherwise it doesn't right so the result
is false
the results equals you know
whether or not these two are equal tells
us the answer
and then we return the results
i've been trying to get in the habit of
not putting parentheses around my
returns because
there's no reason for it but i always do
it
um
i don't know why i got in the habit uh
it's been since
like i think literally since i was like
started programming c but i'm not sure
why i would have done that i don't know
who would have
told me to do that or why um
i i don't know uh so that that's a good
uh that's a good question so anyway
uh let me just go ahead and change this
name because that's right pattern
already exists so let's just call this
tiles
and we will uh
try placing these so the very first step
not is not very interesting
all i'm going to do
at first is make something
that
i guess we'll just say like
at first all we're gonna do is make
something that doesn't ever place
overlapping tiles
which is very simple right so all we're
gonna do
is say look let's start by
placing one tile maybe as a random tile
so you know maybe something
like this where we say find a random
open tile
and at the moment that's doing this
but we could just place it randomly so
who knows
um so at the moment anyway if we take a
look at these two
uh we could randomize those we'll leave
it placed at the center for now so that
it's easy for us to look at what's going
on
but then what i would say is so tile at
uh
rel index is probably what we want
so our gen v3s
in this case
yeah in this case so i'm just going to
do this and say
tell at rel index is going to be the
first
one that we put in there
and i guess i'm not sure
if if we can't find a place to put the
pattern i guess we just don't put in the
pattern
right that just is a failure you know i
mean i don't know
uh but but i guess that's
i guess that's what we would want um
so i think that's what i would do and
then i'll just say like uh a pen tile or
something
and we'll just say look we're gonna give
the tiles
this new um index here so we're going to
put one tile in there
and then what we're going to do is we're
going to keep going until
we we can't anymore so in here what
we'll do is say
uh you know maybe we do this for now
and again like i don't really want to
keep doing this so we're not going to do
this forever but
uh we'll just do a random unilateral uh
where we just say please give us random
tiles that are open
and if the thing we get back
uh happens to be
one of the ones we already placed
we just we just won't place it right
so if it's valid we keep going if it's
not i guess we break
so we say like look if that's okay and
then in here we just say
don't place the tile um
unless uh you know
if it's if it's already overlapping
right
now we have a problem here which is we
would loop forever
if we kept picking if there's only one
tile
um but it happens to be you know in
in the place of um
it happens to be somewhere that's open
but we can't place a tile because we
already placed the tile there
so we may want to do something more
like
you know let's do something more like
this
let's just try random placement and it's
probably true that this is a little bit
weak sauce but i just don't want to ever
have a case
where we can end up looping forever
trying to place things we can't place
so maybe what we do instead is say
look we're gonna go and we're gonna loop
for as long
as we can and we didn't
find the placement we needed so we just
give up
right at that point so then we go like
okay
you know find a random open tile if the
tile is valid
then we append it if it's not then we
don't and we can also say here like and
uh tile uh exists already or whatever
this function was uh tile
already exists so we can call that
to to verify that you know the it's
in this particular pattern um
doesn't already have that tile in it
right
all right so i'm not sure uh that this
is great
there may be some other issues with it
but we're just going to start with this
so i'm going to say that you know
the tiles um
are going to get tested here uh if we
get a tile
that actually works we're going to place
the
you know the tile in there uh and we're
gonna go from there
at the moment we're not gonna do
anything else interesting
we're just gonna leave it at that um we
don't have
that uh particular oh what is tile index
oh it's the number of the tile so in
this case
uh it's the tile count would be uh what
goes in there
and so we would do something like this
right and well you know when actually we
could even do
something more like this this is
probably a little bit
uh more sensible just so we can have
like a clean idea of when you added a
tile what index did it actually get
so that that's not so wishy-washy
right so if we say okay we take the tile
pattern in
we take in what the
gen v3 index is of it
then in here we just want to assert that
no one is trying to
pack in more tiles than than we allow
right um in fact we may even just do max
counts we may say look
uh you should not ever have uh
more than that as well so we'll say has
to be less than max count
has to be less than uh
the at i
and then we just do an insertion so
we'll literally just plop it in there
and
and that'll just you know allow us to to
quickly
sort of figure that out uh the result
index
uh is just whatever the place in the
array is
you know so that's that's easy for us to
provide
um and so now we're quote unquote
placing these in
uh and in theory uh
we should be able to have longer numbers
now uh maybe although the fact that now
i don't see anything means that that
failed spectacularly
um okay so let's go ahead and step
through this now and figure out
uh oh that's why
um so we want to check if it doesn't
exist not if it does
there we go um all right so now let's
take a look
uh and see what's up um it looks like
we're still only getting
one tile there so that seems broken
um oh and that's because this didn't get
fixed
random unilateral series
random unilateral series uh and so now
we should just get scattered tiles um
uh that are sort of placed throughout
the room
and and there's an example although i'm
not sure why
there's only one again still a little
bit weird uh
so that doesn't seem quite right uh
it should give us randomization between
one and four
when we set the max count up so when we
insert these
when we find a random open tile at a
random location
here we should
this may be a case where this doesn't
actually
work for all i know um so we can
double check that but um
this seems fine like though like this
should do it it looks like this will
search it just fine right so it uses the
the
uv to to kind of like um
figure out the distance and then it just
you know loops over the tiles and tries
to find them so i feel like we can
verify that that's actually returning
different stuff but i don't actually
know
as i spill water all over myself i like
this water bottle but it's it's very
wide-mouthed
and when you if you're not careful when
you take a big sip
you definitely get it um you definitely
get it all over you
uh so not not the best
not the best uh but you know what you
gonna do
okay uh so let me just see what's going
on here because this doesn't
this doesn't seem good it could be that
this is failing so the tile already
exists
could be failing um as well so let me
just let me just because we just
slapped that in there let me just make
sure that there's not an obvious problem
with that before we
go any further uh but so you take a look
here you say okay loop through
i'm gonna rename this to tiles to just
be consistent
again not a good day for programming
um just being sloppy today
it's supposed to be not or equal to
um so this should be
let's just do it this way
so if we find a tile then we say look
there's already a tile there
and we break that's what that probably
should have looked like
um but anyway so for some reason we're
only placing one tile
and we should force it to place multiple
tiles so we know that it's not
a random number generation thing but you
know the random number generator should
not be able to generate
one like an infinite number of times
right so it seems pretty clear that it's
not
actually working it is picking one
random tile but somehow it's never
picking any more
than one right so something's busted
there
uh and oh although that
was a room with multiple tiles all right
maybe i spoke too soon hold on a second
so let's also do this where we just say
let's set max count equal to four so we
know there should always be four
and let's just see what it does because
i have no idea
um
so in this particular case it looks like
it actually generated four tiles
there's one down here which we can't the
camera doesn't work when you hop out of
the room like that we should probably
fix the stairs
um one of these days
um but all right so no
the random number generator was just
constantly picking
one somehow
super confused right now i don't know
how that's possible
but that seems to be the case
um so that's weird uh
let's go ahead and and find out what is
going on
with that um
is our random number generator just
super crappy
so this is like an xor shift
right
all right um
let's just do this uh cause cause that
that makes me a grumpy puppy
um and i don't wanna be a grumpy puppy
so here's a question let's suppose that
right in the middle of this for no
apparent reason
uh i'm gonna go ahead and say let's
switch to
debug build like so
um and i'm gonna ask for a histogram
of these sizes and i want to know
like what the random number generator
piece of crap that's in there right now
is doing
uh because i don't like it so what we're
going to do is we're just going to say
4 hist
test equals zero his test is less than
some
number his test
uh and then what i'm going to do is say
okay there's a
histogram um the histogram is going to
have
four things in it because that's what we
did before they're gonna be initialized
to zero
and i'm gonna do a random between zero
and three
uh
which should give us exactly those
things right
so then we can say histogram um
plus plus so so essentially what i'm
doing is i'm just saying look i'm gonna
make
four buckets i'm gonna ask the random
random
number generator if it is
in fact a random number generator to
give me a random number between zero and
three i'm going to count how
lo how often it lands in each of the
four buckets i'm gonna let
run that a bunch of times and then we're
just gonna look and see
like what the heck uh it actually
was and to make it a little easier on
myself
um i'll also just really quickly
do a thing here where i
loop over
[Music]
each of the
each of the histogram values
and just divide by the total so like uh
so i'm going to grab this total count
here
i'm just going to say like do that many
and the hiss percent for each one of
these
buckets i just want that to be equal
to a percentage value
that i can read so like a hundred
percent
times uh a floating point
version of the thing
uh in that bucket so the histogram
at that bucket i just want to make it
into a percentage
and there's no reason for that other
than than me
just wanting to be able to um
read it easily so i can just look at a
percentage and say what percentage went
into each bucket
and i don't want these percentages to be
like widely
different right so i really don't want
to see
them all go into one bucket and none go
into the other and that is just a way of
me
trying to convince myself that the
random number generator works at all
which at this point who knows if it does
we didn't really write one on stream
ever
um so like you know
all right i mean
hard to argue with that right
not to be taken for a con job here
though
let's just find out what happens in a
small number of cases
um just to make sure there aren't like
weird like period problems
where it just like gets into states
where i'll often pick the same thing
but
i mean i guess what i would say about
that
is there's nothing particularly bad
about that
necessarily because you know it's random
it's not supposed to be uniform
distribution
over a very small series of numbers
so i don't know that i would consider
that an issue
right
it's really hard to say what you want to
have happen there
so i'm going to do i'm going to do
something here that's
a little bit um funky uh
but i just again i'm just not sure
i wanna make sure i'm like comfortable
with what's going on
i'm not 100 sure i am uh so what i might
do here is just say
look why don't you give me um
like a a random series here that i'm
just gonna
try doing some munging on
um and yeah you know like
i don't know
maybe maybe that um
i'm not sure um
so i'm just gonna go ahead and dump some
random uh
pseudo assembly-ish code in here and see
what i think about when i actually
um get some random numbers so
let's do like um
like a test series here uh
and we'll just go ahead and and do a few
rounds of aes on it
and just see what happens right
so um
how do you set zero on an on an si 128
or can you
can you yeah i never know i never
remember what the heck
things are all right so let's suppose
that we just like
mix up a uh
you know assembly register a bunch of
times
and then what we do is instead of doing
random between like we were here so
like here's the way we were picking the
index before
you know um and we're not gonna do that
this time
instead what we're gonna do is we're
gonna mix this guy let's say we run
three rounds
of this how how expensive
is the one that's in there right now so
the one that's in there right now is
a bunch of dependent shift xors
so this is like
six cycles so
this would be significantly more
expensive than cis cycles
this would be eight cycles so
so let's see what happens if we just do
eight cycles
with an asni mix let's just
just do that um and then we'll
try extracting one of these i don't know
what the easiest way to extract these is
at the moment
but uh is it like maybe
uh maybe one of these
the the intel intrinsic naming is always
just
i never have any the heck idea
what the stuff is um
all right hold on a second
let's look it up as we always do
because i never remember what the
intrinsics are
they always boggle my mind uh
so convert uh
like is it is it an epi
um
is it like a is it this
okay so this is why i always get it
wrong so
so the thing you're converting from goes
next to the cvt
i gotta like get that into my head right
so it's
cvt si 128 underscore si32
so
[Music]
so it's that and also it's converting
the
yeah i mean well it doesn't matter point
being i
i probably am never going to remember
these let's just be honest i'm going to
be looking them up in that thing forever
all right so that would get us out and
index
and then we need to mod it for at the
moment i mean
for right now we can just end it with
what we were doing so that's not that
big a deal but
so in here we know that we we just want
a number between zero and four
um well i'll just do this for now but
you know we could just do an and right
so that's pretty easy but point being
i'm just doing a check to see what the
histogram
says on something that's a different way
of generating
uh these numbers so if i do that uh what
do i get
so that looks like a similar
distribution to me
on 100 i mean on a thousand
right to the other one um i'm gonna also
try slightly more mixing and just see
what happens
uh but that may be okay
um trying to get it right at the end
there there we go
um so
you know it doesn't it doesn't seem
better right uh
and we can try it on a 100 but again it
doesn't seem
like there's really anything
particularly great about it
so we're just gonna assume
so it seems like the distribution is not
particularly
different um to me
so so that all seems fine and if we went
back up to the
number before i assumed this would also
give i i could have like
not done a very good job with that part
of it but no so it's so it's
nice and distributed so i don't know
seems okay
um not
not a real issue so i guess it's just
it was picking one a lot of the time
for some reason right
um
i don't have an explanation for that but
i guess that's just the way the random
cookie crumbled
right i mean that's just that's just
what happened
so uh
okay back to our story
um
so now i want to try making some
you know differences in how these things
are picked so
for example in here where we uh i said
like
let's make um a couple of these
right so in here what i want to do is is
maybe just do a switch
on the the type
so uh in the tile set um
maybe instead of lying this would be
like horizontal and vertical
you know what i'm saying bro
um
i don't know why there's a semicolon
there don't need that
i will say c did not do a great job uh
with the whole semicolon versus not
semicolon thing
you can understand when looking at the
parser like why it is the way it is but
it's
it's just not it's not particularly
great
um anyway so if we take a look
at uh each of these it should be pretty
easy for us to
determine how to extend the pattern
uh in either case right
so if if we're going to do
[Music]
in in any of these cases uh
you know regardless of
of which ones we do and there's some
cool stuff we can do here but
in any of these cases we can start with
a random open tile
on the first tile so
so this right um
this happens uh any time
we don't have any tiles yet if
the tiles count is zero
then we do that if the tiles count is
non-zero
we find a tile based on some rules about
uh how we want this to work
now i would also argue that
like there's probably two of these
uh
as well so like a snake would never
branch it would just be sequential tiles
but that go in any direction
a branching one is one where like you
can go from anywhere to anywhere
right um
yeah i'm kind of cold
can i be real with you right now i am
i'm cold right now like
i don't quite understand
my it seems like my
master plan for
lighting the studio worked better than
i had originally anticipated
because one of my main goals for doing
the lighting here
was for it to take up no space and not
generate any heat
and it seems like i was able to do both
of those things
uh however the downside is that
i am now cold so
so that happened in the summer we'll be
happy in the in the winter
we are sad um
okay so moving on
um moving on and on
chris flatt so
here's the thing about the webcam i
asked people
i was like should i mirror it or not and
i try and i showed both on stream people
didn't want
it mirrored
people didn't want it mirrored so
so you're gonna have to like you guys
need to have some arguments
you know you need to have some arguments
amongst yourselves
and figure out uh
you know because i was thinking mirrored
as well i was like shouldn't i be facing
the code but like people didn't want
that
and so i feel like there needs to be
some kind of like internal
war for dominance where um
you know there's lots of casualties and
everyone dies and it's a bloodbath but
in the end
we know whether it should be mirrored or
not right
um and so
i don't know if it's local to me but i'm
getting a lot of pixel flickering on the
four coder capture
um
interesting so
[Music]
so i don't know what that's from
i i can pretty much
say that at least looking at the raw
capture there's no flickering on the raw
capture
now what goes out the wire i don't know
um but like the raw capture there
doesn't seem to be pixel flickers so
it may be for the compression
uh are the people who are noticing
flickr are they
on source stream quality or are they on
some other stream quality would be my
other question
because it could also be twitch
introducing it i don't know
so so think about that you i'm gonna go
back
to programming this um but
but you guys should figure it out
on source it's very subtle so my guess
would be that it's
probably obs when it it's
it's lipstick x64 right libec64
probably has problems with it maybe
um you know what i'm saying to you
uh libx 64 may be
sucking um and and we may be able to fix
that
uh by changing the settings for
libx 264.
actually wait a second
we can't fix this now because the stream
is live but actually
are is this still using the amd encoder
no so it's it's set at the moment it is
set to use
x 264
uh as the encoder so
we aren't getting the weird amd bugs
which
which were causing really bad stuff not
flicker they were causing like weird
wave
patterns and it was nuts um
so those are fixed but we may be able to
just change some of the settings on x264
so
when maybe when we're done we'll take a
look at that nothing i can do about it
now because you'd have to change
you have to shut the stream down but
uh but that could be i'm not sure
um but but yeah
all right um so moving on uh
if we if we want to here
the first time if we don't have any
tiles then we need to pick
one randomly if we do have tiles we want
to pick one based on a rule
where the rule uh
allows us to like look around so so
if i do find random open tile um
it looks like this function is all i
would really need
so so i should be able to like move
um around uh if we if we take a look at
edit tile here for example
um in there we should just be able to
adjust this
however we wish right
so if i say um
we come in here we would say
like let's just do each of these in turn
so if we were to do tile
paddle pattern horizontal then what we
would do
is take like the largest tile
pro i'm just guessing right but we would
say like okay
so we'd take the largest one and we'd
say like tile at also this tile at
um uh here
should probably be like a
grid and
we probably would seed it
with so like
even we might even go so far as to do
this
you know i'm saying so we'd start with
the largest tile
by default at tile at and then we would
do something
um like
is valid and traversable
is open
and it doesn't already exist right
so right i mean maybe i don't know
um so in here we would just say look
we're gonna start with one
and if it's horizontal we're just gonna
try
looking in a horizontal direction
uh we can make this better but for now
i'm literally just gonna say
like okay so it's you know it's going
that way
um and so you know here's
us searching in in various directions um
for snake we would just randomly pick a
direction
and when we randomly pick a direction
um so
so the the problem that we're gonna have
is we just want to
only have one or the other so we would
probably do
something like
i don't know
i mean something like this
you know so it'd just be like all right
you know the rel index
plus equals some random direction
uh i
what the heck no
so i i'm assuming we have like a
random in array kind of thing
no random unilateral
um random between
random next do we don't we don't just
have a random count
random choice that's it
random choice
that's all i really wanted um so we'll
just do a random choice of direction
there
um and the same would be true in the
branching case
um in fact i'll pop that out so that
anyone can use
it and the only difference here would be
i would say that like
the tile that we start from would change
so in the branching case
i will pick
um first i i do still want this
i will pick a random choice of tile
as well so random choice
series tile count right so like that
so yeah whatevs
um for scatter i don't know
[Music]
um
is there no plus equals
tile pattern
i agree with you uh what did we call
this
oh we didn't so let's just say there's a
type
like so and
what is the problem
missing i agree
is that better
all right so our gen v3
looks like it doesn't have an operator
plus equals
i not oh so it's just a v3s
oh why did we call it i guess we just
like
didn't remove that type i was wondering
about that
um all right so our v3s
we can't search for operator either yeah
oh well
yep um
that's too bad anyway we don't have an
operator plus equals so let's just put
one in
um and you know that seems fine
so operator plus v3s
uh you know there just needs to be a
plus equals
so i'm just gonna say like okay
here's the plus equals
um i guess
the way you write these and see
would be this
right um so
we would add these two together and
it should call this right uh operator
plus is ambiguous
how is it ambiguous
what is ambiguous about that
oh just forgot the equals
um so anyway that should allow us to do
plus equals which we want to be able to
do
no reason not to um and now we've got
different patterns
um the pattern is not being selected
right now
so it should always be horizontal which
in this case it was
so we should just see like lines
randomly in the world
um of these patterns uh where it just
randomly picks a number and they're as
long as the number is
really no one hopped on that yet all
right uh so if i go ahead and
head out through the world i should just
see only lines and that is what i see
um and and everyone's happy
um and and no one cares
so now let's try some other stuff uh oh
we didn't implement scatter case so in
scatter case
i don't think you know no one cares what
that does
but uh basically that would just be
you know um
i don't know what the range would be
so if it's negative five and the random
choice would give you up to ten so
oh i've ran in between
so let's just say you know it's
there's some kind of radius i don't even
know i don't care
at the moment but we'll just do
something where we randomly pick
a scattering amount um
and so it can scatter and then from
there
we can now try some of these out so
let me like um hardcode this for now
let's say i want eight things and i want
them in
in like the vertical pattern
uh it might be hard to
pick that though a lot of them won't
work we should probably do some retries
because you wouldn't be able to fit
eight vertically so yeah that won't work
um so we can we can put in some lower
number
we should do some retries uh so so
here's another thing let's do that let's
do retries too
let's let's do a double retry um
pattern here uh this is just gonna be
we're just sucking down the cpu
like it's nobody's business um
so let's just move this out so what we
can do
is when we create this tile pattern
right we can just create it without ever
actually creating the tiles
um so then we can come out out here uh
that was very canadian we can come out
out here buddy
and uh we can
create the actual tiles after the fact
right
and if i look at the get tile function
um it looks
like
it looks like i can just pipe that
directly in so i
think and let's see if this is true
i think i can just do like look grid
um with with whatever the
the tiles at i like
things are i should be able to just
do this you know what i'm saying
uh so i i think that would work
oh i can't even pass the gen v3 okay
it's even easier than that it's
literally just that
um so i just do like okay you know get
that tile out and create
things so now it should be able to
create stuff
after it's already got the whole pattern
that it wanted to place
you know what i mean um and off it goes
i gotta actually hop on it there we go
get out of here we gotta add combat
because
that skeleton is getting annoying and i
want to be able to punch it
um oh thank you mr skeleton
i don't know how we're going to fix the
fact that if a snake winds itself into a
corner it's unable to hop
out right because the rule for snakes is
the body has to hop
in the same pattern as the head so if
the head winds itself into a corner it
literally can't get out which
i don't know what we should do about
that maybe the
allow the head to hop over
itself you got me
like i said i ain't no game designer bro
that's a game design question
and i don't know this will get fixed by
me just be able to punch this dude but
you know i don't know i don't know what
you should what what's the game design
answer there
so uh if we do it this way uh now we can
just do the tile pens
pretty pretty trivially and that's all
fine
so let's try some of the other ones now
uh
tile pattern snake
and this should just create a contiguous
line but the line
shouldn't uh or won't necessarily go
in any particular direction right so it
can create
uh any any connected region
that doesn't ever split so
so you know so far so good um those are
all
what you would expect um
[Music]
and come on get out of my way
uh yep and let me let me
make that be a longer pattern so that we
can just kind of verify
um what's going on here
uh oh that's cool it even goes
downstairs we gotta fix that camera so
that it's going outside the room is a
problem
we just need one that doesn't create
stairs
so i i don't actually know what what is
the answer
to that why why is that happening you
know what
we've pretty much this is basically done
let me test it and then we're gonna go
fix the stupid stairs like i don't even
know why the stairs are doing that like
i have no idea why we're creating stairs
down to nowhere
um so somebody should probably do
something about that
and that somebody is gonna have to be me
because i'm the only one here um
but it looks like the snake one is
working fine
um so that's so that's fine
and uh
and no one cares so uh let's try
branching
um well you know what let's let's just
make this pattern larger so
let's let's make a really large pattern
and verify that the snake still looks
snakey
um and then we'll see if the branching
looks branchy
right oh
um what's the maximum count of tile
patterns
i don't even know
um so it's like only 12
uh which is not great like we probably
want more than that
um so i'm gonna say like
buckle up friends brains are big you
know
um they are large and you're gonna have
to
like get with the program
um so
uh again hard to say like but it
you know that's definitely a legal
pattern we don't know for sure that it
didn't branch
but we we know that that's valid
what i will say is i don't love the look
of it
so i might say that snake should maybe
check to make sure
that in general it doesn't place it
next to more than one so like
if i look at how the snake
thing worked
um so
so this code
[Music]
um
ugh
i think what i would want to do is say
when we place a tile
if you're going to if you were about to
place a tile
that would be next to a tile other than
the previous tile
don't place the tile i think that's more
what i would consider
a snake pattern
you know um
i don't i don't know like i just think
that
might be a thing um
and and you could see why you would
want that in either case so like
i'm just gonna i'm just literally making
this up
but let's suppose in here
there's a thing that's like
um max neighbor
count or something uh
and so in here we'd say like the max
neighbor count
um is like four which is the highest it
could possibly be
but then other people
would say um
oh oh and we could do zeros installation
here i could instead say
required empty
neighbor account right
so we could say like look normally it
doesn't require their
empty neighbors it doesn't matter
um but in here we would just say like oh
okay
if we change it to the snake tile
pattern
then we may want to set the required
empty neighbor count to
three meaning every time we place one
you're not allowed to place it somewhere
that has
more than just one neighbor which is
whichever the last one was
uh that you placed and so then in here
we would count the neighbors so we'd do
something like this
um in fact mr uh direction
here uh would actually help us out
tremendously
so we could do something uh like this
where we said you know test for empty
neighbors here
so we have like empty neighbor count
uh equals zero we'll count the empty
neighbors and then we'll say
if the empty neighbor count is less than
the required
empty neighbor count i'm sorry uh
greater than or equal to
um then we go ahead and imp append
uh the tile um
and
and off we go right
so so that seems good and what we'll do
here is we'll just say like dur index
equals zero during
less than array count der plus plus
der index um and then what we can say
is that thing we were doing before where
we say
uh uh tile already exists
so we'll just do tile already exists
uh
for whatever that direction is so we'll
just say
if a tile already exists um well
more specifically i guess i'll say if a
tile doesn't already exist then the
neighbor count goes up
right all right
um so maybe that works maybe it doesn't
who's to say um that looks great
and so now that produces patterns that
are more like
game e to me right it's it's not
placing patterns in locations that
oh i i don't know every time we hop
below the floor level the camera
doesn't know where to go you notice that
it's this is what's above us
right the camera like that you know it's
if we had a if we're at the point we're
actually
in ship mode we would start to write
these down but pretty far from there
um all right so that is a much better
pattern place or
in my opinion and now you can really see
the snake-like nature
of these particular uh patterns
um and that's great uh and everyone
loves it
and the game sold millions of copies on
the epic steam store
so now if we just you know hop around
and such uh you know it's good
um that all looks good so let's try
some other things now let's try
um branching
and branching can still keep that
constraint but we may also want to
reduce that constraint
depending on how we want things to go
but now you can see we're creating some
nice paths
that like have branches in them which is
another thing we want
from a gameplay perspective and we may
want to improve
the like quality of those choices but
you know gives a
who cares is what i meant to say that's
like the
fourth swear on handmade hero we're
going so well
i should have just marked the stream as
adult at the beginning
we need us so we need a thing um
on the episode guide so we can actually
get a definitive
number of times that there was a cuss
word it's been
very few uh but
but i i do not know how many um
but it's been very few i i just don't
actually know
um
is it four
i feel like miblo probably knows
um they're because they're probably
marked but
i don't know
um all right so anyway uh if we want to
now check the scatter pattern
which is the only other one that we
haven't actually tested although i
didn't test the horizontal and vertical
with the required empty neighbor count
but i don't see why those would be
affected so we're probably
we don't really need to do much there um
so let's try the scatter pattern
here's the scatter pattern
that looks pretty good um and the other
cool thing about that is now that we
have this we could also require the
empty neighbor count to be four
and that would put uh only disconnected
um pieces right so that that's pretty
cool too
so so even with just that small bit of
code we've got a lot of options now
so i'm happy with that i think that's
great
um that gives me uh everything i need i
think
um
does anyone know no one knows
anyway uh so now
i think let's fix the uh why are there
stairs
down to nowhere problem um
because that should be pretty
straightforward we should fix that we
can also fix the pressure plates
but we're in good shape here uh
and i also don't know
um so so do we have
lights that light up
i i don't i don't know that we do
so so the the other thing that's a
little annoying
is like
when i generate one of these tiles it
doesn't actually
put so so if you look at what happens
here right if there's a thing that just
changes the color
of the tile but i feel like we also want
a thing that's like
pieces one
um or just you add a piece like i feel
like we want to add
a light you know so so i
like this thing here where we we take
the entity
i i feel like it wants to add um
a light that's placed over
these patterns um
and so
like i don't know
how this should work um
because we haven't really thought this
through but
so so i'm not sure uh about that
but argument three yep
too used to using v3s is here um because
i kind of wanted lights on top of the
tiles
as well um and
so i'm not sure uh
if i draw lights i just want to see if i
can get
lights added on top of each of
the tiles in some way that we can
readily identify
so if i go into the entity code uh
where it draws that there's like a thing
that'll draw like lights
to the extent that there are any lights
um
and so i was wondering if i could just
just put that in there so so like this
code
you know um if i turn that on
we should see like lights and there they
are right so
unfortunately they're like embedded in
the thing which is kind of dumb so i
probably needed to fix that so
you know let's suppose that it was more
like that um
and now if we run
this i'm just wondering if we can get
lights
above our things yeah
so that works a little bit better and so
if if those lights are there
then what i was wondering is like could
the lights kind of follow
the pattern like of being lit or not
meaning that in here if i have these
lights and i just
say well uh
maybe there's no immission color
for the thing uh at first
right and and this thing
again i really don't know because this
isn't my
area of expertise right but like i'm
just thinking like
if the lights um lit up
when you stepped on them you know what
i'm saying uh
so so in here when we have the switches
there's like a thing where
it sets the color so so that's
that's like how the color gets set you
could imagine
like this happening
so it's color emissions so basically
it's like you know
if if it i don't know
um so like in this case right
we're just hopping around and
and the lighting is just you know
whatever
and then i hop on one of those well that
didn't look like it actually turned on
that light at all
also the fact that i'm not seeing any
lights right now
is a little disquieting where have all
the lights gone
that's super creepy
did you notice that
we have to take a look at what's going
on there because i don't really know
um but it's pretty weird
so like this room has lights in it
um and the other room doesn't
like the lighting it just didn't place
any lights in that room
i guess so that's pretty creepy
this room has lights but it doesn't look
like there are any lights
in in our actual where we just
said that i wanted to place them so
that's
weird as well um
i don't have an explanation for that so
in here we're
doing an ad piece light call and you can
see it adding the piece
that's occurring right i mean
uh in entity gen
i mean that that seems all right let me
just
double check that that i'm doing what i
think i'm doing
so there's the entity there's the radius
the offset
the emission and the color the color and
the emission just get
bundled together right um
which is not particularly interesting
the the
ad piece call that's getting called here
it's just an asset tag which we don't
care about
at all um so we're just
spamming the radius three times placing
an offset
and the color that should just work
right so
i don't
oh wait but
no that i mean that should just work
right so i'm not sure
what's the problem why are we not
getting
why are we not able to see this
um i i don't quite
follow because i feel like i should be
able to see that
and something's off right the fact that
i can't that
i i don't think there's anything weird
going on and and in here
what was weird even weirder is when i
had this set
to something
um
it actually worked so so when i did an
ad piece light from before
um it actually worked meaning we saw
them so
it's really strange that i can't change
it after the fact
or something uh i don't know what's
going on there
right you see all of the things and then
somehow like like this wasn't changing
so why is that not the only place that
that
would need to change is there something
more to it than that
um
it's still like kind of impossible to
use this to find anything
i'm hoping we can get this fixed because
this takes forever
it's take would be faster for me to just
go to the file myself right um
okay so in here uh for those pieces
is there some other thing
[Music]
that like
what what else would need to happen
is this just a case of like passing this
down
oh so you know here's a question for you
is this just a case of like the
brightness here
is too bright uh and like you can't
actually set numbers up that high i
thought you could
but i don't know now that i think about
it i don't know
how we have set up the lighting stuff
yet in that way
right so let's take a quick pause and
see if maybe that's
actually what's happening there
because that could be all it is
yeah okay so it's just a case of like
that being too hot now so i don't know
is
is one the brightest thing like what's
the brightest thing
when we're actually adding lights like
here
what we're passing like 10 and crap
right
so i don't understand why that
you know wouldn't work that should make
a light
bright green light
at that location yeah i mean
am i wrong about that um
that'd be my guess um
but it it definitely doesn't do that
right
like it's like that code never got
called
um
so i'm i'm clearly wrong
about that i i'm like just not
understanding something about the way
these lights are working
right because they don't seem to be
doing anything
like you don't see even any bounce on
the wall
there
and so if i were to add that as a
standard piece of lighting
and this could just be bugs in our
lighting code right because the lighting
code's kind of crappy
um but but something's up and so
if we take a look at what happens with
the tiles there
um if i was to do add piece light
oh are there maybe multiple pieces
already in the thing somehow
could that be why
like like is it possible that this is
actually
uh uh not
piece zero
we should check that out that could be
it could be that this is the wrong one
right so like you know
if it turned out there was actually
secretly another piece on there
and we had to set piece two or something
then that might make more sense
i'm not optimistic about that right
um yeah that doesn't seem to have
changed anything
but so i don't know
um that's a really confusing
but let's step in in the debugger and
just see what the heck is going on
because i have no
idea right um
none whatsoever so i'm gonna go ahead
and build this in debug mode and i'm
gonna look to
see like if there's some
magical nonsense happening there the
first i'm gonna do
is just look at this code to see what it
actually adds
just so i make sure that that's not
something strange
so i'm gonna inside entitygen
um i'm gonna just stop right here
and just see what's going on so if we
take a look at the tile um
and i look at the pieces i just want to
know how many pieces there are
and what the count is
okay so so it does look like that's the
case so it
it's there are three pieces
why are there three pieces who is adding
three pieces to this thing
um
so i have no idea why that would be
happening
why would there be three pieces added to
this
thing like
when we place down the structural
entities you don't
place like we don't place pieces on them
do we or do we
so in the room gen
code uh you can see us
placing a piece right here right
um but then
does anyone
oh
my well well well
so actually as it turns out
i'm totally wrong about that
so these are occluder pieces
that are placed in the environment
that we use to create sort of like a
ceiling
very interesting and if i look at place
tree
the tree why would we place an occluder
on the envy this is just stupid
like this is the thing that places the
tree
the ad tree thing should place the
occludor
right so i don't know what the heck
this is supposed to do that is just
dumb right um
because this is actually the code
that you would want
it goes on the tree it doesn't go
in the square so that's nonsense
right total nonsense um
so then the question is just what kind
of nonsense is this
so it looks like there's an occluder the
occluder
is uh placed
overlapping and then there's a ceiling
one
right um
so it does actually look like i was
right
there are more in there um so all right
so it's it's this right
um where we would want to to change uh
which light it is so like you know
and this is not particularly good we
should probably do something other than
this but for right now i'm okay with it
and i don't really remember exactly how
we test to see if something is a light
also i have no idea why there's nothing
right here but okay
uh i also don't know is entity piece
asset
actually being used still
no it's not so goodbye to you as well
all right um so what we want to do here
is say like if this is a light
we're going to change the light that was
all that i was going to say
so in here it would it would literally
just be
that i think
and then we'll see uh what happens
so so all right that seems fine
and uh you know we should probably do
we should oh god no
no no what is happening don't run the
game
um so we should probably do some cleanup
on like debug switches
at some point so that we can quickly
check light locations and stuff like
that without having to actually do any
kinds of like just on hot keys you know
um because it's something we're gonna
want puss
hello
do you wanna say hello here say hello
come on come up and say hello okay
do you want to say hello here come on
come on
there you go there you go no it's over
baby it's over there
it's over there sweetie here here
there you go can you see
can you see do you want to say anything
to the audience
do you want to say anything
are you are you happy puss are you happy
what is going on
you're probably on unhappy about your
flea medicine still huh
it's only once every few months but it's
important
what do you think what do you think
hm i got to finish the stream but then
we can play after
okay you want to do that
okay let's go down let's go down
you just had your lunch huh no actually
you had a lunch
quite some time ago i don't know
all right um just finishing up
uh let's see so that should create like
green lights
where we hop on switches which it does
right
um so that's fine
i don't know that we want quite that but
i just wanted to see if i could do it
right and it does seem
it does seem all right so let me check
out the stairs thing real quick just as
one last thing
before we we uh before we stop
[Music]
um
welcome to way too much light uh so the
other thing i was wondering is what
happens if we just turned off the
standard lighting pattern
so in the like world gen
what if i just like turn that off like
it's not gonna happen
no puss no i gotta finish the stream
puss
you don't want a program right now do
you can you sit on my lap
can you be a good girl instead of my lap
while i finish the stream how about that
what do you think of that no
all right well we're gonna try we're
gonna try okay
so
i'm not sure exactly
entity gen
i'm not sure exactly what happens
in the entity generator here right now
did i
still leave those other lights on
because i think i might have
um which i didn't want to
no see i didn't so so
these should not be generating any light
right so so shouldn't these rooms just
be dark
but they're not which is a little odd
um i guess you can get some light from
above but it shouldn't really be that
much right
so like why is there so much light
coming in here um
i do feel like that's a little bit weird
but i don't know when we go to do a
final pass on lighting it'll be
interesting
all right
so i think that um
i think that that's all fine i'm gonna
take a really quick look at the stairs
thing
just so i can see uh if there's
something obvious going on there
um
so there's some kind of stairwell
nonsense here right
um and if we look at what that's doing
um you can kind of see that we're like
offsetting the stairs
so really what that's saying is it's
like hey
are we on a stairwell up or down
which is not what we want i don't think
um
so when we loop through these
connections
if there's a stairwell up we don't care
so i think it's maybe just that
maybe
um so i think that's more what we want
now there's other stuff we want to do
because we probably don't want to put
like like we shouldn't be able to hop in
there right
so we don't want um on the stairwell
down we probably want to remove
those tiles so so we may
want to do something like this
um
like we want to say that we're on a wall
we want a wall
here i think so we probably want
like
this
uh now might be a good time to start
cleaning this code up too because we're
going to actually care about our rooms
more now
but anyway um we might say is like all
right we're on a wall
if you're here you know what i'm saying
um
[Music]
although we we don't really want a wall
we just don't want
you to be able to walk there so
more specifically like uh
you know
i don't know
something like that um
so so i'm not sure i'm not sure exactly
how i want that to be
but but we'll see but it would be
something like that
um where like if there was an up
connection you're not supposed to be
able to stand there
you know what i'm saying um
uh and only if there wasn't also one
down
so if there's one up and down in the
same room that's a fine but like you
know
so what i would want to do so here it is
it's traversable
right so that's what we actually want so
traversible
uh would be here and the problem that
we're going to have is traversable gets
set somehow in here to true right
when you're not on a wall and maybe what
i want to do is do it the other way
around
so it's false here
and that way i can say look assume that
it's traversable
and that way in here i can say it's not
so if you're on a wall or you're
underneath the place
uh the connection or whatever on wall
can can be moved
back down to to here right
um it doesn't need to be looked at above
and uh puss is so sweet right now she's
sitting right
on my lap you can't see it but she's
behaving so well on the stream
um what a good puss you are
what a good puss you are uh
so now we just can't go there right
um we can't go under the stairs
so that seems good and you know we'll
want to probably make that look a little
different
but at least now it's like sane and it
won't put the
the uh the floor tile
like the the stompable tiles won't go on
there
so that seems good as well right
all right i'm going to call that a day
we will do a brief q a and then that
will be
the end of that uh all right
no questions if there are no questions
then we are done
i'm glad that the audio seems to have
worked today
so hey you know that's pretty good
how you doing miss thing
you doing okay all right
any ideas how to stop the snakes from
getting stuck
no i don't really um so
you know there's a lot of things we
could do we could make the snakes
smarter
so they tried to avoid getting stuck
that's one thing
but that wouldn't necessarily
so i guess what i would say about that
is that wouldn't necessarily stop
the snakes from getting stuck what that
would do is
decrease the likelihood that the snake's
getting stuck so if the snakes were
somewhat smart
and intentionally tried not to do that
then they would do it less often but the
player could probably still force them
to do it or circumstances could force
them to do it
now again that's why i say this is more
of a game design question because i feel
like
you really would want to know you you
want to have a game design opinion about
which one of those it should be
and i don't know which it should be so
so that's what i would say about that
the other things we can do if the idea
is snakes should never get stuck
is we can just make it that if a snake
looks and can't find anywhere to hop
it's allowed to just randomly pick
another place
right um and that's again it's a
gameplay decision
and maybe that's cool like the whole
snake will sn hop over to somewhere
else maybe we don't even want snakes in
the game
right so so i don't know um
that's that's what i would say is it's
it's really
programming it is not super hard so
us writing code to do whatever it is we
want it to do
is not super difficult it's a game
design question
it's what should it do like what what do
we
want to do and that's inherently a game
sign question
for this kind of game i think you
probably don't want
smart ai you know this is a game about
you know it's supposed to feel like
zelda-like or binding of isaac
those games don't want really smart ais
what they want
is like predictable enemy behavior
that the player goes oh i know this
enemy does this pattern
right so i would say that game design
wise in order to remain on theme
we probably don't want the ai doing
anything super smart
so the ais shouldn't think very much
they should do things that a player can
immediately know
that this is the pattern it will do
but beyond that i i just don't know
following up on the question i asked you
before i thought about what you said and
i'm not sure i understand
uh okay well i would need more
information
on what you didn't understand
though in order to answer more
um this is from a question from the
pre-stream so it's
it's it's quite a bit back
oh auroboros is a great idea have the
snake eat its own tail ah
that's that might be cool gameplay-wise
because then if the player traps a snake
into a place where the snake can't get
out it would
uh the player
[Music]
will then have caused the snake to kill
one of its own pieces that could be cool
right
i've seen things about having a fixed
update clock for the game but rendering
at a higher frame rate
requires you to interpolate between
states to do this
would you just duplicate your game state
each time
and interpolate between the current and
previous for every entity
that seems quite expensive so
i mean that is what people generally do
but it's actually not as expensive as
you might think if you want to keep the
cost down it's not that bad because the
renderer doesn't care about the entire
game state
it only needs to know like positions and
orientations usually
um and maybe a few other things that are
dependent on those things
so typically i think what you do is you
you're only talking about
storing a previous like interpolation
position
but you don't have to like duplicate
everything
you could if you wanted to um but you
know
it's not as bad as you might think i
guess is what i'd say
i'm looking for a lightweight way to
traverse 3d voxels along array and
accumulate a color in opengl
any suggestions about algorithms that
are mostly branchless
i'm probably the wrong one to ask i just
don't do a lot of gpu programming these
days
so i'm really the wrong one to ask
stepping along a voxel is not that hard
obviously
um but the question of what's the most
efficient
way to like organize that kind of thing
on a graphics card
is you know i mean i'd pr what i'd
probably do if i were you is i'd go
look at the sparse voxel uh octree paper
and i which was a while ago and i would
go look on like google scholar or
sightseer or something
and look at all the people who reference
that paper that are more
modern so i'd like reverse crawl from
that paper forward
because there's going to be a ton of
papers on
voxel walking on gpus and people have
studied this problem
so so you don't have to come up with the
answer yourself
there's a lot of research on that you
know what i mean
i want to get deeper into c assembly but
i already have three projects ongoing in
c
sharp and running my business how do did
you manage learning new topics
while inundated with other work um
so i guess what i would say is you know
obviously you have to assess how
important it is for you to learn
whatever it is that you want to learn
if you're stressed and you don't have
time
it's not usually going to be a great
environment for learning so
you know you have to ask yourself is
this the right time in my life
to make time for this thing and if you
really want to learn it
then it's always the right time to try
and make time but you may be like nah
i'll wait and i'll do it you know when
i'm a little older and maybe some of
this settles down or you know or i don't
care whatever but so
so make sure it's the right time and
that you want to actually make time for
this thing first don't
pile too much stuff on yourself and
stress yourself out
too much but if you've decided that now
is the time and you want to set aside
some time for learning something what i
would say
is if you're running a business and you
have a bunch of c sharp projects
i guess one thing i would ask is can you
actually just integrate it in
like c sharp can call out to see your
assembly libraries
do you have some stuff you're doing in
your c sharp code right now that's slow
like do you have any performance
critical stuff that you wish would run
faster
what you could do is say let me make a
little c library
dll that i can call from c sharp um
and and let me start trying to optimize
that in assembly or with intrinsics or
something
or multi-threading right so you could
try to just take
little pieces of what you're doing now
and say can i make one of these
be like a learning uh
a learning environment so i just do my
spare time so don't make it business
critical
you don't want something that you're
learning to be
in your critical path but just like you
know i'm gonna spend a few hours a week
tinkering with this
let me see if i can if i can make
something um
that that i can actually use as part of
of what i do so it's not totally
separate right
so
one thing that always gets me how do you
stop yourself from over competing things
i always seem to try to be clever and it
almost always seems to be a bad idea
um so i there's there's no real way to
stop yourself from over complicating
things
because your brain won't pick the
simplest way every time when you start
so i don't think it's worthwhile to to
try to hold yourself to a standard of
always write the simplest code first
you should be trying to write simple
code but you won't always succeed
and even people like me or john blow who
say all the time you can even hear me
say on the stream like i'm just gonna
write the simplest possible thing we'll
say that
he'll say that i'll say that we still
end up with over complicated code all
the time
right the thing that keeps us from
spiraling out of control on it
is that eventually we go this is getting
too complicated let's figure out a way
to
simplify it right um and so it's really
more about putting
in a mental process that you do
periodically where you're like
is there an opportunity to simplify this
is there an opportunity to like just
always thinking about that how can i
reduce the amount of code that's
involved here right
um and so i feel like mostly that
is what you have to learn because
always try to write the simplest code
first but you won't know
like when i sit down to write code i
don't know what
for something that's a complicated
problem i don't know what is the
simplest way to handle it
i may never have thought of the right
techniques that make that code simple
and they may only emerge after i've
written a thousand lines of the wrong
code and be like oh wait i could have
simplified all this down to 20 lines of
code
if i just done this other thing so it's
really more about keeping that mental
process of
focusing on simplicity when you
go back to things looking at the code
i'm going to add a new feature could i
have simplified this is it too
complicated am i actually getting any
benefit out of this and we've done that
many times we do that with the asset
system
we've done that with the entity stuff
the generation code
right and we'll be doing it more as we
get closer to shipping handmade hero
there's always opportunities for
simplicity there's
way too much code in handmade error
right now if we did an audit
and went through and thought about each
section we could simplify each and every
one of them and so it's really just
about making that time
and doing that mental exercise of going
how can i simplify this
you won't always have time i mean i
remember the witness code base there's
tons of stuff in there that's massively
over complicated you won't always have
time to simplify everything
but the way that you keep it from
spiraling out of control
is just by doing that periodic cleanup
and there's no way around that
as you get better at programming and
focus more on simplicity
it's true that you'll create less messes
but it will only be less messes there
will still always be a mess
so you always have to think about how do
i clean up my messes because you're
never going to get out of it completely
unless you're literally writing the
exact same thing you've written many
times before you're not going to pick
the perfectly mess-free way to do it the
first time so it's just about that
mental process
would it be possible to have two switch
tiles in very different rooms that you
have to hop on to
open a door or unlock something um
with the current way that handmade hero
is architected
you would have to do a little a little
bit of extra work to do that you'd have
to add a
field to the entities to do that um
because right now long distance stuff it
doesn't handmade hero thinks in terms
mostly of regions
so if you're talking about two totally
separate switches
what you would need to do is have some
thing that that
tracks like here are some global state
things that are true
through the whole game i don't
want anything like that in the game like
i don't really want the player to have
to go
if the player was supposed to get
something that
has an effect somewhere else i would
want it to be something they carry like
a key or something
i don't really want there to be like
really distant switches that you
switch on and off that are like nowhere
near each other
so i probably won't be adding anything
like that but if you wanted to
you might want to consider having the
brains be
more permanent so there's the first n
brains are permanent brains that can
just track
infinitely large things if you want it'd
be pretty easy architectural change
um but you know it would just mean that
the entity cache would never
page those out they're just permanently
in so that way they can be
as far effecting as possible right but i
would still want to keep all the current
stuff because i don't want most entities
to have that i don't want most entities
to have to be in memory all the time or
in
in play all the time right
thank you for the compliment it is it's
not me unfortunately it's the
it's the camera lighting
yeah oh there is so much cat hair
floating around
in in this household um i keep
the puss very uh brushed i brush
her all the time but i mean she's still
always shedding
all right um
ah okay so from what i understand you
started handmade hero because you
thought people didn't know what it took
to make a real game and it would be good
if they did
so it seems like you do that do care
about instrument um so no
i guess what i would say is um
it was more to make a record of how this
kind of programming works
right so it was it was to have like a
preserved
sort of version of it but for people who
want that
so so the idea is is not to convince
people to do what i do
it's to provide
a a series for the people who
want to do it right
that they can come and watch it or know
how it happened
right so um it's
it's not really supposed to be
evangelical right um not religiously
evangelical but you know what i mean
like
evangelical the literal definition of
that word meaning it's not supposed to
be
pushing people like you need to do this
it's supposed to be if this is something
that interests you here is a series
right
uh so so yeah i and and i actually one
of the things that's true
and and this is a a definitely a
conflict
between me and i guess what i would say
is like the way that people behave
online these days
is i don't like telling other people
what to do
right um so like so like nowadays
the general culture online is that
everyone thinks that they get the right
to tell you what to do like that's
that's the
attitude online um to the point where if
they don't like what you do
they actually literally don't want you
to like exist right they want
you to not have a channel on twitch
because they don't like what you show on
the channel on twitch
or you shouldn't have a twitter account
because they don't like what you post on
twitter
so i am 100 like that is
so terrible to me like i find that not
only to be abhorrent and horrible
as a way of thinking but also i feel
like it's the antithesis
of what the computer revolution was so
the computer evolution to me
was that everyone gets to use a computer
right
and you you can do what you want with
your computer
that that was what it means to me right
and this was a really great thing in my
opinion
because it allowed you to each
individual could do what they wanted to
do with their computer
um this is what the personal computer
revolution was about
and so i want everyone to be able to do
what they want to do with their computer
you know that's what i would prefer
and i and i don't this is why i don't go
to like people
like you've never seen me go to
someone's stream
and complain about the programming
language they were using because
i don't understand why someone would
ever do that it's it's
absolutely nuts to me if you want to
complain on your stream about the
programming language that someone's
using
that makes perfect sense because the
people came to your stream to hear your
opinions
or to hear what you were doing so if i
say that i think it's stupid
to program in modern c plus on my stream
that makes a lot of sense everyone came
here
to to listen to what i have to say but
the idea online that you should go to
someone else's feed or someone else's
stream or someone else's thing and
complain about what
they do or tell them that they have to
change what they do is
is so to me that's horrible
i don't understand why people do it
it's a weird thing that i can't
understand right
and obviously it makes perfect sense to
them
but to me i can't i can't imagine it
so on my stuff you will never see me do
that
i i'm never going to go to like someone
else's thing
and tell them not to do something
because i don't like it right
um and i've tried to really never do
that on twitter anymore at all either
right um so if i complain about
something on twitter i try pretty hard
to complain on like my i just it posts
just to my thing i i try not to go to
like
other people's you know conversations
they're having
and say something um
to the extent that i can and uh or i
just don't use the service anymore right
and so so i didn't want and don't want
handmade hero to be that like i don't
want
people to interpret handmade hero as
me trying to go to where they
are in their computing space and telling
them
not to or to do something
i only want it to be something for
people who who
want to do this right like i want
them to be coming to the stream i do not
want to be going to them
and trying to
convince them in any way whether it's
browbeating or
or like or being very nice about it
doesn't
it's not the tone so much as i just
don't want that behavior right
um so that's
just my mindset of it and so i really
don't want handmade hero to be
about proselytizing or
putting on a hard sell or trying to
appear
in some way as a way of
signaling to people that they should
listen to me
i don't want that like i don't want any
of that to be happening
i just want to say what i think and if
people want to hear that they can
and if they don't they should be able to
not have to listen to it
right um and i don't want to put any
subterfuge in there where i'm trying to
slyly sneak
messages i want people to hear into
things
in a way that is more palatable than it
should be because i know
that that will like help or something
right
so hopefully that makes more sense right
yeah and i and rants are great like i
have no problem with rants just
just don't do them like on in someone
else's turf
right like if if i want to rant on
handmade hero about things
i don't like that seems fine but but
you know there's people who will go on
to other people's twitch streams
and start like ranting to them about
what they're doing and like i just don't
want that like i don't want that to be
happening right
if you don't like what someone's doing
on their twitch stream just don't watch
right don't watch that twitch stream
um and and you know if you don't like
what someone posts on twitter just don't
follow that twitter
you know it's not that hard so to me
like i try to do that as much as i can
so
do you find value in checking out other
parts of the computing space
even those you disagree with without
interfering of course
um yeah i i guess i would say there's
some
there's some parts of computing like
object-oriented programming where i've
just set the bozo bit
on it where it's like i know that
nothing interesting happens there
but uh there's plenty of other spheres
of programming
that you know i don't necessarily think
are good ideas as a whole but they have
good ideas
in them one that came out the other day
was like pure functional programming
like i don't think pure functional
programming is a very good idea
but there are interesting things about
functional programming and people who do
pure functional programming
are forced to do the maximum amount of
stuff
that way so you can look at what they do
and see what all the possibilities are
because unlike procedural programming
where you had other options they had no
options they had to do it that way
they had to do it with purely
functional stuff
and so it can be interesting to look at
what they come up with because you're
like
okay if someone is spending all their
time in this constrained environment
having to follow these rules they will
come up
with things that you may never have come
up with because you wouldn't have to
and looking at that gives you
information that you will therefore
never have
because you will never have been forced
to push in those directions
right and so i do think there are other
things you can learn
about programming by looking at styles
of programming that you yourself don't
do
because if they involve specific kinds
of constraints that you don't subject
yourself to
you will not have necessarily been
pushed as far in certain directions so
that can be very educational
i think
one last question if tomorrow everyone
started using javascript for everything
you wouldn't care at
all like you will probably always use
software written by other people
wouldn't it be better that software was
of good quality and if you agree with
that
should you try to influence people to
care about software being high quality
i mean i guess what i would say is all
the software is
written in javascript for everything
already so i'm not sure
that's a tomorrow question that's a
today question
um
so i don't really know how to answer
that question
exactly it's not that i don't care
it's that i don't really
i just don't really like evangelism
right people you know there are certain
things i'm willing to do and other
things i'm not willing to do and
evangelism just isn't one of them
so i'm willing to say how much i think
javascript is
not great on this stream i'm not gonna
go
i'm not gonna go around
poking into other people's business
telling them not to use javascript right
i mean i'm just that's just not
something i'm going to do
it doesn't necessarily mean
that i don't think there are negative
consequences to it it's just that you
know
i i think that to the extent that i'm
going to be
loud and um
[Music]
proselytized about something it's going
to be more about programmer freedom
to ensure that i never get into a
situation where i am forced to only
write javascript all day
right i want people to have the freedom
to do the kind of programming they want
to do
i i don't want to be going around
putting my nose into other people's
business telling them how to do what
they want to do
right um
so like yeah javascript sucks i know i
have
written a couple thousand lines of code
in it just recently
for the star code galaxy player which is
supposed to be web compatible right and
it sucks
javascript is terrible um
but you know like it's i don't know
it's it's not like
i i don't know
that a the fact that a bad programming
language is common
is enough reason for me to go around
being pushy
you know so so i'm just gonna have
streams where i tell people that i think
this sucks and here's why and here's
alternatives and hopefully people come
to them as they seem to like
i get a lot of people who come watch my
stuff
and that seems like enough i don't think
i need
to go around being pushy about it or
being sly
and trying to convince people because at
the end of the day i think if you don't
know that javascript sucks
i i don't know that there's that much
i'm going to say i mean it's kind of
obvious that it sucks
and by the time someone's learned
a little bit of programming you're kind
of going to know that javascript sucks
even the people who program javascript
know it sucks i mean they created
typescript
so that they wouldn't have to deal with
javascript you know
so i don't know that that these things
are really
all that
much of a problem with proselytization
anyway does anyone think javascript is
good
most people who even use it as their
primary output language don't want a
program in it they use typescript now
right
so
javascript sucks so in so many ways i
mean
you can't even really make threads in
javascript for example
right like try to write a multi-threaded
piece of code in javascript
you know good luck
um but yeah i mean we could go on for a
long time about what javascript
the lack of typing so you can't really
get static type analysis
this is why typescript is useful right
um but there's so many reasons i mean
it's it's got a lot of really bad
[Music]
aspects to it um it's just not a good
language
in general um but like i said i really
don't think that many people think it's
a good language
which is which is why you have things
that people try to put on top of
javascript to make it work
okay you know but anyway
should probably wrap it up
all right
let's switch back thank you everyone for
joining me for the episode handmade here
it's gonna put your coding with you as
always if
you would like to follow along the
series at home you can always period the
game on handmadehero.org and it comes
with source code so that you can play
around with it
uh i will be back here next week at
which point
honestly maybe it's time to put combat
in there um
so we'll probably just we'll do some
stuff where we can fight some enemies
and just try to get that working um and
then i don't know
like probably then after that it's items
right and then we'll sort of have like a
yeah i mean i don't know like i said not
a game designer but we're just gonna
go through things that i think should be
in there and we'll kind of hope that we
get a reasonable enough playing thing
out of it
at the end of the day so that's it uh
see you back here for that until then
have fun programming everyone
and i will see you on the internet take
it easy everybody