alright hello everyone and welcome to
hand made here the show recode a
complete game live on stream today I
would like to pick up where we left off
last weekend and do a little bit of
testing in terms of how we're doing our
integration so there was some confusion
as well and I just wanted to clear this
up just so everyone's kind of clear on
what's going on I'm gonna go to the
blackboard a little bit and just say a
couple things real quick because there
was a bunch of confusion about this
someone filed a github bug report which
was not correct which ironically
mentioned the Stack Exchange
thread that actually was correct they
just read the stock exchange thread
wrong what can you do so so we're going
to talk just really briefly because we
talked about before I just want to
re-emphasize it because I think it's not
coming through let's talk about
hemisphere integration alright so what
we're doing here on handmade hero in
terms of solving for the lighting right
is we have a hemisphere and we're trying
to sample the light over the entire
hemisphere right so our goal is if we
had an infinite amount of computing
power we would literally want to check
what the incoming light was in an
infinite number of directions everywhere
on this hemisphere right and for each
one of those we would multiply the
incoming light by an infinitesimal
quantity but that quantity would still
be proportional to cosine theta why is
it proportional cosine theta because
when you have light shining on a surface
if you imagine a beam of light shining
on a surface the degree to which it can
illuminate that surface depends entirely
on the angle at which it comes right so
if you take a look at the aperture of
light that will illuminate the same size
on the surface so let's say we've got
this size here on the surface in
question if the light is shining
directly down you will notice that you
get a much bigger aperture than if the
light is shining
in right this length is smaller than
this length how much smaller well it
happens to be proportional to the cosine
of the angle right because as this goes
to their right we're gonna find that the
the when we draw the triangle that says
what that proportion is right the angle
that we rotate this down by will change
how long this length is right it's it's
that part of the triangle right wait no
no no no so everyone that part of the
triangle sorry I had that I had that
horribly wrong that was there's a very
bad drawing let me actually drop that
for you again so I should see why I cut
I cut the corner there and and made
myself do something horrifically let me
draw it out full I deserve it now okay
so in the case where we're shining
directly on it right obviously it's
gonna be the same size so that's gonna
be a 1 so that's not really that
interesting so the question is as it
comes down here how much light is
actually coming in right how much of the
cosine is actually getting shown on here
right and what we want to do is take a
look at that angle which is this angle
right here it's the angle off of off of
this right and what we're looking for in
this case is we're looking for figuring
out what that infinitesimal shaft of
light is that's kind of coming up like
this right we're looking at we're
looking at a measure of that proportion
that's changing as it as it comes down
and we want to figure out what that is
now in this particular case right we
don't have any not like the hypotenuse
is sort of out of the equation because
we're just talking about a hypotenuse of
1 here we're just talking about well
whatever the incoming value is so we
just want to know what the ratio is of
whatever the incoming light is to how
much we think would fall on the surface
right and so what we want to know is
from
triangle which we have just the angle of
the light versus the normal right and I
saw they should draw that the other way
around because usually we we would like
to although it doesn't matter which one
we do because we can always change it we
would like to be able to just do one dot
product and get it so the angle we'd
actually like to measure is this right
so this angle here is actually sort of
the inverse of this right it's the it's
the 90 degrees minus theta right or PI
over 2 minus theta right because we know
that this angle is PI over 2 it's 90
degrees and so we know that we could
look at either one of these whichever
one we want to write but this is the one
that we want to do because if we are
going to do dot product based lighting
where we have the normal pointing out
this way and the light pointing out this
way we know that the normal transpose
the light is the operation that's
fastest for us to do so we'd like it to
be proportional to this angle if
possible right okay so obviously just
intuitively speaking this makes some
sense then because if these are pointed
directly at each other it's going to be
one right and in what its going to be
measuring actually in that particular
case is it's going to be measuring this
length right which is completely one as
we come down all the way to here we know
that this cosine because that'll make
this be PI over two when it gets to here
will be zero again exactly what we want
we want it to go from one to zero so
it's doing the right sort of directional
fall-off the question is is it computing
it is the the cosine the correct
fall-off between one and zero for the
light given that we're trying to do is
measure how a shaft would change between
here and here if the the proportion was
the same in the bottom so assuming that
we're talking about something like this
and we want to say okay if I were to
construct one that looks like this right
then I want to get an answer
proportional to that and if I was to
construct one that looks like this so
you know
as the angle comes down here right and
I'm projecting ASEC essentially what
this is I'm projecting it over here
right like that because when I dot
parked these two things together that's
what I'm gonna get right I'm going to
get the projection of this and I should
have drawn that a little bit differently
as it comes down these are both the unit
length vectors right so as they come
down they're gonna form circle I'm gonna
project this over and I'm gonna get
essentially that value right so I'm
going to be end up measuring that
thickness there and so in a sense I mean
there's not a lot we can really say
about that other than if you looked at
how this was structured since we know
this was unit to begin with right we're
talking about some fixed unit here right
and we're talking about you know
everything is basically proportional to
one here we're basically talking about a
square in a sense and so measuring this
fall off as we go down is going to be
roughly the same I know that's not
particularly convincing but if we
imagine for example these looking like
this right as they go like that if that
makes sense then if we're trying to
figure out what proportion of the light
they're actually shining up we could do
the more complicated version of this
constancy if there's a good way I can
illustrate this
yeah if we wanted to construct this
actual triangle here right what you can
see is that there's a right angle that
would be formed to find this length
itself right and so we know that the
angle in question is actually this angle
because this shaft is bending down this
way
so the right angle let me draw that a
little bit bigger down here so you can
actually see it here's the original
shaft of light coming down and we're
basically saying it's gonna Bend outward
like that okay and what we want to find
is we want to find how this amount
changed right how the width of that
light that's coming in changed and
there's the you know there's the 90
degree angle so if this angle here is
the theta that we're measuring right
then you know you can look at which
angles are inside here and say well this
angle is PI over 2 right minus theta
because we know that that angle is Theta
so the angle that would complete the
rest of the 90 returned is PI over 2
minus theta right and furthermore we
know that this angle has to these all
have to sum up to the total sum for the
interior of the circle of for the
triangle right so we know that we have
this angle which is PI over 2 right that
we know that angle sine of degrees
because we dropped it you know it's
perpendicular on purpose we know that
this angle is PI over 2 minus theta
right makes sense and we know that the
entire interior of the circle would have
to add up that's good circle the entire
interior of the triangle would have the
the internals the triangle would have to
add up to PI so if we actually want to
know what this angle is well this angle
also will end up being theta right
because if you take a look
what this simplifies down to we end up
with 2 pi over 2 minus theta right or
theta minus I'm sorry
pi minus theta right which is on this
side of thing and we know that we need
this thing to add up to PI right I got
actually put my yeah did I say that
correctly iPod in second
wow I'm having a rough morning I don't
know why anyway so yeah no I think I
said that correctly anyway doesn't
matter so anyway when we actually look
at what what's going to happen here the
point of this is all just to figure out
that ok so if we actually wanted to look
at what happens when we take cosine
theta right we get we do get this by
taking cosine theta it's just in a very
roundabout sort of old trigonometric
Annamma tree sort of calculation sort of
way right we it's it's weird because the
angle that we're measuring is actually
the one up here which appears to not
really be super related because your it
looks like your cosine theta term is
actually going to take that right
because when you construct the triangle
you're looking at this triangle up here
because this is where the theta is that
we're measuring because this is the
normal and this is the light and so it's
a bit weird but the reason that we're
measuring that is just because I if you
actually go ahead and propagate the
angles through it ends up being the
correct angle to use the cosine for it
to get this length anyway even though
that may seem kind of strange right so
yeah I don't know why you went on that
tangent probably because I'm was so
sleepy this morning I made a sloppy
mistake here and then felt like I needed
the punishment all right so forget
everything I just said that was all just
for me to reinforce the fact that we
have to multiply incoming light by
cosine theta
in order to know how much of that light
we can actually absorb or bounce as a
surface right so whenever we take one of
these in incoming light directions
whatever the light value that comes in
from this thing has to be proportional
to n dot L in terms of how much light we
actually receive now remember this has
nothing to do with how much light we
actually want to reflect afterwards
because every surface has its own
reflectance function and this is not the
reflectance function this is just the
light reception function this is just
the thing that says how much of the
light we can get out of what's coming
towards us from that direction how much
we reflect is a separate function that's
about the properties of the material
right totally separate so this is just a
term that's about the fundamental nature
of of how light coming in at an angle
cannot come in at as you cannot receive
as much of it from a particular angle as
another angle based on how wide that
aperture is so since we knew this is the
fundamental law right that no matter
what surface we're talking about we have
to obey that means that as we take our
integral which you know would be a
double integral over the hemisphere if
we were going to literally take all of
the incoming light of the hemisphere
right we'd have two angles who knows
what they are
I probably shouldn't use those two we'll
just use a and B because theta was the
angle we were using for the for the you
know this n dot L here so we have two
angles right let's say the you know the
orbit around and the azimuth right so
you know maybe something that's like
talking about how far
oops around we go and then something
that talks about how far up we go to
like make our you know to make our
vector so if we were to take the
integral over the entire Hemisphere we
would need to know some measure of the
incoming light so whatever that is right
that's some magic function that we don't
really know that's proportional to a and
B that we're trying to sample but we
always know that we would have to
multiply it by n transpose L on the
outside which is that cosine theta term
right
so every sample we take or every
integral we do would have to have that
in there and again the reason for that
is just because we're trying to mimic
that winnowing of the of the aperture of
life that can come in at that angle so
once we know that this is what this
always looks like it always looks like
some kind of a summation right if we
were to do this discrete it's just some
kind of a summation and you could think
of this summation just virtually a
summation over the hemisphere right even
if we don't write it math wise if it's
just like some summation over the
hemisphere of n transpose L times some
function on the hemisphere that we're
sampling as much as we can write this
term is always there so what I was
trying to say last time was if you look
at how this works it's taking a sampling
of things on the hemisphere and then
weighting them by cosine theta right but
since this sampling is not sufficient
right
meaning we know that we're taking not
all of the samples we're taking less
samples than the total Hemisphere we're
not doing a real integral right we're
not accounting for all the light since
we know this is a sparse sample what we
can do instead of taking a uniform
sparse sample right one that samples the
hemisphere uniformly so one that kind of
goes like okay let's just sample around
this Hemisphere and make sure that we
sample very true so there's no bias in
the sampling if we are going to do a
uniform sampling of the hemisphere then
we have to multiply by n transpose L
because that's what the equation
mandates but if we were to bias this
sampling then that would not necessarily
be true anymore because whatever the
bias is will affect how we are summing
the terms now let me give you an example
of this that doesn't have to do with
hemispheres and lighting because I think
that's maybe
where people are getting hung up let's
suppose that we have a function that we
know exactly what it is let's suppose it
just looks like that right that's our
function here zero here's one and it
goes from zero to one as well right so
if we were to say here's the x-axis
twice if we were to say f of X you know
f of X just equals x right so as it
comes up
we're just sampling it like so right now
if I were to say that we had some reason
why our sampling wanted to have an
equation in it right so you can see this
like n transpose L term was happening
right so maybe I want to say that we're
want to sample this function but our
sampling much like the hemisphere
sampling has some inbound law on it
that's going to weight the samples right
and let's say the weighting term is X so
when we take our integral or our sample
summation right so our summation here
and we want to sample over all the X's
what we're actually gonna do is say X f
of X right is what we actually want a
sample so then what will happen is if we
picked a uniform sampling of X's right
if we said oh here here here here here
and here right so we got like 0 0.1 0.2
0.3 0.4 right we got like 10 samples
uniformly spaced right and we sum those
up what we would get is a bunch of sums
of x squared right which is what we
which is what we're doing here
and what we expect so we would expect to
see essentially the integral from 0 to 1
right of X f of X which actually equals
the integral from 0 to 1 of just x
squared because we know what this is
it's just X right we can substitute it
in okay so we can do that and we can
produce we know what this is right we
know what that integral would actually
be and we're so we're trying to produce
that integral
integral of x-squared there right but if
instead we wanted to just optimize out
this term so we don't want to multiply
by X anymore right then what we can do
is bias our sampling so that the bias
lines up with how this term would have
multiplied out so think about it the X
term is gonna mean that anything down
here is not gonna get weighted hardly at
all when we sample because it's going to
be zero or close to zero so if we just
don't take any samples out here and take
a lot more samples up here where it
would be close to one right we're going
to end up with the same effect because
we're going to overweight the values
that are on the high side and
underweight the ones that are on the low
side thereby mimicking what X does right
we're mimicking what X does assuming we
are mimicking what X does so we don't
have to multiply by it because as we
move these samples around we can cut we
can make them line up in places where
those samples will mimic the behavior of
X just by virtue of their density right
so if we make our sample density equal
to our weighting coefficient right then
we can just remove the weighting
coefficient that's all it's saying if
you have a constant on the outside of
your integral or your sampling or your
summation or whatever if you instead of
actually doing the multiply just move
the samples to be the same distribution
as that weighting would have done then
you're automatically going to have that
same effect right another way to look at
this is let's say you're taking an
average how do you take an average well
you take a bunch of things and you
divide by the number that you got right
so I take you know 3 plus 6 plus 9
right and I divide by three and what do
I get
right I get 18 divided by three right or
six right that's my average right and so
if you think about what this kind of
thing does if you look at what we're
doing here we're essentially taking a
weight which is one-third and
multiplying it by each of the terms that
we're adding together right so this
becomes 1 this becomes 2 and this
becomes 3 you add those together you get
6 right well if I wanted to change my
average to some kind of a weighted
average right so you know this was
clearly you know this is a continuous
number line that we're doing here right
you know maybe I've got 1 plus 2 Plus 3
plus I need more numbers 1 plus 2 plus 3
so if I'm taking some kind of an average
like this and I have a weight that I'm
going to multiply by each of them right
if I start with a uniform set of samples
right in this case and maybe this is
like just the numbers from some one to
ten right or something like that so if I
have a uniform set of samples like this
then I would expect and I multiply them
by uniform weight so my weight is going
to be well I can't okay so let me get
rid of the 10 there right all right
maybe it's a better thing to do to get
rid of the zero we've the tenon
and so if I want to go here and say all
right let's take the average of these
numbers so I'm gonna need one-tenth as
my weighting coefficient right then I'm
gonna get you know one tenth of one and
one tenth of - one tenth of three went
to the four etc etc right and so when I
actually add these up right and then I
divide by my weighting coefficient then
I get whatever my average point would
have been right and I need the zero in
there to actually balance this out but I
ran out of room for it right if that
makes sense
so you know if I had ad in there then we
would have had the eleven numbers and we
could get the five out of it right
anyway so if I take the numbers between
zero and ten inclusive and I divide by
it evenly so each one of these got one
eleventh and pretend my zeros back in
there just because I want that even five
for fun then you can kind of see okay
all I'm doing here is I'm doing that
same sum right I'm doing a sum of
samples of X right as X goes from zero
to ten in integer steps right and for
each of those I'm doing a weight
whatever the weight is times my my f of
X which is just X a my weight in this
case is just one so I'm just doing that
average right well if now I wanted to
change this weighting to what we were
saying before right so my weighting is
going to be X so I have an uneven
weighting of how I want these terms to
go then when we do it I've got it's
going to be a worse equation here but
we're gonna get the same sort of thing
right I'm gonna get 1 times 1/2 times 2
3 times 3 4 times 4 5 times 5 6 times 6
7 times 7 8 times 8 9 times 9
10 times 10 right so there's my waiting
and that's my answer for that waiting
right if that makes sense and so what
you can see there too is the waiting
obviously gets a lot it's it's much more
affected by the higher numbers than the
lower numbers because the waiting is
higher on the higher numbers right so
you know this is going to be multiplied
by 10 and this one's long any multiplied
by one so even regardless what these
samples are this is going to have a lot
more weight up there so if I wanted to
now what I could do is skew my
distribution so that I instead of
multiplying by X I just concentrate all
of my samples up here I could do that
now one of the things that's a little
bit confusing is we kind of have to deal
with distributions that are going to be
normal right so one of the problems with
duplicating these results here is that
we would want to normalize this number
out first so we'd have to know okay
what's the integral what you know what
are we actually dealing with here in
terms of 1/2 of the total amount of
weight right because remember this is
our total total amount of weight is 55
right so really we would want to look at
that number which is the normalized
version if you take a look at because
the weight wants to totally sum to 1 if
that makes sense
so in this case here we would probably
say our answer was more like 7 because
we'd really want to do something like
the weight over the total weight which
in this case again was 55 right so the
idea here now if we want to simplify
this process rather than multiplying
everything by this weighting value which
is you know some x over 55 here or
whatever which is what you know whatever
the X is my over 55 if we want to get
rid of the of having to multiply by that
value what I can do instead is just
sample what the function is going to be
more heavily on this end then on that
end
right if that makes sense and so then
what I could do is change my weight back
to a uniform weight right so instead you
know if I'm going to still take 10
sample
changed the weight back to one over ten
right or one over eleven if there's 11
samples however many we're going to take
right change the weight back to that and
then just sample biased by whatever the
function we're using before which is the
X right so since we know that the X is
going to be higher up here you can even
see since the answer was 7 here if we
just take sort of samples that tend to
skew up around there we would end up
with an answer in here even though we're
not actually multiplying by this anymore
right and that's all we're trying to do
with our weighting function we're trying
to observe the fact that when you take
some function and you weight it by a
certain skew so that it shifts towards
some distribution of its numbers right
in this case you know you can kind of
see exactly what would happen normally
it should have landed right about here
on an even weighting of these values
instead it's going to land right about
here because we've shifted it up by if
effectively squaring it right that's
really all that we're talking about
taking samples that look like that and
turning them into samples that look like
that right so that we get answers that
that shift upward anyway I realize this
kind of weird thing I'm not sure how to
write the more mathematically concise
version of it because it's a discrete
process so I mean one way to think about
it would be that the sampling function
that you use has a bias in it and you
could think about that bias as being
written into the equation so for example
if you were talking about it like this
so here's our Hemisphere sampling
so if you were talking about it like
this this is the function that you're
doing the reason that this FA B just
looks like an FA B term is because the
bias is assumed not to be there so like
it is assumed to be no sampling bias
right but if you imagined writing the
sampling bias in it so let's suppose we
were going to replace F of B with a
different function write GA of B and GA
of B equals FA of B whatever the
function was but it's biased so that its
results come back with the inverse
sampling right so they come back
proportional to 1 over cosine theta then
you could see that when you substitute
this in right um
I guess that's kind of not exactly the
right way I should have written it let
me write that slightly differently
let me write that the backwards way
because I think that would be a little
better so if this is the integral that
we want we're saying we essentially want
to know what we would have to produce
here right if we wanted these two things
to be equal right so we want to take an
integral of some function that will
equal the integral of this function
times the cosine theta right and so when
you look at these two things it just
means that G a of B has to equal cosine
theta FA of B right and then we know it
in order to figure out you know what
this function has to be it has to be the
cosine weighted version of this right
that's just what that ends up being
equal to right it's it's it's exactly
written out you know in that way so if
we can come up with another function
which just happens to have that same
that bias already built in then we know
that we wouldn't have to do this anymore
right we wouldn't have to multiply it by
cuz the actual function actually has it
in there already which is why we say
that if we took our sampling and biased
it so that it takes samples close to
where the cosine theta is one and very
few samples close to where cosine theta
is zero which is down here right that we
expect to get the same answer on the way
out hopefully that makes some sense and
I probably did a horrible job explaining
that it felt like I did probably because
I'm not a ray tracing guy so if I spent
all all my time working on this I
probably would have thought of good ways
to think about that that are clearer to
understand but I'm not so what can you
do we tried to do this at the end of the
previous stream and we haven't quite
gotten there yet so if you remember the
what we were doing in the code here
let's see we put in here we go generate
loading pattern so we put a little thing
in the code here that just tried doing
these samples you can see them do it i
we didn't quite get stable enough
results and we don't really know why now
there's couple of reasons we might not
get stable results one reason might be
that we are doing things correctly and
we just aren't taking enough samples
another reason is we have a bug right
and so we need to investigate this a
little bit further what I'm going to do
first so if you take a look here this is
the random bilateral samples I want to
see what happens with the minimum
maximum testing if we just crank up the
sample count really dramatically here if
that makes sense
and take a look at what the average is
at that point so in this sample count
here I'm gonna just crank it up
massively like so and I want to see if
this converges and this is just taking
random samples sampling a there we go
sampling a a pattern of randomness and
looking at what the minimum and maximum
averages are
what is happening and then not
terminating
- is 10:24 too much on that what's our
sample cam
that's kind of ridiculous that that
would be taking that long what's
happening here
it's a very slow function but I guess it
is taking that long oh you know why
because we're actually doing 1024 tests
of it so that all right I agree that may
have been a little bit much let's tone
it down a little but only a little we
could also just compile with
optimizations on I suppose but all right
so I just want to look at what these
values are
so the sample count here would also have
to be higher to get the actual average
right but I still so something seems a
little bit off because I feel like once
we take enough samples we should be
getting a fairly accurate result unless
it might be that our random number
generator isn't great either but we'll
see so let's do less tests and more
samples
I want a like densely sample of the
hemisphere right so now we're seven cows
4096 we have a lot less tests but here's
our min test average and here's our max
test average and what you can see is
they're still pretty bad right they're
still fairly divergent at which again
makes me wonder like if we've got
something habitually wrong happening
here I'm gonna keep upping the sample
count
and I just want to see okay so they're
they're starting to converge more at a
very very high sample count right let me
run more tests and make sure
yeah so okay so basically at that sample
count at 65,000 samples we start to
converge on an answer right which is
pretty bad right it's not not great and
that's a smooth function that's easy to
integrate that's just I guess goes to
show you just how hard it is to
integrate over a hemisphere unless
there's some kind of bug here now the
other thing is we don't know how our
random function is so you know what I'd
like to do as well since we've got right
now we have X or shift in there but X or
shift is not particularly good right
here's our here's our X or shift what
I'd like to do is I'd like to go ahead
and see if we could do a more precise
version of that maybe taking the PCG
stuff for example and having them one of
these that works a little bit better
so if I remember correctly
[Music]
I want to check because we are taking a
set of these together and I seem to
remember there being some some thing
that needed to happen that is what we're
talking about so k-dimensional equal
distribution is just talking about the
fact that if we were to take several of
these numbers and make sure that if we
use them as euclidean parameters right
like XYZ that they produce equal
distributions in space and we actually
do care about that in this case right
and what you can see here is it says you
know that there's something specific we
need to know about that I'm not sure
where it talks about that let's see
although we can achieve real indicators
for arbitrary K using the counted
assists there is a better method of LSU
extension ethic suppose we have a B bit
generator producing Arabic values which
we shall call the base generator the
extended generic consists of those B
bits of state and K additional arbitrage
issues we'll call the extension array we
use the state of the base generator to
choose a value from the extension array
bypassing the base interest rate through
a selector function of the final output
of the comparator is produced by X
soaring the selected value from the
extension array with the random number
produced by the base generator we stated
using formalizations so we would need we
need sort of an out-of-band thing for
that so there is gonna be an arbitrary
function but for simplicity let us
assume that K equals to the X and that
selection really drops bits to choose X
from the state to obvious choice for
choosing X fix our taking the higher two
bits and take the lorda bits if we wish
to perform party tricks like the ones
just in section 4 3 4 did you load a
bits because they will access all the
elements the extension array before
anyone once repeat start we have an
output function that uniformly in that
state is combined and must have final
extension area advances
you
in figure 16 tip of one p cg x sh r s 64
32 is shown with two-dimensional and
1024 dimensional eco distribution using
this mechanism x2 so we're mostly
interested we don't need quite so much
but let's take a look at where is that o
figure 16 I don't know where figure 16
is
well unfortunately I don't see any
I don't really see a lot of like there's
no plotting in here of exactly how bad
it would be if we just used a basic PC G
versus trying to use an extension array
I guess what I would want to do is I
want to go ahead and take a look at this
random bilateral and I would like to
plot it if that makes sense so I can
actually see what's going on when the
sampling density gets up higher I'd like
to see what the density is
if it tends to be very clumpy or not and
then if I was to improve the random
number generator just for the version
just for this test would it change
that's what I want to see cuz I'm not
sure I have a good sense from just from
the paper just how bad the K dimensional
distribution is if I don't do the more
advanced version so yeah so if I wanted
to draw this we already have the ability
to output these points right I'm doing
it here essentially with this sample
points situation so if we I assume run
this
and I could probably get rid of the test
case now as well but we should be seeing
somewhere in here
the yeah there they are all of the
points getting drawn right and so those
are its currently drawing our sample
points what I want to do is have it draw
random points and I just want to see
what that looks like so if I if 0 this
out here and I make one of these what I
could do is just say like alright let's
just write those to a table when I
generate them and then I'll draw them I
can't draw quite so many but I'll draw
some right in fact I don't really want
to copy this one I want to copy
so if I imagine taking this test series
here and doing exactly the same I'll
literally copy the code here from that
in it
so this will just go ahead and draw that
so yeah that's it I don't really want
line segment if there's my direction and
here's where we'll draw so if I go ahead
and say we've got draw point counts
let's say we draw 1024 of these I don't
know if that'll blow out how much buffer
space we have but once we push one of
these on the start point can stay the
same the normal is just direction here
and I think that should basically do it
and I suppose the other thing I don't
really know at the moment unfortunately
is I don't actually know whether this is
a fair way of generating hemisphere
points so I may also be creating a
problem that way I'm not sure so let's
play around this a little bit all right
so if I do draw a point count here so we
can draw like a lot of these you can see
the sphere here and you know would I
immediately say that it's got a problem
I'm not sure but it kind of looks like
it might
just in terms of weather that you know
how good that random covering is like I
said I don't really know whether this is
a fair way of producing points on a
sphere I could take a look
it's incorrect selects for coordinates
that's okay we don't do that
so they say it's spherical coordinates
proportionable this is one way to do it
so they definitely give ones here that
do it
three gaussian random variables XY and z
then the distribution of vectors is this
so we're definitely wrong because if
because we are not picking Gaussian
we're picking white noise on negative 1
to 1 in theory in theory so for uniform
distributed random numbers they're
suggesting you do this and then that
right
so we could just do this is pretty
straightforward right
so maybe let's try this in C I'm just
curious you can see what that one looked
like right so let's do a little f0 here
all right sweet wants two random numbers
X 1 and X 2 and those are both supposed
to be random bilaterals according to the
text according to mrsa glia or mrsa glia
yeah
George Mossad Leah
from Ohio State University all right so
if we were to follow his formula then we
want to reject pairs that have a length
squared greater than one so and it says
reject anything that's greater than
equal to one and then we just generate
the points directly
supposedly without normalizing because
the normalization is already built into
the equations so our X is two times x
one times square root and it looks like
that value is actually the same so let's
just call that X let's call that root so
it's two times X 1 and then 2 times X 2
times the same root term and then Z is
special as it always is
and that's just x1 yes so it's actually
this term right here and that's in
theory the algorithm if I didn't make a
mistake in translation and we can take a
look at what that looks like
and I wouldn't say that that looks any
different to me I would say that looks
about the same so given the fact that
I'm seeing roughly the same thing with
both of these oops I did that a little
bit poorly there
yeah now I should be able to run either
of these
so yeah like looking at that and looking
at that I mean they're definitely
different
oh but you know what the this is doing
the whole sphere and we only want the
hemisphere so I suppose in that case we
have to modify that formula a little bit
differently right because in this case
here the Z value can range you know all
the way and we don't really want it to
do that right so we want this term here
we want that term there to only be able
to go up to one that's all right go to
0.5 so I believe and yeah we never want
it to get all the way up to one so I
believe that the correct modification to
his routine is that for a hemisphere and
so that's the hemisphere version right
you can see what I mean by that because
you can see here in this case the Z
coordinate is 1 minus 2 x square right
and so if if you normally let this value
go from 0 to 1 this will go from 1 to
negative 1 which would be the whole
hemisphere but if we just cap it so it
can only go from 0 to 0.5 that will make
this go from 1 to 0 which gives us a
hemisphere so I just made that slight
modification to his routine pretty basic
all right so you know that's what that
routine looks like that's what our
tunics like I don't see a lot of
difference there
at least visually nothing jumps out at
me so I'm going to just double-check
what happens if we change our random
number to a different
I don't know what I want to call this
exactly but in our randomness you know
we have this one which is just using an
X or shift and what I want to do is
create a different one that creates
that's an on X or shift that's well I
shouldn't say an onyx worship that does
that PCG version in order to do that
what I'm going to do is say okay let's
say we've got a random serious PCG here
or something in fact I could just say
random serious PCG and then just have
the functions work the same so if I have
a random serious PCG this one will
operate on something fancier
we'll try putting this eight in like so
and we'll have random next few 32 much
like we did
all right so what we want to do here is
I'm gonna start with the same thing that
we had before but I'm gonna try and do a
better random number generator than the
one that we had and then we can swap
between them and see which which one
works out so if we go ahead and so we've
got two ways of picking things on the
sphere we can touch screen and now we
could touch me to different round of
numbers as well and then I can just see
to convince myself that we're okay so 32
bit output 64 bit state is what I wanted
and the reason that I want that is
because I 64 bit state with 32 bit
output on PSG's is like the better in
terms of randomness it performs better
because it has just more bits to store
as it goes forward compared to the
number it needs to actually generate so
let's pick this one because it's the
most random one this one is a more for
speed I guess so we'll see
so let's see suppose for except to
improve the high bits and randomly
rotate other bits with six bits of state
13 on forestry code tricity as this and
so the rotation we do have
we do have in this case it looks like
I guess the idea is that the rotation
only happens on the 32-bit output which
is actually kind of nice I didn't quite
realize that I've never done this one
the 64-bit 32-bit because if you look at
the way this is written here the 32-bit
rotation doesn't ever have to update the
64-bit state so you never need a 64-bit
rotate which is kind of nice because I
don't know if there is a 64-bit rotate
on the x64 there might be I've certainly
never called it there is a 64-bit rotate
I believe though I mean a 32-bit rotate
I believe correctly this is neither here
nor there because the rotation is
actually not hard to code in emulated
basically right because you just do
multiple shifts and or in order together
but it's just kind of interesting I
didn't know that so now if you look at
what's happening here right it's taking
the sort of a fairly straightforward
thing you're doing here which is the
state X sword with itself shifted out of
18 shift it down again 27 and then it's
taking and extracting the high bits of
the state basically bits 59 60 61 I'm
sorry 60 61 62 63 and it's using those
to create no I was right sorry 59 60 61
62 C 3 to create a number between 0 and
31 to use as the rotation right so it's
using the high bits of the state to
rotate the low bits of the state
basically if that makes sense and then
here's a version of that that doesn't
use a rotation it says here it has
slightly worse petitions there's a
school performance but it's got slightly
better speed
so yeah so anyway if we look at this one
this is pretty easy to implement right
it's after we do we're gonna have to do
our X or shift part of this because we
got to do it X or shift 64 here right so
we'll do that in a second but once we
have the result probably just call this
the state once we have the state vector
the idea behind these per muted random
number generators is just to take a
random number that isn't particularly
good like the one that comes out of X or
shift which we'll do in a second here
right the X or shift goes here what we
want to do is take something that was
like a 64-bit XOR shift and now we want
to make it a much better random number
by using the bits in it to produce a
better random number out of it right and
that's what these PSG's do and so what
they do is they say alright let's take
it let's do the state X sword with the
state shifted down by 18 and then what
we want to do is shift that down by 27
and then what we want to do is do the
rotation I lost my place there
sorry about that here it is and I do the
rotation by the top fits like so now we
have a rotate as you can see I don't
remember which one she wanted us to do
[Music]
clockwise rotation so I guess I would
interpret clockwise rotation as a
rightward rotation not sure what
clockwise means in this case but I
assume it means going this way so I'm
gonna go ahead and say it's rotate right
like so and so in this case after this
has been done we want to convert this to
a u 32 because remember this is actually
a 64-bit value and we want this to be
assigned value I guess in this case this
will not give us a signed result so it
should never be signed but that's just
this expects an integer anyway so that's
just what we're gonna have to use there
and so then I believe this gives us the
result that we want here let me go ahead
and give a compilation here I
accidentally I did
yeah and so now if I want to actually do
the random bilateral version here which
is this I can take these two and these
are the same and the only difference is
which kind of random number generator
it's calling so this should be exactly
the same right so now we have one that
uses the PCG there but we are not
actually producing the xor state here
what is this thing so we need to
implement that unreachable code oh
because it actually figured out that
this wouldn't terminate that's amazing
is that actually what it did that's kind
of amazing it figured out that this
would never produce a value that would
pass this check because that was a
constant do you think that is awesome
right I mean the compiler actually
figured out that because we never modify
that state value that we'd never get out
of this loop I think that's what it did
anyway all right so let's take a look at
we need an X or shift 64 now in here
let's see that's a 128 X or shift
but what is the 64-bit version of X or
shift we have a 32-bit and a 128 unless
that extra shift 128 is actually 64-bit
it's no it's not it's at that that's
that's correctly
am I missing something fair
maybe they're too uh well maybe they're
only talking about X or shifting only
the top 32
I'm not sure if we were only gonna use a
60 32-bit xor chef because and it
doesn't look like there is a 64-bit
extra shift only 128 and 32
I'm not sure exactly what she's
referring to in here
let's take a look back
so let's take a look
here's an actual implementation
so the magic constant there's a little
odd since it's not explained anywhere
the this right here is the rotation as
you would expect the rotation to be so
this part is exactly what we wrote here
this rotate right right in fact let me
isolate it for you there so you can see
what I'm talking about
so this internal value if we just grab
that out of here so this right here is
just taking that right there that's the
rotate amount right and you can see it
doing a rotation rather than calling the
actual rotate on the chip because that
doesn't exist in see she's just doing
the rotation manually the remember I
said a few minutes ago you don't have to
worry too much about that because you
can just do it yourself but since we
have a 32-bit rotate we can just use it
it's not a big deal one way or the other
so this part right here is the part that
we're interested in and you can see that
as far as X or ship is concerned it's
just doing that right so the X or shift
part is exactly at like that's the exact
part that we wrote down from the
equation that you have there so this is
the only part that I'm not sure about
right I don't quite know where she got
the magic constant from to advance the
internal state there
looks like if someone wants to
implemented in Java or rest I don't know
she's taking contributions still yeah so
I'm not sure about that one part right
there but I guess that rules the X or
shift into it and I guess
yeah I guess I don't undersell I would
like to see a bigger more full
explanation of this part right here so
for example this rng inc or one it's not
really discussed what that is
or why you would or it with one because
you could have just stored it or with
one so there's more to it than that
right like that's not a complete
understanding of what's going on there I
don't imagine there's any more comments
in here but if there are
of course it is
let's take a look cuz I'd like to
understand where that's coming from I
don't really like it when I don't know
what something's supposed to do I feel
like that just leads to problems hello
windows maybe I won't create a folder
okay
and you want to explain what's happening
right now they went from Microsoft what
is happening right now
let's kill Visual Studio for starters
so this is still working it's just some
maybe explore and you see it could there
we go my lord all I wanted to do was
unpack this file can it do it now no
it's so I just can't hit new okay I
don't even know what to say windows it
can't even create a new director anymore
unbelievable okay so here we are on the
W Drive I'm gonna just make it from the
command line cuz apparently that's all
we can do I will go ahead and do we have
a 7-zip command line we do I guess but
it's not in the path I must see if I can
unzip it using Explorer hope springs
eternal I guess at this point and we'll
just see if that'll work
so here I go hey what do you know these
gentleman Microsoft every version of
Windows they break something new all
right so if we want to take a look at
this cuz I just wanted to see if there
was any more explanation in here of
where the magic constants are coming
from like I assume there's some kind of
a fold-down of something talked about in
the paper you know for optimality or
something like that but if I take a look
at what's going on here let's just take
a look
so it looks like the the in the actual
and petition here it does do exactly
what I said which was boring in the one
bit free so you notice the or is does
not appear here I don't know why her
other version doesn't have that probably
because she was wanted you to be able to
put anything in there even an even
number and then she would just put the
or in there so this is probably just a
more optimized version for when she
knows she's the one who initialized the
values
I guess cuz this is the more sensible
way to write it and that is how she
wrote it so I'm not sure why that other
one had something else going on
unfortunately we still don't know really
where that came from
and we're really no closer to knowing
I mean I guess she just picked a basic
linear congruential generator there
is which one of those was picked talked
about in here
let's see so that number itself appears
nowhere in the paper but it might be
just referenced in the paper to a
previous random number generator that
uses that constant
so yeah I mean it's this is just an LCG
step but I just don't see I just don't
see where in here it talks about the
particular choice I mean we could look
in here for the multiple good stuff for
good lcg's 25 so we could look at that
reference let's take a look here
that may not be online now unfortunately
oh man all right the search isn't going
to work it doesn't correctly identify
those numbers that's weird that's pretty
funny
so yeah it doesn't appear to be a direct
pull from this table but it could be a
fold you know of constants from this
table so it's hard to say
yeah
so we're gonna have to do some more
digging if we want to figure out where
that's from that's the only part that's
a little confusing here because I'm not
really sure how this LCG so you know the
XOR shift is pretty clear right but the
this particular LCG update step I don't
quite know
[Music]
I don't quite know where that's coming
from
so I guess one thing I could do is
search for it
Oh
interesting so there's our answer so
it's actually from the I guess original
Knuth version here although I guess it's
this it's actually this one since the
increment he has an increment and we
don't if that makes sense so I guess
we're actually talking about this one
more directly perhaps because it sounds
like the increment version which is this
is actually fine to be anything in our
version where it was a specific version
in in the mx1 right so
I guess that gives us everything we need
to know basically those are all our
pieces we're doing the Knuth style
linear congruential generator followed
by an X or shift followed by a PCG
rotation or shift and rotation and I
think that's it
so in theory if I want to improve the
quality of this thing then I should be
able to do so the basic version of it
would look something like this and then
we don't actually
really have a use for this right now but
it could what that sort of suggests to a
certain degree is that if we want to
pick those random numbers we may want to
use three different streams for better K
dimensional distribution right like we
were talking about before in order when
we pick our XY z-- and Z's may be a
better way to do that would be to pick
them from three different stream
selectors so that they're not picking
from the same series in order so put
that on the table this state update we
can use the old state as does she
because again she says to maximize ILP
what she means by that is instruction
level parallelism the idea here is that
if we use the state as it comes in we're
getting the previous random number
generator act the previous round number
in the series actually we don't care
whether we use I minus one or I and the
point is these computations can start
before this one finishes that does the
update so it's just better to use the
old state than the new state right since
we don't care whether we use you know
random number 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 or 1 2
3 4 5 7 8 9 10 we don't care which which
one we use we might as well always use
the the one that's one back if that
makes sense so I think that's basically
it and yeah I think that's basically it
so I want to go ahead and take a look at
at the the version of this now when we
do this and how much time you got about
15 minutes left
[Music]
and that uh looks pretty good to me so I
think that's fine
in order to random seed one of these
things though we have to have a seed
function here how are we doing this
before yeah we had random seed so we
need a random seed PCG basically one of
these and that takes the state and a
selector and the idea here again is that
the what it's doing the increment it
really wants to toggle the that bottom
one on and off it looks like because
again the the one always gets ordered in
here so it's a 1 and then any other
random bits you want but you're not
allowed to ever have an even number as
the increment or for whatever reason so
when we do a seed state equals the state
and the selector equals the selector but
we're going to shove the selector up
into the we're gonna move it up one
place when we get it and then make sure
the bottom bid is always 1 and remember
that was the part that was a little
weird about why it was being done in the
external code that was this part this
that was the part I was like why are we
oaring it every time and I guess that's
just so you can put anything you want in
here but it's a better way obviously
just two or at first and then you don't
have to do that every time right so
there's no reason not to just do it like
that alright so if we took that
[Music]
I'm making up complete nonsense there I
second let's see if we get any better
results here we probably should test
these random number generators at some
point as well
but I just want to take a look and see
oh my that's awesome
that is extremely cool not what we
wanted but very interesting so I have to
go yeah I have to go back over here and
make sure I didn't mess anything up here
um so these I think I don't see anything
weird happening here although I don't
know if I have to make sure it will do
this in 64-bit though but I think it
will this is wrong and probably had a
lot to do with it yes unsurprisingly so
that is the PCG version of things and in
theory I wrote this so that we can just
swap between them by changing this to
not be PC j-just look a little better
you know maybe it does but again not not
horrible so I guess on the whole it's
pretty hard to say I don't see a lot of
difference amongst these random number
generators for our purpose
let me also try one more thing before we
conclude for the day
let me try having a different series for
each of these well that was a incredibly
non-random set of numbers to put in
because I'm just curious what happens if
we do that if there's any major
difference between those or if it mostly
looks the same
and I honestly don't see a lot of
difference so I mean I could believe
that there was a imperceptible
difference between those two I cannot
believe that there is a significant
difference between those so as far as
I'm concerned I don't think we really
care
I mean it looks fine the the non-pc g1
looks just as good so as far as I can
tell that part is just not super
relevant like it doesn't look like our
randomness could be really doing all
that much damage maybe there's a slight
bias there but it really just does not
seem particularly bad to me so yeah I'm
gonna go and go to the QA because the
next thing we're gonna do then is just
go back to the other routine there so
I'm pretty satisfied that the randomness
doesn't really make a difference there
unless I did something wrong in my test
but visually speaking if there was a
strong difference between those two I
should be able to see it and I don't see
it so that part yeah we'll see
loketh or you can't have an even number
as a selector because then the ones that
would never flip and your period would
get cut down a few orders of magnitude
the paper goes over that at some point
if I remember correctly yeah I guess
that's true because the X or shift
doesn't modify the actual state value
when you write the state part did I have
a typo there oh I do I do not know why I
typed it that way let me double check to
make sure that didn't make a significant
difference I don't think it will because
actually that selector can be any value
I I believe here's the normal version so
that's using the old way
here's the PCG version and again pretty
similar looking if anything I would have
called it worse for our purposes anyway
let's try yeah
so I got nothing
so yeah so I think like what seems to be
the case here
unless I'm missing something is that our
particular choice of entropy doesn't
really affect this much
and look uh sir says the basic piece of
GPC g32 you're using will only be K
dimension equal distributed for simple
u-32 you three two tuples each you
thirty-two will appear two to the thirty
two times within the two statistics for
a period you'll need pc g 64 or an
extension array if you want KD equi
equidistant for v3 or more however it
probably doesn't actually matter free
rejection because you're unlikely to see
the time your loop around yeah the
generator can't loop around in in our
case right what is your opinion of
events ystem z-- and how would you
implement one I'm sorry I'm not sure
what you mean by an event system that's
a pretty broad term can you be more
specific
is there a way the slack channel can be
set up that way as newbies can catch up
and have a place ask questions as I'm
finding it hard to keep up the earlier
videos with that a lot of side
researching well there are forums if
that's what you mean
are you talking about actual like voice
chat or something
what are we sampling it for what I
missed out on that part we are just
trying to make sure that our lighting
sampling is correct for our lighting
system
so why opt for PCG or else visionary
rather than just hashing the time for a
random number
well because hashing the time is
incredibly expensive and also the time
is not random if you use it but you know
let me say this alternately so let's
suppose you get the time the time on the
system will only be accurate to a
certain degree right so if you want it
so time meaning the actual time you're
only gonna get it once every you know
millisecond or something or you know
some some the actual system time is not
accurate to to very high right it's less
than a millisecond it's probably lower
than that but so you'd have to be
talking about like are DTSC and are DTSC
isn't random
so hashing it to make it into a random
number would just be another exercise in
having a random number generator right
so you'd still do all the work you're
just doing extra work by calling already
TSC which you don't need to do because
it doesn't add entropy right I don't
know if that makes any sense but
Oh an event system for communicating
between interacting systems I mean I
don't know that there's really much to
say about it it's just a enum that says
what the event is and then a package
that has the information and I don't
know that there's a lot to it I don't
tend to think of that as a critically
important thing like if you've got two
systems that need to communicate just
whatever they're trying to communicate I
just usually send it directly in you
know like a you know a linked list queue
or something that's that's really all I
do I don't I don't get particularly
fancy in Monte Carlo estimates usually
error scales like 1 over square root
samples for 1024 samples one expects
error in the order of 0.03 and for
65,000 one expects error on the order of
0.003 therefore seem to theory you're
seeing is pretty reasonable yeah it
might be um but I don't know like I said
I wanted to make sure we didn't have any
problems first before I conclude that
it's okay what would you consider the
most performant rng despite the accuracy
I don't know I'm not an expert I know
almost nothing about random number
generators so I I really couldn't tell
you I use X or shift myself a lot
because it's simple and it's possible to
do it in sim D PSG's you can't do in sim
D really because variable shift isn't
there so like if you're doing SSE 2 or 4
you can't do a variable shift so yeah
well when you work on tomorrow I'm just
gonna take a look at the difference
between our I'm going to rewrite those
other routines that we're finding our
integration test and I'm going to make
sure that they tend to converge to the
same output because right now I think I
I suspect and I could be wrong but I
suspect that the criteria for blue noise
fort the cosine distribution so I think
we need to generate blue noise on the
sphere directly and then have a cosign
waiting I'm pretty sure I I'm just
guessing but I believe we have a problem
of the following form and I want to
track it down before we go any further
so I believe we have a problem that
looks like conventional wisdom is well
if you want to generate cosine theta
distributed points on the on the sphere
so that you get more points at the top
and less points at the periphery right
pointing this way if you want cosine
gender and a cosine theta fell off of
them then what you need to do is you
generate points on a disc that are
equally distributed and then you project
them up to the hemisphere which is what
we did and that gives you a cosine
weighty distribution now that is if the
points in this in the disc are randomly
chosen but blue noise isn't random blue
noises blue noise not white noise so
this is for white noise and white noise
is just wherever right it's completely
random blue noise if we look at the disk
it forces things to be spaced
reasonably
right what that means is there will be
more points on the outer edge right then
on the inside because as you get further
there's more area of the shape towards
the perimeter than there is in the
center that's just the property of
solids right
so for a k-dimensional shape the higher
K is every as you go from one D to 2 to
3 to 4 T to 5 to 260 270 280 290 that's
either side etc more and more of the
total volume is at the border right so
it's not that bad in 2d buts bad it's
worse in 3d very bad in 4d by 5 D 60 70
all the shape is that the border all of
the volume is at the border all of it
right it's it's why you know the it's
the standard pizza thing right if I take
a look at the if I take a look at a
circle if I take a look at our half R
and R if I take a look at these two
circles and I say what's the area of the
outer side and the inner side right well
PI R over 2 squared is this thing right
PI R squared is the outer circle so this
is the inner circle this is the outer
circle okay so the area of the inner one
is PI R squared over 4 right does that
make sense because it's PI R squared and
R in this case is R / - right
whereas the outer circle is PI R squared
but the the area in here this part is
going to be subtracted away so it's
actually PI R squared for the for the
ring
it's PI R squared minus PI R squared
over four right otherwise known as four
PI R squared over four minus PI R
squared over four which is three PI R
squared over four for three loops three
quarters PI R squared right so the inner
one is 1/4 PI R squared would be one way
to think of it versus three quarters PI
R squared right and like which one of
those is bigger well like that one right
so what I'm trying to get out here is
that if you look at how this
distribution ends up being weighted if
you assume that we are forcing even
coverage across the whole thing there's
a lot more points in that outer ring
than in the interior where as if we were
randomly picking points I don't know
that that would necessarily be true it
probably is but I'm not sure so I I
can't say for sure whether R the fact
that we have an equal coverage biases
things towards the outside because
there's more room to put them out there
and we're going to put them out there as
opposed to if we just randomly pick them
so this should be true for white noise
or blue noise I think but it's pretty
complicated and I just I can't guarantee
that I just don't know if it's true and
so without looking into it I can't say
for sure
can you see the current state of the
lighting yes I we do have a test we can
move around here so the white area
outside is the area that's outside the
visible region in the game so we aren't
running the lighting on it and the
inside is the area that we are running
the lighting on and I can move this
light around so you can kind of see how
that lighting is being calculated right
now we're not really using the lighting
points maximally because the renderer
doesn't really use them distributed the
way that it should so we will be doing a
few things to make it smooth through
here which we may or may not want I
don't know how much we want to reinforce
the blockiness
of the game's geometry we may want to
reinforce it in which case we would not
do what I just said but you know there
you go so the lighting seems to be
working pretty good right now but we
just don't have a handle on whether our
sampling weighting is correct and so
that's the part that I wanted to take a
look at right
is there an intention to support shows
from the point lights no because we
don't have any point lights we only have
area lights so we just use diffuse
lighting right now and we're not going
to do direct shadowing and again that's
because we don't currently have a
concept of a light source everything in
the game is gives a light source in a
sense so lighting comes from everywhere
be near a marching volumetric fluid
stuff no I don't think so
all right click we are out of questions
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for another episode of hand made here
it's a pleasure coding with you as
always if you want to play around the
source code at home you can always go to
the game on handmade hero or gonna come
to the source code if you want to play
around with it tomorrow we will take a
look at the actual integration thing
again and see whether or not we think we
need to modify it in some way to make it
more accurate because right now I'm
still a little concerned that it's not
really doing a properly cosine weighted
distribution on the sphere due to what
happens when you project blue noise on a
disc up to a hemisphere I'm just not
sure about it I have a bad feeling about
it
so that's we're gonna take a look at I
think we've eliminated the entropy
source as a problem today I'm pretty
confident that we're not having any
significant error coming from that so I
think we can just rule that out now and
we can just look at the blue noise
projection part and figure out if that's
okay so that's about it I'll be back
here tomorrow hope to see you all for
that until then have fun programming and
I'll see everyone on the Internet take
it easy everybody