hello everybody and welcome handmade
hero show recode a complete game live on
stream we have to do some bit to put our
thinking caps on today because basically
what we have to do now because I think
we are mostly done with asset processing
we tried out some asset pressing in
various ways and it seems to actually
work quite well and so we're mostly I
think down to just stuff that that will
sort of fine tune along the way but
there's a sort of a big issue that we've
got to deal with that I'm not sure how
exactly we're going to deal with it
because there's a lot of you know we've
got options basically and if we go out
here and look at some of the stuff just
in debug mode here that we've got you
can kind of kind of illustrate the point
so if we take a look let me move our
weird blobby thing over to this room
here so if we take a look here we've
placed a little cat in the room and you
can see the our art imports doing
exactly what we want to do which is it
brings in all the art and it tagged it
properly so this is asking for a gray
tabby and it's getting a gray tabby both
the head and the body and so on and it's
asking for the head one in the body the
other and whatever and so that's all
real good but then you see we get to
this point of like assembling the cat
and we don't really have any tools for
assembling the cat right now and the art
that we have is intentionally made with
separated heads and bodies for pretty
much all creatures that's just the
grammar and that's there because we may
want to do like swapping and stuff like
that like we may want to be able to put
different heads on different bodies and
so on maybe not necessarily with the
cats but certainly with all the rest of
the creatures and who knows maybe even
with the cats it's hard to say right and
so what we have here is a case of
needing to augment right our artwork
with information that is not intrinsic
to the artwork itself and in game
development this is a very common
problem and it's a common problem
specifically because art tools
are terrible this is just universally
true we would like ideally to have our
the things which our artists use to make
assets for our games intrinsically
understand everything about the assets
that they need to understand in order to
output the information we want right in
other words ideally if Anna's drawing
cat in Photoshop Photoshop would also
have a really clean way of knowing that
our game needs to know what's ahead and
what's the body what the tags are for
various things such as that so she can
pick them from a list the ability to
find new tags and export them to some
kind of data format we can recognize the
ability to place alignment points that
are also themselves marked so we know
how the head goes onto the body and the
ability to place like measurement
markers that say how big a particular
thing is all of these things would have
been really great and then we could have
just loaded in a data file to had
exactly what we wanted right but that is
never the reality in games art tools are
made entirely for other people
essentially even though you get a lot of
attention paid the games now in some
tools like 3d studio or Maya for example
right they still seem to overwhelmingly
be designed not around what we actually
need them to do and it is always this
kind of shoehorning process the end
result is always this really ugly
unsavory systemic I don't you want to
call its most like a Rube Goldberg sort
of contraption that is created for every
game or at least every game engine that
requires some set of steps and some set
of hacky additional data that augments
the art that gets exported in order to
properly capture at the information
that's necessary to actually represent
an asset in the game not just a bitmap
like you would post on Twitter or a
rendering that you would output
to a movie or something like this right
and it's not that games are particularly
special they happen to be the hardest
case for this sort of thing because you
typically need a lot of information
about how things can be interacted with
and how they can be modified because
games are all about interactivity and
modification but this is true even in
movies like most movies have to
dramatically augment their pipelines
from whatever art tools they have just
because again it's like our jobs are
just more complicated than art tools
typically are able to accommodate and a
lot of times because there are no
standardized ways of doing things and
you're always sort of pushing an
envelope somewhere even if an art tool
managed to internalize some process that
was was you know what we were doing five
years ago by the time they actually get
it into an art packaged and shipped it's
usually old news and not actually what
we're doing anymore anyway and still
obsolete right and so you just this is
just a fact of life it's I guess all I'm
trying to say it's just the way things
go and it's not really gonna get any
better probably so fortunately on
handmade hero we're not trying to do
anything to elaborate we don't have
really complicated 3d assets with all
sorts of additional texturing and markup
and stuff like this that's and hitboxes
and collision and physics and all these
sorts of things that would create a
really onerous load on us in terms of
how we integrate all that data together
and create art assets that we can
actually use in the game we have a much
simpler problem we just have bitmaps and
those bitmaps can largely be used
exactly as they were exported so we had
a pretty easy time devising a way of
getting those into the tool without too
much trouble
but we have now come to the point and
you to be clear you saw me work around
limitations already right
we used a grid to avoid having to have
lots of PNG s and we use the file name
to put tags in so we didn't have to have
a metadata file for each individual
thing that specified those but now we've
come to a point where we really do need
to start thinking about adding the
whatever the minimal amount of metadata
is and the reason we have to think about
that is because there's no other way
we're going to be able to deal with this
kind of scenario right the data about
where the head goes on the body of this
cat or where the head goes on the body
of anything right is simply not present
in the art data and it's not present
because it simply cannot be present
there there really isn't a clean way to
do it and if we were to create a photo
shop based markup system for that it
would probably just be a waste of time
the reason it'd be a waste of time is a
artist would have to learn it because
it's non-standard there isn't such a
thing as body head alignment in
Photoshop so we'd have to make up a
grammar for that like place this not of
a fake curve or make a layer called this
and stick it here right but more
important than that because that would
not be that bad like we could say
artists here's how that goes the worst
part is artists can't see the results
right they have to wait they have to
export out of Photoshop and then wait
for the game to reload it and even if we
make that path really fast it's this
kind of nasty like they can't you know
you want the tool you're actually
working in to show you the result right
that's the real thing that tends to be
the the blocking factor and a lot of
these art tools is you want you the
artist needs be able to see the result
and you want the result immediately if
you can you don't want to have to wait
for Photoshop to save a PNG out you know
and so yet it's it's not great so what
we would like to do potentially it just
say well can we just make a way of us
placing it in here right because if I
had a way to just sort of say here's
where the heads go on this thing and
here's the attachment point you know
here to here that would that would give
us exactly what we need right it would
allow us to instantly specify that and
then we don't have this round tripping
problem where you're gonna be fussing
with it and trying to see what ends up
looking right and other sorts of stuff
like that so I would like
to be able to create some kind of system
for doing that and actually being able
to make that markup isn't really all
that tough probably right like you know
just displaying a bitmap and having us
pick a point on it or something like
that isn't particularly difficult so
that part isn't really the interesting
part it's a little bit of grunt work but
other than that it's pretty basic the
problem that I think we're gonna have to
think about hardest is not that but
rather where does that information go
that's really the thing that's a little
bit more troublesome right and so the
problem that we have is right now we
have a notion of sort of authoritative
and non-authoritative art resources and
this is very common in games
it's in fact common in pretty much all
of computer software engineering at all
which is to say that if you look at for
example our executable our executable
isn't authoritative right the C files
that bill be executable are it's just
assumed that you could delete the
executable at any time and you can
rebuild it from the C files so having
the C files gives you the ability to
build everything the obj is the
executable the PDB they can all be built
from the C files so the thing that's
authoritative there is the C files it's
not the excusable because if you deleted
the C files you could never get them
back the executable is not sufficient to
regenerate the C files right and the
same is true for our hhas they are not
authoritative right the PNG s are
authoritative they store higher res
versions and original versions of the
artwork and we take out pieces munge
them around and produce like final
versions for use in the game from those
PNG s so the PMT's are authoritative the
hhas aren't so normally what we would
want to do is write the data back into
the PNG for example since that's the
authoritative thing we would like to say
oh that PNG now has the information so
its throat ate it
unfortunately our problem goes one
deeper than that the PNG really isn't
even the authoritative thing
it's the Photoshop file the ANA used to
make the PNG that's actually
authoritative and there's no way we're
going back to that because we don't even
have those files less machinery we just
get the exported stuff and the PSD s are
stored somewhere else right now we could
have made a PSD centric export path that
would have been interesting I have done
that before but there's a lot of things
that go along with that that I'd rather
not go into it let's put it that way so
we could have done that and then maybe
what we could have done is reinsert data
back into the PSD but then again you
would even run into problems where we
would be doing that on our machine and
then if we if Ana was working on that
PSD at the same time she would clobber
our changes potentially so you see I'm
just trying to give you some
appreciation for just how complicated
such a simple thing can actually be
because of its insertion into the
process in an unfortunate place so
typically what we do to solve these
kinds of problems is we create a
separate file right so instead of having
the PNG be the only authoritative file
or the PSD for that matter we augment
those files with an additional text file
input of some sort or it could be binary
it doesn't really matter
text is usually preferred because then
you can edit it with a text editor or
merge it with a change utility but a
binary files find - it's just a little
harder to work with sometimes right but
the point is there's a second file so
you've got dot PNG but you also have dot
txt or dot whatever and that extra file
contains whatever data the game wanted
to augment that art asset with that way
when you go and know that you need to
re-import a PNG for some reason you also
reinforce the dot txt or whatever it was
with it and that file contains the
additional information that simply
couldn't be flowed back up the pipeline
so it basically creates a bifurcation
where you say look authoritative lis
there are two files that combine to make
this file one of which we change in the
game
that's like markup specific bullying in
the game and one of which the artist is
free to modify in the tool of their
choice we don't really care what that
tool is and as long as that tool can art
put it out put a PNG we're fine right
and so I don't want to say that's a good
solution of problem because a better way
to say it would be there really isn't
much of a good solution to this problem
without going way further down the art
tool path right to places that are
themselves entire projects if not
products that you could even sell right
so like the text file method which is a
very common method is the easiest way to
create to solve or workaround this
missing data problem where you've got
data you need that the art tool simply
doesn't provide a convenient method for
creating which will hit you pretty much
in every type of game you will ever make
uh it's it's bad enough in 2d it's you
know it's still problem in 2d games for
sure like we're seeing here but it's
even worse in 3d it just gets worse it
always just gets worse right it's a it's
a problem that gets worse forever and
the only thing that really makes it you
know if it's if it is more tolerable at
all in 3d the only thing that makes it
more tolerable is that art tools are
used to in 3d and artists are used to
dealing with in 3d mark up adding
skeletons and bones and helper objects
and naming them all and having that
skeleton come come out in the export
lost art stuff that's a very common
thing to work with and understand in a
3d pipeline it doesn't exist in the 2d
pipeline very much largely again because
the tools just don't have it so you know
wait if you ever do skeletons and stuff
like that in 2d it's augmented by
secondary tool right like Photoshop
doesn't even do it really so you end up
having to have like okay the artist
experts I'm gonna Photoshop then they
loaded
to some kind of a like spriting tool
like spriter or something that allows
you to push put bones in there and then
maybe you had the mark up there right so
just it while it is a much harder and
more extensive problem in 3d because of
the amount of additional markup you need
sometimes paradoxically it's actually
easier to deal with in that realm and
the reason is because the tools always
have built into them all of this
additional markup because it had to be
there for other reasons
whereas 2d as usual you know Adobe
mostly just sucks the thumb all day so
you end up in a situation where that
stuff just isn't there you know why
doesn't Photoshop have a really complete
very good bones animation tool by now
because it doesn't have to write they'll
sell copies either way um so anyway
that's basically where we're at and just
to give you an overview of that problem
otherwise I think we're in good shape I
think we've got everything else we need
and so our goal now for this weekend is
to figure out how we're going to solve
that problem because then I think we're
ready to go on characters as well we
didn't need to solve this problem for
environments and the reason we didn't
need to solve it for environments was
because we understand how these how our
blocks are wrapped with textures and
there isn't really any need to mark them
up right there there was no additional
information we were able to define
entirely intrinsic to the art itself a
rule for how we were going to process
that type type of artwork and so that's
why we didn't have that problem but for
characters as much as we would have
wanted to be able to do the same thing
there really isn't much of a way to make
that work you know there were things I
considered and I just felt like they
were a little bit too silly and
ridiculous to try and go down so I
thought this would just be a place where
we're gonna have to bite the bullet and
add an augmentation so I think like I
said we just want to go ahead and do a
basic text file augmentation why text
file I'm not binary
because generally speaking I think that
in this case simpler is better and while
I prefer binary files typically to text
files honestly that's only once you've
gone a particular distance down your
toolkit approach like you know you want
to be able to dip these things and if
you're never gonna write like a diff
tool for your binary format then you're
not gonna invest in this binary format
long term then text is better there's a
break point there where if you're only I
spend a little bit of time on something
texts will win because there are way
more text utilities if you can just
leverage and binary doesn't really have
that same sort of thing yet I think
someday it might there are people who've
done work on arbitrary definitions of
binary files and stuff I don't know if
you're seeing that there's a project of
github for like making like little
grammatical descriptions of binary files
you know things like that eventually I
think might start to create ways we can
stop relying on ASCII so much which I
don't think is a very good format for
storing pretty much anything but at the
moment just because of the way tools
work it is better if you're only gonna
spend a little bit of time so I'm gonna
go ahead and load up here and I'm gonna
make a min estate you know here's our
art directory right I'm gonna go ahead
and make a imaginary addition to this
art directory and I'm just gonna write
it by hand first right and so what I
want to do is I want to write a text
file by hand that's going to experiment
with what we could do to markup this
stuff with what we need and then we're
going to flow that back through our
pipeline expand our definition of an HHA
to include what we actually want to have
in here in that respect and when I do
that we will get to see it all work and
make sure it's valid and when we're all
done then our tasks say for next weekend
can be to write the editor part in the
game that allows us to quickly make
those modifications visually and save
them back to the text file right and off
we go in some sense you could think of
this as look we
are just going to augment our HSA with
the data we need and we're just gonna
write stuff back to the HSA so it's
always correct the text file is just a
way of also saving that data right and
the reason for that like I said is that
HHA isn't authoritative so ideally we
want to be able to just delete and
rebuild it anytime we want because it's
our shipping format not honest or
editing format we don't want to have to
we want to be able to update like the
format of our HHA and delete it and
rebuild it anytime we want at least up
to a certain point and so you know we at
least at the very least even if we
didn't save out the text files
automatically we were at the very least
one hour HHA edit tool to be able to
unpack an HHA into text files that did
have that additional data or something
like that right so that we could rebuild
the HHA as necessary
and so on okay uh so let's suppose we
were going to work on character cat
Berman ghost here right or I guess let's
do gray tabby because gray tabby
is the one that was in that room that we
were looking at there so that may be an
easier way to do it so if I look at
character cat gray tabby dot PNG if I
just do a markup file here so I make a
you know text in here that goes with it
what we know from looking at the the
tool here let me just go ahead and not
the tool the the source file so what we
know from looking at the source file
right oh that's weird
if you zoom in far enough it handles the
Alpha properly what
what is there a rationale for that oh
okay so I think I get it now they're
scaling so they're down sampler doesn't
handle alpha but they're up sampler does
right that's probably how big it is in
the actual file if you go below that the
alphas wrong if you go above that it's
fine so nobody ever tested like at
Microsoft they were like didn't test the
down sampler for alpha there's like I
don't know man
but for some reason whoever wrote the up
sampler maybe they was the same person I
don't know but they had a bug in one and
not in the other I guess I don't know
that's crazy but there you go
so mystery solved I always wondered why
the Alpha was broken in that then now I
know never notice that before anyway
back to our story
so in each of these cases right we know
the alignment point for where the for
where the head would go would be
specified in each of these sort of each
of these turns right like the head goes
here or here or whatever so we know we'd
have an alignment point that we would
want to write out into the file for each
grid position potentially right
and same with the the heads of cells we
know that there's like an alignment
point there or whatever an alignment
point there and so on so we know we've
got like for each grid square we know we
have an alignment point that we want to
place in there you know what I mean and
that alignment point would would
basically give us the information we we
needed to align heads to bodies and we
could also have alignments for other
things but I don't so I guess we do know
one no I think about we do know one of
the thing too so we had hats first
sample that can go on to heroes and you
know I mean I guess there's no real
reason they couldn't go on to the thing
that they couldn't go on to cats as well
right you just shrink it down or
whatever and so we do also have an
additional placement situation here
which is to say that heads also have a
like adornment that they could put on as
well so if we take a look at how that's
going to work it means that we sort of
have a grids an idea that a particular
grid square has information associated
with it and we probably want to say if
we look at a character here a character
template right
we know that we've got sort of these
grid squares numbered like zero zero and
then over right going down the Y and
over an X that's the way we numbered
them when they come into the file
because again PNG is start at the top
and go down and that's what we're
loading here so you know if we wanted to
specify like a grid square for example
right we could say you know we could we
could make some syntax and I don't know
what that syntax should be right but we
can make some kind of a syntax for
saying look what's the what's the grid
square that we're talking about here you
know what's the what's the actual grid
square we're talking about and then we
could make some way of inside that
talking about properties that that grid
square has you know what I mean like
what are the points that we care about
that are related to this particular
object right and so what we want to do
there is just have a few things that we
can specify and so for example you know
maybe we want to do like two types of
attachments so like attached to or like
you know we want to have sort of
attached parent you know an attached
child or something like this right so in
other words if you put a hat on a head
that's where the try
would attach if you put the head onto a
body the head is saying where what the
parent attach point is the body is
saying what the channel attach point is
and they match up you know what I mean
um and I don't know that right now we
have anything that doesn't follow that
basic pattern meaning there's only
attachments that go on that way I don't
think there's any other kind of
attachment like I don't think we need to
contemplate that there are attachment
like slots right attach parent is
obviously unique but attached child you
know you could imagine there being like
multiple places to put something and I
think we can cross that bridge if we
come to it I mean it's pretty easy to
augment whatever you do here to have
that but at the moment I would say I
don't know that we really need that
because I don't think we're gonna have
that I wish I could think of a place
where that would actually be necessary
but I'm just not
I'm just not thinking of anything off
the top of my head so we'll see you know
we'll see where it goes if we want to be
future proof we could you know we could
do something there maybe when we're in
there we'll make it so that that thing
can be an array and we'll go from there
but you know if you imagine something
like this which just said look here's a
grid square and then for that grid
square we're gonna attach a bunch of
information then what we could say is
you know all right
the parent attachment is some position
right you know it's like this kind of
thing you know what I mean
and then the the child position is some
other thing like so on and I want to say
that we probably want scale as well here
so you know I want to say that we
probably want some way of saying how big
the thing would be you know what I mean
I don't know how we want to specify that
but something where we would say you
know if you attach me to anything I'm
you know half the size that normal stuff
would be or like here's how big I I am
and so I don't know that might be
something that we want to specify as a
scale maybe just in general so you know
maybe we would say something like this
you know and so that would just allow us
to change how big the thing is in the
world right so this is like how many
meters the thing is or who knows what
and maybe I'll say size cuz it's not
really scale you know it's like oh this
is 4 meters big or a point four meters
you know who knows right something that
and then on here what we could do is say
you know when you do an attached child
you can also spell
2phi the size right so you would say
look it's you know anything that I
attach gets a scale value and and you
know you know maybe you could just say
it this way right so like anything that
attaches to me gets it instead of it
being its normal size it's like a tenth
the size the reason I say that is
because you know like let's say these
hats we kind of just want to play fast
and loose with them so you know you put
a hat on one of the hero characters well
not what I hear one of the orphans like
so the hero or any of the orphans you
know it's going to be a particular size
we then put it on two we then put it on
two like the cat it's gonna have to be
smaller so we would want the cat to say
that like the cat's artwork just as look
when you put something on here it gets
this much smaller right so I think I
think that's basically all we need there
yeah trying to think if there's other
stuff we want to but I think that's
basically it so we want something like
this this is the size value this is a
scale value they're different right this
is basically saying this is the
percentage of the size of the child to
use and this is saying here's how big I
am generally speaking when I'm not being
scaled or at a scale of 1.0 so I think
we could do something like that attached
parent attached child birth would just
be percentages inside the square and I
think then we'd be good to go
so I think that's pretty good here's
what I will say I think we also want the
ability to be a little bit more broad
right so I think we want to be able to
say something like well okay you know by
default the size for like some range of
the squares is gonna be you know this
and by default the range of the other
ones is going to be something else or
whatever right so it would be nice to do
something where you said you know maybe
something like this so you could just
say look the default size and child
scale or this and then I'm going to
specify some specifics here which can
override them if you want to I'm trying
to think of like how I want to specify
that
because typically speaking we're gonna
want at least two of those you would
want one for up here and one for down
here right and so you'd want to be able
to do something and I'm not sure exactly
like how to do this but you'd want to do
something that looked like like that you
know where you could just say look for
all of those that's what it is and for
all of these that's what it is not sure
what the best way to annotate that is
cuz there isn't really a way to do that
and see there's no like we don't really
if we're trying to stay with sort of see
like see it see like syntax the ranges
are really the issue but you can you
know imagine these getting applied in
this way right and so we could do
something like that where we've got
different things applied and then any
individual one can also be specified but
in general like you just read these in
order so this gets applied to all of
these this gets applied to all of these
and then this gets applied only to this
particular one you know
that seems fine to me like I don't see
much I don't see much issue there I
don't know how everyone else feels about
that but that seems like a pretty
reasonable syntax and I don't know that
we really need much else there I think
that's all we would actually care about
yeah
all right I suppose the other thing that
I'm not really sure about so one thing
that's a little bit weird there is
trying to understand exactly how those
things would be edited is a little
tricky but I feel like you could pretty
much just do this directly and I think
we'll probably be fine
so we free we're gonna put these in the
HHA so I'm gonna load up file formats so
if we were gonna put those in the HHA i
have to think a little bit about how we
want to represent that so i kind of
almost feel like that wants to be its
own array almost it's hard to say
if you look at the way that HHA bitmap
is defined then a line percentage is
attached parent so we have that in there
currently and the question is just you
know should we all mint that structure
to effectively have a bunch of markup in
it you know we just say this thing is
pretty big so it's got you know a whole
mess of stuff so the size the child
scale the parent attach and all that all
goes in there and I'm not sure my guess
is the answer should be no and the
reason that I say that my answer should
be no is because the HHA bitmap I
believe is streamed in and so really
this is where you would rather oh okay
well so it isn't streamed in so we do
have that loaded so I thought maybe this
data was part of it so okay so that's
fine no then it can totally go here
right
that's totally fun
I just wanted to make sure that this was
always accessible to us at all times and
not something that got streamed in
because I want to be able to know this
information without having to stream it
in and so that's good I'm relatively
happy with that so yeah thinking it
through just in my head
[Music]
I guess I would say it probably belongs
there
and that's a reasonable place to put it
having to attach things that may
actually be separate entities does
become it becomes kind of interesting as
to how we're exactly going to handle
that but I don't think at the end of the
day it's really all that difficult
because once we know where the entities
are then in it's really just the same as
having traversable x' so I think we'll
probably end up doing as traversable x'
when you actually say I need to place
this but this thing on this particular
traversable or whatever I think all you
really have to do is then say okay the
same kind of thing happens for placing
stuff like hats which would maybe be a
separate entity onto a particular
character
right and
yeah and again this is sort of stuff
that we're gonna have to feel it over
time but just thinking it through that
all sounds pretty good to me so yeah
I think I'm good with all that I think
that's all fine I don't really know but
it seems okay and so if we wanted to
make this stuff be represented in here
let's say right and we wanted to augment
the file to have these then what I would
do is say in addition to the dimensions
of the bitmap itself and the align
percentage here right what we want to do
is have the like the child align right
which is this bit we would want a child
scale value and our scale value so we'd
really want to just have these something
like this and so really all we be doing
here is saying in addition to storing
the dimensions of the bitmap as they
actually are we've got a ton of like
floating-point stuff now here that we're
gonna pack in there as well and this is
you know going to be parent blind to
kind of go with this and if we just
adopt this naming convention over here
as well which seems good I could say
that
oops that's okay that was already ranked
and so these would just be directly
imported into the file right I guess
that's all I have to say about that we
can like I said try to plan for future
expansion there by saying if we want
more alignment points per bitmap we can
make that child align be fattier so you
could say you know you get eight of them
or something
I just don't know to what extent that
really makes any sense because I don't
know how we would actually differentiate
between those attachment points in the
first place like we would have to start
like naming them or something right
you'd have to start saying here's the
child Lyman point and what kind of
alignment point it is right and we could
do that if we wanted to you know I don't
know maybe we should I guess it's kind
of free for us to do so so we could do
something like you know this so you just
say like look this is where a hat goes
and you know here's where my belt goes
or something I don't know right so you
could imagine something like that where
you just had like a who knows you know
here's top of head
and here's
you know something like that or like
base of neck right we totally could do
that and if we did want to do that then
you know we could imagine augmenting it
with something like this so we could
essentially say you know okay there's an
HHA alignment point you know and an
alignment point actually has a lot of
information on it it says like you know
how big the child should be that goes
there what type it was so you know what
it what kind of alignment point it is
you know like that who knows and you
know some location like where it is you
know
something like that
so then we could say well now you know
you get some of these you get HHA line
points and you can just put those on if
you want them and then you can attach
things to other things and off you go
and then when we talk about this one how
this one attaches to other things what
we could basically say there was well
okay so we also have an HHA line point
for the parent and that maybe only has
one and it's the same thing right so you
know you could treat it like this where
you just have like here's the parent
side here's the child side and this
stuff is just not there right and maybe
get seven of these total and one of the
other one to make eight in all so if you
look at that that actually I mean it's
pretty good actually now I think about
it it seems pretty reasonable because
now we can basically say all right I've
got one point I specify which tells me
my size relative to my parent right
where it is on me and what I am trying
to attach to so basically like the heads
would all have a base of neck as their
attachment point because that's what
they're trying to go on to you know and
so we could encode what it's supposed to
stick on to then in here when we got
child points you know a body would have
a P percent of where the neck was a size
of probably 1.0 on heroes anyway because
it's not going to be smaller than normal
and then the type would be base of neck
so those two
matchup right and that way you could
just look when you want to put a bitmap
on another bitmap you can just look to
see where there is a point that is the
same as the point that the thing wants
to attach to and you just use it so that
would give us the ability to have lots
of different attachment points on things
and you know obviously each one of these
right has a total of four four byte
values so it's 16 bytes per right and so
really you can even be more generous
here if you wanted to be I also say have
a none value so you know we could even
make it considerably more so in case you
wanted to have something that has stuff
stuck all over it for some reason or
where's multiple hats because you know
you're making portal 2 or something you
could do that
now you know it seems pretty good the
only thing I would say is you know does
rotation need to be in there I mean it
could be that you want to wear a hat
like on the side of your head versus on
the top I don't know that that really
works particularly well so I don't know
that we want to have that in there seems
iffy to me kinda but there there you go
right so I think that's mostly
everything we would need so it would
look kind of like that and this stuff by
default would just be like zeroed out or
set to point five point five and one as
default values might be more sensible
yeah and that'll be that well I mean
really can just be zeroed out because if
the type field was aged a bit that the
line none then you know it's
uninitialized and can't really be used
for anything so that's fine too
so I guess I'd put one more in here
which is if we're just free-floating in
the world like we're not actually
attached to anything then this is the
one to use as well right
and I guess when I think about that the
only thing I'm not sure about is if
there's something that wants to be in
both places and wasps have specified
different values does it imply that you
sometimes need multiple parents as well
right
so I guess what I would say is maybe we
just go absolutely nuts with this and
just say like a line point 16 and then
we just say all right and we say look if
you set the high bit here right which I
technically don't know if it'll complain
about this because C++ is terrible and
Oasis bad at everything I don't know if
you're allowed to have a high bit
because I want to say that it maybe only
wants these to be signed or some stupid
thing like that but we'll find out so if
we were to say that let's take a look
here
yeah so this would have to be a bit
larger to have that many wonder how many
we could have without making ourselves
larger not much huh
13 you 60 floors so there's one new 64
so that would give us 12 so we would
only be able to have six if we were
gonna have the if we were gonna stay
inside the size that we previously
requested for these guys which is 128 2
cache lines wide since I don't know that
we need that many of them I guess I
would be inclined to say maybe we just
leave it at 6 for now because since the
H at JS are just the resource format it
seems like we could add more if we
needed them later and then just rebuild
the output data so it seems fine and
then we don't expand our footprint at
all it keeps it relatively clean and we
can also if we wanted to we could be a
little bit more judicious with our use
of sizes in general so for example we
could just make these more concise as
well right like we could say that this
is all done this way and it really
wouldn't affect things much right so you
could do that
and then you could have twice as many
write in the same size so you know we
could do something like that for P
percent this seems very smart to do it
that way because you don't give up any
precision you effectively have exact
same precision for size it's a little
bit hard to specify what that would mean
because you'd have to say well how am I
supposed to find this size in the first
place like you know how do i encode the
amount of scale that I want
into a u16 but I still think it's
probably pretty easy I mean we're not
going to encode sizes of like more than
you know 50 or 60 or hundred or
something so if you assume that you can
you know you've got six five five three
six total values right so one over six
five five three six there is that if I
multiply that by a hundred to say that
the maximum scale is a hundred then
you'd still have precision all the way
down to like 0.002 at worst right
which seems fine so we can we can do it
this way and then have a lot of them and
still not take up very much space either
and the type field again not a big deal
because we also know for that field I
mean there's only gonna be like 30 or 40
of these in our wildest dreams we're not
gonna have 65,000 of them because oh my
god I don't even want to know what kind
of a world we've created if we have
65,000 different ways that things can
attach to each other the designers have
gone crazy if that's what happened right
so I think that's probably good I think
that's roughly where we would want to be
and so if we just go ahead and clean
that up a little bit then I think we're
good I maybe would say that
HHA bitmap alignment world is maybe
you'll not right
maybe there's default so in other words
if I don't know what I should be doing
then I use this one so if you attach me
to nothing like I'm floating in the
world I would use it and I'll also use
that if you attach me to something I
just don't know what it is so like you
know I attached you to top of head on
somebody but you don't specify
top-of-head then I'll use the default if
there was one specified you know what I
mean so there's kind of like a fallback
procedure there where you know default
will match anything and it's overridden
if you can find a specific match you
know what I mean so that seems
reasonable maybe possibly who knows and
that allow so that would allow Philips
to specify twelve alignment pieces of
alignment information which seems good
and hopefully would get us past anything
that we might need to do but again we
could also expand that if we felt like
we needed to for some reason so I think
that's okay again these are for you 16
so this right here excuse me so this
right here is is 8 bytes right / I want
to say right - 2 - 2 so it's a total of
8 bytes which means that you know let me
just think about how much that would be
yeah so 12 8 byte alignments right is 96
bytes and then we've got the dimensions
here that are specified that gives us us
more there really is no way to trim that
down in any way that we probably care
about because we could change that to 16
but it wouldn't help us get an extra
alignment point in there so I'm not sure
that we really care about that
what we could do here though however mmm
we could do something like this
and so that way all of these things are
encoded in u16s so they're all gonna be
the same size there and then we'd have
two more to play with here in case we
needed to use those for something else
and we just clear that Missouri normally
the other thing we could do there so the
bitmap Jim is specified but the other
thing we could specify there is what the
original dimension of the bitmap was I
don't know if we really need that for
anything I don't think we do because we
could just use that to set the initial
size parameter inside the align point
and so I don't know that we care
particularly much about what that
original dimension is you just probably
don't care
so I'm going to say let's leave it like
that and let's verify that if I up this
by one listen that we aligned it right
yet the sizes is wrong so I think that's
everything there if we look here at when
we're in the hej editor and we're
dumping the information the alignment
information is now incomplete because
we've got multiple alignment points that
we might want to print out right and so
what I'd like to do here is all you know
augment this when we see a bitmap I'd
like to go through and actually print
out all of the alignment points so I'm
gonna say well let's call it point index
I'm gonna say asset oops
zero point index is less than array
count did we cast this bitmap I think
yet we did bitmap align points so just
iterate over all of them and if it's
specified then I will print it so it's a
line point point equals bitmap the line
points point index so I've pulled out
that point and I'm just gonna look to
see if the type is not you know none
then I'm going to print out the data
from that particular point now while I'm
printing this I probably want to use
indentation of some kind so I probably
want to do something like this
and I probably want to do that if it's
not the first one right so I want to do
something like and here you know if
something like that so you know if this
is the first one then let's just mark
the factors alignment in this thing and
then we'll print out that particular
point so you know whichever one it is
which is point index we'll say here's
this one we want to print out the type
so we want like a line type name from
and I'm gonna say whatever this type is
give me back string I could print right
so in here I can say what type it is
and then I want to be able to print out
this stuff so the P percent the size the
type we've already said what it was so
we just need these two now and so in
there I've got point P percent and just
to make that back into a float because
these are encoded like as you sixteens I
probably want to say something like this
right
so we can look at them as percentages
rather than looking at them as u16s
because you know that's the way that
we've encoded it and the size is another
one of those now because this is
something we're probably going to do
frequently we may want to bake that
encoding into a function so we may want
to do something like you know like this
so we can pass in one of these points
and get the decoded version in a
predictable way in case we want to
change the encoding later and again as
you know I am NOT a fan of using get or
set functions I think they're dumb and a
waste of everyone's time but once you
actually have work to do then they're a
good idea because hey now I can just
have that work done for me and I'm
actually creating a function that does
something not just wasting everyone's
time and so in this case since we've
already got that happening everyone's
going to have to do this work let's just
make that a utility so that everyone can
call it and that gets us both things it
allows us to change how we encode it
later and it makes it easier for the
people calling it so it's a win-win
instead of a lose-lose like it would
have been if we just added it for a pair
value like type for example so that
allows us to create recreate the
percentages and then I can just do that
instead so I can do P percent equals get
P percent and then I just passed the
point that I'm asking for here and then
I can just do P % XP percent Y and it's
you know much easier for me to use
because now I don't have to understand
how those values are encoded because
they are encoded
so get science would be the same way you
know it's something like this but it's
not exactly this and that's the that's
the thing that like I sang for is a
little bit confusing to think about
right so if we did this then you could
you could represent any size you wanted
up to 1.0 but you couldn't represent
more than 1.0 and so what I think we
want to do here is say look there's a
additional multiplier on the front end
that just says that's the maximum scale
you can ever scale something and
everything else is going to be less than
that but it's still significant more
than 1.0 right and that seems reasonable
to me so I think that's what we'll do
and could also just been uniformity sake
do it this way just makes it easier to
inspect those values than to bugger when
we're you know invariably stepping
through this because we want to verify
what's working and what's not and so on
so there's the point index there's the
string there's the three values that we
want to know in terms of the location of
things and their size that's all we
really need for this part of the process
but we do need a way to get this data in
here and you know it's the same as you
can see we've got the same stuff that
we're talking about here for other
things like how to get the tag names and
so on and so what I'd like to do there
is just say yeah let's let's do the same
thing for the aligned names and I should
probably just follow exactly what we've
been doing right so you know this exact
thing we should probably just do for the
alignment points as well right so in
here when we say a line type name from
just like we had here and you know I
guess thinking about it going forwards
we're probably going to need this to be
parsable too if we
do you have these in a in a string
format that we're saving out so really I
think we want this whole process like
this whole thing probably needs to be
probably needs to be there as well
right so I'm just gonna go ahead and
copy this and put it in here and so what
we're gonna have here is assuming this
is a a line point name or a line point
type name something like that right and
this would be a line point type there
you go
and so this is literally just gonna
provide that same exact kind of
translation table but for a different
that type of thing right
and so in here we've got this many of
them and it's gonna be a little bit
different so there is a little bit more
we have to do so it's not as
straightforward but it's pretty similar
so that's what we expect so far and then
in here where we go to pull this out if
I say instead of tag name for my D if I
say I'm a line name from type so if I
pass one of those types in and then we
look it up we would do exactly the same
thing here we look through all of the
names that are in the mix we look at one
of them and we see if the types match
and if the types do match then we just
return whatever the name of that one
actually is if not we just return
unknown and the same thing would happen
here so HHA fit map a line type when we
look through here we say a line point
type from name you pass in the name we
search through the list so it's not an
asset tag ID it's an H it's a bitmap a
line type that comes back we assume that
we can't match it so it's a none we look
through all the names and if we
eventually find one that that matches
then we return it
right so the only thing that's important
to remember here is that when we're
working with these we need to also check
for the parent flag because that's going
to be welded onto the type field and so
you know we want to be able to crack
that as well and so one way to do that
is is is to parent and you can pass that
in here and that just says okay you know
if the the type has that flag set then
it is and then the other thing you can
say is
get me the type so here we would say I
want to cast us to an align type and I
want to only have the part of the type
that doesn't have the rest of it in it
right like so so we have yeah as I said
we have this so I'm gonna go ahead and
put those in here just we can expand
them out a bit and see them clearly and
again this is just all of the encoding
and decoding work here well it's really
just a decoding work we haven't done
encoders for these but that's you know
probably less important we may not
actually need those to be their own
functions because less people are going
to be doing that possibly only one
person and then we can just have that in
line all right so now you can kind of
see those a little more clearly there
but but what they're doing is very
obvious right so I've got the align
points there and I can crack out the
data from them now when I do when I need
the information from them I can say oh
is it one that goes to parent or not and
what's the type so that way you know
when I'm actually know what happened
there what I'm actually doing something
like this if I compile it it'll give me
an error because this is not oh well
it'll give me an error because it's
named wrong that wasn't actually what I
was going to say
what I was trying to say is this error
is when I want to do explain so it'll
give me an error because it's not the
right type and that's good because
really this isn't that type this is the
type with with a possible flag well done
and at the top and so what I want to do
is have a way of getting the align type
here from from this and that's what I'm
going to print which is cracked and then
I would say you know is it to parent and
that's to get another thing right so in
here I would print this and then I'd
also want to print something else like
it doesn't attach forward it doesn't
attach you know I don't know how we want
to write that probably I'd want to write
that as like outgoing or incoming so
maybe I would do this I know this is
hard to say but so if it attaches back
to the parent it looks like that if it
attaches to a chart to something on the
other side you know what I mean honestly
I feel like it maybe should be written
like this so like if it goes to the
parent then you'll see a little thing
that sort of says like it's back going
back that way so it would meet something
on the other end and then if it's not
going to the parent then it's an
outgoing connection and would have a
thing going that way you know I don't
know don't look at me uh that's all well
and good
lying type there and I think that gives
us what we want the only issue here is
our percent s is I don't remember if we
ever actually fixed those so that we
could print strings ok it looks like
we're still doing dot stars for those
and I'm not sure that that's like such a
good idea because you could see how no
this gets you know with all the dot
stars so I kind of feel like to a
certain extent you know I don't remember
where we put this stuff probably in
utils right because it's just orb shared
or something yeah so in here you know
when we look at what the type of the
thing is it's coming through in here you
can see us grab a string and we could
instead just have another case where we
know that there are strings that just
get pushed on as strings you know I'm
saying and it would require us to
finding a different letter code that's
like non-standard which is a little bit
bad because compilers now have welded in
checking because of course that's how
they chose to solve that problem instead
of just letting you write your own
checking yeah if you want to know how to
do this correctly go look at how John
did it in his language it's actually
correct so you can add your own codes
and check them which is kind of the
obvious thing that someone who
programmed computers for a living would
do and therefore not what the C++ people
do whatever so what you want to do here
is you want to go well is that worth it
I think it probably is cuz this is just
super error-prone like it's just not
good and so constantly having this
notion of how things are gonna be casted
and dealt with it's just it's just bad
right it leads to a lot of air proneness
so I think because we're using that more
here I just want to go ahead and support
that and so let's say we did add one
here you know I don't know what would be
an unused letter but like a capital S
might be an example of something
reasonable to use and if we then just
grab this here and do the exact same
case really all we're saying is that
it's mostly this
is this case but we're grabbing on a
string like that so we're gonna get a
you know this kind of composite case
right and so when we do this temp equals
thing we're actually gonna do it
this way to grabbed out of the buffer I
don't know why we say obaid precision
and then we proceed to obey the
precision so I think maybe we were only
talking about with there or something
I'm not sure so that's a little bit hard
to square I'm not sure what that to do
actually means in this case but if the
precision is specified then here we say
like okay you know well it's less
imprecision take a look at the size or
whatever and then you know otherwise we
use the full length of the string so
what we can do here is something a
little bit better what we can do instead
is say look set temp test size equal to
what the strings length would be because
we know that we already can get that for
free it's with just a known value we
load and then if the precision is
specified then all we have to do is use
the lesser of the two so if you specify
a particular precision then rather than
doing this we can just say all right if
temp test
size was going to be greater than the
precision then clamp it down to the
precision but otherwise you don't need
to do anything right and so you know we
can even make that part of a compound
predicate here like this and so if we
would need to clamp then clamp otherwise
don't and then when we get the temp test
at out of this we would just say okay
however much
I assume we want the app to always be at
the end it looks like so we just want to
advance to how much we do so that's fine
as well right so I think that would just
output a string for us directly you know
with no with no other fuss and such
right let me take a look at where that
was trying to happen oh sorry
so why isn't that
okay so it's sets so this is just I
don't know why we wrote this like this
so this is just temp as well right so
I'm not sure why it wasn't written like
that but you know it wasn't so I'm not
sure anyway so what we can do here now
is just say look that's the capital S
and that'll print that out oh all right
looks like somebody oh man I take it
back
we're not using our string out are we
here hmm that's unfortunate
well I tried I tried to be good but
we're not using our runtime library so
that's unfortunate that's really too bad
we tried right I mean we tried we tried
to make a good system but again you know
yet another reason not to use a C
runtime library right can't make your
own printf so we guess I'm okay with
guess I'm okay with that
I don't love it but that's where we're
at
now that that's taken care of I think
we're good to go on the HHA edit front
but now we got to go in here and do some
other saucy maneuvers now one thing I
should mention is that when we're
loading the HHA bitmap
these zeroes in yes so in this case here
we need to have this b + HH a bitmap v 0
because we did update how that's stored
right so if you look at I mean this is
not really necessary because really what
we should do eventually is just be able
to rebuild them without having the old
ones ever loaded but you know it used to
look like this
and so you know if we want to continue
to have the ability to load that old
format we should respect it right so
that's the way we were doing that and
what that implies is that here when we
actually load the data in we can't
actually do a trivial conversion like
this anymore what we have to do is
actually convert the data from the old
format to the new format so that we
properly included now that's not
particularly hard to do because in this
case it's really pretty straightforward
we clear the bitmap asset out I believe
to 0 first or at least I hope we do let
me just see if that's actually true no
asset
yes so we clear it out so everything's
set to zero so we only need to set
fields that we actually get from the
original khat one so if we look at what
those are right there just the
dimensions and the align percentage
right that's what we're actually gonna
get but we need to encode them
differently so when we actually set the
encoding for these we probably want like
I saying to do an in-and-out so for
things that are going to encoded in
multiple places we probably want to be
able to do those in and out so for a
line percentage I'm gonna read it out of
the destination like so yeah so a line
percentage of zero and one kind of want
that to be here but for coder thinks
otherwise so that's that's that right so
I can get my aligned percentage like so
and then I can get my dimensions largely
directly
and the only difference here is I have
to truncate the music scene but we know
we don't have any bitmaps larger than 65
thousand pixels so this is free because
we all know all of the visa assets that
exist and none of them have that so once
we grab that let me copy this then all
we need to do is generate one synthetic
align point that mimics our old one
align point that we had right so in a
line points zero which I think I'll make
it a little easier in myself and just
well maybe what I'll do here it actually
is just do one in code that kind of
writes the whole thing so maybe what
I'll do is something like this so set
the first align point right and set it
to when I'm what I've got here
right so it's an align point that goes
to the parent it's not a child align
point right so I want to say that it's
to parent I want to say that it's the
default right something like this I want
to say that the size is 1.0 and I want
to say that the align percentage is the
thing that I read out of the source file
right now I don't know if I really want
to were these two together but maybe I
do so maybe I would just say something
like this and the other way I can do it
is comma true and have it do the or
[Music]
maybe like that I don't know I'm of
mixed feelings on that because in the
one hand I I'm not doing the or makes it
so that I can pass a boolean pretty
cleanly here from some source on the
other hand when it's bare like that it's
a little bit ugly so we'll see but
anyway let's just call it that way for
now and then what I'm going to do is
inside here where we've got the stuff
that does the decode I'm gonna put in a
thing that does the encode right
and so what I'll do here is just say
pass me in a line point as my
destination and then pass me in a line
point type why we didn't just call this
a line point type or maybe we did I feel
like it's a little weird right like this
is called an haja line point and this is
called a bitmap a line type which is
dumb it should look like that
let me just clean that a little bit
there we go all right
much better so anyway once we get all
that in there we should be able to just
do one that truly sets it as well so
when I've got this destination here
parent and then we've got our size and
then we've got our key percent here's
all the information that we want to set
in this thing and what I'm going to do
is just fill it out right so I'm going
to say okay you got the P percent we got
the size we got the type this is all the
stuff that we need actually put in there
and so I will say this is the type board
with two parents and so there we're just
saying look if we know the type goes in
the type field we know that two parent
is going to or in either the two parent
flag or nothing depending on whether
it's set and so that'll take care of
that part of it the size we then have to
encode into a range so that we can use
it as a 16-bit value here so what we
want to do there is say for both that
and P percent we want to essentially do
look we got a cast us to a you 16 but
first we got to convert it so when you
pass in like you know the P percent
whatever that P percent values
X is cuz I gotta do this twice whatever
that P percent values X is I just want
to blow it out to however big a you 16
could be and then leave it at that
right so literally all we're doing here
is saying look it's a zero to one value
that we're talking about so when we go
to read it just multiply it by six five
five three five and store that as a you
16 because we know that's the way we're
going to reverse convert it later and
that'll be the closest we can get to the
input floating point value for the
science we'll do the same thing we just
say look we know we've got this funky
kind of like you know the other way to
look at this would be look we're just
solving the equation right we've got you
know stored equals you 16 max over P
percent so if we want to get people sent
back it's just you know swapping the the
sides that that's already on so anyway
hopefully everyone sees that and I don't
do it on the blackboard but if anyone's
confused about that I can do it on the
blackboard it's just I'm literally
solving the equation you know if result
x equals this right which is what we're
saying here then obviously if what I
wanted to do was get back what's being
stored in here then I just need to
reverse this equation right so I need to
multiply both sides by P percent so that
clears it out of the denominator and
puts it into the numerator times the
numerator but on to the other side the
new the numerator of the other side and
then I need to divide by result X right
I do that right
not so good with doing math in a text
editor
wait so that would be correct but this
is wrong I was gonna say that I did that
math correctly but this is not correct
why did I write that that way that's
what it should be right
all right so glad I happen to do that
out because that was just wrong yeah I
don't know why I wrote that way
originally right why did we do that that
was I don't know I guess I must have
could not be thinking I typed it in but
this P percentage is a value from zero
to you 16 max right so in order to
change it to a value from 0 to 1 we
would want to divide by you 16 max so
that's what should have been written
here not what I wrote before which
probably people on the stream already
caught of course I'm not reading stream
by program as per the rule but
presumably someone saw that hopefully
someone saw that if not then you're
sleeping on on watch as well anyway let
me do that one more time so assuming
that you know we've got this equation
here what I want to do is solve for this
so it's that which now gives us the
answer that I typed in down here which
is what we want but before we didn't get
that because I had written this equation
wrong unsurprisingly if you write the
wrong equation when you solve it you get
a different equation um so yes so that's
all I was trying to say there and I'm
really glad that I happen to digress
there because that saved me the trouble
of having to debug that later and look
under why did I write that so anyway we
should have a complete setting now for
these so we can get and set them and
they will look in code and decode the
sort of values into what they need to be
and I think that's fairly complete right
this has to probably be cast to you 16
because it's not a get like the compiler
PI doesn't necessarily know that its new
16 or not I should double check to see
what it says
see if it's telling me something I
wouldn't order you know yeah I think
that's just integral promotion because
there's nothing in there that's greater
than you 16 but I guess it doesn't
really know that so if we now take a
look at what's going on here let's see
we've got a few places where these type
names are wrong because I've changed
them to be easier to understand and okay
so that's everything we need to do to
handle HHA files in that new way I argue
and then we also have when we're
actually doing work in our bitmaps you
can see there's some places where this
stuff's actually used right and so when
we loft some of these pieces of
information up here you can see us we're
relying on this information and we now
don't necessarily have it anymore right
like we don't have an aligned percentage
anymore to loft up into our bitmap now
what we can do is just read the first
one so we certainly can just say get P
percent and just say look give me the
one from align points zero and off we go
so I have to put it to do here
so we kind of need to make some more
thoughtful stuff here you know we got to
think about this a little bit more so
we'll we'll talk about that a little bit
later obviously but as it is right now
we can sort of just keep that sort of
odd spotlight there inside here where
we're actually creating these we're
gonna have to augment this significantly
because this is where we want to now put
the parser that can read this
information from an actual source file
right and so that's something that we
have to take into account and do more
directly
now storing this stuff this is just a
question of actually packing down to a
u16 which is fine and we may want to
check your but I don't know like I'll
say maybe we check here and an error
it's okay because maybe we do want to do
that the future I don't want to deal
with it now and so really all we're
talking about now is the fact that these
defaults were here and now they're not
gonna be here anymore
what I'm gonna do is again just continue
what we were doing before which is just
say look let's let's go ahead and set
this to the same default it was being
set to just for now and then we'll all
meant that by actually parsing a file
text file and seeing if there is
anything in it that we need to process
there so when I set this a line point
I'm just gonna say like okay got these
bitmaps aligned points and what I want
to do is then set it to exactly the same
default values we were setting the other
ones too so in here right I'm just gonna
say HHA aligned default I'm gonna say
true for the
parents I'm going to say that the size
should be 1.0 and that the P percent
should be 0.5 0.5 and then I'm gonna get
rid of this right so now that should
completely mimic the original behavior
and our only issue that we have now is
that our hhas we want to update them to
the new format right so if I go to our
data directory right like what you can
see is we've got these here and you can
look remember where our be zeros were
there they are so you can see we have
all these V zeros and we want to be able
to use V 1 files so we want to be able
to update those V zeros to the ones
right so what I want to do here is
delete those hhas yeah delete these hhas
that we have that our view ones here and
make the you know sort of into V twos
now I'm not gonna add support for
converting the ones to V 2 because we
don't eat it and really conversion can
go away eventually because we can just
go directly from our source pngs
but what I would like to do is respect
the fact that we change it so if anyone
ever did want to just as an exercise it
would be nice if they could go OK we can
actually tell the difference between all
these version numbers so I'm gonna make
the version number b2 here uh and go
from there right now in the HHA edit
code path let me just see here
where is our ehh ehh there it is
so what I want to do here is essentially
say look we're not gonna actually
preserve this path because I don't care
about it so I'm just gonna go ahead and
do this right like so and so now if I
actually try to HHA edit one of these
files so test one of you and I say it
should tell me that it doesn't should
tell me that doesn't know what it is
right and that's exactly what I want so
you know if I tell it to dump it it
should just not you'll do it and so
that's like I said we could support
those old ones I just don't care about
it so like eventually the hej editor can
just lose backwards-compatibility more
or less for anything that we don't
actually ship a jamais for right up to
the end of hand-made here our production
because we'll just rebuild things from
the pngs and be fine but once if people
start trading a jamais around you know
when the game is released or something
then we would if we updated the format
we would support both formats probably
right ok so what I want to do now is
just quickly check to make sure that
this work that also will just do a
little bugging and then we'll call it a
day so I'd like to see if I can recreate
these hhas so you can see local HHA is
not an issue that's not something to
care about so really what we care about
is intro art test1 test2 test3 and test
fonts right so that's what we want to
actually rebuild so I'm going to delete
those or I could just make a view one
directory and move them in there like so
and so we have to recreate these from
these
right so let's go ahead and do that HHA
edit I believe we can just say rewrite
and we can pass one of these so if we
want to do intro art then we can write
intro art v2 BJJ right and so now in
theory we rewrote that file that has the
intro art in it and in theory I can read
it now right and so we can see what's in
it and let's just verify that I'm right
about that because we want to be able to
you know look at this a little more
cleanly oops
and so in here we should be able to see
all of our assets and that they actually
have something in them so it's not quite
right so we're a little off so you can
see here that the size does not look
right it should be 1.0 and you can see
that this is unknown this is correct so
we're not quite there let's go look at
why we got that happening so we're
definitely passing one point now and
we're definitely passing HHA align
default and so what I'd like to do is
just go in here and and see oh I think I
already know I forgot to and off that
flag so that one makes perfect sense but
let me just see why we got the incorrect
size so for our get size
yeah we just we just never finished we
never finished right so for our get size
it's exactly the same as this right
we've got an f32 here that we then need
to scale up like so but because we want
an extra hundred of range there we need
to first knock it down right so we need
to say look take off some of what you
were gonna do there like so and that way
we can encode up to a hundred and set of
up to 1 so that encoding is fine the get
type is totally wrong I don't again I
think I just wasn't
maybe the coffee we're off right we we
want to knock that off so it should have
been an N with a knotted version so I
don't know what we were thinking there
but just probably asleep at the switch I
guess so yeah let's go ahead and try
that again
so now if I look at that intro or v2
data HHA let's rewrite that a second
time and see if we can get a cleaner
version of that right where's my tab
view at closed it
if I now will put up the assets let's
see if we got smarter alignment in there
so we've got a default alignment that
lines out to the parent which is what we
want
it's 1.04 size which is what we want and
off we go now what we can see here is
there is a little bit of an ugliness
here that sort of suggests we want to be
a little bit more careful with how we're
doing it the fact that I can't represent
exactly half way is not particularly
troublesome but the fact that I can't
represent exactly one is bad right and
so it would be nice to look at why we're
not able to represent exactly one there
and get it so that we can because we
don't really want everything scaled down
by a little bit like that doesn't like
that's actually not great so if we look
at when we're getting the size out
[Music]
these aren't exactly reversed so one
thing we could do maybe is do them
exactly reversed so I think part of the
problem too is a hundred is not a power
of two which probably is bad as well
because it sets us up for being off by
one there let's just try I'm just gonna
say let's try when we actually have six
five five three six right we're gonna be
dividing by I'm just saying like out
loud here so if I have one point oh and
I'm gonna divide it by six five five
three five there or I should say I have
one point oh and I'm in multiply it by
six by five three five I've got six five
five three five right and so when I
actually do a divide there you want to
divide it by something that would evenly
go into six five five three five right
and so you know if you were to divide by
something that could go into it so let's
say six five five three five and I want
to divide it by like let's say 127 or
maybe 126 6 6 5 5 3 5 divided by 255 so
it can it can record that in 57 times 25
can produce can produce that value I
don't know if there's a 126 I don't know
what the factors of 6 5 5 3 5 are is
there like a factorize web page
there we go
so just looking at what the factors are
here 3 5:17 and 257 right so if I was to
take those numbers you know 3 times 17
is 51 5 times 17 is 85 5 times 17 seems
like the best one to me
so let's say that's the maximum and that
way you'll have an even number that
you're then encoding into a u16 and
encoding back out and so you shouldn't
have any weird divides at that point
that's my that's my argument and we can
also as well stick it in this way so
we've done the multiply a head of time
to get it out of the fractional part I
don't think that will help at all
but I you know wave a dead chicken over
the floating point number and pretend
you did something useful so if I leave
that fraction that way I just want to
see if that'll give me a better result
so let's take these guys out and I'm
gonna do rewrite and then I'm gonna do a
dump and then a tab view and things this
time thankfully I didn't close my tab
view so looking at the assets again this
time there we go so now I've got my
exact 1.0 which is what I wanted I don't
know why I don't have an even point five
point five but I don't really care about
that so I'm okay with that I wasn't okay
with not getting an even 1.0 because I
want scale of 1.0 in particular to be
able to represent it exactly because it
is the neutral scale and so that was
important to me what I would like to
quickly look at is just why we're not
getting that direct in and out so if I
do P percent
dot xn dot Y times you see nice I guess
the reason is because of the rounding
error we might want to round these and
if I rounded this guy if I had rounded
this guy it probably would have rounded
us up to one which would have been fine
in that case maybe I don't actually know
if that's true as I'm saying it but
that's when we do it but this is
probably would have
do with the rounding case so when I
truncate this to a you 16
I wanna if I'm closer to the you 16
that's higher up maybe I should round it
so meaning in this case when I do this
multiply ident to do a bias of 1.5 to
make sure that I would round up in the
case where it's up up round a bowl
although really what I would like it to
do is actually round meaning I would
like it to do a rounding conversion
because I don't want to bump it up to
0.5 so I don't know like I don't
remember if our intrinsics have around
so we do have a round real 32 to you int
32 and so what I might do here is say
look let's round this you know I'm
saying and so if we round it then we
will get a more accurate result there
and that might be a good thing to do
across the board so just all of these
are just gonna get rounded and then
truncated that seems better to me I'm
gonna argue that's better so let's try
it one last time and then I think we can
maybe say we we did our work and we're
good to go
there's the rewrite there's the dump and
then if I look at it here let's see now
so the rounding is just all it's doing
is changing which bump I went to so I'm
still not thrilled with that and that's
probably just because the u16 max isn't
evenly divisible by it too so you can't
put a value directly in the middle of it
you know I'm saying
and I guess what I would say is again I
don't really know if I care for any
particular reason there's no nothing
special about directly in the middle of
the bitmap really so I'm not sure if I
really care one way or the other maybe I
do maybe I don't
[Music]
but if we wanted to represent it exactly
I think we would have to use a scaling
value that was capable of representing
the middle perfectly and so in order to
do that you know there's a couple ways
we could do that right we know that you
16 max is not capable beam tools by two
it's pretty trivial to turn into
something that is right I mean you could
just do this and then you lost one 65536
of your ability to be precise but I
think at that point you've gained your
ability to produce a have again right
because you can specify a value that's
exactly halfway between the two so I
think that's true let's see if it
actually is I should really make this
into one command line here oops
and I did it again so I'm gonna go ahead
and say let's leave it that way
it's better to be able to represent
exactly half probably than it is to have
that extra one value there so I'm gonna
leave it at that so okay that's it
really for today but I want to really
quickly see if we can run with these
files just to see if there's anything
else obviously that we did wrong and so
looking at the V one directory here's
again the files that we actually need so
I'm just going to really do a quick hh8
edit rewrite of the v-0 directory test
1v1 hij test 1 V 2 by JJ
and so now I think we have all of our
files right we've got intro art we've
got test1 test2 test3 and test fonts and
so now I can see whether or not we can
actually run and it looks like we can
now the only thing that's a little weird
there is we need to import some stuff
now and we we didn't really test the
import path so all of this stuff seems
to be working pretty good I don't see
any problems right that all seems pretty
reasonable and so all I really need to
do here is if I slap down a local HHA it
should run the import and we can see
whether the importer still does it
properly as well meaning it will is it
capable of creating a version 2 HHA that
will correctly place everything it looks
like it is um so that's good that
verifies a bunch of things like verifies
that we can add stuff to our eh at JS
pretty easily and run a conversion
that's that's really pretty
straightforward so that's good case we
need to modify the file format and don't
want that to be a huge pain in the butt
and now I think we've got roughly what
should be in there and so that's all
good I'll go to a quick Q&amp;A and then
we'll wrap it up
all righty then let's hear loops
no God wish Linux could understand how
to access a mouse
[Applause]
85 isn't a factor of six five five three
four yeah but we don't care
those are your they're two separate
equations right so this equation is the
one that uses the eighty five and it's
still using six five five three six
three five this equation which does not
use eighty five is using the minus one
let's see
could you use you 16 max plus one in a
size modifier of 128 probably not
because you still want to be able to
represent 1.0 I'm sorry okay I see
you're saying you're saying for the
sizing one um yes so yes I think you
could do that yes
color seems like it would make a nice
addition to the bitmap parenting system
a ghost wearing a hat should not have a
hat with a lower alpha value so color is
actually something that it gets is on
the property side of things it doesn't
depend on the artwork really so no I
don't think that needs to be encoded
into the bitmaps like whether or not
something as a ghost is actually a
property and it can be propagated to
children just as easily if we want it to
or not it doesn't have to be in the
artwork
last week you were mulling over whether
or not to separate the head from the
body in the spritesheet since then has
this idea become more solidified now we
haven't really looked at that part yet
also do you plan on giving us some of
the faces more articulate animation an
example I thought of at the start of the
stream today was blinking eyes on the
cats or other characters perhaps as
overlays of eyelids with furs and so for
each head angle yeah we could do
blinking I don't know that I care about
that right now but it's pretty easy for
us to add right because we just have a
blink tag that's like zero one let's see
totally random question graphic do you
like that the C post was professor has
no special syntax for invoking a macro
are there merits to that in your mind or
not would you prefer a special syntax
for invoking macros no I would say it
actually the opposite way around I would
say that the C++ preprocessor does have
a special syntax for invoking a macro
and that's bad a macro processor is
supposed to be a way that you can modify
code that's written to do one thing to
do something else it's the whole point
of a macro preprocessor and there is no
other point in my opinion of the macro
preprocessor in the first place it's
basically for meta programming it's for
reaching into something that was written
textually one way and changing it to be
written textually another way so I would
argue that actually the biggest
limitation of the C bus was preprocessor
besides the fact that it's just really
underpowered in terms of its ability to
program things in general and the fact
that I don't think you should need a
preprocessor your language should just
have the ability to do meta programming
in it if you know those two things I
would then say if you're actually having
a macro preprocessor in the first place
it should allow arbitrary matching
syntax so that you can reach in and grab
anything you want it should be the case
that you can create a C++ macro that
matches against a plus B in the middle
of the text so it can for example
replace in fix notation instead of just
postfix function calls as things that
can be rewritten right it's kind of just
obvious that you should be able to do
that and
I don't know why you would do it another
way but you know there you go
all right I'm gonna close it up I will
leave that as it is if someone wants to
raid a bug on the github about switching
the camera movement by the way I'm fine
with keeping it consistent so that left
right is congruent with up/down but I
probably won't remember to do that by
the time we get back there so if someone
wants to put a bug in there so we get to
it eventually someday when we're doing
bug stuff we can do that all right thank
you for joining me for never said a hand
made here oh it's been a pleasure coding
with you as always if you want to follow
along the series at home you can always
peer to the game on handmade here at
Oregon it comes with a source code so
that you can play around with it
yourself and try to learn along with the
series I will be back here tomorrow when
we will try to parse some files to do
the annotation that we added support for
today and while that probably won't take
too long it is a little bit of busy work
so you know who knows if we finish it
tomorrow then what we'll start on is
just some understanding inside the code
of how to use those alignment points so
we're gonna have to add some code that
does the thinking of like okay I'm
snapping this to this so here's the
alignment point I use or whatever it's
so that's gonna be a little bit of work
to I think that's mostly all the work we
have left to do in terms of importing
characters and having them you know
animate properly and do stuff like that
so hopefully that'll be done probably by
next weekend and then we're free to kind
of drop characters in the game just like
we were currently for you to drop
environment stuff in the game and we can
start playing with that a little bit
more I guess it also allows us to
control how furniture gets set up and
stuff which we kind of want too so it's
actually good not just for the
characters but it'll also allow us to
have more useful control over the not
you know not just not just organic
entities but actually inorganic enemies
too can use those attachment
and things like that for you know other
purposes alright that's about it for
today hope see you back here tomorrow
till then have fun programming and I'll
see everyone on the Internet
take it easy