hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero the show where we code a complete
game live on stream we want to do a
little preamble at the beginning of this
stream we're gonna do a regular
programming as we normally do but there
is one thing that we wanted to do with
the outset which is take a look at some
debugger projects that have been ongoing
one of the things that I've said often
times is I'd like to get rid of the
Microsoft products that are involved in
building games on Windows or anywhere
else that reason is just because they're
they're continuing to get worse and so
you know the writing is kind of on the
wall I would like to replace them with
things that we're going to get better
and that worse much like I replaced
Emacs with for coder and kind of saved
myself from that sinking ship so one of
the things we'd like to do on handmade
hero is replace Microsoft's visual
studio debugger which is the one that
we're currently using with a debugger
that's actually built by people who want
to make debugging better faster easier
quicker with more visibility into the
things we care about rather than making
it bloated and more slow and take more
space and take 50 million gigabytes on
your hard drive and install an SQL
Server and all the other things none of
which I max exaggerating it actually
does to this day so we want to do these
things and I want to talk briefly a
little bit about I'm going to try to on
stream today code clap and cdbg they're
both handmade network projects and I'm
really happy that people have been
trying this I want to say a brief thing
about coding tools and just a little bit
of I think what the problem with coding
tools is these days I just wanted to
quickly say some things about it and
also just address some things about open
source that some people may want to hear
some perspectives on from people like me
who program in the industry one thing
that I think is a huge problem and I
think this has a lot to do with open
source right now is that while open
source is a good thing in certain ways
it allows people to contribute to
projects and fix bugs and projects and
it allows a lot of collaboration that
works pretty well so I feel like there's
a lot to be said for it it has a problem
which is that people don't get paid a
lot of the time and you know that
there's two ways of looking at that one
way of looking at
is like well you know maybe if they if
they wanted to get paid they shouldn't
have put it up as open-source or you
know maybe they should get paid in some
anti way or maybe people don't deserve
to get paid program I don't know what
your philosophy is on it but filosophy
aside what the end result is is that a
lot of tools that fall into the
programming niche aren't very good and
the reason they're not very good is
because there is no money there to
support people making alternatives and
that's the problem right there are
people right now in fact one of the
buggers that we're gonna look at CDBG is
being worked on by somebody who would
work on it full time if they could
figure out a way to get paid to do so
right and that's a failure of the
economic model because we desperately
need new debuggers the debuggers we have
are garbage right but a debugger is a
big undertaking
you can't expect somebody to come out
with a debugger tomorrow that's better
than Visual Studio and then start
selling it there needs to be capital
invested and there to be payouts waiting
for people who are gonna go do the work
of doing these things and they need ways
to survive in the meantime the capital
has to be there form to do it
so we need to find ways to fund these
projects right they need to we need to
find better ways of funding these
projects and I feel like open-source
needs to find better ways to address
those problems because the open source
part ends up producing lots of tools for
free most of which are bad right and
once in a while I produces something
good but a lot of times the only reason
it produces something good is because
people are paid to work on it the Linux
kernel clang these things have massive
monetary pushes behind them now and
there's people getting employed to work
on them right smaller products just
don't have that option right there is no
giant Google fund that's just gonna give
somebody money to work on this debugger
or if there is it's not currently doing
that and the question is how do we get
it to do that right so I do think
there's a bit of an economics problem
that we have and that economics problem
is why our tools are crappy I don't
I have a suggestion for solving the
problem and I'm not trying to throw
shade on anyone's existing economic
models or open source because I don't
have the answer to it I just want to
point out that there's a problem there
that we kind of need to solve because I
don't know how we're gonna get good
tools otherwise people end up having to
kill themselves to try and get these
things done in their spare time this is
it's just it's not fair they should be
getting paid to do this work it's work
we need done and we don't have money to
fund right and I might say we I don't
mean me personally in some specific way
I mean the community that needs these
tools right game developers low level
programmers whatever and so I don't know
how you address that problem we have the
handmade fund which when we have money
we give it to people but it doesn't
collect very much money it kicks a few
hundred dollars like seven eight hundred
dollars a month and we pay that out to
handmade network for hosting and midlow
for doing the NTA the episode guide and
so on we just don't have the kind of
money necessary to pay full-time
programmers on any project let alone a
number of products that would be
important so that's not really an answer
and I don't know what is an answer right
that's about all I have to say on that
front and I think it's an issue that
people need to address at some point
that's all because open-source currently
is really bad at getting over that hump
and I don't know how you fix it to be
able to do that but but it needs to do
that somehow and I and you know that's
and it can be closed source too right so
anyway that's that's per day and Part B
is the knock on from that is I've
definitely been asked a couple times by
people about whether they think whether
I think they should that it's like they
should release their thing as open
source or not and the thing that I say
is if you've put a lot of programming
time with something people should have
to pay for it you should you should get
paid for your programming so there are
ways of doing open source projects that
still involve getting paid I would
HIGHLY encourage looking into one of
them for example you can do a private or
posit Ori that everyone that buys the
thing gets access to right we do that on
handmade hero for example if you
pre-order the game you get access to the
source code right that's a perfectly
reasonable compromise between open
source and paid this still allows you to
sell something and get money for it but
also provide access to the source code
for people who need it right and so I
would highly encourage people to not
feel bad about charging for their work
if you feel bad about charging for your
work that's not a good situation you
should always feel like good programming
deserves to be paid for and any ideology
that doesn't believe that has a
significant issue if we eventually move
to a world where people all just have
their needs met and they can all just go
get food for free or whatever in some
kind of you know socialist utopia great
nobody needs to get paid for PIRG
anymore but when you still need to put
food on the table for your family or
just your even yourself you need to get
paid for your work and this is real work
it's hard work to do you should get paid
for it so never feel bad about that ever
everyone else gets paid for their work
you should get paid for yours it's that
simple that's how society currently
functions and until they change the rest
of it and people don't get paid for
driving cars or building buildings or
anything else you should get paid for
doing programming work alright so that
public service message aside let's talk
about the two debuggers that we've got
today they're in very different states I
would say I've played with them just
only slightly so we'll kind of be
exploring them mostly on stream just a
little bit and I'm gonna move over to
regular programming so we're not gonna
try to switch to either Maday we're just
gonna see what state they're in just
taking a quick little look what I would
say is from briefly looking at them I
would say that CDBG is the less mature
in terms of features debugging features
but is very very usable the human
factors are there it's clean runs really
well
and it's immediately usable I was really
impressed by how close they are to
having something that's just drop in and
you never think about Visual Studio
again
code clap is sort of the opposite it
looks like it's got a lot more features
debugging wise it's got disassembly it's
got a lot of things that CDBG doesn't
have yet but it's the opposite in terms
of human factors it's it's it's almost
impenetrable I would say in terms of
trying to start using it it takes a very
big upfront investment to even figure
out how to get it to work and so I feel
like they're both at different very
different places where they each have
something that's kind of far a little
bit far behind where a finished product
would be but both have shown remarkable
progress in terms of what they've got
and so I think you'll see as we go into
them they both have different strengths
and weaknesses but they've both gotten
the point where you can debug programs
which is pretty cool and especially CDBG
I was impressed with because my
understanding is they don't even use
Microsoft's PDB parser they actually use
their own which is kind of awesome
because that means you could parse the
PDB completely independent of having any
sort of Microsoft help I don't know if
that's really true but it sounded like
that was true which is pretty pretty
hardcore anyway so to the best of my
knowledge CDBG is publicly available you
can download it from here by network so
if you want to try it yourself you just
can code clap to the best my knowledge
is not publicly available but I think it
will eventually be sold I think it's
gonna be sold on each i/o don't quote me
on that but that's where I got mine from
like sort of an early access thing so I
believe code clap will be available for
purchase on each i/o one sheet is ready
to go I don't know when that is exactly
again like I said from beginning a
stream I would highly encourage both
teams well I think City Beach made by
one person I don't know how many people
work on code clap I would highly
encourage both of them to charge for
your work you've both done a lot of work
and you're both on the verge of having a
debugger that people could really use
get paid for it you should get paid for
it alright so let's go ahead and take a
look at these two I'm gonna start with
CDBG first because it's I think it's
much easier to use then code clap is and
but it's a little less far along terms
of debugging so let's just take a look
at that and see where it's at right so I
if you want to launch it
I believe it's the same exact way that
you would launch Visual Studio you can
just type it from the command line and
it should launch we should be able to
basically pass command line I think I
don't remember so it may be that you
have to fill out in the actual program
so we'll try launching it but I don't
know if you can do that or not
we'll see oops sorry it's not in him
it's and build win32 handmade exe so I'm
going to try and launch that and we'll
see so here you can see that even just
right off the bat they've done a nice
thing here which is they've made the
interface look roughly similar to visual
studio or you know another standard
bugger like Qt creator or something
again this is pretty nice because if you
want to do something like fundamentally
change the user interface I you're going
to incur an overhead for people to
switch to it now you may have a really
good reason of change interface maybe
you've got some really great ideas on
how to make the interface way better in
that case go for it but if you don't
have any ideas on how to make the
interface way better maybe you only have
ideas to make it a little bit better or
maybe you just want to make it different
because you want to do it not a great
idea why make people relearn how to
debug a program in order to switch to
your thing just give them the same
interface they're used to on Visual
Studio and just make it better to bugger
right and add to it you know so one of
the things you have to remember is don't
change things unless you have a way of
making them way better don't change
something just to change it right in
terms of user interface that doesn't
really make any sense all you're doing
is adding a barrier to entry there so
like what they've done here they
basically look it's to come up the same
way as Visual Studio we even have the
the keys bound the same f5 starts the
process f10 steps over it now lets us do
great I don't even have to relearn key
combinations fantastic right that's a
great idea
there's also Kilda to access the console
I don't know what the console is so that
doesn't really help me but we'll play
around and see what happens it says here
that I can do LS keys to list a bunch of
keys so there they are
so don't know how to use this again but
you know we'll we'll play around a
little alright so I don't know if I was
able to pass my excuse on the command
line but I'll tell you what it's
printing out here in the title bar so it
looks like it
we did that's great if that's actually
true I'm gonna hit f11 to step here we
are at the start of our program now my
understanding I thought that the
developer of this said that he didn't
support parsing of optimized code in the
PDB which i think is what we're looking
at right now so I may have to compile in
debug mode but so far what he did is
working when I hit step in I landed at
our startup kidding f10 is stepping
through the code exactly as Visual
Studio would probably have done so he
may have been under selling it maybe he
means that like the inspection doesn't
work or something I'm not sure but I'll
be honest with you the inspection
doesn't work in Visual Studio in release
mode either so not sure that's something
I can really talk about but yes so for
example I don't know that we would be
able to find instance even in Visual
Studio so I wouldn't hold that against
tickler program I hit shift f5 to stop
and it stopped again really love that
feature I don't have to learn anything
to use this thing it just feels like the
same debugger I'm used to only guess
what when I hit the step key I have to
wait 12 seconds for it to go to the next
line excellent work here really really
liked it it feels great
let's compile handmade hero in debug
mode so that we can do a test of this in
the way that we would normally do bug
because Visual Studio doesn't handle nan
doesn't handle release mode executables
anyway even though we passed a switch
that supposedly allows it to do so it
doesn't handle them anyway so let's just
a bug the way we would normally do bug
which is with the debug PDB and let's
take a look at how this does so here we
go I'm gonna step in here and now I'm
gonna try and take a look at one of
these it looks like it parsed this
instance just fine I'm looking at the
value here again don't know if these are
correct but they certainly look correct
here we're gonna step in - sorry that's
actually a macro I guess so
you'll notice the one thing that's
missing from this and I said this before
you can't look at this assembly that's
the big thing I would probably the
reason I couldn't switch this right now
would be that so we can't do that
otherwise I'm like doing some hover
stuff here and it's it's working pretty
well it looks like in terms of hovering
over stuff I have over
variable it does show me what it
actually is that's pretty great let's
take a look at query performance counter
here
I'm sorry parents frequency you can see
it kind of output emitter so let me let
me take a look at that so that got UPS I
typed that wrong okay so here's the per
if count frequency result I'm gonna open
it up I don't really know what that is
that looks like that might be some kind
of a bug I don't think there's really
any particular reason why there should
be an uninspected a variable there so
that may just be a PDB parsing error or
something that they don't quite parse
yet so I really couldn't tell you this
looks probably correct otherwise let's
go ahead and step in here
step in seems to work just fine here's
one through to build eggsy path file
name let's take a look at the state that
looks totally and I by the way I just
like that to emphasize you but you can't
really feel this because you're watching
out stream but this is so much snappier
than Visual Studio like already this one
person NYX lifts I believe is his name
who wrote this has bested the entire
visual studio team which is dozens of
people over decades has completely
trounced them in terms of actually
writing a program that inspects their
own format right and so excellent work
here I mean this feels great
it's like way better than Visual Studio
already way better than Visual Studio
and that's a product that they charge
thousands of dollars for right
alright so let's step into cat strings
let's try to stepping through some
things here again everything looks like
it's working really well I'm having no
trouble using it it's updating it
updates instantaneously I mean just
again so much better look at that I mean
this is really quality work here I mean
this is great if I had money I would
just hire this person right John are you
out there
hey John you want a debugger 4ji well
higher Nick all right so anyway this
looks great
let me try stepping out that's harder so
I don't know how to step out maybe there
is no step out I tried getting shift at
11:00 and it doesn't do anything so that
key either there is no step out of or
there or it's not bound to that now I
don't know how to use the console but
but it did tell us how to list those
keys so I'm just gonna use that and see
if I can figure out where step out of
might be if there is something which
there might not be right
so I'm looking here just like a step
into step over there is no step out of
that I can see so I'm gonna go ahead and
assume that that feature isn't
implemented yet that'd be a good one to
implement out of the things that's
missing that probably a big one for me
step out of step out of and again
disassembly only two things I've noticed
so far that I really would that I would
really be missing um so let's try and
set a breakpoint I don't know how to set
a breakpoint in this program control B
looks like it switches buffers to look
at things so that's probably not super
helpful I want to set a breakpoint by
name I don't know how to do that or even
if it can do that so let's just again
take a look we've got let's see
so I don't know let me see
is there tabbed is there like a
breakpoint command or anything
there's a data break so this I'm not
sure this wouldn't may support and I
just don't necessarily know how to do it
is the thing so I I really couldn't say
it's got a data break menu which is
awesome by the way but we don't really
need that at the moment that's good all
this stuff is good so yeah I just can't
figure out how I'd set a breakpoint by
name you might not have that
functionality yet I don't know
again just really hard to say because we
didn't make this thing let's see I like
the phrase pluck and select and pluck I
don't know what they do but I like them
yes oh I guess like I said don't really
know what to do about that
not sure how to set a breakpoint on that
now if I was at a particular line it's
pretty clear that I can just set the
breakpoint however I want so the only
reason I care about the type of
breakpoint that I was talking about it's
just that you've seen me on him a here a
lot of times I'll do that I want to be
able to set a breakpoint on a function
because it's just an easier way to do it
than having to find it right so I really
want a good way to quickly sort of set
the breakpoint in that way so yeah I
just don't know and I can't really look
up any buffers that haven't been loaded
yet probably right I mean I could go
open the file I suppose and look at it
but that's really yeah so that's really
the biggest problem now let's let's take
a look at some of the advanced features
here because I feel like I've read some
stuff in the readme let me just go ahead
and I feel like there's a thing that was
pretty interesting you could like
apparently just view like images and
stuff even so let's take a look at some
of that so let's see there's here we go
so these features like in particular
this one is one of the smartest features
I think I've seen in the debugger I
don't know who came up with that maybe
it's a visual studio guys don't do it
but I love that basically what you can
say is hey I've got a linked list I want
to see the linked list clearly so here
is how we need to go and here's the
field that contains the next pointer
that's just great there are so many
times when I would like that right again
just really really good oh here it is F
break places a breakpoint starts by
function so it does have it so basically
I would just say F break and which
function I want to go into so for
example let's suppose that I want to
stop at I have to imagine the bugging
sir scenario here what might we want to
break that I don't know maybe something
with a linked list so let's look at a
handmade asset here let's try a choir
asset memory right so oops I don't know
how to actually tell it to keep going
maybe I just say that five looks like
maybe there it is all right so that's
pretty cool I need to set our executable
path properly in order for us to be able
to run and ever get to that function so
let's go to go ahead and say handmade
that's the startup oops I guess you have
to do that why is that an invalid path
oh I see because it didn't populate I'm
sorry I edited the wrong thing my bad
let's do that again build win32 handmade
and then this is I this is why I said it
handmade there we go okay so now what I
want to do is run it and see if we get
to that thing I don't know how to list
breakpoints so I don't know what
breakpoints are actively there
the way they do that in Visual Studio is
I've got a little window that lists the
breakpoints I don't know if you can get
one of those in here in terms of the
view I'm not sure what exactly we have
four options in in that - that - that I
did that to the fact there's like a
bunch of stuff here like call stack and
so on I don't know like if I hit alt 0
there's the debug out but you can you
can see I can sort of selective which by
the way it's great the hotkeys to move
to these windows is awesome I would
learn those and start using them um so I
don't know if I can view the breakpoints
it might be here that I could do like a
list command or something that would
show me on my breakpoints
I don't know how to see all of the
things that I can do either so that's a
little bit confusing maybe this is all
of them oops all right
maybe this is all of them I don't know
that's pretty cool right all right so
let me step in yeah that's really cool
this thing is really impressive I mean
this is a very this is a very very good
project here um I'm impressed with this
so there's my answer right it looks like
maybe this isn't quite working it says
that this breakpoint is inactive but I'm
not sure why because it's on a function
so there may be something in here that
needs to get fixed which is that
breakpoints on functions need to remain
on functions let me just see what
happens if I do F break and paste again
acquire asset memory and now I do in
when I'm here it seems like I don't know
it seems like this may be a little bit
broken I'm not sure because it's like it
worked right so it is setting it here
but the listing isn't right
but again pretty minor because it worked
so stepping through here this is great I
mean it looks like it's totally working
I can look at everything yeah I mean
it's really great let's try some of the
advanced features now so we know here
for example this block has a next
pointer right and so when we go ahead
and insert this block we should give us
an opportunity here to look at that
linked list so taking a look at the
linked list here we we can say like okay
here's the block and here's the next
pointer for the block that's pointing to
something else let's say that we want to
look at several of these this is again
something that I'm gonna try and learn
here I don't know how to do this
it says LT a will list a linked list set
for me so let's go ahead and give it a
pointer to the first thing which would
be block in this case next is the field
I don't know if I need to quote that I
probably do so it's probably something
more like that and then we've got a
number to traverse which is going to be
let's say five so I don't know if this
actually will work we'll see if it does
or if it doesn't work on the way down so
here we go here's the first block it's
21 c-deck right and it's got a 8 at the
end there it is right there so this is
the the first one you can see that the
pointers
for it are see here are what they should
be right then we can look at the next
one down and that would be under here
oops sorry that would be where would
that be confusing my own self here so
there's the first one there's the next
one right under blocks that's zero zero
that's this here's the next one it's 110
48 yeah um so again just to underscore
how awesome this is
you saw how confusing it was for me to
even try to verify it but this is so
clean right now you can just see the
array the linked list as if it was just
a list of items exactly what you want
right so good right just so good really
great work there I mean that's just
fantastic right I mean absolutely
fantastic let's try another advanced
feature I'm gonna go ahead here and say
let's run to finalize asset bitmap so I
set a breakpoint there I'm gonna turn
off this breakpoint when we get here now
we've got a texture app that texture app
has an image in it you can actually see
the texture here it's 512 by 512 and
it's got a data pointer to it let's see
if we can actually inspect it here is
the image call so I'm gonna go ahead and
say image and again this is something
that in order to do in Visual Studio you
need to install a plugin right so let's
go ahead and look at image I'm gonna say
op texture data which is a big ask here
like we're asking to do so much stuff
we're asking to like dereference this
whole thing and all this stuff so I'm
gonna try it first this way and if it
doesn't work I'll put in things mostly
so we're just we're giving it the
maximal challenge here if you will so we
need the number that that's always for
we don't need to pass that but now we
need the width and the height so that's
update texture with update
texture height and again this may be too
much to ask we'll see so let's find out
unbelievable look at that this is just I
mean this is just brilliant this is just
great
that's me I mean that's just awesome now
I don't know what that actually does in
terms of launching that I'm gonna leave
this preview open and what I'm gonna do
here I don't know is that like a okay so
I can I I click preview in the pre visit
if I hit f5 to run right a different one
now and I don't know if I can still
preview it I can that's just I mean this
is just phenomenal I mean that's just
that's just really really good so here's
what I would say
it needs a breakpoint list a I would
like to be able to hit f9 to toggle
breakpoints I'd like a breakpoint list
somewhere maybe the console is fine but
it would just have to work and I'd like
disassembly barring that this is I just
switch I'd switch if it had those things
I would switch already I mean this is
way better than Visual Studio way better
than minutes to do faster than Visual
Studio launches immediately it's got
features without having to install
plugins that vigil studio just doesn't
even have out of the box I mean it's
just better it's just better so yeah
disassembly in a register window to
solve that side of things
breakpoints maybe some hotkey changes
and this thing is a drop-in replacement
I mean excellent work just excellent
work across the board
I would pay in me I would pay several
hundred dollars for that product by the
way we would be we would definitely
license it and that's what I would use
so alright um so let's try code clap I
think code cops gonna be a little harder
because again like I said the interface
was pretty challenging but it had a lot
of features as well looks like it has
more features in Visual Studio as well
so we'll try it but I can't promise I'll
get as far as in CD because again the
interface is kind of tricky so I feel
like it's one of those things that the
devs probably to work on the interface
or at least provide some pretty
significant documentation as to how to
use it so I'm gonna go ahead and run it
here I'm gonna try to run it the same
way I ran the other one but again I
don't know if it supports that usage
necessarily so here's code clap
launching I'm launching it on my my
hammy executable we haven't set the
working directory so we need to figure
out a way to do that because that will
be wrong just like it wasn't CDBG we had
to change it right so as you can see
there's a little bit that's the same so
it's got you know two windows over here
that kind of feel a little bit similar
but otherwise it's kind of bizarre like
you know even just this right here I can
sort of see what it is it's a it's a
resizer but a lot of the stuff is kind
of non-standard like I don't know what a
lot of this stuff would necessarily do I
guess that closes it maybe okay so
that's like key by like this is like
settings
it just it's it's you right it's it's
pretty non-standard so it's gonna take
us a little bit to get into right but
we'll try to work around it so I let's
see so the also the stepping is
different so f8 steps a line in f9 steps
in to f7 steps out ugh alright so you
know working through here so I'll tell
you right off the bat really nice
feature is this display you can see what
they're doing here they're just showing
you the values of things add as you move
through so it's pretty great because you
know that save
the trouble of having to add things or
look at a window it's just showing right
in there what the thing is that's a
great feature right I mean why not do
that
there's your you know what I mean
there's no reason not to just show me
what the values are you've got room so
do it right that's brilliant
really really nice what I do yeah so
that's that's really nice
let's try stepping into something step
into is f9 so seemed like it worked
flawlessly there it looks like an output
window has been created for us I kind of
like that translucent thing that's
pretty cool actually I don't know what
it's telling me though that's not
something we output I don't think we
ever print child created do we so I
assume that's a actual output from the
debugger telling us that a child thread
because like that it's something that
would potentially happen in the X input
library for example I don't really know
though so stepping through again here
we're looking at the X input so let's
take a look at can I inspect something
let's look at X input get state I love
the fact that it's got command
completion there right did you see that
how that's doing that now X input get
state unfortunately is not in the
completion so it would be nice if it
actually was able to complete things
that were in the scope it doesn't look
like it is unfortunately but you know
that's what I wanted to do it's saying
that X input get state is undefined but
it is defined so I'm not sure what's
going on there exactly I don't think
that's a pound to fine
but maybe it is
so I don't know I can't seem to get it
to show that we know X input library
since is defined right there is
obviously a real variable and it found
that so I don't know why X input get
state wasn't able to be expanded it may
be a macro is the only thing I can think
of and so if it is a macro then that's
just yeah like something that you know
most debuggers can't handle that so it's
no big deal right
alright so step line is what f8 here
let's try to keep doing that so one
thing that I will say is like it doesn't
step line doesn't seem to quite be
working right like I have to hit it a
lot of times it doesn't seem to actually
be able to step a line also like this
like I can't seem to scroll properly not
really sure what's going on there this
might just be slowness can't quite tell
yeah so I think it's just gotten himself
into a state where it's it's really
struggling with something I'm not sure
what so you can see here it's it's
pegged CPU usage wise right that's a
full peg on some core basically but I'm
not sure what's wrong I don't know yeah
I think it's just kind of a little bit
busted if I try to stop the program
completely see if it can recover
you can't really seem to yeah so I guess
what I would say here is again like it
doesn't it doesn't quite seem to be at
the point in terms of usability that CG
cdbg is it's like not really able to to
reliably debug a program right maybe in
terms of you differently I don't know it
seems like it's got some nice features
kind of like CDBG is looking beyond what
the basic things are that happened in
Visual Studio like putting all the
things into the program to look at
what's really pretty cool but again the
usability is just not there yet so I
feel like that's what needs the work on
code clap I think code clap does support
disassembly so when it is working it's
pretty easy I think to get more features
out of it I'm not sure again because it
is a little bit non-standard it's hard
to know like what how to get to various
things that you might want to do you see
if there's anything in here I thought it
had disassembly but I don't know how to
access it
ah there it is so this little drop-down
here says I can look at the various
kinds all right so it looks like yeah it
looks like mixed isn't really working at
the moment so again I think that one
it just needs reliability testing polish
get it to the point where it doesn't
crash doesn't slow down right it's
really that is step one but it looks
again looks promising like it seems like
it sort of is on the way
cdbg definitely way further along right
now I would say in terms usually I could
I can see myself switching CVB's
probably pretty soon depending on the
situation so there you have it both of
those products seem pretty promising
again I wish I had some way to provide
significant funding to them like I said
CDBG I feel like I would buy for a
significant amount of money right now
actually if it just had a couple things
disassembly reliable breakpoint list
maybe the ability to rebind some the
keys or add a few keys that make it
functionally identical to the things I
click in Visual Studio that's a couple
hundred dollar product for me easily I
would buy that tomorrow I can't I can't
see for other people but again very nice
work so pretty optimistic that those
look like products that are going right
those are going and hopefully they will
come to fruition both of them
we need more debuggers that's all I can
say so anyway thank you very much to
both teams for sending me those and let
me play around with them I wish you both
the best of luck and I hope that you're
able to finish those projects or at
least get them to a version state where
they can be used because I am really
looking forward to being able to use one
or both of them in the future instead of
Visual Studio that said let's go ahead
and move on to actually debugging here
and also for code clap if you want me to
try that against it's like I said it was
looks like it was kind of on the edge of
it just needs some polishing of it I'm
happy to try that again once things are
more stabilized because it looked like I
mean it looked pretty full-featured
right so if it just clean gets cleaned
up it looked like it had most of the
features we wanted like if the mixed
assembly and so on so feel free to ping
me again when it's ready to go and I'll
give it another shot
obviously same with cdbg but I think
like I said that one's pretty close I
think all you really have to do is tell
me this assembly was in there and I just
switch already and that's it all right
I'm gonna go ahead and move those guys
out for now and we will keep a watch on
them and hopefully be able to switch to
one of them someday let's go back to
programming the game we was programming
and if I remember correctly we were
probably at a point where we should
think about fixing the graphics on our
characters because like right now we're
still using ancient art assets right
like ones that don't even match the
perspective so we should probably try to
start doing some stuff there I don't
even know this is gonna like we're
really soon getting into the part where
it's gameplay programming I know John
blow is too busy watching counter-strike
today and and stream sniping us but if
he's listening out there you know like
this is really your problem dude
he's the game designer I'm not a game
designer so he should really have to
come on the stream and design design the
game but you know if if wishes were
horses everyone would have a stable so
anyway we pretty much did what we wanted
to do and we can put our assets in the
game now pretty easily and did we want
to work on our lighting obviously we
don't really need to that right
now let's go ahead and just try to get a
little further down the the our tacit
road just because you know I want to
shake that system out and I would like
to figure out you know essentially how
we're gonna do all of those other little
entity placement things and so on so
what I'd like to do here is let's just
try and replace the hero's art assets
this is gonna be a little bit annoying
because we kind of have some code in
there for like warping the assets around
those were based on a fully upright
drawing character we have a more
top-down drawing character now so it's
not really gonna apply but we can do
some basic things like change the head
and that that's a pretty straightforward
thing and we can also do things like put
the gloves in properly and a lot of
other stuff so we can actually start to
the back we can also populate the world
with some more characters now and so we
should just do those things the other
thing it would be nice to do soon is you
can see there's a bug with the fog and
alpha it's not alpha thing fog properly
uh you might not be able to see that but
there's like cruft in here you see that
those are mild alpha pixels just things
the artist didn't clean up this is
junctions just prototype artwork so it
was not cleaned up or anything um
and normally you'll see that so if I
switch to a mode where there's no fog
you'll notice you don't see it the
reason for that is when fog is not
enabled we don't have the premultiplied
alpha mismatch so basically what we've
got is we've kind of bug in the shader
that's making fog turn our alpha wrong
so again just part of this process of
just getting the game looking right and
making the world look like something you
might want to explore is just gonna be
it's just gonna be cleaning up all these
little little bits right so let's go
ahead and think a little bit harder
about what we're doing here I'm gonna go
ahead and look in that art directory
that we've got so here's all the stuff
we know we've got block walls and floors
we named those properly and they are
imported here is a very long list of
characters we've got we have a template
here I'm going to rename the way we do
templates so that they get ignored
right now we kind of want it to look
more like this so here is the template
for a character here is the template for
an item and we want those to get ignored
by the system so I'm intentionally not
be fixing them with a recognized prefix
right so the template character and
template item are two things that we
know we will never read but they're here
just to remind us of how they're laid
out right and then we've got I don't
think any other template specific things
all the rest of templates are implicit
and things that we can figure out on our
own okay so let's take a look at what we
have four characters so what you can see
here is and of course it's all busted
because Microsoft doesn't know how to
write a picture viewer but what you can
see here is we have various characters
here's a cat three cats actually Fred
Hannah and I think Molly isn't here -
yeah there's Molly so we've got three
cats like everything else in the game
there's a body and a head and you can
kind of see that all the characters are
structured the same way and you can see
in the template for the character
they've got default dodge move hit
attack and so on it can be filled in
here and they've got some facial
expressions - and you can see like the
hero for example has some other people
don't and there's nothing in those right
and that's allowed because we don't want
to force the artist to make too many art
assets so we don't want them to have to
fill in this grid we want them to just
fill in the parks the grid they care
about and that's what Anna's done here
so for example most simple NPCs don't
have things like expressions but maybe
the hero does right and maybe some of
these other characters will get
expressed at some time and you can see
them all here separate it out the way
that they should be I'd like to put
these characters in the game now
but in order to do that we need to think
about how they're gonna be tagged so one
aspect of the tagging list for almost
everybody but the hero we know only this
parts filled in because they're basic
they don't have much extra stuff so the
grid addition of tags is actually pretty
easy and the reason it is even if they
were filled out is because the grid tags
are actually all defined by the grid
itself
we know that the tag hit will apply to
everything in this column that the tag
for facing direction will apply to
everything this column body and head tag
will apply to everything in these
sections so the tags for what these are
- that's define can actually just be
read off of this the grid itself and I
don't think that's going to be much a
problem the problem is going to be here
so in here we sort of have a collection
of things that are all somewhat
interchangeable in terms of characters
all of these orphans can be
interchangeable in terms they're artists
that's for example you could trivially
put the head of this character on the
body for this character if you've wanted
to and so on so what we're really
talking about here is ways of tagging
these ways of tagging these characters
with tags that we would use to identify
them and there's multiple ways that we
could do that
right one way is to just tag them with
their name but another is to tag them
with their sort of attributes you know
for example if this one was tagged with
a sports attribute for example because
and you know
can't really there we go
you know things like that I don't know
to what extent we really want to go down
that route because I don't know how much
we're going to want to interchange them
but it's like it's just worth noting
right so the heads themselves yeah I
don't know I really just don't know how
we want to categorize them exactly some
of them are obvious I mean this is
obviously for baking right and this is a
tailor but the heads I mean you know
they're just faces so there's no real
way to tag faces in a way that the game
would care about what the face is
so that's really tough and that's the
part that I'm not really sure about I'm
not sure what to do there and this has
nothing to do with programming right
this is just how we won our game to talk
about these various these various
components that can be put together
I'm just going to go ahead and do like
yeah like
just trying to think I mean what we
could do is tag the heads with the names
of the characters but the bodies with
not with that and I guess the other
question is would do we ever actually
use the bodies for other person I mean
you know what I guess for now we could
just name the characters and tag them
both I really wish I had a solid idea
about which one I wanted to do but I
just don't
so on these in terms of like the enemies
they're a lot more straightforward
because they probably have elements that
we would actually care about like for
example you know a mummy is maybe undead
and skeletal you know things like that
and and a skeleton is you know undead
these sorts of things we could probably
just codify which we sort of did like
skeleton and dark skeleton broken and
just regular skeleton right and a mummy
is also a skeleton so
so I guess here's how I'd say it so
let's start with the easy ones I'm gonna
talk about character dead and a mummy
sort of has skin so I would say it's
dead with skin this is dead without skin
maybe this is dead and broken this is
dead and dark right so we would have you
know a dead character a dead broken
character a dead dark character and a
dead one that actually has skin so right
because you can sort of see or I guess
we could call it wrap or wrapped like
that
so tagging out that one is pretty easy
and it's really these that are harder so
we have like cat here and we have a
couple of those that we can tag as cats
and then how we want to describe the
cats is a little bit different so Fred
is a tabby but his brown molly is at
Abbey but is gray and Hannah is a
Behrman and a ghost because
unfortunately Hannah died which is sad I
wish she had not died but she is only a
ghost now unfortunately so Hannah is
actually a ghost and a Behrman Fred is a
cat through his brown tabby and Molly is
a gray tabby so those are property eyes
here I don't know if these would be
considered ghosts I don't think they
would they're they're sort of like and
and you know maybe dead is the wrong
word maybe here like Undead
is the correct word right because dead
sort of implies that they're not gonna
move around
whereas undead probably is better okay
so we've got those in there we've got
cats we've got undead so that's all the
characters that are clear and easy to
name krampus and so yeah so the rest of
these I guess what I would say is
Krampus and the orphans and the hero
Krampus and the hero are probably
somewhat specific honestly the hero and
the orphans really probably aren't
because you know you probably want to be
able to play as the other orphans at
some point so I think this might just
more be like orphan zero-zero right so
these are all the different orphan body
parts and the question is just how do we
name these because they're really not
necessarily all that descript you know
and especially because the heads and the
bodies you know it may have been a
mistake to put those in the same file
because the heads are just heads they're
not really very specific I mean you
could say one has you know brown hair or
black hair red hair or something but
that's not really like important you
know it doesn't it's just the face you
would recognize it whereas the bodies
are a little bit more Civic like you
know this one's wearing a sports Jersey
and this one's wearing a dress or a
skirt rather and this one's wearing a
bandanna and so you could kind of think
of those and this was wearing an apron
you could kind of think of those as
being important tags that go with the
body and the head just doesn't really
have that you know so I do wonder if
maybe what we want to do sort of longer
term is just put those in separate files
that would have separate tags
and I really couldn't tell you but that
seems like what we want to do so I think
I'm going to do is I meant tag the
bodies I'm gonna ignore the heads so the
heads we'll just get the tags at the
bodies half and then maybe we'll talk to
Anna and just say look let's change how
we're doing this let's go ahead and
split them out in two separate files
that don't have that property right and
then the heads can just be named
probably because I don't think there's
really gonna be a lot of other ways you
can you know really talk about a head in
a gameplay sense I mean even things like
hair color skin color eye color the game
doesn't care they wouldn't affect the
gameplay in any way so unless there was
something about the head like with the
kid with you know with the NPC's this is
an undead character versus a dark undead
character
those are gameplay related the
characters don't have that their head
could just be whatever it is and that's
just sort of the identity of the
character in the sense that like oh
that's Lisa from the orphanage versus
Carl from the orphanage is the only real
way that the head would come into play
which makes me think that the head is
just specific right the head is just
gonna be named something and like
there'll be an instance of Lisa in the
orphanage and that's her head but the
body you could be a little freer with
because since it is representational you
could say that you know someone puts an
apron on they get the apron body I don't
know right so that's you know again it's
really hard to say and maybe the answer
is you don't really ever want to switch
it maybe like you know Lee if this is
Lisa and that's her body and head maybe
the only time they ever appear together
is with her and they never can you can
never swap out or anything right
and and I don't know so i think the
bodies need to be
visited also you know we've kind of got
to sort of bodies they're stout there's
Sauter bodies and more slender bodies
you could really think of those as just
two types of body and then having
different outfits on them right and so I
would rather categorize it that way
I think that would just be a more sense
way to do it because then again you
could sort of have like the concept of
changing the outfits so so just looking
at I think that's a better way to go and
I think we should probably make that
change looking at the cat's on the other
hand cats don't work that way
cats you can't really swap you can't put
a tabby head on a Behrman body it
doesn't work that way so they're a
little more sensible because the bodies
are not clothed so they are like
naturally going to go with the head in a
very specific way so that's a little bit
more specific so what I may do for now
is say let's go ahead and and maybe have
these art assets get changed out before
we start playing with them and we'll
replace them with other ones and yeah
and maybe we can
I mean I think that's what I'd rather do
so what I think I'm gonna do here is I'm
just gonna create a new folder
temporarily and I'm gonna call this
pending and I'm just gonna shunt all of
the orphan stuff into there and we're
just gonna concentrate just on this part
right and so here we know that we've got
Krampus and Krampus is pretty specific
I think Krampus is just Krampus and
there's probably not going to ever be
another Krampus so I think character
Krampus is pretty much it I don't think
we need to specify anything more it's
just Krampus Krampus default and that
should do it
we're not gonna look at the rest of
these right now we're just gonna look at
these so this should at least allow us
to put cats in the orphanage which allow
us to Bakr and puss in there and we
could even have some monsters right
because those are in there so let's
start by just implementing that because
that's what we can implement and then I
think we might change this out a little
bit again you know maybe I guess the
other thing we could do is put a pause
on all of these and have them all get
separated out I don't think we won't do
that so I think what we want to do is is
maybe yeah ma mi overcomplicate like
that's the other thing is like I don't
know maybe we should just keep all the
characters together and and you know you
just they are named what they're named
and we don't really put much more on it
than that and then we could just proceed
as as giving and you just have
characters just all you know go in the
same files
I really just don't know it just really
kind of feels to me like the heads want
to be different so I'm gonna I'm gonna
stick with that I'm just gonna say
that's what that is because these are
all based on properties and the other
ones just really aren't and so I feel
like we want to try to stick to that as
best we can and and go from there all
right so let's go ahead and define the
tags that we're talking about so that
these can be imported into the system
and we can start using them so we've got
a in the asset import system I think
right now we sort of have character
stubbed-out so you can see that like
hands for example do you get imported
characters do not write and so what we
want to do is we want to set up this
exact same thing for characters but
we've got a change the way that this
stuff is set up pretty dramatically here
because we've got a lot more tags we
have to apply we have to apply tags
based on both the column and the row so
we need a way of looking at both of
those things together so let's start by
looking at the character template sheet
so here it is and what you can see here
is that going down we've got the facing
directions working exactly as they did
with the hands but it happens twice
right so really instead of Y index less
than four what we want to do is
everywhere in the Y index at all we want
to add that tag right and so we want to
sort of look at the tags this way and
say first of all no matter what happens
you're gonna get a facing Direction tag
it's gonna be the Y index times to our
four but this is actually gonna wrap now
so it's really going to be mobbed four
so basically we do for each one of the
one
that we're looking at we get a facing
direction in there and it gets specified
that way now I one thing that's sort of
important to remember here is that this
goes in the direction of the file we
don't flip the file we flip the tiles so
even though the PNG goes down but
graphics goes up for us we're still
going down here which means that this is
the zero zero tile which is kind of nice
because it makes it easier to think
about here so here's where we add the
facing direction now what we need to do
is add body for anything in this here
and head for everything up in here and
then we just need to do these ok so the
first thing I want to do is I want to
bifurcate this we've got an if Y index
is less than four here and then if Y
index is greater than four and that's
exactly what we want so we need in here
to be able to specify whether something
is a head or a body if it's less than
four it's a body if it's greater than
four it's a head and we don't have any
real percentages here they're just
either are or aren't right so it's
pretty straightforward we can just say
look that's what this is and that's you
know all there is to it right so the
next thing we need to do after that is
start to talk about the specific tags
that we want for each of these so then
what we do is say well ok if we're
inside Y index less than four then we're
talking about a body which means this is
what we've got one two three four five
six seven right so what we want to do
here is do a switch on the X index and
we probably want to switch again to be
part of the specifics so in here we
probably want to do this where we say
all right always add that tag and then
add maybe some other tags so here I want
to say if we're in case zero which is to
say the first one we're gonna add a tag
of some kind here which is tag whatever
and off we go
and we want to do a break at the end
right so this just allows us to put a
little cracker in there that basically
says look at which column you're in
we're gonna apply various tags that are
just based on our knowledge of what the
template type is that this person said
the file was there's a default template
for zero which means that I think we
want to just call that an idol so if
you're looking for idol that's what's in
this room if you're looking for dodge
left it's here if you're looking at
Dodge right it's here then we've got
move then we've got hit attack and
nothing in the final one right so this
is just I like to be determined so
anything that comes in in there but
really shouldn't have anything what that
means is I think we want to just not
have that occur meaning we don't want to
set any tags in there we want to leave
those unset so I would say actually here
in fact how did we do that beforehand
yeah we just only set them for those so
what I'd like to do here is just say
look even just around this whole thing
we want to prevent that we what we could
do is prevent it here by just saying
look we only want to go up to number
oops up to number seven right or a
better way to say that might be lesser
you go to 6 because that's the only
cases we actually have right and the
rest of them student at attack could be
that I think it's a little bit more
compelling to do this because since we
have different numbers of acceptable
ones depending on which temperature in I
think what I want to do is something a
little bit more specific here which is
maybe to say look let's actually start
this stuff a little bit more
specifically where we begin and end
inside these so that we can we can
actually tag these like so only if they
actually exist right only if there are
things that exist in the
in the template so one two three four
five six seven of those right so it
should be like that another way to write
it like that this should be less than
seven of them right
I used to say there should be less than
eight of them which is less than seven
that's okay write it like that okay and
in here we have even less so in here
you're actually not allowed to get past
the third one right so it's got to be
less than equal to two as an index and
the switch statement is correspondingly
simpler right so in here I can say well
I want to do a switch case their default
surprised anger something like that
right so now when we import one of these
they'll all get tagged properly and
they'll get shoved into the thing what
they won't have is anything from the
filename and we need them to have
something from the file name because
otherwise they won't be able to
different be differentiated so when we
actually go to parse these we need to
add to our kind of global tag table now
we also need to I mean we can sell right
here that we need to add the tag these
all these tags need to be set up in our
asset tag system that's inside file
format set age so we need to add tags
here for each of those things so we've
got a tag how does this work so we've
got basic category here and I guess
basic category for a head and body I
guess we never cross that phase of
category so those are not really
appropriate tags in that sense they
should just be basic category so let's
go ahead and fix that
so in here look those are all legitimate
tang
and those are all legitimate types these
are not legitimate tags so what we
really want to do here is say this is an
asset body don't need out of tag and
here we want to say this is an asset
head now we don't have any more it's
with specificity there we don't for
example have asset torso or cape and
these sorts of things so I'm gonna
change this to be body and a head are
the two that we'll use and Cape will go
away eventually as we start to clean
those up right so really what we need
are these here to be added to the tag
set let's go ahead and do that we've got
an idol we've got a Dodge left
we've got Dodge right we've got to move
we have a hit we have an attack and so
on idle hips surprise and anger right so
we've got all those tags and now we
should be able to compile this properly
again we have to change anywhere that
was using torso should now be doing body
right and that's fine all right there we
go
and so we mad at all those tanks and
then we need to update our tag table
again because C and C++ toast for an
introspection why would they they've
only have 30 years to have that feature
can't expect miracles let's go ahead and
take a look at what we define to be in
here and copy them in there we go
and so here we just have all of these
different types so your title
here's dodge left oops that's right
move its attack one to surprise anger
and then we're gonna need to add even
more tags here in a second by the way in
case you haven't noticed you can see how
many tags we're adding this is why I was
saying we need to deal with tags
sparsely it's just it's a requirement
because we're gonna have you know
hundred tags by the time this game is
done
and so that thing we're doing now with
the matching not gonna cut it
I said that before and you know I'm not
lying the tag matching is gonna have to
be much better but that's not that hard
to do we'll be able to do it so now we
have to look through here and add all of
these so we have a you know cat
we've got Behrman we've got ghost we've
got tabby and brown
we've got grey we've got
[Music]
Krampus I'm dead broken and so
interesting thing is bones here right
the way that we were doing hand bones so
I feel like these should probably have
bones in them and if furthermore I feel
like this should probably be Undead
something like that
all right so anyway continuing on that
Trent
we've got undead we've got broken we
already have dark and dark energy there
we've got wrapped and I think that's all
of them
so there's cat Berman ghost tabby Brown
ray
Krampus Undead broken and wrapped all of
this extra meaningless typing brought to
you by by the C++ standards committee
because if there's one thing they love
more than anything in the world it's
making programmers type a bunch of
useless garbage so here we are manually
copying none of which would have been
necessary in Ji or any other language
for that matter and built so that's our
tag importing we should now be able to
import those characters in I don't
actually know that I'm right about that
but let's just go ahead and run it
anyway here's me running the import
process and that should just import them
into our local HHA file and be done with
it right okay
so that looks like our multi tile
imports a little bit buggy to me to say
the least
I also like the fact that we're getting
a cat body and head right now that's
awesome so but I'd like to go ahead and
debug our multi tile import because it
looks like you can see that it's it's
got a weird like split happening with
the way that the textures are lined up
there and so I'd like
so go ahead and find out what's going on
there cuz I don't really know I don't
really know what's up in there we have a
number of things we have to address to
get this stuff working properly why does
we have to debug the multi tile import
because it looks like it's importing the
Stride wrong but the other thing that we
have to do that we have that we didn't
have to do for the environment importing
is we need to be able to set hot like
the alignment on the sprites remember we
got an align point to figure out where
we're gonna like place sprites when we
place them the world.i we're gonna have
to do something for that because right
now we don't have that right now just
get set to a default and there's no way
to change it and obviously we can't put
in the PNG cuz Photoshop doesn't really
provide a way for artists to do that in
any way that artists understand there
are actually some ways you could like
add text to a PNG in Photoshop and stuff
like that but that's we don't really
want artists to have to figure that out
it's it's done very poorly
again Photoshop Adobe and the C puzzle
Standards Committee would love each
other they're basically like people who
seem to completely ignore the needs of
the people who actually use their
products they should have like some kind
of a like aggressively we don't want you
to use our stuff conference that they go
to each yours to talk about new ways
they can ignore obvious things that
everyone has to work around in their
products alright so let's go ahead and
work on the bug you met because we
probably are fine for the rest of our
stuff let's double check that the rest
of the tagging and that stuff went okay
I suspect it probably did but neveress
to be careful so I'm gonna go ahead and
use HHA edit and remember we've got a
dump thing here we can I can take local
HHA and export it to a text file that
allows us to use for example tab view
which I have to actually pull out the
bonus pack here and use it on local dot
text so if that lets me just see in here
what the tags are for all the assets so
what I could do is look at all the stuff
that's in here
obviously we have all our flora stuff
then we here's like a bunch of hand
stuff the gun port here's the character
stuff that got imported so for example
the the Bourbon ghost cat here we can
take a look at here it's cat Burman
ghost
it's an idol I mean looks stacked like
what we want so you know guess that I
think it worked just fine let's look at
the gray tabby cat great tabby
so you know looks like the imports
working is fine you know Krampus is
Krampus and that's just true in general
so I feel like this is probably fine so
our problem is just that when we do
these imports here where we know that
our normal path that imports just a
block seems are working properly because
we haven't any trouble and bring those
in but our sort of newly modified
version that does the multi tile because
remember we had another tile working but
we modify little bit it looks like it
doesn't get the stride right necessarily
and so we'd like to do is go look at
what's happening there why is that
airing out and in what cases is there
now because it looks like there's some
some funny business going on there so
I'm gonna go ahead and just inspect that
code path I'm also take a look at it in
the de fire I'm gonna delete the local
about HHA because I want to force a
complete re-export so I'm gonna do a
create for a new local HHA which means
now I can just force it to report
everything into that file from the
source materials that'll allow us to
debug the export that already happen or
sirs say the import that already
happened which is what we want to do I'm
gonna go to the build here and switch
the debug mode so I can step through it
I'm also going to take a brief look to
read familiarize ourselves with exactly
what's happening in that code path make
sure that there's nothing obviously
wrong before I start debugging it and
looking at it in more detail now the
part that's failing specifically is
process multi tile in port right here
this part is working prop
as far as we know single tile import has
not seen any particular eros so we're
really talking about this right here you
can see here when we start down at what
we do is we take the tile dimensions
that we're told to use which is the 1024
tile and we we specify the size for the
test there what we are doing here is
saying look if we took a tile dimension
of 1024 how far should we scale it down
and we get a down sample count there
that's just so we scale all the sprites
uniformly because we are gonna pick out
a region of the sprite based on how much
is used we don't want the amount we
scale it down to be based on that actual
size of the of the used portion of the
rectangle and the reason that we don't
want to do that is because if we were to
do that we would scale some things down
and something's not inside the same
sprite which would lead to weird sizing
artifacts so we really don't want to go
that way so the down sample count has to
be based on the general size of things
that's what that's doing and we save
that for use later we come through here
and say look here's how many x and y
tiles there can be at maximum based on
the tag information we were paid past in
we're not gonna look beyond that so then
here we look to make sure that the size
of the file itself isn't larger than the
maximum number of contemplated rows in
our system and we output areas in that
case we need at some point actually
print these errors that would be nice
we haven't done that yet and that's
something that we probably should put
onto it with we then loop through the
tiles looking for pixels in any of them
when we find pixels in them we sort of
remember the bounding box that was used
you can see us picking out a min/max for
wine x there
all right and what we want to do here is
say okay if we actually found anything
in which case we're gonna need at least
some dimension here if we found
something then we can proceed what we do
here is we first look to see whether the
the minimum is sufficiently outside the
border and if it is we expand it if it's
not we say hey this was a little bit too
big for comfort when this thing gets
down scaled it might not have enough of
a border to prevent some aliasing
artifacts on some anti aliasing
artifacts that's all we're doing here so
we either expand or snap to a particular
tile dimension now here's one thing I
will say these are all relative to the
tile important remember that as we flow
through here right so we're looking at
the min x max X min Y max Y and we're
processing all of those when we get down
to the end what we want to do is call
extract him and share and what that's
going to do is copy this out now extract
image is a prime candidate for a bug
we're gonna want to look at that closely
the reason I say it's a prime candidate
for a bug is when we look at what
happens in here these are happening the
same in both paths it doesn't mean the
bug isn't there the bug still could be
there
the reason the bug could still be
somewhere in there is because we could
be seeing something where if for example
we pass a specific type of dimension to
the down sampler it screws up right we
know we aren't passing any weird
dimensions to the down sampler in the
other case because we're only extracting
the amount of the image that is the
entire we're only ever picking out
entire 1024 by 1024 source art or
whatever it why don't matter what it was
2048 but whatever it was we're only
picking out that one size for
environment tiles so
would never see a bug if there was a bug
in the down sampler where say non power
of two sizes caused a bug on even sizes
cause de bug things like that so we
don't know that the down sampler is
right and we're gonna have to look at
that but extract image is possibly the
more likely candidate because we know
that that's completely different none
III don't think extracting whichever
happens or does well no I lied extract
image does happen so nope
take back everything I just said so it
has to be something with how we're
passing down the information then these
things must behave poorly on certain
parameters because we are calling
extract image in both cases okay so
let's go look at these two we assume the
bug is in one of them we don't know
which one it is
maybe it's an either but we're about to
find out so let's take a look at extract
image that's what runs first first thing
it does is push an image onto the
temporary processing stack which is just
scratch memory that we're using for the
purposes of an individual import and
what you can see here is it takes the
dimensions out here by looking at one
pass the x and y maximum subtracting the
minimums from it perfectly reasonable
way to get the size of the image don't
expect a lot of trouble over there we
then pull out the destination pixels
from whatever got allocated during the
push image call we get the source row by
looking at where we actually wanted to
start at the end because remember I want
to flip the image since they come in
backwards so we intentionally advance in
that way now looking at this
I also don't see any particular reason
why that would be causing the problem
that we're seeing offhand we know we're
gonna be writing this much stuff in
there because here's the result width
and height that our views during that
extraction process so it certainly seems
reasonable we're stepping to the last
row and we're using the source image
width as the stride which is what we
would use and the MINIX is pushing us
forward to the exposition looping over
the x and y we're just starting the
source pixels running through them on
each time we step backwards one whole
row that is what we would expect we're
copying up as many of them as there are
here so death pixels should line up
properly each time again really not
seeing a lot of explanation about why
something to be wrong there now one
thing I would say is do we check make
sure we're actually passing the image
that we prepped so for example here
we've got a tile image or we make sure
passing it we are passing it to down
sample we then take the dest image here
and pass that again that's what we want
to see happening I just want to make
sure we weren't then turning around and
like passing the wrong thing in so we're
gonna be calling down sample we can see
if there's any obvious bugs and down
sample here let's take a look here's the
down sample call the down sample call
takes the image to this web you down
sampling and it returns as far as I can
tell this we no longer do
as far as I can tell it's doing the
downsample in place so it's it's ruining
whatever the input image that you give
it is that should be fine but we would
kind of have to think about is there any
reason why that wouldn't be in this case
I don't think so because it's the tile
image that got passed in so it should
just be able to ruin it because it's not
getting used for anything else I don't
think anyway why there would be a reason
for that so let's take a look at what's
going on here we come into the down
sampler Jimmy and each one of these runs
is going to do one step of the down
sampling the first thing we do is we
snap however much the dimensions of the
image were originally we go ahead and
have both of those so we're going to cut
them down in half we then go through and
do our down sample here by two and let's
see how we do that we have the
destination pixel source pixel zero
source pixel one we advance by whatever
the width was to get to the next row and
otherwise we're just going to be doing
down sampling directly and exactly how
you would expect it to do and I don't
see a lot there we're writing into the
same place as we're reading so that's a
little something to watch out for but in
this particular case there isn't a lot
of reason why that would cause a problem
because we're always reading first and
then writing and we're writing a smaller
thing than we're reading so we shouldn't
be having a lot of problems with that
that I can think of anyway but we'll
have to be on the lookout for it so the
first thing we do is we lift up pixels
from both of our source and destination
we read two pixels at a time from both
the current row and the next row and we
record those we then convert them to
color information we can actually use
it's because you just unpack and then
linearize right we blend weari srgb them
into a single piece of information there
we can pack down well we pack down
and we write on a single destination
pixel for each of those what that means
is we're going to write out with worth
of those which is what we would expect
because we go ahead and write the result
width and height at the end of that so
what I will say is this looks completely
broken to me
I don't even slightly understand how
this was working because if you look at
what's going on here source pixel should
really be source row because adding the
width is going to skip a line but this
already read a whole line
so it assumes yes oh so really this
needs to be and I can see we were being
clever we were being way too clever
there we were assuming that we would
always read the whole line but we won't
because if this number is odd then we
will have missed one pixel right so
that's almost certainly where our bug is
coming from just sloppy I shouldn't have
done that
so what we really want to do here is
this we want to call this source row and
we want to call this source row like so
right and what we can do because we only
really need one source row pointer
because we can probably just do this
because that will be accurate and that
way we know we can get to pixel pointers
out of one base pointer but basically
what I'm saying here is let's take the
road that way where we're starting off
at the top and then when we go here what
we want to do is advance by two rows
every time so we want to go ahead and do
that and that will be correct every time
even when this fails to read an entire
row which will be whenever this is odd
so that was almost certainly what was
happening there and so hopefully I've
corrected that now don't forget to Like
and subscribe so let's go ahead and and
try running a report and this will
reinforce
is good because we can see whether we
broke the other case as well remember we
have two cases like our saying we've got
the case where we're importing something
that's an entire PNG that just gets
shoved into a texture after down
sampling we had the other case we've got
tiles those tiles are extracted that's
just to provide the artist with a little
bit of an easier export path so you
don't have to do as much funny business
there so now we're running me a spry 3 X
4 would be very slow because we're in
debug mode and debug mode is very slow a
lot of our stuff doesn't seem to get
optimized properly in debug like doesn't
seem to be Co gen very efficiently so I
probably should have switched to debug
to release mode to run it but hey it's
not that big of a deal so this is going
through right now and doing it and you
can kind of see it hopefully here you
can see us chewing through these file
here bouncing around on the CPU as we
load and go
of course there we go and now we're back
so looking at what we've created here oh
my goodness
okay well we fixed the striding bug I
can tell you that it's a little bit of a
large cat if we're honest a little bit
maybe um bigger than I was expecting
huh that's fine
all right so let's go ahead and see
about the rest of it so here's the cat
it's now the correct everything except
for size I think and so I think we've we
fixed that problem and so we can now
have arbitrary cats in the game as we
wish but we will have a couple issues
that we have to address so as you can
already see the cat is not lined up
properly although we can switch the
cat's direction just fine but the cat is
not lined up directory and lined up
correctly specifically because we don't
actually have any Hotpoint specified so
it's just centered around the middle of
wherever the the point was that you said
you wanted things placed which means
that the code that we've got in there
right now to deal with the hero's
placement which was all just kind of add
a hawk for whatever the random sprite
hero was that stuff now needs to get
fixed right we need to have a way of
specifying those alignments and that's
probably what we want to do tomorrow
right but for the moment it's pretty
easy for us to switch which cat we are
for example like we're the Birman right
now maybe we don't want to be the Birman
anymore for example and so since that's
the hero in this particular case what we
can do well you know what why even
bother why not just strew some cats
around
Orphanage we can put each of the cats
around the orphanage if we want to it's
pretty easy for us to do actually so
maybe you want to play some cats in the
orphanage again haven't really worked on
that part of the code much the placement
code but we can hack something in just
to place some cats just because we want
to that's actually pretty easy to do
well you know what we'll do it tomorrow
if it's we're at the QA no sense
belaboring it so I think we're good it
seems like everything worked just fine
and we fixed the one bug that we had so
we're in good shape tomorrow to be on
the place characters around and I think
what we're gonna want to do tomorrow
then is just place some cats around to
make sure that we can set their tags
properly we could put Krampus in there
to just put those characters around and
they're all going to be disjoint and
discombobulated so that'll give us a
good motivation to make a little way
inside the game that we can update the
HHA to just reflect the hot spot of the
individual characters right
so tariffs oh I don't really understand
the size bug don't you ask for a
specific science when you push the hero
sprites yes so here's some stuff that's
just been in the game for a long time
because you know we just been making
engine stuff and our goal was not really
looking at art assets but we've switched
now so we have to think about them the
hero sprites that were imported
originally we didn't even write any
import code to actually clean up the
boundaries on them so what happened was
the hero sprites were giant blank like
huge empty space and then a little
sprite in the middle of it so actually
we've been drawing huge blank
transparent nothing with a little sprite
in the middle of it for the hero right
now our import path properly looks for
you know for all the new stuff we've
done it's like a real you know real in
quotes obviously it's still pretty
simplistic because it's just to the
importing but it does a lot of stuff now
right it looks through packed our assets
it picks out the rectangle that's
actually being used it down samples it
doesn't stuff as a result the actual
region of the sprite is now just the
just filled with stuff so the big empty
size right that we were drawing for is
now filled entirely with cat so the cat
is like twice as large as the hero
because this doesn't have any blank
border units right like it used to right
so that's where that's coming from but
that's good because now it means when we
specify a size that the actual size
we'll get we don't have to make big
empty sprites to account for the fact
that most of its empty space right
I'm having trouble understanding the
difference between a tag and a basic
type so there is no difference between
any of them they were kind of an
arbitrary thing that we decided and how
we wanted to do stuff there is no such
thing as a basic type it's just another
tag the only reason that we decided to
make it special was because we wanted to
have one thing that was sort of
immutable meaning it can't be Fuzzle II
picked so for example if you want a body
it has to be a body spray if you want a
head it has to be a head sprite we
decided to treat that tag specially and
never allow cross selection whereas all
the other tags can be cross selected so
if for example you say you want a floor
right you might get any kind of floor
right or sorry a block or something
right you might get any kind of block
like grass or stone or whatever can be
matched across but you'll always get a
block you won't get like a heads right
instead of a block because it's tags
matched better right so it's just a way
of simplifying how we were designed to
structure those things Felix just wanted
to thank you for the link to pseudo
band-limited pixel art filter it was
Eckley I needed excellent someone
emailed me separately and was asking so
I mean I was like here's what I want to
read and I guess that worked for them so
that was great
Pope user when a issue in OpenGL DirectX
call creating for example that takes a
while to complete will the CPU be busy
while the GPU makes it happen or will
the thread be suspended so that Windows
can schedule something else so it's
impossible to really know what's going
on there without looking into it
specifically usually OpenGL and DirectX
calls don't block based on the GPU they
usually block based on the CPU but not
always so most of the time if a OpenGL
DirectX call is taking some time it's
actually the CPU doing something for
example when creating a vertex buffer it
may be playing with like where how it's
mapping memory and deciding where you
should put that particular vertex buffer
and things like this so
usually you're not waiting around on the
GPU usually waiting on the GPU requires
you to actually ask to wait for it such
as calling swap buffers which may wait
if you're too many frames ahead or some
kind of a sync call like if you're
waiting on a fence or something like
that so usually they try not to wait but
sometimes they do when you do have to
wait yes usually your thread would have
been suspended if the drivers support
that sort of thing as far as I know I
don't think you will spin lock but again
that kind of depends a little bit on the
driver I don't really know in all cases
whether you can be scheduled for
something else or not that's probably a
little bit drivers specific and
implementation specific but the first
day correctly says the sprites are
clamped depending on the space that's
actually occupied doesn't that mean
you'll need to adapt the sprite
dimensions to the sprite that is being
drawn not really well I guess I'm not
sure I understand the question I'm sorry
can you be more specific about what
you're actually asking about I can try
to answer that can you pet the cats
possibly cereal PBM why not make the HHA
file generator also load the files and
generate the tags I so I do think I
would probably add that I probably
compound to both but I want it compiled
in the game as well and that's just so
the artist can do something like hit f5
and reload art assets so I want it in
the game as well but I would also like
what you're saying I would like the HSA
to compile that in as well at some point
it's not a high priority right now but I
would like that OpenGL or Vulcan for a
complete beginner OpenGL Volken it has
no reason to exist I just skipped Vulcan
entirely learn OpenGL direct3d or metal
but never never Vulcan Vulcan is useless
what would it look like if you activated
the snake code now and make them cats
just seeing cats walk around randomly in
the rooms will be so cool just adding
random stop and lick your paw calls and
you basically have created life or I
should just deal with halfway from okay
I just wait for having to wait for mark
cuz the snake code isn't even still in
there really
I mean not the snake behavior is but I
mean the like placement code isn't
advice on logging events or dumping in
case of games crash in a customer's
machine I guess questions how to prepare
for Alden customers who had the game
crashed I okay so I thought that steam
would do that for you but I then also
think that there was some weirdness like
they didn't update it for 64-bit or
something so now I'm not sure my answer
should be steam will do that for you but
I don't actually know if it does the
tifinagh says I mean if the idle sprite
body sprite will be smaller in pixels
than the dodge left for example so if
the sprite dimensions you send to the
graphics cards are the same
will the dodge less right be squashed so
yes and no the thing that makes that not
happen or rather that will allow us to
make that not happen is that in the
texture itself we actually store the
width and height in pixels remember
where the texture definition is there it
is
so when we go to render it we actually
can adjust for how many pixels it was
and that will allow us to prevent that
problem right so you're not wrong we do
need to make sure we handle it properly
but I believe we will be able to we'll
see we get there
let's see what's wrong with Vulcan
search the archives I think I've ranted
about it on the stream before Thank You
KC for giving both the buggers a try
even though it failed really bath time
I'll give it best through sport I don't
know about the vs as a standard thing
yeah so basically I guess what I would
say is it should come with visual studio
key bindings by default as an option you
can be able to select that because it's
pretty easy to provide that feature and
then it just needs to yeah like it's it
seems a bit crashing right now so it
needs to like be cleaned up and reliable
your debugger can't crash right you need
to not have even Visual Studio managed
to not crash most of time it needs to be
reliable right so but failing fixing
those two things and I would love to
give it another shot how do you approach
a bitmap that needs to be generated
frequently on the fly would you add it
to your asset system and reference it
through your asset system or would you
skip the asset system in that case well
if it's generated then you don't really
need it to be in in the asset system
probably although it probably still
wants to go through at least some layer
of the asset system to make sure that it
knows that it's occupying a texture slot
right I don't know I mean one way to
answer that question would be our
lighting fits that description and it's
got its own special path right so
between directx and opengl which one
would you recommend for a beginner
probably direct3d 11 super off topic can
you offer me an exhibition as to why
there have never been ps2 based PC
controllers since it's the specific
input port that sends CPU interrupts I
don't understand what you mean like the
plug isn't even compatible but oh oh do
you not talking about PlayStation 2
you're talking about the actual ps2 plug
on the back of some motherboards from
the old days like for keyboards and mice
an explanation as to why they've never
been ps2 based PC controllers for
those ports I don't know enough about
the ports but my suspicion is that they
don't get pulled frequently enough I
don't know I don't know there are ps2
based keyboard controller things aren't
there that are pulled frequently in some
special motherboard way I thought so I
don't know I don't know the answer to
your question it's an interesting idea I
just don't know how many motherboards
support it but support high enough
frequency polling of those how long is
the vada episode usually take come
online about a day I upload them pretty
soon usually after and then you know
YouTube posts them several hours later
after the like frostings finished or
whatever so
yeah all right looks like the end of the
questions
so I think we're good one more will
close on how do you like the progress of
human here so far um it's pretty good
you know I mean for something where I
only get to work on it a very few hours
I think we build some pretty nice stuff
in the engine it's it's in fact maybe
getting to the point where it's where
it's a little bit too it's a little too
far along so we're kind of getting into
stuff that's game design II now and
that's that's not really my area of
expertise so I guess what I would say is
hand-made here has progressed to the
point where it is going to exceed what I
would have liked to have taught on
stream you know I'd like to get the game
running reasonably well as a game just
to like go through and wreak lean up
engine things and fix things that never
quite got finished and you know to just
like do an entity system a nice entity
system in there you know the things that
are only game related which is kind of
what we're starting to do now so
obviously you want to do those things
but you know again like we've kind of
progressed to the point where it's
definitely crossing over into game
design territory now which is you know
not really my thing so I guess what I
would say is we're sort of starting to
transition over to a place where I'll
start having a lot of disclaimers the
begin the screen I'll be like all right
we're gonna do some stuff that's more or
less just game design today and I don't
do game design so ignore this episode
except for the parts where we touch the
engine
alright alright I'm gonna go ahead and
wrap up the string okay thank you
everyone for joining me for the episode
of hand made here it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along series at home you
can always peer into the game on
handmade hair org and it comes with the
source code so you can play around with
it too and learn some stuff hopefully
hopefully some learn some game
programming stuff that's it for today
we'll be back tomorrow for I guess what
I'd like to do is start playing with
that hotspot editing stuff that's the
last part of the importing I can think
of that we haven't handled yet most of
the other things it seems like we've
done and so I'd really like to take a
look at how we want do that just
basically being able to modify the HHA
to have our own hotspots that we sort of
adjust in the game and go from there so
we'll take a look at that and then after
that I think we're kind of back to room
Jen lighting sorts of stuff where we're
gonna have to start looking at bringing
the world together
you know adding features we want there
ground cover those sorts of things that
we will now want to do and other things
like that so that's it for today hope
see you back here for tomorrow till then
have fun programming I'll see you guys
on the Internet take it easy everybody