hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show that we code a complete game
live on stream and part of that complete
means that lighting is in the mix
unfortunately one of the hardest things
to do in 3d graphics or just in graphics
in general he is lighting but we are
working on it right now and we're hoping
to have that wrapped up in the next few
weeks although it is gonna take a while
I'd say a few weeks I probably mean the
next six or seven weeks right but we're
doing the best we can here it's a
difficult problem not the kind of one
you want to solve on a stream that's to
our chunks but we have to do everything
here so we're doing it before I get
started today just want to mention two
things one we do have a discord now
there's a button down on the page here
or if you're using this watch page on
the schedule there's a button here you
can jump to the discord the discord will
hook you up with other folks in the
handmade hero viewing audience as well
as myself I spend a lot of time on there
now I put the little discord app on my
phone
and every time I'm sitting around with
nothing to do
waiting for something I'll just pop it
open so I moderate it and I participate
the discussions there so come say hi
it's been pretty great so far and while
we're on that subject although this
won't make much sense to people watching
these act in fact like if we can wave
some kind of a good luck charm for our
friends over in Japan we got a lot of
people who participate at the discord
and also you know watch serious it Japan
right now they are in the middle of a
pretty nasty typhoon I believe it's
called a hurricane in the US on the East
Coast called the typhoon in Japan but
basically the same thing very very heavy
wind storm with a lot of rain and
flooding and I'm told that like interior
Tokyo is is faring pretty well because
they have a flood control system there
which is pretty awesome actually but the
more outlying areas are getting hit
pretty hard so hopefully everyone's okay
and I guess we'll be checking the
discord later today and tomorrow to see
how everyone fare
hopefully everyone's okay so if you get
a second you know point pointy a good
luck want their way and hope that
everyone comes out of that okay I know
we got at least I think two people over
there who I've are active participants
often times but I'm sure we also
probably have a bunch we don't hear from
very often who are over there so so best
of luck everyone and hopefully it all
works out okay now the other order of
business is after this stream we will be
rolling into another John and KC gaming
extravaganza John and I were gonna play
somewhere multiple ear games today like
some of you caught us playing
satisfactory a couple weeks ago John
wanted to play through two games or well
John picked out two games that maybe
we'd try unreeled was one of them we
were here together I think is the name
of the other one uh and they may not be
good so we don't know maybe we won't
really be playing them but we're at
least gonna give it a shot
so after this stream stay tuned John and
I will be squatting up I believe we will
be streaming it he usually likes to
stream gaming sessions so I'm assuming
unless he says today is the one day he
doesn't want to stream it we will
presumably be streaming that so stay
tuned for that as well on my channel or
on twitch.tv slash naysayer 88 is the
other channel and I think the squad
thing lets you swap between them really
easily so chances are you can just stay
tuned on this channel and you can then
switch over to his channel at any time I
think that's what's supposed to happen
with the new twitch feature I've never
actually seen it myself but we do turn
it on alright moving on what we were
doing last week and we need to basically
finish up or at least come up with our
first draft this week is we were looking
at the way in which it was that's not
what I wanted we were looking at the way
in which we might go about getting
lighting into our pixel shader or as
it's called in OpenGL a fragment shader
and this
is kind of a it's a difficult question
and the reason it's a difficult question
it's because it's very much experimental
for me
I don't do GPU programming really as my
focus and unlike some things some
aspects of coding the difference between
a generalist and a specialist is not
particularly large so you know a a
generalist is gonna do basically the
same thing as a specialist modulo a
little bit of you know improvement maybe
the specialist makes or something some
some areas are like that GPU programming
isn't like that
so in GPU programming the difference
between what a specialist can do and
what a generalist can do is actually
quite large so the difference in quality
in a lighting solution I'm going to do
is going to be pretty dramatic probably
between the difference in quality that
especially to do so somebody for example
who's a graphics researcher at Nvidia is
probably going to be able to design a
much better lighting algorithm for
handmade Hiro were they to do that then
I'm going to be able to do and again
that's because GPU technology moves
quickly if something gets revised year
over year over year over year and so a
generalist such as myself who does all
of the things in a game engine
oftentimes has not had enough experience
with whatever the current target
platform is to really have a strong
point of view on what works well and
what doesn't right so although I do keep
fairly up to date on what's you know
possible meaning I understand the kinds
of things GPUs can do and how they're
doing them because that's important and
not that hard to keep up with for
something like designing a really
difficult algorithm like lighting what
you're talking about is really a very
precise very finicky area of the code
that really only someone who knows
exactly what is possible and how it
works
on a broad range of hardware platforms
that are relevant to
day right that's really the only person
who can do an exemplary job and so for
us this is going to be a bit of a
struggle because we're flying somewhat
blind they're the generalist is flying
somewhat blind they just know here's a
bunch of features that the gravis heart
has that I could access
I don't know how performing each one of
them really will be I can make some
guesses I might be wrong
there could be pitfalls hiding there
that I don't know about and again that's
because if you're just not up-to-date
enough on it so what I would probably do
normally in most circumstances if I was
doing this myself we would go read a
bunch of research papers on this topic
and we'd probably pick based on a lot
more input right we don't do that on
handmade here oh and the reason we don't
do that on handmade hero is because I
want to show the process of muddling
through things sometimes it's important
because there won't always be someone
who's tackled the problem that you're
thinking about or not tackling it in the
way that you need to tackle it and so
you do need to learn to do these things
so it's important to approach problems
even like this one and see how would I
solve it if I just had to write it's
good practice and you should do it too
but it's worth knowing it's worth
understanding that in a professional
setting you would also in addition to
practice you would also want to
understand the fact that reading a bunch
of papers about this and or consulting
with some experts in GPU programming
would be valuable and probably will help
you develop an algorithm better than the
one you can develop yourself because if
you're not a GPU specialist you just
don't have the experience with the
actual practical implications of the
things that you're using so it's worth
getting that out of the way just so
everyone has protective on it but that
said we are gonna do it ourselves and
the reason is that like I said is
because it's important to learn how to
do that because sometimes you do have to
go somewhere that other people haven't
gone and that's just part of programming
part of being a strong engine programmer
is not being afraid of tackling a
problem that doesn't have an easily
published solution that fits your needs
right
so where we left off was in the fragment
shader like I said excuse me a little
bit stuffy today where we left off was
in the fragment shader and what's going
on in the fragment shader is we need to
reconstitute inbound lighting using some
kind of a spatial query we don't know
what it is or what it will be
we need to reconstitute our inbound
lighting so that we can light a pixel
that has never had any lighting computed
on it this is the idea behind light
probes they're saying look it's too
expensive to compute the lighting every
pixel we could never do that with the
horsepower we have available at the time
but what we can do is compute the
lighting at various sparse sparsely
populated points throughout the world
and when we go to light a pixel we'll
look at where those sparse points are
and we'll reconstitute our lighting by
interpolating between the lighting we
solve for at those sparse points that's
all a light probe really is right the
rest of the complexity of a light probe
is in the details and how you implement
it there's really nothing else about it
there's nothing else complicated about
it right the concept is very very simple
ludie is expensive computed as few
places as possible and try to
reconstitute the lighting per pixel by
looking at those sample points right so
for us that means each pixel we need
some way of finding out which of these
light which of these light probes we
want to sample from and the problem that
we have is it would be very very
straightforward and probably preferable
right if we could just pick the closest
light probe and light the pixels as if
they were lit by that probe but by the
lighting if that's at that probe
location right that would be the best
possible case for us and the reason that
that would be the best possible case is
because that would be like one voxel
lookup that would give us back an index
and then we would just look up the
lighting probe inbound light
representation using that index and we
be done right so that's by far the
preferable method and we can implement
that fairly simply it would be one texel
fetch that fetch into the voxel and then
some number of additional textile
fetches depending on how much lighting
data we wanted to extract if we wanted
to extract six separate pieces of
lighting information one for each
direction out of the phases of our light
probe cube for example that would be six
more fetches or if we bundled multiple
directions into one somehow maybe it's
less but you know it would basically be
a total of one texture Texel fetch to
look at the light probe index and six
Texel fetches to look up the lighting
contribution and that's a total of seven
textual fetches and we're done not
particularly complicated and then we
would just go about applying whatever
equations we wanted to to estimate the
inbound light based on that probe so we
then get to sort of an obvious
simplification which is that if we are
assessing what the lighting information
would be at a particular direction well
three of the faces of the cube in a
lighting in a so if you look at how much
inbound light there is in a cube that
we're tracking there are six faces of
the cube
the inbound light coming through each of
those six phases has certain limitations
as to how it could light a particular
object if you assume no translucency and
no subsurface scattering sorts of
operations which we are not considering
because we don't really have any way to
take advantage of that with our sprites
we don't need it right maybe there's
some times that we would but they'd be a
special shader presumably so we're just
talking about reflective light then a
particular pixel that we're trying to
light has a normal pointing in a
particular direction which means that
all of the incident light has to be
pointing into basically or the direction
of sampling has to be pointing in the
same direction let's say as that normal
that means that at any given time three
of the faces of our cube will be
contributing to lighting and three of
the faces won't be so in addition to
that one piece of information we have
about look we would look up a particular
light probe and then we would fetch its
information we can probably cut that
down to three Texel fetches only those
necessary to fetch the three faces of
the cube that will actually contribute
because we know the other three faces if
unless we're in some really weird like
okay we're trying to light smoke or
something right where you're trying to
get back facing light coming through as
well except in special purpose shaders
we really only need three so that would
get us down to just four Texel fetches
for the lighting and so that would be
really nice that would be great but the
problem there is what do you do at the
edges at some point when you move
something around the environment or you
just imagine just a flat plane and we're
lighting each pixel at some point you
cross over to where the closest light
probe is actually different and so when
we look up into the voxel which light
probe we should light with there's going
to be a pixel who says it's this light
from over here a light probe a and then
a pixel right next to it we'll say oh
the closest light probe is light probe B
right and if we haven't done any
blending then those two pixels will get
lit completely differently right and
this creates a huge problem for us we'll
have all of the
hard edges in our lighting and it will
look really bad or maybe if you're you
know into weird artwork you could just
lean into that aesthetic and say well
okay I'm just gonna do it that way and
that's where the game looks right that's
a totally fine decision to make not one
we're gonna make we want to figure out a
way to do the blending and the problem
we have of the blending is that it's a
3-dimensional world so any pixel could
be related to any other pixel by being a
little bit above a little bit below the
bit left right back forward and so
really what we have is effectively a
cube based blend there are eight
lighting probes near to this pixel one
that's to the you know ones that's the
closest in this direction one's lost
that direction this direction right and
so as you move continuously through the
space if we want the lighting to be
continuous we need what is effectively a
trilinear blend we need to blend eight
incoming sample points together so that
we're smooth no matter how we move
through the space and the lighting never
has a hard scene that's what creates a
nasty problem for us so you can see here
where we have our lighting information
this for example is what it looks like
to do Texel fetches on eight different
things right you can see me textile
fetching each of these lights and I
would need to know the index for the
light in each of these three different
places I would then lerp them together
right and you can see me doing some of
that like getting the lighting data here
right and this is if we're only doing
one side so you can see it's like
sixteen Texel fetches really nasty only
to do one face of the cube this will
multiply itself out right I would end up
with three copies of this we're just
drowning in textile fetches right it's
not great and so one thing that was
proposed at the end of the last stream I
and that I think is an interesting idea
and probably one we should explore
because there are some ways you can make
this work
is what is instead of doing this
manually where we actually track light
indices themselves what if instead of
doing that we actually just had a voxel
representation of the lighting itself
and we just went hog-wild and said look
we've got six phases of this cube we're
saying we're tracking the lighting
through those six phases right that's
what we're gonna do or something else
maybe we switched to switch to spherical
harmonics so we saw them in a slightly
different way you know I don't know
right we're what we're gonna do
something where we have some number of
terms stored for lighting into a voxel
and we're gonna fetch them if we were to
store the actual lighting terms into the
voxel then what we can do is instead of
calling Texel fetch here we can just
instead of eight calls to Texel fetch we
can make one call to texture and that
will do a try linear blend on the voxel
for us right now it's still doing a full
try linear blend on the voxel so we
haven't really saved a lot of math but
what we have done is given the graphics
card the opportunity to heavily optimize
that fetch because it knows we're doing
a try linear blend from a 3d texture
which is an operation native to GPUs
right so it can probably run it a lot
more quickly there's a lot less
bookkeeping it needs to do a lot less
work because it already has specialized
circuitry most of the time designed
specifically to fetch texels in a way
that blends them together so it's not
going to be super confused about what
we're doing and has to do each step
manually it's gonna have a bunch of
those steps fuse together and it's gonna
do stuff like pull out bundles of pixels
blend them together directly and do like
the whole thing in one or two steps that
we were having to do in sixteen steps
right and although that savings may not
sound like a huge amount of savings
because hey there's not that much code
here when you think about the fact that
this is code that has to execute on
every
pixal of our screen for our display
right that's a lot of work right
anything we can do to make this simpler
for the graphics card is huge so it does
seem like that may be a better starting
architecture because if we could do it
that way maybe we can avoid some of this
bookkeeping that could slow the GPU down
make it difficult for it to hit 60
frames a second doing this kind of
advanced per pixel work because again
it's just the less you throw at the GPU
per pixel the better so let's think
about what that would look like right
you can see here us operating on our
voxel we're producing our voxel location
and you can see us doing stuff like
flooring right and we're computing these
pieces of information and what I think
we want to do there say all right so
let's just pretend that we don't want to
do that anymore what would it look like
well one of the nice things is even this
information goes away because now that's
part of the texture lookup itself so if
we were to assume that we had some
number of these 3d textures and they
were representing our actual lighting
then what we would say is you know what
what we really have here is the
different sides of the cube and so we
would have something more like this
right we would have well I guess we want
to just do our box surface and we might
call it our box surface ordinals here so
it'd just be like west east south
north down right so we would feed in six
separate samplers one each for the
directions of our lighting and that
would actually be what we sample so then
here we would pull from those lights
that lighting information and again
probably just going to be a v4 sample
here we're going to be looking up in AU
32 texture that will then kind of come
out to the sampler what we want to do
here is say all right let's get the
light from the West right and that's
gonna be a texture look up and that's
gonna be from our light sampler West and
we're just going to use our Vox you can
see here right we have our relative P
that maps in the voxel we have our Vox
index P that makes it into our UV W what
I'm gonna call that instead is our voxel
UV W now because it's really that's what
it is like a texture look up now that's
what we're treating it as same value it
just make it clear what what we're gonna
do with it we're not going to convert it
to indices into the voxel we're gonna
let the graphics card take it as a uvw
it's gonna do that mapping right so what
we want to do now is say well really the
value that we want here is not where it
is in the cell what we want is where it
is in the texture so instead we're just
gonna do in verse voxel total dimension
so we're really is taking how big is
this voxel at all and we're gonna we're
gonna make that be the value that we
actually want so we don't want to map it
into cell so that we have which cell and
how far in cell instead we want to just
say and you know I guess we didn't
actually put these out here it doesn't
look it looks like we didn't really put
these out so these again have to be up
here as things that come in as
parameters that we specify because the
shader itself has no idea how where this
voxel is supposed to be right it doesn't
know any of that information so we need
to tell it we need to have the voxel
mid-corner that's actually three right
because it's where it is in space and
then we have the total inverse total dim
or maybe I should call it voxel inverse
total dim right and that again that's
just a scaling value that says well we
need to you know account for how large
the voxel lists or shrink or scale the
input values to conform to the voxel so
there's zero when you're at the at the
min edge and one we're at the far edge
even though the voxel itself may be 300
meters long or something right
so that's all we really need to do
they're going to produce a voxel UVW for
our lookup and then what we need to do
is do a 3d texture texture fetch which I
never remember the names of any of the
things in OpenGL let's load that up
I should just pin that how do you do
that again you know like this right so
really what we want to do now is just do
a texture fetch right and you can see
here here's the actual information for
how textures are fetched you can see
that you've got samplers here and the
samplers for texture can be anything
right so I can pass it a 1d texture or
2d texture with like we have been doing
or I can just sample from a 3d texture
and all I really need to do is just pass
it the appropriate p-value which again
has to be 0 to 1 from beginning to the
end of the texture on each dimension
that's exactly what I prepared here so
this call doesn't it's exactly the same
as looking at any other texture
we're just saying it's a it's a 3d
texture now so instead of doing a 2d
placement in it's just gonna do a 3d
placement in it and that's that's it
don't do anything else so you can see
that would really give us a very quick
way of producing these values that we
want
west-east south north down up right so I
can get the values out of my cube
lighting by doing six Texel fetches and
why shouldn't I talk about just six
texture lookups that will themselves do
the trilinear filter right to filter the
map and then once we have those values
we just need to combine them into a
lighting solution so we need now some
way of saying okay let's let's you know
let's light the pixel based on now what
we know right okay so when we do this
when you can see here where we do this
some light call well the problem that we
have is when we're summing the lighting
we now need to be able to do the
lighting equation based on light that's
in coming from different directions
right we have a west east north south
down up etc and so we need to be able to
say well like give us you know give us
some indication of if light were coming
from there how much of that light would
be reflected back out at us right how
much of that light would be reflected
back towards the direction of the eye
first of all and then you know related
to the surface normal that we are given
and so this is just going to be a
straight-up flooding equation here and I
want to put that in but at the moment
what I'd rather do is actually say let's
hold off on that for a minute
because if I were to put a complete
lighting equation in here then we also
have the problem of did I write it
correctly right did I screw up the
lighting equation and so when we look at
what comes out of it I could have made
any kind of error there so what I think
they want to do first is let's just test
test each individual lighting channel
and make sure that we can actually
sample them accurately using this
technique to make sure we don't have
bugs elsewhere in the pipeline
and then once I know that I'm actually
sampling each of these lights properly
then we move to computing the lighting
equation with some cops
that we have done the underlying work
properly so we're only debugging the
lighting equation itself not the inputs
and the lending equation and having no
idea what we've screwed up right so
that's what I'd like to do first so
there's going to be to do here that's
like insert lighting equation here but
what we're going to do first is when we
return lighting information from the
sunlight some light we are just going to
return the lighting value from one of
these things let's say that's what we're
going to return and so we ain't going to
have a light data that's going to be an
RGB what I'm going to say right now is
we're going to take light West that RGB
and multiply it by light West a the a
value I'm going to say the Alpha value
we're going to encode the intensity of
the light into that so that way we have
an RGB which gives us 256 levels of
precision on each color gun and then
another value which basically scales
them this is just a crappy way of doing
an HDR encoding basically and so what I
want to do is say all right we'll take
the light here that if I just did it by
itself would allow us to get from zero
to one brightness in our G and B I want
to be able to have a broader range so
what I'm going to do is say max light
intensity right times that a value that
allows me to take the Alpha value and
say how bright is this light relative
that's incoming here relative to the
maximum intensity of a light in general
that we can possibly have in the game
what's the brightest light and then the
RGB is just a way of caller izing that
light so we have a way of having a broad
like basically a an exponent on the
light and you know we may want to change
how this is encoded I'm not saying this
is exactly how we want to encode it or
anything but you know that's we're gonna
start with that and then as we go we may
change it around right
and so then up in here for the moment
because I don't really care
I'm just gonna go ahead and quickly
define this to max light intensity
that's gonna be a floating-point value
that just gets input into the shaders so
cure I will have a max light intensity
value that's probably just gonna be
something that we define in the render
itself so in the handmade renderer code
where we're starting to define things
here like the light data with that sort
of thing we're just gonna say that
there's a max light intensity and that
max light intensity is whatever it is I
don't know what it is maybe it's ten who
knows not my problem right now that will
be something when we go to tune the
actual lighting figure out how bright we
want our brightest light to be don't
have an opinion we don't even have
exposure control in this game so you
know that's for a later day all right
so once we have that piece of
information we now have the ability to
call the some light function and the
some light function returns the
information that we actually needed
which is how bright the lighting should
be on this thing right
what's the inbound RGB light and
eventually we're gonna have to have some
real information there but for right now
all we're gonna do is say what did the
Westfield say the lighting was and we're
just gonna return that don't care what
the normal is don't care about anything
other than the position of the pixel and
what is in the West Side voxel at that
point that's it right okay so assuming
that we wanted to do that what I'd like
to do here is maybe get rid of this if
letting disable thing this sunlight can
just sit here now and if the lighting is
disabled it simply won't call it right
so the fact that some light exists there
and it multiplies reflectance that just
won't happen if lighting is disabled
right so now what I'd like to do is make
lighting not be disabled and so when we
compile the Z bias program you can see
it down here where we call this you can
see that there is like a setting for
letting disabled if we search for that
let's see
that is doo-doo-doo
doo-doo-doo-doo-doo-doo
doo-doo-doo-doo-doo here is our actual
disabled for it dududududu
there you go uh and so if I just say no
we're actually gonna do lighting ma'am
as scary as that may seem we should be
off to the races and we will start
getting compile errors on our shaders
because we probably screwed those up
once the compiler is stopped we will be
totally borked because it'll just be the
cloud just be black presumably because
we haven't even sent down those samplers
they're gone right so now we're just
gonna start the process of feeding
something into these voxels and seeing
if it works right so that's where we're
going now okay I'm gonna open up remedy
the debugger of choice among handmade
zealots such as myself we are going to
run the game and in theory if we don't
well and we didn't even crash oh no we
did I'm like I'm like I'm assuming that
we will crash the wrong word I'm
assuming that we will fail the shader
validation and we did so first things
first let's make our shaders actually
work and then we'll have the problem
that they're sampling no actual light
oops fragment so here's what it reports
back it says error undefined variable
surface reflect let's go see what's
going on there
so if I jump to the Z bias program and I
look at it service reflect isn't used
until down below right so that's
actually here and excuse me it looks
like the problem we have is that it's
only if the model RA is above the
threshold does it actually do this
operation right I think that's because
this and that's probably right but I
think this brace here was like an arrant
brace I think that looks like the actual
problem right and so if we just delete
that brace this this was getting wrapped
into its own little clause here but this
whole Clause wants to actually be that
so I think that was all that particular
error was let's go back in Jimmy
run this again and we're running a debug
mode right now so it's a pretty slow
startup unfortunately so there we go and
I think you know I don't really know but
I think this is sort of what we would
expect
like I said everything would probably be
black and the reason for that you know
and even all this stuff is still going
through that shader and we're gonna have
to make sure that we do a lighting
disable call for those I think some way
of disabling that lighting because
otherwise we can't even access our UI
right but that lighting that's that's in
operation right now what's happening is
or what I believe is happening right is
that we're now sampling lighting which
will affect what we're doing we're
sampling that lighting from a from a
source that's always going to return
zero and so we just get a black screen
which is exactly what we would expect
now I just want to verify that that's
sort of what's happening because again
it's GPU program can never be too
careful I'm just gonna go ahead and
assign the normal whatever the normal is
getting passed down I'm gonna go ahead
and assign the normal to the output
lighting channel just to see whether I
see anything on the screen
and again that's just me trying to
ascertain to what extent this shader is
working right and so if we look at what
we're seeing here this is roughly what
we would expect so here are our normals
and if you look at like a cube you can
see that it looks exactly like what we
would expect the faces that are facing
in the positive direction well actually
no you know what there is one bug which
is I would have expected this top oh you
know what it is blue it's just it's so
dark the top is so dark in the texture
that it's getting nullified because
these are all blue so you can see the
positive direction is always bright so
if I look at it from this angle you can
see I see blue green and red on the
three positive directions and then these
should all be black because they're
negative normals right and I can fix
that obviously if I wanted to I could do
something like this
also isn't eff not allowed in shaders
why didn't I get an error on this I
thought for some reason I thought GLSL
doesn't allow you to put an ass in there
am I just imagining things I thought
like in three and four you can and three
you can't or some crap like this I don't
even know I think maybe we want that I'm
not sure but I'm gonna I'm gonna do that
anyway anyway so I can adjust these into
the visible range just to make sure but
basically yeah it's just you know
something like that and then we would
get you know we bias it up so it's all
in the visible color range because
negative knows no such thing as negative
colors when you're outputting pixels you
can only zeroes the lowest you can be
and so here's what it would look like if
we actually adjusted all the colors into
the visible range you can see these
things getting colorized by their
direction and just the brightness
basically says which direction they're
facing right so there's our our
understanding of the color values there
and everything looks you know roughly
correct ie not scrutinizing it so I
don't want to say it's 100% red but it
looks like we're fine so I think we are
correctly at this point set up to
actually get our voxel sampling working
which of course requires us to actually
provide these voxels somehow in the
first place and in order to do that what
I would like to do I think I'm not sure
because you know it's a little bit it's
a little bit tough to say
but basically what I'd like to do with
this voxel is say okay probably want to
tackle this in two stages in the first
stage I will output voxels directly to
the graphics card and those voxels will
be the lighting that is used that's step
one I want to do that because I think
it's the path with the least number of
calls to the GPU
Erico it is the path with the least
number of GPU Scrooged options in it
then once I am sure that that is working
and possibly when I say once I'm sure
that's working I may mean sure to ask
extreme extent meaning when we know the
entire lighting pipeline is now working
then I will move from submitting the
voxels myself to probably just
submitting a list of lights right so we
will step one as we send down six 128 by
128 by 128 voxels every frame ourselves
and step two is we just send down the
light probes and in step two what we'll
do is we'll take that light probe list
we'll treat it as a vertex buffer as if
it's going to render primitives to the
graphics card right and we will voxel
eyes the lighting into our voxels
ourselves right we'll figure out some
way to do that again that's a much more
complex operation and so I don't want to
mix that with lighting it's just an
optimization there's nothing different
right about that but you know I I don't
even really know exactly now I think
about it I'm not sure what the most
efficient ways to voxel eyes things on
the graphics card anyway it sounds kind
of nasty in the sense that
you don't really specify volumetric
primitives in OpenGL I've never really
thought about this but like if you
wanted to rasterize a voxel I mean I've
written my own voxel rasterizer for
multiple times and you know what you
want to do is have some function that
says which voxels are included and you
typically bound that and then evaluate
it as you step through the voxel that
operation I don't even know how to
provoke that operation in OpenGL if it
even has it right like I don't even know
how you give it a boundary region and
say please step through all of the
pieces of voxels so for all I know and I
don't know but for all I know what you
actually need to do is you actually need
to specify the slice of the texture as a
render target curve but no that wouldn't
work so I guess as I'm thinking this
through I'm like thinking to myself I
don't even know how you induce OpenGL to
produce the correct output to a voxel
anyway so we're gonna have to go look at
that like obviously there's people who
do stuff like voxel cone tracing and
things like this obviously you have to
be able to do that what I don't know is
does it require a computer if it does
forget that like we're not going that
route but I would have hoped that they
would have added some kind of a
rasterization primitive that rasterized
this into 3d cuz gosh that's just kind
of an obvious thing you'd want to do
it's weird that I can't even think of
someone mentioning this it's got to be
in there I'm just kind of curious what's
the what's the
okay so basically the answer is you have
to use an unordered access view so you
don't have to go full pixel shader by
the Ikes
so one ordered access views or look
really bad class is that really true
what disappoints me on so many levels
I'm kind of depressed to hear that if
anyone from Nvidia is out there
listening right now can you please email
me or something and tell me why that's
the case because an unordered access
view is like a very bad primitive right
and on order to access view is
essentially a it's essentially a
construct that breaks the ability of the
GPU to know about the pixels touched by
a shader ahead of time which makes it
much less performant I would think in a
lot of cases and in the case of voxel
ization you could just have voxel
ization the front-end rasterizer knows
it can do the exact same operation on
voxels as it does on pixels
it's just that edge inclusion operation
just uses six planes instead of three
planes right
so is it just that that was impossible
like was it that there's no way we're
gonna add six planes to our rasterizer
we can only have three because even that
doesn't sound like it makes any sense to
me but maybe it's true I don't know but
I would love to know why that was the
answer that just seems really weird to
me I know were to access view
very depressed right now yeah I'm very
depressed right now all right
so if I multiply out how big one of
these voxels is at worst eight megabytes
of throughput times six is fifty
megabytes of GPU throughput per frame if
we wanted to send down the voxel every
frame right so if we wanted to just say
look here comes the voxel bro and we
sent down the whole thing so we never
did that operation that I was just
talking about because oMG acquires
unordered access views which is a
complete nightmare um what we would want
to have to do is send down what a mass
264 K let's just say I'm sorry 64 Meg's
we're trying to send down 64 megabytes
of memory or something actually maybe is
closer to 48 so if I do ten 24/48 mix
sorry I was being being bad math II so
it's 48 megabytes of GPU throughput if
we're sending that down at 60 frames a
second that's 2 gigabytes and sustained
throughput to the graphs card it's not
fantastic right but it's not that high
so it's not out of the question that we
could just do this on the CPU side it's
possible whether that turns out to be
the right answer me and I don't know but
it's possible is all I'm saying
so you know I guess that's just
something for us to think about as we go
so if we go and we stretch our concept
of what's happening here a little bit
you can imagine going through and taking
the
render commands that we have here and
instead of sending down the different
information that we've got here these
are not potentially ever gonna be sent
down then these will just be for our own
personal renderer use we would just end
up being in this land here where we have
the light index voxel being sent down
here and this voxel has the data in it
that we actually use for lighting what
we want to do there is say okay this
goes away perhaps meaning this light
probe irradiance I guess is not really a
thing maybe well we probably still need
that for other reasons but so what we're
gonna have to do here is actually pack
our color values in here and prepare six
separate voxel dated chunks and send
them all down as 3d textures right so we
would need to do something like this
where we're gonna pack that RGB a
lighting in there and send that down as
the light in next voxel each time and
again we'll do that in a not
particularly fancy way at first so here
we would basically just do like some
kind of a nonsense thing where we're
just like all right
each of these we're actually gonna just
send over and once we've got that in
place the OpenGL version of course also
needs to have a six wide thing that it's
keeping for that I guess I'll just use
the compiler to jump me right to it or
not
okay so never mind that isn't actually
tell me so that opened jail structure
there that keeps these guys where does
that go it's here I so here's that light
index voxel that's going to change you
can see we need six of those now so
there's our gigantic thing I suppose
actually we want to do it like that and
then we're good so now we have a place
to put this information we just need to
send it somewhere because right now
we're not actually submitting that
letting information so we need at some
point to say okay let's bind some
textures to this thing and allow them to
get fetched so in the actual code and
we're going to need to do this get a
couple different places first here you
can see where we do our open Joe
link samplers you can see we've got the
lights at the end here we now need to
change that to be linking each of these
right
and so down here we've got effectively
that same list we need to link east west
south north down and up as our set once
of those samplers are all linked up we
have to submit them so when we go to set
the Z bias program anytime that's
actually happening we have to set up the
shaders for it so when we look at the
places where that's actually being done
oh I guess I guess we don't do it that
way
nevermind so I'm just gonna jump down
then to where we actually do the Z bias
program so when we're actually
dispatching primitives here in the
actual renderer loop itself right where
we're dispatching these primitives when
we get down to textured quads then this
is the place we're actually using the Z
bias program right you can see it here
we start setting up our textures you can
see us setting up our textures for like
the depth handle and then you can see us
sending down the light data here this is
where we need to actually specify the
information that we have from the the
game proper so we'd actually be
switching to a GL texture 3d at that
point and we'd be setting these up as
textures 2 3 4 5 etc right so I'm just
gonna make this a loop because you know
why not so in here I'm gonna say well
open drill has some amount of flight
data there's the the voxel index the
voxel index will loop over to the six
once we have I could do it like this
even
and then it's just gonna send down if
light in next two is the first one it's
gonna do lighting mix - I was sorry
texturing next to plus which voxel we're
trying to send down it'll send each one
of those down well won't send them down
it will bind each one of those and get
it ready to go
and then when we come back here we will
turn off those textures right you can
see that happening here and so when we
go to actually bind the other textures
we would want here - probably unbind
those although I don't know that we
really care about
unbinding them they can just be left
bound because no other people use them
really so I'm not sure what we want to
do there but I guess we'll just leave it
like this we send down the lighting
textures here so there we don't some of
that we bind them here we need to send
them down somewhere right so at some
point someone needs to actually like
describe these textures to the graphics
card and so somewhere up here where
we're sending down like our bind buffers
you can see that happening here right
where we're sending down our bind
buffers we need to actually submit the
all of the data it does strike me as odd
that we do this the buffer data
submission before we change the settings
seems like you would really want to do
that after but I guess I don't know
we'll leave it there for now
so what we need to do here is actually
submit these textures so here we need to
effectively do a GL texture 3d call
right and I think we want text sub image
3d in this case because we're not
changing the format of the texture we're
not changing the dimensions we're not
doing really anything to it all we're
trying to do is specify a new set of
data for each one of those handles and
so what I'd rather do here is just like
resubmit right just resubmit the data
that we've got so if we were to look at
the GL text sub image call here's an
example of that call we're gonna be
doing exactly the same thing here only
we're gonna be specifying an entire
texture rather than a slice so if I go
in here and say all right we've got GL
texture 3d is where we're submitting
this thing we've set our GL active
texture to this thing
we then have a MIT level of zero it will
always be zero we're in the upper corner
which is zero zero zero we then have a
width and a height we know what those
are because we've sort of pre specified
the dimension of our lighting voxel it's
actually up here yeah where is it here
right so we know that we're always
sending down something that looks like
that right because it's just we we're
never going to be doing anything
different I don't know if actually we
should be well I don't know we're gonna
leave it like that for now let's just do
that
so we have our voxel sent down as
complete 3d texture let me go back to
our
text image 3d call here we go and then
we just need to know what the format is
so we don't really need be GRA X
probably although we could send them
that since everything else is B GRA we
might as well stick with the format so
it's not like oh just the lighting is
the wrong way round I guess we're gonna
send it down as an unsigned byte and
we're gonna send it down as this voxel
information here right so now all we're
doing is at the head end we're sending
down all that data that we're binding it
later looking here it looks like the
light data is the wrong thing to say
there because that's probably not what
we called it if we look at the open jail
struct like I did before you can see
it's not that here it is right so I
guess we kind of want to call that the
light data array maybe seems to what
we're calling it elsewhere so we'll just
do that for now and we'll worry about
the name of that later once we actually
decide on this technique and make sure
everything actually is working for us we
might change it up and so we need to
know what's going on there
don't ask me what this was supposed to
be I have no idea what was going on
there
that's just my brain being my is a brain
fart straight-up brain fart obviously we
need texture handles this light data so
I'm not sure why I was thinking it's
this that we actually need so we need
six of these these are where we would
specify the textures initially so
they're just handles like this is the
OpenGL handle we're gonna use to talk
about this texture and that's what
actually needs to get bound and
submitted right so that was just brain
fart here we need to do that so we need
to specify that here we say for this
texture we're gonna bind and go this was
the wrong thing to think about we don't
need that right we just need this
right so when we do GL buying texture GL
texture 2d right then we come in here
we're gonna unbind it you know I'm
saying so we do a bind than we do and
unbind just to clear that out so I think
that's what the flow should have look
like I don't know why I did any other
way before I just did so now if we look
at a GL text image 3d you can see that
that getting specified here and here
right and really what I want to do is I
want to do the same thing I was doing in
this call I want to generate these
textures for our light data so in here I
want to do a thing where I say all right
let's loop over the box index here just
like we were doing before I want to
generate texture handles of that order
as well so light data handle and array
count so generate this mini handles for
us each time through here I want to do
exactly this I want to grab out the
light data I want to bind it and then I
want to specify some stuff right so
first of all we're not gonna do any
nipping on these things we are going to
be specifying the standard format that
we have been which i think is GL r g b
a8 right we want the width height and
depth width height and depth it's hard
to get those straight and that's our
light with the fox will dim so we then
need to specify how many it bubbles we
want that is I don't know what that is
then we want to specify the storage
format which is what that is and that
and then we're not going to write
anything so we're
just telling you look this is how much
space we need be ready right so
that's the long and short of it I'm sure
we've made plenty of bugs in there
because GPU code is always riddled with
bugs but that's basically what we're
doing create the handles tell OpenGL how
big they are every frame send down new
data and then bind during Z bias program
that's what we need to do for the most
part and it looks like we got oh yes so
when we're deleting these textures here
with the light data I'm not sure
so are we actually creating them in here
though we are not so this stuff needs to
go because that's not actually happening
anymore
and those I don't think get deleted in
here those are just permanent right yeah
cuz I don't think we need to do that so
that's all fine so all I'm gonna do now
is just go and see about setting up the
filtering on this thing that's the only
thing that we haven't done so if we go
look at our light data handle where we
create this thing this part here where
we set the texture information so I
don't really know what we want to set
here when we do min and mag we're doing
linear sampling I don't know to what
extent that applies in 3d but I assume
it will and I assume we can also do when
we do texture wrap I assume we can clamp
the U as well but don't quote me on that
right so I'll have to look that up let
me see what else we got here
so render in tree lighting transfer
pretty much not gonna allow I don't
think at the moment so I'm gonna get rid
of that and I'm also going to just
assume that no one can send that down so
if I look at the renderer I'm gonna get
rid of the lighting transfer so that's
just not allowed anymore and anyone who
was using anything like that should go
away so let me take a look at what this
is supposed to be I don't know what
these are called
I'm gonna go to Docstoc GL I'm gonna
start to see text per am just to see
what's going on in there if I look at
the settings you can see here's the wrap
so there's wrap s there's wrap t I don't
know what wrap R is but maybe that's the
thing we want STR
say
so that must be it because it's the
third parameter right let's say it is so
we're probably gonna have to define geo
texture wrap our ourselves right because
that's probably an extension that was
just for 3d textures so it wasn't an
OpenGL one so if we go look at like you
know heel core or what was the thing GL
X dot H or whatever so if we look at
like rap are you can see it's just this
thing and that should be all we actually
made so not a big deal right
probably we should have grabbed it in
here just wasn't thinking about having
to do that in fact maybe the best place
to put it would be down here if that's
where it would really be used so I think
that's everything
so now in theory we're sending those
down but again that's really just only a
theory I don't actually know what's
gonna happen here and we may also have
bugs so the first thing we're gonna want
to do now is go into the code and try to
provide like some kind of a that's so
you can see like little seams I wonder
what those are coming from are they fog
maybe anyway we're gonna want to go into
the code and try to stuff one of those
voxels with an actual color so we can
see that it's getting selected right and
so the easiest way for me to do that
would be when we go to finish off our
lighting so in like lighting test for
example oh I guess it's not laying
testing where it's called like and
lighting computation yeah so in end
lighting computation in here what we
would do is when we get down to the end
right we would basically say all right
we now want to write to this voxel so
let's just write something to it and it
won't be correct at all but we'll just
write something too
so that's hmm Jimmy that command buffer
which is in here so here is our command
Meffert we have these light index voxels
here so we're gonna want to do that
gamer into commands commands equals
render group might just be group what is
it called in this function group so we
might wanted to see like okay group
man's now we've got it commands light
index voxel zero or box surface West or
whatever it was box UNIX West so what we
believe to be the westward facing voxel
like so I want to go through and I want
to write to that thing and I could do
this actually by being a little bit more
expansive so maybe we'll actually do it
a little bit differently the point being
maybe we'll do this I'm gonna have like
an X look up here
what was this call again oh you know
what it's actually right here
so if we look at the light index voxel
dim we then we know exactly what we're
talking about here so if we step through
this like so we know that now we should
be able to produce this piece of
information there you go
so in theory this would look what were
the entire voxel and then what we could
do is we can write something in there to
one of the channels whatever channel we
want so maybe we do something like this
play the next voxel box index west and
then we further address it as Z times cz
plus well actually guess we can do this
as sort of a stack maybe I don't know
how we want to do this exactly it's a
good question mmm well I guess we would
do it like this so
I guess I'll just write it like that
so we'll just write it out longhand
that's the address of this particular
cell in the voxel and then I'm just
gonna sign it some color value so I'm
gonna assign it a color value let's say
[Music]
maybe something looks like that so that
would be red with a you know medium
brightness red I guess okay and now we
can do I mean we'll take a look at what
this outputs but now we can do is we can
actually go and start using render dock
or you know something else too well
alright so that just worked right so now
we know we're stuffing that voxel and
what I'm interested now in figuring out
is when we're looking up this voxel to
what extent is it actually spatially
querying so what I want to do is I want
to then say all right let's suppose that
we wanted to introduce some kind of an X
striping so I want to go ahead and say
look let's say X mod 2 so every other
cell I want to do a different color so
I'm going to actually do something like
this where we do red blue red blue in
along X stripes right in sufficient disk
space yeah right
how about you already had the file
locked anyway so now I want to write
that out to the lighting buffer and see
if I see anything right I should now see
different colors coming through and
we'll see what happens but I don't right
so this is pretty important because this
means like something
busted and I'm saying as this steps
through I should be doing like this for
this on alternating indexes of the voxel
as far as I can tell anyway right so I
shouldn't have only seen that one I
should have seen a alternative each of
these and the question is why well the
first thing comes to mind is I think we
forgot to ever actually send down the
constants so probably it's looking into
only one cell of the voxel what I mean
well remember I said in order to map
this thing into the voxel we need to
angrily set up the voxel right and so I
defined these two things voxel min
corner and voxel in total dim but we
never actually specified what they were
so in here where the camera information
and stuff is getting sent down along
with everything else those need to be
there so we need to sort of query these
two constants that are gonna come down
and then we need to actually say what
they are once we get there so in here we
need like voxel min corner to be equal
to something and we need Vox in total
dim to be equal to something and we need
a way of specifying what these are so in
here we would say voxel mid-corner voxel
in turtle dam and then in the actual
definition of the Z bias program which
is this thing right here we need to
remember where those are so here are
those two things
oops that's
and once we have those now we can
actually specify them we need some way
of actually getting them which you know
has to happen as part of the render
pipeline but once we know what they are
the rest of it's pretty simple because
you can see here when we go to do the Z
bias program we already had to do a
bunch of this stuff anyway we have to
send down those constants and so that's
actually something we needed to do when
we specify these constants is anyone's
guess
looks like here so when we specify the
constants here you can see us grabbing
this stuff out of the prog like where we
asked that stuff before and so we need
to you know get this information from
somewhere right and it's going to have
to come down as part of the use program
begin I believe
like that so in order to make this work
this will have to actually get that
information from somewhere the alpha
threshold that's getting sent down I
don't know where that actually comes
from looks like it's oh it's just
determining whether it's peeling or not
right and so what we really want to do
here is say well the the actual drawing
primitive itself this render setup
probably is the thing that has to have
that because it's gonna have to be
specified by the game we don't know
where it wants the lighting applied we
have no idea so we kinda just have to
trust that it will tell us how big it
wants the lighting sampling to be at any
given time right so we're gonna have to
send down the voxel min corner and the
voxel in total Tim that's gonna have to
be like something that just gets told to
us by the game and the render setup in
here for voxel lookups it's just gonna
have to it's gonna have to set up what
those are right so we need to look and
see like where is the game setting up
this sort of stuff you know where is it
actually specifying this information you
can see in here when the game does this
like under set camera transform it puts
a bunch of this stuff in there what
we're gonna need to do is something that
actually like modifies that piece of
information I think to a certain extent
we're gonna have to like write that up
so in there where you see that push
setup call right you can see it doing
this nonsense here when we're doing that
push setup call you can see it writing
it to last set up right and I want to
say that you know yeah like probably we
just have to fatten this up
what you don't love I don't love how fat
this has become don't get me wrong and
we probably should fix it but at the
moment we're not going to because that's
not we're doing right now
some day alright so in here I just got
to set these I shouldn't have done one
it's not a it's not a floating-point
constant it's actually a vector constant
so that should be fine
this right here is just specifying one
of each of these um I guess why did I
pass that I don't know why I passed that
these are actually in the setup that was
just um that looks like that connector I
write 3 2 GL float right sorry about
that
there we go and then this use this
doesn't have to actually send that there
we go so I think that's all good no
worries I and so now I believe we have
the ability to specify this information
if I run the game again as it is
I really shouldn't see anything
different because they're still getting
set to 0 since even though we're
specifying them now nobody's actually
passing anything to that setup routine
so I think it's probably just gonna be
exactly the same as it was and there
really isn't gonna be anything special
going on there so I think that's all
just nonsense and doesn't matter but if
I actually go now specify that part
stuff as part of the camera transform
which is here I'm guessing that if I
start to pass something down for it's
not the not the debug camera but for the
regular camera here if I go to Pat well
I guess I probably want both obviously
but if I go ahead and specify what the
voxel dimension is at that point I
should be able to make this now start to
bound the region during that set camera
trance when we need to know where the
lighting voxel is that creates a little
bit of an issue right because that set
camera transform is sort of happening
before anyone is actually figured out
where the lighting bounds are and if you
look at the world camera rekt well the
world camera rect happens like here and
so we have kind of a nasty like
pre-computation problem where we're like
crap we're asking this thing that look
we need to set the voxels information
after we've already finished we rely on
the camera setting call to tell us where
the lighting should be in the first
place is the problem right and so we do
need that to be fixed and I'm not sure
exactly how to fix that but I guess that
means we will have to fix the thing I
was saying we don't want to fix it right
now if you're doing something else I
guess now we're doing that because this
is exactly the problem right what we
want to be able to do is right here when
we do begin letting computation we want
that to pretty much use the light bounds
to set up the render target right so we
want to do like set light bounds on the
current render setting and we pass those
two things down whatever the min was so
it would basically be like light bounds
oops light bounds min and then we would
take whatever this dimension was
and then we'd want to do like something
that inverts that so then we would do
something like that I don't know if
we've got that so that's what we would
like to do we'd like to be able to call
set light bands and have that just work
and then we would like that call that I
made there that was like the render
group called the set camera transform I
don't really want that right what I want
is something here that sets up the light
bounce separately so you'd pass in just
these two when you want to and that
would sort of like do it as a separate
part of the process so in here do we
ever actually push this on in here we
want to basically like change what the
setup is for people who are currently
using that setup you can see in here you
know people do that push setup call and
I guess I don't know exactly how they
get that information back out I haven't
really you know I don't recall how we
meant for that to work
but like you know here's the setup
that's actually being used in group last
setup right
I'm assuming that it's okay to just call
set light bounds at that point what
happens during get current quads does
the setup get recorded at that point yes
so I think it's really pretty easy now
that I think about it I guess all you
really do is this I think that's it so
now in theory we have the ability to set
the lighting bounds to something and now
we just have to debug that process it
looks like we got lucky that's exactly
what I wanted to see happen first with
the lighting and so you can kind of see
like somehow this went well for us and
you know yeah I mean that's that's rare
that's not how GPU partner usually works
so so that wouldn't wait better than I
expected if we're now gonna try and
verify that the lighting is
interpolating properly across all of our
various dimensions the other thing I do
is I take that west when we're
specifying that voxel in the end
lighting so end lighting computation
here if I was to go ahead and stripe all
three dimensions so so let's say we go
down here and we look at where is that
there it is if I was to sort of build
this up as a progressive value so this
is the light info and I say like okay
it's that you know
if I wanted to build it up incrementally
what I could do is say you know if xmod
to light info or equals something right
Y mod to Z mod - and then here we just
say like light info or something right
and so then when I can do say all right
let's stripe you know each of these will
say that the red stripe green stripe and
blue stripe corresponds to stripes in X
Y and C so we now should see like those
stripes intersecting each other and
providing like an actual different Z X&amp;Y
striping layer right and so if we
actually look now at what we get and we
can ask ourselves the question does this
actually make any sense what we're
seeing so if you look on here you can
see that effectively what it looks like
we have anyway if you can see like a red
stripe well actually what dude doesn't
look like it you can see I said I did
this backwards that's blue this is B GRA
sorry forgot where B GRA everywhere I'm
RGB a everywhere on my code base oh yeah
all right
so now it's a little more sensible
because it's what I said instead of what
I typed so you can see the red stripes
going in X you can see the green stripes
going in Y and the only question is can
we see any blue stripes right and so if
I look from the side here what you can
see is there are some blue stripes but
I'll be honest they don't really seem to
make good sense to me right like I don't
like the green and red stripes seem
pretty clear but if I look from the side
here and I look at the blue strip oh
well that there it looks right the blue
stripes do seem to be stacked which is
what I would expect they just don't seem
to look like it here but I guess that's
what I was gonna say interpreting it it
does kind of look like it now that I
look at it okay um so I think our
lighting is pretty good now in terms of
the lookups like that's looking up
correctly far as I can tell and the only
thing that's a little strange is the
region that is getting lit that's a
little bit strange to me and the reason
that it's a little bit strange is if I
just look at the region it looks to me
like the region is here which well maybe
that's correct
I don't know it's hard to say I would
like to maybe go a little further I'm
gonna go ahead and you know I want to do
I'm gonna go ahead and go into Elise
mode here
so here's me hopping along and you can
see that the lighting volume is kind of
moving through the space we're gonna
want to not have it do that by the way
we're gonna want to move it in any fixed
unit fixed voxel units so that we don't
see any popping but that's kind of a
separate issue anyway I'm gonna go down
here to someplace that has a little more
depth to it right so I can pull back and
just see what that actual region looks
like so yeah I mean it looks alright you
know so I think we're getting I think
we're in usable territory now right
where we can start we can work with this
right and so I think that's a great
place to end for today that's where we
want to be we're doing our voxel lookups
now and I don't know to what extent our
speed has been impacted that's a little
bit tougher to say what I might want to
do here is say alright let's let's see
what insight says for our speed so I'm
just gonna launch and it's like real
quick that looks fine and I'm gonna go
ahead and just launch the frame profile
over here see what it says
so if you look at the actual speed it's
reporting there it's 43 frames per
second
that's like significantly worse than we
had before right we were like way faster
than that previously and so I don't know
what to make of that but if you know I'm
I'm scared I'm a little bit scared of
what that entails if we really are
getting that slow I'm a frame rate
because I don't know what's causing it
necessarily we could look in fact let's
take a quick look
and so looking now at what we're seeing
here you can see this is this draw call
here is taking quite a bit at a time
there although you know honestly looking
at this I'm not sure I understand what
I'm actually seeing because I guess this
would imply that we're cpu-bound though
maybe because just just looking at it
doesn't look like it thinks we're taking
anywhere near what would be like 30
milliseconds no 28 milliseconds it's not
reporting anything close to that right
so this number is drastically higher and
so I don't know if that just means we're
totally cpu-bound at this point which
maybe we are and that's totally great
because if that's true you know
obviously we can try and fix that um let
me real quick just play with one thing
and see if that's true
so if we go in here and say you don't
need to do this anymore how bad is it
doesn't look like it really changed much
so I'm not really sure we're gonna have
to do some inspection we have to like re
enable our profiling as well and stuff
like that so we'll see but that'll be
your work for tomorrow I'm totally fine
with where we're at right now let me go
ahead and terminate here and we'll start
we can start to look at that later all
right let's go to a brief Q&amp;A anyone
have any questions on that
[Music]
silence
all right so I guess no questions sounds
like if there's no questions we can wrap
it up which seems good
all right there are does not appear to
be any questions so I think I will go
ahead and wrap it up oh no there was one
in the priests we're talking about
creating command buffers near through
crabs they probably would this be like a
buffer you were dynamically assemble
GPIO machine code into or is it
something that the driver would need to
translate for you to the GPU machine
code so my opinion on that is it should
be the answer is yes my opinion on that
is what should have happened with for
example Vulcan is rather than making it
all be ridiculous crap we have to call
the driver what should have happened was
they should have specified a specific
format for everything so every possible
command you can send down to the GPU is
SPECT as a data spec you then all of
your first wave drivers have a
translator in them that translate from
the software spec that was specified to
whatever the hardware actually ingests
right then the next round of GPUs are
all they all just make this silicon read
that directly and then that entire part
of the driver is gone for the rest of
time right that's what I think should
have happened
[Music]
it's an SPI RV the thing you're talking
about no SPI RV is not only not related
to command buffers it's for shaders not
command buffers but it also doesn't do
that SV RV is not designed to be
something that Hardware actually
interprets itself SPI RV is designed to
be input to a driver compiler that then
compiles output code machine code for
the chip it's not designed to be
something that a graphics chip would
ever actually execute directly you can
think of it in fact it's writing the
name uh SP IR V the IR is intermediate
representation it is not designed to be
an actual executable format it's
designed to be basically the first step
of the compiler which parses and turns
into an AB set track abstract syntax
tree then possibly salikus einman static
single assignment forms the data of the
code then before you actually generate
any machine code out of it that's what
SP IR V is so no hardware would ever
take SP IR V the only reason hardware
would ever take SP IR V is if you chose
to then actually have a small core in
your graphics card that was like sitting
around running a compiler what you could
do right it's not the world's worst idea
but you know that that's the only way
that a crash car would ever run that
natively it's not it's not machine code
it doesn't look like machine code
if you have a predictor unrelated
question how would a high light shader
work if you want to select a sprite
you'd want to color the edges of his
right in some color is this done via the
stencil buffer so I guess I don't know
how I would implement that I've never
actually implemented that specific thing
you're talking about in that way so my
first thought would be something along
the lines of inside the pixel shader
maybe I would just do a thing where I
sample from the so completely off the
top of my head and probably stupid yes I
would say what is the thickness of the
outline that I want I would sample from
the mipmap that is that thickness that
corresponds to back thickness so if it
was like 4 pixels wide
I would sample from the mipmap that was
2 steps down and I'd say what is the
alpha value and whatever the alpha value
is I would II I would
I would take it and if it was zero I
would discard but if it was nonzero I
would draw the outline that's a really
bad answer but that's the first thing I
thought of
I mean basically what my thought process
was is can we do a signed distance field
here and the problem of the signed
distance field is that you either have
one of you or you don't
and so with sprites that are actually
just stored regularly in the texture you
don't actually have a signed distance
field so you can't just say how far am i
away from the edge of the sprite it
doesn't tell you that information right
but you can approximate that information
by just fetching a sum of the area and
seeing how many how close you are to
actual pixels right and so I don't know
if what I just said would work but it
was the first thing I thought I've to
approximate a signed distance field
Brian asked what happened to profile
just for you the stream you mentioned
you want to re-enable it was it disabled
or not just tracking um the reason that
the profiler is not visible is because
we turn on lighting and so what happens
with lighting is everything is going
through that lighting so we don't
currently have a way to turn the
lighting off when we go to draw our
profiler so the probe is still there
it's just getting lit by black that's
all that's happening
[Music]
all right
no further questions
all right Thank You Bryan that we will
have fun game with John I'm sure all
right thank you everyone for joining me
for this on a handmade here it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow my series at
home you can always pre-order the game
on handmade hero org it comes with the
source code so you can play around with
it yourself we've got the basics of the
lighting system in now maybe today would
be a good day to play with it yourself
see if you can get some lighting working
before I get to it tomorrow everything's
set up for you to do it right so that
might be something to try that's about
it for today I will be back here
tomorrow to do that extra letting work
but eating the meantime you may want to
stay tuned to the handmade hero channel
because we're gonna be hooking up with
Jonathan Blow in a couple minutes here
to do some multiplayer gaming those of
you who joined us for our satisfactory
stream know that we are we are
definitely pro level gaming streamers
obviously don't let the fact that I
don't have a gigantic chair with a
headrest fool you obviously I'm still up
owning noobs with two zeros as they say
all the time and so we're gonna be
getting to that at about 2:30 I think so
about 20 minutes we'll be we'll be
making that happen so stick around for
that I'll shut down the stream and
restart it so you'll get an actual
notification when we go live mm-hmm but
we'll be doing that at 2:30 it'll be on
handmade hero channel and it should be
also on naysayer 88 channel we'll squat
up for that so you should be able to
switch between them cleanly and we'll
see you in a few minutes that's about it
I will catch you all in about 20 minutes
take it easy everybody