hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero the show recode a complete game
live on stream yesterday well that
yesterday sorry last stream it was
friday i believe we finished doing a
to-do item on our list i think we
actually started and finished it we just
wanted to turn off sorting for our debug
system i believe that was the last
element of that thing on the to-do list
so i think we're on to a different sort
of segment of stuff we did this disabled
sorting for debug Usos and slow so i
think today we are going to be on our z
finishing up our z stuff which we've
wanted to do for a long time but there's
just a lot of things that we kept having
to sort of push up against in order to
really make sure that would work and so
i think now we should be able to kind of
go over the final pass we've we've kind
of got most of it doing what it's
supposed to do and I think we're we even
sort of did the thing where we have
multiple like render targets for
different like floor levels and stuff
like that so I think we've really done
most of the stuff that we would need to
do for you nosy handling but now we just
need the final piece of it which is that
it's kind of a two-part projection and
we want to make sure that that's
actually working right and so we kind of
got to go just just work with that a
little bit and just get that into the
sort of a whit make that sort of a
little bit more stable so that we know
what's going on there and along with
that i think we probably want to just
kind of like do a one pass over the
renderer now and just kind of look
through it make sure like i kind of got
the screen world texture coordinate
stuff listed there can I go through it
and just make sure like okay can we
smooth any of this out there's just a
lot of junk in there at this point
because it's kind of like a crude a lot
of different things that we've tried to
do with it you know can we take a look
at some of that and maybe simplify it a
little bit more what about sort of the
performance of it it's got some things
in there right now that are kind of a
little bit questionable in terms of how
slow they would be and so on you know is
there any of that stuff
that we want to kind of work out and I
think that transitions nicely into
particle systems because really these
are sort of all I think kind of lumped
together because there's nothing
particularly special about particle
systems products or particle systems are
very very simple usually the complicated
part of particle systems is not writing
the particle system code which is pretty
random and hackish and not particularly
difficult its just oh I've got all these
little points that I'm moving around
that I'm doing simple physics on them
whatever it's usually the rendering part
that's complicated either because you
just are trying to maximize the the
speed the number of particles you can
get right and you know this this is
something that can take really extreme
forms like you know people nowadays will
do particle systems entirely on the GPU
for example to avoid round-tripping from
the cpu so that you cut down a bandwidth
sir etc right so there's there's a fair
number of things that are involved in
the particles stuff but it's almost all
on that sort of rendering side the
actual idea of like oh can I move some
particles around you know I kind of
covered that already on hand made here
and it's it's really not super
complicated it usually ends up being
kind of the that that second stage how
do i do enough of these how do I you
know maybe light them properly how do i
go out so that's really where more of
the the sort of finesse lies so in terms
of looking at the particle systems even
though we have a fairly simplistic
renderer on handmade here obviously we
would still have sort of some of those
same concerns right look we would want
to kind of look and go all right how do
we make sure that we can send enough
particles down every frame you know how
can we sort of make sure that we're not
we certainly don't want to dump all
those particles into the sorting system
for example as individual sprites
because that would really tank our
performance if we wanted to scale up the
number of particles to a larger number
so there's just kind of like stuff like
that that's you know I think going to be
worth thinking about and furthermore we
kind of have some other things we might
want to look at in terms of particle
systems for example may be may be
included in that or sort of some of the
continuum dynamic stuff like for example
if we wanted to have some low-lying fog
or something like this you know who
knows but something that was more of an
implicit surfacey sort of a thing
so they kind of have a number of things
like that and those would all be about
like how do we communicate those to the
render they're not really so much about
any kind of complicated implementation
on in terms of like the theoretical
aspect of it it's mostly all just all
right once we actually know what we're
trying to simulate what the code is here
how do we actually make sure that it's
not a performance problem how do we make
sure that it dovetails nicely with the
rest of the things we're rendering all
right so I'm going to go ahead and jump
right into looking at that Z stuff
because I'm pretty sure we don't have
any open issues at the moment that I am
interested in looking at I'm still
waiting for someone to tell me clang
compatibility wise if there are macros
we can use that would help with the plan
compatibility because I think that it's
only our macros that are causing clang
to have grumpiness about them so until
then that was kind of on the on the back
burner and these two are not really in
fact what I don't know what this means
this is a I guess we could say
enhancement so I guess I'll say that
these are enhancements let's say right
did that do ya and then this one is is
what is this i don't know this is this
is um compat maybe can I I can't uh uh
what but but but no but I want to apply
a label well that's not very good are we
basically saying that I can't create my
own labels all right well I don't know
doesn't matter anyway point being so
these are enhancements and so those are
not really bugs that we have at the
moment that we want to look into but
this guy is and I'm just waiting for
someone with playing to sort of give us
that and then we can close out that guy
but I think we're otherwise pretty much
good to go here and also i would mention
if you if in general if people would
please like not report non bugs to the
bug thing like i get a lot of people who
like report stuff that
are just like they don't like the way
something was coated but that's not
really a bug right so but you can do
those if you want to but I'm just going
to close them immediately is like this
is not a bug so this is really supposed
to only be for stuff that we actually
care about that's an actual bug meaning
that it causes a bad behavior in the
program not you didn't like how i casted
that pointer or something because that
is not a bug that's a preference that
make sense alright so if we go to our
render stuff here and take a look at it
you can kind of see our particularly
unusual projection stuff here it's not
really what you might normally think of
as projection code it's a little bit odd
right and that's fine because you know
we are a 2-d game and we have some kind
of weird ways in which we project stuff
but if you'll notice we have sort of
already even just at the start because
we had said how we wanted Z to work we
did not want there to be any sort of
like dilation x and y dilation as a
result of Z within one floor level you
can see that we still even though we did
all the work of like doing this whole
like this thing with the fade in right
like that thing we still sort of have
this problem that we like we don't have
those stairs lined up the way they're
supposed to be right they are still
going through a transform that makes
them blow out you know it makes them
sort of scale and do what they're not
supposed to do and this is a problem for
multiple reasons one its not how the
game is supposed to look so that's a
problem we have to go fix that so that
they don't have that happen but to it
also breaks our sorting because our sort
was designed to be kind of a fairly
minimal like we didn't do a very
complicated sort criteria so our sort
criteria isn't really even set up to
handle stuff that's kew like that we
just did a very simple YZ kind of thing
and so you can see that you gets the
sort wrong as well so it creates like
problems for everybody really
it makes it's just not a good thing so
if we want to fix this we need to start
you know we may have to improve the sort
criteria as well that's a separate thing
obviously because we can always go make
our sort criteria better than it
currently is but at the moment we kind
of have this problem where okay so those
stairs need to stop doing that right
they need to stop having that scale
applied to them and so in order to do
that you know we could make all of that
scale and go away if we wanted to
because if you take a look at how that's
that's working here you can kind of see
that the way that we do our distance
killing here is we have like our
distance 2pz and you can see us doing
our projection here where we take one
over just to be Z and we multiply it by
sort of the the standard camera
transform that we talked about way way
back when and that projected XY is what
you know this distance to PZ part of
that projected XY equation is going to
give us that sort of XY dilation and
that is not actually what we want to
have happen right now we could turn it
off entirely if we wanted to right we
could certainly say that instead of
distance to PZ actually including the Z
coordinate that we're dealing with we
could turn it off entirely by saying hey
distance to PZ is just going to be equal
to whatever distance above target is
right and that's all it is and if you
look at what happens there then we do
have sort of what we wanted which is
everything flattened down but we don't
get the y part of things so we kind of
have like these mysterious things in
here which are sort of you know they're
they're kind of totally rendered wrong
because they don't actually sort of go
up the way they're supposed to but at
least they don't do sort of that blowing
out right so what we could do is say
well we know we don't ever want the X to
blow out there you know II on a single
floor so if we wanted to we could say
well alright
so you know we don't want that but when
we go ahead and get this projected XY
when we come through here and we do this
equation instead of having the projected
XYZ X persist we could overwrite the
projected ex-wives X with the original X
right or similarly with some sort of a
distance 2pz here that was fixed right
so we could do something like this of
course I have to actually just get the X
part of it like so and you can now see
that we're sort of starting to get a
little bit better though well you know
what when I said x I meant why I just
said we wanted the X to be the same oh
wait no but that's what I did want
nevermind that's what I did one take it
back ok so anyway you can see what's
going on here right now the x coordinate
is aligned properly right the X these
things are seeing the same place in X
and you can kind of see that as I kind
of pop up these guys it's all good right
I can sort of get in there and you know
it looks like what it should look like
however you can see that the right side
of it is wrong and the reason that the
right side of it is wrong is because
although we are now keeping the
exposition proper we are not we are when
we return the scale value we're
returning a single scale value for x and
y and that scale value is going to make
the thing change size right so although
it's like aligned on the left side
properly it gets too big now since we
don't really want to do any prospective
scaling really all we should have to do
here is instead of using the meters two
pixels times the projected XYZ what we
can do here is just make this be a fixed
factor as well right well of course
fixed factor is probably we needed to
actually be a fixed factor you know what
I can do let me do it this way
so let's compute two of these let's
compute first something that's more like
unscaled XY right something like that so
here we we do the unscaled version right
and so then what I can do is stay
protected XY x equals unscaled X Y dot X
so now we are not doing any perspective
transform on the x value and then the
scale I do the same thing instead of
using the projected XY i'll use the
unscaled XY and then in theory we should
be a little bit better I missed
something here there we go okay so now
we have like a nun scaled one in a
scaled one and now you can see that
we've got something that's a little bit
better it's it's still there's still a
couple things about it that we that
probably would want to fix but you can
kind of see that now we have things that
are the right size but if they are
higher they actually got sort of higher
and why okay so that's good and we're
sort of we're getting better but we
still have a problem which is that when
I hop up these guys you can see what
happens is we get a very unsatisfying
result there on what happens to the the
level above us and the reason for that
is because that level above us we do
actually want to have that do all of the
XY and the scaling and all that sort of
stuff right and so there you can sort of
finally see where we have this sort of
nasty problem that that we've got which
is that we want it to work this way
inside a layer but then when we get up
you know each individual layer that we
get up we then want to do the scaling as
well as we sort of come up to to that
layer right so the layer itself should
be scaled differently so that's kind of
tricky right and the reason that that's
kind of tricky is because we don't
really know exactly we don't have a good
sort of concept when we get into this
part of the renderer we don't really
have a good concept of what that
what those slices in NZ will will mean
right we don't really know what those
are now we could enforce them to be
something in particular meaning we could
just say that we're going to use some
arbitrary set of Z values here and do it
that way but that's not a particularly
satisfying potentially way to go about
this right so you know we're sort of
left with this this ugly problem of do
we have to do something a little bit
more explicit when we're actually
passing these things down do we need to
send a slice index and that slice index
will give us some degree of will go into
the scaling in one way it'll be the
thing that allows sort of the actual
scaling to occur and then you know we've
got in addition to that we also have the
sort of nominal Z which is really just
creating a y displacement for our you
know orthographic look right uh and so
it's yet it's there's probably a reason
why very few games if any games have
ever done something like this because
you know it's just kind of finicky but
it's not you know it shouldn't be
unachievable to want to do a slicing
thing like that we just have to come up
with a relatively easy way of passing it
down now we do have some stuff at our
disposal here right we do have the
object transform and the object
transform itself obviously is passing a
bunch of stuff here and you can kind of
see that inside the audit transform we
do have like a chunk Z thing that's
getting passed here and that chunk Z is
the piece of information that we kind of
want for that additional scaling right
that chunk Z I would tell us exactly
that piece of information it would tell
us how far this thing is in terms of
slices and all we would really need to
know is how that chunk Z lines up with
the Z of that we're looking at right and
so if that chunk Z were in terms of like
negative
positive and so and so on that might be
useful now i'm not sure where that's
being said it's been a while so i kind
of want to see what's going on in terms
of this piece of information I think
yeah so it kind of looks to me like this
is mostly just being used because that
stuff isn't used anymore this was mostly
being used just for the sorting right
you can see that that's going into the
sprite bound there and and it's just
being set to whichever layer we're on
and you know that's that's great the
problem with it is it's a it's just an
integer offset so it doesn't really tell
us all that much about how you know it
gives us a rough idea draw this out for
you so you don't have to guess what I'm
saying oh I tire uh-oh I think Milton is
is not happy
ok
so there's a lot of ways you could do it
we could use that chunk see however I
what I'm thinking in my head is we want
a continuous transfer mob viously and
the thing that we're looking for here
right is we're kind of looking for some
way of having if these are sort of our
levels right and maybe this is where the
hero is he's kind of on this level right
and no baby there's the glove there and
it's not a very good handmade hero maybe
it looks like this much better much
better uh so if this is the the floor of
the hero standing on and this is like
you know one up from and this is one
down or whatever then when we're talking
about a Z essentially what we want to
know is we want to know first of all
what is its displacement off of its
floor right so we're looking for this
piece of information because this piece
of information right here in fact we can
sort of you can sort of talk about this
type of thing this right here that is
sort of an H that's like the height off
the ground let's say H is the
orthographic portion right that's just
going to displace us in Y and no matter
how far you go up or down if you're only
within that floor we're just just
placing you and why that's what we want
to do so then the other thing we want to
know is what is its floors displacement
from the camera right so you know if the
camera is looking right here let's say
at the time then in addition to this H
value we also want to know this other
value which is effectively let's say our
Z value right and the Z value is the
perspective part because however far
that floor is off of the camera that's
how much the whole thing is going to get
you know XY transformed and scaled and
all that stuff right so what we want to
be able to know is where is the camera
relative to the floor
of this thing whatever that is and go
back to our here here it is so we want
to know that so that we can do our
projected XY portion of things based on
that piece of information and then we
also want to know what the just what the
H value is because the H value would
also provide that sort of why dilation
which we could even do explicitly we
really don't need to do the distance
above target focal length thing here and
in fact I think we don't want to because
we want that displacement to be constant
no matter what's going on so I think we
would just want to apply it prior to the
projected so just do the constant first
in here and then apply the projection to
it so that it will scale properly along
with everything else if that makes sense
so really I think all we need to do is
perhaps know what the floor know where
the camera is and then know where the
floor height is for any individual
object that we set so that render
transform kind of just wants to know the
floor for this guy what his floor value
is right or we could call that a z-value
what'swhat's floor value is and then
also that H value which is going to be
different now we can still pass down
absolute xiv al use right so what we can
do is we can pass down an absolute xiv
al you just fine for somebody because if
we're also passing down what the floor
value is we know that the relative h
value the H value would just be whatever
that absolute Z whatever that absolute Z
is we would just subtract the Z of the
floor away from it and that would give
us the H value that we need right so we
can still essentially do almost exactly
the same interface to the render render
that we have been doing aight i said
Randor right rander err it's not a
random renderer that's kind of like when
people say dranks right like you know
when microsoft sent out that recruiting
recruiting letter and said that they
would be supplying i think
use the phrase hella drinks or maybe no
you know what i think they said i think
they said just lots of drinks or
something like that yeah microsoft is
just a party animal they're just party
animals you don't understand they've got
all these dranks you know I'm saying
they just have all these drinks at
Microsoft anyway so uh if you don't know
what I'm talking I'm sure someone on the
chat can post a link to that ridiculous
thing I posted on Twitter it was it was
ridiculous it was crazy anyway um so we
should be able to get that value pretty
easily and so all we should have to do
here is when we set the chunk Z we could
also just set what is the actual Z value
of the floor at that time and then I
think we would have all of the
information that we actually needed for
this process to work properly right
because if you look at how this this
transfer works if i get rid of the
unscaled XY part of this because i was
just sort of doing that for explanation
purposes i don't actually need any of
this stuff too to do what it's doing if
you imagine that i just reset this back
to how it was before right so this was i
believe the way that we'd had it
previously up sorry I didn't mean to
leave that sort of chunk z-test in there
if we take a look at what this was doing
before right we're back to the old way
all I really need to do is say well okay
let's let's do exactly that same thing
keep everything the way that it was
going don't do anything different it's
just now instead of using this P Z value
I'm just going to say well I need some
new stuff here right I need a Z for the
floor right I need whatever that value
is and then I need like a like a height
or something height off floor right
something like this I could also say
floor Z maybe that's a better way to say
that right so don't know exactly where
I'm going to get those yet but I do know
like I said before if I want to this p
value that comes in this P Z value that
I get after I've done sort of my
beginning transform stuff there when i
get that I
easily subtract the floors e to get the
hide off floor part that I wanted and so
really it's just the floor Z that's the
thing that I need everything else would
work fine and then I'm also saying okay
I'm not going to use any of this P Z
value here I'm just going to use the
floor Z and the floor is e alone to
determine how I'm going to do my
perspective transform all the rest of
this stuff will work the same the only
thing that I now need to do is say that
whatever my raw XY is right this Rolex
why here uh whatever that raw XY is and
also by the way I don't really know why
this isn't in there no idea furthermore
I suppose this doesn't need to be in
there all this stuff is kind of let's
try to clean this up so it's clear
what's happening where I don't know what
offset Z is I don't know why that's
still there in fact why is that term
even still there so that was some old
term for off offset see I don't do not
know probably some old code when we were
doing things that we don't need to do
any more anyway uh so yeah point being
we've got that floor Z and now we need
to just find a way to get the floor Z
everything else should work fine the
only thing that we need to do now is
when we compute our raw XY we just want
to take whatever the Y value is and add
to it some displacement based on the
height off the floor and again this is a
purely arbitrary personal artistic
decision here about how much of an
orthographic displacement we want for
each you know bit of Z that you're off
okay and so I don't know what that value
is going to be we're going to want to
tune that value right we're basically
going to have a value here which is like
why you know what ortho why from Z kind
of a thing and we don't know what that's
going to be but we can just tweak it
however we want to tweak it so if we
compile this we should have no problems
other than just we need a place to get
the floor Z and right now we don't know
where to get the floor Z right I have no
idea where to get that floors Ephraim so
when i do the object transform bit i
could just add it in there for now so i
could just say well we're going to need
a floor z here if you don't specify a
floor z then
we can always just make the floor zv 0
which would do no transforming at all
now what's interesting about that is
that would also potentially let us get
rid of some other aspects here but we
could probably make the orthographic
stuff a little bit simpler if we wanted
to I'm not I'm going to ignore that for
now point being if we just add something
to the object transform that says what
the floor Z should be then in theory I
should be able to do something where I
take the object transform grab the floor
as you out of it and although we're not
setting it yet we should presumably be
able to set that pretty easily because
it's not a particularly complicated
thing so if I take a look at where we
actually set these in terms of upright I
think it's here you can see default
upright transform a default flat
transform they don't set the floor Z at
all so it would just be set to zero so
if I actually do this now in theory I
think we would get pretty much exactly
what we had before you can see that
that's happening where we have that
ortho displacement and that's all good
but we don't have we still don't have
any scaling right because the floor Z
has just not been set by anybody so
let's go ahead and try to set that floor
z2 something meaningful now right and
all we need to do to do that is we just
need some Z value for the floor which we
should know when we're actually putting
these guys out because we had to do
stuff like break them up into layers to
begin with so if you take a look at
what's going on here you can see uh
we're starting to compute that outside
this is back in the M in where we're
outputting entities right
so we're we're out putting entities is
where this actually counts will probably
have to clean up some of the other code
where these transforms are being set
because they might might need to set a
floor Z as well like for example when
we're showing debug rectangles and stuff
like that those are going to have to
have their floor as you set properly as
well but for the time being we only
really care about the entities because
that's what pretty much all of our
drawing goes through so if we take a
look here what happens we have this
object transform that's our entity
transform we're generating one of these
default upright transforms for it and I
you know that that's interesting do we
do we ever do a default flat transform
wait a minute when we draw are we
drawing all of our things is upright
that's just a total bug right we're
supposed to be drawing the floors is
flat hey maybe don't send down one
hundred percent of the entities as flat
that would totally break our sorting i'm
not sure why our sorting is even working
half as good as it is right now i guess
would give ourselves a pat on the back
for having a sorter that's way better
than it should be maybe I'm overreacting
maybe that's not what's going on there
but point being that's a screw-up but
that has nothing to do with what we're
talking about right now so that's fine
anyway point being you can see us going
ahead here and setting this offset p to
being this is the the distance of off
the camera so that's going to be the
absolute z displacement so now the
question is where is the actual floor
that this dude would have been on right
and so you can see here where we've got
entity z layer and we've got this sort
of chunk Z situation going on here which
is saying like okay where is this guy in
terms of floors so we know what the
relative layer is here we just don't
necessarily know what the actual Z value
is for that layer but we know that that
is something that we had computed before
and the reason that we know that that is
something that competed before because
you can kind of see in this this thing
right here where we were doing like our
fogging and all that sort of stuff we
already had to compute that right we had
to compute the camera relative Ramsey
because this is it right here right this
is that value so that's the value that
we actually need to set for the sky
unfortunately we're not saving it
anywhere right so we kind of need to
have a thing here which is like camera
relative Brown Z and we kind of need to
store that for everybody and so that
camera relative Brown Z will keep the
value that we actually wanted so there's
camera low to ground Z and we just need
to be able to set when we set the fog
amount we just also need to be able to
set what this is so that we can remember
it now and now we know where the camera
relative ground Z is and the camera
elliptic ground Z is the thing that we
have to look up here what we should be
able to do is just verify that this
thing is actually inside the layers that
we want we've already done that so that
seems fine here so all we should have to
do is in the entity transform when we
get down to this point and we verified
that we should be able to set the floor
Z here to the cam relative ground Z
value for our relative layer so looking
up into there where is our fog I'm out
there it is so our layer index it should
have been computed somewhere I don't
actually know where it is there it is so
just do that here and I think that
should be fine ok so I think this should
set the floor height I mean the floor Z
properly now so when we come up here we
should see that that scaling happen
right and you can see that scaling
happen which is nice so you can see it
it seems to be working fairly correctly
there when we kind of pop up here that's
all good of course those guys are
blocking me I don't know why they're
blocking me that's not very nice of them
but now we do
have the ability to sort of scale those
two things up properly now obviously we
sort of have a problem just with the way
our levels are structured there's
nothing we're ever going to be able to
do to make it render properly here
because we sort of have these solid
stairs coming up here when I hop up here
if I have another stairwell on top of me
I'm not even going to be able to see
myself that's just kind of the way that
would actually happen in real life so we
kind of have to work around that in
terms of the earth there's nothing the
renderer isn't doing anything
particularly stupid at that point that's
just how that's going to be you know and
we could do other things like maybe
alpha those that if we wanted to or
something like that but in general right
we'd probably just don't want to
structure our levels that way we
probably don't want to have to
stairwells on top of each other like put
the other stairwell on the other side of
the screen so that there's a bigger hole
there and we can actually see up through
it or something like that but I believe
that's really all we had to do to get
our Z working properly there and now we
just have to deal with the artistic
concerns of it and off you go now that's
pretty much that entire to do as far as
the Z part of things is concerned but we
do have another sort of separate problem
here which is that I feel like and I
could be wrong but I feel like as I just
added this right here i am and i'm not
flat sorry this is upright I'm a little
bit concerned that we never actually
have any sprites that aren't being
marked as upright because we do default
upright transform here right but then I
don't know that we ever set it to
anything other than an upright transform
which makes me concerned that all that
stuff we did to handle both kinds of
sorting we're never actually taking any
advantage of it which means our sorts
are all going to be kind of busted all
the time no matter what we do I think
again maybe I'm misunderstanding
something because you know hey I have a
day job and I forget a lot of things
about handmade hero while I'm actually
working out of their code for eight
hours a day but
uh that just kind of seems like what's
going on you know and so I feel like
these pieces here when we're sort of
doing these this stuff when we come
through and do these these pushes I feel
like these pushes that we're doing
needed to be marked as flat right and
because these like for example these
right here these entity transforms these
should all have been marked is flat ok
so we are ok we're fine because these
are these are all below it and we're
only doing those for traversable so all
right whoo ok so that's fine that's
gonna say what's going on here I was I
thought I thought I was thought I was
losing my mind man thought I was losing
my mind ok so we're actually fine I
think unless because I feel like those
are the those are the things that we're
actually rendering right because here is
the the occupier tag that turns them the
colors based on whether you're hopping
on them right so it's all good okay I
got nervous there for a second I was
like what's going on but ok so those
those are rendered outside so it's all
good everyone can relax and by everyone
I mean me right all right so that seems
that seems pretty reasonable and I don't
think well we have to really worry about
that now we'll we'll put when you put
the new art in we'll see what happens
we'll try to construct some rooms that
have some multi-layer stuff on them but
I think we're now probably pretty good
in terms of like slight staggering and
you know what I could do is I could also
just turn if I could I could sort of
play with that value a little bit here
let me go ahead and scoot up to the part
where we actually create rooms and I
think we have a thing in here where we
kind of did a random sort of like a sort
of random variants of the height and you
can kind of see here in fact but where
we were doing this in terms of
staggering things
x and y i'm going to enable like a
little bit of a stagger in z instead and
just to see what happens there just a
little tiny bit of of that and I I don't
really remember what our convention is
about where the floor is exactly but
yeah so that's you can kind of see what
that looks like it's pretty
straightforward and now we can kind of
hop along some some sort of uneven
terrain just make sure that that is
working properly and that that looks
fine that looks like what I would have
expected so that's all good I can hop up
here here's another level of that and
and off we go so that seems correct and
it also seems like we do have a little
bit of leeway there so we can displace
downward and it doesn't get floored to
the one below us so I guess there's a
little bit of a gutter in there and so
that should be fine now we do have one
thing that we might want to consider
fixing a little bit i think i'll
probably let that weight though until
the part where i actually care but i
think you can see that like the snapping
that happens there what happens is when
we transition from one layer to another
we might want a kind of a zone where we
apply where we blend between the two Z's
that we would use and so you know try
and explain what I mean here and and I
think maybe by I met tone this down
quite a bit I think maybe the right way
to do it is to sort of construct a room
where you can see this happening a
little bit better so what I want to do
here is I'm going to try and construct a
room that I guess the first thing I'll
do is I'll just turn off the room that's
one above us so we can see a little bit
more easily let's go down two hand made
that sleepy the coop and they just poppy
actually know this would be world and
open it so add standard room
there we go so instead of creating
forest serene stacked on top of each
other i'm just going to create one and
then when i only have one if i come down
here and hop up words right like this
you can kind of see that when i get to
the top well I guess I I don't have
anywhere to go right okay that's not
going to do it kinda i got at least add
2 i'll add to and when i add a standard
room i guess i'll say something about is
there a stairwell so i'll only add the
stairwell by like checking the screen
index parity there i'll just see only a
stairwell on the first room and i will
add it on the second round right so
let's see so what I want to do here is
say okay that's stairwell there I think
let's see know what the difference
between these two things are to be
honest with you the just me or do those
look exactly the same is there any
difference between those two things I
have no idea why we have two paths here
people I think we were doing something
here before then we got rid of it anyway
so I believe this is the part right
that's it creates a stairwell so I'm
going to say if add stairs will do this
otherwise that we're just not going to
do it
so now in theory I should have a room
above us and that room should not have
anything there yeah although actually I
guess that's right I also have to make
sure that we don't do it so yeah we
would have to not put anything there as
well so I guess I want to do if we don't
add stairs then I want to do like a skip
false or maybe a dick is true that it is
false yeah i mean i should just define
to be 32 x in fact why don't i have a be
through 22 x does anyone know why we
don't have one
okay alright so now in theory there's a
hole there right yeah there's the hole
there and so I'm going to make an even
bigger hole so you can see it a little
more clearly what I'm talking about in
terms of the problem and then we can
sort of talk about what we want to do to
solve it I think I don't have very much
time left anyway so we might leave it
for tomorrow I just want to put it in I
want to put in the stuff so that we can
see very clearly what the problem is
that I was kind of talking about okay uh
so yeah what I want to do here I think
is say if offset equals three or you
know we're not adding stairs and offset
x equals 4 so we kind of have a bigger
oops so we kind of have a region to look
into and I think it might I might
actually want to be one over the other
direction I think about it in terms of
what would be easier to see because
that's a not quite what I was hoping for
let's say equals two and maybe we'll
also say here and the offsets rather
than equals negative 2 i'm going to say
the same thing here with offset or add
stairs and offset less than or equal to
3 let's see if that how that treats me
and let's see so I hop up the stairs and
there you can kind of see we've got a
nice big jump leeway so do you see how
when I when I cross that boundary and my
my dude hops down right I've it's hard
to kind of get him to hop down because
it's a sort of a big way but when I make
that jump the
the transform is discontinuous so I just
I just pop right and like I pop scaling
immediately right which is not probably
what we want so and even though this is
like an exaggerated case it's just it's
just going to be bad right you can say
once the once the art is kind of cleaned
up in there you know you're going to
really see that pop but it's not going
to be fun so the question is you know
what can we do about that particular
situation and I think what we probably
want to do there is maybe just make that
scaling be like a little bit cleaner
just give it a little bit more room and
that's not particularly hard to do right
we can if we want to just say well okay
so you can see what we're doing in terms
of the floor Z here here it is what we
could do is say well if we know what the
floor height in general is then it
shouldn't be particularly difficult for
us to just take a little bit of that
range I think I talked about this before
but to just take a little bit of that
range and do sort of into some
interpolation there so for example if
here is the way that we've been doing it
where it's like okay you know here's the
the location of the dude and so we have
sort of our our floor Z is here right
and this is our height and this would be
the next floor up what we can do instead
is introduced a zone in which we
transition between the two and do a
smoother scaling of that of the entities
in that band right and so how we would
do that is just say well you know if the
H is within these it was within this
bound whatever that is then we don't
care but if the H is above that bound
then we use it's a we map this range 20
21 essentially and we lurk between the
floor Z and the next floor Z up from
what it is before we do the transform
right so essentially when we do our
transform here when we take our floor Z
that we're going to use for the actual
projection right what we want to do
there is just linear interpolate this
right so we want to kind of say lurk
between the floor Z and you know floor
height that kind of thing so basically
we would have two things we'd go between
the floor Z and the next floor Z up and
what we would want to do is base that on
where the PZ was relative to the floor Z
which means we do actually then want to
compute this a priority right so we do
want to be able to say okay let's figure
that out and right when we do that
computation will then we'll know however
we kind of do need to know I suppose
since we're looping it we want to do
this subtraction afterwards at with the
real floor Z so that that's continuous
as well so really we want this to be
some other thing which is like you know
our test Z where we compute what the
floor Z is relative to the the point the
Z point right so we kind of know like
okay here's here's where we are and now
we just have to see whether that thing
is roughly in the range of this of this
floor height here right and we've got to
see what that is so we need some kind of
an apron there and we just want to know
I suppose you know is you know clamp I
guess really all we want to do is say
clamp 001 map to range right I I think
that's our sort of all-purpose function
for this
right so this allows us to do a min a
max and a tee so what I think we can do
here is is say that you know our T value
our floor key value in this case in fact
I guess I don't need to show the test Z
there I could just say that you know
this is the value that we have we know
that we want to to lurk it in a sense I
guess we could say next borzi this is
that next floor up right and so what we
want to do is say well okay we know the
high end of the range that's the next
floor Z but we don't want to use the
actual floor Z as the base of the range
because the whole point of this is just
to use like a narrow band so essentially
we just be using like the next floor Z
minus the like the apron value right
whatever that apron value is and we can
make that beef parametric potentially if
you want to in the future for now let's
just say we set it to like Oh point one
or something like that right and then
all we really need to do I don't know
what I call this function tonight did I
just call it work yeah and so when I do
this object transform now I just need
one other thing which is the floor
height now I could do floors II and the
next floor see I suppose I could do it
that way since those are the two things
we actually want maybe I since we don't
actually ever use the floor height
natively maybe we just do that because
then it's a little bit more direct I
suppose right
that definite looks better all right so
let's call it that we compile now that
value is not getting set which is not
going to be good so we need to kind of
go into our entity output again and
actually make sure that we do specify
what these actually are now this is a
pretty easy thing to specify all we have
to do is take whatever the floor is he
was before and just add to it whatever
the height of the floor actually is and
the height of the floor should be just
in here because we're sort of doing that
computation the typical floor height
thing and so the renderer would actually
be supporting you know non-uniform floor
heights we're not really specify we're
not supporting that here in the entity
output but maybe that something will
change later so I don't want to like
force the renderer to have to do that
for no reason all right so now when I
kind of come up here I don't know if
that's what whoa that did not well I
suppose that is sort of LARPing there
but that is not really giving me a very
satisfying results let me see about
increasing that apron just so I can see
I want to see about this here I want to
see that happen a little slower okay I
wish these familiars would would go away
they're real annoying okay
so yeah that is not great not a fan of
that I'm not sure exactly what to make
of it because I don't know any other
real way we would be able to deal with
that we could obviously turn off the
scaling entirely and just leave it so
that it doesn't do that so it doesn't
ever do the sort of sizing stuff the
sizing stuff looks pretty cool but I
don't know that that looks unconvincing
maybe there's something fancier we can
do there maybe there isn't but yeah I
mean it might be that the widest
placement is really the only thing that
we're going to be able to do i'm not
sure if we wanted to do that you know we
could take all of this stuff obviously
that's happening here and just say okay
the floor z we never actually used right
and that would look like this and then
we just sort of have this we're back to
the same situation of you know that all
works it's just a lot more boring it
doesn't have that nice feel that the
perspective version does you know it's
still like fades out and everything but
it's just it just doesn't have that same
kind of feel to it so I don't know what
to do about that
I don't know I mean we're going to have
to keep that apron pretty narrow if we
don't want a bunch of objects sliding
around all the time on it you know and
oops but yeah I just I just don't know
how we would how we would keep that from
getting out of hand let me think is
there any other thing I could do besides
the looping yeah I don't know because it
is a fundamentally kind of nasty problem
I mean you got this thing that's well
I guess maybe you could say that if you
were to keep their if you were to keep
some range in which the scaling didn't
occur maybe that would help I don't know
I make sure I'm doing this right first
of all so assuming that you're close to
the top of the range between the floors
yeah you're just yeah just looking at
the apron then you learn the two floors
ease in terms of what your transform is
that's probably pretty good i mean i
don't know that there's much else i
would do to that ah yeah so I don't know
about that I don't know and here's the
version that that looks I think it looks
like what we want oops because I was
feeling pretty good about this it's just
it's got that popping artifact right
because otherwise it's what I wanted
right that looks exactly like what I
wanted the problem is like I just don't
know how to deal with the popping part
in terms of the transform you know and
maybe there'd be a solution just for the
hero because the hero is always kind of
the where the camera is but you know I'm
thinking about other entities as well
and they they would kind of have this
these problems I think where you know as
you kind of saw them go up and down I'm
going to get rid of that jitter on the
floor as well for the moment while we're
looking at things is kind of distracting
and so I'm going to go ahead and just
take that out of the equation as well
but yeah so I don't know I guess we'll
just we'll leave this till tomorrow
we'll talk about it some more but I'm
worried about that I don't know of an
immediate solution because yeah that
looks like what I want every in all
other respects
but I just don't know how to solve that
popping problem of moving between
because now you essentially got two
spaces in terms of the transform I don't
know how to really get really know how
to get away from that you know I don't
know what I could do to make that not
cause us problems so yeah that's that's
not that's not great maybe we'll think
of something though you know maybe we'll
think of something you want to give up
right away I'm going to go ahead and go
to the queue and the a since it is Q&amp;A
time
you
it's like gonna be an easy night no
questions asked me no more questions
I'll tell you no more lies not know the
rest of that song but I know it's like a
nursery rhyme sort of thing cyberpunk
hobo are there any particular reasons
not to refer continuous scaling and z
besides easy sorting uh yeah I'm like I
just don't feel like the art looks good
with that kind of scaling because so
it's it's not obvious to see because we
haven't tried to drop in the real art
yet but essentially you got this problem
of you know here is what a room looks
like let's say right so that's the top
wall and then here is the ground or
whatever something like that right and
the problem with it is if you do that
scaling then you now you need to have
some way of doing artwork for like these
sides and stuff like that and suddenly
you pretty much have to just do 3d at
that point right whereas if you're
orthographic you know no matter where
something is it still just looks like
this so you can just have one sprite for
that and once right for the top and be
done right because it doesn't matter
where on the screen it is it always is
the same artwork right and so basically
to avoid going to full 3d modeling for
the scenes you pretty much don't ever
want there to be any prospective
transform on the actual stuff on the
actual scenery now you could prospective
transform the people somehow but they
have to line up with the scenery and so
you can't really transform them
completely willy-nilly right you still
have to have some conceptualization of
what's going to happen
and so I don't really know uh how to
make that kind of trade-off right again
I'm not really a 2-d game programmer and
more of a 3d game programmer so it's
kind of not it's not my area of
expertise like how to do like whatever
the hacks are that you might want to do
to make this sort of thing work more
logistical II it's kind of a you know
I'm sure it's a black art right like
it's like hey if you've done some to 2d
games you probably have a lot of tricks
up your sleeve for like well this is how
I do covering this part of it or
whatever uh so you know that's that's
really all that is so I don't really
have anything against the perspective
scaling it's more just that like artwork
wise in 2d it doesn't really super work
and you know you can you can do other
things you could make little blocks and
texture them you know you could sort of
make it pseudo-3d there and then you'd
be fine or you can do a number of things
like that but I don't really want to go
down those those roads I want handmade
hero to just be using straight fit map
part that's kind of you know one of the
limitations that I was sort of saying it
should have and so at that point I don't
know that there's really that much you
can do so yeah so it's yeah it's an
issue I'm not sure what to do about that
issue
so it's the kid asked I may have missed
it but what's the reasoning for type
definite be through 2x as a be through
two and not just use be through to its
the same reason I tend to have like s 32
x and u 3 2 X it's like if I don't care
what size the thing is i'll use the X so
that like you know if for some reason
there was a platform where it's more
efficient to use 64 bits to store the
boolean because like operating on 32-bit
registers it has a cost because it's
like 64-bit native and doesn't like to
downshift or something then it can that
used to be a lot more relevant sort of a
force of habit it's not super relevant
now like I don't know that the x64
architecture cares at all whether you
operate on a 64 or 32 16 or an eight I
don't know I don't know about arm but
generally speaking they're definitely
have bent like I feel like there were
definitely times in the past where there
have been architecture revisions where
you end up in a situation where if you
force the processor to downshift it gets
unhappy right so if you force the
processor to do an operation of some
kind on a 16-bit value instead of a
32-bit value and it's 32 bit native it
gets upset and it goes slower right so I
don't actually know that we need to do
this for a particular reason but my
habit tends to be to type accident of
things and so really most of all that
that typedef was is to make it so that I
don't have to think about it anymore i
can just type the X if I want it and not
if I don't so that's that's really all
it is and it's the same for all the
types that's just what the X means in
general the X is just I'm telling you
that I'm using 32-bit computing here but
I don't care if you go up to 64 bit on
me it wouldn't bother me right and
technically in a lot of those places I
could probably have called it a be 8x
and so in a fair number of them but you
know really I think part of the problem
is just C is not particularly great at
expressing things in size invariant ways
like a lot of equations you want to just
specify and say you know look however
many bits you needed this to be four
this to work out is how many bits the
things should be or what you know it
doesn't have a lot of that unfortunately
let's see the size 'ok thought have the
floor above transform with the widest
placement respective to the current
floor until you jump over to it at which
point the view cuts to be relative to
the new current floor have the floor
above transform with the widest
placement respective to the current
floor until you jump over to it at which
point the view cuts to the relative I
don't think I understand what you're
saying I don't I don't think I followed
that one demon Sookie I just watched
your papers talk and I didn't get the
minkowski sum exactly I don't get where
you deduce the points to subtract from
each other uh that may require a more
elaborate answer do you want it may be
asked that first thing on tomorrow's pre
stream and I could walk you through it
I'm not sure exactly what you're talking
about but I have a guess but either way
I could walk through the portion of it
that would probably explain that in a
little more detail the the papers we
love talk obviously was not supposed to
be a complete explanation of gjk because
it was packed into like something like
15 minutes or something like that so you
know yeah it's a little bit fast but do
you explain on screen before so I can go
to air kiss uh you can if you're looking
for like my old the original one where I
talked about this you can in fact it's
on the first page of Google if you just
go to g JK
a this right here this video from long
long long time ago you can actually
watch and it kind of should walk you
through it maybe a little bit better I
don't know I but if you want to watch
that one it might answer your question
but but it might not saina Crom for the
stairs have you considered stairs on a
particular floor go down instead of up
then you wouldn't have to worry about
alpha uh I'm not sure that I understand
what the difference would be there like
up stairs or stairs they don't go down
or up there just stares right and you
Trevor it's whichever way the player
traverses them that determines whether
they're going upstairs or downstairs
right
yeah an amusing antidote from the papers
we love conferences they were like it's
there they said it's going to be oh well
I'll tell out and out later then thus
Isaac question so instead of the above
floor perspective transforming into
place you move the stairs it stays still
and jump cuts the power perspective once
you hit hop to a tile on the floor well
yeah but the problem is in that case
then I just I would just turn off the
respective all together right the whole
point of this is to have that
perspective transform because it looks
cool right so that's what I'm trying to
get if I wasn't trying to get that i
could just turn it off entirely right so
I'm trying to figure out a way to kind
of have my cake and eat it too which
might not be possible but I'm just
trying to figure out a way that I can
get that nice look of the perspective
floor coming into place but whoo-hoo but
without I having a discontinuity or
weird motion that looks really strange
and I don't know that that might just be
a complete fools are in it might be as
that's not possible at all you know
anyway so the anecdote from the comp the
conference was like they were like oh
you know we're going to have someone
doing live captioning for it so that's
so you know there you go and I'm like uh
like that's not going to work for my
talk I'm like there's no way they're
gonna be able to take captions at the
rate i talk and they're like no no no
they're really good and I'm like okay
and then after the talk it was like nope
they totally can keep up and the person
who was doing the captain came up to me
and was like was saying like well you
know I was keeping up with you up to
about 300 30 words per minute and then I
had to like just kind of skip most of it
that's like yeah I tried to tell them
that but they didn't listen to me sorry
like I because you know you can't type
that fast no one can type that fast I
certainly can't and you know
stenographers are better than me and
they're using shorthand but still
they're not that much fast faster 330
words for a minute I mean my god no one
can type that fast
William Bundy are you doing a whole
layer transfer at once or per object we
actually have per object transform so
you know we can do whatever we want I
just can't think of what we would do
that would work real well so I don't
know santokh Ron yes but currently
stairs are owned by the floor below them
that's true if they were owned by the
floor above them then you wouldn't see
the stairs two floors above since they
would be two floors above thus not
blocking your weight and not ending an
alpha oh I see what you're saying you're
talking about from the thing i said
before where I don't want to have them
kind of on top of you that's true but
then you also wouldn't really be able to
see to get on them in the first place
right
did buckminster fuller speak
particularly fast pseudonym I have never
heard him speak I suppose maybe there is
like a video of him did anyone record
that it would have been a long time ago
but probably someone did maybe or order
an audio recording I suppose this all we
would need not a video all right I'm
going to go ahead and close it down
thank you everyone for joining me for
lips at a handmade here at so I'm
peddler coating with you as always if
you would like to follow along the
series at home you could always pro to
the game on handmade here org it comes
with the source code so you could play
around with it on your own machine we
also have a forum site if you want to
ask questions a patreon page want
support the video series a schedule bot
which tells you when we're going to be
live and an episode guide for catching
up on old parts of the series I will be
out here tomorrow night 8pm again same
time same place hope to see you there
when we will consider this problem
little bit more insight if there's
anything we can do to save our nice
little perspective transform which i
think is kind of cool-looking and so I
was kind of hoping that we could maybe
we can't but will at least try okay so
that's about it for now I will see you
guys tomorrow until then have fun
programming and i'll see you on the
Internet take it easy