hello everybody and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete-game
live on stream we are gonna take a quick
second here before I get started
programming just to mention the fact
that I've pointed out that handmade
Seattle comm which is Abner coin Bray's
conference that he runs I which he ran
last year and everyone loved he was
going to run it again this year but of
course due to the fact that we are
currently in a pandemic wisely decided
that perhaps everyone getting together
in a room would not be the best idea
nevertheless he changed things around
and figured out a way that everyone can
sort of get together virtually and
there's now going to be a handmade
Seattle that just won't be quite so
Seattle maybe it'll be on Seattle time
but it will actually just be throughout
the world since everyone can participate
virtually if you want to get tickets
because I know a lot of folks who watch
this show knew about handmade Seattle
and probably came last year to the show
in person I would suspect mm-hmm I know
I certainly saw a lot of people there
you can go and get tickets now a
previously was just counting down until
the tickets were available the website
you could not buy them you can now buy
early bird tickets and they just went on
sale today and a hundred so last year
when people actually literally had to
get on a plane and fly there there were
way more than 100 tickets sold I think
there was more like 300 tickets sold or
something like this to the show so a
hundred will probably not last very long
so if you do want the cheaper tickets to
the conference you're probably gonna
want to get in on that pretty soon
because I'm guessing a hundred probably
won't last very long especially since
now people don't even have to travel to
go there so a bunch of people who
probably didn't go last year because
traveling is very expensive and or
they have families that they're taking
care of or something I can't just up and
leave for four or five days whatever it
takes to travel to the US and so on I
you really want to probably get in on
this soon if you want one of those
hundred tickets now if you don't need to
get the discounts then that's fine but
again since this year there won't be any
travel involved some people who maybe
can't afford very much in terms of a
ticket price you know it's a pretty good
discount there you probably want to get
in on that because it's a much more
affordable conference now since you
don't have to pay for airfare and hotel
right that really takes a lot of the
sting out of a conference that's
reasonably priced as Abner keeps this
which by the way I would take a minute
to thank him for doing because a lot of
these conferences these days are
absurdly priced I don't even want to
know what the game developer conference
cost these days they're like $1000
tickets or something like this it's kind
of just highway robbery so please take a
look at this you can go directly there
by just doing handmade - Seattle comm
pound tickets and I don't really think
that the majority of the conference has
probably even been scheduled yet so
there's probably going to be a lot of
stuff added to it but there's already
people lining up for presentations as
you can see a lot of them are people
that you've probably heard of before or
who in fact I think Elizabeth was
presented at the last one so if you came
to the original handmade Seattle you
would have seen that and then other
folks on here you probably have heard of
this one's obviously people who've been
doing a lot of handmade stuff that
you've probably seen before so you know
give it a shot and you'll also probably
recognize Alan Webster here from Forker
this is the editor that I actually use
on stream so yeah they'll
it's probably not even really completely
full of of what the actual schedule will
be yet but it's already got a lot of
people that you probably already know
about participating and maybe some that
you don't but either way I guess I just
say now would probably be a good time to
get your early bird tickets if you need
the discount because I don't think
that's gonna last very long based on
last year so that's the URL I will let
everyone else take care of that someone
will probably post it in the chat if you
have the twitch chat up at this moment
I'm sure someone will post this link so
you can just go ahead and click on it
and buy your tickets I will now go do
some programming and we will just
mention that periodically on future
streams so everyone who watches the show
knows about it and maybe can get the
early bird tickets if they want them
alright so let's get started why we
don't have a substance W in there I
don't know you know we just don't
apparently okay so if we go ahead and
take a look at where we were on the sort
of lighting optimization side we've I
think done a really good job honestly I
mean the Lighting's getting the the
major like backhaul part of the lighting
bird we need to do our Ray casting has
just been getting faster and faster to
the point where now it's like actually
quite efficient and honestly we could
probably get a lot more bang for the
buck now by just going over and doing
the filtering work because most of the
noise and the square enos will just go
away once we improve filtering on this
thing so in terms of improving quality
what I'm doing right now is is not
really the highest order action item but
the reason I want to go a little bit
further with it is because it never
hurts to have faster ray casting you can
always just cast more rays and get more
accurate or just take less time and save
more CPU for something else or run on a
lower end system so since the lighting
is by far the most expensive thing that
we're doing I don't want to stop just
yet because we are not really at a point
where I'm out of ideas
if
I was then I might say well that's good
enough let's go over and start working
on quality but at the moment I still am
fairly certain that actually we can
improve the speed quite dramatically
with this this algorithm it can be done
much more efficiently than it's being
done right now so we're slowly shaving
time off of this and what you can see
now from what we have is we actually do
eight rays in a loop we then write eight
at a time and that's our fundamental
like you know sometimes people call
these a kernel or something like the
main unit of work I don't really care
what you call it but point being we now
have effectively two hot zones one is
this grid raycast function which
basically does all of the costly work
involved in determining lighting
transport and then we have one more hot
zone over here
which is well I actually don't think
that fill atlas border is expensive at
all it's it's really just this so this
function right here you can see after we
do so full cast right here is what
actually does the the work of calling
the grid ray cast we could just weld it
right in here we don't really need to
have these you know we can be complex by
that a look but doesn't matter that
function calls not costing us anything
really at this point and there's not a
lot of optimization that's going to go
on by slipstreaming those so really what
we end up with here is just two hot
points one is the grid ray cast that
ends up getting dispatched in there and
the other is this process here whereby
after we do the read cast you can see we
have to loop through and do this sort of
production work to generate the blurred
versions of our mmm excuse me the
blurred versions of our diffuse map it's
really the blurred version of our spec
map so we're kind of turning the spec
map into this fuse map might be the way
to say it but either way that's
what we're doing and so this I believe
could get dramatically faster right and
the reason that I say that is because if
you actually take a look at for example
the HH Life prof results that we're
getting right now so if I go into oops
no yes so if we take a look at the HH
light prof runs and how expensive they
are you can see here that were like you
know something like 4.5 right now and
obviously that's you know numbers pretty
variable because CPUs being what they
are it's not particularly deterministic
but it's hovering around 4.5 depending
on what we do if we just turn this off
so if we say look don't do that right
and we run it again we can have a slight
sort of we can have an idea of how much
time is being taken for that right and
so if you look one full second of time
which is a quarter almost of our entire
time is spent doing nothing but updating
the actual map right so when we look at
this time when you look at 4.5 seconds
actually only 3.5 seconds at most is
being spent doing actual doing the
actual work of computing the light
transport we're then spending a full
second processing those results so I
just wanted to point that out because
this is a massive opportunity for us to
speed up this function here and people
were asking in the pre stream how fast
we think it will get eventually they
were like they they asked to mated they
thought they'd get to 3.8 seconds I
suspect 3.8 seconds is actually not is
not probably plausible as a lower bound
I think will get much lower than that
and the reason I say that is because we
have such a tremendous opportunity for
optimization not only do we have that
but we also have the fact that we're
still doing all this in
floats and we could just do it in 16-bit
so we could produce them every traffic
dramatically as well there's there's
just so much opportunity that really the
only reason we would probably get
stopped at 3.8 seconds
is if we just decided we don't care
about getting it faster than that right
so I think we're in good shape to shave
at least another second office maybe get
down to something like 3.5 but you know
if you really wanted to go hardcore on
this you could probably get it even
lower than that um
I wanted to take a little bit more of a
look at the actual ray caster though I
want to do a little bit more work to see
about whether it can be made a little
bit more efficient than it currently is
if I take a look at this leaf index call
here this is one thing I really want to
look at so what I would like to know
we've already done testing about what
happens when you flatten the cost metric
right so if we wanted to know how fast
this thing would be if it just has to
run the code path but doesn't actually
have to do anything so I'll run with
cost metric zero we know that that takes
us from 4.5 to 2.2 which is pretty
dramatic right so that means we are
spending 2.3 seconds of our test run
time doing the actual work in here on
the cost metric however what I'd like to
know is what happens if we have to just
do one of them so what you'll notice is
that if I set the cost metric to 1 then
we know that when we get through here
will absolutely decrement it at least to
zero there which means that we will do
one pass through the routine and then
exit and I'm very curious to know how
much that costs so if we run something
we know that two point two is the
flattener so what's really fascinating
here right you see this is 2.6 that
gives me a tremendous amount of insight
into what's happening here and it's
exactly what I expected which is great
it's what I wanted to say
so uh the reason that I wanted to see
that so specifically is that if you
think sorry I'm still in under I still
have the current virus or allergies or
something it's been going on forever so
if you look at what that's telling me
and this dovetails nicely with what I
wanted to do to the routine so I was
that's why I was hoping to see that the
thing that I wasn't that it didn't want
was if I did that it jumps back up to
four point five right I didn't want it
to be that just running this code path
once I wanted it to be that there that
it was the repetition of hunting through
the grid squares that was costing us
because that's that could do something
about I didn't want to see that just
running the code path once was the
expensive part because if that was
somehow true then me improving the grid
iteration is not going to fix it right
okay so this is exactly what I wanted to
see and what that tells me is that
actually this routine is quite sensitive
to how many times it actually has to run
the loop which is what I wanted and what
you would is what you would assume that
I try when optimizing things especially
on modern processors not to assume
things because oftentimes you'll find
out your assumptions are wrong so I like
to get some confirmation that my
assumption might at least be somewhat
correct before you know jumping to
conclusions there okay
so what do I want to do here well
there's a couple things so first of all
if you take a look at what's going on in
this routine you can see how its
structured we do a little bit of testing
to see whether we're still inside the
grid and then this is our heavyweight
loop that just wants to loop over all of
the things that we're going to intersect
with soap so possible occluders and
we're going to check against them now
what you will notice is when we hit we
immediately break so if we can find
that's the end of the routine if we
always found a hit on the first time
then we would be really happy because it
means that we wouldn't have to keep
running this loop now maybe this part
right here is the really expensive part
somehow I highly doubt that because
there's very little code this is all got
taken out so it's really just this part
right here so I doubt it because the
part where we actually do the sampling
is down here and that's the part that
would actually be the most expensive and
we're not running that only in the case
where we hit something we're running it
every time so really what that means to
me is that this at least is part of the
expenses doing this loop right and what
you see is that running this thing
repeatedly will cause us to keep going
through this loop and then this post
amble if we took if we don't hit
something we're gonna do this and then
we're gonna run the loop again and so on
right now if you look specifically at
how this is set up what you'll see is
that it does intersections on four boxes
at a time and it has a loop construct
here which is designed to test four
boxes at a time and then go to the next
one what that means is that ideally
because we have a branch in here and
we'd like that branch to do something
and we test four at a time and so we'd
like to test for at least our loop is
set up so that we would really like the
occupancy of a grid to be in some sweet
spot that's probably 12 16 boxes
something like this it's certainly not
one or two boxes right
and so I'm really concerned about this
in the sense that I feel like if I go
look we are probably getting very low
utilization out of this loop because the
size one thing we chose to do as sort of
a simplification is to table drive the
walk along the grid because I was afraid
that that might be too difficult for me
to write inside the loop it might just
take too many instructions or something
like this but the cost of that means
that the table walk has to be aligned
with the sampling voxel and the reason
that it has to be is because otherwise
the table Vox the table walk wouldn't be
table drivable if we could just raycast
from anywhere we wouldn't be able to
table drive it because we wouldn't be
able to pre-compute it right now maybe
we could come up with a different kind
of table but you know it's obviously way
simpler to just say look we're just
always going to go from the voxel and
that way every place we need to sample
we know we just look up in the table and
we're done the cost of that is that now
if you look at how fine-grained our
lighting voxel is right you can kind of
see that like the squares of lighting I
mean everywhere you see a different leaf
looking or one of these like sampling
lines here because you know our sampler
is not very good right now that's sort
of showing you that the resolution of
that voxel and it's pretty fine grain
compared to our geometry like there's
just not very much geometry here and
sure as the game gets sort of
implemented the gameplay gets
implemented there's gonna be more this
is not gonna be that much more you know
this is not a game like there's there's
gonna be like one person maybe tops in
each cell in most of time not even that
because there has to be empty space in
these cells for the characters to move
around it's this is a sparse game for
gameplay purposes you know you're in
thinking Legend of Zelda it's not
thousands the guy is piled into a room
it's you and
three other enemies with some maybe some
geometry in there for strategy or
something right but an empty room like
this one is not that far off from what
we're actively gonna have we're just not
gonna have that much geometry per square
so having our grid be that small is
really inefficient we're probably only
getting to three tops things per grid
we're not getting eight there's just no
way right so I think one of the biggest
problems that we're having right now is
we're just not getting any load out of
this routine right so let me just prove
that to myself because I again don't
like to assume things when we're doing
this sort of work I would like to keep
it as straightforward as possible and
know what I'm getting myself into so
when we do our internal lighting core
here I would like to actually take a
look at what it generates for its
spatial occupancy and print out what the
occupancy actually is so I'm gonna go
through and I'm gonna see if I can
determine the answer to that question so
I'm gonna do a loop and if you take a
look at the oops well you got a spell
stuff right if you take a look at the
actual lighting solution itself in here
what you'll see is there's the spatial
grid nodes and the spatial grid leaves
if we just walk over the spatial grid
nodes we will be able to see how many
leaves there are in each one and for
each leaf we can also look to see how
many actual boxes there are in them by
looking at say the box mean to see you
know what how many of them are filled
right so if we go through
and I just go through each node index
and I'm assuming we can just count on
the fact that the node count is what it
is
so in here Jimmy here you go you can
kind of see we computed total leaf count
and we should also do a total node count
right here there it is so you can see
here we can just do this get total cell
count right so if I just ask it for the
total cell count I should be able to
loop over all of them
and then I can look at the lighting
spatial grid node I can say spatial grid
nodes index and if I now look at how
many I can basically keep two stats
right I could say okay there's the total
you know total leaf
I guess we'll say node count and then
there's the total well these are both
you 32s by the way I guess I'll also say
total grid node count so I'll sum these
up and then I'll say the total box count
right well actually I know the total box
count so I don't really need to keep
that but I can do the min box count and
the max box count I don't really need
this because you know we know there's
ones with nothing in it right and so
another thing that I might want to keep
is a histogram so the other thing I
could do is say like leaves or rather
nodes per count and I could just say
look let's just say we're gonna take up
to 64 well none of these boxes are gonna
have 64 in them anyway
so we're just gonna say let's count a
histogram and just print out the
histogram of you know how many of each
fullness there are right so I can
basically get a bunch of of stats here
and this one's probably the one I really
want so don't don't actually know if I
if I actually care about any of these so
I might I might just say let's do this
so in here what I need to do is I need
to do a box count and produce this
somehow and then I need to say like well
look if the box count is greater than or
equal to well actually I can just i
guess save box count equals the minimum
of the nodes per box counts array and
the box counts so just to make sure we
don't actually like go over and this
will actually set it equal to that
amount so I want to make sure it's
actually one less than so basically like
we're gonna insert 63 we'll get all of
the overflow so if somehow there's
somebody with a hundred in there we'll
stick them into 63 box and that's fine
because I don't honestly think there's
going to be but we don't need that we
that was already like crazy high anyways
so it'll be fine so then I'll just say
nudes per box count box count and I'll
increment it so then we know there was a
node with that many boxes in it and then
when I'm done I could just go through
the like the box count one by one and
just print it out so I can say hey nodes
with you know or sort of like maybe I'll
just do this box count you you and I'll
just say all right the number of nodes
with this box count was nodes per box
count box count and to avoid spamming
with way too many lines that don't give
any information I'm just gonna only do
it if the nodes per box count in this
case is nonzero
all right so the problem we have now is
we have to actually count and Counting
is not trivial in this case it's not
hard but it's also not just one line of
code the reason for that is these are
packed so what we know if we look we can
loop through the leaves so we're gonna
have to do something like this right and
what we're gonna have to do actually I
guess we can use the loop that we have
here we've we've kind of already written
it in the grid right caster right but it
looks like this right so we need to loop
through the leaves and it's easy to know
how many leaves we have because it's
just these two elements of the node we
can just look at the difference between
them to find out how many there are but
the problem is we don't know how full
each one is so we do we could simplify
our calculation here by only looking at
the last one if we wanted to
meaning we know that if we we know that
every single one of these is full except
the last one so we don't actually have
to do what I'm about to do but just for
simplicity I don't get this is not a
speed oriented routine in fact it's not
even in our production code it's just in
the testing the performance testing so I
don't care at all I'm just going to
write it by summing them each so every
time we pull a leaf out what we want to
do now is see how many of these box
values are actually full right so
I guess I could just do this wide which
sounds crazy cuz don't care about how
the fastest runs but honestly it seems
like since these are wide values that's
just the fastest I write like that tells
us how many of these things is zero
right and I don't know if I can do that
can I
oops that's what I meant
there we go like can't we just do that
do we have that now we don't so we do
have this right so I guess some wrong oh
those are VIII's so I think we can just
do it just with one of them right so we
can just say our the X is equal and that
should be sufficient that just gives us
a wide vector so this is like and can
let me do this
so maybe I'll just say has volume well
that's actually already function so so
I'm just gonna do this test that gives
me back a vector where a vector register
where each of the slots for the float so
the four float slots is all ones in the
case where it's a valid box and all
zeros in the case where it's not so then
I can just do a mask move right or a
move mask I should say
and this will just give me back account
right so this will just be like alright
that's the count and in this particular
case it'll just be like a it'll just be
the bits or set depending on whether the
you know the first bits a one or a zero
based on whether the first ones valid or
not and the second one the third one and
so on right so I believe you can just do
a population count in x86 because oh my
god x86 has like every instruction I
don't actually remember what it is
though
so it's this oops
conveniently called pop pop counts and
so then this is how many there are so at
that point I think that's all I actually
need to do so I can just say box count
plus equals valid count right now I
think that might actually be everything
but because I slammed in some crazy SSE
code there with population count and so
on I kind of want to make sure that this
code works at all because that's kind of
absurd so let's just take a look and see
if that's even remotely right cuz yeah
that was kind of a crazy town thing I
just wanted to count as as is you know
what it's probably just easier for me to
write this why I didn't do that to be
fancy
that's just what came to mind you know
maybe I'm writing too much somebody code
lately I don't know so let's take a look
at valid oh by the way George the person
who wrote remedy VG's extracting pixels
on the chat he reminded me of something
that I always forget to do on stream but
that's really awesome so if you notice
if you look at one of these things here
it's a real pain in the butt to like
actually get down to the values you
actually want to see and so in this case
like we kind of probably want to look at
this as a u-32 because we just want to
know what the mask is right you can see
the mask was like these two are valid
and these two are not or something like
this right so I kind of want to just see
valid P that way and it's kind of a pain
in the butt to do this because it still
sucks like it's still hard to see and it
takes up a lot of space and whatever and
remedy BG actually has like way better
stuff in there for that so
I guess I don't really know what the
format specifier is for this though is
it PS or whatever what's the how do it
you know George can tell me how we do it
because I never remember correctly I
need to learn to use some of the more
advanced features of this but it's
something like that I thought you just
did PS George am I wrong about this
maybe I shouldn't be using this feature
yet I don't know
uh-oh it only works on the registers can
I add a request to make it work on
regular variables - I know I asked too
much of George he wrote this debugger in
his spare time by the way and it's the
best debugger for Windows right now
right which is kind of crazy I wish I
was rich if I was rich I'd just you know
ask George to quit his job and and do
the debugger full-time and just be like
I'll just pay whatever your salary was
but you know that's something only rich
people could do anyway if you're rich
out there could you consider doing that
for me because that would be great so if
you take a look at what's happening here
the population count feature seems to
work just great
let's take a look at the valid if the
valid feature works right
leave box men
max rather X so if I take a look at
these the old way yeah
so that just worked that is a tiny
little sliver of a box but that is
actually correct we probably should just
throw out slivers like that to be honest
but who cares at the moment um so anyway
if I now take a look at the results of
this which I now have some reason to
believe might be sort of correct a
little bit oops well probably can't do
it that way if I gotta do it this way
there we go
so if you take a look at the
distribution of these things what you
can see is it's really not what I wanted
you can kind of see that like the
numbers just aren't very high I don't
know what the optimal box load is box
count zeros probably fine because we
know that we're just gonna have empty
spaces in this grid so you know that's
not a problem but if you take a look at
the box counts here you know that's not
great that's not great we really want to
be mostly honestly all these are PI not
great we'd probably really want to see
more up here even higher than that right
so this just again confirms what I was
assuming I really just wanted there to
be some way that I could verify there's
probably a speed when to be had boosting
that occupancy so where I'm going with
all this is just one simple statement
our grid cells are too small we need our
grid cells to be way bigger than the
voxel right
the lighting voxel so our spatial
occupancy grid size is way too tiny it
needs to be much bigger but the only way
we're going to be able to do that
is by not table driving the walk so what
I want to try to do today is I want to
see if I can do the walk in line right
so we find go over to the lighting and
we look in here you can see this is what
I'm talking about right here
so this bit here so you can see here
when it starts the walk it does this
walk table thing and it grabs the walk
table entry and then it starts walking
through here and it grabs using the the
grid index which it got right out of the
walk table I believe oh wait no the grid
index we know to begin with right man
a lot of tissues well that sucks oh well
so if we take a look here at what the
the what's going to happen with the grid
index we would need to find that somehow
so we need some way of finding oh my god
magic Kleenex thank you
so we'll need to find the grid index
somehow but that's not very difficult
because we only have to do that once per
bundle of samples so that's gonna be a
pretty simple thing to do that'll just
be like hey tell me where we are in the
you know in the occupancy here so that's
not going to change that'll just flow
through properly so the only thing that
we really need to do is figure out how
we're gonna get these two things to
happen in line right so what I'm gonna
do is I'm gonna just see if I can fast
enough
get the compute walk table codes so this
is the code that we were doing here can
I get this compute walk table code to
run fast enough in line right so
basically what I need is this and what
I'd like to do also is try to figure out
the way to do this fast with out
introducing breakage so I'd like to be
able to test my results so what I might
do is just copy this and say okay you
know let's take a look at compute walk
table fast or something like this if I
were to not like take this desk part out
of it so we're not going to do we're not
we're not going to do this desk part of
it here and instead what we're gonna do
and we're not gonna return anything I'm
just gonna say hey maybe I'll call that
verify I'm just gonna say hey can we
just verify that the results are the
same right
so everywhere in here that we were doing
something to test I'm actually just
going to do something more like this so
we'll just say this is the T terminate
and this is the D grid value which i
think is what a 16 or something like
this what's the D grid value I don't
know it's the step so it's s 16 so it's
an S 16 value which is exactly what I
thought so we'll just do like a t
terminate results and a D grid results
those are these two things here and then
I just want to say hey let's assert that
these things our you know fast quote
unquote computation is doing are correct
so this will allow me to generate the
table the same way that I was generating
it and verify and then I can start
mutating the routine into something
faster and see if we can maintain
accuracy while reducing the number of
instructions and so on right just so I
can boil it down faster that way first
so in here if you take a look at where
we're actually using derp I don't need
to write that because again while this
is something we need to access here to
get like the radii out of here and all
that stuff I don't need to fill out that
destination so that doesn't need to
happen right and I'm not returning
anything so I'm just asserting stuff
that's all I'm doing
and so I should be able to just do the
test that way
right
so all I'm gonna do is I'm just gonna go
ahead and take this compute walk table
fast and I'm gonna call it and and in
this case since I'm just doing it in the
lighting profiler I'm not gonna bother
with it in the other place just gonna do
it right here so immediately after right
I'm just gonna call this so I'm gonna
take this I'm gonna duplicate the call
to do it exactly the same way that we
were doing it and I'm just gonna call it
like this it won't need a temporary
nough so if I get rid of this memory
nothing should happen right and now we
should be good to go so in theory I can
now run HH light prof and it will do you
know whatever it's going to do and then
if I went in here and intentionally
induced an error such as Haiti
terminates plus equals 0.2 F now if I
run it we should get a UH fault right it
should it should announce this failure
somewhere okay this is actually why I
did that
do we have assertions turned off why did
that
how is that possible I'm so confused
I mean what did I miss
okay so here when we are in compute walk
table fast okay so our assertions are
turned off right now evidently right
I mean you watched it skip straight on
over that right someone want to tell me
what that's about
hand me internal and handmaid slur both
on
oops okay was it just a typo did I like
accidentally not put both things in
there
oh no but that still would have been
wrong so how did our assertions get
compiled out did I do
odhh is this the one that has the
lighting assert turned off I don't think
so
there we go okay so we are just undoing
that because since we're profiling we
both we made sure that the assertions
are on so okay that's all right I guess
I'm not sure what I want to do about
that exactly I guess I'll just
I guess I'll just hand code it so I'm
just gonna put in my own assert here
like so right and then what I'll do is
I'll just all manually fault and so this
way now I should be sure that anytime
there's a there's an error we fault
in theory there we go and so if I don't
do this now we should run clean oops we
should run clean yeah so now I should
have some confidence that I can measure
I may have to do a fuzzy equals for the
float because we may not get the exact
same T terminate value I just want to
make sure I get close so this may be too
precise but we'll cross that bridge when
we come to it so let's suppose that we
were to take this this dim step bit here
this we don't care about because it's
per R a so we actually can still table
drive that if we wanted to right so this
can come from a table and we can so I'm
not going to focus on that here we have
our starting location and our T
terminate we have our cost loop which
will already be there we don't know all
this stuff is fine so the first thing we
see that needs adjustments because you
could see here like there's actually
almost nothing is actually even
happening here really all we need to
look at is this I mean that's the only
thing that's really happening so for
doing this walk honestly we're just
looking at the min here right
so we just want to know what is the
lowest T value
so knowing what's the lowest T value is
a bit of a conundrum we already did one
trick for this for the raycasting and we
could use the same trick again and
that's basically to just use the first
16 bits of the float and ignore the last
16 bits but I don't know if that's gonna
fly here the reason I don't know if it's
gonna fly is because stepping along the
grid kind of needs to be correct we
can't really afford to be just randomly
stepping like into a place the Ray
doesn't actually hit just because we
didn't actually do the test accurately
enough and you know maybe it's just it's
fine because you'd have to be so close
to a corner or an edge in order for that
to tap it doesn't matter which one you
step into first so it's really tough to
say that's a really tough call to say
and we'd have to actually go do some
testing to figure out to be completely
honest however what I will say is we do
have a test now like I'm running this
almost as a unit test honestly so I can
kind of just party on it if I want to
and if it never triggers then I know
it's no worse than the previous one for
the cases we actually are using right so
could do could do that so maybe I will
try it I'm gonna start by not doing that
because I want to make this be a little
bit I want to do this in steps but okay
you know sure so let's see how fast I
could actually make this routine if you
take a look here I probably you just
want to do this three wide I can't
really do it for wide because there
aren't four things to do that I can see
so what I would probably say is if you
look at seldom and at these can just be
vectored up so I can just say look
there's going to be a seldom for and an
at for and these are just going to be
you know kept in registers because they
they can be and then there's going to be
a radius so we're gonna have the Ray
direction and the at and the seldom as
things that we just save and to do that
it's pretty simple because we have these
values so I can just load up the the at
as you know sort of a a vector where I
just keep the last Lane 0 I can do the
same thing for the raid erection and the
same thing for the seldom right and so
at that point this which used to be six
instructions will become two so that's
nice right I can just say okay seldom
for - at for / ready for is our new like
T from T four it's our new like set of T
values so this loop over the dim indexes
doesn't actually have to happen right so
then what I could do is say well now
let's just look at what we're actually
going to get there and say okay so
suppose we then said yeah there's gonna
be like a T this value and that's just
going to be the extraction of each of
these so we'll do an extract
of t4 and extract one of t4 and an
extract two of t4 and I believe I
rewrote these to kind of do that or
something right I don't remember how we
actually looked at these but it's
something like this what is it there it
is
so it's convert f/32 and so again none
of that's necessary in in actuality but
I just want to take it one step at a
time so I want to make sure we can do it
using the the same kind of divide thing
so now we can just get rid of that and
replace in this loop a use of T this
with dim index and then in theory this
should run the same way and I may have
to make those float compares fuzzy
because again we're kind of changing how
they're done and so we'll see if I need
to give them some tolerance here
but first I'm just gonna see and make
sure cuz I could just not be doing this
right let me just make sure I got a
clean compiler so I want to make sure
that that I actually look at the values
first before I assume that I need some
fuzzy float in there okay so if we take
a look at the verify for verify index
here and we just take a look at what
these values actually need to be versus
what they are yes you can see that
that's like totally wrong so we're still
a little bit off here so the question is
what did I what did I screw up there
right cuz it seems like that should have
been fairly straightforward but I
obviously did not do it right right
looking
the values it's pretty clear that I just
kind of brain farted there so you can't
just do this obviously right like I need
to update the I need to actually update
the at four you know I'm saying so like
I don't really know how that should be
done it may need to be done a little
more cleverly for right now I'm gonna do
this and then we'll work on how we're
gonna do that okay so it looks like we
don't need a fuzzy fluke compare there
it looks like that produced exactly the
same answer so that's good but let's
continue to take this a little bit
further before we do anything before we
take a look at the app for part of
things so this stuff is pretty fast like
this part can be made fast obviously
this part is less so so that's going to
be require some thought but this part
right here where we downshift I feel
like that's something we can work on so
if we take a look at how we pick out
that dim index that may give us a clue
and I'm kind of trying to think in my
head also like how this is gonna work
long term so you can you could see how
seldom we would want to do a mask out
here this wants to be a replicates so
I'm just trying to figure out like what
I would actually need
and it's a little bit tough so the step
value right now is like a table driven
thing right so the step value comes out
of a table and we need the index of zero
one or two to figure out what that D
grid results is going to be right
yeah it's just a little tricky I'm gonna
start by just doing that compare because
I'm just not I'm not feeling it right
now I'm not sure how I want to I'm not
I'm not immediately like leaping to like
I kind of know how I want to attack this
so I may sort of do a little fancy dance
and you know put on put on my my large
pantaloons and just kind of like sauce
around for a little bit
to see where it takes me
you saw how we did this before
it was kind of a little like cleverness
here where we kind of did this this age
comp shuffler nonsense where I did a you
know a horizontal compare and all this
and all this stuff we could do a similar
trick right we could do this and get the
answer out this way right like I could
say hey just do a 1 shuffle right so
this is like one instruction and then do
the min pause which is one instruction
and the extract which is one instruction
so three instructions and get them in
into a general purpose register we could
try that that should give the best dim
answer directly which is kind of handy
again don't really know if it will work
it may not be precise enough I really
don't know but that's what we're gonna
try anyway and so if we get best dim out
here then in theory we should be able to
just to get that T best we should be
able to do another shuffle but in this
case I'm not really going to bother
quite yet I'm just gonna say alright
we'll take the T we'll take the actual
extract I think we can do this in just
the slow way like hey
give me the the best DeMuth value right
okay so I think this is possibly
something that will work
I don't really know we're gonna use t4
for this here and the H comp shelter is
what it is everything else should be
roughly the same let's just do that
in fact I think can we even just do this
yeah so we'll give it a shot
I'm not optimistic about it but we'll
see what happens so let's see how far
off we are on on this stuff
what's this is called D grid results and
to terminate results like so so what's
interesting about that is we're getting
the right to terminate value but not the
right best dim here somehow so what's
the deal there
so a couple things about this one I
realize we didn't account for the spare
Lane so probably we're gonna have to
remove that 14 15 so actually I probably
should fix that before we go any further
that doesn't look like this bug but we
can't actually test the final lane the
final Lane has to be not there that's
probably already game taken care of by
like Mans or something anyway because
now actually wouldn't yeah it would
because we divided by zero like this
this is a divide by zero right here so
in fact just to avoid that we could well
no because we know that the radio that
we're dividing by here any of those
could be zero right so actually probably
what we would want to do here is
actually make this be an envy so we
probably actually want to do that I'm
not gonna do that yet but I do want to
do that eventually okay so what I would
also like to do is I'd like to run this
so I can have the values from it so for
example I would like to know like a T
best ref and a best dim ref so I'd like
to keep track of these values just
because that will help me compare and
see what the answer should have been and
why am I getting a different answer
right so I just gonna take a look at
these so if I look at T best ref and
then I look at T best they're actually
different so that looks like you know an
issue probably the issue that we're
having if I look at best dim and best
dim ref you can see that that you know
they're different I'm curious to know
what number were on
so it looks like this is just wrong in
other words we didn't have to it's not
like we got to some subtlety right like
we were like I we you know we stepped a
long way and and and then we found this
like one edge case we did get through
the first three but eventually we got to
one then and it wasn't sufficient again
that could be the case that actually
there's nothing to erroneous here but
the precision of that comparison is just
not sufficient so so I'm going to have
to do something fancier
[Applause]
so I really don't know how I want to do
this and it's not sure I need to have
some way of finding out which of the
values in here is the smallest and I
don't really know how I would do that
the brute force method is I can
replicate the values into another
register with them Swizzle de round and
then I do a comparison and then I masked
move the comparison and then I look that
up in a table to get me the actual
lookup value so you know is it fantastic
no would it possibly work a pop maybe
would it be fast enough maybe I don't
know if we look at what I actually need
to do the other thing I could try to do
here is produce these values correctly
more directly and this one is pretty
straightforward so I would never have to
actually extract to get this one I could
just mask and combine the T values
but I am not sure you can see why I was
worried about this routine right like
so here's another thought maybe I'm
doing this the wrong way
maybe I really want to do more this out
on the scatter pipe anyway because
what's that pipe doing well the rest of
that routine has all of these
floating-point operations all up ons so
it could be that the goal here is not
actually to do it or to keep it wide
it's to do the minimal amount of work in
the sse and then just try to transit it
out to a general purpose register right
I mean you know the problem that I see
is just like it really wants to be float
so I don't know that that's really
possible because it's like look the the
main thing we're doing is actually this
like yes we do need this one value to
come out into the general purpose
registers to do stepping but everything
else is just happening in float so it
really does kind of want to be wide you
know
well I guess we just gotta get started
on it I mean I don't know I'm not I'm
sorry I'm just not seeing anything fancy
here it's not really my strong suit like
cross compares are not really my strong
suit I'm not super good with those
haven't ever really like done routines
that are that rely heavily on those
so wait where is this min pause oh it's
down at the bottom yeah
so one thing I wonder a little bit is I
wonder if you could somehow use two of
these to extract the value like I wonder
if there's some way
you know what I think there is so riddle
me this Batman if I were to first do a
comparison in epu 16 to see oh yeah this
would work is it a good idea I don't
know is it a good idea I don't know but
but I mean
it kind of might be so suppose you had
to age cops huh fleurs right so you're
looking at the high bits here and the
problem that you have is sometimes those
high bits
compare for equivalence and you'd like
it to test the bottom right so suppose I
did this something like that so what if
I said H comp I and H comp low so if I
did two shuffles to put these into place
so this is actually 0 &amp; 1 now 4 &amp; 5 8 &amp;
9 and then these are just 0 1 0 1 0 1 0
1 0 1 so if I did two of those shuffles
which is not great because that's two
cycles those have to issue sequentially
because they're both going to happen on
part 5 which is ugly but so those two
happens sequentially and then I could
say well if there's equivalence in some
of these things then I'm asked
of course now as I'm saying this now I'm
realizing that stupid because how did I
know they were equivalent because in
order to get masks into the channel
first I would have had to do a compare
anyway all right that was dumb they're
mine take it all back you go so so I'm
gonna say as well you could just do when
they're equivalent we just compared the
low 16 but how do you actually get a
mask into that Channel right because in
order to know that they compared
equivalent you would have had to have
lined them up to do equivalence compares
and that's exactly the thing that I'm
trying to avoid right so not great not
great all right so yeah I think we're
just we're in the position of half to
figure out something that's going to be
a little bit more costly involve more
shuffling unless there's something that
I'm missing so if we have a t4 here that
we've produced it's free for us to
reproduce one additional value in here
so I'm just gonna it doesn't matter
which one it is
I'm just gonna end up using X because
there's really no reason not to do that
so I'll get one extra channel out of it
and then when we do our shuffle I can
produce four comparisons at once and you
know we can then use the mask of that to
probably tell us what we need to know so
if in here I say okay you know at four
I'm sorry not at four F 3/2 X t4 like
shuffle or something and I do a shuffle
for X of T 4 and here what I need to do
is just produce
comparison so you know I don't know what
it would actually be but probably
something like that maybe we'll see what
we actually want in a second but here's
where we'll actually get our comparison
so this is our like min comp here where
we would do like teeth for oops I have a
bad keyboard alignment day so there's
our comparison and then we would mask
mob fat right so we would say our sorry
move mask that this is really just a you
ate right but oh well so if we take a
look at what we need for this comp mask
we should be able to do you know you
look at that it's like okay so we have
to do one shuffle one compare one move
mask and then we have a table and we
look up in the table if I can make that
work relatively well then we should be
okay and in fact you know maybe that
argues against doing this sort of fancy
trickery here because it might end up
being exactly the same instructions
right I mean
yeah you know I'm saying so if you look
at how this is doing it you know this it
comes up with a better answer like it
actually gives you the actual answer so
you know your tables are smaller so like
this table for example is only four
entries long but if we were to do it the
other way it would be like 16 entries
long you know potentially so it's saved
some space but it's not as accurate so
I'm not sure I'm not sure we really want
to do the fancy footwork
so we'll see anyway let's see how this
goes so we're getting rid of this the h
comp shuffler here is it's not gonna
happen right so what I need to do now is
I need to find some way of getting the
answer out though and so that takes a
little bit more work here and so what
we're gonna have to do is have some
table that tells us what the answer is
and if you look at how we would do this
normally we would say look if you know
addicts is less than @y then if add X is
less than at Z best equals 0
best equals me best equals to right and
then in the other branch we would say if
at Y is less than at C right
so it looks like to be completely honest
with you we probably only really need
three compares there so honestly we
don't even need the final Channel it
looks like I mean am I wrong so it looks
like we only really need three compares
and so what we could do is just say well
okay so you know if we actually just did
it this way and then we wanted to do the
shuffle we need X to be compared against
Y &amp; Z and then we need Y to be compared
against Z right oh well actually I mean
I guess we kind of do and in fact I
guess can we just do this with well no I
guess we can't remember so I guess we
kind of do want that because then we can
save one shuffle because if we want X to
be compared to two different things then
we can do this way there might be some
way we next we can so we need at least
one of these to be duplicated right so
yeah we need at least one of them to be
duplicated so I think I think that's
fine there might be some other way to do
it trying to think if there's another
rephrase this
I think that's right so anyway if I do
the shuffle this would want the addicts
and the @y compare would be here the @ y
@ z compare would be here and then we
just need an X Z compare which would
just be this one right so I think that
gives me what I want and then my table
can be derived just from that right so
at that point I think you'd probably
want these to be interleaved differently
because you'd want to just get rid of
the final mass values so you want to
just have nothing in that fourth channel
so you probably actually want your thing
to be interleaved as XY XZ that looks
like the more efficient packing in I
mean I could be wrong but that just
looks like what's right so the XY XZ XY
XZ XY XZ in everything and so then what
we would do is we'd say it's X Y X Z so
t-this now is that extraction which will
deal with whether we ever want to do
that extraction later but here's our our
actual comp it's just t4 less t4 s and
then we just have a table which is our
like index you know our best table I
don't know it's the best table so in
here we would say all right let's look
at what these bit patterns mean so we
basically have like 0 0 0 and we know
that we want to mask off the top so
we're really just dealing with
something looks like this right answer
that high bit after we do the mask move
of this the high bit is going to be X
less than
you
there we go so we then so our t4s now
gets packed as our t4 is XY XZ r t4 s is
now Y Z Z right and then X for no reason
and since we're doing a less than if we
want we can just make it always not be
true so that way we don't have to bother
even masking it off so what we would do
is since we know Z is the last thing we
just stuff Z in there and then I think
we're okay because then we know that
that bit on the mask mouth will always
be zero so I'd have to even mask it off
okay so our bit pattern here we know is
in this column in this column we have a
X is less than Z in the next column
right that's the high bit so the high
bit is X is less than Z the middle bit
is going to be y less than Z and the low
bit is gonna be X less than Y right so
if none of these things are true
so X Y so basically that would mean that
Z is primal right because Z X is not
less than it and Y is not less than it
so we would pick Z in that case right in
the case where X is less than Y but
still I think so if neither of these two
things is true again it's just Z because
Z is still primal in this case Y is
primal so Y is less than Z and X is not
less than Y
we would assume that Y is the lessor
right
I would assume trying to think if this
table makes sense to me but I think it
does if X is less than Y and Y is less
than Z but X is not less than Z then we
would assume that that Y is primal
actually is that possible because if Y
is less than Z then Y is the lowest of
them but X is less than Y that's this is
like this is like what so I don't know
what that is we'll just call that one so
then if X is less than Z but Y is not
less than Z and X is not less than Y
then Y would be primal I think if X is
less than Z and X is less than Y then X
is primal if X is less than Z and Y is
less than Z but X is not less than Y
then Y would be primal if X is less than
Z and Y is less than Z and X is less
than Y then X is primal right I think I
might have missed one there
I mean one way to say it is that X can
only be so this tells us whether X is
less than Z so X should only show up
here and it does this tell us whether X
is less than Y and so it should anytime
it's less than Z and why it needs to be
true which is what you expect in terms
of this row here this is when X is less
than Z but X is not less than Y then
it's just going to be Y right and then
here we just have look if no one is less
than Z then Z is primal doesn't matter
how x and y compare we don't care and if
Y is less than Z then it only matters
which one of these two is primal and in
this case it's like we don't really know
we could say anything so somebody here
is gonna get to like we could say that's
X right it doesn't matter because it
shouldn't be possible so some of these
just aren't possible right and that's
okay
it doesn't really matter so anyway um
once we have this table we can look into
it so we can just say like okay best dim
equals best table
mmm of mask PS of our min comp and that
gets us out the the best dim that we
actually wanted we don't need any of
this or that right and I guess we then
just need to figure out how we're going
to get our T best at the moment this is
not particularly good so we probably
would want to look up a shuffle as well
right that allows us to just move the
correct thing into place
so we'd want to do that eventually but
at the moment I suppose I would just
probably do this
so that we can start testing the other
part of it right so let's see if that
works at all it clearly doesn't which is
fine let me make this an easier to read
so what I want to look here is that Tory
terminate results and D grid results and
then I want to look at verify verify
index dot T terminates and actually not
let's do it that way D grid results and
verify so here are the values and then
we also would want to look at some of
this other stuff so we want to look at
like what the best dim invest in ref are
and then the T best and T best right I
don't know
wait what
so like that's a okay
that's a bit scary so I must have
screwed something up when I did like the
XY XZ stuff like I must have pooped out
I must have pooped this out somehow so
if we take a look at T this and wonder
what's going on here so so this just
looks completely busted okay
oh wow
so this was actually correct all the way
up til some kind of very odd case
occurred it looks like because we
actually went through a ton of these hmm
alright so this may be a little bit
trickier for us to wrap our heads around
right so looking at what's going on here
I guess we should maybe verify that this
actually always comes out with something
that I expect so let's do in here
something like you know get that comp
mask if comp mass is greater than or
equal to recount best table we'll put in
another hard coded desert
so interesting so we never get an
erroneous value here but we do somehow
still produce a bunch of man which cost
are we on so Ron cost one so we've only
taken one step right and we've produced
some some nutso values somehow right
which is which is crazy
can I see what our radio R is so the
radio for so what why would there be an
int in this channel though like that's a
one value so like why would that have
come out weird that's that's obviously
just you know we screwed something up
you know why why would that be imp
because here what we're saying is the
seldom - where we are / r ad for that
should have been stepping properly the
entire time so something's getting like
Swizzle de round XY XZ X Y X Z X Y X Z
so I just want to look at this one a
little more closely so which one did we
say this was 135 I'm just gonna wanna
I'm just gonna want to look at that one
so I'm gonna set a breakpoint for just
that specific one so I can watch it when
I say 135 so we're gonna set a little
break point on fru-fru and then when we
walk through here I just want to see
what the heck is going on so if I take a
look at what at is it's you know pretty
NOC Lluis nothing weird going on there
we take a look at Rady nothing weird
going on there take a look at cell dim
nothing weird going on there so let's
see what we get 44 first time out and
this is what we expect so we just have
em fear Oh are we no but we're not we're
correctly accounting for that we do 0 1
&amp; 3 in here so I don't know alright so
min comp what's our actual comp mask
here our comp mask is 2
so I can see why it's 2 because negative
infinity is technically less than 0.6 9
right
you know like I don't disagree what I
don't necessarily quite grasp is how
that is a negative zero so like the
actual source samples ray Direction it's
actually negative zero
so I'm confused about two things first
of all the confusion number one is why
is this coming through as negative zero
right so I guess our table generator has
some kind of a weird thing in it where
it's like actually generating negative
zeros for some reason which I don't know
why it's doing but it is right you can
see there's negative zero right there
but the other thing that's weird about
that is why didn't the other routine
also have the same problem so when we
went through and did that same one here
like is it just because we happen to be
choosing the opposite way around of
these like would it have picked the same
bad answer basically kind of curious
because that's really strange and and
kind of busted so we kind of need to
figure out what was going on there I'm
curious to know so if I just changed
this to this would we have the same
answer actually sorry right you see
where I'm going with this right so yeah
like the only reason we were getting a
different answer there was because of
some some nonsense right so that's
that's real Emes up and we probably
should deal with that separately cuz
that's really not good like for obvious
reasons I think yeah so alright so
looking at the other one here so it
looks like T terminate D Grid results
here is wrong because we're doing best
in one instead of best in zero here for
the reference so it looks like to match
our reference code we actually did have
a preferred order zero gets preferred
when nothing is true right so like in
order to be exactly the same I guess
technically we got to kind of look at
this like the way that our thing was
working before is it would just do like
whichever one was best so do it would do
assume X if Y is less than X take it
right if Z is less than whichever one
you took out of those two then take it
right
so that's what we were doing before and
I guess for sake of of reference because
we don't care I guess I should just make
it be the same right so I want these to
be the same so the way that would work
if we were to compare these it would
really do the other way around I guess
so it would look more like this right
and what we would say here is like look
if X is not greater than Z and X is not
greater than Y you would pick because
you start with X and then you say if
it's greater than Y take Y if it's
greater than then if it was greater than
C take C right so in this case it
wouldn't be here we would say okay X's
is greater than Y so we'd take Y and
then Y is not greater than Z so we would
take Y then doing it again same way we
would say okay X is X is not greater
than Y X is not greater than Z right so
this is like the same case right we
don't care what this value is in this
case um in this case X is greater than Y
so we take Y and then we say Y is
greater than Z so we take C right so
we're just doing it the same way the old
routine did it so here X is not greater
than Y X is greater than Z so we take Z
X is greater than I'm sorry X is greater
than Y so we take Y Y is not greater
than Z so we take Y X is greater than Y
so I'm sorry X is not greater than Y so
we take X X is greater than Z so we take
Z and finally X is greater than Y
so we take Y Y is greater than Z so we
take C right I don't know if I read that
table off correctly but that's looks
like more like what it is
right looks like I missed something here
though cuz we're wrong right off the bat
we just verify it one more time so we're
trying to take the less the least one so
if X is X is not greater than Y we keep
it X is not greater than Z we keep it so
that seems right X is greater than Y so
we keep Y y is not greater than Z so we
keep Y yeah X is greater than Y i sorry
X is not greater than Y so we keep x y
is greater than Z we don't care
X is not greater than Z so we keep X X
is is greater than Y so we keep Y Y is
greater than Z so we keep C right X is
greater than Y nope so we keep x x is
greater than Z so we keep Z X is greater
than Y yes it is so we keep Y Y is
greater than Z nope so we keep Y X
greater than Y no so we keep x x is
greater than Z so we keep Z and same
here so that seems right so why is that
not isn't that correct
doesn't that seem right everywhere
like that looks like it should be
producing their answer alright well
let's find out why not
so it's wrong right off the bat like the
very first one is wrong so it's just
totally wrong what I've done here I
thought I was imitating this table right
I mean isn't that what this table does
it starts with X and then it says I'm
sorry it starts with X and T best
because T best this comparison always
fails so the first times they loop it's
just X right next time through the loop
it's saying look if X is less than Y
oh I've got that backwards Wow
this stuff is too this stuff is too
finicky for me and I need more coffee if
I'm gonna do try to do this so actually
I need to do it sort of the other way
right if I'm actually trying to produce
the exact same thing as this if I need
to produce the comparisons this way so
we start with X if X is less than Y did
we like change this I mean this doesn't
make any sense it has to be greater
right did I do something weird
yeah it needs to do be greater oh so so
that wasn't my fault okay I just when I
was fussing with that routine yeah cuz
that's that's I don't know what I was
thinking there right it has to be this
if the best is greater you know it's
yeah I don't know what's going on there
there we go
so I didn't screw up I just for some
reason translight routine so now we're
doing it exactly the same way as the old
one and it's correct so that's the good
news right
we don't really know how efficient it is
to do it this way but hey it was pretty
simple it was just a shuffle and then I
compared move masks into the table yeah
you know that seems alright that gets us
which of our steps we're going to use
and it also allows us to do this shuffle
if we want to right we can have a
shuffler in here and we can look those
up in see really like right so we can do
this where we have this shuffle table
and we just say okay so it's 0 1 0 2 0 1
0 2 right well that's not quite right
so if you look at what this index is
going to tell you it's they're not
packed that way so 0 1 is correct so 0 1
0 is correct but then 2 is actually
always 3 right so we don't really have
we never get the second you know we get
0 &amp; 1 &amp; 3 but we never get 2 because we
didn't pack it that way so then there's
2 then I want to 1 to 2 so to 1 to 2 so
now I can just do a shuffle epi8 and I
can just get the value out directly so I
don't need to do this anymore
right in theory I can now just use the
shuffle table and extract it that way so
now if I just check I want to make sure
I'm okay here did that and actually run
yes it did um so what I can do now is
just say oh all right like stop doing
this to get to get the actual this value
out of this we don't actually need to do
it that way what we could do instead is
just produce the f30 for X T best
directly so you know delete that for now
and then we'll say that's just going to
be mm shuffle epi8 and it's gonna be out
of the shuffle table for whatever the
comp mask was and again I could have
just used the best in but I don't want
to dependent I don't want to have to
look up into the table and then use the
lookup into the table to look up into
another table I want to just look up
into both tables so I made the other
table slightly larger so I could do that
right so that's all that's going on
there so if we do an m1 28 hi there and
I say okay like when we do the shuffle
here I just want to shuffle the t4 value
that we had before so you know I want to
shuffle this thing to get my tea best
value out I don't care about this
anymore so now I just need to do this
computation this allows me to roll at
four in properly and really this now
becomes my only problem again I'm going
to take this one step at a time so to
avoid taking too many jumps right what I
can do here is just say all right let's
take this and do a convert so let's just
take the zero if value doesn't matter
which one I take let's just take the
zeroth value oops that's
not uh what did i do there shuffle table
accident you ate that should be fine
this however probably needs to be
converted so let me this is the really
annoying thing about the way they do
these this assembly stuff I I absolutely
cannot stand it in Intel land it's it's
so egregiously bad but well you have to
put in a bunch of nonsense casts for no
reason so like I've got to do this did
we make a macro for this didn't we make
like a pea chef B macro oh yeah macro x
alright so it turns out we do so we can
just do that alright um so now we just
have the problem that to terminate here
again is not what but what I'll do is
I'll go and I'll just do a convert to
get that out temporarily and this is
again just me trying to take baby steps
because I don't want to have to debug
more than I have to so I'm just making
sure that I match each time through so
now what I can do is say alright so T
terminate could now just be for wide
like there's nothing that would stop
that from happening
and
yeah
so I'm just gonna go ahead and say a
3040 terminate so I'm going to get rid
of the f32 to terminate here and I'm
just going to go ahead and keep the T
terminate this way from now on
so we're only going to do the convert
f32 on to terminate now to do the check
and everything else will not looks good
and then what I'll do is say let's get
rid of the other place we do so the
other conversion is here so that one's
pretty easy to get rid of as well the
only problem that we're now going to
have is how do we deal with this seldom
right and there's a lot of ways we can
do this you can see us looking up we've
got the best dim we know which one of
these were actually looking at so we
could continue to just table drive it
right if we want to it'd be pretty
straightforward but I just want to take
a look at it just to remind myself of
how we actually have these arranged
because you know for all I know we could
do something better there as well not
sure so hmm
let's just check that out because we're
pretty close now to have in this entire
thing be done in very few instructions
it does take some tables but the actual
amount of work being done here is it's
pretty tiny and that was the whole goal
we can also probably take care of some
get rid of some of these assertions here
because now that we're verifying the
entire table we probably don't need that
and we know asserts returned off anyway
somebody's get that out of there cuz
we're actually look at these and
furthermore we kind of know that this is
working okay because we've already
tested it but
in fact I'll move this down here so now
we have it all in one place right okay
so we look at the instructions here if
there's really not that many right and
that's pretty good so the question is
can we now just let's just loft at four
out of here because we don't want to do
that every time so if I was the left it
out of here what would it look like well
we would then not want to do this
conversion certainly right what we would
want to do instead is just do this as an
at4 plus equals right so we'd just be
doing this and now the only problem
we're gonna have is this this while I
think this actually might work okay
never mind
it's just really wrong right because it
would it's not wide anymore so and the
reason I guess it wouldn't work is
because the two should really be a three
right
so this is actually the thing that's
wrong we can fix it and just for testing
purposes just to make sure that that's
the only thing that we've got wrong here
what I can do instead is is do this
so if the best dim was to we actually
need to do you know what I can actually
sell just do it manually so we can
handle the cases separately here and
I'll just like handwrite them for now
and that will allow us to verify that
that's the only part of the code that we
then need to actually make work properly
so in the zero case we need to do
interleaved so we need to do 0 2 in the
one case we can just do one and in the
two case we have to do three right so
those are the switch cases what is the
problem
oh whoops so this sorry this seldom is
is just a regular thank you compiler
that was handy the seldom is is not it's
not that kind of a value right okay
so now we just need to like make this
work off of at for like so and I think
we're good
okay all right so now we're just left
with one more question and that's how is
this gonna work right so we need to
perform this on at four this is easy
because it's just a wide ad we've
already shuffled it so it's no big deal
but this is trickier so we need seldom
which we actually have up here right we
need sell them to be correct
- we viously need to knock out values
right so what we want to do is do a mask
and then a sub so that we only sub from
the correct channel again the easiest
way to do this would just be to do it
with a shuffle with a table I'm asking
I'm asking table right and I don't
actually know
I mean I don't know like I mean that
just might be that just might be the
easiest thing I really don't know so I'm
just gonna say like if we were to do
that and we're just super table heavy
now which you know maybe is good maybe
as bad I don't know
so if you look at what we would need to
do here effectively what we've got is
look up into this table we know for case
zero we want 0 and 2 to be masked in so
that would look like this
right we know for case 1 we just have
case 1 all right so we're just doing it
is what it is so that's a
straightforward one we know for case two
we just need to do 3 so it's it's almost
what it where it actually it's almost
its index but not quite and then we just
have 2 1 2 2 so then we just have 2 1 2
2 right so this is our luck mask table
and we can just load it in and that
would be it so that's literally just
like minus equals on at 4 we can just
write it like this we need to do an end
here to make sure that we mask it off
but other than that all we're doing is
saying seldom we'll get subtracted but
first it'll get masked right so it's
gonna get masked by maths table we'll
load off the comp mask and we'll just
say hey I guess I don't know how we cast
this thing 32 for X
not the most efficient because it's
aligned so actually that's not great but
oh well I think that's it right I think
I think that would do it and I guess
we'll find out if there's a bug there
and there is always so frustrating
so but I think otherwise I think we're
basically there right so we just need to
make sure this thing works properly we
know this does right so we can take a
look at a gnat for reference on this one
let me just double check my table to
make sure I didn't do anything too
stupid and then we'll go from there
so when we're doing this and to do the
mask outs again just want to make sure
the table lines up properly so if we're
doing zero we need to do the two I mean
once you're in here if we're doing one
we only need to do that one zero again
and - yep there's two one two - so that
I mean that looks right so I'm not sure
what the problem is there but we'll find
out so let's do this let's let's say
if we were to do a comparison between
these two so now we have the correct at
four and our at four let's just see what
they equal right so I should now be able
to set a breakpoint like here and just
compare the two and see what we get so
here's my compare value here's my actual
at four value sure does look close uh
[Music]
okay so I'm guessing there's just some
like really small difference somewhere
like do you mean so somehow doing this
will now magically make it be wrong and
yet I don't really know why so so let's
take a look at the case where it's wrong
cuz I don't know what case that is oops
what the hey oh I'm an idiot so that's a
plus equals although that should work
still what yeah maybe I don't know that
I really am an idiot I mean maybe it was
just off by like a fraction so it could
be that like because it did it in two
steps before I was off by like a low bit
right so I mean I guess technically that
means that if I just did this
everything would be fine yeah all right
so I was just off by the lichen Alice B
or something there like so you know oh
well okay so the sum total of all the
stuff we have to do is this right and
that's not fabulous I mean it's not the
end of the world but like oh that's fine
through three is probably fine but you
can see the latency on that is is high
right it's 11 cycles and the divider
sitting around 12 cycles and divider
like doing doing this thing right so
like do I want to change that to an x
the inverse you know maybe because yeah
it's it's a third latency right like
that's gonna take 11 to 12 cycles to
complete according to that right and you
know this is gonna take four so it's
like three times faster to not do that
and so the only question is like could
can we just do it because we don't care
in the dividers not doing anything
anyway or is this going to be like a
super dependent thing
and it certainly doesn't have to be but
I'm worried the compiler will do it that
way because it's dumb
so so it's a little tricky right but
what I can't say is all right so that's
pretty good you know this is this is
really nice and compact it's a little
table heavy here but otherwise it's it's
actually quite straightforward and you
know this this is just for testing right
so it's really just these is all it is
right um so like one two three four five
six seven eight nine ish 10 ish
instructions
none of which besides the divide are
particularly weird so you know but I'm a
little worried about that serial
dependency so you know here's a 12 cycle
op and then it lines up behind this
which is required to do everything else
right so that that serial dependency
chain is not it's not great right so
that's why I think that that maybe
really wants to be pre inverted right
like you just wanted to do one over that
value and then do the multiply so as the
last thing I do today maybe what I'll do
here is I'll just say like okay I if we
run oh well and you know I should
so if we run this whole situation in you
know if we run this whole thing in in
inverted mode will you know does it ruin
anything so suppose I come in here and I
say look here's the table builder that
we're using currently like the old one
and we can see that there is a divide in
here by rady what if I just change that
to a multiply by the inverse of rady you
know does anyone pitch a fit right so if
I say I've got rady here and I want in
Brady is 1 over ad right I can just
compute that value and then over here I
can just say well let's multiply by that
right so if I do that is there any is
there any noticeable like can you even
tell right Wow the answer is yes to say
the least
so that's odd and that may be because of
those imps and weird things we have in
there right so I guess I'm not sure
exactly what is happening there but
let's say I mean let's just take a look
here so when we do this let's do sort of
a safe ratio on that
so let's actually just do it more like
this
so let's actually do XYZ here let's
produce it that way and when we do this
multiplication I guess the problem that
we're gonna have here is we don't
actually want to step by that ever so
what we want here is the safe ratio
actually wants to be high right so it
actually wants to be a really high value
and I don't know exactly what we do
there we could just stuff it right we
could say like look rady X not equal to
zero or I should say just greater than
zero if it's greater than zero then it's
rady X at one point over ATX right
otherwise it's like you know some some
f/32 max or something right so we could
do it that way
or we could you could even just say look
it's it's some number that's that's way
too high to ever be the span of a cell
anyway right so no one would always hit
one of the other ones first so we could
try something like this I'm not sure if
that'll work or not but we'll see
um and that looks like it's more or less
right but it definitely has a weird bias
up here you can see it doesn't really
get out that direction so there's some
weirdness happening there and I would
imagine that has to do with the way that
I've written this Oh duh you know that's
just because we're not doing this part
yeah that was just dumb
there we go so maybe I could just have
could just do it the other way let me
just see so assuming that I do the
inversion here and we're fine that's
gonna say like that would have been I
was strange right and it's just because
I forgot we were doing that sort of
preconditioning okay so if we assume
that we're going to generate the table
that way then I could also sort of
eliminate this part of it right so now
if i went back to HH light prof and i
compile and test those two routines
against each other I should get a
failure because I'm not doing it that
way right in the second routine but now
if I pre compute my invar ad so I say
look in for ad for equals you know 1.0
divided by r ad for right and then we
change this to a multiplied by the
inverse like so then what happens right
can we get them to match now and we can
so I think that's worth doing because it
doesn't really change the quality of the
result of that much I don't think and
that makes this serial dependency chain
less bad because it doesn't have that
really bad like opt like right at the
head end so now we're pretty good you
know 1 2 3 4 5
six seven eight nine ten ten
instructions plus the lookups is it the
most fabulous thing in the world no but
like if we can trade ten instructions in
the outer loop in exchange for being
able to set arbitrarily large grid sizes
that seems like really good right all
right so let's go ahead and go to brief
Q&amp;A tomorrow we'll roll that into the
loop and we'll see what we get
because if we can roll that into the
loop without taking too much of a speed
hit then we can go widen up the thing
and being good right could you briefly
say what the focus of Hameed here was in
the last three months
sure basically what we've been doing is
streamlining and optimizing the lighting
transport code which is the hardest code
really in the whole engine so I mean
it's hard to really summarize everything
we did because a lot of it's very
specific like you know a lot of stuff
about looking at like how something is
working and what kind of spatial actions
do we wanted and how do we you know what
are the ways we can compute something
and how do we roll that into four wide
versus three wide versus blah blah blah
right so I don't know that there's much
of a summary I can say other than like
actually looking carefully at code and
optimizing it was mostly what we were
doing but the specific steps that we're
taking are pretty varied right anyway
I'm glad to hear that you're feeling
better
as a separate issue hello Casey this
question may be off topic but it's
really important for me okay I know you
were doing some UI development I saw
your video on immediate UI mode
I have the only job opportunities to
develop UI for mobile app but I've never
did that and I need this job
so can you please give me some advice on
where to find information maybe some
guys on UI development and we're using a
library um so I really can't help you
I'm afraid I don't use like all those
like mobile nonsense like web UI things
so like the job that you're gonna be
trying to get is gonna want you to know
like react j/s or something right or
whatever the latest stupid JavaScript
framework is or like some swift thing
written I mean you know nonsense code
built on giant piles of million line
libraries right and so I would probably
say if if you can since you obviously
know if since you obviously know the
company that you would be getting this
job opportunity with can you find out
what kinds of stuff they would probably
use like can you go see what sort of dev
they tend to do and then you could look
to find out what giant pile framework
they're using just go watch the like
crappy tutorial on it right because it's
just gonna be a giant pile of disaster
and as long as you're just familiarize
yourself with that pile of disaster
you'll be as good as anyone else at it
right so the only advice I can really
give you is see if you can find out what
kind of disaster pile this company uses
for their crappy mobile UI or whatever
and use you know brush up on that right
I mean with any luck you can find if
you're trying to get a job with a
company you may even be able to find
some like blog post that they've made
that says exactly what sort of stuff
they're using right and then you can
just make sure you know that
what's the best way to debug something
that only happens in optimized code I
mean I guess I don't know it's the same
as debugging stuff that happens in debug
codes just a little harder to read you
should learn to read assembly language
obviously because that's typically
pretty important because the debug
information that's output with optimized
code is usually pretty bad so you kind
of have to be able to follow you know
but how expensive do you think the table
lookups are well the well table lookups
are free you know they're they're either
one cycle or zero cycles right so
typically when you're talking about the
cost of a table lookup you're not
actually talking about about the lookup
right you're talking about either the
cost of computing and putting the offset
into a general purpose register because
SSE doesn't have scatter gather or
you're talking about the cost of the
amount of l1 cache that the table will
take up that you then can't use for
anything else right so like table
lookups don't cost anything they're free
so if you magically just had infinite l1
cache and wouldn't that be nice and you
could do scatter gather you would just
always use them if you could because
they're always free right it's just free
but the problem is that you care about
how much space they take up so you have
to be careful and getting things into
general-purpose registers costs you
something and computing that the index
may cost you something too in this case
it doesn't really cost us anything above
what we probably would
already been doing anyway but but you
mean the mob mask is not free right so
you at least have to spend the cycle
getting it out there before you can even
use it right I don't know what the
throughput of mob masks is that's not
what we're looking for so three cycles
of latency not that bad right but again
like way way way more expensive than the
table lookup right the table lookup is
either zero is just either is either
free if it's a memory operand because it
will just come with the cycle that you
issued the instruction on right
presumably and so it's actually it's
free to issue but we'll have one cycle
of work to do so you know depending on
you want to cost that so it's it's
either free or one cycle depending on
you look at it but this is three cycles
just to get the thing in there that I
need to look it up right so it's you can
see that like that the table lookup
isn't the thing usually you usually just
don't care about that if you're actually
caring about the cost of the actual
table lookup something weird is going on
usually what you care about is the fact
that the table which will be hot because
it's always getting looked up into over
over and over and over and over and over
and over again however big that table is
it's just sitting in your l1 and you're
that's you're using that amount that you
can't get back right because now your l1
size that you're using for everything
else is now smaller so if you magically
have 128 K of tables all of a sudden
that you've created you've blown out
your l1 and your l2 well at least part
of your l2 and everything's way slower
now
because your tables are taking up all of
your cash right so so it's really more
about about that you know it's it's it's
really not about it's usually not about
the cost of the lookup can you give a
general idea of how to optimize branches
out of a function yeah just go look at
we've done that on Hamming here like a
bunch times right the concepts very
simple you just compute both branches
and then mask the results together based
on the comparison right so if you have
you know I mean another way to look at
it would be
we even did it today so we did a more
complicated version which is using a
table to produce the results usually you
can get by most things you can get by
with just doing a mask
combined but I mean this was the code we
needed to execute right it's three
branches if you know the first time
through the second time through the
third time through the loop we just
replace it with a move mask and a table
right so now there's no branches in here
somebody you watched me do it right so
it's basically just the process of
turning things that used to be branches
into computations that still produce the
same result by just doing the work that
would have happened on all the branches
and making sure that the equation
multiplies those out or masks those out
right and that's it
hello thank you for all the vids I'm
aboard see a student that aces hampson
tapped us know what to do when say
keishon alright cool
well glad we could help what kinds of
things would you like the compiler to do
to help with this table stuff if any
John's compile time code execution is
pretty good because I just write the
code that generated this table instead
of generating the table right do you
swim the compiler excuse me haven't
tried yeah it's it runs the code at
compile time but male hash be suitable
to create a custom UUID it wouldn't be
part of the UID spec but it could serve
the same purpose not sure what you mean
by UUID
alright I'm gonna I'm gonna end it here
I should say we'll end there thank you
everyone for joining me for this sort of
handmade here at San oppose recording
with us always if you would like to
follow on the series at home you can
always go to handmade hero org and
pre-order the game because it comes with
a source code already so you can play
around with it as we are doing it
I pretty much set you up for success
today if you want to go make the routine
stop tape being table-driven and start
actually just running the grid steps
directly because I just did all the work
and so all we need to do is just now go
import that work up into the actual grid
Walker so it stops reading from the
table and just calculates the stuff in
line so you could do that if you were so
inclined so think about it that's about
it for today I'll be back here tomorrow
to do exactly that so see if you can
beat me to it
until then have fun programming everyone
and I'll see you on the Internet tegus
everybody