start recording here we go ladies and
gentlemen welcome to handmade Hero the
show where we code a complete game live
on twitch no engines no libraries just
us and our cross-compiling kettlebell
lifting selves it is time right now for
us to get back to our lighting
computations we have a bunch of work to
do today so I'm gonna get right into it
if you are trying to follow along at
home please keep in mind today is Magic
Day 100 that makes things complicated
because at day 100 I am bifurcating the
two zip files they say every hundred
days I make a new zip file so that the
zip doesn't go out of control so
basically if you're trying to find a 99
remember it's in the 0 to 99 zip not in
the hundreds of 199 zip so that's that's
a little bit weird there so you got to
go unzip day 99 out of that out of the
old source if if you want to follow
along today everyone from now on will be
in the in the hundred 199 until we get
through the next hundred days but
assuming that you got all that under
control
let's go ahead and get things started
now where we were where we left off
yesterday is we had sort of started to
get our reflection stuff working and as
you can see we actually did what we were
trying to do which is get our reflection
or environment maps showing up based on
the normals but what we had not done yet
and what I didn't want to start doing
because we you know we had kind of
gotten to a stopping point we only had
five minutes left in the stream well I
did not get chance to do was actually
implement any kind of code that tries to
compute a reflection vector and as a
result their reflection intersection
code not running since that doesn't run
it means that we just get a flat version
of this in here because we're not
actually doing anything other than just
verifying that we can look up into it so
what I wanted to do today is just kind
of go over how that reflection code
works with you and then go ahead and try
to implement that if we can for the rest
of the stream so that's all we're really
doing today and that's the majority of
what we have left to do for our actual
normal mapping code before we optimize
it there's really not a whole lot else
to do
mostly the rest of the stuff in lighting
has to do with how we actually compute
the environment maps that were sampling
into so let's go over to the blackboard
for a second and just kind of go over
quickly here on day 100 what we're
trying to do okay so that you can
understand the math that we're trying to
simulate in here part of it is very
straightforward and part of its a little
less straightforward just because of
sort of like I said there's a little bit
of happiness that has to go on with 2d
lighting so we can't just implement
things directly but for the first parts
is very direct and quite simple so if
you remember I drew a bunch of diagram
so we were talking about lighting and
they all looked like this right they all
had some surface right and they had an
eye that was looking at them actually I
think I typically drew it this way where
there here was the eyeball right there's
our little eyeball I don't know where
the eyelashes go maybe they go there I
guess right there's our eyeball and we
also have our light source right and
what I was saying was that well what
happens is you know the light source and
the eye they sort of form this this kind
of this kind of Bounce here right and
what I was what I was saying is that
most surfaces right if they're highly
reflective a highly reflective surface
what you're going to see when you look
at it the light most strongly reflects
out in the direction that it would if it
was literally like a ball that was
bouncing off of it right it's a pure
reflection so like this angle and this
angle are the same angle okay and then
what happens as you get into surfaces
that are less and less diffused is
actually you start seeing much more
light so you start seeing light that's
that's that much further off that angle
right like so it starts to be collecting
more of like a cone of light out here
and then the backscatter still does tend
to be less so you know as you get closer
and Glosser you're talking about sort of
widening that cone and so that's not by
any means a physically based lighting
model it's just an approximation to one
a physically based lighting model again
actually takes some kind of functions
that are actual approximations to the
real lighting transfer of the surface
like we talked about in the lighting
show but for most surfaces
we can sort of approximate them in some
way that's good enough for our 2d
approximation by just sort of having
that that sort of simple trade-off right
by just saying okay we're just gonna say
we either take just that direct
reflection if we want or we start taking
wider and wider versions and we talked
about how we might do those wider
versions by sampling out of texture maps
that have been blurred right lighting
lighting environment and bird learn so
for all of the lighting that we want to
do we're basically just going to
concentrate on this very simple setup
that we have here which is the straight
reflection model right sort of this
concept that wherever I'm looking I want
to see lights that are directly you know
that sort of directly come out from
there right so I want to be able to
compute this now this is exactly like
what we did with collision detection
right so if you if you remember when we
did collision detection it's exactly the
same kind of equation where we want to
take a surface which has a normal which
is here right we want to take a surface
as a normal and we want to take a vector
such as this vector to the eye and we
want to produce a vector that's very
similar to that vector only it goes like
in the exact opposite direction or
something right so basically you know
it's got like the same Y component
relative to the surface right but its X
component is negated right again
relative to the surface if this was the
X and y axis this would be trivial you
just negate the actually be done but of
course it isn't and so we have to do a
little bit more work to figure out what
it actually is but it's the exact same
math as collision detection so if you
remember from that it should be very
straight forward let's go ahead and do
it
supposing we have a vector from the
point we're computing out to the eye
here is the eye right so whatever that
vector is let's say that's our I've
Ector that's e right
I apologies to Euler who likes to
reserve that for his number so suppose
we have a vector e that goes out to the
eye right and we want to compute this
vector over here which I gotta know
we'll call it our son vector for our
sampling vector s so off it goes out to
there right so we want to compute
from E right and what we know is we
basically know that all we really need
to do use name
all we really need to do here is we need
to be able to sort of produce this this
negated version of the vector now
remember this is sort of technically in
full 3d if we want to conceptualize it
that way right so really when we're
looking at it like this right we're
really looking at some arbitrary vector
here that's like that and we want to
produce the arbitrary one here and and
it may have you know coordinates on both
XY and Z right we're not so we're not
restricting ourselves to the bounce in
the plane but the bounce itself kind of
always does happen in a plane right you
can always pick a plane that contains
like these three points right so it's
it's about that's happening in a plane
but we don't really know what the plane
is okay so this is not necessarily the X
the Y and the Z right this is just the
normal and we don't really have any
coordinates for the plane that we're
bouncing off because it can be any plane
anywhere in the world so all we have is
the normal and the point right and we
then have that eye vector and we want to
produce our s vector so what we can do
is if we just again negate that a vector
right if we do gate that eave Ector this
is how we did it with the collision
detection right if we but if we have a
vector that essentially points exactly
the same direction as s everything we
want about s is true only instead of
going back out instead of bouncing out
of the plane its penetrating into the
plane going into the plane then all we
have to do is figure out how to you know
pick that back up again and this is that
that normal dot product of thing that we
use for collision detection it's the
exact same thing that we do there right
because what we end up with is we end up
with if we if we come back to our 2d
slice right if we take that eye and we
just look at what the negation is to the
eye right so we have this is negative e
down here right we can see that all we
really need to do is figure out what
this vector is right what's that vector
right there and add two of it in because
if we add two of that vector in it will
first bring us up to the plane where we
bounced off of and then it will bring us
up to the point that we actually want
for our sampling vector right and what
is this vector right
well we know the length of this vector
right it's just the it's just whatever
he was right in fact we don't even have
to think about negative e we know how
long this vector is because that's just
how ever long e was dotted to n right so
if we have a transpose n if we have that
that tells us how long this is right and
we just want to add two of those along
the N direction right so we just want
two of those along the N direction
that's all we really need to do to take
our negative e write and produce that
that result right so so if we have
negative E Plus this vector that will
produce that bounce that we want right
and again this is a purely geometric I
didn't do this in an algebraic way this
is a purely geometric construction I
just looked at the diagram and decided
what I wanted to do and produce the
equation for it there's probably other
ways you could think about doing this
where you you could sort of do this in a
more algebraic way right you could
imagine saying something like I want the
result to be the same dot product on n
as the original but I want it to have
the dot product with itself B I don't
think of how I would say that the dot
product with itself would be negative 1
or negative the length you know I I
don't want to actually try to do it now
because this is one of the things I'd
have to kind of sit there and scratch my
head for a while to figure out exactly
the right way to phrase it
mathematically to solve but you could do
that right you could come up with some
if you're an algebra centric person you
should be able to look at this diagram
and come up with some rules that you
want this result to obey and then solve
for it I tend to use geometry most of
the time because it's faster for my
brain I don't have to sit there
scratching my head for a little while
but some people work better with algebra
and so I don't really want to discourage
that on the screen stream I just I can't
be I can't lead by example there because
as soon as I have to downshift to
algebraic solving I go much slower so
anyway this is roughly what we wanted
the question is just how do we actually
set ourselves up to do this and so let's
go look at the code where is my I didn't
open Emacs it I did not open Emacs yet
it would appear so I guess yeah
I guess we just don't have an Emacs
window open so let's open any Mac's
window so we can go over there to our
code here we go and when we have our
draw a rectangle slowly code you
remember where we have this stuff happen
and we have a little to do here which is
like actually compute a bounce based on
the viewer direction so there's our
there's our oh man I'm out of tea
already and Romanelli like 15 minutes
into the programming that's no good
that's no good at all anyway hmm so if I
want to replace this to do here what I
need to do is put that stuff in then I
just talked about what we're gonna need
as per our diagram is we're gonna need
the I've Ector that goes and we're gonna
need the normal now the normal we have
right because we have our normal map
which is all we really need but we don't
have that eye vector so we need to
figure out a way to figure out what you
know where our eye is kind of looking
and this is actually particularly tricky
for 2d games because we don't actually
have a rigorous definition for it now I
know this sounds a little bit strange
but if you think about it the problem
with 2d games is they don't typically
end up being actually perspective so you
know if you were to think about what
would happened I guess I didn't quite
finish what I needed to draw to tell you
everything if you think about the screen
as being like kind of this monitor
sitting in front of you right and you
think about you being back here looking
at it right if we want to talk about
sort of that midline so here's that
here's the center point right and we
talk about this midline you know any
point that I'm looking at on the screen
we do know a vector that would be sort
of a perspective vector that would be
how I'm looking at this point in space
right but the thing that's kind of
confusing is that our game isn't in
perspective right our game does have
like an orthographic feel to it the way
we were drawing things where you know
a tree looks the same on either side of
the screen so a tree that's here looks
the same as a tree that's over here
which is not how perspective works how
perspective works is you would see more
of this side of the tree over here and
you would see more of this side of the
tree over here you can verify this to
yourself really easily just by looking
at your own monitor you can see the
inside of the bezel on the left-hand
side of the skirt of the thing right and
the inside of the bezel on the
right-hand side as well even those those
are two opposite sides of that bezel
shape right you know your your sort of
your ability to perceive things is is
kind of warped in that way by the
perspective so you're not seeing the
same sides of objects you're seeing
different sides of them depending on
where they are right and you know
another sim exam will be hold up
something in front of you and I'm here
if I'm if I'm holding it on this side I
can see this this part of it right and
if I move it to this side that part is
now occluded and I can see this part
right but that's not what we see when we
do most 2d games especially kinds with
hand-drawn art right what we see is just
that sprite is doesn't work as it moves
across and it's kind of like this
orthographic style projection that we
use so in order to figure out what our
I've Ector is it suggests at least to me
that if we were going to stay
orthographic then what we actually want
to do is pretend always that the that
the vector to the eye is pointing
straight out of the screen right and so
what that means is as if you were to
move this if you're to scroll the screen
left and right you wouldn't see
reflections on objects change but if the
object themselves moved left to right
you would see reflections on the change
does that make sense I hope it does and
I think I want to do that because that
keeps our visual grammar consistent it
doesn't mix two different things
together and I think that might be
better for the overall look of the game
because it feels a little weird use
perspective reflections when the art is
not itself perspective that just seems
like a bad idea
so what that means is we're going to go
ahead and
make the the z-axis right which is
pointing straight on up out of the
screen that is our eye right and so what
that means is our Z you know our our
I've Ector right he's essentially just
pointing straight up it's pointing
straight up back at us now that confers
on us some optimization potential as
well because if you think about that if
we're going to do operations with that
and we know that it's only got the Z
involved that allows us to do some
things that are much more
straightforward right
so we might want to think about doing
that just you know a little
quote-unquote premature optimizations
here we could totally do that if we
wanted to because if you think about
what happens here this equation right
negative E + 2 e transpose in and well e
transpose anything is just going to be
the z coordinate of that thing right I
mean that's just a given because if I
take the dot product right do you
remember what the dot product is right
so ii x ey ez right dotted with n x + y
NZ right equals e^x NX + ey + y + e z NZ
right that's what happens right so if
i'm priy saying that these two are
always going to be 0 because it's
pointing straight out the what the i've
Ector is right
if those two are both 0 then i know and
this is 1 then i already know what this
is before i actually have to do any work
to actually compute it right I know that
the X goes away I know that the Y goes
away and I knew that the EZ is actually
1 right so the only thing we actually
need is the NZ right so this equation is
actually just negative e + 2 NZ x n
right and furthermore what that means is
the negative e we also know that that's
just subtracting 1 from the Z so it's
really just 2 n ZN right like this it's
that vector whatever that vector is
having one subtracted from it z right
- this that's it that would be the
entirety of can
shooting this now if you notice there's
something pretty darn interesting there
which is that if we want to standardize
on this completely what that means is if
we wanted to we could actually get rid
of all this math and just priests or
this directly in our normal map right
because since we know what all of this
is we actually could just go ahead and
make our normal map store to nzn right
instead of storing an actual normal
right so we have options there and it
depends on what ends up being true
because there's reasons why we might not
want to do that there's because we can't
use the squared the the square root
trick to to store only two components
potentially at that point you know
there's there's other reasons why we
might not want to do it but it's just
worth noting that that's very simple and
so if we take a look at what actually
happens here I'm gonna go ahead and say
here I the the I vector is always
assumed to be you know zero zero one
pointing straight up out of the screen
right and so in order to compute that
bounce what we need to figure out is we
need to figure out using what our
negative e to ends en is so to NZ n is
pretty easy we have the normal right
right there and so it's just going to be
the normal Z two times the normal z
times normal X Y Z that's that term
right that we're adding in and then the
vector that we're starting with again is
it's just going to be 0 0 1 so we're
just gonna subtract 1 from that Z
component so this is our you know our
our bounce direction like like so our
bounce directions Z is going to be
subtracting negative 1 from that I'll
even put in here this is just the
simplified version of negative E Plus 2
oops
I'm going to be plus 2 e transpose
and and right the reflection and so
we're gonna go ahead and do that and
that looks about right
so that computes that that other normal
that we're using there right and so
trying to think if there's anything else
that has to happen there I don't I don't
know if there is I think that's about it
so anyway we'll take a look at that a
little more closely later when we step
into this but after that once we have
that bounce direction that bounce
direction I believe just needs to get
past in here so so we got a couple
things we need to do there first of all
we need to say that this is actually
that's direction right and I think
that's we're not sampling from that at
all yet so that's that's really all we
have to do is pass it in here and then
we have to go ahead and do the second
part of our math so this is actually the
this is the sample direction right and
the screen space UV tells us where we
were so now we have to do the second
part which is this intersection math we
can quickly compile this and see what
happens although this it's probably now
will allow illegal results so we may get
an assertion in there if we actually do
that but you know why not we'll just run
it anyway worst that happens is it
asserts let's see here Z there we go
so there it is it actually did not
assert it works okay and so you can kind
of see that's you know it's starting to
get some of that reflectivity in there
but again we haven't actually done the
part that actually does the sampling
properly so we're not quite there yet so
we're but you can sort of see it
starting to round out a little bit which
is nice that probably suggests we didn't
mess up our math too terribly much but
now we have to do the second part so
let's talk about the second part and the
second part is a little nasty because it
involves a fudge factor
as people are commonly fun fond of
saying write a fudge factor the the
thing that's problematic about fudge
factors is that they sound good right
they sound good because at least if
you're not using the scatological
determinant of fudge and you're actually
talking about the stuff that they sell
it in tourist towns for some reason they
sell in all tourist towns because fudge
is tasty but it's actually bad so but
you actually probably want to think
about the scatological fudge when you
think about fudge factor not the like
tourist fudge so think think scat fudge
not tourists fudge right because fudge
factors tend to be bad and the reason
that they tend to be bad is because you
have no idea what they should be set to
and you don't really know much about
their behavior a lot of times right when
you're simulating something using real
world stuff using real world physics
using real world values you kind of know
what they should be and so you can put
in things that you know what they should
be and if it doesn't work you know you
have a bug but when you have a fudge
factor in there you don't know maybe you
just set the fudge factor wrong right
and so it makes debugging a lot harder
when you've got these sort of arbitrary
constants in there that said do they
happen yes do you have to be comfortable
them yes even the most advanced physics
papers often times will have constants
pulled out of thin air in there I am NOT
making this up you can go I was reading
one the other day in fact about
vorticity confinement in fluid dynamics
and sure as the day is long there are
constants that they just flat-out pulled
out of nowhere and this is in like
helicopter vortex simulation literature
right and it's like they're just like
full-on like I don't know here's a
here's a value that we made up it seems
to work and you're like alright great so
yeah don't feel bad about using them
because even the most hardcore math
stuff still tends to use them
unfortunately but do be aware that they
do have these pitfalls so you do try to
want to limit the amount of fudge
factoring you have in your code if you
can so there where is the fudge factor
well here's the problem we
got a screen and we've got a point on
the screen and so if you think about
what's happening now we're thinking
about that screen as being sort of this
flat plane in the world and then we've
got some map up in the world or Spur
haps below in the world depending on the
circumstance and what we want to do is
we want to sample into that map okay so
we've got a direction and we want to
know from this point if we walk in this
direction along the direction is
pointing we're on the upper map we will
hit okay now this is a straightforward
math thing to do and we will do it in a
second but in fact we've already done it
in collision detection collisions action
keeps coming up right but you remember
this we've done this Ray when does a ray
intersect a plane we've done this before
but the problem that we have here is we
don't know how far this is right we have
no idea how far this is because it's
just kind of made-up lighting stuff so
you know we can try to setting it to how
far above the ground we want the sky to
appear to be I don't really know but at
some level we probably don't want that
because then when we get to the edge of
the map it would be a problem there's
there's just a lot of fudging in here
look we don't even really know how big
we want this thing to be right we might
want this thing to be larger than the
world so that stuff that samples near
the edge will still be able to hit it
okay so there's just it's nasty so we've
got some problems here but let's just
assume let's assume that we will handle
those fudge-packers somehow so what we
really just need to know is given some
definition of these things how can we
compute this well let's start off with
the most simple observation that we have
here which is that if we assume we know
how far we are traveling so we assume we
know our Z distance right we'll call
this this one Z and this would be right
if we assume we know our dizzy distance
then really all we need to do is figure
out something that'll tell us how far we
would be displaced
right in the normal excellent because
we've really got do you think about this
normal right this normal has a few
different components it's got two
components in the plain right in fact
you could think of it mapping down like
this it's got chicken poets in the plane
the X and the y in terms of this plane
right and then it's got this other one
that's the Z right that's its z-axis
component so what we can think about is
just in terms of its X&amp;Y
right how far would they how far would
it displace it us from this point if we
you know traveled as far as it takes us
in Z along this thing to get here right
and that's a pretty easy thing to do
because even without thinking about it
much you can see we've already kind of
constructed some similar triangles here
right we have some length of this thing
that is pointing up towards the thing we
want to go to and we're saying we have
some fudge factor which says how far
away it is right we'll call that f4
fudge right f is for fudge right we have
some some F that says what it is all we
need to know is how many of those how
many of those Z components would it take
to get there right so if we call that Z
it's just F over Z right it's all we're
doing we're just saying how many of
those would it take to get up here that
is the coefficient that we would need to
figure out how far we would travel along
the x and y of that normal map right now
of course it's a little confusing
because we have to first think about
whether we're looking down or whether
we're looking up because we had ones
down here as well so we need to take all
of that into account but this is the
only quantity that we actually need to
produce once we produce that we just
multiply that by the components of the
normal that are in the plane and that
gets us where we would be sampling where
what the displacement is from our
location where we would be sampling
right so yeah assuming screen aligned
stuff which there's actually going to
probably be a problem with and so we'll
have to introduce some things to deal
with it but assuming screen analyze
stuff for now the reason I say ice cream
assuming screen
stuff is just like I said we may want
this to be larger and so then the
coordinates we're looking up into this
will not be coincident with the
coordinates for looking up with this
there'll be a subset so there'd really
be another fudge factor right there's
this fudge factor and then there's like
there's a fudge Z and a fudge X or
something like that right which says how
big this thing is and you really only
need to store one of them you like to
store there they're multiple they're
then multiplied together or whatever
right so it doesn't come it doesn't
affect our performance at all that that
would happen but it does add yet more of
that sort of fuzziness that we have to
be wary of so that's why I say this
part's not going to be so clean and easy
it's a little bit nastier but we'll do
the best that we can given the
circumstances so we passed that vouch
direction in here and when we passed
that bounce direction what I'd like to
do is I'd like to set us up for success
by assuming that the bounce direction
always is going in the direction of the
map that it's trying to sample from
right and we know that all of our
normals are pointing up at us and so
what I'd like to do is say all right
we've got this bounce direction and so
now what we're going to do is since
we're not using the normal anymore right
it's our bounce direction that's going
to take into account whatever it is that
we're actually looking at here and I am
trying to remember so oh right it's the
Y it's the Y that tells us whether we're
going down
or whether we're going up which which
one of those two that were we're
sampling towards right and it's going to
be our our z axis that ends up being the
Y it seems like so I wonder if we should
just pre store our normals a little more
sensibly here that's that's kind of well
I don't know we can't really because at
some level we sort of have to
yeah yeah all right let's think this
through a little bit because we have
another problem here which is that
assuming that the normals are actually
all in this space or they correctly in
the space then this all works too as
well I just want to make sure this is
working correctly so if this is pointing
out at me we did treat that as our Z Z 0
0 1 in normal space is pointing back at
us so I guess it should be fine all
right I guess it should be fine
so our TN map is actually going to be
based on that bounce direction right not
the normal because we're trying to use
whatever direction we're sampling in now
we're getting rid of that normal
I suppose that's something we should
have tried here as well you can see
that's still you know it's it's getting
closer but still not quite there yet so
when we do that sampling we're gonna use
that Y and then what we need to do is
say all right if we're sampling from the
bottom map right then our normal is
pointing down in other words it's it's
it's got a why that is is negative right
whereas here it's got a Y that is
positive okay and given those two things
we don't want to have to deal with we
don't want our bounce Direction to have
to account for that I'm trying to think
of how to explain this we want the
sample environment map function to not
have to care whether the normal was
pointing negative Y or positive Y we
want to assume that Y was always
positive because this code right here
has already handled whatever needed to
happen in terms of picking a different
map for which one it is so we want them
all to look the same as if you're just
looking up at the sky even though
sometimes you're looking down at the
ground so all we want to do is say oh ok
if you were looking at that map let's go
ahead and make the bounce direction Y
let's make that equal to the negative so
that we're always talking about an
upwards pointing sample does that make
sense and so here we go with that again
nothing particularly odd there although
again we've got plenty of issues to deal
with but so we've got our bounce
Direction Y and now that's negative that
doesn't affect the magnitude of the
bounce direction at all right it just
changes which way it's pointing and so
then we can go over to sample
environment map and start to actually
figure out what we want to do
so again we've got that sample direction
we're seeing is that our why is the
thing that determines how far along we
go that's just because of the way we've
encoded these maps so we want to take
that why that sample direction why and
we want to assume that why can't be 0
and the reason that we know why can't be
0 is because we've already sort of
nullified that out in here right we've
said already that why can't point to the
side because if it points to the side
it's gonna have to go which only only
this guy goes to the side and we're
gonna have to do some some things with
this to be sure this is in fact I can
delete this because this is more of it
to do how do we sample from the middle
map and I don't know so anyway we've
we've got that that why we can assert
essentially that it's not know that it's
not 0 we could we can assert that Y is
greater than 0 right and we should never
get that case and we don't right so
that's good and then what we need to do
is we need to compute that quotient that
sort of coefficient so our coefficient
is first we have our fudge factor here
is our fudge factor f like we said I
don't know how far away that should
actually be you know let's say that it's
that it's I don't know a meter away for
now not probably a particularly good
value but let's say it's a meter away we
have our coefficient that we need to
compute which is that sample direction
why we're going to take the fudge factor
and divide it by the sample Y and that
will produce our offset for us right and
our offset is going to be that
coefficient times the vector that is the
other components of this now again the X
for our normal goes in the X direction
and we were saying that the sort of the
Z for our normals goes in the z
direction if you will right that goes in
the in the y direction if you will right
again total hackage but that's just how
we encoded them so that as things kind
of twist properly we will you know we'll
sort of pick up short of circular region
around the ground and I guess the sample
direction z
when we go through our coordinate stuff
I'm gonna put to do in here make sure we
know what direction Z should go in why
cuz we may want we've made that may need
to be inverted as well depending on how
we choose to encode these maps but since
we haven't gone through and do it on our
coordinate system past that's going to
be a bit of an issue so once we have
that offset that's going to give us the
offset in meters right from whatever
that point is that we that we're at and
so that's when we then say okay from the
location from our screen space UV right
our screen space you via these T X's do
we actually do bilinear sample LOD X Y
are these t XC y these are in pixels so
we actually have to do a little more
work here right we need to first compute
RP and then multiply out to the size of
the map that we're actually sampling so
it's going to be something you know
along the lines of where is that code
it's gonna be something along the lines
of this code right here right where
we're actually computing the you I'm
sorry not that code this this code right
here where we're computing out how far
we go in U and V right in fact this is I
guess exactly what we would want to do
this is the code that we actually need
here so what we need to do is we need to
take our LOD we need to map that out
like so and then we'll talk about how we
compute this U and V in a second from
the offset I just want to get this in
here so we take that T X and T Y we want
to blow that out to the size of the
texture and we want to clamp it because
again we could be sampling outside so T
X is going to be equal to clamp 0 1 TX
and so is so it's T Y right and now I'll
just prevent us from sampling outside
the texture map so really all we need to
do now is figure out what that UV is so
this will actually be our UV coordinate
so if you'll just do it this way you be
x ug y and that's gonna be our offset
excuse me that's going to be our offset
plus wherever we were in screen space
within the screen space you'd be right
but the offset again this in fact we can
just do it exactly where we did it here
but our C essentially has to have some
scaling value because remember this is
in meters and so we need to convert our
meters to UVs and so there's something
here that's like you know meters to UV
right or you v's per meter kind of a
thing right and UVs per meter whatever
that is that actually needs to get
multiplied in here as well right so that
you can convert between those two spaces
so if we do that whoa that's not good if
we do that we're not quite we're not
getting anything hold on a second
I think our UV stir meter is probably
much too high there right that it should
probably be something more like like
that but we'll have a step do this to
figure out what we're doing wrong here
because I suspect we're doing other
things wrong than just that um I have to
think about how many you v's per meter
are there I guess it's something like
because if that map was the whole screen
yeah I don't know I love to think about
that but anyway so this is actually a
set of our fudge factor I should
probably call this what actually is
which is distance to map or like height
of map off screen or whatever something
like that height of map
distance from map and Z let's just call
it that this is from napkin Z all right
and so I think we've got everything in
here we just have to debug it we are
producing oh that's that's probably most
of the problem there as well we need to
actually clamp these guys because I
actually wanted to clamp the UVs not the
results that would explain why that was
happening all right and that's getting
pretty close right you can see that
we're now sort of getting roughly some
reflection stuff in there I think it's a
little premature to declare victory but
you can sort of see where we're going
with this right we're starting to get to
the point where you can see an actual
reflection in there I also I'm going to
go ahead and introduce a little bit of
motion in there too so we can kind of
just see where we're at at the moment
let's go ahead and and come in here to
our to our call that actually calls
coordinate system so we've got our disk
in here I'm gonna add disk back in and
we were computing disk somewhere and
then aware of disk was actually getting
completed I guess we actually aren't oh
no we are there we go
so you can kind of see we're starting to
get where we want to be but we're not
quite there yet right you know you can
you can see that you're kind of getting
a little bit of a rolling reflection
here this guy looks like he's reflecting
kind of backwards so I think we've got
some bugs on on the sort of downside on
the on the underneath side maybe the way
I negated that Y was not actually legal
I'll have to think about whether that's
correct or not but we're getting you
know a little bit closer here right and
again this is very expensive I can also
for now turn off our maps we we are
completely unoptimized at the moment
which is a problem I guess I could also
do for purposes of this I could also
give us that nice compiler boost here
let's see
-
Oh Oh - mmm God you gotta love
optimizing the optimizing compiler huh
or maybe we should just say man it's
it's kind of crazy how bad the debug
build is but yeah um so you can kind of
see that light now that it's it's
animating a little more quickly you can
kind of see how that light is playing
off there but again I think that that
bottom reflection should be curving this
way and it's not so we've got definitely
a bug in how we were treating that that
flip so let's take a look at that we
also have you can see we're sampling
sort of right at that edge where the
normals
I think that's prompt that to be honest
that might just be because we made the
normals at the edge point straight back
I don't know if you remember that so
that may actually have more to do with
it that may not actually be a bug of
ours that may be just because we don't
we need to fix the normals so that we
don't have
when this where the sphere is not
actually there we're not we're not doing
the wrong thing so yeah I feel like that
that seems reasonable now I'm wondering
- I feel like one question I have is is
aren't these supposed to be pointing
directly back shouldn't we see some
checkerboard though in the area here I
wonder I wonder why we're not because
we're not that seems that seems a little
broken I feel like we've got I feel like
we've got a bug there potentially I'm a
little nervous about that and I'm not
sure not sure what to say about that I
think I think something's a little wonky
because if it just was all zero zero one
who is all pointing directly back
towards us Oh No right because directly
towards us is not up towards the sky
right right right right so if you think
about it I'm this is my first time ever
doing lighting
that's by the way so it's all stuff that
I have to think about for the first time
right so the way that we're encoding
things right pointing up and pointing
down actually Z straight back at you is
in that special sampling plane because
it's not pointing towards the sky right
it's pointing in that in that other
plane so really what we should have done
if we wanted straight up pointing
vectors is we should have made those
point those straight up pointing vectors
instead of being 0 0 1 they actually
should have been 0 1 0 right so so back
here if we were to go into the thing
that actually makes that normal map let
me down can't actually see my mini
buffer if we were to go into thing that
that makes the sphere what was that
normal Maps fear makes fear normal map
makes there we go so it makes for a
normal map what we had is we were sort
of doing something I believe where we
would just yeah this would be our
default normal I think that is actually
probably what we want as our default
normal which would point straight up at
the sky that would make a little bit
more sense in terms of being able to
look at what's going on so I'm gonna go
ahead and and and try that and then
restart so it'll regenerate our texture
maps and see if that does anything
well I still it's not so it's still not
showing me what I think it should show
me I feel like it should show me a it
should show me the checkerboard here
still getting reflected a little bit
right because this is basically like a
mirror right with a bump in it and so I
kind of want to go see why we are having
that that that problem are we actually
using alpha from a sphere some like what
is actually how are we and and for that
matter why are we getting sort of
spherical shading on well I guess
yeah all right I'm a little confused
I'll be honest with you I don't really
know why so I'm gonna go ahead and
usually if you don't know why that's
probably a good indication that you
should be stepping into the bugger
because well you've got something to
learn and so let's go ahead and learn
something
we hope let's go into that that render
call it looks like we don't have it up
here draw a rectangle slowly let's go
ahead and run there and I just want to
see I want to understand a little bit
about what's going on here so when we
come in here and we sample this normal
map what I just want to see what's going
on so so let's see what our first normal
is and so that normal is basically
pointing right up at at the sky like we
thought so I feel like this should be
the first pixel to right like that
should be what it is so let's take a
look at what we compute for our bounce
direction all right let's see what our
bounce Direction is and so our bounce
Direction here is going to be okay
okay I this is very fascinating so it's
actually that's actually understandable
- so if it was pointing perfectly up we
would be looking exactly oblique to it
which means that our reflection to it we
would not it would really not reflect at
all be like holding a mirror sideways
and looking at it right so if we want to
reflect upwards we still need some
degree of tilt to the mirror right and
so yeah I guess I guess now that I think
about it that actually makes some sense
we should still step through some of
this because I have other stuff that I
want to look at but that actually makes
perfect sense and I think about it
there's really just me being kind of
blunt so what we actually want to do
yeah is we'd actually want to say okay
you know let that normal term be
something that's that's maybe half y
half Z or something like that right
that's sort of angled upwards so
something like this but it needs to be
normalized obviously and so what I want
to do is say I don't know can I do
squirt and here can I do the square root
I wanted to square root of one plus one
let me do that right okay and then can I
do
can I do one over square root of one
plus one over there it is so I just want
the normalized version of that I guess I
don't know what does that come out in
here yeah there it is
I just want that value right so there's
my normalized normal that's pointing
sort of half y half Z let me see if that
gives us more of what I was expecting
yeah that's that's more what I was
expecting right and so if I go ahead and
make make us go at o2 here that that is
the sphere right that is the reflective
sphere so yeah I'm
certain that our reflection code is
quite working correctly yet but we're
getting close right we're getting closer
to a working reflection and so that's a
good thing
but we have a ways to go before before
we're done we only have five minutes
left
I'm going to go ahead and inspect sort
of that blue code again we've got a you
know we we've got kind of a in fact I
can go ahead in there put this back down
here I just want to kind of take a look
at what's going on with those
reflections to see if I can't figure out
what we're doing wrong there otherwise
we'll make that the topic of tomorrow so
if we take a look here if we if we just
don't do the top map right the top maps
go on we just get the red so the top map
is the blue map the sky map is the one
that's wrong at the moment and the
question is why is it you know why is it
sampling oddly like that right and I
guess I don't know right I guess I'm not
sure why that actually is the case it's
almost like it wants you know us to do
that that bounce to it it wants us to do
some kind of negation and I'm not sure
why that would be so this is the one
we're passing through the bass direction
right and then we're going ahead and
computing where we're hitting on that
map yeah I don't know I'm probably gonna
have to step through this I think yeah I
think I'm gonna save that for tomorrow
because I'm gonna want to step to this
fairly meticulously because since we're
also doing that solve on the other side
I feel like it's probably one of those
things where yeah where it's gonna in
fact I wonder if in general the bounce
is wrong and really you know what you'd
want to do here is it's actually this
negation or something like that where
it's it's actually supposed to be
negated the whole way so I want to think
through this a little bit more I feel
like we got its feel like it's just not
rigged enough rigorous enough
the moment and so I'm gonna say tomorrow
is going to be stepping through this and
making sure we think about exactly how
everything goes before we call that
before we call that good but we're very
close so that's good so I'm gonna go
ahead and go to the Q&amp;A right like so
and yeah please try to keep your
questions to be ones that that are about
we did on today's stream so that we can
keep things on topic as much as possible
if you want to ask off-topic questions
please come during one of the pre
streams so show up maybe 15 minutes
early tomorrow show up at 4:45 tomorrow
and that's when I
I typically Ansel answer off-topic
questions
yeah
you could try creating a normal map with
a more predictable reflection other than
a sphere is what like what I'm trying to
think of what would have the most
predictable reflection I guess maybe a
waffling surface like a like something
that was like up and then down and then
up and then down or something like that
I don't know I'm not sure what is a very
um what is the more predictable
reflectable surface spheres are usually
pretty good for debugging lighting stuff
because they show you the full yeah the
full set of course I just realized why
we get the attenuation here that's
because of the end map probably the end
map blending coefficients probably
helping there maybe although that's
pointing up so now that shouldn't be
true I don't know I got to think about
it some more it's awfully confusing hmm
we got bugs let's put it that way
tomorrow we'll find them
is the y-axis correctly set in the
normal map well it depends what you mean
by correctly so right now we it's
actually going sort of flipped meaning
the top of the sphere is actually the
bottom and the bottom is the top and the
reason for that is because we decided we
probably were going to flip things in
the coordinate system soon so we didn't
want to change it but so technically
this is actually backwards from what you
would do if we were going to keep this
coordinate system but that shouldn't
really change how the sphere reflects
other than in flipping it right I mean
it shouldn't all it should do like all
that's doing is that's what that's why
the blue is on the bottom of the Reds on
the top is all I think that should be
doing unless I'm mistaken
a pyramid was suggested by a couple
people yeah we could build a pyramid a
pyramid wouldn't be too hard I could
make a thing that's like make pyramid
normal map right make pyramid pyramid
make is that right I don't know a spell
pyramid let's say that's right
so make pyramid normal map that comes in
and that'll just be that's pretty
straightforward I guess right that's
just gonna pick which of the the things
gets are zero point seven seven seven
right so a pyramid I guess we could do a
diamond shape as well but a pyramid
shape would basically be if if X is
greater than Y Jimmy so if I want to if
I want to figure out a pyramid shape
let's see here should be pretty
straightforward so if I want to figure
out a pyramid shape that looks like this
I guess right then this is this line is
x equals y right and this line here is
is like one I'm going to say that
they're between 0 &amp; 1 but this is like 1
minus x equals y right so I guess I
could just do this by classifying which
side of these you're on if you are like
if you're on right if X is less than Y
then you're either here or here right so
if X is less than Y then this you know
we just use this to determine which one
of these two you are yeah okay so that's
that's pretty straightforward I could
totally do that
so all we would do here is we'd say
if the X is less than the Y right then
we are in those two quadrants otherwise
we're not and then then we would say
over here we'd we do if the if the
inverse I think is there's a better way
to phrase that than the 1 minus X equals
y I don't think so I'm just going to do
it that way so we'll just say the call
this in X so we'll call this that I
guess 1 minus X so in X is less than Y
that seem right to everyone all right
and so at the moment like I said our
coordinate system is kind of backwards
but oh well
we'll still do it as if it wasn't so
really if we think about it it's
actually this way that's the x equals y
line and this is the index equals y line
right okay and so if we are if X is less
than Y then we're here or here depending
on whether in X is less than Y so hmm
so this guy would be pointing in I guess
the it would be all of these guys have Z
equals the point 7 whatever right but
this would be an X pointing in negative
x this would be pointing in why this
would be pointing in negative Y and this
would be pointing in X right seems
pretty straightforward so I'll go ahead
and set that so we don't actually need
an X or an Y here we don't need root
term or any of these things we just need
normal like so and we have our real
seven
this value there we go and I guess we'll
initialize that so the compiler doesn't
complain just in case it we're going to
complain mm-hmm and we'll clear that out
so if we're in X less than Y so we're on
that side and then we're so we're X less
than Y so on this side and then our
index is also less than Y then we are in
here so we would have normal and I guess
we could also say that 0 0 7 we can just
save the normal x equals negative 7
right otherwise the normal dot y equals
7 because it's that upwards pointing one
here if we're on this side of the of the
x equals y line then if index is less
than Y it's going to be the negative Y
right so it's that one otherwise it's
the positive x so that seemed right to
people I'm not sure let's give it a shot
no but we'll have to call it makes ear
normal Matt will call make pyramid
so there's pyramid I don't know if that
tells us anything it tells us that the
to Y ones are totally not reflecting but
that maybe just because they're pointing
not towards anything I don't know have
to think about that girl Linda bloom so
it would need to be flipped on both
directions not sure what you're talking
about Carl and Oh
I think the lower reflection also needs
to flip the why there because it's the
incoming vector I don't think that's
quite true I mean it may be true that we
need to flip it but it's not true that
it's the incoming vector because we
already counted for that when we did the
computation right we already did this
and that accounts for the fact that it's
the incoming vector right because this
was solving negative e plus 2 e
transpose MN right and so we already
counted for the negative E or at least
we tried to you said you might have to
make the sky texture larger than the
ground so it wouldn't miss it could you
instead sample from adjacent sky maps
assuming they're not occluded but
there's no such thing as a jacent sky
map because remember this this is
something that we're producing in the
game so there is no adjacent sky map so
we want to just produce one lighting
thing that covers as far as we want to
sample basically and so that's the
because because remember sorry it's not
Vanessa Lee the sky it's like the roof
if you're indoors or whatever and so we
need we want it to kind of be dynamic
and that's that's really why we have to
think about that
grumpy giant says the edge attenuation
is correct given that a reflected vector
right on the edge will have a smaller
y-value than one's reflected from nearer
the center is that true I don't feel
like that's true shouldn't they have a
larger y-value I guess
well no you're right because as the
plane goes there I will yeah yeah that's
true
that's a good point so he he totally
brought up a good point for the
attenuation the edge attenuation is
correct because it's not the normal that
we're using the normals what we're
reflecting off of and so as it becomes
more oblique to us right like basically
you know as we're talking about
something that's pointing fairly fairly
head-on to something that's pointing
less and less head-on right once it's
it's going this way if you know our I've
Ector will not have much of a y
component if the normal is pointing in Y
so actually the Y component will be
highest right in that sort of sweet spot
where it's actually getting some Y but
it's not having it yeah it's not having
it kicked back so we want the thing that
transfers the maximum amount of Y and
that's somewhere like I don't know 45
degrees or something
kronole dragon would it be possible to
rotate the incoming sampling from the
environment map so that it looks like
the sphere is spinning yeah I mean
that's just adding an offset to the
environment map right
you don't only have to rotate it you
could just move it but the problem is
that's not a reflection anymore because
a spinning reflective sphere just looks
like a stationary reflective sphere
right so be careful what your risk for
there right because it's not blue
revenge oh cylinders might be useful
you're correct I think cylinders
cylinders should be better yeah that's a
very good point actually
that's a very very good point and as for
why we're getting this reduction I don't
know this will be what we'll have to
debug tomorrow but adding cylinders is a
very good point I feel like cylinders
would be very instructive as well
yeah what's where is our oops here
I don't know Matt I'm gonna do make
cylinder normal Matt make cylinder and
we'll do this like make an X big
cylinder a normal map X or something
like that and this would just be one
where you know excuse me it's never it's
it's always just the the X right like so
and so you know the root term is always
going to be greater than zero and so you
can always do this
in fact what we could do you know we
could do we could actually make sphere
normalmap could actually make cylinders
by passing in like a CX and a cy which
basically multiply what the NX values
are and then Y values are so something
like this does this make sense what I'm
doing here
where we can sort of turn off the X or
the Y to make a cylinder by not actually
considering those two and so if we do it
you know straight up make your made
normal map so if we do it straight up
and just do sphere normal map this way
right if I rerun the game that's our
sphere right but if we then go in and
say oh yeah you know don't just make it
be an X only for something right so that
will knock out the Y component eyerly I
think that would give us a cylinder or I
could be very wrong about that I feel
like it should let me double check but
that's just not whatever the bug is that
we had that wasn't causing sides to draw
properly yeah there we go
so there's a there's a cylinder right
it's a cylinder rolling this way so yeah
so I think probably what that means is
my pyramid generating code was wrong
we should probably draw it but again
that's something we can do tomorrow so
yeah I don't know that looks pretty good
that looks better than our sphere will
happen we'll have to again we'll have to
tackle this tomorrow it's really
something we need to start stepping
through it figure out what we're doing
wrong
and Gaston 5 at the moment we are
right-handed but we're upper left corner
in terms of our screen space which we
are having the to do lists to change its
it's kind of lingering but we kind of
wanted to finish doing our normal map
stuff first that makes sense
would inverted versions of normal math
fusil I inverted sphere for debugging
possibly not but for gameplay sure like
when we actually have them
abner Cumbre that's disturbing the what
is disturbing about it so one thing I
also don't think we're doing right now
is actually we're actually also not
transforming the normals so that's
another thing we have to do tomorrow
like so for example right if you look at
this let's see this is this one's much
easier certainly but it's something that
we'll have to to think about a little
bit so if you take a look at what
happens in here if I actually was to
start letting this thing rotate right
I said letting this the right angles
why is this not rotating I thought I
told you to rotate I don't know why you
aren't rotating angle is going up as it
should and so you can see that this is
not correct right it it's not actually
transforming those normals to point in
different directions it's leaving the
normals pointing in the same direction
they were pointing and so then another
thing that we will have to do tomorrow
is make sure that we actually handled
that properly right so yeah so I should
put a note in there or while we're doing
it tomorrow so after normal to do KC
rotate normals base
axis so that is definitely something we
will have to handle see any other
questions any other questions questions
looks like there are no more questions
that's a wrap says Abner Cumbre that's a
wrap all right well if Abner says it's a
rap it's a rap people we are in good
shape here I think we probably were
getting real close I think we probably
need about one more day probably to kind
of go through here and and shore up all
of our normal map stuff and then we can
move on to figuring out how we're going
to what we're gonna do for this middle
map which is really the that's the
tricky guy so we'll have to see how
that's gonna go and I have no idea I
really don't know
hopefully we'll figure something clever
out but you know maybe we won't maybe we
won't be as clever as we want to be
either way we will certainly give it a
shot I hope you will join me tomorrow as
we finish up the normal map stuff since
that's something we at least know works
well no mystery there just us doing some
debugging so I hope you'll join me
tomorrow 5:00 p.m. Pacific Standard Time
again right here on Twitch where we'll
finish up our normal mapping code so we
can move on to trying to figure out what
in the world we're gonna do with that
middle map that ought to be interesting
so we'll we'll see but thank you very
much for joining me to pleasure coding
with you as always if you would like to
follow along with the source code you
can always peer out of the game on
handmade hero org you just use this
little pre-order button and you will get
a link where you can download the source
code if you would like to just support
the video series you can always
subscribe to our patreon page it's very
much appreciated we also have a forums
where you can ask questions and you can
look at community ports to Linux and Mac
and you can also use the anti 8 episode
guide to catch up with past episodes if
you've missed episodes or if you're just
starting out it's a great place to go
and finally we have a tweet bot that
will tweet the schedule at you if you're
trying to catch the live stream and want
to know when it's going to be that's the
best way to do it again I hope see
everyone back here at 5 p.m. tomorrow I
think we should be able to wrap up
normal mapping which will feel good and
then we can go ahead and start working
on that lighting puzzle which is gonna
be it's gonna take some ingenuity it's
gonna take some ingenuity so hopefully
we'll figure something good at all right
thanks for joining me and have a
wonderful Wednesday tomorrow
yeah I will see you guys on the Internet