hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero the show Rico to complete game live
on stream we are doing a little bug
fixing we have a little issues page on
the private github and we kind of go
been trying to go through and you know
fix some of these ones that are in here
and we had I don't know about 12 in
there or something like that and we
closed a bunch of them so we're down to
just a few that we know of like we we
closed a bunch when we said well okay
here is a fix but we were like two
people who filed them kind of have to
test them again so I you know I don't
know to what extent they had there was
one that we fixed that we didn't do one
part of the fix that we need to do so
that one's still in there and there's a
couple that we haven't done anything at
all about yet so two of them we won't
like these two we're not going to
anything about at the moment because
this stuff I probably will wait till the
next asset pack to try and deal with
this part right here in terms of how we
get to the point where the assets can be
sort of done in a 1-1 shot easy to easy
to you know work with deal um and guy
entry obviously he is a long-term one
but we can do wrong meters two pixels we
could start taking a shot at klang
compatibility which is going to be a
bunch of things because of the lack of a
printf and stuff like that so that
that's probably and also like macro
incompatibilities and things like this
so that one's going to be a bit of work
not to the whole code base or anything
but just to a certain there's a few
specific things that we do that clang is
not going to like so in order to get
that in there there's some stuff we have
to do I think right now compile playing
probably isn't that hard if you just
don't want to use the debug services but
if you do want to use the debug services
then you got problems and so then this
one's pretty easy to fix and the
asynchronous texture downloads they're
not necessarily easy to fix per se but
they're straight forward to fix
basically with asynchronous texture
downloads we just have to go monkey
around with opengl a little bit and do
some somewhat unsavory stuff but on the
whole it's not you know it's it's not
rocket science it's just babysitting 3d
API babysitting stuff that we have to do
so uh let's just go ahead and keep out
of here because I would like to get
maybe by the time we get because I'm
gonna have to go on break I've got a
better be out of town for a couple weeks
in in a little bit and so I'd like to
get to the point where we kind of have a
clean bug list here where maybe only
these two guys are still left remaining
that would be nice to do potentially I
don't know you know we'll see but I'd
like to you know at least a crack at it
so that we can kind of have that's the
fleen doubt and then just focus on
getting our Z lighting stuff finished
because I think that's really the last
thing that we need to do before we can
move on to doing some world building and
you know kind of move on to the game II
sort of stuff with that doesn't really
have much engine relevance sort of we
don't really have that much engine
relevant code left I guess is what I'm
saying like the engine kind of does what
it does and you know it there's plenty
of things that we could add to it or
improve but nothing particularly is
super necessary you know it can play
cutscenes it can do multi-layered sprite
levels it can do arbitrarily large
worlds it does asset streaming and blah
blah blah blah so while all of those
things could certainly be improved and
we may find that we need to improve some
of them or that there are certain parts
that we kind of left this to do is that
we'll have to loop around back to and we
start to stress them we've built most of
the stuff that you know you would have
if you went and licensed an engine or
something like that there isn't really a
whole lot that we're missing I don't
think so I'd like to kind of get you
know things wrapped up in that sense to
a good sort of you know pinch point so
I'm going to start with de 323 source
code here on day 3 24 so that's the
source
you'll want to start with a few em you
are so inclined to follow along at home
here is the old code base let me go
ahead and compile that there is nothing
particularly unusual about where we are
at you can kind of see it's exactly what
we would expect our software renderer is
working and our Hardware render is
working as best as we know of at the
moment and yeah so there's not a lot to
say about that our Z stuff has still not
been done yet in terms of the offset
stuff we we have the multiplanar stuff
there but like our we have our weird
sort of stairwell thing that's not
correct at the moment so we have to work
on that at some point but otherwise
we're in pretty good shape but we still
got a couple bugs here so let's start
taking a look at those first I'm going
to do is just address this one because
this was just sort of a misstep in the
quick fix we did over here that's not
the I'll actually wanted to actually
want a handmade world I back into T into
chunk the problem was just that our
clear world entity block call at the
moment clears the next pointer
apparently see clear world entity block
so we can't actually call it after we've
initialized the next pointer so we kind
of have to do something like okay when
we grab the free block off the free list
you know then we can do it right so we
can grab it and then clear and then
continue and I think that probably would
do it we grabbed it off here we set the
free block pointer to point to our next
pointer so we can't clear until that's
done then we can clear it so now it's
all zeroed out then we can set its next
pointer to be whatever was in the first
block and that we can chain it so we
just like grab clear chain and that
seems like a reasonable thing to do
there so we'll go ahead and compile that
and again we don't really have a test
a setup for this yet so these are all
very speculative bugs they're like for
people who are maybe doing stuff in
advance of what we're doing so we kind
of have to rely on them for testing at
the moment when we actually get to this
part of the code we can do some more
stress testing of stuff like this to see
if it breaks but at the moment we're not
there yet so yeah let me just double
check to make sure that we didn't break
our only case or there we go yeah I was
going to say we should actually make
sure that we did this properly oh that's
not what I actually wanted to call I
want to call that there we go there we
go and yeah so we'll see if that helps
for for the people who reported this one
and yeah they can tell us there we go ah
oops don't want to do that how do I get
back there we go issues so wrong meters
two pixels is a computation problem
that's been in there for a while and I
think it means our camera offsets and a
couple of things are going to be wrong
so this was not going to be particularly
difficult to fix but it is going to
require perhaps some tweaking anyway you
can kind of see from the description
here what the problem is the problem is
that when we did meters two pixels it
appears that we didn't actually do
meters two pixels per se and you can you
can see that like originally we had this
and then somehow I guess it got mutated
to this this is probably just again one
of the sort of problems with programming
on stream is that I kind of have to talk
and do things at the same time and it's
pretty easy to have cut and paste or
reorganization mistakes
and so yeah that is just what sort of
happens so I what we probably did is
just tune some other values that happen
to be you know we've got a sort of semi
3d projection happening on the world and
so if our meters to pixel value is wrong
well our camera distance could just be
set to compensate and so on so we
probably just never really knew that it
was going to be wrong because we didn't
have any we don't have any like real
world things to test with right so we
won't see those errors so what we kind
of want to do now is is go look at what
we were doing here and see if we can
figure out what would be more correct to
do in context so that is our meters to
pixels line I think that's probably in
the renderer and my guess although I
don't know is that meters to pixels is
you know is probably right throughout
this code meaning I don't know that we
made any errors in here no one has
actually reported a specific bug on this
as per se so it's entirely possible that
our camera transform is using it
correctly but in our world mode or world
where we're actually doing this I assume
it's in world mode yeah you can see it
right there here where we've got meters
two pixels we've basically got pixels
times the width of the monitor which i
think is is kind of backwards so let's
take a look at what that's going to do
dimensional analysis wise assuming that
we really wanted meters two pixels right
which is something that you multiply
well let me just draw it out for you
so if we want something called meters to
pixels right if that's what we're
looking for then what we want to do here
is say well okay uh meters to pixels
means that I've got something that's in
meters right like I've got you know X
meters well let me use a different thing
there a meters right and i want to
multiply it by something right so i want
to to basically multiply this value by
you know who knows what the the actual
value is x over Y or something like this
right again I should I really need to
get better at picking things I don't
know a Q over w so I have a meters i
want to multiply by Q over w and I want
to get out be pixels right because the
idea is I have a value right this is
meters to pixels whatever q / w is right
and I want to figure out if I have a
value in meters and I want to get a
value in pixels i want to multiply by
this thing and so if you just look at
what actually happens here in fact i can
actually just solve this equation and
you can kind of see what ends up
happening in terms of the units q / w if
i was divide both sides by meters i
would get be pixels over a meters right
and so what you can see there is
ignoring the actual quantities the units
of q / w should be pixels over meters in
theory right unless we're missing
something that's what we would expect so
when we say that a value is meters to
pixels we would expect it to look like
in code you know something pixely right
over something meters e this is what we
would expect to see four meters to
pixels but what we see instead is the
opposite of that right what I'm seeing
here is the width of the monitor which
even if it's in
meters which you know maybe it is maybe
doesn't love to check to see what we
actually specified that in but
millimeters meters whatever it's in it's
in a physical measurement we're
multiplying a pixel value by it so it's
like it should be that but instead it's
that right and that seems to be just
straight up erroneous now the width of
the monitor right this is the horizontal
measurement of the monitor in meters
according to what we're saying here that
if you look at that value that's
probably why this wasn't a like heinous
Lee erroneous error for us where
everything was wrong it's point six
right so it's like we were dividing by 2
because of a multiplied instead of
effectively multiplying by 2 which is
what will get here so yeah you know
maybe distance above ground should have
been 16 instead of nine or 4.5 instead
of nine right like you know some values
that were double what they should have
been our half what they should have been
we wouldn't necessarily immediately know
those were wrong right I because we
don't have a clear expectation what's
going on there so in theory right now we
have to go back and sort of readjust
those values because we're going to get
you know some erroneous stuff going on
right so yeah so some of this stuff is
like you know the focal length I don't
know exactly how we decided to pick that
but that seems fine but anyway so you
know if we want to sort of restore
roughly what we were talking about
before you know we can just zoom out a
little bit more and then we'll get
basically the same thing that we had
previously and it's you know it's fine
or whatever so that's all good I don't
know what exactly we want this number to
be specifically but in theory that is
the more correct transform that well
that's a little bit too much let's let's
not go nuts so yeah so you know is that
more correct I think probably because we
said if meteors two pics
and you know maybe we've got bugs
elsewhere or something like that but you
know in lieu of knowing that we've got
any other bugs in some other places in
the code that is is pretty much what it
should be right so I think that's good I
think and there may not really be
anything else that we need to do in
particular because really the only thing
that meters two pixels effects is the
scaling of the screen so the only thing
that it's going to really affect is how
far away we are in terms of our camera
for getting the sort of result that we
want you know that's that's all there
really is to it so I don't think there's
really all that much there's there's not
much more to say about it all right so
I'm going to say that that's probably
okay and let's see what he's just be
sure the number of pixels buffer / the
with the monitor that is exactly what I
think it should be as well found a focal
length 0 point 25 is Victoria of 8.6 to
give an identical image I don't know if
we want to edit the focal length you
know the problem with with not really
doing any kind of real camera simulation
years we don't really know what our
focal lengths should be per se so it
that's going to depend on how much we
want our scaling to happen I suppose I
could go in and return on the edging
there temporarily just to kind of see
what those things look like in the
OpenGL layer here let's see rectangle so
if we go ahead and run this way you can
see kind of now how the how much scaling
we get on other floors right and you
know is that too little scaling because
the focal what the focal length will
basically do is determine how much sort
of contraction there is in terms of the
perspective right how much scaling
we get there so yeah so maybe you know
we want a little more than that because
that wasn't quite that much scaling so
maybe we drop that down to something
else here I guess I should just leave
this running and tweak those values let
me go up a few floors
alright
so if i go ahead and look at the kind of
the hole here we can sort of look at how
we want to how we want to have that be
elongated you know if this is sort of a
little bit more kind of what we want in
terms of that that scaling you know I
don't know if that's too drastic or if
that's it seems like that's probably
good because we want that effect to be
relatively pronounced I think you know
we can we can sort of do something maybe
like this oops and that that seems
reasonable right and that gives a lot of
that gives a pretty good motion as those
things kind of scale out there it would
seem yeah all right so that seems
reasonable so I'm going to go ahead and
say we've got that under control now
hopefully and we'll go ahead and close
that out and see if anyone has anything
to say about it
all right okay so now we're down to
really only two and one of them is I
think definitely more important than the
other one so we'll attack that one first
claim compatibility obviously is not
really relevant to us actually doing the
game that's relevant to people who are
building it on other platforms so well
that's nice to support it's not really
as much of a priority so I'm going to go
with this guy first and of course
there's really nothing to say about this
when we already know what the bug is we
tried using multiple oppa jal contracts
for opengl texture downloads and you
know it doesn't seem to be reliable on
nvidia specifically on AMD it's a little
bit flaky but we don't really know that
something because we never put in any
fencing and it's possible that if we did
put in fencing the driver would work
properly so we don't really know too
much about it other than it seemed very
clear that Nvidia drivers did not like
this so we kind of just rather than
going and doing the fencing and doing
some of those other things more
correctly it seemed like the better
thing to do was just to attack it from
an entirely different perspective and
try to only do single threaded work on
the OpenGL side of things there's really
not much we can do about that
unfortunately for some unknown reason
and I really don't have any idea what
the reason is the OpenGL Standards
Committee has been really reluctant to
make the fundamental changes necessary
which are minor to open jail in order to
make it properly multi-thread it's it's
kind of weird but I don't know maybe
because they're trying to push Vulcan
now but even before before Vulcan was
even a thing they seemed reluctant so I
don't think it's just because of Vulcan
that they don't want to do it it's might
just because it's too big of a change
for them or I don't know what
this is obviously kind of tricky and
I'll show you why it's kind of tricky
here and i'll discuss sort of some
things that we can do and some things
that we can't do so if you take a look
at what happens in our open gel layer
let me take a look at where there it is
so we've got an allocate texture and a
deallocate texture call you can see how
these generally work and what you've got
there is you create a texture handle and
you send the card a texture image that
you want to use and then you set some
parameters on it and then off you go now
normally you would not call GL flush in
a texture buying situation like a
texture submission situation like this
because in single-threaded opengl all
commands are assumed to execute in order
so you the purpose of the GL flush here
is to say finish the OpenGL commands
that I've given you so far normally we
wouldn't care about finishing them so
far because any rendering that we might
do with the texture that we submitted
with that GL text image 2d call is odd
it's going to happen later in the
command stream ergo we know that the
text image 2d specification will have
finished by the time that that rendering
occurs as far as the GL is concerned
because that's like a guarantee that the
GL provides in single-threaded opengl
you know that commands execute as if
they were in order that doesn't mean
they actually acute in order it just
means that from your perspective they
will appear to have executed in order so
therefore it would not be bug so we can
get rid of this openness a GL flush here
and in theory i think i am on the AMD
parts it still just kind of works what
happened what happened here did I
tonight do some kind of thing wrong with
the what did I do
I thought I did I thought I left it
where we were you know what I must have
been standing up a little bit more let
me let me um tweak that a little bit
that better all right yeah I think that
all right I don't know what happened
there I guess I must have tweaked it
when I was standing in a different
amount of scale um so yeah okay uh so
anyway with the back to our story so you
know that'll usually work on AMD card as
well as far as we can tell so the GL
flush was in there we had put it in
there for people using in video where it
didn't work at all uh so what's the
problem here well the problem with the
open Jill multi-threaded stuff wanting
to move to single what we were doing if
you take a look at width you do handmade
is we were doing wiggle create context
for a number of contexts so I don't
really where is this guy it's
let go oops it's not an it or wiggle
piece it would just winter too in it
opengl there it is it's this one went
through to get thread start up for GL
that's the one I was looking for so what
we do here is we have these low priority
queues that are used for streaming
assets and what those low priority
queues could do is they can issue reads
like to load stuff and then as soon as
those reads complete they can submit the
results to OpenGL using their own OpenGL
context but the problem with that is now
we have multiple threads talking to jail
at the same time which pretty much
freaks GL out as far as I've seen
especially like we were saying on the
nvidia cards it just doesn't like it so
the question here is what can we
actually do in order to make it so that
these separate threads are doing asset
loading have some way of making sure
that their textures actually get
submitted and unfortunately really the
only thing we can do is make this part
of the operation synchronous so what we
kind of have to do is instead of calling
allocate texture and deallocate texture
we kind of just have to have a bind on
demand thing that occurs like we we
really do I don't think there's going to
be anything else like we kind of just
need to have it so that when we're going
to use these textures we bind them now
what we originally had in there was not
the most optimal thing we could have
presumably and let me say sort of a
little bit of a caveat here but I'll
just sort of point it out so if we if we
think about what's going on here we have
this notion that you know we're kind of
going forwards in time here
right and you know we've got some frames
so here is frame 0 here's frame one
hears frame two years frame three or
whatever and so what we have is we've
got a mainline thread that's coming
through here and doing like our update
render and then at the same time we have
some some side band threads are doing
things like loading assets right and
these threads have nothing to do with
the frame boundaries right this thread
is like really concerned about frame
boundaries but these threads don't care
at all they're just loading assets and
when the assets get there whenever the
disk says hey here's your asset it's
like great thank you all right that's it
so when these loads finish the problem
with having the load finish is now we
have the data in memory but we don't
have it sent to the GPU at all right we
haven't submitted to open jail so it's
we've loaded the texture off disc but we
haven't minute to the GPU well in this
update and render step what we were
doing originally before we try to do the
secondary context for submission what we
were doing originally is when this thing
got to somebody that had been loaded but
didn't have a texture handle bound when
it was going to render right when was
about to render it would call GL text
image right there and so really that's
potentially much later than when it
could have called GL text image because
let's say on frame 0 by the time I got
to the OpenGL render submission step
right which is maybe right here let's
say that it had been loaded well I could
submit it now even if I'm not going to
use it until next frame and that gives
the driver more visibility of that
texture to start the transfer earlier
now we don't know that the driver will
start the transfer earlier we just know
that it could start the transfer earlier
okay so I think about most basic what we
would like to do is that like have there
be a queue where we can stuff these
textures so that they can be updated in
that fashion right now there's another
thing we could do
that I don't know if we actually will do
or not but that's a more advanced thing
right and that is what's happening right
now is in OpenGL when we do an
allocation so I let me let me try to
explain it like this so on the GPU we
have this is the memory of the GPU
there's going to be a place where this
texture goes and lives right once we
transfer it down there to the card so
all the pixels that are in that texture
the texels that are in that texture are
going to be moved to GPU because that's
really need to be in order to be used
for rendering right and so there's going
to be some stuff here that's like GPU
mapped memory this is actually memory on
the cpu side of things so this is like
this is our DRAM you know this is this
is memory in the computer this is the
GPUs Ram over here you know this is the
card this is in the PCI slot right this
is on the motherboard okay and so
somewhere that texture has to be here in
order for it to transfer because the GPU
over the PCI bus can only see memory
that's in regions that it knows about
right and these are just getting into
sort of the vagaries of how memory is
sort of transferred between PCI cards
and the motherboard right but how that
sort of works there's a number of ways
it can work actually but a lot of times
the way that works is there's address
ranges that are in physical memory
reserved that are mapped for the GPU and
when you put something in there the GPU
can can sort of transfer it over the bus
and say I want this memory range start
start sucking it over and it can do that
without the CPU having to manhandle it
right so it can be like a GPU transfer
that's largely asynchronous of the CPU
having to sit there and feed it bites or
anything like that right uh so what that
means is if we just do an allocation
right and here's our CPU non mapped
memory so this is just regular old cpu
memory hasn't been mapped specifically
for visibility on the GPU if we just
allocated texture here then what may
have to happen depending on the
architecture is that first it has to be
copied from non map memory into mapped
memory and then it can be copied from
non from map memory into actual GPU
texture memory right so it's actually
two times the cop copies that are
necessary right instead of one copy it's
two copies now we don't necessarily know
that that second copy hurts us we don't
have really performance metrics at this
point we're not at the point where we're
trying to profile our game in that way
but that is an additional step we could
take and the step we could take to
eliminate that copy is by using
effectively what what is often called
pinned memory you can do this with pixel
buffer objects and you can also do it
with GPU map memory extensions and
there's a whole bunch of everything's
could do but basically what happens here
is we can allocate memory ourselves in
the GPU mapped memory space and just
load our actual disk read can be
targeted to that location and at that
point what happens is instead of ever
putting it here we just put it directly
here right and so you can see why that
might be important if the memory
bandwidth is the bottleneck in this part
of our process if we find that that's a
problem then we would want to optimize
that away by eliminating one of those
copies so hopefully that makes some
sense it's a pretty basic idea it turns
out to be a little bit fiddly because
you got to do a bunch of random OpenGL
calls to make it happen but you get the
idea all right so let's take the simpler
step first because we're going to have
to do that in both cases right even if
we go and do the more complicated thing
we would still have to do this part of
it as well which is to sort of separate
out that download and what I'm basically
talking about here is inside handmade
OpenGL what I'd like to do is I'd like
to have a sort of a new function in here
we've got OpenGL render commands I'd
like to have another one which is like
OpenGL upload textures
right and what opengl upload textures
would do is open jello textures would do
something like take a chain of stuff
that it needs to go through and upload
so rather than allocate texture ever
existing here instead what would happen
is or you know what and we could do both
of these we could do open Jill you know
manage textures or something like that
what we could do here is say alright
let's just copy both of these things in
here let's eliminate those callbacks
they won't be there anymore and we'll
just have like two things that can do
either it can do the blind texture or it
can do the delete of a texture so in
either case you can do it but basically
what we're doing is we're just taking
the allocate texture and deallocate
texture operations and we are deferring
them so rather than you know if you look
at how it's working right now we have
these separate threads and they're
calling this immediately so I I again I
apologize for be laboring this point if
you're someone who kind of obviously
just knows already what I'm talking
about here but I just want to talk about
this one more time just make it
absolutely clear in fact this is the
diagram that you actually want remember
so we've got these separate threads are
doing the loading what they were doing
before is they were just asynchronously
calling the GL when they were ready to
download the texture right here and we
can't allow that right because they
can't have their own opengl context
because having multiple opengl context
was proving buggy right so what we're
going to do instead is just we'll do our
own atomic operation here to build some
little list of deferred operations we
need to do hand it off to this thread so
that it can all be done on one thread
right opengl will only ever see that one
thread so we would get rid of allocate
in texture and deallocate texture and
instead what we have is just opened jail
managed textures or something like this
and opengl managed textures would take
just some kind of an instruction stream
that basically just tells it this sort
of stuff right and so let's take a look
at what that we
be we already pretty much know what the
API is because we have allocate texture
and deallocate texture so what we can do
is we could just pull these out of here
right and and say that we've got inside
you know rendered H or something like
that say that we have a deferred texture
operation right so we could call this
like deferred texture up for something
like that right or maybe just even call
it a texture up so that we kind of know
that there's this idea of texture
operations that have to happen we can
even make this the relatively platform
generic in the sense that you can have
these texts drops that need to happen
and even the bitmap renderer could still
process them it would just throw them
away right so they you know we wouldn't
have to even special case it we could
always build the texture op list and
then the bitmap render would just go let
go whatever like I don't need to deal
with that we can also choose to make
this just part of the regular stream and
pass along but we'll get to that in a
second so let's just take this on moving
those operations just right up in and
I'm just going to take and and basically
do sort of a union kind of a thing here
where we just say like okay we've got a
texture up we can have like a texture up
allocate and a texture op deallocate and
we know that d allocating a texture is
just going to take you know a void star
for the texture and we know that
allocating a texture is just going to do
a width sort of height data operation
here but and this is a big but we have
sort of this additional problem which is
that we don't actually know where those
where to put back the results and this
is always this is in fact I would argue
the single most crucial aspect of
multi-threaded programming that makes it
more difficult than single threaded
programming it's going to be a weird
thing to say but it's and it's probably
a minority opinion but I find that
concurrency is one thing but
flow control is really the harder thing
right and the nice thing about
single-threaded programming is that the
flow control in terms of return values
always just works if I want to do
something I say like oh you know do this
thing and I know that it's going to go
do it and come back and then I'm going
to have the results of that thing and
it's a very easy way to structure a
program there's a lot of good practices
you can follow to make your code fairly
you know unlikely to have a lot of bugs
and you can make it kind of clean and
easy to read and all these other sorts
of things but as soon as you go to
multi-threading all that goes away when
you have multi threading it's typical
that I have a couple operations I want
to do they're going to complete
asynchronously and I've got this really
nasty routing problem all of a sudden
how do I get the results of one thing to
the input of another thing because now
there isn't this sort of natural glue of
how the code is written with a stack and
all these other sorts of things right
and so that's when you start getting all
these other things of like well there's
co routines but then the co routines
kind of have to be slightly decoupled
from the things and you know you kind of
need compiler support forward or
language support for it to really make
it all that clean in the first place
because you know if you are actually
writing it in a language like C++ the
features for this are woefully
inadequate for it you know shocking
they're a c++ feature being woefully
inadequate who would have thunk it but
anyway so we'll have this problem and
what do I mean by that well if we go
take a look at what happens in our asset
system where this is actually called you
can see what we were doing is inside
finalize asset fit map well we have this
little thing here where we say like hey
let's allocated texture well if we're
going to allocate a texture and stick it
in this texture handle well how are we
going to do that if we if that's not
going to complete for a while right if
the allocate texture call isn't going to
complete for who knows how long well we
can't say equal to texture handle right
we can't actually do that so that's the
problem that we have to deal with now
the easiest way to deal with this is
actually just to give it a pointer of
this and say hey write it into it write
it in there whenever you get a chance
and we can do that but there's a portent
thing that we have to make sure that we
don't do which is that we can
make sure we can't actually mark this
thing as being in its final state until
that actually happens right so you can
see here we do this thing where we do
like work asset state equals work final
state and I believe that you know part
of that process is like well what state
is this bitmap in we know we can like
evict it or not evicted or whatever
we're not going to be able to do that
worked final state bit in here instead
what's going to have to happen is the
work final state is going to actually
have to happen outside in the allocation
right so the person who allocates is
going to have to set the state and the
reason for that is if they didn't then
it would be possible for somebody to
think that it could free an asset that
was being that was currently you know
loaded think that it could free an asset
but really the allocator hadn't actually
finished running yet so when it went to
free it when it after it had been freed
it would go to try and write back the
results and it would write back the
results to some other thing that had now
used that memory right and probably
crash or do some other really bad stuff
so we have this sort of you know
inherent problem there that we're going
to have to take care of which is
effectively how do we make sure that our
asset stays around long enough for the
allocate call to complete and that's
really the only thing that we have to
make sure happens because otherwise
fortunately in this circumstance it's
pretty easy otherwise because we just
have void star star like texture result
right or a result handle or something
like that so we just say hey we want
this with this light in this data and we
want you to put it here in the
deallocate we just say oh this is the
one we want you to calculate now d
allocations a lot easier the reason d
allocation is a lot easier because it's
not going to call talk to us anymore
right he doesn't have to go put the
result anywhere because d allocations
just like hey I don't want this anymore
I don't care when you get around to it I
don't need to know that you even did it
I'm just telling you can do it and if
you do it great and so that's you know
that's that so at the moment I guess
I'll just say like you know is allocate
because we don't really need a type
field for it cuz there's only two types
and then i'll just say we've got a
texture off allocate and a texture up
deallocate and so with their texture up
allocate and texture op deallocate here
we can now sort of see how we will
actually process this guy and we'll come
back to the asset handling stuff in a
second here but when i'm going to go
manage these textures what i need to do
now is say okay let's pretend i have a
texture op stream presumably there's a
next pointer or something like this so
i'm going to kind of chew through these
guys right and so i'm going to take a
texture up that's like the first one and
presumably what i'm going to do is
something like texture up up equals
first op equal OPP equals pop next and
just walk through some list of these
that i have to do oops that was what i
want and so i'll come in here and say is
this an allocation and if it is i'll do
this path and if it's not i'll do this
path and again these are exactly the
same operations we already did if we
take a look at what these operations are
you can see that we have to do jen
textures into a handle that's the same
we have to bind it up we then have to
specify the actual stuff here now this
width and height is now going to come
from the operation so is the data all of
these parameters we just set by rote so
they don't need to look up anything we
then have to do some assertions here
that we could fit inside of a void star
but assuming that we can we then just
have to actually assign this thing to
the destination so we have a result
handle here and we would do that
conversion so once that's all good we
were pretty much done with that when we
want to go to do the opposite one which
is deletion it's really simple we just
pull out at that texture
and do the deletion so that's all we're
talking about here as far as open gel is
concerned and managing those textures
that is it there's nothing else to it
let's go ahead and compile that just to
get the arrows out of the way get rid of
those and so here we sort of have this
we're going to have to deal with how
that's actually going to work obviously
in a second the allocation and the DL
occasion let's kind of come in here and
make sure all this stuff makes sense so
yeah this guy we could we could still
leave allocate texture I suppose looking
at that I want this to still be callable
presumably right so I guess I should
maybe leave it doing it the old way we
had it as a function let's say right
because I could do this because I kind
of forgot that we do want to call it
from another place so seems reasonable
to do so if I do go back to saying okay
hey there's a you know allocate texture
fall we'll say it's open Jill ok texture
there's not a platform specific function
or anything now it's just part of the
open jail normal up in jail layer
then we can still just leave it this way
I suppose and that seems fine to me I
don't have any pressing reason why it
has to be part of that call i'm fine
with other people so it would just look
like that right let's see put that up in
here okay and again I think that just
takes whip height and data right so
anything else it takes an early remember
that is supposed to be an equal sign
okay texture to be okay texture texture
handle opengl and what else we got up
with so that's actually allocate and
okay um yeah so I think that's all good
we don't have to set these anymore and
that's actually kind of nice right any
time we can get rid of a platform
callback thing I'm happy because I like
to keep that side of things as simple as
possible for obvious reasons I mean the
more straightforward the api's across
the boundary the easier it is for people
to port and to understand how to port
and also to just keeps the code from
getting too entangled and difficult so
that's kind of nice as well texture is
not a member of texture oops of texture
opti allocate is that really true if so
we we should do something about it huh
it's called handle
alright so now we have the ability to do
a processing of a list but we don't
actually have anything that ever builds
the list so what we kind of need to do
here is figure out how we're going to
have that process work now remember
we're sort of back in in the danger zone
now in that we have multiple threads who
want to be adding something to a list
and then we have you know a we have a
another person who wants to take things
off of that list and process them this
is traditionally in multi-threading
we've kind of mentioned before but it's
called multiple producer single consumer
a lot of times in multi threading
programming for whatever reason they
talk about the concept of producer and
consumer and the idea is a producer is
somebody who sort of generates things on
a list their tasks or work to do or
whatever and a consumer is somebody who
takes those things off the list and
actually does them so usually there's
you know I say list i really mean just
some kind of a queue so typically you've
got producers on one end of q stuffing
things into the queue and you've got
consumers under them to the cube pulling
things out of the queue and the idea
here is just that you can categorize
certain algorithms by whether they are
multi producer multi consumer or single
producer singer consumer and you end up
with some statement about how many of
our on either side do i because because
sometimes if you only have one person on
a particular side of a queue you can
dispense with some of the qlogic or
whatever else right so you've got single
producer single consumer multiple
producer multiple consumer single
producer multiple consumer multiple
reduced or single consumer are the
various permutations right and you don't
really have to concern yourself too much
with any of that amount of clay sure you
get the idea and the important thing is
to be able to reason about it so anyway
that's what we have here is we have the
necessity to sort of make this work
across these and in order to do that
we're going to actually need to discuss
a little bit i think i'd like to show
you how to do a ticket taking because i
feel like that's just a good thing to
know and
it's really easy to do and it'd be good
for this just to show how to make a
multiple producer single consumer list
and so we should just do that but in
order to do that I'm going to need more
than seven minutes to describe it so i
think i'm going to stop here and i'll
just patch around this with you know and
well you know what i could do i can
actually make these call something and
then we won't actually do anything in
that call now what's interesting here is
when i call i'm already inside a thing
called an asset lock here and i do so i
do wonder a little bit there if we could
just use that but it seems unnecessary
and also probably to be honest i think
if we actually went through and sort of
did a brush-up pass on this code now
because we don't allow background
rendering anymore we don't use the
ground chunks things anymore i feel like
we don't really have a problem we don't
really need asset locking like we used
to because only one thread is ever
calling acquire asset memory at once i
think now whereas before that was not
necessarily the case so I feel like the
asset lock is probably old news a lot of
the stuff is probably old news and we
could probably get rid of it that's just
my assumption but anyway what I was
going to say is we can sort of have a
thing in here which is like an internal
void thing which is like hey do and you
know add an op on here right that's sort
of like you know add up
and you know maybe that just takes
texture up that's going to add right and
so that way we can actually make these
things and do the add up so this way if
I go and look at the if 0 here instead
of having that if zeroed out entirely
what I would do instead is say okay so
there's a texture up here the op is an
allocate the width is the width the
height is the height the data bitmap
memory and the result handle is here so
we'll need to do something there with
add up to actually figure out how we're
even going to do stuff with it but
otherwise you know the basics there you
can kind of see and then similarly in
here i could say like okay this is not
one of those and so the handle that
you're looking for is this one and off
you go right so that's what we need to
do and so this add up here you know will
be roughly something like a begin ticket
you know mutex this sort of a thing and
ticket mutex and it'll be like you know
get from free list add to pending list
like that right so that's really all
we're going to write but I want to
explain a little bit about how it works
and you know give it the proper
trappings so that's what we'll do
tomorrow for now it means we will be in
no man's land where everything is white
well I guess not everything rectangles
still work but our textures don't so
we'll have to go from there but anyway
i'm going to go ahead and go to the QA
and then we'll take a look at that
tomorrow
so as it's a bit late now but i was
thinking debug sliders for fov and
camera distance could be useful yeah
probably we never really made very good
debug sliders someday
snoring tortoise on the bug list what is
that clan compatibility issue so it's
it's not really an issue so much is it's
a collection of the things that clang
doesn't like I think mostly there's two
things one is the sprint f call there's
some casts and pointer cast things and
then there's the big one is it it can't
do constant named function strings so I
don't know why it can't do that that
seems crazy to have done it the way that
they did but you know it doesn't and so
we kind of relied on that in the debug
system so we'll have to come up with
another way to do that
if that makes sense
but yes some of these are easy it's just
the sprint f1 the sprint f1 and the
macro ones are hard that casting is not
a big deal at all we can fix that real
easily so you know basically this will
be one where a couple of the things on
this list will take 10 seconds but a
couple of them may take a whole day or a
whole episode or more to fix so we'll
see
you
so if there's no questions I'll just
wrap it on up
we're da minha I still see flickering on
the stairs as the arts ocean finalized
so we don't actually have the
z-transform correct yet so the stairs
are doing something which is never
actually supposed to happen which is
that their protruding in their moved in
X from where they would normally be
because of the perspective transform and
also we're not actually properly hopping
the hero up to the height that the
stairs are it's he's moving through them
which is also illegal because you know
you're not allowed to move through the
stairs so I wouldn't necessarily call
the sort solution finalized because
that's probably not true but I also
there's really no need to pay attention
the stairs at the moment because we have
to finish the Z so Z handling pass
before we can say definitively what's
going on there whether it's good or bad
or whatever
is the issue list private the issue list
is on the private github but anyone who
pre-orders the game has access to the
private github so it's not that private
it's basically yeah everyone who
pre-orders the game is is on the github
so it's you know it's a heck of a lot of
people I don't even remember how many
thirteen hundred and seventy-four people
are on the github so it's you know the
phrase private is perhaps a little bit
aggressive but it's you know it's only
for pre-orders if that makes sense well
you normally skip straight to open jail
or harbuck station or would you start
with soft rendering yeah normally you
don't write a software renderer the
software rendering part is for the edges
for educational purposes I feel like
everyone should write a software
renderer once like every engine
programmer should have written a
sovereign dur at some point they're not
hard to write anymore because they're so
well understood you know originally it
would would have taken months to figure
out how to write a good software under
but nowadays that's not true at all it
takes only a couple days or a week you
know to write one every I think every
engine program I should write a software
under at some point for sure but once
you've done 11 so I don't think you ever
need to do one again storing tortoise in
terms of asynchronous textures loading
the OpenGL website talks about pixel
transfer operations and references GL
pixel store did you look into these I
don't know about GL pixel store
I'm trying to remember so the way you're
supposed to do them I can point you to
it if you want to look at it yourself I
is is this
so think that's that's talking about it
but it doesn't actually show any code
there I was just hoping that someone had
some codes you could look let's see yeah
that's starting to look right to me so
this is the mapping part that I was
talking about before and then you do the
copy to put the stuff in there and then
you unmap it and you say go for it right
now it's worth noting that that's that's
on older cards basically what's
happening there is that you have to
unmap the buffer after the copy because
you're not allowed to leave memory
pinned uh so in newer opengl like an
opengl 4.5 when you're on more modern
parts you actually don't ever have to
unmap so you can just map some buffers
that you'll use for your pixel transfers
you right into them you issue your
texture uploads then you just know you
you insert fencing to know when they're
done and then when they are done you
just overwrite those segments of memory
with something else so you don't
actually have to unmap on modern parts
but I'm on like Intel Parts I think you
have to unmap right and it's worse so
yeah
so but yeah I think this is roughly
correct I mean it's hard to remember the
open gel stuff sometimes but I think
that's roughly correct
Omnitech gnome answer is that persistent
texture-mapping what is persistent
texture-mapping I'm not sure what that
means
oh I see what you're asking you were
trying to ask about what that extension
is I'm talking about I'm talking about
our buffer storage no persistent mapped
buffers yeah our buffer storage core 4.4
so it's this guy yeah
and and it's great like it's so good it
is hard to describe just how good I
think this is this is probably my
favorite extension of all time
I saw the tweet by sean barrett about
the Vulcan API versus the OpenGL API
what are the main flaws in the OpenGL
API are I'm sorry could you tell me what
tweet sean barrett is tweeted just for
context there I don't know the tweet
you're referring to if you could link to
it or something so I could read it
tweet passion Verret pound include
Vulcan / Vulcan H I can see they put a
lot of work into avoiding making the
same crust so I believe that is sean
barrett being snarky and basically
saying they didn't learn anything right
because obviously you would never want
to specify the path to a file because
why does the API have anything to do
with specifying a file path right that's
totally has nothing to do with C or
anything else and it's just kind of
ridiculous right
and I mean he's referring of course to
this
right opengl was exactly the same way
all right i'm gonna a pit up alrighty
thank you everyone for joining me for
another episode of handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you want to follow along with
at home or if you want to look at that
issues list be or submit to the private
issues list and stuff like that you can
always peer to the game on handmade hero
or get comes with the source code and a
bunch of other random stuff that you
might be interested in so check that out
if your should we also form site you can
go to if you want to ask questions we
have a patreon page you can go if you
want support the video series a schedule
bot that tweets to schedule at you if
you want to where we're going to be live
and an episode guide which you can use
to catch up on old streams I'll be back
here tomorrow same time same place 8
p.m. pacific daylight time until then
have fun programming everyone i'll see
you guys on the internet take it easy
everybody