hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we code a complete game
live on stream we are going to continue
playing around with what we've got now
there's just a it's kind of a wide-open
field there's tons of things to do and
so we're gonna do them I mean that's
just how it goes right so at the end of
the previous stream I if you were here
for that this morning we actually were
fixing some camera stuff and so in here
you can kind of see that we've now got
it so that the camera is nice and smooth
but we've got you know we we had a list
of camera bugs do you want to solve and
that was just one of them so you see
another one is correctly computing the
lighting area because we kind of we I
guess had some kind of hack in there
beforehand so that if you change like
the camera angles and stuff it will no
longer compute the correct area for that
and so we want to do something clean for
that and then we had a whole bunch of
other things too like we wanted the
rooms bigger rooms we want them to
scroll so like a room like this we
wanted to like scroll along with the
player so that's why it doesn't zoom out
as far as it probably should in that
case so because we wanted to scroll back
and forth and so if we're just looking
at these are things I'd like to get
those in there the other thing that I
would like to do is I'd like to get our
hero back in here like we've got our
little cats in there now and they're
using the correct art and I'd like to
get the hero in there as well and so I I
do want to think about that problem a
little bit more and so if if it's sort
of toss-up I'd like to put the hero back
in and so I'm thinking maybe that's what
we'll do like maybe we'll throw the hero
back in there first and get sort of that
stuff going because we really haven't we
haven't done the work to make to make
that happen uh so yeah let's do that and
the camera let's just focus on that and
get in it getting it going what I did
was I asked Anna to change the way that
the files were laid out for us just like
I said
and so if you go now to where's the
desktop there's if you go to your if
you're someone who pre-ordered the game
and you are on the you have your send
I'll download there's a new art pack art
pack too and you can see that like in
here there's bodies and heads now so now
like just like we said we wanted to now
there's just bodies and there's heads
and those are separate right so there's
now like no you know you you're gonna
think of those with totally different
things
and I know it's a little bit weird in
the human world because like if you look
there's like even different skin tones
on these now so you know like some
people have dark darker skins some
people have lighter skins feel have it
in between one of these is a baby
whatever but I mean it's a multicultural
world at this point so as far as I'm
concerned on handmade here you can put
any head on anybody that's just how it's
gonna go so like you know it doesn't
matter I'm not gonna say that you have
to have the right head on the right body
you can just have the head as the
character and the body is just whichever
one you happen to be in at the time it's
fine right so that's the way I wanted to
do it because I wanted those to be more
mix-and-match and and so that's what
we're gonna do so on here we we can
replace those ones that were welded
right the ones from before we can
replace those with the new files and so
they don't have to be sitting here in
pending anymore right so we can just
delete all these and take these ones
from the new art pack and we can drop
those directly in here right before I do
that though I kind of want to look at
these tags and just try to name them up
because you know how we've got these
like different tags that we're using
identify these things I want to be able
to identify all of these like orphans
and stuff by their traits the bodies
anyway the heads can just be arbitrary
right the heads are just like characters
so it's like you know
that's Ralph and that's you know Lisa or
something right
we'll have specific characters that go
with the head but the body is always
just you know kind of whatever the body
is and that's I don't know don't ask me
why that's just how we do it I mean
they're limbless orphans right it's a
that's maybe that's just how they are in
this fantasy world they don't have arms
and legs but they do have the ability to
have any body on any head that they want
because I mean that's how the world
works it's fine don't overthink it
someday in the real world with science
you'll be able to do that too you'll be
able to have your head moved on to a
different body and you it will be
arbitrary it won't have to look anything
like your head it doesn't have to look
the same like it has the same genetics
it can just be like yep we took this
head off of here and we stuck it on this
other body and now you have the other
body right who knows it could happen um
so I want to go ahead and label at least
the body parts I'm not sure how we want
to label the head parts per se because
you know I think we may just want to tag
them with their actual names you know
what I mean so we'll have to name each
of these each of these characters some
you know we'll have to name them
something right so we'll do that after
we do this because this one's a little
more straightforward so this one here is
the the standard hero body and so it's
gonna be like maybe just the the default
I guess is what I'd say like it it maybe
doesn't have a some watch tell me why I
can't hit the f2 key what's going on
with that Oh cuz I've been the zip file
sorry about that
I didn't mean to be in the zip file I
was supposed to unpack that I got
carried away I'm sorry I didn't mean to
get carried away like that so and I
didn't I started talking about what
we're gonna do and I didn't unpack it
let's unpack it into there there we go
and now we're good okay so I'm gonna go
ahead and turn on the preview here
there's like some kind of preview pane
nonsense right usually sometimes
possibly there it is preview pane and so
if we drag this over so we can kind of
see roughly here we're talking about
each of these kind of has some
properties associated with it
potentially right and so I'm gonna name
them like along with you know the the
properties that they have so the idea
behind this character originally was she
was going to be a little bit of like a
green thumb so she has like gardening
you know experience so this is this is
like an extra earth bonus in a sense
when you're playing this character and
so this would be like a like a earth
body I guess is what I'd call it the
Cure was sort of like it's the default
body I mean there isn't really anything
specific about it but I suppose like you
know body hero I don't know if I want to
leave the hero one in there because
maybe there is something special about
that I'm not entirely sure how we want
to look at that so we'll leave that up
so this character was like a tailor like
so this one has the ability like for
crafting you know what I mean would get
a bonus or anything that was along those
lines so you'd have like bonus for Earth
a bonus for crafting there this one
would is cooking bonus for cooking and I
guess I don't know about crafting suited
cuz its clothes clothing specifically so
it's like it's like tailoring you know I
don't know what you would really call
that
maybe like that yeah something like that
this one was like good with animals I
think this one was trying to remember
what these all worst that was sports
this one might be wintry the baby so
yeah I think this one was like this one
was sort of like more gothy like so a
little bit more so what I'm looking for
had like more like necromancy like sort
of sort of vibes you know what I mean
like a little bit more able to deal with
like nature I'm an undead stuff and so I
don't know what we would call that but
something like that
this was sports and trying to remember
like just in terms of the naming here so
I think it would be more like maybe more
like strength this one would be like
warmth right so this one is like
suitable for for cold climates so
insulated I guess I don't remember if
there's anything specific about this one
[Music]
don't really have a plan for that one
maybe I'll call these maybe I'll call
these ones like instead of insulated
I'll call them the season so we'll say
like winter there's like the winter one
there's the there's kind of a fall
looking one will call that fall do we
have a spring that seems spring-like to
me so I don't know what any of these
would have had specifically so maybe
since this one was generally a little
larger we'll call that like you know
resistance like it can it's it's not
really I guess it's not strength it's
more like taking more damage so it's
it's kind of like tanky you know and I
guess it's hard to say you know is that
the more wintery one or is that I think
that is in a sense and maybe that's
maybe that's more like spring and summer
kinds of stuff I don't know
let me see so what was the fall one
maybe we'll call that spring well so
this will be summer this will be spring
and this will be fall
so this one is the baby bottom and I'm
not sure what to make of the baby other
things of the babies awesome so you know
the baby we could have kept the baby as
two pieces but I think it would be even
funnier for some reason the baby can
have different bodies I think that it's
ridiculous but it's still probably good
ridiculous
I'm guessing and so yeah I don't know so
I guess what I would say is we need some
for these and these are kind of just
like generic like these two just look
like any any person to me right they
don't have any clear they don't have any
clear like suggestion of something that
they would be different you know in some
way and the baby unfortunately I would
say the same thing I mean it's a baby
but it's just generic baby so it's not
like it would really have any particular
thing about it otherwise so I'm not sure
so I might just call this one baby and
we'll think about what we do with it
later and then for these two I'm gonna
say like maybe them and the hero
maybe these are sort of just a couple
default bodies you can use and they
don't have any particular thing
associated with them you know tags wise
I guess that's what I could say so
that's one way I could do it the other
way I could do it is now I think that's
the way I want to do it I think that's
the way I want to do it and so with
these ones and the Kiro the problem is
they're just like I said kind of generic
like they don't they don't look like
they suggest anything and so in terms of
what the difference between them is
they're kind of just variants on the
same on just like it's a body right and
it could be anybody's and so I don't
know what to do to differentiate those
you know default0 default one and
default two seems like a bad idea but
that's kind of what they look like to me
and so maybe we'll just call those like
what are some things I would want to
have that are just like
look maybe one of them's like has more
health and one of them has like more
speed or something like so we'll just
say that that's how they work and they
don't necessarily you know line up with
that visually in some specific way
because who knows why you wouldn't
necessarily have that I mean people
don't look different when they have more
stamina in any particular way so who
knows so you know maybe this is just
like I'm just kind of making that up and
it's probably not great to have those
being things that are just like
arbitrary because you'd like the visuals
to like back that up but maybe we can
like redraw these slightly so that it's
like like maybe there's a lightning bolt
on it or something right and maybe like
for for the hero there's some difference
here like yeah I don't know and for the
health when maybe there's some reason
why this would be good maybe it's like a
medic kind of a looking thing or I don't
know right so we could like update some
of these a little bit in the future to
make them go better with whatever that
is and then we're just really left with
the hero who it's like I don't know you
know like I'm not sure I'm not sure what
there is about that it's just default
really
yeah so we already had a thing here
which was dark so I think maybe that
would go on here
as well so that's going to unify these
tags a little it for once we don't have
very many tags yet so I'm just gonna
kind of like get those in there if
there's anything actually lined up but
there really aren't because there aren't
very many right but just to the extent
that there would be um so in addition
here since these are all bodies of
humans you know I'm also gonna put in an
orphan tag they're probably just so we
can select specifically orphans versus
monsters versus whatever you know
and this may be dumb what I'm doing
because you know we have a lot more
editing features now and so it may be
that doing this stuff doing this markup
in in like the in the files is stupid
now and we could just do it inside an
editor in the game oops didn't want to
do that and I you know I'm just gonna
plow forward with how we're doing it for
the time being but we can always we can
always change that later right so if
those are all the bodies right then what
we need is like heads for orphans and so
like all of these here again we have
kind of have the problem of the hero
which is not really a label I'm I don't
know what the I guess we'll leave it as
hero for now but now we can label these
in some other way I suppose where like
they just have names because the heads I
guess will be specific so like whatever
you see that head it is that character
in a sense we don't really need the
orphan tag on it at all because the
character would uniquely identify it but
you know we'll see so I don't know what
I want to name these characters but I'm
just gonna make it up as I go along so
I'm gonna go with lease on that one I'm
just say that that's gonna be like maybe
that's like Brad
um I can't really see these very well
because they're little too tiny I get
there um I'm gonna
how about Carla I like Carla for that
maybe and maybe I could see that being
like a Jenni that's gonna be you know
some of these names I'm kind of just
picking generic names here I wonder if
that's too boring
is so cute is I feel like Drew might be
good
maybe
I'd like to put a Lambert in here just
not sure who the Lambert should be and
I'm saying to you maybe maybe that's
actually amber so I do think these were
a little bit too maybe maybe that's
actually like that's actually like
Cassidy is that a name
that's funny
it's this is actually someone's stage
name I guess or something like and it's
telling me their actual name it's the
hip hop artist that is funny
no I wanted this yeah curly-haired well
I don't know the hair's not that curly
but oh well
so let's see we're back to this this
saucy gentleman here
maybe that's wrong
maybe that's like weird
I could see like is Laird a good name
these baby-naming sites are kind of
crazy
this is not helpful Lord of the land
seems fine to me
none of these are orphans so technically
none of them is the Lord of the land but
I mean this one doesn't have curly hair
either so you know the naming can't
always be so accurate I think that one
was like the Christian Slater orphan so
I think maybe we'll we'll have to call
him something related like let's call
him Slade
I feel like that's like a Rhoda is it
that way is that a name I don't really
love boring names so I kind of like was
trying to give them generic names and it
just didn't work so yeah I mean well you
know there's a TV series with someone
named Anna which you know I've never
seen but it's seems plausible that it's
a name they thought it was because they
named a character that so why can't I
that's the baby
that's that's gonna be that's gonna be
Giles that's gonna be these two are
gonna be the hardest how about her I'm
not sure
you know I could see the speaking of
Dylan actually maybe this is so I know
Aviva is a name but is Viva
a name yeah so I think that's Viva and
this is gonna be like it's gonna be Tony
I think honestly it might be Tony well
it could be Anthony so we're down the
last one here it's a tough call
I'm sorry I don't know I really don't
know
Gordon Tony I'm just not getting a lot
of great name vibes from this guy
how about Klein so the only problem
we've got now I'm pretty happy with the
rest of those names those are all pretty
good Lisa's not doing it for me though
at this point so I'm thinking maybe we
need something a little fancier here she
have there her hair maybe Asian styled
like you know she's got like a pulled
back into a tight bun so maybe we could
give her more like an Asian name like
right yeah maybe maybe you like sunny
yeah maybe something like that I could
give her an actual mitt Asian first name
I probably wouldn't be able to say it
right though I guess I could say it
right if it was Japanese I wouldn't be
able to say right who's Chinese or
Korean I don't not a pronounced most
other Asian languages or Vietnamese or
any anything really pretty much only
know how to pronounce Japanese yeah I'm
gonna stick with sunny
alright so I think that's all our
orphans for now you can always add more
orphans that's and that's true of any
game or any work of any kind really so I
want to go ahead and import those in and
they're they're pretty straightforward
because we already have the tags set up
for importing these just in general so I
should be able to like copy the body and
head stuff I should be able to use the
top half of character in the bottom half
of character as the import rules for
those so we really shouldn't have to do
anything special there right so what I
should be able to do is I should be able
to go edit the tags and just add in the
tags in this case that we need that are
new so the ones that come from you know
the rest of this stuff so we would have
a tag baby a tag cook a tag dark where
it exists earth tag fall tag health hero
it's already attack here
I'm major tech speed and you know nature
might be the wrong way to do it so let's
call it fauna tag spring spring summer
Taylor tank and winter and we also need
tag orphan that's just a separate thing
that's gonna get shoved in there now you
can already kind of see like we're so
one of the things we're gonna have to do
soon as we pull all this stuff in the
game we'll have to finally go really do
a final tag matcher because you don't
want to be doing these the way that we
were doing them anymore because you can
kind of see how huge these vectors would
be if we were doing them non sparse so
it's just dumb the way they're being
done currently but you know again
computers are so fast these days that
sometimes it takes up you have to get
pretty far down the line before it
actually starts getting slow and so just
take my word for it it will be slow it's
just hasn't quite hit there yet right so
in here too
we've got like the I think we've already
got in the assets themselves we already
have like bodies and heads right so we
don't actually need to make that
distinction that's already in there so
in here we have the heads so we just
need all these we've got tagged baby
and so tagged baby and tagged hero
should really probably be specific
because they're actual characters and
then we just go through this we've got
you know Brom
we've got Carla we've got Cassidy we've
got through Dylan
Giles hero put it there Clym Baird
Lambert rota suede it's actually I think
supposed to be sunny with a you right
yeah and so we've got our you know we've
got our named characters in here so
that's all good and then we need inside
of our tag sets to be able to get all
these in there right cuz they're all new
here's where macros would be helpful
Allen now it's probably busy this is
where you would want a keyboard macro
cuz this hold you know well what you
want is not a keyboard macro obviously
what you want is a programming language
with introspection because then you
don't have to do this typing in the
first place
but hey beggars can't be choosers right
all right and last set and the reason
you want to inspect adjust case anyone
couldn't already tell is that you want
to be able to talk about things in code
very easily and things that come from
outside the code itself have to have
ways of corresponding to things that
happen inside the code and the only way
to usually do that is with some kind of
string and so if you want to get some
some type checking you know you need to
define those somewhere and otherwise you
won't get any type checking you know
what I mean and so doing that in C is
just and C++ is horrible because they
never added any compile time code
execution they never added meta
programming of any real kind they never
added introspection and it's just a
disaster and I think they've got a
working group working on it now but
thirty years is too late it's just too
late that should have been in their day
too I mean it's a basic feature of
programming languages in my opinion and
I just I have no idea why it was not in
there
so now we just have that set of tags
available and we can import the bodies
and the heads in there so I'm gonna go
ahead and set that up you can see here
we've got you know the import stuff
that's going to come in here and one of
the things that we've got is an import
type that says like you know are you
what are you loading like a body a head
or whatever right and so where that ends
up being there it is so in here you can
see like we have the character sheet and
we want to have two ways of doing that
we want one to be if you're actually
processing the whole character and then
we also want you to be able to put in a
head or a body separately right so we
want you to be able to do both of these
and this is still the correct iteration
but you know it's we it's it's the
correct inner peace but the outer peace
we only want to do like directly one of
you know what I mean
so this we want to share and you know
the Y index mod for part here like just
kind of still works in either case so I
believe what we want to do is just in
this part here say like this is a head
and you know
you know what I mean now actually this
is backwards that's how that actually
goes and so then in these we want to do
the same and so now we just have to like
extract this piece out of you know of
the the import grid I think that's
basically what we do
[Music]
something like that I mean another way
to do that would be since the tag stuff
is never really discussed anywhere else
you probably actually do it more like
this right
I think that just works so if I was
going to pull that out then all I really
need to do is copy this stuff
this becomes import body what's that
called again a tag court grid tag so in
here we just say import body and we need
all the things that we have here so we
would need game assets we need the X
index and the why index we need file
name and errors
and I'm not sure we really need anything
else I'm pretty sure that's all done at
that point
so I'm gonna say that just works and
then here this can just do an import
body or an import head depending on
which one you actually we're in and then
up here we'll say that there's another
one of those that is internal report
grid tag for the head like so and we say
import head game assets asset I'm get
the file name
there's mix index and the wine index
right I'm not gonna think too hard about
that I'm just gonna say that's fine
there's other ways we could do that that
may be better or clever or but I'm not
gonna care about that and in here I'm
gonna take the liberty of subtracting
3/4 or rather away from this so that
those actually start at 0 it will matter
because this code actually mods by for
anyway so but just in case we start
looking at the value directly that way
these will always have the same X&amp;Y
indexes regardless of whether they came
from a head only body only or combined
file they'll still work right and so
then I also now want to trigger the
import so I want to say here look it's
you know it's a multi tile import in
either of these cases whether it's head
or body or anything else and I think
that's it so now those should like pull
in you know I
who knows if they will or not we haven't
really pounded on this code path much
but basically that's the long short of
it um so in here I'm gonna say let's go
ahead and do the results that we you
know will generate it here that brings
gives us
back to the import grid tag thing and we
should be I guess I gotta do the same
here we should be good to go with that
and then hopefully that'll get pulled
into the HHA so that now we'll have
those available and you know who knows
if it'll work
but in theory it should so you know we
got the game here and we say like okay
why don't you do an import and we'll let
that go we don't have a progress bar yet
sadly but you know now it's just gonna
go through and glued all that junk in
and parse all those things so now it has
theoretically it has so now our HHH HHH
have that which means that if we want to
now we should be able to actually access
those things and again don't know if
that's actually true because we have
really not played with this kind of code
much yet but we can certainly try so if
we now go to like where we create like a
hero or something and we want to see if
we can actually get you know a body in
there I don't want a shadow at the
moment so I'm not gonna put that in
there and we're kind of look mostly at
this there's not gonna be a cape anymore
there's just gonna be the hero and I
don't I mean I think I'll leave it like
that temporarily I don't know I'm not
you know what I'm really not gonna do
that
I'm just gonna do this for now and say
that's what the size of the hero is and
we'll play with that a little bit later
and Indies I'm not gonna specify
anything yet
although the glove will probably need to
put in a in a different place as far as
peace moving is concerned I don't know
why this isn't set to being Bob bass
because I thought it was supposed to
like hop and stuff
so I'm I don't really know maybe that
gets set in here with these controllers
and so maybe that's why that's happening
there I'm not sure what they look but
anyway you know in here when we add
these pieces we now need to do the
connections on those so much like how we
added you know the cat I don't know if
you remember that but now that we
actually have sort of skeletons
happening here whenever we add new
things we have to connect them up so if
you look at here how that's working we
need to do essentially this it's exactly
the same thing and for the glove
I don't really know like that the glove
is a little depressing because the glove
kind of wants to be its own entity so
I'm not sure like I might say that
really shouldn't be there honestly
Oh oh never mind okay I take it all back
there's a there is a separate entity for
the glove so that's actually fine so
these actually are good like I have no
qualms with that like the glove and the
body yeah okay that's good
and so really all we need to do here is
make sure the body is connected to the
head and so that's fine actually okay
that's all good so we have the the body
here and the head here and I guess
what's happening there is like yeah the
the head was moving separate from the
body cuz of dodging there whatever huh
I mean I'll be honest I could leave it
that way for now maybe I will but we
should think about how we want to
animate that a little bit more in the
future all right so if I didn't want to
do anything there that also explains why
this thing didn't have to get set to any
kind of animation parameter there um so
if I want to keep it that way then
really what happens is we don't connect
these up at all they're all separate
things floating in the world getting
animated separately as completely
separate pieces and that's fine
Oh what is the complaint here let's see
and these need to get tagged out as well
which we haven't done yet but those are
all entities body had in glove oh and
right my mistake sorry cannot convert
from any visible piece to entity that's
a good point
so connect peace to world it's inside
entity can I assume and probably just
needs to get expose so that other people
can call it so we need to tag these out
somehow so much like in the entity gen
when we do the cat we need some way of
tagging this entity with tags that mark
who it is you know what I mean so when
we do an ad player I guess you know we
were we weren't calling these directly
because we create little ad specs and
then add them in but in here we are
creating the player directly so we kind
of want to just be able to do this
directly here what I mean
and so we know this is a budding is
ahead we want to add to these things we
want to be able to set the tag so we
know this is like an orphan and we know
that this is the hero for now right and
that's going to be true on the head as
well on the glove we know this is a
glove I'm not sure we know that it's
anything else
it's got fingers other than that I'm
really not sure
okay so inside and again this ad tag
probably also has to get exposed there
so the people can be calling it I think
that's it um okay so now in theory like
looks like we have our orientations
backwards there you can't tell that
that's true because you can't see me
clicking it but you're just gonna have
to trust me it is so we have some tag
issues and we'll have to kind of figure
out what's going on with those we can
add some editing features to help us
with that as well
but but all that's fine for now so you
know we looks kind of fine here I don't
really want to change these but for the
most part you know these these are
selecting the correct things to a
certain extent and so you kind of see
like the scale is bad and all that but
otherwise you know we're not too far off
so I want to know did I accidentally did
I specify the wrong height there some
hat like the wrong selection let's see
what happens with the Berman's they're
like right up left down right up left
down so don't know if I screwed
something up there in terms of facing
direction but I may have either way I
think if we just go in here and set this
down to a more reasonable size we should
be in better shape
all right
I might want to make the debug light not
so big giant cube over my head as well I
still don't know if there's a reason why
we actually put lights in four cubes
when we put cube lights on because we
want the ability to light things
probably without doing that
that makes sense so when we do this push
cube here and we put in a mission in
there you know I wonder if it should
really be like this of course I don't
know if that'll affect the emitter but
see so that way the lights are just not
so gonna risk their right um so yeah so
basically what I want to do now is go
figure out why we're getting that
reflection problem there if I were
getting those things split up and then
we're also picking the lean left lean
right version of that of the body which
I suppose I can temporarily not do by
just picking one of the different bodies
but I'm not sure that's that's not its
immediate the most pressing concern like
the most pressing concern is why does
the head not pick the right angle I do
like the fact that the default head now
is the baby that's pretty awesome
all right sorry I got a little carried
away there it's fun to hop around in
this thing which is a good sign I
suppose so yeah I kind of want to to
figure out what's going on there so you
know I don't know if this is a good time
to maybe focus on the debug stuff a
little bit there where in addition to
looking at things like the HHA editing I
wonder if I want to be able to say look
show me what this entity is currently
doing in terms of picking like what are
the tags on it and stuff like that
so that I can see them and similarly
like when I pick one of these things
like what are the tags on that because
you know I don't know and so like in
when we're when we're assigning these
things and and I also don't know like
for the cat like so let's say you made
it what if you made a cat instead so
instead of this you just said that's not
an orphan it's a cat right would it also
be facing wrong direction or is it only
you know ma only the the split heads and
bodies that are picking the wrong facing
directions because that's like a
relevant piece of debugging information
there right so if I said the body in the
head we're actually cats you know what I
mean
said of orphans what would I get in this
case right
so yeah like those are correct
so that's not fabulous so it means that
there's something wrong with the import
when I did it and I don't know what did
I screw up so that's unfortunate I I
made a I made a boo-boo and I don't know
why
so in both of these cases I'm iterating
over all of these things and then I'm
asking it to do an import and we've got
import body and import head right and
then I'm sitting the tags back this way
you know this routine if I screwed it up
that's not really relevant because we
didn't use this routine this routine
never got called only using these two
that's it so when we do like import head
or import body there's got to be some
reason why it's screwed up so in here we
take the Y index mod for that should
just be 0 1 that should be and I pass in
the wrong thing now
so I don't know what did I do wrong
there the X index is not really relevant
the Y index looks totally fine and as
far as the head is concerned so you know
it's 0 1 2 3 and it would be 0 again 1 2
3 I guess are we going the wrong
direction there though but if we were
going the wrong direction it should have
been wrong in the other one as well
well
I can't guess so I'm just gonna have to
debug there's really not much more to it
than that
so for some reason when we got in here
and we were doing an import head I guess
I also don't know am I am I let slip
straight to another one of those
characters make sure it's wrong
everywhere and not just on the hero and
for some reason but yeah so assuming
that we assuming that we add player here
instead of the hero maybe I can say that
the body type is going to be we had like
the strength body for example and then
at the top of its gonna be I don't know
maybe it's maybe it's layered
so like it's literally just the hero
that has the problem like Laird is
totally right how about somebody else
like I wonder if that's cuz we had like
old data in there that it's that's like
conflicting with it or something I don't
know so you know if we said what about
the baby like what if it's the baby
instead
I gotta turn those particles off or at
least get some real particles in there
so essentially everybody works except
for the hero and it's just wonder if
that that does kind of seem a little
suggestive at this point and I do wonder
if that has something to do with yeah
all right
I'm gonna turn those particles off
temporarily where we spawn them
but anyway at least we got sort of what
I wanted now it looks like we've got a
bug in there now would be a good time to
start working on the camera game look at
debug can write like you can kind of see
there's some garbage there at the top of
the head that I don't think should be
there and that may also be an import
problem like it's not just an import
prob it may be a art source art problem
it's hard to say if I open it up let me
see here open it in
so looking at the baby's head if I load
in the template and I just put it over
here I just want to make sure that it's
actually correctly aligned it looks like
it is though so it looks like some kind
of a asset problem I can't get to move
this there we go
so that looks like it was fine I mean
there's plenty of clearance around there
so I'm not sure what was going on there
with the baby head but it does look like
we've got a import bug on the baby head
I do think also we're a little tinier
than we should be so well three was too
big I think maybe one is too small that
seems like probably more the size it
should be
and so now also we're gonna have to have
some some code in there for you know the
head now is gonna be controlled by the
by the art a little bit more probably
you know it's a little bit hard to say
but
so that mean what's that actually just a
texture transfer issue because you can
if you notice it's not there now
interesting so I wonder if we have a
texture transfer issue there where we
were properly clearing out ooh some like
we were transferring a little bit larger
than we should have been or something
because you can see we're not actually
getting that bug interesting well
alright so let's go from here and see
what's happening if I actually look at
the alignment points for this thing and
I want to align it with the ground it's
gonna be more like there and I kind of
want this thing to have a base of neck
and I want the head to attach to it
probably like that's probably what we
want to do but in order to do that I
have to reduce some of the dependence on
the head code which I don't know to what
extent that's okay you know maybe it's
fine and you know we could test it out
now by just saying all right look the
head is actually now on the body and
we're gonna connect the head to the body
like so so the head piece is actually
its body piece base of neck head piece
default okay so now there are no pieces
on the head so even though the brain
will still move the head around it won't
actually do anything with it and so you
know
you will allow us to see what this is
gonna look like before we pull the head
controller code out because we don't
really know what's gonna happen there
it's a little bit Squinkie see we got a
transfer issue there right there's like
a texture transfer issue there we
probably have some kind of a load race
condition when we or it's the other
thing we could be doing is running out
two extra handles but I think we should
assert in that case right so we'll see
but anyway let's suppose I actually you
know again one thing at a time we have a
ton of stuff to work on now so let's
suppose I actually align this thing with
the world which would be like something
like that right and then I add the base
of neck thing and I don't know exactly
where that should be but like probably
probably like maybe there something like
that and then the head needs to be
aligned like basically like that I guess
and that I think is roughly how the baby
looks right and so just want to look at
how the hopping looks it actually looks
great yeah that actually looks great and
the head does need a little bit of a Z
offset to avoid the Z freighting
obviously but otherwise that just looks
fabulous so let me do the other ones too
right like
so I don't really know and you know I
can kind of like swap this all around
right it looks about right
I'm not out for such yeah I don't really
know but something like this
looks about right you can see why I
wanted an editor for these because can
you imagine not having one like there's
so much art even when you just do a
little bit of importing work there's so
much stuff that just if you couldn't do
it with an editor you would you would go
mad right
you
all right
I think that's probably great
so that's pretty fun I mean that is just
a fun that is just fun um sooo pretty
happy with how that all is coming
together like I said we want to probably
put a little bit of a Z in there for the
head just to give it an offset so that
it floats above the body a little bit I
don't know how much it should be but we
got to find out what that bug is right
there to that transfer bug like what's
happening there but anyway that may be a
little much I think that's what I wanted
all right so I'm pretty happy exploring
around with that little baby it's very
satisfying for some reason I get some
pass through on see that Z clipping
there so I think our yeah we still
probably have a lot of work to do with
our legacy by a stuff it looks like our
Z bias is actually doing the opposite
thing it should be doing there something
like that we've got a lot of work to do
to polish up our graphics here but it's
coming along folks
we kind of need that glove to follow
along with us by the way I don't think
that would be that hard would it I mean
it should just be floating along with us
and then when we hop it hops with us so
I don't know why it's doing what it's
doing at the moment I don't even know
that I don't even remember writing much
glove code so I think it's probably just
doing some random residual stuff who
knows what but I'm liking that so I
think now you know that that's good let
me set ourselves to somebody who's not
busted who is also not the baby and
we'll pick like you know try to figure
out what the right size is so let's
let's take let's take one of these
assets here and maybe we'll pick maybe
we'll pick cassadee and we'll use
actually know what let's do Viva instead
and we will use maybe the spring outfit
so let's set this one up we've never
edited this our asset so it needs to be
aligned as well and so in terms of where
it should sit it's probably like roughly
there ish I would say and again remember
we have to fix although our Z bias tough
so the fact that interpenetrates is
correct like it's supposed to come out a
little bit there right so let's say base
of neck let's place that it's pretty
clear where the base in neck is on this
model it's like actually pretty explicit
what why do I still have a baby head
what's that about
it's not just a tag matching error did I
actually screw that up
Oh
so interestingly enough the tags on the
head so this should actually this is
wrong the tags are supposed to be on the
body now right sorry about that that
explains a lot
right it's vive and she is in the spring
dress it's actually what's going on
there
all right
there we go and we need to edit her head
and set where that goes so that's base
of neck is probably roughly there right
so that's looks sized properly to me
meaning that does look like the size
that the orphan should be so I think we
have the scale set at least somewhat
right
oops
the weight heaven do god it's so weird
we've got like so much advanced stuff
I'm like oh wait I don't have to like
re-edit that thing I have undo all right
so
probably like roughly there keep doing
that
okay that seems better
I want to be able to hide stuff now you
know what I mean
so I can place these things without with
being able to see through them sort of
it's really weird stuff going on with
these texture poles that might be an art
asset error though we'll find out but we
got some debugging to do suffice to say
all right last one
oh whoops I didn't mean that at the hand
and think that's
probably about right
and that seems pretty good
so I'm relatively happy with that
I don't see any obvious problems with
like perspective there we need to get
the Z bias working again and you know
accurately so that we don't have this
sort of problem with the you know
interpenetration there but in terms of
looking proper it seems pretty good
so I think that will probably work just
fine now there is of course the fact
that it feels like the scale wants to be
somewhere around there but it's kind of
ridiculous because the orphans then are
like really much too large for like the
walls and stuff um so there is that and
I don't really know what to do about
that exactly
probably nothing
I mean we'll just try we'll just try and
make sure that our Z bias works so we
don't get that like clipping and you
just that's just what it looks like and
we make sure that you know yeah I mean I
don't I don't know what else we could
really do because you know that seems
like roughly what it should look like
and maybe it's a little large you know I
mean maybe it's like maybe it's like
should be somewhere more around there
but it's still gonna be a problem
because they're still like yeah but at
least they're you're not taller than the
wall so so maybe that's better and then
we only need a little bit of Z biasing
there to fix like the problems where you
would clip through the wall in those
circumstances right but that seems
pretty good otherwise
all right I'm pretty happy with that I
don't know how much time I've got left I
would like to get the debug camera going
probably now we got a lot of stuff to
work on like you know I mean there's a
hundred things to work on now so we got
tons of things like we've got we've got
some import problems we've got some
transfer problems so I think you know in
looking at some of these things I'm just
like where's that coming from right like
if I look in the source assets I'm not
sure that that's there like I'm not sure
that's a bug that maybe our bug and
again it's hard to say so if I go into
handmade art that's vive right so well
yeah I think it's just probably the arts
wrong
yeah the arts just wrong so that's just
an art bug you can see here if I open up
like the grid and do the same thing I
did before I think this time we'll
actually see that it's busted
so that's not our fault right that's
that's actually the the art assets just
wrong and that's not a big deal right
the artist can then just go edit that
later and so we can raid bugs on stuff
like that
I guess that tells me what I do want to
do right now though is you know inside
the in-game editor we know in theory
anyway I think that for any given entity
in the system we should have tracked the
errors on the entity in the system which
means that in the asset stuff here baked
into the annotations should be the
errors
so if one were so inclined we should be
able to write a function because there's
gonna be like a write string function in
this in the asset system write asset
string so there there can be like a
reverse version of this so if you want
to read an asset string you should be
able to do a thing where you say like
hey tell me you know get get an asset
string out of the the file and you can
pass in some kind of a like some kind of
a place to put it so I don't know what
like the I don't know what the best way
to do this would be because in theory
you really don't want to be reading
things out of files a lot of times so if
you're really gonna be mister saucy
pants about it you would probably go and
actually be specific about how you would
cache these things but I don't think I
care so probably all I would do here is
say look tell me where to put it and
that's it right
so I'd say okay tell me what the count
and offset is for this string and and
I'll go read it and so in here we would
have a thing that was like platform read
data from file you know you want to read
from from this thing and here's the
offset we have this count and then it's
just we need that space right so we
would just say and also we in here we'd
say well the count is the count and the
data for the buffer is going to be a
push size of whatever the count is in
the
Marie that you're asking for or that
you're telling me right so and then we
read that thing and so I think that is
all we would really need if we wanted to
display the error messages in the
in-game editor meaning that like you
know when we have the HHA in here or
whatever and then there's like the asset
editor and and whatever else right in
this call here after we're done like
this begins section thing for any asset
we should be able to do a different
section and so like this may be where we
say yeah this is the info section and in
the info section I'm gonna print some
stuff out I guess right I mean that
seems cool enough and so in here I could
print out like information about the
asset
and I don't know that should just work
prop probably I don't actually know but
I don't see why it wouldn't so the
reason I want to do that it's because
then I don't have to let go dump the h
@j or anything to like figure out what's
going on so you know if I come back here
I don't know what's what's going on here
but if I come back here and I you know I
look at one of these you know in theory
there's like an info flag here and that
could now like print out like errors and
stuff if there were errors so you know
going back to the file in question for
that asset we know in the annotation so
here we know that that has the
information about where the thing came
from and the errors that might have been
on it so in theory if I ask it to give
me back some of that stuff like all of
this stuff I should be able to see it
you know so like for example if I say
name I could do like read assets string
and I could say well here's the asset
name offset and here's the asset name
count I don't really remember even
though I just wrote it what the format
was there but it's like you know assets
and then the assets file
and we know what that is because every
asset says which file it's from so we
can get that so we can say hey read the
asset string there and use like the
frame use the frame arena because we're
just gonna render this string although
honestly I don't even really need to do
that I could just use a temporary no
because we do a label F on this thing so
we're already pushing all of the stuff
onto it so I don't even really need to
do that
what I'm basically talking about here is
this I mean I could do that I don't
really know again like this would
probably all just go into the frame
arena because definitely no reason not
to it doesn't really make any sense to
do an actual allocation in here to give
this thing a block of memory but you
know point being that would be all you
really would need to do so asset file
there's a count and the offset it should
look like oops
should look like that and then once you
get that piece of information we should
be able to just print it so if we do
that like you know name that we should
just then be able to like dump those
strings in order I think
so who knows maybe that'll work maybe
that won't but in theory that is
supposed to do something relating to
something so we'll see what goes on here
I don't remember if these assets have
names because I guess they haven't ever
been named in any particular way that I
know of so I would print out some things
that we think should actually be there
because inside the asset there are some
that that we definitely are setting and
so for example I think the author should
be set to Anna and then we can also dump
the error stream and the source file
base name like you know that stuff
should have been in there
name and description I don't know that
we ever set but if we like we just grab
this
I know what I want to call this but well
actually I guess this is name and this
is value so if we did something like
this then we could easily print out a
lot of these and so I can just say all
right there's a UI layout for its rwi
layout that I pass in here I give it the
name of the thing that I'm doing and
then I give it like you know how I'm
gonna load this thing so I say what the
count and the offset is and then it just
does you know that and I would like I
don't want to do and like I said any
kind of like allocation there so I think
I do want to just do that right and so
then in here I should always be able to
now say like annotation label and I can
give it the layout in the temporary now
and I can say name and then I can say a
no-name asset name offset a nano asset
name or app said description offset and
oops sorry asset name count and then in
theory we should be able to do like the
other ones on here as well so there's
like that one
there's the author and the airstream
source file base name for some reason I
skipped some I'm gonna just say like
yeah source and then we'll just see if
that gives us anything interesting I
don't know why assets is being passed
there because it doesn't actually do
anything
so that should really just do that and
it should just take the asset file I
would argue
and that is about all there is to it
layout asset file temporary 'no name
count offsets those backwards so now the
question is do we actually get any of
those and I think this is actually air
stream right uh doesn't even work you
know and I have no idea
interesting so when we try to print this
out we're getting a out-of-bounds fetch
here so our code point our code points
reading out of out of bounds but it
shouldn't really be possible right so
the bitmap ID in this case should have
come back when we say get bitmap for
glyph if it comes back out of Bounce it
should still work right I can see what's
happening there it's just hitting the
new line but that shouldn't cause an
assertion really unless maybe it's just
trying to tell us that we were trying to
draw something that was out of bounds
which could be true I'm gonna go ahead
and since it's a reliable run I'm gonna
let it give me the error in debug mode
so I can just double check it myself
so it's just bitmap ID value zero which
is to say there wasn't one so really
this is just garbage because it was
supposed to allow you to do that right
so that was just us kind of screwing up
that port that that was not that was not
really what was supposed to happen so
when you get the you know when you get
the bitmap info here I'm gonna allow it
to do that because that's so you're
supposed to be able to get the invalid
ones too
so all I wanted to point out now was
that in theory our system knew about
that error and so I kind of wanted to
make sure that we could see it it's
zooming that it did actually in fact no
and so you can see here we've got the
source file
we don't have names of descriptions and
we have who the author was correctly set
you can see here that like for for some
of these it's telling us the error tile
0 to extends into bottom a pixel border
that's what that was right there and
apparently it thinks that that's true of
this as well so I'm not sure that files
must all be aligned wrong basically and
so that's fine we probably want to
highlight things that have an error
stream when they get drawn they get
highlighted you know sue in here you can
see we're getting like texture transfer
problems there or load problem you know
something is going wrong that it's not
that the file is bad because if we run
it again we don't get that right so we
know that's a problem with how we're
like when we load stuff out we're not
properly getting the
the transfer to happen the way that it
should so like inside like load asset
work or something when we're actually
doing this complete texture up like
either that like either the texture
transfer is not actually waiting for us
to have actually finished you know what
I mean or we're doing something else
stupid there but you know that something
along those lines it's like an
unpredictable failure is occurring and
so we have to get that solved so yeah
let me double check that there's nothing
weird going on in there because I feel
like if that could easily just be if we
screwed up the loop in here so that like
we didn't properly you know don't
properly stop the texture transfer
somehow or I don't know
hmm but it looks pretty good right so
these should be set to pending load
so when we hit begin texture up
oh well okay I mean yeah so I guess you
know technically I suppose this can't
this shouldn't be happening because
we're not multi-threaded so this
probably isn't the bug but otherwise it
would have been the bug right you can
see it right here we increment the OP
count before setting the pending load
flag so you know that's obviously not
what you would want to do honestly
though this is synchronous so you know
it doesn't matter
that isn't the bug I'm too used to
looking at things multi-threaded I'm
like oh god this has all these bugs but
like yeah it's not multi-threaded we
only run multi-threaded for like our
lighting computations and the deferred
loading so that's actually fine you know
it'll get set depending load before
anyone could possibly have taken a look
at it
so one thing that we maybe want to do
there is maybe we want to clear the
memory here just so I can see whether
this is an overwrite problem or whether
it's a not filled yet problem so when we
get the transfer memory here I'm just
gonna do real quickly like a mem set
basically I'm just gonna say look for
the entirety of this thing however much
you know the size that you requested
right or maybe I'll just do it like here
for that whole thing set that to
something known like maybe just zero
or maybe full white you know or
something like that and you know that
way we'll see solid white in any case
where and I don't know if I data may not
be a u8 there yeah and that way we would
see solid white instead of a noise
pattern which would give me a little bit
more information about what was going on
there if it's just that we haven't like
filled it in yet of course the problem
is getting it to screw up again you know
you've got to be able to actually make
it screw up
which at the moment doesn't seem to want
to do so yeah maybe not
why won't you break well that's not
great because I kind of wanted to debug
that but I guess we'll have to wait for
a better repro case one could assume
that we maybe we can get a clue from
that if it turns out that just the act
of having that in there is sufficient to
make sure that you don't see the bug
that's also a clue but I'm guessing that
it's not that we just like we're not
hitting it right now for whatever
magical reason right and that does seem
to be the case so so we'll have to hold
off on that for a little bit I'll go
ahead and go to the Q&amp;A now
and we will take it from there I I do
also think that you know now one of the
things that is nice is we can put
orphans around the orphanage you know
which we couldn't do before so we can
also have that happening which I think
would be fun and you know that's pretty
easy right because it's just a that's
it's exactly the same as AD cat you know
it's we don't really have to do anything
to put in those things if we want to add
an orphan then we can just set up the
orphan and the body in the head part
pretty much just is the same as the cat
I mean really everything's the same so
anywhere and here we were using add
orphan and add cat you know you could
almost add just it's really just the
same call but it would be it would vary
slightly once we actually get more stuff
going on so at that point if you wanted
to in the world Jen right you know where
we add like cats and stuff in the place
cat thing like
you know we can just add orphans in
there
and I don't really know how we want to
do that exactly but you know if you just
did this mm-hmm also don't ask me why we
don't have those tags a little bit
differently here though but you know if
we wanted to start placing the orphans
around we could just say like you know
it's an orphan so you know that's gonna
happen up in here and we'd have one of
these things where we place the orphans
and we'd have Jen options for orphans
and really nothing happened special in
here because we want to do more stuff
eventually but for the moment we just
like play some orphans so in here we'd
say like alright let's just place some
orphans here so for example leered we'll
go in mmm and that's it
you know what I mean and since we know
that orphans are individuals in a sense
we could just put roll that in there
directly where we just say yeah like
whoever that is
where's the asset tag ID I'm so you can
just say like put everyone in there you
know we can just say like let's put
people in there and you want like
everybody so here's all the orphans
and they're now gonna be all placed it's
well the heroes not going to get placed
we need to set up some other tags as
well but you know that's the basic idea
and so when we're creating things here
where we iterate over options you can
see here that there'd be options in
these things for the various orphans
if you can't place one here then we just
say you know you don't add that orphan
so that's fine and so if we just added a
few options to who might be in here you
know we probably want to do like a
couple of these but all of these can
have an orphan and the cat probably
right I mean you know why not and the
garden has an orphan so I don't know
something like that and then you would
have like orphans around the orphanage
which is what you would expect because
it's would be kind of dumb if it was an
orphanage that had no orphanage right
and right now we don't do any work to
place the entities in the rooms they
just stack up at the bottom but hey like
at least the orphans are in there now
and so you know we can go like align
them properly and stuff if we want to
but at least it starts to be a little
more gamey like we can place people
around there and who knows what the
orphans are doing probably want to give
them some agency so they can hop around
and do stuff but you know now any room
be going we'll probably have an orphan
in it or something oh I think there's an
orphan blocking our path out there we're
gonna have to read a Bolivia bug camera
so we can see but I believe there's an
orphan blocking or exit so yeah
let's see what we're talking about here
are you going to create a level editor
no the game's entirely procedural so we
will be doing level editing in terms of
code like everything that we generate
has to be able to be programmed in in
some kind of like a logical way of
creating it if that makes sense also by
the way the lighting bounds are just
driving me nuts so I'm gonna hack those
for a second we'll fix them later so
yeah like in here I don't know why we
were really even doing this I think we
were just acting this in originally cuz
it's obviously stupid but I'll just
expand it for now so if we say it bounds
equals can we do a Minkowski grow on
these things or can we do an ADD radius
yeah so if I just make it larger can I
avoid having that horrible weird looking
stuff yeah so this will be slower
because the lighting is now covering a
much too large of an area you're right I
mean but I'm okay with that temporarily
all right
any thoughts of using deal DL opened at
all to do some hot lunching and stuff up
with the feedback loop
sorry no idea what you're talking about
we already do hot load everything so if
you want to you can just hot load code
all the time that's what I did with the
lighting bounds just then I don't know
if you noticed it but we didn't restart
the game you and I mean so like in here
if we just say oh yeah you know don't do
that then you know it's compiling over
here right when it's done compiling
it'll the lighting bounce will be
screwed up right cuz now it's reloaded
the code and then if you just you know
make a pilot it's fixed
how does the back buffer work when you
resize the window do you create a new
back buffer matching the window size
when the window is resized no at the
moment we actually start up the game in
some specific resolution that we want
and we scale that to the window size
afterward and that will probably remain
the way we do it later although we may
occasionally change the back buffer size
the reason we don't want to change the
back buffer size every time you know
just to fit the window is because we may
like only run fast enough at like 1080p
or something and then if they have like
a 4k display we don't want to just run
really slowly and beyond 4k we're on a
run like 1080p and then stretch you know
what I mean so we want the back buffer
to to not really be in sync with the
window size except potentially very
loosely if that makes sense
um and so I don't know if we really need
this to be quite as large as it is so
maybe like
I'm just totally screwing with this by
the way don't do this at home yeah so
we'll compute that correctly later don't
worry I'm not gonna leave it that way
quick question what exactly is theirs we
had temporary 'no framer unit as the
temporary negate collective that
suffering oh yeah like I don't really
want to do what we did there I was just
saying well it's the other I would care
what I do so it's fine but you know
what's up it's just important to
understand always what's actually
happening in your code and I happen to
understand it so I didn't say it but
that was you know that was not correct I
should have said the full thing that was
happening there um so when you're in the
in-game editor right and you might have
some things that are variably sized and
you want them to just work I don't
really like allocating and deleting
things I feel like it leads to
inefficient code and it also encourages
a lot of busy work and and acts there
are prone stuff and so you know I don't
really like garbage section I don't
really like new and delete so I prefer
to just have arenas and I shove
everything into like one of two or three
arenas and they get cleared at certain
times now one of the things that we
don't have in handmade hero but that I
would like and like in my own code bases
I have I just never really did it here
was the concept that there's a sort of
temporary arena that just you can always
use you don't to have one just have a
temporary arena always what happens if
you just create a memory arena
uninitialized in the middle of the code
is the first time someone goes to use it
it will actually just allocate it will
call virtual Alec to get some space
right then
use it and then at the end when I clear
it it just wipes everything away that it
did but the reason that's not that
efficient is because I don't really need
to funk down to virtual a lock right so
what I should have done here that's
that's a way better way to do exactly
the same thing and really isn't any more
difficult I just didn't do it is that in
here you've got this frame arena you
know what I mean
and so I could have just used the frame
arena and stuck a temp block around it
right so if I had just done like
temporary memory like be contemporary
you know what I mean here and said like
frame arena or anything else just
temporary in it it would have worked but
you know this is fine too it's really
something that the language should do
for you but doesn't because it's C++ and
it's horrible yeah what do you what do
you do
as each character going to have an
animation sequence as NPCs or are they
all playable so they're all playable in
a sense like meaning if you want to
switch characters you can I think so
like you know if I go up to one of these
characters here like they'll be a way to
just like talk to them and and switch
and then I'll I'll like hot they'll like
do a switch and then you're playing the
other character right and so there won't
they'll I will want them to move around
occasionally though probably
I mean maybe they'll just stand still
and hang out so that you can easily go
up to them and talk but I don't know
maybe they'll be doing stuff it's hard
to say I'm not a game designer so I
can't I couldn't tell you but well
something will happen
Patricia didn't rename the baby
all right I'll rename the baby the
baby's name can be Gramps
all right so extreme has ended
okay thank you everyone for joining me
for this on handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along the
series at home you can always hear the
game on handmade hero org it comes with
a source code so you can't play around
with it we'll be back here for some more
surprise streams sometimes this weekend
we'll see well we got to schedule stream
this weekend so at least see you for
those don't know if there'll be a
surprise streamer there will be maybe
there won't be we'll see
Krampus laughs is sort of drawing to a
close here but I will see you back here
sometime soon regardless at least by
Saturday morning until then have fun
programming and I'll see everyone on the
Internet take it easy everybody