hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode a complete game live on
stream we are going to take a look today
at cleaning up our sort of on-demand
asset importing and really where we've
gotten with that is we did all the heavy
lifting
we even have now a tool that can manage
our file formats for us and all kinds of
stuff like this and you know the place
that we've kind of gotten to is we now
really have to start deciding what we
want our asset specification to be what
we want our for word specification to be
where the game says I want to put this
asset in in this place and this is a
really tricky problem it's a very tricky
problem because it's not the kind of
thing where the right answers can be
measured in terms of certain specific
things that are easy to understand based
on the other sorts of things we've done
on handmade hero it doesn't have a lot
to do with performance there are some
performance implications but most of
time we have plenty of CPU power around
for matching assets it's not really a
huge deal it's not really a space issue
assets typically the like bitmap data or
whatever else is is the asset that
you're talking about typically the asset
data itself is just much much larger
than any of the metadata associated with
it so it's not a storage concern so we
can't say let's optimize for storage we
can't really say that's optimized for
speed probably cuz both of those two
things really it's not gonna matter very
much which one we do we have a flex way
to either it's not the kind of thing we
can really look at as an API problem and
the reason for that is because a lot of
the things we would look at for an API
problem just aren't involved here this
has to do with communicating between a
programmer and an artist basically not
between two parts of code and so what we
really now have to focus on is something
a little bit more existential a little
bit sort of further out side the
boundaries of what we normally talk
about and just go towards a vague kind
of exploration of like look
if we just kind of follow the API design
principles loosely that I've talked
about in the series before meaning focus
on the usage code what does it look like
what would what would make the most
sense for us to type in here take a look
at that take a look at the other side
the side that's improving the importing
where is it getting a theta from what
kinds of things are the artists making
that sort of thing and just try to see
if we can guess what the right sort of
thing is for all of these kind of
competing all of these things that are
in tension with each other what makes
the most sense for us and we kind of
know that the tagging is a nice flexible
way to just say look we can put a bunch
of stuff onto an asset and say here's
just some values and some tags that say
what those values mean we know that we
can do that and that it's very flexible
and allows us to add new things that's
probably good but the question is how do
we use those tags to actually create a
system that works well on the other side
or on both sides really so how do we
know what the tags are for an imported
asset and then when we load something in
how do we process those tags into some
kind of a state that allows the people
who are using the asset system to
efficiently talk about the kinds of
assets they need and get them and one of
the things that we might want to
consider in the mix here which I mention
a couple times is if this is something
that people continue to learn from in
the future and use as sort of like a
like I've said all the code for hammer
here will be released in the public
domain eventually at that time if it's
sort of used as a playground for things
people trying out various algorithms or
you know learning and experimenting with
low-level code or whatever it's nice to
be able to have them be able to trade
stuff around like it'd be nice to be
able to say here I posted some new mods
to handmade hero and and here are the
sprites that go with it
it would be nice if those
could integrate into the system cleanly
and not require a lot of rewrites of the
asset matching system so be not it'd be
nice to have a way of exposing things
easily when you add something the code
base having it be pretty easy to expose
it such that people can write sprite
sheets for that and have that flow
through the system without everyone
having to change the way they're doing
things or who knows what right so that
miscibility would be nice and you can
even think of it a little bit more
broadly and say if we eventually allow
multiple dll's to be loaded so you know
in the future let's suppose we're done
with with the main part of the game and
we say what if we want to break this
into something easily model how would we
make it so that you could load lots of
different gameplay DLLs and have them
all mixed together right well if we want
to do something like that what
implications would that have for the
asset system right cuz now you've got
multiple people all of whom are talking
about potentially different sorts of
tags maybe even tags that only they
understand and know about how would that
come into play what would that mean
right so we kind of have a lot of
competing concerns there it's difficult
to really think them through so what we
want to do is just be aware of that see
what kind of progress we can make we've
got some obvious clean up stuff we can
do I might start with that today but our
goal with today and tomorrow's ticker to
get to a point where if you know maybe
we're not done with it but at least we
sort of understand what we're gonna do
to finalize that matching in a way that
we think will work going forward it
doesn't have to be completely final we
can always come back and end it but
something that we at least believe to be
you know that we could plausibly say
here this seems like we could ship with
this right we just so we just need a
convincing argument so all right let's
go ahead and remind ourselves of where
we are so what we did last weekend is
this is the game running right now right
and we can sort of see it's running
debug mode so it's slower than normal
this is what we're running right now and
as you can see it's got the hero in
there with the correct sprites as it
should that was actually pretty cool
because what we did is we actually made
an editor binary that would allow us to
mess with our art files right it's
called HHA edit going to the day
director here this HHA edit lets you do
stuff where you can actually work with
the data files and what we did is we
told it to upgrade all our old visa art
files to v1 art files what that allows
us to do and it's pretty cool is it
basically means we can stick with a
binary asset format that's really easy
to work with and doesn't require any
parsing but we also have this external
tool we can use to rewrite it or maybe
merge things in the future if we'd like
to that sort of stuff and that's very
powerful because it means if we want to
upgrade our binary file format we don't
have to have our game understand the
changes the game can just move to the
new version and only understand one
version and then haan it can just
upgrade the the older version files to
the newer ones and so with that lets us
do is that lets us settle on a v1 file
format that's whatever we want it to be
and then we can just upgrade all our v-0
files to be v1 files right so we haven't
necessarily baked this v1 format we can
change this view one format still and
you know kind of go from there and we
may want to do that remember to add
additional things to it but that's where
we're at right now we have that
flexibility and that's a really good
thing right okay so what we need to do
now we've got a couple things we want to
clean up but what we need to do now is
we'd like to start getting this art into
the game and we can start with some
pretty basic stuff right we we're
looking at a world that's mostly doesn't
have art in it and it has the wrong art
for the hero it's the old artwork for
the hero and so what we want to do is be
able to do stuff like put in you know
say like floor textures right on this on
these floor cells here we might want to
put walls textures and ceiling textures
on these tiles right
coming out a bit more let me let me zoom
out here and there we go so coming out a
bit more here if we wanted to go ahead
and and start to to put other characters
in these rooms you know maybe have
someone who walks around in the hallway
how would we specify which sprites they
were using right and so if you take a
look in in the handmade artwork stuff
here that we have we just have a ton of
stuff that we can bring in so we've got
a lot of characters we can bring in here
right lots of different characters all
the sort of different styles to them
I love the braces and this one so how do
we get these characters into the game
and how do we specify what they are
that's the question for us because now
we know we can load them all and put
them into our our system for artwork but
the question is just how do we actually
refer to them right okay
so with that in mind I think there were
a few things we hadn't quite finished
yet and so those are the things that I
think I'd like to focus on today because
we don't really quite need to run up
into the tags issue and I'd like to put
that off as long as possible because
that's the heart that's the like it's
not about writing code it's about making
some hard decisions and that's always a
little bit frustrating right because you
don't really know if you're doing the
right thing and you gotta do some
experimentation but what I'd like to do
first is I'd like to just go ahead and
patch in the stuff that we're missing
that we didn't have a chance to finish
and I'll just quickly go over what that
is so if you remember correctly we have
this check for art changes it actually
runs it startup and what check for art
change is gonna do is it's gonna look
through all of the files and it's gonna
see whether we understand what those
files are and we wrote all this and we
sort of just let put it to the side like
if this is our this is our sort of
runtime updating part and we can sort of
see what it does it loops over a hash
table and looks to see whether or not
the particular file in question that it
sees is a file that we know about and if
that file is a file that we
know about we go to see whether or not
it has changed right we use the file
date as a way of saying look do we have
to reload this thing do we think we have
to reload this thing or is it probably
the same because we've seen it before
have the same file date so it's probably
the same file right and that's what
we're doing but we didn't really have
any way of making that persist that was
what stopped this from being complete so
when this happens we stored this
information into these hash this hash
information stuff here into the hash
table you remember this hash table was a
nice little convenient thing whereas
here as a source file and this asset
source file information here what this
did was say hey here's a source file and
here's the grid that said you know what
assets we imported from that this is
just a very simple structure that lets
us kind of get from a Photoshop export a
PNG that Photoshop export to the assets
in our asset system it's not persistent
and if you remember when we stopped and
we moved over to updating our file
format the thing that wasn't working yet
was that persistence if you ran the game
with an important asset file then what
what happened is it would say okay I'm
gonna import all of these p.m. G's that
you told me about
we actually restricted it to just ones
that that were hand things so that we
could not wait as long so we were just
importing a few it would import all of
those into our assets ISM and that
worked great yay for us but if you close
the game and restart the game it would
import them all again why because this
is memory resident only so when you
close the game it goes away when you run
the game again it sees those pngs it's
like I've never seen this before and
it's right as far as it knows it's never
seen them before because it only has
like short-term memory right it only
knows for that run of the game what it's
seen before
so what we wanted to do was make this
persistent and what I did when we sort
of updated that file format
and hopefully I mentioned why I was
doing this but maybe sometimes I forget
to say why I do things but hopefully
it's clear most of time what I did when
we were updating is I just I gave us a
way to mark that so this HHA annotation
thing that we can now in our new file
format put on every file right
optionally it's just an additional field
that you can stick on every asset it
allows us to say exactly this right it
allows it to say ok here is the file
date of the PNG came from if we want to
we can even have a checksum right we can
cover why we might want to do that and
optionally do that we don't have to do
that but we got space for it if we want
to we can store the name we can store
what the asset was called and what his
description was and if there was an
author again we don't really know that
information right now but if eventually
we wanted to tag things like that we
could and so you could kind of see where
we're going with this
we now have a place that says all of
this information it says what the
spritesheet was
location-wise write all of that stuff ok
so hopefully you can see why this is
gonna well why I put this in there
because this is a way for us to solve
the problem of storing this information
there were two ways I could have solved
the problem one way is to store a
separate file that would keep track of
this information we could have done that
why did I decide not to do that well
again because I really just don't know
how these files are gonna end up getting
used by the world at large once this
game is released you know could be we
release handmade hero and no one cares
right it could be released handmade hero
and people are starting to use it for
educational purposes in some ways right
and maybe it's helping people get
interested in low level programming at
that point I would like this file format
to be against a way that people can
share things with each other and learn
about low-level file formats by looking
at it right and so what I wanted to do
was like okay instead of storing a
separate
file so it won't properly transport when
you send someone in HHA right I want to
make it so that when I send someone in
HHA they get the import data with it
because I feel like that might be a
little bit more powerful a bit more
useful and furthermore if you can tag
these things with names descriptions and
authors again that that fosters a
certain sense of understanding of what's
in the file and ability to share them
with other people in a way that you can
look and go oh okay you know this this
was made by Carl and and then this one
was made by you know Mary and this one
was made by you know someone from chat
this one was made by Sherlock 93 right
and so I think that just is it's just a
better way to do it based on what might
get it might get used for in the future
if it does get used for education
personally if no-one cares about this
after we're done here and it was just
something that that we all did together
and had a good time doing that's totally
fine but I also want to be prepared in
case it ends up being something that
people do learn from and can share with
each other so let's take a look at how
we might do that we know we have this
HHA annotation array at the moment we're
really not doing very much with it and
that's sort of what we need to rectify
we need to weld in our new understanding
of what the file can do into the asset
loader because right now the asset
loader just doesn't care and if we take
a look here like I'll move this over to
this side and let me bring the asset
system up over on the other side here if
we look at how these files are loaded
what you can see is we just load the
assets but we don't care about the
annotation and why should we we don't
have any reason to right so what we want
to do is we want to say okay now let's
start paying attention to have a reason
to we're gonna make this code aware of
where its assets came from so that it
can now make correct decisions on import
right so that's what we're doing we're
just updating this code in a way that
allows us to use annotations from the
file so that it can avoid re-imported
things it already imported on prior runs
of the program and that's all we're
trying to do here that's what we want to
get to
so if we take a look at what's going on
you know
allocate game assets it comes through
and it reads all the HHA files that it
currently has this is that sort of check
to see what's going on there when it
does this you can see that it kind of
snaps an asset base in a tag base and an
asset count and a tag count those are
there to allow it to load the asset and
tag arrays correctly what we want to do
here is also respect the fact that the
annotation array which has the same
number assets in it as the asset array
may be there and we may want to load it
that brings us to this piece of code we
have the information we need to allocate
it because it's the max asset count we
want to have a slot for annotations that
exactly mirrors are in our asset count
our asset array so all we're really
talking about here is in here we would
have in addition to assets we would have
annotations right now the question is do
we need to bother doing that and the
answer is uh well me we we don't really
need to allocate it that way why is that
because if you take a look at what we
would actually be doing with that asset
array we know that it's going to be
stored with the assets proper right we
know that we're essentially going to
take these and store them with the
assets themselves because that's the
only time we're going to be using them
so if we want to we can just weld that
information in because we know we're
already storing things slightly
differently from the way they appear on
disk so if I take a look at the H file
here what you can see right we've got
all this information about the asset
this HHA asset here we can just expand
it to say hey store the annotation as
well right when you load it store the
annotation as well so then we don't
really need an additional push array
we'll just create the space we need
right off the bat right we'll just do
that first and so if we go ahead and
take from here right Jimmy if we go
ahead and take from here when we come
through this part of the code when we do
our data reads we can
now make another right we've got a
temporary data read for those HHS it's
because we're pulling them out and
putting them into sort of a new
structure we're loading them kind of
piecemeal there when we do that
piecemeal merge load when we do that we
also have the option of pulling out the
annotations and loading them that way
right so we can do it either way we can
have a parallel array if we want to we
can have them weld them if we want to
there's not a lot of issues to either
one we I'm just gonna start with this
one custom or straightforward if in the
future we sort of screw around with this
a little bit and end up doing things
more direct load like where we do where
we do more direct loading and less
fussing at the merge stage which we
could do if we want to do that then we
would play with this more right but at
the moment we don't really have to worry
about that nearly as much okay
so how are we gonna do that well right
here where we do platform to you to read
file it like this we read the asset
array and it's really easy for us to
just load the annotation right right
it's literally just a case of changing
from loading one place to loading
another and changing from loading one
struct to loading another right there
there's that's it I mean that's the
entirety of it and so all we really need
is a place to put it temporarily since
we already have temporary memory it's
free for us to do this right we can just
go ahead and push on another temporary
array and we can read it in so when we
read these two arrays in we now have all
the annotations ready and when we pull
them in here we can trivially just use
them right and it's exactly analogous
there's no difference between these two
like so right now there is one thing we
have to be aware of which is that
although the assets array always has to
be there and in fact we just check to
see if there's an asset count to make
sure we need to load it at all but if
there is then it's got to be there
annotations not so right we do not need
to do anything with annotations in a
file
can have the annotation strip so if I
want to I can support that pretty easily
along this code path by saying look
there may or may not be an HHA
annotation array okay in some cases if
we find that there sorry if we find that
this does not evaluate to value X it's
zero instead of a valid offset in the
file then we'll just say hey look there
isn't one so then when we come through
here and we say we're gonna point at one
of these what we can do instead is say
alright let's just pretend that it's
zero for now and then if there is an
annotation array then we set it to
something okay so off we go we can also
make it be a null annotation maybe
that's easier the null annotation can
just be you know something that sticks
sticks around just like hey here's ours
our big old zero and so we could do it
just point at that right just a big ol
block of zeros so that way we know that
the annotation is always valid in here
it just may be a block of zeros but it's
never a null pointer we got to check for
that so we can just check for the actual
parts that we want when we want them and
that will support both cases where we
have an array and where we don't and
where an annotation has or doesn't have
certain of the strings that are there
right so if we look at what goes on in
here you can see here that we track the
asset data when we put it in there you
can see that we assign it here by the
same token right we can assign the
annotation right so we can do this
trivially where we just assign that
annotation and we you know we now have
exactly what we wanted for that once we
have that annotation information in
there it's now the main problem that
we're gonna have is we have to now
rebuild our source file we need to make
this source file information work again
because right now we don't have any way
of reconstructing this we have to
reconstruct it from
the annotations right so our goal now is
to build this asset source file
information up again where we can sort
of say look let's rebuild for every
asset let's let's go ahead and rebuild
sort of the hash table we were using now
we have a couple different ways that we
can proceed so right now what we do is
we have the asset source file and we
then just use this well you know I'm not
gonna go into that part let's just let's
just say we're gonna use this so what we
need to do is we need to look over all
of our assets as we merge them in and we
need to build an asset source file a
sort of backing store that tells us
where these things came from right and
we need to sort of figure out some way
of reconstructing that information now
we have in the file format a bunch of
the stuff we need we know we need the
source file date in fact let me just
bring those both up together so you can
kind of see them here so here is our
asset source file information you can
see that it has a grid here that's
that's well this will tell us where in
the grid various assets go it's got a
file date we've got that too and it's
got a base name and we've got that right
these are not particularly relevant to
the asset source file so they don't
really need to be stored in here those
are just tags that go with any
particular entity any particular asset
Jimmy so really what we're looking at
primarily is we don't really have to
load these right these don't have to be
loaded they might have to be saved but
they don't have to be loaded because we
don't really care we just have to
preserve them so that if we load an
asset and rewrite the asset we need to
remember to repoint to the correct name
description and an author but otherwise
we don't care however the source file
base name offset we do need to load that
that is important for us to load and
when we load it in we're gonna have to
look at that name right now this creates
a bit of a dilemma for us
and that is that we haven't done a
particularly good job looking here at
minimizing the amount of data read we're
gonna have to do and why do I say that
well suppose this this file had 10,000
assets in it but they only came from a
total of 20 files
well if right here I mean the easiest
thing for us to do right you slap this
platform data read directly into this
loop so every time we get an asset we
just read into a little buffer what the
file name was we grab that you know part
out of the file and off we go
it's plausible that we can do that but
that basically means that we're going to
bite an entire kernel transition right
we're gonna like call into the operating
system for every asset so if we have to
load 10,000 assets we're going to hit
10,000 times that's not a very nice way
to do this especially because if you
look at what happens here we only really
issue two reads up sorry three reads
tags assets annotations for every file
so if a file has 10,000 assets in it we
only hit three reads right it's not
great you know yeah I'm saying it's not
great and so to me that kind of suggests
what we would like to do here is perhaps
actually introduce the notion of a
separate array for source files right
because that is something that actually
needs to get read at runtime and so
because it's something that wants to get
read at runtime it kind of seems like
the sort of thing we may want to deal
with more directly there
and I'm just not sure whether that's you
know something we care about or not
here's what I will say we could just
proceed without doing that and the way
we would do that is we wouldn't bother
building the source file information if
this isn't an editable file because we
know we don't care if it's not an
editable file right so meaning if we
don't do if this this file isn't open
for updating and you know we we can add
a tag that says whether a files
available for updating right like that's
something that we can do if we're not
allowing updating on a file at the
moment we can just not process that data
and then if we are allowing updating on
a file we can process the data that
means it will be fundamentally slower to
load in that kind of dev mode because
we're hitting a lot of those asset
loading calls that really should just
all be done as one call but it would not
affect the runtime of the non
development side of things so if you
launch the game and you don't have
anything open for editing it wouldn't
affect things mataf oh I'm out of liquid
horrible state to be in so I really
can't say which of those two I should
pick here's I'm gonna say
rather than comprehend codebase I'm
going to do the simpler one and just
read from the file in the case where the
thing is open for reading and the reason
that I'm going to do that is because
nowadays disk access is getting a lot
cheaper
you know you get em two drives that are
just like absolutely sick at reading and
we're gonna be hitting the cache most
the time anyway so I'm just gonna say
look let's see how bad it is and if it
gets bad enough we'll fix it
but I won't over complicate things now
in a sort of a premature attempt to
avoid that eventualities
I'll just note it in the code and we'll
go from there and we'll just say look
this only happens if you're in dev mode
so we'll put enough around it and I'll
also tag it to say look
so at the moment we'll just say that and
and you know maybe I'll even make it to
do so we'll just say look maybe we will
want to look at this and we'll kind of
feel out how it goes you know I think
that's a reasonable decision so what I
want to do here is I want to have some
notion of whether or not this file has
to be edited whether this file house has
editing allowed if you will so I'm just
gonna say like if file allow editing and
and so that will give us a way to mark
our files specifically and anyone who
wants to know whether a file can be
edited can just look at that one flag
right so what I'll do here is I'll say
look we only have one file that allows
editing at the moment it's this one all
the rest of them don't so that'll make
it easy we would only trigger this path
in that one case and then we'll do the
load here for the asset we can find out
what that asset file is what I'm gonna
do again we've got a temp memory so what
I can do here is I can literally just
make a quick little temp space for this
thing this is the assets source name
right I could even temp around this but
it's probably not even worth it because
it'll get cleaned up at the end but you
know if we cared about the fact that
we're loading 10,000 things so we're you
know wasting you know a megabyte of
memory here or whatever we could clean
that up as well but we don't really care
it's probably faster to just push on
there and then come back to it later I
don't know it's hard to say catch things
blah blah blah you could try the other
way and see which one's faster for you
but
so when we come through here what we
want to do is say hey look for this
annotation right we want to know like
the file name count right the the the
source file name count and we want to
load we want to make an array here that
we can load into that's gonna tell us
that right and I think I don't really
remember exactly what we said here so it
looks like we've got a null terminator
there as well it looks like we wanted a
null terminator I'm not sure what we did
there exactly but you know looks like
what we wanted
so suppose we wanted a melter me I'm
also gonna just give it the padding
right here's that source file name it's
gonna get loaded in the source file name
I'm gonna put the Terminator at the end
of it after it's loaded they do it after
it's loaded I mean it doesn't matter
when I do it either ones fine and then
when we load this year we know we've got
an offset that we want to load from and
so and we know we want to load this many
characters right so when we load this in
I just have to make sure I specify what
exactly what are to read at a piece of
information are so when we do read data
from file right we have to pass it the
location to read from and then the it's
the amount to read is how we did that so
like I said we know the amount to read
it's just the name of thing but we need
to know where well we we know that as
well because we have the annotation so
in fact I can do it this way so from the
annotation we know that the source where
is that here we know that the source
file base name offset is the location
that we actually want to read from and
then again we know the source file name
count because the source file name count
can come from the exact same place
right so we can load these source file
names in once we read them we just need
a place for it well that's exactly what
we made right here so there it goes now
we've got that name from the file and
what we want to do is we want to just
create the placement information for
this asset now right so if we go back
and look we've got this asset source
file what we want to do is say hey the
asset source file in this case we need
to say something here where we passed a
source file name in and it does the hash
lookup for us so we kind of want that to
happen here and then it will give us
back that source file then what we want
to do is look to see whether the
location in this grid is occupied by
somebody who is a newer version than us
or not if that makes sense so we we need
to see when we go look at this asset
import grid here we need to see whether
or not there's already somebody in there
that has a lower precedence than we do
right because we don't you need sort of
a there's a primacy number and we need
to see whether or not the primacy number
is is higher or lower than ours that
makes sense
so when we look in there what we're
effect we can do is say we get the
source file back we're gonna say alright
if the source file asset indices for
wherever we're looking so we need grid Y
and grid X for that asset we want to say
we want to have some kind of query which
says take takes precedence over or like
precedence is lower than right so we
want to do here say look here is the
asset we're talking about okay if this
asset index here and then we know our
number because that's something that we
will have loaded out of our tags right
so I probably want to pull that number
out here so that it's available at all
times because it's going to be relevant
to us as we're doing sort of asset merge
sort of stuff so we probably want to
know when one comes in here there is
another way we could do it we could just
remember everybody like all the assets
that happen to be mapped on to this grid
location rather than just the most
recent one
I'm not sure how we want to do that I
don't know that that would really get us
anything in particular
I don't really think it will so I'm just
not going to bother with that so what we
want to do here is see if the precedents
learned that you know the other thing we
could do is just make this be an error
like you're just not allowed to do it so
we could actually just say hey if
there's already something in this slot
you've got an error and we need to just
let you know that you've got to use HHA
edit to like delete an asset or
something because you've got two assets
open for editing that both came from the
same sprite sheet apparently right so
what I might do is say all right look if
this equals zero we're good to go
if it doesn't it's an error right and if
you remember correctly we actually have
some error reporting in here right you
can see that we've got sort of this out
F to match our thing so we can if we
want to sort of have the notion that
there is an error like an error stream
that's coming and because we were
previously like you know here's the
error stream stuff it just so happens
that this error stream is actually in
the right place for that
right so we can I think just just
literally output the error to that file
and it all just works so I don't even
need that to be it to do I can go do it
right and what I can say is like asset
you know sent you and sent you both
occupy same slot in sprite sheet and
cannot be edited properly something like
that and then what I could say is like
well you know what I should probably do
is say here's the spritesheet and here's
the grid location so I could I can sort
of print this out almost like C style C
compiler style right so this way we can
say here's a source file name here's the
grid Y and grid X and I should reverse
those two because we're in human
readable form here so there's the source
file name the two grid locations we know
which two assets we're talking about
because we know this particular asset
index is
[Music]
this and the other asset index that was
in here we do we know well I guess so
when we are actually looking at assets I
guess we can just use this
so actually we know which asset index it
is there so I can't actually get that
asset out so this that would be a
conflicting asset is alright so if the
grid if what's in there currently is
zero right and I could do it this way as
well just to make it a little bit
clearer so you know we can say all right
in that case the asset that's in this
grid is my asset right so replace it so
that works but what I can also do here
is say like okay hey if we did find a
conflict then whatever the one that was
in there right now
let's print out what its asset index was
to so then we've got alright we've got
the asset asset index in file and we've
got the conflict asset index and file so
that tells you the two assets in that
file that we're wrong and and off we go
so I think that's all good
probably that will print out the error
into the into the source files asset
error buffer and that way when we
actually have a nice way of printing
those out somewhere which we'll want to
do eventually we will have this airport
to us properly so this will place it
into that file correctly there really
isn't anything else we particularly need
to do here except for the fact that when
we are importing these assets in
that file date there we could end up
with a conflict now this is kind of
annoying but it's just the way it is
so we need to set that file date to the
lowest possible file date so what we
want to do here is say when we get grab
this file we need a thing here that's
like you know look up file or whatever
right and then we need to say look if
the source files file date is greater
than our file then what we think the
file date should be right because we
have an opinion about that right our h/h
annotation says what we think the source
file date was if it's higher we need to
set it two hours so that we always pick
the lowest source file date right and
then we can set the checksum if we want
to again we don't have that right now
but the file checksum equals H
sanitation source file checksum so in
this case you know when we goups file
data try validate so in this case when
we look at that information we say okay
when the source file comes back if for
some reason we've got a mismatch here we
need to set it to whatever ours is right
and we can do this a little bit more
strategically here maybe that stuff that
kind of needs to get handled in the
lookup or whatever so what I can do is I
can also just pass those along in case
it wants to do more complicated conflict
resolution maybe we do it like that and
it gets handled in the lookup right so
we've got the date and checksum and
those kind of flow through the pipeline
automatically right so once we've done
that we are ready to go that that pretty
much imports all that information in and
so we just need our lookup file or
whatever function and I think this code
path is good to go what we don't have is
a thing on the other end that will
properly save this information into the
annotation slot for new assets so that
part we still have to do and it's not
very good
cult because we kind of already have it
all set up to to work with the asset
arrays so it's pretty straightforward
but we we got to go do it right so I'm
gonna do that but first let's let's take
care of lookup file or whatever what we
can recall here is back in in check for
our changes here is the thing that does
what we want so really all we have to do
here is extract this code out from what
we're doing in in this scanning loop
here so we just need to extract this
code and we need to make that into like
a callable thing so it could be done
from more than one place right so I'm
going to do first is is sort of pull
this out here and make this me something
we can call again got some compression
or active programming here right just
say look we see ourselves using this
multiple times let's make it into
something we can and most this stuff
here totally straightforward we don't
have is the hash value right so we need
to pass that hash value in and that
means we're probably gonna have a
two-layer thing here because sometimes
people have the hash value other times
they don't so anyway this is going to be
like a get or create asset source file
and this will return that asset source
file we know that we're passing a hash
value here that will allow us to access
it we also know that we need the base
name and the assets right so then we
flew through here okay you can see us
updating the hash value like so
you make that a little clearer there we
passing the unmodern hash value we
produce the hash fire that has been
modded properly we then go ahead and
search for the match if we find the
match we're done when we look through
here if we did not find a match we
create a new one and then we return the
match ready to go right so we've got
some there's more to it than that
potentially but that's mostly what we're
looking at here so then what I want to
do is fill out this in terms of this
other file as it turns of this other
function so here again we don't actually
want to do this anymore now I just want
to pass the hash value in like so and
then the question is well where's the
base name the base name is is in in here
right hash bar there's the assets here's
our match and so then this fought this
stuff doesn't really have to execute now
I thought well good by the way this is
like that
and this is like that right and that all
looks fine so then what we want to do is
say okay this code goes away we can just
get the match directly like so we want
to assert because we're basically saying
look it has to succeed it will create a
new one if it doesn't find one and then
we'll proceed to do some stuff with it
right okay so that's most of the code
that we actually wanted what we want to
do now is say well okay the asset source
file version here get or create asset
source file there's another version we
may want of this it does something
slightly different here we just have the
base name we don't know what the hash
value is for the base name we also have
the file date and the file checksum that
we're passing and what we want to do
here is first produce the string hash
and you can see here the update string
hash function
where that came from this right here I
don't know that we have a thing that
hashes the whole strength we don't so we
should probably make something that just
hashes the whole string where we just
pass as E string here and this is just a
simplest saying alright the hash value
equals 0 to start with right
while star Z update string hash hash
value star Z we can even do that if we
are so inclined right so that lets us
produce the entire string hash in one go
which is something we do want to do you
can see here you're producing it in line
to this so that we don't have to look at
the string twice arguably not necessary
to be that hot all about it but it
doesn't matter that's just how it is we
don't need to undo it so here we know we
want to take the string hash of this
base name so then we can do asset source
file your salt equals get or create
asset source file we can pass that in
here we know we've got the assets hash
of the base name and the base name and
then what we want to do is again take a
look at the date and check some
information on the file so what we want
to do is say look if this files file
date that it's got in there is 0 so you
know the this right here if the file
date is 0 then we know it was new it was
newly we're the first people creating it
so if the file date is 0 we want to
reset it and we also want to reset it in
the case where we have an earlier one
right so if it's 0 or if the file date
is on the the one we find is greater
than our file date then we need to reset
it and the reason to prefer
a file date that's lower is because if
you remember the point of the file date
tracking is to make sure that we don't
use old assets if we have two assets
that came from a source file and one of
them is saying well I was from date this
and I was saying I'm from date VAT right
what we wanted you is use the earliest
date possible because maybe the asset
file has been updated and if we use the
later date
that earlier date asset risks not
getting it's new version there's no harm
done INRI important something right so
we want to make sure that we're always
preferring younger dates in terms of
when files should be operated younger
dates know older dates more elderly if
we want the older file date which is a
lower value right I don't know how you
want to say that but we want dates that
are lower even though that means the
file is older confusing anyway so we
want to prefer those so we do prefer
those here and then this is the file
that we'll call in the case where we're
actually saying look here's the data
here's the date information and stuff
like that that we actually have so now
we know what lookup file or whatever
actually is in its passing exactly the
things we want here just like so so we
just go ahead and suck those up into the
function call and now we're good to go
so now if we look at what we're doing
here what's this game assets actually
yeah game assets don't ask me why as
opposed to like the other kinds of
assets we have apparently anyway if we
go ahead and and
get a great asset source file we passed
the assets game assets the base name
gets passed second right yeah and then
the string hash of the base name gets
passed there that sure looks like it is
the string hash of not produce the right
value it doesn't all right so annotation
index is just a typo here obviously we
don't actually need an annotation index
it's just an asset index because they
are parallel arrays if they exist
they're required to match right so here
we've got you 64's I must have
accidentally said you 32 there I didn't
actually mean for it to be you 32 I want
it to be 64 so apologize for that
supposed to look like that anyway we
then have the grid wide grid X stuff I
wrote those out in shorthand and really
we we have that information we don't
need to compute it it's just it's a
little bit longer handed it's right
sheet X from the Anna
HHH annotation like so and then here
this is not file that's supposed to be
source file so that's a bit of screw-up
glad that got caught and that's it so
that imports all of the annotation data
that we actually care about the rest of
it just leaves us pass through because
we don't need to know the author or the
description or any of that stuff at the
moment maybe we want to load those later
for some other reason in some kind of
editing mode or something I don't know
but the moment we don't care we just
need to preserve them and this will
preserve them so long as when we
actually go to write assets out we write
out their annotations as well which we
have not done yet and that is the last
thing that we want to do to support that
editing I think that's really it I can't
oh wait there's one of the
doing that was down sampling so so after
he finished us we'll do down sampling as
well yeah yeah sorry
so if I want to do that let's just go
ahead and go to the place where we
actually write these things out so you
know we have sort of all of this done
already right we already did the right
changes here it is and we also have
right asset data right you can see it
doing this this stuff here this is
really all we're gonna need so when we
come through here to do write
modifications to HHA now is the point
where we can make this work with the new
file format and include the annotations
with it and I think that's really the
last thing that we need to do there in
terms of bookkeeping I think that's
that's the end of our bookkeeping you
know other than debugging obviously but
off we go and so what we need to do now
is adapt this to the fact that we don't
have to use asset types anymore asset
types are not relevant it's just tags
and assets and what we need to do is
expand this to put in the annotations
because we want our annotations array to
be preserved now so really we're just
replacing one array with another and
that array happens to be one that we
actually wanted instead of one that we
don't so here's our annotation array and
here's our annotation array size so we
need to we know we need to write that
out the question is where is it going to
come from also let's take a look here we
know that we're doing our tag build up
here there's nothing probably specific
that has to happen in this I would like
to assert that this file uh is allows
editing right because if this was set to
false and we got to a write
modifications call that seems really bad
because then we're about to overwrite
data in a file that we said it wasn't
supposed to be edited so we probably
want to alert ourselves in debug mode to
that fact because something's gone us
seriously pear-shaped at that point so
when we come through here we build up
how much tags we want we know all the
rest of the information that we actually
need and what we do now is instead of
that asset types array I just
build the annotation array size and
again that's gonna be the asset count
times the size of the HHA annotations
and that's good to go we then come
through here and say again don't need
this annotations is not something that
gets counted so if we take a look at the
header file now right we got tags asses
annotations we don't need a count for
annotations because either it's 0 or
it's a valid offset that's all the
information we need we know that it has
the same number in it as asset counts if
it exists in the first place but doesn't
exist it's just not there if it does
exist it's got as many as those in it so
no no worries there so now we just put
the annotations in here you can see me
setting that up here so what we say is
like alright header annotations so this
is the tag array size here and this is
going to be sorry assets plus asset
array size right so we just say alright
the tags start at the watermark the
assets are the assets are where the tags
were plus however big the tags were and
the annotations are wherever the assets
were plus however big the assets were
right very straightforward tag those on
we can then go ahead and get those
location sorry not those locations we
can then go ahead and get space to build
those before we write them out again all
we have to do here is just make sure
that we allocate additional one for
annotations replace the asset types with
with that an asset type count there
shouldn't be an asset type count also so
I need to get rid of that so that's gone
right so we go ahead and do that we
don't have a desk type here that's not a
thing so that goes away and then we
start looping over stuff we don't need
to loop by type ID anymore that's not a
thing we can just loop over all the
assets and find the assets that we
actually were trying to output we we
don't need to do this right so here is
the actual thing that we're doing we can
just use the asset index we can start at
and while we can skip asset zero if we
want to and I'll call this this is
really global asset index right so let's
just call it global asset index we go
through all of the assets and for each
one of those we see if it was in this
file if it wasn't this file then we go
ahead and write it out asset index and
file is going to kind of be assigned
going upwards and what we want to do
here because we're resetting this asset
array we probably should reset the
assets idea of which asset it is as well
right so in other words in here we sort
of have the source asset that it came
from it's got an asset index and file
value we want to set that to be the new
asset index and file right because
that's where it is now it we could could
have moved it right
usually we won't because we're going in
order but just in case we should store
that information right we could
alternatively assert that but I don't
know that we care about sorting it
because we just care that it lines up
correctly if that makes sense so anyway
here we are with our do we haven't use
that information now I think about it
though it doesn't matter well look at
that later all right so anyway moving
forwards looking at what we're actually
gonna output here we've got sort of this
guest information so what's actually
stored there so here's our HHA asset we
now need the information that's going to
come with this asset we don't need any
of this stuff right because it's
basically all yeah if this is all for
the type we don't care about that at all
right that's gone goodbye not relevant
so all we need to do is copy the HHA and
then update our tags right because our
tags the tags are going to get repacked
now they might not line up
the way that they used to so we're just
repacking their tags so we grab the
source HHA out then all we need to do is
just like pack the tags in there the
first tag index one past last tag index
bit I that just shouldn't that have been
updated is there a reason we weren't
updating that does anyone know
does that look that that looks wrong to
you right does that not I mean I mean I
mean that's definitely that's got to be
wrong I don't I don't see any way for
that not to be wrong this should say
first tag index equals tag index and
file and this should say one passed last
time circles Tagus and file right I mean
that's just seems pretty obvious to me
let's not missing something anyway so
that's a much simpler loop now that
builds our entire asset array
information up and so now we need to do
is account for the fact that annotations
were never included in here again not
particularly difficult we should be able
to just say agency annotation deaths
annotation equals annotation array plus
asset index and file and then we can
literally just I don't even think we
need to update anything in it I think
it's literally like this
III mean I think that's it cuz all of it
is just some indices and some you know
check sums and stuff and they'll just
copy over and they're correct right so
that they're just gonna reference into
the file as then the file hasn't been
touched in terms of the data that's in
it so I feel like that's just fine there
really isn't anything else to to deal
with in there right so that seems
totally fine to me and I think that's
really all we needed so that should be
fine um oh you can hear must be time for
the Blue Angels
I can hear Jets outside so that all
seems totally reasonable
last but not least to complete this we
get you know obviously besides debugging
that what we need to do is go and make
it so that when we pack in a new ass
asset so in here for example and we're
going through when we pack in a new
asset we need to add information into
the annotation to account for that right
so if you look in here right we come
through and we say we're gonna put a new
asset into this file or whatever else it
is that we're doing here so we're going
to grab a new asset in and what we need
to do is we need to we need to reserve
the asset data for the stuff that we
store right and so what we want to do
here is make sure that the HHA asset
data size gets updated to reflect the
new data size right and this in fact
when this does this it's less about we
don't really need to worry about these
two dimensions anymore
we can actually just check the size
so if it doesn't have storage or
wouldn't fit then we need to update it
right so that's how that works then this
stuff just goes passes on through and
everybody's fine and dandy and that's
all nice so that's fine but then you can
see here when we set up this HHA and we
place the the stuff in here we when we
write the asset data out we don't write
out any annotation information right we
so what we need to do here is we need to
make sure that we're actually going to
store the information for this assets
annotation properly so in order to do
that we kind of have two things that we
want to do so the first is we need to
fill in all of the pieces of the
annotation that are relevant to us right
so when we come through here and we get
the asset out if we had an actual asset
then we'll inherit what its annotations
were at the moment and that's good but
we also need to say look the annotation
itself has a bunch of stuff we may need
to set you know based on what we're
actually doing here okay
so here's all the stuff we may need to
set and let's make sure we set it we
need to set the source file date for
sure we need to set the checksum for
sure and then we need to set the
spritesheet stuff for sure like that's
always going to be updated because all
of that stuff has now been updated maybe
it's the same in the file maybe it isn't
but we we can't hurt to overwrite
something with the same value that it
used to be right then we've got our four
strings and we have to decide what we
want to do with those strings but that's
sort of separate issue that we'll get to
in a second so we need to specify this
information and this information needs
to kind of come in as part of this
process what we don't
have right now is a convenient way for
that to occur what we should do is we
can get some of it out of here so the
check some information that sort of
stuff can get updated here let's take a
look at how that would work so we look
at what's going on here
when we come through here we set the
date let me say do we want to do this
before or after now we can sort of have
a good reason to do it so we can base
say we update this first because assets
that get packed from here on out need to
[Music]
be able to stamp themselves with the
right data right so what we need to do
here is we need to set these two we'll
want to talk about that checksum if we
end up doing that
that'll want to be set here as well we
have those two pieces of information and
they're ready to go what we need to do
now is just copy them in we have the
source file here it's this file just the
file pointer right so we can save file
date well checksum those are both there
spritesheet X&amp;Y we know what they are we
had to figure those out there why index
an X index so we can just copy those in
directly and so then we're really just
left with four strings question is where
do the four strings come from if you
look at what we're dealing with here
these can these we can deal with in one
of two ways we can be maximally pigley
pigley about it
picky about it and put the pig hat on we
could choose to be more efficient it
depends because these strings are going
to appear multiple times right so the
author for a large number of assets will
probably be the same like an ax
has drawn all of the ones that are in
the directory currently so all of those
would have an a record as the author on
them right the source file name is going
to be the same for every sprite that
comes from the same sprite sheet so we
don't really have to write those strings
multiple times right but again
optimization that we don't necessarily
want to make yet because why complicate
our code when we don't actually need to
deal with it quite yet it'd be pretty
easy for us to just make something that
does a string compaction like we could
put that in HHA edit we can have an HHA
edit thing you run that does like an
optimization pass on the thing that
seems better to me because then we're
not worrying about if we've got like
squirrely little errors in here right so
so I'll put it to do in there we can't
choose to address it in the future if we
want to we don't necessarily have to
that's kind of up to us
so then what I'll do is I'll do a ripe
asset string call this directly mirrors
the one that we already did in HHA edit
right it's the same thing and what this
is going to do is this is just going to
let us write these out a little bit more
compactly I should do it this way we
write acid data so I'm going to say
write asset string and then I'm going to
give it the count and the offset those
are gonna go like that and then I just
need the information here we should have
access to that information but we don't
and so one things we're gonna need is
we're gonna need some additional
information we're gonna need a way to
get that additional information that we
don't have right now and so I'm gonna
just introduce a little thing that's
like you know import annotation I'm just
gonna introduce some strings here I'm
gonna say that we've got a asset name or
let's just say name description and
author I'm going to say that we've got
those that those will come in along with
the rest of the import tags so you know
we'll say this actually you know what
import grid tags could actually have
that on it
where did we define that how come my
search didn't work I must have typed it
wrong so with the import grid tags I'm
just gonna put it right there okay so
I'm gonna do that and I'm gonna come
back here and I'm gonna just do a little
bit I might clean up some string stuff
too while I'm at it
we'll see so what I want to do here is
say all right we know that the grid tags
have this information on it so I want to
write this asset string coming from the
grid tags that we have so here's that
grid tag array right the grid tag array
has a name
description just not the sender height
and author and so we've got these three
here and what I want to do now is just
match these up so we've got the name
count asset name count and this is asset
name offset oops I did that wrong
description and then finally we've got
the author it's just off account a size
and this was called annotation array
there we go good tags were a pointer and
off we go
so our final write asset string is a
little bit different this one is the
source base name right
what's that called again source file
base name counts so off we go we had a
lot of these we'd probably introduced a
file string class that somehow had to
deal with that not class bus truck
problem is you want them separated so
it's kind of hard to do it's a long
story anyway so when we deal with this
the only question we have now is where
is that going to come from and the
answers that comes from the file it's
right here
problem is base name is actually an
ASCII Z string we'd rather this not be
we'd rather just be a string so I'm just
gonna go ahead and make it a string and
we're gonna deal with the implications
of that later because I want everything
to be a string now since we introduced
that string type I would like everything
to be it cuz I like those better I like
counted strings better than asked easy
strings they're just easier to use
so anyway I'm gonna say bass name in
here and off we go so now we've got our
right asset string that will write out
all of the strings and so what we need
to do from for that is actually have one
of those and it's gonna mirror our right
asset data so right here it needs to
take the asset file - right - and then
it needs the source and then it just
needs to know hey you know what are we
gonna what are we getting actually right
into and what you can see here is we we
gonna have to call reserve data so we're
basically pushing the data out each
individual time here let me write this
out and you know we could actually see
whether it fits in the old location that
the annotation was I don't know that I'm
super motivated to do that
I really just don't know how I feel
about that let me show you what I mean
what I mean is this
if the source count is less than or
equal to the count this would not need
to be reserved right but if it's the
other way around it would be so if the
source count is greater than the count
that's currently there then the count
that's currently there needs to become
the source count and the offset that's
currently there needs to become a
reserved data right so the reserved data
this would need to take the assets the
game assets like so right and it would
need to reserve that much however much
that is right so the count would need to
get reserved but then when you're when
we're done then this just calls right
asset data and it just passes the file
and the source data that it's trying to
write and just says look right to this
location this amount and off you go
right another way to look at this would
actually be it's a little bit simpler to
preffer eight the code because I would
have to set the count since the count
has to get set in either case we could
just do this like look the counts always
gonna be set so the question is just
whether the offset is set and so we just
do it this way so meaning if the source
count doesn't fit in the space that was
already used for whatever the Sanitation
is then we reserved the data for the new
space and it goes there and then
regardless we're always going to change
the count to be whatever the new count
is and we're gonna write that out right
so it kind of looks more like that we
always write the count and then we
always write the data at the offset one
way
the other right um that seems okay you
know it seems it seems okay I guess it's
all I can really say this has to be au
32 in both cases but that's okay we know
we're not gonna have strings longer than
that because that would be ridiculous
you couldn't even display them on the
screen um I guess I so anyway that
writes out our data moving through here
we now have to deal with the changes
that we made for for the base name stuff
right we need a way to copy on the
regular kind of string there we can do
that pretty easily let me take a look
what else we got
so this has to take assets now and so
really we're just down to the checksum
and being able to push that string on to
the stack there when we're actually I
guess that strings R equals to that yeah
that all just works so what we need to
do is we need to have a thing in our
memory we've got the push string call
here and what we want to do is probably
have a in line I don't know why we
bother ever typing in line that Patrick
Fowler doesn't care so if I do marina
arena and I do something that's that's
like here's the length there's a source
what I can do is just make this thing
Jonica how it is that's kind of more of
a push string Z what I might do is just
say like that you know and and then
regular push string is what I want to
actually move to that'll do the other
kind of push so if we do push string
memory rina rina power source then what
it'll do is basically the same thing
here where it takes the string length I
don't know why we don't just use string
length here but then we push the size on
there and we and copy right and and do
we have a push copy we do so a push push
copy in this case would actually be what
we want so really we can make this much
more simplified than than even that
right what we can do is say this is just
push string is just a pretty basic we
just say look here's the result the
result count is however long that thing
was the result data is just the push
copy
right I mean that's that's all there is
to it it's it's pretty basic so
returning a string here is maybe a
little harder because it doesn't look
like it knows what a buffer is so I
guess that needs to be defined earlier
potentially which is fine with me
copy is something that's probably in
here I don't know where we put copy that
should be in memory anyway I'm not sure
why it's not oh it's just too fine to
lower down right um so copy should
really be up at the top because anybody
who's doing memory pushes might need to
use that so that should actually be up
here and then I think we're good so
there we go so now we're just down to
checksum I don't know how much time I
got left I guess I got about 10 minutes
left so the last thing we want would
want to implement here is to check
something and you know we've we've read
the data in so you can see we've already
got a file buffer so really what we
won't want to do here is say like
checksum of and pass this file buffer in
and so what we want to do is have some
way of asking when we have a file
you know what's the checksum and that
can be a shared call that can be
something that goes in here where we say
you know give me back the 64-bit
checksum of whatever this thing is
and we just need some way of producing
this actual checksum
what is it checksum well a checksum is a
number that's basically it's you've seen
us do stuff with exactly this it's
basically a hash value right they serve
exactly the same purpose it's just they
have slightly different criteria for
which they might
to be judged right so in both cases in a
hash value in a checksum or another name
for a checksum in a lot cases the hash
value in the cryptographic sense right
so cryptographic hash there's a lot of
names for things that are basically very
similar in all of these cases we're
talking about roughly the same thing
we're talking about taking a very large
amount of data an entire files worth of
data in this case but in a hash entire
string or a bitmap or whatever we have a
very large several K several megabytes
several gigabytes even of data and what
we want to do is we want to reduce that
data down to an incredibly tiny size
compared to its original why do we want
to do this not to use it because we
can't write it's not it's not
compression we can't get the original
back so we're not trying to make a
smaller version that we can then expand
original version no we're just trying to
come up with a number that in some way
identifies this larger piece of data why
do we want to do that
well the reason is because in the hash
case we want to try and use that data to
put it into a slot that can identify it
more uniquely so we don't just search a
hole linked list full of things to find
it right we're trying to segregate out a
set into different things by using this
sort of ID value right so in in that
case what a hash is trying to do is
create a value that's likely to be
distinct from the other things we will
also put in the hash right in the file
case it's a little different it's
similar but not exact in the hash table
sense what we wanted is we have many
disparate things there totally different
right a set of strings that are not
coming from the same place one is KC the
other is Carl or Lemongrab right and
what we want to do is file these into
nicely segregated buckets if we
have 10,000 strings and a thousand
buckets what we want ideally is for ten
strings to go in each bucket we want two
perfectly distributed by our hash
buckets right so that's we're trying to
but they're disparate things totally
different Casey and Lemongrab are
totally different strings for our
checksumming not so checksumming is for
a different purpose it's to try to take
two things that are probably very
similar that have only had slight
changes made to them and determine
whether there's any difference so what
it's trying to do is it's more trying to
pick up subtle differences so if I said
Lemongrab and lemongrass I want those
two to hash to something distinct much
more so than I would ever care if KC and
Lemongrab hash two different things
why because I'm expecting my art files
to have small changes made to them I'm
expecting artists to make small changes
and then re-save them I'm not expecting
to be completely different every time so
I would almost rather something that
doesn't quite have the same usage as a
hash in the in the hash table sense it's
not the same thing
often times good functions can do both
they're not completely different
problems they're very similar so it's
not a super disparate thing but the the
end goal is not quite the same I guess
it's all I'm trying to point out all
right um so what would this look like
well first of all
we literally could do this right we
literally could do this if we wanted to
store the checksum we could literally
say look let's let's just straight-up
store the the let's straight-up just
reduce our string hash it would work but
I think we would probably want something
better we would probably want to look at
some cryptographic hashes they're more
sensitive to trying to make small bit
changes guarantee that they produce
different hash values and so that would
be more probably what we would want
something that's more about preventing
small changes here's the thing
I put the Hat this the hash stuff in as
sort of a just in case we want it my
question that I have is do we really
want it what's it gonna do for us right
because I don't know that it's really
gonna do anything for us
right if two hash values matched how
would that help us we still don't really
know it could have been a hash collision
right so I don't really know it seems
more like you would want to match the
asset data and see if the asset data
changed I don't know so we can use a
string - I mean we can use the checksum
or we could not I'm not sure how much we
care about that but this is where we
would do it right let's just finish that
up here
where is our share - there we go so what
I would do here is say okay you know
here's our string and that would give us
a checksum right it's not a good check
sign with something 1 we would want but
it is actually checksum okay and again
the reason for that is just because look
anything you do that mixes all the
values together somehow is a checksum
right if you change some of the values
it might change
there's better and worse versions of it
and we could look at using them for
example you know a common one in this
case might be what's called the bleh
cache oops not black hash play cache
it's probably also something called a
black hash there's red and black trees
for example the play cache is an example
of a hash you might use for something
like this and they oftentimes they'll
produce bigger bigger hash vectors as
well so in this case you can see this
one is what like 512 or 256 right so if
you wanted to we could support bigger
hashes and that gives us more resilience
the more the bigger the hash value the
more of the data you're sort of checking
right the the wider the less likely you
are to be able to have a collision right
but any good hash value you can always
truncate so you can also just take the
first two from it and there's your
64-bit hash so you can always yeah you
can always do sort of sub subgrade
hashes if you want so we could do a
blake hash there's also obviously the
ones that are
sort of the government approved versions
right which is sha
I think sha is not probably as good for
our purposes - I believe sha is more
[Music]
you know I can't remember now I think
about it I'm not gonna say that because
I don't really remember I haven't looked
at Blake very carefully so I'm not gonna
make that statement um there's a lot of
hash values out there we could also use
something more like a murmur hash which
is a faster hash so that it doesn't take
as long to import things and and check
the hash on them so you do a lot of
things we'll pick that up tomorrow and
see what we want to do for now we have a
crappy hash value in there and what I
could do here is just make put that make
sure we put that to do in there where is
our sure but I think that's basically it
and I'll guess I'll run this but it
shouldn't do hopefully we should still
run just fine because again it's not
importing anything right now we didn't
make a local file for importing so we
should be good to go I'll go ahead and
go to the Q&amp;A now but I think we've got
most of the stuff into position that we
needed all I think we redid all of the
import export stuff so tomorrow it's
basically just we should probably put in
a better hash function if we're gonna
use one at all put in a better hash
function there maybe make a little more
space for it look maybe we want a 512
size hash I don't know but we can put in
a better hash if we want to and then we
can we can start the debugging process
on that on the all the stuff we did
a blonde orphan how often are assets
updated what are the performance
characteristics you're aiming at so
mostly I guess what I would say is the
assets are loaded by the artist and so
you don't want anything to slow that
will uh know it like you don't want the
artist sitting around waiting so if you
have a problem with if you've got
something a bit so slow that you don't
actually that you're actually costing
the artist time then you know you you've
you've got issues so you don't want to
do anything obviously stupid but beyond
that we don't care we don't need this
thing to to do anything high throughput
assets will only be updated one sprite
sheet at a time particularly so
basically an artist saves a sprite sheet
we load the sprite sheet we want that to
run in a couple seconds right we we
don't want that to be like basically
think of it as a build when we run a
build if it takes two three seconds for
us that's we don't care right that's
fine if it takes ten seconds if we take
30 seconds really bad right and if it
takes like minutes that's awful so we
don't care if we're one second or three
seconds or half a second those are all
probably equivalent to the artist in
terms of time if we're ten seconds or
over not great not not great so I would
consider that an issue if our import
took longer than a few seconds per
sprite sheet I would I I think we need
to fix we would need to optimize that
because that's not an acceptable
turnaround time for the artist would you
suggest any resources that cover modern
cirrhosis memory management very well I
tend to over his unique pointer
basically C++ memory management modern
zo scenario management
awful don't ever do it if you're trying
to learn it because you're working at it
at a job
hopefully they just sort of have their
own policy about what they're doing and
just follow that policy because you have
to but modern C++ menu management is
awful
don't ever do any of it it's all by
people who don't understand memory
management full stop
it's modern C++ money management is
worse than garbage collection if you
have a choice between C++ memory
management and like c-sharp c-sharp
probably smarter it's probably better
probably better performance - honestly
in most cases modern CMOS memory
management is is terrible it's it's
really really really bad it's it's
extremely bad you already have an adler
3-2 function written out in the PM g
partner why not hit parser you why is
that did we do that where did we do I
don't remember us implementing that
where is that
I don't I don't remember doing that well
GJ Nate where do you think we
implemented Adler 32 I you know I only
work on this on the weekends I may well
have forgotten but if I wanted to run
the game locally is the steps I need to
run the test asset build first and then
we could run the HJ edit to update to v1
if we wanted yes
looking at struct HHA annotation could
we append the authors of assets into the
credits for the assets in the current
rent of the game you could yes Martin
says pre stream off-topic GLS whistling
with GL texture Swizzle RGBA rgba works
fine with GL v 3 + 3 3 point 3 higher
even for core profile before 3 3 it
works only if the extension is present
so you get whatever channel into any
channel you want really is this another
one of those things Martin's although
where you have a magic computer where
this works and I don't that's what
happened with with I control ports I'm
sorry ok I owe completion ports when we
were doing IOC fees I didn't really test
that maybe a third thoroughly though so
that may be true that's good to know if
GL texture special RGBA works fine with
3/3 higher that's probably fine for a
lot of purposes for our purposes that
probably fine and hamate here I think we
require three three or so but that's
good to know if that's actually true nor
declare I do not have any thoughts on
the rest programming language I don't
use it
I thought you added it along with the
Huffman compression I don't think so
what I mean if you can find it let me
know what would we have been doing what
would it have been doing for us that we
would have needed to implement it
Martin's says it's in the core spec okay
well that's good I mean that's good that
they have that because I I kind of
missed it it was really nice when they
used to have it I may have just been
using OpenGL 3 and didn't have the
extension or something in a weird case
and so I thought they'd removed it
permanently but it's good to know that
it's back because I seems pretty useful
right which would be a 7 it C++ memory
management bad for games or just bad
just bad if the latter what's a general
what's a good general purpose memory
management strategy for C++ um so in my
opinion there's really only two sort of
memory cases right there are things that
behave like stacks and things that
behave in random fashions and everything
that can behave like a stack should be
made to in my opinion which meet which
is 90% of all allocations should be done
that way and you should be doing them
that way with arenas basically the other
10% should be done probably with free
list management so that's what I would
do and see those plus I would not use
any of that unique pointer shared
pointer nonsense those are just garbage
ra - and all that stuff is complete is
only for toy programming it's like when
people use that stuff they really don't
know what they're doing sorry and I'm
stepping on a lot of people's toes out
there who are experienced programmers
who say that these are smart things to
do they're wrong I mean they just are
you spend a ton of time your C++ code
just does tons of work that it doesn't
need to do you know so on handmade hero
we don't quite go full pull like a
handmade hero we are not quite as good
as we should be we use arenas so we get
a lot of wind out of that but we don't
really implement much more on top of
that for the more general purpose kinds
of stuff right so we you know we only
can go to we can only do certain things
on handmade hero right it's it's a
limited scope thing and there's only so
much we can do but
the stuff we do with arenas on handmade
hero is kind of similar to what I think
most memory management should look like
in most things most of the time because
most of the time what you want to do is
you want to be working in temporary
stacks most things can be implemented
that way and they're very very fast what
you want new memory you just push
forward you don't need to do anything
there's no mutex thing there's no
looking into tables there's no nothing
you just go can I fit it if yes it just
goes it's like an if or two to go and
that's really important and then cleanup
is instant you just roll back the arena
pointer so you don't have to go through
all of these pointer chains freeing
everything which is really really bad
right that kind of stuff is just bad
programming when you're crawling through
pointers freeing things that you don't
need to do because you know you can
clean up everything in bulk that's
really bad you're wasting a ton of time
right a ton of processor time doing
nothing once you get rid of all that
stuff then you're left with just things
that stay around for like unpredictable
amount of times so like we're allocating
something and we don't know when it's
going to be de-allocated and for those
you need more thoughtful approaches and
that's the place where if you were using
garbage collection or something like
that I'd be like fine that's fine like
you know I'm probably not how I would do
it but it's fine or if you're using
something where you were using some
reference counting again that's fine
like there are cases where things like
that do become okay and they are
reasonable and they aren't costing more
time than they should and so on but
that's the only place that I ever want
to see those sorts of crawley based
pointer looking things like the way
garbage collection analyzes like the
waste modern c++ does all of its stupid
unique pointer sharing pointer smart
pointer kinds of things all that stuff
should only be happening in the case
where the memory lifetime isn't known
and the memory lifetime for almost
everything in almost every
program is known that's the crucial
that's the part that's so frustrating
people act like we don't know when the
memory is going away we almost always do
like 90% is even probably low like 99%
of all memory you probably know exactly
how long it needs to be there at compile
time right and it's just ridiculous to
write code in a way that pretends that
everything is volatile and completely
arbitrary that's almost never true you
know and so all of that - leave us trust
memory management is just based on bad
understandings of how memory works and
it's about focusing on the language not
the hardware which you know I find to be
a grievous error do you use any of the
handmade coding your 9:30 for a project
I don't at the moment but I will be
moving the PNG parser in there now that
I have my own PNG parser I can use that
one currently I have a thing that I have
a PSD loader and that's what we use for
everything and I don't have a PNG or
JPEG loader so for our website which is
the only thing that loads pngs or JPEGs
for our website I actually still call
out to like external tools it like the
the web builder will like all possibly
like free image I think it'll call like
a DLL to put those into other formats
and now I can just switch to using our
PNG ourselves' no sorry it's not that
it's not very much it's some image magic
it calls out like if it needs to do it
needs to produce like multiple sizes of
a thing and it was the website stuff so
I was kind of in a hurry so all I do is
I call out to a shell out to image
magics convert utility so that no matter
what the input file format is it would
resize it down we only use PNG and JPEG
so what I'll probably do is at some
point write my own JPEG and then I can
just have it entirely in our code base
which would be nice that's like one of
the only things we use
now there's like to to external calls we
make in our entire code base right now
one is for that which is the website so
I don't really care it could stay that
way I don't I don't really care about
that but for 1935 we do use one external
tool that's a forbus compressor and so
someday I'd like to put in our own audio
compression because Vorbis sucks anyway
so I'd like to put in our own audio
compressor at some point but that was
just a bridge too far I've already
always swamped with coding work on 1935
I just couldn't afford it so but someday
I'll get there Eliminator will you be
changing your fonts to be packed bitmaps
rather than a bitmap per glyph if not
how would you store the UVs for the
glyphs in the h @j file
no I we probably wouldn't bother cuz we
don't really have to I mean maybe we
would at some point I'm not sure but if
not how would you store the UVs for the
glyphs in the h @j file well so the same
way that we store the glyphs now as just
an array of bit Magnus's indices you
could just or the bitmap index and the
UV right
have you tried the opus codec by the way
no I haven't is but it is is that the
one that's lossless or is that just a
new one that they made what's the what's
the lossless one it's not it's not opus
is it it's it's flax that's the one so
no I have not tried opus is it necessary
to use pragma pack push and pop for the
a jamais tracks it is sort of the reason
that it is sort of is because we don't
want different versions of different
compilers deciding to pack those structs
differently and so we're just trying to
make sure that if other people are
compiling them on say a 32-bit compiler
or something that might make a different
decision about how it got packed they
would say the same are there any things
in there right now that I think it would
affect no so I don't think we need it at
the moment but it's just it's a really
bad idea to roll the dice on that like
you don't generally want to to start
making a file format in something that's
not that doesn't have the C packing
rules turned off right
and you just to expand that a little bit
since people are talking about in the
chat the reason that I say Vorbis sucks
it's not the compression quality or
amount that sucks like I it's acceptable
for youth you know you can compress
things pretty reasonably and they still
sound okay so it's it's I feel like it's
competitive with mp3 just fine
which you know is obviously a standard
that everyone not finds acceptable and
uses for everything so you know it's a
reasonable replacement in that sense the
problem is it's just crappy code right
it's built in two layers for no reason
right so the Orbis the Vorbis if you use
their code for it what ends up happening
is you have to have it encode Vorbis
output into aughh streams that can be
broken up into packets and always it
right none of that stuff i want like i
have a game it's got its own streaming
system its own file format it knows
where everything is it just wants you to
output right data that it can quickly
decompress with a nice clean easy
efficient code stream into sound data
again and it really just isn't set up
for that
it's it's got way too much complexity
the OGG part is just bad and but you
have to use it more or less and so even
if I was gonna stick with it I'd
probably make a thing that parses out
the augs dream that comes out of the
compressor andrey encodes the Vorbis
part and then write my own Vorbis the
compressor part that just went directly
to bypass that kind of crap because it's
got a bunch of cruft you just don't want
so fundamentally the compression model
I'm not an audio compression guy so I'm
not in a position to say whether it's
good or bad right so I'm not complaining
about the compression quality I'm
complaining about the code quality it's
just not suitable for what I want to do
and so I would much rather have a code
base I control so I can make a really
nice clean efficient D
d compressor part that's the important
part
Martin's was posting some stuff about
opus
so here's a question with opus by the
way what is the actual code complexity
level because that's the other thing
that I find is problematic with audio
codecs a lot of time I mean here's the
thing and a lot of people don't
understand this fundamentally right I
don't care how complicated your
compressor is really you know I gotta
use a library to do compression cuz I
ain't gonna do it
and it's super complicated whatever
right I don't want to have to use a
library to decode stuff I want to be
able to write it and I want it to be
simple right it shouldn't be complicated
to do a decode um and so I want to see
like a five thousand line decoder in one
file for your for your audio compressor
if you can't do that you've got a
problem in my opinion right and ya FFTs
can be a little bit nasty in there you
know there's a lot of audio codecs that
rely on FF T's and so you know I'm gonna
cut used to slack on stuff like that I
don't mind but it should be basically
straightforward compared to you know any
reasonable audio codec decoder and if
you're coming to me and go and look you
know we could we can get ten to one if
it was a simple five thousand line
decoder but we really wanted to get
eleven to one and it's now it's this
giant fifty thousand line D compressor
that is a really bad trade-off right
there is no game that I can ship with
eleven to one compression that I
couldn't have just shipped with ten to
one compression it affects me not at all
so really what it did is made my
codebase worse made it more likely to
have bugs and made it harder for me to
maintain because now there's this giant
50,000 line wart sitting in there that I
don't know what it does
I can't evaluate it very effectively
porting it can be problematic it may not
work properly on all processors
I have optimization problems now because
I got to worry about how fifty thousand
lines of
is being executed by something right so
these are bad trade out trade offs in my
opinion um so audio codecs I think once
they get above some magic number I'm not
sure what it is let's say it's 8 to 1
ish maybe 10 to 1 somewhere around there
I don't want any more complexity there's
if you're if if it takes more complexity
to get further down than that I don't
want it you're making a bad trade off
for me I understand why you're doing it
because you're making an audio codec you
want it to be as compressed as possible
that's your whole thing right the
highest quality the lowest data rate but
that's just not what I want so you're
giving me features I don't want or
improvement optimization in the data
rate that I don't want and you're making
it worse for me on the integration side
so that's really crucial to understand I
want a very simple decoder that I can
write myself in a couple weeks right
let's say from your spec I want that so
if if they've got that I'm happy I would
be happy with that
right that's that's really all actually
about that Vorbis is not that right
ruah 47,000 lines yes so 47,000 lines
it's just way too big for a decoder it's
just it's I guarantee you it's not worth
it
right it's worth it for some people
meaning if what you're trying to do is
is maximally get the highest quality in
the lowest space and accept no
substitutes
you know we're sending the probe into
outer space then great but for a game
it's just not necessary if I can't fit
the if the did compressor in like less
than 10 K of code I yeah I don't I don't
really want it right and so I would like
to make a simpler audio codec one that
just gets eight to one ten to one
whatever something reasonable shippable
but simple 5,000 lines 10,000 lines no
more that would be my sweet spot and
that's what I would be aiming for to
replace Vorbis with which may just be
basically Vorbis like I could just do
more or less Vorbis right but trim out
the fat and and maybe it gets there I
don't know opus might be similar right
like for all I know if we went started
looking at opus and how it worked it may
be like yeah okay so if we just get rid
of certain modes that it does like maybe
it's got all these different things you
can do like oh this looks like speech so
I'm gonna do like a speech codec here
and all this looks like music some of
your music codec here and all this looks
like this and it's got like all these
crazy things and maybe they're really
disparate and maybe we only care about
like picking the one that works best and
just using that for everything even
though it's a little less efficient for
some things you know what maybe that you
could make a simplified opus that could
still work right and so that's like
totally viable - right so I don't know
but at some point I would like to figure
out how to do that because that's a
really big nasty wart in our code base
right now that I don't like so all right
that said we are done for today thank
you everyone for joining me for an
episode of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like
to follow along the series at home you
can always go to handmade hero org and
you don't need the slash game on there
that's just what happens if you click
this um go to him meteor org and you can
pre-order the game it comes with all the
source code so that you can play around
with it yourself we also have some other
useful stuff here there's a watch page
where you can go to watch the series
it's got a viewer on there that anytime
we're live it comes up otherwise it'll
show you the schedule so you can know
when we're gonna be live next pretty
handy it's also got an episode guide you
can use to watch old episodes and it has
search by P string it's awesome you can
just type in stuff you want to know
where we did the PNG decompressor just
type PNG in there it's got it all it's
pretty great we also have a FAQ if
there's any question about series you
have that are easily answerable and
finally you have a handmade fun if you
want to support things such as that
awesome episode guide or the forums that
people use a handmade network stuff like
that you can always contribute to the
handmade fund we give that money away
every month however much we get we give
away to the folks doing useful projects
for people who do handmade hero style
programming that's it for this this fine
Saturday we'll be back tomorrow for
another stream probably tomorrow we
could implement the hash and then we're
out of stuff so it's just really
debugging and the hash tomorrow and then
we're we're into that nasty tag problem
that I've talked about started a series
not looking forward to that but
hopefully we will get lucky and be able
to come up with something that works
pretty well we'll see until then have
fun programming and I'll see everyone on
the Internet tegus everybody