hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero show we code a complete game live
on stream we split up the PNG reader
yesterday into two parts because we have
to integrate it into the game now we
built it in a test at first that just
takes in a single PNG and writes out of
BMP so we could verify that we were
reading it correctly and we seem to have
debugged it at least to the extent that
we need to to read the files that we
actually care about which are the ones
that come for from the art department
for our game so at this point really
what we need to do is figure out where
the memory is gonna come from integrate
that in and capture the debug output we
sort of started doing that the end of
last name we didn't get very far because
we ran out of time so that's what we're
doing today this is some very
straightforward architecture work should
not be super complicated but it needs to
get done so if we bring up our test PNG
program here that's this this is still
the code that's necessary to run the PNG
to BMP converter that we basically were
using as a test case we now have pulled
out the PNG part so that the PNG part is
isolated and we can start building into
something else this something else
building part of it however is going to
require us to actually tell it where to
get memory from so really at this point
if you look we have already isolated the
debug output part so that all of the
debug output and information or error
reporting and that stuff now goes to a
stub function that just throws it away
but in the future we can save it so
that's good
the other thing that we need to do here
is we need to make it so that the memory
allocation comes from a known place so
we had already made sure that malloc as
you can see is isolated it's only called
right here in these three places where
we know exactly what we're allocating
and why we have stream chunks pixels and
the Huffman table because we don't know
how big the Huffman table has to be for
example so the
these allocations in question are things
that we want to change into coming from
a particular memory arena and we want to
provide that arena to the system so that
what can happen is as the game is
running what it needs to load a PNG it
can tell the PNG loader where to get the
memory from so it's not just grabbing
memory willy-nilly and in some way that
is uncontrolled so what we want to do is
we want to start breaking this up into
things that are going to use specific
memory arena possibly more than one
because we may want to have one
understanding of where the the memory
arena like one memory arena for
temporary operations and one memory
arena for where we're actually going to
permanently store the data but in
addition to that we have to understand
the fact that because this is actually
just temporary art loading code probably
what's actually going to happen is all
of this is going to be considered
temporary so my assumption of how I
probably want to structure this code is
we're just gonna use a single temporary
arena we're gonna allocate everything
into the temporary rina we're gonna hand
that back to the collar the collar is
probably going to do some pulling out
because remember these are like
basically sprite sheets at this point
that the artist can give us a sprite
sheet so all of these cells in a given
file then want to be pulled out input
for example into permanent store and
into the texture system whatever then it
all gets thrown away we don't need that
sprite sheet anymore right the sprite
sheet is not relevant to us after that
point so I think what we want to do here
is just recognize the fact that probably
we don't need to think about memory
management at all in the system I think
this system just gets an arena it does
all of its work inside the arena then
returns and the caller will just clean
up that whole set of things because
none of it will be relevant once the
caller is done processing the output
image so that's what I want to do at the
moment we can see we have handmade
memory here this memory arena and so on
so you can see I've I've explained how
programming works here in a nice comment
it's only three lines long tells you
everything you need to know about
programming resource acquisition is
initialization is bad zero is
initialization is good so you've got
there you go you that's all you need you
can stop watching handmade here and now
because you've learned it all so what I
want to do now is I want to go in and
make sure that all of these systems that
allocate pixels allocate chunk and
allocate Huffman all of these want to be
able to work with an arena instead of
with malloc to do this I would like to
include the memory system we already
have because obviously I don't see any
need to start creating another one I
want them to be integrated so I'm gonna
see if I can just integrate handmade
memory but don't know that I actually
can yes you can kind of see that one of
the problems that we're gonna have here
is that for example the platform memory
stuff is is it's sort of dependent on
that I don't know to what extent that
will cause us a problem
looks like we need our maximum macro
here and I'm not sure whether or not
that's something we can just you know
replicate here that's in handmade shared
I could just make that also be included
again we don't care what's included in
the test app so in tests
PNG here I could just say hey let's
bring in that shared bit as well and
then I can compile and we'll see what
happens
no such file is it not it's right there
Oh ha ha
got a little transposition there so
oh did we already include it or
something
struct redefinition that's the same did
I already include that somewhere
Color Me confused
is it like included some oh so we
actually include that inside handmade
shared so I guess if we just include
handmade shared we get all of that
probably for reasons I would rather not
think about anyway so if I have the
memory subsystem now what I should be
able to do here is I should be able to
pass the memory that I want into the the
handmade PNG reader and then the same
thing can happen in the game and in the
test app the test app will just create
an arena for it to use and it'll use
that arena so if I just pass in a memory
arena here then this you know which is
just a size malloc this just becomes a
push size that's gonna take you know the
same number of bytes here and produce
the blank sort of block for the pixels
no big mystery about what's going on
there the chunk allocator here really
should be over with the stream stuff I
think we want that to be over in
handmade stream actually so I'm gonna
move that over there at the moment I
want to look to see where we're calling
allocate chunk because he I think it's
getting called actually yeah it is in
here so what we want to do now that the
stream is sort of more of a first class
citizen this operation of adding a chunk
to a stream this will no longer be the
only place where that actually happens
so we probably want to do is make that a
little bit more systemic so in here I
think what we want to do is is pull this
data out and say all right this
piece of code I shouldn't say data
should say code this piece of code here
that appends a chunk that you know
allocate chunk can now sort of be rolled
into one thing that looks more like this
and what we could say is for a
particular stream you know the
allocation can happen and then the
pushing on of the contents size and that
sort of stuff can be something that
happens based on what the parameters of
the function are so you know append
chunk might be our new thing we take
which stream to append to the chunk -
and then we take how big you want it to
be and what the content should be right
and what we could do here is well is say
look do you want this allocated or do
you want this to be you know do you want
me to allocate the size or not we could
have stuff like that and there's well
what I probably would say is since it's
arena based now we don't really have to
care so probably what we could say is
just hey if you wanted some of the
memory to be allocated for storing the
contents you can just do that as well
using the arena doesn't really matter so
when we append a chunk what we really
need to tell it is what the size was and
what the contents are and I think this
is actually technically a weight but we
don't really care so when we allocate
this here what I'd say is we'll just
pass the size we pass the contents and
then everything else just kind of takes
care of itself this is the stream here
and so instead of comp data which was
the old variable name for it we're from
the COBE pulled it out of we're just
gonna go ahead and put this in like so
so that appends the string the chunk to
the stream and now what we want to do is
we want to have this be some kind of an
arena push that we do here now we want
our we want our stream to understand
where to get its memory from I think so
we probably want that to be part of the
stream as well so the stream knows where
it's going to get the stuff that it's
actually pulling from so you know I
don't think we need to pass that in here
I think
want to just say that what we're doing
here is we're doing a push struct on the
screen the memory that was specified for
the stream and we want the stream chunk
from that arena and it's just gonna
allocate one there like you know
increase the space and you know push it
back and I think that's it right now at
some point we probably want you know
this stuff here we probably want to push
stuff on to a free store so when we
advance so when we do refill if
necessary I want to put a little thing
that's here you know it says something
like to do KC I you know use a free list
to recycle chunks if we ever care we
don't really know what we're gonna do
with the stream stuff it's kind of just
a very simple little struct that we're
using for some you know simple streaming
purposes it's just kind of underbaked
right now but I'm gonna leave it under
banked because I don't need to start
engineering this thing it may never
matter to the behavior of our program we
may never need it to do more if we do
need it to do more than at the point
where we need it to do more that's the
time to actually go through and make it
you know conscientious about what it's
doing and all the other sorts of things
we might want this this is not the time
to play around that own thing alright so
this is a pen chunk
it'll append a chunk to the stream that
you give it with that size so inside the
test code now when that actually
happened
I'm sorry inside the handmade PNG code
when actually happens we're really just
doing an append chunk here where we pass
in the information we got like so and we
just want the comp data
struck to be the thing where that that
happens right so the comp data now is
something that you know
again all initialize to zero will just
work but you need to then start placing
some certain pieces of information in
there if you want it to be able to do
things like allocate its own chunk
memory so what I would like to do is
have just a little like why should i
well you know what honestly I think this
is all we really need here so on-demand
memory stream can just take an arena and
it can take an error stream and if you
just set the error stream to zero then
it just won't record any errors right so
I'll actually just say that's what we're
gonna use so you can say I want an
on-demand memory stream and you'll get
one again all this is gonna do is just
say all right
well zero everything because remember
zero is initialization and then we just
set the fields that we actually cared
about which are these two this one may
not be set in fact even this one might
not be set if you didn't ever plan to
allocate anything on it but you know
presumably you do so we can just call
this an on-demand memory stream now and
we pass in the memory arena that we
actually want to use which is something
that should come from the outside so
it'll get passed in here probably and
then we also have where we want the
errors to go and I think we just want
that to be whatever the files air stream
whatever the other streams sort of error
system was that's what we're going to
use so that's where we're at I think
we're pretty good so far
in terms of how that's going to work
again I don't think there's any Malick's
and here other than these two that we
were looking at before so I think that
getting rid of this one oops
should do it so here we have another
thing that's gonna allocate basically an
array we can you know this was kind of
unsafe again I don't like malloc because
it doesn't have the structure that we
want to ensure that we don't make simple
preventable mistakes so if I do a push
our a here that's much better I can say
oh this is how many
any of those I wanted right and this is
what I wanted so it allows me to make a
simpler sort of more understandable more
reliable way of expressing that same
thing that will cast to the right thing
on the way out too so if this you know
if I put the wrong type here it will
error instead of working you know which
like the other line would have done so
that's what we want to convert to
something that requires arenas and now
we're gonna have to make sure that those
things are passed through four chunks I
think I don't know what I want to do in
terms of sizing right now we're kind of
riding out on the 32-bit sizing I don't
know if that's a good idea or not maybe
maybe it's not I'm not sure anyway I'm
gonna have some of this stuff here take
memory again as it was before so like we
said an arena gets passed to everybody
and they all work out of that arena and
that arena will probably get discarded
in the way that arenas gonna come in at
the head end like so so now I think
about it yeah the we could actually pass
the errors as well in there I don't know
or we could get it from the file stream
not sure how we want to do that there's
a lot of ways we could it doesn't really
matter so but anyway I'm gonna do it
like this there we go
so now all that stuff is is coming from
the system correctly we want here to
create one of these memory arenas and
the only thing is we don't really know
how to create it yet because we're gonna
test app not in the actual game so we
have to cross that bridge in a second
here but just other than that it's
pretty straightforward we're just going
to do something like this
now we don't have the ability to specify
an error stream basically until we have
one so this one's not going to have an
error stream but we could have the info
stream have an error stream you know
because once we have an air stream we
can use it so everybody else can use the
air stream that's fine once we do that I
think we're good to go now we just need
some way of getting the memory in here
and so what we want to look at the
memory system and see what's the easiest
way we could emulate the platform layer
effectively in order to make this thing
work
and so if you look at how this is
working when normally when we create one
of these memory arenas we kind of have
to we have to do some kind of
initialization to it that allows it to
get memory you can see in here for
example when you allocate memory it can
try to call to get a new block right so
you see this platform allocate memory
stuff happening there so since we don't
have a platform subsystem outside in
here what we'd have to do is sort of
emulate one which really isn't a big
deal right because the only thing that
that platform substation needs to do is
provide memory to this so we can make it
think that it's sort of running on the
game without too much trouble right
should be fairly straightforward so if I
just initialize this memory system to
zero then what we'll see is everything
actually works fine but because we're
now calling that allocation call off of
the platform global variable the linker
is thrown into a panic because it
doesn't know where it could possibly
receive such a thing right it's like I
don't have that global variable so how
am I supposed to call a function off of
it right which is a very reasonable
thing for a linker to say you know the
linkers is an eminently reasonable sort
of a person I feel and it is right to
complain so where is the struct platform
API stuff in here oh it's right there so
you can see what we're looking at here
you can see there's a number of things
that that deal it's a fairly minimalist
platform layer which is great but what
you can also see is that it has the two
things that we actually care about
allocating dikanka memory so what we
could do again is just say alright you
know we'll we'll put one of those in
here platform API platform now it's been
defined and really all we need to do is
make sure that the one or two functions
we make all which would be allocate and
deallocate memory make sure those
actually exist and so if we go into the
the platform layer
and we look at what's happening you can
see it's it's you know it's got a lot of
stuff in here that we made you know we
don't care about any of this stuff this
is not like we don't need any of this
right all we need is the basic operation
of allocating the memory so I'm going to
call this CRT allocate memory and oops
there it is do you get memory right so
I'm going to call those the CRT versions
and now we can just bunk through to
malloc and free just like we were doing
before so all I'm gonna do here is say
okay if we got a block passed we just
free the block that's it when we do
allocating memory we need to return a
platform memory block that's what has to
happen here platform memory block I
think is kind of a semi opaque thing
it's got a little bit of information on
it but you can see what happens here we
when we come in here we do a size plus
the size of the memory block header then
we do a bunch of stuff and we allocate
the size plus however big the memory
block header is right so I don't know if
I assume the platform memory block yet
has a size you can see it here so what
we want to do here is just say alright
there's a platform memory block that's
what we need to allocate here and we
then we need also the size the amount of
memory that they actually ask for and
you can see here that that's the size
parameter that's coming in in this
through this macro here so what we want
to do is we want to take the size of the
platform memory block we want to add our
size and that's the thing that we
actually want to malloc so when you get
memory you get one of those and that's
it right my understanding is this has to
be cleared as well so what we want to do
is take the memory block that whole
piece of memory
we want to clear the whole thing so I
might do a total size thing here like so
allocate the total size clear it out and
then if there's anything in here that we
need to set we can set it I don't know
that there's anything particularly
relevant to set but you can see it in
here so you know if we we look there's
this stuff so I would say just yeah set
the size we know it right we want to set
the base because I think that's the
thing that's actually gonna get that's
the thing that soccer can be used as the
pointer right yeah so we just want to
offset ourselves from that so we take
what it the block and we add one to it
to move past it and then that's our well
I guess that's it
right oops see you wait and I think
that's really it I guess I put D in
front of that and I think that will
allocate memory for us in exactly the
same way that the game does in terms of
of what the memory arena wants but
instead of calling virtual walk and
virtual free we're just calling the CRT
version so this remains a CRT program
for our test program which is what we
wanted right
so now handmade PNG is nice and schwifty
because it's not relying on anything
that's in the C runtime lever anymore
it's completely platform separated and
now it can exist inside the game or
outside the game and it's happy to do
either which is what we wanted so that's
good now what I want to do as a next
step is I want to make sure a that that
still works and B I want to get the
error streams working so that we can
still see the output of it so again it
compiles just fine we don't know that it
works
I could have introduced a bug I could
have
lamented the memory callbacks wrong
plenty of stuff like that so let's just
see if we get any nonsense happening we
don't quite yet so we're at least we
didn't do anything obviously wrong so
that's fine but we're not quite done yet
like I said inside the stream thing you
can see here we have this out F call the
out of call is something that's designed
to provide printf functionality to
people who don't actually want to call
printf because there may not be a printf
such as in the game so what we want to
do is get that functionality back well
we already implemented I don't remember
where to be completely honest with you
but we already implemented a printf I'm
not shocked well it's right here so I
guess correctly we have this thing
called format string list and you can
see that that gets done will do all the
work for us that we actually cared about
so if I wanted to I could create an
equivalent function to what we've been
using in the game for doing a printf
just like this I can grab the Arg list I
can go ahead and call format string and
then I know that I've got is effectively
like a buffer filled with the data that
I wanted so what I can do here is I can
use a temporary buffer I can say like
okay you know I don't know how big it
has to be but you know we can just have
a 1k buffer on the stack we'll quickly
fill that with something and then when
it's done we know how big it is so I can
then push that thing onto the stack now
I don't know if that includes the null
terminator or not to be completely
honest with you it looks like it does
not so this is the amount of size that
that is not including the null
terminator did we mention that anywhere
so in our case we do want to don't want
to I mean we don't need it because we're
storing these things in chunks I don't
know yeah I mean I got nothing so you
know we we want to append a chunk here
right to the stream that's it's taking
the output we want to pass in that
result site so it's not really the
result anymore right it's just the size
of the thing and we want to pass in the
yeah the contents here but I'm not sure
whether we want to add the mill
Terminator or not
I'm gonna go with not for now
so here's what I'll say let me just
throw this out there
no terminated strings are terrible I
don't like them at all because handmade
here was built on sea without a
preprocessor without any kind of ability
to do length based strings it kind of
has that infection of null-terminated
miss that comes up from it in like you
know at my day job I never used
alternative strings for anything and so
the reason that I'm equivocating about
it here is just because I would normally
never store the null terminator because
it's dumb and it's just wasteful almost
always and harder to compute with rather
than having just the size and the
contents but because we sort of have a
little bit of C miss baggage that comes
with programming in it and the fact that
you can't define a string literal
properly and if you were starting to
call the C runtime library calls yeah
you have to use a macro to define a
string literal that's correct and all
this it's annoying you end up doing this
kind of stuff all the time
you have to like wrap all your strings
it's just like I don't know I think
probably the thing is do it right so I'm
saying I'm not gonna store it and if we
have to go rework some code that'll make
that code better so fine forget it we're
just gonna do it so we're gonna say that
the contents is exactly how much got
returned okay that's just what we're
gonna say so what I want to do here is I
want to do I don't know if we have a
push copy
we do oh but not really so we've got
kind of exactly what I don't want
we've got pushing nil terminate I want
the pushin don't know terminate so I
want by push copy where I can just pass
anything I want right and I want to just
you know copied in there no null
termination return it right so I want to
do a push copy that's gonna give me my
contents the thing that I want to copy
is what's in the buffer I want to copy
as much of it as the format string list
actually put in there and I'm going to
use whatever the memory system is that
came from the from the stream so the
other thing that I should point out is
this is probably its own kind of
operation as well you could imagine if
you look at what this does this says
here's a you know thing that I want to
write into a size destination another
way to look at that would be I want
something that produces the the string
result I want you to make a copied one
of those well you know what I don't I'm
not gonna do that now never mind I'm
gonna leave it like this okay
sooo inside push copy what's the problem
here
push sighs undeclared identifier what
what did I mess up
Identifier push sighs oh is push copy a
macro maybe we already do have a push
copy oh never mind
got ahead of myself there so we did add
the thing that I wanted all right
so push copy we'll take care of all that
for us we're pretty good to go here I'm
gonna go ahead and just say look let's
go ahead and and make this handle
arbitrary sizes fine with that and we'll
just deal with that a pen chunk we'll
have to take that too and so now I think
we're good to go
I don't know yeah so we should be able
to actually test this too if we run this
oh you know what I got set a breakpoint
thugger and never gonna see it we should
see our error streams come back now but
in order to do that we have to prevent
it from closing the window so I'm gonna
go ahead and and run to there hear it it
loaded up that giant 8k by 8k thing so
what we can see here is oh yeah
everything is there's no errors and
here's all the info that's exactly we
wanted this printout looks busted I
think that's because we never actually
stored the information that I wanted us
to store so when we do that a pen chunk
what I want to do here is I'd like to
have the append chakra turn the chunk so
that if you want to store the store the
chunk information you can I could also
make the append chunk call be the thing
that exits but I don't want to do that
for various reasons the reason
specifically is that since this is a
utility function that takes these two if
I had a pen chunk actually be a macro
that took the file in line at all of the
chunks would appear to come from inside
the out F I don't want that I want those
to come from whoever called it right so
I want to set those things
so there's the file and line number that
information is now preserved this just
needs to return the chunk in question
like so and off we go so now when we run
this thing we should get a printout that
says where all that stuff came from too
which is good because again we just it's
just nice to know so here's where all of
that you know if you just wanted to know
where it came from the reason that I
wanted that in there for reference
purposes in the future is that without
that information it becomes harder for a
HUD system or an on-demand display
system like what would be in the game to
be able to tell for example an artist
where a particular problem came from so
for example let's say an artist calls
the programmer over to their machine and
it's like this PNG isn't working and
this is what the game said well if the
programmer just sees some like color
type is unsupported message you know in
this case because I'm the only person
who wrote all the code it's not that big
a deal necessarily but in the grander
scheme of things you have to assume that
programmer may have never even heard of
the PNG code or as maybe never touched
it
being able for having that partner to be
able to see oh here's where that error
is coming from it saves them a lot of
time and energy trying to figure that
out and doing some kind of project wide
search and hoping that the message
happened to be unique enough that it's
easy to search for and blah blah blah so
at that point it's just a way of making
it easy for the person who comes out of
the artist machine when something isn't
working to know where that error is
coming from and how to address it right
how to start debugging it so that's it
the PNG stuff should now be compiled
Belinda handmade hero if we want to be
and I think we do want it to be so if I
just go in here and do it include
handmade that PNG that's EPP and I
should be able to inside here also do
the same thing I don't know where the
asset system gets included here probably
should be here so yeah and then we need
that stream fit I don't think that's in
here anywhere uh so yeah so everywhere
we include in made shared dot H I'm just
gonna go ahead and put handmade stream
that H in there something like this
and so now we should have that code
integrated in and we can call at any
time we can call the PNG reader to load
a PNG in right and once we load a PNG
and then we can do whatever we want with
it and and go from there so what we need
to do now is kind of embark on the task
of like I said the architecture in the
game is probably not going to change
much what we're gonna have to do is make
our asset system the and and that is not
really the asset system the asset
storage format is gonna have to kind of
be more aware of what's going on so what
we need is a way of expressing the fact
that assets can be loaded at runtime and
those become the new permanent assets to
use in the game not sure how to say that
in a better way currently we run
currently the asset storage format right
where is that
I forget worried but that's like I
thought it was called the HHA or
something like this file formats that's
what is so currently what we do is we
have this thing that has all of our
assets in it and the assets in this
system have never had to understand the
concept that they would be overwritten
right so when you look at like an HHA
bitmap for example here's the data for
that bitmap we just expect to load that
out of the file at a particular location
and we don't really have any sort of
awareness of what's gonna happen if that
got overwritten or something we don't
necessarily even have a way to make more
space we can write new HHA files I
suppose because we load we can load
multiple hhas but like for example the
asset count here is you know I guess we
could just append on the end we couldn't
add more types that like there's just a
bunch of issues I'm gonna have to kind
of walk through it and see how I want to
expand it but the point is this is the
part that is currently not really set up
to accept on-demand asset addition to
the system everything else I think kind
of is because the code for all the
rendering doesn't really care about that
at all
so what I think we want to do now is
kind of update this stuff in some way is
to make sure that we can move forward
with that kind of a procedure and that's
gonna be the majority of our work
and it's probably not going to be very
complicated when it's done it's just it
requires us to think it through and do a
little exploration to figure out what
the right way to do that is right that
that's kind of really all we're talking
about here okay so at first I want to
look at the handmade platform system we
have this idea platform get all files of
type begin clap pat platform get all
files of type end right and this allows
us to iterate over files that exist in
the system I don't know what information
it gives us but I suspect we need a
little bit more information I suspect
we'll find out if we look at the asset
system and here's some right here we go
so if you look at the asset system you
can see us iterate over all the HHA
files we say get all files of type we
then say here's how many there are and
let's go over them and when we do an
open file for that file in question we
just get back a handle right that's that
so we just iterate over them one by one
and and we get them back now the problem
with that procedure is that if we now
want to expand that we don't have any
way of doing something like only loading
files that have changed or something
like this right so if you imagine we
wanted to write this system such that
what it does is it waits for the artist
to update a PNG and when the artist
updates that PNG it loads it in we don't
really have any way of doing that Kern
because we don't even know for a given
PNG what the date on the file was so we
don't have any way of only checking pngs
that have at least had their date
changed since the last time we saw them
and that's not gonna work
right so we need that to work and we
need to expand our platform API to
support that otherwise we're never going
to know what to load so in addition to
something that loads pngs extracts the
positions from the sprite sheets and
puts those sprites into our permanent
asset storage we also need to expand the
platform API to give us the ability to
know when we have to do that those are
the two you know issues that we're
facing at the moment now we've got about
an hour left in the stream so we should
be able to start down one of those paths
I'm just not sure which one it should be
I think let's just start at the head end
because we know that part it's fairly
straightforward so what I think we want
to do here is say let's start by let's
start by just making something that
watches a directory and when a PNG and
that directory changes we know and
that's it we're not going to load it or
anything else we're just going to know
that it changed and that I think will
take a day or two of episodes I'm at
work it'll take two episodes because we
need to do two different things one we
need to have the platform API support
that - we need some kind of a
permanently stored checksum for the file
and date for the file so that we don't
reject files every time we load the game
so
to give you some perspective on what I
mean by that we boot up the game the
first time it has to load all the PNG
files because it's never seen any of
them before potentially right but every
time thereafter you don't want it to
load those PNG files anymore
you want it to remember that it had
loaded those PNG files and it doesn't
need to ever press them again otherwise
you end up processing every PNG every
time you load the game which is a
massive amount of startup time I mean
these are 8 K by 8 kpmg's just
decompressing them even if we optimized
the code is it's gonna be a significant
amount of time just in terms of doing
that 8k by 8k extraction and it's a
nasty serialized process too so even if
we spend a bunch of time optimizing that
it's still just dumb to do it every time
especially when you consider I mean
maybe when this game ships there could
be hundreds of PNG x' in there forget it
I mean that's still gonna cause a multi
second even at a very highly optimized
system it will be many seconds of
startup time processing those pngs every
time you load the game not acceptable
right definitely don't want that
we want the game to launch instantly and
the only way to do that is to have a
cache that says here are the PNG s I
already loaded here are the dates on
them here are their check sums don't
load a PNG if it's date matches this
because I already processed that one and
if you do see a date mismatch and you
load it do the checksum if the checksum
matches update your date and don't do
anything if the checksum doesn't match
process the PNG basically right so we
want that sort of two-tiered asset
management system that can understand
how to make that work so I think that's
fundamentally what we want here I and
[Music]
yeah so we've got a lot of work to do
and and let's just get started so inside
the platform layer we already have the
open files blah blah blah
whatever it is it could all file-type
again so what we see here when we do
this we've got this sort of way of
asking for different types of files and
what I think we want to do there is just
go ahead and talk about the different
file types so we've got asset files
we've got savegame files and now we just
want one more or maybe two more which is
a PNG and probably a WAV file because we
want to be able to put both PNG Xin and
sound effects music files in so I think
what we want to do here is say alright
let's go ahead and get those two out so
now we have the ability to switch on
those and produce listings of their
files so if all we wanted to do is load
all the p.m. G's we'd be done that's all
we need to do but we don't want to do
that we want to have a way of getting
information about the files now one of
the things that's kind of a little bit
weird about this right is we've got this
sort of like we've got this like open
file and I think there was like a get
next file how did this work exactly yeah
so it's called open next file right and
we kind of need so we need like another
thing from that that tells us you know
the the information or something right
something that's like like tell me the
file info you know and what I don't
really know is I don't know was there
ever did we ever get a name or anything
it looks like I don't think I guess we
didn't get anything really like there
was no way to get any information
yeah I mean it looks like there's just
no way to get any information out of the
system at all which is again was fine
for what we were doing not really fine
now
so what we want to do here is we want to
have some way of
yeah we want to have some way of getting
that info you know I don't love this
system uh it seems overwrought to me and
I don't really know that it makes a
whole lot of sense I I kind of just want
to fix it and I think we probably should
so if you look at what's happening here
there's just there's iteration for no
reason and I think we deliberated about
this I'm not sure why we decided to go
with it the way that it is but I don't
think it's very smart I think we
probably want to do this a little bit
differently I feel like the better way
to do it would be like this something
where we said okay here's the file count
I'm sorry
here's like the file date that's you
know just some 64-bit integer that
represents the file date we don't
necessarily have to understand it so it
could just you know it could be the date
as far as that platform understands the
date you know it's some platform 64-bit
representative date doesn't have to mean
anything to the application
so we could have the platform file info
there and then we could have you know
the name of the file so something like
in here you know we'd have this is the
name of the file that you would use to
open it or so that we can parse the name
of the file and know what its name is
because that's what we're gonna have to
go on to figure out what this file
should actually be right because you
know we're gonna load something called
character hero if we don't know what the
name of the file is in the app we're not
going to know what to do with the data
in the file we're just gonna have a
bitmap that's gonna be like what is this
bitmap right so we kind of have to know
that information as well yeah
so we're gonna have to have that name at
least the base name so you know we could
we could say this is like without the
path right in fact it could just be it's
just the raw like the name that the
artist gave to the to the name part of
the file right so yeah
so there's a couple extra things here I
think you're worth noting so if we also
consider the fact that these files don't
necessarily have all of the information
in them that they need I'm not sure how
we want to deal with that part for
example suppose we have a like one of
these files just trying to think out
loud here
suppose we take a look at some of these
files here right you think of a good one
maybe like one of those ground cover
uh-oh well you know what this could used
to be stored I guess in the art file so
you know let's say we look at these
right we just got a bunch of little
Tufts of grass or whatever we need some
way of saying like what the different
ones are in there or when they should be
used or something like that right and
some of the stuff is wrote like we know
that the grid tells us that but like
like say this we don't know how big each
of those trees is supposed to be in the
world right we need like a scale
coefficient we might need to know like a
hot spot like a like a you know we need
we might need information we we might
need information to tell us like what to
do with some of these things and
ancillary information and so I was
trying to think of like how would we how
would we handle that and I guess with
the what I'm thinking in my head it's
just well we could just store that that
could just be set in the game using
something and and that's probably fine
so yeah I think I I guess that's not
really that big of an issue
[Music]
I feel like this is a good Krampus I
like this Krampus
so I guess I guess that's all fine so
we'll just say forget about that stuff
and you know we're off we go
so I'm okay with all that so I guess all
we really need here is the ability to
interpret the name we need to know what
the date is and then from there I think
we're okay so what I'd like to do here
is say okay the platform file info is
just going to point to an array of these
so you call this thing and off you go
and then what I'd like to do is say all
right when we do the begin and end of
this when we do platform open file now
and you pass in a name
I'm sorry when you pass in a file group
instead of just the file group now maybe
you pass in the file index so you say I
want to load file 12 you can just load
it so you don't have to do open next
file it's just like platform open file
like that's it right so I feel like
that's better I think that's better
yeah
all right I'm happy with that so that's
gonna cause us that that's gonna mean
that we're gonna have to kind of upgrade
that part of the code a little bit but
that's fine so off we go so this code
can still work the way that it was
working but now it's got to pass the
file index in here right and that's fine
and this code now has to behave
differently right it needs to behave in
a different fashion than it did before
so this whole set of things here the get
all files of type again this thing is
gonna iterate when it iterates over here
it's gonna snap a bunch of information
then when it ends it's just gonna free
this this sort of stuff that it's stored
right and when we do a win32 open file
it's gonna have to look back into the
pieces it's gonna have to look back into
the data that it put forth there and
produce the result that way so like
again this shouldn't be too difficult
but that's just the best is the basic
idea so what you can see here is we just
read and this is probably another thing
we're gonna have to sort of figure out a
little bit here we're just reading out
of a stem we don't know where we're
reading because we assume that we just
are always in the directory that has the
files that we need and now that we're
loading PNG files and stuff out of
potentially a separate art directory or
something like that
we may have to become caught
isn't of what those paths actually are
right so if you look back at how we've
structured the directory in here
you can see that we've got our data and
we'd probably have eventually another
one here that's like music or sound you
know stuff like that
and so when we're inside this data
directory I don't know I mean we could
do it so that the data directory is
still the you know four lakh per term
run tree but usually you want the
ability to do like delete that and
rebuild things from it so I don't really
know that that's the way that we would
want it to work so I'm trying to think
here
so I guess we would you know I'm just
trying to I would say this I guess we
would just expect the run directory to
be here
I'm not sure so this is kind of what I
was thinking
[Music]
something like that
right I just don't know if that's the
right answer or not
hmm so I feel like that's probably the
right answer and then the executable
would just go in the root there when you
ship the thing and when it runs it looks
in data for data stuff art for art stuff
and sound for sound stuff
seems as good as anything else I guess
yeah so basically I I really am kind of
conflicted about that I don't have a lot
to say about it I guess what I'll do is
I'll just do that and we'll see what we
think when I'm done
so if I look at the file info structure
here and you know I might just say that
both of these get a platform pointer so
what we would do is say all right we
pass in the wild-card stuff for
whichever the thing is that you're
trying to load I go in here and I would
I would set you know the where is there
it is that went through handmade it's
just the right one yeah so for the
working directory
it would just be handmade now wouldn't
look it wouldn't go into the day
directory when you iterate over the
files you did a right over them this way
and yes I have one more question there
yeah something like that right so you'd
iterate over them this way and then you
would say okay like we iterate over each
file we push all the information that we
need to push into one of these platform
file infos for one for each file and
then we go from there now what I would
like is I would like a memory arena for
this and I think that's probably what I
will do I can't see a lot of reason not
to so we have a win 32 platform file
group I just don't think we actually
need that for anything I don't know even
where that it's right here
so here's the win32 platform file group
and the win32 platform file handle I
think we can just get rid of those I
think I'm gonna put that down here for
now so I think what I want to do instead
is say alright there's gonna be a memory
arena and that memory arena is what
we're going to use to store the
information here so I need that thing to
persist so really what I want here I
guess is a bootstrap arena right
[Music]
hmm yeah and I don't really want to have
a structure this but I think I need to
just for this purposes right so what I
would really do is say okay here's my
boots cut push trucks I want to grab one
of these things I don't need any of this
and off we go I think right yeah so I
think that's it and that will create one
of those I don't care about any of these
things well I guess I kind of do so I
guess we're returning that and we're
saying that this is the like win32
flower group is this thing now and we
don't care about any of this stuff more
specifically I suppose so it looks
something like that
as I then go forward I just do the
basics here I've got the win32 find
handle thing I guess I don't even really
need that looks like we just kind of go
through here we loop over and do the
file count thing yeah I mean I think I
think what we can do is just do the loop
twice right so figure out how many of
them we have and then do it again and we
want to make sure we only do the right
number of these because the number of
files could have changed in between the
initial call and
next call which is kind of annoying
right but and I suppose one thing we
could do to I suppose we could actually
respect the fact that that happens on
platforms do this a little bit
differently so I suppose what we could
do is say alright really what's gonna
happen here is that you get back
something more like this right you get
back a linked list of file info
structures and this just has the first
one so it tells you how many there are
and it gives you the first one in the
list but you're expected to traverse
them yourself and then when you load one
you say alright open file the file is
this one so you don't do it by index you
do it by info that way if you have
something like this in the base of the
operating system that's going to create
problems for us it's okay it's no big
deal
we just thread them through and off we
go so I think that's all we really need
and it's good
we don't need this because it's
initialized as you're at the beginning
so then when we come through each of
these can just be a push struct that
takes whatever the memory Reena was we
have there but to do file group oops so
each time we go through here we can push
on a platform file info and we can
initialize that info structure to be the
information that comes back from this
particular file handle so we would know
we will know both the date and the file
name because both of those pieces of
information are in the find data right
if you look at wind through to find data
you can see that we get for example last
right time so that's the last time it
was changed and we also have the size of
the high and low so with the with those
I'm sorry the access time and the file
name we don't actually care about the
size now I think about it
we should supply that though because
then you can read the whole file in so
actually I take it back I do I want that
though so I would say let's put that in
there that seems good right so what we
want to do here is we want to say each
of these things it should should get
filled out
and we'll then we just turn through them
and now we can return the correct thing
and everybody's happy right okay so
standard singly linked list operation
here first file info so is going to be
the info we made and if there was a
first file info previously it just
becomes the next pointer so that's
pretty easy the file D is this thing
right here last access time so ft last
act I'm sorry last right time you don't
want the last access time we want the
last right time so we want the last
right time that's gonna be our file date
again we don't care we don't need to
understand the file date we just need to
know that if the file date is the same
as the last time we saw it no one's
touched the file so we don't care what
that number is we just need to know that
the number is the same when the file
hasn't been touched when we look at the
file size we have a high and a low
so we can say M file size high and file
size low and what we want to do here is
just loft those up to 64 bits and and
smoosh them together something like this
so convert the high size to 64 bits
shifted up by 32 to put it into place
there right just make it do everything
in 64 bit and then smoosh it together
and now we've got the 64 bit file size
instead of two 32-bit pieces that we
don't care about right so that's that
first part again these are I should put
these in the structure they're coming
from structs okay it's actually that and
then we have so the platform information
here it's going to be the whole file
name like so what we will actually need
to use to load it but then here in the
base name what we want to do is get rid
of the rest of the stuff that's on that
file name
I'm not sure how to do that well to be
honest but I think we just want to do a
push size on it so I think what we
probably should do is right this is
going to go away as soon as we call fine
next file so we know this is a push copy
so we're just put that on there and this
is also going to be a push copy but the
problem is that we don't actually know
oh and I should say I guess I'll do a
push on all terminate or something yeah
and the base names gonna be the same the
problem with this is we don't actually
know what part of this to use so we
first need to run a search on it to find
what part of the file name actually is
like the part that the artist set - the
extension - the path name so we need to
strip off everything after the dot and
before the slash those have to go away
right now I don't know that we have
stuff for that yet
we don't so I'm gonna say let's let's
introduce a new function here that we
can use called you know parse file named
parsed equals parse file name or
something like that right you know just
with 32 doesn't have one of these does
it
returns a pointer to the address of the
string of successful seriously that's
some interesting documentation Wells
guesses we should defer to the
platform's own parser if it has one
because it's a platform specific file
name but I gotta be honest with you I
don't remember what that is if it is oh
boy and this is not
there's a lot of stuff in here
so they do have a split path but that's
gonna see runtime library I think yeah
this is essentially what we want but we
want an operating system specific
version of it we don't really want to be
calling yeah here we go
pointing to an alternative string of
length max path contains path and
filename when this function returns
excessively this string contains only
the file name with the path removed so
that's good but doesn't strip the the
extension unfortunately
[Music]
this is a mind-numbing array of files of
api's
that's not what we want
it's annoying uh maybe I'll just write
it myself I wanted to try and defer to
Windows on this but it's there making it
really difficult for me to do so
these are URLs which doesn't that
doesn't help me at all so I don't know I
would like to defer to Windows to have
it remove the parts that we don't want
because if you think about it operating
systems differ in how they handle path
names right so in you know in something
like UNIX a path name of the form W :
foo is just the name of a file but W :
foo in dust is actually the name of a
drive plus the name of a file and so
typically speaking you don't usually
want your file name parsing the file
name parsing part of your code wants to
be in the platform specific part of the
code and where possible you'd like to
defer to the operating system to do it
for you because if it can do it for you
it's gonna know better than you what the
legal prefix path names are for example
on Windows there's UNC path names and
all these other nonsense things and we
don't really want to be in the business
of parsing those things out right that
said because we know this is going to
give us back relative paths in theory we
could just skip the part that we know
that we added ourselves and then
truncate the extension which we know
that we added ourselves as well and so
in some sense it's probably pretty easy
for us to do
so given the fact that I just don't have
much confidence that I'm gonna find a
Windows call to do it I guess I'm just
gonna do it myself so what we want to do
here is say okay in this thing here I
want to be able to find the last slash
and I want to be able to find the period
right so I want to do something like
this I want to say find data see file
name is where the base name begins by
default and then I want to say that you
know yeah something like this you know
that's where it ends right and then what
I want to do is I want to couch I want
to encroach on the file name as
necessary so then I'm going to do a push
and they'll terminate with a length on
here or I could do a push guess we don't
have a push
I guess we don't have a push copy that
necessarily does this so I'm not sure
exactly how I want to do this it'd have
to be something like this we'd have to
nail terminated ourselves again this is
why I say a null termination is terrible
you really don't ever want it if you can
get away without it
so anyway starting from the base name
begin and running till the null
terminator we will scan through if in
our process of scanning we see well I
write it like that if we see a slash of
either kind let's say then what we're
gonna do is say that the base name begin
equals scan plus 1 so the next character
will now be considered the start of the
base name and if we see a period then we
will assume that that is where the name
ends and then when we're done we can now
push the cop out we now know the size or
the base name size equals base name and
myspace name again we now know that we
can push a copy on there like so
right and all we need to do here is we
need this to be one larger now you may
ask how can I make it one larger than
the size well we know that the base name
end was either the last period or it was
the null terminator so I can always copy
the null terminator since this has to be
null terminated so I'm not in danger of
over copying there I don't think even if
I was you don't have to really care
because one other handy bit that we know
of course you can't find it there's a
bunch of other garbage after it so
copying one after it even if we did
exceed the path for some reason which we
won't would just copy the first
characteristic element filename and then
immediately overwrite it with a zero so
again all's well that ends well so this
will produce the information that we
want
barring bugs that I put in there and
then when we are done we just need a way
of freeing it we don't need this fine
close stuff anymore all we really need
to do now is we need to delete the
memory so I think that is in here
already as clear that frees everything
and then we're done so we should be able
to do that wipe out all of the memory we
used and then we're done the only thing
that won't work now is win three of you
open file is going to try to look for
stuff that it can't find and so that's a
problem so what we want to do here
instead is we want to get rid of this
entirely right and when we do the win32
open file
we have a closed file I guess we never
closed files so we're gonna have to add
that because we never currently closed
any files and now we would need to do
that so we will have to add a closed
file call because I guess I think about
it the only ever file the only time you
ever open files for we held them open
for the entire game but we're not gonna
do that anymore so when we do a win32
open file it allocates some memory for
the handle it looks like I'm not sure
why it does that
why are we doing that
I kind of feel like that's really dumb
I I just don't know why we were doing
that why were we allocating memory there
there's no need whatsoever for
allocating memory there that's a real
mystery
I do not know fundamentally speaking why
we were doing that that doesn't make any
sense it is not necessary there was no
reason allocate memory there we just
felt like calling virtual a lock for no
reason and that's I I got I don't know
why that happened that just seems real
real dumb because when we call when we
have this platform file handle like when
we call platform open file here and we
return the platform file handle we don't
need to allocate one of these for any
reason because there's nothing in it
right I mean what's it doesn't need to
store anything I I don't understand that
I I don't know what the point of that is
maybe I'm just not remembering something
important or something but I feel like
this should just be this
because we can just make this as big as
we want like we can make this a bunch of
extra room I'm sorry not that here we
can just make this a bunch of extra room
so I yeah that just doesn't make any
sense to me
but oh well and though I was thinking so
what we can see here is look just put it
in here and that should just be fine so
here's the file handle and off we go
so this is using wide characters as well
so I guess we have to kind of deal with
that a little bit I forgot about that
side of things
so let's yeah I'll have to do a little
bit of work there so we'll deal with
that one second but point being we get a
file name here that's just going to be
the platform pointer so that's going to
be the the platform pointer that I
snuggled in here right was was the that
file name so pushing and I'll terminate
isn't quite going to work because these
are wide file names so that's gonna have
to be sort of something a little bit
sexier there and this will have to be
something a little bit sexier here as
well right
these will have to be
things that operate on Windows is
fantastic and oh so helpful utf-16 the
world's worst encoding for unicode
characters so it's alright
most of this stuff will just work if you
just use wide characters for it so
that's all fine but the problem is we
need a we need some yeah like this
string length ain't gonna cut it right
so we need to actually look for the end
of the string as well
which actually is pretty easy so we can
just do that like this right so either
we found the end or we didn't and if we
didn't we just you know find it now so I
think we're okay with most of this stuff
then and what I could say as well is
scan is now the end too so I think all
this stuff now just kind of works the
problem is this part right here so we
now have the info platform bit here this
can just be a push copy it can it can
push on the find data see file name what
we do is we take the file name we know
how long it is now we know it's can -
the beginning right so we know that's
how much there is and we just need to
push that on and I think that just works
because it's pointing at the null
terminator so I don't know if well I
guess we need to copy one past that so
so it's that so we still can't do it
even with wide characters that puts the
wide character ring in there we want to
pass the non wide character version to
the game because the game doesn't just
deals with ASCII so we want to pass it
something that's been converted
that is something windows can do for us
where's my search there we go
win32 wide character to ASCII let's see
here where is the actual I just want the
MSDN version please
this is not even remotely what I was
asking for
you know I can't stand MSDN anymore
you used to be good there's a Windows
API call that does exactly this there it
is
thank you God this is the one that I
actually wanted wait what is it talking
about using multibyte too wide Caro I
don't want multibyte to work I want why
I want the opposite thank you
using wide care to multibyte function
correctly can compromise it's really
okay yes I know that thank you
[Music]
this can take counts of each though
right so as long as you pass the right
counts you're fine am I wrong about that
not sure where the actual problem comes
in but this is what we actually want
right so what we want to do is call this
here to get the you know this one gives
us the platform master's name to get the
platform specific name we need to call
this dude right here so we need in this
case we need to figure out we need to
figure out how to package this up we
don't know how you know if if somebody
used some kind of a Unicode file name
here that was encoded in you fiesta
knows why we want but if someone did in
the future we need to have enough space
to store the entire base name right so
we know that the base name size is this
we then need to say well we know that
we've got the base name size but it
might amplify right so we need to leave
enough space that you could take the
16-bit and turn them into 8-bit ones so
I'm just gonna take and assume that it
might take up to 32 bits worth of the
8-bit space to encode a 16-bit when it
actually blows it out for now we don't
really care
it gets truncated because people are
using it like that I could care less
what happens to them so really all we
want to do is make sure that when that
thing converts if it was trying to
convert a legitimate utf-16 name for
some reason that it can do so and so
we'll just go ahead and make sure that
that happens in here so with wide carat
a multibyte what we need to do is we
need to pass the code page the code page
in this case is going to be utf-8 right
that's the one we're going to if that
makes sense
so CP utf-8 is what we want to convert
to the flags I don't think I care yeah
the wide character string is the stuff
we got back and the number of strip of
characters in it right is going to be
that difference like so then what we
have to do is give it the output pointer
which is this thing and then we have to
do this Windows is use of utf-16 is such
a pain in the butt all of this code is
nonsense it's not necessary if they just
use utf-8 which of course they weren't
smart enough to wait for and/or invent I
think the plan nine guys did it and then
they put it into x windows and linux and
stuff like this but windows had gone
like now you do a 16 great idea so
anyway we have the we have all the stuff
there we just need whatever the default
care parameters are here I don't know
what those are baby care kidnappers we
don't care about that so we can just set
those to 0 and M 0 can we say we don't
have to Pat do we have to pass assume
yeah so we can we can just pass the zero
because it's utf-8 which means it it
could should it should be able to
represent everything in the input there
shouldn't be such thing as an
unrepresentable
input when this thing returns it's the
number of the bytes written does it
include the null terminator does not a
null terminate an output string if the
input length is physically specified
without
okay so what we want to do here is we
want to say this thing that we get back
right we want to say we're gonna give
you that much space we're going to
reserve the right to mil terminate this
thing so when you return the value to us
when you return the value to us we're
gonna do it ourselves right so I think
that's everything we need to do to first
give the application a ANSI compatible
well utf-8 name that it can read and
also preserve the wide character version
which is what Windows needs to actually
load the file so we could preserve both
of those two things and then when we go
to load the file in here we will
actually do that that file load like so
so okay so when we go to open the file
here let me just make sure all this
stuff is right we want to get the file
name out of the platform it's gonna be a
wide character file name which is good
for us we open it for reading we see
whether or not we got errors in there so
that the platform can know we don't need
any of this stuff now but probably what
we could do well I guess know that it's
there only know that was anything we
need to do I think we're fine so the
only thing that we're missing now is we
do need a win32 close file sure well
that's called platform file error I
think it was just a typo there probably
cuz we hadn't finished that yet anyway
what we need here is a platform file
close and the platform close call would
need to be able to take the win32 handle
from here and close it so what we want
to do is say all right if
whatever the handle is that comes in and
let's go to the platform section and
actually make this because we don't have
one at the moment so if we have in here
a way to do a platform close file which
now we're going to need the platform
close file is probably just this right
so you pass in the file handle that
you're talking about what we then want
you to close it so what we're gonna do
here is say all right here's the handle
it is exactly oops
that won't work there we go so we want
to sort of look at that piece of data as
if it were a handle and write it in
there right so that's what we're doing
here we want to get it out the same way
so we just want to say that part we want
to interpret as a handle so then we do
if that handle is not equal to invalid
handle value then we will close it if it
is a invalid handle value then you know
we don't have to close it because it
wasn't ever open effectively when we do
our read we need to do the same thing
here so we don't actually need to do any
of this
nonsense here what we actually want to
do is and let me see if there's anything
safe truncate read file yeah I don't
think we care about any of that so what
we want to do here say okay we've got to
win through to handle that comes off of
the source platform piece there we don't
want that yeah and
I think that's it is there anything I'm
missing there yes so there's now a
little bit of a difference here which is
the platform file info is going to come
from the file group like so so we just
move through these and on each one of
these we and you know what we can also
we're going to need that file index as
well so in here we can also assert the
file index is less than the file grib
file count so I mean here what we're
just gonna say is okay you know we're
going through the files we're looking at
each one of them when we get in here
this is that's the one we're gonna want
to load right so again that loop is not
really had to change any which is good I
didn't want to have to file time I don't
know if there's an easy way to cast this
we may have to sort of reassemble it if
we look at the file time yeah why do I
even bother so the file time structure
has the low and high in there so I can
we can do the same thing here just
assemble the 64 bit version of that
right and we've got low date time and
high date time okay what else we got
yeah
so when we do a push size on this thing
this part is now no longer relevant
there that's care star this doesn't
support UMMS apparently so we're gonna
have to go small on that alright so what
else do we have here
win32 open file that just needs to be a
cast went through your handle is
extracted directly there and
looks like mostly we're good I think
that's supposed to be closed file all
right okay uh so yeah now we got to go
look at all that stuff because we made a
ton of assumptions in there and we're
gonna have to actually figure out what's
going on so let's just this is exactly
where we want to be let's step through
all of this stuff and see get get this
stuff going correctly all right cuz it
shouldn't take too long to buggy I don't
think all right so we do a bootstrap
push struct oh no I guess that's fine so
we do a bootstrap push oh let's make
sure that's all right so here's our
memory
it'll allocate a block to store stuff we
could probably make the block smaller
than that but we don't care at the
moment so we're gonna look for HHA files
so there's the wild-card we initiate a
find on that and we say okay first we
got a file we allocate a file info for
it I'm gonna bring that up here so we
can watch it get filled out there are no
other files in it yet so that's not
gonna you know be anything we create a
date we create a size I think that's
right it looks about right for the name
of the HSA file that big intro art pack
1 then we get the base name begin in the
base name and like so
and then we scan it in this case it just
as intro or two Oh hmm okay so I I will
probably have to do this slightly
differently so it looks like when we do
this find I had forgotten how this works
when we do this find the file stem
doesn't get included so this load will
not work this one here right that
actually needs to kind of have it when
you actually open it here it needs to
actually be relative to where is it here
this actually needs to be relative to
the path that it asked for so that's not
gonna work so we got to fix that but
let's see how the rest of this stuff
worked so in here let's see so we did
get the correct information there 9 1 2
3 4 5 6 7 8 9 yep so we say that we need
a big ol buffer just to make sure that
there's room for it we push that in
there we then say hey Windows can you
convert that for us it did so there it
is we also then push the copy of that
onto here I don't know if that actually
pushed the copy on properly or not no so
we go through and we do this whole
little dance and then we we finish up so
then at that point we effectively have
yeah so we produced all that correctly
looks like and then when we return this
thing pretty much just works the problem
I suspect is just right here because now
we come in here and the file name is oh
and I get looks like we don't we didn't
use the whole size of that thing
so I yeah I got to fix that as well but
this is not right because it doesn't
have the path prefix on it so we kind of
need to do that this is a more involved
process than just that if that makes
sense so looking through here what we
need to do is first of all yeah like
this part I don't know why that part
didn't get the whole thing because it
should have
like I don't know why it didn't include
the extension you know what I'm saying
there that seems a bit weird so yeah the
good news is this doesn't have to happen
basically like this is not relevant the
bad news is that the the stem has to be
added on so we basically need something
that's like this right so we need to
specify that the data comes in here it's
just yeah it's really annoying but
that's just how it's gonna have to be
right so basically we need to we need to
push that on to the beginning of the
access pattern in order for this thing
to work
because yeah that's just how that's
gonna go so it's like it just do that
really but um so once you look at what's
gonna have to happen here then what we
need to do when we actually do the push
copy here is we need to do a push copy
of first the actual see file name part
and and we then we also need the stem
right so in here we need a thing that
says however big the stem is and and
yeah and then we need to push the other
part on now the weird part about this is
that the the extension was getting
stripped off of our platform copied
version and I don't know why because it
should have worked
ah yes I know why so this is a bite
length wheat this actually needs to be
like that right so we need to push on
something that is the size whatever that
C filename is that thing's array size
needs to be taken into account I mean
the other way we could do it is like
this right
we cuz these are just have to be wide
cares what we really want to do is just
be able to sort of upend the stem yeah
we you know this is why I say again no
Terminator is just a pain in the butt
you want all these things to just have
their lengths included with them it
makes all of this code so much more easy
to write and less error-prone but you
know if if wishes were horses we'd all
be at the airport so anyway I what we
need to do is is actually write that
part ourselves I guess which is fine so
we need to include the stem size here
and this can't really be a push copy
right we're gonna have to do it
ourselves so you know forget the push
copy think of it this way that's the the
size of the the scan part that's the
size of the final name part so we can
put that here
we can also actually just include the
plus one and that guy and then we need
the stem size once we have that we can
do two copies to put them in there we
don't have a copy array seriously yeah I
guess we don't it's not really true
that's really true all right well no
time like the present so a copy array is
just a count a source and a desk and
then that just calls copy with the count
parameter times the size of the source
right
and you notice i parenthesize those just
in case yes I can do it here as well
just in case there's any kind of
interceding piece of information there
so you know like we don't if this was a
complex expression we wouldn't want it
to accidently only start part of it or
something like that so I just over
parenthesize that just to make sure
anyway so I want to do these two copies
so what I would like to do in this case
is we push the array on here for the
filing size the stem size and we got the
file the the C file name is actually now
just the thing we're copying from so I
want to copy the stem into the info
platform and then I want to copy the
file name into the platform plus the
stem size right so I want to copy the
stem size here I want to copy the C file
name size here and that should should do
it for us so the only thing we actually
need in this case is we need a way to
know how big the stem actually is and I
don't know that there is a function for
that in Windows there probably just 1/2
C runtime library but not in Windows
I don't think and we could make a thing
here that actually just did it
automatically because we know but you
know I'm not going to start down that
road at the moment and so what I want to
do here is say all right there's a stem
size count it that's it
don't ask me why they're 2 equals there
there shouldn't be and off we go all
right so let's see if we've done any
better now so we're gonna jump in here
let's see how big the stem size is and
what the stem is is five characters long
and it says five characters long that's
good we've got our base name now intro
art
HHA we look at the size nine that's
correct because we're stripping off that
part one two three four five so yeah we
know that's right
so now we're going to push on some
storage do the multiply key thing we
kind of know that that part's already
correct and we haven't touched it right
so now the question is can we produce
this thing right first we got to see
what the C filename size is it's 14
characters that's probably correct one
two three four five six seven eight nine
ten eleven twelve thirteen fourteen
well that doesn't have the extension on
it though
so why doesn't that have the extension
on it oh right because you haven't put
the extent up never mind it has the
extension that we haven't put the other
part on it okay and that's fine so then
we allocate 14 plus 5 right so we've got
we've got a 19 character buffer and it's
W Carty so it's wide so it's actually
twice that size and bytes we copy the
stem on so there's that part then we
copy the file name on and then we're
done I think right and 1 2 3 19 for the
null terminator so it's exactly right
size as well so great okay so now we
have in theory produced the correct
thing so that now when we open files we
have that ability let's take a look what
the file name is that's the correct file
name now so no errors is one that's good
and off we go
so hopefully now we can ya figure out
how to do the rest of this stuff it
looks like we have a bug in there though
I'm not sure
Oh was that the bug about the weird like
if you take too long to start up thing
yeah we should probably fix that
oh no that that's not what that was that
is just the that was just that we're
generating too big of a world to think
is that what that was for a single sim
region maybe not I know what that was
look what was that I'm sure what that
was I don't like I don't like that
though looks like it created more stuff
than we have more elements than we have
but anyway it looks like that's loading
correctly now so that part of the system
is now ready to do dynamic loading I
think so that's good
all right
all right let me see about Q&amp;A stuff
here there we go
where all the assets we stored when
they're not reloaded from the peonies
and waves in our HHA files
so PvP I thought s the system allocates
based on headers read from asset files
that means you can replace resources
with dynamic reload but not add new ones
and you can't add tags or missing
something so you did you not hear me
specifically at the beginning load up
that actual file and say exactly that
that we would have to modify it so that
we can put different tags in there or
maybe you forgot that I said that not
sure how we handle the switch between
HSA and the SAS files we are not
switching to loose asset files they will
all be in an hij it's just we will pack
the HHA as files are updated
future reference since you might be
looking at it in the next episodes get
file attributes e^x with the get file X
info standard flag comes out the fastest
of all the ways to get the file size
from the win32 api but we don't care
about getting the file size from the
win32 api we we already get that when we
do fine first file and we have to do
fine for style because we don't know
what the files are right so it just
getting the file size doesn't really
help us will you do my Comp Sci homework
for me and no so I'm at file my time
yeah same thing
so basically getting the final
modification time doesn't really help us
because the only thing that getting the
file modification time does is allow us
to check for a file that we already know
is in the drive but we don't know what
files are on the drive so we're always
gonna have to run the fine first fine
next anyway right and if we have to run
the fine first fine next anyway we might
as well just get the size out of that
because it's already there right we
don't have to make another call if we
all if we already said these are the
only files we'll ever look at then we
could just look at the mat way but do
you intend to allow hot reload of things
like metadata you sort of mentioned it
but it didn't follow from what you're
thinking I well I don't think those will
be stored in external files I think
those will just get written into the HHA
I guess or we'll put them in the C code
I don't know how we'll do it
I'm not sure about that part
which language is better in the game
industry C C++ C sharp well it's really
not a question of better in terms of
usage
it's basically C++ is the language that
is used different places use more or
less of it so some places use it like I
use it where it's kind of just C but you
still compile and C++ and usually use
some of it other places go nuts and use
tons of C++ features that's pretty much
it
period I mean that's what the whole game
industry is built on once you start
looking at scripting code so stuff
that's above the engine layer then unity
games use C sharp and unreal games use
blueprint as a high as like a higher
level arguably maybe more artist
friendly blueprint is are probably more
artists only c-sharp is not that
friendly by comparison I guess
in my system I have a thing that you can
register file name and when it changes a
callback function is invoked then for
every file I have to load I add an entry
in that table do what do you think of
add callbacks I don't really like
callbacks
so I much prefer you know either
messages that go into a queue and then
you can read those at your leisure or
just the app polls for them I mean
basically I prefer queue based behavior
I don't like callbacks I really don't
like inverted control flow I think it
just generally creates problems
if the artist changes the art then the
hots that might change so it could be
tricky yeah I mean it could but it's one
of those things where like we can just
put something in the game that says a
just hot spot and then it resave z-- it
to the HHA so I'm not sure it's a really
big deal that makes sense like I'm not
sure it's really that big of a problem
how often people in chats are just you
rewrite and rust I don't know because I
don't read the chat except when people
ask questions I don't think people have
ever really asked me a question to
rewrite the thing in rest um I guess I
would say anyone who thinks that rust is
like a significant improvement over C++
probably isn't thinking that hard about
it because it's not like it's probably
better than C++ but it's not enough
better that you would ever rewrite
something right I think that's one of
the things that people don't really seem
to understand is that most programming
languages nowadays are just not very
good so when you say like do you want to
rewrite something in this other language
the answer is like always no you know
the only time that makes sense is if you
wrote something in a high-level language
and you need to move it to a lower level
one right like if you wrote your whole
thing in PHP and it's just dog slow then
rewriting it and C makes a lot of sense
because that's the only way you're ever
gonna fix it whereas if you wrote your
whole thing and C and someone says we
should rewrite this in Python the answer
is just no I mean it's it that's never
gonna be an improvement so it these
other languages aren't enough better
someday we'll probably have languages
that are enough better and then
something like rewrite and rust makes
sense because you know we're rust is
some other language rewrite it why don't
you write this in foo bar and foo bar
actually is a great language that's
super powerful and awesome then yeah it
would make sense to rewrite it right now
it's just like yeah it's it's like
putting different kinds of lipstick on
the pig
and asking you you know what you think
of it it's like it's it's just they're
not very good
either completion ports versus asset
loading thread we don't really have much
need for i/o completion ports because we
don't hit the we don't we don't hit the
kind of outstanding i/o kind of
boundaries that would make that useful
you know I hope completion ports have a
lot of problems so I of completion ports
is a very well-designed API if the only
thing you're using is i/o completion
ports as soon as you have to do other
things
io completion for its sort of start to
fall apart right
so I of completion ports don't help you
if you are trying to make a game that
has a bunch of other things that want to
be on the same thread of see how
completion ports they just don't work
and the reason for that I think is that
Microsoft fundamentally speaking you
know they had like six dudes who came
from you know Digital Equipment
Corporation who knew how to make a good
API and they made the base NT thing and
they made that the i/o conclusion ports
then they got you know hundreds more
people working on the operating system
who either came from the old windows
side of things or were newly came on and
they didn't understand completion boards
right so as a result most things don't
work without completion ports so you
can't really use it the way you would
like ideally you would have everything
in Windows come through and now
completion for it and then you would use
it for everything but of course they
didn't do that
little off-topic there has been a lot of
talk about the deprecation of OpenGL and
using a low-level API to talk to GPU my
question is does invidious who to
satisfy this lower level API requirement
for games so you know I haven't really
written anything in CUDA so I can't
speak to that directly my guess is
probably not
I mean Cudas goal is not really to be
that kind of API it's for it it's a
general-purpose computing API originally
it wasn't even really set up to hit
things like a 60 frames a second hard
budget or things like that so by now it
probably could be used for that because
they have been pushing things like real
time rate racers and stuff on there so
they would have had to address all those
problems so I would guess by now it
could be used as the API I don't know
that it's necessarily a good one because
I have not spent much time with it right
uh-huh whee so here's a question that I
haven't had to answer in a long time how
do you ban people in hex chat anyone
know
you know mid blue could probably tell me
blow out there he seems to know the
sorts of things I don't tend to know
them
yeah but I don't know if that actually
works does it no maybe it doesn't mean I
have no idea
forgive me for I did not watch the
entire episode but instead of iterating
over the entire directory could you not
use functions like read directory
changes W and find first change
notification W or will the number of
files be so small and this is for debug
only and not worth it so it's actually a
little bit more complicated than that
unfortunately so the answer is it
depends on how controlled the
environment is that you're planning on
having this work in so the way that we
wrote it it'll always work if that makes
sense
like there's no configuration that that
will fail on to the best of my knowledge
so so like you know if Windows is
running at all this will detect changes
and find new files if you use read
directory changes W and find first
change notification W I my recollection
is that only certain ways of running the
file system actually will produce
correct results I so and I don't
remember what all those circumstances
are so for example I think it only works
on some file systems so I think like
NTFS maybe he's like the only one or so
you know there's something like this I
think it doesn't work when Network
shares correctly maybe sometimes things
like this I don't remember what they all
are I so don't take any don't take and
either I knew those things I said is
being true I'm just giving examples of
things that could be true I don't know
that that really always gives you the
information you need also I don't know
what the polling what the update
frequency is of that either so if you
don't have you know five thousand files
which we don't and I don't think we will
then I believe it just generally
behooves you to do it manually be
cuz you're at less of the mercy of the
operating system and its own particular
opinions if that makes sense so in fact
it may say
so it doesn't really talk about it too
much here I mean they sort of had a list
of like hey if you use these things that
support it NTFS isn't even one of them
so I don't know what that means because
I'm pretty sure it does work on NTFS or
at least in certain circumstances I
thought it did but I don't know so
there's that
[Music]
not suppose there's a channel missus
there
yeah
so I really just yeah I'm sorry I don't
have better information about this I can
just tell you from experience that it's
not as reliable as one would want and
maybe it's the case that nowadays
everything is going to be running on
something that will generally work and
so it would be fine but I can't promise
you that that's true
it would be nice to have a room and chat
on that to be to be honest would it be a
good idea to abstract render push buffer
that we can use Vulcan commando force or
whatever metal has with less memory
copying uh I mean possibly probably not
because we really don't I think probably
what we'll end up doing is something
that produces a buffer that can be used
with either of those anyway for the most
part because once we net once we don't
have to switch textures per quad then
it's just kind of one dispatch anyway we
are code of to be different when coding
for different video cards AMD versus
Nvidia so possibly there might be
special-purpose code for either of those
if we find we need that for performance
purposes otherwise not really
looks like we're all done
all right
Oh Albus why do sometimes MSDN functions
require buffers to be aligned I have no
idea so my assumption would be that they
thought they were gonna get performance
increases or even potentially did get
slight performance creep increases back
at a time when that mattered to them
more you know nowadays their operating
system is so dog slow and everything
that like there's no I mean forget it
right like the chance that the alignment
of a buffer you pass to the win32 api is
gonna make any difference
ever is like zero but you know you have
to remember the fact that as absolutely
as abhorrent as the performance of
Windows 10 is today you know Windows 3.1
or whatever they were trying real hard
to get everything to run as fast as they
could and there was a lot of work spent
optimizing things and getting them to
run at all because the hardware was
pretty primitive back then and you had
to do a lot of stuff just to make a
multi Windows operating system run at
any kind of reasonable rate so you know
there's sort of an overhang of some of
that and so you know some of it might be
that you're looking at today and also
knowing that Intel chips don't care that
much about alignment anymore you have to
understand that like priorities change
and so the fact that it looks laughable
today does not mean that it wasn't
perhaps a reasonable thing at the time
you know who knows
so
alright alright thanks everyone for
joining me for the Upstate a handmade
hero it's been a pleasure coding with
you as always if you would like to
follow along with the series at home you
can always go to handmade hero org and
pre-order the game it comes with a
source code so you can follow along I
will be back here next week and in
theory the tweet bot is working
correctly also the watch this thing
should in theory be working correctly as
well
of course it's got the stupid twitch
advertisements in it if you sign up for
twitch prime it won't have
advertisements on it I guess I'm not
sure if there's any other way to get
around that but the watch window the
watch button also has the schedule on it
when the stream isn't live so you can
always go there and take a look to see
when our upcoming streams are gonna be
and I try to keep that schedule pretty
updated now so it should always be up to
date with when the next live stream will
be along with a countdown so in case you
don't know what Pacific Daylight Time is
because you don't live anywhere near the
west coast of the US you can just look
at the countdown timer and know it's
gonna be 13 hours from now or 7 days and
13 hours from now or anything else like
that it should be pretty easy for people
to to check so that's about it next week
we will start the process of trying to
move PNG files in through some kind of a
runtime pipeline that goes into the hhha
files so they can be used because now we
have the ability to iterate over them
and do check something testing if
they've changed that sort of stuff so we
now have to put that part in place now
at the platform layer sports it so we'll
go ahead and do that that'll take a
couple days for sure so that'll be next
weekend's job and probably the weekend
after that and then hopefully at that
point we'll have something that we can
do real-time art integration with we can
hand that off to ana to give us art
assets for the game so that'll be good
until then have fun programming everyone
and I'll see you on the Internet
take it easy everybody