start recurring hello everyone and
welcome to handmade here are the show we
could complete game live on stream we
are well you know we're at an
interesting place because we've been
doing some animation code and we're
gonna have to start making some hard
decisions about how we're gonna do some
not not hard code decisions but hard
like essentially aesthetic decisions
which is not really our job because
we're the game programmer not the
designer and not the artist but what are
you gonna do in a situation where you're
doing a game mostly on your own as we do
on animate here oh here you don't really
have the ability to say hey someone else
should tell me so we have to make some
decisions and we'll go ahead and make
those decisions today or at least our
first pass at them this is day 276 so if
you would like to follow along at home
you're gonna want to unpack day 275
source code let's jump in here and take
a little bit of a look at where we where
we were so I'm going to open up for read
here
and I'm gonna open up my handmade
project and then I am going to run it
and show you what the problem is that we
will need to solve it's a little bit of
a tricky problem alright so here is our
little handmade hero fellow and he's
working actually kind of really great in
terms of what I actually wanted to see
happen in the game and as I've explained
before the game design calls for the
fact that the essentially the head moves
separately from the body the body is
always on a square and the head can move
around freely and that's what we've
implemented here you can kind of see it
happening and so actually everything is
is totally fine
I'm totally happy with exactly what
we've got going on here except for the
fact that if you look at what ends up
happening if we just do a standard sort
of like a blind stretch of the body to
reach the head and we haven't accounted
for the bobbing yet so we have to
stretch it even a little more you can
see that it kind of comes separated so
we have to stretch the head out even
more than I mean stretch the body out
even more than we're currently
stretching it
basically what I'm concerned about is
just the fact that that is I don't know
if I'm gonna be able to make that look
good enough I mean certainly like you
can see when we're moving straight up
and down here it's a little bit of a
problem and so the question is just can
we make this look good enough now
there's a few things that I think will
help one is that the final artwork which
we will probably start switching to at
some point here is more top-down than
this is so we're maybe potentially I
don't know but we're maybe in the worst
case for what I want to do here because
the hero is sort of drawn straight up
and down and I told young-shin for the
final versions of everything that we're
doing is that that we're gonna be more
top-down we're not going to be
completely top-down so it won't just be
a head but like a top of a head that
you're seeing but we're gonna be more
top-down right and so what that means is
that you know contrary to the way that
it looks on the screen now I'll draw out
quickly here you know right now we've
got a sort of a situation looks like
this so obviously any motion of the head
needs to have a corresponding motion of
the neck because otherwise you're gonna
end up with it detaching obviously in a
situation where it looks a little bit
more like this where you know it's sort
of more this way so you've kind of got a
top-down where the the the body and I'm
not drawing a very good job drawing this
but you know something more like this so
it's a lot more top-down in the top of
the head you know is here whatever maybe
I'll draw the nose in so it's like this
kind of a thing right in that sense that
the head can move around a lot more
without appearing to be that the two
bowels appear to be detached in the body
because the body is actually right it's
like a thing that looks like this and
the head is like quite a bit over it so
it can move around and not maybe look as
bad especially not in our sort of iconic
art style right we're not trying to
render something that looks real
we've got a sort of cartoony playful
style so you know people are
expecting it to even a thought Call of
Duty the head doesn't have to attach to
the body in a anatomically correct way
or anything like this so I think it's
not quite as bad as it appears here but
it still is a little bit of a problem
like I think even after that we're still
gonna have situations where you know we
just have issues with how the body ends
up being you know in like in situations
like this if we want to still remain
connected I think we're gonna have to
work on
we can't just sheer it arbitrarily and
expect that to be you know a viable
solution so I think what we want to do
now is kind of see if we can play with
these routines and like I said figure
out a way to make it so that in
situations where it's you know it's iffy
like that you know when I'm right on the
line there like that situation there see
what we can do to kind of make it
we got a I want to know by the way why
we don't have any collision happening on
the on that on this wall because you
ever notice like if you collide with
these you actually hit them but if you
collide with the sides you don't I don't
know why that is
I literally have no idea I'm sure it's a
very simple explanation but since we
never looked at it right like I can't I
cannot go past these trees up or down
but I can go past the ones on the left
and the right which I have like no
reason I don't know why at all and so
it's kind of crazy so anyway but that's
okay that's not what we're looking at
now anyway and we did eliminate the
collision detection for our guys in a
couple ways so you know maybe it makes
sense I don't know does not matter to me
point being it may be that we're not
doing collision detection at all and we
we're doing some kind of weird look up
with points we'll get to that when we
get to it
point being that's what we kind of want
to do today so I want to just get that
see what we can do to to minimize that a
little bit and then when we put the
final artwork in there we can hope that
that'll if anything just make things a
little bit better and we won't have to
worry too much about anything beyond
that so let's start with let's start
with a few things here so what I'd like
to do first is I'd like to move the head
down
I think the head at the moment is too
high because it doesn't need to be up
like that I'd like it to be like lower
down anyway and I think that will
approximate more what we have in our in
in the artwork that's coming later right
I think that'll be a little closer to
that and the other thing we should
probably do that we haven't done yet as
well is it would it might be nice to
more closely approximate sort of the way
these things will be constructed later
with by actually having them be
displaced rather than having them cut
out in the artwork but that may it may
be premature to do that so maybe we'll
leave that for now anyway so if I wanted
to move the head down a little bit what
I can do is I can just offset it when I
draw it I can offset it down a little
bit just to see what's happening in the
code there so I'm gonna go into world
mode here and when I draw a hero head
which is in here I can just sort of
arbitrarily decide to move it in why a
little bit further down so you can see
in here I guess we've got this push-fit
map i believe this v3 here is sort of my
ability to displace things so if I
wanted to I could go ahead and displace
it downward and I guess I can also you
know since we are working on animation I
can take the the Liberty here of abusing
the lot of code editing so I can just go
ahead and take a look at it edit on here
alright so first things first like if I
draw this thing displaced I need a way
of making sure that the head shows up on
top of of the other stuff right and the
problem that we have right now is that
the only reason that things aren't
sorting properly just automatically is
because of the again the fact that we we
don't have our artists that's really
prop processed properly these are still
assets oops these are still assets that
are exactly the way they were when we
first started building the game and
really didn't do any sort of testing or
any due diligence with how
we wanted the pact they're still
essentially like this sort of thing
right that's what the assets look like
so even though if our head actually was
up here and here was the actual point
position point for the head that would
just totally work because it would sort
properly as compared to this potentially
you know or we at least be in a position
to make sure it's sorted properly right
now we don't have a lot of options for
doing that because unfortunately we've
got this situation where the the bottom
of these is is actual where it is so we
don't actually know where these things
actually are now what we do know is that
we can still control the sorting with
sort of hack so at the moment we should
be able to come for something clear and
the other thing is I feel like we may
have some kind of a bug in what we're
doing right now because possibly
involving like Z or who knows what but
if we take a look at what's going on
with the head if we are to move the head
downwards then if we move it downwards
an actual lie you would expect it to
sort in front of this because we're we
sort Y as it gets closer to the screen
is how it should go
right and I'll just double check that
but you know if I go into render group
and I look at entity basis P when we
come down here and take a look at what
happens to Y you can see that we
subtract whatever the transformed Y is
from our sorting information right and
so what we would expect to see in that
case is that as that Y comes down those
should be lower sorting values and hence
sort closer to the screen unless I've
forgotten and we actually saw it the
other way I don't actually remember but
I'm pretty sure we sort with things
being less and in fact you can kind of
see that we sort with things being less
because here with our oh wait a minute
maybe we don't actually I think this is
just maybe we just have this busted here
it looks like we're sorting yeah this is
just this is just wrong right
no no is it's correct it's correct
because we're subtracting why and as you
go lower on the screen your Y will
decrease right because Y is positive
going upwards at the moment so as you go
lower on the screen you'll subtract
which will increase that value right and
so I would assume that we would always
see that something that we move lower on
the screen should sort in front of
things that we have not moved lower on
the screen so what I'd like to do now is
just go wait a minute sanity check here
why are these things drawing in the
opposite order let's look at what their
sort key actually is and that way we can
just make sure that nothing particularly
unusual is going on because it seems
like there's a bug there or at least
like maybe a misunderstanding and how
the call is happening and looking at it
here I guess I could double check to you
know you can kind of see you can kind of
see in here how things are getting
called as well so anyway we'll just
we'll just make a breakpoint and I'll
make a breakpoint at each of these
things so we can take a look at what all
of their sort keys actually are and I
guess we'll just look at the cape and
the head for now so here is that push
bit map call for the head and somebody
told me that I could step into there to
step into specific I never knew this was
there by the way I don't know when they
added that but I did not know it was
there it's pretty handy I even set it on
the debugging phim I was like I wish
they had some like that but they do you
just can't apparently get it from the
keyboard or something but you can get it
with the mouse so I come in to push
bitmap and I'm gonna thunk through to
another call now that I I know that I've
gotten an actual bitmap and that's going
to call through and generate one of
these sort keys right so presumably when
I come through here
my entry will now have a sort key that
it can that can be used with it or
actually I guess I that gets stored in
the other things so I'm gonna have to
look in
the dim that comes back for it right
should be in here so there's the sort
key this is the sort key for the head so
there's this four thousand ninety five
point three two zero zero seven that is
the sort key for the head and let's go
ahead and run forward to the sort key
for the body and see what that is
oops forgot to do my step into specific
come here there it is
so inside here I'm just going to do the
same thing follow the push bit map call
through until we actually have a valid
entry and then I'm just gonna look at
what its doom is so there's it's sort
key and this is the sort key for the
body so it's pretty clear that the sort
keys for these two things are different
by a dramatic amount so that's not a
wise sorting issue that's going to be a
Z sorting issue and so what you can see
if you take a look here in the in the
render group calls is that the 4096 is
based on the Z situation so you've got
the object transform upright thing going
on and you've got the original P Z stuff
you've got all of these things happening
here and that's that's doing that
sorting now I guess my first question is
who actually is setting the upright
stuff and or is it getting set for both
of these because I don't actually know
if it is or if it isn't in the object
transform so I'm going to take a look to
just see who gets set to upright and who
doesn't because I don't actually know so
we've got a default upright transform
that's getting set here for the objects
edit eat transform and then I don't know
if it ever gets unset let's see
push bitmap so so everyone is going to
have that everyone's going to have that
set so I assume it can't be that we
could double check we then have the
original PZ and the PZ right the PZ is
the transform Z so let me just take a
quick look and follow that through just
to make sure we have a handle on
so we don't use the original Z in here
anywhere we have the objects transform
offset P and I don't actually know why
we don't include the Z in there but we
don't so we don't have the Z in there
but we do have the object transforms
offset Z whatever that is that does come
in here and then we've got the original
PZ so we use both of those Z's we use
the transform Z and we use the the Z
that comes in both of those things are
added together to produce the final Z so
my first question would just be is there
actually a Z value getting passed here
and it looks like actually there is in
fact there it is so it looks like all we
did is we actually put in a Z value that
that we're actually using here I don't
want that to happen right that is not a
good thing and so that was how we were I
guess that was just because I hacked
that in to sort the cape on top which
again is not really something we
probably should have been doing but
there you go and so as you can see how
the Cape the the on top s of the Cape
there is like is a problem right so what
I can do there is I can address this
slightly differently I suppose I can
make it so that the torso is always
slightly up in Y or rather the Cape is
slightly up in wire the torso is
slightly down and Y I can try to do
something like that again a little bit
of a hack but it's it's less of a hack
we're probably gonna have to confront
the Z sorting stuff at some point here
because again it's gotten a little bit
out of control and we're gonna need
something a little bit better than what
we have so let's take a look here what I
could what I could do so if I was to
displace it downward oh wait that's
gonna do the opposite sorry if I was to
just place it upward I think we still
have a problem of when yeah you can kind
of see that when we get bobbing action
happening we're still going to
occasionally be in there so again we
really kind of need some way of just
because it's 2d and we have to hack
these things we need to clean up that Z
a little bit because we've had
consistent problems where we just don't
have
a handle on where all the Z values are
going to be exactly so we don't have a
great way of knowing like this is how
we're hacking this or this is how we're
actually sorting this and that thing so
we have one more pass to do over that to
actually nail things down I think
because it's very frustrating to not
have that solid it's one of the things
that's really annoying about programming
on stream is because there's such a
limited time I never have those times
that I can just spend eight hours going
through things and like working them out
which are pretty crucial sometimes
you're kind of always in the state of
well we never quite got to the end of
that because it would take too much to
actually do but you know that's just
that's just something you got to live
with the nature Avant's of doing
programming in this fashion so anyway
you know that's a little bit of a
problem there there is probably more we
could do about it we could also say that
we are gonna pesum eyes the torso
instead right we could say that that's
going to have some very slight Z offset
and that's another way that we could go
about that and if we just make that be
some kind of ludicrously small value
then it would always stay sort of behind
I think and that's probably fine right
so that's probably something we can do
for now but again like I think we want
to clean those ease up so here's you
know me walking around and I can also do
that for the Cape so that it never
appears above the head you know I could
say like I want these to be at very
small Z offsets relative to each other
and then you know they're kind of
wouldn't have that sorting problem so at
you know here's here's the dude hopping
around I feel like there's probably
going to be a problem here where this is
gonna be wrong but yeah well no it looks
yes you'd like right there
see how that's wrong that's the
consequence of doing that which is why I
say we'd have to do we're gonna have to
do it correctly when we sort of get get
down to it but anyway so the problem at
the moment that I want to address now
that we've sort of been able to shrink
the guy down a little bit compared to
where you would be and I can do that
even a little bit more I think I want
him to be shrunk leaving a little
than that because like I said I wanted
to be pretty compact because it's gonna
be more of a top-down sort of a thing
there we go and I think that the Cape
also will be a little bit like that as
well I think the Cape will also be kind
of down further so I think this is a
little more representative of what it
will look like you know what I'm saying
so as we're hopping along here I think
what I want to do is just really limit
the degree to which I do that shear so
this shear will not be as exaggerated as
it is because now it doesn't have to to
avoid that offset and then again the
part of the art the final art assets
will job will be to make sure that that
is an okay looking thing to have it sort
of nicely compact like that from a more
top-down perspective so if we wanted to
do that all I really need to do here is
go into where we're actually computing
that sort of displacement code and try
to limit what's actually happening now
you can see here and in fact I guess
I'll go ahead and maybe record a loop
here of him doing some particularly bad
stuff so I feel like going around like
this is a pretty good example of that so
we'll just go ahead and do a loop of him
sort of coming around like that and so
there you can kind of see some really
it's really bad you know the really bad
case is there so as that's looping
around and it's gonna take a look at
what happens if first of all I'm gonna
just go ahead and I'm gonna go ahead and
turn off the shear entirely so that's
what it would look like if we weren't
shearing and you can see that obviously
we do get quite a bit of separation
there so there's that and so there's one
of the things we can do is make it so
that hop baby follows the head more
quickly or something like that you know
we can we can certainly do some things
there to potentially help ourselves but
what I'm gonna do here is see what I can
get away with in terms of shear before
we look bad right
so like that probably doesn't look bad
enough to be too concerned about like
I'm okay with that amount of shearing on
the thing that doesn't seem to be too
bad to me and similarly the other thing
we could do is we could consider
sort of normalizing some of this a
little bit more so it was more of a
rotation and less of a shear in certain
circumstances as well and I'm not sure
whether you know to what degree I want
that or not but point being that's a
little bit more so now the question is
could I make it so that it doesn't
detach as much in the first place you
know maybe it follows the head along a
little bit more more quickly and so I'm
going to take a look at that so in this
case when I've got the when I decide
that I need to hop to the next square
you know I'm going to go into into the
this hopping code here and I guess I
guess there is a little bit of a delay
on the jump which is probably okay but
what I want to do is I just want to I
want to see what happens if I increase
this back up to a really instantaneous
hop which isn't great but so you can see
we still have some problems with
separation there I'm gonna also you know
what I'm gonna do - I'm gonna go into
the config I'm going to slow this down
so we can see it better so I'm gonna
slow it down to a quarter speed so now
we can really see up I always forget
when we do a quarter speed we're not
playing back the input at a quarter
speed so loops don't work that's okay
I'll I'll just do my own real loop
basically so here we go looping
so there's the loop and you can kind of
see that the problem is that you know
even right off the bat there I sort of
get into the situation where you know
just stretching the head around by
itself doesn't really attach to the head
as you would expect because I'm only
going ten percent of the way there and
so I guess you know and the other thing
too is I kind of need that stretch to
happen so maybe that going down is just
not gonna work and you know that sort of
the jumping the springiness thing is not
really gonna be useful and I don't know
to what extent I can really change that
but let's play around with it a little
bit and see what I can do to mitigate at
least to a certain amount that sort of
that sort of bumped that downward
bobbing right so let's say that let's
say for instance that I was to get rid
of that downward motion of the head so
now as I stretch out I'm gonna see how
close I am typically to to the head and
it's not bad
so here's a question I've got my
movement the other thing that might be
kind of bad here is when I'm doing a
movement to hop
I never update it after the hop begins
and maybe what I would like to do is is
be able to change movement to at any
time right so that that might be that
might be a good thing to do as well
which would be difficult it could create
very odd behavior yeah I don't really
think I don't know I don't think I can
really do that to be honest with you I
think that's that's probably too much of
a problem I wish I could I don't think I
can
mm-hmm so I guess the other thing too is
what if the hero was bigger right like
in here you know I'm I'm passing the
let's go here I've got here Oh sighs see
and hear us I see well you know I'm
gonna put that out here and here a sigh
see does control how big the Kuro is and
so when if the hero was closer to the
size of one of the squares right like
what if the hero was big like so that's
because that creates even less of a
problem right because the bigger the
hero is the more the more room that body
takes up you know in terms of the space
of the square similarly like if you look
at yeah if you look at now how how far
are you is let me let me break out of
the loop here there we go similarly if
you look at how he's constructed now I
could move them even further down and
again the art could work there so if I
come into the hero head here and I just
continue to push that here a head down
right like so
now we're now we're getting somewhere
right now we are getting somewhere and
and that's a good thing so I'm gonna see
if I what happens if I increase now that
head Delta amount twice what it was in
terms of how much I'm allowing it to
shear and also I'm gonna let it do its
I'm gonna let it do its bouncy thing as
well
so this is getting much better right
that's getting much better and again
we've got a bunch of things that you
know it's hard to tell without having
the actual art in there but that's
starting to not be so concerning to me
right because if this was a fatter sort
of wider you know if that's more what
the hero looks like art wise then you
know most of these are starting to look
okay and you have to imagine the
perspective is different right so it
would look better than it looks right
now so I'll go ahead and I'm gonna take
off the the time step here
I think this will be okay I think what
we will want to do potentially because
there's some squirrel eNOS when I'm
moving right if I'm moving diagonally
and I happen to get well
besides that if we don't find a thing to
stand on why are we even we should just
that case shouldn't even be happening
why am I even letting that happen right
because if I don't find one of the one
of the new locations right if the
closest traversable isn't actually a
thing then we shouldn't actually allow
the player to go any further like that
should just stop them so you know in
this case people ii ii found or
something i should say if you know found
and right
because you shouldn't ever get to it
something that's not reversible and so
I'm interested to know like how do I
actually get there something bad is
happening but I'm not sure what oh you
know what I know what's happening what's
happening is the camera is transitioning
and we're storing these as raw positions
which we can't do right
where do we store like our P and our DP
these are our totally bogus in that
sense right
like we can't store we can't store
things like movement from and movement
to because they'll change at when the
camera moves if that makes sense so
that's why that's actually the problem
so that'll get fixed actually I suppose
we'll fix that when we update the entity
stuff so I guess I'm less concerned
about that now so anyway yeah I think
this is reasonable but like I said the
problem with that the diagonals where it
kind of does that hop between the two of
them sort of a thing I'm not sure how I
feel about that one way we could do this
is just not allow diagonal motion like
we could say that diagonal motion is not
something you're actually allowed to do
in this game and I'm not sure how I feel
about that I don't know if I if I think
that gives something up I know that
you're only allowed to attack in the
four cardinal directions again this is
very much like Zelda or Binding of Isaac
and now that I think about it in Zelda
in body of Isaac you can definitely move
diagonally but in Zelda you cannot am i
right like you are not allowed to move
diagonally upwards in Legend of Zelda so
it's possible that I could just say you
can't do that which you know I don't
necessarily want to do strictly from
because I'm not sure that how to make
the artwork well but it would be
potentially useful from a game design
standpoint to say that the motion is
always rectilinear given that it's
important that we have this tile based
sort of motion right so yeah like
hmm so yes so what would that feel like
let me just see what that would feel
like because that will at least give me
something to go on in terms of whether I
like that idea as a you know I
if it feels immediately wrong to me then
I would know that that should just be
discounted you know that's not gonna be
a thing but yeah so basically what we'd
say is you know in here we're checking
to see whether or not buttons are down
and if the buttons are down we set these
movement values and so what I'm gonna do
instead I think is look at the half
transition counts and say you know and
the half transition count is is
something that way will will will sort
of leave it as something that's repeated
so we won't clear that we won't clear
the con hero oops
we won't clear the con hero DDP will let
that be set and that DDP will be set
only when the controller move up code
half transition count is greater than
one so only when you've actually pushed
it will we go and set it if that makes
sense
and is that do we already have that is
that just went down button went down I
feel like we had a thing for this
particular case I'm gonna go ahead and
expand this window out so we can see a
little more code I feel like we had a
case for this somewhere in here
maybe is down I feel like there were
some button things but where they are
now nobody knows hmm yeah I thought we
just had some utility functions but
again one of the things that suffers
with brief programming times they don't
have a lot of time to organize things
all that much so I feel like we do have
some sort of button pushing stuff in
here that's you know it was pretty
primitive but I thought we had some
stuff about half transition counts there
it is
was pressed that's what I wanted so I
just want to was press for each of these
so yeah this is way down I believe this
is was pressed was pressed so when we're
pressed we're gonna do this but what I'm
gonna do in addition to this is I'm
going to clear out the X or rather
whatever the corresponding other pair
was I'm gonna clear it so this way
you're only allowed to move in one
direction or will along one axis at a
time if that makes sense
and the other axis will just get zeroed
will get cleared out yeah I guess the
other thing that I have to do is I got
to make it so there's some way that you
can get it so that nothing is down so
basically like if you release everything
so if not and do we have it is down
apparently we don't it's just that so I
suppose it's kind of stupid to even have
but what do you do so in the case where
we don't have anything happening we
clear it so now I can only do one
direction of motion
well to be honest it really doesn't feel
like a too much of a problem and you
know what I should also do that's not
quite the right controller code what I
really want to say is that if neither of
the controllers are down for one of the
axes you clear it right not the fat
really matters all that much
so if move up or move down as are both
off same here
so I feel like that wouldn't be a
problem I'm not sure exactly how I feel
about it yet like I don't know that it's
exactly what I want but it's certainly
not bad and I guess it's closer to the
Zelda ish style of the original Zelda
which was the game that I was interested
in sort of exploring because in that
game if I remember correctly you could
not move in arbitrary you could not move
diagonally you could only move up and
down
all right I'm relatively happy with that
I'm relatively happy with that
all right so I have a little bit more
time left because we didn't start till
really really late I believe so
so it's probably still about 10 to 20
minutes left so the other thing that I
want to do here right is I feel like so
I feel like most of this will take care
of itself when the art when when newer
art is pushed in so I feel like that'll
be okay and yeah so I'm relatively happy
with that I don't I don't think I need
to worry too much more about that I'll
we'll worry about it more when when we
have the final art in there I think
that's probably okay and so what I want
to do now is I want to put it in I want
to maybe make the detection a little bit
better for what's going on keyboard wise
we see to occasionally get some things
where you're kind of in between - I
wonder if I I wonder to what degree I
want to again suck you into the lane if
that makes sense I had it in there so
that you would you that you would get
sucked into the lane but
but I never quite felt right and I don't
know to what degree I want to do that to
keep you from being in between to write
and I don't know I don't know what I
want to do about that it didn't seem
that like a good idea when I tried it
before one thing I do want to do is
right now if you push down both buttons
and then let go of one of them only if
you keep held down the second one you
push will you keep moving so I feel like
that's not a great solution to how to do
that input anyway so I'd rather make
that a little closer to what the final
thing would be if we were gonna go with
this which is that if you do push to
down then you let go of one it should
really just be whichever one got pushed
down last is the is the direction you go
but if you let go of one and you're
still pushing down in another then it
will pick that one up right so I think
what we want to do here is something
like okay when something gets pressed it
takes precedence and that's sort of what
we're doing here but if you were to make
it so that so that something went went
all the way off right but there might
have been a different button that is
down I think I want to do something more
like this where I say like okay in the
in the case where we released all the
ups is there something down that's not
you know that's that's in the Y right so
like I'm sorry I released left or right
and so we're not moving after anymore is
one of the other directions held down
for example if move up is being held
down then let's do that and similarly if
if moved down is there let's put that
back in right and I'll do the exact same
thing over here so if you release the up
or down motion and there happens to
still be a left or right motion
happening
let's reap it that up
yeah so now that's working okay - and
that's kind of nice that's important
because otherwise it would not have
worked
- just tap the up button like in that
sense and leave the right button held
down and I want to make sure that works
so let's take a look at and I'll just
now that I've sort of re-centered on
that a little bit let's just take a
double check to see what's going on here
I'm gonna re I'm gonna switch this
around right we had put in the code for
doing that sort of sucking you back in
and I'll just see if maybe now that
makes any more sense than it used to
well
I mean it feels fine when you're close
the problem is when you're right in the
middle and you kind of end up going
diagonally it just feels a little weird
maybe I could set it on a timer you know
like when we're moving sort of when
we're when we're doing this sort of
thing right what we could do there is
say like well
you know if this is named improperly by
the way this is actually if no push
right there is any pushers so that's
actually not any push it's no push so if
we look at what's happening here one of
the things that I'm just thinking is
like hey what if I only apply the Riesz
entering after a certain amount of time
so for example in the case where we're
in a no push scenario so like we're
doing you know we're doing we know we're
not doing no push right so I'd say like
okay if if it's no push definitely do it
or if like the timer is up and the
square right and then I could introduce
a thing where it's like I don't start
sucking you back in until a certain time
er collapses or something so like timer
is up you know equals you know whatever
the entity the energy like recenter
timer or something is greater than or is
equal to zero right
so I can do something like that and then
every time through here when I'm doing
these controls I could do something like
okay whatever the entities recenter
timer is I'm going to take that vCenter
timer and I'm going to subtract from it
whatever the DT is and I want to do a
clamp here like I want to do like a
clamp 2 to 0 or a clamp clamp above 0 or
something like that where I have this
recenter timer and I want to take that
recenter timer and I want to subtract
whatever the DT is right so whatever the
time is it's going to count down and I
want to make a math function in the
clamps so if that clamp 0 1 and all
right I got this sort of stuff here and
I just want to do a thing that's gonna
auto plant for me so I'm just going to
do a clamp above 0
here's my value and the result is just
going to equal to the value if the value
is less than zero that's going to be
zero otherwise it's going to do the
value so all it's doing is making sure
it doesn't go below zero so that's like
a little clamped update there so we'll
do a clamp above zero off we go
we need in the sim region we need to
have one of these little doodads right
so let's see here that can just be the
central timer and this receptor timer
will be zero normally so if I just do it
without making a changes here then what
I should do is I should always have the
resent ring happen and I can feel it
happening you know it's it's definitely
happening now and but then what I can do
is I can make it so that anytime I push
down one of these buttons so anytime I
get one of these these edge triggers
essentially I can go ahead and say take
whatever the hero is in this case and to
actually have the entity do I know what
the entity actually is don't have the
entity in here I want the env in here oh
you know what I guess that probably
should just be in here now think about
it because this is where the actual
timer is but it's fine I'm going to set
the vCenter timer to whatever the
recenter amount is so basically I'm it's
gonna have a timer that counts down so
that when you move you'll get a reprieve
from the resent ring for a like a half a
second or something we don't know what
that value is going to be and then the
con hero controlled zero I know where
that is that in the world mode
there's that in handmade it's in
handmade so yeah inside handmade I'm
just gonna have that recenter timer is
gonna be in here so I'm not gonna put it
in the sim region because I guess it's
really a property of the control not of
it of the entity per se so we'll put the
entity entities recenter timer in here
like so and we'll test it in here so
yeah
moving on let's run that guy and so now
you kind of get that floatiness and it
kind of it sucks it back in sort of
later so you can see it doing its thing
right and I don't know how I feel about
it let's let's play with it a little I'm
gonna up the coefficient so that it
sucks in relatively quickly so basically
your hop along and it just kind of sucks
you over
and that feels even worse I will loosen
it up a bit try it with a really faint
one
so with it that faint I don't really
notice it so if nothing else I suppose
that's probably good in the sense that
it slowly restores you over time without
it being too noticeable so maybe we can
leave that one in at least for now all
right
so you can still kind of get a few
outside edge cases where you hop along
in weird ways but I still think they're
probably gonna be okay because most of
the time the player is going to want to
control what squares they're stepping on
anyway so they don't really have an
incentive to move wildly differently
from the lines anyway if that makes
sense most of the time like they don't
really want to put themselves in a
position where it's unclear what they're
gonna be stepping on so it's not like
they're gonna be going out of their way
to try that mmm in a normal playthrough
anyway at least I don't think but you
know you never really know yeah all
right so let's uh let's leave it there
for now we'll go to the Q&amp;A
do you think like a sort of rhythmic
based movement where the hero would have
to wait a bit before being able to move
again let's say he's getting ready for a
jump instead of stamina lessly jumping
around non-stop could perhaps help in
this situation realize it's a design
decision it might not be what you're
looking for perhaps you have entertained
the idea I think it yeah it wouldn't be
particularly useful in the way this game
works necessarily that certainly would
be a reasonable thing to do if if that
wasn't you know gonna conflict with
other parts in the design but I don't
feel like that would really be the feel
you want in this game you really want to
you know to move when you move I think
do you think rotating the torso would
help you no not really and the reason
for that at the moment is that like if I
go and look at what the bad cases are
they don't tend to be ones where I'm
moving sideways where rotation would
make sense they seem to be ones where
I'm moving up and down is really the bad
parts right so I feel like mostly what
we're gonna want to do is just make sure
the art is from a more top-down
perspective and then just try to
minimize the degree to which we share it
like right there you know you can kind
of see you see how it gets really far
behind like that and so that that I
think is mostly the problem for the
Kuban and you have the hero walk around
on a live loop yes I can
Shawn McGrath says try wrapping the body
around bezzie a rather than just linear
stretching um I mean I don't think you
know if the problem was just that we
want we want to let's just stretch out
his neck and not the body or something
that I could see that maybe be any case
but I don't in this case we don't really
have a part that's like good to stretch
but another part that's not so the
Bezier I don't know that would really do
much for us
for the for the up-down motion couldn't
you forego the stretch and have a jump
of each part I don't know what that
means
beer chug why wouldn't you shear the top
of the feet to stay under the moving
body the top of the feet first of all
there are no feet because this is a
limbless character so I'm not sure doing
my feet if you mean the bottom of the
torso well they've got to be planted
where they were right so I'm not sure
what you mean by shear them to stay
under the body commandercool what about
a small transition of the body before
and after the jump say 10 to 20 percent
of the distance between Jason dots I
that's an interesting idea
that's an interesting idea I don't know
about that I don't want it to feel non
grounded but you know there might be
some value that's small enough that it
helps but not big enough that it feels
ungrounded so we could certainly try it
if we took a displacement if we just had
a displacement in here that could work
so let me see that's the hero head let's
see if we had we would test this so if
we were standing on the ground then
we've got the head Delta which is here
and I could just multiply I could make a
displacement based on the head Delta so
I could do something like entity P
equals
hmm I guess what I could say is like
there's there's an easy way to do this
just adds a thing I don't want everyone
to do it right now so I'm just going to
I was going to try to hack it so if I
was in here I could say well if I you
know if I didn't find a place to jump to
then we'll just say that enemy P equals
you know whatever the closest P was plus
you know some coefficient times the head
Delta right
seems like it's doing something a little
bit weird compared to what I would have
expected it's doing an extra bounce
which I'm not sure why it would its head
Delta going in some weird direction that
I don't anticipate let me stop the loop
ah you know what the problem is with
changing that is it will change the way
that we were doing the jump Delta yeah
so this this body distance thing why are
we doing it that way I don't actually
know why we were doing it that way it
seems like a weird way to do it but
anyway I'll go ahead and do the actual
way just to see cuz I am curious about
that it's an interesting idea that you
had There so let's double check it so
here in the sim region if I just do some
random thing that's just a cloth floor
displace for now if I come in here and
say like there right so you know the
entity floor displace would not would
get reset here of course there's a
there's a discontinuity so we'd have to
well I guess you know what I know how I
can fix that
so in here we'll just say okay the
entity floor displace is just going to
be some percentage of the head Delta as
you move the head around if we're not in
that mode or really probably at any time
the floor displacement will always decay
downward so we'll just say that the
floor displacement you know whatever
they are will always do a clamp above 0
or will we'd clamp how would we do this
I guess I I have to always just decay
them in the opposite direction so yeah
this is one of those things that we
would not want to do the way that I'm
about to do it
but if we wanted to just to displace it
back to zero then I would do something
like I guess you know what I'll just
leave it for now we'll just say that
this is always going to be the case so
it's always gonna be that the floor
displace is set to that and then when we
go to actually draw this this dude here
right oops
euro body when we actually draw the sky
and we're passing in the transform here
I'm gonna want to give it an offset so
we'll just say the offset is the end of
these floor displace and then in here
whenever we're doing this we'll just say
like okay it's actually there's an
actual offset now
yeah so that's oh right
I always forget this - we do have a
convenient way of doing this we can just
say we want the XY of that so in theory
that would do it so you can kind of see
it happening there right and that I
don't know if that actually helps enough
but it's not that noticeable now could
we crank it up I don't know
it seems possible that maybe we could
apply the floor displacement only to the
Cape though you know what I'm saying to
you so maybe we don't apply the offset
to these at all but we do apply it to
the Cape and if you imagine to the Cape
being wider so that you didn't get that
torso showing through look at the torso
was smaller that that seems useful right
potentially I don't know I think it's
where a stick sticking in there probably
my guess
beauty in games the more I see the more
I like this I wonder whether a subtle
head Bob me add a feeling believe it
really just a thought so
the problem of that is the heads like
really important in the game and I don't
want to move it if the player doesn't
move it that's also why I was a little
bit worried about the sucking in there
so I feel like that needs to stay it
would I 100 said agree with you that it
would look better if you bobbed it but I
want the head to be exactly where the
user places it basically so for the
moment anyway I would like to not do
that but you know when the games like
more completed in terms of playing
through it and at that point we could
revisit that issue and see like hey does
it does it feel wrong but for the for
starting the gameplay stuff I want to
not have the head be moved by the game
at all except when the user lets go
and long boolean it seems like you got
to the same conclusion I got to earlier
on the chat
all right so I think we're good on
questions related to what we were doing
so I think mostly what we need here is
just to see what would happen if and
maybe I'll ask
young-shin to give us some art that just
like most closely approximates this
right so something that's like kind of
really stacked and very top-down II and
see like how that looks if we put it in
here and the torso would be kind of like
you know pretty minimal in terms of its
angle be it would be fat but but very
top-down
and we'll see what we'll see what that
looks like I guess
so yeah so I think that's good I think
that's all reasonable all right
and thus Isaac suggested perhaps a
minimum stretch length so you don't get
disappearing bitmaps while moving down
yeah I agree but let's let's wait till
we get the actual art in there and we'll
see what happens but I think that's a
good idea yeah all right I'm gonna go
ahead and close up okay thank you
everyone for joining me for an episode
of handmade Hiro it's on a pleasure
coating with you as always if you would
like to follow along at home you can
always pre-order the game on handmade
hero dot org which of course comes with
a source code so you can follow along we
also have a forum site you can go to and
ask questions we have a patreon page if
you want support the video series you
have a schedule bot which will tweet the
schedule at you so you can catch
episodes live if you want to and an
episode guide for catching up with past
episodes there is also as was announced
this morning
if you've type handmade con dot org into
your browser you should hopefully if it
works yes get redirected our conference
for 2016 has been announced and the
dates are confirmed I verified just this
weekend in fact that everything has been
successfully rented and locked down so
it is okay to start planning trips and
whatnot if you would like to come to
handmade con 2016 again that's on the
Molly Rocket blog but if you want you
can always just type handmade con org
and it'll go to whatever the latest con
is so if there's 2017 one it would go to
that one and so on so if you come here
you can get tickets through brown paper
tickets as it's exactly the same as last
year if you came to VidCon 2015 the only
difference between last year and this
year is we upgraded like just about
everything we could based on the
feedback from last year which was
essentially that the con was great but
our venue was not and I kind of agree
with that it was basically like it was
planned to be a pretty low cost event
because they didn't know how people are
going to come I didn't know we
gonna get 250 people or whatever it was
so you know we were using a really
low-cost space so this year since I know
that the turnout is pretty high we've
got a much better space and so what we
did is we booked a really nice place
it's got great seats and it's really
beautiful and it's a really great area
as well and we have our own for the
second day we also have our own like
hangout area too so we can hang out
after the conference which is another
big thing about it and we've got it for
two days now so that because a lot of
people you know I was thinking would be
mostly a thing for local people but we
had a tremendous number of people who
travel to go to the conference and they
really wanted to be longer because if
they're gonna you know Trek all this way
having adding more days obviously makes
it a lot nicer for them so they have you
know more stuff to do so it's it's both
Saturday and Sunday now instead of just
Saturday so there's a lot more
conference if that makes sense
so basically everything we wanted we got
and so hopefully that will pretty much
solve all any problems that we had last
year because I think pretty much
everything last year was always like
like the conference didn't like the
venue that's not true people were always
very positive but you know if I looked
at the list of things that people asked
for last year they were never like
really content related they were almost
always venue related we like nice
receipts we'd like more breaktime that
sort of thing more days and so it was
really just a question if could be rent
a nicer venue and could we rent it for
longer and I wasn't been eventually able
to do that so if you like can make
content e15 2016 should be exactly the
same but better and and so check out
those and and see if you can make it to
this one if you can you can get tickets
here and this actually is a shot of the
entrance area of the place where we're
holding it it's pretty cool it's really
nice looking at night they have a pretty
cool lighting scheme and actually these
lights are actually on like a hue
rotation so they kind of like subtly
change over time it's kind of freaky so
somebody's they'll be like deep
bullying other times they'll be like
light blue it's kind of weird it's cool
though
and this actually is also running water
here which is kind of neat has this like
shimmery effect to it it's not on here
because I'm here tonight when they were
off as you can see there's nobody in
there but yeah so it's pretty cool so
yeah all of that stuff should be great
definitely check it out and again that's
just handmade con organ your browser as
with the previous year I tried to keep
it basically as cheap as possible
because I I computed out like how much
we would need to pay like speaker travel
expenses and renting the venue and I
basically just set the price at what it
would take to cover that if we sold how
many tickets I roughly think we will so
it's it's not quite as cheap as last
year because last year was $35 and it's
$60 this year but last year was only one
day so actually the per day price has
gone down the per day price went down
five dollars from year-over-year and so
I think that's pretty good
considering the fact that we will get
everything basically upgraded and it's
you know in in a nicer place a nicer
location in the city the other thing too
is I think I can get that down even
further so you know as we sort of scale
upward depending on how many people if
we have a good turnout this year and you
know we grow a little bit every year
then that allows me to rent like nicer
venues without increasing the cost right
because every additional person you put
in a venue is they flee giving you more
money to work with to rent the venue
without actually creating there's no per
person cost you know the venue cost what
it costs so if you can bump up you know
if you can get to a 2,000 person thing
at some point and you're you know you're
selling tickets to a thousand people or
something like this
then the price can just can go down
dramatically because at that point
you've got so many people paying for
space even though the spaces get more
expensive you can sort of reduce the
ticket price so you know I think it's
entirely likely that we'll be able to
get maybe get the ticket price down to
$50 next year which is where pretty much
I think is a good place for it to be
just like I said keeping it affordable I
don't want it to like creep up so I was
okay with it getting a little higher
this year just because like we're
expanding the conference so dramatically
and it's like a lot more time I'm okay
with it going up but I don't want to see
that being like a trend I don't want the
ticket price to like creep up until it's
you know $100 or $200 I really don't
want that to happen so pretty much every
year I will be trying to like figure out
like what can we do in terms of scale
and can we keep the ticket prices low I
realized that the ticket prices aren't
high compared to anyone else this
conference but at the same time it's
like that's not really reason not to try
to figure out how to keep it as
affordable as possible and it is true
that there are students from who are
local and you know students who are or
fans the serious who are coming from
further away the $60 is not an important
part of the cost because it cost so much
to get a plane ticket and everything
else and hotel but for people who are
coming locally you know it does make a
difference right i if you can get it
down to $30 again for two days or
something then that definitely makes it
a little bit easier on everyone who's
coming locally so so that's stuff that
I'll be working on again that's super
relevant but that's just I'd like to be
upfront about the pricing because again
you know if you've heard me talk about
GDC one of my biggest complaints there
is they just absolutely milk it for as
much money as they can and you see these
ticket prices that are like you know
thousand dollars it's you know I think
regular registration is something like
it's like $1,800 or $1,900 it's crazy
how much they charge and I just don't
think it's ethical because they don't
even really provide the content right
like people come and speak for free at
the thing and so it's kind of crazy like
I just can't even see how you can
justify that to yourself I don't know
how you sleep at night when you do that
kind of thing to people so like that's
like a very hard priority for me is that
I always want to keep the prices really
low on the conference and and that's
basically where we've been at on it this
year and we'll see if I can do better
next year if we weren't paying speaker
travel expenses these prices could be
way lower already right
so in terms of like figuring how to do
like venue negotiate venue negotiations
like that I think I've gotten that
pretty well under control actually
because most of the money this year will
not be going towards the venue rental
necessarily most of the money will
probably going towards paying spiegel
travel and stuff like that
so you know again it's like it's all
just kind of a toss up you know I could
reduce the price but again speakers are
donating their time to come and speak
they should not have to pay out of
pocket things that's like another really
crazy thing about like something like
the GDC which I don't approve of right
and so I try to keep it all as balanced
as possible so that the speakers and the
attendees are getting absolutely as fair
a deal as I can possibly put forward for
them and I spend a ton of time working
that out and so this was I think the
best go around this time but well we can
probably get it even better next year so
that's the complete thing about hammock
contravene the speaker list is not
announced yet it will be similar to last
year in the sense that I will be trying
to get people who I think are very
distinguished in either game development
or field that are extremely relevant to
game development and it will be a very
similar format to last year where a lot
of the content will be basically me sort
of interviewing people and drilling down
into various aspects of what they do and
how they do it and why as well as a
little bit of backstory in history which
i think is always interesting too I
think it's important for people to know
about you know if you've got a great
programmer up there how did they get
started what sort of things are you
because you don't always get a chance to
hear some of those things especially
from some programmers who maybe aren't
famous in some other sense but are you
know basically you know sort of pseudo
legendary in the sense of like what
they've accomplished it's kind of
interesting to see like the back stories
of some of those people and kind of get
a little more information about where
they come from so we'll be keeping the
format basically saying but what'll be a
little bit different this year is
because we have more time we can do a
few more things like we can probably do
questions at the event this year because
questions didn't really work last year I
asked people to send them in after and I
just didn't get very many so it really
wasn't worth I think doing that and so
we will probably make the conference
more interactive this year also will
have longer breaks so during the breaks
you can interact with other attendees or
the speakers as
you know as possible so that you know
you can get a little more of that sort
of organic stuff happening so we'll be
able to do much longer breaks this year
which you know I think should be a
pretty excellent addition as well as
having one dedicated Meetup
because people who weren't aware of some
of the meetups missed out on some of
that and those were pretty great so this
year we'll at least have one where
everyone knows okay for these three
hours you can come and go and this kind
of in this area you know go get your
dinner or whatever but then come back
after you're done and if you want to
hang out and that'll be on Sunday so
that everyone can kind of have a chance
to to hang out and talk and meet each
other and then you know say goodbye
before they head back to their
respective places so that'll I think be
pretty great as well now one thing that
wasn't great
is that this year we could have probably
afforded to have that hangout space
available the entire time which would
have been my preference but one of the
problems of basically like doing the
startup process of getting this con
rolling is that you know in 2015 it was
just like hey I did whatever I could I
did a simple thing low cost just because
to see what would happen and of course
it went way better than I ever could
have expected so 2016 I was way more
serious about it like I know what we're
dealing with here what can we do but
there's a because of the pipeline
there's a little bit of a problem in
getting what we want even if we can
afford it and fight find it and afford
it
and so there simply wasn't any schedule
availability to get a hangout space for
both days so I anticipate you know
well it'll kind of be a test in 2016
what we'll do is we'll see how that
hangout space works I think it'll
probably be really good and assuming
that it is for 2017 I've already kind of
got things slotted and I'm trying to
kind of keep things reserved will for
2017 will probably go ahead and get that
space for both days because that way
will always for the entire length of the
conference they'll always be a place you
can meet up with people even if you're
gonna go somewhere else and hang out
they'll always be a place that you know
you can meet up with people and where
you know people will sort of be
when they don't have anything else
they're doing at the conference and I
think that'll be really great so I wish
I could have got it this year we
couldn't not because of the money I
think we probably could have made the
money or you know I could have raised
the ticket price by five bucks and got
or whatever right I could have made that
happen but it just simply wasn't
available and this venue was by far the
best one in terms of what we needed and
the price and what we could what they
required didn't require us to do all of
those things it was definitely the best
so it was a very very clear choice there
wasn't really any other option and there
just wasn't an ability to make that
happen so for 2017 I think we can
improve on that even a little bit more
but we'll use 2016 as as sort of a test
and if it turns out that that space
really isn't that useful then we'll know
and we won't do it but I feel like it
probably will be in and so sunday will
be the test day to see how we like it
and and then we'll go from there so I
think that is just about it for a
handmade con if you do have questions
about it or want to talk about certain
aspects of it obviously on handmade
network we can kind of go like go on to
handmade oops
he wrote handmade Wow spelling that
Network and you can go into like one of
the code forum serious and like this may
be at some point we should make a forum
for the conference and I don't know if
anyone out there is listening who is
when the mods there are no administrator
options at the moment on these forums
for me so I can't do it but we may want
to make a forum for handmade con because
that way people could post in there if
they have questions or you know and each
con could have you know as we go so if
you do have stuff that you are
interested in knowing you can post it on
there and then I could take care of it
in a blog post or whatever coming
forward so so I think that's basically
it let me double check the chat to see
if anyone has already posted anything
that I should respond to you but I think
we're pretty much
pretty much good
all right so I think we're good so
that's about it thank you very much for
joining me as always and I will catch
you guys on the internet tomorrow I am
off but the day after we will be back
here at 5:00 p.m. Pacific Daylight Time
and we'll probably move on now that I'm
like relatively sure that the hero
movement is going to work the way I
wanted it to you know we can well I'm
sure we'll we'll be tuning it and tuning
it and tuning it over time but I'm
relatively okay with that
we'll probably start working on some
more entity system stuff just sort of
like get that stuff under control so
we'll take care of that and so if you're
interested in that come back Wednesday
until then have fun programming and I
will see you folks on the Internet take
it easy everyone