hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero the show we could a complete game
live on stream we are coming off of a
week where we implemented cutscenes we
put basically our intro cutscene
together and it looked pretty darn
snappy i was very happy with it i
thought it was really exciting to see
all of that coming together and at the
very end of last week friday in the Q&amp;A
i think it might have been midlo that
asked the question can we fade out the
desktop and I was sort of throwing
together really quickly a way to make
that happen but I didn't have time to
actually do it so was thinking we might
do today is just quickly take a look at
that and see if I can get that working
for him is not something we will do for
handmade hero but it's just you know
it's a reasonable question and it seems
like the least we can do for someone who
spent so much time making a great
episode guide for handmade hero so let's
take a look today is day 2 25 so if you
pre-order the game on handmade heroic
and downloaded the source code you want
to start with day 2 24's source code
that's where i'm starting today let's go
ahead and bring that up here and see
what we can do all right so here we are
I believe we were in win32 handmade so
that's right here and what we did is we
had a little fade out function i was
going to hack together and again i'm not
trying to do a super industrial-strength
brainless i just want to kind of show
what the idea was now Martin's mosaico
who often answers questions on the
forums he reminded me on Twitter that I
already covered how to do this a little
more simply earlier on and I forgot
about it entirely but but that's true
instead of using update layered window
we can actually use the set layer window
parameters with you remember way back I
showed how to do this let me look it up
here it's like yeah set layered window
attributes this one here I showed how to
use this completely forgot about the
function my brains old I don't use these
functions very often anymore so I was
just like poof apparently i knew it
earlier on but fortunately martin's was
there to remember so thank you very much
for that
other things thank you for basically
answering everyone's questions on the
forums all the time which is actually
what Martin's often does so anyway let's
take a look at this guy and I'm going to
see if I can hack this together and I
remember what we did is we wanted to
fade out the background and what I said
might be the most compatible way to do
it because there's different ways you
could do it I think maybe the most
compatible way to probably do it would
be just create a full screen window
that's transparent but black and then
gradually increase its opacity until the
point where we can actually see it blot
out the background so I'm going to try
that I don't know if it'll work but I'm
just going to try that here to see if
that gives us a reasonable effect and
then we can go from there so I'm going
to skip this part hopefully we don't
have to do it again i'm not sure we may
or may not i'm going to try using set
layered window and see what i can do so
there's our blend function and all that
sort of thing i'm going to call set
layered window you can see that what it
has here is it takes the the H wind
right and that H wind we already know is
the one that we just created for this
specific purpose right then we've got a
CR key which is the color key now
presumably that's not necessary because
again that's not going to be in our
alpha function this this blend function
is presumably not going to actually need
that because you can see we could
specify it right here so we're going to
do lw8 alpha instead of LW a color key
right so I'm going to grab that out lwa
alpha and oops it's no good and then I
just need to specify these this this
this byte alpha value here so this color
rep I think like before it just can be
anything and so really all we need to do
is specify that bite and we'll see how
that goes ok and I'm going to sleep for
less time there ok so what I want to do
here this alpha value that we specify
it's used to describe the opacity right
so when it's zero is transparent when
it's 225 Sr pig so I should be able to
do is just set it to whatever we're
setting the Alpha value here too and
hopefully that will do something
resembling something I don't actually
know if it will but we're going to find
out so let's see what we get here and if
that Abu
I guess I still have the bugger running
or something here let's go ahead and fix
that see oh yeah gotta actually cast
that to a bite there we go okay um so
yeah that looks exactly what I would
have expected so thank you Martin's
reminding me that saved us a ton of time
so yeah so this should do the fade out
now I suspect right although that I
suppose was a little too fast I admit
that so we need a little bit let's do a
sleep one here there we go so that's a
fade out for you and so what all we
really need to do now in order to sort
of have that fade work a little more
appropriately is we're going to want to
like this this sleep right this is not
really a reasonable way to do timing
right because it's very variable it's
not a guaranteed amount of time you know
we can't just put something in there and
say oh I want this as 60 frames a second
so do sleep 16 you know that doesn't
necessarily guarantee the proper amount
of time right that might be how fast it
is on this machine it might be totally
different on some other machine it's
just all kind of it's just not what we
want right so what we would want to do
here if we were going to try and make
this fade-out be a little bit more
reasonable right is we might want to
make it so that this fade out routine is
something that we could call
incrementally as we sort of go through
our game loop or who knows what else
we're doing and have that fade out
happen it sort of like on our main clock
in our in our main kind of timing you
know basically tie it to something a
little more real if that makes sense and
so we can do that that's actually not
that hard and maybe you know if you want
I can do that now since again since you
guys asked you know let's let's take a
look so if we wanted to do that what we
would do is we would probably just make
this window here that we've got we'd
probably make this a more permanent
installation to our game
so for example in here you know we do
this this register of the registering of
the window class what we would probably
do is we'd register a second window
class like we did here and create a
second window and we do that entirely
permanently right so we do something
like you know before we did this stuff
before we did any of this stuff you know
right after we sort of i suppose do some
of these things for start-up we would
probably create that window now I'm just
thinking and do I want to try to catch
myself I don't think so so what I'm
going to do here is I think I'm just
going to do a thing here where we just
kind of do H wind are fade window right
and our fade window is going to be
handled this way so here is all of that
stuff that happens in here and that's
going to do this registration it's going
to do all this stuff that it needs to do
it's going to make it full screen but
it's not going to do any of that it's
just going to make it full screen then
it's going to stop and then everything
else will do separately from that right
so--okay so starting with that we would
then change this function to be like all
right what's the fade window and what's
the actual value that we're trying to
fade too ok and I'm going to say that
we're going to pass it like some kind of
an r32 which is the opacity something
like this or I could just call it the
Alpha value right and then what I'm
going to do is I'm going to go ahead and
convert that down right so I would do
something like say ok the Alpha value x
2 55 and then I would want to convert
that down to a bite after we were done
to sort of get that value into place so
this is the like this is the windows
alpha value something like this so that
would be what we would pass we would no
longer use this loop at all and then
what I do is when we find out what the
window alpha actually is I'd probably do
something like say oh
a you know if the Alpha value is zero
then I want to hide the window otherwise
I want to show the window like that
something like this ok so then what I
could do at least in theory or like I
guess it could say set fade alpha or
something like this right so if i run
this now and that if i run this now what
we should see is it like absolutely
nothing actually happens right because
we're not we haven't tile like sort of
tied it into anything so it's not going
to do anything obviously but we'll take
care of that in one second so you know i
run this thing now and we basically just
get the app exactly the way that we had
it before there's no fade is no nothing
right but what i can do now is I can say
all right like when we're going to go
start this start the party here right
when we do our like global running
situation or whatever else we're doing
um which happens right here right what i
could do is do something like you know
our fade alpha is going to equal zero
zero or something like that and as we
come through here what we could do is
say the fade alpha that's got to go like
up to 1 point 0 before we do like
anything else right before like anything
else happens we got to make sure that
happens right so as we do that what i
could do is say okay you know we've got
this sort of this thing here that does
our show window oops here it is as you
can see here like we do our toggle
window and we do our show window on our
main window what I could do there to say
like let's not do that let's not show
the main window yet let's withhold that
for later and so if I do that right now
when we run the game we won't see
anything now the game's still running in
the background we just won't see
anything right we won't see the game at
all and so what I could do instead is I
can withhold that show window like
prevent our window from actually shown
until we finish that actual fade out
right
and so what i can do is at the top of
global running for example when we
figure out our target amount per frame i
could do a thing here which basically
says okay let's take that fade alpha
value let's go ahead and take whatever
the dt for the frame actually was will
do like sort of an accumulation there on
it right and we'll do something like
okay if they'd alphas less than zero i'm
going to clamp it actually i don't know
if clamps and you're somebody do the
clamp manually so let me do a fade alpha
is less than zero zero fatalities ero 0
and if fade alpha is greater than 1
point 0 fate alpha equals one point out
now we have functions do that in our
math library i don't remember if we
include the math library in the win32
section probably be down I don't really
remember anyway so we've got our fate
alpha there and what I want to do is say
okay we've got the Fate alpha we're
going to go ahead and update the Fate
alpha every time right but what I'm
going to do instead is I'm going to say
all right if the fade alpha equals 1
point 0 then at that point I know that I
can transition over to the other window
I know that like once we've gotten up to
that epatha TI can transition over to
the other window so what I would do at
that time is I'm going to call that set
fate alpha function and i'm going to
call it to basically turn off the window
entirely right so it's going to get rid
of it and i'm going to show our other
window so that will see our other window
instead so once the Fate alpha hits that
I'm going to do it otherwise if the Fate
alpha hasn't hit that I'm going to like
continue to let it go up right something
like this so I'm just going to make the
Fate alpha kind of go up until it's
completely opaque and then I'm going to
switch to the other window and at that
point we can see the game does that make
sense and now we're on a proper timer as
well so hopefully that will be fine
what's going on here yeah so this guy
should be like nothing should be equal
to nothing okay and so that was
spectacularly bad right I admit that
that was not what I expected to look I
at all it should have looked much
smoother than that but what are you
going to do sometimes you mess it up uh
yeah can't say I immediately know why
that happened but we will step into it
and find out and my room that seemed
really abrupt right you saw it didn't
you yeah that seemed really abrupt I
don't feel like we should have been
going that fast although maybe for all I
know we actually were so yeah that could
be true but we probably would need to do
is actually see what the actual time per
frame was or turn back on our actual
loop of timing so I'm gonna maybe maybe
I'll do that just temporarily so that we
have a more sustainable timing loop in
here to see all right there we go so
that's actually quite a bit better so
yeah we're going to have to fix our
frame right either way to make ourselves
get back to a solid 30 Hertz or 60 Hertz
with you know with with actual real
timing in there what I don't know is
we're getting a little bit of a flicker
there so I think that is not what we
want so there's a little bit of a
problem when we hit fade alpha one this
part obviously is not quite working yet
and I'm not like it's the handoff is not
quite looking like I feel like it should
because you can see and maybe it's too
hard to see on the stream at home but
and that time it didn't happen there it
is you see a brief flash sometimes in
the changeover period and so I don't
know III don't know if we need to like
force an update of the window or
something in order to get that to work
properly or something like this and not
quite sure so I'm not sure what's
actually happening there or if maybe
we're going over our
limit or something I don't know I'm
going to step in just real briefly to
see just to make sure that's all working
properly and make sure that it's just a
Windows things that we know that that's
the problem we're trying to solve if
that makes sense oh of course there's a
now there's a full screen window that I
can't get past great great well in order
to debug that that's not such a bad
that's not such a bad thing I can just
take off the top most flag there the
reason I couldn't see that window right
is because we we made a window that's
called topmost it's on top of all the
other window so i couldn't alt tab to
the debugger one of the reasons is nice
to have a second monitor to say the
least right alright so let's go ahead
and see if we can make this happen again
so there we go so at the break point I
know our windows didn't want to set the
breakpoint before so there we go now
we're at show window so what I'm going
to do is this obviously should show the
window I don't think there's anything
weird happening there but I want to see
what happens in fade window what's the
windows alpha value here it's zero so
it's going to call SW hide on that
window which is exactly what I wanted
I'm going to also step in to see if that
ever happened before that so meaning did
we ever try to hide the window before we
got to that point I just want to make
sure that that didn't happen and it
didn't right there's that's the first
time that we ever hit that case so that
looks pretty good to me so I'm not
really sure what the problem is there I
guess one thing i should say is after we
do this once we don't want to keep doing
this again so i do wonder if maybe
that's causing a little bit of a problem
so i may also try to remove that from
happening so I'm going to just do a
thing that's like you know something
like you know fading complete or
something and I'll do or like you know
maybe a fade in progress well now I'll
do fading complete so what I'll do here
is like if the fading is not complete we
do all this stuff otherwise you know we
don't do anything so it's something like
that and so I don't know if that will
help like I said it doesn't I didn't
it would I just wanted to make sure
there wasn't any kind of glitching
happening there just to be sure so all
right so we've got a little bit of a
glitch there and I'm not exactly sure
quite what it comes from like I said I
don't know if what we need to do is is
like prime this thing a little bit more
so we do like a show window like this
and like for example I guess I should
check the seed if we get a glitch just
doing this I don't think we should
because I believe that topmost window
should say topmost right and so that
looks pretty good there let me run it
again because it didn't always do it so
I just want to make sure okay so it's
basically just weird for some reason
when we disappear that when that window
goes away we're not getting our other
window like up there in time and so I
don't know if we need to go through one
round of the message loop or something
to try and make sure that we've
repainted it I there are some things
like could maybe do here I'm not really
sure you know what I could do I think
our toggle full screen I could do
something like this potentially and I'm
not totally sure but let me just take a
look let's see what happens if we do a
toggle full screen after showing it to
force that repaint I just want to see if
that gives us any better success now
that's even worse we get all kinds of
weird stuff happening there alright so
what I'm going to do here as I'm going
to do a show window I'm going to do an
update window and I'm going to force a
repaint I'm just going to force windows
to ibar them a try to force windows to
repaint the way we do that is going to
call function called invalidate wrecked
and what this does is it basically says
hey I want you two to resour to paint
this window right and we'll see if
that's any any any good here so
basically what this says is all right I
want you to take a window and I feel
like this should have just been being
done so again I don't really have high
hopes for this but with windows
programming I'd there's no way to really
know you can't step through the code so
unless you're raymond chen and can step
through the code it's pretty hard to
find out why windows does whatever
random stupid thing it is that it does
so I'm going to go ahead and force it to
repaint there i'm going to call
updatewindow to try and make that paint
happen and i don't know if that'll help
but i'm going to try right so let's take
a look and see what happens invalidate
rent there we go and we'll see if that
gives us any more success on the glitch
still nothing so again I really just
don't know what where that's coming from
it's at the changeover point to be sure
but I just can't I can't tell why we're
getting that I guess I should also
verify again that there's no weirdness
with the alpha values like that this
alpha value doesn't wrap or something
like that I can't see how it would
because that doesn't really make any
sense but let me see let me just make
sure that it doesn't so what I'm going
to do here is I'm going to replace
windows alpha with 255 this way we're
black the whole time to straight up
black we come on black we stay black and
want to see if there's any glitching
when that happens I just want to see
right so I'm going to run that a couple
times and see if we ever get the glitch
so the fact that we don't get the glitch
there is making me think that maybe
we're wrapping up nope there was the
glitch so even if all we do yet there's
a glitch again so even if all we do is
just call it with black it still happens
so what that says to me is that we're
not like screwing up the calculation and
accidentally passing zero at the end a
little bit early or something like that
so yeah so that's good what I also could
do is have us I could have set layered
window attributes actually it's calling
esta me show every time and that's not
really necessary so I could also do
something like where we are a little bit
saner about that sort of thing I could
do where we don't actually call a yeah
where we don't actually call that and
that would look something more like this
right
showwindow window SW so this could
happen only if the window is not visible
and I don't really remember how you
actually do that I don't think there
isn't is visible call but maybe there is
I guess there is alright perfect is
window visible so what we can do is just
say like okay if the window is visible
you know show it the windows visible
hide it if it's not as well show it in
either the two cases right excuse me
alright so let's see if that does any
better again same thing so it's a little
bit cleaner now but doesn't actually
help with our main problem and again
like I said this is really kind of
annoying I you know exactly the kind of
debugging that I don't recommend people
do with their own code because with your
own code you should just step through
and find the actual problem the super
annoying part about Windows is you can't
write you can't step in and figure out
what's wrong because it's someone else's
code and its proprietary you can't see
it so hey that's why a lot of Windows
things are buggy is because when you
write stuff you don't actually have any
idea what's actually going on you have
no idea what could the bug could be etc
etc etc right so I don't know what else
to do here i'm going to try delaying for
one frame i'm going to do another thing
that's like again just making kind of a
little mini finite state machine here
just to see if it changes this is pure
experimentation like I said before so
we'll do if fading complete and then
we'll do if not showing complete so this
will give us one pass through the
message loop to see if that does
anything I don't know that it will but
we'll just see if it does right so
there's our fading ability if not
showing complete then what I'll do is I
will do this part right so we're going
to try and get that other window up
first and see and then we'll give it one
pass through the windows loop so it
didn't do it that time but again it
seems to only do it once in a while so I
just want to test to see and make sure
that that's actually solving it it does
look like giving it one pass through the
message loop maybe gave it time to do
the repaint and like actually process
the paint message which might have been
the problem either gonna don't know I'm
not saying that's actually what it is
but does look like now we've solved that
problem which is kind of nice so that's
good now what I would like to do is that
cursor is still visible not a huge fan
of the cursor being visible so what I
might do is just as a final touch here
again we've kind of have our window proc
right if you remember how did we make
the cursor just disappear right how do
we you know how do we do that originally
well the way that we did that is here in
our window callback for our main window
is when it asks us to set the cursor we
said shut it off don't show the cursor
like get rid of that cursor and so what
I might do here is have a win32 fade
window call back that's our own call
back again it doesn't handle any
messages at all for the most part it's
just going to and in fact it might
actually be resistant to close and
destroy so that people basically can't
get rid of it if that makes sense it'll
just say like hey I don't care what you
think you're doing we are going to like
full-on ignore you i guess destroy
probably you don't want to do but but
close certainly we could just say like
hey man i don't care if you think you're
closing me you ain't closing me i got
news for you pal that's just how this
goes so we could definitely do something
like that and then in here what we would
have is when we call the fade window
call back right the clothes doesn't do
anything the set cursor is definitely
going to just shut it down and say you
know what don't ever show that cursor so
then what we do is when we have def
window proc which we have what was what
which is what we set the fade window to
call right here we could just call our
you know our new function which will get
rid of that cursor that way the instant
you hit f5 the cursor goes away in the
fade-out happened
there now I don't know whether there's
any way to fade out the cursor right I
never tried something like that before
we could certainly investigate and see
but I also want to see here so we do
have a problem which is that that window
is that's that topmost window there we
want that to go away entirely and you
can see that it's still kind of there I
don't really know why because I feel
like SW hide should have gotten rid of
that that should have got rid of it but
you know what i think i think i may have
passed the wrong flag there I I want to
say that I passed the wrong flag there I
don't know that I did I'm just going to
look and see let's take a look let's see
no there it is so why you can still pick
it I'm not sure if the window is visible
hide the window that's what should have
happened on alpha 0 right and it's a top
most window so we shouldn't even have
seen our window so that's pretty weird
I'm going to go ahead and set a
breakpoint throw to make sure that's
getting called right and it's not
getting called okay ah I don't know that
wait no that should that should still
return the right thing right ha so is
window visible apparently returns false
for layered windows
not sure I know why that would be I'm
going to go ahead and see what's pi plus
plus has to say about that again using
the spy tool which is basically let you
inspect windows on Microsoft Windows I'm
just going to go ahead and look and see
what's actually happening there I want
to look and see if this window is marked
visible or not so I'm going to go into
the styles and I'm going to see so it
does not have the visible style set
which is weird because it definitely is
visible like we were seeing it at that
time and I don't really understand how
how it went away so I'm going to
actually set a breakpoint like earlier
on in this process so let's go ahead and
let it fade out a little bit right and
so here we are with an alpha value of 0
point six and then I'm going to go ahead
and say like what's the visible value
here right so let's go ahead and let's
refresh that I'm gonna look at the
handmade here a fade out window class
take a look at the properties there and
go ahead and look at the styles there's
that visible flag right there right and
so I'm not sure how does it get set to
invisible without us ever calling hide
does someone want to give me a little
primer on that situation because I don't
get it did I act forget like something
in here did I leave something in there
deny deny show window window show when
validate wrecked fading complete set
fate alpha yeah I mean we don't touch we
don't touch that window in any other
place so all right so tell me why mr.
thingy tell me why and and that time we
didn't never even hit this case am I
going crazy here people what's going on
what's going on the alpha is 0
oh the first time we call it though so
the very first time we call it it does
have alpha 0 so this time through it's
not visible and that's fine the next
time through it just never gets called
why does it never get cold why does it
never call with alpha 0 it's supposed to
so it's actually just a bug out here
where I'm like set fate alpha 0 if not
showing complete oh wow that was some
pretty great programming there Casey
nice job parenthesis you're fired so
obviously this is just stupid this would
be calling this all the time which
doesn't even make any sense that's not
what I intended at all what I wanted to
do is probably say this if fading
complete right if the fading is complete
then look to see if the showing is not
complete if it is then go ahead and set
that right if it's not then get rid of
that window right so this may bring back
our bug because it may be that we never
actually got rid of it yeah so that's
good this is this is this is not good
this is bad news bears right because
this means we'll probably get our glitch
back I don't know if we will or not but
I feel like that's entirely possible
well so good so far
alright so that's not bad that's
actually not bad so let's just see now
if we successfully got rid of that
window which is what I actually wanted
so now that's good so now we don't see
that window ever which is what we wanted
and so I think we're in good shape now
right I think we're in good shape that's
pretty that's pretty decent I think
everyone's happy and everyone's smiling
so I think the other thing we could do
right if we wanted to is we could do the
reverse process right we could we could
go the other direction if that makes
sense so what i could do is do something
like you know d fate alpha and and i
could make that be something that you
know as we go through the process we
just say oh okay you know we're going to
do d fade alpha times this so initially
what we're doing is we're fading in and
so that as we do this you know the clamp
still works properly all this sort of
stuff happens and so when the fade is
complete and the showing is not complete
instead of say set fate alpha 200 and
the showing complete thing ash I think
that's all that's probably all fine
actually now I think about it that's all
good yeah and so we could also do a
thing that's like new global running or
like quit on fade equals false right I
could also starting to say like if quit
on fade then global running equals false
or something like that I don't actually
know no idea just giving you what the
idea is there this is kind of just janky
code but it's okay it's in the platform
layer whatever so anyway I oops so
anyway we could do something like that
and then that way we could sort of do
something where we're like okay we
settled that stuff up and it does the
thing that it does or whatever I don't
even know so this stuff is like okay
when we come in here if the faith alpha
is 1 point 0 that means this is the end
of the fade or the beginning of the fade
one of the other so we need to do is we
need to know whether we're on the quit
on fade or not right if we're on the
quit on fade then we're going to we're
fading back in to the desktop if
otherwise we're doing the path that we
already did right so what we would want
to do here is go all right if we're
going to quit on fade then what we need
to do is bring that alpha window back up
to speed right so we need to do like
okay do the set fade alpha that set fade
alpha has to how's it going to work
exactly that set fade alpha is going to
have to be set to 0 to start right
because we don't want or sorry is we
good after that's a one-point oh yeah so
by default if the Fate also imported oil
done if we're quitting on favorite to do
that and we want to set the D alpha yeah
we would want to like well that's really
all we would have to do we just have to
make sure that we actually do this step
right yeah so I think that's okay yeah I
think that's okay that should be fine
and that'll let us go down to zero and
then when we get to zero right we should
be fine so here we take something like
your fate alpha equals 0 0 right at that
point then we're going to say like okay
that's the end of this fade so fading
complete is going to be equal to true at
that point and and yeah and that's all
we really need to do so I think that's
sufficient maybe we got some more work
to do but I think that's sufficient so
then what we would do is say okay when
the quit when the game requests a quit
right then what we would do is we'll
show our our window we get rid of right
and then we set our d fate alpha equal
to 1 negative 1 point out so it's going
to go backwards right it's going to it's
going to go from full black down right
we knew our fate alpha should already be
one point oh so that's fine we want our
quit on fade to become true so we knew
like you're going to quit on two and
then instead of quitting we won't quite
quit not at least right away right and
so yeah that's roughly what we want
alright so we got to make all this stuff
work now let's see where we're at so
when we come in here we'd say
a GF 8 alphas one point out of the Fate
alpha is 0 so we come in here would say
okay if it off oh right this has to be
if quit on fade this is only the quit on
fade put on fade and fade alpha there we
go that's what we want then it would be
complete let's see what happens there so
there's our fade out here is our game
ostensibly and then if I quit this well
that didn't work at all so that's fine
it's great don't worry about it fine
don't let anyone tell you that was a
problem it was exactly what I wanted you
know it's just like it's just let it
happen it's totally fine so let's go
over here and see what happens here gay
memory quit requested we do want our
window to go away and then we want our
fade window to come up so we probably
actually here also want to do something
like set window for a set fade alpha
maybe this maybe how do I want to do
this actually let me let me just jump
back here put this over here so yeah in
here okay so that's what we need to do
we need to go fading complete equals
false showing complete equals false that
might be fine and this I think probably
wants to happen up here as well so when
this happens we want to first get our
fate alpha on then we want to do our our
hide our main window something like that
right
well that was anticlimactic this code is
too stringy at this point I kind of want
to pull this out into something a little
bit more good if that makes sense so I
might just do this I feel like at this
point we're sort of in for a penny in
for a pound I don't really know where
that comes from but you know probably
some kind of British thing because if
there's pennies and pounds involved and
not sure how many replace that could be
other than British currency so let's
just assume that that was the case you
know and say like that's just how it
goes sometimes so I'm just going to go
ahead and say like all right cool in
here we've got all our win32 stuff i
might just straight up your luck hey you
know what we've got a win32 fade window
right and that's just the thing here's
the handle to the window here's the fade
alpha and here's like the state or
something something like that right and
I'm going to grab all this code out and
I'm going to make this into like a thing
that actually just kind of understands
at state and doesn't have to have so
much stringing us to it right so like
I'm gonna just do something like update
fade I don't know something like that at
the moment let's say just say that and
then what update fade will do is it's
just going to take a look right at what
the state of this thing actually was and
so we've got a couple states already
right our first date would be like win32
fade fading in 13 to fade showing or
like waiting for show then they'll be 13
to fade inactive basically went through
to fade I guess in this case we would
also have fading in waiting for show
inactive and then we would also have
like fading out right and each of these
would be its own like thing
yeah so if I have a win through to fade
window and this is the window I now call
it fader in fact we might just call it a
win32 fader something like that then I'm
just going to go ahead and implement
this this thing in its entirety so what
we've got here is all of this code that
we had before right like all this stuff
hopefully we can kind of make this a
little bit more explicit and just kind
of transform it into something a little
more reasonable so here's all that code
right and then the parcel it out into
something hopefully a little bit more
reasonable right so we start with this
and let's see what we've got so for
fading in then really what we want to do
is like do something like whatever the
dt is right we're gonna we're going to
fade that in and some of if we're fading
out we're just going to subtract that
right and if the fade alpha goes below
zero zero that's like our edge condition
our transition condition right and so at
that point when we go below zero we're
going to switch to a different state
we're going to say like okay we've got
if we're fading out that would just give
us win32 fade waiting for clothes or
something I guess which would be our
final state yeah okay
alright so when we're in active that
actually doesn't have to do anything
note nothing to do because we're just
not doing anything when we're waiting
for clothes I think that's also nothing
to do that's just a state that we don't
really care about right I saying like
we're just kind of waiting for someone
to shut us down when we're waiting for
show that is just as soon as we do that
the first time it's only we're only
going to wait one time to the message
loop so really all we do in that case is
immediately transition to the inactive
state and then for fading in we're just
going to do this right okay so I think
that's our complete state transition if
you will so now we just have to actually
do whatever it is that we needed to do
right so when we do our plus equals dt
we would essentially say like okay
whatever the actual in fact I guess this
might be like this so if it's greater
than or equal to 1 point 0 what we would
do is we would set the Fate alpha equal
to 1 point 0 and we transition to our
waiting for show state once we get to
our waiting for show state that's where
we need to actually do this whole
nonsense right so when we go to our
waiting for show state we this is what
we actually want to do I otherwise we're
going to do the update same with this
guy I think we want to do something like
this where when we get down to zero
we've got to do whatever the thing is
we're going to do so we do it like our
set fade alpha with zero for example and
then we would go ahead and yeah and two
hour wait for clothes and i think is
there anything else that happened in
here the quit on fade thing so that's
that Fadal fasho window hide that that
whole situation so i think no
that actually needs to occur just yet so
when i get rid of these guys alright so
there's our little state diagram like i
said we haven't really super covered
finite state machines here so this is
kind of a little cursory introduction i
mean basically what we're doing is we're
taking a bunch of code that was based on
several different variables and then
making explicit the different modes
right and each mode gets a name and then
we have transitions between the modes
right and so that's really all I was
doing and we'll cover those maybe a
little bit more in detail later but for
now you can kind of see what that
transformation look like and that's just
to make a code a little more explicit so
it's not so hard to figure out what gets
called when so we'll tune that and debug
that in a minute here but now I just
have to wire it up but there's one more
thing I want to do and that is right
here so when we do our fade in I feel
like we may also want to do one more
thing which would be maybe like
yeah like instead of fading in we might
do something like you know a fading you
know fading like game or something I
don't know we might want to fade the
game to black and we might want to do
that the same way it seems better to
make the game fate itself out to black
but I'm just going to throw this in here
anyway because why not right so I'm
going to have fading gaming here and
what fading game would do is it would do
this exact same thing it would say like
okay if it's greater than one point oh I
want to do the thing here but instead of
this stuff what I want to do is get rid
of the game window right this is all
game window stuff right I want to get
rid of the game window so it hides it at
that point and then I want to switch us
to fading out which will start so we'll
go to black will get rid of the game
window then we'll come back from black
to show the desktop right that was all
that I was thinking there so yeah that
seems that seems reasonable to me uh so
yeah game window game window game window
game window game window so you'd pass
the game window into this thing like
this probably so in here I just say like
begin fade in and this would be like
again fade out something like that and
this would be like you know in it fader
right that sort of thing and so when we
go to do begin fade in we would just say
all right our state is going to be win32
fade fading in our you know our fate
alpha is going to be 00 at the start and
then the fader our fader state for this
is going to be fading game probably name
these states a little bit better in a
second here once we see them all and the
alpha is going to be again 00 and that
would be pretty much all there would be
to it I would think our anit fader is
just going to take that construction
code which I kind of already nicely
segregated there I'm going to go ahead
and make that this part right here and
I'm also going to go ahead and move this
guy up because he's referenced by these
guys so we're just going to put them in
up there as a utility all right so if we
assume that that's going to work at all
which we don't know that well let's go
ahead and make this happen here ah yeah
there we go hopefully that's all good
this all looks fine fade window you know
H min fade window just fader window
could just replace fade window with
fader window bat and now when I compile
we should have most of our stuff working
okay but there should be some weird
things here still with that okay uh so
yeah a couple more things that need to
happen now in the main loop i think is
about it
so we've got to do our fader alpha here
so fade alpha is going to be fader alpha
like oops not that way try that one more
time so there we go yep nope nope yup
yup yup yup nope nope you up all right
good good deal okay so that's all good
and I think now that we should we should
i'll be able to do this so now what we
would do is we would say out here begin
fade out and we would do yeah guess
those are bad names in fade out i'm
going to call this begin fade to game
begin fade to desktop so this is going
to be begin fade to desktop and this is
going to take our fader there and this
stuff is all going to go away right
that's all good and then what I'm going
to do up here when we update this guy so
where we were doing it before after we
do our target seconds for frame and all
that stuff what I'm going to do is ahead
here is say okay update fade we're going
to update the fader and what that's
going to do I'm going to have that that
return what the the new state is if that
makes sense look what the state that it
transitions to was like that so it's
basically going to say like oh yeah you
know like I'm going to return fader
state like so I might also go ahead and
do a little assertion here
so and so when I do this what I'm trying
to do now is just say like okay once i
do my update fade if i needed to take an
action based on that i will take that
action so for example for now I'll just
do the only one I actually care about is
waiting for clothes so if this thing
says that I need to close then i'm going
to say like okay global runnings going
to get killed here when when the fade
thing is finished that's the only actual
state i care about the moment and so I
think that's all I really need to do now
I just need to initialize our windows
properly and that's a real simple matter
of just saying like here's our win
through to fader and what I'm going to
do here just do initialize fader and
that needs to take our instance but
that's it and now we're good so hey man
I probably got some bugs in there it's
true and oops and I gotta pass the game
window there but that's at least
structurally a little more sound now and
so I can actually like relate to a
little bit more and hopefully debug it
more so hey the fade-out worked first
time that's pretty handy but now we've
got to work on that fade back to the
desktop right so yeah first problem is
alt f4 kind of immediately killed our
window that's not very reassuring and so
let's take a look at why that actually
happened there oh I forgot that actually
is supposed to immediately kill our
window its escape that actually exit the
game now so let's try that and see if
that does anything that does absolutely
nothing nothing nothing nothing nothing
nothing right and if doing absolutely
nothing is not really what I wanted if I
wanted to do nothing I would have well I
don't know why I would have done that
alright so we've got oh well that would
do it I think we can see why that's the
case so begin figure desktop this quit
requested will presumably stay set to
true and it'll keep resetting over and
over again it'll keep for calling begin
fade to desktop over and over again
resetting our alpha value so we actually
want to do is say okay
if the fader state you know is is if we
haven't started one of these yet right
then we would want to do that so it's
only if the fader state is inactive that
we actually probably want to let that
happen so that's a bit of a hacky way to
do it we should probably make the
transition a little more explicit there
but for now that should be fine there's
that darn window again so we also have a
problem where we're not hiding that guy
so let's take a look at that bug first
so why aren't we hiding that guy uh
let's see well when we set the window
set fader alpha when we fade in that's
supposed to set to zero so that's just a
mess up isn't it oh no it's not a mess
up that's supposed to happen here where
we do waiting for show it's supposed to
happen here right that's when we're
supposed to set that that zero to clear
out the window yeah to avoid the glitch
right so now we don't have that window
in the alt tab hierarchy which is what
we want that's good and now if I hit
escape there's our fade out and hey
there's our fade back to the desktop so
now we're actually working properly fade
out run the game and we can make that
fade in if we wanted to write we could
do that in any number of ways I suppose
but yet that's all good and then escape
fades out the game faiths back in the
desktop and hopefully midlo that is what
you wanted that's about it not a whole
lot to say about that other than
hopefully we did what may blow wanting
and now you know how to fade the desktop
in and out happy birthday and again a
big thank you to Martin's mosaico who
reminded me of something that I
ostensibly taught on the stream earlier
but I guess I didn't teach it very well
because I myself didn't remember it what
I'm going to do anyway let's go ahead
and go to the Q &amp; A in case you have any
questions about what you just saw we can
go ahead and answer them now
midlo says casey you need one more state
to wait for alpha enabled window to show
because you might have the same bug when
you fade to desktop do you think that's
true because I don't I didn't think that
would really be the case and I'll
explain to you why I also don't see it
happen so I'm assuming I'm I'm right but
I don't really know so let me explain to
you why I didn't think I would have that
bug and here's the reason right so set
layered window goes through the Alpha
compositing phase and as soon as you
call it I believe it goes into the Alpha
compositing channel of windows which is
synced properly and does its thing so my
assumption is in here when you go from
an active to fading game right as soon
as we call SW ha as soon as we call set
fade win fade alpha that layered window
is active right then it's not going
through this path which goes through the
message pump because set layered window
is actually the call that updates the
window whereas show window is actually
just a call that kicks off the whole
message loop thing so my assumption is
there actually is no bug between these
two because this doesn't go through the
same path right there are different ways
of working that's my assumption again
like I said I don't know so until I see
a bug I'm going to assume that that's
true but if somebody encounters it doing
that please let me know and we can try
and reproduce it but that's my
assumption that wasn't midlo that was m1
al sorry didn't mean my blue
steel golem you're fading setup seems
overcomplicated me why not just take a
screenshot blip that to the back buffer
and fade that what platforms wouldn't
that work for so there's a number of
reasons why you wouldn't want to do that
one is you don't know if you can
reliably get a copy of the back buffer
for example suppose that someone is
playing an hdcp protected movie and has
paused it in the background well you
can't get a copy of that from the back
buffer because windows will prevent you
from getting copy that prep the black
buffer and so when you try to fade out
what you'll actually get is in the
instant where you transition from your
from the desktop to your buffer you'll
just get garbage where that window was
right number two what if there was an
alpha overlay right there might be a y
UV composite overlay that someone was
using on the graphics card this is like
an older thing that was often done but
still you know might be happening to
this day for all you know where there's
a color key and the color key is getting
replaced by the graphics card with a y
UV overlay that used to happen all the
time that wouldn't capture properly and
again you'd get that glitch right you
get that glitch on the transition next
one and there's like tons of reasons you
don't want to do it so I'm just listing
as many as I could think of so the next
way you don't really don't reason you
don't want to do it that way is because
you don't know what the resolution of
the desktop is right so what you'd have
to do first is you have to ask what the
resolution of the desktop is because if
you actually just create a back buffer
that's the resolution that you want to
run the game at right um and you know
you either going to change the display
resolution to your game or you're going
to just blit at the end do stretch wit
to put it up there or you've got the
OpenGL is going to go fullscreen who
knows what happens right if your
resolution doesn't match the desktop
resolution then on that part where
you're about to fade out everything
change it you know you get a it all goes
crunky because like let's say the
resolution of your game is 1080 x you
know 1280 by 1024 or something like that
right and the desktop resolution was you
know 2400 by whatever 2440 or by
whatever you're gonna the screen going
to first down res and then fade out
right and
so door to combat that you would have to
do something where you like you know
first created a back buffer that was the
resolution of the desktop copied to that
faded out in that closed that down
created a back buffer for your game
which was their games resolution bring
that up right and so now who's more
overcomplicated all of a sudden this
thing that was like less complicated
than just having this window is actually
way more complicated as we more things
that can go wrong right so really like
that's just a really bad idea and if you
can get away without doing that I don't
think you want to because doing the
faith this way goes entirely through
windows composite engine and so as long
as Windows is able to composite we're
good right that's what I would say why
are using a second window for the fade
in instead of just fading in the main
window very glad you asked that question
that is what I would have done a couple
months ago however I was actually
playing recently with Laird windows and
transparency and what I found was that
if you set the Laird window flag on your
window your performance goes to I won't
say the word on the stream because this
is for children as well we're trying to
keep this safe for children but point
being you don't get very good
performance setting the Laird flag
actually reduces your performance
dramatically and I don't know if this is
necessarily true for stretch blit which
is what we're using now but it is
definitely true for OpenGL which is what
we will use eventually right and so you
absolutely positively one hundred
percent in no way ever ever ever ever
want to set the Laird window flag if you
are trying to do high performance
graphics it's just doesn't work it's not
the fast path for OpenGL so there's just
problems in the driver I guess where
whatever it has to negotiate with
windows just isn't right so yeah I would
love to actually do it that way that
would be way more sensical
but it's just it's it doesn't work in
windows it's unreliable in terms of
performance midlo wow thank you for such
comprehensive answer to my question
that's exactly what I wanted and they're
small one would it be possible to make
bits of the window transparent EG for
the situation where some monster or
Monstar as you said has torn a hole in
the game window revealing to us a leaf
unfortunately no it is not possible for
the reason I just said which is to say
that technically you could totally do
that with the layered window things but
performance wise you can't because for
some reason you get really bad behavior
when you go through that layered window
path like I tested this myself and
literally just setting the flag even if
you did not use it meaning even if you
were still at full opacity so there was
no actual transparency occurring just
setting the flag reduced OpenGL
performance dramatically but
dramatically okay very measurable number
of milliseconds and again maybe that's
fixed in you know Windows 10 or
something so maybe you could do it on
certain Microsoft platforms but
definitely on the platform on the
machine that I was even testing on it I
didn't have to go test it on like
hundreds of machines find my dev machine
it didn't work
mr. Forrester mentioned suppose your
Microsoft but instead of wanting all the
money in the world you just want to make
a living selling your operating system
do you think you could do that while
providing a good way for users of your
platform to debug the code that uses
your API yes I strongly suspect that you
could because I'll be honest I really
don't think there would be much
difference to Microsoft's actual
business model if they just flat-out
ship the source code to everything but
like you know the kernel level stuff you
know like shipping the source code you
user32 would not change Microsoft sales
at all at all at all in fact it might
increase them because people could debug
it better and security researchers could
find bugs faster and like help patch the
OS and all the bugs in it you know so i
think they absolutely could because no
one is going to step through kernel code
anyway unless you're a really really
hard core and have a kernel debugger set
up which very very few people do so you
don't need to ship the source code to
all the other stuff but you could
absolutely ship the source code to the
higher level stuff and like if there are
certain parts which you don't want ship
like don't ship those parts but like
Microsoft off already ships symbol
server which has like the symbols for
like stack traces so you do know we're
in the code you are you just don't get
any actual source you just only could
see the like assembly right I think they
should just ship the source of that just
forget it just shift the source and and
then people could just step through it I
don't think it would affect their
business model at all if anything have
to go ahead and prove it
hmm let's see do have any other
questions insofar as can you not unset
the Laird window flag after doing the
fade so do not 100-percent quote me on
this but i am ninety-nine point nine
nine nine nine nine percent positive i
tried exactly that and the answer is no
if you like what you might be able to do
and i don't know because I don't think I
tried this but what you might be able to
do is unset the Laird window flag
destroy the OpenGL context and create a
new OpenGL context or something like
that or only create the OpenGL context
after you unset the Laird window flag or
something that might work because it
might be that that it's when you create
the OpenGL context that it does it I
don't know right I don't know but simply
on setting the flag is not sufficient
right so yeah so if you citizen you
really cared about a lot right you could
go do some more testing I did not test
it extensive I did not like exhaustively
sit down and see can I make this work
right I was just like oh whoa didn't
know that one ok I won't set this
anymore because it wasn't like critical
I was doing but if you were like no I've
got to make the thing that does this
then you might be able to do something
like oh I as I I do some rendering and
it's like slower and less efficient when
I do the transparent stuff but then as
soon as I'm untranslated do this other
stuff I like shut down the consecrate
new context forever like you might be
able make something work I don't know
but the trivial case of just fun saying
the flag I'm like I pretty much pause I
tried that and though it doesn't help if
all you do is on set the flag that
doesn't restore the performance
you
steel column wait why can I alt print
screen to capture hdcp with Windows but
I can't take a screen cap manually I
have lots of screenshots of my ps3
through the player via print screen so
it depends entirely on what they like I
guess who I should say is what the
content protections actually are is my
understanding so for example I don't
really know I don't really know what
like I don't know the details of the
hdcp spec if that makes sense and what
you are not allowed to do all I know is
that it's definitely possible for it to
be prevented it for it to be prohibited
for you to capture video it's like
full-on not even like you're not even
allowed to do it right so I don't know
what the circumstances are where that
happens but it definitely does happen
and the ps3 doesn't have hdcp by the way
by default right the ps3 will only send
out hdcp as far as I know it only sends
out a CCP if you're playing actual hdcp
media I don't think it it's not going to
turn on the protected flag if you're
just dreaming a game as far as i know so
i would say are you absolutely sure that
you actually use something with HTTP
actually tried to capture like an actual
frame of a movie or something that was
hdcp protected and did it have like no
screenshot as the thing blah 238 this
detour was all about startup and
shutdown fades but how would you fading
in between in-game scenes this shouldn't
involve the windows api correct yes so
once we're in our game so we're only
talking about fading between our stuff
that we just can do in our own renderer
right so that's nice because we don't
have to do we don't care when is at all
so feeding in and out to blacks really
simple that's just a case of modulating
20 and if you see we've actually already
got where is our Emacs window there it
is we've actually already got that in
I believe in handmade optimized otsuka p
so when we do drawn out quickly I think
we've got it yes so you see we've got
this color modulation happening here so
if you look at handmade render group and
who calls this you can see that when we
when we do this there's an entry color
parameter right there right and what
that does right is it modulates the
bitmap that we're drawing you know
whatever that texture is it module eight
sit by particular color so if you wanted
to fade something to black it'd be
really pretty easy to do for example
inside our cut scene that was happening
here we could do and I'll just sketch it
out for you if you want to do something
where you said like okay this particular
layered scene is going to have a thing
where it like fades you know from black
or something right I don't even know so
we just have a thing that's like fades
from black that's the thing that you set
then you could do something and in fact
I could even do something like a fade in
you know T fade in I don't know right
then what you can do is when we create
these layered scenes right you can kind
of see that all the Laird scenes
happening here that I'm like that first
shot if you want that fateful blackridge
to say like okay it you know ten percent
of the way in I want the fade to have
been completed right and everyone else
doesn't have it set to anything then
what we do is when we do render cutting
the time we go through the shots we
figure out whether we've got a shot we
said we're going to render a particular
layered seen off we come right inside
rendered layered seen we have teen
normal okay and what we're going to do
is we're going to say what's the Alpha
value for this right what's the Alpha
value for the global thing right what's
the or i should say alpha but the global
fade value right the whole shop whatever
that shop date is so you know seeing
fade value so seen fit value is going to
by default be one which means that
you're going to see you know the scenes
just fulbright but what we're going to
do is say okay if T normal is less than
whatever the scene says it's t fade in
is whatever that is if that's the case
then we're going to set the scene fade
value equal to the map that like a map
of smooth 021 based on that whatever
that time period is
and we already did that we already know
exactly how to do this right we did it
down here where we do right here right
this this function right here clamp zr1
map terrain sing between these two and a
value that lies between these other two
values I want you to give me a number
from 0 to 1 that tells me how far
through there I actually am right so I
go in here and I say okay give me that
we know it comes between 0 and whatever
the fade in value is and I've got mighty
normal value and so I want you to map
that out into my fade value now I've
just got a color right and that color
can just be the scene fade value every
time now remember i'm not sitting the
alpha here this is not an alpha fade i'm
not making it transparent what i'm doing
is i'm making it black right i'm
starting it at black because if i
multiply every color by 0 r g and b x 0
i get black if i multiply them by less
than 0 right I get you know a fade to
black so one will give me the color 0
gives me black anywhere in between there
lets me fade to that black right so now
all I have to do is every time i render
a layer I just give it that color right
so after we get the bitmap out we do
whatever the thing is we're doing here
then at the end I just past that color I
say that's the color I want you to use
for the bitmap right so now when we do
it you know we fade out we go to black
and then we fade back in right and
that's it and now we can control that
fade value by using that 0 to 1 look
maybe you want to fade in a little
slower me you want it you know let's say
I want a really slow fade instead of
that 0.1 value that I stuck in there I'm
just arbitrarily right I could make it
take half you know ten seconds to fade
in if I wanted to and now we fade out
and then we slowly fade back in again
right and and and that's how that goes
now there's a problem with that I think
I have to think about it which is that
it's in the wrong alpha space so what we
probably need to do like if you want to
be correct about that is like I is we
need to make sure that alpha
is is gamma corrected Elsa I think this
is we're kind of out of time so I really
don't wanna talk about that right now
but it's going to be ramped wrong so
really what has to happen with that
scene fade value is you have to go like
and I don't really remember where this
was probably in math I don't know I
don't know no no remember no
recollection whatsoever none yeah I just
don't know let me let me double-check
that I'm actually right yeah I mean see
that just gets that just get straight up
used right so that's it's going to be
like the wrong it's going to modulate
its modulating in linear space I believe
largely by incoming colored go from srgb
to linear brightness space oh weird no
we modulate the textures beforehand well
that seems really wrong to me so I guess
I was right we would have put the gamma
but that's only because of I think we
did this wrong would you agree with that
assessment look I feel like that's just
wrong oh but that's the desk that just
being loaded out so never mind where do
we do that that's a desk that I was
looking out there so where does this
happen where does this happen when we do
the mole PS what are those texels in
when we load those out unpack brother in
your samples so these all get unpacked
srl I epi 32 blah blah blah original
desk here we go convert excerpt from 0
to 25 that's hard to beat a linear so
they're in linear
so I feel like that should be okay I
feel like that should be okay that's
think about that because if they're if
they're in linear and we're multiplying
by linear that feels like that should
work so I'm not really sure lets us save
that because you notice what happened
when I did that over slow time period at
right it ramps up in like a very
nonlinear way to me that at least that's
what it looked like to me and so that
looks more like the gamma curve was not
being applied correctly in some way that
died am NOT doing like so something is
not right right something's not right so
that's something that to look at that
might be something good to look at
tomorrow anyway there you go and we're
on time so that's it so you're just
going to have to deal with the fact that
we are out out of time just straight up
at the time just like out of it all
right so that's it i will i will wrap it
up for today and i'm going to say in
here to do okay see why does this fades
seem to be wrong it appears nonlinear
but if it is a linear brightness
shouldn't get a pure linear and maybe
that's just we're not understanding it
properly or i don't know what but i
would like to know what's going on there
because i don't really understand so
leave it that close it down alright
thank you everyone for joining me for
another episode of handmade here at some
Podrick coding with us always if you
would like to follow along with the
source code you can always do that by
pre-ordering the game handmade hero org
this little handy dandy pre-order button
it comes with a source code so that you
can download it and follow along with
everything I do and it comes to the art
pack too so if you can play around those
cutscenes just like I am maybe you can
figure out why the fade is wrong before
I do will challenge for you we can go to
other places to the forum site place to
answer quick get your questions answered
ask
about the series all sorts of good stuff
like that there's an tied episode guide
up there you should definitely check out
there's a patreon page you want support
the video series you can pledge to that
very much appreciated we also have a
tweet bot between schedule at you and
that tweet bot will tell you that we are
off tomorrow we are off tomorrow because
it is the Molly rocket holiday party
quote unquote but we will be back on
Wednesday 5 p.m. pacific standard time
so i will see you guys then when maybe
we will look at the Alpha problem and
see why that fade was was it's not later
who knows maybe we'll figure it out or
maybe we'll do something else who knows
only one way to find out and that's to
come back love to see you until then
have a good time programming and I'll
see you guys on the internet take it
easy everyone