hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could complete game live
on stream I have an announcement to make
at the beginning of the stream here that
is basically it's you know it's it's
more or less handmade hero job job
listings I guess is what I would say and
hopefully there's enough people out
there watching to maybe help out with
this so let me let me give you the
rundown so a fellow I know his name's
Alex Austin and he's been a game
developer for a long time and you may
know some of his games if you follow
indie gaming in fact if you were around
for the original Humble Bundle I believe
that you would probably know his work so
he did gif which was a game with Edmund
McMillen he did a hockey game I think
just called hockey question mark can't
matter what it's called he did golf for
workgroups and he's currently and other
games too but he also now is working on
a game called Subrosa and you can find
this game on on the web here and
actually see what's what it's about
it's basically a game where in you you
know you you sort of play
this trying to I'm trying to think of of
what the the right way to describe it is
you are in a city and you have teams and
rather than be like a simple kind of
deathmatch or capture the flag kind of
thing where the teams try to shoot each
other over some objective I it's
actually a game that involves a handoff
so there's at least three teams one team
has a disc another team has money for
the disc and the third team has neither
and the goal
for the team with the disk to sell it to
the team with the money in exchange for
the money however in some sense that's
not really the goal either the goal is
just to get the money really and so
there's many ways that can go down the
team with the disk can arrange a drop
with the team who has the money and you
know you can actually do legit exchange
and if no one gets an itchy trigger
finger it doesn't erupt into a firefight
and it's fine but the third team could
always stumble in on this and you know
start shooting and whatever so it's kind
of a game that's about taking the
standard grand theft auto mechanics
where there's cars and people with guns
and making sort of a standard Hollywood
style drop be part of it so there's you
know plenty of deception and saying
you're gonna meet someplace when you're
not actually going to or you know don't
actually bring the cash or you know
doing sort of the thing where you both
put it down on the ground and step away
slowly so it's it's a interesting take
on first-person shooters it's been
around a while and it's published by
devolver digital and the long and short
of it is he's the only programmer on the
project and he needs a second programmer
on the project so there is contract work
that's going to be available for this
game and like I've said many times it's
always hard to find engine people people
who can do low-level code work it's an
entirely C engine so it needs to be
somebody who understands how to program
things like we program on handmade hero
you can't be throwing templates into the
mix it's not going to work you won't
even be able to build and so if this is
something that interests you feel free
to to bring it up contact me you can
actually at the end of the game on the
chat if you want to bring it up or you
can just mail me
people know how to contact me or you can
find Alex Austin on Twitter
and just shout directly at him but point
being get in touch this is him
and you know you can't okay it's got all
physics space movement in it as well so
it's kind of amusing into a lot of kind
of crazy things with the system but
anyway just wanted to put the word out
because like I said engine programmers
are hard to find the type of people who
watch handmade here are kind of probably
the people who could help out here
getting the project finished so if that
sounds like something you'd be
interested in again I make I am not
involved in this process whatsoever I
make no warranties about the job or vice
versa I told Alex I am NOT vetting
anyone for it either so I'm simply
acting as someone who lets you know that
job is out there and maybe you want to
see if you can get it I know nothing
about the project or its state I don't
vote for it and I won't vouch for you I
am totally disinterested third party
although I guess I'm interested enough
to say I like Alex and wanted to help
him out so we'll save that but I make no
warranties to anybody I just want to
help get people connected and then I
trust that the two of you can figure out
whether you would work well together or
not so there you go so you've got the
information now and this is obviously in
the main part of the hand-made here of
video so it will be uploaded to youtube
if you need that contact information
later you can go get it from this
episode's video on demand okay so today
we are going to start working with our
tags file we have a typo in there that
has been noted and so we've got to go
take a look at
at what we've got for for bugs in there
in terms of our data entry you know no
one ever said I was great at clerical
but let me go ahead and load it up the
project here and we'll load up that that
source aren't there
oops that is in tags and you know so
here's another thing remember I was
wondering whether I should put these in
a separate directory or not so here's
another thing that's actually kind of
nice is that since these hht files are
here I could auto load them as well when
we load the project by saying load
everything in the tags directory in for
coder so that's another nice reason to
say that they exist in their own
separate directory because that just
kind of yeah it just makes it a little
bit easier on us
alright so let's address these two typos
that I made apparently I said under oops
that's not what I want
apparently I said undead and bones yeah
I did and presumably I only said that in
one place and then it looks like we've
got a hands that's marked instead of a
head and so let's just double check that
yeah so this is supposed to be a head I
don't know if we've got any other issues
someone was saying maybe there was some
missing common here one of the things is
that we probably don't need to worry too
much about it because at you know once
we build which I guess is what we're
starting on today once we build
something that compiles this it should
be able to report to us things like the
fact that the undead word wasn't in the
the set of things oh there's the missing
comma or that there's no comma between
things when there should be now granted
I guess to be completely honest with you
I don't know why I put a comma in there
there really isn't a need to have a
comma in there because it's not like you
couldn't just interpret a space as being
the thing that separated tags so I'll be
honest maybe we just shouldn't bother
having the comma in the first place but
who cares so I think I might just leave
it at the moment that way because
I just want to do that right yeah I
don't have another explanation for it
okay so what I would like to do now is I
would like to make a way to load this
tag file and make that be the way that
we get the information that we need
there's sort of two steps to this
process now we could get rid of one of
the steps right
and I'll sue that doesn't sound good
that sounds that sounds ambulance fire
engine II I hope that's not my building
otherwise the stream will be cut
relatively short so there's two parts
this process one part is parsing this
file that's really pretty
straightforward you see me parse things
before so we should be able to do that
without really encountering anything
that you haven't already seen on
handmade hero but the other thing is
that we need to be able to find these
files once they're described and there's
two ways you could do that one is that
we can augment this information here
with information about the complete path
so I could manually go and markup each
of these things with where it comes from
but I'd rather not do that what I'd
rather do is say look there's some rule
for how these things are found and once
you know that rule you can just know
where to look and we'll sort of scan the
directory for that you know piece of
information now this part may not like
we we may want to further say that this
part is just kind of hard-coded we could
make it so that we don't really search
sub directories we just say it has to be
in base game and then depending on which
one of these it is it'll either be an
art music or sound certainly could do
that but one way or another we're gonna
have to make a way to find these and if
we wanted to just search through the
entire directory structure including
finding them if you arbitrarily made
random categorizations of things here
and then anytime you typed Black Forest
dot oh you know oh one PNG it would find
it or something like that we also have
to have a way of searching sort of
through subdirectories if this makes
sense so we will have to address some of
these issues we're going to have to
figure out how to do a little bit better
file assessment then we were doing
previously because at the very least we
need some way of loading things out of
sort of a deeper nested hierarchy than
we have before because before we were
just saying we just iterate over just
the one
just the one directory okay so in this
schema I'm gonna go ahead and say that
probably what I would do is if we parse
this file we can parse the file and
create sort of an understanding of what
the assets are and I think we could
potentially look at this process as a
way of also giving us our like also
giving us a potential for how to make
placeholders for things so for example
if I have one of these one of these
things like a block and I give it a PNG
name that doesn't exist and I put tags
in there we could just have that thing
show up in the game and it could write
out a temporary PNG that is ready to be
filled in by the artist right because
before we didn't really have much of a
way of doing that we would have just had
to create the PNG ourselves in like
or something I guess but this would give
us a way right from the text editor also
to sort of say look there needs to be
other stuff in here and
just make those right and so that's one
thing we could do and it seems good
because as we develop this what's gonna
happen is we're gonna want to have
things that we need Anna to create our
for but we don't want to wait for her to
make the art for us to actually put it
in the game and get it working and so
this would give us also a really nice
way of just stubbing that out and then
we can just hand the game to her with
those placeholders that are generated
sitting there and she can just open them
up and draw over them and that's all
that needs to happen right and so that
gives us a pretty compelling way to sort
of drive that process potentially and
maybe there are some details that need
to get ironed down in there but that's
something we didn't really have a way to
do quickly in text before we would have
had to create an actual art file and so
this is one thing we might want to think
about is you know can we sort of create
that that opportunity to improve you
know what we were doing and so I think
that's a good idea and I think you know
what we could do is take in the art
directory you know we've got these
template files for example and one of
the things we could do is we could take
those template files we could draw into
the template file some like placeholder
garbage that's just what you know will
what we'll expect to see when we don't
have an asset for something that we
actually want and then we could take
those template files and copy those out
into like when we want to create a stub
we just have the game automatically
copied those template files into the
location that it wanted there to be a
file and that there currently is not a
file right it's so that's that's where
I'm at and yeah I don't think I have
anything else to say about it
I think that's it all right
so let's go ahead and get started I'm
just gonna do the basic thing you know
I'm not going to try to do anything
fancy at first and we'll kind of just
work towards getting to what I just said
if you remember we actually already have
in our project we have a thing that does
parsing right we have a tokenizer and
you can kind of see in here we've got a
bunch of stuff that we use to make it
work
this tokenizer is in our like was in our
meta programming demo that we did where
we just kind of made this simple
preprocessor right thing that we wasn't
designed to actually be used on handmade
hero it was just something that I showed
one time about how you might do meta
programming and so that's already there
and is capable of parsing see like stuff
and so we can just use this code and
make that into a thing that actually
exists inside handmade hero for real and
so that's what I would like to do now if
we look back at what's happening inside
handmade hero I believe you know inside
the asset builder we also do have some
token sort of stuff I don't remember
exactly how we were doing it to
completely honest with you because it's
been a while since we've been
programming handmade here we just got
back from break but if you remember
correctly we got this asset type stuff
and we sort of had a thing here that
would you know do some kind of crappy
HHA like that's it's not in there where
is the actual parse part of things I
don't actually know where it is let me
see what we've got here it's not in the
asset builder anymore is it
might be and non handmade types but it
might be in the HHA stuff which is in
file formats I'm not sure where we
actually put this let me see where we
call a tag ID from name it looks like
it's okay so it's in end tags so here's
the begin tag sirs the end tags I just
want to look at how we're doing the
parsing here so there's pop token right
so you see what I mean we kind of got
code that does this in here as well
right and it pulls tokens off lists in a
pretty undignified fashion right it's
just a simple thing and so you know I
think what we can do is say let's unify
these get a real tokenizer in here
because we already wrote one and then we
know that we're gonna be ignoring file
names from now on so we don't need this
nonsense here anymore so basically this
stuff can kind of go away right so
that's what I want to do so I'm gonna
make a handmade tokenizer here right and
in here we're just gonna populate that
by again going out to the simple
preprocessor and saying let's take a
look at what we had in there now I don't
know so it looks like here's our token
stuff right so I'm gonna pull that stuff
out and one of the things I might do is
we could still leave that this tokenizer
in I mean not leave sometimes we could
still leave the meta permian thing in
place we could still have it work and so
we might want to do that
if we hit build at the moment we still
can build the simple processor I don't
think it actually is being built at the
moment simple pre process or
there's the build line and here's us
running it so let me go ahead and build
it you can see it getting built there so
I can leave it building and I can even
run it if I want to and it produces
handmade generated H which to be honest
with you I assume is still sitting
around here because probably it would be
looks like so did we delete it or is it
in the build so I'm not sure I'm not
sure where this would have been in it is
would have been in build so it would
have created it in the build directory
and I guess we just never run this on
this machine so I'm gonna go ahead and
run it right and see oh that's fantastic
so this is good we've got an old
preprocessor that's kind of necrotic at
this point so let's just get that
reworking and then we'll pull the
tokenizer out and we'll share the
tokenizer across those two projects and
then we'll know that we've got something
that's in good shape so let's go ahead
and do an MS dev on that and and and see
what's going on there so simple
preprocessor we'll load that up and
inside here we'll you know set the
properties to the extent that we need
them I don't actually know what the
properties are it looks like there
aren't any it looks like it just dumps
to standard out I guess might be what
happens so let me see what does it do oh
it just reads these file names
I guess directly
I see so it just couldn't find the files
so it probably just asserted so it's
probably fine if I ran out the entire
thing yeah so never mind it's not
actually crash II it's actually just
asserting which is probably what it
should have done anyway so never mind
all right so that produced handmade
generated eh and so we can look at that
and verify that's actually building
something reasonable
so here's handmade generated eh let's
see it okay so it doesn't have anything
in it that may be intentional because
again handmade the simple preprocessor
was looking for particular tokens to
signify that something should be read
and I think we got rid of those so let's
just add one back in synthetically at
the moment just to make sure that this
thing still works so in here let's see
what's our keyword it's called
introspect and I'm loading like sim
regions so like if I go into sim region
eh if I just put like introspects in
here in a couple of these places then I
should get something I guess in turr
spec needed like a group so you know
maybe I'll just say this is the same
region introspection code or something
like that let's just say and so now if I
look at that generated code if I reload
this hopefully I get something so I
didn't get anything so that makes me
think that this is slightly busted
although it did give us an error so it's
at least parsing this when it said par
struct tokenizer
it looks like it looks like it would
have just print EFT directly in here
right
[Music]
so I'm not 100% certain what's wrong
there so maybe I will
Emma stove that and just see what
happens so I guess I have to set the
directory and I guess that handmade
generated oh you know what the problem
was the handmade generated does get does
get created in here because this is
where it this is where it actually did
the build so the fact that I ran it in
the wrong directory before was the only
reason that it generated this file so I
actually don't want to look at that one
so maybe it actually is fine so if I
look in the current handmade code
directory for handmade generated and
just look at it so there okay so it
totally is still generating everything
just fine and you know off we go
so that's all fine it's so our
introspection code is is just fine
and does exactly what we think it should
do and so let's go ahead and verify that
we can make the tokenizer
work sort of separate from that right so
if in here I want to do a comparison I
can take handmade generated and what I'm
going to do is I'm going to take this
age file that I know is what I expect
this thing to output using the tokenizer
as it was originally intended and I'm
just going to rename it to ma generated
original and that way I can run a diff
against them and see what the difference
is between that one and a new one so for
example if I run the code again it'll
generate the handmade generated and now
what I can do is I don't know if I have
a diff installed in this machine I do so
this is meld I don't know if we've ever
used this on stream before but basically
meld is just a program you can download
for free and if you've never seen a diff
utility before then you won't be
familiar with it but if you ever have
then you know what this is essentially
what it lets you do is load two files or
two directories or you know various
other things and seshu
any differences between them so you can
download it from here at meld merge
there's a get it button and you can get
it and then here is the two buttons this
is the Windows version that we're using
I think we might not be on 3.2 but we're
you know we're something along those
lines and so if I go ahead and open up
meld and say look could you please grab
w handmade code handmade generated dot h
here's the original here is the new one
right so it's the original versus the
new one and then I say compare what I
should be able to do now is I should be
able to let me see I don't know if
there's a refresh button I would hope
that there was but there might not be
okay so f5 does refresh so what I'm
going to do is let's suppose that I
broke the tokenizer right so in here
when it's gonna look for I don't know
when it's gonna look for pointer I just
it's gone
so it'll never it'll never say that
there's a pointer or better yet it just
says that the pointer is like an
identifier or something right
so it's just busted now when I run it
and I and I hit f5 I want to see it
break right
for some reason oh there we go so it's
asking me to reload I say yes and so now
I can see that it's not producing the
correct results so this basically allows
me to set up a standing test to verify
that what I think should be happening
with tokenizer is happening and so that
will allow me to check to make sure that
I haven't broken it as we go
so again just takes a couple seconds to
set that up it's an easy test to get so
I might as well
I'll get it alright so inside handmade
code I'm gonna open up handmade
tokenizer dot HD I already created it
but I guess I didn't save it to a file
and so what I want to do now is I just
want to put the sort of the the base
information that you actually need for
the tokenizer in here and I need to grab
like the support for the tokenizer which
is this stuff and I need to put that
into the C file the corresponding C file
so just cooling these out of the simple
preprocessor and I'm putting them into
this separate code that I will include
in both places so now in here where I've
got this little preprocessor now I'm
just gonna want it to say okay you can
go ahead and grab the handmade tokenizer
and use that instead of having to you
know implement your own and that way
both programs can share it so I'm gonna
go ahead and compile it and I think we
what is what's the problem here
handmade took in our study H I isn't
there a handmade took a nicer dot H it's
right there what's the problem is it not
in the right place so it turns out I put
neither of those in the right place
where did I put them probably in the
build directory huh
where did they go I need some way of in
in for coder to say where stuff is
better I get confused about that a lot
and I don't necessarily know where
things go when they're created once
they're created I don't have to care
so here we are it created them in the
tags rectory because that's where I
happen to be at the time yeah not what I
wanted there we go
so ignoring that slight inconvenience
okay
so the simple preprocessor just gets
compiled again and you know it should be
like I said here it should just be
identical because I haven't done
anything yet right and so the first
thing I want to do is I don't want the
tokenizer to be working on C strings I
want it to be working on length style
strings and so you know you can see that
the tokens themselves already have this
structure they already have a text
length and a text so really the only
problem is that the tokenizer itself
does not work that way
so the tokenizer is based on null
terminated strings so the tokens I can
trivially convert to strings
very easily it's just going to be the
tokenizer
checking that actually needs to get
improved okay so what I need to do here
is I need to look at the definition of
string you can see here that it's just a
buffer and a buffer is just a counting
data right and so what I need to do is I
need to sort of import this as something
that's going to happen into my my code
here and so I sort of need this to
include handmade shared which means that
the simple preprocessor wants that
information right so in here I'm going
to try to do that here's handmade shared
age and I probably will need some other
things like it probably needs like
handmade platform that H probably not
sure so let's take a look at what it's
complaining about there for V fours and
in fact then I think about it really
that buffer stuff should probably be in
the platform part because that's just
sort of a fundamental type
we could obviously just put it in here
now I think about it yeah in fact that
is handmade types why did I think I
needed handmade shared good question
Casey um so if I get handmade types then
I can get the tokenizer and that would
allow me to say look there's a string in
here that's just the value of the token
right and then I should be able to
basically port the code forward without
doing much work just looping through the
errors here that I have and fixing those
so like I said in here if we look at the
type it's just counting data so anywhere
there was a text length is now just
gonna be like you know text length is
gonna be valued count right and really
it's just a straight replacement and
then it should work so then the only
question is well what about text which
is this one that one's a little bit more
difficult because again it's a you eight
pointer because we don't really use care
pointers in handmade here oh but no big
deal right it's still something we can
handle pretty easily so a dot text is
really gonna be a dot value dot data
right
and then we'll compile again so then at
that point really all we have to worry
about you can see well there's really
not many so it's very very few right so
other than the ones that are in the
preprocessor which we'll deal with in a
second you can kind of see that we have
very very few things here that we
actually need to fix and they're all
exactly the same thing they are because
the tokenizer itself is still using a
null terminated string right okay so I'm
gonna kind of cheese this out for a
minute here and say I'm gonna cast these
two you eights knowing full well that
pretty soon I well in fact I might even
do this so we can just see this in a
second and and remove it because I don't
actually want it there
in the long in in the eventual system it
will get removed so I want to oh don't
ask me why I put up Prentiss ease around
that which was not at all necessary and
so now if you look there are no more
errors in the actual tokenizer so the
tokenizer itself is self-contained and
uses the string the only difference that
we're getting errors from now is that
the preprocessor which uses the
tokenizer that is not so if you look at
where that's happening you can see it's
mostly when it goes to try and print
things out you can see that it's
grabbing those things here and having
trouble right but again same text
replacement will work here so where I
was saying dot text length before dot
value dot count will suffice
pretty much for everything no big deal
there right and the same is true for
text so every word that I was seeing dot
text I can do dot value data
lovely and so now of course we can check
and say make sure they're still
identical they should because we haven't
really done anything we just changed a
little tiny bit of it but now let's take
that one extra step and say okay the
tokenizer itself is going to need to
operate on strings not carry stars so
what I need to do now is sort of change
the way in which that tokenizer was
operating which will involve some
significant changes because while some
of the things like these comparisons
will be just fine some of the other
things will not be because there will be
issues regarding how Jimmy regarding how
they check for the end of the stream so
that's really what we got to look at
here okay so looking back at the
tokenizer we want this to take a string
before I do that actually let me just go
ahead and turn this into handmade Caro
internal style we'll turn those in lines
into internals and we'll turn these
pools into b32 X's just so we're more in
line with with the way that we tend to
mark things up in the code similarly
where I've got those intz I'll probably
fix those as well let me do that as I go
through it though it's not very much
code here it won't take very long
okay so we've got this stuff is end of
line is whitespace and so on and what
I'm curious about is do we have
multiples right and what you can see
right here is we absolutely do we've got
two different versions of its whitespace
because hey unsurprisingly we had to do
that before and so we have a version of
is whitespace that's happening inside
some of the shared code here and that's
something that multiple people were
using we've got string hash of and so on
and so you can kind of get the sense
that these sorts of things already are
happening elsewhere and so I don't
really want that to occur also I kind of
want to do
listen here - this stuff should all be I
should really not have in line anywhere
we don't really need in line as a thing
I don't know why we've got it doesn't
really do anything um so anyway let's
let's just look at making sure that we
don't have duplicates here this stuff is
all in the shared code I believe and
again you can kind of see that's in here
we've got a like mostly string sorts of
stuff you can see that there's just a
lot of string based stuff in here so
what file is this actually I'm actually
know which file this is it is handmade
shared so the interesting thing about
handmade shared like looking at it is
that it's almost all string utilities
it's like all string memory utilities
which is kind of kind of odd um so yeah
and if you look at like this stuff is a
little bit out of place like getting the
debug color that's why those like v3 is
before dependencies were in there so
what I kind of want to do is sort of
delineate this code a little bit better
let's find a place for those debug
colors that makes a little bit more
sense how about for example in like some
of the debug actual files like can we
just put that in here
like is there any downside the bat just
what I'm wondering like could I just
have done this and does that work right
and I don't know if that's a problem but
so in entity an in-game editor there's
our third why aren't there is that
because the debug the debug dot H file
wasn't included or what right because
here it is which which one are we in
here have made us CBP yeah I'm not sure
why why that wouldn't be there so debug
dot CPP is there but debug H I guess
isn't so we keep that included kind of
out to the back if so I'm not sure like
we're the best place for that to go
would be right it's a little bit tricky
to say but I really want to split this
into two because I really just don't
find that to be appropriate you know um
what I might do for now is just I might
go ahead and say let's put it in here by
the way this is such busy work and
nonsense like if c plus plus had ever
added a proper parsing model you
wouldn't have to care where things went
right it's kind of ludicrous that you
ever have to but that's just no par for
the course so anyway I can just put them
in handmade for now and they can just
sit there is something that people can
access but that way I don't have to
worry too much about that and then
inside the the preprocessor I'll include
that shared code right and we'll take a
look at what has to happen there
perfect and so now I also am getting an
error on those multiple-- defined
functions which is even better that
means I don't have to go remove them
myself I can have the compiler tell me
that there are two and so all I really
want to do now is say look at the two is
end of lines and I just want to get rid
of one of them I want to get rid of the
one that's in the tokenizer and use the
one that's in the shared set but I just
want to make sure that they're the same
and so there's is white spacing is end
of line so in here I don't know if we've
gotten is alpha anywhere it looks like
we've only got one of those so I would
say these also should probably come out
in here as things that can be used by
anybody and so then we're just left with
the ones that are actual token you know
tokenizer based operations and that's
good so now what I've done again just
really tiny little baby steps that just
get things into a good position I now am
running the the simple preprocessor so I
know there's a test case it's producing
the correct output I know that I've got
a parser running on this tokenizer so I
know that it works and now what I can do
is make that one last change that I
wanted to make and what I want to make
here is a thing that says here is the
input to the tokenizer
and it can run very very straightforward
right so let's go ahead and do that in
here where I create the tokenizer in the
first place wherever that is yeah
so I'm not crazy about this the reason
I'm not crazy about this doesn't give
any structured place for initialization
the tokenizer and I probably want
something like that to happen because
maybe I want to set some additional
parameters or whatever so I probably
want to stop this way of doing
initialization and what I would like to
do is I'd like to move to something a
little bit more specific so I'd like to
be able to oh and let's get rid of these
statics while we're at it - what I'd
like to do is move to something more
like this
hey I'll give you the string - tokenize
you give me back the tokenizer right and
so then I can just say all right the
results is just going to be copying this
in and returning it but at least then I
know I have a structured place where
that's occurring and I can fuss with it
later and so then you hear what we'll do
is we'll say hey let's tokenize this we
want to organize the final contents but
of course the file contents are a string
now so the care star isn't going to cut
it what that also means is read entire
file into the memory and I'll terminate
doesn't need to be none anymore they can
just be read into a fire file into
memory and it can return a string itself
which is nice that means I come up here
and again this simplifies this piece of
code quite nicely for us in here when we
actually do this we no longer need the
plus one instead all we have to do is
actually just do the read and when we
produce that result which we malloc
right we can now just bundle those two
things up into the string result in one
go and so the way we would do that is
say oops that we would not leave
ourselves in command mode otherwise that
happens instead we would say start with
a null result so if we return it the
person knows there is nothing in the
file or we couldn't open it who knows
again this is just for the symbol
processor so we really don't care but
then we say ok the result count is gonna
be whatever the file size was you tell
me the result data is going to be
allocated by this handy little malloc
call here we're gonna read into that
piece of information based on the count
into the data and then instead of saying
a null terminator we're not going to
bother
because now we're returning the size
that means all of this stuff flows
nicely and works exactly as it should
however now you can see all of our
parsing is busted because we change from
having a cursor base null-terminated
input to having a string based input and
now we have to go deal with that but you
can see there isn't much else that's a
problem here
I accidentally here forgot to replace
that result count so that's not really
something we have to address read and
tariff on to memory we've got to rename
and then tokenize we have to fix right
it's just a R that was missing so that's
really it for the mods to the using code
very straightforward which is great but
now we have to go back to the tokenizer
and do the more difficult work so if we
look at what's gonna happen here token
equals is fine because token already was
a string like class and it has to do
this operation anyway we probably don't
have to actually use this anymore
because strings are equal probably
exists for a string you can see it right
here this is the code we actually needed
so I believe that we can effectively say
you don't actually need to call this
instead you know you could just do this
because again we already had that code
now info and you know what it's we even
had an even simpler we already have one
that cracks it for you too so it's it's
actually that it's it's that simple so I
think you know that becomes pretty
obvious and presumably that's all we we
need to do there this code can be
eliminated as soon as I verify that
everything's fine and there wasn't
something strange going here and think
of so that's just fine so now we're down
to the code we actually have to play
with and what you can see here is if you
change from nil terminated strings to
length based strings which I highly
recommend by the way I think length
based rings are the only real way to go
literally everything that you ever do
gets easier with length based strings
except one thing and it's this thing so
checking for tokens by hand is the one
thing that gets harder I don't know
anything else that does every other
piece of code usually gets easier not
this one
right so there you go but that's what's
gonna happen so I in here when we have
to do something like you know whitespace
this obviously will work just fine
because what we can do is anytime we're
looking at one character we can just
first say that this is while there's any
left in the input so here I can say
while you know tokenizer input dot count
that lets me know that there is
something to check in the buffer still
and not nothing
that means anywhere here where I'm
checking at zero will just work but any
where here where I'm checking at one
won't right however I can cheat okay
there's a pretty easy way to cheat one
character look ahead token lookups and
that's just pre do it
so what I can say here is I can say at
zero equals tokenizer input data zero
and then I can say at 1 equals tokenizer
input data 1 the problem is this right
will crash bomb on a site crash but
it'll read off the end of the buffer at
least if the count is not greater than 1
so what I can do instead is just say
let's make sure it has to be right token
as their input count is greater than 1
then I use this it's otherwise a zero
right now all of this code just kind of
works because all I have to do is just
look at the two pre-prepared values I
have and everyone's happy right no big
deal how it we now have the problem of
how do we advance I probably should have
done all that removal by the way because
I'm kind of doing to illustrate a point
but we're about to do another change
that will probably make it not be so
good right so how do I advance now
because you know I I need to move this
forward and so like all these statements
have to have moving forward
and these things won't get updated
properly if I update it and then check
them again right so in addition to be
able to update each time through the
loop I have to be able to update it
maybe more frequently like right here or
right here right well as you might
expect I can just make this be more
systematic I can make the tokenizer
itself have its read ahead buffer
actually be something that's updated out
of the regular buffer right now again
maybe this is a little bit of a cheating
kind of thing I don't know how you want
to look at it
I just find it to be kind of convenient
right so what I can do here is say okay
suppose we left it the way it was and
just said look let's actually make there
be a thing in here that is caressed are
at but maybe it's not really at because
I want to go through the code and change
it so that we're not ever incrementing
that pointer or something right so we'll
call it something else which is just
like you know a and there's two of them
or something right
then from then on I can just have any
time I would have been doing a plus plus
I can just call advance an advance takes
however many characters to go forward
right so oops maybe something like that
advance cares so now any time I was
doing this I can just call advanced
cares like so and that moves my
tokenizer forwards in the same way that
it used to but I can still keep all of
the checking exactly the same cuz all I
have to know is what's the farthest
ahead that I ever look and I just make
sure that I actually have that right
makes sense I'll leave it as that for
now what what the hey live dangerously
pretty straightforward right and so then
if I come down here to this code I can
do this stuff exactly the same way if I
want to write I can say okay this is
this is gonna be advance cares to open
answer one right so I do this kind of
nonsense I just say well I need this
thing to be whatever the actual you know
string is that I would get instead of
doing it that way
why had to say you know what there was
is just gonna be whatever the input was
and then you know if the count was valid
at all it's one so it'll either be 0 or
1 based on what we have so we initialize
this basically the same way but we do a
little check there and so then we say
all right grab that see out and then
advance one so we're just gonna eat one
character I don't really that's the best
way to do this but that's how we were
doing it so we'll just stick with that
for now
all this stuff just works if it wants to
read one token if it doesn't want to
read one token then it has to do this
sort of thing and that's fine too
right so again we can kind of do the
exact same thing that we were doing
before so at this point we can just say
that the token value is going to be the
tokenizer input that just works and it
just has the wrong count so then all we
have to do is actually get the count
correct so as we do this I'll do
advanced cares advanced cares and in
here where we're doing this difference
this difference will now work properly
so I can just say look the input dot
data minus the value dot data that gives
me the correct count for my token and
we're done right so that should work as
well in here all of this stuff should
still work and you can see that nowhere
in here have we ever looked past that
second character either right so we
believe or like you know we don't have
any reason to believe that that won't
just be fine
off we go we do need our parse number in
here so we should probably enable this
but we'll cross that bridge in a second
here and then we're good so now we've
got the rest of this code doesn't care
really at all how these things are going
right okay so what I want to do now is I
need something here and so what I want
to do is every time you were gonna do
this advanced Kerris thing I need to
make that actually work and so I need
something up here that's gonna let me do
that motion right so let me go ahead and
and speck that in here so if I pass a
tokenizer and then I pass the like you
know the count here that I'm trying to
go forwards then what I want to do is I
have fundamentally two cases on the one
hand I've got the case where the count
is some amount that I could move
forwards and the other case I have one
where it would extend past the end of
the buffer right and so what I want to
do is say take the tokenizer input I
know that has a count if my count is
greater than the count of that thing
right then I want to clamp it and then
at the end I want to do a move forward
by that amount and then I also want to
reflect the fact that there isn't you
know I move it forwards and go right now
that's an operation that we would
normally have just advancing a string
and so I think we already have it right
I wanted to sketch it in there because
you know I wanted to explain what was
going on there but you can see here we
already have a thing that does that
exact operation right look at this it's
the same code right furthermore it will
return I guess the it will return the
part of the data that it consumed as
sort of a separate chunk which in this
case I guess we don't really need but
there you go so instead of even
bothering with any of this I can
actually
just say look advance this by that and
that's the end of it right so that's
even easier because now I don't even
have to implant that part of the code so
then the last part of the code I need is
I need to be able to have that at array
actually work so I need a way of saying
after I've moved please refill the at
buffers so at zero needs to equal
something and at one needs to equal
something right and so please do that
and if I structure it so that I've got
two of those it means that I can also
just call that same thing here so that I
don't have to treat startup separately
from moot from moving forwards right so
I'm gonna go ahead and do that here and
just say look I've got three cases
because and so I'm just gonna handle all
three right because why not so the cases
I have is I have the case where the
tokenizer value count equals zero I have
the case oops where it equals one and I
have everything else in the case where
it's anything else then it just works
right no issues in the case where I only
have one then I can set the first one
but the second one can't be and if I
have neither then I can set neither
right oh and don't ask me why I've typed
value when it's not value its input
all right so moving on let's see what
we've messed up you can kind of see here
that for some reason I I don't know why
I did that
what I actually meant to do was that I
was trying to assign the value there not
the rest of it um so when we do this
advance Chara's bit here
I forgot my comma looks like that's
about it and so now we have a parser
I'm sorry tokenizer that's running using
fixed length strings instead of null
terminated now we don't know if it works
it didn't crash but we don't know if it
works
let's check the files are identical so
it looks like it did correctly produce
the same results so hopefully that's
mostly correct now we didn't parse
numbers we should let's go ahead and
parse one of these numbers here so what
I'd like to do if we're gonna parse a
number I think we already have this
right we in the shared code there was a
way to parse like a like a an ASCII
thing like sp2 from ze right and stuff
so we've got these here right so we can
parse numbers well actually no what do I
care about parsing numbers
you know I probably do but I'm gonna
hold off on that because I guess we can
implement everything we were going to
implement today or you know the next
couple days without it so I guess why
complicate matters so now I have a
tokenizer that I can use to you know
grab all of that data that we were
creating in those tags files so it you
know in one of these guys here where
we've got this thing if now I just want
to parse that thing I should now be able
to do that now looking at it there's a
couple things that I'm gonna have to
augment my tokenizer to handle so let's
just do a little awed it and say what do
we got to add so you're looking here and
you say well we've got some identifiers
those will just work we've got strings
those are just work braces semicolons
equals commas braces semicolons
we don't have equals and we don't have
comma right so let's just start by
adding
going to the tokenizer it's pretty
trivial we can add any single character
things we want you know with no effort
so that's good and then we just need to
know do we support comments properly and
since eat all whitespace we'll skip the
commas first I can tell we don't have to
worry about the fact that this is up
there so should be able to parse this
whole thing right no issue um so let's
see we just go into the asset import
stuff and this probably needs to get
broken out at this point into like an
asset import versus the asset loading
but you know one thing at a time
so let's suppose we do have some code
here and we just want to parse one of
these things and say you know read the
whole thing let's verify that we can do
that right so let's suppose we have a
parse HH t I believe is what it's called
right and if I want to try and test this
outside of handmade here oh maybe it
makes sense for me to just put this you
know I mean I could even put this in the
preprocessor right but anyway let's just
try to make this be something you know
what actually let's just go let's just
go for the gusto let's actually put this
into its own own like handmade hht or
something right like I don't know and so
inside here will just write the parser
and then that way we can include it
anywhere we want to and it'll just work
right and that seems good so how will we
parse this thing well it shouldn't be
that hard there's not a lot of
constructs in this thing so what we'll
say is look you want a person hht a
great give us the input right just give
us the give us the thing and furthermore
I could just say look let's even just
say that you give me the tokenizer
so you've prepared it and you're just
gonna pass me and I'm gonna assume that
you've prepared to organize that I can
get tokens from and I don't care how you
got it into that stage just make sure it
works right and so let's do that if we
want to parse this thing then all we
have to do is say start by grabbing
tokens off the stream so you know here's
a token from the tokenizer look at the
type of the token right as you do and in
this case you know I could do a switch
here but really I don't need to um
because we only support one thing right
if the token is not an identifier it
doesn't matter right I mean that's not
an identifier at the root we don't
handle so you know this is the end of
parsing right here and we can choose to
issue an error or not you know based on
whether or not it's it's actually the
end so one way to look at it would be
well if token end of stream happened
that's great because that means that
that was the end of the file so we do
want to break but otherwise we could say
look there's an error in that case right
and that brings up another thing that we
want to do which is have some way of
handling how errors work right that's
something we'd want to do so we'll talk
about that a second assuming we get an
identifier then we just want to do some
way of like parse top-level block right
and we pass the tokenizer down and we
pass whatever the type of the thing was
like whatever that top-level block type
was right and so then we'd start here
and we'd say okay we're going to parse
the top little block that's all well and
good in the token that we passed down
here this is now gonna have to look to
see what kind of token that was
so of the token types it could be we
only have unknown set so we're basically
going to do something like this and this
would be an unknown type of top-level
block so in here when I have like token
equals toucan equals and so on we know
what those are going to be so it's going
to be default right block and then some
host of other things that we've got so
body character hand cover head item
obstacles and that's it that's all we've
got so far right so each of these we
would have some kind of parsing for
ambles kind of figure out how we want do
that
later on and we may want to roll these
into an array as well we'll kind of see
how we want to do that in a second but
assuming that we want a purse one of
those we would press it and we'd parse
the block up until the closing semicolon
and then in return there right and
that's all we would have to do should
call this block type or block token
so let's see what we've got with respect
to that information like what do we have
for the file formats like do we know
what those different types of things are
because we probably don't actually write
in terms of the parsable things but
maybe we do so I'm gonna go into hamid
asset and see like where is character as
a string right and so you can see it
here it's kind of doing this this
breakout here where it's got the you
know the different pieces of like tag
information that it's kind of generating
off of the fact that it knows you know
what the what the block had body a lot
so you know this is basically what we're
gonna do so in some sense we could go
ahead and pull this code into here
because this is literally exactly what
we're gonna do and they begin tags end
tags part of this itself is also exactly
what we're gonna do because exactly
which tags are in here that's what's
gonna get added to the tag set right so
it depends also on whether we want to do
an intermediary like whether we want to
create a standing data structure for
this or not that you know or whether we
want to weld it in directly in the you
know into this code because this is the
only thing that it really needs to do
and I don't know the answer to that
question unfortunately
that's a little harder to say you know
I'm gonna I'm gonna kind of put a pause
on that thought pattern right now but
this is basically all we're doing right
it's just this so assuming that we stick
with that right all of these things are
then gonna have a parse where they then
you know get the tags and other things
that might be associated with them and
if we go back to the way the hht works
you can kind of see that you know it has
like an author and description those can
appear here and then it has tags those
are the three things we know about so
far but we actually have some other
things that are going to happen as well
so remember we've got a line points and
so if we want to go look at what's going
to happen there we're gonna need to
store this information as well in here
so the P percent size and type that's
going to have to be stored in there
along with like it just says right there
these are generally imported from the
text file augmentation of the PNG right
and so we're gonna have to store that
data in here too we don't actually know
what that looks like yet but it's just
any textual representation of this so
it's gotta have these it's got to have
the scaling value and it's got to have
the alignment percent value and those
can just be represented by
floating-point numbers so that's that's
the time what I'll have to add the
actual number parser into the mix
because it's got to be able to be read
from this file as it goes
hmm whoa I did not get much sleep last
night
all right so working through that I
think all of these things basically this
head part is really more of like a piece
of type information this head obstacles
default block that sort of stuff
right and so what I'm thinking is I
think we kind of want to just table
drive that probably and go from there so
I think what I'd like to do is say you
know lock type here are my block types
and since really that's just something
that lets you know what the default tags
that should be I can just store the
deeps fault tag set somewhere and leave
that so the table driving should be fine
I don't think we need to you know deal
with anything more complicated
so then I can just do you know block
type index and for each one of the block
types that we've got then I can do and
if it's choking equals and say the block
type block type index order I go ahead
and check if they are great if they
aren't no big deal and then you know
it's an error if we never found one and
so for now I'll just do like a found
equals false and here I'll do with found
equals true and then we'll just say if
found else you know error and once we've
got that then what I want to do is say
well if we found one then we kind of
need to actually parse the remaining
components of the block so if I go into
this hht here I want to be able to grab
the rest of this stuff so at that part I
kind of need to do a thing that's like
going to get each of those pieces I need
to know what the file name is so I need
to do a get token there and what you'll
see if I create this codes you can see a
pattern emerges I need to do you know an
open brace right I need to do sort of
like parse all the fields here and then
I need to do a like close brace and
semicolon right and now in order to give
errors when something doesn't work I
need to be able to guarantee that this
is the case so I would be sitting around
doing stuff like well alright let's you
know make sure this like string is here
or whatever let me that's called
oops
not my intention I wanted to cognise
about age there we go
soo and here I'm like yeah yeah okay so
there's got to be a token string and
there's got to be you know an open brace
and then you know if not there's then
there's an error but oh wait you know
then I'm not really saying which one was
the error right so I'd really need to do
it like this in order to report that
error nicely right and you can kind of
see how that gets fairly tedious and I
need to do that for all of these it's
just it's not very satisfying to keep
doing that reporting and so what I'd
rather do is just have there be an
understanding that there is a concept
inside the tokenizer that when I want
only one particular type of token oh and
we already have it that I can just ask
for just that type of token right and so
that way I can do a require token I
don't know why it returns a bool it
shouldn't it should return the token so
that's just unfortunate right so what
this should really do is say
that right and then it should return the
token in question that's what should be
going on unfortunately that wasn't
what's going on but there you go now I
do have to then look back at my
professor and see how was required token
being used here right yeah you can kind
of see it was being used in and in these
cases here where it was like trying to
open the if block and that's probably
not what I want to do right like I mean
you can do it that way if we're going to
do it that way you would have to at
least have a way to point to the thing
that you wanted to actually get so but
it opens a valid question right and it's
the other aspect of this so once we
start getting into the mix you can see
that two things become clearer one is
we'd like to be able to do stuff like
this with this sort of syntax right so I
want to be able to do that's not what I
wanted right so once it looks like that
I want to be able to not have to do this
and I would like to know at various
points in time whether I should even
bother so I might want to be able to do
something like this and go that would
allow me to do stuff like require a
bunch of tokens and then just do one
check look are we still parsing or did
we hit an error condition and then don't
keep trying afterwards right furthermore
it would let me do this in these loops
so that if there's an error if they
don't just loop forever on the error if
you forgot to put a case they stop
looping when they hit an error right so
you can see how you can start to build
up the tokenizer into a thing that sort
of has
more utility than just getting the
tokens you can also put into there some
error handling right so I can have here
a thing that's like error you know and I
can also have a thing in here that
stores those errors for me if I want to
so you know I can have a thing that's
like structs you know tokenizer air or
whatever right but since I think we
already have the notion of a narrow
stream I think I'll probably just link
those up together we'll look at that in
a second but the long and short of it is
what I want to have is I want to have
therefore a thing that's like hey
there's an error call on the tokenizer
right and it allows me to pass some
message that says what's wrong
furthermore I'd like to be able to pass
the token in question so whatever the
token was that caused the error at the
point that I know about it I'd like to
be able to specify that because it might
be some token from further back in the
stream and I don't want to try to I
don't want a report mirror on token that
isn't actually the correct one right so
what this would do at a very minimum is
set the error to true but beyond that
it'll be like to do like hook up to an
air stream right so pretty easy here and
now what we can do is say all right when
we get a required token and in here I
can just say look when I got this token
that you asked me to get it was not the
kind I expected it to be right and we
can get better error messages later if
we need them by doing more work here but
at the moment this at least tells us
exactly what we need to know which is
what caused the error right okay so
that's pretty straightforward and now
this code again becomes very simple we
can also go back to the simple
preprocessor and make that work as well
so when you do if require token here we
can just make that again be an
now there's a couple different things we
can do one is we could say that here
when you do the open brace if it doesn't
actually want to do a par struct if it
doesn't actually want to raise an ear he
doesn't have to
we can also retain the old behavior
under a different thing which is called
optional token right and if you look at
what happens here you can see that we
had one here that didn't produce an
error message so that can still be after
token but here we have required token
and that we can rely on the actual error
reporting to occur right similarly in
here we could require that the word is
struct so you could actually make a
require identifier I don't know that I
really care about that so we're probably
not going to bother but you can see how
you can start you know continue to lever
those things up until you had a pretty
capable little utility there okay so I'm
gonna go ahead and put the optional
token part in as well so here we've got
require token we're also going to have
that same call that we had before I
probably just kept it and I could have
renamed it but I just wasn't thinking at
the time so here we just say look if the
token equals is arrow type then it's
it's the right thing right and we just
never issue an error so that's just
saying look here's an optional token if
it has up being this type you know get a
token if it's that type go tell me true
otherwise don't so we can still retain
that functionality just call it
something else okay so in here we can
say that there was an unexpected token
again so pretty easy on this token we
just say you know unexpected top token
you know whatever and in here same thing
like anything that was happening here
parse a little top of our block we did
token equals if we found one otherwise
here we can say yeah that block type
that you passed down
I don't recognize that right
unrecognized Loctite you know I'm saying
so off we go with that and then in here
we now have the way to do this checking
we want that parsing check to occur and
so the way we're going to do that again
is very very straightforward in here we
just have a be 32 that says hey tell me
if I'm parsing or not all that has to do
is say result equals tokenizer error
right if that's not set we're going done
deal right so in here the same thing we
can come in here parse all of the fields
that we have like so we don't have to
report in error because we know it would
have already got reported and then we
know that we have to require a
particular way of closing the tokenizer
here and so we expect to see the close
brace and the semicolon right so that's
all we really need to do to get the
basic parsing flow going now what we
need is some of the more specialized
stuff that has to do with what's
actually inside these files right but
we're basically good to go
let me handle that one error there yeah
so this one doesn't have to do an if
here this one can actually you know if
we wanted to do it we would just say it
like this but I don't even know if we
needed to do that if we could have
structure this a little bit differently
if we want to let's just verify that
that still works though because we've
replaced those let's verify that still
produces two correct results because we
may have made a little error there or
something but that's fine okay all right
so they require to can stuff should
presumably fine in here we've got the
case where we found a block that is one
of the types that we want and so now
let's just make sure that we can parse
the actual contents of that
Blagh and looking in here there's only
three things that it can actually be so
when we actually now inside here do our
loop
remember we're gonna parse as many of
these as occur in the block so actually
we can do this you know what I mean
where we actually do a while parsing and
go from there now I'll take this
opportunity to show you another
ridiculous trick that's probably too
clever for its own good and I don't
necessarily recommend it but I can show
it to you anyway
we'll get to that a second so let's say
I go in here actually know what I
probably won't even need it now so I
won't actually show the drinking
probably but anyway so what we're gonna
do now is we need everything in here to
basically be look I let's get a token we
don't know what it is if it's going to
be a close brace right good we're done
otherwise we got work to do
right and then I can get rid of this so
as we go through here we can then say
all right we then therefore expect it to
be a token identifier and we can process
that if it's neither of those two things
we're kind of done right then that's
just an error that we can't recover from
because we have no idea what you're
trying to say here right
or I guess I could say like expected
fields name but instead I got this
garbage
if I get an actual identifier out of it
then I can look to see what kind of
identifiers it actually is now I could
just skip this and say look it's just
too token equals instead and that's
totally valid we know what they are
they're author description and tags
right for these two there really isn't
much to it we're basically just gonna
get a token that has to it has to be
equals there's no other thing that's
allowed there and then it has to be a
string and then it has to be a semicolon
that's all that we get right and the
same is true of the description here
right that's what we have to do and so
we can get the description and we can
get the author and we could do something
with them but of course at the moment
we're just parsing so we don't really
have any thing to do but obviously we're
going to do something with those in the
future and then furthermore for our tags
here we now want to be able to parse
comma separated lists right and so what
I want to do there again is just open
another one of these because I can and
in here we're just going to continue
down now what I would like to do is pull
this out because I don't really want to
read too many nests in here again just
matter of personal preference you could
just leave it in there there's no
there's no right or wrong answer there
it makes it a little easier to read and
one way to move it out in these a little
harder in because now the person's got
to go up there so you know this it's
always a little imperfect in that
respect but so we have parks tag lists
we're gonna pass the tokenizer and say
hey you got a person's tag list for me
please do so
and so one of things I want to do here
is get rid of the equals right and then
I expect you to eat up the rest of the
tag list right and so when here again
I'm gonna say give me a token just you
know push it forward and then I'm gonna
say if the token is a semicolon then
we're done here if the token is an
identifier then what I need to do is
call the tag to ID call and if it's
something else were in trouble because
there shouldn't be anything else in the
tag list right or expected tag name at
that point we just need to know if we
got an identifier we would require a
token to be a comma if the next thing
isn't a semicolon right so there's a
couple different ways you can do this a
possibly smarter way than what we do it
is to have a peek token call we don't
really need one here so I'm not going to
bother so I'm just going to call this
comma Chuck
and I'm gonna say get the token and then
I'm gonna say like if comma check dot
type equals token semicolon then you
know we're good to go
else if comma check equals type token
comma then you know how about it oh this
actually has to happen here though
then we're fine
and I guess actually the way to put it
would be if it's not a comma at that
point we've got an issue there's a
couple other ways you can do that part
two again all of this stuff is just hey
when you're writing parsers by hand
there's a lot of different ways you can
kind of keep things compressed and not
have to type too much out and it's
really up to you which one you use and
how you want to do it anyway once you've
got that I think we're we're pretty much
parsing the file I mean that's it so you
know like 50 lines of code or something
and you're done so I don't actually know
exactly how we want to test this there's
a couple of ways we could do it what I'm
gonna do for now is let's just get it
compiling I'm gonna throw it in here
as you know handmade hht that's CPP the
asset system is going to want to call
that which is fine and we'll just do
this you know I go up to the hht file
here I assume those are soon here inside
here I can just say look this is the
call to that thing so if you want to
call it you know be my guest
and now at least we can compile it and
go get rid of the obvious compilers
stuff like that right so let's see what
the bugs are here we've got
the use of type Oh ask me why I did that
I don't know all right so the tokenizer
undeclared identifier right that's
because we have not yet put the
tokenizer in here so in addition we're
gonna have to put that guy in there and
that should probably moved up a little
further because that's going to be more
of a utility guy so he's going to be
done it's gonna be used by probably more
people than just the hhd I would imagine
but who knows I'm awesome typing those
two letters in order apparently so let's
go ahead and take a look at some of
these so you can kind of see here now
we've got the conflict and this is good
because now we're talking about merging
these two code paths in a sense now we
don't really care because this code
paths going away I could just nuke this
code path and be done with it um but you
know why not just take this part of the
code in and make it work in both cases
right there's no reason not to and so
what I'm gonna do here is just say all
right in the in the tokenizer case I
kind of think yeah maybe I was maybe my
past self a smarter my for yourself
maybe this should be called text not
value why do I think that because the
text is different than the value right
and so I might say that this is is a
little bit more how that should go you
know you know maybe you want something
more like this right where you got a
couple of different value types that can
happen like an f32 or an S 32 value type
on the token so let's go ahead and like
move forward with that as more of the
idea for how this is going to work right
and so for these wherever you saw result
value before so here
you is gonna have to become f/32 and
that's all fine you can see that really
wasn't much of a thing so whatever that
didn't really happen in very many places
but now we're gonna have to do is kind
of retcon that back and pretend to we
knew what we were doing over here
so everywhere that we saw something like
token value that's gonna have to be
token dot text right
and so that's unfortunate but again like
we just we screwed up look you know if
you screw it up you screw up I'm behind
my head I can't even see what that last
one was okay there we go that's fine um
so again same thing here so like you
know value dot count is gonna have to be
a text count right just fix all those
and similarly here like text dot data
I'm sorry value data it's gonna have to
be text dot data and so we're just kind
of cleaning up that you know worse
naming using the better one all right so
here for some reason I did require I
meant tokenizer it just I typed it wrong
there so let's just go ahead and fix
those and get these two things merged so
what else we got there
looks like error is busted in that one I
just missed in one of these
what is the problem exactly Oh block
type is not a thing this is supposed to
be blocked
okay that's just a naming fail uh I
think that's about it so now we release
it to do the parsing process and then we
have the ingest done and we have to
decide how we want to actually interface
it with the main asset system right and
that's kind of a little bit of a
boundary value problem you know think
about both sides like how do we want
this took up and do we need this parser
to operate anywhere else or can it just
literally operate in that one place and
you know I'm not sure right so I think
that's all we really need to do here
let's go ahead and try calling it just
as a simple matter of course on
something and see whether or not we can
get a reasonable result so what I'm
gonna do because I feel like it because
I'm going to go into the simple
preprocessor here and or maybe HHA edit
and just say let's call it from there
because it's easier
so inside HHA edit I think I've got like
read entire file right you know here it
is and
[Music]
so like looking at how this code works
I'm thinking maybe I can just drop a
thing in here that does like a parse and
maybe we just make that happen
right so just to give you some just give
you a little back home I'm sorry my here
so what if I just add a thing here the
slack all right yeah like if args 1 you
know instead of - create is like - I
don't know check each HT who knew who
knows great this would be something that
just runs the parser and then prints out
the error message just right and just
because I want a convenient way to run
this and test it and so you know it
would do this exact thing here it would
load that file in and it would have to
exist we would read it in its entirety
in fact I really just want the read
entire file does anyone actually call
that yes
so when Reid HHA it calls that but other
people don't use it or something all
right who cares anyway so if I was going
to do this I just say all right get that
for me I'm gonna say read entire file
and off you go
I don't care about any of this I can't
find it I say that and then here I'll
just do tokenizer tokenizer it was
tokenize I'm gonna pretend this returns
a string and then I'm going to called
parse hhd
so this probably needs to be a little
bit more robust than that
but I don't know you know maybe we don't
care super much we could look at that a
little bit later but now if I did this
that would give me what I want which is
the way to run this a little bit more
straightforwardly and simply right if I
go back to read entire file and I could
I could clearly say that this returns a
string I can't really say that the
hh-hey edit which already includes these
things can call that and so I can also
say in here too that you know handmade
tokenizer that age and handmade hht that
a chirp both in there because I already
have worked all that out so good news
everyone right so all that stuff is just
there and here we do read entire file
like I said this is kind of the the same
thing so if I just go to the
preprocessor the one I already had this
thing is basically the same but it uses
this file handle like assuming that
you've already opened it so really it's
just this code again exactly this code
again and so I should be able to just do
that here right like that and you can
see that this code is exactly the same
oops
so that's all good and this code gives
also exactly the same
so there you go so if we do the read
entire file on that then we've got that
ability to you know call that
tribulation to our file the fact that
that's clogging of datastore doesn't
matter we can just say that and it still
would work so we have the ability to
load it this way here we need to do the
open file so we do need this and that is
good actually because that loves to
check for the error which is what we
wanted to do so here we can do this and
print out the error message if we can't
find it so you know can't open file and
then here we'll get the file out we can
load it in and then we can F close it
not that it matters because it's not a
big deal so death in this case is
actually source because we're not doing
anything to the file all right so that
should work let's see I've got an issue
somewhere here I was missing a open
paren there we go and let's see so can't
convert argument oh nice so I think that
does it and now we could if we want to
just run this code and should probably
also at some point nuke the
introspection marker or spit anyway so
once I've got that under control I
should be able to call it check hht
which means I can step through the code
and debugger and see what actually
happens so if I go into here and say all
right let's load up a che edit which it
looks like we don't have in here so let
me actually call it chemist of W build a
che che edit dot exe so if I say
the properties on the sky and set the
parameters to like - Shrek hht and I say
you know we'll start with simple one
intro cutscene
hht yeah so start with a simple one and
try to run that so let's just step in
there and see and then we'll save for
next week the issue of how to integrate
things and how to debug this a little
bit more further right so let's try to
open it we're gonna read the entire file
we look at what the contents are or we
try to let's see here all right chances
aren't that is because we are not
building in debug mode and of course
Visual Studio can never find the results
of anything if you're not in debug mode
might as well not even be there alright
so let's go ahead and run
oops let's go ahead and run here we are
loading the contents there looks pretty
good we're going to the tokenizer let's
look at that refill make sure that works
okay should work fine and so you know if
we look at the state of the tokenizer
here you can see loading those first two
characters in setting the error to
nothing so then we go into the parse hht
we say let's see what we've got we
immediately get a token back and that
token is plate right 5 and there's the
pointer so we go to parse top level
block oh we didn't put plate in there
right we don't have plate yet we got to
put plate in there I didn't check that
one so we do want pleat as an as a valid
top-level block there we go and so let's
try that one more time
set a breakpoint here
okay so after initializing this I guess
I'll run to here we're going to loop
through and see if we find anything I'll
skip to the to the exciting conclusion
find is true or found is true so we did
find it we then have to require that
this thing is a string did we get back a
string turns out we did everyone's happy
so then we can continue parsing we get
the token back we look at what it is it
says it's a closed brace why do I not
believe you is that actually true
where's the where's the actual contents
of this file am I missing something
parce hht here's the file contents
so this is what I expected to see in
that file right where is it where is
that data I'm so confused right now okay
to someone want to tell me what's going
on is this just a for coder thing or
something so if I were to open another
for coder and go to tags in chore
cutscene it just wouldn't show up if I
was to open note pad would it show up
asking for a friend
well I don't know
that's a weird fur coder thing I'm
creeped out I don't know what's
happening there
so we'll have to look into that as a
separate thing but the good news is our
parser worked because it actually is a
close race is the next thing so it broke
out of this and it requires a token
semicolon I don't think there was one
actually so it sets an error which is
correct and we would have had the error
that there was expected semicolon we
then break out and we're done right
so I might set a breakpoint at the error
function and say let's run there it
should be an error and the error is that
there was a missing sound the error was
that there was unexpected token Tech has
expected a semicolon didn't get one
and so that's correct let's try loading
the more difficult one and see where
that gets to so here's our base game hht
and we'll run that we get in here what's
the error unexpected token type where
are we on that
we're on interesting so we're on the
open brace for default oh yeah that's
actually true so we actually have
another type here that we didn't think
of which is that when it's default it
doesn't need a name
so really what we need to do here is
handle default separately and it doesn't
need a file name
in that case right so that's actually
kind of tricky so we actually have a
token file name and you know I don't
know how exactly we want to do that but
here's one way we could do a require
token here and so we would do something
like
this I and we'd probably do some other
things here like set up where we were
writing to or whatever right but so
that's important actually so we had
forgotten that defaults don't have a
file name so that's a good one
and so now the entire fire file parses
properly
looks like right so hey good job we
wrote a parser for hht good to go next
weekend we can just use that data that
we get just parsed and off we go let's
go ahead and go to the
question-and-answer I see if I can make
that happen there
could the fork odor bug be it all
related to your in comment calculator I
mean certainly could low employee now
that we are using this method assigned
taxes this change how you plan to
organize lots of little items on a sheet
that may have differing non sheet wide
tags and in cases where using
significance of positioning in the
spreadsheet is too limiting for example
maybe collection of different fauna each
plant may have different tags for
attributes but cannot easily put into
categories yeah we could just have a
type that's like misc and then we could
just have it so that you have to specify
a tag per panel or something right yeah
so absolutely I just I probably wait
until I actually have that in front of
me so like when we do the cover maybe if
the cover works that way kind of you
know we can we can deal with that we
have some Advanced Pricing features that
are interesting to you but may be too
much working on this very for handmade
hero parsing is not really advanced like
what I wrote here is just all you need
really I mean you can that's pretty much
it right one of the things that you know
you would probably do if you were doing
a more real thing like something that
wasn't just made for a simple game data
file and you're trying to do you know
something else one thing you might do is
instead of just having a club called get
token you usually have peak token so you
can just look at a token or be able to
go backwards and forwards and tokens for
example so you don't just get them off
the input stream you can actually like
move around and the other thing is raw
versus regular tokens so when I do
parsers for a
sort of more industrial-strength use
Tilly what I'll do is there's one call
which is called get raw token and that
literally produces the next thing that
was seen in the input stream so if it
was whitespace it'll say whitespace as a
token that comes back if it was a comma
comment it'll say comment right and then
get token as opposed to get token raw
we'll just keep calling get token raw
until it sees a non white space or
comment result right that's really the
only thing that you might do differently
and the reason for that is so that you
can do things like write translation
layers that preserve the comments and
spacing of input things and only
modifying the tokens they actually care
about because you don't always just want
to understand your input you also
sometimes want to preserve it in ways
that are important and the other thing
that we would we will probably add this
though so I wouldn't say it's something
that we that is advanced it's probably
something else at is tracking the line
and column number so that just just for
it just for air reporting right
so
what is the community
are there things that recursive descent
is not good for or does it cut it for
them for most of the parsing stuff I
guess what I would say is recursive
descent doesn't really work very well
and if you're talking about that alone
and you'll notice that like I didn't
even do recursive descent so we do a
little bit of descent and we could have
recursion if we wanted to but you'll
notice even I did loops and stuff in
there right technically a recursive
descent parser would not have loops and
custom checking and stuff like that it
would always recurse to repeat right and
so I think I would say recursive descent
is not really good for anything other
than recursively descending it's one way
that you structure a parser by hand for
the parts of the parser that are
conveniently done that way like I want
to parse an expression here so I call
parse expression but don't parse the
expression with recursive descent
because recursive descent sucks at
parsing expressions right that's all
so things that are lists of things
should be parsed with a simple list
parser right
what is your opinion the Vulcan API in
its future I don't think it really has a
future except maybe as androids default
API so maybe that's where that'll be
I've talked about multiple time so you
can go look up in the search I wasn't
here for all face cream but it's
required took and what you'd use for
look-ahead No so for look ahead so
there's okay I mean I guess I didn't
mean to open up a Pandora's box of
parsing questions you know I was just
trying to say let's have the text file
that we can use you know so I was more
to typing in the parser because I wanted
to make sure that we had what we needed
I wasn't really trying to open the
bigger topic of like if you were gonna
write a compiler you know what should
your parser look like if you were doing
look ahead then there's two types of
look ahead that you have to handle and
one is like way harder than the other so
the type of look ahead that's easy to
handle is when the token types can't
vary so to give an example of that is
let's suppose that there's a rigorous
definition of every type of thing that
might get tokenized and anything that is
ambiguous grammatically can still be
just represented by a token the thing
gets disambiguated later and so the
example would be like in C and C++
you can pretty much do this I get a
token and yeah technically the grammar
wants to know something like is this a
type or is this an identifier and you
can't really know that without having
more context to the system but it
doesn't really cause a problem for a
fixed tokenizer because you can still
just call that like an indeterminate
name and then further up the stream when
people are actually trying to resolve
stuff they can go ahead and change how
they decided to
parce right but the tokenizer doesn't
have to care so that kind of look ahead
is easy to implement the way I do it
typically is I tokenize the whole darn
file and I actually just have the parser
work on that right that way they can
jump all around they can look as me
tokens in as they want they can reverse
back to previous tokens they can do
whatever they want so I just tokenize a
file and then you operate on the tokens
done there's another kind of language
and I don't really know what an example
is Swift might have this I can't
remember but if you define a language
where things directives in the language
can change the token definition so you
know let's say for example that I
defined a language doesn't have strings
in it so like quote a bunch of stuff and
then quote isn't a thing right
well if I tokenize something with that
then anything that appears like quote
author quote like what I'm looking at
the screen right now will appear as
three tokens double quote is token one
identify our author is token two and
then double quote is token three again
right
but if inside that language I have the
ability to describe it's using I don't
know a regular expression or something
or some other definition if I have the
ability to describe how to create a
token and I add the ability to say if
you see a quote take everything up till
the next quote no matter what it is is
one token now you can't do that right so
basically you have two different types
of parser problem one is where token the
act of determining what isn't isn't a
whole piece of text for tokenizing
purposes is
able to be locked down at compile-time
of the language then that's really easy
just tokenize the entire file if you
don't have that and you have the ability
to define in the language what's going
on then you've got it harder and you
have to make all kinds of concession
stat as well as you'd better know what
you're doing because the language if
you're not careful could have all kinds
of ambiguities and like things where you
have no idea like what you know things
where the user can accidentally make
totally indeterminate files a campy
parser that you don't know if they're
correct or not or other things like that
right
all right so I think that's everything
for questions socially so I'm gonna go
ahead and bow out gracefully as
gracefully as as I can ever really do so
let's go ahead and close this down no
complaints with how that went today I
would say that was great we did exactly
what we wanted which is basically we
made a parser for our file format and we
are good to go so we can pretty much
just start working with those files
immediately when we return next weekend
so thank you everyone for joining me for
those sort of handmade here oaths what a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow series at home
you can always go to handmade hero org
and press that pre-order button it comes
with the source code so you can play
around at home and you can play around
with your own parts or designs if you'd
like that's about it for this weekend
I don't know that there'll be any
streams this week but I have already
posted a schedule on the watch page
unfortunately the watch page is my
stream from hive right now but once that
stream ends it will pop back to the
schedule so you can see when we're gonna
be live next weekend same time same
place is pretty much the short answer
but if there are any updates it'll show
up on the watch page you can also
obviously subscribe on YouTube or twitch
for notifications and all that stuff
work check the handmade hero Twitter all
that stuff
also yeah well it's not subscribe on
Twitch subscribe is for paying money
what is it that's follow follow if you
can also follow it on Twitch and set
your notifications to on and that I'll
just email you whenever we're live so
you can also get notified that way
that's it for this week have fun
programming everyone over the coming
week and I will see everyone back here
next weekend