start recording hello everyone and
welcome to handmade here on the show
Rico two complete games live on stream
or as is the case yesterday try to
figure out some way to get OpenGL to
stream over OBS which we maybe did maybe
didn't I don't know so we're gonna go
ahead and try to do today's stream which
is how to get the game displaying on
OpenGL I'm gonna go ahead and try to do
it and hopefully folks will see
something but if they don't see
something that's just the way it goes
sometimes with live streaming so here we
go
on day 237 if you have pre-ordered the
game on handmade hero dorg and you would
like to follow along at home that means
you will want to unpack day 236 is
source code is that correct cuz we had
to reboot the machine so we lost the day
counter as well but yeah day 236 is the
last day unpacked day 236 is south code
and you will be where I am right now and
you can go ahead and follow along so
okay the first thing that we have to do
is get the streaming working and like I
said we spent all yesterday trying to
figure out how to do that and here is
what we decided it seemed like if we
turned off double buffering then we
would be able to to display so if we
take this here and we do something like
this and maybe we have a thing that's
like handmade I don't know what here
will we need some additional flag like
handmade streaming and we would just say
okay in the case where we are streaming
we don't include the double buffer flag
and we just say note PFD double buffer
appears to prevent OBS from reliably
streaming the window and then we just
hope that what we discovered yesterday
actually is some general true thing
about streaming OpenGL that works so
let's give it a shot here and and
there's our pink window and the question
is can you guys see
the pink window or not do you see black
do you see pink what do you see or do
you just see a Windows Visual Studio
screen what do you see
and hopefully the answer is that you see
pink good it sounds like people do see
pink so okay so we're good
alright so let's we had our on day 236
we had an explanation of how what GPUs
basically are and just how to think
about them in general and as you know
like I said on that day our first step
because we already have a software
renderer at this point we don't actually
need to get our whole game rendering
through open jail all we really need to
do as a first step is we just need to
find a way to move the image that we've
created of our game we need to figure a
toe move that down to the graphics card
so that you can see the image rendering
through OpenGL so right now what I like
I said before what we do is we just call
GL clear color and then call GL clear
and that's why we're seeing pink is
because the only instructions we've
given to OpenGL as far as what to create
for a command buffer for our graphics
card is just that we want to clear the
screen to pink and that is it that's all
we've done right this said how how how
big of the window should this sort of
gave the extents of how the clear should
happen this gave what the color should
be this gave what buffer to clear and
then we said go ahead and display that
so what we'd like to do here is we'd
like to be able to put something on the
screen that's actually going to come
from our memory so we want something
that will take this buffer that we've
got here and get that buffer down to the
graphics card so that it we can display
it now the way that this works is is
very very similar to the way that we
wrote our software renderer and that's
why we wrote software under that way so
they want you guys to see how a graphics
card works so you if you remember if you
don't go back and re-watch the things we
implemented it because this is exactly
how the card works what we need to do is
we need up need to set up an image for
it to read from which we is a texture in
this case that's what they're generally
called on the card so we need to set up
something that's gonna be a texture and
then we need to draw some
and the word primitive is just used for
anything like a triangle or a line or a
point something that the graphics card
understands how to draw look at our case
our only primitive really in our render
is a rectangle right that's the one that
we implemented on a graphics card
triangles that is the most typical
primitive and the reasons for that are a
sort of a separate thing we could go
into at some point but for right now
suffice to say if we want to do
something like draw a rectangle we need
to draw of the rectangle with either two
triangles to make a rectangle shape
right I couldn't go ahead and sort of
draw that for you here on day 237 we can
either draw it what we want by just
creating say two sort of two triangles
that encompass the rectangle right that
basically say here's here's what it is
or we can draw a single triangle right
we could draw one triangle and try to
clip that triangle to a rectangle
because OpenGL actually has ways of
clipping things obviously it has to
because just like we had to clip things
to the screen boundary open just to clip
things from you better - and just like
we did where we made our clipping be
generic so we could do like tiled
rendering stuff OpenGL clipping is
generic as well
you can choose to clip to some region
that's actually smaller than what the
screen is if you wish so we could use a
thing this is called scissoring we could
use a thing called GL scissor to do it
I'm not gonna do this one right now I'm
gonna do this one because this is the
more generally interesting case because
this would allow us you to draw
rectangles anywhere you want without
having to reset any kind of clipping
mode which you know depending on the
card can be an expensive operation
potentially and you know it can't be
this sort of thing can't exactly be
thought of in the same way sometimes so
we're gonna talk about it in the in the
sense of how you would generally draw
quads not the special case of how you
might draw one when you're only bleeding
to the screen because this is the one
that we will actually want to do when we
move the rendering over to OpenGL so
that you can choose to render everything
through up in jail rather than running
the software rasterizer
we will need to be able to do this for
each of our sprites right because each
of our sprites would be something like
this
so we're gonna literally do exactly this
thing okay
and so the process for doing this is
literally the same exactly the same as
what we did we need to basically
construct this thing and then we need to
have those UV coordinates remember we
did UV coordinates and what the UV
coordinates did is they said you know
okay we've got this this sort of thing
we're filling on the screen and then
we've got some image in memory somewhere
and the UV coordinates are what tell us
right where to go look to find a piece
of the image exactly exactly the same
thing here as what we did in our
software rasterizer
okay so we need to set up a situation
that looks like this right we need to
set the UV coordinates of the rectangle
to be like you know 0 to 1 0 to 1 just
like they were in our rectangle we need
to load this texture into memory and
then once we have all of that working we
should be able to draw two triangles
that show that basically display our
image on the screen ok so we're gonna go
ahead and do that all right so the first
thing we're gonna try is drawing our
quad our you know a rectangle out of two
triangles we're gonna try a drawing that
without actually filling it with a
texture because the texture is obviously
a harder step so we're gonna start off
by doing something simpler so we're
still going to keep this clear to pink
because that'll give us a good sense of
whether or not we're actually drawing
over it so we're gonna keep that clear
to pink and then we're going to make
some calls that allow us to specify our
triangle we're going to do this because
right now we're going to we're going to
do this in the old-school way first the
way that the original OpenGL did it and
then probably not today but next week
we'll talk about why this is not the way
that we will end up doing it why we will
replace this but this is the easiest one
to learn it's the easiest one to get
your head around because it involves
less maneuvering ok so the way that
OpenGL works in the old-school way is
you said Gio
begin angieland to bracket a series of
operations that would construct some
primitives so like I said primitives in
this case refers to something the graphs
code understands like a triangle so in
this case we're trying to draw some
primitives primitive schools are like
the smallest building block right
primitives and so the primitives that
we're trying to draw here are gonna be
triangles and again there's actually
some things we could do that actually be
even in this circumstance a little more
efficient than a triangle but again I
want to start with the most basic stuff
so you know yes everyone on the stream
yes you could use a triangle strip yes
you could do whatever
please don't focus on optimization stuff
when I'm just trying to give the idea of
how something works because that's not
the right mental piece here right you
want to make sure you understand
everything from sort of the ground up
and not concern yourself with whether
there's some weird like optimization
thing especially because in this case no
optimizations will be relevant for
putting something to the screen it
literally does not matter how you do
this so in this case I want to say I'm
just gonna start by drawing some
triangles and the GL begins GL end tells
it that everything in between there is
information about what triangles to draw
then there's a command called GL vertex
which specifies points in space and the
way that they chose to do their naming
screen is its GL anytime you see GL and
a command right it can then be sort of
suffixed if it takes various different
types so for example if I wanted to say
there was gonna be a 2d point that was
specified in floating-point format it
would be GL vertex to s and then I would
pass the coordinates the XY coordinates
let's say in floating-point format of
that point now if I wanted to pass them
as integers I would say to I right and
if I wanted to pass a three-dimensional
point I might say 3f right and again
only a certain subset of the functions
exist RC these are actual separate
functions so they did not supply
necessary every possible function but
that is the naming scheme for them so
for every possible GL vertex that they
implemented there's 3f to UB for
unsigned byte you know stuff like that
okay so if we want to produce triangles
here that are going to cover the screen
where are the triangles going to be
right
well the viewport sort of like I said
that this this GL command we set up to
say where we're trying to render right
that the extent of the screen is zero to
the window width right and zero to the
window height on the Y side so if I want
to draw some triangles hmm I am going to
have to specify triangles perhaps like
this right I'm gonna have to perhaps
specify a triangle that's like here here
here and a triangle that's here here
here okay and we know the coordinates of
all these points right all of these
points are very easy for us to see what
they are so let's take this triangle
first it's zero zero two width comma
zero to width comma height right and so
that's a very easy triangle to draw that
would just be let's see here
that would just be zero zero window
width zero zero that's all right
window with window height that's why I
said right so that'd be that first
triangle and then the other triangle
would be almost the same thing except
this time it would go the other way
round right so it would go it would go
from zero zero up to window F 2 with
height and then over to zero height
right and those would be our two
triangles so this I could label these
right this is the lower triangle and
this is the upper triangle all right so
when I do this in theory I think if we
ran it now maybe we would actually get a
triangle there's a bunch of other things
involved here but you know let's just
see what happens right all right so
there we go there is our there's our
lovely two triangles being drawn
but as you'll notice they're not where
we expected them to be right they if if
the coordinate system were actually zero
zero was here and you know the this was
zero height
this was width height and this was zero
this was with zero we would expect this
thing we drew to fill the screen but
it's not filling the screen at this
point okay so why not what's going on
and the answer is that because whether
you want it to or not
opengl mm-hmm when you use the
old-school way of doing things meaning
you're not going through a shader what
you're going through is called the fixed
function pipeline so there's two sort of
schools here fixed function and
programmable okay so the fixed function
pipeline is the old-school way of doing
things that comes from when GPUs were
not programmable they only did one thing
which was a certain way of processing
vertices in a certain way of filling
pixels right and similarly in the
new-school way we have everything is
programmable so we always have these
shaders and things like that that we
write so in the old fixed function way
of doing things what happened is it
basically had what you would typically
write for a very basic vertex shader was
built into the hardware directly and
what that was was a transform on the
vertices right followed by clipping the
triangles mm-hmm followed by what's
called a Windows face transform
and in programmable land we actually
have some of the same stuff the clipping
for example is still usually done in a
fixed function way but this part here
the transfer on the vertices part and
usually this window space transform same
comes right across so usually this part
stay the same these two parts here so
this is where it was filling pixels
right these two parts here used to be
very very rigid with how they operated
now they are all in shaders so this part
all happens in shader is this all part
all happens in shaders and you can
customize them to do basically whatever
you want right so what's happening and
the reason why we don't see this where
we would have expected it to based on
what we set up for the screen is because
the transform that's happening on the
vertices is is we haven't set it up it's
whatever the default was and the default
in this case doesn't happen to be
something that takes input vertices and
map them directly to the screen that's
not at all what actually happens so as a
result we get something random that we
don't necessarily even understand right
because we haven't actually looked at
what that transform does we don't
necessarily know so you know the filling
pixels part is probably fine for us
right now but the transform on the
vertices part isn't now one thing we can
do is we can just step right up the
shaders and implement it ourselves
exactly where we want to put things we
could do that but what I'd rather do is
show you a little bit about how that
fixed function pipeline it's good to
understand kind of how it used to work
because the shader that you would
implement is actually pretty much
exactly the same as what the fixed
function think is actually doing if you
set some of the parameters all right so
what happens with OpenGL is they specify
two different kinds of matrices now
we've talked about matrices before right
matrices are things that are sort of
recording a series of math operations
that you're going to do on vectors in
this case right and so I don't know if
you remember but I did something where I
showed kind of like how to do vector
matrix multiplication where we have
something like this right and then we
have something like this
right and I taught you guys how to do
this multiplication where basically you
you use vertical and horizontal here to
line up which terms go with which terms
so you always start and read down
vertically the vector that you're trying
to multiply this is like the incoming
point so in our case this is this thing
here at the vertex to I right but in
this case I've shown it with three I'll
tell you why in a second and then here
is like the matrix for example when you
do this you essentially get ax plus B y
plus cz right so you take first times
first second times second third times
third right then you move down to the
next row do the same thing again e^x +
FY plus GZ right and then you move down
again IX plus jy
too bad it wasn't J Z plus KZ right and
so that's how matrix multiplication
works for vectors it's also how it works
for matrices but we don't really have to
care about that too much right now and
this is a sort of fairly crucial to
understand if you want to start working
with opengl especially the fixed
function pipeline but to a certain
extent also the programmable pipeline
because matrices and vectors are kind of
native to it in some way and you kind of
have to start thinking in terms of that
so we haven't really had to do too much
dancers I've explained it before on the
stream but now you're gonna have to get
a little bit more comfortable with it
okay and the important thing to note
about these is there's nothing
mysterious about a matrix this is not
mysterious right if you can understand
this procedure right here you can see
exactly the math that actually happens
when you transform something by a matrix
so it's very easy for you to see what
you want to have happen when you pass in
an XYZ and you're transforming it by a
matrix you know that you've just got one
parameter that that multiplies the x one
parameter that multiplies is the the Y
and one parameter that multiplies the Z
to produce the final X so basically you
have three dials right that you can turn
for the incoming values that will
produce the resulting X prime right the
the vector like the the new vector that
comes out
right and so you can kind of just
arbitrarily create anything you want as
long as it's just a straightforward
linear transform right as long as it can
be represented by three coefficients and
two additions on the input values you
can do it you can do anything you want
because you can set these values to
anything you want and as you can see you
get three of them per output value so
you have the complete freedom to adjust
each individual output component
separately right does that make sense
so what OpenGL does is OpenGL takes this
one step further and what you can see
here are hopefully you can see here is
that there's something you might want to
do that is not captured by this this is
a this is this right here what I've
drawn is called a linear transform and
it's linear because it's it's lines two
lines right it's like basically I can
only sort of change I I when I am
transforming these things right it's
it's something that when I do this
multiplication there's no way for me to
nonlinearly warp it I can't square any
terms I can't produce an x squared on
the input right whatever this x value is
here there's no way for me to square it
the only way for me to square it would
be to know beforehand what its value was
and stick it in the matrix but that
doesn't count right if I'm talking about
arbitrary input values there's no
nothing I could ever put here would lead
to an x squared so it's always lines to
lines there's no way to take a line and
turn into a parabola right there's no
way to take something in that was linear
and produce something nonlinear on the
output okay but linear specifically does
not allow offsets you will notice there
is no way to add a fixed value here
right and you'll notice I was sly I left
out you know
values here right I left out D I left
out H I left out L right there and
weren't in there there's no way to add a
value that isn't multiplied by the input
let's say I passed into vector zero zero
zero there'd it just comes out a zero
zero zero right there's no way to move
things around
I can only sort of reorient them I can
skew them I could scale them I could
rotate them even but what I can't do is
displace them because everything is a
function of the input here and so what
OpenGL does is OpenGL uses what's called
homogeneous coordinates and what they do
is they artificially pretend that the
vector that comes in actually has a 1
here so it's X Y Z 1 now you will notice
that the this column of the matrix here
DHL just comes through as an offset on
the input so now I have a way to
positionally offset my my folks that is
called an affine transform when you when
you add the ability to displace that is
an affine transform and then down here
we just usually pretend that the matrix
doesn't have anything it's just 0 0 0 1
why is it 0 0 0 1 per se well that's if
you want to leave this 1 a 1 right
because then when I multiply I always
get a 1 in the W coordinate that's what
this is called which is just a synthetic
coordinate right now there's an
interesting aspect of this technically
in OpenGL it allows you to actually pass
full 4 dimensional parameters if you
want to play with this value you
actually may want to play with that
value why might you want to play with
that value well if you've set it to 0
you get no displacement right because
all of these guys would drop out because
they'd be multiplied by 0 now so in some
sense there's a way now to distinguish
between a vector which is a direction
and a point a vector would be something
that is X Y Z 1 and a point would be
something that is X Y Z 0 because X Y Z
0 knocks out the translation component
leaving only the direction change right
whereas X Y Z 1 is a point because it
picks up that translation so these are
things that can move the
things that do not move right so that's
a little trick eNOS it's just a little
bit of understanding how the math works
out allows you to do some things that
you might want to do you spent want to
be aware of it right okay so that's the
idea right that's that's the general
idea and so again there's called
homogeneous coordinates in the three
graphs searchers do I look them up
that's what they're called and it's
called an affine transform once it
allows that displacement as opposed to a
linear displacement which is not a
linear transform which does not
generally have this placement in it okay
so what OpenGL does is it defines two
matrices there are other matrices that
they don't come in here it defines two
matrices that you can use Model View and
projection in the fixed function
pipeline we have both of these and what
it does is it allows you to set them
separately but it used to be a there
used to be a reason why for built in
lighting which nobody uses pretty much
didn't really even use back then but for
built-in lighting there used to be a
reason I'm not even to go into it cause
it's completely irrelevant why these two
things had to be separate because
there's really no reason for them to be
separate because basically what happens
in OpenGL is what they do is they take
the modelview matrix and they
concatenate these two matrices together
so they multiply the modelview matrix by
the projection matrix and that is
actually the matrix they use to
transform all your inputs right so all
the input points that come in are always
multiplied by the combination of these
two matrices which just applies matrices
multiplication literally is just a way
of combining two matrix operations
together and what happens is the the the
order is essentially reversed from how
you might read it so if you see like if
you start from the the vector that's
being transformed you read in this order
to figure out what's going to happen to
the vector first that's gonna get
transformed by the modelview then it's
going to get transformed by the
projection and that gives the new point
right now why matrix multiplication
combine things I think that's probably
better saved for ten
for a later stream we want to talk about
the bat math a little more especially
because we're not actually gonna use
that even this stuff we're just gonna
pretend the modelview matrix doesn't
even exist because we only need one
matrix to do the operations we're going
to do anyway and like I said actually
we'll find out a little bit later on
when we maybe look at matrices in a
little more detail if we decide we need
to really any number of matrices can be
smooshed down into a single matrix just
by multiplying them all together so
there really was never uh need that hat
they should never have really had two
matrices but because of some aspects of
built-in lighting there was a reason why
they chose to separate them and and
really that's not necessary
so in we're gonna pretend that the the
modelview matrix never exists and what
we're gonna do is we're gonna set that
modelview matrix to always just be the
identity makes rent we're gonna pretend
it doesn't do anything and so the way
you do that is GL has something called
matrix mode and you can pass what matrix
are trying to operate on at a given time
again that basically just stores two
matrices the modelview matrix a
projection matrix and i believe you can
just call GL identity which just clears
out that matrix and makes it the
identity matrix the identity matrix at
least I think that's true I guess not
geo load identity there it is geo load
identity
alright so an identity matrix is
literally one that just passes
everything through exactly it's this
matrix
and what's interesting about this matrix
right is no matter what I stick in here
right X Y Z W you can see that it
basically just picks out the component
that that it's trying to generate and
leaves everything else be right it's
just X Y Z W so everything the identity
matrix does nothing it is a no op it's
the no op matrix it's the thing that
just picks out the component that came
in right that's in that slot that's it
this is as opposed to like a permutation
matrix which is one which would maybe
pick a different component so let's say
I wanna like swap the X and y right I
could do this right and then the X and y
would swap right so basically
permutations and identity matrices are
very similar if they just you know they
just take the terms and shove them out
directly as they come in it just maybe
they rearranged them a little right okay
so anyway GL load identity just says
replace whatever is in this matrix slot
remember I have two matrix slots Model
View projection there's actually another
one for textures and we'll get to later
but for the for the points that we're
sending down
there's the modelview matrix and then
there's the projection matrix and so if
I did this both of our majors will be
set to the identity matrix
which I believe is what they're set to
at the beginning anyway so if I run it I
should get the exact same thing I
started with and I do right and so now
we're in a position to start thinking
about what would we actually need to put
into the projection matrix in order to
get out right in order to actually well
I say in order to get what we expected
to see here right okay and so to learn
to understand this we have to go back to
our diagram if this is starting to sound
overly complicated this is why GPUs are
awful it's because you have to learn
every little last thing about how they
work internally before you can actually
do stuff instead of just writing code
that you know how to write but what can
you do so in order to say that you have
to go back to this thing it is this part
right here that is confounding us right
look I just said our points are now
getting multiplied by the identity
matrix we said everything that animate
so we're just passing the points are
exactly what we pass in so why aren't we
seeing them where we should see them on
the screen and the answer is because of
the definition of what happens here with
the clipping and window space transform
okay so let's talk a little bit about
that okay so for clipping this is just
the process where open Jill's doing
exactly what we wanted to do right
exactly what we had to do ourselves
triangles are gonna come in to OpenGL or
whatever and they're gonna look like
this and here is the screen okay
and obviously OpenGL can't just start
drawing off the screen although I'll
throw in a little mention here just goes
time to be aware of actually it can
there's this concept typically called
guard band clipping so actually when I
say it's going to clip it to the screen
it actually often doesn't clip it to the
screen it actually Clips it to a guard
band which is a thing that's bigger than
the screen that is GPU implementation
specific kinds of stuff but just to be
aware of that can happen but point being
it has to clip it to something and that
something has to be a way of producing a
set of triangles that actually can be
drawn right so like something like this
for example might be a way to clip it to
you know some triangles that actually
fall within the region it's trying to
draw okay we had an easier time of it
than OpenGL because we were just trying
to clip rectangles that were aligned
with the screen for the most part I
don't remember what we did for clipping
for rotate when we rotated stuff to be
honestly I don't even remember what we
did but point being I think oh I think
we just took we still just clip to the
rectangle of the rotated thing so yeah
so we always were able to just do
rectangle clipping they don't
necessarily they might not necessarily
be able do that or they could do the
exact same thing right they might
implement their stuff because they
implement it with they implement it very
close to how we implemented it so they
may do exactly the same thing but either
way they're gonna do something to do
this clip in here before they actually
start to rasterize things and the way
that they do clipping is they do
flipping to be honest with you I I don't
really remember the details of why they
chose to do clipping this way but they
do clipping in something that they call
the unit cube so what they do is the
projection matrix instead of
transforming things the way we think of
it where they transform them into where
they should be on the screen which is
how we were thinking projection what the
projection matrix actually does is it
projects things into the unit cube so
basically it says all right I
whatever my screen was like my screen is
this 16 by 9 like TV thing or whatever
right well whatever is gonna fit on the
screen I'm actually gonna try to fit it
into a unit cube which depending on how
you actually whether your directory to
your opengl and depending exactly how
they want to do things but in general
it's something like say negative one to
one
right so negative 1 1 is here negative 1
I'm sorry 1 is here negative 1 on Y
right what it says is I'm gonna pretend
that everything always falls into this
unit cube here right which is actually
too wide outside but it's a unit radius
and I'm then going to after I do all my
clipping in the unit cube space and
figure out exactly what I'm going to
keep right then I blow it out i scale it
back out to fit the actual screen so
first we do this then we do this okay
and so you can imagine what happens here
what that says is after projection right
so I've got my projection matrix maybe
I'll call this matrix oops matrix
projection I take an input point I
multiply it by price by projection
matrix I get a P Prime out what is this
P Prime out this is P in clip space
right that is something that's in this
space here and what that means is the
projection matrix does not move things
to screen space it moves them to unit
space which explains exactly why having
nothing in
here does not work if we're doing 0-0 -
width height of the screen as our as our
values we pass in right because when we
do that what we're effectively doing is
getting something that starts in the
middle right there zero zero in the unit
cube and goes way the heck out here with
height is like way out there right in
fact it's that direction right because
the width is wider than the height so
then when this thing gets blown up to
fit the screen we see exactly what we
just saw which is it only fills that
upper rectangle okay because it's we we
basically the screen space coordinates
and it want eclipses coordinates so the
trivial fix for this if we wanted to
write would just be to actually pass it
things in its coordinate space right and
that would look like this just pass it
in the unit cube and we would have to do
anything else if we don't want to okay
oops that's one one right that is now
directly in clip space which will not
get transformed by anything during
projection and then after the clip space
part of things it'll blow it out to the
screen size so there we go now we're
filling the screen similarly if we
wanted to verify that we weren't like
thinking of it wrong we could change
these two EPs and do something like
percent or just let's just do P is like
0.9 and so then we'll change all of
these to peas and then we can see that
we can draw a smaller thing that's with
inside the balance right inside the
balance of the screen
all right and so there you can see we've
we've shrunk in by 10% the width and the
height and as you can see 10% is
relative to with their height so there's
less of a margin on the top than on the
bottom right because in clip space were
in we're in a unit cube and then we're
blowing it out to a rectangle and that
scale to the rectangle is gonna scale X
is bigger than wise okay hopefully that
makes sense to everyone I know this is a
lot of information fast but you know
like I said a week it will go over it
multiple times we'll get it so hopefully
everyone can be on the same page okay so
that's just what's defined is happening
that's why why that's happening cuz
that's how open Gela to find a work you
move in eclipses space first and then
you move out to the screen so clipping
happens here don't you have to screen
what does it move out to the screen mean
well okay we have P and clip space right
it's very simple to think about what
happens all we're trying to do here to
move into creat it's a screen space is
we now need to move negative one to one
needs to move to zero zero right so you
know first we V Center we could take P
clip right and add to it just 1 1 right
so that would basically say take the
bottom here move it up to 0 0 so that
like anchors that to here and then we
would have to multiply what is now a 2
by 2 cube right that cube would be like
you know it's 2 units 2 pixels tall 2
pixels wide right we would have to
multiply it by half the width and half
the height right to get it up right so I
take this and then I would multiply that
by this would be a Hadamard product here
right and multiply straight through I
know how you write that Hadamard
whatever I would multiply that by the
width / 2
and the height / - right so I move it to
the corner I blow it out to the whole
side that's it so so when I say it moves
it over the manner it's literally we're
just talking about multiplying the
points by that to figure out where they
are in screen space that's it
that's all there is so if nothing
mystical it's not magic it's just a
straight up
trivial transportation transformation if
you want to see it written out in scalar
form right it's literally like you know
the the new x-coordinate equals the the
transform you know the clip coordinates
oh I don't know how you want to write
that but like you know the clip
x-coordinate you know plus that one and
then times the width over to right and
the y prime would be the same you know
I'm saying but we don't care about any
of that right it suffice to say mentally
we know it's doing this we never touch
that anyway the only way that we have an
effect on it is this GL viewport call is
the thing that gives it that piece of
information right so it uses these to
know how it should blow out so when we
say width over to where's the width
coming from it's coming from right here
right where's the zero zero coming from
so it knew where to put the thing it's
right here so if you wanted to put the
viewport somewhere else you could put it
somewhere else on the screen if you
wanted to because these could be
anywhere it's basically the transform in
some sense I should say the transform
goes from clip to the viewport which
might not actually be aligned with the
TV we lined it with the screen because
that's what we want but we could have
maybe made something else right we could
have made a different shape for it if
we'd wanted to we don't but we could've
alright so that's the first step of
things drawing an actual rectangle
screen we did it yay congratulations
everyone wins so now the question is how
do we get a texture down there how do we
get something that's drawn on to the
screen well what we need to actually do
now is draw something that actually has
some UV coordinates right because we
need to tell it to pull from our texture
we need to do the thing that I that I
was saying we did our cells before so we
need to set up these UV coordinates 0 to
1 0 to 1 so it knows how to grab from
the image this is exactly like what we
implemented so you all should be very
familiar with this the concept of of
thinking about an image as having a UV
coordinate where 0 0 is the bottom
corner 1 1 is the top corner right and
anywhere between 0 &amp; 1 is picking out
like pixels in this thing ok well the
way OpenGL
works in this old-school fashion here
again like I said the old-school way is
the GL vertex call is considered the
finalization call for that vertex and
anything that happens before it is
considered as associating an attribute
with that vertex so for example if I
said GL color 3f and I pass a color here
like for example I pass magenta and then
down here I pass another color that is
white you will note that the white color
applies to these very the magenta color
plus these receipts the white color
applies to these ok and hopefully I
don't know if I have setup and modulate
as a blend note here I don't think so so
there you go right oh why did I say
magenta I put in yellow yeah
and similarly I can associate a
different one with every single one if I
want to like I can do an R a G and a B
here for example an OpenGL will
automatically interpolate between those
colors just like we did our
interpolation right just like we were
doing interpolation of UV coordinates
it'll interpolate the colors right so
all we have to do if we want to
associate UV coordinates is we just have
to call the opengl function that
specifies texture coordinates and we
have to specify the texture coordinates
for each of these vertices that
logically would go with that particular
vertex so we're gonna have to figure out
what that is we'll do that on the
blackboard in just one second let me
first spam our thing here there we go so
what are the texture coordinates that we
actually need to fill with well if we're
doing this right here this is what we
chose to draw obviously we want the
bottom of our image the 0 0 UV to be
here right so the first one would be 0 0
this one would be 1 0 right and this one
would be 1 1 those would be the UV
coordinates right because we want to
overlay the image exactly on the
triangles okay so we've got 0 0 then
we've got 1 0 then we've got 1 1 okay
and that again associates thusly
yeah hopefully that makes sense and then
similarly for the other guys down here
we've got the same thing 0 0 for the
negative P negative P case right and
then we've got this guy is 1 1 because
he's all the way over and then this guy
here would be 0 1 because he's like up
and over
right you can almost just read off the
negatives on the peas right kind of tell
us where those are so now if we run it
again we won't actually see anything
here but we've associated touch
coordinates we won't see anything
different because there is no texture
being specified but we specify the
coordinates and similarly those
coordinates get multiplied by a texture
matrix I don't know if what the actual
let me see here you know matrix mode I
don't remember so a long time so I used
the fixed function pipeline I don't
remember if it's geo texture it is geo
texture so GL colors and geo textures
also are considered essentially points
so I'll just put this here for your sort
of amusement we can if we want to
transform our textures by a matrix as
well if we want to move the texture
coordinates separate from the thing we
are not going to but I'll just sort of
clearly state there that we're trying to
transfer everything not at all basically
okay so there's our two triangles
there's our texture coordinates so
they're the only thing that we actually
have to do now is we have to get a
texture down to the card and that's
actually not that difficult in theory
it's just really difficult in practice
because OpenGL does not make it easy and
I don't think we'll have time to do it
today we only have 11 minutes left I
will basically put in the calls and talk
about them and they won't work and then
we'll have to talk about why and that
will be our job for Monday ok so the way
you specify a texture is with the call
GL text image 2d and what this is saying
is exactly what it sounds like it's
saying I want to specify the image for a
texture okay and the parameters of GL
text to D are some of the worst
parameters ever devised for submitting a
texture by mankind they are awful all
one of the all-time worst
api's in OpenGL because OpenGL was
actually fairly reasonably designed for
back in the day these are awful so let's
talk about this so GL text image 2d a
little bit of it should look familiar to
you you can see here that there's a GL
void star pixels as the last remember
that is the pointer to the buffer of
pixels just like we have created so that
part you
understand width and height pretty clear
border is sort of a separate thing that
we won't go into now which is saying if
you want there to consider an extra ring
around the pixels that gets into
mipmapping
and a whole ball of wax 3d cards don't
do MIT mapping properly they never have
it was probably one of the worst design
aspects of them and I have a gigantic
rant about how broken MIT mapping is but
we will save that for some other day
when we actually care about MIT mapping
which we may never actually on handmade
here so separating that part we have the
width and the height which you
understand and then we've got some
things here we've got stuff like
internal format and format what does
that even mean well what happens is this
format here the second format the one
that comes before are the pixels just
before the pixels in the type right he's
saying how we're submitting it right and
we've got an RGBA right we've got RGB a
RGB a rgba right that's what we've got
in our texture only we actually are
backwards I don't know if they've got
BGR right here they don't exactly be grx
there we go we are actually backwards
because we use the windows format since
we wrote on Windows originally so
remember byte order in both in on in
memory and and in registers and stuff
are different on little-endian hopefully
you remember this from way way back when
right if you take a look at how Intel
architectures right little-endian how
they store things here is a register
here's how you typically would write a
register write the least significant
bits go here the most significant bits
go here but they're read in memory in
the opposite order so this is actually
the zeroth location in memory this is
actually the the first and the second
and the third right so what that means
is when you look at a register and you
see our a RGB if that's the way you
actually put them in your register when
you wrote that out to memory the order
was B GRA because this is the byte that
comes first on a PowerPC that wouldn't
be true it would have actually written
it out a RGB right and so Windows
machines are often BGR
the reason they are be GRA is because
the graphics programmers of Windows
wanted to see them in registers in the
RGB order so that's actually the format
that we are for amusement purposes maybe
we'll pass it and just to not pass it
that way if we could we could not pass
it that way and see the color reversal
you want to the point being it's okay
because there is actually a format for
that VLB GRA X so it's actually totally
fine we can just tell it that's what
we've got right and then we have of
course our pixels which come from buffer
memory okay and then we've got some
other information here right we've got
hmm what was the other things we knew
okay so type we know what that is we
know that like we specified the order of
the components with this field we now
know that we have to specify actually
the the type of them they're unsigned
bytes right because it's talking about
the the size of each component not the
size the whole thing so we're taking
we're 32-bit colors right in hammer here
we're 8-bit great 8-bit are 8-bit g8 b8
bit a so we're unsigned bytes for each
one of them 0 to 255 and we're BGR a so
that's specifying the image that's
coming in and then we've got some other
things as Best Buy here so we've got the
target and the target in OpenGL is just
specifying essentially which texture
slot you're talking about this is a very
confusing thing but what it essentially
means is there's texture 1d texture 2d
and so on and these are talking about a
1d texture a 2d texture a 3d texture and
so on and they often have functions that
will take which one you're trying to
talk about the currently loaded 1d text
or the currently 2d texture current load
3d texture GL text image 2d it's stupid
that it takes one because like you can
see it has state go2 actually I think
they were trying to leave room for
extensions which wanted to target
something else and I think they actually
do use that in some cases but for our
purposes we're just trying to specify a
2d texture that we're going to use right
we then have a level the level is for
specifying what are called MIT Maps
we're not going to talk about them right
now so we only need to set specify zero
because we're not trying to address
anything more copy than that and then we
have internal format and what internal
format is is how we want OpenGL to store
it right because again here we were in
this lower part we were talking about
how we were passing it in here we're
talking about how we want OpenGL to
handle it on its side which is really
just a suggestion it doesn't have to
store it this way it's just suggestion
and in our cases we probably want GL
rgba 8 right because we want to store 8
bits per channel
RGBA which is what we're passing it in
and that's that right we also then have
to specify the width and the height we
come after it and the border value which
again is 0 so we have our buffer width
and our buffer height and then we have
our 0 border and that's how you specify
a texture oops that's how you specify a
texture in OpenGL but as you can see
when we run it we're not actually gonna
it's not actually going to draw anything
ok so why is it drawing anything well
there's a lot of reasons a bunch of
things we have to do like I said I don't
think we'll get to them in five minutes
but when we submit a texture to OpenGL
that again and I think hopefully I
hammered this home on Wednesday when I
did the overview all of these things are
basically just giving the the OpenGL
driver layer what we're trying to tell
the card to do so what this actually
turns into is a request to transfer a
buffer memory over and how does that
work well what's actually gonna happen
when they call GL text image 2d is the
driver is gonna snap a copy of this
buffer memory into its own memory and
then later it will kick off a transfer
possibly at that very moment but
possibly later it'll kick off a transfer
that'll start sending it down to the
card right then all of these things will
build up a command buffer that's how to
draw these primitives and that'll get
kicked off to the card and then the swap
buffers right is just saying hey we're
ready to present now so it knows that
all of this stuff goes with a single
frame and it can like do it all finish
it and present it to the screen right so
again none of this stuff is necessarily
happening exactly when we call it it's
all sort of telling the driver what we
want
and the driver is doing whatever it
wants to make that happen okay so why
are we seeing a texture well first of
all we have to enable texturing OpenGL
fixed function pipeline was set up so
that you could turn the features on and
off as necessary and so there's a
function called GL enable which allows
you to say whether you want something
like texturing to happen so the first
thing we have to do is set up an actual
you know we have to actually enable
texturing so it knows we want it to pull
from the texture okay but just doing
that unless there's some weird thing
that happens here I don't think will be
enough for us to actually see our
texture on the screen right okay so why
are we still not saying we said texture
the texture image why aren't we seeing a
texture on the screen well there's more
to it than that the next thing we have
to do is we actually have to look at how
the texturing API works which is that we
can have more than one texture obviously
like if you see games they have lots of
different textures and one of the things
that OpenGL wants to be able to do is
store multiple textures on the card so
that as we draw things we can select
which texture we wanted to use right we
can just say oh oh all this trying to
let that texture draw this triangle that
texture or whatever that sort of thing
right and so although this submits the
texture of the card what you're supposed
to do first and again you can sort of
see here as we're as I'm giving you the
introduction to OpenGL basic OpenGL
operations you can see it's very
stateful right there's a lot of things
like we turn on texturing and it's just
assumed that everything else has that
texture we want to clear the screen well
it's just assumed that it knows what the
color is because we set that color at
some earlier time we could have set that
color like way up here right so it's
very stateful it stores a lot of state
and the same is true of texturing what
happens with texturing is there's a
concept of what texture is bound all
right
there's a thing called like bind I think
it's bind texture
and there's a concept of saying by
texture what happens with binding is you
need to essentially create slots that
name the textures you will submit so
that you can refer to them now this may
seem superfluous in our case because we
only have one texture that we ever want
to draw which is the thing that came out
of our own renderer but as you might
imagine if we convert over to rendering
with OpenGL itself we might want to have
multiple textures that are different
images that were you know putting on
things right and so this is what this
part is for and what we need to do is do
this we need to bind texture that target
is again the thing I was talking about
where it says which texture slot you're
talking about the 1d 2d 3d texture and
then the texture is something that we
need to create so how do we do that
right mm-hmm
well we want to do this at startup but
I'll just do a static init here just for
a quick thing to do move this
so we'll do a static init equals false
if in it yeah so what we need here is we
need one of these texture handles and
the way that we get a texture handle is
we just ask OpenGL for one so we say GL
gen textures which is a request to get
textures we say we would like one
texture there's like a count and then we
say where to put it and if we made this
an array we could generate multiple
textures at a time so if we do that we
can then bind that texture and really
all this is doing literally the only
thing that GL gen textures does is it's
like giving us a name it's basically
getting us a pointer it's saying give us
something we can use to refer to this
image in the future when we need it and
all we're ever gonna do is just bind it
and submit an image that's it okay so
we're getting closer now but I think
we're still not quite we're probably not
quite there because there's one more
thing I believe we have to do but we're
almost there
to singhsoumya screen so there's our GL
bind texture what is the problem you put
into there sighs okay fine
there you go
so I don't think we'll see the texture
still because there's one more
I think we have to do so we're still
white and that is we have to set up the
rules for how the texture is sampled and
applied to our image because remember
our texture is just one of the things
that might contribute to the color of a
point in this fixed function pipeline we
saw before that I could set colors right
I was able to set for example a yellow
here you know and the points came up
yellow so what would it mean if I had
the color set to yellow and the texture
was something else right what does it
mean so you have to set up what's called
the texture environment which says what
to do with the texture and so you can
see there's a function called GN Tex Tex
M or let's see GL of text here we go so
here is our GL texts them there's I both
I and F V say how to sort of sample from
the texture I'm not sure if they've got
much in here here we go yeah here we go
so GL Tex am I for example right we can
say what we're trying to do with our
texture and in this case we can say like
replace blend decal modulate and we can
set the mode and what this allows us to
do is say what we want our texture to do
like how we want our texture to affect
the color of the pixels that we're
drawing and so this is pretty
straightforward in our case modulate
means multiply that's what we're going
to want and the reason for that is it
means that when we set colors whatever
our texture actually has in it will just
get multiplied by those colors right so
I can do geo text and I here I can say
that we have GL texture and and I want
to set it to yellow texture and mode GL
modulate right and that says whenever
you sample a texture and you have an
incoming color multiply them together
right we have another set of things here
which are GL text parameter
gl Tech's parameter so good the search
there they couldn't even that was great
nice job MSDN really fantastic
good job all right um so let's take a
look here where is our geo texture Doc's
good yeah so if we well this is 4.0
though that's probably not the best
thing let's try this there we go so
here's GL @ x parameter and you can see
that this is just kind of a
multi-function which allows you to set a
whole bunch of things here right and so
these are just tons and tons of settings
that we might want to set for our
texture and we'll kind of see how to set
those here so let's go ahead and put
them in here all right so GL text
parameter and then there's one more
thing so even after all this I don't
think we will actually see anything
because there's one more thing I'm
pretty sure that we have wrong that
we'll have to fix but that'll be left as
an exercise for the reader the rest of
these in here
yeah okay so what are all these things a
lot of these we probably don't ever want
to actually set but I'm just gonna kind
of show them out here so you can kind of
see how much randomness there isn't here
all right so we'll get to those a little
bit later and all of those are going to
be target P named int right afterwards
so all of these were going to have TL
texture 2d in front of them and then
they're gonna have some parameter and so
we'll talk about these I guess we'll
talk about these on Monday and so then
the final thing that I again like I
think we have wrong here is that this GL
text image 2d you'll notice what we did
not specify because we've got the width
at the height we have the fact that it's
PG RA we have it in fact this GL and
sign byte but what we don't still have
is any specification of what the stride
or packing is on this pointer right and
if you remember this is actually
something that's a you know it's like a
bottom up right and it maybe has a
certain stride we haven't specified any
of that so we have to go actually verify
that we're passing something to it
that's sort of in the write that the
stride is correct and there's a there's
a there's a bunch of functions you
actually call for OpenGL to set up how
it's expecting this it's like pixel
transfer settings and all this other
stuff all right
so let's go through these really quick
let me see we got maybe a couple minutes
we can spare here we just set let me
just say what a couple of these are all
right so there's a thing called GL min
textured min filter and GL texture mag
filter what those are is again these are
based on mipmapping
and so
these I I don't really want to get into
what mipmapping is full of these min
loud max lot all of these are are
basically all mipmapping things and I
don't really want to deal with any of
those so I'm just gonna set these to
essentially admit mapping off right I
don't want any MIT mapping of any kind
and similarly I don't even want any
texture filtering like you know we
implemented bilinear filtering I don't
want any of that on right now so texture
min filter and mag filter min filter
says when you are shrinking the image
down so when you're taking a texture
that's bigger than how it's showing up
on screen what do you want to do and GL
nearest says just pick the nearest Texel
and show it right so don't do like
bilinear filtering like we were doing
remember we did nearest we did that when
we actually made our render we just
grabbed the pixel and it kind of looks
kind of sparkly and not that good we
just want to stick with that for now
because we're just bleeding to the
screen we should be able to get that
fine anyway mag filter is the opposite
it's what to do when the texture is
smaller than how it's appearing on
screen so how do you want to blow it up
again I'm just gonna turn all that up
min LOD max laud is if you start using
mipmapping which we're like I said not
doing so we're gonna ignore those for
now base level and max level I don't
actually remember exactly how those are
used for computing those are again all
of those things so texture rap s T and R
so although we use the terms U and V
OpenGL uses the terms s T and R to talk
I believe about texture coordinates
after they've been transformed I believe
I don't quite remember but I believe
that's true so if you have like the uvw
coordinates of your textures like we was
talking about UV coordinates and then I
said there's a texture matrix you can
use to transfer them if you want well
what comes out the other side of that I
believe they refer to is st and then the
third ones are a few F again if you have
3d texturing or something like that
involved and so these rap here allows
you to set how you want your textures to
wrap do you want them to clamp to the
border color do you want them to mirror
do you want them to repeat right and so
in this case we want clamping because I
don't actually want to do anything where
mid mirrors or appie training like that
these guys here texture priority
Parramatta pear phone we don't even want
to set any of these these are things
that are specific to like texture
priority can say when we're putting
textures in memory if you have to
discard one if we fill up texture memory
or something which one should take
priority we don't really want to talk
about any of these these are all kind of
non sequitur for us all right
so that's I guess these are not SPECT in
our version of OpenGL it looks like
they're not so this is probably I guess
this is too early for OpenGL to even
have that the opengl that we're using
doesn't even have that apparently so
that's kind of terrifying but okay all
right so we're getting closer we're not
quite there yet
yeah okay we're not quite there yet but
we're almost there I think and so yeah
like I said well alright or we just are
there yet all right well when I said we
weren't there yet what I meant is we are
there yet and please don't listen to
what I have to say because it's all lie
and so we are there yet there is the
game running through open gel with all
the parameters set and I guess we just
happened to look out and our buffer
happens to be exactly packed the way
that OpenGL was going to read it and so
we got lucky which means if we just go
ahead and set this thing to 1.0 and we
could also set our buffer size back up
if we want to here we could set it to
1920 by 1080 we should have a full
screen OpenGL
thing running and so there it is and
here we go into the game and there's
there's our little dude and he's going
around so okay so good we did it a lot
of ground covered there and like I said
we were going to want to kind of go
through this stuff a little more slowly
that's like the first pass we're gonna
go want to go through each part of that
a little more slowly as we sort of
expand out our usage of open G
to encompass actual rendering of the
game instead of just splitting of the
image but that was it and hopefully you
guys could actually see that like I said
I don't actually know if you can but
hopefully you can I'm not sure so yeah
let's see here let's go ahead and go to
some Q &amp; A if you guys have any
questions now would be a great time to
put a Q :
up on the screen for me to look at yeah
wretched freak you use static instead of
local persister in it yeah that's
because this is not actually this is not
staying right in fact I not it's it's so
not saying we should probably just get
rid of it right now like we can just do
this if we want for the moment so yeah
we just have to do that at some point
you know this has to happen so I just
didn't feel like bothering at that
particular moment so actually when we do
in it OpenGL as soon as we actually make
our current thing we can go ahead and
engine our texture there so as soon as
we have a context we can Jen our texture
that's really all that has to happen
where is that whipped texture
yeah I just didn't want to do that at
that time but that's not gonna you know
that's not gonna stay in there Nixie can
we verify the vsync somehow oh we have
not actually requested vsync yet to be
clear we have not requested vsync yet so
there's nothing to verify we have not
asked OpenGL to vsync us that's that's a
little bit later
let's see soy sauce the kid are there
any stretching issues when going from UV
coordinates to screen coordinates if so
how would you fix it there are if like I
said it Maps screens it maps the unit
cube directly to the window to the
viewport there so in this case I believe
we are one-to-one but if you didn't if
you you would hat you do have to make
sure that those line up I mean that is
that it you do have to make sure the
points you're passing in do line up
properly so I'm not I'm not sure what
you mean by necessarily how can you how
would you fix it you have to make sure
the math is correct to to line it up but
let's see here the texture name your
binding is always zero after the first
iteration no no it's not why do you say
that messy oh that I disagree with that
insofar us I think an old open Jill you
don't ever need GL gen textures you can
just pick your own arbitrary intz I
don't think that's true
I'm pretty sure you have to call Jen
textures but we can test it we can
certainly test it so let's see here
yeah
so global blit texture handle let's see
what happens if I just set it to one
alright maybe that just works
are you sure that works I'm not sure if
that actually works though still because
that might just be setting the default
texture always that might just be
setting texture zero jr. and I mean so
I'm not sure I still don't actually know
if that's a fair test you'd have to be
able to set two textures and pick
between them if that makes sense
not sure how to do a good test of that
at the moment I do know how to test that
so if that were true I should then be
able to set a different texture here
after submitting this one I should be
able to set like texture ten and get
white again because that texture doesn't
have anything in it right
all right I am like I literally never
knew that that is totally news to me and
I have no I so wait are you telling me
there was never any reason to call gl
gem textures ever that makes no sense I
didn't how did I never know that I've
never heard anyone mentioned that I
totally I have nothing I'm speechless
how is that possible
that look why do they even have Jen
textures that's very strange wood
texture filtering GL nearest even occur
when image and texture size is the same
as it is now
yes filtering always occurs so what
happens is it's always going to do if if
you set something other than nearest if
you set GL linear for example to do
bilinear filtering what it will do is it
will still apply the bilinear filtering
and it will just so happen that the
coefficients of bilinear filtering end
up to be zero and one
like zero zero zero one and so you'd
still get the correct sampling in theory
assuming the card does it right and
there's no weird bugs or anything but
the the filtering is still applied it
just doesn't actually look like anything
happened but it's still happening Kerry
Johansson in your professional career
what GPU library have you preferred to
just OpenGL DirectX GLSL etc I tend to
use OpenGL because it's more
cross-platform but I don't really like
any of them I think they're all pretty
bad they're definitely not how I would
design it can tell you that
criminal dragon later on after we
upgrade to more modern OpenGL with a
game render into a frame buffer and then
on to the same triangles or will you
just have it render directly to the main
window buffer well I guess that depends
if you have any post past effects so if
you have any post fast effects then you
render the game into a buffer and do
some effects on that buffer like
sequentially usually like ping pong or
not usually ping pong but usually like
using a buffer chain and then you
finally the last thing you do is you
resolve the buffer - to actually display
it but you you will often render your
game into something that's not the final
thing you're gonna flip if that makes
sense
let's see here I need to check climb
even saw a chat clients thing I can't
see anything
Oh computers they're so great let's see
let's see here before you remove the
unit variable and inline Ashland the
texture you were always passing zero as
the name by the way
oh I see what you're saying yeah okay
because I forgot to put a static in
front of the thing is that what you're
saying
I maybe forgot to say static which could
have been true messy Elda so there is no
way to blitt directly to the back buffer
anymore
well it depends what you mean right I
mean technically that the back buffer
quote-unquote is on a separate card so
there's obviously no way for the CPU to
directly write to it it has to go across
the PCI bus now in the directdraw days
what happened is they would map the
memory so that as you wrote to the
memory in main memory would it would
basically you know actually be mapped so
that would right out to the card so it
would like right through the PCI bus and
it would appear that the CPU was writing
directly to the graphics card but it
wasn't really writing right as we're
still going over the PCI bus so nowadays
since things are so much more
asynchronous you just that would be a
very slow way to do it what you'd rather
do is get it in memory somewhere and
then tell the guard to come get it right
and so it went it changed from being
something that was a direct cpu right to
being something that was like more of a
gather from the car because it's just
way more efficient I don't know that
there's no way to blitt directly to it
though presumably if you wrote you could
still write a direct route driver
potentially if you wanted to that that
allowed you to basically map some GPU
memory and write directly to it it might
still work it just wouldn't be a very
efficient way to do it compared to I
think what they currently do
if that makes sense is there a
difference in speed now we use OpenGL to
move the buffer to the GPU no I mean
there shouldn't really be a yeah I don't
think there's gonna be any I mean I
didn't see any we we didn't really we
weren't super measuring it but no I mean
I think it's basically the same it might
even be a little slower than it was
before
because it's a little it's gonna be a
little less predictable now the way that
it works so it's it's you know it's it's
not the greatest way to to get something
on the screen to render it yourself and
then hand it off to a graphics library
but yes I mean you can see right here
like you kind of oscillates but the
frame time is something like you know
between 50 and 60 milliseconds and you
know we can if we want to get rid of the
in it and do that just do the blit
ourselves let's see here
stretch bits
yeah so it doesn't look particularly
different not particularly different I
guess not too much the other thing you
have to remember is the double buffer is
turned off so you guys can see it if I
was to turn that off right I don't know
if if if allowing double buffering would
also improve the speed of things let me
just check yeah it might so it might be
that also not having did the the
concession we're making for streaming
there to allow the streaming capture
that that may also be hurting us a bit
but you know
Carrie Johansson is there a way you know
of to optimize PCI transfers between CPU
and GPU using OpenGL yeah I don't think
there's actually gonna be anything
particularly optimized I don't think
there's very much you could do to
optimize this particular transfer and
the reason for that is basically you're
just sending down a texture and you're
drawing at once and that's all that's
happening I think the driver will
probably do a pretty good job of that
you know the only thing I can think of
that you might be able to do is is get
rid of the extra copy here by well okay
so let's say that you cared about how
long this took right here to copy into
the driver memory you could possibly
overlap that by doing this on a separate
thread while you started rendering the
rest of your stuff right so I don't
think you could optimize the time that
it's taking to transfer this really in
any big way because like apparently and
this is might be a little bit old but at
least previously it was actually a
slower way to go to lock memory on the
GPU side to lock a region of memory
write it into there let go and allow it
to transfer that out that was actually
slower because it caused what are called
a synchronization point in the driver
which is basically saying that the
driver has to kind of coordinate with
the GPU at that point to find it bytes
of memory that's gonna lock down for
that or whatever and so this was
actually a faster way to do those
transfers but while it's doing the copy
while the driver is taking the text
image call what you could do is do that
like we could do this on a thread so all
of our OpenGL happened on a thread so
that while we were transferring the
other image we could be rendering you
know we could be actually doing work
like running the game simulation or
something that so
while you're not really speeding it up
you're overlapping it more that could
potentially be right but again I don't
think this is not a huge part of our
time anyway so I'm not sure that's a
really big deal
all right I think we are done
I don't know if this is applicable to
the last question either just got here
but geotextile beverage TV could be
faster than geotextile to D I seriously
doubt that because you're replacing in
fact I think it could be slower in this
case because the card passed a detect
that you're not replacing the texture
right so so Shawn just to give you why I
think that would be a bad idea for this
although I don't know for sure is so
tech sub image which you already know
but I'm just gonna tell it for other
people so text image 2d just romps over
the entire thing right
so it just replaces everything in the
image text sub image 2d replaces just a
piece so the rest of the texture stays
the same so why would I think that this
one might be faster than this one okay
the reason is because if you look at
what's actually going to happen here
what's going to happen here in terms of
like the sequence of events right is
you've got the GPU and you've got the
CPU the GPU here in this case like I'm
coming to the CPU I call GL text image
okay
just specify an image that's going to
basically copy things this is that's
gonna do the copy right then it's gonna
kick off a transfer of the GPU then it's
gonna put a fence it's gonna fence right
so that it knows when that texture is
done because the texture is actually
getting used well if that could really
put a fence probably what it's gonna do
is it's gonna create it I don't even
know why I drew this diagram it's gonna
create a dependency chain let's just
talk about that way it's gonna create a
dependency chain and the dependency
chain looks like this right it looks
like GL swap buffers at the bottom right
the swap buffers call depends directly
on the those primitives that GL begin
end right
and that GL begin end depends on that
texture okay so when the graphics card
sees GL text sub image what that does is
that means for frame 1 this is the swap
buffers on frame 1 let's say or frame 0
okay and this is the texture on frame 0
when I call GL Tech's image it knows
that you're replacing the image entirely
so on frame the next frame the
dependency chain looks like this right
they're totally separate so it's not it
doesn't have to worry can issue these in
complete parallel right what happens if
I do text sub image is the dependency
chain actually looks like this right it
says oh I can't use a separate one here
it's actually this one and I gotta wait
for this to finish because it's using
this one before I can do let me draw
this a little bit better right the
depending looks like this everyone
depends on this including this texture
update because it can update the texture
till this guy's done so in a sense it
ends up pointing to here which
serializes these guys into just a big
old chain right so now I have a chain
that's six deep dependency instead of
two-three deeps right so text some image
is usually a bad idea if you're just
replacing the whole image you usually
don't want to do that because you're
letting the graphics card fix it right
if that makes sense
so yeah yes uh Sean so I don't I don't
think that's the case I could be wrong
about that but I don't think that's the
case I think most drivers would prefer
it the other way round so yeah but at
the very least if it was so if GL tech
sub image 2d actually was faster for
some reason you would probably still
want to break the dependency chain so
you'd probably still want to create two
textures one for ultra either or like
even odd parity does that make sense so
yeah so one thing I can tell you for
sure for example is you definitely don't
want to do that with vertex buffers
right like you definitely don't want to
do sub range updates of an index buffer
or a vertex buffer it's way faster if
you're replacing all of them to just
have a separate buffer right because you
just don't want to create the finished
reigns text image 2d doesn't text sub
image and text image don't neither they
don't have to do anything separate but
it can be implemented sacked ly the same
in the driver right saying it has to
allocute storage the texture well that's
not any that's that's what allows you to
break the dependency chain right so the
driver probably understands that and
will know that it can make a second slop
the second time it sees the GL texture
and then it'll have to for that texture
which is just good right so yeah I'd be
real surprised but like I said you know
we'd have to actually time it or ask an
actual driver person to tell us in this
case it's not taking enough time as it
is I think probably for us to even
notice
meaning I'm pretty sure that like we
could switch between them either way
and we'd never know we'd have to
actually put in some better timing to
even tell like the frame times probably
is too variant right now especially with
the especially with the I'm not gonna
bout doing it right now but it's too
variant right now especially with the
streaming to really have any idea which
one of those faster is by switching we'd
have to do some kind of better timing to
really even tell quarter Tron at what
point in the chain of GL commands does
the card actually get involved command
dependent driver dependent entirely
driver dependent as far as I know well
can card dependent I mean it's it's
entirely dependent on how they chose to
optimize things
all right I'm gonna wrap it up yeah so
GL text image versus text image if you
guys want to play with it you probably
could create a pretty easy test case for
it
well I mean this is an okay test case
just got it you have to put in some
better timing and run it on a machine
that's not streaming I think
all right I'm gonna wrap it up let's go
ahead and close this down
that's not quite closed
all right everybody thank you for
joining me for another episode of
handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along at home you can
always peer to the game on Hammacher org
and it comes with a source code so you
could follow along and for example if
you'd like to play with timing text
images 2d verses sub image 2d for
whatever that's worth you could do that
there is a forum site you can go to ask
questions a patreon page we have if you
wants about the video series and a tweet
bot if you would like to follow the
series live it tells you when we're
going to be live so you can plan your
whole life around handmade hero we will
be back next week and I will post the
schedule to that tweet bot so check it
during the weekend or Monday morning to
see when we're going to be live until
then have a good weekend programming and
I will see you guys on the Internet take
it easy everyone