hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode a complete-game live on
stream we are going to go use our
parsing our tag parsing that we've
implemented to try to rebuild our entire
HHA set with the exception of fonts
because we're gonna take a look at those
as a sort of separate thing we're gonna
rebuild everything but the font HHA set
strictly from the tag files that's what
we'd like to get accomplished today
maybe that's a little bit ambitious for
today but at least we want to get most
of that accomplished today and so that
next weekend we can kind of look at
wrapping that up and having kind of a
nice art asset pipeline that we are
happy with and think will be sufficient
for not only shipping the game but
allowing people who are modifying the
game or adding their own things to the
game to have a reasonable time doing so
right so you know making it so that we
don't really have a lot of concerns
about how that would work
so we have we've had one request today
and oops you know what I am not even my
keyboard switcher was not even switched
on to the correct the correct that sir
okay sorry about that my keyboard
switcher was still switched to the other
machine so that's about to start typing
into the machine that actually runs the
stream which would not have been good
who knows what that would have done all
kinds of crazy stuff perhaps with as I
was like trying to figure out why the
keyboard isn't working as I was trying
to say today is Dave 512 which of course
as you know is a power of two we will
possibly never have another power of two
on hand made here oh I don't know it's
possible that we'll go to date 1024 but
it's also possible perhaps even likely
that we'll stop somewhere on you know
day 800 or something will be the last
stream when we sign off I've said we're
doing at least 600 so we never getting
past there but I never say anything
about doing over a thousand so we may
stop before day 1024 and so in
honor of the 512 stream we had a request
on the pre stream that I use my
announcer voice for at least part of the
episode I don't really use the announcer
voice much anymore because I I'm more
comfortable just doing regular talking
on Twitch you know when I first started
doing the series I I did an announcer
voice for folks and I guess some people
miss it which is totally fair and I
think that's a totally reasonable
request so without further ado I will
start doing announcer style for this day
512 I can't remember who asked for it
who asked for it I've read the sequel
ask for it I've read the sequel this one
is for you I wish I had some almond milk
sorry I don't I don't have any okay
ladies and gentlemen we are here at
handmade hero as was the case with the
very first time that we did programming
on handmade hero I am doing my announcer
voice by request for day 512 really
excited today because today we are going
to be looking at the parsing code and
seeing if we can actually get it to
generate some hhas now it's not a given
there's a lot of things that can go
wrong here we've tested the parser so
that we know the parser works pretty
darn well but here's the thing it's
reading into sort of the asset system
which as we know just deals with packed
assets any time you're trying to go
directly into a runtime format like that
it's a little bit dicey it's one of the
reasons that people often don't try to
pull off something like this they
typically use more intermediate object
formats and stuff like that or they kind
of move things through the pipeline a
little bit more slowly than this but
that's okay this is handmade here oh
we're good for it we can go ahead and
try so I am not concerned about it I
just think you might expect it to take a
little bit longer as we kind of work our
way through it now I'm gonna pop open
the hand mate here a project here so all
the files are loaded we're gonna first
jump into that asset system as I said we
did a lot of the work already so we're
kind of in good shape here everything's
you know in a reasonable setup so you
know we've left ourselves a good chance
of success remember we've got this parse
hht here and what we're doing right now
is we're calling that with a couple
different things
first of all we'll give me the a game
asset structure and I remember this
thing allows us to get at absolutely
everything that's stored in the asset
system at any give
time as far as a game know so it's low
to the hhas it knows about all the
source files that we've actually used so
far because it's actually created sort
of a backing like a backing network if
you will but tell us where absolutely
everything is so that's the key for us
differentiating anything that comes in
anew it's a key for us to be able to
look up and say do we already know about
this thing do we have this things stored
already in an HHA if so we can just
update it if not then we're gonna have
to add a new thing for it and so on so
that's where all the tags go that's
where all the the sort of higher level
information goes after we kind of get it
into the system we've also got this
import source info import source info
very important structure tells us about
where it's coming from now write that
import starts info tells us things now
what you could kind of see here is that
the flow is a little bit broken wise a
little bit programmer I remember where
you do this before is we're iterating
over PNG files first okay we were saying
look operating system tell me where all
the PMT's are looking each PMG in series
okay take that say what's the source if
over that PNG right what's the name of
it what's the last right modification
time okay that's the formation we had
for a PNG we were looking for it we then
know that PNG maps to a game asset okay
one of those game assets we've already
processed it maps to it or it doesn't if
we haven't seen it yet but if we have
see before it maps to one of those
things so that source info represents a
particular PNG backing file now what's
the problem here can you see it
hopefully you can before we were doing
with the import changed assets we're
looting of the PNG we have the source
info coming into the stage where we're
looking at things for the first time
that's where that source info is coming
from we're not gonna have that here at
parse hht this time so it's a little
premature for us to flow that down the
pipeline like this import source infos
actually gonna happen
in the next stage right why because the
h80 is just one big text file and it's
got a number of blocks each of which
refer to one of those specific PNG files
so every single block we parse we're
going to be generating a new source info
don't believe me well let's take a look
if I go over here to import source info
like so what you can see is it's got a
name a description and an author the
name is the thing that's going to name
this but
Euler asset the description is the thing
that tells us about the asset we want
and the author is a thing that said who
made it now we don't know that stuff
till we parse the block right so that's
where this big change is coming from so
again we did this I'm not upset that we
did this is totally fine we were just
trying to piece together the process
from before we were we were locking the
two things in together to make sure that
they float all right so we weren't
thinking about that time and we were
supposed to be thinking about the time
but now that we're gonna get it working
correctly we need to start thinking
about how that flow goes so the first
I'm going to do is remove that import
source info we're gonna move it over
here to parse top level block because
that's where it's going to go okay so we
know that that's gonna come in here
somewhere all right so we don't actually
want this hht context to actually have
this in it anymore because that hht
context is really the thing that flows
from top level block the top level block
and so that's kind of coming in here now
what you can also see is hey look at
this
it's basically destruct so really we
already had this concept from before we
just remade it it was just kind of a
slight mistake that we made there where
we're thinking like ah whoops right so
we don't really want that we don't
really want that at all so this import
source info it's actually something that
we can generate almost entirely to pass
down we don't really have to track it at
all so when we actually come in here to
parse pieces right infinitive parse
pieces we were actually gonna have to
pass that source info we would just
generate it right here because we have
the actual information now there's
something to remind yourself up here you
can notice we had that there was that
name field there why was there a name
field there well turns out you can name
each individual one of these assets I
don't know that we really want to do
that but we have the ability to do it
why do we have the ability to do it well
if we look at the source file format
right so here's the file format for
handmade here what we decide to do is
have these annotations the annotation
can be stripped we probably won't strip
them but we designed it to be stripped
as sort of a nod towards professional
programming where we're saying like look
you'd probably want to strip these if
you're actually shipping this as an
unmodeled game this game will be shipped
in a way that allows people to mod it
obviously because hey the old point of
handmade hero is that you learn to
program so we're probably not gonna
strip these annotations but we want to
be able to say you could strip them if
you wanted to so you want to run the
game without any of the cruft
that's sitting there that's giving you
this markup you could strip these
annotations but if you look at what's in
the annotations themselves
you can see we've got the source file
date source file checksum the base name
offset the asset name asset description
author the Airstream right sorry it's
the base name AUSA I assume a base name
right all assets in there asset name
that's the one right that we don't fill
out currently nobody fills that out we
don't have a name for the asset right so
what we want to do here is say well wait
now we could if we wanted to we might as
well support the features that we
actually created so if we go into that
hht which I guess I haven't loaded yet
so I don't know why I thought I could
bring it up but here we go
it's right here right if we went into
this hht what I could do is say oh all
right so if I wanted to name one of
these things I could I couldn't cure say
that I've got a name for this you know
this this block whatever it is block for
us though one I could just call this
like you know forest terrain or
something if I wanted to now again I
don't actually know that we care about
this we don't know but we've got the
ability to do it so we buy diesel
support in the parser and you see what
happens because basically free for us to
do so if you look at what's happening
here the author of the description these
things are just meaningless feels that
we parsed they take almost no effort to
do we can simplify even further than
we've simplified it here if you want to
by just having a closet of a set of name
fields based on an enum we don't even
need to do that right now it's not
necessary so I'm not gonna bother doing
that but if you look I can just sort of
do it here as a way of saying look let's
just get the name into our fields as we
were doing everything else and then we
now support that right so now we've
magically got that working so now the
agency the the hht feels that we've got
there we could support them all we can
support all the things that were
actually in that part of the the file
format exactly as they were so that's
great that's all done and now we know
what that source info is that we've
looked at it we can generate that at any
time so if someone actually wants that
source info we're good to go
where would we use that source info well
now let's start to peel that apart right
because let's let's look at where that
was actually going on drop down in here
and report our assets here's where parse
pieces was getting called right right
here you could see how a parse piece was
getting called we're still be calling
parse pieces remember we did the work to
generate that tag stuff we still got a
little more work to do because we have
two packs with those tags into an append
array we want to have a way of appending
those tags that we read inside the text
file right these tags
here right we need to append those to
everything in addition to the ones that
we automatically fill in on the grid for
the user as part of that knowledge of
what is a block what is a character we
know certain tags apply to every single
grid right each individual grid cell in
one of those files has an acidic set of
tags that always go with it but then
there's the additional tags that come
from the actual agency markup file those
have to get combined right so what we
want to do is parse that tag array into
a tag block then the other tags that are
coming from you automatically me
understood ones from the cell layout
those are sort of getting merged
together each time I do it and we can
probably clean up the way that's
happening right now you know it's a
little bit janky the way that's doing
that we're just trying to keep the code
that we have we could try to tease that
out a little bit more there's a bunch of
things that we could do if we really
wanted to that we would be able to sort
of like make that a little bit more of a
a programmable or richer system we could
consider that a little later on right
now I don't want to put too many things
in the mix at once I just want to do it
as close as positive regional way that
we're going to do it right so that's
fine anyway when we go back here to the
parts pieces set the parts pieces set is
going to give us back the import type so
the import so it's getting acted on here
if you look at how that import type is
being acted on what you can see is that
in there the source info is actually
getting pushed down because multi-talent
import signal time prayer and plate
import all generate actual assets in the
backing asset store in the HHA right
when it generates those hht assets
that's what it needs those strings so
that's the time that we need to provide
this info structure and so if you look
at how that was happening up here right
we can just mirror this process almost
exactly the way that we were going to do
it before so let's go ahead and do that
let's just pull this code out because
it's exactly the code that we need let's
just pull this code out and work with it
so I'm gonna grab it here I'm gonna pull
it up to do this parse top level block
we've got when we come through here
after we're done parsing assuming that
we had a valid parse right because I can
if I want to I can couch this I can say
look as I went through here I did
bunch of parsing I can always do a
really simple check mirror we designed
that parser pretty nice that was the
primary parts of tokenizer we designed
that token as your nightly show that it
just remembers if it's ever had an error
so when we're doing parsing we can just
say look if there was ever an error we
don't want to do this so we just wrap it
in an if parsing block and off we go
right so that's really a pretty simple
way to make sure that we don't get into
here I'm gonna move it over here so it's
outside away in my head right I'm that's
a pretty simple way to make sure that
we're not gonna have any problems
processing our data when we actually got
some kind of a bogus block in the file
right so we're just only keep it -
syntactically correct blocks that's the
only kind that we're gonna process we
won't look at anything else
we'll stop the processing there and say
look you got a problem your HTTP I'll
fix it and then we'll talk right so
parse pieces really wants to go down
here and this is why I was saying before
this found equals true or found equals
false or is that we kind of want to
change a little bit about the way that's
working I think that import type is
really the you know sort of something
that wants to happen a little later on
and so on so we really want to do I
think is we want to say when we set up
the default situation here that's more
what we're looking for so when we come
through here we want to pull out this
part where we grab and you can sort of
see there's one part week we we have an
issue this require token part we do the
token string we still need that part
here to occur only in the case where
it's not the default right so we still
want to be able to do it this way we say
look is it the default blah blah blah
doesn't have a name if it does have a
name or if it rather there's nothing
well block it does have a names to make
sure we get that and get that file name
out of there but either way we just need
to know which one it is
and so the found part of things is gonna
change I'm gonna change us to is default
and I'm gonna say that the is default is
true I'm sorry as false I'm gonna say
that is default gets set to true on the
case for the token equals the default
otherwise what I'm gonna do down here is
say alright we'll get the filename and
we'll leave is default to false right so
hopefully that makes sense
for everybody
okay so now as we go what we want to do
down here is say look if pretty much
period we want a partial thing but if
it's the default block we don't want to
process any art assets right like we
don't want to do anything with art
assets if we don't yeah if we if we are
saying that we're just gonna set the
default settings for any given block we
don't want to like read PNG or like
create the tag the matrix for the tag
grid and all that sort of stuff right we
don't want to do that ever if we're
actually just parts of people up block
we just want to get the defaults in and
be done with it so we want to make sure
that we do that check later so I'm gonna
go ahead and grab this part here we're
gonna move it down and then we're
getting rid of that found right this
found thing is not we want we want an if
default and we want that to happen down
here so what we want to do is say all
right in the case that we have a default
then we're gonna set that if up down
here to deal with that right so if it is
not the default then off we go so all of
this stuff here right this all just
works fine now
what I could do and this now gives us
the opportunity to make this maybe even
a little more clean than it was before i
we've got those fields right we've got
these fields here these HTT fields what
I could do is say look let's take those
fields and let's let's think about a
little bit how we want those to work if
I just said from now on we've got hht
fields and that's gonna start out with
nothing in it right we just have to wait
we've got no no fields in there we look
and see if it's the default we you know
we're gonna do this and if it wasn't we
gonna do this what if we just said now
let's not do that let's just say is
default is directly defined by this
right so meaning we just set is default
right away and then the only thing that
we actually need to do here is we just
need to say well if it's not the default
then we need to read in that file name
but otherwise we don't have to right
then this whole thing can just operate
on the fields array that we've got right
so I can replace all of those that were
previously using
in Texas the dot syntax we're just
putting it into our local the one on the
stack right and then what I could do is
say at the end once we've parsed all of
the stuff like everything that there is
right at the end if it's the default
then we'll write the default otherwise
we'll merge in the default right and
similarly up here we could do that part
as well if we want to I don't really
know you know in other words we could do
it this way where we're saying look if
it's the default well actually I guess
it's it's just this part to be honest
right we would just say look if it's the
default then we don't have to do
anything if it is other than the default
then we write our fields from the the
ones that are in the in the context
right so that's like if it's a default
we go just by reading a new set of
defaults and presumably we don't want to
keep the defaults from before because
maybe you were trying to remove some
defaults or something I'm not sure we
could choose to merge default I'm not
sure which one we want to do it would
the only difference would be we would
put this line up here and I just don't
know which of those we want to do I
suppose you can always clear defaults by
just putting in a quote unquote
so maybe you want to just have them you
know let's just let's just say that we
always cascade defaults so so that would
just look like this right so the fields
always gets initialized to the defaults
and then even if you're reading defaults
then all we do is just like overwrite
ones that you change what we keep any
ones that you didn't talk about so that
just parses straight through and then at
the end we say look if it's the default
we'll write back the default right so
we'll say the default fields come from
whichever fields we just process
otherwise we just process this as a
normal art asset right so now you can
see that got a little cleaner this is
now straight line code you don't have to
read anything around it or in that stuff
literally the only thing we do is say
well if it's a default it doesn't have a
name because we just don't put one there
so we don't require you to have that
name string that we would otherwise
require to have that's the only
difference right between them so all
this stuff flows properly now I think
looks nice to me we've got the default
handling or not as appropriate in here
we can also say that we won't set the
default if we could we can if this
entire thing if you want to so it looks
a little bit more like that and that way
we just say look don't enter this block
unless things went
properly now the other thing we can do
here is go and do this part a little bit
differently as well so we'll do it like
that
so now we could do is make our parse
pieces call actually get all the data
that it actually needed because we've
already parsed everything I mean only
big if the only big if is this guy right
here we haven't done him yet but that's
okay because actually is gonna be pretty
simple we're just gonna use the tag
builder we already have and then parse
the array that comes back from it or I
should say pass the array that comes
back to it over to parse pieces as the
append tag type it's gonna be easy
you'll see trust me on this one's gonna
be easy alright so anyway we come down
through here but this import tag array
that we do for a pen that's the thing
that we know we're gonna have to deal
with that in a little bit right so that
append tagger is gonna have to be up
here and it's gonna have to get filled
out by this part sag list so I mean I
might as well just do that and say hey
give us back the tag right I guess I
could do another way and say look return
that to us there we go um so and maybe
I'll call that append tags just to make
it a little bit clearer what that is
okay someone's reading through the code
just the word depends like what's going
on there so we got a pin tags we're
gonna grab those tags out those the
Pentax are gonna get added on here right
and then we've got those imported tags
right here so this little thing where we
do parse pieces that should actually
work because I think we poured it all
yesterday it should be pretty good
actually so I think we're actually
fairly good to go there then what's
gonna happen is when we're done with
that what we're gonna do is we're gonna
get back whatever the import type is you
can see how we're doing this here this
was old news we don't really need that
anymore because we got this right up
here here's the code that allows us to
actually do the import and then here is
the part where we air out on the case
where we don't actually know what the
block type is so we just need that block
token to get passed in here I remember
the block token was passed in to us
right and so we you know kind of know
there what's going on all right so once
we have all of that working and we do
that parse pieces and all that stuff and
everything's fine dandy this is the only
part that we now have to parse remember
we've got some some busy work to do here
we need to know like sort of stuff about
where we're gonna put the memory and all
that sort stuff we have all that worked
out it's not really a big deal but we
need to kind of merge these things
together and so if you look here
we've got the error stream you can see
where we've got the the error buffer
going here and what we wanted to do in
each of these cases is we want the error
stream to go with the file in question
so any time we get errors we want to
vector them towards the file in question
now in order to do that we want to start
making it so that we're looking at which
file is talked about by the block so if
the block says block o1 bla bla bla bla
or whatever dot PNG we want to put all
the errors so that they are on that PNG
so anyways looking at that page here as
in wants to ask about was in on this PNG
work okay it'll be like no it didn't if
there was an error in there so we've got
those recorded with the actual art asset
as well as whatever the actual import
process is so we kind of want that to be
a little bit clearer so let's see how we
start to make this stuff all flow
together first of all this needs the
temporary nough that's totally fine
because we can add that in here so you
know we've got the temporary note put in
the context no problem so anyone who
wanted to use a temporary nough here i
can just do that although it you know
what now i look at it it looks like it
only wants it local it doesn't really
even need it for anything else so to be
honest with you i guess we don't even
need that it can just do it here so
that's all fine so that just looks like
it's totally fine it'll it'll handle
itself no issues so really i guess what
we need is here we need that the file
group that we're opening the file with
and then we've got some some more
information here that we've got to fill
in like that file infrastructure
remember we added support to the
platform layer yesterday to be able to
give us file infos by name so you should
be able to use that here to construct a
name that we can then get a filing for
from so that's going to be the main
thing other than that this all looks
like it flows you can see it getting the
file buffer size here it's going to read
the data in that's going to close it
it's gonna look at the matching and see
whether or not the thing changed since
the last time it read it and if it did
or didn't it's going to have to do some
time frames now there's an interesting
thing about this that we're going to
have to consider that's a little bit
Swing key here right and this parts
going to be hard
we don't know whether or not the user
has changed the data in the hht that
corresponds to this file right we're
looking at the PMG we can see whether or
not you've touched a PNG because the
date on the PNG will tell us whether or
not it's the same as the one that we
read in last time if the two dates are
different then we have reason to believe
that they've changed right so that's
pretty simple we don't have to do a lot
of work there to know whether we should
be processed a file really clean and
simple not a lot of problems there now
there are really you know you could say
well the date isn't completely
dispositive you know maybe the dates say
the same or who knows what right we'd
only care about crazy education like
this because the person could always
retouch the file if they for some reason
it's not reinforcing for them if some
weird education occurs so don't really
care too much about that but we know
that the file date will give us that
information pretty much anytime that
there's any bit of substantive change -
the thing is I'm gonna repaint anything
in it receives it it's gonna have a
different file date on it on that
machine so it will force re-importation
and so that works totally fine what
doesn't work totally fine is the fact
that when are we looking here and we see
that the hht file has these tags or the
name or the description or anything else
in there we don't know whether that has
changed so that information that's in
the hht file that says what should
happen Zack could have changed and the
only way we can really know whether that
has changed or not is to actually do
some kind of a diff on the data right
we're going to have to have some kind of
of checksumming
that says is this actual data different
because if the data is different then
we're going to have to do something
about it
and the data's not different then we
only have to do something about it if
the underlying files date has changed or
the checksum we also do check something
in here as sort of a backup to the file
date right
that's trickier so if we go over to the
shared side of things we actually have a
murmur hash that was thrown in here
right this thing right here and we have
the ability to do sort of this mirror
hash update and so if we want to murmur
hash something you can see we call this
checksum of and we give it a buffer
right and we can also just feed it one
thing at a time right you can see here
we can just call murmur hash update as
many times as we want to and then call
murmur hash finalize and be done with it
right so if we wanted to we could
actually in here have a thing that check
sums the actual data that we're going to
store prior to doing anything else right
and so what we could do is say let's
start check something that in addition
to the rest of the stuff that we check
something so that we can know whether or
not this thing changed right so we can
know whether or not the PNG changed or
not now if you look at what happens in
here we can start getting now into the
part that's going to be a little bit
sort of a squeakier right this part is
the part that's going to be tough okay
so if you look at what happens here we
generate the string hash we get the the
backing file and then we see whether the
dates have changed if the dates have
changed then we start processing the
thing we need to duplicate this logic
certainly so that we can do the same
sort of backing store testing that we've
done before the problem is like I said
we don't know whether the ATAC changed
and I don't know where we're gonna store
that information I guess we have to put
some checksumming into the annotations
for the HHA file I'm not sure what else
we could do I think we're gonna have to
do that because you don't really have
any other way now we left ourselves
space to throw it in there seems like
we're probably gonna have to if you take
a look at what we've actually got here
in terms of check something I'm not sure
where we were putting that information
it looks like source file checksum is
what we store there right so you can
kind of see that we're keeping that
information and so the source file
checksum probably has to be augmented to
be like hht block checksum and
that block of data that actually tells
us what you know that actually describes
the file that's gonna have to be
checksum I don't see any other way
around it do you I don't
so I'm gonna go ahead and add it in
there so I think in our H of T
annotation we're going to have to have a
thing called like hht block checksum
like so and that will use one of our u
64 so we didn't have in there what we're
gonna have to do is build that H woops I
spelled it wrong we're gonna have to
build that checksum in there and
furthermore in here where we got the
loaded HHA annotation we don't actually
I don't really know where that's
actually gonna use I'm gonna take a
quick look actually to see where that's
gonna use cuz I don't know so if I do a
quick check for where that's actually
getting used it's only getting used in
the hej edit at the moment it looks like
so basically what's happening in there
is when you load those in they go in
here and there I guess they're probably
being used for like transferring things
back and forth that is important so
let's go ahead and put that in here so
this is the hht block checksum I'm just
gonna call it that and what I'm gonna do
is let me go in there and look at any
place that we were previously using
those annotations I want to make sure
that we we cop capture both of those and
so here I'm gonna go over here some of
my head's not in the way if we look at
those check sums that we've got here you
can see them getting printed out here
all I want to do is just augment this so
that we have the hht block checksum in
both cases right and that allows us to
copy these around and do all the stuff
that we were doing before with our HHA
files without having to really worry
about it right so we know that now the
hht block checksum will get kind of
convected around in that way so that
seems fine to me again I don't see any
other way to do it if I saw a simpler
way to make sure we were keeping up to
date I would but I just don't know any
other way to do it I can't think of
anything that would help there so when
we're printing this out like again this
this sort of from situation I will I
will also add the hht printout in here
so that we have an H at each checksum so
here I'm going to put that in as a
key and and I'm gonna put hht block
checks them and we'll just call that
done for now and then we just actually
have to use it so I'm gonna go ahead and
build right and get that going and then
I'm gonna go jump back to what we were
doing before
okay so a Pentax we haven't done yet and
all this sort of stuff we're gonna have
to start making all this stuff work
clean and make sure that everything's
fine okay so two sets of things there's
that source file checksum I don't even
know for really using that right now I
don't think we actually do an out if the
check sums match I think we leave it
sort of the way it is but what we want
to do here is kind of move and move
forward a little bit on that now there's
there's a couple things there's a little
bit of an issue there that I want to
talk about real for it's just that the
tiny a little bit so if you go back to
what's happening with the check sums and
the file dates file dates are great for
letting the system know whether or not
it should process the particular file or
look at that file for changes right now
there is a thing that we probably did
and I don't know maybe we did it wrong
I'll kind of explain you what the
problem is and then you can sort of
think about whether we did it wrong or
we did it right it's hard to say so
inside the HTT annotation you can see
that we store the source file date right
that source file date is actually stored
in the HHA file itself and it says hey
this is my the the date of the PNG or
whatever that that you know that this
this thing came from right that's that
that's the date now there's an issue so
if I go here oops I want to show you
what I'm talking about just just give
you a full illustration so let's suppose
that I mistake to hand me a hero
site okay if I inspect this bitmap here
or whatever right I'm gonna get an
actual PNG you know here's the PNG it's
stored on the web somewhere right now
that PNG wasn't made today that PNG was
made a long time ago when I made this
website right but if I were to save this
image so you know let's say I let's say
I go here and that you can grab this out
right there's the path to the actual
image so I stick that on here
I say well you know what let's take a
look at the image there it is right I
hit save image as and I'll just save it
to the desktop as exactly what the name
of the thing is and I'm gonna open it
here it is so now this is local on my
machine same image exactly the same
right the problem is if I then go to the
desktop here and I look at the
properties of this image what you can
see is that the date right
the last modification time is today why
do I bring this up the problem is when
people download these things from the
internet the PNG s for hand made here or
anything else it's gonna have the date
they downloaded it so all of those dates
are not gonna match the first time they
download that gives us the following
problem and I don't know if it's a
problem but I'm just trying to give you
what it is
I haven't HHH file the agency file I got
what my distribution a hand made here
inside the HHA files the checksum and
the date of the source file that was
used to create it so far so good problem
is if I download all the sets of pngs
and I say hey do you need to rebuild
anything it's gonna go look and say all
of these dates mich match now we've got
to check some so it's not a huge deal
it's gonna look at the checksum and say
oh you know what the check sums actually
matched so it turns out the date was
just it's just the day in the file got
changed but didn't actually update I
don't have to update this HHA great news
problem is where's it gonna put that
information so it doesn't have to check
it next time it's gotta set that source
file date so that the source file date
now matches the one that got written on
the drive that means that the HH a file
has to get edited even though note and
its occurred you with me so far so in
some sense what we really want to do
here is we want the source file date to
be stored out-of-band from the HHA
because really all it is is the machine
specific optimization file that says on
this machine have I or haven't I had to
update this file yet and what was the
date when I did ok
so I think we made kind of mistake there
because file dates are not preserved
across copies now the art preservers are
some copies right when you actually copy
on the machine the machine sometimes
that actually does preserve it so it's
not entirely true to say that it's never
preserved but it's most of the time not
preserved and most importantly it's not
preserved to the one case we actually
care about which is this somebody
downloaded these Pink's from the
internet they may very well not be think
I don't remember what happens if you
take a zip file and you zip up a bunch
of PNG and unzip it I don't know whether
they get the dates from when they were
zipped in or whether they get the dates
or when they were zipped out I'm not
sure I remember which one it is but
point being there are plenty of cases as
I just demonstrated to you where you
could go get PNG at the exact same PNG
so we used to believe it's a file but
they would all have different dates the
only thing that remain the same is the
checksum so that's something that we
really want to be aware of and we kind
of need to figure out some way of having
that be remembered in a way that doesn't
require updating a chat a file so we
kind of need a local cache file but it's
written there when it's actually doing
that kind of mashup I don't know any
other way to do that other than creating
sort of like a separate file that starts
on like a backing store right and that
backing store will give us that
information that's all I could think of
I don't have any better ideas than that
just a local cache file that writes that
information out now since we already
have the concept that we're gonna have
to have saved games like that it seems
fine to have that as a separate file in
there so there's kind of like a save
package and that state Packers used to
have like oh here's all the things in it
that we're actually using right to run
on this machine specifically this
machine and we can have those packaged
in there what those tourists all dates
are that seems like an okay trade-off I
guess maybe I don't know possibly but we
you know I'm not sure I'm not sure again
if that's maybe a bridge too far are we
being too professional almost at this
point you know is that something that
should get serviced or is it now so
that's the part that I want to raise
your awareness up so for now we're going
to use that but I'm gonna put a big ole
to do in here and say to do
should we start storing source file date
out of bands so that we don't have to
update
hhas when dates change but checksum
stone right so that's just some way of
saying hey look we're probably gonna
have to address this and maybe remove
this and this will be a dead field as
everything we can't still fill it out we
can't still fill it out and say this is
when the HHA when you received it when
you received the packaged version and so
anytime we actually update the actual
data in here we will set it so you kind
of know what the date was that's not a
bad idea
like should say it that way right but we
need that other one so that we don't
keep rechecking the files I'm just gonna
mark that I think we should probably do
it I'm not gonna do it right now but
that's something to be aware of all
right let's move the rest of this stuff
over let's grab all this stuff out and
we've got the sort of file group part
here this is actually gonna awesome
about but it's gonna probably be
something that happens around the parse
hht itself which is sort of the file
group backing store stuff so I'm gonna
go ahead and grab that here I'm gonna go
ahead and grab the one down here as well
and again these are just sort of another
thing that we're gonna have to work with
there all right okay actually you know
what I lied
that's not true I think those are
actually have stay exactly where they
are because we're gonna do that for ehh
T's okay so what we're going to do here
is gonna say alright for each of these h
h TS we're gonna want to iterate over
all ehh TS in it we're gonna wanna load
each of them right so here's us doing
that and in here we don't actually care
about this anymore what we're gonna do
what was that to do do a sweep around
all supposed to be unseen then mark each
one we see so we can check that we don't
have to do any more because actually the
hht lets us know although well inside
the hmj we don't really do that
so we maybe I'll leave that to do I
don't know that we ever actually want to
do that because we just delete the HHA
every build it from scratches you want
to get rid of anything that was in there
so maybe not but anyway so here we go
this is gonna let us loop over each of
those HS key files that are currently
being stored to drive
so we get that data out we'll process
each one of them this part right here we
still probably want to do we're using
the asset source match here as sort of a
separate thing that means that this sort
of thing where we do the string hashing
is going to be something that we
actually do multiple times and so we
kind of want that string hash to be
something that we can call more easily
so this particular thing yeah like I
don't also why do we write it this way
do we is there a reason we didn't write
that and is there also a reason that we
didn't put the skit like what what
happened here is there a reason that
didn't look like that no no we got a
pretty torture thing there all right I
don't know what was going on there
so we're actually doing that we got the
scan here it looks like we would
probably my guess is we were doing
something with the file name inside
there in addition to to what it was
before so you know maybe this was was
previously I think maybe a little bit
more elaborate and so then it kind of
kept some else what we should probably
do is just use the hash of I think we
have a hash of that that actually takes
a string as it is right there's string
hash of right there so we really don't
need to do any of this we got the hash
tag so we should actually be able to
just do that right I would think and
just say give us what the hash of the
base name is all of this can just go
away right I mean I I think we were just
maybe being a little bit overly Squinkie
there I mean we didn't really need to do
that so I don't know and the anchor part
yeah again this so I think that's all
residual right I think that was all
there because we were parsing the file
names before on we were doing other
stuff I that's done now so that was like
old vestigial remains we remove stuff we
didn't really realize me that all that
something go away now we don't need the
anchor part or any that stuff we can
just hash the base name directly and be
done with it we don't even really need
to store the hash value because that
actually happens here so what we can do
it you know I mean I'll keep it there
but we could just actually even inline
it right here
so all that would be fine so there we go
get a create a source file name we got
the hash file there value there this
file this could now generate that hash
value if we want to probably should
because there's really no reason for it
not to
let's just jump back up there to get or
create asset source file name
I started get your create asset source
file looking at that we've got father
checksum ba ba ba ba ba
there's the unmodern hash value so yeah
like we don't really need to do that
anymore the unmounted hash value who's
actually calling this I mean and does
anyone actually care because what we
could just do is pass just the base name
from now on excuse me
and you can see you can see that we just
I don't think we need that I don't think
we need that on there because you can
see it's it's already got the one that
just takes a base yeah so so really I
don't even know why we have that
separate call that was just kind of dumb
it's not really even necessary way I
could break that out into two now so
let's just forget this whole thing just
pretend it never happened we're just
gonna say that it was you know forget it
and then down in here we do a get or
create asset source file what I'm gonna
do there is I'm gonna go ahead and grab
this version of the call and call that
instead so that we just passed the base
name down there we've got the file date
and the file checksum that actually get
passed there I don't know which version
of this we were calling before or why
those weren't getting passed I guess
because in here we we were just calling
this one and so the file date stuff you
can see it doing some modifications
there on those yeah now I think about I
guess I can't really do that because
that is is is one that automatically
always updates to checksum and the file
date we don't have the checks time to
pass it yet because we haven't actually
done that so I do have to pass the
unmounted hash value here but I think
again not really necessary because what
I can do is just change the way this is
working to say look just passing that
base name so we can keep doing an exact
like this family no one has to know
about the fact that it's getting hashed
one way or the other in here we'll just
go ahead and delete this and then we do
isn't create an amount of hash value
ourselves we just say right in here
grab that base name hash right at the
time right so that just cleans all of
that up and now we're done with that so
I think that's the way we want to do
that going forwards and that way we can
get our create the assets relative here
but you look at the match dates this is
the hht remember it's not a PNG it's not
any source file that's actually a
creating or and I said it's just the
thing that creates the tag set right
it's the thing that like does all the
markup for them so we grab that if we
get a match then
we want to parse this thing we're gonna
call the hht parser right here we're
gonna call it with all the info that we
have so I'm gonna go ahead and set this
up this is no longer to do we actually
now have ability to mark that up thanks
the h of t file so thankfully that is
all just fine no issues there we've got
the tokenizer we need to set up the game
assets are already set up for us we
don't have to worry about those at all
we've got this import situation going on
here again I'm gonna just copy this code
up here in case me to look at it for
some other reason I don't think we're
going to because we're already calling
part pieces if you look at it okay we've
already got that and this part right
here I don't know if love to look at so
I'm just gonna comment it out there till
we go up and look on that code we'll
take a look but for right now we don't
care so here we're coming here looking
all the HT files parse each one in turn
only thing we haven't done create that
tokenizer source info not necessary it
doesn't get parsed it gets created a
little bit earlier a little bit later
down the line so we don't need to worry
about that but we do need to worry about
is the fact that here we do want to be
passing that file group because remember
the file group is what keeps all those
infos made all those infos and those
weird UTF strings and all that crap so
we're going to kind of need that as
we're doing our file pulling later on so
we are gonna want to pass that down into
the tokenizer so that's thing that's
gonna get passed down through it's
probably also gonna be out into the
context here so right here where we
passed that file group down it's
probably gonna get added in here so it's
gonna go ahead and do that just ahead of
time because I know I'm gonna need it
the hhp context itself again hasn't been
pulled out yet it's right in here I'm
gonna go ahead and pull it out so we can
see it a little bit easier put it in the
H file just so it's clear what's going
on so I'm gonna put it out here and that
means in here we got that file goop up
sorry it's platform file group right
platform file group like so and that's
gonna get added on there right again
we're gonna use that a little bit later
you'll see because we need to get that
file info back so we have that whole set
of stuff it's got to happen and we'll
deal with that in a second
so anyhow import eske's now looking
pretty good import changed assets rather
he's looking pretty good we're looking
overreaching and difficult file shows
getting the assets for us file for each
of them based off of that name that's
coming back from the file info iteration
and any time we see one that doesn't
match this file date wise we go ahead
and parse it right we go ahead and pull
things in there now
we have a problem here and I guess what
I would say is excuse me
we need this to run in two different
ways
and I'm not sure exactly which way we
want it to run I'm gonna start by doing
it one way and then we might change to
do it the other way if we did it this
way what would happen is you'd have to
touch an hht file in order to gain time
to reload why because the hht files are
the only things that are getting
iterated over at the top level right
there are the things that tell us what
all the other stuff we should look for
is so if you were to update a PNG and
save it we would not know that we need
to reload because the AJC hasn't changed
so we never even look at the PNG right
so what I'm going to do first is I'm
going to say let's always when we do
import changes parts the hht s and then
is a second step we will look at this
part for each of our file matches ok so
that information would go down in here
and so every time we do that parse piece
is called in fact we would do it right
here
every time we're gonna do that parsing
call will do this right and so we're
doing that shucking every time we're
gonna do the file that checking every
time on every PNG we're gonna do the
full parse each time now the question is
do we need to early out the hht testing
if we do need to do early out the agency
testing then we will have to put in
something here which does that date
checking differently so that we never
load the files I'm just gonna guess that
hht files are never gonna be big enough
that we ever have to do it and so I'm
just to put a note here that says at the
moment we can afford to parse the H HTS
every time so we don't try to do a
separated file date checking right so
we're just not gonna do that right now
it's gonna be fine okay and so we do
need to do the sweep of the unseen asset
stuff here that's still it to do that we
might want to concern ourselves with
that bottom part won't necessarily be so
we're gonna come through here every time
we'll pre parse the whole ATT so every
time you say reload will reap arch the
hht files
and then what we need to do in here is
just say look anytime we get a
particular file that the hht references
that's when we're now gonna have to do
this part right so the question is where
does bass name come from well bass name
comes almost almost not quite almost it
almost comes from whatever the string is
that we pulled out a file name so this
right here tells us the text sort of
right now why do I say sort of because
it hasn't actually had the rest of its
path appended okay so what we need to do
is we need to rebuild here a bigger file
name right a file name that's more
explicit what do I mean by that well
let's take a look at our directory
structure if I jump into ma here I look
at our directory structure cusine here
we've got a whole bunch of things going
on we know the inside our sources
directory we've got sources and then we
got like bass game intro cutscene right
inside bass game and got the art music
directory blah blah blah blah blah right
we need this stuff to be appended we
don't have any of that in there the base
name is just like block dot PNG or
something right it doesn't know where it
comes from so we have to build a file
name that actually will reach into the
correct location we know that handmade
hero gets run in the hand made directory
that's a requirement that's how it knows
where all of its files are gonna come
from but it needs to be able to search
down that source tree all the way as far
as it needs to go right that's pretty
important so what we need to do is we
need to have our HHA file stuff so that
that all works and all the stuff gets
found correctly so I want the HHA here
to be maybe specified that way I'm gonna
say to the intro cutscene and that one
should specify that way
you can see it's not actually getting
one in there I'm gonna go ahead and cure
and put put that in here oh oh oh oh
look at this
look at this though look at this we're
using it we're using it already look at
this check it out we can actually label
the office properly really easily pretty
nice huh yeah you didn't think it was
cool it's cool right
because Anna made this and young-shin
made these right I rest my case anyway
getting back to the actual code when we
actually lose in there right
got an HSA that tells us where these
things are supposed to go and so what we
want to do is say look we can build it
the path based on that we just needed
append a bunch of things together in
order to actually figure out what the
actual path is so you know if we wanted
to be kind of cheesy about it
temporarily we could just say look I
don't know how big this family is gonna
be but it's probably not gonna be that
big
and again cheesing out for a second what
I need to do is just do an actual format
string to put it in here I guess that's
a front string like that yeah where I
could pass in okay we're gonna we're
gonna put this thing in here it's gonna
be about that big or whatever right or
can't be bigger than that and we're
going to put in a thing that says look
we know we've got a string that tells us
this goes a certain you know it goes
into a certain base directory right so
it's gonna be source slash the HHA name
slash arts slash the thing right and
even this part here is something that we
might actually want to have be different
because it might be art it might be
music whatever so we've got a sub dirt
here we know it's always are at the
moment cuz we're always pulling in p.m.
G's but we're gonna change that to music
or sound based on other things that we
might you know based on what the block
type actually might imply in this
particular case so we sort of have
another thing we might want to do there
right and we'll work on that cut a
little bit later and then down here we
also have another one that's gonna say
look that's there's the actual file name
that that was given to us right and so
if we want to build up a whole path that
tells us the entire thing we need all of
those pieces so first we need the HHA
file so that's gonna be in that fields
right so we've got that fields HHA and
so that's gonna have two things gonna
have the size and and the data right and
I think if I'm not mistaken that's a
size key always and this is a care star
always for these that's just what those
have to be to parse them in there I
think we may have added something
smarter I think we added this I'm just
gonna say that we did that because we're
awesome I don't know if we did it cuz
we're awesome maybe we did it for a
different reason but let's just say that
we did and then we'll let the compiler
tell us we didn't or rather the code
tells we didn't later on when we crash
alright since the operating system is a
person's ring it tells me crash so when
we load this stuff out we're gonna have
that fields HHA root that's gonna give
us where
eh-eh-eh was we used that as a
determiner here we got that art part in
here and then we got that file name
that's what we're actually gonna load
that's the complete file directory right
the the complete der name the complete
path the only thing we don't really know
is how big that path is that's why I
seem choosing out here I don't know if
this is big enough if we have a little
bit more of a robust system we just do
some concatenations that look at what
the size has to be and go from there
we certainly could do something of that
we just didn't this time because again
we haven't built up as enough of a
standard library to really make that
sort of thing work sweetly but ignore
all that for now that's not really the
thing we're focusing on what we want to
do now is have that path part in there
and I think that's all we really need so
then we'll do our get our create asset
source file will do all the merchants
that way what we want to do now is say
look when we look at these file dates
we're gonna need to know what the actual
file info was here's that part remember
we did this work here's our big chance
this is our big moment in the spotlight
this is where we get to actually call
the function we used before right
that platform call like we're doing in
here right where we do get all file
types begin that sort of stuff we've got
to get file info by path and exactly
what we need right it's almost like I
knew it was almost I got Superboy get
file info bypass is already in here
because we already import it let's say
get file info by card get file by path
right that's exactly what we need to
generate one of these file info which is
what we need to do our loading and other
checking right so here's our file info
I'm gonna say get my path we know we
have the file group in here hallelujah
we just have it exactly where we need it
there I just have to pass that Pat that
that path we've generated which we've
got here and then we're good to go
right everything's good so here we go
let's see if there's anything else that
we needed I don't think there was it's
just that that's all there is so off we
go right everything's great we get back
to file info now if there was no file
right then we could issue an error so
we'd probably want to check here because
I think it's legal for that thing to
return zero and say look I don't know
what you're talking about I ain't never
heard of no file by that name and so you
can't have it that's totally valid
because there might not be a file we may
have just had some kind of an error
like a when we actually went to to type
in that that HST file we made a typo
right we may already have a typo in
there right where it can't find the file
so we need to say like file not found
right we don't know where that file is
and I could also say looked in here
right because we know the full path we
looked for makes sense so I think that's
pretty good that gives me basically what
I want there I'm gonna go ahead and try
and compiling this and then we'll start
to look for ears and maybe it's getting
time for us to start to try and run this
and actually make sense of everything
right okay so coming back here we didn't
really do the append tags thing let's
actually do it because we might as well
get everything working at once it's not
that hard we've got sort of an import
tag array here that we want to actually
specify again this should be pretty
simple because we already did the work
of building tag lists we have this
notion of a tag builder thing we've got
all that working so we can just go ahead
and say look have this thing do the tag
build like it's doing right you can see
it here and the only problem that we're
gonna run into is in here you can see
it's got this sort of category of stuff
that we don't need doesn't matter
because we don't use it for anything
right it doesn't get used at all
anywhere in here nobody cares right as
far as I can tell anyway so import grid
tag part yeah it's a little bit more
than what we need that's okay we can
build it it doesn't harm us right it
doesn't hurt us at all
so let's go ahead and do that we'll say
here it's our builder we're gonna do
begin tags all we need is that assets
array that's all we actually need there
so we're gonna go ahead and pass that in
here's the assets like so we'll begin
those tags during that building every
time you see one of these here we go
this is us doing that so let's go ahead
and say we've got the tag we don't need
this tech tote type token name count
bah-bah-bah we don't need that right
that was old news and here all we need
to do is say look give us the tag ID
from this particular name we know what
it is because in here we've actually
done it right this token is the
identifier that gives us that
information so that's all we really need
to get back that tag ID assuming we got
back a tag ID then we can do our add if
we didn't then we need to actually go
ahead and oh hey by the way we did that
string format specifier didn't we right
that's the capital S pretty sure it's in
there don't actually know let's double
check to make sure I'm not making things
up so we look at for about string list
here it is let's see if we put in a
capital S because we're really because
we're baller let's see if we did that
there it is
bang right capital S right there how
awesome are we very very very awesome so
now we can see unrecognized tag name
surprise surprise we actually don't even
need the strings for us that's right
though because we take a token now we
print out our heirs and that's something
we can work on a little bit later but
that means that all that stuff would
have got handled for us so we can say in
here look we don't know that tag name we
have no idea what tag name you're
talking about so please don't ask me to
add that's a tag because I have no idea
how that would work we also now need to
do the f32 part of things let me do this
open print here you can see us parsing
the number so we need to do is say look
by default the tag value is going to be
1.0 if you don't specify a parenthetical
in your tag name you're gonna get a one
point let's create a boolean tag this is
that thing it's not zero it's one off
you go in here we need to say is well if
you did have an open paren then when we
get that value back that's where we're
gonna set that so in here we're gonna
say okay the tag value is going to be
the value as an f32
so that we can set it later on bingo
we've got it right here either it'll be
one or the parenthetical done deal so
now we can specify tags an explicit
values reason per have it form or is it
boolean by just Festiva tag alone right
either one will work it makes it really
nice and convenient Rusted build those
havs so just again if you don't remember
what I'm talking about and here we've
got this sort of stuff where we say okay
tags is florets grass whatever those are
boolean tags they just get set to one if
they're there they're set to nothing if
they're not we also have the concept
that we might want to set a value for it
looking here shot index one layer
indexed for those are the same tag
specifications same exact thing it's
just now it's got a parenthetical to set
with the values act OB cuz we need to be
all set one two three and so forth right
okay all good let's move on back here to
tag value you can see us adding it here
we got the errors here semicolon blah
blah blah that parsing is just gonna
work we already made that stuff happen
properly so I think we're all good there
I don't know we ever did that we didn't
ever check the parenthetical parsing
surprise to do that part but otherwise
we're good we get to the end of this we
can call em tags that's the thing that's
going to let us get back the information
that we actually needed and so we can
create our import tag away result when
we call em tags we're gonna pass it that
builder and if you remember if ID
jump back here to the end tax function
oh man I love this jump thing that we've
added um
winter back to the untaxed function
that's gonna give us about import grid
tag import grid taggers what we need
when I do this thing here builder I
gotta pass the tokenizer which we have
asset basic category which I don't care
about it all
so that asset basic category just gonna
be elect asset none or something right I
don't know what it's gonna be but it's
just gonna be meaningless because we
don't use it and then we've got this a
Pentax there are no append tags so we'd
actually just pass the result there
because we don't need to append anything
to it so this whole thing could just be
skipped and will be skipped because it's
zero and zero so nothing will happen
there so when we come out of here you
can see that the result we actually
receive from this import grid tag right
this thing right here import grid tagged
temp that's going to come back we don't
actually need that data but we do need
to grab what was in it really quickly we
don't need the struct I should say but
we do need this part so the first tag in
text in the one passed last tag index
that's what we're looking for so we grab
those two out that gives us the parts we
needed to fill out the structure the way
we needed to fill it out
for our return values so there it is
done right now our tag parser parses
tags puts them in the format that we
need it before and hands them off a
thing that can always be copied by
anybody else if I actually go here and
look I just need to do some anding here
and I got a past the tokenize don't know
why we're passing errors there that was
just because we modified that used to be
an out F so let's fix that right so now
we've got all that straightened out what
I new need to do now is take a look at
anything here that okay that's a that's
an ampersand I'll take a look at
anything here that I didn't actually
quite clean up so parse tags list has
got to have those assets right remember
when we had that in here we got to pass
the token eyes and the assets so let's
just add the assets in there that's how
it's gonna that's where it's gonna put
that tag array for sure so in here we
can look and say okay we've got a pen
tags Asus undeclared that's because
that's comes off the context right we
don't actually have it as a local
variable so there we go chat almost
certainly do it's supposed to be car I
don't know how it got to be chat so
that's a good question so let's take a
look at this year size of up that's my
habit in my internal code base I always
use capitalized sizeof I never did that
for handmade hero for reasons I don't
actually know what they are let's see
here
get file by path so
I don't know that we ever actually added
it to the call table we probably didn't
let's go ahead and take a look if that
was true so in here we have like open
file and that sort of stuff
where we got the platform file callbacks
right so we have in here a thing that's
like you know what was it open file
right there's a callback for open file
right right here we never actually added
the calling here to get file of a
specific type so the platform
I'm sorry perfect name get a file from
path that has to be him here so like get
filed by path has to be an actual call
that's in here and when we actually put
in the wintery to side of things we also
have to actually fill it out so when we
say open file in here equals win32 open
file we needed the same thing for the
platform API we need to say that that
get filed by path actually has to be in
here as well so when three to get file
by path has to be in there right so once
those files are in there we're good to
go
let's take a look at any other errors we
have in here again that's gonna be the
context assets that we need to put in
there I'm not sure file group here is
gonna have to come from the context as
well but that's fine what else we got a
platform handle a context file group
that's good
press button for again context that's
this is all context here context context
context right and what I'd probably like
to do here I'm just looking at it I
don't know about that info struct that
info structs getting used in a bunch of
places we could just fill it out maybe
I'll do that now but I'm gonna add it to
do I you know should this just be the
hht fields right so meaning do we really
need this what was it what was it called
I don't even remember what it was called
it was something like a source import
source of import source info right so
import source info is just the same
thing and so I kind of don't think it
should really be there it's just a thing
that says hey like give me the specific
subset of the fields but there's no harm
in just passing the rest of the fields
there's no reason we need to hide that
data from the code it's not like it can
anything horrible with it or something
like that so I don't really know what
the point of that would be right it just
doesn't make any sense
so that all looks pretty good now
there's one thing that's kind of janky
here and I'll tell you what it is in a
second and then that's the last thing we
probably have to address before we are
really just into debugging I don't know
much time I got left I think I've got to
about one o'clock so I think I have a
half hour left actually which means we
can do some debugging today to get this
code into sort of semi working order
probably not fully working order so
sourcing folk here that was a mistake I
didn't actually mean that I'm not sure I
think that was just a brain fart
remember I'm talking my announcer voice
takes an incredible amount of energy to
program and do the announcer voice at
the same time because you know if we're
honest about it it constantly talking is
using an entire part of the brain that
normally I'm using for Burgamy so makes
it a lot harder to program what I'm
actually doing that voice I meant a type
of alter a type sourced in for a product
as I was talking about sourcing for at
the time and that's just how the brain
works anyway moving along we've got all
that stuff now we have to grab these out
of the fields oops that's not correct I
totally and again even does the
explanation it was a brain fart so let's
get rid of that all right so now moving
out of tokenizer we have 2x2 self that
tokenizer if you remember correctly we
you know wrote this tokenizer code here
there isn't actually a thing for
starting tokenizing
other than this one tokenized call it
takes a string as input that's okay we
actually have what is the krims that was
string when we open an actual file we've
got to do that read so what we need here
is we need to parse we need to pass like
a buffer this thing so when we do this
you know tokenize here when we do this I
can say tokenizer just organize
something right this has to be file
contents basically right and then I can
pass the address of that and it can
parse the file so question is how to
actually read that file later well you
know we already did that right we
already know what that is right in here
we've got this make read stream thing
where we can read a content stream and
then parse PNG like takes that content
stream right so when I do that make you
that file buffer all that sort of stuff
that file buffer that we pass the
restream that's all I really need so how
do I get that where you can see it
happening right here right when we do
the open file we did the close file we
do the read that's all we really need
so in here when I
do that I'm gonna skip the foul bait
part we can still do all of this get the
file handle right I've got the file
group it's right here so I can just say
there's the file group we've got the
file info I can say I want to read it I
can create a buffer here that I can pass
as file contents I'll just go up file
buffer reply as well right
we know what the file size is we can
grab a part of data that's big enough
for it we can read that data in and then
we can close it right so the only
question is where do we get that data
from again we can use a temporary and if
we want to here or not it's really
entirely up to us since we've got this
temporary nough here I'm kind of leaning
towards maybe just using one arena that
kind of expands and contracts for
everything seems like it would be the
right idea why bother having two of them
that just seems easy to me so I think I
might just do it like this where we just
say okay yeah
inside here when we go to do import our
assets will create the temporary no like
so and that will just store all the
stuff that we're working on as we go
when we pass into the parse hht I will
pass the temporary nough in there so
that's how it knows where it's gonna get
us memory from right very very simple
and so all the temporariness stuff will
just work since I want to minimize the
amount of memory and give him time just
cuz I'm a nice guy I wouldn't have to
because I could just let it stack up and
then clear it all at the end but why not
what I'm going to do is do a beginning
temporary memory right so on that
temporary nough that we've got I'll just
do a temporary memory so that in here
when we do that temp marker something
like that I can do an end temporary
memory on the temp marker right and
that'll just allow us to sort of keep
everything in one arena so we know all
of the you know everything is just gonna
get cleaned up by that arena we don't
have to care about it at all right it's
like free garbage collection you don't
have to pay for it and it does what you
would have done if you had a garbage
collector so it's pretty nice so in here
excuse me
we just have to clean up the places
where we were addressing that temporary
net so every time in here we were
passing that temporary nough around all
we have to do is just say look the
temporary noops is
is already a pointer so off you go
and I think that's that's was bad there
we go all we have to do is we compile
and we should be down to our last few
things parse top level block I don't
know what that takes as a as a as a
function skull such as cleanup our
function calls parsed of a block
okay so parse the top-level block does
take a memory arena right I skipped one
person in the chain here I could I
suppose then put it in the context maybe
I should do that this is what I was
gonna do originally and I stopped I
think I'm gonna actually do that so it
doesn't actually need to pass it down in
case other people want to use that
temporary nough it can just be hanging
out in there all the time that seems
like a better idea to me so in here I'm
just gonna say the temporary nough is
gonna come from the context like so and
everyone can use it and we're good to go
that means out here on the on the
context I'm gonna always pass that
around so the temporary knows in here
done deal I think that's everything
pretty much nothing left to do this
parse hht
doesn't mean anything but an ampersand
amber now okay let's talk about the last
thing we didn't do where are all of
these files going to get written once
I'm reading every single PMC I've got a
problem
I'm gonna put them somewhere we're going
to put them well our old method of
putting them somewhere just assumed that
it always goes into the same HHA file
but that's not true it doesn't go into
the seamy at a save file anymore it's
got to go into a specific HHA file and
the agency files got to go into is
whichever one is paired with this
particular part of the block right
because any time I'm in here let's say I
go to one of those hht files anytime I
go into here I say oh here's the HHA
that's where it's supposed to go it
doesn't go into local 8h a it goes into
intro cutscene date it a right so in
order to rebuild that file I have to be
able to know this is the HH day that I'm
supposed to be targeting put all the
data in there right that's gotta happen
and so I have to have some way of
breaking out of this notion that where
I'm putting these things has something
to do with this local HHA file that's
gone right so this local HH a bit here
this part that's gone and the allow
editing that stuff we just need
everything to allow editing at this
point I think right so we need to
reassess how we're doing that we need to
look at this a little bit differently
and this assets default append HHA index
not a thing anymore right not a thing so
let's go ahead and look at where that's
happening I'm gonna go ahead and search
for allow editing what's going on where
are we using that better yet nuke it
it's gone who's using it tell me now mr.
compiler tell me what I need to change
so here you can see we were doing an
assertion on to make sure we're gonna
edit it forget that you can edit
everything now that's just how that goes
the hht is tell you inside allow editing
here we're setting that that codes gonna
get nuked no big deal you know what
goodbye you're out of here right done
deal
let's keep looking who else in if allow
editing this is very inefficient and we
could modify the photo cube separate
array of file names blah blah blah so
here
we are doing our sort of look up stuff
so you know what again this is code that
could just be run on everybody so you
know maybe we just want to do this on if
internal um but that's it because I
think that's the only thing right so
this is just a if handmade internal you
know off you go so if you've done your
compile in a way that's suggesting
you're gonna actually be doing edits to
the code that's the only thing that
would determine whether you call this I
think right that's it um so I think
that's what we want to do if I come down
to the import code I'll put that around
it as well so if handmade internal but
that's the only thing otherwise you're
good to go
make sense oops okay so now every HHA is
available for editing and so now we just
need to actually figure out for any
given asset which ones are gonna go into
because it can go into anything and it's
just based on which one you said it was
supposed to go into that's we're gonna
pack it so let's go ahead and take a
look inside
the asset code where we have that going
so in here we can go ahead and take a
look at default append HHA index that's
gonna get out of here right there it
goes
so now we just need to see who's
actually using that and remember it's
probably gonna be pretty simple yeah you
can see it right here so when we do
write image to HH a file you can see
that our situation as it as it exists is
it needs to know which file index it's
appending to right that's the thing that
we actually need so when we and in fact
when we actually do that at this point
in the code we could actually create a
new HHA if that HHA didn't exist before
right we could actually create it so
what we want to do here is have our
source info in effect tell us that
information let's go ahead and add that
in so in here here's our import source
info what I'm gonna do is say when we
create that import source info we also
need which file index the hfj is going
to be so we're going to call this like
append HHA index right we're gonna keep
this code path the way it was we're
doing a little bit higher up so that
asset file index equals zero asset file
index equals default append right now
what I'd like to do here is
maybe we don't even do the if we just
say we always append to the place that
we said we would append because the user
may want to change the target for this
particular PA PNG and that's fine
right so what we're going to do here is
say look that asset is gonna get that
from the append HHA index always okay
now we'll compile fine we just won't run
fine or well no we won't because I used
the wrong thing
I meant info right I meant that source
info this thing right here now I do me
now I will run compile fine but I won't
run fine why would I run fine I won't
run fine because what's gonna happen
here is that's when we can they set to
zero we've never initialized it to
anything so it's just gonna be garbage
and we're gonna not actually append the
file we want to so we have to do is go
back to where we built that source info
right and when we pass it down we've got
to actually do the work of finding out
what HHA this thing actually goes in
right we've got to do some kind of a
search to figure that out and so what I
can do is I can again promote that up to
the HHA fields because there's no sense
in me creating it every time so what I
can do is I mean maybe there is I don't
know it's it's maybe it's just like it
is six of one half dozen other hard to
say it doesn't really matter point being
at some point and we can do it like here
for now and we can decide if we want to
promote it up later when we actually
create that type right here what we need
to do is say all right the append HHA
index has to equal something so what are
you to do is take this
HHA feels request here and i need to get
the HHA from that name right now you use
that name to go find the HHA and if i
don't already have it i need to make it
okay that's important because so far we
haven't done that particular operation
other than in the HHA edit so we also
need the ability to sort of create an
HHA from whole cloth where none existed
prior okay and so that's another thing
that we're gonna have to do it's okay
let's get started
how much time do I have
Oh retino I like I said before I got 30
minutes right I got 30 minutes yeah I'm
drinking a very strange concoctions day
this is what I've been drinking lately
for reasons unknown to man and just who
knows why do I do common milk don't know
this is 25% Newman's own lemonade 75%
water solution so it's like a 1 2 3
ratio filled with 1/8 of a cup of chia
seeds per gallon and out them hydrate
overnight
that's one record back to our story
all right append h h index needs to get
this from somewhere okay we need to be
able to look up this HH a and if the HIV
doesn't exist already in the asset
system we need to actually create one so
we're gonna create a file from whole
cloth it's not something we really done
before so again this is something that
we need to maybe add a little bit of a
support to the to the file system before
so we can actually say hey when we pass
to you and i don't know if we've done
this from that but inside wintered new
handmade like if we do open file or
something like that we're going to have
to actually tell you stuff like you can
you know do and open always right so you
can see in here if we pass open file
right we'll do that but i don't really
necessarily know how we would even get
to this win32 open file because we don't
have a file name yet so when we do get
filed by path we may have to augment get
file by path to support the case where
we actually don't have a file so in the
case where this actually returns nothing
we couldn't find the file we still need
to return a result right in that case
with just null or whatever right so
we're gonna have to have some way of
having that happen so there might be a
little bit of an update here there might
be a little tiny bit of a thing that's
actually gonna happen there that it
wasn't happening before so we kind of
got to work with that and see how we
want to do things here right so we've
got some work to do there and and and we
also have some things we might want to
change for example this stuff here we
may want to change this as well the wild
carding stuff may want to be changed a
little bit we've got a lot of things
we've got to kind of look at but you
know as we go also this can go away as
we're sort of going through it we can do
you know updates as necessary so let's
first get this to write the files that
actually do exist and then we'll try to
make it right to files that don't exist
because that one's gonna be a little
harder so you don't have the s back and
yet in place for that I don't think so
here we go inside the asset system if
you remember correctly each individual
source file I'm sorry each individual
source
HHA that we load remembers the fact that
it was loaded you can see it here in
asset file what it doesn't actually
remember is the name of that file and so
one of the things
you can see here as we got this platform
file handle I don't actually know that
the platform file handle tells you
anything about the name in fact I'm
pretty sure that it doesn't tell you
anything about the name so you don't
actually have any idea what you're
looking at right and so what we would
need at least here is something that we
can use to match say the HHA name
against this asset file that we've got
loaded so we can search for them by name
as necessary I really would love to know
what all this beeping is about I'm
hearing it but I can't see it I don't
know
hopefully they're not beating at me I
don't see how they could because I'm up
are you hearing this I have no idea
who's beeping why are you beeping who
are you beeping at oh well you know
there's like a giant truck or something
that's in the alley I'm guessing that
maybe that maybe nobody kicked I I think
a giant truck may have blocked the the
entrance to the building and someone is
like Rage Horning right now they're just
like slamming on the horn hoping it will
move is that what's happening oh yeah
yeah and then they just moved yeah they
moved far enough forwards all right nice
work folks ah yes living in cities it's
always so good all right anyway I'm
moving on so we need some way of
actually looking these things up by name
so we at least need to store in here
something like a hash value for the file
name so we can see whether or not this
is it so let's let that least do that
right let's say here this is like the
hash of name or something or hash of
file name let's put that in there so
that when we load these things up we can
actually use that file name to hash it
right so we can see what the actual file
name is and that's pretty easy to do so
in here we can say when we do our when
we actually go through here and Lodi
these in right you can see us doing it
here we go through our files we can load
you know we load each of these in we
could check that checksum or something
and use that right so in order to do
that it's a little bit Squinkie to me
when we load each of these hhas what you
can see that happening curious we don't
ever really strip the name down we just
used the name that came back
or rather we you know at this point
don't really even look at the name that
came back but we have no idea all we
know is that we got back some kind of
base name so what we can do is hash that
base name I guess and then what we'll do
is use the name that we create out of
the HHA side of things to go from there
so in here what I can do is say look
this file it's got the asset base type
is that stuff while I'm at it let's do
hash of filename and so hash a file name
will just say the file info base name
here let's go ahead and take the hash of
that right to me but I may want to do it
maybe I want to do this right we've got
the space name maybe what I want to do
is create a string here that's going to
be instead of base name it's gonna be
like the stem or something right without
the extension because I don't really
necessarily want the HHA extension in
there because we we just refer to things
that way sort of a little bit more
generically perhaps so maybe I want to
be able to get just the stem and if I
want to do that then what I do is I say
hash of filename is actually going to be
stem or you know in this case I can say
hash of stem right so we know that it's
you know specifically not including that
part so I can just call a hash hash of
okay string hash up there it is so if I
just do string hash of stem then we can
get that out and then you hear what I do
the stem I just need to find out where
the extension is right uh and so like I
don't know if we've got anything like
that like fine fine first or you know
fine for slash or anything like that
extension do we have any of this stuff
remove extension here hey look there we
go so remove extension we'll get rid of
the period for us so this is exactly
what I wanted right um so you can remove
the path and the remove the extension if
you want to which is actually what
exactly what I wanted
Wow thank you past me for giving future
me a library use so what I want to do
here is I want to remove the path and
read the extension from this base name
that I'm getting I think the base name
is just a care star and so what I want
to do I need a way of wrapping that
together tuning where is this in does
this do we have this in is this in the
h2o so I want this code and shared I
want this give to KC immediately so I
need a way to wrap Z I've got that so
basically this ridiculous line of code
here gives me what I want right that
removes everything from it and now I
just have the stem and then I can cut
the hash of it and now I know for any
given file that we floated I can look at
the hashes to see if the names match
right I want to so here where I remove
the extension cannot be read one from
string to string star that's totally
fine I guess I should have done this
right string stem equals rap Z and then
I can just say hey
there we go that's why you probably want
to return those rather than take the
address up that's why this is not the
best form because you can't do
functional composite you can't compose
them right and so it's really better
typically to do returns you know this
this should really return the the thing
and then you can compose them exactly
the way that I did it before and so you
know since I moved those two shared I'm
just going to go ahead and do that right
I'm just gonna do it exactly the way
that I wanted to because why not so what
do I do here say look let's return these
so here we're gonna do it like this and
that you know it's still pretty easy to
do so here's just filename in it and
then here's file name right and then you
can just run the exact same code exactly
the way you did it before right easy
peasy lemon squeezy and so all I need to
do is change these to that and you know
off you go and then the same thing
happens with this removed path one so we
here you know you pass in the filename
and I just create a temporary and I
return that temporary and I replace all
these so they're different they work on
a local really really easy but you can
see why it makes sense there because
it's just it's nice to be able to
functionally compose these things
without having to like line them all up
you can just put them on the same line
and then get the thing you actually
wanted I mean here you can even go even
more ridiculous if you just want to be
some kind of you know crazy superhero
you can just say look give me the whole
thing I'm not even gonna ever create a
temporary I just want the hash so
there's this giant hash right I mean why
not you know pretty easy so let's just
fix the place in here where that was
happening so we can cure this default
annotation all I have to do is again
just pass this in like this so the
default annotation source file and you
know what here you can see it it's being
used exactly the same way so I can
literally just do this and then get rid
of this code entirely right so again
nice and clean no reason not to do that
so I think you just do going on from
there let me switch it here so you can
see this appendage index I have the HHA
stem what I need to do is I need to get
the stem I need to go
I need to add something that searches
through all the files we have open and
finds the one that has this particular
stem so I'm innocent get a function for
that because we probably want to do that
in multiple places potentially I don't
know to be necessarily will but we might
want to so I'm gonna do like a get or
create HHA kind of call here and I'm
gonna pass the game assets and I'm gonna
pass that HHA stem right and again
that's just the stem and maybe I'll say
like a buy stem right and so in here
I'll say the get or create HHA buy stem
maybe we'll have the getter create take
a true which means hey look if you can't
find it create it because we do actually
need you to always make one of these and
then I'll put that in here so I can say
okay here's a way to do that right so
here's the stem that's the second
parameter that's actually telling us
okay look this is what we actually want
thing to be called so you got to find
something matches that stem and then
we're gonna have in here you know
whether or not you should create create
if not found right something that says
if you don't find this I need you to
make one we're not going to support that
just yet but we will you know support a
little bit later on okay so in here we
say here's the assets here's the stem
what I want to do is loop over all the
files that are in the asset system so
let's go take a look at where those are
inside the asset system we just have a
flat array I think probably maybe I'm
not really sure I don't remember exactly
how that worked
yeah you can see it here it's file count
and files so all I need to do is start
out for the loop I'm gonna go ahead and
say which is the file index so here's
the HSA in next I'm going from one to
the next to the next
I'm gonna look for each through each of
them to see if I can find that file if I
remember correctly zero doesn't actually
exist so I think I can skip zero but I
shouldn't need to because that stem
should work one way or the other right
we should be able get that hash that
hash time to work one way or the other
so the first thing I want to do is
actually create that hash so here's the
stem hash itself I'm gonna go ahead and
call that string hash right here's that
thing string hash for your string F
rather I'm gonna get that out each time
I go through one of these I'm gonna pull
out that asset file so here's the file
that I'm checking I'm gonna look and see
from the array of files which I'm going
through the HHA index here so from that
array of files and we'll look at this
HHA index and remember this thing is
going to return me
one of those indices right so it has to
have a result here and that result can
be zero so I getting it yeah if that
result can be zero again but it means
that the HSV index right of zero should
be nothing if I look in here I want to
make sure that that's actually true that
I did leave one space for a file that's
like of the null file right let me just
double check that that's actually the
case so when we get files of type back
in the original situation here where we
look at that get file handle stuff now
not the little bit map get files by type
where is that no no no no no no it's in
the startup code I can't remember what
any of it's called the moment so I don't
actually remember there it is right so
this is cuz I'm talking about right here
you can see file and x equals one I'm
enforcing a zero file beginning that
means in here I only need to check that
first one so as we go you know we're
fine when I look through here if I find
one I'm gonna set the result each of the
HHA index and break so all I need to do
is say look look if the file stem hash
equals the stem hash that I'm looking
for then we'll consider the match right
now I could check the string if I want
to I don't really care to do that at the
moment but maybe I'll put to do here you
know check that stem matches exactly
right should I do it should I do it
should I do it should I not do it you
know what when we think about it look
here's where we're opening those things
in the first place right so here's me
opening those I say file this is one
here I come through here I'm doing a
bunch of pushes on here anyway let's see
if I love a lot I account file blah blah
blah get all files of type and and then
I come through here and I read the data
for the file handle which is open for
that file I you can see right on here
I've gotten arena for pushing the file
count on so you know what let's just
store it let's just store it I mean so
we use a little bit extra in release
mode when we shouldn't I can always if
around it if I want to I could do like
an if handmade internal right if I want
to so sure sure I'm just gonna do it so
in here where we actually do the hash of
stem I'm gonna do what the stem actually
is so here's the the part where I create
the stem in and of itself so if you take
a look at this code right here I am
to put in a temporary here's my stem
what I want to do is just like push
string right I want to do a push string
here so put on the arena this this thing
right and give me back a copy of that
thing and then I've got it right so when
I put that string on I'm good to go I
have a copy now so we can hear I can say
if the stem hash is equal then compare
the strings themselves and see another
thing you can say is maybe we don't even
bother looking at the stem hash at all I
don't know it's a little bit faster
probably not the names aren't that long
so who knows maybe that we don't
actually need that stem hash at all yeah
mmm yeah probably not so yeah yeah okay
just get rid of it there's no sense in
having the stem if we're going to store
that the hash rather so if we're going
to store that we don't really need it so
let's just say here's the file name or
the file stem we're just going to store
that so we don't have anymore we
just stored the actual stem so here we
just say look if strings are equal and
we have the file stem hash I'm sorry the
file stem and the stem that you passed
us if those two things are equal then
it's the file that we're looking for and
we're done right so that's all we need
to do we won't have to put that to do in
there anymore cuz we're done and that's
exactly what we wanted so when we push
that on there we've now got it we don't
need that stem hash at all at any time
really any more and so now all we have
to do is fight the fact that I think
nope yeah and that's not necessary that
I'm I don't think the push actually
works there I'm not sure about that what
just happened there I thought we had a
push string what I didn't where did I
put that
come on second I put it in the wrong
place apparently what's just what just
happened did you not see me okay I'm an
idiot
I obviously deleted the wrong thing or
something cuz I'm just um I'm just that
dumb I guess I guess I don't know
speaking the announcer voice is hard
like I said it just requires a way too
much talking you probably shouldn't be
talking that much but anyway this was
supposed to be a push string and it was
supposed to be stem and I guess I
deleted the wrong one but it supposed to
look like that right that was what was
supposed to happen and apparently I
deleted the wrong one I have no idea why
I did that because I spent the time to
write it you'd think I'd have some
appreciation for it but
anyway when it comes back I believe
again that push string call I don't
really ever wrote one that pushes an
actual-size string on we take a looking
to see what we did there so you see we
got a push string Z and a push string
right it's really this push string here
that we're talking about what I want to
do is put on there a thing that says
okay you know what you can also take a
regular string source because why not
and then when we do that on here you can
see we don't need to call the string
length it also in the source it's
actually got the count on there right
it's got the size of that buffer and so
then that pretty much gives us exactly
what we need so let me just go ahead and
and finish that up that looks good so in
here where we do assets file count I
don't know why that got set to game
state just a completion bug there it's
actually game assets so off we go and so
that's good there and then here where we
do a getter create h2 by stem that
assets is coming from the context so we
need to put that on there right and so
that's the thing that we needed pretty
much all of its written now except for
the part that we need to create one of
these hhas
if we don't have one right now I'm not
going to do that so what I'm going to do
here is say if result equals zero then
we would need to do it if we're doing
create if not found
so if create if not found is set and
result equals zero is set or rather
result is not set meaning it is equal to
zero then what I need to do is create
the actual HHA so create you know a
blank
HHA here okay I don't actually know that
we want to do that we could make it so
that for you what you actually are
supposed to do is call HHA edit yourself
to create a blank
HHA to write into we could do that I
just don't know whether we want to do
that or not like it's hard to say it's
hard to say I don't know I really don't
because what we could say instead here's
what we could say we could just call
this gate get HHA by stab remove that
and say they've got to be there let's
start up right you're required to create
the missing ones with HHA edit right and
if we were going to do that
then yeah you would have because to
avoid creating them in case of typos
like that I don't know if we want to do
that it's hard to say
leave it like this for now and and say
that we would do that if we try to do it
and can't we still want to have the
support for the failure there in a sense
right though so what we probably want to
do too is when we actually do this info
get here what we want to do is say if
you know info dot append HHA index do
the actual append with the with the
switch right but then if we can't we
want to issue an error we want to issue
an error based on the HHA which
basically says look couldn't open HHA
this for writing because like somehow we
couldn't get to it right for whatever
reason we don't know if the reason is
and then we're done so I think that's it
so the fields HSA is put in here so I
think that's everything we need and you
know now in theory the game can actually
update the hhas
in theory right and I don't know if it
will work like I said probably we got
tons of bugs in there that we'll have to
debug but the games just still run just
fine as it is right we should be able to
run the game OOP that's HHA in it I
don't actually need HHA to run there's
no reason for that
that's good pop over here to win 32
handmade so the game should still run
just fine and you know it does so we
don't have any issues with what's
loading the a change that we had
originally what we don't have right now
is probably any of the editor stuff
right so if we actually switch into the
editor mode which we will want to do
later I don't know if that will actually
work but we did all the code we needed
to do so we'll save the debugging for
next weekend when we can do that and
then also address things like fonts and
sounds or stuff we can get him to
finishing up that code but we did
everything we need to do yay for us just
another wire let me go ahead and go to a
real quick Q&amp;A here anyone who happens
to have any because I got to go soon
after this so let's just go ahead and do
Q&amp;A any questions
I'm presence Eagle says I actually
thought you were just gonna vary your
pitch a lot more in terms of inflection
not go fast everyone else dream wasn't
off how faster going to be kept for 10
Cyril no I don't think so it's in fact
probably less that I have to do so much
mental processing to talk what sort of
pre-release checks actions do you do how
do you make your programs
industrial-strength for example do you
turn all of your ass into fatal errors
or certain to fail errors do you add
verbose logging crashed reporters etc so
a couple of things about that
first of all never turn asserts into
fatal errors because the worst so the
worst that could have happened with the
assert was that it would crash if you
ignored the assert so all you're doing
by turning assert into a fatal error is
guaranteeing that you will crash right
which is not a very good idea so that
doesn't seem like a good idea in assert
is it as a check that you do want on
there but don't make your code crash
because maybe the code that came after
the assert could have handled it
properly so don't assume it's gonna
crash not a good idea but on the more
general on the more general concept of
how do you harden code there's a couple
things that you need to do right the
first thing you need to do is you need
to actually think very carefully about
what the critical failure consequences
are for your app in a game this means
losing the player state right if a game
crashes that's bad but if a game crashes
and the user can't keep continue from
where they left off it's I mean horrible
right like I'm if players played like 20
hours of your game and they crash and
they're saved games gone right I mean
that's just horrible similarly if it's
like a Productivity app or
app or something like that if that
crashes that's bad if it crashes and
loses the work that's horrible right so
the first step to hardening any app is
identifying what cannot fail and then
focus your attention on that first right
so the first thing you want to do in any
of these apps is put in crash protection
and when crashes occur make sure you
protect your savegame files
the data from any art that you've
created or that sort of make sure those
can get emergency written to a temp file
that you can check as crash prevention
that's the most important thing for
hardening the next step is to try and
eliminate crashes that are probably
going to happen right eliminate those
together in games usually that means
randomize testing there is no way to
write unit tests for games it's not
possible because games are all about
user input and you have no idea what
that inputs going to be so what you want
to try and do is push as much possible
user input through it to find the places
that are going to crash right if you can
isolate parts of the code that you can
test with some kind of unit testing or
testing in a reasonable amount of time
do it that certainly helps but a lot of
things there are no ways to write unit
tests for in any reasonable amount of
time the amount of time you would spend
unit testing it you would probably are
just wasting your time because it would
have been better spent on a randomized
tester because that's actually gonna
find things that players are actually
gonna hit so randomized testing is a
very good way to harden the code
basically write something that sits on
your game and plays it literally 24
hours a day all day every day run it on
as many machines as you have and wait
for it to crash right when it crashes
look where it crashed in the debugger
this is very very useful and it's
especially useful because it's
relentless it will never stop testing
your game and that is exactly what you
need to find those questions those those
crashes right midlist is I think I spent
a tape on that final print string
percent s not percent lowercase s
which one
genre this one that's that's a lowercase
s right that should be a lowercase s
right all right last question how do you
keep your mind fresh at your age you
talk really fast
don't third from the bottom third from
the bottom of what all right let me just
search
that shouldn't be there at all so that
was good one that looks right
although filename is a token right yeah
so that should actually be that that's
fine and that's fine
right
[Music]
yeah percent s capital means a length
based string how do you keep your mind
fresh period you talk about fast so let
me just try answer that real quickly and
that'd be the last question so I guess
what I would say is I don't know if
there's any particular thing that I do
that's just the way my brain tends to
work and it likes to be working all the
time so it's not particularly hard to
keep it fresh I don't know I couldn't
tell you I like to think about things so
I think that creates natural practice
for your brain I don't know
someone said exercise that helps you
breathe a lot I do exercise regularly
I exercise five or six times a week
rock climbing and running I don't know
what else yeah that's about it alright
thanks for joining me for an episode of
handmade Europe it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always let me go
ahead and close this out here thank you
for joining me for this special episode
512 if you want to follow along with the
series you can always pier to the game
on handmade hero or it comes the source
code so you can follow along at home I
will be back next week when we will do
bug our asset-building from h h TS which
will be kind of a fun thing to get
working because then we can just ship
the game as a completely buildable set
after that's gone done and we can kind
of call the asset system baked at that
point which I'll be pretty happy with
because there's a lot of things we had
to figure out there to make it all work
right
you know it's stuff streaming it does
you know streaming sound playback and
streaming asset playback and it does
on-the-fly updating and all that stuff
it's pretty darn good for something that
we only make an hour at a time or two
hours of time so up see you back here
for that until then have fun party
everyone I'll see you on the Internet
take it easy everybody