hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero show recode a complete game live on
stream wanted to mention something to
you before we get started today there
has been and I don't actually know why
exactly but there was a thread on it I
actually linked to it here and my
Twitter feed you can see here there's a
post I made on March 13th there and you
can see the thread over here and some
folks were talking about the fact that
they're having trouble meeting up with
even virtually meaning you know kind of
getting getting groups together of
people in their local areas that do you
know actual native programming and it
led to the creation of a spreadsheet not
sure who did that or why I think it may
have been Seth I'm not sure but anyway
point being it led to the creation of a
spreadsheet I just wanted to call your
attention to again the tweet has the
link to the spreadsheet but also there's
a tiny URL for it someone made that'll
probably work for a little while it's
just s rf3 tqu
so tinyurl.com /sr f3t qu and if you go
there there is a place if you just want
to build a public remember this is
available to everybody so if you don't
want people contacting you regarding
native programming stuff you probably
wouldn't want to actually fill in your
email address although you could put in
your city just to be counted some people
have done that my email address is
already public unfortunately so I've
kind of got that either way so I put
mine in here but you know if you want to
keep it as private don't put it in here
and then it's just been doing tallying
what is going on over here people keep
messing up the this thing my my lord
what are they doing like what what's
going on folks why are people doing this
stop messing with the spreadsheet it's
not hard I do not understand what's
going on with this alright anyway
doesn't matter point being everyone
always is messing with the spreadsheet I
don't know why they're messing with the
spread
she probably because it's a public
spreadsheet which is just a generally
bad idea anyway
it will then sum up the people in
various areas which appears to someone
has now broken but you know what are you
gonna do this is why we can't have nice
things people can't leave the
spreadsheet alone and this is all messed
up now they're supposed to be like that
and it's supposed to ya have all of
these things yeah there we go
and then this was supposed to be up at
the top why is it from 50 what are
people doing alright I do not understand
why people can't handle the spreadsheet
like just don't touch the spreadsheet
you don't need to touch that what is
this part here h2 there we go and then
you can see it will sum up on the side
here up until someone breaks the
spreadsheet again as people continue to
break the spreadsheet with with the
people on this so looks like the
spreadsheet you know if you want to go
add yourself to it go ahead it looks
like people are intent on or through
apparently not even vandalism just sheer
incompetence constantly breaking a
spreadsheet even though they literally
only have to add their name to the
bottom of it that's apparently too much
to ask this is also why we have
coronavirus basic stuff is very
complicated for humans and that's where
we're at on that good news let's go
ahead and work on our lighting so we
basically stopped in the middle of doing
code hygiene effectively we had just
kind of done a bunch of sprawling stuff
for lighting and now we're trying to
contract it back down also to get
ourselves some nice features we want to
be able to have everything work off of a
single lighting representation and this
will allow us to get diffused dynamic
bounce which we were previously only
able to do specular dynamic bounce and
that's just because we didn't have
access to the filtered version of our
lighting and so I'm gonna go in to the
lighting system here and I'm just going
to take a quick second to fix the bug
someone reported that was just a copy
bug um I assume it was here somewhere
this probably I'm guessing so my
assumption is like these so this should
have been X the entire time and this
should have been Y the entire time I
believe this was the bug that we're
talking about here but I could be wrong
about that so I'll double check it later
it was reported on the github and it was
just a change now we wouldn't see the
effects of that change till we start
testing for rectangular stuff so yeah I
just want to fix that because we and we
may never even switch to rectangles just
we'd never even see it if we don't
actually end up testing that as a thing
we want to do so you just wanted to
patch that up because we may never see
it if we didn't actually go start
testing for rectangular because we may
never use rectangular anyway so where we
left off was we had done a fair bit of
work porting everything over so that
everything could work out of the texture
specifically and you can see that
happening here if I actually go to the
handmade hero app you can see it running
here where you know we've got the
lighting system working but it's using
only specular for indirect bounce which
is why we're not getting much indirect
bounce lighting and you you can see the
diffuse map over here so we do produce
the diffuse map instead of down the
grass card but we can't use it because
again we've we've been using sort of an
intermediate voxel representation for
doing the lighting and so basically we
need to do is now use the Atlas directly
and so there's a couple of things we
need to do for that but we're just gonna
start in on that right away
by forcing the compiler to tell us
everywhere that that was happening so
I'm just gonna go ahead to the lighting
and I'm gonna go ahead and remove the
ability to access the light voxel cells
so this right here which is what we were
doing for a lot of stuff that's just
gonna go away like this and then we're
just gonna take a look at everything
that was previously operating on this
voxel cells now this is a to pass
process because anyone who was taking a
voxel cell as a parameter still can
so at the moment anyway we won't
actually have to touch that piece of
code but we will have to touch everyone
who was trying to like look up a voxel
cell because they're gonna get a
different answer now right okay so what
we want to do now is we want to change a
couple of these things so for example
lookup voxel clamped so like this sort
of stuff does if you look at what's
happening here this is actually talking
about and you know this is an
interesting question so and I don't know
the answer to it I'm thinking we
probably want to actually do this change
which I hadn't really considered before
but it almost seems like what it is what
we would want to do so if you look at
what's going on here where we have the
voxel like the the diffuse atlas if we
look at how we're working with it we
were previously keeping around a larger
section of it then we were using and we
were copying in just the section that we
were talking about so the like you know
we were keeping around a big one and
only updating like sections of it as we
could see them and I don't know that may
be a very good idea I'm not sure to be
honest I'm not sure we really want to
keep doing that I'm not gonna nerf it
entirely per se but it I do think you
know the more I think about it the less
I'm sure why we would want it because if
the idea is for the lighting to be
fairly real-time you don't really want
to be just be keeping a bunch of scale
lighting around so I'm not sure we
really want that to be happening either
way so what I would like to do is
probably just translate this over to
just like looking up voxels in a more
straightforward fashion right so what I
think I'm gonna do is say alright look
there's this light voxel cell nonsense
and maybe we sort of keep what that is
and we'll just say look there's a v3 for
now and the v3 pointer is like the base
pointer for it and then there's just
like a stride value
you add to that thing to get to like the
next row and that's all you do
so maybe the light voxel cell we go
ahead and say look when we look up one
of these you get back one of these light
voxel cells that you can pass around
which is just a thing that allows you to
access the light voxel in some kind of
way and we can move this information
into the actual like like this we can
actually put this into the light atlas
code itself
so effectively we'd have something like
this and maybe we'll call this a light
Atlas cell or an a la talla style and
we'll kind of work on this a little bit
more and you can see with light Atlas
and float here this stuff is maybe gonna
change a little bit and I don't really
want to think about that yet so I'm not
gonna worry about this part until a
little bit later on so in here we're
gonna say light that was tile we're
gonna return that so here I'm gonna say
light Atlas tile and this is gonna be
the result the result stride is gonna be
one thing and the base is gonna be
another
so the stride is always just gonna be
the get stride of the Atlas it's the
same stride of fer forever really and so
we got two different kinds of stride
we've got a u you know we've got stride
for the voxel and stride for the tiles
I'd like to make it clear this is the
tile stride and maybe well I guess it's
in the light Atlas now so it's the tile
stride no matter what I'll just make a
note for it though because you're really
not supposed to be writing outside of
the tile when you're looking at a
particular tile anyway so here we just
say look let's get one of these off we
go the clamped voxel now can just it
doesn't need the lighting solution it
can just use the Atlas because it
doesn't need access to these cells
anymore so basically we just need
something here right
get where the first thing in this the
tile is and then we just need the way to
compute the stride from one row to the
next and that's mostly what we're
looking at in here we've already got the
answer this is going to be the voxel dim
right
and so the voxel dim X is what we would
be clamping at in each of these cases
y&amp;z right and that's all we really need
so after we do that clamp we can do the
lookup and then we can keep going we're
not gonna look at this here so I'm going
to move this look up clamped the voxel
clamped bit and it probably called
lookup tile clamps right
I don't move that in here and so we'll
just call this get tile clamped and it
does the clamp returns the correct
pointer for you that's what we want it
to do now we have light atlas offset
here and that's more or less what we
need right so we can in here say look
this is going to be the XYZ of this
Atlas offset that we're doing and it's
gonna just be the zero zero value so all
we really need here is whatever the
stride value is from one row to the next
so we just need some way of getting you
know a stride value and we could just
say get stride atlas and this might be
fine but again it's gonna be a little
ambiguous so I think I think I might
want to make it explicit just say it's
the tile row stride so it's from one row
to the next of this tile so that we can
look at it based like an image and
that's the thing that people need to use
to add to the base pointer to get to the
next row and so that should be pretty
clear for everyone to be able to use and
we should be able to go from there so
with that in mind with that information
we should then be able to figure out
what this value should actually be so if
I want to produce a result here well
what do I have to do to get from one row
of this Atlas to the other and the
answer is well we don't have to think
about that because we already did
once right this is the T Y value which
is the tile y-coordinate and you can see
here what we multiplied it by right so
you can kind of see like it's voxel dim
X voxel dim Y tile dim X and that's the
complete stride right like so and with
that information we could also simplify
that particular piece of code here if we
wanted to because that expression the
dim X dim white tiled MX we could just
like precompute in store for example so
we could actually put this into because
it never changes we could actually put
this into the light atlas itself and if
we look at that
it's voxels MX voxel dim white tiled MX
you can see that that expression that
actually appears in more than one place
so voxel DMX voxel dim white tiled MX is
actually also this sub expression here
so X Y X right is actually this sub
expression here so we could say this is
like the tile ro stride right and it
replaces that and then the same thing
would be true here so this X Y X value
here is also the Atlas tile ro stride
right and so and what we can do is we
can make this something that doesn't
even need to be computed so you can have
a tile ro stride here that just gets
computed once and then we can just stuff
it in here so that way this actually
doesn't have to actually should boobs
there we go
so this can actually be moved up into
the initialization code so when we do
make light Atlas those dependent
variables get computed and we can just
say oh well the result tile ro stride
will just save it and then anyone who
needs to get from one row to the other
can just use it right again it's both
simplifying our code
and making it faster so it's bit it's
both things right hmm I guess I
shouldn't say it makes it faster we
haven't tested it mm-hmm
but it probably does because you know
that you're gonna be pulling this stuff
into the cache so you're probably it's
probably pretty free for you to get that
so rather than doing mm-hmm a set of
multiplies every time you can just go
ahead and look it up directly anyway so
in here we now have a couple other
values that we could look at to see
whether we want to you know sort of
memorize them as well so you can look at
what the Z value is there what the Y
value is there what the t Y is and what
the t the X and T X are right and what
you can see is there's really not
anything else that's particularly
compelling like there's just not that
much so there doesn't seem to be a lot
of other sub expressions that we might
actually care about so I think that's
probably it for our things we want to
cache I'm pretty sure I don't know that
for a fact but it seems likely anyway so
let's go ahead and finish off this year
so moving this in requires us to turn
change us into results since this the
Atlas has not been made yet so it's
using the one that's making there and
then here we're doing this light Atlas
offset that light Atlas offset code is
basically producing a u-32 that is not
counting the size of anything in
particular right so we would want to
take a v3 like we'd want to actually do
something that gets the the the texels
right like this so you'd want to get the
actual texels and we want to cast that
to a v3 like this
and then we would want to add to the
texels here so this would give us our
offset as we move you know forward there
okay so at that point yeah you can see
what we're doing here we've got this
light voxel cell and what we could do as
well is if we know that since this is
now something that we don't have to
compute we actually could just make this
part be nothing but the pointer and
that's somewhat compelling because now
you might figure well it just helps the
compiler out the compiler might be able
to see that this is the same all the
time or it might not be able to like who
knows how that analysis goes so I might
even just go one further and say all
right forget it since now that's just
something you look up we're good okay so
now if we take a look what happens here
these are all gonna be light atlas tiles
right and so all of the cells that we're
working with you should probably rename
this tiles but well I guess I'm why not
right and so here we grab out all of the
tiles that we're looking at and that
should work now because you know there's
nothing particularly fancy about this so
the only thing we need to do is pass
whose we were looking up so in this case
it's the diffuse atlas so that will get
each of these base pointers right and
what you can see here too is you know
hopefully this gets computed into
something reasonable I don't know we'll
have to look and see if it does but
hopefully this gets us all the pointers
we need quickly and then after we get
sort of where we're looking up in them
we should be able to figure out how to
blend them pretty easily so what does
this mean that's a good to do it tells
us we have an error her okay
so that's not very helpful but alright
I'm not sure what the sampling area is
exactly in this particular case that's
kind of a bit of a mystery I guess and
we don't really know but we could
probably go watch the video that's one
of the interesting things about
recording yourself programming is we
could actually find out what the error
was and that would probably be good
anyway when we go ahead and do the
results here we're just going to be
looping between the various tiles that
we looked up and we need to get a
particular T YT X out of this right so
when we do our lookup voxel clamped here
what we really want to do is for each
one of these we just want a particular T
YT X right and so another thing we could
consider here and maybe we should write
is that since this it's free for me to
move this up above here what we could do
is pre compute an offset like whatever
the offset is and just add the offset
right so we could just do like yeah I
mean we could actually just change this
entirely and just pass the offset in
here right and I don't know like you
know I'm not sure exactly how we want to
do this we'll have to take a look at how
the code is I'll do it the simple way
first but it may be too obtuse for the
compiler I'm not sure but basically what
we want to do here is when we do lookup
voxel clamped we would want to say hey
the txt Y value we want to bake those in
there right so just like give me an
actual txt Y out of this thing so
instead of just looking up the voxel
give me the individual Texel as well and
when we do that function so the lookup
the get tile clamped that way we can
actually do something like this and when
we specify the prototype for get clamped
we can actually you know put the TYT X
in there I'm gonna put a note
only the voxel is clamped not the tile
just for efficiency stand for for
efficiency sake I am NOT gonna clamp the
txt why I'm just gonna clamp the X Y and
the Z because I'm pretty sure that I'm
never gonna need to clamp the txt Y so I
don't want to like slow down that path
just for something that's never gonna
happen but I don't want to leave that
sitting there for somebody who thinks
it's entirely clamped so I'm just making
a quick note of it so if they have bugs
with that they're like oh woops sorry
just wanted to make sure that's clear so
inside this we can now change this to
get tile clamped and we can pass the TX
dy that we wanted and then inside here
we just need that so when we're doing
our lerp here we actually now don't need
any of this anymore
these arrow functions are not arrows
anymore they're just a direct access or
so it just be like bass or I don't know
what we want to call this
but I guess Texel right something like
this so in here we're just gonna call
the Texel like this and we should be
fine now there's some things we might
want to do to this later and I'm
probably not gonna bother mention them
at the moment because we'll let those
happen organically but they basically
have to do with once we want to change
this to doing some to working in ways
that are not with float we may need to
restructure us a little bit possibly
make a custom thing here just so that it
works with both float and non float but
you know I don't know all right
so if we then press forward here here's
our textile access or we already have
the ability to pass the txt Y here so
that was like zero work for us and then
in here where we're doing our lips these
pointers I guess the only thing we need
to do is is down ref them because
they're supposed to be v 3s that we
blend and they are they're just a porter
2 V 3 so I believe all I'd have to do is
something like this and now we've
actually got we're actually passing v 3s
by value here to the lerp function and
that should be the end of it right I
don't know about this part where this is
taking this is basically doing a
reflection
so maybe the we have a sample is that we
have that mirror here the fact that
we're not doing the reflection I don't
think we care about that because the
reflection vector
I don't think that matters I don't think
we want to do a bounce
well maybe we do so maybe what we were
talking about the sampling error I'm
just talking out loud here is the fact
that we want to do a bounce off of this
surface and so we want to use the
incoming light that hits the surface and
then we want to modulate by that so I'm
thinking maybe that's what we actually
want to do here so so maybe what we're
actually talking about is this and this
I'm gonna say that's what that is so
we'll take a look at that in a second so
I'm gonna I'm gonna hope that's what we
were talking about because I don't have
any idea what else we could have been
talking about for example here's the you
know here's that same exact code that's
just doing the reflection in here so
basically you know we want to be able to
bounce off the surface and we also want
to modulate by whatever the surface
color is that we hit because the fuze
reflections so it should get modulated
right so we'll have to take a look at
that hopefully by the end of the day
we'll be at a position to do more of
that work but at the moment we're just
trying to get our pipeline working
properly here okay so when we need to
actually update a voxel what we need to
do for updating the voxel is you can see
here that we could we probably just want
to pass like the base pointer in here
right so this should probably just take
a light Atlas tile and then what we do
is we just use the pointer so this right
here where we do the lerp with the with
the T offset Y and the T offset X I'm
guessing we don't really need to do that
but maybe we do right so depending on
how we want to do this we can assume
that this is a base tile if we want to
so we can do the offset here using a
tea offset which is what we got past so
I'm gonna assume that that's what we
want and the way we would do that is we
would just say all right the tile Texel
we need to be able to get a new one like
like this I don't know what I should say
you're like that was tile maybe it
should be this something like that I'm
not sure let's let's just say it's this
I like that better so here we would say
light athelets Texel this is the tile
then we would say light atlas Texel
Texel equals like offset tile offset of
let's say so for this tile we want to
get to this offset right and then we
would just say all right so the Texel
value here is the lerp version of this
and this is just me now making a little
think and work with so if we want to do
an offset from a particular ly tactless
Texel I now want something that
effectively does this it takes one texel
or maybe I'd say like get or offset from
tile Texel I don't know something like
that I'm just not sure to call it but
offset from Texel seems alright and
offset from Texel would take the light
Atlas Texel that's the base Texel and
then it would take the T offset and the
thing other thing we would need is we
would need that stride value so we would
need to know what this was right
so again the fact that's not stored here
is like the ideal thing would be with
store here but I just don't want to
introduce that overhead so I'm going to
say that the Atlas comes in here so you
do that right and so assuming we've got
this now when we do the offset from
Texel of course it went behind my head
let me just scroll that up there so get
tile clamped will produce whichever one
we want but then if we have one of those
and we want to get to a different one
what we would like to be able to do is
say alright there's a light axis Texel
that's the result here it's going to
equal the base Texel and then we're just
going to take that Texel and we're gonna
add to it the T offset X but also the
Atlas tile Rho stride times the T offset
Y right so that will move us to from any
base Texel it'll move us that many
texels in x and y which is what we would
need to get from like the upper or the
lower left corner I should say up to
some arbitrary pick Texel that we want
to talk about and that seems better
alright so that said this is not Texel
anymore sorry this valium yeah I could
have also called it at I'm just not sure
what it should be called so I apologize
so alright now when we get to something
like test cast for example in this case
we should be able to see like what we
might wanna pass here if we're working
on a particular cell we should just be
able to say look which cell are we
looking at here so here's the you know
maybe I'll call this tile and so then
before when we were looking at cell now
we would just say well here's the tile
we're actually working on and we're
doing this into the spec atlas so that's
pretty much all we really need to say
right
this is not a point juror there we go
and now when we're down to test fear the
same thing should happen so when we have
a light Atlas Texel here's the tile we
can go down here to the exact same
function basically where we're going to
assign it and all we would do there is
say give us the offset and the offset is
this DX dy here right so we'd say for
the speck Atlas and the tile that we're
on we want a V to U of T Y T X that will
give us a value that we can use so the
point this this particular pointer there
can now get assigned to right so then
finally we get to full cast which is
actually where the real work gets done
and so now we have a light Atlas tile
there that we're gonna work on and when
we actually go to use it which is here
we just have to pass what we're updating
so it's the speck Atlas and the tile and
that's it
we already updated that that function so
then we come down and finally we've got
this compute light propagation work this
is looking up the cell we want to now
look up that cell in our actual light
Atlas itself instead of in the voxel so
the light Atlas Texel in this case is
just gonna be the get tile clamped for
whatever it is that we're doing excuse
me hmm
it she knows all right so the get tile
clamped function here so this is the
tile that we're on we're going to pass
it's definitely allergy season here by
the way I've been sneezing so much
excuse me
yeah
hmm
mate tonight that was that was a mistake
um I think all the rest of this was
right though yeah okay so anyway where
do we go from here okay so when i get
this tile here i want to get the tile
out of the spec atlas because that's the
one we're actually updating we don't
need anything else I don't think we just
use the X Y &amp; Z we don't need the hot
corner offset because we're just using
the standard size of things we're going
to do the full cast here it needs to
take the spec atlas as well as the sell
oh well I guess no it doesn't what am I
talking about it just needs to take tile
like so and then in here where we're
actually doing sort of the updates to it
this is where things start to get kind
of hairy because now we're gonna
actually have to implement something
real here so if you take a look at what
happens here I don't know this was
probably doing something a little bit
different previously we don't actually
need this at the moment so this can
actually go away that probably happens
in here so really what we need update is
this
okay when we're looping over these two
things remember this is going to be kind
of crunky because we actually have two
different atlases now we have the
specular Atlas which is the one that
we're actually computing on and we have
the diffuse Atlas which is produced by
generating a blur right and this is the
thing that blur is from the specular
Atlas to the diffuse Atlas it's
currently looping over the diffuse Atlas
properly here as you can see and so what
we actually need to do is when we're
doing the light atlas when we're when
we're looping over the tiles of the
diffuse Atlas we can do this work right
here exactly as we have been doing it so
if for example in here we just said get
us the that you know if we if we did
this for the diffuse Atlas and we don't
really need the XYZ here because
remember we've already produced this
tile so actually now I think about it
well know the tile suspect guy so I take
that back so really what we probably
want to do here is say okay look get us
the diffuse tile and maybe this will be
called the speck tile like that so get
us the diffuse tile for this XYZ that
we're on and you know that'll just be
the tile base that we're gonna work with
so get that tile base and then we'll
just do an offset from Texel to get the
diffuse Texel for a particular one of
these right and I might make a way of
calling this directly here so what I
might do is say all right this actually
is just going to return
offset from Texel atlas vase T offset XT
offset Y so and then in the offset from
Texel here I'm just gonna use T X T y
and leave it like that so if we do an
offset from Texel with 1t Y there and I
pass here the diffuse tile that gives me
the specific diffuse Texel from there if
I want to I can access a particular
diffuse Texel off of the pointer here so
I can just say now diffuse texels value
and get rid of all of this then when we
come through here and we need to write
to it this should all work the same way
so I don't think any of that needs to
change
and so then oops I need to actually
rename the speck tile where we grabbed
that there we go
so then we just need a way of accessing
the specular Atlas properly so if you
look at the way this is working this
actually loops over the speck Atlas dim
X&amp;Y properly here so maybe this is okay
but where we actually get the tile out
you can see this is nonsense now so we
need to get the speck tile but
fortunately we already have that so
really all we need to do now is ask for
the offset inside the so like here right
we just need to ask for the offset now
we could use this where we actually go
by rows and Load incrementally and you
know this that's gonna be stuff when we
go to the action to the optimization
pass we'll look at what the compiler is
doing there and it may do that
transformation for us but if it doesn't
that's something we're gonna have to do
so this wants the SX plus 1 sy plus 1
right that's what it's looking for here
and that's how it's producing this Val
so the spec Texel should just be that
and if we then say load the spec Texel
value this spec Texel value here out of
the specular and you know write it in
that should be all we really need to do
I think not entire don't quote me on
that
so that should give us what we need
there we then have this copy the block
copy voxel routine and I don't actually
know that we need to do this anymore so
we may just say like that's not gonna
happen so yeah call it all you want but
we're not actually gonna use this
anymore
actually let's just not call it at all
and the problem that we're gonna have
here again is that as we move around
well no you know what I take that back
so we probably do want to do this and we
do we just want to copy the part that
we're looking at at the moment so if we
happen to have some overlap as it moves
we are we are gonna want that so I think
we want to do this we just need it to
copy tiles instead right so the thing is
the large this is not going to operate
this at the moment is now going to be
something that actually happens per
Atlas right
for copying and so we would want to do
this on the atlases itself right so this
would actually be a thing that's like
block copy Atlas and it would take a
light Atlas and it would take a debauch
soul and it would basically do exactly
the same thing right I'm gonna go ahead
and if one in here so that we can use
this version well no that's but that's
wrong because that actually only works
if you're not overlapping so I don't
know that this actually helps us at all
really I think we can get rid of that
path because I don't think that would
that would have an overwrite error right
so unless you copied the Atlas it
wouldn't work so just get rid of that
it's not useful all right so this
routine here basically all we need to do
is change the light large voxel dim to
use whatever the Atlas voxel dim is
right so since this is why I think it
means it should be why right so all of
these should be Y values here we then
have X values and the X values should
should do the same I would say right so
this is Atlas voxel dim X like so
and this is Z and this would just copy
the tiles around now the interesting
thing about this is there's probably a
lot of ways we can make this a lot
faster now that it's laid out as an
actual sheet we could probably do things
that are fancier than this so like you
know so there's probably ways we could
do something like that that don't
involve individual tile copies but at
the moment that's not something we're
going to explore so all we really need
now is the thing that's like a copy tile
function that copies from one atlas to a
nut from the atlas into itself a zero
tile function that zeros out a tile and
so all we would really have to do here
is say like look XYZ zero this tile
practice is all the same so this is also
an XYZ zero tile this is also an XYZ
zero tile so all of those clears would
work just fine and so all we would need
here is the copy function and so it
would be a from into so we're copying to
this right from this like that
and let me just put these in Xyz order
here so we just basically do a copy from
there to here or I should say source
desk and there yeah so as long as we can
implement a function that copies tiles
and a function that zeros tiles neither
of which should be too tricky that
should give us what we need right so
let's go ahead and do that here's our
copy tile function and we need our
source X I guess these are s 32 s see
there you three 2's aren't they I mean
they can't be outside
right so what we need to do now is we
need to do for example our get tile
clamped source X source Y source Z and
this will give us our source tile and
then we get our desk tile right and from
source tile the desktop now we just need
to copy the entirety of the you know we
we now just need to advance those
basically in fact we could do this even
by by having a function that does that
for us so if we want to go row by row we
should be able to just do this right and
then here we can just say look for Texel
equals you know whatever the Atlas tile
dim X is copy it
so that would copy one of these things
just loop through it grab each
individual Texel move it over for a row
and then we just need something that
does that for each row which looks like
this right in fact let's call these what
we've been calling them right and that
should be our entire copy function all
we need is an advanced row function to
do you know basically take a light Atlas
Texel which is an access er into our
light atlas right and move it from one
row to the next and that's super simple
because whatever the value is of this
thing all we're gonna do is move it by
that row stride right that just moves it
to the next row so really really
straightforward not anything fancy going
on there and that's it now if we want to
the zero function would be literally the
same code the only difference is we
don't have a source so instead of ever
working with the source we just say look
this thing is whatever the zero value is
right and that's it I think so I think
that's pretty much all we need and now
that function has been ported as well
right okay now this again we need to
make relative to the atlas so this is
going to be the voxel dim x and this is
going to be the voxel dim y this will be
the X here there we go and I think we're
all good so that looks good so then here
we've got you know these functions the
advanced row function that's probably
generally useful to like I could easily
use that elsewhere so like here
then we've got our copy tile function
that anyone can use if they want to
right to move tiles around in the Atlas
and then we have our zero tile function
same thing right and actually let me do
that like this so this just gives our
Atlas some pretty nice features there
and now you can kind of build whatever
you need there looks like we forgot a
semicolon so that all works good I think
all right so when we do this we need to
update both of our atlases so in begin
lighting computation we're going to want
to grab the render commands here out of
the render group that we've been given
actually I should go in here and do it
so that will do this so the commands
diffuse light Atlas and the commands
spec light Atlas those should be updated
like thusly and whoops specular and now
we've updated both of those for movement
in our code and that's good right okay
so now
I'm not sure what the natural next thing
to do is I'm guessing just put a lot of
assertions in here and try to catch bugs
that we've introduced by moving to the
system because there's a lot of indexing
going on and that's usually when you
have a lot of different pieces that all
get like you know dese whistled in place
in areas it's usually very easy to make
small mistakes and so like putting a
bunch of assertions in here and trying
to catch bugs is probably the easiest
thing to do at this point in the code so
we'll go through crashbug first because
obviously that's easy enough not sure
what's going on here is that a let me
let me get going debug mode I'm assuming
that's actually not this line because
that probably wouldn't produce an error
right like you can see that tile dim is
totally fine here so it's probably
actually complaining about something
else not this
show me the actual hair please
hmm well that's not good
so that's complaining that actually we
only have a bug in the release version
of the program which makes very little
sense I mean that is the sort of thing
that can happen when you're doing a
bunch of memory work like this because
we're you know we're definitely tempting
fate there but that's kind of
interesting because that's not what you
would normally expect to see with this
particular type of thing so we may be
over writing something somewhere or
something like this
hard to say let's take a look at where
we are so on a fill light atlas border
here we come in let's see where we're
actually we're literally hitting it
right after the stack setup so this
looks like probably just a memory over I
kind of thing I'm guessing I'm gonna go
ahead and start putting some assertions
in here real quick just to see what
we've got going on so when we do like
any of these sorts of things the get
tile clamped function should be
preventing us from ever writing outside
the bounds of the voxel right and so I'm
not sure like we could do some pointer
checking there I'm not sure though gosh
I'm not I'm really not sure like because
because this is doing clamped it
shouldn't probably be doing clamped so
you know what we really shouldn't be
doing a clamp here what we should be
doing there is get tile unclamped really
right so it should probably be this you
know I'm saying and I might just make
one of those like this
like that so this would just give me a
way of accessing something without
clamping because in these cases this
thing should never actually be called on
anyone who's out anyone who's out of
bounds so I'm going to do that and I'm
also going to go ahead and assert here
that were in bounds right so just want
to go ahead and check these values for
validity so this just true let me go
ahead and push this up to the parameter
area and set defaults for txt Y to 0
like so all right this somebody took my
name's that's all just moving memory
around that is literally all the
computer does you're so right like
basically everything that you think
you're doing is really just moving
memory to one place or another and
changing it along the way right like
it's it's pretty much all it does
transforms is all a computer does
basically question is which the
transform um should be computed by
semicolon I agree let's go ahead and fix
that all right so I don't know how to
proceed on this other than to start
adding you know how should I put this
other than to start adding like stuff
that tries to catch the error earlier
right so basically like there's a couple
ways we could do this one way is to sort
of
try to find this specific bug but
because this is a very low-level finicky
moving data around with with offsets
kind of a thing what I'd rather do is
just put like incrementally build up the
safety net until the safety net itself
catches us that way hopefully it'll
catch other bugs too June and I'm saying
so rather than just try to find this one
bug I want to try and put in a bunch of
like assertions to find classes of bugs
so that anywhere that I'm actually doing
stuff I get an assertion if somebody
screwed up so for example in this block
copy Atlas routine
I know it's always calling in to get a
tile unclamped so I know that if it ever
passes anything wrong in terms of a
voxel offset it'll get here right
similarly I can in here say look T X T Y
I want to make sure that these values
are in bounds so that will make sure
that that always tells me if they are
and similarly the other thing I can do
is when we actually go to get the
pointer here anytime we have one of
these I can also do a like pointer in
bounds I can do an assertion on the
pointer is in bounds and just check it
right so I want to basically have a way
that every time I produce one of these
just even redundantly when I don't need
it there I guess I can always check the
resulting pointer to see whether the
pointer has gone inside or outside the
bounds of the Atlas so let me pass the
Atlas there too right and again this is
just defensive programming to catch my
own mistakes these will go away in
release mode but it's just there to as a
scaffold to try and catch yours I want
to try and catch the errors with this
rather than try to catch the error
manually because I won't be able to
catch all errors manually is my thinking
whereas this will catch some errors I
might not have seen because they just
happen to not like cause a problem or
something
oops um all right well that's the same
call so we don't need it there this is
good all right that's all good and so in
here what I'm going to do is just say
all right we know we have the texels
here right so what we should be able to
do is we should be able to make this
pointer inbounds which is just a way of
quickly checking to see whether the
thing you're about to use actually can
be used or not so when we do any of
these things we can just do an internal
be 32x pointer is inbounds we take the
light Atlas itself we take the light
Atlas Texel and we basically just say
the result of this check is going to be
the test cell value being required to be
higher than this base pointer right I
want to put that here so we're going to
cast that to a regular generic bite
pointer we're gonna check to make sure
that it's greater than the Atlas texels
so it's not off the beginning of our
buffer and then we're gonna check to see
I don't know why I've got an extra
parenthesis in there we're gonna check
to see if it's less than whatever the
end pointer would have been so rather
than do that here I'm gonna put that out
of Lion so we can inspect it so that's
just whatever the check pointer was or
you know that which is the the up sorry
not the check pointer that's whatever
the Atlas texels pointer is plus
whatever the total size of this thing is
so if we want to we can call our get
light Atlas Texel size because we know
that's what we use to allocate this
thing in the first place right
and so we can just call that and say
well whatever that is that's what we're
gonna check right I think that's all we
actually needed there what is the
problem here
all right so now we're just going to run
this and see if we catch we think of
those asserts I'm not certain that we
will because again it may not ever find
anything oh and it did so that's good so
you can see here the get tile unclamped
call so we can walk backwards to see
who's doing this you can see here we
have somebody working with the geta
clamped here it's calling the spec atlas
and the x y&amp;z here I so I I have a
feeling I know what's happening I want
to say that the work distribution call
has not been updated to take into
account the fact that we no longer have
a large voxel and so what I want to do
first before I even go look at that is I
want to get rid of that idea in the
first place
so there's now this light lookup voxel
dim right and there's also this other
like large voxel dim nonsense this bit
here so what we want to do there I think
is just get rid of this entirely right
that's going to be gone and we only have
our interior voxel now right so let's
take care of that code because that code
needs to be updated it's wrong so the
large dim goes away and now we've got
some work to do here we've got the light
large voxel dim and the large cell count
and all this stuff we got to fix all
this right so let's get rid of large
cell count because that's gone and
propagate it through when we do the
offset
there is no offset I because
the hot corner I now has to be based on
wherever the we've we've got a we've got
work to do we now want to take like
wherever the cameras looking and we want
to Center the voxel around the correct
area and we have to floor it so that it
aligns properly with like how the chunks
are lined up you know I'm saying so will
yeah so we've got work to do if we go in
here we can see we've got min corner
large and min corner hot min corner
large is now gone Vox Selden and in
voxel dim those are fine I think because
they're just a cell so that should be
totally fine the only thing we don't
have here well I guess that's it so
that's all we really need to get rid of
there all right so yeah if we want to do
get voxel Center P here and we're
looping over the voxel then instead of
min corner large this is just going to
be Vox min corner hot because that's the
only voxel we now have min corner hot
right and then is that all yeah so this
part now doesn't actually happen none of
this matters so that's all gone and so
now we just have to figure out how to
place our like hot Vox look it's the
only thing we actually have right and if
we take a look at the center moved stuff
right and all of this this is so what
you can see here is this is not really
what we want to base our voxel placement
on and in fact what we may want to do is
turn the lighting off for a second and
actually get this voxel sliding around
properly so that it you know encompasses
what we actually need it to encompass
would be another way to look at it if we
look at what the actual lighting size is
here
I have no idea what this is and I don't
think anyone uses it I mean it's
verified that's the case it is I might
also move this into the renderer just
for now there we go just to keep all
these in one place so you know if we
look at what's going on here we've got a
32 by 32 by 32 voxel that's what we're
using and I don't actually know if
that's going to be sufficient it may or
may not be we may have to go to 64 by 64
by 32 or 64 by 6 4 by 16 or something
like that which will now have the
flexibility to do but either way we need
to place this thing and we need to slide
the voxel around properly and one of the
things that we need to do for that is we
need to actually work with the act the
camera placement now and so what I'm
gonna do I think is I want to turn off
the lightning computations entirely so
that they're not actually occurring if
you look in here I don't know that we
actually do turn off the lighting ever
like this whole thing should kind of
have a if lighting enabled around it I
would think and doesn't really so like
this I think we kind of need to store
right so probably what I would say is on
here I would want something to select
lighting enabled would actually go in
you know into the lighting solution
itself so solution lighting enable it
equals letting enabled and then it would
check it and then when we do the end
call in here we would just do this take
the whole thing and wrap it so we
wouldn't actually you know do any of
this stuff
in in the case where the lighting was
disabled so then what I want to do is I
want to set an if 0 here and I want to
disable the lighting I don't want it to
do the lighting
and I want to work on the voxel
placement in a second so we'll do that
all right so get rid of this put that
here go ahead and now what I want to do
is I want to nerf the lighting actually
at this point so lighting enabled was
false and you'll see why I want to do
this in a second so let's go ahead and
run now and we should get hopefully no
lighting yeah
which makes it a little bit hard to see
that's okay because I think if I want to
I should excuse me where's the thought
we had a thing for lighting or something
that was like whether or not the
lighting was on I don't know yeah all
right so I shouldn't be able to do this
we got to work on our render switches
maybe that'll be another cleanup Pass
will do after this so if I turn the
lighting off why is this even being done
who is calling this what oh right that
does still get called okay well that's
good to know too so that means we have
an offset error in there as well so this
is great will be finding all sorts of
things here in fact let me do bug that
one now and then I'll go debug the voxel
placement later well you know what I
take that back because since we're not
placing the voxel correctly here maybe
that wouldn't ever matter no that's not
true
so let's debug that one real quick
because that seems like it's easy to
debug right so you can see here we're
calling it Tallinn clamped with the I
don't know what the XYZ is but you would
think that would have asserted a little
earlier if that's the actual XYZ let me
see if this works in debug mode those
might be bogus values because I'm like
that's totally wrong
why wouldn't it have asserted on the
bounced check
so there we go so the x y&amp;z those are
saying values so that was what I
expected
pointer is in bounds here you can see
seems to have an issue so let's figure
out you know is this busted so what's it
actually doing with the light Atlas
offset there with the XY and Z and so on
our txt Y is just 0 and 0 so there
should be no problem with that
and the result value here is just the
texels plus whatever that offset is so
you would think that this should
definitely be in bounds maybe this
functions broken I don't know but you
can see that whatever the light acts
whatever the get light Atlas Texel sighs
oh all right
that's a copypasta that should be get
light atlas sighs that was a very narrow
range that we could have accessed in one
texel let's try that again all right so
hopefully this will be fine now because
I was gonna say I didn't think that
routine would be bad so this is a busted
okay that's good so this is good to know
so let's verify that that's actually
reporting a real error first but that's
good so this zero tile is somehow
advancing too much so somehow this is
like outside of where it should be right
so let's see if that's actually true I
don't know let's just take a look so
let's see if it's plausibly outside at
all so it is on the last row so that's
consistent with this being a plausible
error right so if we look at what we're
doing here we're looping over a certain
number of X's certain number of Y's that
looks like it should be correct because
here's the Atlas tile dim right and
here's the Atlas tyldum X so in theory
this this seems like it should be
plausible but yet somehow this advance
row
well you know what it could be the last
one though so it should be like pointing
now to one past the last there so if T Y
is nine that means it's gonna exit the
loop yeah so the problem is with
checking an advance row
I'm really glad like this is good
because now we're seeing that it is
actually checking the correct ranges now
that pointer is an invalid pointer but
we're never gonna use it so I guess with
advance row it's kind of one of those
things where I can't actually check it
which is a bummer but I guess I'll do
the best I can and I can I can do those
checks before I operate on the value and
hopefully that'll give me most of the
protection but we'll see all right so
what's you're complaining about atlas oh
it's just Texel okay so I don't actually
need it I can just do this right so
hopefully we'll get something out of
this we'll find out there we go
there we go so now what I want to do is
I want to draw those voxels in here so
you can see that I'm not drawing the
voxels in here but if I go into this
piece of code here and enable it I will
start drawing the voxels the problem is
I don't actually know where they're
placed currently because you can see
that like the offset eye is like a thing
that produces you know a hot corner hot
corner information here we don't want a
hot corner eye anymore it's just the min
corner and the dimension is all we
actually need so that kind of goes away
but this part here still remains so we
have this up this is the dimensions and
that's correct this is the inverse
dimensions and that's all correct so
then what we really need to do is just
figure out where this stuff is this
places it the large corner doesn't need
to be computed and the large rec doesn't
need to be computed so then we're just
down to this now we need to figure out
some way oh so we found another error
here get tile unclamped the Y is in the
wrong place so what happened there who
is causing this problem let me take a
look
block copy begin so this is this D voxel
here and presumably no matter what you
pass through this it should work because
like it should do the clamping interior
to this so I feel like I feel like this
should work
so this this should be a legitimate bug
meaning there's an actual bug in the
routine so like this copy tile for
example should should hopefully this
should actually be wrong would be my
guess
so source X source y source Z you know
that's not a good source Z so it looks
like source Y went like below zero here
right in this routine somehow so this
was not correct and I'm not sure why so
let's take a look so we have initial Z
final Z and stop z
and looking at where we are the z-value
that we're passing in here the D voxel Z
is zero good didn't I look at the wrong
value wait a minute
it's Y that I'm looking at what am i
doing it's Y so what we want to do is
look at Y there and you know
[Music]
I don't see anything obviously wrong
there's someone look at the individual
values so taking a look at D voxel why
it's garbage which is fine though I
would think because it should clamp it
right like or do we not have that
I wonder why that doesn't work all right
let's take a look so that's our D voxel
Y so our D Y is negative our stop Y is
so I guess the problem here is that
since these values are actually signed
they wrap around which makes it look
like it works to the algorithm which is
pretty janky
see equals initial Z Z is not equal to
stop Z Y is initial Y Y not equal to
stop Y so that actually is fine Maya
plus equals dy over negative Y and so
the problem is this value will not stop
at a property at time I'll just keep
going right
so my assumption here is just that this
routine I guess doesn't contemplate the
concept that you wouldn't do any copying
at all
I mean it doesn't look like we ever
really handled that case somehow which I
guess why not I wonder what makes it so
that we I guess I'm not really sure what
we were doing before that made it so
that this wasn't a problem you know what
I mean I'm guessing that maybe this was
a bug that we just hadn't addressed
because it seems like this just wouldn't
work for this case where you have
something where the the devoxx 'el is
too large so we may just want to
presuppose that we don't do the block
copy if it's so egregious right but that
the idea was that should fall down to
this case right so what we really want
to have happened here is in a case where
we need to clear everything you know we
want to fall through to these cases so
the why and the stop why should be equal
to each other in this case and they're
not right
so like initial why and stop why should
be equal to each other in the case where
you cannot do any copies because the
Delta was too large and that's totally
not going to happen right so is it just
me or maybe the only thing we really
need to do is just clamp this
I mean is that right just clamp the stop
wine I think that might be it so
basically those things needed to be
clamped and just never were I want to
say so right here this should be clamped
because you should never be allowed to
sample outside of that why right I want
to say and I don't know if that's
exactly right but I think that's right
so it's basically and that's like the
initial Y right
so in fact we probably could do it this
way
and so here the vox of my - 1 - d voxel
y and we know that d voxel i is positive
so really this just needs to be clamped
to 0 right and i guess in this case the
same is true so maybe that was a little
premature we really only need one check
here right so in here we just need to
make sure this doesn't exceed initial Y
right so it's more like stop Y is right
we want to make sure that we are the the
the D voxel Y is negative so this is
going to be positive right so so this
value we really just want to set it to
the minimum of these two right I believe
and then here we want to set it to the
maximum of these two maybe I'll do it
this way
so I think that's more correct now cuz
you're basically saying look I know that
this could be arbitrarily large and it
might be so large that it spans the
entire buffer and at that point we want
the stop and the initial to be equal to
each other so that we don't enter the
loop right so we just needed a bounds
check there and I think that's what we
want to do for each of these guys so
that each of them is going to be like
okay we've gots you know this one is
minimum initial X and this one is
maximum initial X and then minimum
initial Z maximum initial Z and so those
values have to be checked there and I
think that's what we need let me hop
around a little bit and see if that
addresses that but I think I've
interpreted that loop correctly and and
that's what we would need there so when
you actually go into an area that's like
large enough you would get that problem
right
all right so I'm glad we got that out of
the way and again that's exactly the
kind of errors I was talking about I was
like I want to add enough checks that we
start to catch errors that I don't even
know are there right and that's exactly
what that just did so whenever you're
doing kind of this relatively finicky
stuff sometimes it behooves you to be
paranoid and to put in a bunch of bounds
checking because you're not gonna
necessarily see all the errors but they
might be there right ok so now if I want
to go back to what I was doing before
where I want to draw where the actual
voxel is so in end lighting OOP sorry in
begin lighting actually I want to take a
look at this outline so if I'm running
oops
I didn't mean to attach the process
there so if I'm running no I don't want
to be on the title screen if I'm running
the game and looking at sort of the
bounds here that's the wow that's the
lighting voxel all right that's a pretty
large span and not particularly tight to
the camera but ok all right so if that's
weld I mean that's fine for now I guess
so I guess I don't care so we can leave
that be so let's go ahead and re-enable
then and let's look for more bugs so
that's fine for now we want to do better
than that in the future but that's
beside the point realized we had already
had it centering that way ok so let me
just double check our lighting
distribution here I'm going to turn the
lighting back on here although we're not
going to render with it yet and I just
want to look at what's going on in the
work distribution where we're setting
the work index here for voxel X light
look up Fox at him so that's all correct
looks like so we'll go ahead and run and
see where we're at
and now we're looking for bugs again so
we're looking to get rid of the access
our bugs and we believe at least we have
some more of those all right so they're
not triggering in debug mode let's try
to get them triggering in release mode
so looks like we can trigger one in
release mode again so is this random or
specific it seems pretty reproducible so
that's good so we believe we have a bug
in here you know inside where we're
actually accessing and and this is not
any kind of a special move so this is
just us like accessing memory improperly
or something and so we want to take a
look at this routine and what I would
like to do is just get rid of it
temporarily
so let's verify that we actually think
we have a bug there in that code
specifically and see if everything runs
fine with with that code out and then
we'll start to look at putting that code
in right and and and we'll go from there
Oh computation work lighting where's the
where's that you know what the problem
is it's in one of those macros and I
don't have any way of searching for
those macros it's in one of those work
callbacks right someday I have to figure
out how I don't even know how you would
do that but if you I guess you just look
use internal as a cheat but this problem
is you can't tell what this is it's a
macro when the editor is like searching
for it long story but doesn't matter
anyway so in here we're we're actually
doing this
smackdown I'm gonna go ahead and just
get rid of it and let this run and see
if we still get crashes elsewhere and
then I'm gonna put it back in okay so
basically if we just have only the spec
map which you can see on the right side
we're not getting that crash right and
you can see the specular lighting over
on the side there right specular bounce
lighting and it actually looks fine I
mean I don't know if it's right or wrong
but if you know there's no obvious
errors it looks like what a bunch of
specular bounce would look like right so
you know it doesn't look obviously
stupid it might be but just doesn't you
can't obviously tell it's wrong
all right so in our diffuse blur this is
where looks like it's having trouble so
let's take a look at what this is
actually doing and see if we can make
some sense of it all so one thing I
would note is at this point one thing I
might also want to do is this light
Atlas offset might now now want to go
away so if I look at all the places that
were using it and you can see like this
is the complete list so one of them is
here and that's where it should go now I
think and then there's these and so I
don't
necessarily want these in here
fortunately I think that's the only
place that it is so I'm okay with that
for the immediate moment but you can
kind of see that like this should
probably go away and and work through
those tile accessors now just so we can
track them more carefully so I just
wanted to make sure that that was the
only place and it is that's okay so now
if we come back here and look at this we
got to figure out what we're doing here
we're accessing a diffuse tile here and
we go and get a diffuse textile out of
that tile using a particular access or
we then take a look at it as if it's a
three-wide so what we're doing here is
just just doing computing three of the
diffuse computing four of the diffuse
blends at once just to make the math
faster by taking advantage of a wide
factor that's all we're trying to do
here so this is figuring out how many of
those we have and so it's however like
this would be ten minus two divided by
four or two right sets of four we're
loading out of the diffuse weight map
which we have not worked on so this is
kind of a garbage thing at this point
but it should be wide enough to store
the information we actually need because
we made it like oversized so presumably
this will be fine make sure that's true
yep
and then inside here where we're looping
over the spec Atlas again we're just
looping over the sys X for that and for
each one of these were just accessing it
so inside the Select axis we get this
out and off we go
right so in theory that should be fine
because it's just using the standard
offsets and we're looping over literally
just the specular values there so yeah
unless we're loading out of the weights
wrong or something how big is the
diffuse from a 6-minute yeah so we
shouldn't be able do that either I mean
it looks fine to me I'm not I'm not
seeing anything stupid there right
we unsold the results and then we go to
store them and when we store them I mean
we're not doing anything interesting
there either
so to be honest I'm not really seeing
the bug ohyou nothing's jumping out at
me so here's the first thing I'll do I I
will just take a minute to see what
happens if we nerf some of these stores
now the problem with doing this is the
optimizer may remove the entire loop if
we don't store so that's a little bit of
an issue I will just check to see if it
did that or not by quickly going to the
disassembly and just looking at what
it's doing so
I mean it sure looks like it's doing the
transpose like it's got a bunch of chef
PS is in there right so I think it's
still generating the loop even though
it's not using the values from it yeah
it is so if we just run this loop
[Music]
although it's probably not loading this
well it is it's gonna transpose it so I
think it's just this part that's wrong
let's check I mean let's see what we can
see here if in here I was in the desc
see value where we are getting this
offset out of here if I was to do
something Oh duh that was pretty much it
that was just a bad address we were we
were actually targeting this particular
pointer rather than using the pointer to
point at something so I think that was
all that was alright so I mean seems
plausible what I'm looking at now this
should actually be using the diffuse
bounce lighting for propagation now so
that's good if we actually enable the
lighting in the Z bias program we can
look at what it looks like so I'll just
turn that on real quick I don't know why
I stopped the program I guess that would
a hot loaded just fine but we don't
really care I mean it's not a big deal
so if now we look at what we've got you
know you can see that the light
propagates a lot more which is what it's
supposed to do because now we're
actually looking at the diffuse lighting
correctly and so like outdoors right it
doesn't have anything to bounce off of
these treat like at the moment we don't
put in
ders for these trees we should but
that's a world Jen thing not a that's
nothing to do with the with the lighting
stuff right but hopefully you can see
now yes oh the bounce letting it fills
up the space a lot more with light right
which is what it's supposed to do and
maybe those lights are a little bit
bright like you know you can see that
they're getting fully bounced around but
a lot of that is just because we're not
taking into we're not taking any light
out on the bounce
so like when we go over to the the the
irradiance computation so here we're not
actually modulating this bounce
we're just saying here's the actual
color that the full color that was
sampled at this point so we probably
want to be doing here where we look at
this value as we've got the sample P
sample N and so when we do get voxel
irradiance at why are we not o compute
voxels so we're looking at compute voxel
irradiance at there what we don't have
the sample ref color here are we
actually using that oh we are we are
using a sample ref color so are those
sample ref colors set properly
would be my next question
as you can see there's just way too much
light coming in here like all the light
is bouncing around infinitely which is
not what we want
so let me just see what happens if we
have some bounce degradation
still looks like way too much
transmission so that seems like maybe
we've just got some bugginess there of
course we also aren't doing the bounce
which is sort of a separate issue but so
here's with lower transmission
that's interesting so is this where we
crash in there oh just in the debug data
nevermind so I'm not sure this is
probably a point where I should stop for
today because we're pretty much at the
end but alright so we're you know we're
getting closer we're not really there
yet but we're getting closer and now we
can bounce our light around much better
and we're not actually doing the bounce
like I mean the actual bounce
computation right in here should be
should do this so when we do when we hit
this surface we've got the normal we
want to bounce off and sample what the
incident lighting would be right and so
I guess the only thing I'm not sure
about is well no you know I think that's
not true because we're just sampling
diffused so as long as we do a sample
and here we should be good so actually
this is all none of this is necessary
yeah that's that's just that's that's
not true
so all we should that should be it if we
should be able to sample that in because
that's to some of the diffuse light in
that direction right so the the outgoing
should just be the sample end I think
and then we you know then we multiply it
so I don't know what sample Ref why it
seems like we're getting too much
buildup of light which is not what I
would have expected but that seems to be
what's happening and I don't know if
that's just because of the way the
diffuse sum is working out we've got
like a bug in there where you know it
should be knocked down by some constant
value where there's an integral and
we're missing the light constant term so
it could be that like these things here
are wrong you know what I mean it could
be that like you know this is supposed
to be that right or that and it could be
like that's what's actually causing our
problem and you know I have no idea
right
so it's really hard to say so I think
this about we have to go work on this
stuff
more so like for example if we've stuck
a fudge value in here just curious what
happens
where are we getting these bugs from
just our debug record stuff is our debug
record stuff needs work we tried to get
too fancy with it and it didn't pay off
it just creates headaches really
just empirically looking at what this
value would be just so we can see where
our actual bug like what our bug level
like where the bug actually is sort of
more or less
so I mean looking at it I would say like
that looks kind of more correct in terms
of like what you would want the answer
to be
so it's a little bit hard to say but
that seems more like roughly where it
should be
all right so I think unfortunately the
next thing we would have to do is go
through and actually tighten down the
lighting equations which is always a
little bit difficult for me because I
don't work with them very often like I'm
very comfortable with camera stuff and
lens stuff and I'm very uncomfortable
with lighting stuff which just because
it's just not something I work on very
often and so like figuring out exactly
what the values are and how to keep them
to unbiased so they stay you know within
a range that is mathematically
determined rather I mean because we can
go in and add fudge values like this to
make it work right but I don't really
want to I want to know what the actual
equations are and that they're roughly
correct and what's interesting is like
not sure where this value is coming from
but it's very close to one which means
the amount of fudging that we actually
need to do to keep the lighting stable
is quite low so I'm not sure if we just
have some stupid thing we're doing that
I'm just not thinking of that's actually
like the only problem or something but I
mean it's like shockingly low amount of
fudge to keep it stable so I don't know
I mean is it just like a rounding error
kind of thing I doubt that so I do want
to look at it more carefully where is
the actual explosion point nine point
five five point nine five or what
I mean right it's it's crazy that that's
the fudge value that's so close to one
that also makes me confused about like
because that still looks right to me
especially if we added some you know
exposure control in there so that the
brights weren't quite so bright you know
I'm Santi
real weird so basically as far as I can
tell as long as you take any energy out
of the system whatsoever like as long as
you don't use literally one the system
seems stable or am I wrong about that
but like at one it appears to be
unstable maybe it's not unstable maybe
that's a lie and it's totally stable at
one and I just need to exposure mapping
and that's the case I'm pretty happy but
let's leave it here and we'll see
alright let's go ahead and do Q&amp;A for
the moment
what's the cause of the flickering in
the lighting will you do some denoising
or cast my Raiders or to try to fix it
yet well it's just yeah it's just
sampling noise no and I probably
wouldn't I would leave it flickery I
like the flickery look eventually
probably make I probably just keep that
if you want to denoise it then yeah you
would have to basically do it pass it
this looks unstable this looks like it's
continuing to go right so it looks like
something is you know what's the
spelling of that that's the worst
feeling ever empirically
yeah that's what we're looking for so
that's some kind of a bug right
I think it might have flippity xpy in
tests fear I think we fixed that though
right because that was flip but wery
flipped it right
could it be useful to have it print of
value like the average textile color of
the diffuse Center specular maps on the
screen yeah I mean it could you could
sum them up and just see what the total
amount of light is right I'm not sure
how useful that is because you can kind
of see that it's happening I mean either
it explodes or it doesn't so at the
moment I wouldn't get very much
information out of that value but it's
not a bad value to print are using a
different level of assert for release
build no actually I'm not so if you want
the full speed build
you actually would need to go like turn
off like this stuff right which are
other things like insertions that slow
down the code and looks like timed
function it looks like we're not
properly undef
so I guess so handmade internal is
clamping out all of this which is a
mistake it looks like right so the
problem is like this stuff for handmade
slow if you undefined both of them it
looks like these are not included in
that right so that seems like an issue
I'm not sure what we would do about that
so I guess the best thing to do would be
to say well if this all has to be inside
internal anyway yeah I don't know what
to make of that it looks like we were
trying to make it so that that would be
a separate thing we could access and I'm
not sure what the easiest way to prevent
that problem would be I guess you would
do something like this so this is
running with none of the stuff enabled
right but as you can see like it's not
like that much faster so that's why I
don't generally do it because we don't
get like a huge speed boost from it or
anything so it's usually not an issue
like we don't put asserts in like places
where they're really hugely problematic
because usually it's pretty simple for
the compiler to output something where
the branch is predicted anyway so you
typically don't gain as much as you
might think right so we just haven't
bothered with that particular with that
particular thing so yeah
[Music]
anyway we don't really know the lighting
probably has tons of broken stuff in it
now we now need to go through that now
that we've got the pathway working
properly we now need to go through and
actually start to do transmission tests
and like see if we can actually get the
lighting correct because that's the next
step and then finally we would go to
optimization which is like the final
thing
yeah I would agree about DuckDuckGo I've
been trying it because Google is so bad
now with the search results I hate this
it's just so hard to read it's just
terrible and so I just don't like it
so I want another search engine
unfortunately duck tacos search is
crappy but um how slow are we I don't
know pretty slow at the moment but it's
mostly in the raycast if I remember
correctly so it actually doesn't have
that much to do with the sampling so you
can see here that full cast takes up
most of the frame time but there is a
part of it here that's the diffuse blur
so this is the diffuse blur here right
and this is the Ray casting and
irradiance sampling amusingly like I was
surprised to learn that the all of the
actual irradiance sampling does not
account for as much time as I would have
expected when we nerf that out so that
was weird but basically we're still
looking at a problem of like hey we can
this we can probably do something about
without too much effort so improving the
speed of the diffuse blur because we can
cut corners there there's stuff we could
do there I think that we're not doing
now so that's probably because we could
probably do something separable for that
I wouldn't be surprised if we could and
cut down that computation pretty
dramatically so I'm guessing that this
could be flattened without too much
trouble the full cast I'm sure we can
speed up but that's gonna be the more
complicated thing because then we got to
start looking at like okay how's the
spatial partitioning is it you know is
it working okay
like we got to be more serious about
that set of things and so that's gonna
take more work and I also think it's
probably getting called too many times
at the moment so if you look at what's
going on there you know if we look
across this distribution what you can
see is that if I switch to the thread
view we've got like six worker threads
working on this thing right and I don't
know if the main thread counts or not
but whether it does or it doesn't isn't
really relevant the point is we've got
all these threads that are working on
the that are working on the raycast and
and mixdown and so the thirty-two here
is because it's being distributed so
it's it's basically four cut four times
per thread each thread is sorry
that's wrong climb like five well four
to five per thread working here possibly
even six doesn't matter point being a
few times per thread it's gonna do this
crew and then that the full cast call
this is for each raycast
it's getting entered many many times
here I don't know if that's just too
much setup this is just a lot of calls
right I don't know if it's actually
doing a call if it is that's probably
bad as well and so these just need to be
done more efficiently right like we need
this whole thing to be more efficient
and at the moment it's not particularly
but basically what you can see is 90
plus percent of the time is just in that
lighting update so we know what the
problem is right
is the goal get 30 frames a second debug
no no the goal is to get 30 frames a
second in release mode are we faster
than the previous solution so it's
really not a question of faster we
didn't have a previous solution I mean
that's that's the bottom line right
because the previous way we were doing
it we had no way of lighting our sprites
at all we just didn't have it so this is
the first time we've really had a way of
lighting everything instead of just the
geometry around the world right and so
this allows us to light our sprites as
they move through the system which is
important you know it's one thing I
would like to know by the way is what
would happen now if we got rid of any
mention of the light lookup Fox will dim
[Music]
so if we went through here and stopped
doing this stuff I wonder to what extent
[Music]
this thing would work with with now
asymmetric voxels right so
hmm
so it's a little bit of work but it's
not much so we'll be able to use
asymmetric voxels - which would be
pretty handy right because one of the
things is like if we were to reduce the
number of voxels we have to deal with
that gives us a free speed win that
doesn't evolve any work right so for
example if we reduce the number of
voxels like here you can see that we
still get the lighting and it works just
fine but now it's much faster right and
so you know we can definitely do
something like that
but we just you know again we just need
to kind of know what we're doing here
right and so that's another free speed
win sort of thing we have and so if we
just reduce the number of voxels by
being placing them more accurately and
maybe reducing the number of Z slices
that gets us the 30 frames a second
without doing anything right and again
that's just because there's a lot less
of them so you know as we go forwards I
think we'll be able to do some things
but the question is just you know
can you still parameterize the voxel
size yes you can
I'm curious if decreasing the voxel size
will remove some cuban Apsara probably
other ways we can make there be less
cube miss for example by doing blending
that is more fuzzy and less by linear
for example might help that also just as
the lighting solution gets better
they'll be less of that probably fall
off as well so hard to say for what are
you still using voxels everything all
the lighting happens on voxels right now
and so also it does seem like we can
probably get rid of our light probes
which is good like I said I want to pull
that path out so we probably will get
rid of them because we don't need them
now
no good
looks like we are good off-topic do you
see rust replacing see syphilis in the
game industry in the next five to ten
years no I mean it doesn't really offer
anything interesting so it's it's a very
very very minor improvement over C C++
so I don't see why most most people
would have really no motivation to
switch they already have code bases
written in C C++ rust offers them almost
nothing so I wouldn't see that being
likely I can see something like ji
replacing C C++ because it offers a lot
but you know unlike rust like from what
I've seen rust is mostly about people
being loud and annoying and telling
people they should use it even though
there's really no reason to and
sometimes that's what makes languages
succeed so that's why C++ is here for
example it's also why Java is here and
so you know maybe just the belligerent
nature of rust developers will be
something that you know causes it to
gain more adoption but it's it's not a
particular Singh language to me it's
it's got very rudimentary improvements
over CV post less that I don't consider
them to be very important however I
could easily see a language that did
offer something and if there was such a
language available I could see that
being being really relevant right and I
don't know if that'll happen or not but
like the reason I mentioned ji because
it has real meta programming support and
I think that's a massive feature like I
really think people underestimate how
important meta programming is it's the
most important thing for a new language
rust is just a bunch of syntactic
nonsense that doesn't really do you any
good
ji has actual real ast meta programming
support like that's very good I
has correctly integrated compile-time
execution of everything and so it's the
right model right and moving something
like that would be a real improvement
you know I would seriously think about
it
and I don't know what other C C++ people
would think about it but that's a
compelling argument as to why I should
rewrite my codebase or at least port a
you know poured it over time whereas the
argument for rust is nowhere to be found
it's just a bunch of loud people saying
things that aren't actually particularly
applicable to what I do did today right
so so that's why I say it would help
yeah if people were less interested in
language nonsense and more interested in
what actually happens to your code right
and you know when I care what I care
about is like really good stuff that
will like memory safety I don't care
about like you saw what I do today for a
memory safety and it just works it takes
me like a couple hours of time for
memory safety and I'm just fine I never
have this praten issue for me right so
adding a bunch of crap to your language
for memory safety is just wasting my
time and adding complexity or language
for no reason I don't need it and I
don't care right
and in my opinion other kinds of bugs
are way more important their kinds that
you tend to see a lot more often and
that are way more difficult to diagnose
and find such as index Swizzle problems
and stuff like that rust does absolutely
nothing for you the heavy lifting work
that I have to do day to day usually has
nothing to do with memory safety it
doesn't have anything to do with memory
even it usually has a lot more to do
with things like how to notate things
concisely and as usual rust delivers you
literally nothing on that front they
decided what they think the syntactic
sugar bees should be for their language
and they just stuff it down your throat
exactly like C++ this interests me not
at all if I'm going to switch through
language it's going to be one that
allows me to create the correct
shorthand at all times for what
I am trying to do and that is what ji
does it gives me the ast I can actually
do correct metaprogramming fully
throughout my entire code base including
mixing asti's together using convenient
things that's what I want
rust doesn't offer any of this and I
have no idea why people are so excited
about it I guess they just I don't know
they're probably the same people are
excited about modern C++ it's just
people get it in their heads that the
language is the interesting thing it's
not the language of thing that enables
you to create the code and what you
should be focusing on is what kind of
new code does this let me create and in
rust the answer is none so I do not
understand why people keep telling me
about it I really just do not care about
rust even a little bit it seems like
it's targeted at people who are not me
rev ryx it actually is a language
problem Swiss Ling is 100% a language
solvable problem so one of the things I
designed a trad was a program called
mustache I've given a demo of it before
and what it is is an augmentation that
you have to manually put in C that
allows you to find all your specialty
problems trivially it like automatically
finds them basically if I had J I I
could just put that in my ast front end
and it would apply to automatically to
any part of the code that I wanted rust
can't do anything like that
they haven't even discussed that as far
as I can tell they don't even know that
these are the kinds of things you should
be doing in a programming language right
so they're just not they're not working
in the same headspace that I am like I'm
thinking about how do I solve the hard
programming problems that I hit every
day and they're thinking about how do I
protect someone from running off the end
of a buffer which is like the least
interesting thing to me are their
language features in C++ that you like
no are there other language features
than metaprogramming that you want in a
new language um not really like what I
would like is a as a programming
language where I can make my own things
in the meta programming so that it works
the way I want it to right that's mostly
what I want I just you know I'm not
interested in any of the other stuff j
ai if anything doesn't go far enough
with the meta programming like ideally
if you were to hand me language I would
want one where I can change my internal
a B eyes and stuff like that so like I'm
actually in control of function
preambles and all that sort of thing
internal to my code right yeah I mean
you know and I'm not I don't want to
bash too much on the rest I mean I do
because I really hate the way people
advocate it because they're doing
exactly the same thing that C++ people
did they're kind of trying to jam it
down people's throats by claiming
there's these benefits that aren't
actually there or aren't very
interesting right and I that really
annoys me but it's not like rust is
unique in this like that's like most
languages nowadays is a bunch of
evangelist and not like a whole lot of
sizzle and
not much actual meat right
so Rev Rex if you want me to comment on
a specific rest feature just point me at
the actual feature page and I can sort
of go through it if you want
yeah and neither EXO functional
languages like Haskell and also just
like completely generic languages like
Lisp they offer a lot of these function
these options the problem is the
language itself isn't set up to be
particularly good for programming right
like Lisp for example can do all these
things and and not only that could be
doing at run time right but it's not
really set up to get good output code
with concise input code right it doesn't
actually when you actually look at the
resulting list program a the output
tends to be actually quite poor because
you don't have control of the lower
level stuff at like you would want but
be the actual legibility of the
resulting code is really bad right
because it doesn't allow much constructs
for human readability and that's sort of
a crucial part so what you're kind of
looking for is a way to get your meta
programming language to allow you to
create constructs that are easy to read
that produce good high quality code on
the other side right but absolutely like
you can go back to Lisp which is
extremely early programming it had all
this stuff but things like C they don't
have this the power of Lisp at all and
you know you can see why because of the
trade-offs that were being made so what
you're really looking to do is to get
like the concise legibility of simple C
code right and the performance you can
get by hand tuning that code in a
language that has the kinds of features
that list does where you can manipulate
all the code very concretely in multiple
passes and all these sorts of things
right and this is a difficult language
to build that's why nobody builds it
they usually build some for things like
rust right because those are easier to
make it's much easier to make the rust
compiler than it would be to make a
compiler to do for the language that I'm
talking about so
did someone want to send them at the
rust macro page
someone wanted me to comment on the rest
mattress page but the person who asked
me to comment on them didn't actually
provide the link they wanted someone
else suggested maybe it was Doc rust
Lang dot org and the answer is if it's a
macro system then I don't want it
because I don't want macros but that's a
separate issue
I want a thing that allows me to modify
the ast which is not the same but anyway
so here's one is this the one we're
talking about or do you want to talk
about the other one
I don't know which one you want
I think it was ravaged originally ask
the question so I just waiting for them
to so are we talking about what's on
this page or because I'm not there was
it was not specific what was being asked
about right
oh if i looked at it all yes i mean i
don't program an arrest so I'm not
qualified to comment on like extreme
nitty-gritty but in order to be a proper
meta programming system what you need to
do is you need to have exactly what ji
has which is a message processing loop
or other kind of high-level iterator
that hop happens as a procedural piece
of code at compile time in your code
that can look across the entire code
bases AST and make modifications to any
of it as it wishes right and that is not
what rust has it doesn't have anything
like that right all it has is some
little like nonsense stuff where it can
like turn strings and ast Zoar that sort
of like spot stuff right and that's just
not useful right it's it's not it's it's
not the same it's not a real meta
programming environment it's a crap
programming environment right we're
gonna find mustache oh you can't its
proprietary I gave a demo of some of it
on streams you can find that but what do
you think of clang tooling to create
such a Estimate emulation tools as part
of the build pipeline I don't think it's
a good idea I mean it's not a spec it's
not a language I really wouldn't want to
lean on that right so
also compiling clangs nightmare anyway
all right I'm gonna go ahead and wrap
this up thank you everyone for joining
me for the nuff sort of a handmade hero
it has been a pleasure coding with you
as always if you would like to follow on
the series you can always pre-order the
game on here or kit comes the source
code which you can use to follow along
with at home I will be back here next
week although I don't think I posted the
schedule yet so the schedule will be on
here as soon as I post it until then
have fun programming everyone and I will
see you on the internet tickety's
everybody