uh so where I left off let's see here we
go hello everyone and welcome to
handmade Hiro sure we could a complete
game live on stream we are streaming
over YouTube today because twitch
totally rolled over and died on us and
is refusing to let us stream anything at
all so that's just where we're at
hopefully everyone can hear me okay and
see me okay if you can't I am recording
this locally so hopefully we will be
able to post it online and you can watch
it after the fact
where I left off yesterday was I just
cranked the number of things in the
scene up to the full size that will
probably in be in a rendered scene in
the actual game during gameplay so that
we could see the slowest the lighting
would get right now the lighting is
totally unoptimized and so the idea now
is just to start working on optimizing
the lighting to get it to a point where
we can run it at 60 frames a second now
I don't actually think this is going to
be that hard because we found that for a
simplified room one that we were not
actually doing the size of a real level
where there was lots of stuff in it in
this in the simulation region in that
case we actually were running just fine
with the completely unoptimized lighting
that was super crappy in terms of how it
does performance and and so that's just
a good example of how fast computers are
these days when you when you have real
absolutely simple level geometry you can
just have them like the whole thing so
we've gotten it now to a point where
it's relatively slow and so our goal is
now to start thinking about how we're
gonna get this running faster and so
really we're just looking at
streamlining this stuff and starting to
think about how it's going to be
spatially a partition that sort of thing
so let me go ahead and show you what I'm
talking about for those of you who maybe
didn't see yesterday's stream or who
have very short memories and can't
remember what happened on yesterday's
stream I'm going to go ahead and run
this here and what you can see is we get
a very very slow frame rate here because
the level is nice and big you can see up
here you know the its it's like 1.2
seconds per frame right that's what
happens when we get a whole level size
and so that's just an example of where
we are starting from
now our goal of course is to make it run
nice and smoothly there and again I
don't think that's gonna be too much of
a struggle though we'll take you know a
few steps to get there if I show let's
see here if I make it so that doesn't
quite generate as much stuff as that for
example if we just generate a single
seam a single room whatever you want to
call it then we can get we can actually
have fairly playable rates right so you
know even the completely unoptimized
version it doesn't really run in real
time it runs an interactive time though
and the lighting works with shadowing
and everything else and all that good
stuff so we're in relatively good shape
I don't think we're gonna have to
struggle too much but we do need to do a
bunch of work to get us to the point
where we'll be running at 60 frames a
second with real lighting so let's talk
about what the source of the slowness is
in this algorithm because right now
we're not we're not whenever you look at
an optimization problem right there's
different sort of slices of the
optimization that you're thinking about
and in the case that we're talking about
right now
we're really talking about algorithmic
optimization so what I mean by that is
obviously there's you know very
meticulous optimization of like what the
actual CPU and GPU are doing and talking
about the exact performance
characteristics of that and so on we're
not really at that point yet we haven't
even moved legging to the GPU we're
actually doing letting entirely on the
CPU right now and we're not even doing
it with Cindy or any of that stuff so
we're not talking about optimizing the
lighting from a processor standpoint yet
because it's a little bit premature what
we're talking about right now is just
lets architect the lighting algorithm so
that it's running in a reasonable way
that we think will give us reasonable
performance right because there's only
so much you can do to speed up the
computation of the lighting brute force
which is how we're doing it now what
we'd rather do is use some more subtlety
in the way that we compute the lighting
so that we don't have to do as much work
just in the in the abstract sense right
the actual the actual number of work
items we have to actually do to perform
the lighting we're trying to reduce that
down rather than talking about speeding
up an individual piece of work right
those are sort of the two right the two
sort of big parts oxidation so we're not
really gonna be timing stuff right now
or getting into instruction because
that's our stuff we're just at a very
broad phase where we need to just reduce
the total amount of work we're even
considering because that's already just
out in in a ridiculous place okay so let
me show you what I mean by that so if we
go into the render group here what you
can see if we look at the compute light
propagation function and I think now we
did solve this problem we I guess I
should say that the index assignment is
not quite done yet so I'm going to still
put one here that says you know we want
to make sure that we do index
reassignment properly because right now
if you started to move around the scene
we wouldn't necessarily we don't have a
way of like freeing light indices when
they're not used so we want to make sure
that we do that eventually it's not
important to do right now because we're
not moving around so we don't have to
really get inside the the light
algorithm itself it doesn't care because
the lighting indices have already been
assigned
but once we sort of finished the
lighting and say that's done we do in
the renderer need to have a little thing
that can allocate and deallocate like
blocks basically so that they are that
they correspond properly and this isn't
about memory allocation it's just about
correspondence allocation again because
rather than doing spatial correspondence
we're just doing identificar spawned
it's to keep it really smooth and clear
right so this is presumably where we're
spending all the time and why do I say
presumably because I haven't actually
measured it yet but what I can pretty
much tell you is this is our problem the
reason that I know this is our problem
is because it is way too loopy right
loopiness equals slowness basically what
happens is here we have a number of
light propagation iteration
so there's one you know if you if you
imagine the amount of work that has to
be done I'm gonna go ahead and and
switch over to Milton here really
quickly just so I can draw this out for
you
and here's day 420 so let's talk about
the lighting work here so if you look at
what we're actually talking about we
have a number of iterations so we have
to do the number of iterations and then
it's gonna do everything inside why am I
not there we go
so we have however many iterations we're
doing right then we're gonna look at
every emitter right so times the number
of emitters then we're gonna look at at
the number of rays which is the rate
count here and then for each one of
those we're gonna look at the raycast
function itself right here's the raycast
and that's gonna go over all the
surfaces and we end up with this really
big nasty equation for the amount of
work that we're gonna do right we know
that this thing is not particularly high
right I mean it could be as low as
something like four right it's it's not
a particularly high number so that's not
the end of the world necessarily but you
know you get the idea so we have a
certain number of iterations we have a
number of emitters this is going to be
huge right this is gonna be on the order
of like 32,000 or something like this
right this is a huge number potentially
you know we can get that down certainly
to a lower number but this is gonna be
huge so you know maybe this gets down to
something like 16 K or something like
that but all of you remember emitter is
just a term here talking about services
that are reflecting light off of them so
really it's every surface in the game is
in this emitter category here right then
we have some number of rays right and
the number of rays goes potentially down
with each iteration but you know this
number here is going to be something in
the range of like you know between 4 and
64 so it's again a pretty high number
and then the number of surfaces is
basically the same as
more or less there's less surfaces than
emitters because surfaces are a big sort
of occluders whereas emitters are
individual points that might be you know
receiving and sending light and so so
within in surfaces let's say you know
there's a significantly less than this
but there's still a large number like
eight thousand or something right so
when you look at how many of these
things we have you can see why this is
something that can't be run in real time
the way that it is written at the moment
right
oops I remember people gave me this
little speed crunch thing here so yeah
I'm not really very familiar with speed
crunch but it's oops it seems like a
reasonable thing to use so if we look at
what happens here let's say we do 4
times 32 okay then times I don't know
the average of that maybe let's say is
somewhere around 24 depending on how I
don't remember exactly how we break it
down but it's something like that
times 8,000 and you can see that it's
just this ridiculously massive number
here right and remember the number of
cycles per second we're going to get on
something like a CPU is you know in the
ballpark of of this right right
something like 3 gigahertz is is what
we're expecting to get in terms of
cycles it's it when you compare these
two things together it's just a really
unflattering comparison not particularly
good at all so you can see why you start
spiking up to really high numbers
because you need just a ton of
computation time for something that does
this much work even if the work is very
simple and mind you the work is very
simple these are just Rea checks it's
not doing a lot of math but it's enough
right so you can just see that these
numbers have to be pared down
substantially so if you were to imagine
how you might pair these numbers down
substantially right you've got a number
of ways that you could start to look at
reducing these first of all this is a
really easy number to start reducing
right here
and and so in some sense is this one and
so let's talk about that because the ray
count and the iteration count themselves
are very minor right we're talking about
worst case you know it's it's something
like this I mean it's actually I think
it's 64 like
32 plus 16 plus 8 it's something like
this right it's a very low low number so
the number of Ray casts were actually
doing just in terms of the iteration and
raise is extremely low it's just because
there's so many things to recast from
and so many reasons very cost to doing a
hundred and twenty raise you know
millions of times is you know 120
millions of raise you get the idea
so what we're looking at here is these
are the big numbers these are the really
big numbers that are blowing out our
system so what we're really looking at
here is forget these because these are
not that important and can be addressed
in a number of different ways these are
really not that important it's these
that are important so what we're talking
about here is reducing the emitter times
surface Oh N squared part of this
problem right because if these are both
proportional to n they're proportional
to the number of things you know it
looks like an H I apologize for that
these are both proportional to the
number of things in the game right the
number of things that are bouncing light
around and the number of things that are
stopping light from bouncing around are
both proportional to the number of
things in the game so the number of
things that we have in the game squared
is going to be this you know central
problem so as we crank that number up
right that is where we get into hot
water so the question is how do we do
something that takes this central
product and reduces it to something
that's more manageable right how do we
make it so that we can still do
something because we know the lighting
has to do this we know the lighting has
to be about all the emitters emitting to
all the surfaces so how do we do
something smart here and so the answer
is we're probably going to end up with
something that's multi-resolution right
so what we can probably say is all right
look
let's say we have a fairly detailed
thing in the scene where we've got you
know sort of all of these cubes right
around and they're all kind of bouncing
light around
in each other and they're stopping light
from coming in from the outside and
whatever obviously we need to do a full
N squared thing on these five emitters
occluders whatever they are well I mean
everything is kind of both in the game
right so we need to do something like
that so you know we might have a 5 x 5
kind of a situation here that's 25
things right but that's a totally
reasonable number of things to do and
then over here we may have a similar
thing set up right it's bouncing light
all around it right and maybe there's
six of these right so it's a 6 x 6
situation right again totally reasonable
the problem comes when these interact
with each other now right if we
aggregate everything up then we start
saying well now it's you know 11 times
11 if these all have to go into each
other and now we start to get into much
higher numbers right this is a much
higher number than just doing these two
things separately right 25 plus 36 is
much lower than 121 right and this gets
worse and worse as you go this is the Oh
n versus Oh N squared problem if we just
look at little local clusters and add
them together that's gonna scale as a
nice line if we always put them so that
they all have to compute crosswise
that's where we get this sort of nasty
spiral off into infinity kind of Oh N
squared thing right so this is our own
squared curve this is our Oh n line and
we want to try and stay on this line as
much as possible this is where 60 frames
per second lives this is where you know
I don't even I don't know this is where
a pub G server lives right it's out on
this ridiculous line where you can't
even you know you rubberband all over
the place um so this is what we want to
be we want to be on this 60 frames per
second line in order to do that we have
to break this N squared problem and so
when I say multi-resolution I'm saying
is let's look for ways that we can
cleave these things apart and say that
things that are next to each other we
will solve em squared because that's how
light transfer works but can we
basically break things into clusters
which will then just transmit light as
clusters to each other and if you
remember when I started out the lighting
thing
I was talking about doing lighting in
this way we just never actually got to a
point where that multi-resolution thing
I wasn't sure how it's gonna work
so now is the part where that finally
comes in now we can actually implement
something both a resolution because we
have an algorithm that's actually
working with full N squared and now we
just need to figure out a way to break
it into something that's based on unless
how should I put this that's based on
more of an Owen curve of breaking things
down into smaller sections now there's
again two ways you can sort of look at
this problem you can look at this
problem as Oh n versus some small number
right so we can look at it as om versus
some very small number right or we can
look at this as you know small number
versus small number and I want to talk
about the difference between these two
things because they're two different
types of algorithms so this is the
standard ray casting approach for like
offline rendering we still loop over
everything that is going to be doing say
transmission or something so we still
loop over 32,000 things for transmission
or reception whichever one we want to do
but then we employ some kind of a
spatial partition so that we only
consider a subset of the N when we
actually go to do like intersection or
something like that right so for example
let's say we have a KD tree we've talked
about these before or an octree or a
quad tree or a BSP tree right let's say
we have any kind of spatial partition so
one way of looking at this is saying
well let's loop over everything we were
going to do before so for example up
here when we wrote this giant equation
let's say that all of this is going to
be exactly the same as it was and then
the only thing we're going to do is
employ a spatial partition here one of
those tree types here so
that surfaces instead of being o n is
like o log N or something right so this
is our small number so it's saying take
all of this leave them as large numbers
knock one down to a small number but
this this guy is still o n right that's
one way to do it that way will be slower
but potentially more accurate maybe it's
still operating on everything right that
way will be more accurate but slower
than something that is not actually
accelerating the exact equation right Oh
looks like steam is still running on my
machine how do I exit good there we go
sorry about that
little steam toasts there everywhere uh
so basically what I'm trying to say here
is if you take a look at how that was
working we're taking one part of the of
the giant multiplication expression and
we're simplifying that one down to be a
small number but everything else is
working exactly the way it was so we're
really just accelerating one search part
one part that was saying what did I
intersect we're accelerating just that
one part right but another way of
looking at it is again sort of the
multi-resolution or approach is not that
the multi-resolution approach says let's
simplify things down so that rather than
ever working on the whole problem
exactly as it was we're just gonna work
on clusters that sort of smush down into
approximations for areas and so that was
sort of what I was interested in
exploring now in terms of how we
accelerate things and what that means is
exactly what I was drawing before when
we have sort of that that example that I
was saying oh you've got these people
are transmitting light right well the
way that the tree based sort of
accelerate just one half of the problem
works is when we go to transmit light
say from here to here what we're doing
is we're saying well we binary space
partition to this or something in some
way that cleaves up the space so that
really we just do in
of having to check against all six well
not just all six but all eleven of the
things here we're only gonna check do
like a couple plane tests so like three
tests and then we know that we only
really have to check this guy or
something right so again that's using
we're doing exactly all the same work as
we were doing before but we're just
knocking down the number of things we
consider when we go to do our expensive
tests right
the multi-resolution approach is
different it knocks everything down to
small numbers the way that works it says
let's identify clusters that will
transmit light amongst themselves and
have some idea of how the light
transmits out from them and then this
whole segment gets reduced to just its
cluster right so now this thing is just
a single it's one emitter you know
occluder for all five same with this one
so that by the time we do transfer
between these two things we're talking
about a one-to-one transfer right and
this is I talked about this as a multi
grid right approach to lighting and what
that means is it's saying okay let's
just say there's a very you know we have
a very granular 32 thousand things or
whatever at the bottom we're simply not
going to do light transmission between
32,000 things we don't even want to
consider that as an option instead what
we're going to do is we're going to
bounce light around clusters of these
things that then collapse in on
themselves into sort of smaller and
smaller groups those groups then
transfer light between each other and
propagate back down to the lower levels
right so I don't know these are two ways
of approaching the problem one benefit
of the one benefit of the one that is
not multi-resolution that's basically
just saying hey let's go ahead and and
just use acceleration for the query is
you don't have to worry about how those
cluster boundaries affect things the
strictly multi-resolution approach which
is an up it or
and then down like n up iterations and
end down iterations is that it's
perfectly login all the time it always
is looking at that subdividing thing sub
something like how do I say it like sub
collapsing right it's it's it's reducing
the numbers up up up up up does that
some things and then it goes back down
the problem with it of course is that
you have to figure out what you do at
these cluster boundaries to not see
seams or things like this and so one
potential way that we could mix these
two approaches together is to you know
sort of take a page from the thing that
we were experimenting with early on as
well where where we actually do still
loop over every receptor surface but
when we look at where it's getting its
light from we do that in a multi
resolution fashion so we just look at
things that are far you know we we sort
of have some entirely grouped version
some tree that talks about grouped
occluders emitters and we just go
through that that sort of grouped
version and we subdivide it down to as
detailed as we need to in terms of
things that should be considered so the
way to think about that is that we have
some multi resolution version of this
thing where okay let's say that here's
all of the things we have in the scene
and we start the lighting algorithm by
just collapsing everything up into a
tree so these things form a tree where
there's a root node right that
encompasses everything in here
it split into some number of child nodes
right those are split into some number
of child nodes blah blah blah right and
then eventually you get down and the
Leafs are individual ones of these right
so we just have an entire tree when we
go to compute a lighting transfer for
any given one of these what we do is we
use the leaf nodes for the things that
are close to it so these things let's
say here are all involved in direct
computations but then anything that's
further away that doesn't need to be
split say this cluster here this cluster
here
this cluster here maybe that's clustered
right just transmit light as a group you
know they transmit in block oral light
as a group and you know I don't know is
it is it the right way to do it I am Not
sure it's just a thought right and so
the way that that I'm thinking about
that is to just say okay for any given
lighting computation we just have a tree
walk that goes downward that's something
we can implement in a shader assuming
the tree has been built ahead of time
building the tree in a shader might not
work but that's okay we could build the
tree on the CPU so so basically the CPU
builds the tree and sends it down a
computer shader could build the tree
just fine but I don't know that we want
to go into that territory because
sometimes you're you know
better off keeping things simple enough
that you don't require compute shaders
so anyway that's the sort of thing that
I'm thinking about is just could be
maybe multiple multi Reza
just one side now on the other side so
we're still not doing the thing where
we're doing you know technically Oh N
squared but we're breaking one half of
the Oh N squared by using a spatial
partition instead we're doing o n versus
some sort of multi resolution thing
where we don't even we're not even doing
spatial partitioning to figure out what
we hit in a faster fashion we're
literally testing against things that
are multi resolution as you go further
out so that's my you know that's my sort
of rough feeling on that and you know in
order to do this I think because our
world is kind of cube like I feel like
one thing we could do is just do all of
this on cubes so we could say that every
lighting element is really just a cube
and you know we just sort of coalesce
these cubes together and off we go so we
would have sort of a the way this would
look look is we'd have a giant like mama
cube you know which would be sort of the
the cube that contains all cubes then
inside there we have you know some
smaller cubes and inside those cubes we
have smaller cubes yet until eventually
we have the level geometry right and the
way that we would build this is probably
doing some kind of thing where we take
closest you know
the beginning we sort of take a spatial
partition and dump things in and find
the closest cubes we collapse those
cubes together up and up and up and up
and to end we may be group you know four
cubes at a time or something like this I
don't know so we can do something like
that where we just kind of group these
things together based on their proximity
and hey our world storage already stores
things based on proximity so in theory
if we played our cards right we could
even keep that flowing through the whole
pipeline and not have to do a lot of
work to create the sort of higher higher
order work there in the first place
that might be good as well so I feel
like we're you know that's based on the
fact that our world is supposed to be
kind of QB anyway it seems like that's
the case now when I say cube I don't
really mean cube I really mean right
rectangular prism obviously like it's
something that has a width a height and
a depth these are not all the same it's
not with cubed right so it's not really
a cube it's actually a right rectangular
prism but you know what I mean so that
is and I and I mortally mean an axis
aligned right rectangular prism often
called an access aligned bounding box
for it a ABB uh so I think you know
that's a relatively reasonable way we
could start to approach things and again
it's hard to know ahead of time whether
it's intelligent or not sometimes you
have to just explore but that's I think
what I would like to go down and the
steps to this would be basically like
Cuba five the lighting so basically
right now we're actually talking about
services as being individual plates I
think maybe we switched to cubes because
that way we can just talk about a whole
cube at a time and we know that
everything is always a cube or right
rectangle prison or a a B Cuba Phi the
lighting build cube tree and then you
know update lighting with the tree and
so it's actually three fairly simple
steps
I think honestly this is the only hard
one right the rest is just busy work but
building a tree of spatially coherent
lighting elements is actually something
that is a little bit touchy right like
that's yeah you know so you know this is
something that we can that we can do and
I think this bottom step here you know
the update lighting with tree
I summon ulti there right like so if you
think about what has to happen there if
we imagine that we're talking about the
concept that this thing is an emitter
then it's kind of it's it's gonna be a
little bit subtle to say well if I've
got a bunch of cubes and I want to talk
about an enclosing cube knowing how much
light hits like exits here right is
relatively difficult I say relatively
difficult because it's not that
difficult it's just relative to the rest
of stuff for doing but honestly I think
all it is is just saying all right when
we do light transport do light transport
amongst the things in the set and have a
bound around the set such that when you
hit that bound you add lighting to the
boundary element right so that these
boundary elements gain their lighting
from things that would have exited the
volume right we store those up and so
then we just have two light passes we
have the emission phase where things are
transmitting light amongst themselves
here and any light errant light that
would go out hits the boundary element
hits the bound and gets stored there
then when we do light transfer between
the larger elements they just transfer
light among those bounds just like they
were in
here and they've got a large amount as
well right then when we come down to
propagate the things that come in we
just have that inbound lighting now what
we could do as well is stagger that by
one frame so on every frame we just do
an up lighting pass that's all we do and
during the up lighting pass wheats are
emitting from these surfaces as well
right in skew surfaces or interior
surfaces and I think that's a reasonable
I think that's a reasonable approach
right I mean I can't see I can't see
much peculiar about that right whether
it works in whether it's great or not I
don't know again you know when you're
talking about sort of exploring novel
routines you kind of have to wing it a
little bit and just go with some
experiments the whole lighting so far
has been experiments and it's gotten us
to a pretty good place and so now we're
just talking about some experiments to
figure out how we get the performance up
to where we want it to be and so I guess
that's yeah I guess that all sounds
plausible enough to me that I think I'd
be ready to pull the trigger on that I'm
just kind of ruminating it in my head a
little bit and trying to think if
there's anything that I'm forgetting
there in terms of things that are why
you obviously shouldn't start down this
path but I'm not really coming up with
much
so I will see one thing that is kind of
difficult about it that I think is a
little bit tricky is that in the case of
our world we're talking about there's
like things like lots of little cubes
that make up the ground or something
right and so what's gonna happen if you
imagine you take a look at these systems
as they are when you imagine breaking
these into chunks you're gonna get
something where you've got one bounding
cube like so and one bounding cube like
so and these are tight right so you've
got cubes that are like this next to
each other talking about light transfer
and then you've got an additional
version of that right in other words all
of these cubes are tight together if
they were broken up in this way those
two are also tight together meaning
their faces are coincident I think
that's gonna make it relatively
difficult to that's gonna make it
relatively difficult to do the light
transfer if these were sort of cubes
that were floating in space you could be
a lot sloppier with how this was working
because you don't have a budding phases
of you're sort of multi-resolution
groups but here we do have a budding
phases and I think that that's going to
make the letting transfer more difficult
because when you're talking about two
phases that are right coincident with
each other figuring out how the light
transfers between them is relatively
difficult you have to start being
precise with how you are treating values
in the system because simple ray casting
is not going to work if you talk about
two surfaces that are directly on top of
each other right one pointing this way
one pointing that way figuring out that
the light that leaves this surface is
100% going to go into this surface
basically is a lot more difficult than
having surfaces that are separated from
each other and again it's because the
raycast itself now is numerically
finicky because you're talking about
coincident points that are exactly on
planes transmitting to those planes you
have no room for error anymore and so
one of the things that we might have to
do is sort of special you know treat
these value especially we did say that
they're going to be access aligned that
gives us an advantage the advantage that
it gives us is we know that things are
going to line up exactly they're not you
know if you're talking about two planes
that look like this that are right on
top of each other they're not going to
line up exactly once you reduce them to
floating point you know they could look
a little bit more like this where
they're slight even though they're
supposed to be exact they're sort of
tilted with a with axis aligned stuff we
know that the value of x here will be
exact on both so we can't actually check
for equivalence if we want to when we're
building these things we could in theory
make that work you probably don't want
to but you know I'm just saying we we
have some advantages that there's got to
be a little bit more numerically
feasible to work with because they are
axis to line then if they weren't access
aligned for when we do our transmission
in that case so yeah just trying to
think that through is there any is that
how problematic is that going to be I'm
thinking about in my head I'm thinking
about the case for the floor so again we
kind of have these grounds that we want
to be to look sort of cube ish and they
kind of look like you know if this is a
floating piece you know there's another
piece next to it like this and so on and
I'm just thinking so there's some
unevenness there and so you're gonna get
situations where you're looking at the
side one of these larger cube transfer
elements and it's actually got the
elements inside it kind of look like
this let's say on the other side so when
you're asking about transmission between
these two I
think we solve again that problem by
just having points scattered on that
surface each time we kind of go up so
you kind of know whether the
transmission is happening more at the
top or more at the bottom so I think the
like cubes with points scattered on them
approach is actually relatively stable
the whole way up and hopefully we'll
just kind of work again we just have to
make sure that we're really careful
about allowing points that are right on
the boundary to transmit properly and I
think that's all I have to say about it
how much time we got here I don't even
because of that whole you having to
switch to YouTube because twitch
exploded disaster I don't even know when
we started this thing can't just does
that doesn't the does in Saibot on there
tell us how long how far we into the
episode we are 38 minutes into the
mainstream okay so we've got an hour and
20 minutes left or something like that
at least an hour anyway
so we should be able to sort of take
some first steps here and I think the
thing that we would want to do here
probably is just again switch to cube
based lighting for this stuff and that
way we can start right because we've
we've we've already got ourselves at a
more granular thing that we're doing
which is actually just a plate based
lighting we could stick with place based
lighting but we would probably be
somewhat wasteful there because rather
than doing things in terms of plates we
can just switch to doing things as a a B
B's and one of the nice things about a a
B's is it's faster to check for
intersection on them anyway and that
would allow us to get a speed increase
on that part of the problem as well one
of the nice things about a a B B's again
is if you and really not save use any
bounding box if it's a right rectangular
prism one of the nice things about it is
that when you go to do a collision with
array right because that's what we're
trying to do here
doing coaching with array you actually
can just take the min and Max of these
things to figure out where the Ray is
probably going to hit you it's actually
not that hard right because you can
figure out what the closest point is
going to be on here you can figure out
whether you're inside or outside of it
right so it you can usually do some some
pretty good stuff in terms of figuring
out where where you're going to
intersect one of these things if it's
array for example we can immediately
discount all of the back faces right
just by knowing by classifying which
side the you know which direction the
Ray is pointing right so if the you know
if the Ray just and if it's an accent
line batas it's it's so simple to figure
that out because the sine of these
values relative to the center of this
thing is gonna tell us which side it's
on right if it's got a negative X
relative to where we are then we know
that you know this this face is not
gonna hit it's got to be the negative x
facing face that we would check and so
we can immediately just using like the
sine of the elements after a simple
subtract we could do a lot of nice stuff
we don't have to do dot products to
figure out which of the faces is in the
mix we can literally just use the sine
of the values to see which faces we're
even testing against and then test
against the faces is even simpler
because the faces themselves only really
have one parameter in the mix right
because you know that they're always
going to be aligned to one of the
primary axes so again that simplifies
that intersection equation down as well
and changes it to just a simple like
range comparison you know once you do
you do the 1 divide to figure out where
you would end up on the face and then
you can do the range comparison so we
have a lot of options of simplifying
down how we test these things and so I
think that that might be a good
operation as well because since we know
that so many of our things do look that
way you know just looking at the world
let me go in head and turn the lighting
off here so we can just inspect it a
little bit but you know looking at the
world here assuming that again we change
all of these trees to computing their
lighting based on a cube which is what
we said we wanted to
anyway everything here is just gonna fit
slap nicely into that concept right so I
think that's pretty pretty reasonable
and I think that is what I'd like to go
with so let's go ahead and just modify
today well our goal will be to modify
the lighting to be working on a a B B's
and then the next thing that we'll do is
ease take that a b b lighting and the
next time we do hamid here our sessions
we will try to build trees based on that
that sort of work in a multi resolution
fashion and then finally our final step
of algorithmic optimization would be to
make those trees make the lighting work
using those trees i so ok if we assume
that that's how we're gonna do things
then when we go ahead the first thing
we're gonna have to do here is when we
actually push cubes on we're gonna have
to push lighting cubes on as a specific
thing so letting cubes are gonna have to
actually be specified directly and i'm
fine with taking that step now so again
I want to take baby steps it's a
complicated system I don't want to
change too many things at once just
little tiny steps pick the simplest
thing we can do and work towards the the
change we want to make so that we don't
rip everything apart and end up with a
huge debugging nightmare on our hands
right so if we take a look at what we're
actually communicating to the render
side of things in here we've got sort of
our our lighting surface lighting point
textured vertex stuff right so what we
want to do here is say all right when we
send down lighting things instead of
sending down lighting services right
which are currently the thing that we're
talking about lighting points will still
be what we're talking about certainly
but instead of lighting services now
what we're going to talk about is
something different we're gonna be
talking about lighting boxes basically
right so instead of lighting surface
we're gonna call this the lighting box
it's gonna have a position but it's not
going to have
a normal in fact it's not even gonna
really have a position it's probably
going to have more of a min/max right so
we've got a minimum quart minimum corner
of lemon backs maximum corner of it and
it's just axis aligned so it doesn't get
an x axis or y axis or any of that stuff
that's gone it's just min and Max and
that's all it doesn't have a width and
height in that way because the min and
Max will completely specify it and as
far as transparency is concerned I don't
know whether we want to preserve that or
not that's gonna be kind of a whole
nother question about whether light can
pass through these things or not pass
through these things I think we maybe
want to keep that in there just
nominally as a thing we might want to do
because if we put in a little mist
lighting thing I don't know I you know
we we may want to play with this in the
future for right now we can kind of
ignore it as we have been and just leave
it in there as as sort of a nominal
thing so now we have these lighting
boxes we don't have lighting services
yet and so we have to kind of forgot to
change that name there we don't have
lighting services anymore we just have
lighting boxes so now we should get as
compiler errors everywhere that people
were dealing with these things as a
single surface and our job is to go
through these and basically change them
to work as boxes now we know that our
lighting surface count has to be a lot
less than our point count but we're not
going to deal with that quite yet cuz
again we're gonna make another step
later where we talk about those things
directly and so here we go
when we look at our quads here one of
the problems that we're gonna have is
when we do extract reflectors from quads
that's not really sufficient anymore
because the quads won't tell us the
information we need about these things
specifically so we're gonna have to
change over finally to actually pushing
these things down for reals in the
renderer because we've kind of been
avoiding that step every step of the way
and one thing we could do first is is
actually I suppose we could change it in
fact maybe maybe this is even even
smaller step maybe I say all right look
let's leave these
as they were temporarily right and say
well what we want to do is move to this
soon but let's leave the lighting
surfaces as a thing for now and what
we'll do is change it so that we're
actually pushing these things on so
instead of this sort of janky routine
here that we were using to sort of port
our old stuff into a thing that has
lighting let's actually go and do the
actual lighting push right and so what
that would be here is on the I ended up
in the wrong file on the actual platform
stuff that gets passed to the renderer
we're now gonna really pass down lights
as a thing right and so the way we're
going to do that is we're gonna pass
down when we're pushing things on we're
gonna pass down I guess a u-32 that
would tell us here what our surface
count is and we're gonna pass down a
array of surfaces here and those are
just gonna stack up just like they did
before so if we search for where we do
that quad bitmap push right you can kind
of see right here where we initialize
our default render setup we need to
provide memory to store these letting
services right so we need to put a thing
in here that says the surface is what I
actually call this
oh hey it's even right there we need to
pass down memory for that that gets
allocated for use by the renderer like
so so now whenever there's a default
rendered commands call whoever is
setting that up is responsible for also
setting this up what you can see is
there some win32 allocate memory stuff
going on here
again we can just sort of do the same
thing and here we'll just say like use
that light data width so you know that's
the maximum we can have at the moment
and later again we'll probably change
this stuff to be a little once we finish
this up we'll probably save it to
something reasonable and you can notice
it's marked as non restored because if
you use the like playback and recordings
features we don't care about this it's
transient so that's about it and that
will that will give us what we need
right yeah hold on one second here I
want to make sure I'm calling this
correctly yeah all right I so now those
lighting surfaces can get passed it can
be sort of pushed on directly and we
don't have any we don't have any letting
points yet so I think probably while
we're at it we want to push the lighting
points on directly to so if you come
down and look at what we were doing
right we were computing these letting
points by just arbitrarily pushing them
on here I think while we're at it we
want to move both things over because we
wanted both things to be pushed there so
I think we also want to say light points
because light points like so so we kind
of want to say all right we've got
lighting points oops
a lot of spurious caps-lock pushing
problems so something like this and then
again the win32 stuff will have to do
the same thing I don't know why we're
quite doing it this way I don't know why
we don't just say arrow base after it I
couldn't really tell you because we
don't actually use these anywhere do we
oops yeah we don't so you don't really
need to do this you know you can just do
this right so I don't really know why I
was doing it before that way but I don't
know I was so maybe the better way to
indent that it's like this so it can be
a little more legible but that's it
and so here if I want to do lighting
points again the same thing and also
this should just be whole lighting
surfaces and whole any points so that's
the correct size of the things and we're
going to do that many of them for now
that memory gets allocated and then
passed down and then you can just sort
of fill it up so this gets us out of the
of the problem where we were having to
store these separately and generate them
every frame or whatever where now
they'll just get pushed directly off the
renderer so this will get generated
every frame will get generated directly
where they were supposed to get
generated instead of the sort of port
thing that we were doing before
all right
so in order to update this to this new
routine to work the way the old routine
was working what we want to do is
basically get rid of the extract
reflectors from quads function more or
less we want to pretty much eliminate it
right so what we want to do there is we
want to say okay let's start eliminating
the things that that does slowly but
surely in order to do that what we want
to do is go into the renderer and when
it's pushing lighting on which it knows
that it is because you know we've got
sort of our lighting enabled stuff
happening here as you can see
hey there we're entering a second error
so we have another hour to go which is
which is nice
thank you in savate for basically
telling us the exact right thing I so
anyway let me go ahead and do a push
cube or things like that if the lighting
is enabled we know that we're gonna push
on lighting information as well and so
in order to do that what I want to do
here is is actually push things on
coherently that that you know makes
sense and we don't really have this
lighting structure worked out exactly
the way we want it probably yet but it's
pretty close right the thing that's a
little bit weird about is the is the
cross-indexing which is a little weird
so you can see you've got like a
lighting surface here and then you've
got a lighting point and the lighting
point kind of talks back to about which
its lighting surfaces and so I don't
really know how those really want to I I
don't really know exactly how we want to
treat those because I it would be nice
if everything just correspondent
directly the problem is that in order to
correspond them directly we couldn't
more highly sample some surfaces than
others and we also do have a problem of
sharing lights points between surfaces
and I'm not sure exactly how we're going
to do that but we're gonna want to do
that and
so I think what we're going to have to
do at least my guess is is that this is
going to have to be a general index back
to any lighting surface potentially and
potentially tube lighting surfaces I
don't know it's it's going to be a
problem let me just put it to you that
way
we're going to have to do something with
lighting points and services that allow
them to be correspondent in a flexible
way it may require essentially a linking
table kind of approach where we we put
pairs of indices lighting points surface
and you can have any number of those
pairs that you want we may have to do
something crazy there right now we don't
have to because we're not doing the
thing where we put points on the borders
that share behavior between the two or
anything like that but we may get to the
point where we're doing things that are
somewhat complicated there so there's a
couple different ways we can do it and
I'm not sure exactly how we're going to
but one way that we could do it in the
future and in fact now I'm saying it's
probably a good idea is just to link
light points together so if we have two
points that want to become the same what
we'll do is we'll have a separate pass
that happens afterwards that just
averages those together so something
like that where we're basically saying
and and just I'm sorry to be throwing so
many things at you here I realize it's a
lot to take in but you know lighting is
complicated it's one of the hardest
things you can possibly do in graphics
full-stop so what I'm saying is we
talked before about how I will
eventually want to get rid of this this
scene here and there's pretty pretty
easy ways to do it what I was talking
about is you want to share lighting
information across that boundary in
order to do that right we need points
that will say Oh interpolate the
lighting along here is the same on
either side of it so we need to put the
terpil Asian points there that know that
the lighting should be equivalent but
remember we want these lighting points
to be associated with services so that
when we hit surfaces we know to
distribute light to the points we can't
have lighting points that are that are
shared between services without more
complicated linking but what we can do
instead is just say or
let's just put points duplicated that
are just close to each other and we'll
just say after you're completely done
average those two together and update
the the light with that information
right so there's like a post pass like a
convolution on the lighting that happens
to smooth it out along boundaries that
should not have seams and so that's I
think probably where I'd go with that
sometimes you want to duplicate effort
to avoid complicated linkage and I think
this is gonna be one of those situations
right so that convolution process I
think would give us a lot of nice
opportunity to smooth out the lighting
in places where we know we're never
gonna sample it high enough to not have
a least a subtle seam in it right so
that's I think where we're gonna go with
that as I'm saying it out loud I'm
really liking the sound of it so I think
that's probably where I have to go with
that so let's come in here and now let's
let's work on getting these lighting
services pushed properly here so what I
want to do is I want to push a these on
in the same way that we're pushing on
the existing ones we've got basically
all the information that we need to do
so because we're gonna push on the cloth
the cubes the the quadrilaterals on the
faces of a cube so we know we can first
push the lighting services that are
exactly those right so what I can do
here is sort of say like okay I've got a
lighting surface and maybe I'll just
call it surface here and that's going to
be equal to something we'll figure out
where that goes in a second and then
what I'm gonna say is like okay surface
zero or rather just surface blah blah
blah surface blah blah blah right and
then I will plus plus surface and I'll
just do this for the six faces that I
want to have there and then I'll be done
so what I'll do is say all right the
point here I have to figure out what
that point is we already did the work of
figuring out what that that surface
point is and the other one but we can
probably do something simpler here
because with this cube we're getting
exactly information we need right so you
can see here
we're getting all of this information we
know what the normals are we've already
said what they are in a lot of cases we
know what the points are Bob you know
etc etc so we kind of know all the
information that we need here we don't
even really need to do arithmetic on
these probably to get back the
information we want like we're having to
construct them before because we
actually know that the real cube now we
can just push the the services on
directly right so we know we need a P
and an N the surface the transparency I
don't know how we were doing it for them
I'm just set that to zero for now
because we don't care what it is we need
the width and the height of that surface
we need the x-axis and the Y's and you
can see how much information is getting
push on here it's way too much which is
why switching to a a B these gonna be
great here we're gonna simplify all this
stuff and just really get it down to a
much more straightforward thing we can
use for letting transfer that's gonna be
really nice I think in and of itself
that just that will actually speed us up
probably maybe not 8x but something like
an 8x speed increased probably just from
stopping proliferating cubes into their
faces for no reason right all right
so if we take a look at the surface
points here what we want to do is say
okay when we created these we said
alright the the NX P X n YP y + Z PZ
that's the negative maximum X positive
maximum X negative maximum Y positive
maximum Y and so on right so this cube
is always access aligned in this case
already so we don't really even have to
think about it harder than that and we
already have them in Max's that we need
here so what we can do is just start
talking about the center point but the
center point we have it's just px py P
at Z whatever so when we're trying to
produce say one of these services all
we're really saying is oh let's take
like the negative x negative Y negative
Z that would be the corner the most
negative corner point right let me I'm
sorry this is probably something where
you would like a diagram to understand
it better so we have a cube its axis
aligned here are the axis of the cube X
Y Z right all at right angles and if you
think about what we're talking about
here negative x negative Y negative Z
it's this corner down here right what we
might want to do is say well let's
produce this point right so all we have
to do is say well that point is going to
be the center point of the cube with
just its Y value change to negative
right so if we were instead to say start
at the center point and just take the
negative Y right it's hard to type of
the pen in your hand or the negative x
or the positive x that gives us the
center points of each of the phases
right so we can trivially arrive at all
six of these just by taking the positive
and negative faces that's all we need to
do
oops and again you can see how many
things are pushing on for a cube it's
just a ton of work so we'll get to see
all of this collapse to a much simpler
thing when we switch to the abbs so
that's going to be very satisfying I
think all right so as we push these
services on here we have to pick one of
these to do so I'm just going to suit
like negative x first then positive x
negative Y first then positive Y
negative Z first then positive Z and now
we have each of the center points of all
of our faces now the other thing that we
know is generating the normal is
actually extremely easy because the
normal is always going to look like an
axis aligned normal right so we just
have to know which one of these were
doing well if we flip back to the
diagram what you can see is that
whatever the thing is so here was the y
axis I replaced the y coordinate of the
center with the negative Y well then the
normal is just a long y- so whichever
one I put in there is the one I do if I
put negative x in there right if I put
positive x in there if I put negative Y
in there if I put positive Y in there
negative Z
positive Z so hopefully that's all very
clear like it's it's hopefully you can
see all of the things that are going on
in that geometrically are very simple
and very straightforward and it just
allows us to generate it without doing
any arithmetic like we're doing before
it's just rote it's just it's like a
tableau you can just read it directly
off now the width and height are a
little bit more finicky again we can
read them directly off but we have to
make sure we're reading the right thing
off now fortunately for us we actually
only have two values radius and height
so that makes things a little bit easier
but we're gonna have to adjust the Z
values here because we did a little bit
of a weird thing when we were specifying
these cubes where we specify that the
top point I don't know why we decided do
this way cuz just I think cuz we
thinking ground based I really kind of
wish we didn't do this I don't know that
I want to change it right now but I kind
of want to change it right now like it's
it's I think this is it's whatever it is
what it is
um so we're gonna have to go modify
those Z's later but I'm just gonna do
everything uniform and then we're just
gonna touch up the Z when we're when
we're done with it right because
actually the negative Z you can see it's
still I think it's correct what we wrote
but you can see that these two values
are a little bit different so you know
you have to think about them a little
bit differently when when we get to them
that's all so width and Heights are
gonna be a little more finicky x-axis
y-axis are going to be not so finicky
right so let's just go ahead and and
look at those first so when we're
talking about positive X which is going
in this direction here so for positive x
we know that our x-axis right is this
way and our y-axis is this way so we
know that for positive x the x axis is
actually the y axis and the y axis is
actually the z axis
right that makes sense
oops
right so z-axis is that is going along
our Y and and our x axis is going I'm
sorry X that's going or why our waxes is
going along our Z right world Z that's
going in there um on the other hand in
the back version here at the back
versions cube where we were talking
about negative x right OOP and you know
what I just put that in the wrong place
yeah so we're talking about the negative
x axis the y axis is still going to be z
right it's still gonna be facing up but
this time instead of pointing this way
it's gonna be pointing this way
right so it's actually gonna be negative
Y axis for our X and that's just because
we're on the back face of the cube right
so we've rotated around and we want to
still keep the winding to uniform right
so there we go
alright now let's talk about the Y ones
so on negative Y you can see again Z is
still our y axis and our x axis is
actually our x axis right so on the
negative Y front we have an x axis that
is the x axis and we have a y axis that
is the z axis when we go the positive
round we're rotating around here our you
know our Z is the same I mean our wax
this is still the z axis our x axis
going back to the other direction and
then finally we get down to our Z's for
our z- right you have to imagine looking
at the cube from the back or well I mean
I guess we could do it the other way
around if we start with our positive z
axis right and we're looking down at
this
there's our you know would be one way of
doing it it doesn't really matter which
way we can always pick as long as these
axis are stable it's fine so if we take
a look at how we're doing this here
negative x axis
it's going that way positive y-axis is
going this way
so negative access sry native x-axis is
our Y positive z-axis
it's our X and if you imagine that
rotating around again this this axis
doesn't change so the positive Y axis is
still X right as we rotate this around
you can imagine the x axis is still
going and positive Y but this is it's
different now so instead of the x axis
being positive I'm sorry in any of this
case it becomes positive so there you go
now we filled out all of the things that
were pushing on there finally we have to
do the rest of this stuff so what you
can see here is our light count in this
case is always for our light indices in
this case you can kind of see we started
with it here it's just going to be light
index and we'll just update that as we
go
and that will just become like so now
one of the problems that is this again
has to kind of be placed down in here
correctly we can worry about that in a
second I suppose what we really want to
do here is maybe have these services
still be coherent but we'll we'll deal
with that again in one second let's just
finish the width height stuff instead
all right so we got to look at the width
and height here of these things so we're
now talking about the negative
x-direction right so the negative
x-direction is the thing that points out
this way
and so what we said is that our negative
x is axis is negative x-axis is I'm
sorry negative y-axis is our X right and
so that was what we were talking about
we were talking about
I say negative y-axis yeah negative
y-axis is our x axis and Z is our or y
axis right so width and height have to
be measured along these so our width is
going to be our y ry with right and
we've said that that's the radius of
this thing right since it's the width we
need to multiply it by 2 I believe
because radius is you know goes in both
directions and so really all we have to
look at is what are the two we're doing
here and so the on for Z we are using
height instead which is a total so
height is actually just type in this
case now the same thing is going to be
true here since we're not changing that
interpretation at all it's going to be
the same in both cases right we then
ever are ones for negative and positive
Y so negative and positive Y are going
these ways so again our X is our radius
but our Y in this case is going to be a
height based thing so I think we've
still got the exact same concept going
on here
but our Z on the other hand takes that
out of the equation so for our Z it's
always gonna be radius no matter which
side it's on so it's always to point our
F times radius in this case and then
what we need to do is we need to make
sure that these services that we've
pushed on correspond to the light in the
the light points that we push on as well
right we want we need to push on
individual points that are kind of on
these things and so if we go back and
look at the you know I wonder if I kind
of was just wasting everyone's time
there by doing that too because the
other thing I think units can't we just
copy the routine that we were doing over
here like could we just copy this thing
shouldn't I have just put this thing
directly in there in fact why did I just
waste everyone's time by doing that well
I don't know why I wasted your time
doing that I'll be honest don't have a
lot of explanation for it but what I
will do is I won't waste your time any
further what I will do is I'll say all
right let's grab this chunky monkey out
of here and and put that in so once we
have the surfaces we can generate the
points right so once we have the
services will generate the points from
the services just by using the the sub
counts here so we'll go through and
generate them this way we'll iterate
over the letting points that we're gonna
push in here and we have to reset our
lighting index variable for that so when
we go through here right we're gonna
want to
reset this back then we're going to want
to push these on we're gonna push these
on exactly the same way as we were
before and so we need to now have for
our letting points we need to have some
sort of a idea of what's going on here
inside the platform layer when we push
these letting points on we do P P R FCN
and surface index so we need you know
these guys here
we don't initialize these because these
are not part of it yet so we'll let
those get handled a little bit further
down although I guess ostensibly we
should move this into here eventually in
some way I mean in fact I could just do
that in this pass as well
yeah I guess I could just do that in
this pass as well all right well that's
fine let's go whole log so in the
lighting solution some world mode here
we've got sort of the informational
stuff we were doing before where we've
got emit c0 and emit c1 and average
direction to light those things get
initialized in certain ways the average
direction to average direction to light
and c1 are used in the computations and
held although average direction to light
gets reset here which is wrong
so we had a bug in here that we didn't
address average direction to light is
supposed to be held over correct yeah
that was a bug
we were probably getting better lighting
results than we thought we were getting
because we had a bug here mm-hmm I say
hold on one second
I want to test something
so this is what we were running before
and you know what let me generate a
small world so we can run the lighting
in interactive time as well
so here is the old version and here
let's see these are cleared normally
right I think so let's just see what
happens if we don't clear that value
because I thought weren't wheeler ping
those so how was that working let's
maybe amer I must be wrong because I
thought we were blending those values
over time but what are we blending them
with
okay so we do have lat never mind I was
I was a little nervous there that we
were clearing the wrong thing so that's
okay because we do have it's stored in a
separate one so it's all fine
yeah and we just lurk between those two
so that's fine okay okay I got very
nervous there for a second
but we're all good I was like it should
have been super flickery and weird like
and wrong not flickery but it should
have been really wrong and dark if we
were doing that so I was like really
confused I wanted to make sure I wasn't
totally crazy
but I'm not so anyway uh going back here
so if I jump back to the render group
where we're pushing these lights on
[Music]
there we go
so if I push all these services on and
then I want to push these points on
average direction to light is just a
temporary rendering buffer so it doesn't
need to get cleared here because it can
get cleared anywhere right it can get
cleared back in the other routine or
whatever so that one's not a big deal
but the emission is actually an
important part of the light information
which needs to get sent down on the
frame because it's the new emission
that's being said you know this is the
emission that we're actually sending
down so we do want that to be stored in
the render information as well and so
I'm just going to put that at least
temporarily into the the stuff that we
passed down I'm gonna bake that in to
the lighting point and the reason I'm
gonna bake that into the lighting point
is because I think we're gonna use
buffers for iterating over these and so
I think there'll be a source buffer from
the lending points we'll do a pass first
that well I don't know since I don't
know I'll just leave it separate I I'm
getting ahead of myself here so we emit
c0 we'll go here with lighting points
and it'll have as many in it as this
does and so what we'll do here is again
say that whatever the whatever the emit
c0 is for this particular light index is
going to be the max mission times
whatever the emission is for this value
which should be just a value right here
we
have to get out of a vertex or anything
because we could just use it directly so
we'll put the emission in there and then
we'll continue on right all right so
we're getting closer but we still have a
few things to deal with here so we have
to figure out which order we need to
push the service in to line up with
these right so p0 p1 p2 p3 is p0 p1 p2
p3 is N and P P and P P P P and P P
right so this is a positive Z face of
the cube right so the first thing we're
pushing is the positive z face and this
is our positive z face so this goes
first right the next thing we're pushing
is seven six five four seven six five
four that's the negative Z face so
positive Z face negative Z face what are
we doing next four or five one zero four
five one zero that's the negative Y face
this one right here
keep track of where I am superfish
positive easy face negative z face
positive i'm sorry negative live face
i'm just gonna guess positive y face
let's see if I'm right
2 6 7 3 2 6 7 3 yep
so probably negative X face now and then
positive X face let's take a look 1 5 6
2 1 5 6 2 lovely so here we've pushed on
the surfaces now in the same order that
they're getting pushed on in here which
is obviously important and so then we
need to make sure that our light index
aligns up I'm this is really cheesy I'm
only just not caring about this because
we're gonna delete it like immediately
after we get it working so we're you
know resetting it or pushing on the
points resetting it again pushing on the
points right but that's really all we
should have to do so now what we need to
do is actually grab these out of
somewhere now we've got our rendered
entry texture quad stuff here where we
got entry right and this is using sort
of this information for where we're
supposed to push the quads we need to
specify we need to be able to get out
the rest of the stuff from the render
group as well so like this we need to
access these two things right we need
command surfaces and commands points so
in here where we do lighting surface
surface equals command surfaces commands
surface count plus equals 6 what we need
to do here is basically say like okay
commands surface count
we need to make sure all these indices
line up and there's way too many of them
right so we need to be able to say like
okay what's the surfaced in next year
the surface index is whatever the
surface count was so now we've got the
surface index properly here and then all
of these can all of the points can know
what their surface index should have
been I guess is what I'm saying there
when they get pushed on we'll deal with
that in a second so anyway here's our
surface indices we know what surface
index were on we go sort of through them
we'll use this in a minute because we
don't actually need it for anything at
the exact moment we update the surface
count so this process should push all
the surfaces on we just need to know
what this commands value is and I think
we can do it just by doing group
commands I think it's literally just
that right we also want to assert that
surface index is I should say commands
surface count less than or equal to like
data width like so and this should push
all of those services directly on we
then when we're pushing the points on
need to do exactly the same thing so we
have the light index stuff here needs to
be on here so
this is actually just group commands
white points and similarly we have here
when we're doing this check this is
going to be group commands light point
count
like so
alright don't ask me what that's
supposed to be all right and now we need
to allocate these points per surface
right so really what we want to do is
loop over the surfaces here like so this
would be surface width and height we
need to know the surface index as well
which should be pretty straightforward
and I think that's all I think that's
all that we actually is right so yeah in
here we can just say all right we know
that our surface index this is our
starting surface index right here all
right so we know that our surface index
we're just going to loop over all six
phases once we get the surface index we
can pull the surface out from that
that's actually fine better right
all right and so for each of these
points the point P is gonna have to be
something on the surface right so what
we can do here is say well you know we
know what the point we want to change
this from being generated off of
vertices which is how it was working
before into something that's generated
off of the center point probably right
so what we can do here is say like okay
the vert well I can really even just
translate this exactly so if we just use
the surfaces x-axis that we've already
computed in the surfaces y-axis that
we've already computed we can replicate
this as in its entirety by just saying
all right they're vert we know what this
would be it's just gonna be kind of
annoying when we write it out but if we
just take the surfaces P value then we
just need to step backwards by the x and
y-axes by by half the width and height
of the actual thing right so we just
need to say like half we're gonna step
backwards by half surface with backwards
by half surface height and again that's
totally unnecessary because we could
just make that directly to here because
we know that sub width is just half of
it already so I guess one thing we could
say it's just like alright forget that
we know we're subtracting off the point
five here so just get rid of the point
five of this or whatever but let's just
replicate it exactly for now and again
this is saxis
omit see zero in this case is just our
group commands omitsu zero max emission
is sort of the value we've we haven't
really decided what that value actually
is ever going to be so that'll be
something that we work on a little bit
later but it's just a way of encoding
our light sources
we'll handle that like so um yeah
cannot convert f/32 ah
and there we go so now we have
ostensibly started pushing these things
on to that memory oh and we need to
allocate this in in our win32 layer
still being here and these will probably
be transfer buffers eventually because
this is all stuff that goes to the card
so I'm not sure how this will actually
pan out when we finish up but you know
it's gonna be something like this and
then when we do our default render
commands you have to pass these in like
so
so now that stuff should be getting
pushed on there it's however is not
actually going to get used and we have
to it that's odd is this not getting
reset
oh right we don't reset this so we have
to where is our there we go so we have
to clear this out every time we restart
as well right so we have to clear out
our surface count we have to clear out
our light point count and we have to
clear out our admit well our emitters
just use the same indices so that
doesn't actually need to get cleared out
so at least in theory now we should be
good to go on the
on the lighting front there all that
stuff's getting pushed down we're just
not using it yet and so now we have to
we have to see about actually using it
and we have to see about pushing the
light points on are they all getting
pushed on correctly I think they are
actually doing press on correctly
so now or at least we made an attempt to
push them on correctly we may not have
done it correctly yet so now we just
need to go and actually start using them
so what we want to do here is in when we
do our extraction process here we do
extract reflectors from quads what we
want to do is say well we don't really
do that anymore let's just obviate the
need for that entirely get rid of all
this and the only thing we really have
to do then is let's clear out like emit
c0 I mean I mean average direction to
light right because that needs to get
cleared properly so average direction to
light needs to be zeroed no if we have a
thing to zero here
zero size so if I want to I can zero out
that entire array and so now that's
cleared and now we don't do the
extraction process at all
we just need to hoist these values out
here and use them right so what we want
to do is in the lighting solution where
we've got like the service count
services the point count points the emit
Caesar bitsy one direction delight last
is valid blah blah blah we want to do
here is we want to start taking some of
these out okay and so now what we want
to do is we want to get those from
somewhere else and you know that
somewhere else is going to be the
lighting commands right so we have to
when we go to do that extraction what we
need to do is actually extract those
from exactly that place now I guess we
could actually do this in a in a really
smoothly kind of way by just saying like
alright well you know what maybe we just
actually copy everything for the moment
you know
so let's just do this solution omit c0
is gonna come from group commands omit
c0 let's just copy all this stuff
surfaces light points and emit c0
surfaces points emit c0 and then let's
also just copy the point counts so now
we're just going to won't copy that
stuff in here and now we can actually
debug this as we go and this was already
a local so we could just do that so now
we do the extraction we're literally
just copying the stuff out into our own
temporary space working on it and then
putting it back and as you can see when
I'm doing this we actually seem to have
got incorrect results which is kind of
surprising to be honest but it seems to
still be behaving the way that it was
behaving before it does seem slower now
which I'm not sure exactly why that
would be but we can investigate that a
little bit further I just wanted to make
sure that was working at all and it sort
of is one of the reasons it might be
slower is because of all this copying
that we're doing for no reason
obviously you pick part of it
we are a compelling optimization mode
but that copy could be kind of slow so
let's go ahead and get rid of the copy
and get rid of the extraction altogether
we can now get rid of this because we
don't use it anymore I will go ahead and
and nuke that there we go and then when
we do extract the selectors from quads
where we were calling that before I'm
just going to put this directly in line
here and I'm going to eliminate these
copies by just making them be local
pointers right so where we do extract
reflectors quads can go what we need to
do here is just say that solutions
surfaces equals command surfaces
solution points equals group command
light points and solution emits c0
equals rib commands emit c0 like so and
we need to move this stuff down here
this needs to happen at the end like so
so when we do this right now we're gonna
grab all the pointers out we're gonna do
our we're gonna save our average
direction copy here and then we're gonna
clear it that's really it not a lot more
to it than that so I think we're all
good
[Music]
the only question is hey when we're
storing these here we should probably
now do this a little bit more sane we
should probably say something like well
for the points that we're actually using
so you know this is probably more
appropriate
let's not clear parts of the buffer that
we don't actually use or save parts the
buffer that we don't actually use in
that case but that's about it so
assuming that we're gonna do everything
that way then what we want to do is and
we have to do some some stuff here to
make sure the things as we add more
points won't be completely borked there
but that's sort of a separate issue we
have to zero some things out and and
stuff like that but we'll get to that a
little bit further down they will
already be zeroed because they're win32
initialized blocks so that part is easy
as well but anyway what we need to do
now is make sure that we're not using
array count anywhere because these
things are no longer directly accessible
so this you know becomes that this
becomes that this becomes that so you
have to watch out right so I'm just
gonna go see if we have any other size
of zin here that we're happening
there isn't and I'm gonna see if we have
any array counts in here
it doesn't look like we do so I'm gonna
see if that works a little bit better or
I should say if it works at all because
I don't actually know it does appear to
be working I'm gonna take a look at the
profile you can see update and render
world is taking all the time that's the
compute lighting stuff I'm gonna go
ahead and take a look at the I'm gonna
I'm gonna add some timed blocks in here
so all I have to do yeah
[Music]
assuming that all the time will be spent
in there but I don't actually know
so compute light propagation is taking
all the time which is what I had assumed
would be happening and is happening so
that's good the only problem is I don't
know why it seems significantly slower
than it was before cuz I think it was
running faster than this before I could
be wrong about that so maybe there's no
need for concern but I was trying to
figure out whether we were pushing too
many points on potentially so it might
be nice to see what the point count is
for example in here in the renderer how
many lighting points is actually doing
how many plotting points is actually
using or stuff like that so I might just
add a thing that allows that to be
output I know in our debug system we
have the ability to save debug value
I just never remember how it works so it
looks like you just say debug value that
seems pretty simple so yeah if I was to
do that here would that just work
I don't really know I guess it does so
we've got 1849 points and 462 surfaces
so that does still seem like the right
number so yeah I'm just not sure if we
accidentally slowed things down because
I don't remember how fast this thing was
running before I think maybe it didn't
slow down I don't know we should
probably check we're gonna have to
optimize this all anyway so I guess I
don't really care too much but I
probably shouldn't double-check that we
didn't slow it down it would have been
nice we can go check the video I suppose
all right so that's how we're pushing
all that stuff on there and now the
question is just and
you know I might have pushed so I I
don't know if I actually pushed
everything on exactly right
fortunately it it looks like I did I
mean all the phases seemed to be
responding properly if I switch
temporarily to what it looks like what
the incoming light is you can see that
it looks about right
this yellow incoming light to all those
there's white incoming light over where
the white light is that all looks pretty
reasonable right I can switch the number
of iterations down very low and then
we're back up to 60 frames a second
there's one iteration
there's two iterations and so on uh you
know in another thing that's worth
noting is since we're sort of doing
smoothing overtime now we can even we
could allow light to propagate to
continue propagation across frames
potentially I don't know how I feel
about that necessarily but you know it's
worth noting that one of the things we
could do is say well lighting bounces
happen can happen outside of a frame so
you know you bounce light somewhere and
it can it can bounce light again next
frame that it received the previous
frame I don't know if we really want to
go that route because I'm not sure how
you know you have to decay those over
time in order to make sure that they
would not bounce around forever or
whatever but you know we'll see anyway
so given the fact that that's all fairly
reasonable now the next step that we
would do is change this to a a B P so
that we just passed down a B piece
directly instead of having to pass down
all of this extra mumbo-jumbo right I
don't want to do that yet because we are
out of time now so what I want to do is
next time that's the next step will take
change to a BBS so that everything this
works on a a B B's instead and off we go
right so I'll go ahead and go to the QA
for now and hopefully YouTube stayed up
the whole time
you
all right oh how can - isn't used
prevalently at that in video playback
across all the video playback in use
cases why is it the incumbent sovereign
only in video games well I think two
reasons one is that the companies that
get together to do the standard like
MPEG license are all kind of in a cabal
together - they all do like this giant
patent nonsense and make this like you
know codec that they're all gonna put in
their things so like you know that's why
I like Blu ray or something is this
standard it's because all the people who
make blu-ray players and blu-ray discs
you all get together and have a giant
festival where they make a really crappy
standard and then ship it right but the
other reason is because - is very
specifically designed for games and it's
very explicitly doesn't do things you
might want to do if you weren't worried
about games for example encoding is very
slow in big - because it assumes that
what you want to do is bake all the
videos for your games down and you want
to put a lot of thought into the
encoding of those and then you want the
playback to be extremely fast but that's
not true of other thing it's like for
example this is a live stream right now
I don't know that could livestream
something it's compressor is not meant
to run in real time right you know maybe
it can by now I don't know what they've
done to it since last I've worked on it
but so it makes three different
trade-offs than you would for a
general-purpose codec that doesn't have
any specific use case in mind like MPEG
or something like that
and the other reason is because
will sacrifice compression quality for
playback speed for example right so one
of the things that - definitely
does is it make sure it uses very little
memory and make sure it uses very little
CPU right as much as possible
that's not again true of MPEG MPEG is
maybe just going for the like best
quality with the highest compression
right and it doesn't care if it's using
urine
higher machine resources just to
playback a single video your pink
wouldn't want to make that decision
because pink knows that you want to be
doing loading and processing of your
assets while you're streaming a video so
that there's not a load screen or
something right so that's that's
probably most of the reason pink to just
isn't trying to target general purpose
it's only trying to target what game
people do that's what it tries to do
that's who they sell to and that's
intentional to fuel our descent
alright so light leaking it's entirely
possible that we have light leaking
because when we push these things on we
may have pushed them on incorrectly
right let's take a look could you be
more specific about where the light is
leaking I guess maybe the yellow light
is leaking is it leaking
I can't tell I'm not seeing the leaking
I don't see any light leaking at the
moment
trying to see if anyone has some can say
where the leaking is
I thought I saw the light leak through
the bottom wall that would be the red
wall right well remember we can push
ourselves through right so what you may
have seen is is this if we allow the
cube to penetrate through this surface
which is the only one blocking it then
it will leak through right so right now
you can see we're not getting any white
light leaking here but if I push through
then you would get it it's that's not a
leak that's because we assume you don't
enter penetrate because you normally
wouldn't be able to
Asaf said that I'm getting pretty
frequent audio popping other people
notice it as well I required a sample
here so I'm assuming that's the YouTube
streaming from OBS not working or maybe
YouTube isn't working
cuz I'm assuming that the audio popping
is not gonna be on the recording
recorded version unfortunately I'm not
sure how we would fix that maybe I have
to change the encoding settings for
YouTube or something not sure when you
write code in exploratory fashion and
you end up with something that works
well but it's too large and complex to
fit in your head at once how do you
simplify it back into something
manageable um well the same way that you
do anything else right like you go back
through it and you look at what it's
doing and you say alright how can I
break this into chunks that I can sort
of calve off as something that it does
right so like with the light we're like
okay you know maybe it does this
particular pass and then it does this
other particular pass let's break those
into two functions and sort of document
what they do and then then lock it down
like okay here's what it does right so
usually what you do is you just take
sort of spaghetti ish stuff right which
the light system is kind of now it's
like pushing it all over the place right
and then when we know that it's kind of
working the way we want then we just go
in and we start isolating the parts and
how they work and we just lock those
down right make them nice and clean and
say here's here's how the data comes in
here's how the data goes out everyone
understands it now and off we go
right it's it's really not that hard to
usually to go back through and scho what
is this actually doing how do I break
this into sections that I can clearly
say what they do and what they don't do
and what they ingest in what they output
right will you continue dual streaming
to YouTube I'm not gonna dual stream
like I'm only gonna stream to one place
if we can get the YouTube streaming
working well we could just switch to
that permanently I'd be fine with that
but
I don't knit it's very hard to get dual
streaming to work it's it's not reliable
and OBS doesn't support it natively so
I'm not gonna go down that route
are you concerned with compiled times at
all so far I saw see time reporting 2.7
seconds no that's plenty fine for me
that's 2.7 seconds is the optimized
build so if we switch to the debug build
it's only one point six four seconds so
I'm fine with those two as compiled
times
anything under 10 seconds I'm I'm
usually fine with I find anything over
10 seconds and I noticed the iteration I
I noticed that it like by the time I
switch here it's not ready to run yet
anything under 10 seconds I'm usually
fine no more questions
if there are no more questions then I
will end the stream for today for two
day
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for an episode of handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to well you
know what I just realized that before I
do end it I don't know if there were
some questions on the YouTube one cuz
that would not have shown up did anyone
have questions on the YouTube chat I
don't see any Q colons on here
alright looks like now alright thank you
very much I kept aside of ham in here
that's Leonard's coach pleasure coding
with you as always if you want to follow
along series at home you can always
pre-order the game at handmade hero
organic comes with all the source code
so you can play around with it we also
have a schedule bot if you want to know
when we're gonna be live and the little
live Now button will tell you as well
periodically as soon as the schedule is
updated it will tell you how long it's
gonna be till we're up obviously once
we're done it will switch to nothing
scheduled until the next schedule gets
posted I also have an episode guide go
to watch I got past episode of the
series I'll contribute button if you
want to contribute to the sort of how
should I put it community projects like
the for coder editor we use on the
stream or the although I think that is
went to itch i/o now so it'd just be the
episode guide the hosting for the
handmade hero forums and the hammering
Network stuff all that sort of thing we
do to collect community contributions to
pay for those projects and we just give
out the money to the folks who are doing
them that's about it for today I do not
know if I will be back next week or not
because I may be out of town and away
from this computer on the days we would
have normally scheduled them I might try
to reschedule them for other times we'll
see
so no process on that but we will be
back the week afterwards regardless and
then we'll be regularly scheduled
broadcasting from then on out until then
have fun programming I'll see everyone
on the internet and we will try to
figure out what's going to go on with
our streaming setup in the future as
well since now we know that twitch is
not really reliable we'll probably have
to have something backup like this
YouTube situation so we'll play around
with that a little bit and see what we
can do that's it for now catch everybody
later and thanks for joining