hello everyone and welcome to handmade
here are the show we could a
complete-game live on stream and I
wanted to I would I guess clarify the
wrong word but rather I wanted to fill
in something that I failed to mention
when we were talking about on this the
sparse energy system I like made the
whole analogy but I never came out and
said it and Chris Hecker emailed me this
morning I think mentioning that he had
watched it and I never said the thing
that I should have said about it and I
went back and looked and he's totally
right I never said it I I basically like
I drew a diagram
I made an analogy and then never
actually said what the analogy was
actually about which is not very useful
to anybody so let me go ahead and finish
this off here if you remember when we
were talking about entity systems I
mentioned this one here called act react
by Looking Glass which is the first time
I'd ever heard of anyone doing a system
of this form and what I was explaining
about that was that it was equivalent
we're not really equivalent but it was
analogous to sort of the way we had been
thinking about Cindy before where
there's an array of structures method of
thinking about entities and there's a
structure of arrays method of thinking
about entities and previously mostly
people were thinking about array of
structure style ways of working
identities and they had sort of changed
it into SOA by doing this and what I
never actually mentioned is why you
would want to do that I pointed out the
drawback to it one of the things that I
don't like about it which is that
anytime I want to do something that that
talks about multiple aspects of an
entity I have to go grab that
information from lots of different
tables right and you can see why that
might be a concern but that is not
actually the reason why you do it
obviously that's that's strictly a
downside so if that was the only thing
you wouldn't ever do this the reason you
do this is because you can get a win
from grouping all of the properties
together just the same as you do when
you're talking about
you know structure of arrays rest of
array of structures right so the form
that this takes is let's say using the
example that was here where I've got
burnable
if I've just got this the burning State
you know what the what the amount of
fire is on the sky if I've got that set
on each individual entity well now if my
fire system has a propagation pattern to
it like when I have fire and I propagate
those two things that are nearby me or
something like this that may be a very
specific simulation algorithm that wants
to store like things in a finite mesh
grid thing to like speed up how it's
computed and maybe it's got all this
stuff what you might want to do is have
that be its own separate sim where
everything is organized for optimally
processing fight right and that way you
can sort of optimize that path and make
it very fast without having to have this
whole gather step where you bring in all
of those things right and so what you
kind of get here is this idea of well
sometimes maybe it's faster than
everything's with the entity sometimes
maybe it's faster that everything's with
the property right and if that's not I
don't really think that's a super useful
way to break things down to be honest
but then again you know I'm not a game
play coder kind of person so you know my
opinion on it is not super relevant I
don't think you know there might be
really good reasons to do it but it's
not probably how I would approach the
problem because I don't see that as
being the most common case for how you
would want to optimize things because it
just seems like it's not gonna come up
that often but that may not be true at
the very least what I can say about it
is that if you find yourself in that
scenario where you've got a certain set
of properties that want very specific
optimized patterns to them then you can
kind of clearly open you can clearly see
why this might be a useful way of doing
that and you don't have to do it for
everything you could still have some
things that are AOS right you can still
have entity struts or classes or
whatever else you want and then you can
just have this side thing that's like
okay because fire or water or something
is this special property that's much
more difficult to simulate and we need
this sort of separate system for it we
keep that out in its own thing that's
optimized very specifically and we do
lookups into it on the occasions when
the entities themselves need to like
a particular thing out of it but
otherwise it's always kind of its own
thing you know you can see why having
that architectural option might be a
valid way to you know might be a viable
thing for you to want to do so hopefully
that gives a little bit better because I
basically skipped that part and yeah I
drew this out but then I never really
said what it was so hopefully that's a
little more clear all right that was all
I want to mention we are right in the
middle of changing the entity system
over so there's not much to talk about
right now we're just finishing what we
said we were going to do yesterday and
did a lot of but not all of right so we
did you know as much as we could in an
hour but we still have more to go to
finish converting everything over and so
if you ran the game right now you would
be in a very sorry state because it
doesn't actually have a way to well
actually I guess I don't know if that's
true or not I don't remember exactly
where we got to because we did actually
move her thing over to us I think what
would probably happen right now
is that when you when you call an entity
it doesn't ever actually go pack that
entity into an a chunk anywhere so
basically what happens is we're building
these entities and then just they just
would get thrown away they wouldn't
actually happen so what we need to do is
actually go finish all that work we need
to do that in entity and we also need to
do that in the the code for sim region
so those two code paths want to kind of
coalesce and that's exactly what I think
we will be doing today in order to get
things back to working State with the
new design today is day 279 so if you're
following along the source code go ahead
and load 278 and here we go
alright so the part that I was talking
about just now when I said you know it
would it would get to the point where it
created the enemy and throw it away
that's this code right here and you can
see that I've got a not implementing it
so what's going to happen is we're going
to do this begin low entity the entity
will get built out and this is just that
creation time it's like world creation
time we build a little entity we set all
the parameters for it but then we
immediately just throw it away right and
what do I mean by throw it away well
what I mean by throw it away is we're
constructing it into a temporary buffer
here this right here we're constructing
into that buffer and what we need to do
if we actually wanna save it is now is
to move it over into permanent storage
somewhere into the world where it's
getting tracked ok and by the exact same
token if we go back to our handmade sim
region that same process we have not
implemented over here either right so if
we come back over to this piece of code
where we've got to not move entity where
is n sim and and CIN here it is when we
go back over here I've seared it out but
this is the exact same code this enzyme
has to track what's happening here as
well now what I think I'm gonna do
because it's a fresh day and a fresh
start and you know it's like the coding
has been rolling all day and is ready to
keep on rolling I'm just gonna say let's
go for gust oh let's just keep let's
just forget it let's not even do baby
steps here let's just get the sim stuff
working the way that it should actually
work and so what's gonna happen here if
you look at the way this code is
structured inside the begins sim when
I'm pulling this data out of the chunk
so you can kind of see how I'm doing
that here right I loop over the chunks
that are like whatever the sort of block
of chunks that would be related to the
place that I want to sim and I'm calling
get world chunk on them and then I'm
loading in all of the entities that that
pertains to right now what I want to do
here is again this sim is meant to be an
a stream in stream out system so the
goal here is to pull everything out of
the world and I'm not actually even
going to leave it in there meaning it's
not like I leave the backing store in
place I'm gonna obliterate the Blackie's
back in store so I like pull that stuff
out and it's gone
and then I sin it right and then I put
it back in that's the current way that
I'm conceptualizing this working again I
said it's a crazy system I don't pretend
that it's not on the on the fringe it is
but that's the way we roll here at
handmade hero so just you know you best
not step to it Pro or something
so anyway point being in here we have
the handmade world code and we sort of
made a slight concession to this where
we change the world chunk to a world
chunk star here in the chunk cash and
then we basically put in these things
where we had like first block and
whatever and it occurs to me that this
may actually be again one of those
things where it's it's I'm not certain
that we really I'm not certain we nailed
it I guess is my is my concern what I
think might be more appropriate is we
might want to change where the pointer
is I think that may be a better place
for the pointer if that makes sense
and this I'm sorry that may be a bad
place is where and this may be a better
place to the pointer and the reason that
I say that is because uh well actually
you know let me before I even say that
because that may not be true let me tell
you what the problem is instead of
jumping to a solution which may not even
work the problem is we're gonna go in
here to the chunk hash and the way this
is going to work is we're gonna pull out
all of the world entity blocks and
they're gonna disappear right so they're
just gone and then we're gonna put them
back in later so what we kind of want to
do is pull things out of the hash
entirely to a certain extent I suppose
and then put them back in entirely right
so I don't know maybe this is still fine
because I guess we want to pull things
out of the hash entirely and the hash
does have to have this and then it's got
to have an exporter so I don't know
maybe that makes sense I'm not sure so
let's just pretend that it does for a
moment and we'll go from there okay
so what if I was gonna actually do it
and leave it instead of me saying that
was gonna be better when I don't really
know it would be let's just do it the
way that it was and leave it that way
okay so what I want to do here is I want
to excise the world chunk that I'm
talking about so instead of me looking
through these and saying get the world
chunk like I want you to give me back
the world chunk and and like what's the
right I'm looking for like I want you to
give me back the world chunk and keep it
where it is and I'm just iterating over
it I want to actually pull it out so
it's gone so it's not there anymore and
now that I'm thinking about this too as
I'm saying it again I'm leaning more
towards a solution that I'm talking
about before so here is another sort of
example of where this is kind you know
where there's another thing that we
might want to consider right and that is
if I want to leave the world chunk in
place as a marker that I then go and
vaporize only later and let me tell you
a little bit about why I might want to
do this now I don't suspect that I do
but I'm just gonna I'm just gonna tell
you what is sort of in the back of my
head with respect to that here on day
279 right oops
okay so what I'm thinking is I was sort
of thinking about the concept of
transactional memory here and what
transactional memory is is it's a very
very simple concept that is dressed up
by a very fancy term and all it really
means is if I want to do something
multi-threaded and I have a chunk of
memory that I know that I'm going to
operate on right so I've kind of got
this thing where you know I don't know
what this is but this is like my target
this is the thing that I'm actually
operating on okay then the standard
multi-threading problem that I run into
you know if we didn't ever have to worry
about threads colliding with each other
then we just run all the threads at the
same time and we don't care nothing
doesn't matter right you just everything
works it's great but we obviously when
we talk about multi-threading we always
talk about these problems that we get
we're you know we've got thread a here
that's coming in to do something and
we've got thread B here that's coming in
to do something as well right and so
what we end up with is a situation where
we do something like oh okay
you know I'm gonna come in here and I'm
gonna do something to this target right
my thread is gonna do something to this
target and then later thread B is gonna
come in here and and they're gonna try
to sell you this target as well at a
separate time if this is T right here
right and a is not gonna finish until
after B starts right so if we just allow
these two threads to just run then what
we would get is some kind of probably
corrupted State because B is reading a
partial update of a like whatever got
finished up to here making some changes
and then a is completing not knowing
that B read that data and then B what
it's actually writing stuff out is gonna
write out using part of what a updated
and right and you got this nasty kind of
partial visibility it could be even
worse if they're doing reads and writes
at the same time B gets some of the A's
data against some of these data you know
it's just it's just bad right and so one
thing that I was thinking about in terms
of the streaming system was like well
what we could do
is have some sort of system where when
you get something out of the world
storage you actually just mark it as to
whether or not you were going to edit it
or not right and if you're not editing
it you leave it in place as marked as
something that you read from and you
know that anyone who's coming in who
just also wants to read from it doesn't
collide right and so the reason I think
about transactional memory is the way
transactional memory works is all you do
is you do the update right exactly as
you would have on a peon whatever you
basically do the thread as if you were
going to do the thread normally and
everyone just operates as if they can
write as if there is nothing stopping
them and then when they go to actually
commit their changes all the changes are
gonna make get buffered till the end and
then get written out and what happens is
it's only those rights that are checked
and when that right is about to happen
when that block writes about to happen
it checks to see like some value in here
right that you use as a key value that
says you know it's basically just a you
know an incrementing integer or whatever
you want that basically says has anyone
touched this since I read it so when a
comes in here and grabs this value out
you know and this value is set to 1 or
something right becomes in here and it
grabs this value it's still set to 1
right a then commits its changes which
sets this value to 2 B then goes and
says oh I need to commit my changes what
is the change value oh it's two i F
stale data it just restarts itself right
it just goes all right let me start over
and so transactional memory is just
something that allows everybody to run
at the normal speed they're gonna run at
and all they do is they just if they
find that when they go to commit their
changes somebody has come in and changed
stuff before they were able to write out
their changes they just restart and so I
was thinking a little bit about that in
terms of our system because if we want
to have multiple threads running that
all update different parts of the world
at the same time I feel like probably
what we're gonna do is try to make them
not overlap but
easier said than done sometimes so one
thing that I was thinking about is well
if we have a system you know and the
system is is updating to people and like
one of them's updating here and one of
them's updating here so they both have
like an apron that looks like this you
know I was wondering about potentially
supporting the case where even though a
is only updating this region and B is
only updating this region their each
reading out of regions that are being
updated by somebody else and if we
wanted to support the case where where
there's no locking we don't prevent this
case we just let it happen right but
what we do is when we go to commit the
sim region changes out we check to see
whether any of the chunks that we read
have been updated since then and if they
are we abort and restart the the sim
right that if we did that would argue
strongly for leaving the chunks in place
right because if we don't leave the
chunks in place we can never do this
because when this went to update would
find nothing was here there was actually
it all the data is gone because be
sucked it all in and and you know what
you don't even know it's there
so if we don't have a higher level
scheme somewhere that thinks about who
is updating what where and make sure
that they don't overlap we would have
this problem and I don't really know
what our best approach is for solving
that right so it's something to think
about I suppose we could start with the
simplest thing first and not really
worry about this too much but I just
wanted to kind of give you what was in
the back of my head and why I'm not
really sure exactly how I want this
process to occur thankfully because it's
a stream in stream out system it means
that all of the entity code we write is
isolated to the simulation part of
things which I really like that's the
part I think is cool about this system
and so that means we can change the
decompress compress step a lot without
having to really change any code anymore
like those two pieces are now completely
separate from all the entity code and I
love that I think that's really great
but we still are gonna have to figure
out how they work eventually so for
right now I guess I won't think about it
too much because like I said I'm not
sure what to do and it's not something
that is going to affect dramatically all
of this other code we're gonna write so
I think that's okay because this will be
a fairly isolated piece that we can play
with over time so when we go and drop in
that multi-threading I can I can change
it then and that's a good thing right I
think that's what we want because until
we actually try doing multi-threaded
entity updating we won't really know
probably what the exact right format
should be for what we're going to do and
so I'm thinking that probably we want to
keep that as a thing that we do when we
try to multi thread it so I'm gonna go
in here and say when we do get world
chunk I'm gonna say like you know
something like remove world chunk and
then when we do this iteration we do all
the loading as we normally would
and then what we're gonna do is we're
gonna take that world chunk and we're
gonna put it on the free list
essentially so we're gonna say like add
chunk to free list and and that's going
to presumably be on the world so we'll
just put those chunks back we grab them
off and we'll we throw them back to be
used at some later date basically and
then in here where we have the blocks
exact same thing so instead of doing it
this way I'm gonna pull those blocks off
one by one
and return those to the free store as
well right and this is why I say that
pointer is kind of inconvenient cuz it
makes this code harder to write if this
block was just a pointer it's easy to
just pull things off the block as we go
but if we don't you know if we if we
instead do it a slightly different way
where we've got this sort of the block
is the first block in there then it's
kind of this annoying thing where I have
to write that code a little bit
differently and that's why I wanted this
to potentially have it that'd be a
pointer but let's see I'll see how
annoying it is to actually do that it's
probably not too bad so in here we've
got this block
here we go iterating over it and pulling
all the entities out and so what I could
do is just say well alright if we start
with the first one like so and we do a
while loop over it then what I can do is
say well okay
you know we're gonna snap a copy of
whatever the next block is right I guess
we're not threaded here so I guess I
don't even have to do that
to be honest with you what I can do here
is just say like alright flock equals
block next block as we were doing before
oops and what I want to do here is right
before I do that I want to put this
block on the free list right so well I
guess I still so I still do need to do
this actually now think about it because
this will probably get overwritten right
all right
so essentially you could see why I'm
doing that right because this this
adding block the free list will probably
overwrite the next pointer and I won't
be able to use it so when we call add
block to free list all I would have to
do to support the way we've got things
written currently is do a quick check to
see is the lock we're talking about the
same I should say is not the same as the
chunk that we start on and if it's not
we don't add it to the free list cuz hey
it's just that you know that block is
sitting there right so that's that's
basically all we're talking about and so
all that would require here is us
expanding the notion of world chunks to
have like first free chunk and a first
feed block
that's really all that matters so when
we come into this code in Ansem let's
take a look at what that's got to look
like so in this code what we want to do
here and we can probably make this more
efficient by bidding things more
intelligently potentially but really all
we want to do is when we come through
here instead of having this concept of
change entity location we're never going
to do that anymore instead what we're
going to do is just the enemy is going
to get packed right and that packing is
going to be the thing that that moves
the Edit e essentially into a new chunk
it's gonna find the chunk to pack it
into and it's going to pack it and like
I said this will lead to probably more
hash lookups then we really need it to
do and so we probably will want to do
something like in the sim entity it's in
the sim region itself what we'll
probably do is keep the world chunks
around as a spatial partition of some
kind
probably I'm just guessing or something
like this and then when we actually do
move entity we'll see if you exited your
boundary and if you are will update you
and that way you can stream everyone out
in those chunks really quickly without
having to constantly hit the hash
because I'm guessing that'll become a
problem for us eventually if we have an
affinities maybe it never does and if
that's true great but if it does then
that's where I think that approach you
know that's where I think we would hit
that approach all right so here we go
with with that code you can see from
cure where we kind of have the change on
a new location what I want to do now is
say well ok I don't care about any of
this stuff at the very end what I want
to do is pack the entity down so what I
want to do here is call something like
packed entity into chunk right and are I
probably just should just say into world
and that will be the call that actually
goes in finds
what chunk it should be in and puts it
in there as opposed to there might be an
actual pack entity into truck call which
is once you have the chunk then it packs
it in there right
so so and that would be the one we'd
call as an in an accelerated case where
we knew which chunk we were talking
about a priori so again that's probably
going to take the world that's true it's
not gonna have to dereference the entity
storage it is going to need that stored
entity which that's the actual entity
that we kept is wait is that true no so
we don't want any of this stored stuff
anymore at all right what is that doing
stored sim we don't want this no no no
no no no no no no I mean we can keep
these assertions I guess entity Flags
simming I don't think we need any of
that anymore since an entity now can
only be edited by pulling it into the
database the flag seaming on entity is
completely redundant you can never have
an entity by itself be siming and in DB
comes symbol when it's whole chunk gets
moved in so if we were ever gonna flag
something it wouldn't be an entity
because you know if you can look at the
ending struct at all it's being
simulated because otherwise it's packed
and you can't see anything right so we
would only need to set that if you were
saying that on world things so this is
is just gone right this is not a thing
anymore at all so that's good goodbye so
these are all going to be on the
entities themselves right and that
stored concept just goes away so
anywhere that we were seeing a story
before don't need to do that anymore so
what we're actually going to pack here
is the entity we can see the the is set
non-spatial stuff again that non-spatial
stuff I don't know that we ever want
anymore really I think we're probably
always gonna want the spatial stuff now
because it even if you're non facial you
will move around with somebody whoever
the person who's carrying you or whose
property you belong to you will be with
them and you will move with them and so
that is probably not a thing any more
than non spatial so I don't think we'll
need that either and when we do this map
into chunk space here that is this new P
we can leave that for now
we probably don't really need to do that
manually because that could probably be
something that is done in in this pack
entity into world right so if that makes
sense
map in the chunk space there we go so
that's really what that is about and
once I know that that's happening right
now that I have that that's a complete
streaming system right from start to
finish you can see it here and so what I
really need now is I just need some way
of calling that externally here and I
think we've pretty much set ourselves up
to do exactly that
so when we call pack entity into chunk
here which is the bad name for it oh
wait no this is fine
this is that what I wanted that was that
was some placeholder for just what we
were yeah when we were just sort of
sketching that in so what I want to do
here is I want to call this right I want
to call pack entity into world and so
the way I can do that is this world
position P right is sitting there on the
entity lo which we're still actually
tracking for no apparent reason I think
what we want to do is collapse that down
because again we don't really need the
low entity thing anymore and we don't
even really need to we don't need to
distinguish mean any of these things so
what I can do is I can stop having that
concept of the low entity which where
was that in sim region no so it's in the
world node so in low entity we were
keeping this I'm just gonna for now grab
that that out and I'm gonna put that
into the actual entity struct itself in
preparation for getting rid of that
entirely so this is going to be called
like you know chunk P or something and
we're just moving everything over in
here and then we're gonna collapse us
down so that's kind of the plan right so
this is gonna look like that now and
that means that when we do pack entity
into chunk we should be able to just do
something
like this where when we call that we
pass well and I guess we don't even have
to worry about that we can just pass
whatever the entity low sim is there
right
so you just pass the same entity and
that can get the P out of it because the
P is right there right and that's what I
want so this is gonna be called pack
entity into world because that's the one
that packs into the world and similarly
inside sim region now what I want to do
is make that symmetric so instead of
passing the new P here I don't actually
want to pass the new P and furthermore I
don't need to pass the World Arena can
get it itself obviously so what I want
to do here is I want to take this map of
the trunk space thing and I'll take that
operation and do it here to me so I'll
take that chunk P and I'll generate it
by doing the mapping back right so
that's that's what we're doing there
okay now and eventually all this stuff
can continue to go away like I said this
stuff this stuff is all like we're gonna
be able to sort of clean and clean and
clean and clean I think and then and
then we'll be good to go
all right so and and you know I'll
probably lock that P out again in a
second here but that's that's a separate
issue so we don't care about any of
stuff anymore change in a new location
really not relevant in any way and does
not matter to us at all anymore so this
is just gone and goodbye right then we
come up here and we say get sim space P
right anyone who was looking for that
before can get it if you want you can
just do the reference the sim off of the
stored entity if you want to but you
shouldn't have to really even do that
anymore because pretty soon that that
won't be a thing anyway what is the
complaint here world position oh sorry
I'm a chumpy not Chuck P that sounds
like some kind of a sneaker all right so
remove world chunk is something we need
to implement add block to face that
Chuck play us both are as
well let's take a look at this year
entity storage index this is the thing
that we had before about tracking values
obviously those are going to get cleaned
up as well too in a separate pass but
I'm not gonna do too much with those at
the moment what did I do here so this is
also a value there we go I curious the
stored value we don't want that anymore
so what we really want is just the
entity chunk P here which we've already
computed so that's fine and the same
thing is true of this right so that's
all good and when we do pack entity in
the world like I said you know I think I
will for now continue to pass that
through and the reason for that is
because eventually we can get rid of it
all together and eventually we can just
make this be something that gets passed
and in fact I guess well you know no
time like the present so here's our
world see here H here is our world
position so we'll just go ahead and
generate that and I'll pass that through
here and so that when we call pac----
entity the world you pass that chunk P
and there you go
and I think and like I said it's gonna
take a flying leap out of here I think I
can actually get rid of that then
entirely and the reason that I think
that is because inside world mode if I
just changed from when I do begin low
entity if I just move the world position
P down to end entity right then I could
just pass it here for free and I
wouldn't have to store it anywhere so it
wouldn't have to live here
we know the sim doesn't need it so
creation time shouldn't need it either
so let's just make that happen
right if that makes sense so we'll get
rid of these world positions on creation
and pass them on end and I'm just going
to go ahead and see if that works
right
now ma'am so here and begin grounded
entity we're passing the P so really
again like I said this should be really
straightforward all I have to do is move
it from the beginning to the end same
thing here
right I just move it from the beginning
to the end keep on going here it is same
exact pattern so I say that's where I
want it to be placed right and I'm just
sort of saying like place the entity
here let's see there's another begin get
that going and these are both placed at
the same place so I actually can just do
both of them goodbye
and see here code modification someday
if Alan Webster does like actually
complete his code intelligence editing
thing as he suggested I wonder if this
is the kind of editor if this kind of
thing that for ED will do automatically
which would be kind of ridiculously
awesome if it was I haven't thought it
through if that's something it could
have done like hey I had this pair of
things and I wanted to move a parameter
from one to the other it's within the
realm of possibility right I mean you
could see the editor going like oh yeah
okay I'll do that for you no problem so
I don't know I guess only Allen can tell
us what does this key do well that's a
key that deletes my buffers I forgot
that's zero oh I have my num lock on
that's why all right well I don't want
that on so I'm gonna reboot I'm gonna
reboot hold on a second
sorry zero is my key for a kill buffer
and I had mem lock on yeah I'm not used
to even having in them a numeric keypad
but all my other keyboards now don't
have that on there anymore so anyway so
that's I think it for the structural
changes there and what we can do now if
we wanted to and we might as well
because like I said we're just going
nuts here we're just having a little
a little piss already as they would say
you know on the streets so basically
what I want to do is just get rid of the
whole that whole double notion because
now we know we never need low entity so
we only have cemento tea right and so
what I can do here is I can just replace
anywhere that we were using low entity I
can replace it with just entity right if
that makes sense though entity Kennedy
oops
what did I do I've done something
horribly wrong
I don't know what Oh entity with entity
okay yes yes yes yes these are all yes
okay so if I replace entity with low
entity and then I go into some region
dot H I should now be able to say all
right instead of a simonetti there's
just an entity and now we only have one
in any type and we still have all the
benefits of having to edit e types but
we don't actually have to deal with it
right which is great it's double plus
awesome in a special awesome sauce with
awesome on top all right dude do do
there's just a lot of things called sim
entity as it turns out sin entity oh and
that's not good sin entity entity
love that scroll one more time so now
we've got some low entities here and I'm
just gonna take low entity and change
that to entity as well so there it goes
right and what else we got
so we've got this kind of stored sim
thing here and stored sim is no longer
necessary so really those can all be
changed I guess if there's anywhere that
has the pattern of stored sim that can
be changed to just stored now which was
not very many all right so that still
wants to be arrow that just needs to be
that right let's see so source see start
entity equals source what is source what
was that again oh right so I've just got
to do a star source source is just a
pointer to the entity that it's coming
from and this is just gonna be all yeah
this is definitely the sort of thing
that wait and that's right this is
definitely a sort of thing that for
coder could do eventually I think based
on what Allen was talking about anyway
so let's see we will remove world chunk
now the thing lo let's keep going
and in the overlaps rectangle low
collision low storage index and
see people on going no don't care so
here I guess we could probably do this
where we have entity lo eros in dot it
could just be entity lo arrow right and
that's probably just gonna be true
basically everywhere that that was
happening why did that not know why that
didn't that didn't seem to get them
although I wrong about that there we go
maybe I did it wrong entity lo oh it's
because some of them were in the lilo
not guys see what it was all right well
anyway point being
all right so similarly so this I can
just replaces well I think humanity with
Kennedy is now good to do and we're
almost there let's see entity sim for
add wall that's just gonna be gonna add
Flags call let's see same thing here
let's take a look for add Flags I think
those can all be done same way
yeah and almost there okay so now that
all that's done I think we're basically
at the point where all of the structural
changes have occurred and so really all
we have to do is implement those couple
of functions that we don't have yet and
those are on the world right so the way
I want to do that and I'm trying to look
here to see change in any location raw
like I just don't even think we need any
of this stuff anymore right that just
does not matter pulling the thing out of
the chunk does none of this all of this
janky code can just go away like goodbye
not relevant it doesn't matter
not important right because no one's
going to call it so all we have to do
now is we just have to pull it out of
the hash completely and then you know
put it back in so I'm going to start
with the easy case first the easy case
is packed entity into world that's very
simple
because we already have get world chunk
which does exactly what we want in this
case it returns to us specifically the
world chunk that we would write this
thing into right and that's exactly what
we need so what I'm going to do is going
to start with PAC entity into world
internal void PAC entity into world that
takes of course the world and it takes
the entity and it takes the location
right and then what we're gonna do is
we're gonna get that world chunk out and
we're gonna get that world chunk out in
a way that tells that underlying routine
hey by the way I would like you to loops
I would like you to create a world chunk
in this location if there isn't one
already right so I'm gonna give it the
arena pointer here like so so I'm gonna
say all right let's have get world chunk
operate and and give us back a world
chuck we know we can pack this thing
into so then all the only thing that I
need to do is figure out will it fit in
the current place in the chunk or won't
it and the way that I can do that I say
well right now our pack function is
completely neutered it's just a copy
right we haven't gotten to the point
where we actually do the logic of
packing some compacting something down
to only the part that's necessary right
so instead what we're gonna do here is
we're just gonna do a copy but that
means that we know the total size we
need to pack right and the total pack
size is just whatever the entity size is
so if the entity is how we're big that's
how much room we need so we need to see
if the chunk and you remember how this
is stored here right
if the chunk entity data size is at a
point where we could add to it and not
overflow so if the entity data size plus
our pack size is less than or equal to
however big the Jimmy however big the
entity data is right that's all we need
to know
right so we can come in here and say all
right that's our pack size we can see if
it's less or equal to that means we can
pack it right now what we want to know
actually though because we always try to
succeed in packing we actually want to
know if we exceeded right and if we
exceeded we need to make a new chunk
okay so impact entity into world we
would need to do a push struct right of
a world chunk in here now since we're
you know we're gonna have a free list
what I could say is well okay if that's
the case I'm sorry I'm sorry the block
now volts on I mean a world block what I
could say is okay world entity block new
block I'm gonna first DQ off of the free
list right so I'll say the the the new
block equals whatever the world's first
free block is now I've got one if it's
there if new block actually worked then
I will say the first free block becomes
the next block otherwise I'll do a push
truck to get myself a new one so the
world's oops you know what I could do
that's actually a lot smarter than that
now think about it I could just do if
not world first feed block world first
food block equals push truck that's a
little bit better because then this is
just that right it's a it's it's more
it's a better way of writing that code I
in fact I don't know do I normally write
it that way I feel like that's better
than the way that I normally write it I
probably should be running it this way
am I missing something here
oops arena so if you look it's like if
we don't have a free block we put one on
there right and otherwise we
right otherwise we grab it questions the
otherwise then we always grab it that
seems right to me
probably anyway there you go mm-hmm so
we dq1 here and then we need to do the
initialize I don't remember what it's
called here it's like a clear world
entity block so we want to do a clear
world entity block on this new block
because it just has garbage whatever was
in there when we threw it away before
right so we want to clear that block and
then we want to pack into the block
right so this is what we do if we need
more space if we don't need more space
then we go ahead and continue now what
we could do is we can throw an assertion
in here we could say like hey after all
that funny business let's at least
verify that whatever we were about to do
does work now like we actually did get
the size the space we needed if we
needed space okay
so now I need to do my pack so here's my
destination pointer my destination
pointer is just the entity data plus
whatever the current size is so there we
go and I can kind of cast that right to
it to the entity I can say that's where
I'm going to store it then what I can do
is say well the chunk entity data size
I'm going to add however much I packed
on there right so I've advanced it's
like an arena I just kind of push on to
it right I did that push and now I'm
done all I need to do is my actual copy
so I could do my copy because we're not
actually packing normally this would be
the step right actually pack but here
instead because I'm just copying the
enemy directly in off you go right and
we could make this even a little closer
to what we're really expecting something
more like this right and then it's only
here where we actually do the cast
because later we'll just be packing so
we won't it won't be an entity struct
it'll just be partially an instructor
when we get to that phase of things
right so that's how can entity into
world would work and similarly what we
can do in here is if we want to avoid
the the lookup pack entity
into chunk like I was saying this can be
two phases because you can see where we
looked up the chunk and then we packed
into the chunk so what I can do is make
this a separate phase here and that way
in the future if people want to
accelerate that process and not hit the
hash all the time they can do that very
simply by bypassing it if they already
know what the chunk is and so that's
kind of nice so I'll call PAC entity
into chunk here passing the world the
same entity and then instead of the
position at you just pass the chunk
you're like this is the chunk I wanted
to pack to write okay so this takes the
world the entity and you and I might
call this source instead of entity so
that it's clear what's the source and
what's the destination of the packing
process right because they're both
representations in anyone's a pact and
anyone's a unpacked entity and so right
you know it seems reasonable all right
so PAC entity into world that's what we
need in tubes and it just passes the
chunk in and then once we have the chunk
and here we know that we can execute
without having to hit the hash we just
pack on to that first chunk and if we
need to we can push it down again right
in fact you know what I was just
realizing though that's not quite enough
because this I I didn't actually do the
I didn't actually do this part I missed
one layer so what I actually need to do
when we get the chunk here this is
actually supposed to be this is actually
supposed to be on the block oops so what
I actually meant to do was grab the
block out here
and oh okay so we finally gotten to a
place where I care about the Pointer so
if I want to constantly do push down
right if I want to basically fill it up
and then move it out I can't do that
unless this is a pointer I will have to
keep a second pointer here that tells me
where the last one was right so I think
that finally answers the question for me
of what I actually want to do and I
think the answer is I want first block
to to be a pointer right I think that's
I think that's clear right you want that
to look like this if that makes sense
because otherwise what am I gonna do I
don't want to chase that pointer every
time I don't want have to walk it to the
end so it does seem to me that that's
just better even though it's wfq we're
gonna have to dereference anyway as that
thing fills up I think that's probably
what you want the other thing to do is
somehow try to mix this with the hash
and I don't know what I think about that
but you could imagine doing it that way
right like what we could do instead is
actually just say anything in this
bucket that matches the hash and you
walk through and you pull those out I
don't know what to think about that
doesn't seem great to me
I guess is what I'd say so I think that
is actually the way that I would prefer
it if that if that makes sense
so what I'll say here is you know we're
gonna pull this block out we'll take a
look at the first block I haven't got
much time left in about five minutes or
so so we'll pull that block out and then
I'll say hey if we don't if there is no
block right or I can't fit right this
thing doesn't actually fit then I need
to do I got to do the action right then
I got to say all right let's grab this
block out here and and then what I need
to do is I need to push it onto the
stack basically right and I could sort
of even make this be a little bit more
explicit by just using chunk first block
and not actually having block as a
pointer at all if I want to write I
could say if not you know chop that
chunk first block and you know what I
could do here has write a bool 32 of has
room for which would take a world entity
block and a size and figure out whether
or not it could fit right and that would
just be this and the reason that I like
that as well is because it's easier to
see what's going on and I can call it
the same for the assertion right so I
can say has room for pack size and here
is my block chunk first block and then
when we start will always just say okay
what we're packing into here is always
the chunk first block okay
so that's good all right so let's push
forward on that a little bit so here is
the results the result of this function
is going to be if whatever the block you
pass me
well it's the same thing that we were
doing before right it's the exact same
thing and so all I'm gonna do is say if
it has room for is gonna be phrased that
way so it has to be less than or equal
to right and then I'm going to return it
so in here we're gonna say if if there's
no first block or if the first block
doesn't have room then what we're gonna
do is we're gonna pack and we're gonna
do that like this by first I'm sorry
then what we're gonna do is we're gonna
make a new one we're gonna do that by
either getting one out of the arena or
grabbing it from the FreeStore whichever
one will actually satisfy us in the case
the arena's like the secondary fallback
right so then we grab out whatever the
first block actually is we come in here
to these sort of pack size things this I
can now replace with the has room for of
the block and I can text it with the
pack size to verify that that works then
we go ahead and say if we can pack it
into this block
well actually guess we know we can pack
into this block so let's find the
location and then do the actual pack and
this this records the fact that we use
that much space to me so that's it and
that all seems pretty good now we're
gonna have to modify our get world chunk
a little bit here excuse me because our
get world chunk now has to have this
notion that there is a first three block
pointer now I don't actually think
that's necessary to do pretty much
anything other than setting its pointer
to zero on an it in here I think that's
all that actually has to happen so it's
really really simple not very much
difficulty whether we want to now switch
it so that the world chunk is like
whether we want to now get rid of this
pointer I don't know
right we may want to we may not want to
I'm I'm just not sure which we want to
do there I
it's hard to say I suspect we'll just
leave it as a pointer for now and we'll
see if whether we have performance
issues in the future and only change it
then because the point is gonna be
easier to work with all right so I think
that's everything four pack entity into
chunk let's take a look
block equals first free block actually
so what I'm doing is chunk first block
equals world first free block there we
go there we go okay the entity here in
this case is source not entity and so
now let's see initializing reinterpret
cast a buck fears okay so it looks like
mostly now we are in good shape because
now all we have to do is implement the
part where we pull the things out right
and that's again not super difficult
inside world here we have to have things
for adding we need these two functions
basically right we need add block to
free list and look at all the pretty
colors and adjunct free list so in this
case here is internal void add buck to
this internal void chunk to free list so
so we've got our world this is honestly
an inline because this is really really
straightforward
so we have our world pointer
and we now have this world entity block
that's like some old thing we want to to
free and so all we have to do there say
well the old next just equals same thing
we do all the time equals the first free
block and and then the world first free
block equals the old right same old same
old
really boring like I said if you've got
any meta programming in the language
you're using you can trivially you can
metaphor met a program of a free list
style allocator it's so so simple right
you can kind of see how that works but
anyway so four world chunks same thing
for each chunk and the reason you view
that is just because it's not like it's
hard to type this but I might make a
mistake right like anytime I type that
in I might make a mistake on how the
free this works so that's the reason you
met a partner to us like it's only two
lines of code so you're not really
you're certainly not saving any effort
but it's that mistake if that error
prone it's like oh did I mess up the
free list right that's that's why you
better program those things so that you
can reuse them that way anyway so in
remove world chunk we haven't touched
that one yet this one where we do world
that ID block for this first block thing
for this one now we can do this the way
that I had said that I wanted to do it
before so instead what I can do now is
say all right let's do a let's just DQ
it directly here and I guess I don't
have to do anything else that that is
what it is
I can just make this more
straightforward and be done right so
that's good all right so all we need now
is a remove world chunk so hey you know
I'll take I'll go a little over time and
we're basically we are out of time
technically at the moment we'll go a
little more time just so I can type it
in and then that way next week we can
start with all of our changes having
been made and then we can just focus on
actually like getting everything to work
right doing the debugging and that sort
of stuff and that'll be nice so here we
go here's my remove world shock now
remove world chunk is basically this
code for all intents and purposes as the
get world shop code right so this code
right here so what we need to do is we
need to just make it work slightly
differently when it the the reason we
can't just call it directly and the
reason we're gonna have to modify these
a little bit is removing the world chunk
requires knowing the in pointer right
and I'll show you why so let's say I was
to call get world chunk right here
because I want to remove the world chunk
so hey I know I can reuse this code I
can say hey world chunk you know chunk
equals get world chunk and I can just
pass I've got all of the exact data that
I would have needed right it's all here
so that'll work right but the problem is
now how do I actually get it out of the
hash chain right I can't I can't
actually get it out of the hash chain
because the person who's pointing to it
is before it I don't have a previous
pointer but I would have had the
previous pointer if I implemented this
loop myself so really all I have to do
is say okay get world chunk as it stands
before right let's grab out this part of
the code and instead let's actually call
get world chunk internal or something
now when I've got that code and what I'm
going to do is I'm going to modify what
it returns so that I do have the in
pointer right so here we go let me just
show you what I'm talking about so in
here I'm gonna I'm gonna make this my
new get world chunk that every one the
outside calls this is a very standard
technique right you've got some people
flowing into an entrance point and I'm
just pushing the actual internals of
that down one layer so I can have two
entry points that both use its logic but
do different things on the outside so
this is get world chunk and so now in
order to get the chunk I need to call
right get world chunk eternal and I'm
passing the same parameters saans arena
right and the problem is now you can see
all of the the same issues that occur
here I can do all the work right up into
the point where I needed to know what
was my end pointer right so all I'm
gonna do is say from now on instead of
returning the actual pointer to the
chunk I'm going to return a pointer to
where it's pointer would have been right
so I'm going to say hey let's find the
person who would have pointed to the
correct chunk which tells you both
things you needed to know so here's my
here's my iterator right over the chunks
and here's my result
so instead same exact loop all I'm gonna
do now is instead I'm gonna use the
ampersand for those pointers and I'm
going to look at the dereferenced
version right that's it
so now it's always using a pointer to
the pointer to find it and then when it
returns it gives it back right actually
that's that's all we need there
makes sense so now in here when we come
back
I've got chunk pointer right and I can
dereference it and what I can say is
well well in fact I can just say result
what I can say is okay if results isn't
valid I do all the same things I doing
before but now I have the actual
information that I actually wanted here
I want to know what was in the slot that
was my in pointer what was it
right and I want I want to know what was
there so I just dereference what was in
that pointer right if that makes sense
and try to think about this this is
slightly different in the way that it
worked and that this adds to the end
instead of the beginning now but I don't
think we care right in fact I don't know
why we would care we don't care right
and similarly I'm just going to go ahead
and put the tail on here I can just say
well whatever that was in that slot
before I'm gonna make that point to me
now so it's exactly the same thing
because now we have the information to
do it for remove world chunk same exact
thing I now have a pointer to a pointer
so what I want to do is save what was
there as my result because that's what
the person needs to know right but now
that actual pointer wants to be modified
so I wanted then take what was in that
slot and I want to leapfrog it over the
one I actually grabbed removing it from
the list does that make sense hopefully
it does
okay and got a return my results so I
know that's a little complicated and
like I said we're done now so let's run
it and let it crash and burn because it
will and then we will go and and the
Baron well I guess this one's probably
simple to bug the my always I always
like can't help but debug right so right
that makes perfect sense I no longer
want to ever return zero in this case
right I always want to return whatever
the world chunk is so this is really I
always want to return that in pointer
because there's always a valid in
pointer
voila
in fact I guess this is now not even
right this is actually this poops this
is just saying hey while there's a chunk
and it's not the chunk we're looking for
indentation read Vance do we have the
right number of parentheses no all right
so sorry now we can let it crash and
burn there we go that's what we actually
wanted to see happen and hey that caught
a buck did that catch a bug creation
buffer locked ad player yeah we tried to
create two entities at the same time
which we don't support see caught a bug
how good is that how good is that I
could fix that one too while we're at it
I suppose ad player but because these
both these are to begin about these
things so I mean I feel like I just want
to support that kind of to be honest so
I don't know like you know maybe I want
to support creating multiple of these
entities at the same time you know
could imagine something like this right
where I like let you use a couple there
on in off you go
now you could just do it with temporary
memory - now I think about it why did I
even do that why did I even do it that
way you could just push it on the
transient arena and go
so that's arguably perhaps a little bit
stupid just in general but yeah yeah
that's that's uh that's questionable but
I could totally do it this way right I
can just do something like this begin
low entity just does assert rolled mode
operation buffer index is less than a
read count world mode creation buffer
and then I just say world mode
right and then in here when we do and
entity we just go like okay the creation
buffer gets docked and we can also
assert that once it gets docked that you
are pointing to the correct one okay
lovely all right okay so I think yeah
okay so I think in that case I'm sorry
I'm kind of just obsessing over like
since I did all that code I usually like
to leave it in a good state like I said
the whole I have to end an hour thing
you know it's always a little bit of a
struggle for me because it's if you're
obsessive programmer you don't like to
leave something you want to like finish
it it's just how it is
you can't I don't know that's just how
that's just life
so anyway what I was gonna say is that's
an easy one to write it's like we
occasionally don't remove any chunks so
I was I didn't bother to check to see if
there were any chunks in there so in
removed world chunk when we get back our
chunk pointer what we want to do is say
hey don't if we're not gonna remove
anything then don't try to write don't
try to leapfrog over something that's
not there right so that's easy as well
all right so we're good now we're we're
on a thing where we've got to actually
we have to actually figure out if there
are running heroes and all that kind of
stuff and have the camera like we got it
we got a bunch of new stuff to do but
we're running now so we can at least
leave it in an OK spot and so that's
good so I'll go ahead to the Q&amp;A and
while I'm waiting for the Q&amp;A to Q&amp;A
itself up
I will also why am i see Mira torii -
can we talk about why it insists on
logging me in as see Mira Tori - I don't
know how to change my name
why am i see Mira Tori to
there we go okay okay so what I'm gonna
say is while I'm waiting for some cues I
am going to mention what happened with
that list situation so here is how this
worked okay well let me show you exactly
what happened so here's the world right
and it's got a hash table in it right
so in here inside it if we were to talk
about this one part portion here I'm
going to blow that out here's the hash
and the hash is a series of pointers so
each one of these is a pointer right so
in one of these hash entries there's
just a pointer and it points out to a
chunk so here's a chunk and inside this
chunk we have another pointer to a block
right now we don't care about this part
for this so I'm just going to leave it
out in addition to that we also chained
these so the chunks keep going
okay so what I had was a function that
does the hash lookup and finds the right
chunk in the chain right because in the
hash bucket there may be multiple chunks
that are not the same that are different
right places in the world and we got to
find the match so we have a function
that finds the hash bucket and then it
looks for the right match in the in the
external chained hash right now what I
had was a problem where I was returning
the actual pointer to the chunk so let's
say this was the matching chunk I found
it right well that's just great for
anyone who wants to use that chunk but
if what the person wants to do is
actually remove the chunk they can't
because the piece of information they
need to edit is right here and they have
no pointer that goes back to it so
instead what I did is I said okay
instead of giving them back a pointer to
the chunk I'll give them back a pointer
to the pointer of the chunk so what I
did is I start the loop pointing at this
location so now anyone who wants to know
if I if the iteration stopped there so I
check this chunk because right I look at
what's pointed to and what that's
pointing to and I look at that chunk and
if that chunk matches then this is what
I return is this pointer to here so now
if the person wants to edit it they have
that position if I need to advance this
so this is not the chunk I need to look
at the next one I make my pointer point
here so when I return this chunk I
actually return this location of this
pointer so that I can both get to the
chunk by doing referencing it or edit
what's pointing there by overwriting it
right so that's why the pointer to the
pointer hopefully that makes sense
no even how are you finding Milton I
didn't catch the start of the stream
sorry so basically I think the only
problem with Milton is currently the
brush tracking it's just not good enough
yet like the I think it needs like some
tapering at the end on the pressure it
needs like a little pressure taper just
a bit maybe more than it is and it needs
a higher sampling rate or less lag it's
just basically the brush handling is the
only thing that's a problem other than
that it's way better actually because
the interface gets out of my way
trivially which is nice oh that's
interesting that's interesting tab when
I when the interface comes back switches
to tabbing between those two I feel like
that's probably a bug I should right and
forth that anyway the interface gets out
of my way which I like and it handles
auto savings so I never have to save it
and wait that big long spinny cursor
thing so I would say if if Sergio can
fix the brush handling I would say it's
a straight win across the board and it's
it's basically like just straight up
better than mischief period as for now
it's a bit of a trade-off because the
brush handling is not as good that's
where I'm at so far
pulse-ox how do you pronounce your name
Casey Mira Tori is how I pronounce my
name
Elvin is the sparsity system the same as
mix-ins that you mentioned before if not
are we ever going to use or talk about
mix-ins I'm really curious as to what
they are yes so mix-ins it is not a
technique it's a ability if you will
like the concept of a mixin is just what
it kind of sounds like it's like I want
to be able to combine a bunch of these
things together arbitrarily at runtime
right it's exactly what C++ can't do
right
C++ at runtime can't say I want this and
this to be combined or any that sort of
stuff now you could say that multiple
inheritance in C++ right is compile time
mixin which is basically saying at
compile time I can compose multiple
things together using modes one here
it's you of those seamless US has no
runtime mixing ability that's why we
implemented ourselves using as for our
sanity system is my way that I'm going
to do that there's other ways right like
I I went over those when I talked about
the annex parse a system I said hey here
is you know how you know here is like
you could keep a list of properties and
you add and remove them at runtime that
sort of thing that make sense
do friend classes count as mix-ins no
four well first of all a mixin to be
clear there's there's two things right
there's compile-time and run-time Frank
classes and unions obviously are
compile-time so they don't have anything
to do with with with a run-time mixin
which is what we actually want
we need runtime mixin like we need to be
able to do runtime combination arbitrary
combinations of types right so no
features of C++ help you they are all
compiled time so they can't do this
right so you have to implement it
yourself using you know things that are
in C++ you need to implement it using
those you can't use some feature of the
language if that makes sense
pulse excavate having to compress the
entities if you use some unions in the
enemy No
and the reason for that is that as soon
as you use unions you lose the ability
to mix in the two things being Union
right so whatever I made a union out of
I now can't have both of those things
happening at once on this entity which
may be you know in a in a real rare case
we might do that when we know there's
literally no way these two things could
happen right but that's almost never
what we want in this game we want to
always have every possible combination
is allowed
Elvan how are you finding for kotas so
far any features you find missing is it
worth getting into coming from Emacs
yeah I like it way better than Emacs
there's a few Emacs features that aren't
in there yet but you know they're coming
and also some of them are just because I
haven't gone and made my for code
accustomed have them yet so some of them
are waiting on me not Allen but
basically like the indentation is a
little buggy that's the biggest problem
right now this problems no macros
indentation is a little buggy and
autocomplete doesn't use nearby to pick
the the matches in that order that's
mostly all I'm missing everything else I
could do in custom code for code across
to myself and for modal which is the way
I'm editing now it's way better than a
mess is Emacs with super buggy and modal
like them just crazy buggy which is why
I switched in the first place cuz it's
you know like it's pretty early in
development for for coders so I mean I
may not have switched this early but but
Emacs was killing me
what do you think of the other more data
oriented entity system implementations
online like a knacks entity X etc I
don't know I've never looked at them it
would probably be something I can't just
search and read quickly I'm guessing but
let's see
I mean the fact that like the number of
semicolons per line appears to approach
eight fairly frequently means there's no
way I would ever even touch this code
with a 12-foot Pole but that doesn't
mean it's necessarily designed poorly or
anything it means it just uses the kinds
of stuff that I find very superfluous
and too much typing necessarily but who
knows maybe it's designed well I'd have
to actually go look at the design and
see right
all right I'm going to wrap it up let's
see here
doo doo doo doo doo doo where is it
there we go thank you everybody for
joining me for an episode another
episode of handmade hero it's what a
pleasure coated with you as always if
you would like to follow along at home
you can always do so if you peer out of
the game on handmade hero or gate comes
the source code so you can follow along
also a forum site you can go to through
- questions a patreon page if you want
support the video series a schedule
about the tweets the schedule at you and
a FSO guide if you're trying to catch up
on old episodes that is it for today I
will be back here next week check the
schedule bot if you want to know when
until then have fun programming and I
will see you on the Internet take it
easy everyone