start recording hello everyone and
welcome to handmade Hero the show where
we code a complete game live on Twitch
and we're in the middle of some grabs
programming right now so you know what
I'm not even gonna explain what we're
doing am I'm gonna say anything I'm just
gonna say if you are someone who wants
to program some graphics you came to the
right place because that is exactly what
we're about to do okay we talked about
Basie's yesterday and we got some trippy
rotating nonsense happening on the
screen because people kept egging me
egging me on to do more weird cosine
sine theta stuff it got a little out of
hand the Q&amp;A it's true but we're back on
track today okay to actually focus on
stuff we actually care about and not
messing around although you know with
graphics programming it's easy to kind
of go off on a little bit of a tangent
there you know it happens it does so I'm
gonna get right into it let me just
mention briefly we're on day 92 so unzip
day 91 source code if you're someone who
pre-ordered the game on handmade hero
org and you you're one of those folks
who'd like to follow along at home unzip
that source code so you'll be where I am
today let's go to the blackboard okay
let us go to the blackboard because the
blackboard is really where the magic
happens first okay because we say what
we're gonna do it's like in pool where
you call your shot you know you're like
you know 9 in the corner pocket or
whatever and you hit it there and it
goes in that's the blackboard
of course there's rarely any bugs when
you do well there are bugs in the pool
you pull table you try to hit it and if
you miss you know it goes somewhere else
right that happens sometimes ignoring
all that let's get down to business here
so what I would like to introduce now to
get take the next step forward because
remember what we're trying to do here is
we want rotation and scaling rotation
and scaling right we already have
something that blitz tough to the screen
but before we do anything to try and
make it faster or do anything like that
we have to make sure that we have the
actual features that we need and
rotation and scaling are features that
we actually want now what do I mean by
that well what I mean by that is our
artists reaction right she draws some
stuff and the stuff looks pretty awesome
right it's like the little dude the hero
or something she draws that in a bitmap
and then that bitmap we have code right
now that will display that bitmap on
screen anywhere we want but it has to be
exactly the same as what she drew okay
there's no it can't we can't do anything
to it right now
literally nothing in fact right so all
we've done is something that basically
does a block copy of some memory to
another location and we've only
implemented one thing right which is
alpha blending right we did implement
alpha blending and that's the thing that
allows us to kind of mask away all of
the stuff in the bitmap that's supposed
to be transparent so that when we blit
it you know stuff can show through like
if there's a tree back here you know it
can show through or whatever right so we
did that and that's good but what we'd
like to be able to do is we'd like to be
able to do various effects on these
things as we've lit them and there are
several that we might find important for
compositing for getting the most out of
the stuff that yangshin draws for us
right and so one of the things that we'd
like to be able to do is we'd like to be
able to scale these things and rotate
them right scaling is useful for a
number of reasons it's useful for
effects like if we want you know let's
say we drew you maybe she draws like
some smoke or something right and we
want that smoke to start tiny and like
get bigger right as it animates or
something that would be scaling right or
maybe we want something like she draws
like some little throwing star weird
thing right and we want it to throw
across the screen but we want it to
rotate as it does so right so we want it
to spin right and so what we'd like to
be able to do is just take art assets in
our art artists make and we'd like to be
able to apply arbitrary rotations and
scales to them and there's other things
that we like to be able to do too like
for example we might want to colorize
these like for example change the colors
from red to green to whatever right
there's other things I don't want to do
they're pixel operations but in terms of
geometric operations on the shape of the
thing we at least want to be able to do
these two things because they're gonna
be important for allowing us to animate
stuff in the way that sort of gets the
most out of our artwork because remember
artwork is expensive right whether it's
in terms of money if you're paying an
artist or time if you are the artist it
takes a long time to draw a good art and
so what you want to always be thinking
about is how can I make programming
things that will get the most bang for
the buck out of the art that I have
because no matter what you do your game
will get better no matter how much money
you have your game will always get
better the better code you have to get
that are on to the screen because you
can always do more with whatever it is
that you had right all right so how do
we do this rotation of scaling
okay well let's start with something
very simple let's start with the first
step of the process okay let's just talk
about what pixels are filled okay
so what we did yesterday is we we
figured out how to you know do simple
bases right where we could sort of say
all right we've got a coordinate system
and we could rotate that coordinate
system and so we made something that was
pretty straightforward that was
basically a thing that would allow us to
draw like little squares right and we
could rotate those squares around okay
and if you remember in fact I'll just go
ahead and run it here why don't I you
know let's just run it let's go nuts you
know what I'm saying let's not why do we
have to why do we have to always be so
serious all the time really you're
people you know you're just bringing me
down let's lighten up a little bit let's
go ahead and run the game all right so
here's this this ridiculousness that we
made there right it was it was totally
crazy and the reason it was totally
crazy is because people kept egging me
on to change stuff in it when we were in
the QA it was relatively sane originally
but then you know it just got out of
hand and so what happened was people
started adding these weird well people
people I did it but you know people were
egging me on like I said so let's let's
clip away all this ridiculousness let's
just just cut it out for now so we can
see the original thing none of this
weird wobbly stuff none of this
craziness right let's let's try to get
back to something reasonable okay
let's just go ahead and get it back to
where it was before we started the
craziness right and now you can see that
it's just oops more thing negative
x-axis dot Y x axis X do we have
everything proper here I think so why
are we still collapsed that's like our
y-axis doesn't actually have a length to
it oh because it's a hundred times right
we don't need do that
it's already scaled there we go so this
was our little coordinate system and you
can kind of see us rotating it around
here right and we put a little 4x4 grid
of points in there so we could see that
they all rotate with it
right and so all this was showing was
how we create a coordinate system that
can rotate in scale right because we can
we can scale it as well right like if I
do that you can see it gets larger right
and if I do that you can see it gets
smaller so we can multiply it by
whatever we want to scale it right but
that only tells us how to work with
points right that tells us how to
compute points on the screen that are
rotated in scale but we don't actually
know how to do like what we want to do
which is take a bitmap right that's
that's you know this rect Lerner bitmap
and rotate that and scale that onto the
screen right and so the very first thing
we're gonna have to do is do something a
little fancier than what we're doing
there right we got to do something
a little fancier because what we need to
know is when we're on the screen right
here's these pixels right this is our
screen with all the pixels on it we we
can't just have something that tells us
okay you know we did some rotation and
scaling you know and here are those
those points right that we that we
wanted to compute we computed the point
so we can rotate and scale them around
right what we actually want to know is
if we were to rotate and scale an entire
rectangle right what would we actually
fill on the screen what are all the
pixels that would actually be included
in that rectangle right you feel me on
that one see where I'm going with that
that's what we need that's our next step
right so essentially what I want to do
today if we can get if we can have
enough time to do it
I want to change this into something
that draws a solid rectangle that's
rotating and scaling right solid because
that's the next step in our process
we're great basically have two steps
right make a solid spinning thing and
then fill it with the correct colors to
make that texture there's a bunch of
other stuff along the way or rather that
come after that to start tighten things
down but that's the basics right so how
we gonna do that well to remember our
collision detector right do remember
collision detection we sort it's well we
sort of started talking about a lot of
the things that we would need to do it
when we were talking about the collision
detection because collision detection
and rendering are actually not that
different they both involve
substantively the same sorts of
operations and specifically pixel
filling has a lot to do with collision
detection because think about what I'm
asking if I think about this pixel as a
point and I say is this pixel something
that I should light up for this scaled
and rotated rectangle well what is that
if not a point inside rotated and scaled
rectangle test which is collision
detection it's saying does this pixel
hit this shape right and so really all
we need to do is extend our collision
detection understanding a little bit
past where we did it and in fact if we
had done the collision detection to
handle rotation we would already know
everything that we need to do but we
have it yet and so you know we got a we
got to start up this is the first time
we'll be into it but we'll be able to go
back to Architecture later and use this
what we've learned here to make it
better right okay
so what I want to suggest to you is that
let's suppose that I just want to know
if a given pixel on the screen given by
let's say it's center point if that
center point falls within a rectangle
and I'll make it easier for you at the
moment I'll simply say well let's
suppose temporarily that you don't even
have to worry about rotation and scaling
I'm letting you off the hook there all
you have to do is for a rectangle that
is aligned with the screen and here
comes my you know pixels or whatever
right there they are for a rectangle
that's aligned with the screen tell me
which of these are in and which are out
right distinguish between these ones
that overlap the shape right here is the
shape and these ones that don't okay now
I hope that after this long and
hand-made here you would all be able to
tell me the answer to that question what
you would say to me is well okay if I
have a minimum X right and I have a
minimum I'm sorry in a maximum X right
and I have a minimum Y and a maximum Y
right like so and again I'm using this
coordinate system for now but it doesn't
matter whichever direction is
doesn't matter if I have those minimums
and maximums right you should be able to
tell me for a given pixel if this is an
x and a y right does that overlap or
doesn't it right how would you do that
test well I hope you would say something
like alright if the X is greater than or
equal to the X minimum right and right
we'd say and and I'll guess I'll write
it in the C++ version here right the X
is less than the X maximum right and
remember we did that sort of inclusion
rule so that things that abut work
properly right if it's greater than or
equal to the minimum meaning it's on
this side of the minimum and it is less
than the maximum it's on that side of
the maximum right then it's in for X and
furthermore I could do the exact same
thing of Y right it's greater than or
equal to the minimum and right less than
the maximum this complete test here
would tell me if a pixel was inside or
not right so for any given pixel I could
just check is it greater than the
minimum bound and less than the maximum
bound for each of my two axes and then I
would know hopefully that makes perfect
sense hopefully that's something that
should be relatively straightforward to
you if you've been watching all of the
episodes if you haven't well go back and
watch them I guess
very very simple stuff right very very
simple so now the question is well you
know what I'll take it one step further
so I could write something that actually
fills all you know these pixels for a
rectangle that is not rotated and scaled
right I could write something by just
iterating over all pixels on the screen
right all of them and doing this test
right that would feel
so you may say that's very inefficient
well you're right it is inefficient
because we'd be testing all the pixels
even though we don't need to right but
we could make it much more efficient by
just doing all the pixels you know in
some conservative bound right right we
could say well we know that the
rectangle is roughly in this region of
the screen so we'll just iterate over
those pixels and then our wastage would
be very small right and furthermore
because it's a aligned rectangle we
could even go well okay we actually know
exactly what pixels it fills so we'll
just only iterate over those pixels and
then this test would not be necessary
right and that's the routine we actually
wrote right that's the routine that we
wrote before when we did draw rectangle
what we did is we just we did all of
that checking and decided to only loop
over the pixels where we knew the test
was already true but we didn't have to
do that right if we couldn't have
produced that minimal bound we could
have just iterated over some wider set
of pixels a little bit more than we
needed to write or even the whole screen
if we wanted to and inside this loop
check to see whether x and y were inside
and only colored the ones that we showed
up right we could have done that and in
fact let's do it mm-hmm let's just prove
that that's true right I'm gonna take
this thing this coordinate system call
that we've got here and this is just
gonna be our little plaything because
since it's not something we actually
ever need to use let's actually write a
function that literally does draw a
rectangle but it does draw a rectangle
in the least efficient way possible okay
so here's our draw rectangle we'll call
it draw a rectangle slowly let's say
here's our buffer here's our min and Max
and here's our colors it takes the exact
same parameters as the other one and off
we go
we start off with exactly the same loop
and we say okay we're gonna start at the
buffer memory and instead of advancing
it to the min X in the mid why we're not
gonna we're just gonna start right there
and we're going to go through every last
pixel
on the screen makes sense so here we go
we've got our our buffer we're gonna go
I forget what these are actually called
I think they're width and height oops
that supposed to be height
there's whip and so I'm not going to try
at all to do anything smart here right
I'm not going to try to to to call or
anything I'm literally just gonna say in
here for every pixel I'm gonna test to
see whether it's inside or outside using
exactly the thing I just ripped X should
be greater than equal to my my minimum
coordinate right and it should be less
than my maximum coordinate on X and then
the exact same thing should be true for
my Y coordinates right my Y should also
be in range if it is in range I will set
the color of the pixel that we're on if
it is not I will leave it alone okay so
very very straightforward oops I've got
it still build that color like doing
this much down here so there we go
and why not I'll make this a v4 since we
previously we now have that capability
I'll just go ahead and and put in that's
this routines a little more modern right
okay
this will be our color 32 so that draws
rectangles extremely slowly right and if
I want to I can take that coordinate
system thing that we did before right
where we do the y axis and all that sort
of stuff
when we go to draw one of those instead
of drawing the weird grid pattern stuff
that we did there well you know what
I'll still draw it right but instead
what I'll do is I'll just draw a
rectangle that's at that location and
I'll use the X and the y axes to kind of
to move out to to compute that Batman in
the max right so what I'll say is we'll
do draw a rectangle slowly we know what
the color is we'll turn this off don't
need that now we'll turn we'll turn that
off so what we want to do is say okay
we're gonna draw from the origin
right and we're gonna draw from the
origin to the that mid in the max right
so we're gonna say entry origin plus
entry x axis plus entry y axis and
that's going to be our maximum okay and
so we just need to pass it the output
target we need to pass it the color and
then we should be good to go and of
course let me see I don't know if I
forgot anything there or not let's see
so aperture get entry origin I need to
add the entry origin there we go because
I need the minimum and the maximum so
that should do it right so in theory I
believe well there's one thing that we
didn't quite do there so I got to stop
it rotating first because when it
rotates we're not actually taking the
min and the max so I gotta make it so
it's actually stable if that makes sense
so I can't you got to make sure that our
angle for at the moment is not gonna be
anything it's just gonna stay stationary
there we go and so I think that's too
large so I feel like our axes where our
axes getting scaled somehow here because
it shouldn't be I maybe I've got a bug
in my draw a rectangle slowly it should
be only filling a smaller region than
that if X is less than V Max X y la
pixel equals Rho that looks correct to
me V min X V min Y V Max X V max why the
X's and the Y's look right there our
axes should be pointing straight up and
down so that should be fine as well so
yeah
not seeing why that's wrong hold on one
second sorry it's important to get this
part right because that way we won't
have to deal with it in the end the
other one there so if I add the x-axis I
go over an X if I add the wax I go up
that should have given us a valid
minimum location there and in fact what
I could do to I would like to do this
just so we can see them I'm gonna draw
these after the fact like this I'm gonna
draw these in a in a different color so
I'm gonna draw these in some kind of
color that's it's a little bit easier
for us to distinguish from the one that
the other things drawing in so we're
just going to go ahead and do this so I
want to be able to see those points on
top of the rectangle there we go okay so
that is where we are in pixel space and
for some reason our rectangle is not
properly clipping to its max bounds of
course I don't actually know for sure
that the max is where the max says it is
so I do also want to just quickly make
sure that I've got that so I'm gonna do
a thing here where we just draw that max
in that max location like so the max I
guess so I'm gonna compute that by
saying V Max here it is so that way I
can see where it is and make sure that
it's not an incorrect value yeah so it's
not my V Max computation is somehow
incorrect oh because I added it twice
why it's a typo dated it there it is all
right that should have worked the first
time but we were passing the wrong
parameter so yeah all right it's a typo
day what can I say all right so back to
the point at hand now that we actually
have this you can notice that this fills
the rectangle correctly right we have
the rectangle there and we you know
we're not doing it an efficient way cuz
we're filling the entire screen but it's
okay in terms of correctness right we're
filling the rectangle that we want to
fill by just doing a pass over the
entire screen and you can see draw a
rectangle slowly here
it checks every pixel and just sees
which of them are inside right which of
those are inside the the pixel right and
so what I could do again like I said is
I could say you know what I'm going to
restrict the area that you march over to
something smaller than that right and
then we would just restrict these to
something smaller and we would only test
a fewer number of pixels we could go all
the way to only testing the ones that we
need to test which means you don't test
at all but same deal right all right so
that's all good and so you may ask all
right how does that help us do our
rotation and scaling right how does that
help at all we're basically just back
where we started only were much slower
well the answer is these right here
think about what these are doing okay
what are these ands what are we actually
computing what we're saying is for any
given pixel on the screen we are making
sure that the result of a series of four
edge tests all comes back stating that
we were on the inside of whatever that
edges right we are first testing its
x-men and saying we want to make sure
that we are on this side of that edge
right or on it that's the case maybe for
X max we're saying the same thing we
want to make sure that we're on this
side of that edge right same with y-min
and y-max right same with y-min and
y-max so the question is now well if we
wanted to rotate this couldn't we just
do the same thing right
can't we just test against four corners
of our rectangle and if they all come
back true we know we're inside the
answer is absolutely we can so instead
of thinking about it this way let's just
change this to a slightly different
format let's say is inside right or abet
better yet let's just say edge test
right you know and we'll take that first
one right so we'll you know we'll take
whatever this is this is 0 this is 1
this is 2 this is 3 we have you know 4
edges to test against right edge test 0
we want edge test zero to come out true
we
edge test right one to come out true we
want edge test two to come out true and
we want edge test three to come out true
right we want all the edge tests to come
out true and if they all come out true
we assume that we are inside ok so all
we would need to fill a rotated and
scaled one is some way of producing an
edge test for our rotated and scaled our
rotated and scaled rectangle now before
we get to any fancy this year I'm gonna
show you how you could have done that
without my help if you have watched all
of handmade hero you already know the
answer to this question okay let's make
the construction here is that basis of
our rectangle here is the one of the
points right here is another one of the
points and here is the final point okay
right so I want to test against these
four edges well I only need to make code
that test against one edge and then I
can call it four times right so we're
only looking at one problem here and
that problem is given one edge let's say
this edge right here right so I've got
p0 and p1 right or I could think of it
as having the actual edge there in fact
maybe we do that
I've got p0 and in this case this was my
x-axis right I'm sorry that would be the
y-axis what am I so I seem to do that a
lot here I mix up the excess of the Y's
all right so this is that origin right
this is the origin and this is the
x-axis right and I want to test to see
whether on this side of it how would I
do that
so I told you already about the
perpendicular operator right so it would
be free for me if I wanted to for
example to produce a vector
perpendicular to the x-axis now it turns
out that I don't even really need to do
that right because we know that the y
axis is perpendicular to the x axis
correct so we know that this vector here
are perpendicular to the x axis we know
that that's just the y axis we already
had it right very very straightforward
so if I wanted to know if a point
somewhere in the world was on this side
of it how would I do that
anyway now remember we've already done
everything you would need to be able to
do this to answer this question we've
done it on handmade hero so the answer
is the dot product right the dot product
the inner product we covered it that is
the all that we would really need to do
this right
because if we have this vector right if
we could take P and subtract the origin
from it we end up in the exact classic
dot product scenario we have a base we
have two vectors we have the one that
goes to P and then we have the edge that
we're testing against right we have its
perpendicular which is the perpendicular
to the edge right here all we need to
know if we want to know which side of
this edge P is on is take its
perpendicular and do the dot product if
that dot product again that map's P onto
here it tells us how far along this we
would go if that dot product is positive
we know that we were on this side of the
edge if it is negative we know that P
was over here so the sign of that dot
product will tell us which side of the
edge we are on and it's trivial for us
to compute it's just inner product right
of P minus the origin it's just the
inner product of that with our
perpendicular right in our perpendicular
in this case we already know it is we
don't ever have to compute them if it's
the if we're testing against this x-axis
we know that it's gonna be the y-axis
we're testing against this upper limit
to the x-axis we know it's the negative
y-axis right so on and so forth so it's
really really simple this is the entire
edge test that we would need that's the
only thing we would need to do to
determine whether or not a pixel was in
we just do that four times we do that
four times and we're done right and all
we need to do is check the sign of it we
don't even need to know what its
magnitude is we don't need to compute
anything other than was it going to be
positive or negative and we just want to
see if it's positive that's
so the edge test is just is it greater
than zero and we could flip it we can
choose which way we want we can we can
choose whether we want these normals to
point in or out right we can choose
whether which way we want to frame it
right because we could speak instead use
the negative y-axis there right we could
do we can do whatever you want there so
let's just implement one of these as an
example right let's just implement one
of these okay so here we go let's
suppose that I start this rotating again
right it's not rotating right now
I started rotating again and now we got
a situation that's kind of nasty which
is basically that we only actually are
able to fill our rectangle you know in
this kind of lame way right because it's
really just filling it to whatever this
point is here it's trying to fill a
rectangle between these two points so
when this point is in the positive
direction it works and at other times it
doesn't because our edge tests all fail
right so all we need to do now is change
from those bad edge tests that were just
totally for rectilinear ones all we need
to do is change it to using edge tests
that are actually based on the four
points that we actually have right and
we could do them for arbitrary for four
points actually if you want to but I'm
gonna do them for the rectilinear ones
because that's all we actually care
about since we're not gonna be filling
arbitrary shapes and hammer here we just
need to blitt you know rectilinear
bitmaps all right so how do we do that
off we go let's go back to our draw
rectangle slowly so here is our V min so
what we want to do now is change this
draw rectangle slowly to actually take
maybe all the things right so we've got
our origin we've got our x-axis we've
got our y-axis right and now we want to
go ahead and fill that now we could just
quickly verify that that stuff's getting
passed correctly if we wanted to we
could go ahead and say that we're going
to compute V min from these right
there's our V min there's our V Max
origin plus x axis plus y axis like so
like that and then we go down to draw a
rectangle slowly oops
rectangle slowly rectangle slowly and
instead here when we pass that we will
actually pass entry x axis entry y axis
right and then that color and now we
should see in fear
exactly the same thing happen right
meaning can't feel anything until that
comes down to the positive they could
fill and then it goes away all right
exactly what we would expected so back
up to draw a rectangle slowly here we go
when we are drawing the rectangle slowly
we now need to say let's test these
edges as they actually were using the
edge test that I just described all
right so first off we need to test you
know we need to test each of them and so
I'm just going to actually record here
what the edge functions were so they can
see it in a little more detail right so
I'm gonna do an edge zero
you know edge one edge two right edge
three like so and then like I said all
we need to do is test that all of the
edges are actually in and so what I
could do here is I could I could
actually sort of do a version of this
right I could do I could do the version
of this that is the same as what we're
doing now because if you think about it
these are sort of like dot products
right this is like saying well I'm just
taking the x Gordon don't need to dot it
with the x-axis because I'm with the
with the the X X because I already have
it right I already have what its value
is so I'm just testing it against the
min right I could phrase that
differently by saying I just want to
know if the X minus the X men right is
positive right that's like doing that
sort of rebasing
putting it around I'll be I'll be a
hundred percent explicit here just so
you can see what I'm saying right we can
rephrase these edge tests even in the
rectilinear case to be much closer than
to what we expect by saying ok before we
had an X min right and we had an X right
and we wanted to know well was it on
this side so what we're doing is we were
just writing the test explicitly we were
saying we want X to be greater than or
equal to X men but that is the same
thing as actually doing the dot product
effectively right it's the same thing as
saying all right take X and subtract X
min from it you will now get a positive
or a negative value that tells us which
side we are on right and then we can
test to see whether it's greater than or
equal to
right so we could have phrased it the
other way we just didn't because it was
so simple we didn't need to so we can
turn it around in a slightly different
way we could we could do it this way and
say all right
we want X minus V men then we want X
minus V Max dot X we want that to be
less than zero we want Y minus V men
sees in there we want Y minus V men to
be greater than zero and we want Y minus
y max to be less than zero right again
same exact thing happening all I've done
here is just change those into stuff
that looks right like this I did the P
minus origin and then I did the dot
product with the perpendicular doesn't
need to happen because they're already
in the perpendicular coordinates right x
and y we're not rotated at all so we
don't actually need to do this part but
this part we had to do right so that's
all I did right here I did it now what
you'll notice as well is because we're
not doing the dot product the sign
doesn't flip right and so that's why
these are different comparisons here
right what would normally be happening
is we'd be testing against normals that
we're in different directions right
those perpendiculars would be pointing
in different directions so we could
always test greater than or less than
right but we're not doing anyone here so
it doesn't actually reverse it if that
makes sense
so that's why we have to do the
different ones there but we can easily
go ahead and sort of fool that right
what we can do is say all right let's
suppose we want to make greater than B
our standard so everything's always
going to be greater than greater than
greater than greater than right like so
so I want to change all these so if I do
edge 0 H 1 H 2 X 3 I want them all to
just be using the same comparison right
I want them all to be using like that
comparison let's say or something right
so they're greater than and maybe you
know what it probably makes more sense
to think of these as pointing outwards
you know because that's the way you
normally think of surface
most pointing we'll get to that sort of
stuff a little bit later but let's make
them point outwards so let's say that we
want positive means you're outside the
shape negative means are inside the
shape let's just use that as our
convention right so I want all of my
edge functions to actually be negative I
want them all to be negative and so in
order to do that I have to reverse the
sense of some of these right every other
one that the edge one and the edge three
are going to be wrong because they were
based or you know they're going to be
the opposite of the other two right so
in this case X minus X min X I want that
to actually be a reverse test because
before that was giving me a positive
answer on one side of X a negative
answer on the wrong side right and so I
need to flip the sense of that so again
it's just a simple negation I just flip
it same thing true of 'man Y right and
the other ones were already producing
negative values when they were on the
correct side of the edge so those are
just fine right and so this gives us
again the exact same results as we had
before but we're one step closer we're
one step closer right so there we go
we're super close all we have to do now
is is lever up one more time and
actually get the dot product in there
right because remember I said we want
inner product right we've got our inner
product we want to do our inner product
after doing the rebasing okay so let's
do that so here's our forage and
subtraction right reversing it back to
the same way it was and now we just have
to make synthetic edge values right
things that point in those directions
okay so we've got our V min right that's
here's our here's our X min right so the
edge that we want we said we want
pointing outwards right so I'll clear
the diagram so we can be completely
clean
we want our edges are perpendicular
pointing outwards right so here we are
in the minimum what is that vector right
well that vector is pretty simple it's
just negative one zero correct pretty
simple the one for the for the x max is
just one zero right same thing here
right we've just got this as negative
one zero
oops this is zero negative 1 and this is
0 1 right so are we
it's totally trivial what those those
Edge's actually are we are perpendicular
actually are we could just read them
straight off the diagram okay so at zero
again I said was negative one zero the
the max version was one zero right
again minimum here for Y and maximum for
Y okay oops
and of course in this particular case we
have the we have the the problem that
the inner is going to do the full dot
product so I really need to do
essentially like okay I've got my pixel
P right and it's the XY coordinate of
that pixel right and I need to then say
okay it's it's technically it's time
they're going to be the pixel P minus
you know the vmon pixel P minus the V
Max to do that full sort of vector
subtraction right the pixel P minus the
DMX so again they're just producing one
that's based off of whatever that
location is so for example when we want
to do this one we have to subtract
whatever the point is from this because
that is what we're testing against right
so there we go
almost there we go there we go now we're
actually doing the full test right
you'll notice we got a lot slower
because it's doing a ton more operations
for every pixel on the screen it's gonna
get worse before it gets better people
we're we're gonna be super slow for a
little while before we get it before we
get better but you can see that it's
still doing the same thing now but it's
doing those edge tests right and then
finally all I have to do is now actually
change these edge tests to using actual
edges of the rotated thing which again
hopefully you've seen is pretty
straightforward there's not a whole lot
that we will have to do there to do that
so let's just go ahead and create those
we have the x-axis and the y-axis so
let's think about what these would be
here is my x-axis here is my y-axis so
if I want to test against this first
edge we'll treat this as our first edge
actually let's treat this as our first
edge because I keep saying X X's and Y's
backwards
time so let's let's try and try and not
say X's and Y's loggers I'll do my best
so cures our origin right so what I can
do now is just say ok the pixel the
pixel this stuff here this V min V Max
we're just gonna rid up there's no more
V min and V Max so now we're just going
to use the the origin x-axis and y-axis
stuff alright so the first thing we need
to do is say ok where's my blackboard
let's test against this edge here so
that's the x-axis it's going from the
origin to like the one you know along
the bottom right in our case it's the
top because that screen coordinate
systems actually flipped but it doesn't
matter it doesn't any space this all
this math still works no matter what the
space is right so we have the origin we
have the x-axis is running across here
what we want to do is say is it on the
correct side of this right so we want to
use the negative y-axis would be the
perpendicular right the negative y-axis
so our first test is going to be against
the negative y-axis that dot product
right and we're gonna use the origin as
our basis because that is a point that
runs through this edge so we can again
make sure that we put P in the same
space to test which side it's on right
so we just say P minus the origin that's
our first test ok next we'll test
against this guy right here now this
base point to do that test that's going
to be the origin plus the x-axis right
so we actually need to do the origin
plus the x-axis for the base point that
we're going to test off of okay and then
we need to say which is the axis that
we're going to test well we want it
pointing outwards that's the x-axis that
points in that direction right so that's
just the x-axis all right
next we'll do this guy ok and so that's
you know that's that v-max
point that we're based off of there
essentially I'm just going around this
counterclockwise force of habit
as a graphics programmer so the test of
the axis is going to be the y-axis there
right so that's going to be the wax test
and the point that we're on is going to
be just the origin plus the X and the
y-axis right so there's origin plus the
x axis plus the y axis
we're on and then finally our final edge
coming down right is going to be this
which is just you know the origin plus
the x-axis
I'm sorry plus the y-axis and you can
tell which one is going to be because we
haven't used it yet that's gonna be the
negative x-axis right is pointing out in
that direction okay so there we go
now if I could compile that you will now
notice that without actually really
changing anything about what we were
doing just following it step by step we
are now filling a rectangle right and
we're filling the rectangle with
rotation and scaling just fine we can do
anything we want to that and it would
just go ahead and work right you can see
it rotating there but if I wanted to I
could go ahead and introduce some
scaling to it right mm-hmm by just going
back to that code let's see here I made
a few yeah here we are
if I wanted to introduce some scaling to
it again I could I could do sort of the
same thing that we were doing yesterday
by just saying let's put in some notion
of a change in scale that happens over
time and you can see that that works
fine right now again we're very slow
right now because we're not doing
anything we're not even compiling with
optimizations on so we're like the
slowest we could possibly be we're
filling all the pixel off screen so what
we might want to do is say well okay
let's at least we can do a little bit
better than that without actually it
would you know just algorithmically we
can do something smarter there right
because what we could do is we could say
well we know very trivially that the
only pixels that could possibly be
involved in this right are bounded by
the by the minimum and maximum x and y
values of those points right I mean if I
come in here and I have some rotated
shape right and so it's got four points
right well I know that no pixels outside
of this right this this oriented
rectangle right if I just take the
minimum and maximum of all the points I
would end up having all the pictures
that could possibly filled so I could
restrict my choice of pixels to just
those and then we wouldn't have to fill
the whole screen
we'd feel a much smaller region so
that's a good first step to to what we
should do so let's let's just go ahead
and do that right that's that's you know
very very simple for us to do so in this
render group here right I'm just going
to introduce the same things we had
before right I've got a I got an int Y
min and in Y Max and in X Men and an int
X Max right I've got those and all I'm
going to do here is first I'm going to
set them to be exactly what they were
before right Y min Y max so X min x max
but I am going to change to saying that
we will actually consider whatever that
max actually is right so we'll go will
actually test all of them because now
our inclusion and exclusion is going to
be based on these tests not on this this
is just pixel coverage right and so I'm
going to say all right oops
yeah buffer weight and so that's all the
pixels on the screen again so if I
compile this we get the same result and
it's still quite slow but what I can do
now is I can say all right let's go
ahead and introduce something that
actually tries to get the min and the
max out of this right so I've got four
points essentially that I could have
four minimums and maximums right so I've
got essentially four points that are the
the you know the points of this weird
rotated shape
I've got the origin I've got the origin
plus the x-axis about the origin plus
the x-axis and the y-axis right and I've
got the origin plus the y-axis right so
I've got four points so what I'd like to
do is just loop through those points and
I'd like to go ahead and take sort of I
like to shrink it down so that they sort
of fit around that guy right so what I'm
going to do is say all right let's say
we loop over these int P index equals 0
P index is less than an array count p
plus plus index right and what I'm gonna
do is going to take that P
like a test point out of it the index
and I'm going to say all right I want to
now take the the Y min the Y max all
those guys I'm going to say if I well
you know what I'll do first I don't
actually need to do that we'll do int px
and py and these are just going to be
the floors and ceilings of those values
numerically right I have a floating
point value I want to see what its
closest real value is right so I believe
we have these in our in our handmade
intrinsics right we've got floor yeah
conceal so here's our floor and our
ceiling
so we'll do our p RP xf i guess or will
do will do floor something like that
floor x CL x that seems good so yeah
that seems like the right thing to do so
B 2 P equals P P index sorry getting a
little tripped up here all right so
there's my floor X and my CL X I'm gonna
take the 10 minutes that I started late
because we're right we're right at
finishing this part up so we might as
well so there's the seal and then I've
got same things happening in Y like so
and so now that I've got those this is
sort of like the min X the max X and
that sort of thing
for this guy right so this is the test
min X and the test max X and so on that
this guy would represent and so all I
have to do now and in fact I don't
really have to take this the the floor
and seal in that way I could just say
that the ceiling of why is the floor Y
plus 1 right because we know that
they're on either side of each other but
I'll leave it that way for now so now
all I have to do is say well if the Y
minimum right if the minimum Y we've
seen is actually greater than that floor
Y right then I want to assign them right
I want to take I want to accept the new
floor Y as my minimum right and again
all I'm doing is just again gathering up
sort of the the minimum and maximum so
that we know what we actually need to
test against and similarly I'll expand
the
some to go ahead and and you know
encompass that whole area right so seal
why seal X like so right and so that'll
that'll actually grab those and then all
I have to do is actually go ahead and
make this excuse me
start out the opposite way right like so
so now we're starting essentially as big
as possible right we're starting with
I'm sorry we're starting with nothing
included right and we're just kind of
moving the x-men back and moving the the
xmax back as far as possible now this
could still produce things that were off
the screen so at the end we do have to
clamp them we have to say if the x-men
you know you know I should probably do
you know I should probably do some kind
of a width thing here like like with
masks or something like that max I don't
know whit max something like that tight
max just these values so I don't keep
half left - one right it's like the
inclusive version so that's with Max and
that's height max and yeah and so all I
really have to do now is just finish
clipping those so I say if X min is less
than zero
you know then X min equals 0 if Y min is
less than zero then Y min equals zero if
X max is greater than with Max then X
min oops sorry x max X max equals with
Max and the same is true for Y type max
right max right and these are lower seal
there we go
all right uh-oh
but of course that didn't quite work
hold on one second I have to we're
almost done
just got to fix a couple of things first
so mm-hmm
just double-checking we've got our with
max and our height max I want to do
something quickly which is just to not
test the edges I'm just gonna always
Phil right so instead of this I'm just
gonna always Phil so we can see where
our bounding region is so I'm gonna say
all right everywhere in the bounty
region that we use we are going to fill
and then now we can test our boundaries
so we start x-min off at the maximum
possible value it could be and then as
we step through each of these points in
our index we floor them so that we baste
and seal them so that we know what their
floor and ceiling values are we then go
ahead and say if the xmin that we
currently have is greater than whatever
the floor is then we are going to accept
the new floor value and then that will
basically keep moving X min down as we
go
same with Y min so as we you know find
lower Wyman's we accept lower Wyman's
right and then similarly if the x max is
ever less than whatever the ceiling was
we accept that oops
and there's our typo knew there was
going to be one and so there we go
although why are we still up in the
corner we're getting our range Oh
because now right now we have to restore
our buffer pre step rank because we have
an actual min X and min Y so we're going
to have to do this again to step to the
correct location so there we go there's
our X Men oops
there's our X Men and there's our Y min
right and now you can see we are
correctly picking the rectangle to test
and so now if we reenable our test we
get our correctly filled guy and it's
you know it's still not a fast fill but
it's much faster than it was now we have
a ton of stuff still left to talk
we are not home free but again like I
said I'm out of time we're now just
about running into where I won hours
worth of code we've got a bunch stuff to
talk about like sub-pixel stuff and what
pixel centers are and a bunch of other
things about sort of finicky stuff in
there and there's a bunch of things that
we also didn't talk about we can we can
go in and simplify a lot of these like
we don't need to do these expressions
exactly we did them but I'd like to go
ahead and wait we'll we'll pick back up
here tomorrow and clean a bunch of this
stuff up as we move towards actually
getting our full flitting working so
there you go let's go and go to the Q &amp;
A like so and I will you know I will
start taking questions now please prefix
your questions with Q : and ply it
please try to keep them to what we're
doing if you want to ask off-topic
question stuff like that please come
back before the stream starts because
that's really the best time to do that
sort of stuff we I tend to skip anything
that's off topic during this so we can
concentrate on just questions about what
we're working on
do you Seven Samurai what are your
computer specs so this computer is super
old but at the time it was like a fancy
Xeon so it's kind of a little bit tricky
to talk about its performance because
it's not the kind of performance that
you would get on on 'men of those things
right where you're you're kind of you're
kind of in an unusual scenario like most
users don't have Zeon's right so it's a
w55 80 which and I think it's so it's
about five years old I think maybe six
years old it's about five or six years
old so Triola processor but at the time
it was a Xeon so it's got like a bigger
cache than most things do and so on so
it's not probably as fast as most of the
computers that people are probably
following handmade hero on but either
way like like I said we haven't we're
not really dealing with performance yet
so you know any any computer probably
can do what we're doing here though
because even even though we're doing it
super inefficiently it's it's just not
much to do right just one little
rectangle so
is it weird that I got really excited
once the rotated fill got faster no that
probably just means you should be an
optimizer guy right if you're not
already that means you'll be kind of
excited as we do our performance stuff I
guess
I mean basically getting excited when
stuff like this happens is what
determines whether probably you're going
to be a good programmer because if
you're not excited about this sort of
stuff you probably don't really want to
be shouldn't be a programmer right you
should do something else because you
want to do stuff that you're excited
about the little things about it right
that's what makes you know I'm assuming
what makes a great basketball player I
mean besides physical build or whatever
right and programmed that too you got to
be you know have a good brain for it or
whatever right but what determines that
you're gonna go do that thing it's like
you're gonna be great Bassel player if
you love the feel of shooting a basket
right because you're gonna sit there and
do it all the time and earn it really
good and so yeah I mean that's that's
kind of how that works which skewing the
axes still work yeah yet wood so if you
wanted to skew the axes that probably
would still work because it's long well
so no if we wanted to skew the axes we
couldn't take the shortcut that I took
which is using the axes as the perps you
would have to actually compute the perps
because because if we skew the axes then
they will no longer be perpendicular to
each other I'll show you what happens if
you do it but it would be really trivial
to support it you just actually compute
the perp right so if you skewed the axes
Janee skewing the axes was was this
right y-axis equals you know cosine
angle plus something that wasn't 90
right
and so can you kind of see what's
happening there do you see how that's
going you get this kind of I'll try to
skew the axes even a little more maybe
than they were before
so it's a little more pronounced that
effect do you see what's happening there
you you end up in this situation where
basically like that that perpendicular
is not perpendicular anymore so you're
not actually getting the proper test if
you wanted that to work though it's not
that big of a deal we can go in and add
a more proper perpendicular right so to
do a proper perpendicular I already
showed you how to do that and I said
there's even let's add a perp operator
right here right and so so let's let's
do that I mean that's that's not so I
don't mind doing that in the Q&amp;A because
I already explained it all in a
different one so let's do that right
let's do perp x-axis right like that
and so in handmade math right dot H in
here I can just add one of those that's
an easy v2 operation that's just in line
v2 perp v2 a and in here we just have
literally just that result right it's
just v2 equals whatever the negative
thing is like that right there's that
perp makes sense so you know if we if we
did that then if we do this here we can
we've actually added the perp operator
oops
e to result
there we go so mm-hmm
once we have that perp we can go ahead
and tackle this guy a little bit better
which is that in here now instead of
doing this we would actually always use
the perpendicular of the other axis so
we would essentially say okay this we
don't actually want the negative x-axis
what we want is the negative perp of the
x-axis right we don't want the native
black so you want the negative purpose
the x-axis we don't actually want the
x-axis here what we want is the perp of
the y-axis right you don't actually want
the waxes here we want the perk of the
x-axis we don't actually want the
negative axis here we want the perp of
the y-axis negative right mm-hmm and in
theory that should work although is this
gonna be backwards I got to think about
that so let's let's think about well the
fact that's not feeling suggested to
this so let's just double check okay so
what we want here right is we've got
this is the origin this is the x-axis
point when we step out to it and so what
we want here is we want the perp of the
x-axis right which is going to go this
direction so we want the negative of
that negative perp x-axis that's correct
we then are here going this way on that
y-axis so we want to test that which is
going to be so the perp of this is going
to be pointing that way so it's the
negative perp of the y-axis right so
it's actually that right and then we go
this way we want the thing pointing that
way so that's going to be again for that
x-axis that's just going to be the perp
of the x axis so we just yet so so it's
a negative y-axis nativist that's just
that so that's that's the way that it
would be right and so once you do that
it'll work just fine so you can't take
the shortcut that I took before but but
if you if you don't take that shortcut
and and really so you know I'll I'll put
the Jews in here so we don't forget but
this is what I was going to do next
anyway perp dot products a perp inner
simpler origin calyx
he's downscaling bitmaps correctly
correctly slower than Oh is down
something bitmaps correctly slower than
upscaling
more color points to blend well it
depends what your it depends how the
answer in general is yes but it may not
be as yes as you think so the answer is
that typically nobody down scales
bitmaps more than 2x what they do
instead is they use mipmapping so
typically and we'll be doing this on the
stream although I don't know that will
actually need MIT maps but we'll be
doing the down sampling part so
typically what happens is this right so
let's say I want to down sample this
bitmap right so I want to make it
smaller and what I want to do is I want
to take this this block right and I want
it to become a single pixel so I've got
you know something like this right and
so on and I'm doing a 2x scale on the
two axes so basically these four right
map to here so this a actually takes its
values from all of these things right so
what I need to do there is I need to
sample four pixels right and I need to
produce I need to average them together
or do some other filter to get that a
that's a very simple it's called a box
filter right so that would be down
sampling right now if I was up sampling
I have to do the exact same thing right
to up sample what I need to do is I need
to again sample these but instead now
I'm producing many A's from it right so
instead now this is going to let's say
I'm up sampling by two right well now I
need to produce this region and so the a
is all fill falling here and what I do
is exactly the same thing right I to
compute this a or maybe this one's a
better example to compute this a right I
need to get all four of these and then
compute the sort of a weighted blend
between them that produces that sort of
you know oh it's a little bit more
towards this guy than the other four
right
that kind of thing right so up sampling
and down sampling are exactly as
expensive when you're only talking about
between you know 0.5 X and 2x they're
doing exactly the same thing the problem
comes when you have a greater than 2x
factor of shrinkage right so you're
doing like 0.25 X or something right but
the way that video cards and everyone
else do this to get around that problem
of well okay if I wanted to down sample
like this you know this thing and I'm
down something to just one pixel so I
got to do the whole map I want to down
sample to one pixel it's a super tiny
stretch right I've got to read all these
guys and produce this one pixel right or
something like that
that may seem like a lot of work but it
isn't because what they end up doing is
they just create MIT Maps which are pre
filtered versions so for every bitmap
let's say you have a 256 by 256 bitmap
right
they actually pre compute a 128 by 128
right then a 64 by 64 then a 32 by 32
then a 16 by 16 then an 8 by 8 then a 4
by 4 then a 2 by 2 and then a 1 by 1 and
what they do is they say how far down am
i scaling this if I'm scaling it from
its normal size all the way down to say
30 by 30 I will pull from the the mipmap
that is close to that the 32 so that I
know I'm still only sampling 4 pixels
for any pixel that I draw right I don't
have to sample some giant region like of
this thing I'm just sampling one little
4x4 and what the reason I say that it's
still more expensive is because
typically what you do is called
trilinear filtering here and what
trilinear filtering does is it samples
from both the next highest and next
lowest so they get samples for texels
from each of these to produce this guy
and blends the result together and the
reason for that is to prevent any
noticeable popping as you transition
between them
eventually will you implement
anti-aliasing into the rendering of the
rectangle or is that too much for the
CPU actually so the answer is yes we
will be implementing it but no we don't
actually need anti-aliasing of the
rectangle I don't want to explain why
quite yet but the reason is because
since we are pulling from alpha bitmaps
it turns out that will get anti-aliasing
for free so we don't have to use multi
sampling if you are actually drawing
actual shapes whose edges are visible
that's when you have to worry about that
anti-aliasing and just to be a little
more concrete on that what I mean is to
say here is if we are bleeding a bitmap
that has a border of 0 alpha around it
we get anti-aliasing for free as part of
our texture sampling our texture
sampling actually handles this for us
texture sampling handles the
anti-aliasing and we'll show how that
happens when we go there but if we were
actually drawing shapes so if we were
actually drawing a solid rectangle that
didn't have any alpha then we don't have
that texture sampling to save us and
that's why graphics cards have things
like MSAA or you know multi sampling
right it is not to anti-alias bitmaps
you never need MSA or any of that stuff
to anti-alias bitmap blitz that have
alpha in them what you need it for is
the edges so MSA and that stuff only
actually works on the edges of things
it's the only place you actually need it
to do stuff and so the way that that
works is it takes many samples inside a
pixel of the edges that pass through
them right and then uses that to sort of
smooth that edge but we don't have any
edges because we are always bleeding
bitmaps that have a contour that's
defined in the Alpha Channel so we don't
ever have to do this so fast or no we
just don't have to care we are going to
be doing this texture sampling because
we need that for quality and so the
anti-aliasing will just be baked into
that and we'll get it for free which is
nice none of what I just said would have
been true if we were rendering 3d shapes
that had contour is defined by polygons
right then that's that's when this comes
in and we're fortunate that we're not
doing that because yeah that that would
be a whole thing that the CPU would have
to do all right no more questions
it's a pretty hilarious little shape we
made there believe it or not you know I
mean what has it been two days or
something believe it or not we are just
not far
like from having rotated and scaled
bitmaps
in fact like we're we might even have
them tomorrow it depends on what order
we tend to we do things like I might
show you how to get the rotated scale
bitmap first but it's kind of janky and
then we'll go back and do a pass over
all of the math to show like okay how do
we make sure we're always some pixel
accurate how do we make sure where this
how many make sure were that but like I
said this stuff ain't that hard once you
kind of know how to do it it's actually
real simple it's just building up all
this knowledge of like how all these
things work and like having them
introduced to you in a reasonable way is
most is most of it once you actually see
it you're like oh like I mean you saw
what I did it was not that complicated
it was not that much complicated much
more company than just filling a
rectangle that was aligned with the
screen right real simple all you have to
do is just make that small step of like
okay let me define some other edges and
there we go now again it keeps layering
on top of each other and would you have
known to do all that stuff if it wasn't
for 30 years or 40 years of graphics
researchers figuring stuff out no right
but they have figured it all out
and so the nice thing is we can just
kind of keep you know leveraging all of
their work to very quickly go okay
here's how we do it we're good to go
Garlan doubloon historically did we ever
do anti-aliasing with CPU rendering well
that is a very good question and I don't
know the answer to it I mean obviously
we've done anti aliasing and CP
rendering for some definition for a
certain problem that means right but if
you're talking about game software
rendering of 3d stuff I don't know I
really don't it's not actually that
expensive probably to implement like
oddly enough I don't know that MSAA
would really actually be all that
expensive in software like it's
expensive but you only pay for it at
actual edges because anything that has a
complete coverage you don't actually
ever compute the msaa for it so it's
really just more of a sort of how of an
edge complexity thing how many edges are
there in the scene how many pixels are
are have edges passing through them
right so I don't know so I think it
wouldn't be that expensive mean usually
the expensive thing is texture sampling
right and and we're gonna see that like
that's what will that is texture
sampling is presumably I would suspect
texture sampling is going to be the
reason why we can't really use our
software rasterizer to shift the game
right we're never gonna get that as fast
as the GPUs have it and that's why you
use GPUs for a 2-d game it's it's that
ability to pull the textures through the
writes are probably not as big of a deal
I mean yes the GPU does a better job of
that too but it prob we could probably
get around that by tiling we could
probably get around that right so the
real killer is that texture sampling and
so msaa if we had to implement that
which we don't because we won't have a
use for it because we don't have edges
but even if we did that probably
wouldn't be the biggest deal I bet MSA
really wouldn't be that big of a deal
for us because the texture sampling
would still be would probably still
dominate or run time that's just my
guess
so alright looks like we're done with on
topics so I'm gonna postpone anything
more till tomorrow when we will talk
about you know what I think we we should
just keep the trend of just like getting
the first thing going and then go back
and revisit so I think we maybe will do
it in two ways what we'll do is we'll
we'll just get a janky bitmap Phil going
so we'll fill this with an actual
texture like we'll map the guy's head in
there or something we'll do that
tomorrow and Friday or whatever and then
next week what we'll do is we'll start
on going through and cleaning up all
that math so that everything is just so
and we can be pretty happy that things
are in the right place before we start
any optimization work but yeah good work
today people good work today we filled a
rotated scaling shape and another thing
that that you know we didn't quite
mention but that might be worth
mentioning is this will work for any
convex shape right that inclusion test
that idea of checking all the edges and
seeing if they're all inside any convex
shape that'll work so we could actually
have an arbitrary end gone essentially
as long as it's always was with convex
and didn't have like any you know in
notches cut into it basically it would
work and if you want to you can even use
the same sort of a test to do something
for concave shapes it's just again we
don't need those frame things so I'm
sticking with the stuff that's the most
accelerate able because you know you
always want to do the fastest thing you
can for what for the for the thing that
you need alright so I'll go ahead and
wrap that up here close things down
let's go ahead and save our mischief
board I don't know how big that files
gotten probably pretty big huh all right
thank you everyone for joining me for
another episode of hand made hero it has
been a pleasure coding with as always
and I gotta be honest with you software
rasterizer are just so much darn fun
collision detection is always a
nightmare it's always bogged down when
we do clear detection when you do
rasterization it's just so much fun like
I had a blast
yesterday and today doing the coding was
just fun and and pulling the bitmaps
tomorrow is gonna be a blast I hope
you'll join me for that 5:00 p.m. same
time same place we'll go ahead and do
that and I think it'll be a lot of fun
what is it oh it's Thursday already
I said Thursday Friday oh man so we've
only got an hour we've got an hour new
bitmap sampling tomorrow all right we
can do it I think we can do it I don't
know we'll see I'll think about it I'll
give it a little thought between now and
then and see if I can align the things I
need to teach in just the right way so
that we can make sure that we fitted in
in an hour if not maybe we go long
maybe tomorrow's the day we go along
because we wouldn't you know one hour
two I think we'll be able to do it so
anyway I hope you'll join me for that
it's been a lot of fun I think it'll
keep being a lot of fun so I'd love to
see you back here tomorrow for that
anyway if you want to follow along at
home of course and and check out some of
the stuff that we've been doing
you can always pre-order the game on
hand made here org it comes with a
source code as we do it every day so you
can download it and play with it just
like I did on the stream and and do
whatever you want to do to kind of you
know learn more effectively by trial and
error basically right so if you want to
do that you can pre-order it here we
also have a patreon if you want to
support the video series you can always
subscribe to that it's much appreciated
and we have a forum site where you can
ask questions as well and there's also
community ports to Linux and Mac and
stuff like that there if you wanna check
those out and we have a tweet bot but
tweets the schedule at you so if you
want to catch the video series live that
is the thing to subscribe to it will
tell you every day it sends out in the
morning when it's gonna be and then an
hour beforehand so it always gives you a
big heads up
alright thanks everyone for joining me I
will see you tomorrow hopefully if not
have a wonderful weekend and I'll see
you on Monday either way so take it easy
everyone