hello everybody and welcome to hand made
here on the show we code a complete game
live on stream we are doing some
lighting today and by lighting on me and
my really weird nonsense idea for doing
lighting by a multi grid simulation
which doesn't make a whole lot of sense
for reasons I've explained earlier but
you know just because something doesn't
make sense doesn't mean you shouldn't
try it we're on day 395 here and we
pretty much left off yesterday yes
that's good left off last time with you
know we could have just kept coding we
were right in the middle of something we
had just gotten light textures down
sampling and so I'm just going to hop
right back into it today because
essentially we've just got to implement
a bunch of stuff and test it out get
working to see if this lady's game is at
all interesting so today again day 395
so if you want to follow along at home
with what I'm doing
you want day 394 as your your jumping
off point alright so I'm going to go
ahead and load up what we had here and
just mention what it is it's currently
we've got you know sort of the rendering
of the game is happening in the
background but we're drawing over it
with just directly our textures our
lighting textures and I made it so we
could actually step through those
textures and see what each of them look
like and we're right now drawing a test
red light into the center of them so
what I want to point out here I just at
the start because I wanted to test one
thing before we get much further into it
is that if you look at what's going on
here with this red light you can imagine
how far you might want that red light to
propagate in terms of diffuse lighting
it doesn't propagate very far even at
the highest level so by the time we get
out to here you know the red light has
not gone very far and then eventually it
averages
- nothing and so what I wanted to take a
look at was just thinking about what we
would do if we wanted to make this light
go further out and one of the things
that is something we have to play with
obviously we can change our algorithm
for distributing lighting around but one
of things I wanted to mention is the
ratio of the numbers where a light
source is present in the bitmap versus
everywhere else in the bitmap is what
will control how far it spreads to a
certain degree so what I wanted to take
a look at is what happens if you take
the light source values and you make
them much higher so for example if a
neighboring pixel is 0 for meaning no
light and we have one for meaning light
then in terms of just a visible range of
what we see which is 0 to 1 what would
happen if we boosted those lights up
well above the 0 to 1 range in terms of
how far they would spread that's
basically what I want to know you can
see here we've got our fake like feeding
code and our fake like feeding code is
just going to put ones in there you can
see so I'm just curious what happens if
I put 100 in instead so now when I am
creating that fake bitmap it's 100
instead of 1 and now let's see what
happens when it when it propagates so it
looks to me at the moment like we're not
really getting proper spreading either
so I think there's something slightly
wrong with our down sampling here
because it might just be that we tapped
the down sample at more than 2 X I'll
have to think about that but that
doesn't seem right to me either
so when you know when this gets larger
you can see that it's still at full
value so when I switch each time I go up
I should expect to see at least one
pixel pick up that value and I'm not
seeing that
so that concerns me a little bit and I
want to find out why that is because I
don't know why that is so I think we
just want to take a look at this here
and see what's going on I think yeah so
I think just looking at this code here
we do have the problem that as we're
going through the UVs for these things
we may not be using the bilinear sample
to actually do a bilinear sample right
and so this code really probably has to
get a little bit better now there's a
couple things we can do here and let me
just say what I mean by that in fact let
me see if I can find the pen amid this
mess that is this desk right now the pen
for the Wacom tablet which you know you
would think that I would have around
there it is
alright so allergies allergies
everybody loves I'll actually no one
loves allergies
except allergists they'd be out of the
job I suppose all right Milton has lost
connection to tablet as is its way
I need to add just a button there just
needs to be a button in Milton it's like
reconnect to the tablet that we could
just hit there we go so here we are on
day three ninety four and what we want
to do here is we want to look at multi
period up so what we have essentially is
a texture and let's pretend it's a four
by four texture and we're going to go to
a two by two texture so when we do this
sampling the most primitive version of
the up sampling we could do would need
to take into account at least four of
the lower-level texels the the higher
resolution texels if you will so if we
have a B C and D that has to map to just
a in this one right and the reason why
we have to have at least four of these
is because if we want like to be able to
propagate two large two cells in the by
using sort of this bigger coverage area
at each level we can't lose any cells so
each down sample we have to look at the
contribution from all of the lower level
cells when we go up to a higher level
and the key there is that if we don't
look at at least four then the collapse
will be losing some cells right because
if we just looked at say the a cell then
the B D and C cells would not be there
for is the smallest set you could look
at two in each direction in order to
produce the higher level version so when
we do that there's two ways we can do
that one is we can write our own the
sampler and our own sampler would be one
which just grabbed the texels and did
the bi-linear ourselves now why would we
do that well the reason we would do that
is if
we thought we wanted to eventually do
something other than bi-linear which is
fairly likely this is a weird lighting
propagation algorithm the chances that
we're going to want to do something
other than just by letting your sample
are pretty high what else could we do
well we could just pick this center
point 100% correctly so that when we are
sampling a wee sample right there okay
and then the bilinear filter would add
those up and divide by 4 4 s awful
allergies I don't think they are all
that seasonal honestly I think it's more
like there's so much construction in
Seattle there's just tons of debris in
the air and you breathe it all in
progress all right I so what I would
like to do I think is write the shader
such that we are manually doing that
process and the reason that I'd like to
do that rather than try to make sure
that we have the sample working 100%
properly is because again I think we
might want to fuss with the math
eventually and if we don't want to fuss
with the math then maybe this will be a
little bit slower because it's not using
the built-in bilinear filtering and so
you know that's not a great decision in
the end if it turns out we just end up
with bilinear but if we do end up with
just by linear in the end it's not a big
deal to just turn it back whereas since
I have to go do some debugging work now
to make sure this propagation works in
the first place
I might as well do the full-bore one so
that there's no cost to us in the future
in changing that algorithm so what I
want to do here you can see when we do
the sample is I want to be able to get
out four samples one from each of the
corners and so what I'd like to do here
to me
for now is introduce my own function
that'll do that for me so of these three
which is like a manual trample or
whatever and manual sample would get
from a texture that is passed right so
we want to pass one of these samplers
here right so we want to pass a sampler
2d the texture to read from your book
called sampler and then we want to do
this operation now to begin with again
I'm going to start simple here's a the
texture call I'm just going to pass in
the sampler here we have the fragment UV
and the fragment UV is going to get
passed in there and then we have the RGB
on the end so that should be about it
and then I just return that result and
now what I want to do is make sure that
I'm able to do just that operation
and if I do just that operation and I
guess I should probably switch over here
so I will end up behind my head again
what I should see now is when I go look
back at the game running after taking
care of any compilers in the shader I
should see exactly the same thing as I
saw before right that's the sort of the
expectation or the hope looks like I
accidentally left the word texture on
there there we go
and so it looks like everything's fine
here right all of these are totally fine
so that's good
and so now inside manual sample we want
to be able to do the operation that I
was just talking about now the
interesting thing about this operation
is that we essentially have possibly we
may at this point not need the frag UV
anymore because of the way that we're
going to do the sampling here although
I'm not really sure about that because
again we sort of have this problem where
we're down sampling past the point where
we can actually guarantee that there's a
two to one ratio I would prefer it if
there always was a two to one ratio and
maybe we'll have to enforce that in the
future but right now I guess we're sort
of still trying to get away with not
doing that anyway so let's go ahead and
see here what we can do about that so if
I take a look at my open gel and Doc's
shoulda left them open
what you can see is that right now
here's the page where we where we can
see all the textile operations we have
and the kind of texture fetching that
we've been doing is this kind of work
here but remember I think we mentioned
this before because we used it for when
we were doing the Deaf feeling stuff or
at least try to use it at one point I
don't remember what we ended up settling
on for that but there's the thing called
textile fetch and what textile fetch
does is textile fetch will produce for
you a specific texture sample without
any adulteration so it'll just get back
a texture literally and when it does
that what we will be able to do is take
neighboring samples and get their exact
value so that we can average them using
our own map if we want to right now the
thing about this that's a little bit
confusing right is when you do a textile
fest you have to look up directly into
the texture what that means is you have
to pass as you can see here the actual
textual textile coordinates that you
wanted
now that is easy to do in some sense if
you know what the size of the thing is
that you're looking into but harder if
you don't and so that's why I say if
this was only two to one it would be a
lot easier now we can start by doing it
just two to one and see what happens
but the problem like I said it's just
going to be that when you get at some
point you get to a place where the
downsample doesn't quite go 2 to 1 now
what I'm as I'm sort of saying that in
my in my head the thing I'm realizing
too is I wonder how much of that is a
problem here we're at some point we end
up below the level where we're going to
be two to one so we go into a place
where we're
actually not mapping exactly because
again we know that 1920 by 1080 won't
have that be the case what I was
thinking is you know if we wanted to we
could take that out of the equation by
forcing the lighting at the moment to
always be something that isn't 1920 by
1080 right because when we do our
lighting we could choose to do it on
some other grid that's not the same as
the resolution so if I want to for
example I could go and what's a here it
is I could go and force the lighting
texture width and height to be something
else
right so suppose I always pick 1024 by
512 for example in that case right now
I've got so that I'm always down
sampling by exactly 2 now it's not going
to be when stretched to the screen it's
not going to be square pixels right and
you can kind of see that happening here
and so as I kind of come out yes so you
can see actually in this case exactly
what I said would happen did happen
actually so the problem was not the
bilinear sample there I guess it was
just the fact that we eventually got
down below the 2 to 1 ratio so that's
good to know right now what I'm not sure
about is why we don't eventually get to
a place where we've got the whole screen
filled there so that's a little bit
weird to me so I'd like to investigate
that a little bit further but now at
least we're propagating the light out in
the way that I had wanted it to do so
it's a little bit better right that's
that's what I wanted to see is having it
eventually go to fill the whole screen
and so now if I go back and switch out
of doing the 1.0 that's re the 100
strong version and I switch back to just
doing a emission of
one right so now we can see how far it
propagates we can see a little bit
better it propagates quite far still
right so that means the light with a
power of ten in our made-up units
remember these are not lumens or
anything we're just playing with with
just a value that means something only
to us a light with power 10 still
affects like that much of the screen
right and and that's exactly what I
wanted right that's exactly what I want
so now the question is I guess we don't
really need to worry too much about the
upsample process now which is good let's
also take a look at some of these other
ones here so you can see these are like
our other reflection pieces of
reflection information and that all
looks pretty good too right
all right so that's all good um so yeah
what I'd like to do now is potentially
start fussing with that mat now again
like I said why do we want to fuss with
the math the reason I want to fuss with
the math is so I think we're going to
need our own versions of it and even
just looking at it now I realize I think
we we do have something already where we
would want to fix so if you think about
what's going on here
we are trying to mix light sources
together and in order to mix the light
sources together what we need to do is
we need to do stuff like say well if a
surface was pointing or an emitter or
whatever else it was pointing that
direction escapes a submitter on the up
path if an emitter was twenty math
direction and another emitter was
pointing that direction then when we
blend those together
if this emitter was much stronger than
this emitter we don't want to weight
them equally we want the stronger
emitter to take more of that to be more
dominant right so when we do that blend
what we want to do is wait the blend by
the emitter now there's two ways we can
do that
we can either pre multiply the values or
we can waste them during the blend the
reason waiting them during the blend
might be better is because it could lead
to smaller data for us the example is
right now we only need an RGB texture
for our NX and Y D which is the pack
texture that has the normal to the
surface x and y in it well the normal
X&amp;Y can only be expressed in two values
if we a you know if we a priori know
that they are always going to be
normalized so NX + y + Z the N Z can be
recovered from just the n XM e and Y
only in the circumstance where we know
that they you know the length of these
this thing is 1 right because then we've
got something to solve for if we can't
do that then we have no idea get rid of
this milton really doesn't did not like
having that run in the background I was
taking if all the GPU time or CPU time
not sure which probably GP time anyway I
so if we want to do stuff like that then
we have to do the blend correctly we
can't just pre multiply these values by
the strength of the light and have it
come out in the wash the alternative
again would be to do NX + y + Z D as an
RGBA then those can be pre multiplied by
the strength of the light and the
blending will just work so again options
there I'm not sure which one we want to
do but we have to do something right and
the same would be true for the
reflectance of the surface I guess if
the surfaces were bigger or smaller
which on earth so I think it's really
only the nxny that I can think of at
this point that would actually need that
so that does seem like at that point if
that was the case if it's only
in x and y then maybe you know for the
sake of preserving our ability to
potentially still use the bilinear
hardware that does have me kind of
thinking that maybe it would be better
if we just expanded nxny and ZD 2 in our
GBA because at that point we could still
rely on the bilinear filter to do the
work for us
and that would be good well I'm going to
go ahead and I think implement this in
the bilinear downsample sense I would
also like to know I think here's the
other thing that probably we want to do
to keep ourselves from being in trouble
here and I didn't do it I wasn't careful
about it before so the other thing that
I think we want to do here is as the
light indexes light buffer count stuff
is is happening where we're going
successively smaller here when we do
this text whip text height we're
dividing it by two and what you can see
there is when we do that / - it's a
destructive / - so what I mean by that
is let's suppose we divide by two down
below the level where we would be doing
one-to-one now I did isolate it like I
said - doing just powers of two here so
we know that now we're not getting a
problem where we're not taking enough
samples at some particular level but if
you imagine we were doing 1920 by 1080
right then what you can see happened
there is if I look at 1080 that's the
one that'll blow up first I divide by 2
I get 540 I divide by 2 I get to 70 / -
135 this is no longer even so when I
divide by 2 now I'll get 67.5
now if I were to round that up to 68
then I would still be able to divide by
two and know that the 68 right the the
texture that 68 long would still have at
least one sample for every two Texas in
the 135 texture right however if I round
down to 67 then at least in one place
we're going to skip a Texel right we're
going to have a place where we're
sampling only from one text so instead
of two texels if that just has to be the
case right because we don't have as many
samples as half the number we have point
five less instead of point five more
right and so you can imagine you know
how this works right let's say we took a
4 wide text texture right we said
instead of four wide it's five wide ok
and now we're going to represent that in
one of two ways one way we're going to
round the half-up so we're going to say
we're going to map it to three right
well how does it map to three it Maps
the three like roughly right like this
okay and what you can see there is for
any given Texel we have at least two
things it could map to when you take
that sample right so if we wanted to
guarantee that we always had a new
sample for every two samples we would so
the thing we be introducing is some
Texel would actually be able to touch
three and we'd have to come up with just
some arbitrary rule for picking which
two it used but we would never have the
case where it wouldn't on the other hand
let's say we pick one where we've got
two well in this case we've got more
than one texel
that has three so whatever we pick we'll
never be able to get all of our texels
for this one we would these two go to
here these two go to here and these two
go to here and we over sampled this
Texel so the only bug is over sampling
in this one we have the
problem these two go to here and these
two go to here we don't have any way of
sampling this middle Texel this middle
text we'll just got lost now normally
you think that's not that big of a deal
in our case where we're counting on this
to propagate light it could be huge
because if that's the only textile
that's recording the information for a
very powerful light in the scene and
that isn't picked up we get a flicker on
that frame where that light goes away
entirely at the high level of
propagation and we don't want that right
so what we probably want to do here is
well like I was saying is when we do
this / - we probably want to do a safe /
- so what we probably want to do is
detect with plus 1/2 so that way we're
always going to keep ourselves at an
even divide down and we're never going
to get into a situation where the
texture would drop below that sampling
boundary okay so here's that process
again right that operation will not
affect the 1024 by 512 let's go back to
using render with render height for a
second which is not 1920 by 1080 it's
one drop below that because we were
running at a lower resolution and let's
see what happens here so yeah you can
see now we've got it so that it's
actually working correctly even at the
render resolution and and that was
exactly what I had hoped to see right so
I think that was our only problem is
forgetting that fact you know that we
had sort of a problem yeah with that
aspect of of the situation so what I'd
like to do now is go ahead and and try
doing this propagation
the sort of the final down sample
version
we're after we propagate the stuff up we
also propagate it back down right so now
that we can look at the of the up
propagation and it looks like what I
want we could do the propagation down
now the other thing we can do like I
said at this point is is fix the
blending so that lights get averaged
properly at the moment we don't really
have to worry about that because we only
have one light but we will have to fix
that when we add a second light source
right so we can do either those I guess
it's hard to decide I guess let's just
go ahead and try to do let's try to do
that process where we where we manually
sample and we'll wait by the light
intensity right and the way we could
test that is so here is I believe the NZ
map the NZD map so the MVP map is the
thing that needs to get that weight
distributed properly so what we could do
is make two lights one week and one
strong that will you know hit each other
in the blend and we could then you know
see if they properly combine the way
that we think they should where the
strong one will dominate in the
successive blending right so what I want
to do is my fake seed lighting here I
want to update the fake seed lighting
shader
so that now when it does this business
to light thing it can do multiple of
those lights and so I want to be able to
do that oops I want to be able to do
that pretty easily so we can add lots of
life into our test eventually because we
want to be able to test a number of
things before we get to the point where
we're actually getting lights from the
real render because again it's much
easier for us to debug it in it sort of
this fake way where everything is under
our control and constructed very
carefully that
is once we start throwing real data into
it because once you throw real data into
it it's really hard to know what's right
and what's wrong sometimes you can maybe
think something you know if it's close
to working but not quite right you're
not going to be able to see those errors
and you're just going to have subtly
wrong lighting instead of getting to
that really nice crisp correct point so
what I want to do here is just make a
function called light and what that'll
be is it'll take this sort of data here
we go
and I'm going to have to make these
Global's I believe that's allowed I
don't know if it's actually less I hope
it's left I'm going to make these
Global's and what light will do is it's
just going to do that same operation
that we were doing before but it's going
to do it with a you know parametric
position for the light source size of
the light source and strength of the
light source so in this case we need a a
light P and you can see that coming in
here and it doesn't need to be X wide
anymore so here we'll just do light it P
and everything else here should work as
expected we just want to sort of add
some stuff in here so when we take a
look at the the light radius and we want
the light strength so we want basically
a light radius we want a front emit we
want to vacuum it we want a surface
color actually we'll just leave circular
zero and we want a
so this is actually good that I'm
looking at this so where there is
lighting the surface color also you want
to ignore anyone who has lighting
information you want to make sure
surface color is only blended from
things that don't that are going to
reflect light not just a minute right so
that's another place that we might find
that our up sample needs to be smart
right so that's another good reason to
do the up sample so anyway here's what
we want all of these values to be so
this is like a the light front emit the
light back emit and the light and key
and what we're going to do is replace
all of those so in here where I call
that going to look a little results
there we're just going to pass those
values that we were setting before
exactly as they were and now we just
need also that light radius so that's 10
so now we're passing the light radius
we're passing the front emit the back
emit the light MP we don't need the
surface color at the moment and there
we've got our light we also can now say
all right with our front emit and
everything else I can now change this to
using the ones that are passed in
[Applause]
no weight side of that one's just zero
and so that's really all there is there
so let's do ticks compile errors Matt
what are they tell me no matching
overloaded function for light there we
go
and so there's the the light source
looks all good and now I should be able
to freely just add a second one in here
where maybe I'll just take whatever this
is and add move it over slightly and
I'll make this light significantly less
powerful so this is like a super weak
light or whatever
[Applause]
so there's my two light sources and see
the weak one the strong one I think
since I want them to collide rather
violently what I want to do here
probably is say well you know as these
two collide let's make sure that they're
both strong enough to be interesting so
I'll make one 10 and 100 like so oops
that's not right no wait I know that is
right that was 10 and that was 100 I
just move these up so they align there
we go
so yeah let's take a look at those and
I'll also make this one have as a D
value of 1 and I might as well make some
different colors so I'll make the weaker
light green and red so the the polarity
of them basically flip or maybe I'll
make it blue so that it's clear which
texture we're looking at I don't get
confused or something why did that go
and modify that it's just a displacement
all right so now as we go yeah so now it
looks roughly correct in the sense that
it appears to be propagating that light
out reasonably well I am a little
troubled by the green motion there but I
guess it's ok yeah it's just because of
the weird non power of Tunis of these
textures but that looks pretty good so
what you can see here is that even that
I think they need to be a little closer
together for me to really
to this test because the other ones
still a little too weak and blends out a
little bit faster than I would need it
to
all right so what you can see here is
these lights blend relatively correctly
I mean correctly for some weird
definition of correctly since this is a
weird system that doesn't have units but
you can see how that at a certain level
they're both powerful enough when
they're propagating to remember we can't
visualize these light values properly so
at this point they're both clamping off
the end but you can see the green is
much more dominant because as it
continues to blend the green value is
the one that persists and that's because
again here you know they're both at like
you know one of them's at 30 in one of
them 3 or something right but as they go
forward you can kind of get that sense
right of the the green is the higher
value so it continues to preserve itself
right so what we want to do though is
focus our attention more on like this so
if you take a look at this I will say
I'm not sure why so looking at this I'm
a little confused the surface color is 0
where the light sources are so that that
bitmap looks like I would expect it to
no no problem there
but the where's my where is my actual
editor to my editors get closed Thanks
once they hit alt f4 once many times
let's try that one more time
all right so everything looks correct to
me except for one thing that I'm little
confused about which is looking at this
bitmap oh I know why because everywhere
else we are saying that the normal is
pointing up so I need something that's
not going to look like that so that does
make sense however if we look at it here
in this case my NP right my light NP
here so I should be seeing 0 1 1 which
is cyan is that what I normally set
everything to by default okay I do I set
0 1 10 all right well that's just the
way it goes sometimes all right so let's
suppose I wanted to sort of make
something that would make more sense
here what could I do
well I guess I could set it to point the
other direction which is like negative 1
or something which would make it harder
to view it but I would probably work I
could also just say for the sake of an
argument let's suppose I blacked out the
rest of the area for now even though
that's not realistic at all right all
right so you can see how this one's
blending and you can see how I'm getting
exactly what I said I don't want right
which is that I've got a bright light
next to a less bright light and there
unfortunately a little bit overlapping
at the moment so maybe I shouldn't quite
have them be that close to each other
but I want them to be almost that close
to each other there we go
so when I take a look here and these
guys intersect what I want to do is I
don't I want that that information about
the normals for that light to be
persisting properly right because right
now they're not and what I guess the the
thing that's kind of bugging me about
this is for surface reflectors versus
surface lighting elements I wonder I do
wonder a little bit about how this is
really going to work because you know
we're kind of treating this in such a
weird in a such a strange fashion when
you do the lighting transfer you know
you're going to be looking at if the
lights always predominate the surface
shape then you're going to end up in
this situation where yeah I guess maybe
I really don't want that as much as it
sounds weird maybe I really just want to
keep it doing just the averaging
see the dilemma I'm having here is that
you know if you think about what you'd
want to have happen is you've got you're
sort of treating these things as you get
further and further up the chain as more
and more averaged versions of sort of a
reflective of a piece of geometry almost
right so you know as you go up you're
trying to compute what the average
facing direction of stuff in this area
happens to be so that you can figure out
how much transfer is happening to that
area as a whole now the problem with
that is this the light direction if you
treat it as as one piece of geometry
that is both trans is emitting and
receiving light then you end up with the
light you can't use the light direction
and make it predominate because you
would lose the information about the
reflectors in that area so it makes me
wonder a little bit whether the smarter
way to do it is to have two textures one
for the surface direction like we kind
of like we have surface color and so you
basically got you know emission color
emission direction and surface color a
surface direction and you know you you
kind of you kind of sum them separately
and I really don't know that's the best
something I'm not super sure about like
I don't have a good idea
I guess what I say is since we probably
want to try both I guess we should try
it this way first because since we don't
really know what we're dealing with here
it'd be premature to say I mean you know
they're both sort of just approximations
to something one is a more crude
approximation potentially
but you know if they're already both of
them are accrued so I don't know what to
say about that really so I guess we'll
just continue forward in along this path
so I'm going to restore this to being I
think there should be negative time
actually and so these will be negative
ten pointing upwards so they'll be kind
of dropped back a bit that would also
let me see them more clearly so there
you can actually see the lights versus
the backdrop and there's the surface
reflectance there's the backside
emission there's the front side emission
all right okay
so now what I want to do is I want to
start looking at guess that the downward
propagation part of this because we now
do produce averaged versions we are not
doing anything special with the multi
with the up sampling I'm literally just
leaving it as bilinear filtering for
right now now in the future like I said
we probably want to do something
different there but at the moment that's
what we're going to do
okay so we need to create another shader
now and this shader the multi light down
shader is going to do sort of a similar
process but it's going to have a ton
more code in it the multi light-up
shader is a pretty cheap pretty
uninteresting shader the only thing
about if it's a little bit out of the
the that's out of the ordinary in this
case is just the fact that it happens to
write to more than one target so in to
the extent where it is or to tip except
where it has anything particularly odd
about it at all that's what it is right
so when we look at the compiled multiple
light down shader this is really the one
that's going to do all of the work and
so this was going to be much more
expensive although it's going to write
two less textures so instead of having
an out where we're going
front emit vacuum it service color MP
the surface color and the NP are never
going to change we can't change the
color of surfaces we can't change the
direction they're pointing on the way
down all we can change is how much light
got sort of we're saying is bouncing off
of them which is the front and back emit
for those surfaces so we're going to see
something like this where we're going to
be writing our desk front and desk back
and MIT out in this to these two and
then the surface color and the NP are
only going to be sources right so
there's only going to be sources for
that there's not going to be any
anything else
and so the way that we are going to
propagate this down is a little bit hard
for me to say how we want to do it but
effectively what we want to do is we
want to take the higher level texture
and we want to propagate the lighting
down to the lower level so let's think
about this for a second so that we know
what we're going to be try to say what
we're going to try to sample here so if
you imagine us having a four wide at the
highest level if we had a four wide now
they're technically is even a 1 wide
version and so if you think about what
we have to do to make this work we're
going to be talking about something that
goes successively down from like the 1
to the 4 2 to the 8 our sixteen rather
that's drawn very poorly there we go
I'm like why does that not look like
sixteen to me because it's not so when
we look at what's happening here for a
particular textile say this textile here
we have to go figure out and maybe I'll
make it a little bit simpler so for this
textile here right I'm going to be
looking up into this upper level texture
to try and figure out what's going on
with like the surface formation right
and then I'm going to use that
information to adjust what I have on my
own texture now the thing is I really
want to be doing some reflection at my
own level as well I think so
this is why I sort of was talking before
about how we might want to have
different textures for the for the route
down because what I'm thinking is I'm
thinking we probably want to actually do
the light propagation step such that we
read from both our level and the upper
level so we look at the upper level and
we suck those results down right and
then we look at our level and we compute
our new value from both that value we
suck down for the wider area and looking
at the reflectance we get from our
neighbors right and we can do that in as
big a kernel as we want so you know we
could even choose to do it on a 3x3
basically like to fetch sort of around
the relative boundary there
and I guess what I would say about that
is I'm not super sure I'm not super sure
which of those we need to do I would
think that we would have to do them
I mean I would think that we would have
to do them on something that was going
to be propagating in a neighborhood
fashion like that right like I would
think that we would have to do them
where we were sampling from the you know
we took nine samples and did the
computation for the center sample based
on the eight surround examples because
otherwise I feel like you're never going
to be able to get the propagation to be
fair in all directions
so that seems like what we would have to
do so for every cell in the destination
texture we would sample the eight
surrounding texels and we would use the
data from a surrounding texels to
compute the value for this Texel and
we'd read back
I don't really see anything else we
could do besides that so it seems to me
like that that's what we're looking at
right I mean that is that is the
situation and presumably from that we
again that computation is going to be
sort of following what we said was our
basic idea for computing the lighting
which is to say that we have where's
that little diagram how come we can't
get the diagrams here this is not
this isn't that we want how do we end up
on fluid flow
how did we end up on fluid flow folks
well in theory we should be able to find
here again
history
if it this one I mean how did we lose
this we had it up and now it thinks we
were always on that page how does it
think we were always on that page that
doesn't make any sense does it
here it is man I just remember Michael
bundle for bune L and now pronounce that
I so this is a computation that I said
we were going to try using which is just
the if we've got two reflectors we go
ahead and say here is the approximate
transfer between them right so you can
see that this is not a particularly
complicated expression basically what
they're saying here is the if you take
the vector that connects the two surface
elements that you've got then what you
want to do is say the cosine of the
angle of the emitters normal to that
which again is just going to be a dot
product right because you imagine we've
got this line and we've got the emitters
normal so basically just this is just a
dot product so it's 1 minus the length
of this line times the dot product of
the emitter versus the line times the
max of 1 and 4 times the cosine of the
reflector and the line divided by the
square root of the area over PI plus R 2
and so in our case the area in question
is like they've they are modeling the
area of these reflectors because they're
actually treating them as individual
points in the world we aren't so we
don't have an area for the emitter it's
just assumed to emit right like the area
of the emitter and the area of the
receiver are always the same and so we
don't really have a term that's going to
change the amount of light that gets
projected onto it based on that because
these two things scale separately right
now what I don't see here what I don't
see is that this I don't see the area of
the receiver anywhere
here we go oh wait no it's already two
minutes so I don't know so I guess
they're factoring that out of the
equation entirely
I guess because they're just computing
the well actually I guess I don't know
I'm not sure I know exactly why that
wouldn't be at least somewhat relevant
but I guess I guess the size of the
receiver doesn't really matter because
it's like well the light is falling on
this thing it doesn't matter how big it
is it just matters what angle it's
falling out I guess so either or in this
case our emitter area like I saying
our emitter area doesn't really mean
anything in this case because we don't
have different sizes so yeah
and this is a lie see never mind
this is their shadowing equation I
looking in the wrong part I was just
looking for their transference equation
but that's their shadowing equation so
did they talk about the transference
equation here or not
which were all okay and it is useful is
above above Allah it is all speculative
values the percentage of the hemisphere
above each service point not occluded by
geometry sure you justice we also use
detective the direction of the exclusion
coins a bit normal that normal Jews in
place the regular normal when shading
the service for more accurate
environment lighting so that's basically
saying well you should look in the
direction that you're not getting
shadowed because hey that's where most
of your life is going to come from
ensure that makes sense too but yeah I
just am Not sure so they're talking
about the shadow approximation here
which is to say that that's where the
one minus comes from right it's saying I
would normally have 100% of the light
incoming but for any given other person
who might be blocking me here's you know
what I here's the equation to see how
much of the angle of the sky they are
taking out and as they pointed out in
this case they don't know how much to
occluders may be shadowing each other
like this for example so given that fact
they try to use that too they try to use
how much somebody was shadowing in a
previous path in order to mitigate those
effects right so since a is shadowing B
in this case C would pick up less of
these shadowing effect for ambient
occlusion but again so that part is not
really the part I was interested in
indirect lighting in area lights is the
thing that I was more interested in
right so this is a part I actually
wanted to know which is this to this
form factor for approximation and what
they mean by form factor approximation
here is that's from the radiosity
terminology I believe which is what I
want to know so for two discs I wanted
to know what they were using for how the
lights
transfers from one disk to another okay
and so you can see here like they have a
little discussion of this justice
ratings transfer function we need to
catch the amount of light to reflect off
the front face of each terrorist element
we compute a mcruiz data first which is
we're not looking at that just yet if we
first use direct lighting from pointer
directions to compute the light at each
element just officiating service to exam
I think we can also do both level block
here's the fragment program function to
calculate element element radians
transfer and you can see the way they're
doing it curious they've got the two
normals which we have both of they have
the emitter area which like I said we
don't really have explicit but we know
based on the level of approximation what
its size would be effectively and then
we've got these two values they don't
explain here so they've got one this is
presumably a position and then I'm not
sure what d2 is so I'll have to look
okay so what they do is they say the
area of the emitter the two cosines
which is again just that that sort of
squishing that we were talking about
where as you get more oblique to
something you the shaft of light gets
C's less of the area so we have the area
of the emitter of both cosines over pi
times the R squared distance that's the
distance between the two so I guess
that's what this is right here that's
what the d2 is plus the area of the
admit er now they didn't put a
derivation in here which is a little
annoying but we can at least see what
most of it is I we can probably just
look up just this transfer somewhere
else but we can only see what most of it
is so if we have two surface elements
and we're looking at them like they have
their diagram before and here's our R
and here's our two normals right then
what we end up with
in this case is we know that if they
were directly facing each other so if we
had two disks that were directly facing
each other like so then we know that
what would happen in that scenario is
the full lighting transfer would occur
the angle would not be coming down it at
all but as we change the angle in both
cases less of the discs are seen in the
visible hemisphere by the receiver and
less of the light is emitted by the
emitter in that direction right so hence
we end up with cosines for both of these
in each case taking the area of the
emitter and scaling it down as a result
so that's like this is the area that it
would be taking up in terms of the like
the hemisphere of incoming light we
multiply it by both cosines to take out
the amount that the tilt is preventing
it from doing so and then we divide here
by the PI R squared plus a this is the
part that I'm not sure about obviously
what we're taking into effect there is
the distance that the emitter is moving
away from you is going to attenuate how
much do to the inverse square law we're
getting so pretty obvious here the
inverse square law is the R squared term
that's not a mystery the PI in this case
I assume is just because the area of the
thing is a disk so we end up with the PI
in there but this plus a bit which is
the area of the emitter so honestly
knows I can't put the PI is because the
area of the emitter is always going to
already going to have PI in there right
PI is already factored into there so I
really don't know what the PI R squared
is there you know PI R squared is the
area of a disk but it's the area of a
disk if this was the radius so I'm not
really sure where exactly they got that
denominator and I would have liked to
have seen it
do they reference somebody here
yeah so I can't really see I can't
really see how they got that
everything else makes good sense in
there but not that and so if we take a
look at how they're computing it here in
the actual shader where they assumed the
emitter area has already been divided by
pi then what they've got in that case is
they've got emitter area times cosine
times cosine divided by R squared plus a
right and so I see what they did here
it's a yeah if everything in here is
divided by pi then you could just
multiply through by pi course just out
of giving you a PI squared there I mean
if we have this so let's take a look
here so we have a cosine theta I'm going
to use these like that over PI R squared
plus a so if in this case what we're
saying is we assume that a was already
divided by the the value pi so to do
that we would have to divide both of
these by pi okay I guess I see how they
did it yet
that makes sense so in order to divide
both of these by PI I'll just do it out
so you can see it - there's the divide
by PI
so all I've done is divide all of these
terms by PI right because what I what
I'm saying I want to do is is do that
pre division by PI another way to think
of this was I multiply this by 1 over PI
over 1 over PI which is legal right I
can multiply anything by 1 and it's fine
so if I look at what happens here the
PI's cancel here and I end up with and I
can just associate this all right so I
can basically say okay I've got a over
PI cosine theta at cosine Phi over R
squared plus a over pi and hey there I'm
down to just my two areas over pi and
then we get exactly what they said they
would get which is the emitter area pre
divided by PI which is that cosine
cosine divided by the R squared plus the
emitter area already divided by PI so
that all checks out so literally the
only thing I'm not 100% happy with like
my understanding of what they were
trying to say here is the PI R squared
plus a part I'm just not sure what
that's supposed to represent and again
that just comes from I'm sure working
out the gist of this radius transfer in
this case the R squared makes good sense
to me the PI doesn't I'm guessing that
that must come from the solid angle
computation so for example you know I'm
imagining that this surface is looking
out at something and I'm trying to
figure out how much of this solid angle
of the of the hemisphere this disc is
taking up the R squared part tells me
what the projection is the PI is
probably coming from specifically that
that solid angle calculation I don't
know if I can quickly find something
that would confirm Mac how that's funny
can we access this
not very quickly well you maybe we won't
read that paper I just wanted to take a
look at it just to this radio's transfer
function so we could see you know if I'm
right about that big muscle an angular
part and just we could see what the plus
a was exactly again I'm assuming that
that is from the solid angle computation
we should probably try to work that at
some point just so we could reassure
ourselves that that is actually what's
going on but at least we know mostly
what we're doing here and can certainly
compute this pretty easily because we
know what all the terms are even if
we're not 100% sure why they quite
worked out to be what they are in the
radians transfer function and again this
is just trying to say so for a
hemisphere how much of the incoming
light of this for this surface is going
to come from you know whatever this disk
of is up in the sky the other
interesting thing about this is we don't
have to use a disk for any particular
reason could really use any shape we
want we could use a sphere we could use
whatever it just so happens that a disk
is a nice element for being able to sort
of just splat things in space and have
them have a direction okay
hmm
so thinking about this a little bit
further - another thing we could try a
little further on after we play with
this a little bit is having our
reflectors be discs and our emitter see
spheres if our meters were spheres and
it didn't hamper us too much in our
ability to actually create the lighting
that we wanted which it might then we
would be an interesting situation where
we could not have front-and-back
emission storage so we could just have
emission storage and that'd be it and
that would be pretty nice because that
would get us out of the business of
dealing with those extra textures and it
would also make it so that it was easier
to conceptualize what was happening when
we averaged lights together we would
just be averaging kind of like spheres
together which is a little easier to
understand then discs averaging together
where you end up with something pointing
in a direction that neither of the two
was pointing to before that's just kind
of a half way pointing so I get a some
of my here so you know there's something
to be said for thinking about alternate
ways of conceptualizing how the lights
average up as they get higher alright so
what we want to do here is we want to
start getting the compute multi light
down to do something and so in order to
do that we need to actually get it set
up reasonably and at the moment we don't
have that happening so we need two
things one is we've got to be able to
sample so let's talk about we need here
so we need the one level up so we need
basically our parent and we need to get
from our parent all of the values right
so we need our parent
[Applause]
for all of these and then we need our
neighbor right
so basically we're saying is we're going
to sample from the higher res version
and then we're going to sample from our
res version and then that would give us
all of the data that we wanted right
and we furthermore need to be able to do
that neighborhood calculation very
specifically so we're going to need
something better than frag UV here right
we can use frag QV to sample from our
parent but we can't use fried UV to
sample from our neighbor but that's okay
because the neighbor is the same
resolution as us so that should be the
easier case for us to handle right so
then we get into this nasty business of
of sampling kind of get it rid of this
here we get into this nasty business of
sampling this whole ring of data values
which is going to be a pain in the butt
but that's just how it has to go so what
we want to do here is say alright we've
got our parent front commit and that's
going to be sampling from the frag UV
and these are the only ones that have to
use the frag UV because these are the
ones that are that are going to have to
be blended meaning they're sampling up
over here they're sampling up to the
parent and that's not a direct sample
it's going to be an average of a few
values now in terms of the immittance
that upper-level immittance that we're
going to do there so we got to think
about this a little bit too this is
actually somewhat complicated so the
sampling here is going to be a little
bit different than what I drew
originally I was drawing something that
was a little bit sort of simpler than
what's actually going to go on let me
let me draw this one more time I had not
thought it through yet
so here we have the parent version of
the texture and here we have the
neighbour version of the texture and I
believe what we want to do here is say
well for any given person in here we
want them to essentially be able to
sample from who is going to contribute
light around them but also further away
right so in this case what you can
imagine is suppose I'm doing a better
person to talk about for example might
be this person right here we want them
to take into account all of this
lighting information that's right next
to them but we also want them to take
into account the lighting information of
all these other things that we don't
have the computational budget to go ask
about right so what we want to do is we
want to sample from the higher
resolution bitmap that's our high
resolution lower resolution bitmap
higher sort of coverage so what we kind
of want to do is take samples of the
neighbors for this pixel in the places
that it's not going to check on its own
so I think that's roughly what we want
to do is say let's use these three
emitters and these three emitters as the
emitters to use and if we had to do nine
right
we could do nine or we could do four
right we could just do the cardinal
directions so that's one thing we could
do is we could just do cardinal
directions but we do them on both grids
so we do it on the parent grid we'll do
it and we do it on the neighbor grid we
just go one texel to each side on both
grids and then we consider all of those
to be emitters and the ones in the
parent level are considered to be twice
as large as the ones in the neighbor
grid because they have been upsampled
right so there my guess is what we would
want to do that seems like the more
logical thing to me yeah so there seems
like what we would want to do and
furthermore we can if we want to we can
still use bilinear filtering in this
case if we want to for sampling the
parent so that we're really just talking
about moving a certain Delta in in terms
of the U and the V and then we're just
taking that whatever that comes out and
we're assuming that that's the lighting
contribution from there again it's very
sloppy but that's okay again we're just
playing around with it all right so if
you take a look at what's happening here
the parent front back surface and BTEC
bit here then when we go ahead and do
the sampling for that what we want to do
is we want to take for texture samples
there and so what I'd like to do is I'd
like to introduce a way to bundle these
into a struct I'm not sure to what
extent I have the ability to do that but
I'm going to try so let's say I said we
have a struct light
value and a light value is going to be
one of each of these things so it's the
front emit the back emit the surface
color apparent or what's on the empty
and what I would like is I'd like to go
say I want to get a light value from a
function that's just like you know
parent sample and it's from particular
UV and so what I'd like to do there is
say I have a light value result the
result front emit equals texture at the
UV and so basically I'm just going to
fill in each of these values by sampling
[Applause]
from the corresponding texture now
looking at this I don't think we need
the surface color for these right in
fact when we sample lighting values we
never need the surface color the surface
color is just for us to compute our own
reflection so I think at least I think
we're never going to do anything with
the surface color because that's already
been stored into that lighting value I
think
and you know you know what else I think
I think we can
ping-pong this as well so I think we
could do this in two passes the first
pass does the computation that transfers
the lighting down one level and the next
pass does the one that transfers it
within a level
so probably the neighbor stuff doesn't
have to happen right
so probably compute compiled multi light
down here o is probably what this
actually is or maybe we'll have it look
like down to because there's going to be
two steps to this all right
so in terms of taking the parent sample
then we're going to say is like okay
we're going to get all these values but
we don't need to know the service color
at all because the surface color isn't
used for for that transfer so really
only sampling from three textures the
two emitters and then the normal of them
so really this is what this looks like
right so if I go ahead and say there's
my way to take a parent sample then what
I can do is say well I've got a couple
of these I've got the left version of it
[Applause]
and in this case I don't know what the
UV step is so I guess what I want to do
is say you know something like this so
basically all I'm saying here is like
yeah we can get the neighbor you know
the up the left right the up the down
from wherever we are right now when we
look into our parent we can see what the
neighboring what the neighboring values
are by just looking using the U and the
V step now I'm going to call this UV
step and I'm going to do like dot view
dot view and dot V dot B so assuming
that they allow me to do that I don't
know if they do I guess I could just do
x and y so we would need to pass in
whatever that UV step was I believe in
shader version 4 you can just find out
what that UV step is because you know
the size of the texture in our case we
don't have that I don't think I don't
think shader 150 has that I mean I'll
double-check but I don't think it does
yeah
definitely does not
I helped C struct anywhere in here I
sure hope we can do struct
it's going to be super annoying if we
can't make us trucks it has nothing to
do with the graphics card whether you
can do a struct or not right it's just a
compilation language
yeah there we go
it's always hard to remember what you
can do in each shader language version
alright so we would need some way of
getting the few V step in so we're going
to probably have to pass it down like I
said you don't need it in shader
language for enough you can just get
this information but we will probably
have to just specify it so we're going
to have a uniform v2 here that's gonna
be the UV step which all that is it's
how far it takes you to go from one
texel to the next Texel in you and B
right that's that's all we want to be
able to do
so basically when we go up to you know
take a look at mmm you were we go take a
look at whatever our values are in the
parent bitmap we take where we would
have been for our textile and we look to
you know up down left right alright so
that's all we want to do from there we
can get rid of these entirely and then
if we want to do something really just
dumb here we could just average these
values together even though that's not
at all what we're going to do eventually
like I could say okay
point two five times like left front
commit plus right front commit plus up
front payment plus back front Emmitt
and put the live types back there yeah
and so that just produces another
averaging step which is not what we
actually want to do here we want to
actually do the lighting computation
here but for now we can actually test
this by just you know throwing some
arbitrary values in there it can based
on the averaging and so this would be
the way we would do the down sampling
from the parent and then the the
calculation of the of the lighting for
the neighborhood around us we could do
as a separate pass now the interesting
thing about this is this will still work
will still be able to we don't have to
do a neighborhood around us at the lower
level we could just always use larger
emitters and just leave it at that so we
don't actually have to even do that we
could always just take the lighting from
our parent and so for at the moment we
can run the entire algorithm just this
way and never use the local refinement
step so I'm going to leave compute no I
think about it I'll just leave compile
month elect down as the only thing
happening at the moment and let's just
get this one working so we know we have
to do parents back and NP and then we've
got the UV step so let's get that
we don't have this one the surface color
is not going to be there but what is
going to be there eventually so we might
as well just prepare for it is we do
need to know two of the values here we
need to know what our MP text is right
we need to know what our surface color
is because even though we're not using
those yes we will have to use them
eventually right so because in order to
compute the lighting equation in
addition to the lights we're checking
against we need to know what our
reflection direction is and what our
surface color is right so those two have
to you know those two have to be sampled
they don't have to be sampled from
anywhere other than the exact current
location so we can just use a
straightforward right I suppose these
have to be
[Applause]
so that's all the stuff we will need to
compute the lighting equation and then
what we would do in here is do to verse
two evaluations of the lighting equation
one with the front values and one with
the back values right that's that's all
we would be doing there and we can't set
ourselves up for slightly more success
there by saying something like well okay
you know compute light or something or
you know transfer a light and what we
want to do here is be able to
effectively you know evaluate each of
each of these things this contribution
so in this case we would end up with a
situation where we wanted to say all
right what's you know the reflecting the
reflectance color
what's the reflecting normal what's the
reflector position
something like this will probably pass
them in the other order so we've got the
position of the reflector is a position
of the asteroid the direction of the
reflector and the color of the reflector
and then we would also do like ok what's
the light key the light normal and the
light emission something like that and
when we do that letting transfer what we
want to know is you know
this is where the disk to disk radians
transfer would be computed now we're not
actually going to do that at the moment
we're just going to take the results to
be whatever the light emission was and
assume that it gets transferred entirely
right so the way this would break down
here is we would need to call that
transfer light for each one of these
functions so this is going to be kind of
annoying since we have no indentation
but it's basically going to look like
this right so we're going to say
transfer light we know we have and we
probably want a this is the transfer
light explicit where everything's been
broken down we probably also have a
transfer light where we have just the
emit and the NP for the light although
that's not really true I guess because
the NP has to be broken out anyway so I
take it back I guess we don't really
need that because probably what we want
to do here is say okay let's actually
break this out to the position and the
normal right so we're going to sample
the NP but then we need to compute both
of these values now the N is a pretty
easy value to compute because since we
know that the two values that we get in
the NP x and y are the actual x and y
values we just need to take
the V value and compute that somehow in
order to compute that we know the
Pythagorean theorem right we know that
this is a normalized vector so it's
pretty easy we know that this has to sum
to one
so we know that the square root of n x
squared plus n y squared plus NZ squared
has to equal one so if we square both
sides in this case we just end up with
this and because one squared is one
and so we just end up with NZ squared
equaling these two sausage gentlemen
transferred over to the other side right
so you have n Z squared equals one minus
NX squared minus n y squared and so it
just means that this simple equation
right here is is all there is right so
in order to reproduce this this
operation we just need to take the
square root of one minus NX x NX + - + y
x + y right so in that case we just have
a pretty straightforward operation to
reconstruct the NPV value which then we
do the result p value on the other hand
is harder to compute the reason it's
hard to compute is because we have to do
some real work there to figure out where
it is going to be in world space based
on strictly application on the screen
right now I'm not going to do that I'm
just going to say that it's the MP Z
value taken directly here because that's
the we do know that that is going to be
the depth of it we just don't know what
second wire so I put the view in there
compute the X&amp;Y from the flag and so
that's all we really need to do there
and then we have the P and the N
correctly so then that lets us do
transfer light as we would want to
actually call it right now we can just
say left up P left n left up front omit
and then we can just do recipe riff and
recipe right so what we want to do is
since the transfer light is a summation
in this case each of the transfer lights
I believe yes I'm going to can actually
line up like that because the
invitationals is never respected but
[Applause]
each of these is just going to sum
together we're transferring the light
from each of the places so there is not
any attenuation on it so right now we'll
we'll take that approximate attenuation
and we can throw it into here if we want
to but that's the only place that we
should put it right so this is the
reflectance color directly that doesn't
get modified but these we have to
compute so the recipe the ref n these
are the same
[Applause]
the restaurant in this case is going to
be and so since that's going to get done
in both cases I'm going to make that a
function so now we can do this
reconstruct normal step anytime we want
and all I have to do is just pass in the
texture sample like so and it will be
constructed furthermore I could do
reconstruct position and the same thing
so that way once we get this working
properly it'll just work everywhere
right that one will have to take a UV as
well so I'll pass that second
[Applause]
it doesn't need at the moment but it
will eventually so we then have these
two terms here which I'll do the same
way and now we have all the values that
we need for our lighting transfer so I
can do the same for both of these so now
front and back are both included okay so
I think that's what we want here again
we've got a six texture sample from all
three of the parent values that deal
with lighting but not the surface color
and then just the surface color MIMP of
the level that we're currently on
because we're going to need that and
then we'll write to the other two which
are the two emission textures so that
excuse me should suffice and now we just
need to actually get those values out
like the bind locations out and see with
all the compiler errors that I'm sure
that we're going to have for this shader
so here's all the stuff we were
specifying so you can see here we've got
parent front emit parent back parent and
P and then we want
so that's parent front emit parent back
identity Co that's good
and then we've got our Mt and our
surface color
[Applause]
we then have the UV step and those are
all the things that we would have to
bind for this particular one as far as I
can tell anyway so all that stuff has to
get found and it has to have its own
multi grid it has to have its own
information
oops I want to do so here's our UV step
here's our surface color here is our MP
and then here we just want our front
emit vacuum it MP and that's everybody
yeah so now when we actually get down to
using this we've got some work to do
there as well so when we do our multi
grid up
just here when we do our multigrid up
we're going to do essentially the same
set of process in Reverse right so
during the downward phase we're going to
want almost exactly this so what we're
going to do is start at the top and if
the light buffer counts you have to
think about this a little bit so the
light buffer counselled is how many
there are
if we actually access into that one we
would end up axing into a non-existent
light buffer right so life of our count
minus one is the index of the most
simple light buffer recomputed right
it's the most average up so what we want
to do is we want to start at that one
and we want to propagate down to the
lower level one what that means is we
are essentially going to be going
backwards and be testing for our our
desk light buffer index and this is
actually the source right now and we're
going to test for our source to be
greater than zero right because when we
get down to zero that means that we
can't go any further that that's already
on that you know we've already
propagated down as much as we can so
we're starting at the top one we're
going to propagate down so here this is
exactly opposite of the other of the
upper tasks we've got the destination
light buffer is whatever the source was
minus one right is going to go down so
then we've got the source and the
deathly buffers are both selected
exactly the same way and we're going to
do another full screen fill so all of
the stuff is exactly the way that you
would expect so the only change here is
what we are going to be binding right
and so we want to bind a couple of
different things here the right all
frame buffer is not the one we're going
to use because remember we're only
writing to the emissions now so we're
going to use the right emit frame buffer
and it's a good thing too because we
couldn't read from the surface plate or
the MP text for our for the desk which
we need to if we were writing to it so
here we go so we've got 0 1 2 3 4 5 here
we know we've got front emit back in it
we're not going to use the surface color
so we're just using the env tech in this
case from the source and then for the
desk
we do need that surface color and we do
need that MP tech for the destination so
there's our 5 textures we also need to
specify when we do our use program begin
here we also need to bind that UV step
value the UV step value is how far it
takes to get from one textile to the
next Texel in the particular texture
that we're looking at and so since these
things are essentially 0 to 1 mapped
versions of the width and the height we
can determine this value very easily so
if we take a look at how we would do the
the source UV step which is what this
really is and we probably should have
called it that because it's different
for the destination the source UV step
is going to be 1 over the width and
height of the source right because
that's how far one texel would be in UV
space I don't know if we did a 1-over
operator for our things I'm not sure if
that's true it looks like we did oops
[Applause]
exam I so we did not do them that's
alright
[Applause]
and so the only thing I think we should
have to do now what is exciting about
here
Sheila texture for is an undeclared
identifier that's so apparently that is
so well that's just ridiculous
give me all your textures or maybe not
all of them but let's take eight of them
okay so that takes care of most of what
we need to do the only thing we need to
do is make sure that we actually bind
this stuff up so we've got our used
program begin for multi light up we
basically need the same thing for multi
light down and in this case we now have
one two three four so we've got parent
front emit parent back admit parent and
key
[Applause]
and those two then we also have a Geo
uniform to pass
that's the UV step ah probably 2fv right
we've got one of them
there we go
so we've got lots of grid light up now
we've got multi grid light down we're
all bound up and so I think that should
be all we really need to do mm yeah I
think that's about it for doing our our
sort of reverse propagation now we're
going to have a lot of compiler errors
here and they're going to be hard to
track down
let me cardigan fur and okay so what are
you talking about undeclared in fire n
well I agree with you it turns out
there's not a lot of n there let's try
that one more time
I'm comparing in firelight and that is
the typo as well
what's next mmm okay that's not very
helpful let's go ahead and continue
stepping through there and see if we can
get the individual validation errors a
function does not return a value parent
sample okay that is a very true
statement
under present for a fragmovie
[Applause]
this is true I did not put in my smooth
I guess I must have accidentally deleted
that when I was deleting the other
things this is a smooth in Veck to frag
UV that should be there
undeclared ref see take care of that all
right and let's try recompiling
kanakam cops low-to-high p3 component
vector of loads that's your early
function to reconstruct this position
alright let's take a look at that as
well correct you are yeah and then
there's something where we have it where
we're trying to make a float become a3
value which should not be happening so
let's figure out why that's occurring as
well yeah all right well we're running
out but running is not particularly
helpful obviously for a number of
reasons as you might imagine simply
running is not going to get us very far
let's take a look real quick at what
these ended up being so there's our
upward propagation
these are obviously not changed by the
downward run so as you'd expect there
just fine
these on the other hand are quite a bit
different which may be correct or may be
incorrect we haven't thought about it
yet I don't have time to do any
debugging today or to really do anything
particular with them so we're going to
have to kind of leave it as it is but
tomorrow we will then be able to
actually play with the lighting transfer
and see if we can get some sort of
crappy version of that working at by the
end of the day let's go ahead and do QA
there we go
oh and yeah I did forget to do these
have to get replaced with left right fix
that
[Applause]
just used have you seen the doom 2016
rendering paper I saw the slide
presentation on it but I have not seen
uh I haven't up in my downline ah thank
you I saw the slide presentation that
Iago Sousa gave on it if that's what
you're talking about
let me see here Oh Oh just use this
isn't a paper on it this is the dude who
does the like reverse engineering the
rendering process from taking the GL
snapshots yes I have seen it I love this
disguised stuff where he just like looks
at each of the frame captures he's got
one on GTA as well that's good if you
haven't seen it
the lead tech I'm on day 18 and I'm
looking at the scene for the first time
and I'm wondering what happened I have
these sweet colorful gradients and sound
and all you have is two round circles
well we were playing around with
lighting if you want to see where we're
actually at we can turn off that debug
render and and draw actually where we
were at which is say that we're quite a
bit further along in terms of of text
stuff but we wanted to do some light
propagation work so what we're looking
at right now is just the the reason
we're looking at some dots on the screen
is because we wanted to play around with
some light propagation stuff so we're
just drawing those light propagation
textures that make sense
um
like 93 do you usually do a lot of
programming before you run like you did
today or you program a bit and then run
into bug is because you knew what you
were doing that you take big terms to
programming then run well I run the
program anytime I can but sometimes
you're doing stuff where you can't run
it to get any meaningful output right so
sometimes you might program for several
days without being able to run the
program because we're doing so much
stuff that has to get into place before
anything can happen so I guess what I
would say is I like to run the program I
mean it's always useful information to
run the program but yeah I just don't
think that you're always in a position
to sometimes it helps if you're trying
to get through something if it would
take a long time to program and without
running you can try to come up with
interim things it's good to come up with
like fake ways to run the program like
oh I could just sort of stub this out
and you see me do that so much times the
lighting you could have imagined this
doing this a very different way we could
have tried to write an entire lighting
propagation system without ever running
it and then running it right but we
haven't been doing that right we've been
drawing these little tiny steps along
the way and that is intentional because
that allows us to check the state of the
system much more frequently rather than
just doing the whole thing running it
it's not working and having to go back
and look at each component separately
right try running now that we fixed the
stupid error in the shader
well it's but I don't think it's really
gonna do anything differently I mean we
aren't propagating light at the moment
right we're we're just you know we're
we're just adding values together so
um let's see
sexy rage how long do you think this
projects gonna take I don't know since
it's it's a teaching stream it really
it's hard to guess as long as it takes
slag my name new here started this path
before if you were working on this on
your own time how long do you think it
would take you to complete well you know
I mean you can Ballpark it just you know
the upper bound right because the upper
bound is going to just be the total time
we spent on stream compressed so right
now we spent something like I don't know
450 hours so you know I mean I don't
know how much you want to program a day
I would say 6 hours a day is a good
amount of programming to generally do so
75 days if you if you assume that you
were working five days a week it's about
15 weeks he's done so far it would
probably go a lot faster if I was
programming on my own though like it's
probably more like 10 weeks or less
because if I was working myself I
wouldn't have to be talking explaining
stuff all the time and I mean we spend
huge amounts of time on the blackboard
talking about stuff and some of that
stuff I would still do because I'd have
to work it out in a notebook if it was
that content but most of it's just
explanatory and that all goes away
do you think that game engines have a
place or is it just pure evil I'm not
sure I understand the question I mean
how can you have a game without a game
engine every game in a sense has an
engine or do you just mean with the
reusing the engine like like something
isn't an engineer this gets reused did
you just mean the concept of reusing the
the code for like the the core code of
the game from one game in another game I
guess I'm just not sure where you're
asking because the game you know every
game essentially runs on an engine which
is the code necessary to do all the work
that isn't specifically gameplay code is
typically how that's defined so I
they're definitely not pure evil because
there's no I mean what's the alternative
do you have any good practice to keep
your brain motivated after months and
months of programming I don't really
ever have a problem being motivated to
program for whatever reason like I
really like programming so I always want
a program I would say the hard thing the
more difficult thing for me is usually
well it is really just keeping myself
programming something specific and that
makes money right if left to my own
devices I just program all day and I
wouldn't necessarily ever ship anything
or I might ship something but it
wouldn't be something that makes money
like you know I might ship utilities or
ship a new operating system or something
and you know that is completely
something that can't make any money
right so I guess I would say the only
part that I find hard is defining a
programming scope that is something that
when done will make money so that you
can keep living and programming forcing
yourself to always be working towards
that goal and I don't have a lot of good
solutions for that it's hard you know
but in terms of keeping programming I've
never had a problem I always want a
program like every day I do it and I've
never had to convince myself to do it
sharra luck 93 if we feed you sandwiches
and keep you alive would you work what
would you work on for the rest of your
life
well what I'm working on at Molly right
now is is pretty much what I would want
to do right if Molly survives as a
company then I will be pretty much set
because that's what I want to do we make
all our own stuff in-house and it's
stuff that I think needs doing
well it's offering to that's very
generous of you but we're not at that
point quite yet so I think we're good on
financing until we ship 1935 and then if
1935 is successful I think we're good
if it's not successful then we'll have
to think about what to do as a back-up
plan right so we may may come with our
hand out in exactly such a fashion at
that point at the moment where we're
okay but I do appreciate the concern
have you found the need to write certain
algorithms directly in assembly for
performance reasons no I haven't but
that's only because my interests tend to
be much broader so I tend to write large
systems that are very intricate and
that's my focus area I am NOT the kind
of person who tends to focus on bringing
the maximum performance out of a
particular piece of code that's like
what rad game tools does for example and
I can tell you they definitely have
written things directly an assembly for
performance reasons because they often
hit times when they know they can do
something better than what the compiler
is outputting with say in the intrinsic
and they will have to drop to assembly
to get it to do those things because
they just can't get the compiler to
output the right string of code or
whatever right and I have had that
situation when I was working at rad I
did at that situation I did do assembly
language optimization for some stuff on
the Xbox 360 for example but that was
the only time I really did it and that's
also one of the reasons that my
optimization knowledge for extra c4
isn't great is because like my
optimization knowledge for 360 was very
good like I beat the their compiler by
like I would I think they were twice as
slow or three times the slow on like
some filter kernel stuff I had done then
the assembly language that I ended up
generating I had like a metropolis
optimizer thing I wrote and that thing
was pretty cool so I had a lot of
understanding of how to optimize that
machine but I don't have a lot of
understanding of how to optimize like
the x64 because I just haven't done it
so like I have a vague recollection I
mean like when we did on this dream like
someone had to tell me about IACA I
didn't even know they
that such a thing and looking at how it
worked
took me a while to understand exactly
how the x64 port stuff worked and that
sort of thing so I just don't have a lot
of experience with that and and so you
know I I would have to be more
experienced to begin with in order to
get to the point where I felt like I
needed to take control away from the
compiler and go to assembly for x64
so the risk any word on getting other
programs to work on some code on
handmade hero Shawn I'm assuming based
on the spelling of Shawn there you're
talking about I not Shawn Barrett but
maybe you are talking about Tom Barrett
for graphics which Shawn are you talking
about anyway we said adult our Edition
which I guess could be either Shawn
because I think they did that together
for graphics Fabien prepetition John for
game design Shawn to dance oh you had
the other sign in there as well to dance
and party does Shawn Barrett dance and
party a lot that is news to me if that
is true I know he drums he plays the
drums I don't know that he dances he
could play the drums so other people
could dance although I know he liked odd
time signatures so it might be hard to
dance - Shawn strumming but I don't know
as to the actual Grothman of the
question there or I guess I shouldn't
say gravamen because you're not
complaining um but the heart of the
question let's say I don't know whether
people want to work on the code or not I
feel like in general that sort of thing
would probably be more comfortable for
other programmers to give me something I
could use
so for example if I ask you know Fabien
or something to give us a compressor we
could use to compress our art pack file
or something right
and he streamed development of that
compressor that might be a more
comfortable thing for someone to do then
here's a code base that's not your code
base and now you have to work on it all
of a sudden on stream while talking
right just seems kind of
like a big app you know one of the
reasons I'm able to do handmade hero and
explain it as I'm going is because I'm
doing all stuff the way I do it and the
code is all familiar to me because I
wrote it all right and that makes it a
lot easier if you're sitting here
reading the code trying to figure out
how something works all the time because
it's not your code and you don't you
know recognize it that's you know I feel
like that's pretty tough right I'm
probably not much fun because the other
thing right you can reading other
people's code is usually not not much
fun you do it because you have to to
learn from it or to modify it but it's
not the fun part of the problem
obviously
so you know stuff about 360 hardware how
much of a problem was in order execution
did that cause performance problems do
you view out of order execution as the
performance convenience it claims to be
at least with respect to instruction
level parallelism so I guess what I
would say about that is that it really
depends I would say that out of order
execution and in order execution are not
there is not a strict one of the two
that is better and the reason that
there's not a strict one of the two
that's better is because it very much
depends on what kind of code you're
running so if you are running code that
you understand very well and have
optimized very carefully and which works
on very predictable workloads so for
example shader code in the earlier days
when it was kind of rote sampling from
textures and writing to frame buffers in
a very understood way that is something
that is very easy to do as an inorder
execution model because there's almost
never a mystery as to where the memory
bubble is right you always know when
you're going to stall because you know
exactly where your fetches are and you
know exactly how long they're probably
going to take in most cases so in
circumstances where you have workloads
like that out of order execution is
strictly a waste of course base you
should have just stamped down more in
order cores if you can because out of
order cores are typically much more
complicated however
if instead you start looking at more
modern graphics workloads that involve
things like ray tracing and
unpredictable kinds of queries into the
memory space that are very difficult to
know whether something is going to
complete in 16 cycles or 300 cycles
suddenly out of order execution may
become a little bit more attractive
right because you might not be able to
really figure out exactly how the memory
bubbles are going to line up and it may
be that dynamic arrangement of code
execution is the only way to get around
that now that becomes even more true
when you start talking about things like
AI code and game code where we're
walking arbitrary structures in no
particular way who knows what's going on
right and it's very hard to predict when
you're going to hit a memory stall but
you know there's going to be a lot of
them again out of order execution may
really be a win there so I would say
it's very difficult to really predict
whether in order execution or out of
order execution is better for a CPU
without really being able to test it on
the workloads you want to run I think
that's why you see you know a console
can get away with in order execution and
a PC can't because a PC is running such
varied workloads and if a moving target
that changes over time as the processor
evolves asking programmers to optimize
memory bubbles to a moving target like
that I think is just going to fail and
so I think that's why out of order
execution makes sense on the PC because
it has to be there in order for the
ecosystem to work even if in isolation
if you just took one SKU of the chip it
might not make sense
if everyone could and all the compilers
and all the programmers could optimize
just to that one
ship and know that that was the only
chip then you know in order might
suddenly be okay or something like that
right so my my statement on that is just
that in order isn't that big of a deal
in my experience to work around if
you're talking about looking at a
specific workload optimizing to that
specific workload and the workload is
somewhat predictable and you only have
one chip suddenly it's pretty plausible
when you look at the broader case it
just becomes a lot less a lot less
tractable to do that and still get high
performance out of the chip if you don't
have those things
and I think so I think that's basically
all I had to say about 360 hardware what
I mean
the thing about the PowerPC at that time
was it also had the load hit store
penalty which is a real pain in the butt
so you had to be really careful with the
way things got written read and written
I would say if anything the load hit
store penalty was the much worse calm
much risk problem with that chip then in
order execution was because the loaded
store penalty was a lot like in order
execution in the sense that load hit
store panel T is easy to avoid if you
know specifically what workload you're
doing and the code that you're working
on but once you start talking about
things that operate like cross function
all of a sudden load hit store becomes a
lot harder to avoid because load hits
start penalties inside a particular
function you can analyze explicitly and
you can go okay I know that I once I
store to something I can't ever load
from that thing again until I can't
remember it was like 40 cycles or
something like this so I know that I
just need to go look at the cycle does
nice thing about in order execution is
the cycle counts are perfectly
predictable so you can look through the
assembly code and know exactly how many
cycles you have until you could load
from that address again so that's really
easy to avoid inside a particular
function because you know all the
parameters and easy is a little bit
weird because you know well easy it
could be hard to structure the code in
the right way to make sure it doesn't
happen but easy
in the sense that you know whether it's
happening or not and you know what you
need to do to fix it
however cross-functionally that becomes
a lot more annoying so now when you talk
about like a function calling another
function and you know it's going to call
for multiple places
well this function is going to load
something at the start in order that you
know from some shared thing a structure
global structure whatever it's going to
load something that might have been
stored by the caller recently inside the
40 cycle window well now you're going to
get that load hit store penalty and
that's much harder to analyze right
because now you have to look at a call
graph and you know modern programming
tools just aren't set up to let you do
stuff like quickly iterate on what the
assembly language layout of all the
things in your code that call each other
are and look for loaded store penalties
right like you're talking about really
special purpose tools for that sort of
thing to make that convenient that just
didn't exist and so the law of historic
penalty I would say was actually
considerably worse than the inorder
thing but there's sort of two sides of
the same thing they're both two stalls
that can occur than out of order
processor wouldn't have because when it
hit that stall it would just switch to
the next thing it could execute down the
road
last question if you have seem decode
for sse2 but also have the same
algorithm for a VX 256-bit is there a
way to run only the avx2 a VX in the
shipping version if the hardware
supports it must it be decided compile
time so the answer is yep there's two
ways you can do it they're both
basically the same but one's a little
more drastic on the other so when you
start your program you can do a check on
the CPU type C because they have
capability flags you can do a check on
the CPU type to see whether or not it
supports AV X and then you can set your
function pointers to point to either the
SSE two versions of your functions or
the AV X versions of your functions
right so you don't have to do it at
compile time you can compile both
versions and then just jump to the
correct version now the other thing you
can do if you just don't want to deal
with it at all is you can actually write
your program in two parts and so
handmade here is kind of already set up
this way right so handmade hero when we
launch the game that's actually a win32
executable that loads a dll that has the
game in it so the other what we could do
very simply on handmade hero right is
compile the dll in sse2 topology VV dll
in AV x 256 as you say and then a
startup we just check in the win32
executable which one we have and we load
the corresponding dll and that just lets
the compiler optimize everything it
wants to optimize even stuff you didn't
optimize as it wants to it can in
depending on your compiler whether it
supports anything interesting there
that's a way to just have everything
compiled sse2 and AVX and then just pick
run-time so you've got two ways ones
like fine-grained ones coarser grained
with the way handmade hero set up I'd
say just use the latter because then the
compiler can use avx-512 for example
even you could have one version for each
because avx-512 is a really good
instruction set
when compilers get better at making
avx-512 code they could do some really
great stuff so I would say you know
that's probably the easiest and best way
to do it is just make one dll for every
chip and launch the right one at startup
all right
too many windows alright thank you in
for joining me for another episode of
hand made he wrote so in pledge
recording with you as always if you
would like to follow along the theories
yourself you can always appear to the
game on handmade hero org it comes with
a source code so you can follow along at
home we also forum site and go to ask
questions the patreon page you can go to
if you want support the video series a
schedule about you can use the tweets to
schedule out use if you want to catch us
when we're live that's the way to find
out and an episode guide that you can
use to figure out what we've done in the
past very quickly it has a nice search
feature now too so you can just drop to
anywhere that we've talked about a
particular topic you could jump straight
to it that's about it I will be back
here tomorrow I will be back here in 23
hours and 9 minutes
as you can see tomorrow's time will be
noon Pacific Daylight Time we'll be
playing around that lighting a little
more start to get the lighting transfer
working and yeah we will end up with
something that's at least somewhat
usable possibly tomorrow we'll have
something that's not doing any shadowing
but that kind of does a little bit of
transfer and then the next weekend we'll
have to start looking at maybe doing
something that it's a little smarter
about how things get shadowed another
stuff like that so that's about it
thanks for joining me until tomorrow
have fun programming and I'll see you on
the Internet take it easy