hello everybody and welcome to handmade
Hero the show recode a complete game
live on stream we are going to take a
little spin through the API today if I
remember correctly we had gotten last
week
pretty good at sort of the the basic we
went through and we kind of commented
and explained and fine-tuned some of the
code in the basic like startup frame
rendering like essentially all of the
things that you do before you actually
start sending things down to the
renderer and we've done a pretty good
job with with getting sort of that stuff
cleaned up and removing extraneous
features and making it pretty clear what
was going on in there so if we take a
look at the code here like in the render
loop this is all of the code necessary
to talk to the renderer you can see that
here we've kind of boiled it down to
some pretty basic calls you can make you
set up the memory of yourself so that
doesn't even require calling us you set
up a texture queue you set up your
OpenGL all of this is just you know
stuff that's happening not in the API
exactly and then when you come through
here it's again very straightforward to
do the rendering right you're kind of
just saying look here's some rendering
we're gonna do here's a renderer group
which is a group of things we're sending
down to render in a particular way you
render them and then you finish and so
this is starting to look pretty good and
I think it wouldn't be that hard for
someone who didn't really know the
intimate of the renderer to to start
working with this sort of stuff there's
more we could do here but the parts that
I want to focus on today are first of
all maybe making this camera code a
little more straightforward because this
is all while this is all code that is
nothing to do with the renderer the
render doesn't care I set the camera it
is stuff that people need to be able to
do and since we've already figured out
good ways to do it it seems to make
sense to go ahead and put that in to our
code on the render side in an
easy-to-use way so you know maybe
streamlining this part right here just
so this looks a little bit better
then fixing some of the render API stuff
so right now you notice fog is turned
off why is fog turned off it's turned
off because at the moment the values for
fog where the they starting to end are
actually hard-coded in set camera
transform that's obviously not we want
we would much rather have the ability to
specify the fog in the API and it's easy
to do so those are just some cleanup
things you want to do so that's
something we want to take a look at
so like the fixing this camera transfer
call making some utilities to make this
easy for people who don't necessarily
know 3d math very well that's something
we could do and then finally the final
the last thing that I want to take a
look at is these calls here our basic
calls that we use for drawing things on
the screen those calls I think need to
clean up as well there's a number of
things we might want to do to make this
work better than they do currently so
there's just several things there that
are just like API polish that's all I
really want to do today and then
tomorrow
I feel like assuming we can get those
into worked into a reasonable state
tomorrow what I'd like to do is start on
the sensible texture array stuff that
allows us to get better frame rates to
be fair at the moment I think we have
two problems really with frame rates one
problem we have is that at the moment
we've got me see where this is yes so
one problem we we have at the moment is
that our actual Z bias program which is
the program that's used to fill most of
things on the screen this just takes too
long and a lot of the reason that it
probably takes too long is is this sort
of stuff that's happening in here so one
of the things that we do is we sum a
bunch of lighting sample points the
number of letting sample points is
arbitrary and it's in directed that may
just be a bad idea and we may sort of
act i said as we could sort of go
further on the lighting we may be able
to well hopefully we will be able to
change this and to maybe something
more light probe oriented something that
doesn't require as much work inside the
pixel shader as this does because
obviously a pixel shading is expensive
and we don't want to do it if we don't
have to so that's one thing another
thing that we could do obviously there
is we could switch to something that did
more deferred rendering at the moment we
do def PS and we actually compute all of
that lighting for everything every time
we do every depth field because we don't
guarantee currently that we send things
down in any particular order obviously
because the entire point of the depth
feeling is that we didn't want to have
to sort our sprites before we sent them
down and so we kind of wanted the
renderer to be sort of a general-purpose
renderer to this handle that for us that
means that we would like to stop doing
things that involve lighting on anything
that isn't actually being used and one
of the things that we could do here is
try to defer that computation to later
so there's a lot of things that we could
do in here I don't know which one of
them which ones of them we will actually
need to do and there's a bunch of things
we can probably do to speed this up
suffice to say this is a big part of our
problem right now as well so of those
two things one of them is one I think
will tackle right away the other one out
know if we'll tackle it right away we
may may wait to sort of get back to
lighting and playing around with the
visual quality of things before we
really start to look at how this works
because we don't really want to optimize
something that's not final in any sort
of serious way so this stuff right now
is what I want to focus on today so I'm
going to go ahead and jump into it again
looking through this this is pretty easy
to understand I think these parts are
pretty clean this is I think pretty easy
to understand how this works here the
only thing I would say is you know if we
want to stop having these things be
copied we could make this be a buffer
that we map and fill if we wanted to do
that these should be allocated sort of
behind you know in the render or proper
right and I don't really know to what
extent we want to do that where we want
you know how we might want to push that
kind of back into the system in a
slightly different way so that's worth
noting right that that's like something
that it's not clear exactly how we want
that to work I would see that the push
buffer size of 64 megabytes is now
absolutely ridiculous because the push
buffer itself does not store any data
you know it doesn't store vertices or
bitmaps the actual size even in a heavy
usage scenario is probably quite small
so for example if I was to crank this
cover index up to something fairly large
which lose our framerate down
considerably right and if we look at the
resulting scene oops this is the wrong
program if we look at the resulting seen
in the render test you can see it
running very slowly here again there's
two potential culprits here texture
changes and lighting computations on
each individual pixel we will look at
why those are but either way it looks
like texture changes is the problem
mostly in this case but that's that
pretty sure so again fixing that issue
is one thing but again assuming that all
that gets fixing you're running full
speed this is an awful lot of sprites to
be sending down and so if we look at how
much memory is actually being used to
send those sprites down in terms of the
actual render group itself we can do
that pretty easily right if we stop here
the render commands will show us exactly
how much has been used out of that push
buffer so you can see here the maximum
push buffer size is 64 megabytes right
the push buffer Bay
is the start of that and here's the push
buffer data at right so by subtracting
the push buffer data app from the push
buffer base I can see how many bytes we
used in the push buffer itself and there
it is a whopping 184 bytes so you can
see that that is kind of an absolutely
absurd amount of memory to be allocating
for something that ends up using 184
bytes and again the reason for that is
simply because we were previously
storing all of our data in there and now
we're not storing any of our data in
there and so it becomes something that
is just sort of a legacy feature this
push buffer size could now be made much
more succinct and we could easily make
it so that the push buffer is say one
megabyte and literally never have to
think about it again it's now almost
entirely the texture and vertex arrays
that are the issue here these are the
things that we are primarily worried
about and those are the things that we
will need to actually make work right so
these are the things that are that our
memory allocation sort of specific to
that end we could make this be a non
allocated thing the way that we would do
that is by making the push buffer
actually reference into itself so for
example if we wanted to we could
alleviate that burden on the user by
recognizing that we're pretty much never
going to blow out that part of things
and by making this just be a static
array in here of some certain number
right and so when this push buffer for
example and another way to look at it
would be so if we look at what the
renderer has in you know just in terms
of what the renderer can do up at the
top here we can sort of see the
different entries we've got a textured
quad entry a full clear a depth we're
clear and then up you know sort of set
of peels one of the things that we can
say about this is that there's
so few of these we could probably we
don't really need a lot of the stuff
that we were doing before where these
things are actually sized relative to I
mean let's let's put it this way we
could just get rid of this and actually
just use like per frame based allocation
to store these things as well right it's
just all I'm trying to say here is that
these are really really simple now and
it's probably not worth us forcing the
user to think about how many they're
gonna have it's just not something
that's super relevant so one thing we
could do is say hey yeah like maybe we
just say the you know render entry or
the push buffer here you know we could
just say that there's a you know a a 4k
push buffer and that's it and there's
pretty much no chance of us ever blowing
that out
so furthermore one other thing we could
do here again if we chose to kind of
regularize the renderer a bit more is we
could make it so there really isn't a
push buffer at all right we could make
it so that really you don't get render
groups in the first place you only get
the ability to specify a set of things
that go through the DEF peeler and a set
of things that don't and that's all you
get right so if we wanted to we could
also simplify things further by making
it so that you don't really get to put a
command stream down at all you only get
to put things in to two buckets depth
field and non depth field I don't know
exactly how I feel about that it's a
little confusing I'm just not sure
whether that's a good idea or a bad idea
and so I think I'll probably hold off on
that
but generally speaking as far as the
game render commands are concerned you
know I do think it'd be pretty easy for
us like I said to sort of make sure that
that that these things could be kept
right you know in this in this format
and make it easier people to deal with
if we were to do that default render
commands would not really be something
you would want to return a game render
command structure a game render command
structure you know would be something
that you wouldn't save like that but
hard to say so I don't know exactly what
want to do there but I really do think
that this is now a little bit long in
the tooth and probably isn't something
that the user should have to worry about
thinking through how I could alleviate
that for them without them having to
know about this stuff is a little tricky
and I'm not sure exactly how I might
want to do it when this gets called
I guess just thinking it through so if
we look at what's happening here one of
the things that that probably should be
changed is if we went to a system where
the OpenGL renderer was more of an
explicit thing so when we actually call
win32 init OpenGL we actually get back a
pointer to some sort of thing so that's
not it's not using a global variable or
anything like that if we were to do that
we could imagine the push buffer and
stuff living in there and when we do our
render commands here we would actually
get the memory that we're gonna use we
could actually get that directly from
the renderer now the reason that's kind
of compelling is because if we get the
memory directly from the renderer every
time through then we could also write
our render instructions in terms of
vertices we could write those directly
into card memory in places where it was
appropriate which would make it so that
there wouldn't have to be an extra copy
into Locke's memory in order to do that
transfer I don't know to what extent
again that that really makes much of a
difference for this amount of stuff that
we're sending down but you know not
blowing a bunch of CPU time on the copy
does seem potentially useful uh so I'm
gonna play around with this a little bit
I'm gonna go ahead and say that in our
win32 handmade open shell when we do our
win32 and an open jail one thing you can
see here is that we actually do some
allocation essentially of a renderer the
only difference is we chose to put it
allocations the wrong word
initialization I should say we chose to
make it be a global variable right it's
actually something that's that's defined
globally
and so I think if we look at the hoops
if we look at the open Jill code here we
have this this gentleman right here this
OpenGL struct here where that actually
gets specified yeah so you can see that
is actually something that gets
specified as a global in the world so
you know that seems kind of ugly to me
and it seems like we could improve
things a bit by kind of going down the
route of figuring out where that memory
is coming from and making that stuff
actually work so I'm gonna go ahead and
see what it would take to do that and
clean that stuff up as a start so one
thing you can see here when we do win32
set pixel format that is taking a window
DC here and one of the things that we
would need that to do is have access to
the opengl struck that it's looking the
you know the this the sort of OpenGL
structure that stores everything here we
would need that to be accessible to it
I'm just gonna go ahead and push that
through so that there's no longer a
global and just everyone is passing it
around again it's a little bit of a pain
but it's not a huge deal especially if
we expect this thing to be working as
sort of a generic API thing that people
outside of handmade hero can use it
seems like a good thing to make sure we
get right so let's take a look here
again these are now just most of this is
just turning something that was static
dot reference into something that that
actually has a you know a valid pointer
here so what I miss assuming will happen
here is will actually allocate this
right so this is something that will do
a platform allocation for us
whether that'll be a win32 version
specifically or just a generic version
dad I'm not sure but we'll see so this
should crash immediately for us so we'll
remember to go back and do that right
now I just want to thread the open jail
through it so that everyone has it
properly and we'll go from there um
let's see so this needs here
and most of these things all sort of
artifact I mean this is really what they
should have looked like it's just
there's not a lot of reason for it
meaning it's you know when you're if
you're not trying to sort of push things
out to a sort of more generic generic
generically applicable situation there's
not a lot of reason why you would need
to and generally speaking you should not
do things you don't need to do for lack
of a better for lack of them of a better
way to say it don't do things you don't
need to do because otherwise you're just
wasting time and so this is just kind of
making this into something that has
passed through to people who are using
it don't ask me why we decided to put an
underscore in there when we don't put an
underscore in anywhere else we'll just
pretend we had a good reason for that we
didn't at least not that I know of right
like why is it that way if it's going to
be that way and the answer is lost to
the sands of time at this point where is
that at there we go
okay and the other thing that we could
do here too
is if we want to write this will allow
us during that initialization phase this
will allow us to be a little bit more
specific about what's going on there and
the user will be able to see and they go
ahead and do a certain place on this the
user will be able to see more clearly
where their stuff is coming from which
is good too
it'll be a little clearer to them sort
of how that's working and when they need
to actually pass the renderer handle
around and so on
um so yeah this is just straightforward
text transformation here yeah never mind
guess that's unnecessary
hi so looks like this is the only one
that actually takes the open jail for
some reason is it no
we also don't use multi light down and
multi light up so I feel like they
should probably just get removed I don't
know why we would spend time maintaining
them there we go
please don't require that pal fake seed
letting pod FPL to learning I'll have to
see whether those are used at all
anymore either because I don't think
those are these obviously require the
pointer these
see how we're doing here
you
um wait you know won't this anymore
doing yeah we don't even want this this
is again just old biting test stuff
pretty sure we don't want this either
but
all right I think that's good all right
sue kidding yeah all of this stuff is
just old we don't use any of this
anymore
so that can all go what else we got
again nothing really interesting
happening here we're just kind of doing
a rigid transformation to make these
operate off of a structure that's passed
let's see what else okay oops
you actually get those weird inter caps
right all right so now you know if we
look at sort of what's going on here I I
kind of feel like the so this sort of
thing is probably something that I would
rather have be done up in this
initialization right so this was sort of
something that I hinted at before but
just again simplifying this process of
startup we can do even further here so
in this wind through tune of gel you can
see we've got our OpenGL RC that comes
back here that OpenGL RC is never used
anywhere and so I think the easiest
thing to do here would just be to say
look this returns our OpenGL renderer
and then from then on anywhere we want
to use that we can but I don't think we
want to do this this way because again
this is like really kind of reaching
into that structure we don't want the
people use this to have to understand
that stuff and so like I said I think we
really want to change the to be a little
bit more conventional here so that
people can sort of understand oh I call
this thing to initialize it and then I
get one back and I just use that that
han't you know like a handle so you know
this is I think more what we want it to
look like and when you return you return
that and off you go
so I think that's what we want here and
I think we can go from there so even
just doing this I feel like that was
worth it but we're gonna be able to get
a lot more out of it now because we can
now push that further and make
handle those allocations the beginning
so those can get out of the way of the
user as well okay so let's see here so
one of the things about this you can see
so we would like you to not know in
places like this we'd like you not to
know what renderer you're actually using
so one thing we could also choose to do
here is make this handle be a little bit
more opaque right so inside the renderer
itself we could sort of have the notion
that you don't know what kind of
renderer you got and you know the fact
that it's an OpenGL renderer is just
happens to be the fact that you called
the initialization on OpenGL right so we
could if we wanted to say hey look
there's just a thing called the renderer
and you're gonna get one back right
whatever it is and you don't necessarily
know what what kind it was if you're not
the person who like literally called the
thing initially so for example in here
if we did something like this then when
we come through and we're talking about
OpenGL everywhere what we'd really want
to do is talk about the renderer
everywhere and the reason I'm doing this
is because let's suppose we wanted to
switch to using something else like
direct3d we don't want everyone in our
code here to be passing around a thing
they know to the OpenGL and if they use
in a way that's specific to the way you
would use OpenGL right that's not what
we would want at all and so in order to
sort of make that in order to simplify
that quite a bit
what we would prefer here is if we
always had some way of dealing with
things through a handle we don't
understand okay because that prevents us
from ever baking that understanding into
the rest of the code path so what I'm
suggesting here is for example we do
something like this where we say how
many texture apps we want or something
like that and then this code goes into
the OpenGL side of things
somewhere right something like this so
when we do our initialize OpenGL we say
how many texture apps we want maybe we
even do this where we say what our
maximum vertex counts are so maybe we
even do something where we say okay you
know here is our max vertex count and
those are like basically the parameters
for the render you know that go through
and so these are just things that come
in to that come in through here and so
that kind of looks nice to me because in
that sense when you get back a renderer
now everywhere that we were gonna use
something OpenGL related instead we can
just say okay let's you know let's make
sure that this is something that can be
used just more generically and the other
thing we could do is make something like
this call here B again also somewhat
generic we can actually make all of
these fairly generic and I'll show you
what I mean by that in a second so that
I think we can clean up quite a bit and
we'll go from there
so all right so again mmm just looking
back at what we want to do here so now
anybody who was talking about OpenGL
outside of things we want to make sure
that that's not happening anymore and I
thought there was someone
oh yeah load bitmap right so again load
bitmap here you can see is something
that needs to send down a texture I
again don't want to I don't want to make
that be something that this thinks is
specifically OpenGL so what I want to do
is I want to say something like add
texture up or basically queue texture up
and so what you would do is you would
say here is the texture operation that I
want to do and then you know if we do
want to make sure that that happens
immediately we can write that is not
something I will probably do that way in
the future this will probably be
something that's feed-forward so we
should be able to get rid of this call
in the future now I put out putting out
to that effect to do this call should
could be removed once result texture is
feed forward instead of reported back um
so that's something that we want to
improve a little bit separately but
again that's for tomorrow not something
to consider today so the platform
renderer gets passed into load bitmap
here platform renderer under and that's
something that again we just count on
having been supplied to us and so
everywhere that we have a load BMP call
instead of just passing the name we also
pass the renderer which is you know
where it's going to send that texture
okay
so that's mostly what we need to do here
and if you take a look at the stuff that
still has to now be fixed in here
obviously this is the texture vertex op
stuff the init scene just has to take
that renderer
this default render commands one of the
things that's kind of annoying about the
wave even doing things is this notion of
the white bitmap since we now have an
understanding of a platform handle and
what that platform handle like since we
have an understanding of a platform
texture handle I think we're going to be
able to get rid of white bitmap and make
that be something that we don't have to
have in there anymore
and so hopefully that's something we can
kind of we can kind of nuke a little bit
but we'll see in the meantime it still
needs to be there so what I'm gonna do
is I'm just gonna say that we have a
call we call and that gets whatever the
you know whatever the white bitmap was
for putting in there and again that's
not something that we really need to
think about too hard at the moment
because I think hopefully I'm hoping
anyway that it will go away so moving
along from here what we'd like to do is
just you know have something generic
here we say okay issue all the render
commands that you're going to issue
here's the renderer to issue them to
here's a render commands and so on and
one of the things that I think is kind
of annoying about this is if you look at
when you call issue render commands when
you initialize the render commands here
it seems like we've really kind of we've
got more stuff than we really need to
have going on in these two calls as well
so the window within the window Heights
obviously are things that are not known
here but the draw region is something
that is kind of known here and should
probably have been passed and placed
into here so I'm not super sure why
we're doing both of those things I'd
like to take a little bit of a look at
that
similarly the renderer I think should
get
locked in here and furthermore this this
should probably be more of a pointer
than an actual strut so I think what I
would like to do is do something more
like this you know begin frame and then
down here it's more like end frame right
and that looks a little bit more sane to
me and again this part this right here I
don't actually know what I want to do
with the window width window height
thing I'm conflicted as to whether I
want to pass it here I want to look
inside open jail and just see what we're
doing as far as yeah let me just take a
look here
open jail oh well that's actually gonna
be in here OpenGL render commands yeah I
want to know what we're doing with this
draw region because I don't actually
know so you can see us doing sort of
like the viewport scissor stuff there
right and we use the minimax so really
like I feel like the draw region could
just be passed there the window width
and window height is just for the
overall region so yeah so I'm not sure
how we want to approach that I kind of
feel like we just want to approach that
by passing everything at the head end
and then anything that you know needs to
get saved gets saved you know I feel
like that is just a more sane way to do
this I also feel like max vertex count
probably shouldn't be specified there
probably should be specified here but
it's hard to say right we could make it
so that it can adapt a little bit more
dynamically to the vertex counts that
you want and you can specify those on
demand I'm not sure
whether I care about that or not it's
pretty hard to say seemingly push buffer
and push buffer size that stuff would go
away so ideally what this would look
like is something like this we passed
the render of the draw region in the
window with the window height and and
you know what if we're sending the
renderer down now that I think about it
it can also fill out that white bitmap
so what we end up with is something
that's a lot cleaner we can just say a
begin frame here's the information that
you're actually going to need to draw to
the surface you're drawing to maybe it
looks a little bit more like this a
render window with window height and
draw region of that then you come down
here and you say and and frame this game
render commands this is really like you
know the frame and we could call this
like a you know game render frame I
don't know if you want to actually go
that far or not but you know it could
happen so yeah if we take a look at what
happens here this makes a lot more sense
now so you can just see it flows really
nicely through this whole system and
looks pretty good as far as the swap
buffers call on the OpenGL DC I think
that still wants to be on the outside
because it's very platform specific in
that sense so I think this all looks
relatively good to me
and so you know this begin frame and end
frame call these are sort of virtualized
in the sense that they're going to call
different things depending on which
renderer you were using but I think
other than that it's pretty
straightforward
I mean that looks pretty good to me I'm
pretty happy with that so let's go ahead
and take a look at what we would have to
do to implement something like this you
can see here we're calling we call
something specific when we actually want
to you know to execute this particular
[Music]
we want to start to start up this
particular renderer and then in these
cases when we do our rendering we we
would call with the render handle which
ones were actually wanting to use now
what we're going to need here as far as
the render is concerned this platform
renderer is going to need something that
can identify it and we have a couple
different ways we can do this so one way
we can do this is we can put an enum in
here right which tells us which kind it
is another way we can do it is by having
a pointer to the actual functions that
are going to get called so for example
you know we have a begin frame and an
end frame and then there's a like an add
texture up where is that here it is in a
cue texture app so as far as we're
concerned those you know are things that
have to kind of go through this system
now like I said this this part is kind
of troubling because I almost feel like
this wants to be sort of separate but at
the same time it can't really be
separate because it may want to be
something intimately tied to how the
renderer works and that's that's sort of
the weird part about it so I'm not sure
exactly how we want to how we want this
to play out one thing I would like to
know is inside win32 handmade inside the
actual handmade Hiro codebase I'm
actually kind of curious as far as the
texture ops are concerned
I'm not sure yeah like it uses a texture
op to handle their that it has to know
where to add things and so the texture
op queue itself is you know is sort of
this this secondary thing right it's
this thing and so I suppose that is
actually the thing that we want to have
for add up here so I think I probably
should leave this we do it this way
rather than passing the renderer there I
think I just want the texture up that
the texture queue to be the thing that
we pass here right so I can make that be
so and the problem that we're gonna have
again is just that yeah like until
someone actually calls this all of these
pointers or not all of these like result
textures are not valid now I really
don't like that so I think you know one
thing I might do is say this instead of
that maybe we do this and that way the
result itself yes I could say texture
handle that way the result itself can
get written back later so something like
this our cube texture is yeah right
there so maybe that is a better way to
do this that way when we're loading
bitmaps here we can just do one one
update to the textures and they'll get
loaded into their correct locations
right I guess this might be one way to
do it and again this is mostly just
because I don't really even want this
behavior
I don't like it it's not good I don't I
don't really want these things to be
involved in the process at all what I
wanted was just to have it so that they
are passed forward like you just pass a
number forward 0 1 2 3 or whatever and
off you go
so that's kind of a separate issue all
together but you know that's neither
here nor there so I want to try and make
it so that this thing is the least
dependent on that as I can just cuz I
don't even want that I don't even really
want to have to wait for those things
either way but anyway when we do in it
tests seen here so if we pass the
renderer down the thing is so when we're
actually doing this again that texture
op q thing is something we would need to
be able to get back the knowledge of
where the texture Q was right so we need
a thing here where we can get a texture
op Q I always call it the wrong thing
it's called a render or texture Q I call
texture op Q could you just call it
texture cube the thing that I don't know
about this I'm quite sure that these
should come off of the renderer that
seems pretty obvious because we want the
texture Q's to be able to be things that
are you know per renderer I would think
and again maybe that's wrong maybe we
want the texture Q to just be generic
and it doesn't have anything to do with
the renderer and you just pass in one of
these Q's and they're always hailed the
same way you know maybe that's a smarter
way to do it it's really a tough call
I'm just not sure and so I could see I
mean I could see that being
just a better a better thing and if we
did it that way it would just look like
this yes I just don't do this so if we
did something like this we'd say okay we
can allocate a texture cue from the
renderer and maybe that's the sort of
thing that we then say when we do
texture management we would say on every
frame when we wanted to do that we could
say something like yeah
right something like this and so yeah
like every time before we would go to do
anything on the frame we would maybe
process the textures and then we would
submit the scene and that would just
work and everyone would be happy so it
you know if we did it that way again I'm
just I'm just kind of having a long a
little about this because I'm just not a
hundred percent certain exactly the way
I wanted it but it would look something
like that right
you could allocate extra cue here and
then you you know you would just go
ahead and process the texture cue
anytime you want to by linking the
renderer to it saying like okay hey
render here's the texture cue I expect
you to process this off you go
right so really what we need now is a
dispatch mechanism to make sure that the
right renderer gets called for whatever
it is that you're actually looking at
and there's a couple things we would
need to do there but really you can sort
of see immediately what those calls are
so allocate texture cue will work the
same no matter who you are and so if I
look at the renderer itself I believe we
stuck those in here somewhere
yeah so in it texture cue right and so
this just kind of wants to be something
that put that in here for now it doesn't
need to be out there I don't know where
I don't know if these need to be out
here or not but either way so just
looking at these this needs to be
something that gets called once the
thing is allocated and so allocate
texture queue would just be something
that's in the win32 part of the renderer
because it's an allocation based thing
and so you know we would have in hand
made code something that's like win32
just renderer right dot cpp which is the
startup code for windows ii renderer
sorts of things and the allocate texture
q code would have to live in there again
because it is specific in that sense
right now wouldn't necessarily have to
be it could be that you just need some
kind of a callback to handle memory
allocation I mean just to be a little
bit more specific about how that would
look
so suppose we actually did a thing that
just said allocate texture cube and you
you do it like this right
do something like this if you have a way
to actually do a memory allocation on
the platform something like this you
just use the memory that you're you use
the platform allocation call right and
off you would go and again I'm just not
sure how that wants to look it's a
little bit of an open question again
without knowing like how the person is
integrating this in it's a little bit
difficult to say so again I guess that's
that's sort of the open question of
exactly how that looks I mean maybe the
way we had it was really the best way to
have it where you know hey it's just in
it texture queue so you provide it with
the thing right and it does seem like
you know I don't know after all that
hemming and hawing it does seem like
maybe that's still the best way to do it
because that way you can feed the memory
forward because it's never going to be
something where we where we actually
care how much there is when to to
allocate memory
and I guess I could just also this is
probably something I could do here so I
could just say alright however many of
these I want times the size of the
texture up I don't remember what these
are called just text you out and so you
know yeah I'm okay with that and as long
as it gets passed around I'm fine with
that
all right so that part I think survive
scrutiny the only thing we might want to
do is have a thing in here where we say
what this size is that we wanted rather
than do this multiply ourselves that's
the only thing that looks a little bit
wonky
[Music]
so here's one thing we could do is we
could just say here's how much memory
you get to work with and off you go
right that's kind of a little bit more
interesting potentially so you know this
is another way we could do it we could
just say hey we could say this and that
would basically be saying look here's
how much memory I'm giving you to work
with and if you happen to want to
compute that based out of the texture
app size go nuts otherwise just don't
and I don't care
right yeah it seems pretty recently and
that prevents you from having a mistake
where you're passing that like as long
as you just can pass the size that you
allocated you're fine right so it's just
like in Natick you use this memory
please right that seems totally
reasonable to me because then we can
just say look the texture up count is
the memory size divided by the size of a
texture ah done right and then you know
you go from there
texture
[Music]
something like that so that is a little
bit better I like that better so that's
good all right
um so I don't have any problem with that
and like I said because I felt like
moving that in was starting to get a
little bit weird because really there's
nothing render or specific in here and
unless I can come up with a good
argument for why it needs to be render
so Civic it seems like it just shouldn't
be and so at that point we just say look
this is the memory that we're gonna use
for this I again we you know we could do
it this way or we could do it the other
way that's not really the point here
either way we pass the memory to a thing
and we and at the texture cue and it
goes from there right so that seems good
to me this seems good to me now
again the max vertex count I'm not sure
that's a good way to parameterize this I
think what we'd rather do because this
is fright render just say max fright
count max bright count is going to be
you know for each one of these things
we're gonna need probably like roughly
six vertices I don't know I'm gonna go
ahead and say that the max sprite count
you know maybe our max sprite count is
something like this if I wanted to just
I mean this right here is that and this
right here is that right so I guess I
could just say this is that that's how
many sprites we would be at maximum
pushing down per frame which is a heck
of a lot of sprites I don't know if I
really want that many sprites let's say
we're gonna push that sprite nice price
down we'll see how that is so this will
be our max bright count or another way
to say that might be our max quad count
because that's a little clearer since
since cubes occupy a couple different
ones of those so maybe you know we say
look this is the max quad count per
frame and then you should balance out
your allocations based on what you're
gonna need for that to be true right and
the reason that I don't want to do the
same thing here like I'm passing the
memory in here the reason I don't really
want to pass the memory in here is
because we may need the operating system
to allocate this memory for us in a
special way and so I'm just want to
leave that possibility open so that the
renderer doesn't have to assume that the
memory that it's got is the memory that
it would need it can allocate its own
memory as necessary so we'll let that
happen the rest of this stuff is pretty
straightforward I'm gonna change the
order of these things slightly oops I
have a little key to change to the
opposite way of reading to pet you so if
it's like too sunny out or whatever you
can use that it helps read on a laptop
screen so that all seems good and then
again we've got sort of the begin frame
end frame thing happening here and that
is pretty much what we have to now go
improve because this is going to be this
should be pretty simple to improve or
this should be pretty simple to make
fall in line but the other ones probably
not so much all right
so in here when we do our win32 init
OpenGL let's just do the simplest
possible thing at first we know that
we're going to be getting a max quad
count value in here and so what I want
to do is just let that flow through here
this allocation stuff here we know we're
on win32 so I probably want to just do a
straightforward plat allocate here so I
just want to do like a virtual a lock
and in order to to
get this memory like I said we kind of
want to do we might want to do some more
specific things here now since we know
that the OpenGL part of things right
here is going to be a virtual Alec call
excuse me again that allows me to do I
can make stuff like the push buffer just
be directly bound in here I that's not
gonna be there anymore so what I want to
do here is just say alright there's
going to be let's just say push buffer
memory thing here and that can be 64k if
I want to and that way that's not going
to be a separate allocation then through
here I'm gonna first start out I'll do a
virtual a lock or I can do a win through
to something like that I can do a thing
here where I just allocate whatever one
of these is and I get that back and then
down here I can similarly do a thing
that goes exactly that for these and
this can be well you know what these can
still be max vertex count and then what
I can do is say well alright so as far
as textured rotate vertices are
concerned like I don't know exactly
we're probably end up passing out
indices pretty soon as well so we'll
have to kind of fuss with this stuff a
little bit more but when we do this
allocation we're gonna have to compute
that matched vertex count first and
that's just the max quad count for frame
let's just say times four at the moment
even though that'll be changed push
buffer size and push buffer or now are
not actually going to be used for
anything and in here inside the opengl
subsystem i'm going to store this vertex
array and this bitmap array as being
allocated here and that will not
probably stay true for the duration
but for the immediate moment it will and
we'll sort of see where that goes a
little bit later on I'm going to take
for a minute the allocation from here
and we'll see what we want to do kind of
going forward with that a little bit
later but basically it's just this and
we'll kind of let that ride for now all
right don't know why there's an Y on the
end of that okay so when we go to opengl
managed textures now that's actually not
what that's going to be it's gonna yes
you will get the renderer here but
you'll also get the texture op to
um so I think I don't know why that's
still happening here
I'm not sure maybe we do want to have
that automatic I don't think we do so
I'm gonna not make that be automatic so
I think we're okay with that yeah these
are really memory sized heaven forfend
you've actually passing that many
texture ops but there's no particular
reason for us not to support it so what
the heck let's go ahead and the only
other thing I want to do real quick
before I forget is in win32 handmade I
don't know that we ever call managed
textures and we kind of want to make
sure we do so we do actually there so
that's okay but so we have to actually
change that to make sure that we are
calling that at a reasonable time right
oh sorry I also forgot that this wants a
result pointer okay so now we just have
to do sort of the for lack of a better
term the insulation layer like the thing
that makes it so that you're not dealing
directly with the OpenGL handle let me
see let me just get rid of any other
warnings we have here so this actually
wants that texture cue that's fine this
would be an address though that's fine
and that's fine what is the problem here
load BMP yes okay and now I think we're
down to only the things that I actually
want to fix right so we have to make
that return a renderer let's edit cetera
all right so now we're in a position
where we have to actually decide how we
want to make this thing be abstracted
and you've got lots of options in C++
and they're all lousy which is
unfortunate so one thing you can do is
you can go the regular C++ virtual
function call route and you can go ahead
and where is the renderer here yeah and
you can go ahead and do something you
know like this where you say okay we've
got a like a begin frame call and it's
virtual on the platform renderer and
then like you know the OpenGL renderer
is something that like inherits from one
of those right and what that does is
that essentially what that does is it
implements the following thing like just
so you know this is not magic it's just
a very very simple way of implementing
an abstraction layer that forces you to
do the following thing it basically says
that at the front of platform renderer
or anything that I say derives from
platform renderer there's going to be a
thing that points to a renderer function
table and then it defines something that
looks like this and that something has
like the begin frame function it's got
the end frame function right and that is
literally all it does and then what it
does for you is if you have a platform
renderer in a piece of code something
that looks like this
and then you do begin frame like that
all it does is rewrite everywhere that
you did that to look like this
okay so this is literally all
inheritance does like literally so you
know you don't need C++ to do this for
you it's a convenience feature that if
you want this rewrite rule and this
specific way of building function tables
it can do it for you that's it that's
all if you can't do anything else that's
all it can do there's a lot of reasons
you don't want this and the biggest one
of course is that you don't control this
function table how it works or how you
would save that information if you had
to write meaning if you wanted to record
what type one of these was not only are
you not really supposed to access this
pointer without enabling a thing called
R TTI but it's not stable across runs so
typically I don't prefer to do that in
this case I wouldn't necessarily
discourage someone from going that route
because I don't think the risks are very
high here I don't think we'll have to be
storing information necessarily about
the renderer in that way so normally I
would caution you to be very wary of
using C++ as inheritance model because
it's a very bad model doesn't really
work for a lot of reasons but in this
case I wouldn't be too adverse to it I
don't think you're gonna run into a lot
of problems here because this is an
incredibly simplistic use of multiple
different types that want to be used in
the same way I'm still not going to do
it because I hate it that much even in a
case where I think it wouldn't be too
deleterious I'm not going to use it
instead what I'd rather do is make a
platform renderer type field and I'm
just gonna use that type field myself
it's a little more typing than using the
C++ as automated way but it means I can
guarantee to myself that if I ever want
to refer to one of these renderers
across runs I can using a stable enum
that I know what it means and that can't
be changed by the compiler out from
underneath me without warning and/or
change when I go to compile on a
different platform but where it may be
incompatible
so what I'm gonna do here is say okay my
renderer type I can be a couple of
different things there's a software
renderer and OpenGL renderer mm-hmm
maybe a direct3d renderer right so I'm
just guessing like let's suppose that
this is sort of what we expected to see
in the future these are the types of
renderers that we want to have and so
what I'm going to say is that every
renderer that we've got has to start
with one of these and then based on
which one of those it actually says I
will do something different on each of
those dispatches so I will take a
different course of action based on
which one of those I saw okay so once I
have this piece of information there
what that implies to me is that I'm
going to have inside my renderer when I
actually create these things I want to
have a thing where I can in OpenGL right
in the actual structure any renderer
that we have is gonna start with one of
these like what does call that header so
again what I'm doing is I'm literally
doing the exact same thing C++ would
have done I'm just doing it in a
slightly different way C++ would have
put a pointer here for every struct one
that you couldn't see but that was
actually there and that pointer would
tell you in a specific way which one of
these was that's instead of that I'm
using an enum and then we're gonna
dispatch on the enum so every renderer
will start with one of these and when I
go to allocate one I'm responsible in my
initialization call for just saying
which one I am but that's about it
right so inside win32 handmade opengl in
here where we initialize one of these
load the wiggle extensions do all those
sorts of things when we're actually
doing all this I want to at some point
have someplace and do I really not have
oh there it is OpenGL in it I'm like in
whatever the function call that's that's
generally the same for all the platforms
which it looks like in this case is open
jail in it which is this I'm just gonna
set the renderer type and maybe I'll
actually call this renderer type I'm
gonna set the renderer type in this case
to be renderer type OpenGL that way
everyone who dispatches on this in the
future can immediately tell which type
of renderer they're dealing with and
they can go from there which is nice
that also means because I did this you
actually get something else for free
something that C++ sucks at doing which
is that you can actually just load from
a file the kind of thing that you want
and initialize that one because
basically you are already gonna write
the code necessary to do that whereas
C++ doesn't write that code for you
which is kind of annoying right so what
I can do here is instead of calling
win32 init OpenGL what I could do here
is say win32 you know init renderer and
pass the type of the renderer that I
actually wanted so for example what I
could say is instead of inside here
instead of this being win32 in an OpenGL
that I call directly I could have a
thing where we just say all right
there's a win32 allocate renderer and in
here we pass a platform render type and
we also expect you to pass the window DC
right if we're gonna do so and and that
I still do actually want this max quad
count per frame as well so then if you
do something like that it's pretty easy
for me to say look let's switch on the
render type let's see which one you
asked for and we'll give you back that
one so then in the future this gives us
the place where we would actually have
these sorts of things occur
like so now in general one can assume
that something like metal is not going
to happen right this by the way turns
the platform renderer so you know in the
future we might also want to make a
thing which just announces ahead of time
which ones are supported on a particular
platform I'm not sure how we would
necessarily want to do that but you know
something like this and then these
aren't ready yet but this one is and we
just thumb through to this just like
that so that's just a way to make it so
that we can call that sort of
generically and that way inside a
renderer you don't have to actually say
you want opengl specifically you could
instead say i want you know this
renderer type here's the max quad count
for frame and here's the OpenGL DC right
and that way this could actually be
something that's parametric it could be
passed it on the command line it could
be something that you switch at runtime
in a dialog box and you know you're
gonna get back the renderer that you
asked for here right so now this also
gives us a way to implement these calls
here so you know these are the calls
we're actually dealing with like so
and so each of these now has the ability
to do a switch to figure out which one
it's going to use right now one of the
interesting things about this is you can
actually also because you have a switch
statement you can do some things that
you couldn't otherwise have done such as
amortise like code across that jump so
for example inside process text or cue
if we wanted to we could actually do the
DQ first then do the dispatch after the
DQ and that would just work right so
there's other stuff we could choose to
do in here if we wanted to and it just
depends on whether we actually do want
to or not now as far as the game render
commands are concerned I think these are
just gonna mostly be straight dispatches
so for the moment I'm not gonna do
anything fancy I'm literally just gonna
do a thing here where we do our switch
we know that these are the only ones
that we're going to be handling on
Windows and right now we also know that
it's always going to look like that
because you're pretty much going to
always we're never gonna implement any
other renderers in here although if
someone else wanted to obviously they
could add more people in here if they
wished but that's not really probably
something we would be doing ourselves
anyway so as far as these dispatches are
concerned here we now just want to go
like okay how do we want to actually
dispatch out here again these are just
ones that we're not going to deal with
so for right now we're just going to
call things exactly we were calling them
which may not be the thing that we want
to do eventually but it's something that
will do for the moment just to keep the
current process correct
so anyway
there we go so this will dispatch off to
our OpenGL managed textures call which
again you can kind of see the way that
it works I almost want to put the switch
statement inside the DQ part because
once you DQ really it's simpler to just
have a single call implemented at the
render layer so it doesn't have to do it
this way and this is a pretty expensive
thing to do so I don't know to what
extent we really wanna I'm thinking this
might be a little bit this might be
changed a little bit from the way that
it's currently being done but you know
we'll see so as far as n frame is
concerned we know that all that does is
it just calls this it's gonna use oops
well actually to be honest I think it
probably should just dispatch directly
and just call frame and so this in the
future this OpenGL render commands I
think that really should just take game
render commands like so and this should
be commands renderer and while we're at
it we can assert that the type of the
renderer is the one that we think it
should be just in case somebody really
screwed up and for some reason is
passing around completely bogus handles
which we don't want them to do it would
be kind of weird if they did but you
know who knows
so here's us sort of extracting the
previous knowledge that we actually
needed and calling this thing the way
that we're calling this thing and again
these would be pretty straightforward as
well once we actually have this
implemented we just call them here and
off we go and again in here we if we
were free to basically complain about
any buddy who we don't want to support
on this platform okay and again another
way to look at this is just to say that
well you know the downside of doing a
switch dispatch is that it's people have
to add their stuff to these tables right
whereas if you do a planar based one
they just fill in the pointer that they
want and it can be it doesn't have to
touch these I don't have a strong
opinion one way or the other because the
bonus of the switch style is you can see
how everyone is working in one place
which I tend to prefer I like being able
to look inside a particular call and go
who are all the people who might be
fielding this thing and so absent an
eventual tool that actually allows us to
have both which is what we would want I
actually tend to prefer this way better
I would rather know the code then not
know the code like the other way the
benefit is not knowing the code you
don't have to know all the people who
might feel to render a call someone can
just add a new one in there and you'd
never know right sometimes I find that
to be off-putting and so I tend to like
things that use central dispatch more
than things that don't if you like
things that don't that's when you want
to use function pointers hopefully
that's a reasonable way to understand it
right
anyway so looking at this as far as the
dispatch is concerned the only thing
we're really interested in here is a
begin frame and as far as begin frame is
concerned I don't really know to what
extent we want to go down the OpenGL
specific allocation route but I want us
to be able to go down that route so what
I want to do is inside OpenGL in it I
want to have the the initialization part
of things I want to have that be able to
do those buffer sorts of operations as
necessary if that makes sense
um so I'm just leaving that Avenue open
and that's why this looks the way it
does I'm gonna take the game render
commands and just put them in here for
now but again that's not what we might
do in the eventual far future right so
I'm gonna call open she'll begin Frank
here I'll go ahead and change the name
of this to OpenGL and frame just to line
up with it and all I'm gonna do is
translate the pointer and then I'm gonna
pass these types along like so and I'm
just going to expect it to figure out
what to do in this circumstance
all right so in the event that we're
going to call open Jill begin frame
here's the renderer I'm gonna pass the
window with the window height and the
draw region what I want to do now is I
want to go into the platform layer and I
want to get rid of the that sort of
defaults I think it's actually not in
there anymore I think it's in their
default render yeah this thing I want
this to go away and I'm gonna put this
in here and probably I will I will do a
little bit more work than just that as
well so we'll kind of we'll see sort of
how that shakes itself out as we go a
little further down the line but that's
sort of a separate issue alright so in
here when we actually do begin frame
we're gonna set this stuff up here and
we're probably going to have some more
work to do with how we want this to be
set up in general but what am I do here
is this stuff is all known right so
inside the OpenGL renderer we know like
this is a our white bitmap is known our
bitmap array is also known so is our
vertex array and our map max vertex
count
we didn't store but we should
when we actually initialize this stuff
okay so we want that and as far as these
push buffer things are concerned like I
saying those should now just be we don't
need to have those be separately
allocated so here I'm just gonna say
look we want the size of whatever our
push buffer memory is the base pointer
for that is just going to be whatever
the push buffer memory was and same
would be true of where we're at
currently those pointers kind of advance
this is all fine but not exactly what I
want in this case so the these widths
and Heights are based on this draw
region that's passed in and the window
is not the window width and height is
really just something that is used later
on that doesn't actually have to be
observed much as far as the switches
back to the renderer it doesn't really
have to be observed much as far as
anyone else is concerned so it's not a
setting the settings these two are
settings because they affect how big our
back our backing textures are so those
are important settings wise but the rest
of it really isn't an issue so what I'm
gonna do here is make a few make a few
changes to start with what I'm going to
do is say all right the draw region is
an actual parameter that just gets saved
in here as is the window width and the
window height so the game render
commands will keep that information with
them as a direct setting so the commands
and these this is going to be an arrow
in a second here the commands will save
directly what those are for future
reference but then it will also and let
me go ahead and change these two arrows
here because remember we're actually
just going to use
a dresser so what we want to do here is
say okay these settings actually
reinitialize when we see these change so
we're gonna save these but they're not
actually part of the settings and then
we are going to use these this width and
height here is actually the width and
height that we get from the draw region
so this coming here but the important
thing to remember is this stuff should
actually now come from the renderer so
if we actually go back to the opengl
side of things and when we're actually
initializing OpenGL itself what we want
to do in there is Jonas there it is when
we actually initialize our settings
which I don't know when we if we ever do
if we just let them get zeroed out what
I want to do here is actually set those
settings here because that way what I
can do is say the command settings are
going to come from the settings that we
had set in OpenGL these right here
current settings
so that will be initialized here and
then these when you start will just be
these game Raider commands will just be
initialized from whatever the whatever
the render was currently using you know
I'm saying cuz that's what I actually
want that to come from so the current
settings is what the settings will be
but then they immediately get
overwritten by the draw region because
we know that that gets updated every
frame anything else you might want to
update you would have to change send to
the commands separately and we could now
that we have a more official rendering
API we could take these out of here and
actually put them into a separate call
you make but I don't really think I want
to do that because it seems like a
totally reasonable place to bundle them
up and put them here so I'm gonna just
leave that the way it is okay so
renderer so as far as this just
concerned really doesn't do anything
right now and that's just because we
don't have other renderers at the moment
that's just you know that's just the way
it is OpenGL managed textures begin
frame and end frame I guess are not
actually defined in these yet which why
is that oh it's because these are kind
of in a weird order which is a little
bit bizarre but that's fine so I'll just
go ahead and define these
and that reminds me we did not add as I
wanted to add into the render commands a
pointer to the actual renderer now we
don't really have to do that and maybe
the argument is we shouldn't I mean when
we look at it it's like do we really
need that in there because we could just
do this right and maybe that's better
because why not hard to say I'm not sure
I have a strong opinion about that
either way but I mean I can see an
argument for it either way
right I don't know how I feel about that
I really don't have strong opinion but
that's what that's what we're going with
for now
um what do you say you needed a renderer
we can provide one of those to you all
right
so just to walk through that my OpenGL
in it here
[Music]
how does definition changed okay and so
open drilling it in this context needs
to take opengl pointer itself and i
think everything else is right yeah so I
think that's basically it let's just go
through and debug and then we'll just do
a quick little check to make sure our
API is what we want
hmm oh that's not debugging it's not
what I meant to do at all
although I guess we've got a good bug
there so let me just go ahead and do it
so we're not resetting our our vertex
count it looks like so I think I just
forgot to zero out that structure let me
just do that first and then we'll step
through I want to step through I just
figured since there was an obvious bug
we might as well do it
all right so in the render commands
themselves what I wanted I want to make
sure I set everything so we've got yeah
it's just the vertex count is the only
thing we didn't set so now that's
initialized and we're good to go so
that's everything and let me just double
check to make sure everything is kosher
here if we take a look at our our
process after the eight billion windows
processes a lot of machine that's not
doing anything mind you unbelievable
here's us let me just get a few more can
I get more columns in here
how do i how do I get there we go like
how do I get something I actually find
useful
what just happened I can't click on
anything I have no idea what is going on
all right
so let me sort by image name here just
so I could find us
there's our renderer
I will say as far as like as far as
commit is concerned there it's quite
large is that actually us did we
actually allocate that much and if so
when did we allocate it I'd like to take
a quick look at that if you don't mind
so let's take a look here I'm gonna
force this to be on top assuming it
still has that feature of course it
doesn't well so I'm just want to look at
see when that commit actually happens
I'm assuming it's part of our render
initialization I just want to know who's
responsible so here's our commit charge
currently so if you look at how much is
committed there that's 23 megabytes if
I'm reading this correctly right because
this is this is in kilobytes already so
this is 20 3 megabytes committed I don't
actually know why because if you
actually look at what we've done here
it's almost nothing so who actually
committed the 23 megabytes I guess
that's just what Windows what it costs
to open a single window with nothing in
it because we haven't done anything or
unless the C runtime library maybe did
something I don't know anyway not great
let's take a look at this allocation
here again doesn't affect us much in
terms of our committee charged I'm gonna
go ahead and step over the renderer
allocation and see what happens there
I'm assuming that's where a lot of that
comes from well you know it's a fair bit
of allocation but more in line with what
I would have expected right so because
we do we allocate sizeable very large
buffers for streaming vertices so 132
megabytes is not what I would like to
see there but I could we should go check
but I could buy that so I don't know if
our test scene it might be our test
scene it's I don't know how much space
we surrend test see how much we store in
there but we'll see so when we load
these textures in I'm assuming those
don't really do much yeah
so still right around there nothing
particularly weird going on so now I'm
going to call begin frame again render
group push simple scene again not really
you can see some of that stuff getting
paged in because we're now actually
using it well page gin is wrong but
becoming active and then we'll do it end
frame to render and whoa
so really beefy I mean just a massive
hit for calling in frame right so I
don't know I mean I'm assuming that's a
driver situation that the driver is
allocating all that on our behalf
like it's compiler or something but I
don't know I just want to make sure
we're not doing something really dumb so
let's just double check here we are
again at a you know somewhat reasonable
size for what we would expect just going
through here we're you know
so even just even just this it's
probably this this is maybe where our
textures get allocated or something I'm
guessing so here we are at a sort of
somewhat understandable amount of memory
we step into opengl chains settings I'm
assuming that freeing frame buffers
isn't going to do anything and freeing
programs cuz that's just getting rid of
stuff right so that won't change much so
here's the compile phase no big hit
there we're gonna create the resolved
frame buffer so that took a hit but not
of the form we're talking about here
gonna create another frame buffer so
just just that it's just that one call
allocated 300 megabytes and when I say
Alkaid I mean like reserved we don't you
know we don't know that anyone actually
needs it it's just reserved I don't know
why but that's where it is going right I
mean that's let's step in there so
there's our bind nothing has happened
yet
here's our color handle
so yeah it's it's reserving 200
megabytes for that texture is that a
reasonable amount for it to do I'm
curious you know maybe it is so we have
width times height so that's the size of
in pixels like that's how many pixels
there are the filter type is and the
multi sampled thing is relevant only in
that multi sample will need to store
more data so what's our default texture
format here I assume color index
well color index is 0 in this case so
it's GL rgba 8 is what's actually being
allocated here oops
so if that were the case I mean this
should be pretty tiny is this multi
sampled it is so if it's multi sampled
so this is RGB a eight so it's four
that's three megabytes right and so how
many multi samples are there gonna be
right well we know it allocated 200
megabytes roughly you know I'm saying so
how many samples would it have to store
if how come I can't edit this I hate
Visual Studio come on here we go
so it would be 56 samples maybe it's
forcing it into a non RGB a 8 state or
well you know it could be that because
later ones are in different
are in different formats
we should look so they're 16 so right so
this would be more like that
so you know it's not out of the question
I mean I guess what I would say is this
multisample
buffers are pretty darn expensive that's
the case I hadn't really thought that
through before but that's really nasty I
feel like that gives us a good impetus
to only use that just to rasterize our
[Music]
cube edges because that's the only thing
we use multi sampling for cuz that's
just too much memory you know
especially if we're if we store things
in 16 that you know obviously if we
store them in not in 16 bit it's a lot
easier but I mean looking through there
so I'm just gonna run this one more time
here looking at the the memory usage
there I do feel like and again this to
be just to be clear the reason that I
assumed that it's we're seeing that hit
on our side is because OpenGL probably
is allocating a backing region for those
textures should they need to get swapped
out of the card so it's actually telling
insert in a way it's sort of telling us
a proxy for what's happening on the card
right
those those frame buffers are being
reserved on the card and we're reserving
a matching space for them on the CPU
side but I care about it either way
right even though this isn't really
getting used in terms of CPU memory I
still it's a problem in fact it's it's a
worse problem because the GPU is the one
that actually has the more constrained
memory in most circumstances I'm
interested to see if I change this to
RGB a8 if that memory drops in half and
it didn't quite so it does a little bit
right you can see that it does it shaves
quite a bit off there's like 300
megabytes saved there but again I think
probably because there's a bunch that
are allocated that we're already RGB a
color color channel 0 was always that
way yeah you don't really get you don't
really get much of a other having for
the the earlier parts
what I will say is that you don't see
much of a difference so probably we
could have gone with with a bit either
way like it's not really causing any
problems for us either but that's kind
of a separate issue lighting might be a
place where we see that causing more of
a problem but you know we'll see
either way I'm fine with all that the
the the amount of memory that's required
for those buffers though just seems like
a problem to me
and again I think that's pretty much
entirely due to the multi sampling so
you know if we were to turn multi
sampling off
so here we are with multi sampling off
and I mean I just look at the difference
between those you know it's it's kind of
nuts right so it's hard to say I mean
the problem is I really do think we want
the multi sampling so I think we're
gonna want to do some work to minimize
the degree to which multi sampling comes
into play perhaps making it so that it
doesn't happen on the other on on other
depth feels which I think we try to do a
little bit of but you know it's a little
bit hard to do I'm gonna go in here and
make it so that we're back up to a
reasonable frame rate just by again
reducing those texture change calls
since I believe that's our stress point
currently so what I'm gonna do here is
just change it so that we don't have
that and so then now if we look kind of
at the at the just the image quality
it's a little bit probably difficult for
folks to see it out there because it's a
relatively it 1080p is a relatively high
resolution for internet video
compression so you're probably just not
gonna see the quality difference but I'm
just taking a little look there at that
I'm gonna now turn that multi sampling
off
and take a look at what ends up
happening again just looking at the
lines and it's it's obvious like you
could it's it's much better with the
multi sampling on there's really no
question I'll just double check more - I
should I could just make a key that
turns out on and off since we allow that
but you just see you see a lot less
creepy crawlies on those edges I mean
I'm looking at them and I just it really
looks a lot it a lot smoother to me on
those edges with the multi sampling
turned on so I feel like I feel like we
need to go ahead and figure out a way to
just make sure the depth peels don't use
multi sampling because it's maybe just a
little too much at that point I don't
know what else to do because the problem
is we compound like you know one multi
sampling buffer maybe okay
but in multi sampling buffers where n is
however may depth peels we want with
right now we're using four and you know
I don't see us using appreciably you
last two would be the absolute minimum
but we probably need at least three and
the more you use the nicer it is I just
don't see a lot of ways around having
that sort of deeper color effects so I
don't know what to say obviously if you
can afford it you leave it on I mean you
know in the future graphics cards they
always have more and more and more
memory on them so you know it's fine but
we probably will need a mode that and I
mean maybe the answer is no we don't do
that we just you turn multi sampling off
on lower memory graphics cards right
wait why is pixelation hint true if
pixelation hint is true shouldn't the
renderer be pixel izing things
why is that set to true
I think that was just a bug that was
probably causing our image quality to be
considerably worse than it was yeah that
was just a bug all right anyway so I'm
gonna pop over to win32 hand-made now
and just fix the places where this was
something that was where our API changes
cause problems so I'm gonna go ahead and
and sort of change the way that was
working here so if we take a look at the
game render commands here Jimmy what I'd
like to do you can kind of see this the
way this stuff was working at ahead of
time we were coming in through the main
sortie and only initializing that render
commands once I don't want to do that
anymore what I'd like to do instead
right is I want to move this stuff up to
the allocation phase and I want this
default render commands to be called
every time so when we start doing the
stuff in here I mean doesn't really
matter where we call it but you know
here is fine
what I'd like to do is sort of harmonize
all of this with what we were doing for
we want this the Settings width and
height here that's actually what we're
sort of as far as our drawing is
concerned that's sort of something
that's set a little differently this
this global back buffer nonsense here
that's actually where we want to get
this from so it's a little weird the way
that we're doing it but you know it
should look like this
just the way that we're doing it it
should look like that all right so those
are the things that actually determine
what you know what we're going to use is
our basic basic size is and then when
you when you actually call a renderer
begin frame where is that call
it is so when you actually call begin
frame we want to pass the renderer here
and then we want that window width and
window height which are these two things
and we want the draw rich and that we
computed that this all then goes away
and anything that's using render clean
sphere kind of needs to now use an arrow
instead of what it was using before but
that sort of separate issue I don't know
what this was doing this probably
doesn't want to be doing this anymore
I'm gonna get rid of this stuff okay
we're gonna address those two guys in a
second this is gonna give us back our
renderer so this here is just the same
as what we did in our render a test
write this code wants to be essentially
the same so I'm just gonna go ahead and
do that so if we do this it's like
literally exactly the same code except
for who we call to give us the texture
cue memory so in here what I want to do
and you know we could we could do this
without an allocate to this could
literally just be like how many of these
we want
I mean maybe an easier way to do it
would have literally been to say oops
instead of this we could just do
hey here's the texture ops right and
then it's just like hey that way you
never really call an alligator and you
can just say look you know use use
whatever man it's fine
and so we can do that certainly you know
and maybe that's a better way to go for
now so it's it's you're not calling an
alligator when there was no reason to
call an alligator right so we've got the
OpenGL DC here we know our max called
cloth for frames we pretty much this is
just as is like there's nothing magic
about that and then if we've got our an
it texture cube clock here we need to
actually include those into here which
we'll do in a second the texture queue
is now just that texture queue so we
don't need to call any of this stuff
I'm not sure
not sure why we decided to do this this
again looks like kind of when we took
out all of that stuff where we were
starting to use normalized device
coordinates it feels like we should just
leave this I mean it kind of seems like
that's what we should have done because
since we come through here and we
already did the work of mapping the
coordinates into normalized device
coordinates we add 0 to 1 instead of
negative to 1 but I mean big deal that's
a pretty easy thing to change we then go
through a ton of gyrations just to like
undo that later I kind of just want to
go do that I'm you know what remind me
before we end here and I want to go do
that right now
but anyway render commands should not be
oh because I changed it to frame that's
why I say it should not be an unknown
identifier see here just frame frame
[Music]
this is process texture cue takes the
renderer and the texture cue where we
want to do that it's hard to say because
there's a lot of different places you
could choose to do it and there's
different reasons why you might choose
different ones
that's just frame this stuff now doesn't
have to happen which simplifies that
which is kind of nice
where do we all are we call it in here
though yeah
okay so finally what I would like to do
here is this actually needs to be
handled a little bit more specifically I
suppose that there is one more thing we
might want to do here which is that the
swap buffers call is still on the
outside which is probably not correct
probably what we want to do is have that
just bound in there so you know it's
it's kind of hard to say but it feels
like that's probably what would want to
happen the reason I say that is because
you're only gonna call swap buffers if
you're running OpenGL and since the
renderer needs to eventually support
direct3d we probably don't want to have
a hard-coded call to swap buffers on the
outside when that should really be
wrapped up in the rest of the code now
since this is a CS own DC window I have
no idea why we're calling get DC again
in fact we kind of call get DC a
ridiculous number of times for no reason
whatsoever
it's just kind of dumb and I don't know
why we do it just because we're
ridiculous maybe that's the reason
because you can see here in each case
we're actually getting the same DC as
well so it doesn't make a lot of sense
let's just not we'll just call this
surrender or DC and go from there the
OpenGL RC is not something we actually
care about in this case and that's
something we actually use so let's call
this the renderer DC here and let's go
ahead and move the swap buffers out to
somewhere that makes some sense
rid of it here and get rid of it here so
if I now go back into the OpenGL
renderer and we take a look at what's
happening an end frame here I'm just
going to go ahead and throw that
and one of the things that we're
actually going to need on that endframe
call is again we're gonna need a way to
know which DC we were supposed to be
using now we could choose to save that
DC and it's kind of a little bit hard to
say whether we should or should not do
that since we know this is called from
the platform side of things it's pretty
easy for the platform to just tell us
what the DC is we're supposed to be
using I don't know to what extent I
don't know to what extent that is what
we would want
I guess for now we can just do this and
I think that's what I'll do to avoid
having to think about it too hard but in
the future we may want to do something
fancier there I guess it's all I would
say and that means that in here we no
longer have to call that right okay so
for this stuff here I'm just gonna go
ahead and nerf that out for now and and
really actually I think I'll do one
better I'm actually gonna move it out of
here it doesn't really belong in here
anymore
and I'm just gonna put it inside here as
sort of a like hey by the way remember
this thing sort of a situation because
when we want to eventually make this go
and do a direct3d and so forth and and
put the software under back in I don't
know if we're gonna want to look at what
we did here probably not but we'll see
so when we actually do win32 display
buffer and window what I want to do is
go ahead and nerf that and instead just
have that call end frame on the renderer
and leave it at that right so I think
that's everything that I wanted this is
supposed to take the frame as well so we
knit texture cue is the only thing
that's not defined in here why it's not
defined in here I'm not sure probably
because we're not actually including
renderer dot C I can't say whether I
care whether we include that or not so I
guess I just will for now so taking a
look at the renderer test I want to make
sure it still works okay and then I
would also like to make sure that the
game works okay which it might not
because we just made a major set of
changes to it mm-hmm but it actually
appears fine at the moment so that seems
all good so that's a pretty nice change
pulling those out I think is good again
that's just getting us further along the
line I didn't get to a couple of things
I want to do today unfortunately but
that's just the nature of API cleanup I
mean the important part is that you have
to focus on things you want to make
cleaner they're right I did want to do
that one mouse oriented to do so I just
wanted to take a look at that so just to
refresh your memory and what that is in
the win32 code where we've got the mouse
you in the mouse v you can see us
translating them here into
device-independent coordinates and then
we immediately blow them back out now
the reason that's weird is because if
you remember we actually set the the
mouse x and mouse Y up when we go to use
them we are actually doing that
translation right so you can see here
when we actually use the mouse X here's
us setting it so that's irrelevant
here's us defining where it gets past
also irrelevant in here where we have
the world mode using this for update and
render world where we set this you can
see us just storing it in here right and
we just use a delta to figure out how
much it's moving so literally that is
just relative to the screen size which
we don't have to care about really one
way or the other right that will just
affect these about these constants that
we stuck in there is about the only
thing that that would change because the
game doesn't use mouse input so it
doesn't matter right so the only place
that we're actually using that in here
is is this and we then have to call clip
space from pixel space I think the only
reason we even have that function is to
support this in fact that is true
so we're forcing the renderer to have
this thing for no reason and
the we could just leave this in clip
space the mouse coordinates and clip
space and that would solve our problem
completely right um so I feel like we
kind of just want to do that maybe this
is dumb and I'll regret it later I'm not
sure but if you notice what happens when
I do that if I just do this because it's
not coming in and clip space at the
moment then you notice we can't click on
anything here right because the mouse is
wrong
let me also set the bill to to optimize
build so that you can see the frame rate
full frame rate so you know it's not
just lag causing it there oops right I
can't I can't do anything here I can't
click don't ask me why those are down
there that's interesting anyway so given
that that's the case I need some way now
to fix that and like I said I think all
that we have to do is just make sure
that when we are actually processing
these mouse coordinates we just make
sure that we put them into negative one
to one space right I don't know that we
have any way to do that in a single call
where is our clamp here it is so we have
a clamp zero to one map to range and you
can see the way that that works here
right
if we wanted a negative one to one map
to range I don't know what exactly we'd
call it but like
something like that it's not a great
name I apologize
so if we if we have a function here
that's gonna produce this result for us
then if you look at what happens we look
at the range max min and we say look if
we can then we're going to divide by
that range so we get the T excuse me
we get the t-value mapped within it now
the easiest way to do this without
thinking about it too hard is just to
say well when this comes out what we
really wanted to do is start from here
and then go out to there right we could
try to be fancier and multiply this in
I'm not going to bother right another
thing we could do is just say it like
this because we know this for use of the
number from zero to one so this will
produce the number from negative one to
one
right so if we then go back to our win32
code and we do a clamp by normal map to
range and I didn't really mean to put
that whole thing in there now when we do
this the mouse U and V will be in clip
space which is what we want and we can
simply ignore this in its entirety here
and and make this all happy right I can
also change these to the more modern way
that we've been writing those types
which is f/32 and off we go so now these
are in clip space and that should be a
handier sort of a handy way to pass them
down and in theory now we should get
what we want
right and that's a really nice thing
because now everything's flowing through
nicely and you're not undoing things too
so you can do them again right which
doesn't seem like a good reason
now why these things aren't pinned to
the top of the screen I'm sure there's a
good reason for that I don't really want
to know what it is the moment so what
you'll notice now is my my mouse
controls however for rotation and
scaling are broken why again it's just
because we've changed the scale on those
and all we had done before is just used
some arbitrary constants to scale how
fast these things were going we want to
probably Jack them up quite a bit
probably even more than what I just did
because that's not going to be enough
you can see how slow they're still doing
let's do another 10 10x
still too slow this may have gotten too
fast now
a little bit too fast
the rotation actually feels okay it's
really just the scaling maybe that feels
a little bit fast I might back it down
just a hair and this one down maybe even
more of a hair a bigger hair that feels
pretty good and then I think we're good
to go alright so that seems good to me
and while we're at it in there I mean we
might as well make it explicit that this
is like clip space right and again since
I think we allow VIII's as types now we
could also just say that right and then
anyone who is actually working on these
you know in this case if you just want a
mass fee you can just say input clip
Mouse good space Mouse pee and you can
grab that like so that's a good point
in here again this is just now something
you can access directly clip space mouse
pee and then finally when we set it in
here when we're setting these we can
just set these directly so you know
let's just set them here clip space
Mouse px is that clips facemask pe why
is that and then so that sets all of
those up and it's clear now to the user
what that value is which we didn't
really have before so that seems also
like a good thing this is also easier to
do now because that just copies all
three values which is easier so that's
nice too so I think that's I'm pretty
happy with that that all seems
reasonable all of this seems to be
working properly as well which is nice
and yeah I don't see anything I don't I
have to figure out why those get set to
why those don't get snapped to normalize
positions I must have changed how that
worked inadvertently when we were
changing the other stuff but we'll see
anyway so
I feel like this is backwards
the rotation feels backwards based from
the Y version tonight
it feels weird to have one of them be
one way one of them in there I don't
know it love to think about that anyway
I think that's all for today that I want
to do at the moment I'm pretty happy
with all of that um and if we actually
look at the renderer API now in win32
render test that startup looks even
better than it used to right so you make
a texture queue that seems nice right
you make a renderer that seems nice
and in fact this doesn't need the DC
anymore
so we could even just do that if we
wanted to I wonder if it should pass the
window handle there it may be that we
want to just pass the window we'll see
I'll wait till we do addy 3d render or
some day to think about whether which
one we want there it's pretty easy to
change we can set the vsync this should
probably be a call on the renderer so
that might be something we want to
change I'm not sure about that though to
be honest that may be something that's
better put into the settings so that I'm
not quite sure about like in fact I kind
of do think that should be in the
settings I kind of think this should
probably go in the settings you know
what I mean so I almost feel like this
should be something that that in that
settings stuff where we do like Open GL
change settings
I feel like in here is almost where that
should be
so whenever we change the settings we
would do something like this and since
we don't want to make a wiggle call
there you know we would just thunk down
to the OpenGL platform layer for win32
like at that point so yeah I kind of
feel like that's what should be
happening there one way or the other I'm
going to go ahead and not do that yet
and I'm gonna go ahead and put inside no
let's do it let's just do it you might
as well so what I'll do there is just
say that inside the settings when we set
this here I'm gonna say like vsync was
false so they'll be a request vsync that
happens in the settings and then we'll
just say look in here if that setting is
is that setting will be you know will
try to be respected in here to the
extent that it can be and so when we're
actually going through here and
processing the new settings we'll will
do that right so OpenGL current settings
we will do it like this and then say
request vsync if so we'll do that if not
we'll do this and what we can do is
again make this be a platform specific
call because we don't necessarily know
that that is a call we will have
available to us right we don't know we
don't know whether you know what that
might be on a particular platform or
anything like that so we'll just do a
platform opengl set vsync here and we'll
put the vsync enabled
we can also pass the OpenGL renderer
here and then what I'll do is I'll just
do vsync enabled 1 or 0 I guess and this
will just pass you know this here and
since we don't know whether we're gonna
get this call I mean I think we always
will but just in case let's only call it
if we actually have it also seems like a
pretty obvious thing to want to do and
so in here we can also say like this has
to be defined by the platform layer you
know I'm saying by default we'll set
we'll set it up so that we ask for vsync
by default because that's what we
normally want like we normally don't
want to tear but if the person doing the
rendering wants us to tear then okay you
know it's a it's something they can do
and that's fine so then all we need is a
place for that to actually exist so in
the render setup when we issue those
commands which should be here there it
is we just want to have a request vsync
and now I think we're good you know as
far as requesting vsync or not it's
concerned let me make sure that we
aren't getting it over here
hard to say
sure looks vsync II let me just see what
ends up happening there what's the name
of that call
that is not working
we're never getting to that call what's
going on
is that just because we're in was it
compiled out what happened I guess it
was compiled out so we are calling
Wiggles swept interval zero although I
guess I should verify that we never call
it again so we did request that we not
do it so I think we're good there and
again it doesn't actually obey it
because we're going through the windows
compositor and we'd have to actually
open a full screen window for real in
order to not get throttled I think all
right so I'm happy with that we'll go
ahead and go to the Q&amp;A there we go
and again just looking over that API
there that's starting to look nice and
clean right so you initialize a texture
queue if you want one and you can use as
many as you want we don't really care as
long as you tell us to process them
which seems good you can do a platform
renderer allocation that just gets
everything ready for you this is not
really part of the API almost like
nothing here is this is just you doing
your camera setup which again I think we
can make some utility functions to make
them simpler then we've got the begin
frame render group transform and render
group end frame and that all seems
pretty reasonable
so if you've answered this before but
why do you make all of your functions
internal some in chat we're saying that
doesn't seem to make sense in a unity
build for just wondering for your
general case the reason is because you
don't know that the compiler is smart
enough to realize it's a unity build
it's really that simple right so you are
sort of taking if you don't declare all
of your functions internal you're taking
it on faith that the compiler will not
waste a bunch of time building an export
table or doing things to make sure that
functions could be externally linked so
having them all marked internal tells it
you can inline this as much as you want
you don't have to remember anything
about it you don't have to build a
linking table you have to do any of
those things that you might have done
and granted I don't know on a naked
particular compiler when I'm you know
calling it to compile my code I don't
know if that particular compiler has
anything that it will do like that that
would be bad but why take the chance
right I prefer to just make it so that
everything is marked internal and
honestly if I'd ever if I thought about
it a lot when I first did it I probably
would have just done this right because
that's nice too because it tells you
it's a function which actually in C it's
incredibly hard to tell if you're
looking at a function declaration it's a
lot harder than you think there are some
ways you can cheat it but it's it's a
lot harder than you think and the reason
is because there's so many different
ways you can write things in C and there
is no keyword like struct class externs
type def s-- enums all of these things
have key
that introduce them but variables and
functions have no keyword that
introduces them so telling the
difference between the declaration of a
function and the Declaration of in
variable actually takes a little bit of
parsing like you have to actually expand
all your macros look at all of the
actual stuff in there and figure out
that it is in fact a function is it
impossible no it just is it way harder
than most languages where you actually
just type the word like function right
in front of a function and you know that
anything that's called a function is a
function and anything else is a variable
it's a lot easier for a simple parser to
know what to do in those cases oh
someone was saying that we can remove
some code from the load bitmap case yeah
we don't
oops not that we we are no we're not I
don't think we are where are we I don't
see any us declaring a render texture
result anywhere is there something like
you writer passed that prohibits hybrid
anti-aliasing techniques like MSA 4x
plus conservative ethics a MSA 16 X is
way overkill yeah no we
we tried a couple different ones and I
don't remember what our opinion ended up
being sorry this is Taksim I remember a
little bit here that's um yeah
create frame buffer so our 2d multi
sample
[Music]
I don't remember how we picked this
I vaguely recall us having a weight that
we tested and I just can't remember what
we actually did there this is not what
we want we clamp it at 16
[Music]
so I guess we just so since we clamp it
at 16 here I suppose I thought we
probably tried some different ones but I
don't know if we really yeah I cannot
remember and I agree that 16 probably
isn't necessary
as far as well you know what we do sure
okay this is starting come back to me
you know what probably it was we were
actually relying on multisample to do
transparency for us I think that's what
happened so we probably never tuned this
variable otherwise like yeah we could
probably I mean dropping it to eight
would probably you wouldn't notice a
thing right like I mean I would be
surprised if you could tell the
difference you know maybe I'm wrong
about that but eight steps on the
Draghi's would probably not be too bad
let me see it's hard to say this is a
scaled buffer too which is not a fair
comparison you want to be one-to-one and
not scaled take a look here
so really we should we should be trying
to do one-to-one here but
this is not a very scientific way to do
this
I mean I don't know I would say I still
see a quality difference between those
two actually to be completely honest
with you we should probably do a more
scientific comparison of the two it's a
little hard to because we haven't turned
on any kind of MIT mapping or
anisotropic filtering for textures that
I have lines in them so you have to be
careful to let make sure your eye
ignores like lines inside the texture
you have to only look at lines that are
external to a texture like for example
these borders here and I admit they look
pretty good on eighth but I do feel like
you still see an improvement in 16 so I
don't know I mean I would think you'd
still want to turn them on and you could
you know in scenarios where you were on
a worst card sure turn it off but I'm
not sure I want to say like oh right on
the cost to turn that off now in terms
of hybrid techniques I don't really want
to go down that route to be honest I'd
rather just turn it on if it's there and
not if it's not
someone with sending a github thing Oh
typing them in through to render test
sure I can take look at that
so that is line 155 where there abouts
yes that is just incorrect
it's cool that GCC catches that like
looping over a static array because yeah
the compiler has all the information it
needs to make that not be a bug you know
um sue as far as the plants looking
worse with a bit I I would so the plants
you have to ignore we don't we have not
generated MIT Maps yet and they're way
too big a bit maps so don't look at
anything bitmap related it's not a fair
comparison you have to just look at
edges for the MSA a there's a bunch of
things we'll want to do with the plants
to make those look better that just
revolve around generating MIT Maps
have we used the Malik from the CRT or
have we always used Windows Alek is it
okay to use the Malik in the game so it
depends on what you mean by okay so no
we do not use Malik the reason we don't
use Malik is because we want to manage
our own memory and we actually do a
bunch of things with that in the game so
one of the ways that we support for
example dynamic code reloading and live
code editing and loop live code editing
and stuff like that is because we keep
all of our memory allocations tracked
ourselves and that way we can load and
save those memory allocations from disk
so we are pretty hardcore about never
calling any CRT functions for that
reason and also that we would like to
compile without the CRT right now the
reason we still compose charity is just
for sine and cosine which is just it's
been a long time we really should get
rid of them that's really the only thing
we need in the future we probably will
get rid of it entirely so that's another
reason I don't call malloc that's it if
you want to use the C runtime library
you know that's up to you I don't like
the C runtime library I don't think it's
very well written and I don't want it to
be I don't want to use it so if you like
it and want to use it that's your
decision just make sure you know what
you're getting into
I've read the sequel on internal sorry I
was just wondering on a more fundamental
level I only knew it makes that function
only accessible from that translation
unit I may have this wrong and I wanted
to know what it did for you in general
not just in response to the unity build
part or is that really all it does um
yeah I mean just to be really clear
about what the reason it's there it's
it's just a define for static right and
in C and C++ the the static keyword in
front of a function tells the compiler
it doesn't have to worry about that
function ever getting used outside of
the current translation unit now because
you don't necessarily know how each
individual compiler that you're going to
use GCC LLVM Microsoft Visual C because
you don't necessarily know what those
compilers are doing internally if you
don't mark something as being
translation unit only then you run the
risk that the compiler will spend longer
processing that file because it may
generate a bunch of extra stuff you
don't need like an export table which at
the end when it goes to start the linker
it realizes it didn't ever need right so
what ends up happening is if you imagine
let's imagine a compiler that isn't
smart enough to understand how the
being called which is perfectly rational
like if you're running compiler maybe
you just wrote something that just
compiles a translation unit it doesn't
know how it was invoked it doesn't know
what the result is going to be used for
right so it just goes along if it sees
all of the functions don't have the word
static in front of them it's gonna start
building an export table okay here's I
got to maintain this hash table of names
and I gotta like organize it for saving
out to an obj file and then maybe I
actually produce this whole I wrote like
a whole linkage table to disk which by
the way is massive because C++ name
mangling turns every function name into
like a
in 30 character string right so just to
be clear there's a lot can go wrong if
you don't put static in there so it's
important to understand that yes the
compiler may be smart enough not to
waste a bunch of time and energy doing
things you didn't need it to do
but why count on that when you can just
help it out and tell it look it's a
unity build none of these things are
gonna have external linkage trust me
here you go right
looks like we're all good okay
all right thank you very much for
joining me for the set a handmade Hero
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
with a stream at home you can always
peer to the game on handmade hero org
and it comes with the source code so
that you can play around with it we also
have a bunch of other stuff you can
check out on here there's a watch page
which will show the current schedule of
when we're going to be live and also
shows the stream when it is live and has
an episode guide you can use to search
the episode archives for all kinds of
stuff it's really cool you can jump
right to different topics and catch up
on anything you may have missed we also
have the handmade fun which is a place
where we fund things like that episode
guide which is actually community
maintained so if you want to contribute
to that there's a whole description of
it on there and all that also we have
mailing lists if you want to know what
we're up to it Molly Rocket and you can
always click on the little handmade hero
head to get to the rest of our projects
and our personal blogs if you want to
see what we're up to that's it for today
I will be back here tomorrow when we'll
take a look at some of those other API
calls I didn't get it didn't get to go
to today again all we're really doing
for this for that stream is just making
it nice and clean so the renderer can
kind of be baked and say here it is it's
all done and something that can be used
in you know external projects and so on
hope see you back here for that until
then have fun programming and I'll see
on the Internet take it easy everybody