all righty hello everyone and welcome to
handmade Hiro sure we code a complete
game live on stream what I would like to
say today is we are trying streaming
from a new location today the the
streaming setup has been moved so
hopefully we don't have any problems it
seemed to be solid during the pre stream
it looks like it's streaming at 30
frames a second with no dropped frames
so hopefully everything is fine if it's
not fine we'll have to address that
after the stream I guess so we're just
gonna go full pull and cross our fingers
here that nothing goes awry if you
remember from last time where we were at
on the programming front oops
try that one more time where we were at
on the programming front we had sort of
you know this is where it would be nice
if I was completely caught up on all of
the graphics literature because honestly
we did something I've actually never
seen before I've never seen anyone
talking about this so it was kind of
interesting and and neat we developed a
scheme for interpolating lighting that
allows us to interpolate lighting on a
very low resolution grid but still get
perfect spherical lighting fall-off so
if you look at our test pattern here you
can see that it appears like we have
effectively infinite resolution on our
spherical lights the actual voxel we are
using is incredibly sparse it's like one
per like one of these tiles right and
yet we get this perfect fall-off and
that's just because we invented on
stream a different way of interpolating
the lighting based on signed distance
fields that I'm quite sure someone has
probably invented before us we're
probably not first but it was pretty
exciting to do it anyway and so that's
where we left off and using the
knowledge of that what I'm hoping to do
now is switch sides because it you know
pretty clearly now at least in theory we
could use this light field
interpolation that we've got here to
push a lot of good lighting into the
system and have it be interpolated
in theory right in broad theory meaning
like hypothetically speaking if we do a
good job with it then we could write and
the only question is with this
interpolation scheme that we have how
easy is it to actually generate
something that can be used with that
scheme so if you know you know if you
just want to do cheese lighting like
we've got in there right now you know
you can see I'm just literally feeding
in four spheres you know you can kind of
see it here there's a red sphere a blue
sphere a green sphere and a white sphere
of lighting and I'm literally just
dumping those spheres in and setting the
lighting and what that means is you know
you get none of the nice lighting
effects you would get if you actually do
some light transport which is what we
want you can see like the way that we
have this setup here right you can see
that the light transport allows the
green sphere to go right on through the
wall so it's not like we've got a point
light here that actually is like gonna
get shadowed and you also don't get a
new bounce right so you know a green
light over here would bounce off of this
and you'd get more green over here or
something right so just generally
speaking you know this this doesn't
produce any we're not doing any light
transfer it's dumping stairs and his
test fears you can see we can
interpolate those test lights perfectly
because we happen to know exactly how
the light goes it's a perfect sphere
fall off so it's trivial to put an
analytic answer in there right but the
problem we get now is we need to somehow
take light transport into effect and
when we compute that light transport
transport it's not obvious necessarily
how we would go about translating a
light transport results computed it's a
like a number of probes like this or
whatever how we would go about computing
a
interpolation field of the kind that we
need from those answers right and so
that's really the thing that we don't
know and I'm not sure
what we can do necessarily to make that
work well and so that's gonna kind of be
a open research topic for us going
forwards and and I really don't know
what I do know is we've got something
usable here I and so what I want to do
is kind of flip sides if you will
we've got like one end of the the things
sort of we have a plausible answer for
one of the things that seems to work
really nicely and and that I you know
could make a strong argument for it
being good right what I'd like to do is
have some answer now about what the
other side of the equation looks like so
I'd like to start working for the next
couple of weekends on the upgrading or
light transport side of things so that
our light transport works and produces
reasonable light transport results at
light probe points or something right so
we had light probe we had light
transport working before working on
surfaces that wasn't particularly useful
for us because again we don't we just
have letting it services we don't know
how to light things like sprites that
are standing up on a square I mean we
could have lit them just from the square
but what we'd rather have is our sprites
and everything be lit continuously just
like any surface would be and now you
can see that our lighting voxel in real
time is doing that 100%
we just need to feed it with some good
data so what I want to do is flip over
to the light transport side of things
try to work on that light transport here
so that you know at each of these cubes
that we got drawn in there try to
produce good light transport at those
points and with a sort of an eye a
squinting eye if you will towards how we
will output that to an interpolation
scheme based on a voxel and so knowing
what we know now about how we can do
really good light reconstruction if we
magically can turn something into a
scientist in sealed then we just need to
figure out how we would actually compute
light transport data at some
points that would then translate into a
sign business field right and that's
really where we're at now so that's what
we have to work on and it's going to be
a while it's gonna take us a while to do
that because we have several steps of
the problem that we need to really think
through and implement and they're all
fairly tricky the raycasting we've at
least already written a version of so we
can at least start with something
reasonable with the raycasting but every
other part we don't really know how
we're gonna do so to give you an
overview of what those parts are first
we need at the end of the Ray Kassar so
the Ray caster knows what service was
hit we need a sampling solution so
something that will sample the lighting
voxel on the CPU side for example we
need to write that code we have a little
bit of it written already but we need to
write it better so something that will
sample last frames lighting voxel and
give us back a useful answer there so we
doing that we need because otherwise our
ray casting doesn't generate anything
right we yeah we cast array we know what
we hit but who cares because just
hitting something doesn't tell you
anything you need to know about what the
light coming back from that hit is and
you don't really get anywhere with that
right so when you do that then we need
to do something that stores the light in
the light probes because what we learned
from our experience is I'm really glad
we did this
from our interpolation experimentation
is you really don't want cubic light
samples it doesn't really work it's not
particularly helpful so what we'd much
rather have and what we need to sort of
work towards is some fundamental
representation of the lighting at our
light probes that allows us to
reconstruct 3/4 to our really at the
moment except for extract for different
we want to basically be able to attract
four signed distance fields where it has
assigned a sense
intensity for RGB plus a normal a
smoothly varying normal we want to
reconstruct those values four of them
per voxel square and so they correspond
roughly to the four most important
directions of light in coming to that
voxel square you might say and you know
who the heck knows how you want to do
that right and so if you think about how
we might do that there's a lot of ways
we could do it but it's pretty tough to
say and we don't really even know if
that's what we want to do like we may
want to end up storing spherical
harmonics at these lights source points
instead or in the voxel right because
that's a more complete representation of
the light source however you know again
we don't really know we don't know if
that would have us good visual
interpolation qualities I did check off
stream separately about the thing I was
curious about just to verify that you
could add spherical harmonics
coefficients together I was like if you
remember last time I was sort of
pontificating about it I was like quite
certain that you should be able to
because it's just a decomposition of the
light into basis functions that should
be orthogonal so you should be able to
add them no problem but for some reason
we weren't seeing that like obviously
listed when we looked at a couple of
reference pages so I didn't want to just
declare that it was true but it does
appear to be true right and so I guess
all I would say is we really just don't
know going into this exactly what we
want to do and that's why I say it's
gonna take us a while we have a lot to
figure out and the reason that we can't
just use exactly what we have right now
with no thought is because when we're
doing ray casting fundamentally what
we're doing when we cast array is we're
taking a normal that's the Ray direction
that we cast the rayon and we're taking
that normal and getting a piece of
information back that's like what is the
intensity of lighting coming in from
that direction
from that piece of information who knows
what we do right we don't know how to
store that in any particular way we
can't just store it because we can't
record every ray that we cast from every
point they accumulate over time and we
end up with like thousands of rays
potentially per light probe stored and
what would we do like it's way too
expensive to work with all that data and
so what we kind of need is some way of
summing up what all the light that
income that all the incoming light at
any given point actually is and we don't
have any way of doing that right now the
reason spherical harmonics are sort of
attractive as a way of keeping a running
tally of light is because since they are
a decomposition of lighting an
orthogonal decomposition of lighting
what we could do is take the
decomposition of the light at each point
when we do our ray cast and just take
that decomposition of the incoming ray
cast light add it to the existing
circular monix fee Racal harmonics
coefficients at every given light probe
and just keep their running tally that
way that is pretty attractive as an
option right because it does allow us to
sum things together
however we don't actually know if that's
the best way to do it there are other
ways we could be tracking the lighting
information at these points one way for
example is using some kind of a like
almost a cake clustering scheme where we
would say something like alright each
time we go to put a light sample in we
look to see if there's like we keep for
actual light directions and for
intensities and when we go to add
something in we add it to whatever light
is closest like whichever lighting
direction is closest and we bend the
light in like we bend the normals
towards it right so we kind of keep like
a running K clusters algorithm almost of
the four light directions and the four
intensity's right
it's just who knows I don't have an
answer I'm just I'm as like non
knowledgeable about this as you are I've
never implemented a spatial accumulation
lighting scheme like this before so I
don't have any preconceived notions
about what we should be doing I
obviously am familiar with some of the
literature so the reason that I think
about spherical harmonics is because
it's the thing that comes to mind that
people generally use when they need to
some lighting like that and so it seems
like the obvious answer in our case the
only thing I don't know is is it really
the best thing for interpolating
lighting because you know Fourier
transforms which is sort of what it is
Fourier transforms of things have a lot
of kind of weird side effects to them
they try to represent periodic functions
they try to represent things that are
fundamentally not periodic functions as
things that are periodic functions and I
just don't know I just don't know what
to expect this is where lack of
experience is you know it's tough but
again that's the point of handmade here
oh I like showing how I go about
exploring things that I haven't done
before because I think that's the most
important thing for people to learn from
a serious like this it's not how to do
something you can always go read about
how to do something if it's something
someone's already done before the more
interesting thing is how do you explore
things people haven't done before or
slight differences right so anyway if I
had a lot of experience with spherical
harmonics I would already know what
things I think they're okay for what
things I don't and so I just I don't
know if I want to go down that road or
not and I don't know if I want explore
other options or not so it's really just
gonna be a constant sort of learning
mechanism there where I think about it
and say maybe maybe not whatever right
okay so I think the first thing I want
to do now that I've kind of
jabbered about that extensively i think
i want to break this problem into
smaller problems as i often do we have
something very complicated now what i
want to do is say alright we know that
we can do four light-filled
interpolations really nicely here i
really like the look of that so
artistically i feel like that's a good
mesh it feels like this game to me and
that's always important thing to keep in
the back of your mind when you're doing
rendering because remember the point of
rendering in a game is not to be
accurate it's not to be what real light
does we don't care what real light does
the point is to look like we want the
game to look it's aesthetics
right we simulate a lot of the real
properties of lighting because they
produce raising aesthetics right not
because we care if the answer is right
some games may care if they're if
there's something specific about them
but for most games it's about achieving
an aesthetic we like shadows we like
gradual fall we like for now all of
these things they're pleasing to the eye
that's why we put them in there but it's
important not to lose sight of the fact
that we put them in because they look
good not because they are real we don't
care about reality in a game we care
about pleasing visuals or jarring
visuals or grotesque visuals or whatever
the goal of the game is there's an
aesthetic there set by the design and
your job as a graphics programmer is
never to produce realistic imagery is to
produce imagery that comports with the
aesthetic of the game and if that if
that game is supposed to be
photorealistic then that's your job but
if that game is supposed to not be photo
realistic as ours is not then that is
not part of the job criteria so it's
really important to remember that as we
go forward we're not looking for realism
here we're looking for beauty we're
looking for aesthetic comportment with
the style of the game that plays nicely
with Anna's artwork that makes its
natural richness come out and not trying
to make something that looks realistic
right that's always important to keep in
the back of your mind so because I like
the wave
signed distance field interpolation
looks and it gives me some of that nice
cartoon feel I really like that look I
want to start without the spherical
harmonics and see if I can do something
without them if I can't we might fall
back to that as our second attempt but
that's where I'm thinking in my head I
want to go so going from there what I
want to do is break this up into smaller
problems and just see how far I can get
on smaller problems so the first problem
I want to do is let's do direct
recasting of one light and see if we can
just produce just produce a version of
what we see on the screen right now
perhaps let's just pop over really
quickly here to the lighting algorithm
perhaps just one so I'm gonna take we
have four lights going in here right you
can see the four lights going in right
here
I'm gonna take out three of those lights
and so if I just take take out three of
those lights now what you will see is
they don't well okay they're still set
to their original value so I really what
I actually need to do is actually clear
them here so for example if I just go
ahead and say light so you want to go
zero light see two equals zero light
it's light see three equals zero if we
just truncate those light values so we
only have the first light and I pop back
to the game here then what you can see
is a single light source that's just a
sphere it's placed roughly above the
head of the player and you can see that
it actually produces a really pleasing
look but it doesn't have any light
transport so like when I'm here right
what I want to see is I want to see this
be shadowed out here right and it so
there should be some I want to see some
second area but I want to see any direct
lighting over here like I'm getting
right now right so what I want to do is
let's start with this let's add our ray
casting back in which will take a while
because we again we haven't turned that
on so we're gonna have to start really
thinking about how that works let's turn
that ray fasting on get the Ray casting
working but we're gonna do
instead of using the raycasting
degenerate simulate actual secondary
bounce transport we're just gonna do
direct transport so all we're gonna do
is at each of our light probes now right
we're going to cast array from the light
pour probe just one ray and the only
thing we're going to do is cast it
directly at the debug light if it hits
the debug light we will basically stuff
into the light probe the value that
we're getting right now
the direction to the light source and
the intensity as a distance fall-off so
no other light simulation whatsoever
just that if it doesn't get the light
source black no secondary transport
right so that's the simplest possible
thing we could do with the ray tracer
compute a direct shadow let's try that
and see if we can make that work if we
can make that work that's a good first
step forward and we'll see what the
natural next step is after that maybe
multiple light sources and we try to
start tracking those directions right
skip the secondary transport that's
stage two right in order to get in that
stage the first thing I need to do is
actually get the light probe to voxel
trans transcription working which we
haven't done yet so that's actually
direct light casting would be step 2
step 1 or step that step 1 step 0 if you
will is we need to go from light probes
storage which is basically things that
store information in the world to a
screen space voxel that we use for light
reconstruction so that's what we need to
do now let's work on it okay so what we
have here right is we've got a test
light sphere turned on and what test
light sphere does is it stuffs values
directly into the voxel you can see that
happening here it's just a thing they
pull over here so my head's not in the
way it's just a series of lights we
could actually have turned this into for
a lot I loop I was too lazy to do that
but what you can see here
this takes four light sources here and
it just literally stuffs the values
directly into the voxel right we also
have the ability to set a checkerboard I
don't know if that's still working but
we could take a quick moment to set that
up here is a checkerboard and so we turn
off test fear we turn on checkerboard
and I guess yeah like so we haven't
actually ported that one yet so let's
port our checkerboard let's get that
going so what we need in our
checkerboard is just one light source so
probably just this one for the
checkerboard I don't know that we want
any other light sources we can see
whether this actually works for us or
not let me go ahead I shouldn't have
closed the game I don't know why I was
closed the game but because the code
reloading would work
so our checkerboard still works here you
can kind of see an overlay of how big
the voxel is right it's just this thing
right here you can see it clamping out
to the values there so in here we've got
a checkerboard and a sphere like test
pattern that's good we want to keep them
in there but the actual pattern we need
to start working on is what happens when
we enable the light probes right and
what the light probes do is the light
probes are the the information we store
in the scene to get frame to frame
oops frame to frame coherence so we need
this to be we need the light probes to
work perfectly we want them to be able
to reconstruct light as well as the
other thing preferably now I can't be
perfect because nothing's as perfect as
an analytic solution right that test
sphere is literally perfect analytic
light fall-off there's nothing we can do
better than an analytic solution for a
light source so it can't quite be that
good but we'd like to see is it getting
almost that good we want to get as good
close as we can to that solution
all right
so let's think about how we're gonna do
that in our test light probes situation
here right what you can see is we loop
over our probes you can see we've got
compile errors here and that's because
this code has not been ported yet anyway
right so you can kind of ignore that
part for now but what we want to do in
the light probe system is now set up
something that's going to map light
probes down onto something that we can
use for our interpolation scheme right
something that will allow us some nice
light interpolation and again that's not
it's not trivial it's it's something
that we got to think about exactly how
we're gonna do but you know off we go
so in here where you can see we've got
our probe index what we're doing is
we're running through each probe as we
go and we're looking at the probe that's
inside a particular voxel and you know I
don't really know if this is the best
way for us to be doing this right now to
be completely honest it seems like maybe
it's not but we'll stick with it
temporarily because I don't really know
one way or the other what I would say is
you know now that I think about it as
I'm kind of thinking about it in my head
I almost want to say we just don't want
to do this so so let me tell you just
just basically what I'm thinking here I
think light probes are really not the
thing that we want to use probably ever
for actually reconstructing the voxel
light probes are just a way of storing
the voxels spatially from so from frame
to frame we don't have to redo anything
and light probes are places we want to
cast from right but fundamentally
speaking I think most of what we want to
do is think of light probes as just ways
of storing information for
the voxel frame-to-frame so that when
you come back the next frame you
reconstruct what was in the voxel right
I think that's mostly what we want
and even as I'm saying that I'm thinking
maybe even that isn't what we really
want so so let let me let me suggest
something even more ridiculous to you
I'm thinking maybe what we want to do is
just lock the light voxel in place so
basically like the light voxel stays in
one place and as you move the camera
around it is it just is where it is
right and when the camera when the
center of simulation shifts so when we
move the simulation center from one
place to another what we will do is just
copy the part of the voxel that overlaps
to the new location and then the the new
part of the voxel will just have to get
new lighting thrown into it right I
think that's mostly what we want stated
alternately what I think we might want
to do is store a large light voxel maybe
one that's significantly bigger than the
one we have so for example if we go to
light voxel blah blah blah whatever it's
called something here yeah um so when we
look at this stuff
this voxel Wow
so right now we're using literally it's
it's so crazy how small the voxel is so
right now we're just using a 16 by 16 by
16 voxel you see what I need about how
good that lighting interpolation was
that is just a really good lighting
interpolation scheme don't let anyone
tell you that handmade hero doesn't give
you the sweet light interpolation
schemes because we do that was pretty
baller alright anyway so I guess what
I'm saying is if we've got a 16 by 16 by
16 view reagent voxel what I'm
suggesting is maybe we store like a 128
by 128 by 128 voxel
as just like a region around the
simulation area where we remember what
the voxel values were so that we get
that frame-to-frame coherence right then
light probes don't store anything the
only thing a light probe is a light
probe is just a place that says here is
some place that cast rays from for
modifying the voxel but it's just
letting us know we're like interiors of
rooms are right or places that we want
light information to be and maybe in the
future we just get rid of them entirely
and we just generate those values
procedurally so like any place you can
stand we just spam light rock I don't I
don't care
the point is light probes to generate to
store nothing all they are is just
telling you where to cast so if you go
back and you look at the actual like
platform code right and in here we kind
of go through and we look at the stuff
we were actually sending down with
commands and all that nonsense right so
this stuff this just goes away the only
thing we know is this which is saying
how many places do you want to cast
light from and the really interesting
thing about this is if we did that and
that worked well it means we can get rid
of light probe index assignment so we no
longer need those indices to be stable
either and how baller is that that is
really baller right so I'm loving the
way this is coming together I just don't
want to get too excited about it because
until we actually have it looking nice
with real light transport you know it's
it's it's it's not over to to till the
try think of what the programming
version of the phrase it's not over till
the fat lady sings from opera
it's not over till the high bit is set
right it's not over til the most
significant bit
set so let's just say that that's the
case so let's just say that we are now
no longer going to be using that
information and all we're gonna do from
the light probe positions is we're going
to cast rays and then inside the
lighting system we will be tracking the
radiance and that stuff will be tracking
it as the actual voxel so inside
lighting what I want to see here then is
I want to see like our lighting solution
and here we sort of have this light
probe irradiance and the spatial probe
index and all this garbage it's just no
the answer is no we're not going to do
it it doesn't happen false right so this
would go away and we just wouldn't be
worried about the probes and where they
are in the box little we don't care
about that we never have to look them up
that way anymore and I love the sound of
that so I'm really hoping that I can
actually make that be true so we nuke
that part and then what we say is in
here we do have a voxel but the voxel is
just the light box so it's actually just
this thing right and that's the thing
that we would use to look up but we want
bigger we want a bigger version so we
have a large version of this thing and
we're sending down the small version of
it right so we keep a 120 by 120 by 128
we send down just the 16 by 16 center
piece of that right or something like
that and that's probably overkill so
maybe maybe 64 by 6 4 by 64
I don't know don't look at me I'm not a
graphics programmer I'm not supposed to
have to know this stuff
all right anyway so this stuff goes away
goodbye it was nice seeing you but no
and then we say all right in here we
have a light voxel cell and in there
we're just going to store the light
color and the light normal like we are
sending down to the system but we
actually want to keep some number of
these just like this right so what we're
gonna do is we're going to raycast you
know each of the locations in the voxel
and actually now that I think about it
we may not even really need the light
probes we may just be able to use the
lights that are in the voxel cell and
cast in their centers or something so
again don't know we haven't thought it
through yet so I'm not sure but chances
are we want the light probe still
because chances are we don't want to
actually cast from just one location
inside the voxel cell because we'll be
too susceptible to voxel cell alignment
at that point and that isn't really good
right so all right just gonna start by
trying to get this stuff working really
really basic try to have something
bigger than the original voxel and where
we copy just out of the center so what
we're gonna have in here is our cells
the cells are going to be again a
three-dimensional array and that
3-dimensional rate is going to be
related related to that light voxel that
we have but it's not going to be the
same dimension we want it to be bigger
we want to encompass a larger space so
when we go ahead and look at like in
here where we've got like look up box
will dab so where we've got the light
look up voxel here you can see that the
power is listed here and so maybe what
we want here is the like sort of light
large voxel
and this is just a larger one and I
don't know that we really need this one
to be a power of two because I can't
think of a lot of reasons why it would
have to be for indexing into the voxel I
guess that would maybe make it a little
bit easier so maybe it is nice to still
stick with a power of two the reason
that a power two is maybe not the most
nicest thing in the world is because the
power of tube will never Center exactly
you'll always be a little off-center
right if you wanted to be centered
perfectly you would want like an odd
number of copies of the voxel so for
example if you've got a sixteen by
sixteen by sixteen like we were
simulating before and we wanted to
basically have like one cell around in
every direction that would be three
times the sixteen right and so I don't
know if we really how we really wanna do
that
oh that was Molly's feeder its food time
for the puss does she know I'm looking
at a cat tree right now she is not even
moving she's just a fully sleeping puss
she she was exhausted from the move so I
don't blame her all right anyway so I
don't know exactly what we want to do
here with that and so what I guess I'll
say at the moment is I'm not gonna care
I'm gonna use a pair of two that might
be stupid so we're gonna kind of keep an
eye on that let's put it that way as we
go and what I'm gonna say is the light
lookup voxel what we're gonna do is
we're going to use two stops up so if
we're using a 16 by 16 by 16 voxel at
actual pixel shader time then we're
going to be two stops up from that so
we're gonna be 32 to 64
so we're 64 by 64 by 64 on the storage
voxel okay that's what we're doing
I have to creat it and it's my codebase
what are you gonna do about it nothing
I'm the only one with right access to
the repository and actually they were
positive just up my mirror too so even
if you hacked my repository anyway I
hate kit case couldn't tell anyway uh so
what we want to do here is we want to
start
initializing these cells with lighting
data and what we want to do is when we
go to output the lighting to the card
we're gonna do now is output the
lighting from these cells to those cells
right so it's like a copy of the voxel
from our internal version to the
external version the graphics card is
actually going to use and what we want
to do to sort of take this in slow steps
is the first thing we'll do is going to
waves so instead of test light probes
which is now not a thing we're not going
to have that anymore um we're gonna call
it test light transfer and what we're
gonna do is we're gonna transfer
lighting information in so it's a copy
the probes are gone so here's our test
transfer code we don't want any of this
really all we're gonna have here is the
irradiance pack is still going to be
there but otherwise pretty much that's
it right and then this stuff obviously
is gonna occur as well I'm gonna get rid
of this clearing here because we don't
really need that at the immediate moment
but here we have like how we're gonna
pack this stuff together what I want to
do is I want to assume then I get a
light voxel cell back somehow and I want
to pack the data in so now we've got our
light and zero or light C zero right and
we have this oops copied them I was a
little aggressive there oh did the
puss-puss find out that her food went
off I think the post did I missed that I
missed the puss head into the food I
heard it go off she must have woken
slowly gotten out of her sleep
and and done it I don't know all right
so yeah irradiance pack on a light just
does the right thing right yeah um so we
what we need to do now is just
irradiance pack our light that doesn't
go on the end channel that goes in the C
channel we do irradiance pack our light
and each of these light voxel cells
right has the data we need right in it
it's got the light that's what we're
gonna be tracking so for each one of
these we pack the light like so enemies
say there's the transfer the normal is
way easier as well because instead of
just like having to pack it down we just
copy it directly there is no encoding of
our normals yet right we don't actually
do that it's just this by normal to
normal calls the only thing we actually
do so right now we can just set this
directly to light n that may get more
complicated the future but at the moment
it's just that by normal to normal call
and that's all we actually do so let's
go ahead and keep that
so there's us doing the straight copy
from the cell and that's all we need to
do for the transfer the only question is
where do we get it from and again here
we sort of say well alright we need to
again keep this centered around wherever
the view is actually looking at this
particular time right
and I don't you know I wish I had a
better handle on exactly how I want to
do this I don't know
so right now I'm just gonna do something
that it may be a little Squinkie you
know it may be I may be Squinkie a
little bit too swiftly on this
particular one and and you know we'll
see in a second exactly house cranked it
ends up being but
bear with me because we're kind of
exploring this territory and I don't
actually know what I want yet and I will
you know much like Potter Stewart said
of pornography I will know it when I see
it I may just not be able to quite
define it oh we got the puss hello puss
how are you doing
did you have a good did you have a good
lunch yeah I wish I had lunch right now
I wish I had lunch right now I don't
have an automated feeder do I I just
have to do this dream but no fluid at
all I have to do this dream with no food
I'm a starving now but you got all kinds
of good food didn't you what are you
you're eating you're eating that that
prescription food aren't you you're
eating Royal Canin
it's not what you're eating I think
that's what she was eating all right
plus I got access to keyboard though so
is it possible could you possibly hang
out over here for a little while
no satin I'm on the table is that I got
it I got puts I gotta type in some code
baby is that okay Molly can I can I can
i code some stuff we have a bit of a
push situation here I don't know what
we're gonna do about that exactly
she likes to type on the keyboard out at
this point so I don't know we're gonna
have a little bit romantic try and type
around the puss I'll try to type around
the puss but we'll see she's basically
sitting on the wrist rest now so you
know how it is those of you cats at home
will be familiar with this situation
they like to be where the action is they
don't necessarily understand the fact
that you have work that you're trying to
do we'll see all right so anyway inside
here if I grab out my light cells and I
pack them down then the question is just
where do I get them from right so if I
have some kind of an X Y Z okay now the
puss is stepping on the keyboard
that's good let's just keep keep going
there we go so she's going off
so if we take a look at the X Y Z's of
the cells that we actually have here you
can see we do have them the problem is
they're just not in a particularly good
location for our offsetting right so we
probably want to do here is we just have
like a Z offset a y offset or something
like that
OOP okay there's some push typing okay
you're sitting on the Delete key baby
that's not that's gonna be bad okay we
don't and the tail right now is going
like literally right along the prime
part of the keyboard moly baby could we
move could we possibly move you to the
seat do you think that's a possible
possibility what if we just come on baby
what if we just if we just moved you
right there would that be a good place
do you wanna sit there sit down there at
all I don't think it's I don't think she
likes that seat very much what do you
think about that well you think about
that seat huh do you like that at all
it's playing not warm enough huh
all right she's going she's going okay
so you know when the puss comes you just
got to deal with it that's just part of
programming a lot of people ask me you
like as a junior programmer what should
I be focusing on the answer is your cat
skills you should be good with with cats
especially if you've ever gonna work
with me you gotta be good with cats okay
so light box will sell we've got a zy in
an X here and if we were just looking in
the bottom corner that would be fine but
what we actually want to do is we want
to look at some portion of our larger
voxel that's where we've decided we are
I don't want to have to do anything
fancy here so I'm just gonna do like the
sort of like hot Zee hot X hot Y kind of
a thing where we basically say we've got
some portion of the voxel that's sort of
the interior part we care about and
we're going to offset our larger voxel
by that voxel right so this is just a
transfer from one voxel to another and
that's all we're doing here
and so what I'd like to do now is just
have a way of initializing our larger
voxel maybe with the test fear and then
verifying that that can actually be
copied in so let's say that I do this
here and we in fact I just literally
want to do this I'm gonna loop over the
large voxel initialize the large voxel
and then from the large voxel goat to
the small voxel right that's that's all
I really want to do all right so if I
was to literally just cut and paste all
this code right so I'm literally just
gonna cut and paste this entire thing
although I guess I only need one of them
we're only dealing with one light so I'm
not gonna I'm gonna do that right so
what I want to do here is I want to
store and in the light c0 I want to
actually again keep as a full light
value now so this is not gonna look like
that instead what we're gonna do is take
the actual like v4 we would have packed
down and and keep it right so that we
have what I think is the correct
settings here and then when we go to
pack it down later we'll you know pull
that out of it
so again gotta go through this with like
a finer tooth comb than we are at the
moment but basically what we're going to
do is we're going to insert into our
larger voxel the small smaller voxel
information here right and we compute
Vox Center P I now need an offset that's
like the hot voxel P part of that so
that's moved up so when we compute this
stuff right what we do trying to explain
this we have a small voxel inside a
large voxel I should probably draw this
out for you but I'm too lazy at the
moment we have a small box on a large
voxel the small voxel is some cut out of
the larger voxel we now want to test
that we can copy things from the small
part from some subset of the large box
boxes so what I want to do is initialize
the entire large voxel with the distance
to the light so this will basically be
you know something like this right and
that's all we actually need oops so we
just want to initialize the whole box
with that light the problem with doing
it this way is we previously said where
the light was in UVW space which doesn't
necessarily help us you can see us doing
that computation here so the vox uvw
like this this computation is kind of
useless right because we don't actually
know where the light is we this is
telling us where the light is in the
small voxel but this is the large voxel
right so while it's easy for us to tell
what the UVW is in the large voxel it's
not easy for us to tell what it is in
the small voxel so we kind of want to
make this work
a little bit more broadly and we want to
start talking about where this stuff is
in actual real space so we're getting
like I said we're gonna have to grind a
little bit get all this stuff working in
a slightly different way than it was
working before but the good news is like
hey this uvw stuff was just things that
we were sort of pre computing for using
the in voxel dim and this kind of
nonsense so what we can do is start to
just work back towards the world space
we had those values already those were
these like light P light p2 light p3
light before those are already in world
space so what I'd like to do here is say
we've got a Vox Center P and I'm going
to compute that as an actual location
the Vox Center P is going to be a offset
so if we said like Vox VIN corner
we had that value and then I added an
offset to it that was the you know
amount sort of of the voxel scaled by
whatever the voxel dim is right so we
have some notion of the minimum corner
we have some notion of the cell
dimension we scale that out and this is
where the center of our axle is now in
world space then we get rid of this and
now when we talk about our like normal
it's just going to be the light P minus
the Vox Center P the rest of this can
stay the same now we have a little bit
of an issue here because you can see
we've got a light color that's gonna be
the fall-off here that fall-off needs to
be broader right so it needs to be more
like you know like that or something
where it falls off at like a 4 meter
radius or something like that maybe even
a little bit more than that 8 meter
radius I don't know who knows doesn't
matter but it's something right then
we've got our light intensity and the
light intensity is again just something
we use to figure out how bright the
lights going to be back and stay the
same at the moment but we'll play with
that later and now we've got something
that will go through the whole world
space of this sort of voxel initializing
it to be the correct values for this one
light source that we're tracking then we
go through here we get rid of the probe
stuff we go through this and we say all
right when we do the light transfer we
pick stuff back up out of the voxel
based on just that center point
and you can see that happening here we
copy it in and that's the part that now
we're trying to get ok so let's move
towards that first thing we need to do
is actually put those values in there so
if you take a look in the lighting
solution we've got sort of this
information here about the voxel
that we commented out we now need to put
some of that back in here so for the
cells I want to do the Vox min corner
and the Vox seldom that that's how we're
gonna map from the voxel back out right
we're also gonna need the in seldom so
all that stuff basically just needs to
be known to us these two values are the
same
but what we probably want to do is be a
little bit careful about how we're
naming these things these two are the
same so they are the voxel like the cell
dim and the inverse seldom those are
correct no matter which voxel you're
talking about because our voxels line up
right the small one is just a subset of
the larger one so you only ever need to
talk about one set of dimensional values
right the cell dim and the emcell dim
are this the same no matter what fox are
talking about but in this case we
actually have two so we have a Vox min
corner for the large and a Vox min
corner for the small and they're not the
same right and we similarly that like
hot min coordinate maybe we'll call it
the hot location so we could actually
say this hot X Y Z
so we kind of have a Vox Minh corner hot
and then also a box in or hot corner I
that's the index of the hot corner
inside the large voxel right so that's
roughly what we need to track through
the system in order for it to work
properly
right we're gonna need to set those up
and then let me start cleaning a
compilers now so we're gonna start to
test this out so this stuff is no longer
with us it was not long for this world
we thought we were gonna need it we
didn't end up needing it it was just
something we played around with in here
where we do the spatial index again
don't care this stuff
similarly don't care so when we go
through the light probes now oh well
actually that's fine so the light probe
Peas we may still want but those are
just gonna be kind of directly used
without that box apart so we'll keep
those temporary likes think we may still
want those okay so if we do to the
spatial index here this stuff we don't
actually want so this this needs to stop
and this we now will have to reckon with
how the transfer like this is going to
end up being a voxel lookup so it's
gonna be a get probe lighting based on a
position now
so it's kind of a separate a separate
thing we need to go in let's just do
this who's next
so all of this code is just not a thing
anymore
right so these are just completely if
zeroed out like all of this stuff is not
a thing
and we'll delete it as soon as we are
sure we don't actually need it so in
here you can see where we are
initializing the spatial probe index
what we probably wanna do now is
actually initialize the rest of our
solution stuff so when we go in here and
that's not what I want there it is when
we get all this stuff all of this stuff
has to kind of be initialized this stuff
will vary per frame this stuff won't and
so what we should be able to do is just
set these here right if we want to I'm
going to let it vary for print per frame
probably so what I might do is say look
we'll we'll take that over here so when
we begin the letting computation if
every frame you wanted to vary it you
could and off you go right
I'm not sure that's the smartest way to
do this but alright and yet so now we
just kind of need to deal with exactly
how the light corner stuff is working
and we'll talk about that a little bit
more a little bit later on because
there's a bunch of stuff we have to do
to make that work properly but yes this
stuff now can go away and now we really
just need these two and this is all this
is all stuff we're gonna have to
actually fix so like what we need to do
now is we need to take the lighting
bounds and regularize them so instead of
when you call begin lighting computation
you're no longer going to be able to
call begin lighting computation with an
actual bounds you're gonna have to call
begin lighting computation with like a
center point or like a viewing point or
something and when we change the camera
location we have to update the lights as
well right so the lighting system will
now have to be camera aware and it has
to do transfers that will like be able
to copy parts of the voxels around if
that makes sense it's more complicated
than we're doing before but way better
like this will prevent us from having to
do a ton of the work we were doing like
we won't have to translate to and from
light probes anymore and the values that
we copied to the graphics card are the
same values we'd be tracking and all
that stuff so this is just way better I
think this is what we should have been
doing so yeah getting rid of the light
probes seems like a great idea because
there's just no need for it
and it also means that the entities
won't need to have light index as a sign
anything like that because we'll be
keeping track of the light spatially not
in terms of probes and that just seems
strictly better to me yeah so I think
that's all just better and we'll go from
there
all right so we have a ton of stuff to
do now to get that going
I think probably my goal for today cuz I
don't I have like maybe what 28 minutes
so 30 I maybe like 35 minutes so I think
of most what I want to do today is I
just want to go through and try to get
the voxels tracking properly we probably
won't be able to actually get to the
point where they're where they're
actually running properly just today
because there's a lot of plumbing that
has to happen but clean all that stuff
up and then tomorrow our goal will be to
get the light voxel reproducing the same
effect we have today and then we are
really in good shape because at that
point we are ready to just do ray
casting and go from there right and I
think that'll be really really pretty
easy we're even ready to sample we can
sample the lighting tribute at that
point too so yeah I think that at that
point it starts to be really good so
that's our goal for this weekend get
most of the plumbing them today as much
as we can tomorrow get it working and
then I'm and then at that point I'm a
happy camper because weed weed we've
been in really good shape
alright so let's push through what I
want to do is is now kind of go back and
and go to the outer code fix a little
bit of how that's working and we'll go
from there
so inside the world mode what we have
right now is like the camera right it
updates in a number of ways so when we
actually find those light pounds you can
see me look into the light bounce here
right and you can see when we do begin
lighting computation what we do is we
say we tell the lighting system where
the light pounds are I and the part of
the problem that is the lighting system
doesn't really know where the where the
light bounds are in absolute
space this is just telling it kind of
based on the random like location that's
it's based around the simulation center
they're not absolute coordinates right
and so I think what we would want to do
here is say alright you know we've got
the we've got the world camera rectangle
that we produce from the render group
here right and that is sort of use well
it's not really that useful I it's yeah
it's really not that useful what we
would probably rather have is actually
like look at what we're using for the
cameras absolute Center so you know when
we're actually doing the camera pulling
the camera information out here where we
grab that group know this so where we
actually look at the world camera P and
the simulation centre P like that
difference going on here right I think
what we actually want to do now is the
camera P is like where we are and we
know we can go from that some distance
forward and know that that's like
roughly what we're focusing on because
we do have a focal point like we know
roughly how far away we are from the
camera in terms of what we're trying to
look at and so I think what we want to
do is actually just ask or rather tell
the lighting system that like that's
what it should actually be given so I
think instead of light bounds which I
don't think we want anymore I think what
we want is more like here's the camera
position right and since this lighting
has to be stable we're going to tell you
the camera position and one other piece
of information which is how far away we
expect the camera to actually focus on
right so you can see the focus Z kind of
comes in here and so
we may need more information than that
but you know we'll we'll say we we do
something like this at the moment and
then what I'm going to do is say all
right that camera rect does that
actually get you straining because if it
doesn't then we're just going to we're
going to toast some of that stuff now
yes so all this stuff now I think we
want to kind of get rid of right and we
need this to sort of be a value that we
tune because we need the lighting to now
be stable we don't want the lighting
sampling points to shift around so we
want to just pick the largest volume we
need to light a line to that and that's
the end of it right so we then say all
right all of this stuff I think goes
away
well no it doesn't so the simulation
bounds are still are based on the camera
size what
that just seems totally busted I don't
want that at all
Wow okay so I don't really want that and
I don't know what that is doing there so
I want to start eliminating more of this
code actually quite a bit more so we're
gonna organize this a little differently
world camera rect is gonna get pulled
out screen bounds so on so symbols we
want but that's literally just gonna be
this all of this stuff I don't really
want happening more including this so I
don't know why we were still doing that
I feel like we should have removed that
but I guess we were trying to be
Squinkie I don't think we should have
been Squinkie like that I think that was
a bad squink so I'm gonna I wonder if
all of those and clean up the results
because I didn't like that that was
giving me a bad vibe a very bad vibe all
right so we're gonna deal with the
fallout from that in a minute here we
don't need this you don't need any of
this
and this is the large corner
specifically this is a Hadamard product
I'm not sure why I wrote that as a
standard product which we don't allow
for vectors specifically because it's
ambiguous which kind of product did you
want how do my products dot product
cross product here it looks like this is
a little weird because that should have
just been a multiplication so that we
had the red green and blue is all equal
channel there so don't ask me why that
was looking like that it was just a
holdover from when I did the cut
copypasta there this is just needs to be
an address of and now I think we're good
so in terms of the focus Z here again
I'm not really even sure we need the
focus Z so maybe I won't even use that
because we really need this voxel to be
stable so I'm not sure we can afford
stuff like the focus Z you probably just
needed to capsulate the frustum reliably
so we'll see alright so let's go ahead
and jump to begin the lightening
computation and now the big change here
is instead of a rectangle 3 this is
going to take a world position and
that's the location of the camera
all right so now we have to do is you
have to work backwards right we have to
now like figure out how we're going to
make this voxel be properly aligned with
our view now in order to make sure that
we have lighting that kind of covers the
region that we want obviously you know
you figure we got to push this thing out
along negative Z a certain ways and and
so on right and furthermore with the
world position with the camera P here we
also need to know the simulation center
because that's like the coordinate
system center so in order to get that
information we also need to produce like
let's see here where is that information
actually
so I guess actually the simulation
center is all is always at zero zero
zero but we just need to know yeah you
can see here so we actually have the
delta from sim value so actually what we
probably want to do is maybe something
more like this we would tell it where
the simulation center is or like that
and where the camera is relative to the
origin and those are the two things we
would pass because the simulation center
is zero zero zero so we want to know
where that is so that we have the
correct relative positioning for
everything so we'd actually want to do
this and then we would have Delta from
sim and you know Delta from sim just
tells us where the camera is relative to
that simulation center right and so what
we want to do now is say all right the
world origin P is sort of a way that we
would track where we line everything up
where
Vox OS and all that sort of stuff right
and so there's a yeah there's a lot of
different ways we might want this to
work but generally speaking what we want
to do is think about the voxel getting
updated over time so when we do begin
letting computation and you tell us the
origin P the first thing we want to do
is kind of move the existing voxel data
copy a subset of the voxel data and
clear the rest of the voxel if you will
so that we're like shifting the voxel
around in like a locked fashion with the
with the motion of the of the simulation
in the camera right that's what we
pretty much want now thankfully for us
we don't have to care about that stuff
yet and the reason that we don't have to
care about that stuff yet is because we
are just trying to do the basic
operation of computing the lighting on a
single frame so we don't need
hello plus hello so we don't really need
any particular frame to frame coherent
so we can skip that for now but this is
what we will need to to carry forward
with us and similarly when we look at
the voxel dimension stuff that stuff
okay plus can you just give me just not
okay thank you okay
yeah so when we want to compute the rest
of this stuff we we now need with this
like the set light bounds as well I'm
not sure what that's actually oh so the
set light bounds this stuff is important
to tell the pixel shader like what's
going on so we need them in and the
inverse light dim and all that stuff so
that's the stuff that we need to get
right at this point right so let's go
ahead and compute that stuff stabili so
the first thing I want to do is say we
know that the cell count for the small
voxel is is this right and so we know
that we want to set the debentures
for the light to be something based on
that that captures the size we actually
needed to capture and this has to now be
hard-coded so we can more or less just
Hardwell doesn't have be hard-coded this
has to be stable so we can now just hard
code it because it can't change frame to
frame or we would get like you'd see
visible artifacts if we were changing
where the light information was stored
from frame to frame so what I want to do
here is say well the lighting dimension
is therefore going to be like computed
this way the light dim is in fact I
guess if I look at light dim
I just need seldom though here right so
if I look at the voxel cell dim what I
want to do is say it's the cell count
right times the cell dimension or rather
this is that so I guess I don't need the
entire light tube so what I want to
actually say here is this
and I guess I'm not sure why do we have
a thing that both enables the light
bounce this way and then does it this
way I'm not really sure again we can
clean up I think we can clean up the
pipeline a bit once you get all this
working because then it will be
absolutely clear what actually needs to
go down to the graphics card and when so
we'll be able to simplify this a bit
anyway so when we do begin letting
concrete computation we've got our
solution flowing in here assuming the
lighting is enabled we've got our cell
information producing here our seldom is
just going to be some value that is
hard-coded to produce a large enough you
know a large enough size I'm gonna start
with two meters per voxel and we're
gonna see what that translates to that
may be too big I don't know what the
size of the voxel was before maybe we'll
start with one and we'll kind of go from
there we'll scale it as necessary maybe
it should be too I don't know um so then
we need to figure out like where this
thing is in terms of the sort of where
the the actual voxel is in space and
again we need this to be like locked to
the voxel seldom so we need it to be
spatially coherent so that it's
basically truncated right we don't want
it to have I mean we want it to be so
that it moves an entire voxel cell at a
time when it moves so we need the large
voxel and the hot voxel to be like
aligned in that way so if we look at how
we're gonna do this part here and we'll
look and we'll construct the the light
bounds in a second here
this is gonna just be this actually
remember what we had for our VIII's so
if we look at what we would use to
construct this it's like a rectangle dim
right like it's a record rectum in dim
so it's rectum in dim and it's
specifically the three-dimensional
version so it's this so the light bounds
is going to be reverse constructive now
so instead of passing it in we're gonna
construct it from the voxel and we're
gonna say that it's the light dimension
which is this Hadamard product here
whatever the cell did cell count is
times the box will sell Tim and then the
minimum value is just the that hot
corner right so then what we have to do
is figure out where this goes right and
this is relative to the camera but again
then truncated based on it's sort of
divisor right now the Vox mid corner
large is easier because that is
literally just an offset from the hop
from the hot corner so this is literally
just like you know a displacement and
it's specifically a displacement of the
cell dimension x however you know
whatever that hot corner value is that's
like the offset inside our larger voxel
so you know if we look at what we've got
here and we've got like min corner hot
and corner large this hot corner eye is
the thing that says how many voxels
squares you go to get from the large
corner to the hot corner that
lives inside of it so it would be this I
don't know if we have a v3 converter for
v3 s is just I must say we do and if we
don't I'll make one um so we have a
Hadamard product between those two and I
think that's it alright so obviously our
box sell dim and I don't know why I
didn't set this to an actual full vector
obviously it is this is supposed to be
yeah the mid corner hot this is actually
offset that way in this case it looks
like hot corner I'd most missing its
access pointer what else you got for me
compiler yeah so this cell count is not
an actual vector so that's a bit of a
screw-up there so what we actually want
here is the cell count in cell count
really doesn't need to exist I guess and
so in this case the cell count doesn't
vary over the voxel so we're really just
lofting it to it f32 and multiplying it
by the dim right it's just a scalar
multiply and in the light dim we don't
really compute at this point so we would
need to
so we're looking at something more like
that and so the only thing we really
need to know now is where actually is
the lighting relative to the camera and
it's kind of a little bit tricky to
figure out where that's going to be
obviously but again what we need it to
what we need to do is we need to
determine like what that value would be
locked to a world space coordinate right
so if you take a look at the origin P
and then you look at the camera offset
from origin so the problem that we have
now is we need to like make sure that
the camera offset in actual like like
literal space we need to make sure these
voxels don't shift around right now what
I would like to say so if we take a look
at the world position right then inside
where we actually determine the world
physician information you know we've got
a value in here that's like chunk dim in
meters and if we look at what that is
set to right the crate world
[Music]
there it is so if you look at where we
set world chunked him in meters you can
see that like the actual like sort of
stepping of the world in integer
coordinates ends up mapping down to like
sort of roughly like a room ish sized
area more or less so you know we don't
probably want the lighting voxel locked
well maybe we do I don't know that we
really want the lighting voxel locked to
that I mean maybe we do but doesn't seem
good so the problem that we're gonna
have here is we have to figure out how
to produce an accurate locked light
value that's truncated but that's
actually pretty tough so the reason that
this is difficult right is because if
you look at what we need to compute
coming into this function we have an
origin p value which we can turn into a
full float if we want to but the problem
is it will lose precision when we do
that so we need to figure out is where
should we be like we almost need to know
what the low bits are of the thing which
is is tricky so I I gotta think about
how we would do this hmm that's a tough
one
[Music]
this is something I wish I wasn't so
hungry I'm very hungry right now I don't
think very good what I'm not eating
I feel like this demands like at least
some peanuts or something whole a second
all right so the problem that we have
let's crunch on some peanuts shall we
much there all right so the problem that
we have here is the thing we want to
compute is you want to take origin P
plus the camera offset from the origin
we want to produce like a v3 from those
and then we want to divide by the voxel
seldom so x infox seldom basically write
and use something rounded to that as a
whole number right we want we want to
align this to a whole number multiple of
the voxel seldom in space right and the
problem is
if we literally did just a step so I was
sang we would lose precision in our
floats so we can do this a number of
ways one is we can just do the
computation in doubles I could the other
is we have to work out the math to
compute the value we actually want
without ever actually explicitly
creating the values right hopefully that
makes some sense so
I already need the whiteboard for this I
don't know if I can do it in ten minutes
but I'll try and we'll see where we go
from now I own room to have some peanuts
on hand for streams in general all right
problem solved so I neglected to test
the actual welcome Tabet when I moved
the set up here so this may not even
work it looks like it is at least
nominally plugged in so that's a good
sign
let's go ahead and open up Milton here
so Milton
I don't know what I want to call this
wait how does it day 563 is that really
right hold on a minute is that it is
that is that wrong it's a little late
now but is that wrong yeah that's
totally wrong
how did we end up if this is this is not
this is day 566 isn't it anyone isn't it
isn't it day 566 does anyone know I'm
gonna leave it as that if somebody knows
what day it actually is please tell me
all right
I think it's day 566 better I think so
look what was it up here so that was a
564 right so if that was day 564 then it
certainly can't be day 562 or whatever
we had on there that's like totally
wrong
so we need to align our voxels and what
we've got here is we have essentially a
problem of one set of grids oh wait
there we go we have what amounts to one
set of grids and we have another set of
grids that we want on top of those sets
of grids and we want to make sure that
they always line up right
not these two grids but this grid that
operates inside of this other grid we
want to make sure that they always line
up like that right so or like this or
whatever we never want to voxel it like
we never want our voxel to be like here
on one frame and then the simulation
center shifts and on the next frame it's
like that or something right so we
always want cells to have their centers
in the same places and we just shift the
voxel around so from frame to frame we
may move it's like they're on one frame
and on the next frame it should be like
exactly there but one cell over or
something but it always should move on
multiples in in some way like that right
okay
so the problem that we have is we are
working off of some oops we're working
off of some center point where that
center point is not the same size grid
right so if I actually bring up the the
grid size here let's suppose the tile
size is is really big right so like
here's the world grid and then our voxel
grid is like this tiny grid inside there
right it looks like that
that makes sense and we're trying to
align to this but our coordinate system
is based off of like the center of like
this right and that makes it really
difficult to reason about because if
we're trying to align two
this grid spacing this grid spacing is
unrelated right it doesn't we don't
start off being aligned to this grid
when we're at the center point of the
other grid if we were we'd be done
because we just align the camera offset
vector and be done right so our problem
boils down to giving a world position
right which remember is like written in
the form like index X index y index Z
right how to mark product with the world
chunk dim so chunk X chunk Y chunk Z
right this is the like index this is the
chunk dim so the Hadamard product here
of these two gives us what we want to
know about the center point perhaps of
this right eye and if I'm not mistaken
is that is that the entirety of it
yes oh you can see here like when you
subtract two of these positions right
all you really do is and when you when
you look at the offset as well right you
can see we can we can alkalis chord
hmm so I don't really see anywhere where
we make any other assumptions about the
world at all honestly so all we really
know is that we have a world chunk
dimming meters you can see we literally
are producing this and we want to make
sure that the thing that comes like when
we come out of this we're gonna have
some position like here and we just want
to know what the closest thing would be
aligned to our voxel grid right so we
basically have another thing here which
is the light like dim the light cell dim
right and this is the chunk dim so we
have like an LX and ly and LZ right and
what we want to know is after we do this
multiplication we want to know our
relative standing versus the light voxel
so we want to be able to to round it to
the nearest one of those right so if you
wanted to know you know I times C
because we could this is entirely scaler
right so we don't actually care about
the fact that these are vectors at all
this is a completely separate thing so
if we take I times C and divide it by L
right this value is going to tell us
which cell we're in in the light voxel
in absolute terms and all we really want
to know
it is essentially the modulus here right
so what we really want to know is what
is I times C mod L right that's what we
want to know because if we have that
value then we can do then we can solve
the problem because then we know how far
we are from an actual from the part of
the cell that would be perfectly aligned
with our light boxes in world space
right so
I mean since this is just a
multiplication presumably it's more or
less going to be the same thing like if
you imagined that this was a divide
instead of a modulus right then what you
would expect to see is you would expect
to see I times C divided by L could be
factored separately as I over L times C
over L and you'd get the same I'm sorry
that's not correct
trying to think of how I would factor
this cuz it would just be I times C over
L right that's all you would see so I
trying to think of yet what I could do
here that wouldn't have this problem
you'd think in all these years of
programming I would have had some time
when I wanted to factor a mod just I've
never done that before
I mean I can certainly add more stuff in
here right so like if I wanted to I
could factor it as I over L times C over
L and what I would end up with is I see
l squared at the bottom so if I wanted
to I could just knock out an L right
meaning this L over 1 here so if I do I
over L times C over L times L over 1
that would give me the factored version
right you know that multiplies to this
so if it was a divide and I just want to
know what the divided number is I can
break it apart and if I broke it apart
each one of these terms can be dealt
with separately and I know this one is
safe and I know this one is safe and
then this one I could guarantee was safe
because I could make sure that this
value was in integer right I can totally
make like right now I was thinking that
it would just be 2 right here's what I
think I put in there um and then this
would be safe as well right so if I want
to do a divide I certainly can the
question is just how would I recompose
the modulus because a modulus and divide
aren't the same thing right so
this tells me what I need to know for
how far yeah yeah like I don't really
see that really tells me much of
anything at all right so I'm curious
that's not really what I wanted this
this looks like what you would want of
course I don't know enough math to know
whether I should trust the math version
of statics changed the programming
version of Stack Exchange is pretty
risky but and these are additions so I
really want just a concise statement of
the of how which options I really have
modulus right
isn't there something from mathworld or
something that I could use here
this is not well okay maybe it is sort
of
I mean yeah I mean you could phrase it
in this in this way right so if a times
B mod C is the same as a mod C times B
mod C mod C then we certainly could
phrase it that way because we do have
that the problem is I'm not 100% certain
that we actually get much out of that
because again you can kind of see the
nastiness here right like if we have a
times B mod C equals a mod C did that
right a mod C times B mod C mod C right
if we're doing that then the problem
that we have is let's suppose we break
it up that way
it's pretty easy for us to say well it's
the index and the chunk mob the L right
and so here we would just say well index
mod L times chunk mod L mod L right and
that's fine the problem is this we still
don't really know what to do with
oh well no it's okay
so all right no we're fine we're fine
we're fine Thank You Khan Academy for
having that as the first thing on the
page
I do think that's fine because if we
think about what's gonna happen here
these two both are going to be just the
modulus that we've done right so if we
do I mod L we will get a small number
and if we do see mod L will also get a
small number right no matter how big I
and C were we should be fine there and
so as long as this we this number we
know is small and this number is small
and this number is small and that R so
this is the only number that could be
quite large so as long as we could
compute the modulus of that easily then
I think we're okay and so I think all we
need to do is make sure that the that
the that the light cell dimension is an
integer right if we just make sure that
the lights all dimension is an integer
we should be able to take the mod very
easily for example if we did pick a
number like 2 or 4 right then we would
be able to do the mod on the index for
the chunks we'd be able to do that
directly we would not need to ever
actually compute it right we could just
do a straightforward bit operation
because the mod the mod 2 or the mod 4
or whatever of you know any power of 2
value would just be the bottom bits of
the number so we know we wouldn't have
any numerical stability issues if we
just take the bottom bits of the number
and we know that those there's only a
few so we take like the to bottom it's
of the number and we multiply that by
the actual modulus of C times L of C mod
L right
would give us another small number that
could then be model so I'm okay with
that
right if we were to say like it's 2:00
or something right then we wouldn't we
want it when we want to take this
modulus we take a look at the origin P
so in world position right and it's got
this like chunk x y and z so if we were
to just look at those base values I have
to think about what happens with those
values when they're negative because
when they're negative then the mod the
low bits may need to be like flipped in
order to get us the right value so I'd
have to think about that but otherwise
otherwise I think we're okay
so what we want to do here is say yeah
like chunk XY and Z if we just look at
like what happens with chunk X for
example and we say we need to know the
mod of that for a 2 wide cell right then
all we should have to do I argue is just
take the inverse of like whatever the
bottom bits are right and and out the
rest so and out the top so for two I
think we just do this right
that is the mod of yeah of that index
right so then we need to know what the
modulus is don't we have modules
we must have a modulus somewhere we've
never done a floating-point modulus
there's no way that can't be true
seriously huh alright well we'll have to
get that in there tomorrow as well then
so we would need the modulus of whatever
the actual world sizes as well so we
would need that
where are you there is just too many
meters so we need the chunk dim in
meters and we would need to take the
modulus of that with respect to the
light as well so we'd basically need a
mod to of the chunk dim in meters and
then we would need to take the modulus
of the whole thing right like so but in
theory that's for our particular
coordinate origin
that's the offset from an even spacing
of the voxel cell dimension right so we
know that this is the you know the X
displacement basically like this is the
the offset that we would need to either
add up to top ourselves off or subtract
it a way to get to the origin so when we
want to determine like what the min
corner is let's say we were doing the
min corner off of just the origin P as
opposed to using the camera offset we do
want to use the camera offset probably
but let's suppose we did then the min
corner hot would just be whatever like
zero zero zero is minus that exodus
right so it would subtract away that and
then we would be flooring to the to the
box hold okay and that's really all we
were doing unfortunately we don't have a
modulus operator apparently which is
news to me so we need to kind of put
this stuff in there
I think that's stuff that we will save
till next time and we'll go to a QA now
but yeah but that's basically it
okay good so someone confirmed it was
day 566 which is what I thought it was
and so I think that I just set the timer
wrong or something so wanted to get that
corrected
you talking about non-realism
non-realistic but good-looking art got
me thinking do you plan on having game
entities that manipulate light in
extremely non real ways no we could
certainly play with it but I had not
really been considering any of that at
the moment it would be interesting to
have entities that sucked light out of a
room potentially that seems like it
might be fun I'm not sure about bending
normals around that sounds like I don't
think humans would necessarily like that
effect because they're they wouldn't
know what to make of it probably it's a
little bit too much if that makes sense
why not use mod directly so the the
modulus this operator doesn't actually
work for floating-point right it only
works for it only works for integer
values and if we're doing modulus on an
integer then yeah I mean I could write
it this way and presumably the compiler
is smart enough to do the right thing
there but again I kind of want to think
about what I want to happen when it's
negative and I need to think about a
bunch of stuff so I'm just gonna write
it like this for now and kind of remind
myself to go in and figure out what I
actually want to have happen in terms of
the the floating-point part a
floating-point modulus you actually have
to do right you actually have to
implement that in float somehow and in
this particular case because it happens
to be a mod by two honestly we could do
some bit manipulation and do it if we
wanted to because a mod by two just so
happens to be something you could do
more directly on the
bit values but I don't know that we
really want to do that I probably just
want to implement a regular modulus SSE
modulus that we just do like a floor a
floor whistle subtract kind of a thing
so I don't I don't anticipate doing that
but you know couldn't you contrive it so
that chunk dim is always an even
multiple of light seldom I certainly
could I could also do the opposite of
that
and make sure that that light dim is
always some small some even proportion
chunk dim right and that might be
smarter you know it's hard to say like
we could just take whatever the size of
the world dimension is divide it by some
known value that's the resolution we
want so we divide it by 17 or we divide
it by 10 or whatever and we say all
right now it's just matches in fact yeah
now that you bring that up I that might
be smarter because then you don't have
to worry about this anymore
that's a really good point I don't know
I didn't think of that I guess I didn't
have peanuts for most of the stream
called a view so are you asking
basically like how do you write math
stuff for people to understand clearly
is that what you're asking
rational coder asks I'm missing
something fundamental about spherical
harmonics I get the idea of decomposing
areas into spheres but I don't get how
you could use something like that to
accumulate some representation of light
that you can reconstruct would you like
to provide an interest some time so I
haven't ever worked with robotics so I
don't really feel qualified to give an
intro but what I can tell you to maybe
help frame the understanding there but
you should go read about it more it's
just that the idea of orthogonal basis
for things in general is that they can
be added I mean that's sort of why you
use them in a sense so for example if I
take and I break down a light source
right into a set of base light values
that I know are orthogonal right so I
know that they don't overlap right in in
any way they're they're linearly
independent of each other or whatever
right then I know that I can add those
together like a normal vector space and
I know that I'm getting standard vector
addition rules out of them right I know
that all the things that I would want to
do will work I can scale them by a
certain amount I can split one into two
halves and add them back together and
get the same result rights within the
two have scaled them add them and I get
the same result of scaling the original
right like all the same stuff you would
want to do in vector spaces spherical
harmonics are an orthogonal basis in
that regard as far as I know and so what
that means is that what you have done
when you decompose a spherical lighting
a set of spherical egg samples and you
can pose them into into basis functions
that
Saphira karmic basis functions what
you're basically saying is specifically
that they do add to reconstruct the
original and it was an orthogonal
decomposition so that if you want to add
those parameters separately
they will reconstruct if you'd added the
two Lighting's
separately right and this is no
different than any other deconstruction
you normally use like the discrete
cosine transform Fourier transform you
know laplacian like any kind of
transform that you normally use they all
share this property and that's the
reason why we like them right the reason
why people like these kind of transforms
is specifically because if you have a
transform that you just transfer them
some values you need you transform it
and then whatever you do in the other
space wouldn't correspond to the same
operations in the original space it's
really hard to work with that right
because if you have a nonlinear
transform like that then unless the
whole goal of the thing was to do
nonlinear work with it then you end up
with a problem of not being able to just
say oh I want to add these two lights
together I just add their circle
harmonic coefficients together whatever
or I have the Fourier transform of these
two waveforms I just add them together
and I get the same thing as adding the
two waveforms right that is typically
why you want these kinds of basis
functions they are the basis functions
which give you back useful operations we
can pick other basis functions all day
long but they won't have those same
properties if we just randomly pick them
you have to specifically construct basis
functions that have our thuggin
properties if you want to end up with a
vector space at the end of it right
okay so-called abuse is yeah essentially
or maybe anything with lots of jargon
that's kind of essential to working with
the subject seriously I find myself on
the other side a lot when I'm doing like
FPGA stuff and I have no idea what
people are talking about but once I
learn all the jargon it becomes second
nature to think about things in those
terms if that makes sense um so I guess
what I would say is when you are
explaining something I think it's
crucial to remember that what you are
trying to do is form a picture in the
person's head that works as a matter of
course right at least this is how I
think about it because you haven't
really understood something if you only
understand it in terms of the jargon you
only understand it if you understand it
without meeting the jargon that's how I
look at things right and as a
consequence it becomes pretty easy for
you to know if your explanation actually
is accessible to a beginner because it
should be possible to explain the thing
without any jargon and just mention what
the jargon is for the thing as you're
explaining it right so for example when
I answer a question in the QA I will
often use jargon because their brief
answers right like to give a various
example I just used the word orthogonal
in an explanation to somebody asking
about circular or onyx but I didn't
explain where orthogonal was right when
I explain things on handmade hero actual
the first time when we do something I
don't do that right if I say orthogonal
I then explain what does that actually
mean
right and usually what I see when I see
math explanations is they're almost
completely useless
so for example
I usually you get this sort of thing
right so if you look at this this is a
perfect example of a completely useless
explanation I would contend that there
is literally no person on earth period
full stop there are literally no people
who don't already know what an
orthogonal function is who could read
this right because there's nobody who
knows integral calculus who doesn't know
what an orthogonal function is right and
right off the bat you introduce all of
this garbage right which is like an
integral of three functions nobody has
told you what they are or how to think
about them right with an integral right
off the bat
you've got bracket syntax here write it
just forget it
right it's just a it's a nightmare right
and this is how most math is I don't
know why I have no idea why
mathematicians tend to write this way
right and similarly like if you look at
like something like the Fourier
transform that which is like you know
related here I bet we can get another
exact version of that right so this is
completely useless no one who doesn't
know what the Fourier transform is will
ever be able to read that equation
period I guarantee you there is not a
single human being on earth ever in the
history of time who didn't know what a
Fourier transform was read that and went
oh I understand now no chance zero the
only people who can use this equation
are people who already know what the
Fourier transform is and just need to
remember what the equation is because
they forgot or don't want to derive it
or something right like that's it okay
similarly this stuff is also completely
useless F : Arta C is completely
fricking useless right you
not like it literally first of all it
doesn't save any space I don't know why
mathematicians write stuff like this
especially not for like in an
explanatory context right because if you
just said if you just literally rip
wrote out the words a Fourier transform
is something that takes real numbers as
an input and outputs clump complex
numbers almost everyone who has had a
high school math class would understand
what you meant almost nobody who hasn't
had graduate math has any idea what that
is
right at least not in the US I guarantee
you if I went to anybody who went to
high school with me who didn't then go
on to be a mathematician and I said what
is F : are arris II mean to you they'd
say I have no frickin clue right and so
the important thing is constructing the
image in someone's mind this is useless
this is talking to an expert they
already know what a fourier transform is
so I have no idea why this is here what
you want to say instead is a Fourier
transform is is basically a function it
converts one thing into another thing
what are those two things well
the input to it is a real number the
output to it is a complex number you
remember what complex numbers are right
a complex number is the thing that has a
real number part right it's a regular
number like 3.2 and then a complex part
that's something times I now if you
forgot what I was from your high school
math class I is the square root of
negative one it might be kind of weird
to think about what the square root of
negative 1 is because it doesn't
actually exist that's why we call an
imaginary number but actually it's not
so weird if you think about it and the
reason is it's not so weird is because
look what if I wanted to say I gave you
a number right any number seven right
and I said take the square root of it
you know how to do it on your calculator
right you know how to do it you could
just type seven in its square root and
you even know what it means you means
that the answer
you get back if you square it you get
seven right everyone knows that so
you're like what's I am so confused I
don't get an imaginary number I don't
know it didn't make sense of my high
school math class that's correct it
didn't make sense because high school
math class suck in the textbooks suck
but it's not that hard to understand
what it is now I give you a negative
number I said can you tell me what the
square root of negative 7 is right well
you know what the square root of 7 was
because you just did it and so the only
thing we really need to do right is we
need to have a way of remembering that
the thing was negative because when we
square a number right if the thing that
we square is negative it just becomes
positive right negative 2 squared is 4
and 2 squared is 4 so if I ask you to
take the square root of 4 you can tell
me to I say take the square root of
negative 4 you're like I know that's
still - but it's like gotta be negative
so all we were trying to do with that is
remember we're trying to remember what
the sign was it's the thing that tells
us what the sign was when we started
right so you can actually get an
intuitive understanding of what I is
it's the place that the negative goes
when we Square rooted because we need it
to go somewhere we need to remember
right so we create an extra dimension to
our number system to remember that sign
and that allows us more flexibility
because now instead of when you ask me
what the red square root of negative 7
is and I say I don't know because it
can't exist right I say ah I can tell
you what the square root of 7 is and
then I can use an extra piece I can add
a piece to my representation of numbers
to remember whether it came from a
negative number to begin with right so
that's what we're gonna do with the
Fourier transform when we do that
transform we can think about that the
that I that we need there it actually
has some meaning it's not purely
imaginary it really does have some
connection to reality if you think about
it there's ways we can can connect it
back and that's one of them so before
you transform is one that's going to
take in a regular old number of the kind
you're
used to and it's gonna turn it into a
complex number which is maybe a number
you're not quite so used to but that
number is not that complicated it's
really just the same as a real number in
some sense with that extra accent
dimension added so that we can
understand a wider range of source for
our numbers okay so when we take the
Fourier transform what we're gonna do is
we need to turn something into we need
to turn something from the basic old
boring variety that you're used to right
the Euclidean space as you're usually
used to which is just the thing where
you know it's like the world around us
we walk in one direction we go straight
we walk in another direction we go
straight we start putting coordinate
systems on these things we're talking
about these like perpendicular lines
right that are just like rulers going in
directions and that's how we think of
our coordinate systems right but what a
Fourier transform does is it asks a
different question it's saying what if
we wanted to represent where we are in a
space or you know what the value of
something is with basis functions that
aren't just little rulers right they're
actually sine waves they're actually
wave forms thing is that oscillate right
and so rather than you just thinking
about as I turn a number up in my
coordinate system as X gets higher and
higher I'm just going further and
further along the x axis rather than
thinking about that we need to think
about is as I turn up my number X it
does get higher yes but then it starts
getting lower again and then it gets
negative and then it comes back up to
positive and then it goes up right so
it's oscillating okay and so what the
Fourier transform does is it tries to
take values that we were previously
maybe representing in some other space
that was actually like just representing
things as little rulers and we're trying
to then turn it into something that is
represented by sine waves adding these
sine waves together to reproduce the
result right so the basis functions the
output of a Fourier transform is a
representation of the input that's made
using sine waves
is kind of a weird thing to think about
but if you think about the kinds of
things that we need went and I could
keep going on about this but you get the
idea right so does that give you some
perspective I could keep going and talk
about how all right how do we start
making sine waves that cancel each other
out so that we can have the same sorts
of things that we want to have with
Rebecca right blah blah blah that's how
you explain something because now
someone has something in their brains
that can actually think about when
they're thinking about a Fourier
transform instead of this which is
nothing there's nothing in here to think
about it's just purely abstract right
there's nothing to hold on to you're
just floating in space and this is the
way math things often look right
serious thanks I guess I put too much
emphasis on accumulation and
reconstruction I can understand about
what you just said about the re now in
addition my misunderstanding is more
fundamental I understand how you can use
ray-tracing to get light intensities and
colors at probe points which can be
passed to your fragment shader but I
don't get how you can get some spherical
representation of light at probe points
and what the heck your fragment shader
would do with it
so again if we're talking about
spherical harmonics so spherical
harmonics are a series of lobe shapes
right much like the Fourier transform is
a series of sine waves that just are
linear like we're in time right look we
think of an audio waveform for a Fourier
transform let's say right we are just
taking a chunk and we're gonna pretend
that it's periodic so it's just
infinitely repeating because that's part
of the definition of how the Fourier
transform works see if you need the
Fourier transform to operate on a finite
window you actually it's actually kind
of wrong right but I we're gonna add a
bunch of sine waves together to
reconstruct some arbitrary signal that
we had right and you see this in the
Fourier transform the graphic equalizer
on your stereo is a Fourier transform of
the sound wave right a very low
resolution Fourier transform it's
showing you the various frequencies that
you would add together to get back the
sound wave it's just instead of showing
you the actual number you would need to
reconstruct it showing you a average of
those Bend into six buckets or five
buckets or whatever right so spherical
harmonics is the same way it's saying
look let's do basically the Fourier
transform on a sphere and so instead of
each thing just being a sine wave it's
actually like a sinusoidal lobe and if
we imagine taking any sphere with any
number any amount of data on it just
like the Fourier transform says that
with an infinite number of sine waves we
can reconstruct an infinitely precise
signal that you input the same is true
of the sphere a
infinitely large number of spherical
harmonic coefficients can reconstruct
any spherical information right so we
are never going to use infinite but if
we use enough we can reconstruct the
sphere of lighting from our spherical
harmonic coefficients and if we can
reconstruct the sphere of information
then when we actually need to do our
lighting lighting is just a series of
questions about what is coming in from a
sphere right that's what light is off of
the surface is it's you know a brdf or
any kind of like lighting transfer
function is just saying for some in
output direction I need to do some
summation over the sphere of different
you know input directions and that's how
much light goes out right and so as long
as the spherical harmonics can
reconstruct the data of the sphere it's
pretty easy actually because you just
ask the spherical harmonics anytime you
want
what's the lighting in this area and it
tells you right the same way a Fourier
transform can reconstruct a particular
part of a signal the spherical aromatic
ovations can reconstruct a particular
part of the sphere and how bright it was
at that point and so that's
fundamentally all you would be doing
with spherical harmonics right
all right let's end of the queues
all right thank you everybody for
joining me for this and a handmade hero
sort of pleasure coating with you as
always I am in the process of collecting
some questions because I'm going to be
doing a little bit of tutorial video
series at some point here soon in the
future and I am collecting questions
that are I would say generally
applicable novice questions was sort of
what I'm trying to get a collection of
and I've gotten a ton a ton a ton of
emails I don't know it might even be
over a hundred at this point but I
basically asked the question on Twitter
lo this Twitter maybe but here is the
the specific tweet that I'm talking
about but I said dear aspiring
Asperger's what programming concepts
techniques or processes do you most want
explained in tutorials and I said just
mail them to fact Molly rocket comm and
I've got like just tons and tons of
responses which is great so I'm kind of
going through and collating all of those
and planning exactly how I want to do
them but if anybody wasn't aware of this
I feel like I should mention on the
stream a few times just so people who
maybe don't read Twitter which honestly
should be pretty much everyone at this
point because it's a terrible platform
go ahead and email me your questions
there if you have some that you think
would be appropriate or even if you know
you think that there if you don't know
because I can always like I'll be like
sipping them and the things I think will
work well and things that I don't so you
don't you don't really need to censor
yourself just if you think you have a
question you might want to ask and send
it in and I'll deal with it
the reason I bring that up is because
during the presume we had a good one
which was a pointer aliasing it's
something a lot of novice programmers
don't know what it is but they probably
have heard of it and they aren't sure
whether they should care or what it
would mean
and so pointer aliasing is a good
example and I'm gonna add that one to
the list because I'm gonna probably want
to make a specific video that's like
what is pointer aliasing and why you
should care so if you have some of that
stuff
you think you might want to know about
yourself
that you think would make a good topic
as sort of a standalone piece that just
says here is a self-contained like 15
minute video explaining X that is
exactly what this project is about so do
send those two FAQ at Mali rocket comm
and more broadly if I get them on stream
I'll also try to remember ones that I
think would be good for that but I do
kind of use the number of times that a
question is asked as sort of a little
bit of an impromptu vote on which ones I
should prioritize covering because
they're the things that more people are
confused about or more people think they
want to know about and might spend time
to learn about so do send it in and that
way it kind of will will count as part
of that vote as well alright that's it
for today I'll be back tomorrow when
we're gonna finish doing the sort of
voxel large small voxel work and that's
really my goal for the weekend now I
think that's in good shape I'm glad we
thought of that stuff today I think
that's a good way to do things and
excited for that going forward so we can
get that finished up tomorrow same time
same place and then next week we can
start to focus on light transport and
working back through and then you know
we're getting closer we're getting
closer to having a really good lighting
solution which which is really where I
want to be lighting is is very difficult
and so getting good lighting solution in
places is a it's an accomplishment we
should give ourselves a pat on the back
floor
alright that's it if you want to follow
the series at home of course you can
always go to handmade here org and
pre-order the game it comes with a
source code so you can compile it
yourself and your own machine play
around with it if you would like to
finish the voxel work before I do it's a
good exercise to do it's pretty
straightforward
so maybe give that a shot and then tune
back in tomorrow and I will do it myself
until then have fun program everyone and
I'll see y'all on the Internet
take it easy everybody