like so and then we can get started
hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hiro the show Rico to complete game live
on Twitch no engine no libraries and and
basically like you know I have to say
I've been having a lot of fun with it I
really have I'm looking forward to some
of the stuff that's coming up now we're
kind of trying to wind things down
because we're gonna take a week off next
week people have been asking for some
time to catch up and I'm gonna be
traveling next week so I thought that
would be a good time to do it
it would kind of prevent what I'm sure
will be a lot of frustrations if we were
trying to stream next week and were
we're constantly having tons of dropped
frames and other sorts of nasty ices
that will happen from various inter
internet connections elsewhere in the
world but anyway I like I said I've been
pretty excited with how it's been going
in I'm pretty happy with the progress
we've been making so let's go ahead and
get back into it right now we're working
on deciding how we want to handle Z so
we're just gonna play around that today
and see what happens if you have
pre-ordered the game on handmade hero
org you should have gotten a link in
your email and that link in that email
is something that you can open up to
download the source code anytime you
want and if you download that source
code you get the zip file that zip file
has little tiny baby zip files all in it
one for each day today is day 73
unzipped day 72 source code and you will
be exactly where I am right now and you
could follow along with me at home it's
kind of like does anyone ever watch Bill
Cosby's picture pages when they were a
kid this is before lawsuits and things
when Bill Cosby was just a person who
had a kid show and you know you would
color along with Bill Cosby or something
like this I don't know I don't think I
ever had the picture pages but he would
come on he'd be like picture pages
picture pages you know something along
with picture pages come and watch Bill
Cosby do with picture page with you it's
like that you can follow it at home just
like with Bill Cosby before the
controversy you know what I'm saying and
that's the best time probably to enjoy
Bill Cosby when you didn't have to worry
about other sorts of things he might be
doing now let's go ahead and get back to
where we were like I said we kind of
finished up yesterday I don't think we
had any particular bugs or to dues that
we're kind of left hanging we we sort of
just recreated
everything that we were doing before but
with full Z handling and the pipeline
and so now we kinda have to think about
is what are we actually going to do with
Z we don't really know we need some kind
of a feel for that and so what I want to
do is I want to be able to make it so I
can go like up and down stairs and stuff
and I think that will help me to
understand what I want to have happen
with Z and we can kind of sort of you
know get some idea for it now in order
to do that we have a little bit of a
problem
there is no ground right now so there is
no real understanding of even where a
stairwell would be so I kind of need to
put something in I guess that would be a
stairwell put put in something that's
that's going to indicate that we can go
up and down in a particular area and
then I can you know do something about
it from there so let's just start with
doing that because I got to get
somewhere before I can even really do
anything else with it now we have some
more stuff in the art directory I'm just
gonna pick something random we don't
actually have anything that is drawn for
this purpose yet I could certainly ask
for it but we just haven't got to that
point yet and we basically got some
ground patches we've got a rock-like so
we've got trees we've got some grass so
I don't know maybe I'll just use one of
these rocks
we'll use this Rocco to bitmap maybe
I'll just use Rocco to dot bitmap and
we'll basically say that that's gonna be
a stairwell and then we'll just kind of
pretend that it is one and we'll see
what happens
you know kind of as we play route that
with going up and down and so on I can
also do some stuff where maybe I put
something in front of the stairwell and
you know you can walk down and go sort
of behind it so it occludes it I don't
know we'll play with that a little bit
and if we need to make a test asset we
can also go ahead and open up and
just make a test asset right that sort
of is whatever we want as a debugging
aid so that's what I'd like to do so
let's go ahead and load that what did I
say that was that's Rocco to dot bitmap
let's just load that into the set so we
can play with it
and we'll go from there right so we have
that quote unquote sword and now we have
a quote unquote stairwell right and I
don't know I guess we
got stairs up and stairs down so we have
stair up and stare down so maybe we need
to do actually like two different kinds
of rock woman one that's gonna be the up
and one that's gonna be the down now
it's a little bit a little bit crazy but
you know what are you gonna do so
there's our stair up there's our stair
down so we'll load those two in and now
we can draw this I don't actually know
if we ever made a stairwell type we may
never have actually done that let's take
a look it looks like we've never
actually made one of those so let me go
ahead and make a stairwell here we'll do
a stairwell I guess we'll do a stairwell
up and a stairwell down I don't know if
we really need to do that in fact I
guess if we want it to be kind of fancy
about it we could sort of think of it as
one entity that was just placed there
and it's if you're coming from the
bottom of it you go up and if you're
coming from the top of it you go down we
could do it that way maybe that makes
some sense
I don't really know that's a good
question I suppose it all right you know
let's do it that way I mean you might as
well start with something we'll just you
know we'll just start with it that way
so then we'll just place it there and
you know assume it's got a little
graphic and it shows on either side I
really don't like I said I've never made
a game of this kind I've never worked on
a game of this kind before where you had
like I usually work on 3d stuff and in
there you've got to build an actual
stairwell that actually you walk up the
stairs and all this stuff so I don't
know what the good approximation is I've
certainly seen plenty of games do like
you know things ranging from very cheesy
to not so cheesy and 2d about it and you
know where we want to be on that cheese
cheese scale I don't know
so all right so we got our stairwell
here we've got that loaded so let's go
ahead and re-enable I think we had some
code that already generated a concept of
up and down levels basically and you
know maybe let's go ahead and try to try
to put that in here just just sort of
re-enable the code if you will that was
creating those so that we can have some
of levels and so this I believe is what
we were doing before we were you know
it's basically saying that we could have
doors that go up and down when we're
doing our random number generation and I
think that's probably all we need but we
will need to now put in a thing I don't
know that there's any actual code in
here so yeah this tile value equals 1 2
&amp; 3 stuff basically what we need to do
because these tile values we used to
write into our tile map but we got rid
of the tile map we just use entities now
for everything what we want to do is
take whatever the tile map was that
chorus bonded to a stairwell and
actually just put that in there and you
can see us doing that here essentially
right this is where we were setting
those tile values so really we can kind
of change this code up a little bit we
could we could just well I mean I might
as well leave a guess that the way it
was but what we can do here is say
alright if they've got a tile value 3 or
a tile value for what we can do is add
in that stairwell right there
so door up and door down we want to if
we're going to add an entity the way
that I was saying where there's just one
entity then we don't really need to
think about both door types we just add
one and we don't need to add the reverse
kind if that makes sense because it's
just sitting there
so thinking about how that works what we
do here is when we do a random choice we
do a created Z door thing the created Z
door flag it tells us essentially I
guess whether we created it on this path
so what we really want to do here is we
want to say you know we only really want
to do this work if we created a Z door
right like so so if we created a Z door
then we're gonna say you know whichever
kind it was we're gonna put it in there
we don't care if it's a door up or a
door or a door down we we only need to
know that to position where the entity
is in Z I guess right that's pretty much
all we need to do so what we're going to
do is we're gonna do an ADD stairs here
and when we do our add stairs
I guess what we have to do is say we're
gonna put it at this AB style x ab cell
y ab style Z what we want to do is say
if it was a door going down let's put
the base let's say let's say that we put
the stairwell starting at the lower
level so either it's at our ab stiles e
or if it's a door that's going downward
then we would like to put it at one
below us right so we're basically gonna
say if it's a door going downwards its
AB x -1
otherwise it's that AB Stiles E and then
we don't really care about this anymore
at all we also don't really care about
this tile value stuff very much we
really just want to know should be door
right and that's gonna equal false and
these are basically just should be door
equal true cases right I think that's
basically it these are just kind of kind
of wrote so let's just get rid of that
so we don't have this concept of tile
bail anymore so should be door and will
basically say like okay if it should be
a door then we'll add a wall otherwise
if we created a Z door here then we'll
do this add stair nests and again this
code is all just garbage we're sort of
waiting to do world creation until a
little bit further down but we need to
always kind of come back to it and add
little things for now just so we have
stuff that we can test and so that's
really all I'm doing here this code is
is it's just complete throwaway code it
doesn't matter at all it's not like some
of this other codes where we're actually
trying to design something that works
well so that we can see how you know
it's gonna slot in the world code is
assumed to just be you know complete
stand-in so if we add a stairwell at
this location we're gonna go ahead and
do this so we add an enmity and then all
we really have to do I guess is set its
extents to be reasonable I think that
this should be basically the same as a
wall take up roughly the same amount of
space let's say for now but it's also
we're gonna use that that Z value now
that height value to sort of say well
how how tall really do we want
stairwells to be right
and we've got this stuff here we've got
tile depth in meters so we kind of want
to be one full depth high one full tile
high I would say so it stretches up to
the next floor wherever that next floor
is that seems to me like probably what I
want to do right so I want to say that
so it's that high I don't know if maybe
it needs to be higher than that I don't
know how we're in but that's really what
we need to start figuring out now is how
we're gonna sort of size this stuff okay
so if I do this I'm not sure we need to
think about how we're doing our collide
stuff that stuff sort of still needs to
get worked on a little bit still on our
to-do list I'm gonna say it doesn't
collide at the moment I got to think
about a little bit more about how that's
gonna work okay so what we want to do
now is draw our stairwell as well we
want to be able to kind of put that in
here somehow and so when we're actually
doing our loop throughs when we do our
our stairwell we need to decide how we
want to draw stairwells for now I mean I
think we're just gonna draw just that
bitmap there and it's you know nothing
particularly useful going on there and
we need to figure out what the offset is
for that bitmap because we don't
actually know I guess I said it was rock
OH - so let's take a look at that in the
ladies and gentlemen the I
present to you the and so I guess
we'll just put it at the center roughly
or maybe right about there I guess might
be the thing because it sort of extends
up it does I don't know so what we want
to do is say all right that guy is 37 37
roughly let's say so that's right about
there oops and and we'll see how that
goes so now we should in theory get a
stairwell Oh our poor are poor Monstar
has been created where the stairwell is
which is not really what we want to do
so maybe I will
the Monstar around I could move the
stairwell as well I suppose but let's go
ahead and move the Monstar
let's move the Monstar out of the way so
now we've got our stairwell there and
that's good again we don't see sort I
mean we don't why sort our entities yet
that's why these things are in showing
up in totally random order something I
don't really want to deal with at the
moment so we're gonna do that when we
start doing the renderer work but you
know the familiar is kind of annoying
it's annoying to have someone follow you
around all the time
you know what I'm saying it's like go
get your own life you know Sam anyway so
we've got our our our quote-unquote
stairwell in here now and so what we
want to do now is make it so that when
we walk over this we can kind of go up
and down the stairs and so maybe just
what I'll say is that like you know
going I'm trying to think of how we went
do this like going forwards into a
stairs is goes down them and going back
from a stairs kind of comes up them or
something like that I don't know if
there should be a convention so the
player knows like you know they just
walk you know down it or something like
this but this may tie in to our
collision detection stuff we may end up
wanting to do just take a look here
right we may want to do this stuff as
well because what we sort of want to do
now is we want to say when my guy starts
walking on top of this entity right when
I walk on this thing I want that entity
to take me down in Z as I go right
that's what I'd like to write and again
since we haven't really gotten much in
the way of collision detection in there
yet beyond just the basic sort of did I
hit something that seems harder to do so
I think maybe this may imply that we've
got to take these two guys together
because that's what I want to write and
I'm not thinking of a lot of ways to
write that right now conveniently with
what we have so does that make sense
hopefully that makes sense what I want
to do is say what I want to be able to
do is okay so we're on day 73 let's see
here let's get some space day 73 what I
want to be able to do is sort of say
okay
if you imagine this in actual three
dimensions right what we have here
here's one plane of motion and here's
another one that's below it right so
what we want to do here is we want to
basically draw in you know something
that's gonna operate like a stairwell or
you know a ramp a ramp is probably more
more accurate because we I don't know
that we care about sternness we just
want the player to be able to go down so
we've got something that essentially
like you know the player approach is and
we want them to be able to move forward
and have them go down as they move
forwards whereas if they were going the
other direction they would move upwards
right so kind of what I want to do is
something roughly that says you know if
you imagine this part projected in a to
a top view I think what I'd like is I'd
like to say okay we've got you know
we've got a region and when the player
enters this region I want their Z
coordinate to equal how far you know in
Y they've gone right so when they're
here when they're at this level I want
their Z loops whatever happened there Z
to be the stair max right wherever the
maximum is and when they come here I
want this Z to be the stair minimum
right and as they walk along it I want
it to change now what I'd like to do
further is I'd like to say when they
exit the stairwell I'd like to probably
create some regions here I suppose right
something like this I'd like to be able
to say that when the player is in this
region they cannot exit the stairwell
right like I want them to only exit the
stairwell relatively close to one or the
other side of it and so when they are
within you know when they're in like the
bottom third
they can exit out to the zmax when
they're in maybe the the far third they
can exit out to z-man but we're in when
they're in the middle third of the
stairwell they just can't leave either
side right and I don't know that we
necessarily want that we may find that
it's better to just let them exit and
we'll just snap them to which either
side it is but point being I want that
option I want whatever solution we come
up here come up with here to allow me to
choose that if I find that it's better I
don't want that to be like some really
impossible thing it's like oh my god how
I can implement that I want that to be
like pretty obvious in the
implementation like no you just do it
this way and it's easy and if we choose
not to use it that's fine but it should
be possible so I don't know if that
makes sense to you hopefully that makes
some sense so what I want to do now is I
want to talk about that in terms of how
we're going to actually implement it so
you'll notice on the collision detection
thing I was talking about reprojection
basically what I want to do is I want to
have a concept of inside and outside in
our collision system I want to be able
to say is am i inside or outside some
region and we're going to use that for
two purposes purpose one is for like
behavior you know actual game logic
right and this is an example of that
right in this case I'm just saying when
the player enters into this stairwell
region that I've created I want it to
behave in a specific fashion right
that's that's sort of what we're saying
here but the second thing that we want
to do is we want to use that for
robustness in the collision sector
because right now we have a problem in
the collision sector where you know we
are currently doing it such that you
know if you have a wall and you you sort
of go against that wall we try to put
you so that you're not when you hit that
wall we're try to put you so that you're
not interpenetrating the wall but if due
to floating-point precision we mess that
up meaning we do place you just slightly
on the other side of the wall since all
we check for is collision with that
all you've now been embedded inside the
wall and you can only walk around inside
the wall right and so we could choose to
solve that problem by just constantly
fighting there buses and try to make our
collision detector so that it never did
that but that's kind of a losing battle
usually because sweating point precision
is very hard to do properly in all cases
it's very hard to know if you've tested
all of the possible ways so what I'd
rather do is go ahead and say okay once
we have this inside outside concept we
can then use it to say are we inside a
wall if we are project the player out to
whatever the closest place is that's not
inside the wall right so I'd like this
for both reasons right I wanted it we
were gonna do it primarily for the
robustness but it's already the case if
we want to do our Z stuff it's already
the case that I also would like it for
actual gameplay purposes and so let's
start out by doing the gameplay part of
it which is what we were trying to do
and then we'll also keep an eye on this
because maybe we can do it all in one
sort of series where we actually do
everything there where we get all of
that stuff worked out together and that
would be nice right so yes so what I'd
like to do is is go ahead into the
collision system and sort of take a look
at what's going on in there right let's
take a look I don't know why where did
my yeah we have that bug there's a weird
bug if someone could remind me to write
this down after streams over there's
some kind of bug with my weird little
clock thing that I wrote where the it
goes the little head outline thing goes
away which is you I use to prevent
myself from typing where you can't see
it basically where did it go so remind
me to go take a look at that bug because
it's probably just a bug in the code for
a little timer app and I'd like to fix
it so let's see here we have our move
entity code which is really all that
we've written for collision detection so
far so it's pretty easy for us to test
to see if we are inside something
we've already done that with the is
inside rectangle thing and so really
what we need to do in here is sort of
say all right we've got you know we're
doing these this this movement we need
to start thinking about the concept that
the player may be inside regions of
space when he actually moves and to do
things you know based on that so how do
I want to do that I don't know that I
want to store that stuff at the moment
doesn't seem like a good idea
I think what I'd rather do is just
quickly build the set of things so I'd
like to do say like what are all the
entities that were inside at the start
and again this just shows the need for
that spatial partition again because you
can see how much of this entity like
testing that we're doing it's it's too
much right so what we want to do is be
able to quickly test the entities here
we really want a spatial partition for
this right but we haven't done that work
yet anyway
so we've got we're gonna go ahead and
check for the entities we're gonna see
for any entity for any entity that we
basically is not us I guess I would say
so we have should collide I don't know
if we actually want should collide as a
thing probably we can just you should
collide for now so let's do that
so basically say that assuming that this
is a should collide scenario so if
should collide past the game state and
the entity and the test entity so
assuming that we should collide I just
want to test to see whether I'm inside
that entity or not right I just want to
see so we can go ahead and do that we
can say all right for all of the
entities that are there you know if the
rectangles overlap because we know that
they both have a dimension so we can say
if rectangles overlap or intersect say
so
we can pass the the rectangles in so I
guess they would basically be let's see
and that's right there so we've got that
dim that's the dimension of the entity
so I'm gonna say I want to make a
rectangle I don't remember what we
called this but I think we called it
Center plot Center diameter is what we
want and if I don't have that I'll write
it so we want to make one rectangle and
we want to make it from the entities
position and then using the entities
dimension and then we want to do the
same thing for the test entity right I
want to say the test entities so and
we're just gonna say if those two
rectangles intersect and maybe so that I
can inspect it easier in the debugger
I'll say you know MTT rect equals this
and you know that doesn't change as well
so really I can also just put that right
here I should say right here where we
just node that's what the entity rect is
at the moment and I might bind this up
so we can see what stuff is in here as
well so let's do it this way and just
put a little note here check for initial
inclusion and so we've got our entity
rect and then we've got our tests in an
erect and that will just come here
so rectangle three rep so now I've got
both rectangles and I can test to see if
they intersect right so if the
rectangles intersect then we know that
we started out basically overlapping
whatever this thing was right and I
don't really know so it's hard for me to
say really what we want to do in terms
of the stairwell stuff but I'm gonna go
ahead and say probably you know here's
what I'm thinking just just to give you
a little a little sort of diagrammatical
it was a little illustration so in some
sense we may only want the player
in this case - we may not really want
overlap testing right because if the
players sort of stance point is anywhere
other than being included sort of mostly
within the stairwell we don't really
wanted to go down the stairs we wanted
to kind of channel in there we want to
make like a sort of a thin region but he
can walk up and down in but instead of
having that especially I think what I'm
gonna do is just say that our stairwells
will have their collision area specified
to be narrow like that or something
similar to that where it's basically
like the stairwells this wide but the
air you can walk down so actually only
that wide and we'll try to deal with it
in in that way perhaps the other thing
we could do is say once you overlap it
we kind of suck you into it I don't know
we have to think about how we want to
deal with that and and that's kind of
more gonna be about player movement
handling and stuff like that but for now
I'm just gonna say that we'll just do
this test uniformly and we'll kind of
work up towards how we're gonna deal
with that more friendly wise when we get
there so I'm going to check to see if
the entities intersect assuming they do
intersect then I'm going to kind of
record the fact that this is one of them
and I don't know how I want to do this
exactly yet I think I want to sort of
say that we'll process some number of
overlapping nests but only a certain
number right meaning like I don't think
we want to say that we just kind of have
an unbounded number of overlapping
things that you can do that seems like
that would be problematic and costly so
I think I just want to keep it to sort
of a more I don't know a more limited
set if you will but assuming that they
intersect then this means that we've got
a new intersection and so I'll basically
say that we have you know an overlapping
account here like so and we'll also say
that we have you know overlapping and
please write and we'll just say that
like there's not you can't just have an
arbitrary number of those you know I
don't know that's way too many already I
don't even like that number I feel like
that's ridiculous but you know whatever
so what we'll do here is we'll we'll
basically say if the overlapping count
is less than overlapping entities
overlapping kennedys I just make it
through this the gameplay bug because I
don't think we can reliably write the
engine to handle an arbitrary number of
those it sounds just sounds bad let's
put it that way
I'll put got an invalid code path right
yeah I'll just say that's an invalid
code path there and so assuming that we
can add another one we'll basically just
say that overlapping entities with the
overlapping count plus plus is going to
be equal to whatever this entity was
that we just tested there now test
entity needs to get advanced in this
loop why where does test enemy get
advanced in this loop I don't understand
oh it's it's not actually done it's
grabbed out there I see so we actually
need me to that grab out as well there
we go so and so that'll tell us all the
things that we're overlapping initially
and then whenever we sort of collide
with something in particular if that was
one of the things that we were already
colliding with we want to remove that
from the set of things that need to get
processed because we're on top of them
if that makes sense so assuming that the
hit entity if the hit entity is
something that was in our our set right
in our overlapping entity set then
that's something that we want to do so I
guess I'll do that as a check again I'm
not sure exactly how I want to do this
we may have speed concerns here that we
want to address later but so I'm just
going to do the most straightforward
thing so assuming that we have a hit
entity then in the case where we are
leaving which means right like if I go
through all of my entities if if overlap
index or index is less than what I call
it overlapping camp yeah it's less than
overlapping count so on then I will
go ahead and remove it from there so if
hit entity equals overlap the entities
overlap index assuming that I find it in
that list then I need to remove it so
basically what I'll do is I'll just
again remove it from the end of that
list so if that's the case then whatever
the one is here equals whatever is at
the end essentially of my list so
something like this you think and this
of course has to do incrementing only
when I don't so basically I'll just go
through here I'll say is the thing that
I ran is the thing whose boundary I'm
crossing at this time one of the
overlapping entities if if it is then I
want to remove it for my list of
overlapping entities otherwise if it
turns out that it's not then I want to
actually add this to the list of
overlapping entities right so I want to
do is say you know removed is false in
this case removed equals true right like
so and you can break out of that as well
because once you remove it you don't
need to keep looking so if we do that
then we can also say at the end if we
didn't remove it then we need to add it
because that means we're entering into
it right like if we hit something
either it was something we're
overlapping and now it's not or you know
vice-versa so if we hit entity I suppose
stops on collision is really the only is
really the case where if we were
entering if we if we stop ourselves from
entering it yeah in fact now that I
think about it this is almost we could
almost use this to make our stuff a
little more logical because we don't
want to prevent you from leaving things
most of the time so actually we could
kind of think of this as
one step maybe towards doing more
reasonable collision stuff right instead
of doing it the way I was going to do it
where it's like a separate handle thing
we could just say here like okay when
you hit an entity let's first figure out
were you was that entity that you were
overlapping with in the first place
right so I could do that so let's let's
let's do that that seems that seems a
little bit better actually so in here we
could sort of say all right let's take
over overlap index or something like
this right and we'll do a test we'll run
through the things that are in our
overlapping our set of overlapping
entities and if we find it in there we
will set our I don't know why that's set
to false that's no good we will set our
overlap index equal to the one that we
found and then we'll break so now we
know definitively whether or not we
overlapped because overlap index will
either be equal to overlap and count or
it will be equal to the entity that we
were overlapping with so then when we
come through here we can look we can we
now know whether we're supposed to stop
when we hit this entity whether we can
go into it or not
and so in the case where it does not
stop on collision then we just need to
do the toggle like we were doing it
before right either we add it or we
remove it depending on the circumstance
but in the case where we do stuff on
collision then what we could sort of do
is say don't stop you from leaving
something you weren't supposed to be
ever in right I don't know if that makes
sense so basically we kind of need sort
of yeah and we might even pass this in
here that that might be interesting so
we'll basically say we've got a bull
which says was over laughing right and
that's like overlap index not equal to
overlapping count like so and so then
when we come in here we could also say
what do we actually want to do do we
want to add the thing do we want to
remove the thing and so I'll do add to
overlapping equals false and
to remove from over laughing it was
false
again just writing this out as
explicitly as I can think and we can
worry about collapsing it down to better
code later so anyway if we're supposed
to stop on collision then what I might
say is let's let's if we're supposed to
stop on collision then the state doesn't
change I guess it's the way I would say
it right if we're supposed to stop the
player the state doesn't change so we
probably should do is pass was
overlapping in just to handle collision
it will then decide do you want to stop
the player from crossing this boundary
now knowing whether you were leaving it
or entering it right and that seems good
right that seems like a good thing I
don't actually know did I accidentally
oh no so candle collision will will
actually now also be able to do yes so
that's perfect
I like this I like this already it's
it's a little jakey I think we got a
ways to go but I like this already we
passing to handle collision whether it
was overlapping it can now take the
appropriate action because it knows
whether it was entering or exiting the
thing which is a nice additional piece
of information right then we can say
okay did you want us to stop it or not
if you wanted us to stop it then it does
not change right then then it didn't
enter or exit because we stopped so
we're not supposed to go in or out but
on the other hand if we're not supposed
to stop on collision then what we can do
is say all right let's go ahead and
let's go ahead and and start tracking
that guy either we remove him or we or
we or we add him so if he was
overlapping me after remove him if he
wasn't overlapping we have to add him so
if he was overlapping again that's the
really simple case that I just said
which is we're going to take wherever he
was and we just need to move whatever's
at the end of the array into that
position right so that's just going to
be that overlapping count like
said- - right so what that's doing is
basically saying wherever the guy that
we restoring was let's just get rid of
him by taking whatever was at the end of
the array which is obviously the count
minus one and stuffing that into where
he is this is exactly the same code that
we wrote code the one line of code but
it's the same exact thing we did right
here
right just remember this guy where we
basically just want it's it's how you
take an array and you remove an item
from in the middle of it you just copy
the last thing into its slot it's very
very simple right so there you go that's
that's what that is and that's what this
is and it decrements the count by one so
that you know that those no less in
there now on the other hand if we're in
this circumstance we want to go ahead
and do this exact thing that we did
before we want to do an invalid code
bath in the case that we can't fit it
but otherwise we say assuming that
overlapping entities can fit it we will
go ahead and add it right overlapping
count plus plus equals that at that new
entity whatever that hit entity was you
know so that's pretty good and then our
handle collision just has to now take a
bill 32 was overlapping and now it knows
whether it's something's going into or
coming out of something and that's you
know that's what we want to know so now
we can sort of start to construct some
more interesting things that happen in
collision this is probably some code
that we should start to think about a
little bit more specifically and how we
want to write it more cleanly as well we
haven't talked about that too much again
but assuming that assuming that we want
to start start
using this a little bit more I feel like
this would be a good example of how we
could do the sort of collision for
example without actually needing to do
week we could we could basically get rid
of some of that code that we're doing
with add collision rule we could
implement the sword this way as well we
would have a problem with if we had
floating-point precision things were you
know we might get problems but we could
start implementing the sword thing now
that we have exit and entrance we would
not need to add those collision rules
anymore because they'd be handled just
inside this logic right here so let's
let's go ahead and take a look at this
let me just go ahead and finish this
stuff out so when we do that rectangle
Center diameter test right I've said
when we do that construction it's not
actually a five-minute warning it's the
20 minute warning because remember I
said we'd go we'd go for an hour and we
started 15 minutes late so we've got
some extra we've got some extra the time
to play with here so we've got rec
centre dim and rec center dim is exactly
I guess the thing we want I don't know
if rec center dim is the best name for
it cuz diameters a little bit better but
you know we'll we'll stick with it for
now so we'll do that and that's actually
exactly the thing that I wanted so that
creates that rec center dim so on and
the rectangles are sucked call we have
never actually written we were doing it
before by just doing the Minkowski sum
and we could do it exactly that way
again here now what's the problem test
entity ref that isn't that what we want
you want to store the test entity not
it's rectangle so the rectangles
intersect call we could choose to do
this by using the entity overlaps
rectangle version of this right and in
fact we could call that directly but
instead what I'm going to do is just
break that out into a rectangle overlap
function angles overlap or sorry inter
intersect so and then we'll just sort of
do do it that way so we've got a
rectangle three
so this isn't I shouldn't - that this is
not exactly the same right in fact in
fact this is not correct now that I
think about it is it no I guess it is
because it checks the ingrown point P so
it's fine no that's correct
never mind I lied I was I was at the I
was in the moment I was like wait a
minute that's not quite right but then I
realize it is cuz it checks for is a
rectangle P sorry I just got I got
nervous there for a second
wasn't necessary so we've got two
rectangles and we want to test to see if
they overlap right and I could reduce it
down to this but it might be interesting
to just go ahead and write it in a
different way just for fun just to see a
different way to do it so how would we
know right if our rectangles intersected
you know how would we figure that out so
if we had two rectangles and we just
wanted to do some checks to see if they
did or if they didn't right so I've got
my two rectangles here and I want to
know if they intersect so what you can
actually do to figure this out is you
can actually think about it strictly in
terms of one axis at a time and it will
actually tell you the answer because
since we know that in order for
rectangles to intersect they must have
to have at least one point in common
right so they must have one point
somewhere at least one that they share
if they don't have one point that they
share then there's no way they could
intersect because they share no common
points so one easy way to think about
that problem is if I have one point in
common then
these rectangles must overlap in all
three of their dimensions because their
axis aligned right and so if any of the
dimensions has a gap in it right if
which it does in this case right here
right if any of the dimensions has a gap
in it then I know that it could not have
intersected but if none of them have
have a gap then because their access a
line because you know they're strictly
existing on the on the XY and z axes
they're totally authoring with each
other
there's no way that they could possibly
they could possibly not intersect they
have to at that point that's not true if
these things rotate right like if you
imagine these things being rotated you
could have something that that projected
onto all three axes such that it looked
like it was overlapping but it never
actually did because the plane along
which they don't overlap is actually you
know that that's separating act plane if
you will kind of passes diagonally
through things so it is true that that
that trick doesn't actually work in the
case where you've got rotation but in
the case where both things are have the
same rotation in this case they do it
doesn't actually matter if it's axes
like just as long as the axes were
measuring are the same on each of the
guys we can trivially do that so really
all we have to end up doing is checking
to see if in each axis they overlap at
all and that's actually relatively
straightforward to do because in any one
axis right let's just take this axis
here for example we have you know a min
and a max and a min and a max right for
a and for B and so all we need to do is
go well all right I know that the
minimum so for a right the minimum for a
if the maximum for B was below it then
it would not be touching right it'd be
somewhere over here right so if the
maximum for B is is on the other side of
the minimum then I know that the min
obviously nothing inside it could be
touching right so I'm basically checking
the the min of a versus the max of be
there right similarly if the min for B
is on the other side of the max of a
then they couldn't be touching in any
other case they are touching right if
the min isn't is
not going to be you know if the min is
not greater than the max and that means
that this interval for B is somewhere
behind the max which means that the only
way they couldn't overlap is if the max
for B goes below the min for a which was
the other check and the same is true in
Reverse so you can imagine sliding this
right you can imagine saying I've got my
a here's the min and the max you could
imagine sliding this right here this B
you can imagine sliding it sort of down
right and as you slide it down you can
think of projecting it up on to here and
see where it can go and all the times
when it's intersecting you know that
that minimum bound of B must not be past
the max and you know similarly you
haven't slid it far enough to slide it
past the min of a right to slide the max
past the min of a and so that's really
the only check that we need to do on an
axis right so if you imagine writing
this all we really need to say to find
the result for a given axis we would
just need to say okay we've got a min
and we've got a max so what we want to
do is say like I said before in our
diagram so I got to grab that Mouse
again in our diagram we wanted to say if
B's max is less than a x' min right so
if if these max is less than s min and
B's min you know I should say or right
so so if see if I got this right
B's max is less than s min so B's max is
less than as men and B's min is greater
than or B's min is greater than as Max
so B's min is greater than nice max then
it's not going to do it right so that
would be right that would be a
determination right there now we could
also multiply that through we could we
could do you know the binary logic
therap to change these around but it's
really not much point in doing so that
pretty much tells us what we would need
to do for any individual axis so if we
wanted to do you know dot X we just do
that X and there's a check for the
x-axis right assuming that I didn't mess
something up so similarly we can check
all the rest of the axes and they just
all kind of compound in there right we
can just keep on checking our Y's and
our Z's and say okay if any of those if
any of those at all happen to to fall on
either side of the boundary like we're
checking then we know that the whole
thing can't intersect so you know we're
done in that case so all of them are
essentially ORS and we want we can say
that any of them is sufficient for
telling that the rectangles don't
actually intersect so that's pretty much
all we need to do I'm going to move that
over to our math library though because
that's that's more of a math library
thing right and that should should
basically do it barring some kind of
error in in how I've constructed it
there that's really all we need to do
oops didn't mean to put an X there fix
that and what was the actual I don't
actually even remember what our I don't
actually even remember what our what our
rectangle structure things are called oh
it's just capitalized capitalization
very important okay so that's about it
and now we just have to think a little
bit more about our collision detection
stuff I didn't realize the game was
still running I guess that it is so now
inside our closure detector we in theory
are keeping track of those things so we
could pass through something if we
wanted to and not have to use a
collision rule to do it so let's see if
we can do that for our stairwell let's
just go in here and change that code in
hand-made sim region move entity so what
I'd like to do is say while we're
actually I guess we don't need to that
it's it's actually an should collide so
in should collide
and or and handle collision so what we
want to do here is say when we handle a
collision between the stairwell and the
guy right and we're sort of saying if if
the a type equals a hero and the B type
equals the stairwell then what we're
going to do is say that stops on
collision is false you do not have stop
on collision you can go ahead through
now the collision rule stuff we don't
have really enough here to to deal with
that I wonder if this add collision rule
stuff should actually yeah I feel like
that should really be happening sort of
up one level right I feel like that
should be something it's kind of at the
wrong place
I feel like inside our handle collision
is the place to do that
because the only time we really wanted
to do that was for our sword right we
wanted that to happen here and so really
this was the place for that kind of that
seems better so I'm going to do that
here for now and again we kind of want
to start to work with this code and make
it a little cleaner anyway so we'll just
start with that and we'll see where that
takes us okay so our sword still works
presumably it does look like it does
let's just make sure cuz that's the
other thing that was using the system
that looks fine and now let's see if we
can pass through our stairwell no so
let's double check and see why that is
not working because that is what we want
to to get working so let's take a look
at handle collision I'll go ahead and
stop in here let's see there we go so we
have we have hit and let's take a look
at what our a type and our B type is so
a type B type oh you know what I think I
already know what this is actually now
that
think about it this is just the problem
that we're still actually going to then
reprocess the collision inside our
collision iterations because our should
collide doesn't check against that
temporary list right which we needed to
do we needed to act just like the other
one so really we want that that list to
to check in here which I wonder if that
argues for us just actually using the
collision rules locally now that I think
about it right
we could just have our add collision
rules it adds them and removes the
collision rules as like something that
it does inside so it doesn't have to
keep a separate list right because
should collide is already checking that
hash table right it's already doing this
hash bucket thing we could just use that
instead of the little separate stack and
then remove them at the end so we add
and then remove that is kind of
appealing I don't know why and think of
that in the first place because there's
no reason we can't just do it that way
that actually sounds pretty good yeah
doesn't that sound good to you that
sounds pretty good to me
yeah I like that better I like that
better than what my first instinct was
which was having the separate
overlapping thing so I think what we
actually do here is instead of doing
this we just had a collision rule right
so check this out this is this is this
is how I think we should roll let's go
into and made whatever we want to call
it handmade handmade just in here
pushing rules yeah so let's go in here
and take a look at this we've got our
collision rule hash what we could do is
just add them in there and when we add
it so when we do add collision rule when
we add it we'll just return essentially
our our hash bucket if you or our hash
entry will add it so that it can be
removed right we can just sort of say
all right you know we'll we'll pull that
back out what's the best way for us to
to record that I guess it's I guess we
don't really even need to we can just
yeah this is this is this is really
simple trying to think if there's any
downside to this there's a slight
downside I guess which is we're using
the centralized hash function instead of
a little localized table which maybe
isn't such a great idea
it's really tough mmm I don't know I
think let's let's go ahead and let's go
ahead and do it let's go ahead and do it
so what we want to do here is say
alright we're gonna when we do add
collision rule we're gonna return a
boolean and the boolean is whether or
not we added it right whether or not it
was already there so we're gonna do
added equals false and then when we come
in here we're gonna do added equals true
in the case where it wasn't found right
that's what we're going to do and then
we're going to return at it like so and
so what I want to do with that is
basically say okay every time through
when we do this every time through I
want to
basically say that we're gonna add a
collision rule and I'm gonna record the
fact that I added that collision rule if
I it was new so if there wasn't already
collision rule in there for this guy so
we're gonna do add collision rule like
so on and we're gonna pass those those
indices so here's the Kennedy right
storage index storage index and the test
entity storage index we're gonna go
ahead and add that collision rule and
we're gonna say that this should not
collide because we're you know we're
penetrating it already so let's do that
so then assuming that this that the
collision rule stuff actually I guess we
do that in here so assuming that the
collision rule actually is new I'm going
to record it and we'll just track it
right track it is something that we need
to remember to remove like so on and
again I don't actually know if we need
to do that we could we could do this
even in a slightly different way where
we just do something a little more a
little more clever I don't know if I
want to do that or not but we'll do it
this way for now so we still do the same
tracking and then when we come back out
here we'll just remove those ones when
we're done right so at the end we we go
ahead and remove the coalition rule I
don't know we don't really want to clear
collision rules we want to just remove a
single one at a time so we basically
have removed collision rule right like
so on remove collision rule which is not
really clear yeah so we need to
implement that that hasn't been
implemented yet so we remove a collision
rule and and you know off the coast so
when we remove a collision rule we will
do that by doing and in fact we really
don't have to track these that accurate
cuz we could do a slightly different
scheme which maybe we should go with
something to basically restore in the
collision rule whether it's going to be
a temporary thing and then we
pull it out right and similarly we could
we could even do that using something
like this where we just actually search
the ones that might be even better god
there's so many options this all just
opened up for me it's too bad this is
right at the end of the stream let's put
it that way I'm gonna I'm gonna stop
because we're at 5:15 I'm gonna write
down what I want to do we're gonna do
this tomorrow cuz I think this is
basically does exactly what I want it to
do so I'm gonna go ahead and do this
here we're gonna take ad collision rule
let's see ad collision rule I think we
maybe don't even need to return that
then right I'm just gonna say that
probably what we'll do is we'll start
passing here a more than just a bool for
should collide will actually pass
transience like say say whether it's
supposed to be transient or not right so
what I'm thinking here and this as well
just make the notes for tomorrow what
I'm thinking here is if we kind of come
up here to our collision royal thing
what I want to do is change this to a
pair wise gudgeon rule flag and that
flag will tell us like collision flag
pair collision flag or something like
that that that flag will tell us two
things it'll say whether or not this is
the thing that should collide like
whether or not we're overriding that
right and then the other thing it will
do is it will tell us whether it was
temporary right like that and so then we
can pass these flags here like so and
have those stored instead of should
collide right that's what we'll do
now I won't do that quite yet because
we'll need the code compiling oops a
mistake
so that actually will allow us to make
it so that we just add the temporary one
and then we just clear out the
temporaries when we're done with the
movement and then everything just goes
to do the same table we can have
permanent things in there as well as
transient things in there and that
it's pretty compelling to me so I'm
gonna go ahead and make that be that to
do for tomorrow that I really like that
we'll see that maybe it won't work out
but I feel like I really like that
so actually what we're gonna do here is
we're moving this up because we've kind
of got that
so we'll basically say transient
collision rules we are based on flag
right and allow non transient rules to
override transient ones I think this is
gonna be good all right all right so
that's about it for that I am pretty
psyched about that that was not
something I thought about when I came
into this but I think that is good it's
pretty cool
basically what I'm thinking is will sort
of make it so that when we're doing our
movement inside the movement we can just
put those collision rules in transiently
then when we're done we remove them and
that way whatever stuff we wanted that
doesn't necessarily have to last can all
just sort of be cleaned up automatically
in there and that gets rid of the
lifetime management problem that I was
worried about for pairwise collision
rules because remember the problem that
I was saying we were gonna have before
was for these pairwise collision rules
well if you go into something and we add
a rule that says that's okay you can
move around in it we never know when to
get rid of that right for those of you
that like garbage collection this is
like the garbage collectors worst
nightmare right it's a thing that we the
rule comes into existence and then we
never know when to get rid of we don't
know when we're done right and so that
was a problem in it was gonna keep us
from using pairwise collision rules for
everything so I kind of implemented them
just for stuff like the sword but with
this because we can just can't we can
what would I and so again what I was
thinking with entry/exit right was oh
well we'll just implement a more
standard entry/exit scheme where you
just when you go into something you go
out of something those are lucky
notifications we can act on or something
and that's how we'll do like stepping on
triggers and stuff we can actually unify
these two schemes bring them together by
saying okay the pairwise digital rules
can just be transient and will
them up at the end of the move that way
there's no lifetime and we'll recreate
them at the start by checking for
overlapping right so now we don't have
that lifetime problem and we can push
everything in the same system we don't
care whether they're things that should
live for a long time or things are doing
for a brief time so we don't have to
worry about that lifetime management
problem that we had before where we
don't ever know we can't tell the system
yes it's ok to forget about this rule we
wouldn't know now we know so that's
really nice I really like that I think
we can build on this so I'm excited
about that that's definitely we're gonna
do tomorrow all right so let's go ahead
and and do it let's go ahead and do it
go to the QA we've still got about 11
minutes left you might as well do some
QA
in the meantime I'm very happy about
that that was a good discovery
accidental discovery so that's what
we're going to do yes I like it I like
it I like it
okay let's go to the QA does anyone have
any questions if you could please prefix
time with Q :
that'll help I can see them I have a
little filter that looks for things that
you : so I don't have to look at the
chat and try to mine questions out I'd
like him to see them come out so if
anyone has questions please prefix time
with Q : and type them in and I will
answer them but if you could please keep
them to coding questions stuff we've
done on the stream you know so that we
can kind of keep it on topic and then we
can always do off-topic questions at the
King industry we did a bunch of them
today we do a bunch from tomorrow too
no questions it's question free
apparently everyone totally was down
with everything well that seems good
certainly we can all go home early
anyone anyone no why did you decide to
code at like four actually it was
because of a reschedule had to happen
family emergency wise death and the
family is the short answer
long answer is more complicated but I
had to move the stream
glad to see the AABB collision detection
code come up took me way too long to
figure that one out yeah I didn't
explain it super well I I think like
most of my collision stuff was gjk
oriented so I don't think about overlap
test that well the way to think about
overlap testing is is usually in terms
of the separating oops parading rating I
don't know having a Facebook spelling
moment they're separating axis theorem
which is usually to say that for any two
shapes it doesn't matter what they are
if they overlap then I'm sorry if they
do not overlap you will be able to find
some axis along which they are separated
right and basically you can think of a
separating plane and the access is like
you know normal to that plane or
whatever right and so a lot of times
what you're trying to do when you're
doing quick overlap tests like the ABB
one is you're trying to figure out what
are the possible axes what are the
possible right axes that you could test
and so for arbitrary shapes it's
somewhat complicated because you have to
think about what all of the possible
planes that could separate the two
objects would be right and that's a more
complicated thing there are proofs that
say that you know for comics objects it
has to be a combination of elements on
the abused and bla bla bla bla bla
there's like things that can help you
but in general it's complicated right
for axis aligned bounding boxes the nice
part about it is things that are so
straight forward is that they it's it's
basically a convex object with a known
alignment where the actual shape of the
object lines up with the axis system you
have this nice pasta sort of thing that
happens where the possible
separating axes are the actual axes of
the coordinate system right it's x y and
z are the three possible separating axes
so you only have to look to see that all
three of them are SEP that that you have
to look to three to see that none of
those three are separated and then you
know you have an intersection but it's
harder when you go up to other kinds of
shapes like I said usually I end up
going gjk for arbitrary stuff just
because that's what I'm familiar with
and so my experience with these kinds of
algorithms is much more limited I am NOT
a very good separating access guy but
there are people who do a lot more work
with those because you knows you can
come up with fast separating access
theorems they help you make ways of you
know figure out ways to do you know
simple kind of tests for things
sometimes a really good example would be
if you had two spheres right because
spheres are equidistant in all
directions from their center point right
then what you know is if you connect
those two Center points you know that if
anything was ever going to separate them
it would have to be a plane
perpendicular to that right because that
is the closest a point of approach for
those spheres always and so you know
that if those were touching if those
were not touching then no other point
could be touching right
and so sphere separating access is
really nice it's just whatever the the
axis is that that runs between the two
sphere centers and that's really handy
but for arbitration it's much more
complicated X line bounding boxes
spheres very good right skiers are
actually easier than axel I'm bounding
boxes in some sense conceptually because
you only have to check one axis although
it may not work out that the
calculations are easier because you do
have to do that subtraction and other
things like that but you get the idea
you mentioned yesterday about choosing
between two ways to solve the problem of
large entities that overlap the same
region but are not in the selected
chunks it looked to me like you could
use both solutions if the entity is
larger than the max entity size still
allow it and use the add it twice
approach would this get you all the
advantages of both with neither of the
disadvantages um I guess what I would
say is that does sound like a very good
idea to me
I like that the thing I don't love is
just the concept of doing the double ad
I wanted to stay away from that if
possible but I do like the idea of when
we get down to it maybe we find that
that we want to do things more
efficiently that does sound pretty good
I like that approach let's let's make a
note of that in the collision system
because yeah that is a pretty good idea
there's no reason we know for any given
entity we would know that as long as we
formalize the notion of when its bounds
can be set we would know at all times
wet which one of those two it would be
so I do like that's a very good idea
good thinking let's say perhaps try
using a dual system here where we
support entities larger than the max
empty radius by adding them multiple
times to the spatial partition yeah
that's a good idea
would it make sense to just put a wall
of 1/3 the length on each side of the
stairwell to handle the collision um we
could certainly do that I think that
because we have to do all the work of
handling walking down the stairs I think
it'll probably end up being free at the
end of that to prevent motion outside of
it but that would be a totally
reasonable solution but because we have
to do that thing where we walk down I
think we're gonna already know where we
are
along the stairwell and so I think we'll
be able to kind of just do it but yeah
if it turned out to be really
problematic for some reason we could do
we could do the wall method is that you
do this in the platform layer a more or
less comprehensive list of change do you
do before shipping or there's some
additional things one should note I'm
not sure I don't know that it's
exhaustive it had most of the things I
thought of at the time but it might not
be exhaustive it there may be other
things
yesterday you mentioned that when
jumping up to a chunk above the
character would jump over the ground
level z equals zero and then come down
however since the jump go is making the
Z position go to zero if negative
wouldn't the character be pushed up to
zero as soon as it reached the low side
of the upper chunk and won't this cause
problems when trying to move the
character up the stairs yeah I mean it
it presumably will do that that's a
that's a correct way to think about it
we need to get rid of that code entirely
because it's not correct even for
jumping right so what we need to do is
we need to do something that actually
looks to see what we are actually doing
a Z motion wise and that's why we have
this to do that's why we're doing what
we're doing now is because we have to go
through and kind of actually handle how
we want to do that kind of motion now
for jumping we don't have to care
because we don't really actually allow
jumping right but for the stairwells we
need to do this properly either way and
so we'll be actually writing some code
that actually thinks about the Z
logically it doesn't compare to the
arbitrary value of zero which means
nothing really if that makes sense
all of these algorithms all specify
convex shapes
is there anything usable for concave
shapes or is it usually always the case
that it's better to just split up a
concave shape into multiple convex
shapes I don't want to say that there's
nothing usable for concave shapes but I
will say that I don't know any
algorithms that are usable for concave
shapes so they might exist some out
there I just don't know what they are
I've certainly never written one on the
whole everyone I've ever seen do
collision detection always does it by
first breaking things up into concave
pieces because you can take any I'm
sorry convex pieces you can always take
a concave shape and break it up into
convex shapes so you can always produce
the convex problem from the concave
problem and everyone I've ever seen
solve collision protection always does
that step they always take their concave
shapes break them into convex shapes and
then run them that way
about the to-do lists you mentioned a
while back that you want to code some
sort of zooming out that would let you
see entities outside the sim region yes
and I may want to do zooming out just in
general the promise our renderer doesn't
really handle it yet so I'm hoping we
can kind of do that once the renderer
has scaling in it but we'll see an
episode on metaprogramming please you
seem to ignore it I'm not going to teach
meta programming down the stream it's
it's too far outside what we're doing so
we're sticking with regular programming
after what the end of handmade hero if
everyone totally is down at that point
with everything we've done maybe we can
think about starting on meta programming
at that point but but we're not gonna do
meta programming until we've got
programming down so yeah I could throw
that in here
for multiple sim regions where is our
multiple sim region stuff zoomed simple
zoom mount simple zoomed out view for
testing there yeah alright so we're out
of time you're out of time we go ahead
and save our blackboard I'm gonna go
ahead and close this down and conclude
the screen thank you everyone for
joining me for another episode of hand
made here it's been a pleasure coding
with you as always
in the especially a pleasure today
because we figured out something that I
haven't been thinking about that seems
like a pretty cool thing that we can
pursue so I'm gonna be working on that
tomorrow tomorrow will be at our
regularly scheduled time I believe it
should be 8 p.m. stick Standard Time
tomorrow as originally scheduled it will
not be one that we have to move like we
did today apologize for that so yeah if
you come back tomorrow 8 p.m. Pacific
Standard Time we will take a look at
that collision real stuff now that we
kind of had a good idea about it and see
what we can do that's that's cool in
there I think we'll be able to do some
cool stuff so I'm looking forward to
that I think that'll be pretty awesome
if you want to follow along at home at
the source code you can always do so by
pre-ordering the game on handmade here
org if you preorder the game you can get
a link that allows you download source
code all the time and follow along at
home which is kind of cool it also comes
with the test assets you see us using on
the stream so you can
you know play around with it and it
looks exactly like what I'm working with
we also have a patreon if you want
support the video series you can
subscribe to that it's very much
appreciated we also have a tweet bot
that tweets the schedule so if you want
to know when the things are or you want
to be notified of last-minute changes
like what happened today the tweet bot
is is the place to go it always tweets
the most accurate version of the
schedule in so much as we can make it do
so and so that's a good place for that
also we have a news and forum site which
is pretty cool it has a bunch of
resources on there people have ported
the thing to Mac &amp; Linux so if you want
to follow on another platform there's
also Android and iOS ports up there NAT
- I think there's a coding forum you can
ask questions on I answer questions over
there as do other people and there's
also a great episode guide made by the
community which says like notes on the
episodes and things like that as people
work through them so we've got all kinds
of great stuff on there I highly
recommend you check it out if you're
trying to learn for the stream it's a
really great resource thanks everyone
for joining me I hope to see you again
here tomorrow have a fabulous Thursday
if I don't or if I do just have a
fabulous Thursday I'll tell you see you
guys later