hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show recoat a complete game
live on stream we are going to be doing
some work with lighting today we kind of
got to a place where the lighting
bounces were actually working pretty
well last time but I think today what we
probably want to start looking at a
little more seriously because I think
it's probably our biggest problem at the
moment is how we're going to correctly
deal with the reconstruction of the
lighting from the samples that we have
because that's actually something that
right now we don't have a very good
handle on furthermore I think the other
thing that we bob would probably want to
do and we might do this first because
it's a little more straightforward is
now that we pretty much know how we want
things to work we might want to do
something where our render system allows
you to send down two things one
occluders that are blocking light and we
could send those down separately so we
can basically say like okay not
everything like for example sprites are
not occluders cubes are occluders
sprites will have a separate thing sent
down with them let's say which says what
the shape of the occluder is or how the
occluder works so that we won't Jimmy so
we won't actually have to worry about
that stuff like the incredibly weird
bent
you know sprites for so things that
still face the camera are drawn properly
so that those themselves aren't what's
blocking the light there's actually like
a little invisible cube or something in
there that is what's blocking the light
so that the shadowing can work more
correctly even though the drawing is not
done quite that way
so that's one thing the other thing that
we can choose to do there is think a
little bit about how we want to specify
the sampling area as well so for example
right now we always sample things based
entirely on the occluders themselves but
we don't have to do that right we can
choose our gather points separately from
exactly where our occluders happen to be
if we wanted to there's nothing really
stopping us from doing that so we kind
of have to do some thinking about how
that sort of thing wants to work and
there's a lot of different ways that we
can do it and so that's I think the next
thing that we have to experiment with in
order to converge towards a better
lighting solution because we sort of
have a good way to bounce light around
now and while we will refine that a
little bit in the future I think what's
holding us back at the moment is really
has more to do with specifying and
reconstructing their lighting samples
than it does with computing the actual
lighting which is something that I think
is not quite as it's not quite as
problematic at the moment so let me just
give you a little example of what I'm
talking about if I go ahead here and
load up our current state of the game so
here's that project file if I go ahead
and build the project file what you will
notice is that at the top of the
platform file we do have a thing which
just is like a hard-coded lighting
resolution and what we can do in the
future is this doesn't have to be
hard-coded we can easily just allocate
space for these dynamically so that you
could switch their resolution of the
lighting on the fly so we just have it
hard-coded for now because that's was
the easier thing to do at the time
there's nothing magic about it that
means it has to be hard-coded so that's
not really a concern but well you'll
notice is if I change it to large cells
so this is 8 8 by 8 by 8 voxel so the
cells
are twice as large in every dimension as
say the sixteen by sixteen when was
right so if I run the game with that as
the arrangement and I asked for a
lighting solution what you can see is
that the lighting solution actually
looks pretty reasonable and when I
switch back I actually get something
that's that's probably usable now
there's some things with it that still
probably should be improved so I'm not
trying to suggest that it's great or
anything but it's definitely a lighting
solution that you know could could be
could be considered usable already even
in its current state so you know because
remember these will all have bitmaps on
them eventually too so we're looking at
kind of pure lighting right now
whereas in the future it will be even
noisier because of the bitmap interface
that's on there so be less heart it will
be much harder for you to tell that
there are certain bugs in the lighting
interpolation or things like that right
okay
so looking at this that's actually not a
bad lighting solution like I'm actually
okay with that
and I wouldn't be like you know super
worried about this as my lighting
solution this is fine however if I am
now to change my lighting solution over
to sixteen by sixteen by sixteen
oops which is a more detailed lighting
solution so this is actually like a
better lighting solution if you will
right in a way it's basically keeping
more accurate track of where things were
sorting wise I mean it's not really more
accurate but it's like I should I put it
it's the vaak the voxels are now more
smaller so when you ask for what's in
one you only get stuff that's closer to
you than before right but what you see
is it starts to ruin the lighting right
and the reason is because you get too
many voxel samples and there's places in
the voxel where just we didn't take a
lighting sample at all and so the
interpolation starts to break down or
there's some bugs in it like we don't
really know but this would be this would
be perfectly explica ball by
I just said and that's bad because we
would like to be able to run the voxel
at a fairly reasonable discritization
level because the bigger the voxel the
the bigger the voxel region is the
slower our lighting runs if the voxels
are very large then each pixel when it
goes to fetch all of the lights it needs
to consider is going to be fetching way
more information that it has to sift
through and that is what will cost the
majority of our time right so we want to
be able to make these voxels actually
very small if we wanted to a 32 by 32 by
32 voxel oh we installed something for
this calculator thing didn't we speed
crunch people worth telling me to try
maybe I should try this program I will
paint it to the taskbar it was
recommended on stream so if I do 32
times 32 times 32 then that is the
number of cells in our voxel right if I
assume that each voxel is using
something on the order of a u16 right
then it's really only times 2 that
that's only 64 K right so you know we
can have a very detailed voxel here
right like even a voxel that was 64 by
64 by 64 is only gonna be half a
megabyte I mean we could go up probably
I don't even know how far we could go
here but we could go pretty far that is
only 32 megabytes right so you know we
could choose to have an extremely
detailed voxel here like so and not
really be using very much graphics card
memory compared to what you have today
and that would allow our lighting to be
like really fast right but the problem
is if we actually look at what will
occur when we see this result
you can see where the lighting samples
are taken now quite clearly right and
there's just not enough information in
each voxel area right so when it goes to
interpolate between them you know the
next voxel area is like right there
right and so the problem that we see now
that that we need to figure out a way to
start working away from is that voxel
queries aren't necessarily what we want
in all cases because while they're
really efficient at telling us what's
next to us they're not so efficient at
telling us what the closest things to us
are right because that's actually what
we want to know we want some let me go
ahead and pop over to Milton actually
just so I can describe this in a little
bit better detail yeah gonna grab the
drawing tablet here for a second just so
I can illustrate something so let's say
I go ahead and open up Milton here and
draw a little picture of this J 4 1 5 so
voxel interpolation of lighting that
handwriting some majesty of it so the
problem that we face here and I could
just do the 2d version because easier to
visualize but the 3d version just gets
worse because now you have one more
dimension in which the same thing is
true you can imagine what happens for
this problem we have some lighting like
so right each of these lighting
locations will have an actual valid
value of lighting at it and so if we are
to pick some point let's say here
question we are trying to ask of our
system is I would like to know what the
clothes sample points are so that I may
mix them together and produce a
reasonable lighting result for my
location right that's what I'm trying to
do so in the case where the voxel areas
are large let's say that this whole
thing is fixed in one voxel right then
this is no problem because not only I'm
gonna light by these voxels I'm also
gonna slowly blend to the lighting of
this next voxel over as I move in this
direction so as I move this point over
this way I'm gonna be including more and
more stamp weight from samples over here
so not really a big deal and we get some
reasonable results out of it right
however what we don't have is anything
that allows us to solve the situation
where it looks more like this let's say
the voxels are only that big now
well now hey I know really definitively
when I ask for what's nearby me I know
that nothing is immediately nearby me
but that's not really what I want to
know I wanted to know if I had to go get
a lighting sample where would I get it
from right I need lighting samples I
can't the answer there are no lighting
samples next to you while accurate is
not useful right I need to know about
these lighting samples and I need to get
enough of them so that I can actually do
some work right and so that's the
current problem that we face when
dealing with this voxel ization
situation is we're not really doing a
good enough job here of representing a
query that gives us back the lighting
samples that are nearby and it's fun
clear how to really do that this is a
classic reconstruction problem it would
be great if I was an expert in
reconstruction problems I'm not
so that does put us in a bit of a
disadvantage but whether or other
disadvantage or not we're gonna have to
solve it so thinking through in my head
some information about this what I'm
kind of thinking is you know if you had
a spatial query one thing you might want
to do is have this query be somewhat
adaptive based on the density of
lighting samples in a region right I
mean that's another way we could sort of
think about it a little bit better right
so let's say for example you were
putting in lighting samples into
something right you could imagine an
alternate style of system that basically
said well once I get too many lighting
samples in an area then like I split the
area right so once you know I get too
many I split it in half or something
right and then I keep adding them and
once I get too many of those I split
that in half right and I keep adding and
then I split that one in half or
something and then I keep adding right
and so on so if the lighting locations
were done on CPU side that doesn't seem
like a bad idea necessarily it's hard to
say but you could imagine doing
something like constructing a KD tree
where now you would basically say well
we break the world into buckets and the
buckets all have a reasonable number of
lighting samples so when you query your
location you will get a bucket back that
has like for lighting samples because
there are no buckets that don't have for
letting samples or more right and that
seems somewhat useful to solving the
first problem which is not enough
lighting samples in my region right so
we could imagine constructing a data
structure that was a little bit
different than a voxel although still
quite simple and it would have that
property to it right the problem with
that is
if we do want to do that construction of
the location of the letting samples on
the GPU that could be harder if we do it
on the CPU side it's not because the CPU
side has random access to memory can do
anything it really wants to doesn't
necessarily have to be parallelized
to be fast depending on how many of
these we're talking about so on so you
could see this being something that
maybe it's possible to do every frame or
every two frames you know we can update
our lighting sample points more slowly
if we have to for example so you know
you could see this being something that
that is plausible to do on the CPU side
and send down and then we could use
whatever structure you wanted because we
can always bake that structure into a
texture and then the GPU is the GPU is
just fine it using a data structure like
this it's just harder for it to build it
and you can't do it but usually you end
up with wanting to do things like use
CUDA or something or a computer you
typically don't want to be doing this
sort of thing in a non random access
fashion but it is done it's not
completely of question so that's one
thing I'm thinking of and like I said
the downside to it there is that with a
voxel you kind of have a nicer situation
of well with a voxel if you do want to
keep a linked list price per voxel like
we're doing now then you do need Atomics
in the shader so you do need to be able
to keep a linked list which requires a
shader atomic but that's really the only
thing you need right you don't actually
need any random writes or anything like
that you just need the ability to access
that one atomic so I guess what I would
say is you know there's there's that as
an approach I like the sound of that
approach because I think it offers a
couple different things first of all
allows us to get access to more points
initially with our first query so I like
that part and the other thing that I
like about that is I like this
that it will also subdivide regions
which are overpopulated even if they're
already pretty small so with our voxel
for example once we set a voxel
dimension if we started having lots of
sample points in one area now I don't
think that's likely but let's say we did
we could now with a system like this it
could get subdivided further so it puts
the detail where the detail is needed
rather than just presuming a sort of a
known thing up front so that's all good
stuff about it but I think there's bad
things about it too which means I'm not
really excited to jump at it quite yet
one is again the complexity of building
one of these while not too bad is much
more than a voxel it's still a big step
up from voxel in terms of the complexity
necessary to build one so that makes it
less likely to work on the GPU it makes
it more expensive even if it's on the
CPU probably right so that's one
downside is the expense of building the
other downside that's relative to
performance is the expense of
computation that's probably the wrong
way to say that let's say expensive
lookup so one nice thing about the voxel
is its immediate right I take a set of
coordinates I truncate those coordinates
to a voxel cell and now I I'm going I'm
off right that doesn't work anymore once
you have a variable space partition like
this one because at that point what you
have to do is Traverse from like a root
node down right you have to start at you
know the whole thing go where is my
point on this classifier oh it's on like
this side of it okay where is my point
on this classifier oh it's on this side
of it where is my point on this
classifier oh it's on this side of it
okay this is my region right
so each one of our pixel lookups now has
this much more expensive traversal
scheme involved right and that to me
sounds bad for obvious reasons so the
third thing is the boundary problem and
that is that while this would fix the
empty cell problem right voxels have the
empty sub-problem and they also have the
boundary problem it would fix the empty
cell problem but the boundary problem
remains
and what's that problem well in either
case if I am here and I see this sample
here's a lighting sample right
so here's some lighting samples ideally
what I would like to do right here is
I'd like to interpolate between here and
here possibly even a little bit of here
hard to say right but I don't really
have a way of doing that because in
order to look at the samples in here I
have to compute the lighting for my cell
and the cell next to me right and the
problem that we get there is then you
end up with the fall-off the
fall-off functions for reconstruction
now have problems where the voxel
boundary right causes them to snap in or
out of consideration because this one
here right would not be considered right
but this one would as it moves towards
this boundary you end up in a situation
where the consideration region falls out
of where this possibly would be and then
when you get into this region right
across the border maybe one of these
guys pops in it's you you end up in this
situation where you have to be really
careful about how you set up your
reconstruction because you can't have
things pop across voxel boundaries right
letting has to be continuous otherwise a
pixel right here at a pixel right here
will get two different results
completely different results and you'll
see a seam running along the voxel
boundary so what we're really trying to
avoid here is that problem of seams that
show up because of the spatial partition
and in order to get rid of those we need
something in either case because even if
we say that we pre divided everything
down right so that we always have you
know four samples for region or
something close to it then we know we're
never in a case where we're sampling a
region that's empty but we don't know if
for example we're sampling a region
where there was a lighting sample right
here that we should have been taking
into account and we're not taking into
account and when we move over here we
are starting to take it into account
right so the boundary problem kind of
remains luckily to a certain extent we
were doing interpolation between fixed
points in space in our voxel case and
that's how we got around that we would
just say well we always blend but you
know between the eight voxels that are
all in the area right but again even
that's kind of ugly because that means
we're doing eight times as much work for
only one reason and that is to prevent
that is to prevent that overlap that
that snapping problem those like seams
so the reconstruction problem is like
really hard for all of these reasons
right and you want to find something I
mean your ideal thing is something that
it's continuous everywhere
because that means no visible seams
has nice accuracy what uses samples well
and low overhead right
not too many samples considered and
there's some aspects this so continuous
everywhere no visible seams is kind of
the one we're talking about about how
you make sure that you know as your
because you're not considering all 8,000
samples every pixel how do you make sure
that the subset of samples that you
consider doesn't lead to seams that's
one problem we got to deal with the nice
accuracy when we haven't talked about
too much but you know let's say we've
got a place in the world where there is
a seam that's really supposed to be
there right so there's a lighting at a
corner or something like this right and
you know it's dark here it's light here
it's light here maybe right and dark
here or something we want to as much as
possible to try and reconstruct the fact
that you know if there's a bunch of dark
samples here and a bunch of light
samples here that the lighting should
change pretty rapidly in between those
two and we should have a dark side and
the light side right we really don't
want something where like the light side
bleeds way over here or the dark side
pleads way over here or whatever right
so if we do a good job placing our
initial samples in the world to capture
the lighting features we care about
which we probably can do because we know
what the scene looks like so we can
probably place samples fairly
intelligently we want those samples then
to to make sense when you use when you
reconstruct them we want them to you
know to produce good results based on
the information that was presented right
so yeah so one thing that I am thinking
about is well is I wonder if we need to
I wonder if we need to think about this
problem in a slightly different fashion
too
so one way of looking at this problem is
that we have an unordered set of samples
and we're trying to reconstruct from
those samples right but another way to
look at this problem would be that we're
actually just gonna take lighting
samples and we're gonna use those
lighting samples directly right that is
one way we could look at this problem
and it might be that we have so few
lighting samples that we actually care
about that that would work and I
realized that what I'm saying is a
little bit strange at the moment so let
me explain but what I what I mean is
well we're looking at this problem like
I've got a cube and so when I send this
down I know that I'm going to produce
like some occluders or whatever right or
something like this yeah
and then I do some stuff and then I draw
this polygon and I go sample and I look
to see where I've got my various
lighting samples right and this is what
leads to the reconstruction problem
because I need to look out into the
world and find what samples are relevant
to where I am now this has a nice
benefit of if we were to have lots of
things in this area they could possibly
pull from lots of lighting
however we could alternately say we
don't want to bother with that instead
what we'll do is we'll just say that a
cube gets some lighting samples on it
and it just uses exactly those letting
samples to interpolate period right like
it doesn't do anything else so when you
are actually drawing one of these you
just always have each quad that you draw
let's say just has its lighting samples
prescribed and it just uses those 4
lighting samples end of story right so
we could do something like that
where we basically say these are our
letting samples and we pre say which
levy samples you're interpreting between
there's no voxel involved those lighting
samples the occluders and the lighting
samples all go into letting solution but
the results of the lighting samples are
only sampled by the people who actually
wanted those light examples specifically
and there's a one-to-one correspondence
between the two no spatial partition at
all right
so looking here this is our scene broken
down in this way kind of already you can
kind of see if we looked at this right
if we were just to say look forget it we
don't want to do the reconstruction
problem we're not going to bother with
that
no more voxel it's just a waste of our
time this is the chunking of the scene
that we'll use and we'll just render it
on these borders right now we can even
go one step further and say it doesn't
have to be regular because one of the
things that will run into problems with
with any regular sampling scheme is you
will see the sampling scheme right but
we could say no forget it
we don't even want to do that we want to
be saucy ER gentlemen we're gonna be
even saucy er right what we want to do
instead is say look here's a plate and
here's where we put the lighting samples
so they're just gonna still do the splat
right with some radial interpolation so
it's really hard for you to see where
the seam is because it's not this
regular thing where you can see the seam
is like running look right like that
because we can still do a thing where
instead of the plate being instead of
tying it to the vertices we can instead
just tie it to points and when you draw
this surface sample these eight sample
points or whatever right and as I'm
seeing this out loud I've never
considered something like this before
it just sounds like a really good idea
now maybe that's famous less words but
this to me seems a lot more sane because
the reconstruction problem goes away
right because now you could reconstruct
your points however you want because
you're always using the same points on
this surface
so this flat because everything in our
game is a flat surface with a bitmap
mapped on it right
so everything across that entire surface
will be lit by the same end sample
points so any arbitrary scan
reconstruction scheme you use will be
continuous as long as the actual
addition is not itself discontinuous
which is really easy to avoid there are
no sampling boundaries because that
shape never never crosses any boundary
right - it's faster because now you
don't have to look up in voxels or
anything else you just every polygon
comes down with an ID it looks up that
ID and that gets it the linked list of
samples to use right and it just goes
through them so it's the same scheme we
have now but instead of first looking
into a voxel to find that first u16
forget that lookup just pass down the
u16 that you wanted to use directly prob
right
I mean I think that may just that may be
the winner because then all we really
have to do is come up with a good way of
scattering points across our geometries
right of where we want to take those
lighting samples and then we're pretty
much done we don't have to create a
spatial hierarchy or transmit it all we
have to do is pre scatter those points
and make sure that then the GPU has that
array of points and I think that's it we
still have the trouble of we have to
move the ray tracer over to the GPU at
some point but we knew we were gonna
have to do that regardless because
that's how we're generating our lighting
solution so I think this may be the
thing I want to try I can't think of a
lot of reasons not to so I think I'm
gonna do that
that seems like the best approach all
right this thing is kind of fun well
anyway it's not as artificially as
intelligent to some calculators maybe
but I mean it's no WolframAlpha anyway
so if we were going to do that then we
wouldn't need this voxel here at all
right I'll leave it in place in case we
decide we need it later
I won't delete it till we're sure this
is working the way we want but yeah so
everything else can stay the same the C
and D values we can leave because we do
still want a light lookup table that is
a linked list so that part should remain
roughly the same what we do need to
change is when we're actually sending
these down we've got these textured
vertices here those are going to go into
this push buffer and all that and so
we've got these quad bitmaps texture
vertex array situation right and what
this is is this is just a big array of
that says what bitmap to use and what
the vertices are so there's four
vertices four bitmap and so on right so
what we want to do here is we want to
augment this structure right now what we
pass the GPU is just this textured
vertex this big textured vertex array
what we want to do in addition to that
now is we're gonna want to pass a u16
which is like a lighting sample index
right
something like this so it's basically
every quad will have a light sample that
gets handed down with it and that light
sample is you know the thing that it
needs to work with right and to be
honest I'm not 100% sure I think somehow
I've never done something which gets
streamed into the pixel shader that way
so it may be an interesting it may be
kind of an interesting thing to see how
we do that because I don't think I've
ever tried it before it should work but
setting up an array that's per primitive
is not the same as setting up an array
that's per vertex most things are done
per vertex and so I don't really
remember or know I think you have to set
something up with the with the strides
to make it work properly it's it's gonna
be odd right but what I mean to say is
so in here when we're sending down
primitives right we've got stuff like
here where we've got these in vert PE
vert and vert UV vert color right those
are all inputs to the vertex shader that
happened one per vertex and are
transformed what we want to do here is
we want to have ins like down here in
the fragment shader but we want them to
be per primitive right so every triangle
actually every quad but OpenGL doesn't
really deal with quads every triangle
wants to have au 16 input that doesn't
vary over the face of the triangle and
that only came from one point in the in
an array now we can choose this if we
needed to
by just replicating the U 16 multiple
times right we could just write the U 16
three times or four times like one per
vertex right in other words up here in
this textured vertex thing we could just
have like a u 16 that was in here or
something like this and that would say
like here's the light value to get or
whatever right and we would just
replicate it or just use the first one
but at the moment that doesn't seem like
a particularly good idea I don't know
maybe maybe it would be good for now in
fact maybe maybe that's the easier way
to do it for now instead of moving it
out to a separate thing because since
we're just doing this for testing yeah I
mean you know I could see that being
good idea so maybe I'll do that for now
so right now we've got textured vertex
Commission color P and UV right and what
we would be doing here is saying well
we're gonna add something to the end of
this and at the moment there's what like
10 floats in this thing or something
like this 10 32-bit values right that's
9 right there 10 it's actually is it 11
is that right
so here's four well you know what
check this out now that I've got the
speed crunch the four plus three plus
two plus one plus one so I guess maybe
it wouldn't be the worst thing in the
world to get off of eleven as a stride
but even so we don't really need it to
be in here as my point an omission I
guess probably doesn't really need to be
in here anymore either
but that's a separate issue maybe it
still does we'll see and I suppose what
we could do there even is just say like
okay there's the light offset and it
could even be a 32-bit value if we want
it to be because at this point we don't
have the problem of needing to really
use linked lists so much anyway we can
just point directly into an array and
have like a zero terminator so we just
go till you get a zero or something like
this or you can even go we could even do
something like this
use a 16-bit offset and account so that
the count basically just says how many
to read right we could do a lot of stuff
like that
so we have a lot of ways of playing with
this but for now we have to get in here
and I'm gonna put to do on it because
like I said we don't need it for vertex
so when we're ready when we're in the
mood to like get into another protracted
fight with opengl about some basic stuff
switching to sending that down in a
separate buffer that gets read per
vertex
I'm sorry per primitive would be good
the reason I don't want to do that right
now is cuz I'm imagining it will be a
complete mess to do so it might even
require us to do like a geometry shader
or something that replicates for all I
know there may not be a built-in way to
actually set that up which is stupid but
that may be the case
you never know is grabs stuff rocks
api's are almost universally lousy so
what we need to do is just have some way
for the moment to sort of hack it in
there and then once we have it working
in the hacked way then we will figure
out how to sort of play with it further
alright so if we were going to do that
then what we need to do here is extend
our notion in the Z biased program of
what comes in so here you can see the
things that we're coming in P and UV and
color emission wasn't getting read in
this one and that's because we didn't
actually use it for anything but the
rest of the things were so if we have a
light offset and a light count we want
to read those values in and those are
integer values but don't actually know
whether it will allow us to specify an
integer as an integer in the vertex data
I'm not 100% sure whether it allows that
or not in our voxel how we used to do
that here in the in in this thing we did
use to sample the texture that way but I
don't know so we can sample we were able
to sample texture integers I just don't
know whether we're allowed to sample
vertex buffer integers I'm assuming we
will so I'll try that first but we'll
find out in a second I'm sure right so
if we do
and in here this is going to be a short
right and I don't know whether we can do
an unsigned short here or not but that's
what I'm going to try and really all I
want to do right now is just see whether
or not these work right that's it that's
all I want to try and do so I'm gonna go
ahead and say these are both ends I'm
just gonna run the program now and see
whether that shader compiles that's all
I want to do at first right so it looks
like it at least compiles that's good
news
so now what I need to do is go all right
if we have these things getting put in I
also need them to be put out as well
right now normally we type this right
you can see up here we've done smooth
out smooth that's Matt now smooth what
that actually means is prospectively
correct interpolated across the triangle
that's what that means we don't want
that right we're just this is just a
hack to get this in there so all we
actually want to do is just pass it
straight through so if we take a look at
the open gel GLSL quick reference we
should be able to
yeah where is arduous oh that's not it
these are not gos oh there it is um so
the things that we can specify in terms
of how we want things interpolated
hopefully are listed on here of course
the fact that I don't see that listed
anywhere here doesn't fill me with
confidence
um am i missing it or did they just not
put it on here we may have to go to the
actual spec cuz I don't see it I might
just be missing it though here okay
there it is there it is
I blew right by it so here's the part
we're talking about which are qualifiers
and specifically we're talking about
interpolation qualifiers and as you can
see here what I just said is listed at
the top smooth is perspective correct
interpolation right what we actually
want if you wanted some weird sauciness
you could do no perspective
interpolation right and that would give
you linear that would give you the old
effects of the PlayStation 1 if you
wanted right so you could have some fun
with that flat though is what we're
actually looking for we want it to not
touch our values at all because we just
don't we don't have multiple of them to
interpolate in the first place so just
to avoid any wackiness with the
interpolation we're just gonna say look
what I output leave exactly the same
right don't interpolate at all now the
problem with this is I don't actually
know if I can like I said if I can
actually get this into the the pixel
shader itself and not have to put it in
here so that's why I'm doing this
compilation test to see ok so that
suggests wait
oh okay so I assume and I don't really
know but I assume that I have to output
this to the like I have to actually send
this down to the pixel shader what I
would have liked to have done right is
just said that this comes directly in in
the pixel shader but I just don't know
if that's actually possible right that's
what I'm trying to guess really I know
exactly what I want the GPU to do but I
don't really know how to make it do it
which is generally the case with GPUs so
these are gonna be flat in here right
like so and in theory this should look
now yeah now what I don't really
understand is what no interpolation
really means in this case because if we
are talking about something that's
declared both in the vertex shader and
in the fragment shader as not having any
interpolation then which vertex does it
take presumably it takes the one from
the first vertex but I don't know it
doesn't matter because we'll just send
the same one down all the time but
either way
so in here where we've got this flat in
unsigned short right these are now our
light offsets or no light counts and
what we can do now is in our some voxel
light routine right we can leave that in
there again we'll delete it later when
we're sure we don't need it anymore but
what I can do is say okay let me cut and
paste that a second time and just have a
Sun light routine and that sunlight
routine will do the light summation for
us without having to do any of the voxel
stuffs so this light I here thing that's
just going to take this frag light
offset directly
and it's gonna start at that and it's
gonna count down the light or I guess I
could count up the frag light count and
it's just going to sample into the
texture based directly on that right so
what we want to do is something like
something like this so we grab a count
of the lights that we're going to use we
grabbed the first one and then each time
through we just loop through right I
don't know enough about GPUs to know
what the fastest way to do loops like
that is that's probably something we
would want to look up eventually if this
turns out to be a thing that we do but
for now it will work which is all we
really want we just want a way to test
it right so while there is lights left
we just keep going and that's really it
we do the summation exactly the way that
we were doing it before and off we go
then in here instead of doing the sum
voxel I thing we just say okay that's
gone we're not going to do it anymore
instead of all of this stuff we're just
going to do a v3l and actually all
literally all of this stuff we're just
going to do a v3l that's what are we
calling this just some light
and that's it right so all we need to do
is just now some of the lights that
we've been told this primitive cares
about and they can be whatever we don't
care what they are
we're gonna use them right and then we
output a final interpolated value and
we're done that's it
and a story so one nice bonus to this is
this will be way faster right this is a
way more efficient way of doing the
lighting than reading it for the
question is just will it work and we
don't know but we're gonna try ok so now
we just have to get this compiling so
that we can get somewhere to start from
implicit cast from medium PU it to int
is that so tell me pray tell wouldn't
right here where did I do that and it's
like right on that line actually
implicit castrum into bool okay while
light count is greater than zero are you
happy now compiler okay so now and we're
still working just fine to you'll notice
we don't get any light because of course
we're not actually passing any values
down there so the light count will
always be zero but we're running under
that shader now so now our job is just
to actually pass down some light
information that actually correctly
lines up with these surfaces right so
the first thing that I want to do is I
want to cheese out right that's the
right the most important thing to do is
to cheese out first
using of course what I always say
structure dark
concept of structured art first
introduced to me actually by Mike bilko
he was a programmer from the the it was
a company that can't remember was
distinctive suffer no I can't remember
the name of the company because it had
gone away and got merged into another
company by the time I met him but it was
a company that did hockey games and I
think they got absorbed by EA or
something eventually I can't quite
remember but anyway he was the first
person who used the term structured art
that I had heard and it's like the
greatest technique right like it's
always a good thing to drill into your
head like whenever you're going to do
something new that's whose only real way
of verifying what it's doing is by
visually looking at it instead of trying
the real solution first do a fake one
first that outputs very obvious values
and if you don't see those values you
know you have a bug before you even got
to the like full part of it right so
structured out sending down solids red
greens and blues and various patterns
like that sort of thing
checkerboards blah blah blah very
important right it's it's how you can
see more clearly when you have bugs
because a lot of graphic stuff is very
subtle you might think that you've
gotten something working but you really
don't or you may have stuff that's so
hard to tell what you know it's wrong
but you can't tell why structured art
can help reveal those patterns to you so
that you can more quickly zero in on
what you actually have to fix and what's
wrong right so what I want to do is I
want to start with some structured art I
want to try to figure out a way to start
by sending down let's say red green blue
white as the for as for lighting samples
on the corner of every quad so that way
every quad we look at should have a red
corner a green corner a blue corner and
a white corner and a wash in between as
it interpolates between those samples
right I
that's what we want okay
so let's figure out a way to do that
let's go ahead into our render group
here and we need to start thinking about
how this is going to work this is going
to get more complicated our render group
is going to have to get smarter over
time but at the moment we can do
something relatively straightforward
when we go to push a quad down the pipe
like so what we can do in that push quad
is we can then use that push quad to
reserve the texture room that we needed
right so here is the the funnel through
which everything in our game goes you
can see it like right here so what I'm
gonna say is I'm just gonna start with a
stupidest possible thing I'm gonna say
all right vert zero gets a light index
and a light color and I'm gonna
replicate it to all vertices now why am
i replicating it to all vertices again
the only reason for it is just to
eliminate possible mistakes thus far in
the future what we would like to do is
make it per fragment and then we will
not be specifying it here anymore it we
specify it in a separate side band array
for the moment though we're not going to
do that yeah okay
so what we're gonna do here is we're
gonna hard code these in the future we
will probably I don't know it's not like
color it's like Talent
okay so we've got the the light count in
here and what we want to do is say from
now on we're just gonna have the light
count as always for right and the light
index is always going to be whatever our
quad index was right so we know that we
have a quad index which is the vert cap
in fact we know that that's what it is
right so we know that like our vert
index is this
so we can just use that because it's
already going up by four right
so that should allow us to do what we
wanted to do which is just striate these
correctly what did I actually call this
is it first light index light offset
surprise it's light index now all right
what did I call it a fragment shader I
call it light offset it's not light
offsets light index it's an actual index
all right lovely now when we run this we
should not see any real difference here
Jimmy ooh did I mess up something when I
changed that
I did my bad this was supposed to be
replaced as well and wasn't lovely so
now we have a vertex stream that
properly has four spaces reserved in the
texture for it right because I have
properly placed you know each one of
them has four spaces we say that there
are four of them so now our shader
should be able to read that we just now
have two steps we have to do one we have
to put something in there right and
we'll do that step second the other
thing we have to do is actually bind the
vertex these additional vertex values
right so what you can see here is is
when we do for example this this binding
down here right you can see we're not
actually binding any vertex information
up here in the use program begin you can
see we've got the is valid array stuff
that is what we actually now need to do
so we're gonna have to do a thing that's
like is valid array light offset is
valid or a light count
so those two things we now have to
describe and they are both the same kind
right they're unsigned short there's
only one of them in each case since
they're pairs I guess now that I think
about it I probably should just do them
as one but I don't know if you can do
that I don't know what you call that
it's because there's a Veck - I don't
know in the shader if there's a unsigned
short - so I'm just going to leave it as
two separate arrays for now but that's
worth noting so I don't know we don't
want them normalized that's what this
parameter is right we want them to
remain unknown alized
right yeah so we don't want them
normalized like the GL unsigned byte for
example it gets normalized so it's a it
takes a zero to two to five range in
maps at zero to one we don't want to do
that for some reason I did it again I
really want to call this light offset in
some places in light index in others we
don't know why so once we've got that we
should be pretty good to go here that
should all be sent down but we need
obviously somewhere that this gets
recorded
so we disabled it probably should have
put these in an array
I didn't put a Rea on the end of these
for reasons that nobody knows we don't
know why probably because I don't really
care about them it's like I said we
should probably sent down as a single
array and it probably should be sent
down only the fragment shader but we
don't really know how to do that just
yet all right so we'll disable those two
and enable them as necessary when we do
use program begin that will
automatically happen so I think that's
all good so really then what we have to
do is make sure that the part where we
actually get the locations so this Open
GL create program for example right here
we need light vert light index vert
light count and those should just give
us back at the binding location so now
in theory anyway we are sending down
those values we have not put well
actually no so so now in theory anyway
we know we have a bug because the
lighting when I run the lighting it will
write values in there they they'll be
like you know who knows what the values
will be but they'll be in there so we do
sort of know that that's not quite right
yet because we must be binding something
incorrectly or we would be seeing some
of that information coming through I
think I don't want a 100% count on that
just yet so I am going to go ahead and
set the lighting stuff anyway
just to be safe
but I'm pretty sure I did I must have
not quite gotten everything set up
properly there because I think we should
have seen that come through and we
didn't right so ah you know what though
this right here is the wrong name that's
that's one of it
so here in the Z bias program if we want
this this would have to be vert light
index and vert light count and and right
and we didn't set them either so you
have to finish this part of it as a
pass-through
Am I
something very bad has happened but I
don't know what it's just getting slower
and slower and slower that's a very
curious result wouldn't you say
so why is it doing that that's as if the
frag light count values were going up
and up and up and up or something right
something strange is happening there
can't say I see immediately what it is
it could be that we're not unbinding
something that we bound would be another
thing that could cause something like
that like if we're constantly adding
more and more vertex buffers right so if
for example so here's where we enable
our vertex array a trip array is here
right the light of next to the light
count we enable both of these and give
them pointers and so maybe I didn't
actually do this right here although it
sure looks like I did right it looks
like they both get disabled and Plus
that couldn't really have done it I
don't think
so let me flip back over here real quick
I just want to make sure what we're
passing down do we ever pass anything
else down I don't think I think
everything goes through push quad right
yeah
so looking at this the light index goes
goes up the light count doesn't just one
thing I should change or verify light
index is light index and like count is
like count correct that would also be
potentially bad yeah so I'm not sure
what that's what's happening there
that's very interesting right
you see what's happening there right it
starts out fast ends up getting slower
and slower and slower and slower
now that could just be because more
stuff is on the screen but I can't
imagine why let me just let me just do a
quick check here just to see
let's suppose we don't do this right
like we don't we don't do this call so
instead we just do like
so it's definitely the while loop that's
the problem here
right
oh I know what the problem is
we were still fetching the next light
index we don't want that we just want to
loop loops we just want to loop through
that could that could easily be it so
let's let's double check that nope still
wrong because the light index was yeah
was getting modified there so I feel
like that could have been bad although
well no because it would still only do
however many it was supposed to do in
count so even though it was reading from
that light index that shouldn't really
have been a problem right all right well
so let's set light count equal to four
which is what we think it should be and
let's try to verify that it actually
works okay if it's four all right so it
looks like what we're having is a
problem that the light count is not
properly getting set to four always I
guess because in theory we should never
have a vertex whose light count is not
four
right I mean you can look at this and
see four at zero light count equals
light count verticals let count for it
to let connects like I have for three
electronics like count they're all set
to light count and light count is equal
to four so I'm not sure why it would
ever not be equal to four but guess what
it isn't the question is how is it
getting set to something other than four
is there anything that draws non quads
thought everything drew quads at the end
of the day I thought everything went
through that pipe and I don't mean I
don't really mean that I don't mean is
everything about quads what I mean is
does everything draw actual does
everything go through the actual draw
quad call
so yeah I'm not too sure about that
let's maybe try to take advantage of the
fact that we in theory can run graphics
debugging here and let's see what
happens
whoo here we we only have about 20
minutes left or so but let's just take a
look and see if we can get that part
working because that way we can start
tomorrow with a working way of sending
these down in a working order so I
forget the magic dance I had to do to
get this thing to work before I'm just
gonna try to do stark graphics to
bugging hopefully that'll work
and now I'll just go ahead and do pause
and capture frame I think this how think
that works yeah so here we have here we
have paused and captured a frame so if
we go into our vertex attributes now we
should be able to see what we're
actually getting so you know here's a
pass right here for example we should be
able to see what elements are being set
and all that good stuff all right so
unfortunately I guess we have to use the
buggy version because you can see it is
optimized out our other our other short
I guess one thing we could do to prevent
disaster let's try that start graphics
debugging
so that's still nice and zippy so that
is working insight
pause and capture frame and now
hopefully we have to know we still don't
well maybe that explains it if the
problem is that we're not binding that
array because we should see two unsigned
short arrays here but we're not so let's
figure out why all right maybe I just
have a spelling error and that would be
simple so in here the name of this input
oh great well that was easy so I guess
we did have a spelling error that's
probably it
that was just a typo but it was a bad
type of thank you to the graphics
devoted her for working and there we go
all right so I still would have expected
to see some data in there so I'm not
sure everything's working quite right
yet but at least we got rid of that
that was definitely a bad typo so that's
no good so let's finish by stuffing some
things into that array and then we will
go ahead and play around with things
tomorrow in in actually sort of setting
up the lighting samples so what I want
to do again is just push some structured
art down here so I'm gonna go into
render drilling put it you know one that
doesn't have my head in front of it so
when we do our output lighting textures
now we don't really need to do a lot of
the stuff that we were doing before so
we'll have to kind of rewrite these
routine since we don't need the voxel
stuff like none of this
it's necessary right
this stuff is all kind of old news and
so what we can do what we got to do now
is kind of think about this a little bit
differently but for now let's just let's
do this the simple way so in here where
we've got like PAC index and that stuff
and we're sort of creating linked lists
we're gonna nuke that out right that's
not gonna happen anymore and in fact
maybe I'll just leave this in again
because we don't really know what we're
gonna do here this is all experimental
code so you don't want to delete a bunch
of code that maybe then I decided I
actually need again so let's start with
this and delete it in a separate pass
here so we can kind of keep the old one
around so we don't need any of this
voxel stuff right the voxel stuff goes
away and so we don't eat any of the
packing stuff either like the lookup or
the next pointers those are no longer
relevant to us and we can ignore them
completely so then what we have here in
our lighting element is when we pull it
out what we want to do is basically have
the packing index specified in the
lighting element I think that's probably
what we want to do so what we want to do
is say alright the place that we're
gonna pack this thing that pack index
should probably be directly in the
lighting element self so where we're
gonna put this lighting sample back
that's gonna just be directly specified
by the lighting element right so
everything we write from here on out is
going to go there no voxel involved I'm
going to compile that it should complain
because there won't be a pack index but
we're gonna add one now the destination
of stuff here this stuff is all garbage
now so this is not relevant I guess the
way the right way to do this to leave
that probably in there and getting set
let me just go ahead and create false
versions of these
let's see what else we got seldom an
inverse seldom and so now all we should
have to do is just augment that lighting
element right to specify where it should
get packed like we're into the lighting
array it needs to get packed so here
I'll just have the pack index sitting at
the bottom we're able to compile now but
we're not actually setting it anywhere
so when we do extract oops
reflectors from quads and we come down
through here whatever we create in terms
of things that we want to pack in here
we're gonna have to we're gonna have to
set each lighting elements pack index to
something same right now it occurs to me
that actually we can overwrite the
packing values here so we could actually
keep pretty much exactly what we have we
really don't need to change this at all
so what we could probably do is say all
right you know what forget about that
lets say the packing index here is equal
to zero let's say that every time we
create a new element we set its packing
index whatever the packing index
actually is and here we'll do an elk
count like an element count
we don't I guess we know what it is it's
just it's just sub count the two sub
counts down times each other right but
then what we can do is say all right
well now that we know like we grat we're
grabbing out these vertices here right
vert 0 1 2 right what we can do is say 4
at 0 light index equals 4 1 light index
equals vert 2 light index equals 4 3
light index equals pack index right vert
zero light count wouldn't it be great if
like C could actually do stuff like this
you know such a piece of junk it's
hilarious how they've like never added
anything that's any good ever and
there's so much stuff that's like so
obvious they're just like yeah we'd
rather just dink around with stupid
changes designed to make lousy
programmers make less mistakes
it's like merit thanks for nothing guys
all right so X sub count times y sub
count so there I will basically say okay
let's just actually have to set this
first let's just actually have this
thing however much subdivides we'll use
that number of lighting samples for this
particular surface so that will actually
be accurate right at least I think it
should be
yeah but these do clip out that's true
all right so I don't think this will
work though because like I said before
even though now in theory we're packing
the lights into the right locations it
seemed like we weren't actually grabbing
them out properly before so something's
a little bit busted in that gather so we
don't really know I'm gonna stuff
structured light down ahead of time I
think like I was saying in order to make
sure things work but we also need to go
take a look and find out
why we're getting this sort of never
actually able to grab the colors and
it's probably just something that I
messed up in the OpenGL setup because
it's really easy to do mess ups with
your OpenGL setup so anyway like looking
through here I just wanna make sure this
is sane I've got the sunlight call with
the what's being returned from that
discuss directly modulated looking at
the result it's doing Texel fetches the
way that we normally would and that
seems okay it's so yeah everything's
fetching off of that light I which seems
okay
that seems like what I would expect so I
think let me just go ahead and see if
this is working at all though I just
want to I just want to bump a red
channel there to make sure yeah I didn't
know if there was like something else
that was potentially going on there I
wasn't sure so I just want to make sure
that we can actually so we know that our
summations if if something properly
summed into that light we would see the
result there there's not like some
Squinkie thing happening that would you
know knock that out so we did we have
one of two things potentially happening
we don't know which either we are the
actual packing somehow is now really
wrong and the light is not getting put
into the light array in the same fashion
or this light sampling where we're
sampling the light index here we're
somehow getting the value the actual
light index value is not properly at
pointing to one of these arrays in the
right way like it's you know it's
indexing off of the wrong things somehow
we're just not sure how so that I'm just
not sure what the best way to go about
looking at is probably see if we can
capture frame and take a look to see
what these values are likely to be we
can't say for sure what they are because
we can't step into the shader I found
out why that was by the way I think
James Whitman was the person who wrote
in and mentioned it which is that the
reason I can debug shaders on my dev
machine and not this machine is actually
just because they haven't supported
shader debugging on the 1080s
that graphics card doesn't support them
yet so the fact that I'm using an older
graph
Fix card in my main debt machine is
actually a plus because I don't remember
what that thing is it might be a 600
series might be an 800 sir I don't
remember it's an Nvidia card running in
sight on that card you can step through
the shaders running in sight on this
card you can't so what are you gonna do
so we can't actually step through and
see specifically what might be wrong
there but we can look at those arrays
right that will be inspected and so
let's just go on a little bit of a
fishing expedition here because rather
than start fiddling with it completely
blind why not use the tool we do have to
just eliminate some parts of the problem
from suspicion right so what I'm gonna
do here is I'm gonna do a pause and
capture frame and just look to see if I
can at least verify that those are rate
well you know what we gotta actually run
the lighting or there won't be anything
in those arrays all right so do one more
time okay so if i run the lighting
solution under on the lighting solution
well this'll just switch back to regular
mode this should now have sent something
down to those arrays and we can now look
and see whether it actually did and what
those if those values are coherent or if
they're not right so here's the vertex
attributes and we can read across and
see the buffers that correspond to them
so but for us four and five are
correctly set to non-normalized and they
are the two values that should have our
light counts and our light indices so
what we should see is one of these
should just have a bunch of count values
in it and one of them let's I guess we
need to set this to 16-bit integer
unsigned did that show us so that's not
good at all if that's actually right
that's not good
oh okay but that's the whole buffer so
okay ignore that for one second that's
the whole buffer there I don't know if
it lets us see it strided so that might
be harder to deal with so here's the
entire buffer right it's we're gonna
have to sort of pick and choose through
it to figure out where our actual
unsigned int values are but we do know
the size of the thing so we should be
able to take our vertex layout and see
it correctly right I don't know if
there's any nice tool in here that
really lets us do it probably there
isn't it would be nice though if there
was like because it should be able to do
that maybe it can if I go to the vertex
shader maybe you could do that so we
don't have to slice it out I'm not sure
yeah I don't know there might be a
smarter way to do this than what I'm
about to do so I apologize for that
I am NOT the kind of person who spends
all their day day and graphics coding so
I'm just gonna have to do this the hard
way for now I'm going to set it to
16-bit unsigned which is what we want to
see but remember we're looking at the
buffer that actually represents all of
our vertex data so what that means is
that all we're really seeing that memory
view is we're just seeing these textured
vertices stacked up so if you take a
look at how many there are here right
there's there's 32-bit values at the
front there is four plus three plus two
of them right pluck these it's 11 so we
know there's 12 32-bit values in here
right twelve thirty-two values is 24 no
if we get set now we can't
so three rows of this is how many there
are for each of our vertices you can see
that there's nonsense sides you know
that's their floating-point values right
so we see here is zero four zero four
zero four zero four four four four four
four four four four right 8 for 8 for 8
for 8 for 12 for 12 for 12 for that's
exactly what we would expect everything
has four we should be able to get to
some of that more than four those would
be ones that are subdivided right so we
should be able to find some in here that
are so divided I would hope although I'm
not really seeing it
oh well you know what unless we call
that every frame that wouldn't work
either so yeah I guess that's true we
have to actually do that reassignment a
little more carefully we have to do this
is not necessarily related to the
problem we were tracking but I just
realized we've got one of the problem
since we don't run the lighting solution
every frame because we just we're not
trying to do the full gpu-accelerated
frame by frame one and we just want to
be able to it to be as slow as we need
it to be to test this extract can't
really do the remap I would kind of got
overzealous there there's extract can't
do the remap because it has to it has to
be run only when you hit the f1 key so
we can't actually have this correspond
properly so when we do that f1 there and
we do output lighting quads this would
actually have to reconstruct that
information right and there's really
nothing we can do about that
unfortunately
so we may have to kind of step up our
game here a little bit or just leave
things the way that they were without
subdividing right
so yeah so we can't really write into
that we have to use what we've got and
so for now we would have to do something
where we would say okay the X sub count
and the Y sub count they pretty much
have to be fixed that too because we
know we only have four elements to write
into for every quad that comes down
right so the PAC index here in fact has
to be exactly zero one two three four
that's what has to happen and the PAC
index has to come from the vertex right
so we have to do PAC and x equals vert
zero light index we have to target that
we don't have a choice and we can only
do four that's just that's what we have
to do right now and we can improve that
going forwards when we actually have a
more streamlined light situation but
that's actually what we have to do so
that's the only fair way to do it and
now we will actually have a lighting
solution that would line up properly in
theory okay so that's fine before I go
to Q&amp;A I do want to finish what I was
doing though which is to run the
graphics debugger and just see what's in
those other buffers the lighting buffers
themselves so here if I was to capture a
frame I should be able to look at what
the lighting buffers are that the vertex
I'm sorry the fragment shader is
sampling from so that I would like to
take a look at here is the verse there
is here is the actually you know what no
that's not it that's the frame buffer
which I don't care about I actually want
the fragment shader which I have to move
to different before there we go so
here's the see sampler in the D sampler
the PX sampler it's at etc I'm just
going to look and see what whether these
have anything in them
make sense right I mean they should in
theory but I don't really know so oops I
gotta remember which one I clicked on
since it doesn't really give me any
information so let's take a look at the
SI sampler that should be the color
values right
all right so I mean there's plenty of
color values in here there's definitely
a lot of blacks but there's definitely a
lot of colors so I don't know that's a
little bit hard to say but there's
certainly you certainly expect to see
something right so I'm a little confused
as to why we're not able to see anything
at all that seems a bit odd to me I
would like to just verify again that the
vertex shader is getting that
information but I'm thinking that it is
I mean based on what we looked at before
it certainly seemed like it was so
that's a little bit odd does the
fragment shader list an input how come
like this I don't really want uniforms I
just want the here it is this is what I
wanted
can you show me this I just want to look
at this why does it say Jail unsigned
int I guess that's because that's what
it comes through as I wonder if that
means I've defining it as a short is
wrong and I need to define it as an
integer instead because I told it it was
an unsigned short but it says it's an
unsigned int and I don't know exactly
how that fetch is gonna be working I
feel like the vertex specification does
correctly say that's an unsigned short
so I feel like the fetch should fetch
you to the short and turn it into an int
but I don't know if that means that it
shouldn't be specified that way in the
actual
in the actual shader itself you and I'm
saying like I'm wondering if that means
that that this is not actually it should
be just unsigned int here you know or
just plain int we don't need it to be
unsigned for any particular reason
obviously I don't know that doesn't seem
likely but if that's what it actually
thinks the actual input is I wonder if
that implies we have to set it this way
like maybe it just doesn't deal with
shorts well that definitely changed
things right I mean before we were kind
of crashing out there and now all of a
sudden we're getting a kind of a freeze
in there right and all I did was change
it to an unsigned in in each of these
cases that's it I didn't touch anything
else right so I'm interested to see is
there a way we can get some is there a
way we can get some debug info on that
yeah
doesn't look like let's never put
anything into the log that really tells
us anything
so let's play with that a little bit
when we actually go in here to some
light and we get our fried light index
out here and our frag light count I'm
wondering if our frag let count is
completely bogus now somehow I'm gonna
go ahead and do the same trick we did
before first we'll try this so it is
that light count value is a bogus value
at the moment it would seem right so I'm
not sure where we're getting those
errant values in there but somehow we're
not set up to read this properly we just
don't know how sooo what what would be
the best way since we can't see what
these values are when we look at what
they should be in the buffer they look
correct right it was like 0 for 4 for 12
for 16 for those sorts of values right
which was exactly what we thought they
should be and the indices are also
correct so we don't really know why
we're getting weird results in here but
for now I'll leave this in and we'll go
to the Q&amp;A I like to revisit tomorrow
all right
okay question time what texture file
type will you use we actually at the
moment just have our own pack file we
probably will just use a basic like a
very simple zip to zip them or something
like this we don't need to do texture
compression because we don't have enough
textures that that would require it and
if you use texture if you use Hardware
texture compression your quality suffers
and I don't want that so because we
don't need it we won't come we won't use
like txt or anything TC or anything like
that because that just makes our quality
lower for no benefit we don't need the
extra bandwidth and we don't need the
extra space so someone asked if we get
set oh it's a soft he asked if we could
set the font larger and that does look
like we can
I don't know what font we actually want
though
I think I use liberation mono or droid
sans' mono Keys droid sans' mono now oh
I forgot
right windows can't install a font from
a substituted Drive because you know
they're just that good at their job
there we go
so now we should be able to pick droid
sans mono in here or not can we not do a
fixed font
I guess I had to reboot the program so
now it should be roughly the same font
as in the as in the editor
in what structure do you organize world
objects we use a sparse grid basically
it's basically like a how should I put
it we use a hash table of 3d locations
and we truncate everything to a sort of
course 3d location and store it into
sort of a block that's and we store all
the entities and their actual locations
inside that block I think you missed an
equal sign in one of the shaders when
defining him something one one one that
wouldn't have been a shader would it you
talking about this you're correct I did
I don't think that'll help us but thanks
for the a for the catch
oh good bye Emma stove
just used any comments on using sequel
light as a file format for a game uh I
guess I would say I don't have any
objections to using sequel light as the
file for a game as long as you're not
performance critical I would not use
sequel light for anything that was
performance critical but if it's not
performance critical like you're not
storing very much data in it then it
should be okay so the risk oh man isn't
it weird how OpenGL is with how you have
to interface with it to do things like
you send it a string and then you put
two shaders together to make a program
it's like esoteric and stuff yeah it's
awful net modern computers have two
chips in them of equal complexity more
or less the GPU in the CPU the CPU has a
real compiler that you can edit with
real language with a real debugger and a
real memory system and the GP has none
of those things so you can't even just
code GPU code into your regular code and
have it go through the same linker and
output actual code into an executable
that gets bound like the whole there
isn't even a executable file format for
these things that works together right
it's this ugly polyp off to the side
it's horrible
right it's as if you couldn't have to
see program to see files have the same
variable in them they had to like create
a string that named that variable and
then manually call the function to look
it up right it's just nuts the whole
point of the compiler is it does it does
the mapping of strings to offsets for
you that's what compiler does right so
one of the main things it does and we
just don't even have that yet and it's
crazy we've been programming these GPUs
for like I don't even
No almost 20 years now I want to say and
we haven't gotten it it's it's crazy
murk Elbe what percentage is the way
through the game do you think you are I
have no idea we do a lot of educational
stuff on the stream that isn't
necessarily about trying to finish the
game so it's hard to say careers
question why f/32 has a lowercase F
while F 32 maxes up again stuff because
I use lowercase four types and uppercase
four values in what video index do you
start with discretion about using a
three-dimensional voxel for lighting uh
I don't know we've done a bunch of
streams unloading cuz it's a tough
problem and I'm just kind of like
developing a new solution I'm not just
implementing an existing solution so we
didn't start right off with a voxel so I
don't remember it be you know 15 streams
back 15 episodes back maybe somewhere in
there
could we use the normalized light count
index to one and use them to build a
color maybe in this way we can see what
value we get yeah we could try to just
use those as colored values and see what
we see
that's not a bad idea I don't know
so if we were to do that right what we
could do is say instead of calling some
light at all which is down here and we
could you know just directly write it
out the the color we could say that the
light value equals the frag light
account and the green value equals the
frag light offset since we know this
value should be pretty small what we
could do is say like oh it's whatever
this is divided by you know 16 so we
just have a red channel that was like a
quarter hot when there were four which
is what we should see most the time for
the frag light offset we'd have to
divide it by a much higher number you
know but that should give us two
channels that you know show us roughly
what's going on there I so
[Music]
Oh
of course it doesn't yeah guess I don't
need to cast those I mean they are
floating point values already and when
it doesn't like the F suffix as well so
get rid of those undefined variable frag
light offset of course I always want to
call it light offset instead of light
index don't ask me why
so you know I mean this is what we
thought right which is that we're
getting completely bogus values in there
the question is just why you know we
looked at the values in the buffer and
they looked right let me see what
happens if I change it back to shorts
excuse I assume it will make a
difference but I don't really know
so we're just we're just not getting the
values that we should be getting based
on the buffer we must have like the
offset wrong or something or like the
vertex pointer is off somehow you know
but basically that's I mean it was still
it's a good suggestion right it totally
confirms what we thought was happening
but it doesn't really help us figure out
why I just don't know why we're getting
those bogus values in there I mean these
look like the right thing
[Music]
I mean I guess uh yeah I don't know
I really just don't know why we're doing
this well after we're gonna have to
figure out mr. Alda have you considered
cascaded voxels as investigated Bosco in
tracing as the data structure for
handmade here are letting samples not
for the samples but we will when we
eventually go to do the ray tracing
accelerated we probably will do
something multi res have you ever seen
the source code of a GPU driver not one
of the not Nvidia's or a TIA
AMD's I have seen the source code of the
Intel drivers at least one of them
because I worked on it the one that was
going to be for Al Arabi so I have seen
that code
oh you're right I did not run the
Ludington well no but we don't need to
run the loading calculation because the
letting calculation isn't required these
values are set at push time they're
supposed to be set to 0 for 8 right so
they're always set and we're just not
getting those values we don't need to
run the learning calculation because
those values are actually just getting
set immediately they get set in push
quad and we should say should just look
like monotonically increasing values but
they don't so we're getting something is
is weird about the way we're pulling
these values in is not good but I'm not
sure because we should see a range of
values and we're not out so what kind of
work did you in the Intel driver so I
didn't do much I was just contracting
and it wasn't it was the Intel driver
for when they were going to make a x86
based graphics part it was the Larrabee
project which eventually became the like
Xeon Phi you can buy them now but
they're not used for graphics they were
trying to make those work for like
DirectX rendering and stuff like that
and most of stuff I did was I only did
like a few months of work on it but I
did stuff to analyze like state
transitions and some stuff to play with
house shaders were compiled onto it but
that's really and they did not end up
shipping those cards for that purpose so
it was purely like research oriented
black pants see what kinds of things do
you most enjoy coding and what things
the least so the only thing is I don't
really enjoy coding are things where I
don't have access to what's actually
happening so you could say like this
kind of GPU coding is something I enjoy
least and the reason is because I'm not
really programming computer I'm
programming somebody's idea of how I
should program a computer same reason I
don't like we're gonna be C++ high-level
constructs same reason I don't like
programming operating system API calls I
like programming you know something
that's well specified and complete I
don't really like programming on top of
like hacky nonsense so you know I don't
like using graphics api's and I don't
like using a spring system API is
because I disagree with how they've been
designed and I know that they're not
doing what I probably think they should
be doing in terms of how I want them to
talk to the hardware that is underneath
right so that's the thing I like least
what I'd like most is when I have the
control to do what I want to do so when
I'm just doing my own code that's much
more satisfying and when I'm using a
language that's sane
if you're recruiting for Casso would be
would you be able to debug the graphs
part of it do they give you hardware
info down to and potatios
some do some don't depends on the
console but yet almost universally you
have a lot more so for example you may
not necessarily have great debugging but
you will have a lot more information on
what the chip does and you will have a
lot more opportunities to you know
program it the way you think and create
an API that makes sense and works well
alright that soon the queues so tomorrow
we will pick up where we left off and
try to figure out why we're getting kind
of wrong values in ingested into the
shader there there's probably something
happening but we'll see
draaga do you normally comment more than
you do for this stream your code is
clean to look at but it feels like it
big companies they would eat you up for
not decorating a lot more well that's
yeah that's no I actually don't comment
more than this and I would say that in
general that's why I don't work at big
companies I think big companies are
basically like kind of living examples
of how to take a problem that should
take like one or two programmers to
solve and take 500 programmers to solve
it I mean that's that's what they do I I
wouldn't work at a big company unless I
had to
if I needed the money you know I
couldn't get a job and I need the money
then you know I'm I'll I'll do whatever
but that's why I don't work at them I
think they don't have good processes and
I think their output speaks for itself
you know I mean I think I can't think of
a large company whose software is
shipped in a routine manner at a high
quality level with good features and
same design they I can't think of a
single one on the other hand I can think
of some small companies that do so you
know yeah I I think you would I think at
a big company after I don't know how
many episodes of handmade here we've
done here I think if you took the
equivalent of time it's taken us to do
this stuff on here I think in at a big
company even if you they didn't have to
be explaining it on streem they probably
would have gotten almost to the point
where they could maybe show a bitmap on
the screen or something because they
would have had so many code reviews and
meetings and everything else related to
every last little thing they did they
would never have been able to ever do
hardly any of the stuff that we ended up
doing and they certainly wouldn't have
been able to do all the experiments that
we've done or
all of the learning digressions we've
done and so on they're just incredibly
slow they get incredibly low output per
programmer at big companies it's nuts I
mean I think Twitter is a classic
example I would challenge you to try and
figure out how Twitter has I don't even
know my engineers they have they have
something like over a thousand engineers
I mean I I just don't I can't even
in my brain imagine what they're all
doing I don't know but the answer is
usually that they're all really not
doing anything they're mostly spending
their time doing stuff like adhering to
weird coding standards or arguing with
their manager about something or being
in the meeting being dismayed or
spending a lot of time in code reviews
reviewing code that will get deleted the
week after and it just sucks up all your
productivity so that you need ten times
a hundred times the number of engineers
you should need to do something I don't
necessarily blame them for this because
I don't know how you scale up if you
really want that many engineers working
I don't know how you make them all
efficient you probably can't or maybe
you need much more advanced stuff than
we have now but the same time that's why
I would never work there especially not
on something small like it's weird like
things like Twitter they ship an
incredibly small product that's like a
four or five person team I would think
could ship Twitter right but it takes
them one two thousand engineers you know
and I'm just like I don't know yeah I
mean why do you what why and how come
you haven't asked the question why like
what how come you don't have a good
answer as to why right so I don't know
well feel I work for a large company but
in a very researchy area honestly I feel
like I have the best of both worlds and
yeah you might be able to sew like one
of the nice things about if you can if
you can work in a pocket of a large
company that's sane like Microsoft
Research at least for a while I don't
know if it's the same these days but you
know you could just be doing research on
your own thing publishing papers and no
one's bothering you right you get a
paycheck and a nice office and you can
go explore important problems and you
probably aren't bothered a ton and
they're probably not forcing a code
review stuff and they're probably not
forcing you to do this or that right and
so you know that's that's a good option
costs eighty said I work at Frostbite
and I think you would fit right in
yeah like I said you know big company is
hard to specify like like I said I can
think of small teams that do good work
and there might be some medium-sized
teams that do big work I wouldn't
consider the Frostbite team to be that
large to be honest with you compared to
what I assume people mean by big company
and there are obviously teams like I
don't think the Bungie team goes nuts
with code reviews for example right and
so I think there's there's definitely
like fifty to a hundred sighs
programming teams usually in the game
industry but not always like the team
that does Reaper the audio editor for
example I bet they don't spend a lot of
time doing stupid stuff like you know
commenting a bunch of code and then that
way the comments will be wrong the next
day when you change something in the
algorithm right so yeah
and for all I know there might be some
large company summer that does have a
thousand engineers and actually somehow
maintain sanity and doesn't force them
to do a bunch of stupid stuff I don't
know but a lot of large companies don't
a lot of large companies are very bad at
that right and I can I can speak from a
little bit of insider information I
suppose for a company like Microsoft for
example if you're on I guess saying
Microsoft Research might be saying
Microsoft Windows for example is
completely I mean forget it I've seen
what goes on in the development of stuff
on there and it's there will never be
another you know there will never be a
positive development in Microsoft
Windows it's over because the way they
do development doesn't even allow people
to be effective even if if they were a
good programmer wouldn't matter right
and so it's definitely very risky and
very possible for your company to
develop these methodologies that it
thinks are good ideas but that actually
mean that you will just never be
productive again right and then your
code will always be big and bloated and
slow and bad and you will be have
trouble adding features in the features
you do add will be lousy right so yeah
so anyway so I stay away from big
companies for this reason but again yeah
that doesn't really mean that all big
companies are awful to work at or
anything and it also doesn't mean that
you can't take a company even one like I
said that I know is really bad in some
product areas and he would never want to
work there you still might find
divisions or regions inside that company
that are nice to work for right that
happens so it's it depends you know if
someone says you work for Microsoft it
could mean a lot of
things it might mean that you're
absolutely miserable and and every day
is horrible because you're working on I
guess stuff windows or something or it
might mean that you're having a great
time researching like cool speech
recognition stuff in some corner of the
Microsoft Research building and nobody
bothers you and you're you've got plenty
of smart people around to to talk to you
know so like when a company gets that
big another sort of corollary that is
there are going to be very big
differences potentially in what it feels
like to work at different sections of
the company and I feel like the person
you mentioned dice that's probably could
be true at EA as well it could be that
dice is very nice to work at but other
parts of EA are right so I think that's
just the case
having worked at a few large companies I
found the need for commenting code arise
from disproportionate skill levels among
the developer is less skilled or less
interested engineers tend to complain
about uncommented code so my problem
with comments is that it's almost
impossible to keep them accurate that's
the problem I don't really have a
problem with commented code if the code
is finished
and no one's ever going to touch it
again then commenting it is kind of like
just writing the docs for the code right
and that's fine
but if you know a piece of code isn't
done it should never be commented with
anything other than notes about what you
still need to do to it or pitfalls that
you need to watch out for that you think
you might forget that's the only thing
that should be in the comments but
commenting the code like what the code
does is not acceptable to me because
I've never seen it stay in sync the
amount of effort you have to put in to
keep the comments in sync is way more
than the effort you're saving on the
other engineers part who has to come in
and read it so the only time I you think
commenting is valid is in those cases
right either you you finish this code
it's like a library right and it's like
the code is done I'm not changing it at
all for quite some time except to fix
bugs that would be in contrast to the
comments right that would be violating
comments then okay here is some
documentation that says how the code
works and how you should use it yes
right but on the other hand if it's code
that's under active development no no
comments like the comments should only
be notes about what you've learned in
development or something like that
because those can will always be correct
if they're just saying something that
happened right so you know I think -
duze is mostly what should be in here
and notes like you know like this are
fine we'll just say why I did something
in case I forgot or whatever fine but
something that says like here's how this
piece of code works always bad if the
code isn't done because it will just rot
and you'll forget to update the comment
you know
and that's the problem so you know I
mean one of the main things I shipped
was the animation library for rad and
you might say that was commented very
extensively because it had documentation
that shipped with it right and I kept
that documentation up to date by when I
finished something I would change the
doc documentation in like a separate
pass and then that which about two
customers right
very important very necessary but
commenting code as you're developing it
just doesn't make sense it's a real
waste of time
and I and I really feel like people who
think you should comment code while
you're in the process of developing it I
don't think they know what they're
talking about I think that's something
they're saying that they haven't really
tested and haven't really measured which
which is unfortunately what a lot of
people when they say things like that
they haven't really measured it right
all right that's about it I'm gonna wind
it down
all righty thank you everyone for
joining me for another set of handmade
hero it's been a pleasure coding with
you as always if you want to follow
along with the series as always you can
pre-order the game on handmade hero org
and it comes with a source code so you
can play around with it yourself you
could for example find the lighting bug
that we're gonna have to find tomorrow
you could find it before me it would be
great practice for you you don't know
the answer already and it would give you
some practice working with GPU code
which can be kind of tricky to to work
with because you can't do things like
step through it so that might be a good
exercise for tonight for those of you
who are looking for some homework anyway
and I will try to upload this
immediately so I will upload it
immediately after this so you guys can
can can debug it anyway
we also a forum site you can go to flask
questions we have a new non patreon
contribution page so you don't have to
use patreon anymore we got rid of it it
just goes through our own send out
back-end stuff now so it should be all
nice and clean no weird changes coming
down the pipe or anything and it now has
yearly contribution options to try and
help people making small contributions
to not have to worry about the credit
card fees you can pledge a larger amount
less frequently instead of a smaller
amount more frequently and and help to
get rid of some of those fees that were
the bane of the patreon problem we also
have a schedule bot that says we're
going to be live case you want to cut
the stream live we also have an episode
guide which should be updated shortly I
know it's missing a few episodes on
there that apparently they had some
problems integrating it with they did
some moves to the server over at ham
main network not something I have a lot
of insight into but they are dealing
with it right now and so hopefully the
episode guide will be up-to-date the
annotations have been done midlow has
been on top of it it's just they can't
get pushed to the server for some reason
so that'll get sorted out soon and then
the episode guide I'll be out back up to
date that's ready for today I'll be back
here tomorrow defiance what's going on
with why we can't send those letting
vibes down to the GPU correctly until
then have fun programming and I'll see
everyone on the Internet take it easy
everybody