okay hello everybody and welcome to hand
made here the show recode a complete
game live on stream we did some work on
lighting last weekend and today is day
391 so if you're following along at home
you want to grab day 392 source code if
you take a look at where we left off we
actually were in a pretty good place in
terms of just really basic kind of you
know the rudimentary lighting now if I
go ahead and build here there we go and
I run the game it seems like code excel
has kind of permanently destroyed our
original studio in some way it's like
now when we launch Visual Studio it
takes like eons for it to load and we
have no idea why just who knows maybe
that's just how the dual studio is
because you'll see was amazing but we
had done the work for lighting the world
from a single light source like this and
we played around with the specular
effect of it this is like kind of tight
specular highlight here and there right
now the effect the light position is
locked to the hero's head so we could
move it around those the experiment and
you can see we've got kind of a specular
highlight here that travels around and
bounces off shapes as if it was a fairly
mirrored shape a little bit glossy
obviously compared to a real mirror but
that's you know basic Phong lighting and
it works mostly the way you expect now
what we talked about last week at the
end though was of course that you know
we have a lot of things that we might
want to do now in order to make this
lighting useful in the general game
sense so two things kind of come to mind
rather immediately right one is that we
would potentially like to set these
responses to the light of
per surface right so if you take a look
at what you know as we sort of travel
around you can see that this light
behaves the same on all surfaces so each
one of these cubes as well as the hero
himself or any other sprite in the world
is all behaving with one particular
reflection model even though we are only
in this case we only did like a very
simple fog model for example and we'll
probably talk a little bit more about
lighting models in a bit but even though
we only did a very simple thing which is
just like a specular and a diffused
coefficient if we wanted to make the
world appear a little more varied in
terms of its surfaces we could already
do that just by allowing the parameters
on the phone model to vary per surface
rather than having every surface need to
use the exact same Phong parameters
right so for example if we wanted this
to cube to appear very diffuse and this
one to appear very mirrored all we would
have to do is change the coefficients
for the final model between the two of
them and you would immediately see a
difference there right now we can't do
that because we have no way of varying
the parameters per surface we don't
specify any kind of additional
information with the services that would
allow the game in the renderer to know
what kind of surface it was looking at
right so that's one thing another thing
is that we don't really have any idea at
the moment how we would do like more of
them right we just hard-coded a simple
Phong reflection model into our shader
we don't have any idea how we would you
know do something more like ten lights
20 lights 30 lights we could make a for
loop in the shader right it loops over
the constant store and the
door has that many lights entered or
something so there are criminal
extensions of it we could do but you
know is that really going to be an
efficient way lot to do our lighting is
that feasible or is that going to be
cost prohibitive and so on so that's
another thing and then finally we also
obviously have no indirect lighting so
we're only computing lighting from a
particular light source where the light
source shining off of something there's
also some ancillary things we can do for
example now that we have lighting you
can see things like radial banding where
the color fidelity isn't high enough so
differing there would improve the visual
quality of that for example so there are
some other like cleanup kinds of things
we can do but that has that's like
really a fairly minor thing compared to
the other aspects of it which are kind
of more critical right you can ship a
game with banding but you can't ship a
game with one light mmm I guess you
could but it'd be kind of questionable
so we kind of get a start to attack
these and obviously you know we don't
want to spend in an infinite amount of
time working on the lighting because you
could write lighting algorithms are
still an open area of study you know
every new triple-a game that comes out
or I should say engine for Triple A
games that comes out whether it's you
know unity or unreal or if it's one of
the more custom ones like frostbite or
snowflake or snowdrop or whatever that
one is from Ubisoft blah blah blah
they all have ways of doing lighting
that vary dramatically right like
everybody comes up with new ways to do
it in fact I even like it it tech engine
the new one for Doom
did a totally like you know new take I
mean it was not totally new take it was
like a consortium of the chequered like
like gridded voxels rendering
that you break up the scene into sort of
like small pieces and render them
separately so that you can break down
what lights contribute where and stuff
like this so you know every time a new
engine comes out or there's a new
upgrade to the engine
lighting is something that's typically
improved or is a very least changed to
attempt to find like sort of the holy
grail of like it just magically works
she put lights in the theme and they
like the scene the way life light scenes
and you know none of them is perfect and
none of them quite works right they all
have drawbacks or weirdnesses or things
but they keep getting better and so
there's kind of just an infinite
sinkhole there at the moment that you
could go down in terms of how you know
what you want to do to try to make the
best possible lighting for any game
regardless and we're not going to try
and do that but we are going to see you
know what could we do that's something
reasonable here that would improve some
of the aspects of our lighting so for
example one of the things that I think
would be probably useful for us to
explore is rather than getting our
lighting from something like a piece a
single vector in the cosmos or of the
shader that just says this is the
location of the light what we would
rather do is have some sort of a way of
producing lighting information in the
same way that we produce our actual like
the actual game information for review
and that is to say that we have a
pipeline now that we can use to render
things right we have a pipeline we can
use to render the game world and we are
rendering the game world it would be
probably advisable to do something in
that system that allows us to render the
lighting of the world and what I mean by
render the lighting is produce some kind
of intermedia
get lookup structure that allows us to
query what the lighting should be at
various places in the world without
having to recompute the lighting in its
entirety so for example one very common
way of doing lighting these days is a
method called light probes and let me
sort of give a brief sort of idea of
what a light probe system looks like and
then you can hopefully see more what I
mean about creating an intermediate
structure so uh here we go so I make
sure my Milton is working and it is here
we are in day 391 so let's talk about
light rendering so one of the things
that we haven't talked about yet right
is we sort of talk about the basics of
lighting we gave this sort of you know
discussion about like alright so we have
these surfaces and the surface has a
particular normal and there's all this
sort of light that's incoming to the
surface right all of this light is
incident light on the surface and that
light is collected if the surface is not
transmitted so you know you can have
services where light comes from the back
like a rice paper screen or glass and
light from the back comes through right
but if we're talking strictly about
reflective surfaces at least for the
moment we're talking about a hemisphere
here of light that comes in so there's
you know if you if you looked at it in
three dimensions instead of two
dimensions there's a hemisphere of light
here where every direction conceivable
on the front side of the surface life is
coming into it and similarly there's an
entire hemisphere of light that's
bouncing out of it right and fortunately
for us all we really care about for
the individual pixel that we're
rendering not the world because the
world will meet we care about how the
light bounces around its entirety but
all we really care about is that that
one light bounce that goes out towards
the camera from that particular location
on the screen right so what we want to
know typically speaking is for all the
incident light across the entire
hemisphere right what actually bounces
out in the direction of the eye now
obviously you can get extremely
complicated versions of this and if
you're talking about a more forward
scheme like a sorry backward scheme like
a ray tracer where we start here and we
come out we hit this point and we go oh
let's collect samples at by shooting out
from the hemisphere into various places
and see what we get it's a little more
easy to understand how you might take a
reflectance function so some idea of how
the surface is supposed to behave
where just light bounce from into in
some kind of coherent way it's a little
more easy to understand how you might
implement that because you're literally
doing the operation of the reflectance
function just in Reverse you're going oh
I come out to the surface I hit a
particular point I can then go out and
sample the light in various directions
and I could pick which directions I
sample based on how I know that surface
reflects light if it reflects a lot of
light from over here in that direction
but not much from over here I can take a
lot of samples in that direction right
and furthermore for every sample I take
I know how it should be weighted because
I know how what the reflection
coefficient is for that bounce right
because I usually have something called
a brdf or something or BRS
I think there would be SSDs there's
there's all kinds of Nimes names to this
but by a bi-directional reflections
distribution function I believe is this
one
bi-directional subsurface distribution
function is this one which allows
bouncing in here and stuff like this I
don't know this might be BRS SPF I don't
even know it doesn't matter the point is
there's a bunch of four-dimensional
and people even take real services like
they'll take these real services and
they'll put them in a thing called a
doneö reflectometer or other kind of
like ridiculous machine designed to
measure their reflectance and they
actually come up with transfer functions
that say for each individual incoming
light Direction sample at some
discretization here is what the outbound
light you know in what other direction
is so it's really the four-dimensional
function you can active transference
right so you can actually simulate real
services this way by saying here's the
actual way that this surface reflects
life and I'll actually simulated in my
renderer by going what's the incoming
angle what's the outgoing angle use the
coefficient of transfer that we actually
measured from the real world right so
that's like you know the the sort of
ridiculous high end we've got a render
node cluster rendering these things and
we don't care how long it takes we just
want to produce a really accurate image
right well you can do that but the
question becomes I want to now do this
in a game and I want to do you know I
want surface properties in a game in you
know if you're somebody again like let's
say you are the the team working on
something like you know frostbite or
unreal one of the higher end rendering
engines what you're trying to do is
basically this you know you still want
to have these surface parameters that
give you something like a brdf that's
actually been sampled but maybe it's you
know not quite as detailed as that it's
more approximate like you print you know
you bake it down to some reasonable
number of parameters that kind of just
shape the reflective functions so it can
be fit to real data or you know
approximate the kinds of real services
that you commonly have in games and you
know you you can come up with some
reflectance functions that make sense
here but the question is well what do
you do in the rendering context because
you don't necessarily have the ability
to shoot Ray's around anymore that's not
a thing that the graphics card necessary
is going to do and then there are some
systems that even try to do that right
like voxel cone tracing renderers for
example do this it's not ray tracing is
actually not not not done these days
because GPUs are so nuts you might
actually do something that allows you to
do that you don't tend to do it the same
way that a strict Ray trader does those
tend to use things more like KD trees
for acceleration and stuff like this in
this case you're talking about something
that needs to be handled in a forward
process so you're talking about
something that usually works more with
voxels something that the GPU itself can
produce for acceleration structures in
terms of lookup but all that being said
despite those facts the rendering
process still might do some ray tracing
in there we're not going to really
consider that because that's going a
little bit to banana cakes like I sent
down that rat hole you can go down it
and people do but you know we're not
going to go that nuts so we're talking
about a more traditional version of the
render here where we just want to do
some kind of forward rendering but we
want to be able to have our surfaces
perhaps do something a little more
interesting here so what we Ori did is
something that kind of looks like a Fong
reflectance model and what a following
reflectance model does the following
reflectance model assumes a couple of
very drastic I would say and rightfully
so for the era in which fog was created
because remember we're talking decades
ago when computing power was very even
offline rendering was very limited and
you couldn't go nuts with things flan
makes a very important simplification
that's very drastic and that
simplification specifically is that
while it does not really simplify the
concept of the eye much we're still
talking about a point I source a lot of
the times sometimes you get a little
more complicated where you have a lens
aperture but you're still it does the
eye is usually not the hard part unless
you start talking about four-dimensional
like motion blur kinds of things stuff
like that so assuming the eye we're just
talking about stationary eye
a point approximation for an AI doesn't
lose you that much
especially not with surface reflectance
and so when we take a look at the eye
here and we're talking about this
approximation
yeah we're approximating some things so
first of all we're not taking into
account the fact that the eye is really
a lens that focuses a cone to a point
and we're not talking about the fact
that that focusing process actually has
depth of field to it stuff like that so
we lose some effects at the eye but in
terms of service focus we don't lose a
huge amount
other than that cone but what song does
in terms of approximation that's so much
more drastic than probably what we would
want is it assumes that the light is a
point right and I'm not talking about
just the light meaning a light in the
world I'm talking about it assumes all
lighting incident on the surface comes
from a point light source and even if
you want to extend it to multiple point
like multiple lights you're talking
about multiple single points of light
and the reason that this is such a
drastic simplification of the lighting
model is just because most surfaces get
their look from the fact that light
comes from a tremendous array of sources
around around it you know most surfaces
are going to get at least fifty percent
of the light that you see coming off of
them from indirect light because you
know light sources tend to be very small
and they tend to be very few whereas
that light even though the light source
is very small bounces all around
something like a room for example and
you know it will mean that any
individual surface that's trying to that
you're looking at is going to be getting
light from so many more places than just
the actual light source itself never
mind the fact that you've shrunk that
light source from an actual shape to a
point the real simplification here is
that you're not collecting light from
everywhere else right
and this goes double for outdoors even
though this
is the closest thing to a point light
source you're probably ever going to get
it's very small
from our perspective right like yes the
Sun may be huge but from where we can
see it it's really tiny and it's so far
away as to be highly correlated so like
it's light is almost directional right
so it's kind of easy to extract it comes
late start however the atmospheric
scattering being what it is in the earth
the light actually during the day comes
from a huge canopy of blue a you know
sort of light white whitish blue sky
dome right it's a big hemisphere of blue
that's lighting up the world I and so
again there really is no circumstance
that you ever really look at you know
you'd have to construct a really strange
sort of flashlight holding kind of a
thing to really get anything even close
to what a fond lighting model is going
to give you specifically because it just
doesn't take into account the sort of
broad reception of light that you can
get from the the way the real world does
its lighting so that's the really huge
simplification that you get with a fog
light model and the problem that we
would have in handmade hero is if we
want to move past that we would need
some kind of way to take the you know
take the hemisphere of light that's
being ignored by the fog model and say
if we want to step up to something
better
the problem here is not the fog model
per se it's that simplification of the
fog model and that simplification of the
fog model is what gives us the ability
to compute it with just the with the all
the information being where the light is
we have no other information than just
where is the light so if we wanted to
step up from that we now need
information about what the whole
hemisphere of light is right what's all
the light coming in across small
hemisphere and once we have that
information we could even just use
something like a fog light model and
take lots of samples and produce perhaps
a better result so the actual concept of
a diffuse specular coefficient or
something fat with a fog lighting model
that's not so bad necessarily what the
really the thing that makes it look
really unnatural and weird is less that
although that is important to have more
robust ways of shaping reflectance
certainly what's more important is the
fact that we're just not taking into
account how the light flows around the
scene at all and all that that
hemisphere of of input so one thing we
can do in terms of storing and looking
up that information there there are some
interesting ways we can do that the hard
part is going to be figuring out how to
produce those in the first place for a
game that is generated on the fly right
but let's talk about that for a second
so what would we do if we wanted to
improve this lighting model by you know
ignore the the lighting model so for a
second but just say we know we're going
to move away from something that treats
life as idealized point sources and we
want to move towards something that has
more sort of global information about
the in radiance a light at a particular
point in the world that we're trying to
simulate the lighting and the answer
there is that like there are some simple
techniques you can use
I mentioned light probing and that's
probably the easiest one and it's really
easy to describe what that means is well
let's assume temporarily and again this
is the hard part of the problem for
something like light probing so it's not
a easy thing to assume but we'll talk
about that second let's assume
temporarily that you could do something
to calculate the lighting but it was
pretty expensive and you certainly
weren't going to do it per pixel what
would you do if you could afford to say
do that 20 or 30 times but you can't
afford to do it 1920 x 1080
time's right so you can do a few
determinations of what the lighting
might be in a few places but then you
can't do it everywhere right so what
would you do well light probes are one
way that people have a taxes problem and
they're pretty straightforward they rely
on what I always say is the most
important equation in all computer games
linear interpolation and how they work
as they say okay suppose I'm looking
down for game world here you know here's
my hero and I know the hero is going to
move around the screen and I need to be
able to life the hero no matter where
they go and I also need to light
everybody else so you know we've got the
little snake dude who's coming in here
or whatever and everybody needs to get
with coming into it well let's say we
have enough horsepower to compute what
the lighting Hemisphere and that sort of
stuff would be at you know let's say 12
places right well what I can do is I can
scatter those 12 places in a grid
like so right and if I scattered these
places around and I compute what that
lighting is going to be at each
individual place what I can do is I can
produce some intermediate structure for
storing it and in this case because GPUs
tend to have this built in they usually
use a thing called a cube map now you
can use other sorts of things like
there's a various ways of storing a like
spherical harmonic style reduced
coordinate versions of lighting there's
others all sorts of things you might do
but one thing that's very common is the
sort what's called a cube map a cube map
is literally a cube with a texture map
on each of its faces so it's really it's
just a glorified way of saying I have 6
square textures and the only thing that
makes it a cube map per se rather than
just making six square textures is that
it's fast to do lookups into it based on
a normal so basically the the computer
graphics hardware before it was more
programmable nowadays you could write
your own cube map look up function so
it's really not a big deal but in the
old days it was a big deal because they
basically put a special reverse Hardware
just to do this and it was to say that
if I have a normal that's pointing in a
particular direction I can figure out
what pixel I get or textile I should say
on the feud map so it will look at which
direction the normal is pointing
whichever face that would have hit if
you started in the center of the cube
and went out it picks that face and then
it picks the pixel but it would have or
Texel it would have hit I should say for
textile because it will still do a
bilinear sample if you want to right so
it can smoothly do it but that's a cube
map very simple concept it's basically
those six textures you can look up in a
special way and the interesting thing
about this cube map is that this cube
map is a good way to store the inbound
lighting at a point right because if I
take a particular point and I rendered
the world let's say I literally just use
my same
graphics pipeline to render the world in
each of six directions I would get an
image that told me the inbound light at
that point right and then I can use
these cube Maps to light something so if
somebody's right here I can do a
bilinear sample between my cube maps
right I would simply say what is each of
these cube maps say the lighting is in a
particular direction
if I want to know and then I just buy
linearly filter that based on where I
ambulators the cube maps and now I've
got interpolated lighting it's not
perfect but it's useful right it can
give you a proximate lighting when you
can afford to compute the lighting in
certain places but not everywhere right
and furthermore if you want to if
depending on your circumstances if you
have additional knowledge you can
leverage that additional knowledge
meaning that if you happen to know
places where the lighting changes a lot
you could put more cube maps down in
that area I could more densely put them
here for example if this were an area
where the lighting was very finicky and
I could leave them sparser over here
where the lighting is maybe not so
variable maybe there's no real there's
no light sources over here for example
maybe all the lights are over here and
so the lighting changes a lot in this
area but over here it's just kind of
smoothly decaying so you don't really
need to know much about it right so
that's you know one example and you can
see why that's that's kind of useful
because basically what it does is even
though that can be kind of expensive so
obviously producing all these cube Maps
would be expensive it is a way of
reducing the cost down to a fixed number
right so you can just say how many Cube
apps can I afford to make if that number
is 16 well I put 16 down and now my
performance is consistent because it's
only 16 x cube mapping whatever that
amount of render and cube map is and
then I know I always have a constant
time per pixel from then on no matter
how complicated the lighting is it's
never going to produce more
complicated per-pixel lighting right so
that's a pretty interesting way to kind
of look at lighting in the world
certainly and it's a pretty simple
caching mechanism right it's a way of
sort of caching what the lights doing in
various areas and then reusing that to
predict you know to sort of up sample it
so that it's as if you kind of had it in
all the places but you don't have to
actually compute it in all the places
will it be accurate no will it be good
enough probably now the interesting
thing about this though is that it
doesn't solve the problem completely
it's just a step in solving the problem
it's a way to cache intermediate
lighting information that the useful
might be useful for us some handmade
here us useful be aware of this kind of
game certainly and why does it only
solve part of the problem well part of
the problem that we have here on
handmade hero is we don't have a pre
pass so a lot of times where you'll see
light probing being used it doesn't
solve the problem completely right you
know if you have a game ask us today it
might be that that solves completely why
is that solve the problem completely
well because you have an offline step so
what will often happen in a more simple
renderer for example is that the level
designers create levels those levels are
baked offline and some scheme that
actually does accurate lighting
computation produces cube maps for these
light probes so for example you will go
okay done with the level baked the
lighting it'll go around dropping cube
maps down it will do a raytrace render
to calculate what the lighting is at
each textile in the cube map using some
kind of a ray tracing scheme and then
when you go to run the game you have all
the information you need you just got
these cube maps that tell you what the
lighting is and the only problem is you
can't really do dynamic lighting with
that so you have to compensate by adding
the dynamic lighting in somehow
now but since those are usually minor
for these types of games which have
usually don't have that many moving
light sources or if they do they're like
explosions or things that don't actually
super accurate they're just temporary
that solves the problem right because
the offline version can just use
whatever slow random ray tracing thing
you want and the online version just has
the cube maps that it needs and that's
all good the problem with our situation
is we don't have any ability to do
offline lighting so we still have the
problem of how to produce the lighting
in the first place and this is a real
problem it's a real problem because we
don't know what the lighting of the
scene is until we create the lighting of
the scene this is the eternal problem of
ray tracing it sounds like a circular
statement but it is a circular problem
the statement is accurate what do I mean
by Matt well ok let's think about this
for a second I've got two surfaces there
in the world here is surface a and here
is surface B right and I just said what
I want to do is I want to create a
hemisphere of incident light so that I
can light this surface properly and hey
guess what I also want that over here
right
I want a hemisphere of incident light so
I can figure out what the lighting of
this surface is in any particular
direction
well I start by saying ok I'm going to
create that for surface a I need to
create a hemisphere of incident light
let's see what the incident light is in
this direction
well hey guess what in that direction
the light comes from light reflected off
of surface B ok what's the color of
surface B what colour light and how
bright does it reflect in that direction
that's the information I need to know
right well in order to do that I've got
to produce a hemisphere of light let's
produce a hemisphere of light well in
order to produce atmosphere of light I
need to know what light came in from
this direction what light comes in that
direction well it's whatever a reflected
in that direction
okay let's compute what a reflects in
that direction in order to do that I
have to produce a hemisphere of light in
order to produce atmosphere of light I
have to know what light is incident on a
for example in this direction and it's B
na NB n a and B na and it wouldn't even
ever terminate right so one of the
classic problems of light transport is
very specifically that because the
real-world activity of light is a bunch
of photons that bounce around the room
ad infinitum until they hit something
like an eye or a camera or get absorbed
by a surface it's incredibly difficult
to produce the initial lighting for a
scene because it's a very dynamic highly
diffusive process that really defies any
kind of exhausted computation you cannot
simulate the lighting for a scene in
reality photon tracing just doesn't work
there's been scheme to do it but it's
just it's way too expensive the number
of photons you have to shoot and so any
photon scheme that has ever really done
anything useful massively approximates
the photons in a lot of ways right so
what we need is some way of producing a
very approximated solution that is still
related to the actual solution that
involves this sort of infinite bouncing
of things around and infinite's the
wrong word it's not really infinite
because obviously photons don't bounce
around forever eventually they get
absorbed somewhere but if you ever have
held two mirrors up next to each other
and seen the sort of what appears to be
an infinite copy of images well that's
how many times those photons were
bouncing back and forth right so while
it's not infinite in the real sense of
the word infinite it's certainly
infinite related to today's computing
power because when you think about how
many billions of photons there are or
trillions of photons that are bouncing
around the scene and the fact that some
of them may bounce hundreds thousands I
don't know millions of times
before they're absorbed I don't know
what's the average life of a photon is
in that sense from a light source but
it's a lot this it's just it's a
completely intractable problem in terms
of the computing resources we have so
what we're typically trying to figure
out is what are approximate algorithms
we can use that tend to get similar
results as what would happen if you
bounced all the hotels around like that
but but absolutely in no way involved
bouncing those jumps around like that
and so the typical way that these are
solved offline is always what are called
Monte Carlo schemes and Monte Carlo
schemes that it's called Monte Carlo
integration and really obviously Monte
Carlo refers to sort of the gambling
aspect of it but really all that it
means is they're randomized integration
schemes what randomized integration
schemes are is they're saying well ok so
I've got some function that I know is
simply impossible for me to actually
compute right so for example in this
case we're talking my integration we
have an integral right over a hemisphere
and we know that there's no closed-form
way to produce that integral we can't
even sample the integral densely enough
forget it because at every every
function that goes out from the
hemisphere itself bounces around on
hemispheres so the dimensionality of
this function is just huge is to forget
right there's no way we can even
consider solving it directly so don't
try and what these schemes you know the
reason that they're called amount of
concentration schemes is because what
they do is say well ok if we have
something that's too high dimensional
for us to really solve we can still take
randomised samples and combine them in
ways that produce an approximate result
and that's what
pretty much all high end rate racers
these days are they are all Monte Carlo
integration schemes and they range from
incredibly stupid such as pure Monte
Carlo like pure random selection of rays
with only a slight buy the only real
modification being looking at the
lighting equation for the surface and
biasing in directions where the lighting
contribution is going to be the highest
right that's about it
so those are like kind of more pure
Monte Carlo pure random I should say
integration schemes all the way to ones
that are actually incredibly
sophisticated and complicated to
understand such as metropolis light
transport or metropolis manifold tracing
things like this that involve very
complicated analysis of how paths behave
and how we can assign probabilities and
properly combine probabilities along
those paths to produce the highest
accuracy integrals that we can and know
that will always converge to a fair
solution no matter how many samples we
take and bla bla bla bla bla right so
there's a wide range of these schemes
that they all boil down to basically the
same concept which is that we know we
can't actually sample the function
densely enough to produce an answer so
instead what we're going to do is
randomly sample it and we'll just try to
come up with schemes that put those
random samples to the best use possible
but that's all we're doing right so that
tends to be how these things are worked
out and so the answer to the question of
how do you solve a problem where the
light bounces around infinitely the
answer is you just kind of use a
termination criteria so what will
typically happen in this situation for
example is what you'll say is all right
let's pick because of the the Montecarlo
nature let's pick a number of bounces
ahead of time out of a hat sort of if
you will right so we'll say that this is
going to be a 7 bounce pass right we
pick 7 out of a hat
random number why did we take it out of
a hat
well if we didn't pick it out of a hat
we would be biasing ourselves towards a
particular number of bounces which will
affect the lighting solution so if we
want to try and produce a fair lighting
solution we need to pick everything
randomly right and this is an
interesting aspect of Monte Carlo
generation that I'm not really qualified
even to give you a good explanation of
it I don't study probabilistic light
transport and it's a very touchy field
so I it's easy to think you wrote an
unbiased Monte Carlo integration
renderer and you didn't so I will leave
that kind of explanation for the
exercise simply say that you need to
study this stuff a little more carefully
and make sure that when you are
producing a ray tracer of this nature
you have to really understand where you
might introduce bias into the system
bias of course will then produce you
know brighter or darker images in places
and things like this because you have
biased towards a particular type of
solution that is not really fairly
sampling the high dimensional integral
in a truly random way because the truly
random way of sampling it of course will
not bias it it will produce on average
the correct result this is why we talk
about you'll often see is this an
unbiased or biased right renderer and
these are terms used more or less
exclusively in the offline or some some
of our not our kind of sort of off-white
like Brigade from octane for example is
a real-time ish ray tracer that uh sorry
not from what they call their hello toy
OTO why I think octane is a real-time
ray tracer for example that is tries to
be I think largely unbiased I don't know
if it actually succeeds what I think it
does but anyway so these things are uh
are used largely because in the offline
world you actually care about converging
reasonably after some number of samples
to a solution that correctly
approximates the light on average a bias
render will not necessarily do that an
unbiased renderer will the way to look
at this probably and this is kind of
getting a little off-topic here
certainly but if you imagine I'll give
you a case here's two graphs suppose
that this is the brightness that a
particular pixels would be in either
case so this brightness is some number
of lumens right some color value
whatever it is if I am a unbiased
renderer then as I take samples to
produce my solution for a particular
pixel my my lighting value looks like
this right my lighting value sort of
converges on the correct sample on
average so as I take samples they're
going to be you know and is that's
probably the wrong way to do it right so
as I go through this I'm going to kind
of narrow in I'm going to start off kind
of wrong and then as I take more samples
I'm going to converge on average towards
the correct solution right on the other
hand a bias renderer usually looks more
like this right eventually we'll get to
the correct answer but it starts off in
the wrong direction and is never going
to be on the other side of the wrong
it's never going to be wrong in the
other way so it tends to be wrong like
strictly undervaluing or strictly
overvaluing the lighting contribution at
a pixel and then the more samples you
take it may eventually converge to the
right result but it will
always approach from one side now you
may ask why you would care about this
the reason you would care about this is
because if you look at an unbiased
rendered image because you know that
you're taking random samples and you're
going to go like this
a rather the two random samples are
truly distributed around the the
lighting of the of the point what you're
going to see on the screen is a true
representation at all times of the
lighting it's just going to be very
noisy and as you take more samples the
noise will go away so you'll start with
an image that looks like the correct
image but it's very noisy and it will
get less and less less noisy why because
any two neighboring pixels while they
will both be quite wrong at the
beginning they will be quite wrong in
opposite directions potentially right
and not only in opposite directions but
different magnitudes right because
you're all over the place on the other
hand a biased version will just be like
a really over bright image the whole
image will be over bright or the whole
image will be dark and then it will get
brighter as it goes right so at no time
until the final convergence will you
ever really see an accurate version of
the image the reason this is kind of
nice is because a you can stop at any
time and have an image that looks sort
of right it's just much more noisy than
it should be and be it helps pretty well
with previewing because even the first
thing that comes up on the screen after
very little computation time with an
unbiased render is at least sort of
representative of the overall image
lighting right whereas this one may be
nothing like it you may start the render
and it appears like you can't see hardly
anything at all and it's way too dark
like ah should crank up the light values
but in reality if you'd let it run to
completion after seven hours it would
have been quite bright and fine that's
not something that will happen with an
unbiased renderer right all right so
again sorry to get too far off topic
there just was try to like touch on
various subjects when we talk about
things so that people who are interested
in various s with us know that the stuff
out there that they can go read about or
find out about it
something that sounds interesting to
them okay so you know given that we've
got this situation let me go back to
what I was really trying playing which
is how do you how do you break this
problem like how this seems kind of some
you know like a relatively intractable
problem how are we ever going to fix
this infinite bounce nastiness of not
knowing what to do
well Monte Carlo sound sells this rather
nicely by saying we'll just pick a
number of bounces ahead of time who
knows what it is it's just any number
about this does not matter and then what
we're going to do you know here's my
services in the world here's my camera
or whatever is we're just going to do it
right we're just going to say all right
send it out that's a really bad light
ray there we go send it out right bounce
it around when I pick seven right so
seven one two three four five six right
there's my light pass and now I'm here
and I know that this will be a seven
bounce pass so what do I do now I go
where is an actual emitter right where
is a light source and now trace to the
light source and now I have picked on
that seventh bounce I've connected it up
I've connected the AI with the light and
can compute a lighting contribution for
this path right so that's the way you
break it is yes these things can bounce
around forever
but if we pre pick ahead of time
basically a kill number where we
basically say after this number of
bounces we will specifically target the
light source and see what's there that's
the way that you break that cycle
now again doing that in a very in an
unbiased way can be very difficult
because the fact that you're picking
intentionally something is the light
source at some point can be rough but
again you know that's sort of a separate
topic of study
similarly enough they can do is at every
bounce you can check the light source so
I could say every time I hit a surface
let me see what the light source would
contribute to the surface
we'll add that in then I'll do the
bounce and then I'll do the light right
and I'll keep doing that for every
bounce I'll figure out what the lytic
contribution is for the partial path as
well right and so in this way you just
build up a collection of light path
contributions throughout the scene and
that gives you an approximation to what
the light is actually doing that is good
enough for full lighting now if you want
to see these in action again because
we're not writing a one of these because
we can't actually really write one
because we need something that runs in
real time unreasonable hardware but you
can take a look at say Maxwell render
and octane render here are some sort of
more state-of-the-art offline renders
and you can take a look at what they
look like I don't know if there's a good
you can you can kind of see the kinds of
images they produce here obviously I
don't know if we've got me here well
here's a demo oh wait no oh
so you can actually try these I guess
right I don't even know what this is
going to do this is probably going to
crash my machine I don't really want to
do that I would rather just see a video
here let's see if octane render has a
youtube video let's see here
go ahead and just mute the sound here so
here's somebody running octane render on
a machine that's really beefy right but
you can see that you know it's pretty
fast right here's Tim pushing the or
whoever this person is going over they
are pressing the render button and yeah
you could you can see them kind of drag
the scene around right and you can see
that you know with that kind of GPU
power it computes the lighting pretty
quickly and you can also see like I was
saying how it kind of like it starts off
pretty noisy and then converge a little
bit I don't know if this is an unbiased
render it looks to me like it starts off
a little dark obviously so it might be
more of a bias render I'm not sure but
you can kind of see how an offline
render works and with that much GPU
power you can also see this it's not
real time but it's close you know it's
like maybe 1/10 real-time or something
to produce an image right and so that's
pretty good Maxwell render is is less of
a real-time in that sense it's more
about accuracy and I don't know if we've
got a Maxwell render video I don't know
if we've got one here
let's see you next year under 4.1 let me
see if there's a video of that happening
let's see I don't know there's pride I
don't know if there's anything
particularly good here for Maxwell oops
I have videos I want to have a YouTube
good be Maxwell render 4.1 all right
let's take a look here all right or we
could just watch an ad for something
instead okay here we go I yes you can
see here like this is they've got sort
of a preview window thing going here and
onofre getting good shots of them
actually rendering
yeah I don't know well point being you
can go find these yourself and most of
them have demo versions as well so you
could probably download them and play
with them but I don't want to waste any
more time like looking for good videos
of them point being there are plenty of
rendered renderers out there that are
this way there's also some free ones
I don't think indigo is free anymore
indigo used to be one that was free and
there's one that's kind of crappy called
cycles that's built into blender for
example that was lastly also free it's
real bad but it's free but you could you
know take a look at one of those as well
so there's a lot of stuff out there that
you can look at if you're more
interested in learning about sort of
this sort of light propagation stuff and
you can read papers on it there's
hundreds of papers every year written on
this topic because light transport is
just a tough problem and it gets easier
every year is they give us more and more
CPU and GPU power to play with thanks to
Hardware adding more and more cores
light transport is a very parallel
parallelizable problem so it becomes
very nicely - huge amounts of flops
which is why GPUs have been such a big
boon for it and you can get things like
that octane render where you're kind of
almost real-time like transporting
around fairly complicated light
transport certainly awesome but all that
being said that is the offline version
and unfortunately unless you are doing
it you know if you're working on a your
own product at home that might be very
relevant to you because you might be
able to just do a little offline Monte
Carlo a pacer that can produce a totally
reasonable thing set of light probes for
your game and then you're done right and
incidentally I believe that's pretty
much how the witness' worked I didn't do
the renderer for the witness that was
Ignacio Castagna did it so I don't
really know very much about how it works
but I believe it was a light probe based
renderer and the way that it did that
was it produced light Maps for surfaces
and light probes using an offline ray
tracing process I don't know that it was
exactly ray-tracing I think it used GPU
acceleration to actually just render
successive versions of the scene or
something if I'm not really sure exactly
how it did it because again I didn't
write that part of it but it was offline
so it basically produced light probes
and surface lighting offline using
basically a light map baking machine a
light probe generating machine and then
during gameplay it would sample from
those offline produced results to give
you the final render and plenty of
things worked this way right so that's a
very common technique but it's not
really going to work on handmade here
because we don't have a pre pass I wish
we did but we don't and so we have to
come up with some way of producing some
lighting without the advantage of being
able to spend a lot of time producing
that lighting in an offline scenario so
we have to do something that propagates
light around our scene online and
whether or not we use something like
cube maps to store the result we need
some way of producing something
reasonable right so what we need is
something that you know takes n light
sources bounces them around some degree
and produces approximate in radiance at
places right that's what we're looking
for we want to be able to throw some
light sources into this bonus points if
those light sources can be creative like
sky dome right but if they can't oh well
you know point light sources you can
always just the fungus can handle a
reasonable number of them you can always
approximate most lighting by just
throwing in more point oh we need to
throw some light sources we need to sort
of diffuse themselves and then we need
to be able to produce some kind of
approximate idea about how the lighting
is working at any particular point right
and I don't have a pre I don't have any
kind of like preconceived idea about how
this should work in a game like handmade
hero the sort of bounce is the hard part
I think taking in a bunch of light
sources and just rendering from the
light sources isn't particularly tough
right it's not particularly tough
primarily because if we just rendered to
you maps directly like every frame or
every few frames you know update our
cube map sort of gradually or something
if we have to uh even if you had like a
thousand lights in in there I mean how
hard would it really be right rendering
a thousand light flaps into a cube map
is trivial I mean that's you know a
thousand little you don't even need
texture samples to render a light source
because the light source is just a
little point right I
so you know something where we're just
renting a bunch of lights into a cube
map is pretty easy I think and so
producing that element of it is
shouldn't be too hard the hard part is
the bounces and the bounces are
problematic primarily because I they
involve this sort of traversal of the
scene right if there's one thing that a
GPU is awful at its traversing a scene
why is it awful at it because we added
we would have to send the scene down to
it in the first place which you don't
really want to have to do right and yet
we have to send the scene down to it and
it has to do a bunch of like
intersections and searches through JIT
which exactly it doesn't want to do like
like GPUs hate traversing memory
randomly they like having everything run
in a very like methodical consistent way
I'm always sampling from nearby stuff
and whatever right so GPUs actually hate
ray-tracing it's like their least
favorite thing typically so the bounce
is a problem now one thing that's
interesting and I'll point this out is
that in general it's usually possible to
turn to turn if to transform if you will
a aerial lighting problem into a point
lighting problem just by using more
points right and what do I mean by that
well let's suppose that we take a very
very simple scenario I want to know
I've got like a cube or something that's
floating above a giant plane and up in
the sky there is going to be a Sun of
some kind
find shining down right and I know that
I can compute the lighting from the Sun
very accurately very easily because
again it's sort of a point light source
it's sort of easy to deal with we
already did the phone version there you
can imagine us doing sort of more
creative things with it it's not very
complicated when you're just talking
about one point of light and so the
question is well what if I wanted to
extend to this scenario to include the
backscatter
from this plane so this Sun is also
shining all on the plane maybe this
plane so the Sun let's say is yellow the
plane let's say is green and so we would
expect to see some green under lighting
on this cube so like down here it should
be kind of green the underside surface
should be almost completely green
because the only thing can hit it is the
bounce light of the green so we want to
see a yellow top green bottom right
something like this well one thing that
we can do is say all right before we
start let's shoot a few rays not too
many maybe 10 right maybe 50 not very
many shoot some rays out from the light
source and see what they hit wherever
they hit we will add a new pretend
temporary light source with the color of
whatever the reflected light is from
that surface so it's basically just
produces a bunch of point light sources
from a single point light source we then
light the scene with 50 point light
sources and we're done these will all be
green so this will see a bunch of green
light sources this will see the yellow
light source and and that's that's the
end of it right so you know there is a
right of way to sort of turn a
complicated lighting problem that
appears to involve more than just point
lighting
is something that only involves point
lighting and so you know that to me
sounds kind of enticing because what I
could do for example is every frame on
the CPU I could do some ray tracing to
spread out my lights to various parts of
the scene in a sort of homogeneous way
and then I could treat each of those as
a point that I then render into my cube
maps and as long as I keep that number
like I said to something saying like a
thousand rendering even you know thirty
or forty cube maps of a low resolution
when the only thing I'm rendering into
those cube maps are some points seems
pretty doable right now there's a little
bit more to it than that and and so the
you know it's not quite as rosy a
picture as I painted and the reason that
it's not quite as rosy of a picture is
because in order to make the lighting
work in in a way that implies shadowing
which we would like and we don't have to
again we're you know we're not trying to
be a Pixar movie here we're not trying
to light the scene in a 50 hour
offline render well they don't allow 50
our offline renders out like a Pixar but
12 hour of line render we don't want to
try to compete with that but we do want
to capture as many lighting elements as
we can and one of the useful ones is
occlusion of the light sources so for
example if I have in this same scenario
let's suppose that I did something
slightly more complicated but again
still not particularly unusual so you
can easily imagine the scenario in which
it exists suppose I have a something
that's just a simple thin here and then
I'm talking about the lighting on the
cube
with the Sun so all I've done is I've
split my plane in half and now what I'm
going to say is this side is red this
side is green right and this is yellow
right and I really don't need the fin in
fact really I probably overcomplicated
it here in a large to large extent let's
just say it's just two things a red and
a green well now I would expect this
side this underside of the cube to be
more red this side of the underside to
be more green in the middle it should be
more of a wash right because you know
especially this side of it is really
only seeing the green it can't see the
red at all so this should be more green
and the famous tree over here this one
should have some red contribution the
bottom should up the competition from
both right so in that scenario right you
can see why it's important to do some
basic occlusion now one kind of
occlusion is just the hemisphere
occlusion so for this scenario it's
sufficient to simply say well only
sample from the hemisphere that would
get me the occlusion that I want right
but now if I go and I add the thing that
I was talking about let's say I put in a
blocking plate here right and this is
black it doesn't reflect light at all
right now well that's a bad example
because the lights coming from this
direction okay I can't quite do that
here's the blocking plate here right so
now this blocking plate doesn't
intercept the light at all the light
still Falls everywhere it would have
because this blocking plate is just
under the cube
well now the underside of the cube
should get much darker right and the
closer I move the blocking plate to the
cube but you get extremely dark because
it can't see hardly any of the light but
if all I was doing was rendering these
point light sources into the cube maps
or or just leave and forget to Maps no
matter what I'm doing if I'm only
considering the point light sources and
I don't see whether the point light
source has occluding geometry in between
it
won't pick up that shadowing effect
right so in that scenario I've got a
really nasty problem which is that while
it would be very efficient to like do
something like produce cubemap strictly
from point light sources what do I do
about the fact that my surfaces will
intercede now the interesting thing
about this is it may still be for a game
like handmade hero that it's actually
okay if you actually just wanted to
produce the lighting by rendering all
the services and all the point light
sources every frame it might still work
why because there just aren't that many
surfaces right and most of the problem
that we have right now is the fact that
we do def peeling that makes the cost of
a render four times more than it should
be there would be no depth peeling and
producing the lighting because remember
we're not trying to get pixel accurate
transparency or anything like that we're
just trying to get an approximation for
the light furthermore the cube map
doesn't have to be particularly high-res
the cube map could be 64 by 64 128 by
128 a drastically smaller size than what
we would be using to render the actual
game and so really the only problem that
we would have is the fact that we've got
sprites in the world and we would have
to sample from their textures in order
to correctly produce the occlusion
necessary for you know the fact that
things are silhouetted we could even use
that if we had texture atlas so we may
have to go to a texture atlas to do that
if that makes sense because in order to
get the speed up for something like that
we can't be switching textures every
quad like we are right now we know that
that probably has to go and it would
definitely have to go once we're doing
even more passes than we are right now
because of things like the lighting but
this is a pretty reasonable scheme right
I could convince myself that this would
produce a fairly read
results and you know I don't know it
seems like something we could try
basically did the algorithm is pretty
straightforward right it's just scatter
point lights throughout the world based
on wherever we think they need to be for
the current simulation steps gather up
all the light sources in the region
let's say that's 100 multiply that
number by like at least 10 by just
shooting 10 random rays out from each
light source and seeing what they hit
and sticking a light source there and
then rendering those into cube maps
that's the entirety of the scheme right
and so we could take that a set of of
lights we could you know again push it
through as as points that render it to
these cube maps and then we would just
sample our lighting from the cube map
that that'd be it I you know would that
work I have no idea it's purely me just
randomly guessing about something that
could work I have no idea whether it
would be efficient or not it could be it
might not be we also could consider ways
that are more reverse than that people
actually do sort of like weak radiosity
origins there we have a weak sort of ray
tracing in the on the GPU as well and we
could do something like that one of the
advantages that we certainly have we
don't have very many primitives so doing
something like voxel cone tracing on our
scene would not be very difficult
probably I'm guessing because there just
isn't a lot there so I don't know so
it's possible that that maybe is a more
sensible way to do something like that
because that's something that operates
entirely on the GPU doesn't actually
are any CPU participation whatsoever
however like I said I don't know the
accuracy of something like voxel code
tracing can be kind of iffy because a
voxels are very expensive
three-dimensional things eat up memory
very quickly and eat up processing power
very quickly much more so than 2d things
and so you do end up in a situation
where something like box eco interest
and can be pretty tough to get not
working in any reasonable sense because
specifically because of that nasty cubed
element of everything that you do so you
know again something like that might be
more sensible because again we do have a
very low primitive count because we're a
sprite game so it keeps the number of
things we're doing much more bounded and
presumably you know we would have more
flexibility there to do something like
voxel eyes things or whatever else we
might want to do to them is not going to
be as costly but I don't know
it's a tough call because I don't really
want to like I said I don't want to
spend a huge amount of time going down
the path of like doing lighting I just
want to do a scheme and then say that's
the lighting and we'll just you know it
might have some drawbacks that we use it
and so I don't know which scheme is the
one that's going to be the most likely
to succeed reasonably and you know that
normally the course of action that you
take when you're working on a render as
you try a bunch of things and you pick
the one that seems to work the best
that's not really an option for us here
so we kind of have to make it get a good
guess ahead of time hmm
[Music]
well
I guess one thing that I could say is
that there certainly is some
attractiveness to using a system that
doesn't involve the CPU or rather
doesn't involve the bifurcation of the
renderer into two parts one part that
does the light propagation like ray
tracing in this case and another part
that does the actual rendering which in
this case would be on the GPU so a
scheme where we rasterize the light and
then use some kind of sampling from from
that rasterization like something that
is voxel cone tracing esque
certainly seems attractive right like
because that allows it to be
compartmentalized in the renderer which
also allows people who want to do a port
of hand made hero that is to a platform
that can't afford to do anything
particularly nuts
you know they could basically cut out a
lot of that stuff in the port whoo-hoo
so you know I feel like there is some
there there is some architectural
niceness to saying the renderer does the
lighting and it doesn't however it wants
right so it's hard for me to say but
that that does seem kind of attractive
so it's sort of a lighting scheme that
just sort of did something on the GPU
that rasterized the light into some kind
of a lookup system and then from there
produced you know whatever the the
whatever the approximate lighting
version is uh but yeah it's stuff I
can't really think of of I can't really
think of what the right way to progress
is I know that for example on like a
little big planet they did something
like that Alex Evans I believe is the
fellow's name who did the render for
that and they did something that was
kind of a scheme on the ps3 that did
lighting in sort of a rasp restaurant
that was not full voxel Cohen tracing
but that sort of did a similar situation
I don't remember
this is not what I wanted can I go to
scholar.google.com there are more for
that no it's probably no one's written
the paper on it yeah
[Applause]
well let's put it this way there is a
lecture out there by Alex Evans on maybe
I could stew it plugs and then Red River
lecture me that would work
so
this might be what we want
although except same Alex Evans
I guess what I would say is I feel like
we kind of want to we kind of want to
have some idea of what we're going into
first yeah okay so it is
this is a this is a 20 great slide has a
lot of that
so this is yet this is the thing that I
was talking about the thing about for a
little bit clinic because like I said
you know we we have sort of a similar
situation to LittleBigPlanet in a lot of
ways we don't have really long view
distances for example we're just talking
about a couple of slices at the level is
all we ever look at and it's pretty
clearly bounded and so you can see here
like they're talking about sort of the
box going to kind of approach they have
volume textures that they store the
licen I talked about this a long time
ago on handmade here and so they kind of
go through like okay so they yeah so
they talk about irradiance places and
they basically say like okay I these are
some I like how these are like draw them
look like magic marker or some things
and I like that a lot
so basically what they do is they take a
light source and they slice the world
into slices based on light source and
you know that's basically going to make
a box where it's going to make a 3d
thing of information about the light and
you can see that like what they do is
they say well alright I want to
basically store a lighting information
into these slices so that I can
accelerate rendering and not have to
actually trace lice around now how they
do the actual tracing I'm not sure let
me see here so here you go
render a front and back z-buffer for
each slice so that's basically taking
the the range like of the figure out
what's in that place right of as far as
geometry is concerned
and minimax these are tracing today is
just a matter of comparing lots of Z's
okay I see so they're basically just
saying like okay we're trying to retrace
in a slice
we can write directly to volume textures
so we can probably avoid some of the
hassle here find the nearest point in
the slice volume and sample will become
more efficient abuser Othar doe
so that all makes good sense except yeah
like they were saying there that's for
one light which isn't really going to
help us so I'm kind of interested to
know here's a surface function
so this is more like what we want right
we are sort of 2.5 D and this is sort of
talking similar to what we were talking
about where we're saying like yet you
know we could do cube maps in here some
like this based on a grid an example
from those or who knows what
so this is their technique which is
different from this we're going to clean
up slides GPU at low resolution based on
pictures are some good light emitters
yes that's what exactly what we want to
do computing in screen space also seems
reasonable I see here added the
composite these visual aids on by
intersecting it's oriented very much of
the slice of the volume okay that's
pretty easy to do they're just saying
like blob in the light sources to the
volume that we're tracking dependence on
direction of the irradiance at a given
point is off from sort of use for
Akamai's okay so we could get into
something like that it looks like they
did something even simpler which is
which is not even sure if our Mac they
just have a basic like a basic idea of
the light contribution see here
this is just figuring out how they're
actually using the gradient but that's a
little bit more specific so that's
pretty cool right like
and we don't care too much about shadows
right like again occluder is this sort
of something we'll have to think about a
little bit but
but yeah I mean that's the kind of thing
that I'm just thinking like I don't know
if we went down a road that looked more
like that it seems like maybe that's
smarter thing to do because we do know
we can kind of slice the road up
relatively predictably
and it's fairly confined so producing
the lighting in that sense if we did
something that was more about Surrey
environment I think I talked about this
when we originally talked about lighting
way back when on handmade hero talking
about propagating light around in the
grid I just wonder if that might be sort
of a more feasible way to do it than to
try to do something fancier and I don't
know I it's really hard to say you now
know basically all I know about like
what we maybe should should or shouldn't
be doing and so I don't know if we
should just flip a coin about what we
try it what we end up trying haha it's a
good question and like everything else
right it's annoying because the only way
to know which is the right solution is
to try everything and see what ends up
being the most cost effective for you
know getting good results and not being
too you know compute-intensive
so I don't know I really don't I don't
have I don't have a good plan it feels
like one of those flipper coin kind of
situations and I don't know if there's
any way we can really narrow down any
further I like the idea of feeding life
as a volume and I like the idea of box
realizing things I just don't know how
well it works out in practice you know
one of the things is if we were to take
let's say a you know fairly high res
sample of the world so let's say we took
a ten
four by five twelve or something sample
of the world right and I don't know how
much information we'll need in order to
store some useful lighting information
in that that's but that's a very
high-res version so let's say it was you
know still we're still talking about you
know maybe four bytes per sample there
so that's going to be let's see that's
going to be what two megabytes per slice
of a thing and so if we wanted to do a
certain number of slices through the
world even such a high resolution what
would be the you know what would be the
cost for that kind of thing well you
know we could afford quite a few slices
at that point like let's say you wanted
to spend 256 megabytes on lighting which
is not a huge amount we could do it that
would give us 128 slices through the
world which is a lot of slices right so
it seems to me like the voxel izing
techniques just just
back-of-the-envelope the problem would
only be if if the computation was too
expensive in them because it really
doesn't seem like the memory is going to
be a problem for what we're doing right
it seems like the memory for what we're
doing would be fine so you know it might
be that something let's just take a look
here let me see what we would have for
if we were to do something like box with
on tracing
oh my goodness this is not a very fast
server is it it's run a pretty fast
connection here this is a one gigabit
connection here but that is I guess it's
from France maybe it's got to travel all
the way around the world right
so if we were to do something more like
this where we actually kind of you know
went went nuts you know this kind of
technique is it's kind of amusing right
so the idea here is that you know if you
are to produce something that's
relatively seems kind of expensive voxel
wise right so let's say that we produce
something of our world that was like
1024 by 512 by 128 or something right
the idea is well once you produce
something like that you can then pretty
cheaply filter it down right to submit
map versions so you can then do you know
when you have a 1024 by 512 by 128 one
you can then do your 512 by 256 right by
64 one and your 256 by 128 by 32 and
your 128 by 64 or 16 right and it
contracts down each time and so what you
do when you talk about sampling the
lighting for something like this is you
can kind of sample everything that's out
in a direction light wise by just
sampling from successively lower res
versions of the voxel you know because
tracing through the voxel would be way
too expensive per pixel but we could
take only a few samples one really close
to us one further away one further away
from that that are from higher and
higher coarseness or I should say lower
and lower resolution to do something
reasonable like that right I and you can
kind of see like they get good results
for things like this it's a bit finicky
of a process but yeah so you can see I'm
just this is the part that I want to
look at so if you want to do indirect
illumination here I what's interesting
is I really don't know I've never I
haven't read this paper and implemented
or anything so I'm curious to know what
they do for indirect light I I guess so
it says here the computer a location of
a point light is more involved in it we
use a two-step approach first we capture
the incoming radiance for light starts
in the leaves of our senior Association
storing incoming radiance not outgoing
will ask to me like cloud services we
filter industry distribute the incoming
radiance over all levels of our octree
finally we prefer approximate current
ratings to make light transport writing
the incoming radiance in the actually
structures complex therefore we will for
moment assume it's already present in
the architecture before detailing the
process all right so where is that here
we go a very simplified explanation
we'll consider that our oak tree is
complete so that we can then launch one
thread per leaf dude okay we'll perform
six passes blah blah blah
just remember levels at this point we
have coherent friction a simple solution
would be to launch one thread for each
Fox will the higher level officiated
from the lower level nonetheless
advantage for shared voxels blah blah
blah
so I'm not sure without reading some
more detail I really know exactly what
they're doing here but it sounds like
what they end up doing is the volume
transfer what you can kind of see the
diagram here actually the volume
transfer is kind of just like a
propagation through the octree so you
kind of like take services and you splat
it looks it is basically photon tracing
right in fact Harry said after photon
flooding you just kind of like propagate
a little bit out to give you some amount
of bleed and off you go right and I
assume they did this in a somewhat
multi-resolution fashion but I don't
know
so you can see here what they do is they
take the light position and they
basically treat the light as they render
the world from the light source and
treat that as basically like a where to
sort of shine where to sort of speed the
lights into the voxel right
so I feel like we would want an approach
that's simpler than that just because I
feel like that's going to really be
fairly demanding that's going to require
Atomics even so yeah it's really tough
to say
so I want to get a decision by the time
we end the stream today because you know
I walking through this process and again
the reason I include this on the stream
is just because this is what actually
happens when you're doing game
development right you have to make
decisions like this like I said the
decision here probably would be we want
to try a couple different things and I
don't really want to do that but just
thinking it through despite the fact
that it seems like there's more
information in the area of sort of the
spreading splatting LittleBigPlanet
Boskone tracing kind of thing I feel
like I actually like the point light
propagation model a little bit better
and the reason that I like that model a
little bit better is it just feels more
coherent to me like the voxel thing
feels a little too imprecise and I feel
like I would constantly be wrestling
with the discretization of that voxel
and what gets stored in a particular
node in like ways that are problematic
so it kind of feels like to me doing
something where we've got you know where
we've got those point lights seems a
little more st. in and the first step of
the voxel cone tracing process is
basically that step that I described
before totally without having looked at
the voxel under thing which is that
taking the light source and splatting
out point lights is actually the first
step of their process that the photon
feeding right that they were talking
about so that step has to happen one way
or the other and so to a certain extent
I feel like I might want to start with
the idea that that's going to happen
regardless so we're basically going to
produce a series of points and we're
talking about how were then going to use
those points but at the beginning we're
going to produce a series of point
lights one way or the other
really it would seem and so when you
produce that series of point lights it's
really a question of what are we going
to do with them after that rendering
cube Maps was one option and then the
other option is well we do something
more like the voxel or the splatting and
that would basically say we take those
light sources and we splat them into
some kind of a volume texture and then
we we sort of let the volume texture do
something interesting in terms of
propagation and so my question is is it
worth that does that actually get us
something or are we just wasting our
time and we should have just rendered
cube Maps everywhere
or if not cube maps then something else
right should we just render some other
thing that captures what those point
let's our lights are actually
representing and again it's kind of hard
to say
but I feel I feel like if we can produce
those point lights relatively quickly
and who knows maybe the right answer is
to produce those point lights in more
the fashion they were talking about but
for example I'm not really sure how they
how they do something like a skylight at
that point because the skylight you know
I know exactly how we would do a
skylight with our scheme are they
suggesting that if they were going to do
a skylight in the voxel code racing
world they would have to render from
many different points on the skylight
and then feed the light out that way
that seems rough to say the least I
don't know that that would really work
it seems like that might be cost
prohibitive whereas rate racing from
different points on the skylight is kind
of a more constant time manageable
process right
so what way
suppose we were to CPU raytrace light
propagation
and generate to generate point life okay
to render cube Maps at low res
throughout world and let's say we maybe
do something like you know 64 of these
three render um so look at those two
scuffs I don't think they're that
complicated right and I feel like
furthermore because we keep textures on
the CPU side anyway because we want to
support software rendering and that
doesn't seem prohibitive expensive
because CPUs always have more memory
than GPUs anyway and we don't use that
memory for anything else so keeping the
textures on the CPU side doesn't seem
problematic so when we trace we will
know what color we hit so CPU ray
tracing doesn't seem to be something
that would be prohibitive especially
because we don't have that many
primitives in the scene so I feel like
the biggest stumbling block here is what
is the acceleration structure because
right now our world is not really sorted
into anything that we can Ray trace into
particularly coherently you know we
don't have them sorted by anything
particularly convenient I guess we've
got world chunks and we can keep the
world chunks relatively small and maybe
that is sufficient but I don't remember
what the actual size of those world
Trump's are so maybe that's good enough
maybe the world chunks would be
sufficient to keep the computation cost
down but that would really be the
question there would just be you know
how Spencer would that be right
producing the point lights from that
process then is pretty straightforward
whenever we have a hit we just sample
the texture and we produce the point
light color based on its reflectance
right based on its color so that seems
pretty straightforward rendering the
cube maps at that point is real easy you
just take the array of point lights and
the current scene geometry and you
render it with the z-buffer
and you let it occlude that's about it
where I don't think there's much more to
it than that and that would produce the
cube Maps
so the real question is just is there
enough GPU power to render you know
these these cube maps and I guess yeah
like I said we would definitely have to
have a texture atlas or something it's
not going to fly with the number of
texture changes that are in there now
but that's not you know an impossible
thing to do we could we could just use a
texture array and be done with it so I
don't know that seems like what I would
probably say is the best approach to
getting some reasonable lighting without
too much this is the only thing that
scares me a little bit about it is I
don't want the game to have to do a lot
of work maintaining a separate
acceleration structure in order to do
the the raytrace acceleration but
it might be that since we've got the
world chunked up already that's the
vision because there just isn't that
much stuff in it but I don't know so I'm
going to go ahead and go to the Q&amp;A
you've heard my thoughts on this kind of
my just exploration of it and so if
you've got opinions on it or questions
about it
now would be a good time to air them
because tomorrow I will probably start
coding something so if you have a
notable objection or idea that needs
considering now is the time to get it in
there before the typing begins
MTS mocks says don't we already need
acceleration because the lookups for the
closest traversable is already slow yes
but unfortunately and this is the this
is the eternal bummer right is that the
acceleration is a different kind right
and so maybe this is why I'm saying like
maybe it turns out that they can be the
same because if the world chunks just
work for both of these or something then
maybe it's fine but the problem is that
one is a closest point query kind of a
thing
and one is a line query right I so in
the case of wanting to accelerate the
closest traversals which we definitely
want to do what we're looking at doing
there is saying well okay we've got the
world jumped up in some way a straight
up voxel ization of the world that just
deals with chunks will just work because
we know we just want to search for
whatever is in the closest area right so
we know this will work for that just
fine and that's all we want to do and we
already sort of have that so all you
have to do is actually start to preserve
it in the same region when we bring
things into some region we want to keep
that but for line queries is a little
bit different because line queries want
to do this sort of thing and they need
to be able to figure out what's the you
know what's the thing they will first
hit and so the problem with that is that
if you have a voxel ization and the
first thing you're going to hit is way
on the other side of it you're
traversing like tons of voxels to get to
the answer and it ends up not being
particularly um it ends up not being a
particularly fast solution right and so
the question is just will that kind of
solution be fast enough
and if it isn't great because like you
say we know that we will be taking
advantage of some acceleration structure
probably something based on the world
chunks because we're already packing and
unpacking things from them so we'll
probably just keep things we pull them
in the sim region will keep them
arranged in a spatially coherent way but
the question is just does that produce a
fast enough line query and I don't know
but even if it doesn't produce the best
online query we may still be saved by
the fact that perhaps we can put
something on top of it that does so that
we don't need to acceleration structures
we just augment our existing
acceleration structure with one more
thing for example we might put a
secondary layer on top of our of our
grid our world grid that's a little more
like an octree so four nodes four times
when there's just empty space there will
record the bigger empty space nosov it
so that the raytracer can skip through
it what are these called as they have a
name can't remember the name so there's
a name for this process where you
basically have a world rid let's say
like we will have and I need to draw a
fairly dense one here to get the point
across
right so we got the world oh you know
what now I think about it
this works in 2d too so there I can I
can make a simpler diagram for you I
forgot this is this is not something
that requires the full volume to
understand how it works so the idea here
is well okay I'm going to write trace
through a grid the slowness of ray
tracing through a good comes when you
don't hit something so if I start my ray
trace here and I start tracing through
the grid if this cell contains the thing
I hit right that's great because I'm
going to get the answer right away the
problem comes when there's nothing in
that area and I end up having to go all
the way out here because now I'm looking
through 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 ish I
don't know how many they're exactly to
be something like that 11 fells for the
answer which is a lot of iteration right
and so what what acceleration structure
you can use for this is to store
basically empty space specifically so in
every cell that doesn't have something
in it you store a sort of you don't have
to do it per cell you can do it as sort
of a separate region on top which is
basically just you store cubes or I
should say not cubes right rectangular
prisms so like rectangular shapes in 2d
that are empty and you test against
those as you pass through them so you go
here you go oh I hit this thing I know I
can skip all the way to here and start
my ray tracing there which stops you
from mapping to consider any of these
cells because you already know they're
all in the empty area so we might be
able to pile something on top that
doesn't really conflict that's just an
augmentation of the data structure that
would allow us to do the ray tracing
faster on it right so it's entirely
possible that we could do something that
it just builds on the stream scheme that
we already have so that we don't have
two schemes which starts to get a little
long in the tooth
my opinion if we have to have one for
our closest point queries and one for
our rate racing if that starts to get
like how many explorers detectors are we
really going to have here folks
right so that's something
Jerzy says why not use a single distance
field I assume you mean signed distance
fields but I'm not 100% sure if single
distance field is a thing I don't know
what it is but if signed distance field
is the question why don't you just use
scientific fields there best for line
queries sorry a bit of context just
joining the stream so yeah that's a good
question scientists and fields obviously
are pretty popular in like the demo
scene right and they have kind of a nice
process that they're relatively easy to
raytrace through because at any time you
can figure out roughly how far away you
are from the nearest surface so you know
how far you can step along the Ray
without hitting anything right and just
for those of you who aren't familiar
with these I'll I'll sort of give you a
little bit of a breakdown actually I
guess I don't really want to draw it
quite that way so I'll just pretend this
is a very dense grid right so let's say
that I wanted to retrace and let's say
for sake of argument because it's the
easiest thing to talk about in a signed
distance field let's say I've got some
spheres right so I've got a sphere
that's sitting here and I've got a
sphere that's sitting here and I've got
a sphere that's sitting here right and
now I want a ray trace and this is what
I'm doing so I'm looking from here and
I'm looking that direction so obviously
the thing I'm looking for is the Ray
trace of that sphere right I want that
intersection point well if I take a look
at this I could say all right if I
wanted to produce some kind of a
acceleration structure of this I could
produce a signed distance field
acceleration search for a grid and we'll
see in a minute that you can actually
get rid of the grid entirely but I could
say for any particular point I could
imagine computing what the
distance is to every object in the scene
from that point and storing whatever the
one is that's the closest right so at
this point in the grid right at these
points in the grid I would say oh well
the closest thing in this case is there
so this this the point in my textile or
whatever would be that distance right
and when I got closer to say to this one
which was here it would be that distance
right so at every point in my texture or
my volume or whatever I would just store
the distance to the closest object now
what would happen is when I look and say
okay I want to start retracing from here
I would look up into the textile at that
location and say what is the closest
thing well the closest thing is like
probably that far away which means I can
step that far along the Ray right and
now I can do it again what's the closest
thing here well the closest thing here
is there okay can step that far along
the Ray and eventually I look in the
signed distance field and I find the
distance is small enough that I no
longer want to step any further I'm like
I basically hit something right I'm
close enough to an object that I can
consider it ahead right so that's how
sinusoidal works and the nice part about
them is if you have surfaces whose
distances can be computed relatively
efficiently you don't need an
acceleration structure almost at all
right you can use a very simple binning
to just kind of go what objects do I
need to look at but for example here if
I just have three spheres rather than
ever computing any kind of grid or
anything I can just say well whatever
point I'm at just compute the distance
to each of the three spheres right and
it's exact now it doesn't have any kind
of discretization or anything and so at
that point you end up going well all
right now I just have an acceleration
structure that lets me know which rough
objects I need to consider the reason
I'm not a huge fan of slime distance
field is that they tend to
a kind of special case like it's sort of
hard to do polygamous things of signed
distance fields in a particularly useful
way because you end up having to do the
polygons sorting into some kind of
acceleration structure anyway at that
point it's unclear why you weren't just
ray tracing it right and the same person
suggested KD tree afterwards and I guess
what I would say is the the KD tree is
the primary way you accelerate ray
tracing and what I was trying to say
before is that's the part I don't like
about this idea is I don't want to have
two KD tree my scene just for the light
propagation step it feels like adding a
lot of complexity KD trees are what you
use for ray tracing acceleration
normally you don't typically use sighing
distance fields scientists and fields
are usually if you have very special
purpose kinds of shapes not polygons Kim
Jorgen said shouldn't we get the frame
rate to reasonable range before adding
more complexity how do we knew our
budget but our frame rates excellent
right now isn't it what's wrong with our
frame rate this is this machine is like
what eight years old now at this point
seven years old something like that and
if I compile our game in you know a
release
configuration the I'm pretty sure the
frame rate is totally usable right like
I mean I what's wrong with that frame
rate would be my first question like
what what do you feel like you need to
fix I'm pretty sure we already run at
six
frame the second we definitely run it 30
even in debug so I'm not sure what the
problem with the frame rate would be if
that makes sense
are there obvious visual differences in
these different lighting methods well I
mean yes and no so all of them are kind
of approximate and it's hard to know
what the differences will be a parent in
any particular game without doing it
especially a sprite based game like
handmade arrow is pretty different from
the kinds of scenes you typically would
see these lighting models tested on so
we're a bit in uncharted territory to a
certain extent because we don't even
have 3d geometry so I'm not really I
mean the cubes are but the rest of it
isn't so I really don't know what the
visual quality difference would be
between them Valdis I'm not planning on
putting in shadows I don't tend to like
hard shadowy looks I like the softer
kind of just sort of ambient lighting
look so I only care about light
occlusion like we talked about already
but like hard shadows I don't want so
those will just be baked into the art
assets as a little like ambient
occlusion kind of ground thing that's
there but I don't want shadows in the in
the hard shadows sense so that I am just
not putting into the renderer in any way
if that makes sense
Illume e25 do you know if your
broadcasts have inspired improvements in
popular game engines out there um I
don't know I guess what I would say is I
[Applause]
you know certainly for something like
rendering the answer is definitely going
to be no because we're you know they're
doing stuff that's way more complicated
and a 3d based than what we're doing but
I guess what I would say is I I have
heard from experienced developers who've
seen stuff on the stream like the
dynamic code loading or stuff like that
our loop-de-loop like coding stuff for
example is what common one occasionally
we will do so technique that they had
not thought of or something that they
then go and do I don't know that that's
led to any improvements in game engines
like unreal or unity or something like
that I have no idea but you know those
are probably going to be few and far
between because this is a very
educational scroot stream and most of
the time I would suspect that the things
I talked about are things that
experience engine programmers should
already know and so the chance that I'm
covering something that they have not
already had to do is not high that would
be what I would say so once in a while
we do cover something that kind of may
be something that that is a little bit
more special in that sense but that's
the rare case right and the sorts of
things that we could do on the show that
might be pretty interesting like you
know building with a build dot bat file
very quickly and architecting the game
so it's a very hard separation between
the platform layer in the game layer or
things like this a lot of those are
things that you know modern engines
can't even do at this point because
there's
so overweight and massive they're like
these you know 3 million lines
monstrosity and so either they thought
of at the beginning and it works that
way or they didn't and they ain't fixing
it now
right so you know architectural things
we may do on the stream that might be
particularly good or better than average
I think there's a pretty limited degree
to which that can have an effect on an
existing engine because either they
already knew how to do it well and it's
done well or they didn't and seeing it
on this stream ain't going to help them
because they're already so far down a
tangled path that it would be very hard
to untangle
valve booths so all of this is still not
a physically based rendering renderer
correct so we are not trying to do any
kind of physically based rendering
physically based rendering is trying to
take into account the actual laws of
physical light transport you know the
way in which photons actually have to
behave to conserve energy you know for
now sorts of stuff a spectrum crowd
criteria all these other sorts of things
we don't have any of that information in
our assets anyway they're just
hand-painted cartoon sprites so
physically based rendering makes like
almost no sense at all
for something like handmade hero so what
we want is not physically based
rendering but we do want some of the
physics of rendering to come into play
to give us a nice look right and that is
why I care about things like bounce
lighting and I would like those things
to be in the game the reason for that is
because they lead to a softer satisfying
look that's more like real light we
don't need to simulate the real physics
of light because our art is itself
impressionistic and is not meant to look
realistic but we do want the ability to
get some of the physical aspects of
light because they produce a nice look
for the game and bouncing bounce light
is one of those things right so yeah
it's important to draw a distinction
between a completely physics based
renderer which is one that every stage
has to take into account the real
physical behavior of the light and
cherry-picking certain aspects of light
that are important to how light
skills and looks but not hat but leaving
other parts of the physics of light out
write a proper physically based
rendering into account throughout we are
talking about taking specific aspects of
the physics of light and using them but
only those aspects that we actually want
all right I didn't hear but so Kim you
didn't post again though so did you talk
about that what you were at like what is
the frame rate problem that you were
talking about did you have something
particular in mind or
I just I just haven't seen that follow
up on that so I don't know I was curious
nothing
concurrences really slow on my opt-in
debug mode did you look to see though if
that has anything to do with the
rendering right and if so is it just the
texture changes because right now we
spend a lot of time in the texture
changes if you run on a modern Nvidia
card which has no cost for texture
changes it's like a very flat profile
for rendering actually it's pretty good
as well and old PCs I don't really care
about particularly much either right
it's like you know we can set our
minimum platform to whatever we want yes
but if your question is more how do we
know our budget the answer is that we
don't and with rendering you never do
right so one of the problems with
producing rendering it renders in
general is you don't know what the cost
will be for a scheme you have no idea
that is why renderers are you know what
makes them difficult is there's a lot of
trade-offs you could make and there's a
lot of approximations you can make and
there's a lot of schemes you can use and
you don't know ahead of time which one
of them is going to be the one that
produces the best visual quality for the
time budget you can afford and so that's
why you use if achill II have on a game
somebody working at least one person
oftentimes more than one on rendering
for the entire time because
experimentation is the only way to
produce a good quality render on modern
hardware right there is no way to know
ahead of time here's what we can afford
to do for lighting
we have no idea right and we don't know
what the slow part of that lighting
process will be maybe it's the ray
tracing
maybe it's the rendering of the tube
maps maybe it's just the act of doing
the changes of the render targets to
target different cube maps and how many
things we render doesn't matter it's
time to cube master your render that
matter
and like all that sort of stuff is just
really difficult to ever know without
trying you can make guesses but you
can't know so I'm really talking more
about hey here's an example of a letting
scheme let's try it if it doesn't work
then we'll back off or if it's too slow
back off but I don't think it will be
because we can always just say well you
know if we need to we just have a switch
that turns off lighting effectively and
if you're running on a really crappy
machine turn it off if you're running on
some key ports Titan machine you turn it
on right so it's a PC there's a wide
spectrum there's no chance that what we
do for lighting will be so slow that a
high-end PC you can't do it because
high-end pcs are orders of magnitude
faster than the thing I'm using right
now all right
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for an episode of handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
at home you can always peer to the game
on handmade hero or again it comes with
a source code so you can play around
with it yourself we also have a form so
you can go to to want to ask questions
we have a patreon page you can go to if
you want to support our video series a
schedule bot that tells you when we're
going to be live to want to catch us
live and an episode guide where you can
catch up on old versions of the series
if you had a topic you wanted to go
catch up on it's really easy to do now
they've done a great job putting in
search in there now so you can actually
go search for different topics you want
pretty awesome that's about it for today
I'll be back here tomorrow same time
same place for starting to play around
with that lighting stuff we'll see what
we would have to do maybe try to figure
out how to get that ray-tracing working
to produce our initial seed set of point
light sources that seems like probably
the best thing to do until then have fun
programming and I'll see you on the
Internet
take it easy everybody