hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here the show Rico to complete game live
on stream we have to go put PNG reading
integrated into our game we already
wrote the reader and now our goal is to
sort of retrofit that into our existing
asset system which loads out of our own
file format and so what we want to do
now is support the ability to take PNG
files that an artist drops into say a
directory somewhere and import them into
our data files so that we know that
they've been processed and can now be
used as regular game assets in the
course of running the game you know as
normal so that's our goal let's see last
week we made an extension to our
platform layer to support our ability to
watch files and this is important
because what we would like to do
eventually is make it so that the artist
can just save a new PNG over an old PNG
and it'll just magically appear in the
game because that's generally what you
expect from like a hot loading system it
basically it's exactly analogous to how
we do our code right the way we do our
code currently is when you compile the
code the game looks and sees if a the
game DLL has changed and if it has it
just loads it in and runs with that
instead of the old one and that's
exactly what we want to do with our PNG
s now we want to make it so that if it
sees that there's a change we load it
but obviously we don't want to load
every PNG every time to see if there's a
change because that's going to be too
slow so what we did instead is made it
so that we can actually see what the
date stamps are on the p on the PNG
files themselves and then if we see one
of those date stamps change we then know
that we should look at that PNG to see
whether it the contents of it have also
changed we don't know when the date
changes that the PNG has actually
changed in any meaningful way right you
can do something you could open up a PNG
and resave it over itself but not
actually change the data so we do want
to actually compare the
when we load it in we probably want to
look to see if it's actually change
because if it hasn't changed then we
don't actually need to update the art
pack file at all but we do need to at
least look at it once the date changes
because it means that the contents may
have changed so the way to think about
the date is that the date is something
that is sort of a marker that just says
could the contents have changed and then
once we see that marker we then know
okay we have to go do further
investigation but it's not actually
telling us that the file changed it's
just telling it us it might have changed
so that's what we're gonna look at now
let's go ahead and and get started on
that so if I load up our current state
of affairs here what we did sorry the
project file what we did with our PNG
reader is we first of all extracted the
PNG reader into a useable chunk here so
now we've got sort of this bit right
here where you can call parse PNG
passage memory Reena and you get back
the image so that's been we did a good
job like pulling that out that's all
ready to go so now what we're just
looking for is when do we actually call
it how do we use that feature now that
we have it and the answer to that is
okay inside our asset system as you may
recall we sort of have this notion that
we at startup look through the assets
that we have you can see here we loop
over them and we create sort of like a
indexing of what the tags are for each
of our assets and that sort of thing and
that is immutable
it doesn't change for the entirety of
the run of the program and that's the
part that we need to expand now because
when we look in here right we've got
this game assets you can see we have
some set of loaded files we have some
set of loaded tags and some set of
loaded assets and what those are is
they're basically a raised we use to
look up into when the game asks for a
particular thing it jumps in there to
use it
now we have two distinct jobs now two
that we want to tackle to modify what
we're looking at here and the reason
that we want to modify what we're
looking at here is because in addition
to now sort of having an artist who can
work on the project directly we also are
in a situation where we know more
specifically what that artist is
producing so oops let me go in the art
director here so if you look for example
at some of the test art that we have
here that is you know indicative of what
we might see in the game you can see
that there is various structural
concerns so we have a type of image
that's just what a block looks like
right and you can see that like a block
has different components there's like
different sightedness to blocks and
stuff like that and so you know then we
look at something like a character and a
character has like a head and a body
right and stuff like this and different
facing directions and that's what's
gonna get added into the game now right
so we kind of know exactly what's being
put in there now we have two ways we can
go about tackling this particular
problem one is that we can just
translate those into tags right which is
maybe what we should do the other is now
we can also take this opportunity to
refine our tag system to more closely
approximate what it is we're actually
doing now because you know we now know a
lot more because once an artist is
making art assets for something we now
know a lot more about what's going on
right so we have we can sort of look a
little bit - we can
not try to say this we can envision
making changes to how the assets are
stored in something that makes it more
specific now and more efficient with the
tag system it's very generic you can do
whatever you want with it but it's more
expensive right you have to do matching
on values and it creates sort of a more
extensive process for the game to figure
out what asset you're actually talking
about and so we have to kind of make a
decision at some point whether we really
care about that anymore if we have a set
of art assets and we now are going to
just lock it down and say this is how
assets will come into the game then we
really don't have to worry anymore very
much about those assets being tagged in
arbitrary ways we can simplify that
system to a more direct indexing that
wouldn't require us to have tag matching
per se okay so I really don't know what
we want to do about that but it's kind
of a good idea to keep that in the back
of our heads now because we definitely
have the opportunity to change how that
works so that's what I would say all
right so let's move forward here
so if we take a look at the assets that
we're actually storing right now an
asset is defined right here it has a
state and that state has to do with
whether or not it's like what we've done
with it right so so if we do a live VSS
state here we can have something that's
unloaded something that is trying to be
loaded and something that is loaded
right and what that does is it basically
allows us to determine whether we need
to load it from disk or not when it gets
used right because if it gets if it's
going to be used we need it to be in a
loaded state if it's not in a loaded
state we need to do something about it
if it's queued we can just wait because
it'll will get loaded if it's not loaded
yet we need to queue it so that's our
you know that's the way the state works
we then have a memory header the memory
header I think probably can go away now
and the reason that I think the memory
header can probably go away now is
because all of our stuff is going to be
the same size now one of the nice things
that we did with now that we moved to
OpenGL is we can just introduce a
constant size for asset stuff we can
just I had Anna put them into fixed size
boxes so that we can do more reliable
memory allocation on them and stuff like
that so I think we can probably get rid
of this asset memory header idea in the
future I mean not get rid of the not get
rid of the information in here like the
total size and stuff probably well we
might be only over that as well but I'm
just talking about the fact that we had
to look at memory to reuse it in a non
direct free list kind of way
that stuff we can probably simplify
quite considerably now if we would like
so that's nice so anyway inside here
we've got this this asset it's got a
point to the memory header there and
then it's got the actual asset in
question which is this information here
and a file index as to which file that
came out of right so if it needs to get
reloaded that's where that would come
from so what we need to do now is start
thinking about how this is going to have
to change
so you can see here we've got first tag
index and one passed last tag index
right we really four in our first
attempt we really can if we want to just
not touch the tag system at all and the
reason for that is even though this
seems like a tightly packed system its
indirectly offset so what you can see
here is these are indexes not pointers
which means that if we wanted to when we
look at this tagger right here and we've
got a tag count in a tag array what we
can do is it startup allocate vastly
more tags than we actually need and just
leave Headroom there to put more tags in
so then every time we load an asset we
just blast tags in there right and so
that's a pretty straightforward way of
making the system expandable that
actually doesn't really cost us anything
and I know that that sounds a little bit
cheesy at first because you may be
thinking well if you were to do that
what happens if the artist is just
running the game for a really long time
and eventually they reload the art
enough times to hit the top of a tag
count well guess what
no one cares why because the game assets
could just be restarted right remember
we have a way already of just
reinitializing the art asset system at
startup it just looks through the files
and loads the indexes out of the files
right that's all it would have to do we
can just do that again and then we have
a nice tightly compacted tag set that
just is exactly the right number of tags
without we you know without having all
that dead zone in there right so I think
our main problem that we're going to
have is is not with that right it
wouldn't be with with dealing with
in-memory tag stuff I think the problem
that we're more going to have is the
fact that when we replace a particular
set of of assets that already exist
we need to reuse the tags from that
asset or remember that we
freed it to put other tags in there
eventually for the permanently stored
file so it's really updating the
permanently stored file that's the hard
part because that's the thing that has
to have the data actually correct now I
that and that's also like I was saying
why I think it might be nice if we had a
different way of indexing things since
we know that we don't really need the
tag stuff now I don't think based on
just the kind of our assets that we have
and we'll have it doesn't look like it's
super necessary so it may that's the
reason I say we may want to move away
from that going forwards just because it
doesn't seem like something that's
really necessary and it will create
headaches for us on for management I
mean you could just never deal with it
and let the tag array just get massive
but that's just you know that doesn't
seem very efficient and you're just
blurting things out for no reason when
we I think we could probably do
something better and the thing that we
would probably do better here right is
again it depends really on how we're
gonna use these I had originally
envisioned a system that maybe was a
little bit more arbitrary with how
things were loaded but looking at how we
ended up kind of going with it just in
terms of how the art wanted to be made
it seems like it kind of wants to be I
don't know it's I think that that we may
want to rethink the tagging from a
standpoint of rather than having a
collection of tags in that sense you may
just want to have more of a fixed set of
tags that aren't arbitrary and yeah I
really just don't know so when you're
picking something like a hat there's
just two parameters or three parameters
or something that define hat I don't
know when you pick them I'm not sure
again like I said it's it's really kind
of confusing to me how this is actually
gonna shake out and so we may have to
get a little further down the road till
we really know
but yeah anyway that's that's the
situation and we'll have to think about
it a little more so anyway that's the
only part that I think is going to be
particularly problematic for us there
where we're gonna have to start thinking
about things a little bit more carefully
so yeah we've got like yet we've got
these types here and these will now
start to reflect what we actually have
in the art in the art itself yeah anyway
so thinking about those tags is sort of
something I guess I my brain keeps kind
of going there and I don't know that I
really want to do that yet
but anyway now that I've got that all
out in the open and you can think about
it - I'm gonna go ahead and do the stuff
we actually know how to do and then
we'll come back to how we want to be the
tags which I don't think we know how to
do yet because I mean obviously we know
how to do any particular implementation
of it of we want it's not hard the
question is what is the correct design
for that that makes us have the minimal
amount of frustration for what we
actually want the game to query and it
may be that we just need to wait a
little longer and start doing stuff like
putting some of those little orphans in
the game and having you be able to wear
different hats and stuff and then when
we see what the code looks like that
does that in the entity system we can
have a better understanding of how we
actually want to query these things that
will be the least amount of frustration
for both sides of the system right we
want the entity system to have an easy
time saying what it's trying to do and
then we also want the asset system to
have an easy time managing it so we'll
look at it all that being said let's go
ahead and look at what we actually want
to do here so what we've got do you
think is the ability to loop over these
files
we have the ability to loop over these
files and we have you build to see
what's changed but one of the things
we're gonna have to do is keep a record
of what those were so at the very least
I know I'm gonna have to do something
like this where I have a file that I
know that I'm watching and I know that
I've got some date that's involved that
I can look at so if I go here to the
platform layer if you remember we sort
of made this platform file info here we
had this file date so I know that there
is a file date involved right and
furthermore I know that there was a file
name right so there was some kind of a
name that I was looking at there that
that I need to like be aware of right so
I've got something like this where we've
we've got a name that says what the file
is and we've got a date that says what
we think the last time the file in
question you know when we think that
actually was last changed and so then
what we want to do is we want to be able
to do something where we kind of check
these things periodically for updates
right so when we have one of these watch
files and got a base name and a file
date I can use something like this to
check to trigger it now I'm gonna want
to look it up on the base name because
that's what's gonna be coming back and I
want to match that out so I'm probably
gonna want something like this where I
just have a hash of the of the names and
I can look them up in there via some
kind of a string hash right so I can
look these up I can get information
about them as I go so when I have this
information and I do the watched file
stuff what I want to be able to do after
that process is I want to be able to
reload a file if it's changed so the
additional thing that this watch file
would have to have is it has to have
some knowledge of what assets came from
this watch file right so inside here
we've got some number of
that's those assets correspond to what
was in the file so for example if we
look at one of these files here at you
know I should load one of these
templates like this so when we load up a
PNG we've got something looks like this
and each of these squares is a different
art asset right so for example up in
here we have the rightward facing
default body leftward facing default
body and so on
right I'm sorry dodging left leftward
facing default body right blah blah blah
and then if you take a look at the
actual monsters and stuff that are in
here or whatever you know the whatever
are the various like things are that
you've got to go into that slot right
here's one that's a mummy again I don't
we have to look at these and something
that actually knows how to look at
transparency what the heck is this
alright I've never seen this program
before but anyway at least it handled
the transparency properly all right I
don't know who mate who makes an art
package that actually has stuff that
isn't in the art sort of like showing up
I yeah alright Microsoft was the answer
so looking at this and here you can see
like we've got the different bodies of
this thing but a bunch of them are are
left empty this is by design so when we
look at one of these things we don't
want let me get that template back when
we looking at one of these things we
don't want the artists to have to do any
more work than necessary for a
particular character so a lot of times
characters might just have say this part
here in fact sometimes if the character
for example doesn't have a head that
really turns there might only just be
one right look maybe there's only this
one so it might have all the bodies with
just that one or maybe just this and
this there might be only two in there so
every one of these squares is a
potential asset but only you know maybe
even just two or one of those squares is
actually required to make a usable
monster or something like that
potentially right because some monsters
may be very simple while others might
have more stuff in them right so what we
want to do here is we want to categorize
the we want to put these things in
categorically so that we extract the
squares put them into assets and we want
to remember for any given one of these
files we want to remember where we put
everything right that's kind of crucial
so what I want to do here is I want to
say all right we know there's
effectively a maximum because those
tiles there it's like an 8x8 grid right
the maximum thing is an 8x8 grid of
things so there's no more than 64 actual
assets that could have come out of here
so there's sort of an asset count if you
will but I'm not gonna even have an
asset count I'm just gonna say like
asset indices I'm gonna say there's 64
of them right
we can even say 8x8 if we want it to be
a little bit more specific about what we
were doing here and note which one it is
right so it's like X and then Y or let's
do Y the next cuz that's how we would do
it if it's pixels right and what I want
to do here is when we load in one of
those files and I look through all of
the squares what I'm gonna do is every
time there's an asset in one of them I'm
gonna record that so this will be all
zeros but initially and every time I see
want to record that I'm gonna say what
asset then takes that place right and
fortunately for me I think and I'm just
guessing here but I think our tag
problem is kind of not that big of a
deal here because if you think about
what's gonna happen anytime you look at
an asset the tags that go with that
asset are the same no matter
what square they're in in a sense right
that's and I said that exactly backwards
the tags that go with an asset are the
same for that square no matter what the
asset is that's what I was trying to say
and failing to say unfortunately so if
you yeah if you think about what that
means when you look at one of these this
asset here that's from this square if I
replace this asset with a different
image the tags don't change the tags are
the same so I can literally replace the
asset and just refer to the same set of
tags I originally added which stops the
tag bloat from happening pretty
conveniently right so that's something
good too
[Music]
that's something pretty good to keep in
mind right again I'm not sure we really
want to have the tags go down that far
because we know that this is a fixed
layout so in the future we probably just
want to use a fixed layout for it
and we'll have to think about how we
want to do that going forward but yeah
there you go okay so I think this would
tell us what we need to know so we could
look at a watch file we could say okay
if it changed these are the assets that
need to be replaced we loop through all
of the the new file any plate time we
see an asset we will put that asset into
place and replace the old assets
information with it and we can probably
use reuse the same asset as well so
that's probably easy to do I don't know
we'll see but when we take a look at the
asset itself let me take a look at where
that is here this is the wrong file
we take a look at the asset itself in
the case of a bitmap which is the thing
that we're working with here when we
look at the way this is stored it looks
like we just have a header that's the
dimension in the line percentage and
then we have the pixels that come after
it
so what we would need to do there for
the HHA bitmap
just thinking it through is when we look
at the asset it's gonna have this stuff
here
oh it no it doesn't nevermind data
offset tells where it goes yeah so it
looks like the main problem we would get
there is that the data offset would have
to potentially be changed but again the
nice thing here is if all of our assets
are the same size and we store them
uncompressed at least during development
like we could try to do compression on
them later when it comes time to ship
but when we're just during development
we can leave them uncompressed if we
want to if we leave them uncompressed
that means that any asset that replaces
another asset came from the same
location in the bitmap file which means
it's still the same dimensions which
means that the data offset already
points to exactly enough space to hold
it so we shouldn't actually have to do
any reallocation you know I'm Sam so I
think
I think this part of the process is
actually going to be pretty
straightforward
I think reorganizing the tags is gonna
be the hard part here because we need
the really because it's it's something
we need to think of hard about an
experiment with but I think the asset
part is actually pretty straightforward
all right so I'm just gonna make a
standard half set up here exactly we've
done it many times before so what we'll
do is we'll just look in the hash file
we'll see when when we get something
that has changed we'll just go in there
we'll modify it this HHA asset is just
inside the asset system here right where
we have that asset listed the only thing
that I think we're gonna have to be
aware of is when we look at this h/h a
asset here this part this may need to be
a more extended piece of information so
this HHA asset is telling us where to
put the new the replacement data but
that data that we're over writing I'm
not explaining myself well an hh8 asset
comes potentially originally from a data
file that we don't know how it got there
right when we boot up the game
our HHA assets that we have right now
for example that did not come from the
hot loading system in any way those
assets we don't know anything about them
right this this assets pointer here is
just a big list of these things I wear
was that right here right so we don't
know where it came from we copy this
information out of the file and then we
don't have it we don't know where it
came from so when we go to replace one
of those assets we're in trouble
because we don't know where
overwrite the file to tell us so in a
sense we actually need to store an
additional piece of information here
that tells us how to overwrite this
particular asset now what I'm gonna
propose is that since all of our assets
going forwards go through the watched
file system I think maybe that's the
right way to do that because we know
that we're never going to replace an old
asset with a new asset in the this way
that what wasn't through the watched
file system because all of our old
assets are the wrong dimensions anyway
so we can't reuse an old asset header
anyway so we could do it through here
the only thing that I think maybe trips
us up there is that we still need to go
back and nerf the old asset so that it
doesn't participate in matching if we
want to overwrite it so that part yeah
that part seems like something that we
just have to deal with
so I guess I guess I will just put it
here so everything every time an asset
gets loaded I'm just gonna remember
where it came from
I'm just gonna say that that's something
that it has to has to record and I think
like I said I think this part can
simpkin get simplified in the future so
basically what I would propose proposed
is eventually we probably want to just
move to a fixed size system where we
just have like a couple different buffer
types and the reason for that is we want
to kind of use the texture memory this
way and move things into the texture
system in a way that doesn't require
redraw restarts all the time and stuff
like that so I feel like we kind of want
to play with that a little bit and I
think we're gonna get to a point where
we can sort of collapse this stuff down
in a nice way we're not there yet but
we're gonna want to I'm gonna leave that
alone for now and just work with the
asset reload for right now because that
needs to get into place either way so
this is like asset in mexican file that
just tells us for this file here's which
one of the assets we need to overwrite
in that case
I'm also gonna make a note here that
we're talking about this right here this
assets array because asset index now as
a phrase is ambiguous do I mean the
asset index in the final that it came
from or do I mean the asset index in the
global assets array which has had all of
those merged together right because
those are two different things
and in this case I'm talking about the
global one right okay so let's do the
watch fineness right now and what I'm
gonna do is I'm gonna make it so that at
first what we'll do is if you hit a key
it'll do the reload so basically like
you can save as much as you want and
then you hit a key and it'll do the
reload eventually what I'd like to do is
probably just put it on a background
task so that it'll just automatically
reload right one of the nice things
about dev machines nowadays is we've
gotten back to the point where a
consumer machine is underpowered
compared to a developer's machine
usually right so typically for example
an end users machine you're not going to
be counting on having you know 24 cores
or something but a dev machine you can
you can buy a 24 core dev machine or
something ridiculous like this if you
really want to in theory right isn't
there some nutso thread Ripper thing
coming to like so 32 cores in a thread
Ripper - right so eventually what we
will definitely see is if not today at
least a little bit down the road but I
would argue today any artists machine
can trivially be made to have a ton of
course right so you can't afford to have
a background core doing nothing but
reloading artwork 24/7 if that's what
you want and will not really materially
affect the performance of the game
because even if your game scales
perfectly and scales to all 64 threads
on a thread Ripper 2
causing one of those threads to have to
sit around reloading artwork is only
gonna slow your game down by 1/64 of its
speed right now that's not entirely true
because loading artwork involves the
disk inin but right bla bla bla like who
knows how it might affect it a little
bit but we're splitting hairs the
machine power is such that if you would
like to you can easily just say on a
developer's machine we have a something
in the background sitting around that
does nothing but developer work and it
won't really make it so that the artist
can't play the game as intended it
should be fine right that was not the
case you know maybe 10 years ago right
but it is now so anyway so we have one
of these watch files and what I want to
do is make it so that maybe you had a
key and then we reload some stuff so
what I'm going to do here is gonna make
a little thing that's like checked for
art changes or something I don't know
I'm just making up this name and what I
want to do is pass it the game assets
structure and what it's going to do is
it's going to petition the file system
again and say a operating system layer
can you tell me what all the files are
that are in the art directory I might
want to reload some of them right and
we've already got the we're already sort
of doing one of those in here already
this file loading part here you can see
oh this was snuffleupagus oriented
programming by the way so what I want to
do is I want to you know load that in I
want to ask the platform to get me all
of the type files that are pngs I
believe yeah and so I want to say how
many P and G's are there I want to go
ahead and loop through each of those
like so and then every time we get one
of those out it's gonna have a base name
what I want to do is I want to create a
stat a standing structure that will
never go away it's just a
permanent record of the fact that this
file existed right what I want to do is
I want to create a permanent record of
the file so what its name was what its
date was and what assets it used right
so I want to make this and then I want
to see for anyone that I have that
appears to have changed I want to
actually ask the PNG loader to load it
and then I want to look through each of
the chunks in the file looking to see
what information there is about look
like I want to see what I should I say
this I want to see what assets actually
exist in the grid and whether or not
those assets are different from ones
that I have already in my permanent
storage now one of the things that I
probably should do is instead of calling
this a watch file I might call this
something slightly different I might
call this a source file and the reason
I'm gonna call it that is because I want
to think of this as something that
probably has a broader scope than just
watching the file so for example we may
want a bunch of information like tweaks
and stuff to apply to the things in this
file you remember us mentioning maybe it
was last weekend I think when we were
sort of doing some preliminary work here
there's information that may need to be
added that is additional on this file so
you know if we look at this for example
I really need something that's gonna
what's paint 3d though that's this thing
all right
so check it out of curiosity what is 3d
about this like what what happens in 3d
here does anyone know like how did how
do I make this 3d exactly okay all right
so what why was it only painting on the
plane is that can I paint on this block
they're just trolling at this point are
they just trolling me at this point
they made a 3d paint program that can't
paint in 3d and I mean am i missing is
that actually what I'm looking at right
now or is that I just do I just not know
how to use the program
I mean if it's 3d paint I should be able
to paint on the cube right I mean that's
like the minimum that would be necessary
to make this a 3d paint program am I
just am I am i way off in the field here
folks
please please tell me if I'm being
unreasonable but it kind of feels to me
like to call something paint 3d you have
to be able to paint outside of the plane
but maybe I'm missing something
like can i is there a way to get some
other plane so I can have like two
planes or something oh I can have a
little sticky star can i okay so so I
can stamp things on to it
but I just can't draw onto it
it's fine I don't know why I even bother
all right so let's just go back to
something I don't know what about this
is this a normal can't read that file
okay you know what developer studio can
read these although it may roll over and
die if it tries to read a file that big
I'll load it with I tell you
Windows 10 never stops trolling me it
reboots whenever it wants and it
installs a program called paint 3d that
can't paint in three dimensions that's
that's that's a new one
I guess that's kind of the same as
calling Windows 10 profession of Windows
10 professional when it is like like one
of the most unprofessional things I've
ever seen okay so here is ya all right
so here is an example of one of our
files right what I was trying to say
before I was interrupted by that sort of
like that Microsoft role is we may need
to annotate this with additional
information so for example if I wanted
to say like this is the ground put like
this is where this thing sits on a hard
point so like you know if this is where
it's supposed to be hopping to or
whatever that it hops to right you know
that's the alignment of that thing
versus a ground point or similarly if I
wanted to say here's the neck like
that's where the head attaches to
there's you know so if we want to
annotate these with particular pieces of
information that information really
isn't super plausible to edit in pngs
now it's not that you can't
so p.m. G's as we saw can have
information embedded in them so you know
for example if Photoshop were a nice
easy to use program that
artists had fun with it would have
things like alignment point as an easy
thing to do and then it could store that
into when it exported a PNG could store
that into the text fields or something
right
but even though Photoshop does sort of
have some features like that that you
can kind of co-op for this purpose
they're not easy for artists to use and
artists don't know how to use them
they're not intuitive and they don't
really do that sort of stuff very well
and so you typically don't find artists
who would know how to do that
necessarily you could force them to
learn but usually it's better not to
make an artist life miserable and make
them use problematic pieces of a tool if
you don't have to so an easier thing to
do because of Photoshop sort of lack of
really targeting the game industry as a
thing what we want to do is add our own
ability to specify this markup but then
that means where does it go
it won't go back into the Photoshop
files that the artist was using to make
it so the onus becomes on us to store
that information somewhere meaningful
right and so what we need to do is we
need to keep this information around so
what I'd like to do is say that we
probably want something like this
right and so this way in addition to
storing where I put everything I can
also store some additional information
that means something to me now when I
look back and go what's the actual data
that we're using here that should
hopefully give me some information so we
see in here for the HHA bitmap which is
the thing that we're talking about now
we've got these two things the dimension
the align percentage right so what I
could do is just store this exactly this
way right I could store the align
percentage in here and that's like the
marked up alignment percentage I suppose
maybe what I could do as well is just
say look you know maybe this is it this
doesn't actually need to be done this
way maybe I could say hey look that's
just stored in the file
so the HHA bit map tells us that
information how do I feel about that
I guess that's fine so I guess I guess
maybe this was not really that necessary
because what we can do is we can just go
back in there and get it right we can
just go back in there and look up what
the align percentage was because
anything that we needed to mark up get
stored in the file by default so it's
really this thing that we would have to
change seems reasonable to me and that's
really the only thing that we've got we
don't really mark up anything else I
don't think yeah so I think that should
probably be fine I think that should
probably be fine all right so anyway
looking through here we've got the asset
indices in the file date base name and
the hash that should be sufficient for
doing what we want to do so when we do
our check for our changes and we come
through here we're gonna do our platform
get all file to files of type begin get
all files of type and I think we passed
this back in right so here's our actual
change check when we come through here
to look up something for the base name
we're going to want to hash this string
I believe we already have a string hash
if we look here
ya know if we actually have any string
hashes besides that custom one I know I
can search for a better hash function
and see it but it looks like it's only
in the yeah so I guess we don't we never
really had one yeah so I guess I will
add one here that's just a way to do a
generic string hash in here that's used
the same way because it doesn't look
like we've ever done any string hashing
that wasn't custom that wasn't specific
to some part of the system like the
debug system that was trying to loop
through and do other things at the same
time that's a pointer hash this is looks
like this is the only string hash we
have and it's doing other stuff at the
same time which we don't really want to
do in this case what we could do is sort
of localize this hash function a little
bit here which is to say that the update
mode of this is something we could break
out so we could make a thing here that
was like in line void update string hash
that you know that I think just works so
we could do something like this where
you could do this update step and that
way everyone just uses it so that if we
do make a better hash function someday
everyone would get it so that seems kind
of nice
right and then this sort of thing just
does update string hash and off you go
so that seems kind of nice to me because
it occurred to me as I was doing that
that actually this is going to be the
same sort of thing so where we where we
actually go through here we probably do
want to do two different operations one
of which is we're going to actually
produce the string hash that we would
need to look it up quickly but the other
one is we're going to want to look at
the file name to figure out what it is
that we're looking at because that's the
only information that we actually have
to figure out what this should be block
underscore character underscore cover
underscore hand underscore item
underscore obstacles underscore or none
of the above so for example the title
screen is kind of just its own thing
here all of those different pieces of
information are gonna have to be
parceled out because that's the only way
we really know what we're looking at
here and so we kind of need some
scanning that's kind of in line with
this so we are gonna do an update string
hash here but while we're doing it we're
probably going to look for some other
things that's just how it's gonna go
right okay so coming through here let's
take a little bit more of
let's take a little bit more of an
excursion in here so looking at the
platform information that we get I think
it's just a date in the base name that
we actually need I don't think we need
anything else right well I mean the size
we would use once we actually go to read
it I suppose but that's about it
actually so what we want to do here is
we're gonna have to take the base name
let's actually scan over that so we'll
look so we get to the null terminator on
that so looking over the base name that
will allow us to Britt bring up our hash
value we're gonna want some extra
information here as well and I think one
of the things that we probably want and
I talked about this before is that I
think we're gonna want to start actually
having a real string here the reason for
that again is just because Jimmy once
you start picking like plucking pieces
out of things you tend to want to just
have like non null term and strings null
terminated strings are not good I wish
they had not been the standard and see
they're not a good way of storing
strings strings should be stored as a
length plus the pointer to the actual
value the reason for this is because
once you do any non-trivial operations
with strings whatsoever you typically
want to start talking about sub regions
of the string and null termination does
not allow you to do that null
termination just to give you a little
bit of a background here of what I'm
talking about go ahead and move this out
of the way
so null termination
so what are the advantages of melter
mination versus length plus of military
of Riesling sprinter and what are the
advantages like 4e versus an alternation
like look what's better and how does it
work so this C style is null termination
right it says that you have an 8 byte
pointer right that points to just some
series of characters and we know that
the last one is well one byte of zeros
so what that means is it takes I guess
you might say 10 bytes to store the most
minimal string right because the minimal
string would be one character long we
won't really talk about the null string
because the null string in C style is
difficult to define you could argue that
the null string is takes 8 bytes to
store or 9 bytes to store depending on
whether you're talking about a valid
string that has nothing in it or a zero
pointer which maybe you consider valid
or not so there's actually multiple
states there with C style it's worth
noting so ignoring that for one second
the minimal string let's say of one
character is 10 bytes long and generally
speaking right the overhead is 9 bytes
so it's 9 bytes plus the character count
for the string right so for a length
plus pointer it's usually going to be
depending on how big you want your
string Maxon to be you could say that
you only have a 16-bit count and a
pointer but typically you use more of a
4 byte count at a pointer because why
not allow gigantic strings right because
remember the C style could have you
could have pointed to something that
happened to be 4 gigabytes long it would
be just fine the seesaw doesn't care how
long it is so in order to be able to
store very large strings you would want
at least a 4 byte count
and then you have an 8-byte pointer
which means that you actually have a 12
light overhead right so it's three more
bytes of overhead than the other one did
and if you really wanted the same
flexibility as a c-- style you would
technically need the eight bytes on a
64-bit machine now to be fair it would
never really be that many it would be
more like six bytes because there is no
machine that can actually have 64 bits
of actual memory in it so you're never
really gonna have that so it's more like
maybe fourteen bytes versus nine bytes
but whatever either way what I would
like to make very clear here is you're
dealing with just a few bytes of
difference between the two so there's
very little overhead in either case that
you really care about you're pretty good
to go in either one and if you really
cared about overhead all that much you
would probably have to do something
different altogether anyway that was
more about storing the thing inside the
space itself or other kind of bit
encoding and all these other sorts of
things so ignoring that assuming you're
just doing the generic version you don't
suffer that much more overhead in terms
of actual memory you're gonna care about
like with the the count string because
you just don't typically have this many
of these anyway so the reason that I
don't like the null termination is
pretty simple usually you have things
like you know character underscore
orphan underscore o 2 dot PNG right and
so this for example is a string it's the
file name let's say I want to parse this
file name so what I typically want to
produce oops
are things like this you know string
type equals character right string
name equals orphan my hand ranks really
bad today even worse than normal string
number equals o to write string
extension equals PNG right so typically
what we want to do is like parse these
things out so they look like this
now the nonsense way to do this is to
actually allocate strings all the time
so you actually go through and you parse
this out you allocate a new string you
copy it into here and it's just a
disaster
right tons of allocations tons of memory
copies blah blah blah blah blah but
there's really not much other way to do
it if you're forcing to you if you're
going to use a null terminator version
because the null terminator version the
only way it could do it without
allocation would be to overwrite the
string so you'd have to actually insert
null terminators into these locations in
order to point directly into the
original string at these to give you
these results right and once you do that
you can't use the original string
anymore
because now the original string
character or 4 no 2 dot PNG has been
corrupted so you couldn't then go use it
to say load the file off disk by saying
here is the file I wanted to load
because now it just points to something
that just says character and then
there's a null terminator right however
if you use length strings all of this
stuff becomes trivial you this is just a
block of memory it has the original
stuff in it these now just become length
strings that point to here and have the
length point to here has the length
point to here has the length point to
here has the length right so length
strings allow you to break up blocks of
memory into regions extremely trivially
and then you don't have any of these
problems so what I would like to say
is that if you are programming in C and
you're using the built-in kind of
functions that they use then you end up
with a null Terminator system like we
have on handmade hero because we haven't
really cared much we don't do a lot of
operations with strings but once you
start doing a lot of operations on
strings like we're sort of storing you
now we're gonna parse this file name
into pieces and do stuff with it having
a length string becomes very important
because length strings are way way way
way way better than null terminated
strings for just about everything you
might want to do the only thing that
gets a little bit harder is you have to
actually check against the count when
you're processing them and occasionally
that's a little bit harder like
sometimes when you're just ingesting
characters just checking for null is
easier I'm not sure if we'll actually
see this occur in practice in what we're
about to do probably not but I can give
you a simple example let's suppose you
wanted to parse a number and I just want
to say hey let's take the as much of the
string as has numbers in it and turn
that into a number right so what I might
do there if I was using an ultra
measuring is just say while the
character is a digit continue because I
know that if I hit the end of the string
I will get a character that isn't a
digit the null character right so I
don't have to also check for the end of
the string because checking to see if
something's a digit also checks if it's
the end of the string that convenience
goes away when you have length strings
because length strings do not have any
special character at the end of them
they simply told you where the end was
and they expect you to observe it which
means that every operation that you do
of that form has to have an
additional check sometimes that check is
free because the way you would have been
checking before would have been to check
explicitly for the null terminator in
which case it costs you effectively
nothing but in other cases you could
have gotten the check for free because
you were doing let's say a bounced check
on a character to see whether or not it
fell within a range already that check
will also check for the null terminator
for you for free so you've added one
additional bit operation on there that
has to get ended in and that's kind of
yeah that's kind of what I would point
out there as a downside to this part of
the process
so what I'm gonna do here is I'm just
gonna say that there's a struct string
and what I might do is I may even go a
little bit further and just call this
unify this actually with what we had I
think we've got one in here yeah so we
have this this sort of concept in here
of these stream chunks right what I
might do is say that let's just call
this actually you know a buffer or
something like this let's just let's
just make this fairly generic and say
that maybe we'll actually just make this
16 bytes long so it's you know a nice
aligned little thing and it can remember
any size plus a region right and then
inside here where we have this content
size and contents I could just make this
like that right something like this so
that's what I'm gonna do and so here
we'll do this like so go in there
[Music]
Oh
whoops what is this what is this stream
file bit
that's so this is the same thing here so
this should just be one of these and
then this gets even better because then
that just works right all right
so contents count and that's all good
contents count contents data contents
got data
this is just advancing this so actually
this is now just that right like so and
what you can see they're actually also
that is if I start to do this you can
see some operations that actually
already make sense right so I can do a
thing where I just say like okay I've
got a buffer I want to advance it by a
certain amount and what I can do here is
actually just do something like this
where I say if you want to advance a
buffer by a certain amount I can
actually just make this be sort of the
operation in question so assume if you
know this buffer can support in advance
by the count that we're talking about
then we then it does right whereas if
you know if it can't it can't and I
could also make that so that it you know
returns the the result here in this
fashion right so if you want the old
pointer you can have the old pointer
back if it returns zero that means that
you weren't able to it will suck up that
amount of data here we go
and in the case where it can't do it
it'll just say that you know it'll say
that it's at the end what I might do to
is put it at the end so that will
basically just advance the pointer by
exactly how much there actually was
right not sure if that's exactly the
function I want but it seems reasonable
so here we could just say like oh yeah
you know do you feel if necessary file
here's my results my results is just
advanced by whatever this count is the
file contents and then if you know the
result comes back null then I want to
just you know mark that down as a bad
situation that we didn't want to have
happen right and then off we go let's
see here I feel like is Alan on today
Alan is probably not I think he's on
vacation I have noticed that for some
reason I've been having for kotor jump
to the second error in the stream
sometimes i didn't know if that got
fixed yet i wanted to check like it
doesn't jump to this it jumps to this
for some reason sometimes i'm not sure
why because it didn't used to do that i
don't know why it does that I do have to
update this for coder so it may already
be fixed I should probably update this
for a coder I've been waiting till the
next or code or update because it's a
pretty big one it's got the list or API
so I'm probably gonna do a pretty big
update at that point but figured I'd
check anyway all right so but moving on
so let me just finish porting this here
so at content size again that's actually
going to be contents count
comdata count with intense count count
Count count contents count that'll
probably air out because we can't
actually this won't support a 64-bit
read what's safe what's our safe
truncate
I feel like that should really be safe
truncate to you at 32 to you 32 like so
um so I'm gonna rename it that there we
go
buffer - oh no that's not true
who's complaining about something else I
think it does accept a size T there so
that's great even better so those are
64-bit now oh that's great good job see
runtime library content stuff data
contents count all right so now these
are just safe truncate to you thirty-two
safe truncate to you thirty-two and
we're so I think that's all we need
I'm gonna go ahead and run just to make
sure that I didn't break anything with
that change I'm gonna make sure that the
PNG reader runs and doesn't you know
roll over and die or anything like that
so there we go all good I think let me
just verify that it actually was oh good
delete those and make it rewrite them
just to prove to ourselves that it's not
busted yeah I also should double check
the output make sure there's no errors
yeah so good while I'm in there I can
fix the error that someone mentioned on
the pre stream in the the PNG the test
PNG reader it it swaps as you can see
here right and so one of the problems is
that if you swap twice you get an
upside-down alpha right because you've
swapped once and then you swap again we
might as well put the Alpha allow the
alpha be right call this invert
we can trivially just not convert so if
I add that as a pixel up pixel up invert
go x8 then when we do this I can say oh
yeah first time pixel up invert second
time don't right now
these are upside-down or what the alphas
upside down if I run it now hopefully
the Alpha will be right side up and in
it is right so there that's actually
much nicer right uh so there you go
that's that's that change so if I now
have one of these little buffer doodads
in there you can see how that's kind of
just a little bit nicer and you can sort
of see how it actually also opens up the
door to having some other nice
opportunities here like things that
operate on regional data we can sort of
create utility functions now that
operate on those conveniently that saves
us some typing so that's all nice and
good and what I'd like to do is come on
in here to the asset system part that
we're talking about and I want to go
ahead and parse out this name into
pieces so I'm gonna have some different
pieces here that go along with sort of
the stuff that we know is in there at
the moment and what you can see is we've
sort of got underscores separating
different parts what I'm gonna do is
just say look what we have is up to
three of these
underscore separated pieces so I'm gonna
just call these
like pieces here and say that there's
three of them and the first three
underscore based pieces that we have I'm
going to separate out into those strings
for us to use later as token values
because we're gonna potentially want to
have a sort of pseudo parser it's not
really a parser in the strict sense of
the term because it only is doing very
basic matching but it is more or less a
parser trying to guess what the artist
was trying to tell us with the filename
so that we know how to interpret the
file that we get at the very least we
need to know obstacles item and cover
character and block need to be handled
specially what we do with the rest of
the information is kind of a different
story so you know that's yeah we'll see
what we want to do with that a little
bit later we also want to ignore
anything called template so blank
template needs to be not processed
because those are just there for our
reference they don't actually
participate in in the end like in the
final sort of finished product that we
ship to people so they shouldn't be
extracted by this reader they should be
ignored completely so when we scan
through here I'm gonna want to gather
those pieces so let's go ahead and do
that I'm gonna go ahead and and have an
anchor here if the anchor is gonna start
at the base name itself and then what
I'm gonna do is say alright we've got
the scan I'm coming through here I look
at the hash value I update that every
time through the loop with the new
character that I see and I'm gonna use
this hash value later on outside in the
meantime what I'm gonna do here is I'm
going to look to see if the scan value
happens to be an underscore if the scan
value does happen to be an underscore
I'm going to take a look to see about a
piece count
if the piece count is less than the
array count of pieces then I'm going to
consider this a piece and I'm going to
retire it so I want to do this in one of
two cases if there is an underscore then
I want to do it but also if there's
going to be a null I want to do it so if
star scan equals that or and in the one
way to write this perhaps a little bit
nicer is if this value is I'm looking at
right now the reason for that is then I
can look at this next value as well so
if the next value would have been a null
Terminator then I want to end as well
right in either case so looking at these
two we have the differentiate between
them eventually but for the moment we
can do the same code path on either one
so pieces piece count plus plus will get
retired here that's going to be the
string that I'm writing like that so
this string needs to get a count and it
needs to get data we know what the data
is the data is the anchor value right
that's this right here similarly as soon
as we're done with this the anchor value
can be equal to skin plus one because
that's where the next anchor would be
assuming that we continue it's only
really relevant in this case but we can
set it in either case and it's not a
problem so when we look at the piece
count here and we say what is the you
know what is the next one going to be
well the count is going to be everywhere
from where we're at now back all the way
to the anchor right so it's gonna be
scan - anchor however in the case where
we're actually looking at the null
Terminator here it actually needs to be
one further than that right because the
null Terminator happened actually on the
next one so in the case where I'm not
looking at an underscore I need to
advance my count to account for one more
so I need to basically say if this was
an underscore then I need one more
character otherwise everything's
we're so off I go that's all fine
that'll break it up into pieces and then
I also have the hash value at the end so
now I've got just like the chunks and
the hash and I'm ready to go so assuming
that I see this hash value here and I'm
ready to reload this what I then need to
do is I need to find out if I've already
got one of these or not so what I can do
there is I can just say for remember we
made this asset source file thing here
so for each source file that might match
the hash and I could just I might just
again keep changing the names here to
just say okay this is these are source
files it's not really about the fact
that they're watched they're just source
files so sorry for each source file that
the asset system is aware of off of this
hash value if that makes sense then I'm
just gonna loop through and check them
like so so what I want to do here is
match if I find one that matches and how
would I do that
well I have here a base name right and
that base name has to match the base
name that I was given so what I want to
do is say if you know strings are equal
if the base name that I have is going to
match the base name that I got from the
from the file system if those two things
are equal then these are the same file
now there is one sort of bizarre feature
that we might want to consider here and
it's difficult to say whether we want to
or not on a linux like machine you would
have files be treated the same if they
have the exact same file name but no
other time on a Windows like machine
files are considered the same file name
if the lowercase
version of the file name matches the
lowercase version of the other like if
they would be the same if converted to
lowercase right so capitalization is not
relevant to the matching in a
windows-based file name it's kind of
busted best just how it is how do I want
to deal with that well I don't want the
game to think about that because the
game would then have to understand what
platform it was running on to a greater
extent than I feel is necessary so what
I'm gonna claim instead what I'm gonna
claim instead is that what we will do is
we will force the operating system layer
to prepare that for us basically so down
there on win32 handmade when it's
actually doing like so here we've got
our situation with with win32 get all
files of type again and so on right
we're coming through here we get all
these things and then we do wild card
and multi-byte right here and we produce
the base name and that's the thing that
we pay back to the app and blah blah
blah well right there we are now in a
perfect position to lowercase eyes this
name right now I don't know if we have a
lowercase or we don't it's a little
right one but right here that's one
thing that we can do so I'm gonna go
through
and make each one of these lowercase now
the problem with this is that it's not
quite right if you use Unicode so I'm
gonna I don't know if wipe
let me check to make sure wide care
doesn't do that I don't think it can I
don't think it the OS can do that for us
unfortunately
it is
[Applause]
and this is notice as useful
I just wanted to check to see if they
had one I'll skip it for now
um so I'm not a language expert so I
have no idea but if you convert
something to utf-8 it's safe to convert
it to lowercase and it will do an ASCII
based lowercase because anything that
was extended will have the high bit set
so you won't accidentally lowercase a
value that shouldn't have been a lower
cased right you won't corrupt the string
however what I don't know is to what
extent lower casing needs to be Unicode
aware so if you actually want to produce
the lowercase version of a Unicode
string that would have to include lower
casing four characters above the base
127 character set right and so we're not
doing that so we're not technically
doing the full Unicode lowercase I don't
care because our artists are never going
to produce anything like that and it's
not a particularly bad bug even if we
did it just means if they use two
different cases the files would maybe I
don't even know it's it's not a
particularly bad bug either way but it
would create issues with our asset
system until they went in and actually
deleted one of the two files right or
restored the case to the correct case so
Darius that it's worth noting so if you
actually want a good eunuch good Unicode
lower case you can't assume that the
characters are only ANSI because you may
have extended ones that are multibyte
long that's just the nature of the beast
right however if you just want to do a
basic one it's actually pretty simple
all you have to do is say if the
character that you're talking about is
greater than equal to capital a and it's
less than or equal to capital Z then you
know that's inside the range of
characters right and this works because
you know fortunately people who designed
ASCII how to clue if you go look at what
an ASCII table looks like what you can
see is that all of the you know capital
letters can occur contiguously and all
of the lowercase letters occur
contiguously
so all we have to do once we look for a
range check and see that it's in between
these is we just have to apply the
offset so all we have to do is then say
okay just add however much it takes to
change a capital into a lowercase right
so I want to change capital A into a
lowercase a however much that distance
is just adding that will automatically
lowercase it because no matter where you
are in the table that same stride will
get you to the right lowercase value
right so you can kind you can see it
even in the numbers 41 maps to 61 42
maps to 62 in hex right so you can see
that you're just twiddling some bits at
the high end and you've changed it from
uppercase to lowercase right and and
again that's because the people who
design ASCII they knew what they were
doing they made it nice and easy to use
in that way okay
so this will lowercase those file names
that we don't actually care and then
when we string match we're fine right if
we find that we actually have a match we
can stop and we now know that this file
is a file we were already aware of on
the way out if we don't know about this
file so we didn't find a match then what
we need to do is actually create one of
them and we need to initialize it into a
state where it appears to be completely
not to not have not had any data in it
because we're going to want to then load
the file and actually process it so that
turns out to be pretty easy right so
anyway if we push a struct here where we
have an asset source file a new one what
we can do here and and we're gonna this
will clear it as well what we can do
here is then put the copy of the string
on why don't you just a push copy
[Music]
actually I guess I can do a pushing I'll
terminate well actually what what's my
easiest thing to do here for copying
this string I know we had a couple
different ones here there it is so I'm
just gonna do a push string here it's a
little inefficient because technically I
should just save the scan value because
then I know how long it is and I can
just do it in one go but I'm not going
to because it's not really going to
matter at all
so anyway pushing in the source here I'm
just gonna say okay there's my base name
I'm gonna push this string on and so I
just need my memory Rini here now we've
got a bunch of stuff pointed to here
this is the non restored memory and then
we've got I guess so when you reset the
game it's non restored memory because we
don't yeah so this is the non restored
memory Reena and that's where we
actually want this because we don't want
this tracked across like loop code
editing because this is for assets which
are not don't participate in that stuff
so here we could just say all right give
us a new one of these now it's there we
leave the file date at zero because we
now want them to not match so by now we
have to assert that we do have a match
and we now want to say has it changed so
if the match file date is not equal to
the current file date then what we want
to do is update this file and remember
that fact right that's what we're trying
to do here so in addition to and this is
like a to-do update the actual assets
that's the part that we now want to
write so the other thing we have to do
here is actually store it into the hash
show the source file hash at the hash
value right that thing is gonna
to the end like so and then the source
file hash itself is going to point to
this as our first one but that's it
right so it's pretty simple that builds
up the entire hash so now we just know
what we've got and this now tracks
everything right that's all we needed to
basically have a change processor now
the more complicated part is to actually
go through and process the individual
assets that are part of file right and
we've got a couple different things that
we're gonna have to do there and yeah I
want to kind of go through those more
specifically so not sure exactly I want
to structure this suffice to say this
call right here is the call that
actually needs to do the processing so
here we have a update you know asset
package from PNG we're gonna pass that
file info actually I you know I probably
won't quite do that so what I'll
probably do here is load the file and
then call this with the file data so
what I probably do here is push a
temporary on and then rescind that
temporary right so I'm gonna want to
load in a block trying to think of what
I want there but the long and short of
it is I'm going to call this stuff so
when we actually go to load a file here
I want to call this
to load it in so I have a platform file
handle so what I need to do here is I
need to open it like so and this would
be platform this is open file so that
will open the file then I would do a
platform close file like so and I would
just issue one read here platform read
data from file and that'd just passed
the handle offset size test and we know
that we're reading the entire thing so
it's really just the file info file size
and this destination here is gonna be a
buffer that is however big the file size
was so we just need a temporary we need
to push a temporary on and then we can
after we load it into that temporary
storage then we can just get rid of that
right so this is our file buffer that
file buffer will then be passed here and
the other thing that I would mention is
this gives us yet another place we can
actually use this system like I said
having one of these comes in handy
pretty frequently so I can just say like
alright
got to get to memory from somewhere but
otherwise once we figure out where we
want to store that that's all we have to
do then we pass that file buffer to
update asset package from ping and what
we want to send that is the match that
we used the asset system obviously and
we're going to let that function take it
from there I this update here tells us
what the file date change was I don't
know whether we want to do that before
or after you know do we want to do this
before or after I'm not sure you know I
think I do want that on the same line so
it doesn't get separated so I'm not 100%
sure what I want to do there but
something like that and then once the
update once the package is updated I
also kind of want to record the fact
that it's dirty
because I think we're probably going to
want to do here is have a like made
changes thing and in here I guess I
would say this thing maybe returns
whether it made changes and in the case
that we made changes
we probably need there to then update
like some kind of asset information file
that we have and what that asset
information file is going to be is just
something that sits there telling us
what the source files are what their
dates were so that when and and that
information about what assets went with
them so that when we close the game and
reload the game back in it will know
that information right
I think that's it yeah so I think that's
everything that we need there in our
shared directory so it's not a string
it's a buffer like so and I you know
what I could do I can also make it so
that buffer and string are the same
thing like we can do this as well
because sometimes I'd like to be able to
say string because it's just a note to
myself what's going on even though those
two things are exactly the same anyway
so
Jimmy I think that's just about
everything so I think the only problem
is now getting that actual data out let
me make sure that's true
all right uh so then we just have the
actual update happen here oops that
needs to take the assets it needs to
take the source file
oops source a source file in the
contents then when we look at the PNG
reader here when that takes the Parsis
PNG bit here like so that's going to
take one of these file streams and again
that's something that we can pretty
easily that's something that we can
generate trivially from one of these
little buffers so you should be good to
go
so I think that's just about everything
we need for the change management and so
the one thing we don't know is how we
want to deal with that temporary there
so we have obviously in the in the game
proper we have the notion here oops it's
not the file I wanted inside the game
state we have you know various arenas
that store stuff and so I'm not sure
what we want to do for the temporary
memory here I kind of feel like we
probably just want to allocate and
deallocate it directly from the platform
because there's no reason not to its
development only so I feel like we
almost want to just do that by just
doing a platform allocate memory and
then a platform do allocate memory
and that should be fine
so there's memory block that's our tenth
lock allocate memory takes the size and
the flags we don't care about that so
the size is just that and that's it so I
think that's all we need
pretty sure anyway and I think that just
does everything we want so the next step
is to go in here right into update asset
package from PNG and loop through all of
those tiles so this is going to be like
a for loop right it's going to first
call handmade PNG you know in here you
know what now I think about it we
actually can do this this this isn't
this is not necessary yeah I think about
it this is not necessary at all we can
actually just have this be a temporary
arena right so basically everything that
it does in here can just be done like
this
right because that'll just automatically
do it and then when we come up here and
we need to push a memory arena in here
we can also just say we can say what the
memory arena is that gets used for
everything for all the temporary
processing and that gets nicely cleaned
up everything works just fine
trivial no code everyone's happy
so really what we need is just the file
stream here the info bits here is for
the error so but I'm not gonna do that
right now
that'll be tomorrow's job but that's how
that's gonna work
and so we would just pass that temporary
nough in and then I think we're good to
go so I think that's the whole
superstructure for it right now that
pretty much does everything we want in
here we'll have the four I loop that
will loop over each of the tiles we'll
look to see if there's any data in that
tile if there is any data in the tile we
will record it as a new asset if the
data doesn't match the asset that's in
there currently I think that's it
all right let's Q&amp;A
thoughts on the use of persistent memory
eg in to obtain in game programming so I
guess what I would say is I don't have a
lot of thoughts on it because it's not
really different from what you already
have to deal with so it should slot into
your system pretty routinely without a
lot of effort the reason I say that is
because game developers are already used
to nonsense like there's a server and
the server sends you no data to the
client where it has to write it to a
harddrive cache where it has to move it
into memory where it has to move it into
texture memory right and you're used to
all of these like different levels of
locality it's just something that game
developers have to live with you know
that other developers too often don't
think about but game developers have to
constantly think about making sure
things are in the right place the right
time so if you want to slot another
thing in there that's like a different
level of cache along the way it usually
doesn't really change the design of your
system a whole heck of a lot it's just
adding some other cache that has a
little bit faster speed and a little bit
smaller size right Martens are you sure
always lowering finite file name to
lowercase is a good solution because
case sensitivity is a feature of the
file system not the whole OS on NTFS you
can enable case sensitivity individually
per folder you can mount NTFS disk on
Linux Mac and on Apple HFS+ or a FPS can
be both case incitive case insensitive
depends on how you format it yet I know
I mean like I said I'm not sure I'm also
just not sure there is a good solution I
don't know what the right solution is
for this case because the file name
actually means something so you're just
not really allowed to save to files that
have the same file name and just
different case and expect
to the game to care about that right one
is gonna have to overwrite the other so
I think what I want is to just always
flatten it down I think I may want it to
flatten always period meaning the OS
layer even on a case where it does
differentiate by case still shouldn't
because we we can only pick one if that
makes sense
long billion I can't remember are the
bitmap assets stored next to the audio
and font cliff assets in memory this may
be relevant if those are not the same
size as the bitmaps it's not really
relevant no the reason for that is if a
bitmap is always replacing another
bitmap you don't care where it is you
just care that the size was that big
right so all we really care about is
that the hot loadable assets slot into a
particular size type because that allows
us to overwrite the old version without
having to do a lot of memory without
having to do analysis of a free store
which is not the end of the world anyway
like we could just do that it's just
it's a waste of time if you don't
actually need it and a lot of times you
don't because you need to end up with
unit size like things that are a
particular size for the texture on the
core the texture memory on the graphics
card anyway so a lot of times it's not
really up to you if that makes sense
what's the mnemonic device used in ummm
I get that it's a size T but what does
um M stand for quite a few people in the
stream ask so the reason for that is
that the convention that I had for using
signed and unsigned was the first thing
tells you whether it's signed or
unsigned so SRU and then the number
tells you how many bits it is 32-bit
64-bit 16 bits 8 bits the problem then
becomes when you get something that you
just want to say I need this to be the
same size as some logical thing so in
the case of you mmm it's like I need to
say that it's the size that a pointer is
and so I just picked memory model like
it's the size of whatever the memory
model needs it to be so it's just you mM
and that's it
I don't have a strong opinion about that
you PTR would be another reasonable one
UST if you wanted to be like use size T
UPP for put you know pointer Oh
anything is fine as long as you remember
it yeah pick whatever you want just as
long as you remember it thoughts on use
of Vulcan for a 2.5 do you gain like
this is it over killers or a benefit so
again I don't think Vulcans particularly
useful it kind of is an API they don't
see the point of anymore but I'll get to
the more general question should you
write like a metal version of the game
on Mac and a d3 12 or you know 11
version on the PC yes it's valuable like
with d3 d12 you could definitely do some
things with how you overlap the texture
downloads and things like that you could
definitely do useful things with it so
it's not overkill on the other hand is
it strictly necessary probably not
because well no you know I mean I think
it is so for example say you want to
keep pushing on the lighting quality
which we might want to do later on right
you know maybe we want two modes of the
game in the final version one that's you
know can be run on low-end systems and
the Lighting's kind of crappy and one
that runs on high-end systems only like
you know GeForce Titan or something
right but that has really cool lighting
and doing all this ray tracing and stuff
on the graphics card or something right
those things are typically good to
program in like a d3 d12 or whatever
right that would be my guess
and on the Vulcan front the reason I say
it's not useful anymore is because Apple
made it clear that metals the only game
in town
so for Mac OS 10 and iOS you're gonna be
programming metal full-stop
nobody cares about Android unless you
ship free-to-play nonsense games so
which we don't write they don't have a
market for paid games on Android pretty
much period so hand made heroes not an
issue on Android neither is anything
anyone would ship probably as a game you
have to be shipping like free-to-play
nonsense if you want to be on Android so
assuming you charging money for your
game you're talking about iOS you have
to use metal same with Mac OS 10
that's the only game in town now they
have officially said that OpenGL is gone
right so if you're programming metal on
that it only leaves one other platform
for you besides consoles which are all
custom and the other platform you have
is Windows and Windows is d3d there's no
point in Vulcan right there literally
doesn't give you anything you can't use
it for cross-platform because it's gonna
be it's gonna be a cruft layer on top of
anything you use on an apple platform so
you might as well just use the actual
thing that the operating system supports
and get rid of the Vulcan layer which is
just cruft right it's no longer the
direct layer it's it's bulkan is
basically OpenGL now it's a thing that
sits on top of the actual graphic system
and probably will
you know not be nearly as
well-maintained as the official thing
that the operating system itself is
running through so as far as I'm sure
you could forget Vulcan I mean Vulcans a
non-issue maybe on Linux and Android it
matters but it it's completely
irrelevant I think for the future of
games at this point unless there's some
major change in the future and and one
of the platform holders adopts it but
assuming that neither Apple nor
Microsoft adopt Vulkan
it's it's dead I mean it's it's a
non-issue it literally won't matter to
anybody people might use it as a
compatibility layer the same way they
were using OpenGL but if you're looking
for something that's a smart way to
partition your games rendering system
it's gonna be metal D 3d and end of
story
right and I really don't see any
arguments the other way if Vulcans
certainly not a good API so you're not
getting anything there either it's it's
it's a bad it's a lousy API so you're
not getting like any kind of good like
ease of use or like well-thought-out
clean bonus from it it's it's you know
it's it's a giant tangled mess oh yes
someone just pointed out a typo
uh but that is what I did sorry I'm not
sure what you're talking about
I think you meant to add two string
count when scan zero is not equal to
oh yes yes sorry yes that was the typo
alright looks like that's like the end
of the questions
I've been listening to early episodes of
Jeff and Casey podcast and wanted to ask
me feel guilty for giving ei all the
advice which they definitely follow I
feel like I'm absolved because I feel
like they would have come with it
themselves there are some very smart
people there those people are not
necessarily putting their smarts to
ethical use per se but they're smart I
think they would have come up with it
themselves I think they would have I
don't think they needed to take advice
from me so I my hands clean of that some
Suzy thanks a lot for all these great
educational materials
you're very welcome thank you for saying
so could you explain why open jail is a
state machine I guess I'm not sure what
you mean by that question couldn't you
be a little bit more specific about that
do you have a particular piece of
documentation to which you're referring
Brian why is scan one equal zero and not
scan Oh so in this case so what what
this is doing here and I probably should
have explained this a little bit more
carefully I just kind of wrote it out in
a hurry what I want to do is I want to
separate something out into chunks based
on where the underscores are so if I see
an underscore I want to record a chunk
but the last character in the file name
will not be an underscore probably it
will just be a regular character and so
I want to also record that as a chunk or
a piece I should say so I want to do is
look to see am i on and underscore if I
am then
hit the end of a chunk or is the next
one a zero and if so then I've hit the
chunk hit the end of a chunk as well
right so there's two ways to write this
I could write it looking at the current
one to see if it's zero but then I would
need it and if in here that does if you
know if stars' can break right here or I
can use a for loop that checks it here
and then do the the plus plus string
count thing it's six of one half dozen
of the other
I don't know that that there's strong
opinion about it I'm happy to write it
the other way as well
so like the just show what the other way
would be what I mean by that is I could
take scan and move it outside right I
and then I would say that this is just a
four i looped it looks like that every
time through here I do a plus plus scan
like so and then here I do a thing that
says you know if scan zero or equals
zero break and then this thing does like
if you know scan zero equals zero then
I'm also at the end and we always do the
count like that right I don't know that
there's necessarily like a clear reason
to prefer one over the other
[Music]
yeah I don't know furthermore you could
technically you could still put the wat
you could put the wild down here if you
wanted get rid of this and actually just
count it but you know anyway that's the
other way to write it if you like that
one better by all means write it that
way I don't know that there's a clear
reason to write it one way or the other
so because the answer is still no to
doing my Comp Sci homework for me yes it
is I'm not gonna do your Comp Sci
homework for you have to do it yourself
you're not gonna learn anything if you
don't do it yourself Brian okay sorry I
missed the scan check first which of
course would mean scan zero would never
happen
yes exactly a bit off-topic birthday
intrinsics 4-bit interleaving I can't
find on the Intel intrinsic web pages
but thinking they might not have named
it interleave or somesuch
can you be more specific about bit
interleaving do you mean literally
taking every other bit so like take one
bit from one value one bit from another
value one bit from one value like that
like each individual bit is that is that
what you're asking
once the game is completed and I know
that will take a long while are there
any plans to do similar educational
series no should those pieces also be
passed to update asset package from PNG
as far as I can tell you're pricing them
out but using them yeah I don't think so
so I think what's probably gonna happen
not to you know spoiler warning up the
asset package from PNG is probably gonna
take something we could pass it don't
get me wrong maybe we will but probably
what I'll do is have a parsing function
I call here that produces a 8x8 that
says what all of the tags should be
based on these names and then that that
is probably what I'll pass to update
asset package from ping probably don't
quote me on that
but that's probably what will happen
they will get used though they're just I
don't have anything yet for it
VT element yes yes every other bit mm
every other get huh
so I'll be honest nothing comes to mind
but for pretty much the entire almost
the entirety of my sim deprogramming
I've always been confined to sse2 and I
don't remember there being one in sse2
but it may just be that I never needed
to use that I can't think offhand of any
time I would have had to do that so I
think I probably wouldn't remember it I
probably would have seen it if it was
there but I probably wouldn't remember
it was there
uh so I'm assuming so which I don't know
which you're talking about here but
let's say you're talking about modern
ships so we're looking at these and you
know you want to see if what with the
unpack with the unpack stuff is so
obviously you can in you can interleave
byte at a time that's what the unpacked
low epi8 would do yeah not not looking
great
[Music]
trying to think
wait what did that really suggest that
there's no bit manipulation in any of
these other ones all right that seems a
bit weird because masks move is that is
a bit manipulation in a sense right yeah
I don't know um
so I'm thinking that insert is probably
the only thing I've never looked at that
could do something like that
and I don't think it does so all I can
say is I don't remember one but there's
definitely some of these that I never
looked at because they weren't available
at the time and there might be something
in here that can help you so I would
just keep that in mind
[Music]
insert still only works on on bytes at a
time
yeah I know
sorry I really don't know blend
also is only bytes at a time if I
remember correctly
pretty sure gathers are only bytes at a
time - I just I don't know so the one
thing I could think of was the mask
moves and it's not that it's it's not
mask move it's it's move mask it's the
it's the opposite it moved these the one
thing I could think of was these and
they don't really do what you want but
they're at least something that actually
it actually takes bits
unfortunately it it's going out to the
general-purpose registers if I remember
correctly I so it's designed for
branching and stuff like that so I still
it probably really just doesn't help you
but it does do that interleave so let's
say you've got you know 16 bytes in a
register you wish you a move mask you
get the top bit of each you can then
shift it one over do it again and get
the top bit of each right so that does
do a bit interleave but I don't know the
speed of it and it's not it's not
internal to the like you want I think
wants something internal to the xmm
registers and this goes from xmm to
purpose which is not probably not not
what you want at all
so yeah I'm sorry I'm just I'm having
trouble thinking of anything that's
gonna help sorry
it could be that once you go up to
avx-512
you know it's in the mix sorry I I
really I can't think anything
you
Brian I seem to have missed a lot of the
memory arena work but you create a
temporary memory Reena where do you pass
in the original memory that you've
allocated normally I would think global
variable but if in the game layer that
would get your set when you reloaded so
currently the way it works is it just if
if you don't provide any memory it just
asks the platform layer for it
and that's it Geoff Phoenix I don't know
if this has been asked for but would you
consider having your vods do reruns on
days you aren't going to stream just so
people can still participate in the chat
you mean like why wouldn't they just go
to the episode guide and watch them
whenever they want like look what would
be the point of the rerun is it just to
have the chat or on my day to day I find
myself using standard string very often
should I write my own string library or
what other options would you recommend
if so how do I handle allocations a
single huge allocation doesn't seem to
the right choice since I'm not writing
game allocations are obviously something
that's kind of a broader topics is kind
of hard for me to discuss without
knowing what you're doing but standard
string is a piece of garbage and you
should never use it for anything it's
it's just terrible so yeah definitely
don't use standard string I would highly
recommend writing your own string
library even if that string library just
does raw allocations anyway it's still
gonna be better than standard string
because standard string is absolutely
horrid it does everything wrong that you
can do wrong don't ever touch it it's
awful just absolutely terrible I would
use something very much like the buffer
struct that I just wrote out there and
write a little library that works with
those and how you want to do your memory
allocation is kind of a broader topic
that isn't really restricted to string
libraries what I would point out is that
once you have a count string where you
say here's the number of characters and
here's a string you find that you really
have to allocate memory all that often
when you concatenate two strings
together you do but that's about it for
absolutely everything else you can just
use sub-regions and it works pretty well
so you'll find your allocation count
goes down dramatically when you stop
using the old terminated strings which
helps make the memory less of an issue
because even if you just use a
general-purpose allocator and allocate
every time you're still probably going
to be fine I'll just have the Kaval so I
was curious why you don't have your
marquessate on twitch say someone misses
something you said wrote and wants to go
back in this and watch quickly there's
no way to do that until the basel on
youtube because the pre streams are
supposed to be just for people who watch
they if you want to hear the pre stream
you gotta show up if some I related
thought to Gigi Nate have you ever
considered using a program that overlays
the twitch chat into OBS I see
entertainment focused streamers using
them and it's really nice for when they
reference something from chat and you're
watching the YouTube app allows for you
know I don't like that because that
allows other people to basically post
into the video which I don't allow
months ago when you were playing
intrinsic you added one to use this a
four point two instruction this isn't
supported by most older AMD chips like
mine we consider workaround for this
possibly but no guarantees all right
let's take a look here looks like we
need to update Google Chrome maybe I'll
do that later
all right thanks everyone for joining me
for an episode of handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
with the series at home you can always
hear the game on handmade hero org and
it comes with the source code so you can
play around with it
we also now have some random new website
stuff that you can go to which is kind
of fun we've got the handmade fund which
is a thing that supports community
projects I would highly recommend
checking that out and you get a little
bonus pack that's fun with a bunch of
different source code things from old
products of mine that's definitely
something to check out we also have a
watch page now that has the live stream
on it when it's when it's streaming and
also it has the episode guide integrated
into it so that's like kind of a nice
place you can go to watch stuff and yeah
it all works pretty well it also has the
schedule posted on here so as soon as I
go off the air this stream is replaced
with something that tells you when I'm
going to be on the air again which is
pretty handy
so yeah highly recommend checking that
out as well and it has hot links on it
for other things like pre or in the game
we're signing up for the mailing list or
going to the forum's that sort of stuff
so definitely check out the new website
and also you can check out any of our
Molly Rocket websites just by clicking
on the little icon at the top and that
goes to all of our pages for quick links
as well so anything that you might want
to do we've got up there and now for you
because we move the handmade hero
website over to our general website
stuff that handles all the stuff on
Molly rockets so it's a lot more
functional and interesting now that used
to be so check that out I'll be back
here tomorrow to do some more on the
asset loading we've got our stuff self
in position to actually process the PNG
data now and put it into the asset file
so that's what we want to do next time
that should be pretty straightforward
but then I think when we get to the tags
part that's when we're gonna have to
start really putting on our thinking
caps
so tomorrow should probably be pretty
straightforward but next weekend that
might be a little bit saucy ER so
definitely you'll you'll be able to have
a couple days of rest before we head
into that next week but tomorrow should
be pretty straight
we already wrote the PNG reader so we're
just doing something that scans those
blocks and and looks at when it actually
needs to update stuff shouldn't be too
hard
hopes me back here for that till then
have fun programming and I'll see
everyone on the Internet take it easy
everybody