hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero sure we could a complete game
live on stream uh we um
we don't really know what we're gonna do
today um
because we
we sort of finished the layout stuff
that we wanted to do
and i think in terms of like moving
forward on gameplay stuff
probably the next good thing to work on
would be like
trying to play around with uh like
with combat stuff just so i can get a
feel for like
how to make that interesting like how
like essentially i kind of like the tile
stuff
it worked out roughly the way that i
thought it would um
and so i i like more or less
where the uh where that's going uh
and i think it's good enough now that we
can play with it
i don't know why what's going on here
oops
there we go um and so i
i don't know on the other hand much
about the combat
so i kind of want some way of
like investigating that and figuring out
like
just sort of some basic ways that that
can be fun
um and part of that may just be like
making sure that it feels
good and that's you know just a matter
of like
polish but uh there's also just a
question of like what exactly
you do in there right um so at least
at the moment i like the the tiles uh
and you know there's a couple things too
while we're doing the gameplay stuff
we should fix the tile so that uh it it
triggers when you land on them
just so you can see so it looks better
uh
and then there's also a couple other
things like we want to fix the like um
going down too far issue uh where
you're allowed to like push them down
really far so there's a couple things
we'd like to do
but on the whole i would say like kind
of minor and we can get to those at any
time
whereas like combat stuff we just don't
know right so i'd like to go in
and and try to make like punching feel
good we don't really have anything in
there except for just the fact that we
you know proved we could animate this
little glove thing um
but i don't really know how this is
going to feel and
furthermore
um furthermore i don't actually know
uh how we might want to deal with
the like you'll notice this this dude
just left right um we also have that
weird room thing where if you go
outside of the room it can't it doesn't
find a room volume
and we would should probably fix that
not that it will happen because
that's just a bug that those go down far
enough anyway but it's still just kind
of weird so
we we don't also know like what we want
our enemies to do so for example right
now that guy's just moving randomly and
you can see he just like left
right he just walks out of the room that
he's in uh
and you know i mean it's kind of
interesting to be able to have enemies
that can move from room to room but at
the same time it's like well that's not
very interesting
from the standpoint of like actually
playing the game so we probably need
things that are like
okay enemies you know well you know
maybe having them seek the player will
be enough to prevent that
maybe it won't i don't know um but we
probably need some idea
of like we don't want all the enemies
like leaving the rooms they're in
and that because that doesn't really
make for very good gameplay either
so i think you know i don't know and
like i've said many times before on the
stream
my understanding of how usually to
proceed in game design
um which i don't do so i don't pretend
to know but my understanding is that
like usually you want to sort of play
with things
and try out some ideas and try to follow
ideas that feel good when you actually
put them together
because much like with programming you
can't really know ahead of time
all of the subtle issues that might be
involved in what you're doing
and so if you try to like plan
everything out ahead of time
it doesn't really work very well and so
you know
i'm gonna try and follow that advice
right
um so uh let's go ahead and take a look
at that
and and we'll go from there by the way i
noticed the chat was talking about the
fact that i'm not facing what i'm doing
yes
i flipped it and everyone freaked out
they were like no you have to be facing
the other way
so you guys need to argue uh among
yourselves
about that uh because that is not my
responsibility
that was that was you you folks
not knowing what you wanted so you're
going to have to uh
you're going to have to to to have your
own little um
yeah you're going to have to have your
own little little argument there
all right so what do we want to do here
i i guess uh
gosh i just don't know because like i
said this isn't really something i do
but i guess what i'd like to do
is maybe have i i'd like to maybe start
out
by having the combat be a little bit
asymmetric
so i'd like to start out by having
you on squares which you are
right um and
the enemy that you're fighting just
floating
so so the enemy is not like on
a square at all right
um the enemy will be like
the enemy will be
moving continuously over the board like
a hovering thing
uh and i feel like that would be
probably the best
option that's my guess right
um that's what i want to start with and
there will be hopping enemies for sure
but i think those will be like later
so i think the first thing you encounter
would be
a floating enemy and so its movement and
your movement are different
because i think that's somewhat
interesting um
so so i don't know uh but i think that's
what i'd like to start with
and i don't really remember to what
extent we preserved we had some test
code in for something like that a long
time ago
just because we know we did um
and if i remember correctly there was
ways of doing that
like uh
um i don't i don't know what that means
but uh we had like the familiar and
the familiar for example uh as far as i
know this thing just kind of floated
around right now i don't know
uh we haven't tried it in a while so i
don't know we probably need to update
some of that code or whatever
but we can start with that and try to
make an enemy
that uses basically that path that
basically you know does
does the same basic stuff which
we can go to uh
like the room gen thing and just have it
everywhere that we were adding monstars
um we could add sorry world gen
we could add uh just the
familiar and see what happens now i
don't actually remember
i think the there is no actual like
logic to it at the moment right it just
kind of slaps down
uh enemies in rooms
any any dungeon room i think uh so like
when it does add
uh what is it create dungeon
in here it does a thing where it adds uh
something like this uh it adds a snake
so so this snake pattern so i assume
that we can just add a familiar
and see if it works right it's just been
kind of sitting in there
for a long time uh and i think we can do
that so if you look
um the snake pattern is somewhat
complicated because it actually adds a
bunch of stuff
we can have sort of a more generic uh
entity pattern thing
that just plops down uh anything for now
so i can do like you know um
single enemy pattern i don't know just
some pattern that we're gonna place
in here uh and what i can do is just
literally ask for a random tile anywhere
uh and then place it down and i think
that's all i need to do
excuse me um
and again i don't actually know we added
the familiars
it looks like we still have the code for
how it worked
um in here when we added it so what i'll
do is i'll just kind of grab
that code for now because i don't have
any better idea
um and we'll just go in here and and
make a thing that like places the head
and the shadow on there
uh and it and for now it's going to be a
familiar which will not attack you it'll
just follow you around
right so if i compile this i should get
any errors that are like
you know what do we need to fix to make
this work uh the way we would expect
so first of all this was done before we
were using the construction grid so we
just move
to using the construction grid to get
the region um for occupying here
what you can see here is we're using
this pattern here where we do place
entity on traversible right and it's
it's this kind of
code where we just say we want to put it
on this tile so
this code specifically we can just
replace uh
here by by calling um
calling this code and we're going to use
the head tile instead of the standing on
that was the thing that used to get
passed
so in theory i believe we can just do
that
and that will place entity onto the tile
that was supposedly open
um using the find random tile thing
and then when we do the add piece code
here we're just
we just have to make sure that we can
construct a familiar
using uh the stuff that we you know
basically we just need to uh change this
stuff so that it
gives the proper asset tags to
add the familiar so again not much to
really do here we don't have to
actually assign an entity position
because that will get taken care of for
us
so really we're just giving it a
familiar brain we're giving it
a location we're replacing it on this
this tile here
and then we just need to update this
code so if i look at the way that we've
been doing that
in fact i can just go down here and you
can see it
so when we actually do the piece
construction
you can see this is the piece here um
right let's see it so if i
grab that stuff i don't know if we we
probably need to do
uh some extra like stuff where we
actually do the connections and such
right um and i don't know about shadows
because
kind of now we're not i don't think
we're putting those in anymore
manually so it may be that we don't
really
care about any of that stuff we do have
the peace move
bob offset part of things which we may
want to do now i don't know
how we've been like doing that looks
like you just called the flop you just
added up the flags at the end
still like we used to so in theory that
should just work um
and we probably don't need like most the
rest of this stuff
apparently the familiar was larger than
so you know i don't know if it still
should be or not uh
but you know it was and then it was also
just like floating
directly right it didn't have an offset
so that
may all be wrong um we don't really know
and i'm just gonna try it and we'll see
what happens
uh oh yeah this is supposed to be entity
and this is just
the piece so i think that's about
it uh the base asset in this case for
the body and it might
it probably should be the head right i
assume uh but here that's going to come
from the pattern
so the base asset so that people can
change like the look of it right
um so i suppose that just gets added
uh like this i and so now i don't know
um
i suppose we should reduce the number of
of these this is gonna get old
if i have to i probably need a hotkey
that's just like open
open all of the doors in this room
because we're testing
because that's going to get old pretty
fast right
but you know so hopefully
let's take a look uh we are able to add
a familiar here i don't actually see one
though
did i ever actually add it you know what
i don't think i ever actually added it i
think i spaced yeah i did
so you can see here like if we just
wanted to add one of these to rooms
generally uh here's the familiar
um and actually uh i'm just gonna call
this enemy for now
because we're not gonna actually want it
to be familiar eventually so
i'm gonna change that anyway but we'll
just do all right this is a single enemy
pattern
um i don't know which of these we want
but i'm gonna leave those
as they are for the moment uh and
and now we'll try again uh and also i'll
go in
and do uh the so there's the
there's the tile switch pattern i'm just
going to if zero that out
you know it's working just fine so i'll
if zero that out
and i'll also remove we were drawing
lights before and i'm also going to turn
that off because i don't have any real
need to
see that at the moment so in the
uh the piece type light code there i'm
just going to turn off the little cubes
that were floating
wherever we had lights because we don't
need to see them they just are where
they are
now so i turned off the switches uh oh
and there's the familiar
so i think now we can just go ahead and
try to turn that code back on and see if
we can get the familiar floating around
which again we don't actually care about
uh
the familiar per se i just want to get
floating working properly
so that we can use it more generally so
you can see here
where the brain code executes it's
looking for the head
it tries to find a location
it looks like and i don't know what
blocked
is supposed to mean i guess it's just
can it occupy the place where it is i'm
not sure what that means
why would it be looking for that
so so i don't really know
i don't really know what this first part
is supposed to be doing
so there's a target p right
um and i guess
just looking at this it looks like
nobody ever uses it
so i'm guessing we just cut and pasted
some of this code when we wanted to keep
it
but it doesn't look like anyone uses it
right
oh no okay sir never mind it is used
right down here at the bottom
so this applies an acceleration to this
character
based on the target p so it's got a
little like this is a proportional
derivative controller
here right um also known as the pdc
uh so just a basic spring attached
uh from the uh
from the position that you are at
currently to wherever it is you want to
go
and it was supposed to kind of spring
them along so it does look like it's
actually using it
and the question of course is why is
this target p
not actually therefore being effective
so what i might say uh
is the blocked part of things i'm just
gonna turn
off for now so i'm gonna say
that um well actually you know i don't
even have to do that i can just do this
so i just want to see what happens if
this code is still working
it looks like it's looking for a hero to
follow and so i'm assuming that if i do
that
uh i can go in and debug that code now
to find out why it's not actually moving
right because you can see it's not
moving it should be locating me
it may just not be finding it um
so in other words it may like be doing
this and not getting anything
back or this isn't working anymore right
again this code is ancient we just have
never used it
um with any of the new stuff so
let's just go in and see because now we
know that this case won't
be uh obviated by the the traversable
check up here so we take that out of the
system
uh and we know that we're just going to
use this target p
and off we go so let's just see what
happens here
i'm gonna quick set to debug mode
um and just see what's going on
and that's going to be in the brain code
right here so i'm just going to set like
a
i guess i'm not going to set the break
point yet i'm going to like slowly debug
mode hop
my uh hero up here
into this room
so that i know that this dude is there
and
now i'm just gonna look at that uh brain
code here and just see what happens i
have no idea what it will do
so uh it does look like the target p
is getting assigned here right and
if i look at the head p
and the target p i should be able to see
i mean i mean they're definitely
different um
so you know i don't really quite
understand
it maybe did we take acceleration out of
the system it's entirely possible i
suppose
uh
i hate the fact that when you step out
of things you can't look inside you used
to be able to do that
all the time and now you can't anymore
and it sucks
so uh let me go ahead and oops
let me go ahead and take a look in here
at
the different slots and i'm going to
see if i can determine what happens with
this ddp
so this is the acceleration on here
and you can see that it's trying to push
relatively hard
so it looks like the familiar code is is
still in play
and so that just suggests we probably
just nerfed that stuff
on the entity side so meaning we
probably just don't
allow that stuff anymore and so it's
you know using a physics thing that
you know we just don't do because
everybody's been doing the tile based
movement
so if i look uh at this code right
we're just gonna take a look and see
where this movement stuff
would would normally be happening and is
any of it happening anymore
uh you can see all the rendering code
here um
and so that all that stuff is just stuff
that happens downwind of determining
where the enemy actually is uh and you
can see
that we've got like planted which is
just they're
sitting in one place hopping which is
when they're you know
kind of doing a a jump sort of thing and
then you know there's
some stuff for like swiping or offset
angles that like determine where things
are none of that stuff
is going to do any kind of physical
movement at all
so it kind of looks like
it the yeah
it kind of looks like we just got rid of
it
right this was the code that would have
done
this stuff and we just said that's not
happening anymore
so i don't actually know why
because it's been so long since we've
done any of that stuff
but at this point we don't actually use
any of the movement stuff it seems like
we would probably
like to so my assumption is
that you know this at least this code
um we probably want to keep
inside some kind of a like free like a
movement mode
free kind of thing um
so like movement mode floating
i i would think which is currently not
used anywhere
um if we had a movement mode floating i
would think it would do
this thing you know like i would think
it would do a
check to see if there was any velocity
on this thing and then it would move it
if it was and again i don't really know
if that's what we want or not um or
how we even really want to process that
stuff
but i'm just going to start playing
around with this until i get
uh until i'm satisfied with it
so i'm going to go ahead and say that up
here we're just going to turn this on
for now
and we'll see what happens nothing good
will come of it i'm sure but that's just
what we're going to do
and then similarly we need to set this
thing to a movement mode
floating because it's not going to set
itself
you know so in here when something's
floating around
what we would like to do is set the
movement mode uh for the head
to always be that so the movement mode
should be floating all the time and
you know maybe there's some other modes
that this thing can go through but
you know at the moment we don't we don't
have any
so it's just gonna go uh do its thing
i can keep running from where i am uh
and take a look
uh how do i tell this to keep running
keep running please there we go
um so there and that that worked so
that's fine
uh and and so it just looks like the
problem with that was that you know we
we kind of took out that
that movement mode so actually all the
code still worked uh it just kind of had
to be rewired up
uh and that's fine so you know
that's that's a possibility for an enemy
oh and here
there you go
um so as you can see these folks are not
subject to any
uh actual collisions right now well i
mean that's not entirely true
uh i they are sort of
subject to collisions but they're only
subject to collision volumes
so one of the things that we haven't
been doing for example
is we haven't been placing collision
volumes in
like walls we just don't put movement
things there we don't put um
what's the word form we don't put
traversibles so you can't hop there
because there's no traversable but one
of these
floating people could just go right
through
because there are no collision volumes
there to stop them and they
only check in that move entity routine
they only check against collision
volumes
so if we wanted to we could
check uh collision volumes
but i think the idea here
was that this code was what
this is what that that code was supposed
to be doing i think
i'm not really sure so what i'm going to
do is temporarily turn that on
let's and we'll look at it because i
don't really know what it did we'll have
to look
um but i suspect that's what that was
for no it doesn't look like it looks
like it's still able to do it
yeah so uh i'm not sure
what this was supposed to do um
doesn't make a whole lot of sense either
uh which is why i want to turn it on to
see if it somehow magically worked
because
when i looked at it before i was like
that doesn't make much sense
um so yeah this this does not really
make any sense to me so
probably what i would say here is
that what we would rather do uh
i would i would i would like to get rid
of this entirely
uh and what we would rather do is say
look it's floating we're gonna try and
find a location
for it to go to and when we do
we would probably like to say you know
when we when we find a traversible
a long array uh we
need to see whether or not we could have
gone
when we're going to move get closest
traversable along rey will look for a
traversible
that it can go to in the direction that
it's trying to go
right the problem with this
is that it doesn't matter how many
squares in between
where you are and where it finds it
doesn't matter if there are actual
places
you can go right
so i think what we in a sense
we could
we could just say like if i get rid of
all this stuff
right
if we just say look
get the closest sim space uh traversable
from wherever we are oh and i guess the
occupying part here
i guess we do need this though um
so really here we would we would want to
do something slightly different
which is we would want to say
i see so i guess i do see what this code
does all this code does is it tracks
what traversable we're on
that's it right so it says look
we're going to try to occupy the place
that we're floating over uh and the
blocked part
seems a little weird but we'll look at
that later all i was going to say is
so this part here where we do get
closest reversible along rey
i think all we have to do is clamp this
we just clamp this in fact i don't even
really know
why we would need to do that
i mean i get oh so you know what i take
it back
so we probably do just want to slap
collision volumes in for these things
because now i think about it
you want floating people to be able to
float over chasms
so we really do need to know the
difference between walls so
forget it this code is fine i guess
we're just gonna leave it
so i guess what we do is in room gen
when we're placing walls
we should place collision volumes right
so we want to be able to place collision
volumes
uh and and if we look so if i go into
the entity code and i draw
what collision volumes we're actually
seeing here
we can just go ahead and like
and watch right um
there we go here are the collision
volumes
right and so for whatever reason you
know we
i i guess that's even much better than i
was thinking
if that's true then that means all of
these already have collision volumes so
all we really have to do is enable
the uh collision volumes to let this uh
saucy gentleman
collide so i guess
it's actually easier than i thought it
was going to be
of course he stopped moving for some
reason which i guess i don't
know why that happened but
um oh because i accidentally deleted the
head movement code
um so i guess this code worked even
better
than we thought because um all we have
to do
is give this fellow a collision volume
and then i guess he will collide
so i don't know i
i guess it's better than i thought it
was that's so so he's nice if the code
is better than we thought it was
i'm a little surprised um so here where
we do make simple collision volume for
example this part right here
uh we would want to just just add one
for this
this dude uh so you know i don't
actually know
um if there's anything special i guess
it can just use
this the same kind as the other one was
using
i'm not sure there's any magic to it um
we may want to change the size of it uh
or who knows what
like that probably looks a little bit
too small you know
um so so maybe we don't want to do that
uh maybe we want this to be more like
you know
something like that
well i don't know
hard to say um but anyway in theory
now uh i would think
that collisions would now prevent
this fellow from moving i don't actually
know that that's true so we'll take a
look
um but we'll see so it doesn't look like
that collision was prevented though so i
guess not
i don't actually know when entity is any
collide set for any of these things
though
um because that's the other thing like
if the if this flag isn't set
yeah so all of these are not set to
colliding so
the other thing i think we would have to
do is say that it was
and the only thing that's a little weird
about that is i don't
know that uh
i i don't know if collides like i'm not
totally sure
why that's a thing like i don't know why
we don't just always have collisions if
there was some
rational reason for that to keep that uh
currently or not i'm not sure
but it looks like and they can still go
through these walls presumably because
those are not set to collide
so i don't really know why
i don't really know why we have this
flag
um because it seems like you would just
not add a collision volume
if something didn't collide you know
what i'm saying so i'm a
little bit again we're just kind of
paging this code back in
so we you know we've said a bunch of
times like i'm not sure why x happened
and then it you know turns out there's a
good
reason for x or at least it worked
better than we thought so i'm not ready
to say that it doesn't need to be there
um i'm just not sure
uh i'm just not sure i understand what
we were intending that to do
so when we call move entity here you can
see us iterating to try and move the
entity
um this code is probably crap uh yeah
um but uh
when we move like
it looks like it's not gonna do this
so it's not gonna do this if we don't
have these set
so again i don't know why um i don't
know why we have that flag
uh if i just turn off that flag i'm
curious what happens
because it seems like just don't add a
collision volume i don't know
why we have that right um
looks like for some reason that
gentleman can't get through but i'm not
sure why because it doesn't look like
there's anything there to stop them
it might be that this is too low but at
least hey we know that
it is actually colliding so in the makes
a simple grounded collision
i'm going to take a look at the symbol
ground collision uh offset z presumably
needs to be
slightly higher up off the ground so
that it can float around
but other than that it looks fine
if i go ahead and run um yeah so i don't
know
why that why uh that person's being
stopped there
when the collisions are turned on if i
go uh
look at it a little bit more closely
here
like it sure doesn't look like anything
would be stopping
right like that looks like you would fit
through just fine
obviously that's not true
so i'm not really sure i'm not sure
what's going on there
um if there's some kind of weird
yeah if there's some kind of weird thing
i don't know but uh in terms of can
collide
yeah i don't see a lot of reason not to
just turn this off for now so i'm gonna
see
i'm just gonna see if we can remove that
flag entirely
because i can see having uh stuff that
says what to do
on collision like um
i can see having stuff that says look
when this thing collides
let it keep going but you know it
you have to at least want collision
processing to take place otherwise why
did you put
uh you know why did you put one on there
you know what i'm saying so it doesn't
make a lot of sense to me
um so it just kind of seems like
something must be up um i don't know
so if i were to to turn this off
completely i just want to see
uh what happens here uh
you know here's us adding these flags to
everybody
yeah i mean i just i i'm just gonna turn
this off
i'm just gonna get rid of it i i think
it's gonna be redundant and i
i don't know it's it's just adding
complexity for no real reason
um so let's just get rid of it
uh
okay uh and now we know that
that this saucy gentleman uh is is stuck
um
and now we just have to see why is that
movement code
uh busted right because there's
no obvious reason uh why you can't move
through there um
and and so like i said uh well uh okay
so you know what it could be if it's the
room
if it's colliding with the room boundary
you know what i'm saying um which
which would be right there so it's that
that's probably what's happening
it's colliding with the room boundary so
i would suspect that again what we want
to do there
is just say hey uh
when you collide with the room boundary
you
you know you just do whatever it is that
you do when you enter that room
um but you don't have to actually
this is what i say so rather than have
this can collide
like what we want to do instead is talk
about what happens when you collide
right and so we're effectively
i think wanting to we want to replace
that flag that was like does it collide
or doesn't it
with what is the response right
so in here we have like this response
for example
uh which is really horrible um
like yeah i mean this this code is very
old and crappy
um but this response here is like
is just like one thing we would do right
this i don't know what
this was for climbing up and down
stairwells
smooth this was like for smooth going up
ramps
right
this is so old um so in here i think we
just want to process a collision
right so so when this happens we just
want to say look
uh you know don't just assume
that we're going to do some kind of a uh
you know assume that we always check
collision volumes because if you didn't
want to know when things collided
then you wouldn't add a collision volume
right
and then instead of what we were doing
before
which is just always applying the same
kind of collision stuff
what we want to do here is actually do
something smart
uh whenever we see one
assuming so in here where we do hit this
right um this code
is the code that stops us so what we
would like to do
is have this speculative collide thing
we could actually you know we could
actually do something like this
where we say look if it's not a room
then
you you know you can't go right
that kind of thing um
and so again we want to start building
this out and so we kind of want to
replace like that
that entity flag collides i don't think
we need that anymore
you collide if you have collision
volumes and then what we're going to
want to do
is have effectively an enum in there
that says
when you collide with this entity what
is the action that we're supposed to be
taking
right and we may want it to be even more
complicated than just an enum but what
we want to do now is say look
when something collides we need to take
an action
that action may just be as simple as
stopping someone from moving
but it may be more like oh we need to
uh you know trigger some kind of a
combat event
because that's what we're going to be
working on for the next few weeks right
is like combat stuff
so we're going to want to know okay
these two things collided
maybe they can just pass right through
each other but maybe they apply damage
maybe something you know some particles
effects happen you know all that kind of
stuff
we're going to kind of need to
have you know a more complex notion of
what happens with two things hit each
other
uh so this crap is gone like i don't
care about this at all
uh and so right now we'll just do this
but but pretty in
just a moment uh we will update this
code
to use something more complicated and i
want to say that we also
might be able to collapse some code down
here because
don't we also use these collision
volumes for like camera
like lookables and stuff so we might be
able to like kind of roll those systems
in together
um but i don't know so anyway
let's turn off room boundary collisions
and see and and yeah that was it
um so now we we at least know that that
these collisions are working
right um and so you can kind of see that
dude even
grinding along the wall there which is
nice right
um and and i think that's it
presumably now they also can't go
through the snake uh
i don't know how to test that i have to
kind of yeah there you go so that seems
good
um uh and i think we're okay but
the main problem we're gonna have now
and i think this even happened just now
right i think those two guys are like
locked is that like the collision code
is super crappy as well
um and so what we probably want to do is
actually get some good collision code
in there too right um so
face collision code and and then you
know maybe let's let's also put in while
we're at it
some like glove collision right because
you can see me punching through here
they both have collision volumes
we would know that the glove hit and we
should do something
right we should right
i thought exactly the same thing when i
said that so
yeah as i was saying like that doesn't
sound good
can i say
um so all right
so that's all good um so one of the
things we could do
here is also like change the
way that the glove works to be an actual
so the glove right now
since i want combat to start being a
thing we're doing here
uh the glove right now doesn't is not
moving
under physics so so you have to
understand
um some basic concepts here
and you know we've never really talked
about them too extensively on handmade
hero and i'm not going to belabor them
right now because
we're just kind of playing with gameplay
stuff and it's it's not super important
that you understand it right now but
it's worth in putting in your head just
the notion
that in general there's kind of two
broad
way you know two fundamental categories
you can classify movement schemes into
uh especially when you're talking about
from a gameplay perspective
uh and the idea here is that
you can have movement schemes that are
sort of
based on a movement algorithm
like a prescribed way
a prescribed path in which something
will trace out a shape
we generally think of these things we
use terms for them such as generalized
coordinates
and what we mean by that is that there's
some kind of value
like for the glove there's like the
angle of swipe
you know and we just run that angle and
in the glove swipes
you know what i mean and it doesn't
matter there's no more complexity in the
system to it
than that there's just a few parameters
that describe completely
where the thing is supposed to be and by
feeding those parameters into the system
you get back out the position of the
glove
right and it doesn't mean you can't do
physics
you actually can do physics on those
systems generalized coordinate physics
systems are a
very well studied well understood thing
but what it does mean is that the system
will always be constrained
to occupy a space allowed by those
generalized coordinates
so if the only thing the generalized
coordinates can represent is
that path of the glove then we could
start doing physics on it but we would
never be have be able
we would never be able to have it get
knocked away from that path
it could be stopped on its way through
the path and come back
right but it could never be knocked
totally away
and and that sort of thing so
it's worth understanding between
generalized coordinates which are that
kind of system
and then a system where you're just
talking about
straightforward uh you know
kinematic or dynamics simulations that
just have like position and velocity
right a lot of times these things are
called like lagrangian systems
i don't know if there's a really good
term for them just
rigid body dynamics just general like
the
the completely free formulated version
of them
i don't know what the diff what the name
is because generalized coordinates
you still do rigid body dynamics on if
you want to like i said
we're not doing that here this is purely
kinematic it's just setting a number
and you get out the position but you
could have been doing ridge by dinosaur
the uh the corresponding way which is
just saying look we're going to have
these things be fully 3d
simulated we're just going to completely
allow that
and then we're going to try and
constrain
using either you know springs like the
floating head
or other techniques we're going to try
to use those techniques
to enforce a type of motion that we want
but it's strictly an attempt to get that
path
it may not get that path right it's just
going to push towards that path and
either it gets it or doesn't
so i think for this kind of game
that's over all that was a very
long-winded wind-up
for me to say that i think in this kind
of game
i actually want to simulate the glove
as a free-floating body for a number of
reasons
one is i want active glove control to be
like a big thing of what you do in the
game
so i want a lot of unintended quote
unquote
where they're quite intended but you
know whatever uh
consequences of the glove being a
separate body not
attached to the hero for example
if you walk through this door without
first like pushing the glove forwards
i want the glove to get caught on the
door
and come in behind you so that when you
hop through
you can't punch right away you have to
wait for the glove to come in
right i want stuff like that to happen
in this game
like the glove managing where the glove
is
should be something that a good player
does uh
the door example is pretty stupid
because you know it would take you five
seconds to learn
to always push the glove forward but
that's just like
one example of things you know that we
could do
there's lots of stuff we could do where
you know keeping the glove in a
particular position
is something that the player actively
learns to do better
so when they first start they they're
crappy at it
and the glove is always in a bad
position and they're not getting as many
hits off
as they could or they're not doing as
much damage as they could
because they're just not managing the
glove very well uh
and then later when they get better at
it they're really good at glove
management
and their oh the glove is always in a
good place and they know how to like
sequence hits so that when they hit
something
they know how to manage like the bounce
back on the glove and all these other
sorts of things
um so what i'd like to do is decouple
the glove as the first step we're gonna
do for combat i'd like to decouple this
sort of like
kinematic movement system we got here i
want to get that out
and i want to make the glove be more of
an active management
um where so you you're kind of like when
you punch
it's less of a like i push the button to
punch and more of a like
i'm pushing buttons at times to control
where the glove is
and obviously there's a lot of subtlety
to that but you know
this is why i say um so design forward
versus design backward right
go listen to some game designers the
ones that i tend to respect
all say that you you experiment with the
gameplay ideas
in the game and you learn from them so
i'm not going to say anything else about
what we're doing because i don't know
i'm just going to assume that we will
learn
when i go ahead and decouple this from
you know when i decouple this uh this
glove from when i decouple
the glove from being kinematic so that
it's floating
at that point i think we will
we will just explore what kinds of
control
we can impart to the glove
and and i will try to find
something that feels like what i want
the game to feel like right
and like i said that my understanding
from listening to the game designers i
respect of which there are very few
um they all seem to say that
and nobody says go write a document out
that
like details all the things the glove's
gonna do it's like
no you know you can brainstorm and have
a notebook filled with ideas
and that's great because you need those
as raw materials for your explorations
go nuts it's fine but when it actually
comes down to
the day you you are doing some design
that day
you never just implement something
because your notebook told you to you
always have to treat it like an
exploration like the notebook
was like a map of some buried treasure
that you're looking for
but you're not sure where it is right um
so you need to just kind of explore and
have like a
you know a feel for that
um okay also you notice we really need
to fix our filtering on lighting you
notice like
where we get nice smooth lighting in
here and then the hard edge
there uh which we don't even really have
an explanation for why that happens
right um and we sort of know something
about how those
functions fall off but it's just kind of
like weird that we have that issue
um it's neither here nor there but
it's like a thresholding problem right
um
yeah doesn't matter so anyway
i'm going to go ahead and decouple that
so now
where we have that glove uh you we've
got this
add player thing right and and you can
see we actually created
a separate one here and we've got this
movement mode
angle offset and so we really just want
that to not be true anymore
and all of this stuff uh just goes away
right so it's just gonna be in movement
mode floating
uh which means that the glove is just
gonna do its own thing and it'll just be
kind of like you know the hero
has this glove if i run the game now uh
because there's no controller on the
glove it should just
sort of you know move around with us
right um and you can
okay i guess we reset those
things i'm like what the heck happened
there
all right um so hold on a second
so uh this must set that
on the glove probably does
yeah so okay so the glove yeah the glove
actually gets this stuff
set all right so uh
forget all this right like we don't want
any of this happening anymore
so all this should kind of go away you
know
that goes away uh and then in here
where we've got the movement mode uh
floating thing
this is what we actually want uh and so
you know we we we want this uh
[Music]
we want this to kind of always be the
case and this right here
wants to not be like rigid anymore right
so this just wants to be a target and
we've got sort of that pdc
nonsense going right where if you
look at the code for
um this ddp
we can just probably make this be like a
function that you call
because we're probably going to want to
slap some some of that crap on there
pdcs are not great but they get the job
done
you know they like they're okay
and so you usually start with them and
then you step up to something more
hardcore when you need to
uh okay so in here what i want to do
is when we have the uh
when we have someone who wants to apply
proportional different
proportional derivative controller we
can just do like pdc
where you say look here's the entity
you're trying to do it on
uh and then we have uh the coefficients
which they have they have names i
remember
but i it's been so long
it's like p s and p d what are the let's
use the standard let's just take a
second and look up the standards
launching a super crappy microsoft edge
so here's the proportional derivative
controller
uh entry uh and i just want to look up
there's standard terms i want to i want
to use the standard terms here uh if i
can
uh there they are so it's k k
d that's what i was looking for um so
yeah
so if you look at uh let's see
kp for the first order
and kd for the second order looks
like kp what is k
i oh that's proportional integral
controller
yes it is i'm like so why would we want
that no we don't want that so it's p
and d so kp and kd
uh if i want to be
consistent with the literature so
our kp is here and in fact we can also
just have like this is our standard one
and people can override it or something
um but we can just say look kp applies
here
kd applies here and all you need to do
is tell us
like what did you actually want um
the like what did you actually want the
uh target to be and we'll try and get it
there whatever the energies you give us
um so that way we can have the glove be
like kind of laggy
and smooth behind you know just mousse
along uh
with the with the body instead of this
which rigidly locked its position
so we can set his movement mode to
floating and then i could say like
look give a portion of the controller
here to
this which is the actual like
thing that it was trying to achieve
which we'll probably change at a moment
here
uh but this is our target p so we've got
basically like a target p
that's the body location uh plus this
you know nonsense of like
where we're kind of going off of the uh
where we're offset from the hero
and so now we're just gonna say look try
to get there
but don't uh don't force it right before
it was just like literally
sticking the the glove there now like
the glove
has to actually track right and so what
we could do
is set that to be like springy um
in a way right we can set that to be
springy so it's kind
kind of trying to trace out
uh and get to the place where we said it
should be
right so if i go ahead and change
uh what the ks and kd are here k p and
kd
sorry um
if i have like a really strong one so
much stronger than uh the ones that we
had before
i can crank up the stiffness on this
particular
uh it's called stiffness on them uh and
it will hew closer to me
the the further up i i crank them
right and this is why i say you don't
always want to
stick with something like this because
you can get into situations where the
springs are too stiff and
so we may want to change this to
something else but you can kind of see
here
how like if i want the glove to lag
behind me um i can make it so that it's
it's compare it to the familiar
right which is using the the other uh
the the other um settings
uh and hopefully you can see sort of the
difference there right
and one of the problems that we have
here as well
is it's not going to match the velocity
and that's a problem we really want this
before
to probably match the velocity as well
so we probably want to do is have the
body's dp
in there the problem is i don't actually
know that we know what the body's dp is
because i don't know if we compute it
we probably should always be computing
it um for for this very purpose
but you can see here how like already
just with that setting i could keep the
glove
uh relatively close uh to the hero at
all times
which is what we wanted right
um but that velocity match is going to
be important so i feel like that's
something
to to put in there and for those of you
don't know what i'm talking about see oh
that
that's what i wanted to have happen
right i kind of want it to be able to
glide off of there so i don't know that
i want
um it to be that easy for it to get
stuck i want it to just lag so we may
want to have it roll
we may want to have a collision model
that does a little bit more of a roll
than that
um why can't that guy come through here
because oh is it stuck to this dude
again yeah i don't know doesn't matter
um
like i said we got to fix our collision
stuff anyway so
uh you know we could do that and then
for punching
right um i just want to say something
maybe along the lines of
um
i really don't want to set like angle
attack swipe or any of that stuff
so
so really if attacked uh
i don't know that we even care about
that really
like more what i want to be able to do
here um
is just say well when we do if attacked
uh maybe we want the offset to be
whatever
the facing direction is you know i don't
care about this
right um i want to like push it in the
direction of the attack
which which i don't know
i i don't know exactly what i want to do
there right but but like
something
so something like this so when we get
the
uh when we get the actual attack you can
see like we've got like move
right and then we've got um
we've got action for like doing it's
called sword for some reason even though
it's a glove
so i don't know why we kept that naming
but it doesn't matter
um so you can see here we set the d
sword value
so like i'm just guessing that like we
should set the d
sword value to be or rather we use the d
sword value as like an offset here so in
you know if
we look at uh how this is being used you
can see that we're like
setting the facing direction based on
the d sort it's ridiculous that we don't
just set the facing direction
it's just um he's like welcome to
calling a tan to every frame for no
reason at all
it's like a stack overflow move right
there
it's like some high quality stack
overflow coding
um i i say that only because i literally
saw a thing just the other day on stack
overflow where someone was like
oh yeah just call a tan two and it was a
thing that you would never call a tantu
for because you already had the answer
so this is some stack overflow like like
you know
to do like stop
with the stack overflow quality
um so you know we want to de-stack
overflow that
um but you know what i want to do here
is
is i don't care about that at all i just
want to use that d sword value here
so i want to be able to add d sword and
this will just like however far
out like that punch is going
um and and the only problem with this is
i don't actually know
like how d sword works with diagonals
um like it never gets normalized
probably so so we probably want to do a
gnaws on this
so that we can just say look if you're
going diagonally you don't get like more
distance
on the sword um so we'd have like
a glove disc and you you know that's
going to be a thing that's
a property of the player right they're
gonna upgrade their glove and have
higher glove discs or whatever
the heck um so like that'll probably
come
you know to do like glove discs is
probably a
upgradeable thing you know um
so you've got glove discs and glove
discs is going to be
how far away from the player you can get
so you know maybe you can punch
you know three three units away
or some garbage like that
and i think this is i
want to say that that's a 2d value
oops so i i i want to say we have to
uh 3d it first because it's not it's not
going to it's
you can't punch up and down in this game
you can only you can only hit people on
on the floor you're on uh at the moment
and maybe that'll change
so it's weirdly laggy there
and i'm not sure why
i think probably because of collision
weirdness
maybe
um but anyway uh so
you can see like you can basically see
what i'm getting at here though yeah i
think we just need to fix our collision
routine
i think it's getting stuck on things
perhaps let me take a look
yeah yeah i mean it's like skating right
on the ground in fact why is it on the
ground
why why is the
where is glove float height and why is
it so tiny
so why is this not why is it not
actually floating
above the ground is it that it can't get
off the ground
like what's going on yeah like what's
the problem
hmm yeah i don't know what's going on
with that
um so you can see here like if you want
a punch right
you punch you punch like this
um and you want that to be like
pretty springy probably more springy
than that even
you know what i'm saying like you really
want that to fly out there
uh but again so you know you go through
a door or something like
like like i said i kind of want it to be
that as you go through the door it'll
just get stuck
or something you know to that effect if
you don't first like punch it out
right you want to like punch it in the
direction so you want to manage like the
glove movement
um and then i'm imagining uh
i think i'm gonna go fix that collision
do i have time today to fix the
collision sector
we started at 11. so i have an hour so i
might go fish the fixed collision sector
um so you know if you punch through
people or do whatever you're gonna do
uh i'm imagining that like the damage
would be based
on the speed of the punch so that
basically like if you
if you just run into somebody like this
you know um it doesn't do anything
right so that like doesn't do damage you
have to like
have a certain velocity on the glove so
when you punch
the velocity of the glove will be like
when the glove reaches a high enough
velocity to do damage
it'll like get particles on it or
something right
so you know you know when a punch will
do something and otherwise a glove
just does a push right like it would it
would just push against
something but it wouldn't actually
damage them just like a regular punch
like if you just
push on something versus you hit it
right it's going to be different
so so i kind of want the glove to have
that feel to it
if that makes sense um so
we'll see um but
but yeah uh and and it looks like that
was a little too far
as well so so i might just switch it up
a little bit here uh but then let's go
we're gonna have to like improve our
collision stuff there and
and all that but yeah
it's still really weird how the glove
like gets stuck on things like that i
don't really understand what's going on
there so again i want to fix collision
routines so we can get that out of the
way
but like i don't know like
it was like it felt like it was getting
stuck on stuff but it you know it's
kind of weird i can't really see it
actually happen
like there it's looking correct right
um and again i really don't know what
the pdc
max value should be are these movement
speeds capped
by the way we should go look because
that might also be why you can't get
all right so i'm going to look at this
because something's weird i don't
i don't even think that is the collision
detector there's weird stuff with the
with the floating mode i don't i don't
get it
i'm not sure what's going on there it
doesn't look good though
um so like what's up with that does the
glove
do anything else like are there other
things happening with the glove
in here that i'm not aware of um
so this might have something to do with
it although
since movement mode is always floating
it shouldn't be
um
so it it does only seem to be that
though i mean
there's no i guess and d sword
doesn't really get used uh anywhere
either so
so i i don't know about that
um it seems just it just seems to be
behaving
rather oddly
um so i don't know what to make of that
uh separately we probably do still want
this
um but but yeah
it just feels really odd is all i can
say it doesn't
it feels like there's a stopping point
in
the middle as it moves over the first
square
and i have no explanation for why it
would do that
because it looks like we're just using a
straight
offset there's no like
there's no like additional thing
happening there
big stretch okay so so that's just weird
so i guess the first thing i would say
is because i don't know much about this
move entity call
except that it's a piece of crap
[Music]
what the heck
does somebody want to tell me what that
is
um okay
hold please
so what was that for
like that literally does nothing
[Music]
so
if the player delta length is greater
than the distance remaining
so this was something that like we
wanted to clamp
the movement of some entities
or something
i mean whatever this was it sucked like
what would be the point of that
like because we should be doing a better
like physical movement here where we
just say look this is the place the
player was trying to go to
put them at the closest location to that
that you can
i'm not player but whatever the entity
was trying to go here
like this is where the entity is
supposed to be
so put it as close as dairy as you can
without
causing a a collision right
i mean that's all we really want to do
so so i'm just going to take a hatch
into this routine because frankly this
sucks
and and i don't want it
um
i i guess we want to say that maybe
we'll see
all right um so this
this is gone like that's gotta go um
this whole thing is stupid like this is
dumb
but um
yeah i don't like any of this
we're probably gonna hatch it this this
up quite a bit
yeah this this is all horrible and i
don't like any of it
all right so i think what we're doing
now is we're just going to rewrite this
routine
um this
this looks like something that tries to
change the facing direction
based on how an entity moved here
i'm gonna say that that will get handled
elsewhere anyway it already is and it
was commented out
so that was fine um
so this was trying to do like a branch
and bound kind of thing
it looks like uh
which we again don't really want
so
i mean yeah let's take this
step by step so if you take a look at
how this is working
we're going to move entities it looks
like this is set up to move entities
like one at a time
which is fine um because this game isn't
really about physical simulation so we
don't have a lot of
problems where we want to solve stuff
like you know
four entities that are all kind of
moving that are all in contact with each
other or something like this
in which case this wouldn't work very
well um
but if we take a look here what we're
doing is we're saying well here is where
we expect the player to end up
right like we're taking this is standard
this is one half a t squared plus
uh plus v t dt right
uh i should say one half a
d t squared plus v dt uh
meaning the standard like what's the
position
uh going to be after we apply the
velocity
and acceleration over the time step that
we've been given
right and that's all that is
uh and so what we want to do here is say
okay
if we know that that is and and to be
honest
um you know we probably want to compute
here in addition to a delta
i i'd like to just say like where the
desired position is it looks like we
compute that inside the loop
um but i kind of like to just make that
be
a a main thing that we actually like
said we were looking for
in general so we're gonna call desire
position just a thing
um outside and if we have intermediate
targets
then we will deal with those later right
um i don't know
what this is about and i don't much care
because we're going to try to place the
player where we're placing them
whether or not they moved is not really
the issue
right so i'll keep this iteration
stuff although i don't know how many
iterations we're really going to do
but i guess we'll find out so
this says this as an optimization but
that optimization is no longer there
right so we can get rid of that
so that goes away um
and so while we're in here it looks like
we're getting
uh the dimensions and centers of our
collision volumes
right and we're doing a minkowski test
um
on these which is fine
and it looks like this is using some
kind of crappy
wall code thing that i guess we wrote
a long time ago to just go like hey uh
let's test against like bumping into
these things
i guess
but i don't know that we care about that
right so
my guess is look
we're gonna have a couple different
problems here
one of the problems is what happens when
we want to find
how far we can go in a particular
direction
and that is
uh you know that is just a problem
with the fact that we
we can just raycast and know the answer
to that pretty much
right so the more interesting problem
here
that we have to focus on is the fact
that we we do want things to slide
so we want things to slide against
surfaces
and in order to do that we're going to
have to
make sure that we use something like a
cylinder
or a sphere
for the shapes that we move around
so we can totally have square shapes
like rectangles like we have for like
the walls because they're trying to fill
a rectangular space and prevent you from
moving
through it but we definitely want to
have
the shapes that we move through the
world be smoother
because if they're not when you have
like two cubes that hit each other right
you have just two flat things there's
not a way for it to clearly
roll off edges it's why we use things
like cylinders and spheres
for collision in games because we want
things to roll off each other at the
edges
and they won't do that if they're flat
so in terms of like uh yeah how we want
to deal with that i think we'd like to
change probably i'm just thinking to
myself
i think we would want to make it so that
things that move are considered to be
spheres
because i'm just thinking everything
that moves in this game with collisions
is like floating so we probably want
everything that moves to be a sphere
and everything that doesn't move to be a
cube
well a right rectangular prism right
um so i think that's what i would say
like
i think that's what i would say so i'm
gonna enter this assuming that that's
the case
and we'll see so uh
i don't care about an epsilon here uh
hopefully we can get away without one
epsilons are usually not great so we
probably want to try and write this code
in a way that doesn't really use one to
the extent that we can
um and so when we look here we're gonna
iterate over these entities and i think
what we wanna do now is figure out how
we can do
uh sort of a closest point placement
test
um based on the entity and
uh you know
i would like to do something that's
that's as close as possible to sort of
maybe what i did in the witness
where i'm placing entities
the furthest that they could go
based on the distance
for the distance from uh
i want to put them at the closest point
they can get
within a search region
that is the closest point to the point
they were trying to get to
is the way to say it
and in order to do that i just need a
way of
locally for this particular whatever the
thing is that i'm looking at
i just need a way of figuring out where
that point is
[Music]
um
and the reason it's kind of tricky and i
might want to go
to the board for this uh
the reason it's kind of tricky is i
don't actually
know offhand
what the most efficient way to do that
is if i'm not can going to actually
construct a localized grid
there's probably like a hackier way to
do it
that just gets the answer for floating
things
as opposed to like the one i did in the
witness which was was more much more
complicated
we should probably just do this on the
board
you
all right sorry that took a second there
um i guess i don't actually know i
should just check to make sure everyone
hear me okay
i wasn't planning on doing any board
stuff today so i didn't have it set up
so i had to quickly get it set up
but let me just check
can you hear me
cool
all right so what i'm basically talking
about here
is is pretty simple in theory it's just
kind of hard to implement
and uh again if you go look at the stuff
the talks i've done
on the witness collision detector they
talk a lot about
uh sort of the goals of doing a hardcore
one of these
and in this case we don't really need to
hardcore one of these but i would like
to sort of use the same principles
because when i thought through the
problem which i did
on that project to me this is the only
logical conclusion about how to do these
sorts of systems
so i kind of want one that's that hughes
as close to that as possible without
really being quite so hardcore because
it doesn't really need to do the same
kind of stuff that the witness needed to
do
um but here's the essential uh issue
so let's suppose that we have a
you know some some kind of a blocking
piece like a wall like we saw uh before
and we have you know a something that
we're moving
and the idea is we want this thing to be
able to sort of slide so you know as
this
sphere kind of comes up through here at
some point
this thing you know if we're talking
about moving the center here
at some point we hit we can no longer go
you know for talking about physically we
can't go because we would interpenetrate
and if we just want to solve that
problem it's not
quite as hard because we can use for
example
the minkowski sum like we've talked
about before where we can just say look
a sphere plus a uh you know a a
cube is just a rounded cube kind of
thing
so we could just do a raycast against
the rounded cube and find the point
where we have to stop moving and that
would be our answer
but the reason that it's more
complicated than that
is because we don't want to just stop
when we hit something we want to keep
moving
in the direction that we're going minus
whatever the actual stopping
part was so if this was stopping us
we want to stop moving that way and
start moving this way when we hit
and we want that to happen automatically
so we don't want the player to like
go up and just stop against the thing we
want them to glide along the edge
and you may ask why we want this who
knows
we don't know why we want this we just
know that when you implement
something that that works like that in a
game it feels better to play
so we don't know why it feels better to
do that we just know that when you do it
pretty much no players that anyone's
ever seen
prefer something to just get stopped
immediately on a wall and then they have
to push
up to keep going they all prefer if it
just kind of when they hit
if they're keep pushing in that
direction they just slide
and go off it and then you know go like
this
if you don't implement system that
handles this then you your game feels
sticky it feels like things are getting
stuck to surfaces all the time
um and you know if you want that great
but if you don't and you pretty much
never do
you need a better answer so
the problem that we get here is that if
we start to
to do too much fanciness if we actually
implement these things
literally so if we implement these
things as literally
i'm going to do a movement to hear see
that i've hit this thing then try a
movement to here and so on
you end up in kind of a nasty place
where you're trying
to do lots of little movements and it's
very
easy for the numerical imprecision of
the system
because remember each time you do one of
these you're slightly numerically
imprecise
you're never getting an exact answer
it's very easy to end up in situations
where especially when you have stuff
like two you know pieces or three
pieces like this that are all abutting
it's very easy to get into situations
where
you end up putting something inside
another thing or you don't quite
get the numerical stuff worked out and
things get stuck so
you need to be very careful when you
construct these systems
so that the thing that they're actually
solving for and the way that they're
solving for it
is very unlikely to produce bad
numerical outcomes
and that can be really difficult to do
so the kind that we had in there from
way back when was just a super crappy
collision thing
i think we called it crappy at the time
as well um
and so what we want to do is start
thinking about
something that's better than that right
now what i was saying before is i like
systems uh like for the witness um
i like systems that have i'm erasing
this because this is no longer
we don't need any of these diagrams
these are just me kind of idly
explaining stuff right
this will not be part of the exam uh
okay so basically what happens now
is we need a system that has a good
sort of uh overall structure for
producing results that we think might be
good
right and to me what the way i like to
think about these
is at any given time we start with the
entity that we're moving
and we produce a
candidate position that is where we
would like it to be
and instead of thinking of this as a
problem of
tracing a movement pattern which gets
into that iterative like i hit something
and then i go
and it's it's not clear where that ends
like
you know i could keep bouncing around in
there and never
really you know and do i just cap the
iteration
i want something where i know when i'm
done like i want to be able to do
an exhaustive search over something
so that the definition of when i have
finished
is clear right i want a stronger metric
than
i don't know i just started searching in
that direction and did stuff that to me
doesn't feel very good
so what i want to do is i want to do
something
where i produce a candidate location
and then what which is where you would
move if you didn't collide and that's
free because we're just
adding the vector the motion vector we
know we will go to this position so it's
trivial for us to find that and then
what i want to do
is say in the presence of some kind of
collision
where we know that if we were to put the
thing there
it would end up being um
it would end up creating a situation
where we would overlap in a way that we
don't want to
then what i want to do is search for
the closest continuous place
where i can place
the the entity right so what i'd like to
do is then say
okay you know and and you can see the
really simple version of this
would be to just sort of look for places
i could put
right and that would be like a certainty
kind of situation
where i basically just look along here
for places i could put
and why don't i want to do that well
because again it doesn't work for
sliding
so if i do this and i just start looking
along this line i will find
this location here where i first hit
right
but that is not as far as i could have
gone
i could have gone as far as here right
um that would have been a legal motion
for me to do
and if if the total path length here
is less than the motion vector that
would have presumably been legal
right so you know maybe this is a little
bit further back
you know what i'm saying um
so i'm trying to think if there's some
way
of doing a similar sort of thing to the
witness which is producing an exhaustive
search over some amount of space
um but that doesn't put me into that
situation
right um and so here's you know some
things that i'm thinking about right
so if instead
if instead of i'm trying i'm trying to
think of like how we would
we would phrase this here right um
if every if if instead of thinking of
this as a problem
where we update the position we were at
and then look for places
to go what if we turned this into more
of like a pathfinding problem
right so we would say something like
oh
i'm just trying to think of exactly how
this is formulated so
we know that we can't move backwards
along this line right so the player
if it was if the player was faced with
an obstacle that was literally
100 uh perpendicular
shaped to the direction of motion right
against them so you know it was like
this
or anywhere in here then it would stop
and it should actually stop
right but anything else any other
deflection angle we want them to start
gliding
along that right so if there's another
you know if
it hits something and that something is
tilted like this it wants to go this way
if uh it hits something uh and it's
tilted like that it wants to go that way
right so every time we put an
obstacle in we're effectively creating
like a glide angle
and the problem that we would get right
uh that makes this kind of an annoying
problem
is that the problem we will end up with
is they can
stack so you know you'd hit one
you'd glide there might but then there
might be one here right so you'd hit
that
and and you know you'd glide or you'd
try to glide upward and you'd hit right
so what we want to do is figure out some
way we can sweep over
all of the things that we might hit and
we assume that eventually we'll have a
spatial partition right that
will make that an easy query so we're
not worried about that but we take all
the things in
that are ostensibly going to affect our
movement and what we want to do is be
able to pile those
into something that allows us to find
what would be the closest point we could
actually get to
that's closest to our ending position
now again the way that i did this on
the witness was i built a localized grid
so you would take and you would overlay
something
like this right onto the system
and you would as you sort of got
obstacles that came in
you would sort of like fill in pieces
of the grid so that you knew when you
were actually
then later trying to move um you would
know like what were the closest
you know when you tried to get somewhere
it'd be like where was the closest place
you could get relative to that so if
that thing
actually got filled in you would find
the closest point um
by searching through the grid for
wherever was the closest point to that
and
i'm just trying to figure out if there's
a way to do that
more simply for the
this type of a problem where you're just
where maybe we don't care as much about
the robustness of it
you know as long as we can guarantee
that things don't get stuck
we don't have as we're not trying to
reach as high level as quality as maybe
of guarantees about
what happens in the system but still
sort of roughly keeping this right
um
and and so i guess you know
if i were to if hmm
so let's suppose we start plopping
things down here right
and we've got some object that's trying
to go through
and we know that like as this object
gets to like here
right we want it to start sliding
so what this effectively
and and the reason that this is even
more complicated is
we want it to be able to go around this
if it had enough momentum to do so
right so if it if it could have gotten
around here we probably want it to do
that
right because we don't really want you
to get stuck on edges
right we want you to be able to go
around so at a micro level because these
are very small movements
right it really wouldn't look like this
this would be a much larger thing
right um and this would be like you know
a much larger thing and if there was a
small amount
right if you just had to just move a
little bit
you just want to glide through that you
don't really want the player to get
stuck there
right um so i guess what i would say
is
you know can we just treat this as a
path finding problem i think i'm just
gonna try it that way
so suppose we took and we just said yeah
like we're gonna literally do that we're
gonna take
this guy and we have the end point and
we create a path
to the end point right and then
when we slap in something so we we go
ahead and we intersect the current path
that we've got with the object that
comes down
and we find right that that it looks
like this so we we do the raycast we
find that we hit
here so then we just say well whatever
surface we hit
we're going to do uh like a path update
now
and we'll we'll recast
in the direction of that to see how
far well i guess we don't really have to
we know here
right what the distance to the edge of
that thing
would be so we know that it would like
come to here so we like update the path
to look like this
right
i'm just spitballing here so we update
the path to look like this
now the problem that we have is we don't
know
whether this particular point is
actually legal
right because it may be that transiting
through that point
was actually prevented by some other
object
we already processed that doesn't hit
this line
so maybe there was an obstacle here this
could go straight through it and it
would be fine
but it can't actually handle the fact
that um
you wouldn't have been able to go
through here because there was something
there right
so maybe what we can do is instead of
thinking of this
as a problem where we move and we do
like stateful motion like that
what if we just treated it as same basic
idea so we're still doing the crappy
kind of we raycast we hit something
we consider that a new position but
instead of thinking of it as
updating the position and then we do a
new raycast
what if we just think of it as a
continuous path
so we say we restart our pass
through the system after we do that with
this as the path now
and we recast these legs to see if any
of those hit
if one of them do we insert a new leg
into the pet
right and we keep doing that
and then we just take the longest we
when we're done when we're doing doing n
paths
of that we just take the longest legal
one we can find
right
and i feel like that's a little bit
better of a structure for it because now
we can look at that path
at each iteration and know that we at
least know
we're always going to re-go from we
won't get into those weird situations
where like you
you accidentally numerically like wiggle
your way through something
because we're always just keeping these
actual segments
on hand and we can even just say if
there's a segment that looks like that
like if a segment is too small we just
throw
that out right it seems like potentially
a better framing for the problem i don't
know it might not really be it might be
that it doesn't actually
improve our odds at all and that you
could have just done exactly that
by just doing it incrementally
um
yeah so let's talk about a couple other
things here so
the other thing we need to make sure
that we have here is a way that
again if we construct this path by using
a displacement method
we will always we could we could
probably come out with ways that we
always push
away from obstacles which is the other
thing that we want to do so we don't
want things to be able to get stuck
so maybe raycast is the wrong term so
maybe what we want to do is say
look we can test segments for overlap
when we test segments for overlap what
we do is we
insert a point and the point we insert
is the one that's like however like
we we sort of do the raycast but really
we're just inserting a path point
that is a known good distance away from
the thing that we're at
we insert the path point there right
um and and also the path point
you know uh we introduced the new
segment that we're gonna start testing
um we know that those are
at the safe locations of this thing
so like that way if you were already
inside the thing
like let's say you end up getting stuck
in the thing for some reason
right for whatever reason like like the
entity system just farts
and it like accidentally puts somebody
inside
a collider right um
then you say like i uh
so yeah so this is what we want to do
okay so
we say that the person was trying to
move
right um and i guess this is the tough
part
let's say they were trying to move that
direction i guess maybe it's fine that
that wouldn't work
so but then they try to move this
direction so they are trying to move out
right so now what we would do is say
well
okay we tested this segment right
and the person is inside the
uh is inside the i don't know cube
whatever you want to call this
the person's inside the cube right now
so if the person is inside the cube on
the if the first
point of a segment is inside the cube
right
then we introduce a path segment that is
outside that is the legal place outside
the cube
in that direction that's the new path
segment
um and then when we evaluate the path
we would just say well if you're inside
to begin with
then we do allow you to pick an outside
point
if if the next segment on the path is
outside you can pick it
right so we could actually use that as
something reasonable if we have a way of
testing and saying are you inside or
outside
of this thing
and maybe we just skip the raycast part
altogether and just treat this as an
overlap problem
for now so that we don't ever raycast we
just say are you inside or outside and
make sure that it works with that
you know it's not great um
it's getting there but it's not great um
so if i am
if i am like summarizing this right so
we start with a point that's either in
or out
and another point that's either in or
out right
so we have you know in
out on these that we test
and then we have um a
a place you know a segment that goes
between them so
the reason we need a raycast is to know
whether this segment would be legal
because it's possible that it's not
right
we we need some way of knowing if this
segment is a legal segment like could
you actually move along it
and i guess what we're saying is if the
segment is in
and this is out then we just don't
bother
i guess um the problem is you could end
up with issues there as well like you
kind of don't ever want people to be
inside stuff but
i'm not sure that we want to be robust
enough to never have that happen because
again then you're into witness territory
i think at that point when you make that
actually a hard requirement that you can
prove
um so if you start i want to find the
closest point that i can put this
this thing at and so i can start
searching along this thing
i could just use overlap testing um
to say well you know uh
we could just overlap tests at discrete
intervals along this thing
and then find the furthest one uh that
we can
and you know if we're going from in then
we're looking for the first
out if we're going for out we're looking
for the first in
and then we place the point uh
at that transition right at that place
where
uh either on the outside or the in
side if we were going from into out we
place it on the far end if we're going
from out to end we place it on the near
end
um and then you know you know what you
hit
so you should be able to then do an
update uh
of of where your path would go and i
think you always kind of just
know um
well you might not so for example you
could say well the path just now looks
like that
but really you could have maybe done it
if you'd gone just a little bit further
so i'm still not quite happy with this
it's still not positional enough for me
for my tastes
so if we assume that things that are all
that are moving
in general uh are always like spherical
then you can think of the thing that is
you know the actual shape
of positions you were trying as being
that sphere
right now let's suppose
uh i'm gonna need some more space here
by the way somebody out there who's like
a engineer uh
physical like if of physical like
hardware
stuff please invent
the instant erase light board
like i guess maybe there's no point to
it because we'll all be wearing ar
goggles eventually with like then it'll
just be a position thing that i draw in
the air
although man without haptic feedback
writing is going to be like
so even my handwriting will you think my
handwriting is bad now
hoo boy but um yeah i mean or
you know solve the haptic feedback
problem i guess could be the other thing
you could do
um and then we all wear like annoying vr
goggles
um and we have to use our facebook login
to write on a white
light board because you know
silicon valley is so amazing and they're
so interested in humans and
making sure they can communicate well
and they definitely don't do anything
like primarily concern themselves only
with making money
because that would be nuts um but
basically like
this process is annoying and takes
forever and it doesn't ever get
completely clean anyway
and so that if you could just solve that
problem somehow
like with some kind of magical like
super easy to remove
um ink so it's just quick
or better yet like electrostatic like
the
like it's like an etch-a-sketch or
something you push the button just goes
clunk
and it all falls down right um i don't
know
please do it it would be great um
so so i'm taking a total i'm just keep
continuing to kind of go through here
and think this
this out so suppose i've got
um you know uh
a motion plan where this thing is trying
to go here
well we know that like if we're assuming
that you can
only go uh so if that was the amount of
like movement you had
then we know that you've effectively got
sort of
at the micro level right because
remember these are very small distances
at a 60th of a second things are not
moving that far
so these are pretty small but you've
effectively got a hemisphere
in which you could move so this is the
move we're trying to accomplish
and we have a hemisphere of possible
positions we could end up in but we
fundamentally know
that because we're saying that the
person only well person the
entity the any could be an inanimate
object the glove whatever
could only move this far whatever this
distance is
we know that like whatever that distance
is
they should never be able to get any
further than that
right so if i'm running this way
and i hit some surface i'm supposed to
glide along well
you we can never get any more
than that because because that would be
how far we would go if we had been going
straight that direction
right and furthermore we could probably
classify this into something even
less uh pronounced than a hemisphere
because since you were pushing in this
direction
we would also assume that the thing that
you
hit is absorbing some of that so you
might also
say that like you know
if if i'm pushing in this direction
and i hit something with that normal
that actually
you should get like the cosine falloff
of the speed
you know what i'm saying so like as you
go this way
it might be that this is really more
like
you know that right
so fundamentally we know that we're only
looking
in like a pattern that looks like this
and what we really need to do
like the uh the best possible thing we
could do
is and unfortunately this is 3d so it's
actually a thing that kind of looks like
a nose cone of a ship
right it's a thing that actually looks
like this
right um
so the nose cone of the ship right we
know that we have to
the placement of the entity at the end
of the day
will be in this space because it can't
be anywhere else
right if it was anywhere else you would
be moving the player in the opposite
direction that they asked for
so it has to occur in here can occur
like back there
um and so when we are looking through
this what we then have is we have a
series of obstacles that come in
that prevent the player from going into
certain
regions of this space so let's suppose
now that i i come in and i place this
thing down and again
we know that it's minkowski right
because if we're talking about this as
points we can place we grow this
rectangle
by that by those spheres so now we know
that
this shape right comes in
and blocks off this portion
so now we know that actually the place
we would put the player is actually
here to here right
and the closest point is wherever the
closest point is in there right
so
at the end of the day
at the end of the day i'm wondering
maybe we just do this
almost the same way as we do it with the
with in the witness
i wonder if we can just treat this as
like a simple
a small scale subdivision problem
like assuming there's not that many
entities you know how many entities are
really going to be
in just that one location like 10 20
not very many if we just said
what if we just treated this area as a
locally
like subdividable place
and the 2d version would just be like
okay so we create
a little like you know maybe we even
treat it like a quad tree right
so we just say okay we overlay the grid
on top of this and maybe we're feeling
like super saucy
so we just like align the grid with this
thing so actually
it doesn't look like that it looks like
this
right and then we just go okay
which of these things are in or out so
we iterate over each entity and we
perform the overlap test
and the only thing we need to know is
partially
covered or not like is it is
is there or i should say any is there
any place that's still open
or did it completely cover and
completely cover is pretty easy with
these convex shapes i should be able to
write a pretty fast routine
that just says completely covered or not
anything
of these that isn't completely covered
right
survives to the next round and gets like
subdivided right
so we could do something like that and
discretize the space
to the point where we actually can
pick a place and it would be an octree
you know
so it actually you know it would
actually be eight because we're doing
this in 3d
but we could actually discretize the
space and the only hard part
at that point is
that we have to make sure you can
contiguously
get there from where you started right
so from where you started we have to
make sure that you could actually
get there
and i'm i'm kind of thinking to myself
that's not even maybe that hard
so actually
actually that might not be that hard so
let's suppose
uh that we do this thing that i'm
talking about
right and we say okay
let's start with two cells the place
we're at
and the place we're going and i'll just
draw this in 2d but we're going to have
to do it in 3d so it'll be a little
harder
but what we say is okay we're going
somewhere and so we place
two cells down and the cells look like
this
right so we're going from here to here
we run the overlap test and if we get
nothing so if it just says
nothing occludes these at all right then
you're just done and the entity goes
yeah now if
if one of them says there's nothing then
great we just keep that cell
but if another one says there is
something we're like okay like let's say
this one says there is something
then we're like okay we have to
subdivide this cell
into more cells right
so then what we do is we take that cell
and we say
split the cell up right
and the problem is i don't like that
subdivision because it pla the point is
then
at a intersection
which is fine okay so we do this
slightly differently
so we say okay we're going from here to
here
these are going to be the centers of the
cells
right um
i think unfortunately i'm still gonna
have the same problem
there's got to be some way to do this
subdivision clever it's just not
clicking in my brain
because fundamentally we need a way of
subdividing maybe you subdivide nines
you subdivide on nines
so you know you do this
and then when you subdivide you
subdivide like this
i i don't love it but i'm not sure what
else you do
because if you don't do that it seems
like you're always going to split
right on where your point is which seems
bad
i don't know maybe it's not but anyway
if we subdivide this
and we just keep subdividing it down by
the reachable cells
so if it's like oh it's still
overlapping a silver wrapping eventually
we're going to end up with a discretized
version of the space
at each time through we just throw out
cells that you can't reach
and we stop subdividing them right
eventually we get
a version that's at a resolution where
we can just pick
the closest one and be done right
i don't know we could do this
yeah and then you yeah you would
literally just iterate over these in
fact you could even do it
as a single check for spheres this would
be very simple
for the rounded rectangles it'll be a
little bit harder
we could do this
and so then this has the nice aspect of
you're always p picking positions
that are actually legal right
um and so my only concern is i'm not
sure what the subdivision scheme is
that keeps you from putting the points i
mean i guess you could just pick a weird
like offset of the thing
so that you knew that it never would be
but that's a little odd
i don't know but you don't really want
you usually don't want
your you know main points of interest
you know
things you're asking about to be like
right on the boundary
seems like you're asking for numerical
problems there
but you know so if you took something
that looked like this
and you're like how do we align this so
that subdivisions don't keep
causing problems i'm just fundamentally
not sure how you do that right
so one way to do that is to just make it
slightly off
so like
it's aligned like that so that like you
never
really get down to the point where you
would
ever you know by the time you subdivided
out that far you were done
so we could do that just off it's offset
slightly so the cell
the cell is like whatever the smallest
cell size
so let's say we you know we end up with
a small cell size it's like oh you know
we subdivide down to that or something
then you just say well that's how far
off we are
so the main problem i see here is with
cell tracking
and so oh you know what so here's the
other optimization we can use
so this is great so the nice part about
this is we never really
have to remember do we
because we never have to actually keep
these cells around
so we can avoid storing them and
processing them
in any way because we can just remember
the connectivity
because that's all we care about right
all we care about
is is the connectivity of the cells
yeah so we only need two things from
this right we need the closest point
to the destination so closest to dust
so as we're doing the subdivision
checking we just need the closest point
to the destination
and we need the connectivity to the to
the
next level up
connectivity um
so in other words when we process this
cell for subdivision we don't care at
all
what the pattern of cells is after we're
done processing it
we just care about whether or not you
know you can get from any particular one
of these to any other particular one of
these
and furthermore we only really care like
we're not gonna do
like entry and re-exit like the person
can't go
out here and come back in here as as a
legal path
because that would require them changing
the direction 180 degrees which we're
not going to let them do
right so i don't think we care about
that
so the only thing we care about is for
each
edge wall which edge wall could you have
left through
right um and the problem there is we do
care sort of on the smaller scale about
like
you know which of these you go through
but we only need the edges
right we only need the edges
it's still a kind of squared
connectivity problem so i'm still not
sure it's great
if you do the one with the here we go
where you're starting with the like
with the starting position in it then
you know the places you could have left
right which means those are inputs to
the new system
which then it knows where it could have
left
so i think you can always propagate if
you just choose the starting position
you do all the subdivisions you find all
the edges you could have left on
then those get fed into whatever the
next
two cells are the two neighboring cells
to that one
and this should be true all the way down
right
so you say you say we've got the
connectivity
but we really don't care about this we
just care about exits
right so you subdivide down and you
remember what the exits are so
eventually you're looking at something
that looks like this
is your furthest subdivision down right
and
like it turns out this one's blocked and
these two aren't
right so you know that your exits are
here here and here
and your closest point you know if this
was where you were trying to get to your
closest point is there
right so then you just
feed that information up to the next
level so if that square
right if this square
was here then when you go to process
this one
it has an entrance of here right
so it knows that if if it actually
had this solid
and this solid so that it can't actually
get to that square
it knows that there are no exits but
here because it couldn't get to that one
right these aren't connected
so then when you look at the final one
of these
right you would you'd call this one uh
only when you finished these two right
so you do
the one you're in then you do the two
that neighbor that one
right so you do the two that neighbor
that one and the two that neighbor that
one well they came in here so they
actually
have both of these so then you know that
these are the entrance cells
here and here right and then you would
look and say okay well i can leave here
right so you know what your what your
entrances and exits are so now you've
got
that all of those as what you would feed
into
your neighbor right
uh
so does this work
i mean the other way to look at this is
it's just you change the enlargement
radius of the sphere
and you think of it you know if the
cells are too confusing
you know don't think of it as cells
right so you start out and you've got
these two positions so it's back to my
old path sort of thing
right and you make the spheres enlarged
or you can even large either side
doesn't matter you make the spheres
enlarged so that they cover the entire
distance
right so maybe your first check is
actually
a thing that checks to see whether it
could go the whole way
conservatively if it can't it subdivides
and
checks two here and here right
and if those are fine then it's done if
it can't right it keeps adding
more and when i subdivide down right so
if it's here and here
we actually subdivide out to like a
more like this right so we subdivide
positions so we are actually standing
instead of using cells we just consider
it as standing on the actual quad tree
or octree in this case and we just keep
subdividing
the octree down with positions we know
we can stand
on while there's still a connected path
to the destination
while we still know there are
potentially more
ways to get there
so i kind of like this idea it just may
be too complicated i mean not too
complicated
it might just be overkill right for what
we want
um
so i think i want to sleep on that we're
probably out of time
i'm guessing so i probably want to sleep
on that so let's just go back
and maybe call it a day and the next
week we'll think about if we want to do
this or not
that's my thinking
all right uh so where we we yeah we're
out of time
so i think we're out of time for now so
that's my thinking on this
um so i'm i'm not gonna
i'm not gonna really make a decision
about this either or
um but i want to just kind of like think
about it
any questions on what i was saying there
wouldn't this allow larger longer pass
than the original since you could still
reach the goal while
going a longer route uh yeah so
again when we actually evaluate those
we can if we want to like
put some constraints on the total
distance but
remember these are micro movements
they're pretty small
right so we may just not want to do that
and say look there's
flex in how the player or the entities
move
so that if there's a little obstacle and
they would have had to have done
a little thing in there that's fine
because remember it's a 60th of a second
or something that we're talking about
this motion it's a very tiny motion
so if there's if if we need them to like
kind of go around
something it seems like it's fine
so i don't know that i would want to
clamp it because i don't want the player
like the players not
thinking about that right they just want
it if it looks like they could go
it should just go at full speed right
that's my thinking at the moment anyway
has there been any advancement in the
four simplex case of gjk
um
so i don't know i haven't verified it i
want to say that
um dirk gregorius had some stuff on that
uh because i remember going out to
dinner with him and jay one time
and he was saying some stuff but uh i i
not i haven't looked
at ggk in a long time so i i don't know
ask dirk
why not just move the character to the
closest legal point of the desired
endpoint uh because of gliding
that's that's the whole thing i was
saying with gliding
so the part that the player wants to end
up at is
is not actually just the closest point
if there's something in the way they
want to glide along that
something
couldn't you squeegee the light board um
no
like basically that's what you're doing
with the micro fiber cloth
and as far as i know it doesn't really
help to be a squeegee versus a
microfiber cloth in fact the microfiber
cloth picks up things almost better
so i maybe but i don't think so
and plus you it still takes a while
you'd have to like get um
you know you'd have to dunk a thing and
pull it down and then dunk a thing and
pull it down and dunk a thing and pull
it down
and maybe you know you have a good
trough for the runoff and it's fine and
still maybe it's probably faster than
what i'm doing so
you might make an improvement but it's
not the like it's not the instant clear
i want the instant clear
that's all
i mean not the closest point of the path
close by than halfway uh yeah
so um that's literally the algorithm i
was just describing
so so you're yes that is what we want to
do
the problem is how do we find the
closest point that you can get to
because remember if you just if you
literally just take the closest point
then the person might be able to get
somewhere they shouldn't be able to get
right
because you don't know if those points
were connected
you know what i'm saying now we could
try
just doing that anyway like we could say
we don't care right because we're only
going to place
slow enough moving things with
large enough objects that we just don't
care and we could even
subdivide movements into small enough
increments so maybe we should do that
right so so that we don't have to worry
about connectivity we just do
subdivision to find the closest point
and that's it
in in fact volcanic popsicle you said
that's probably a stupid question but
actually
i think your stupid question is not
stupid
i think it's very smart and um
and and probably i should consider that
right
i should probably consider going look we
don't care
we're just going to say we know the
sizes of collision volumes
so we're going to subdivide motions into
pieces that are that's
that are appropriate size so if
something's moving really fast
we just do a few iterations to do the
placement
a few sequential iterations right um
or we just clamp velocity to that speed
and then we say all right all we're
going to do is look for closest point
so we just subdivide into cells and we
just look for the closest point and then
we place you there and we don't care if
it's contiguous because we assume
that there can't be micro channels of
that size love it
love it love that idea change what you
said
to that's probably a stupid question to
i have a great idea
and and off we go
just just just go edit your chat message
i know you can't
if you could
so no uh again frame stutter is not a
problem here because
like i said we just take a look at
we can we can artificially say that if
we need to move more than a certain time
step we just do
multiple rounds of this right because
the only benefit to not subdividing the
problem is speed
so if actually we can get a massive
speed increase by saying we
we need this bounce on the size of the
search space
then it becomes better to just run that
a few times
right because each iteration if if you
need to run
four iterations of something that's 10
times faster
that's a win right so
i i do i think we could make something
that just finds the closest point
run way faster than something that has
to remember the connectivity
because it can also be massively
parallelized it doesn't have to have a
cleanup phase we could run this
multi-threaded if we wanted to right we
could go nuts
um although i don't think that actually
matters because you just run multiple
entities probably so
yeah whatever but you get the idea
for the light board there are already
large transparent tvs so the only
question is price and pen tracking
so if you can make that
like that is like please make this
please make a transparent tv with like a
wacom tablet
digitizer like that
if you made that you would sell
thousands of those as well because every
educator like if you can get that out
before the pandemic ends
which honestly will probably be like
five years anyway and plus there'll be
another pandemic
right there'll be another pandemic and
if you can get that out
because everyone needs to do this
right so if you can make a transparent
tv
where you draw on the back of it with a
pen
um i mean dude like
that'd be so good you know i don't have
hardware skills so i can't make that
you know i totally agree that if you can
get a transparent tv
a large transparent tv which lcds
should be able to do right because an
lcd is is fundamentally transparent
um
so if you could just get a pen
that was like built into that system i
mean you could even
you maybe wouldn't even have to do that
you could even use like lighthouse or
something
you could use like a you could use a vr
kind of style tracking system if you
wanted to
at that point you you could you wouldn't
need the pen
to actually be a digitizer pen like a
wacom tablet
because you could actually put if you
wanted to
you could just use lighthouse or
something i suppose
uh nairo 2 says
at any point your development as a
programmer have you ever dealt with
pointer aversion i tend to avoid storing
pointers using array index lookups every
time instead
to avoid the possibility of a bad null
pointer i feel like i'm limiting myself
by doing this
but it also feels valid have you dealt
with this and have any advice on it
um yes i guess what i would say is uh
no that's great um we do that in
handmade hero all over the place
and uh it's probably the right way to
program
right fundamentally speaking the only
benefit that a pointer provides is the
ability to like relocate the memory
around
so that it doesn't have to be like
contiguous with something
i mean because that's what an index
that's that's the problem you get with
an
index is that it has to be quick
to get the index translated to where the
thing actually is
now if you don't have to do a lot of
lookups even that's not a problem
because just
grab a hash table and you're done right
then it doesn't matter but
if you want really instant in lookups
like you get with a planer which is you
know basically instant
um if you want instant lookups then your
index
indices need to be contiguous off a base
which which adds some work for you
right thankfully nowadays it's easier
than ever because you can do stuff like
reserve 64 gigabytes for every array
and just never commit them and then
they're all contiguous no matter how far
they grow right so it's not that hard
actually um
and and so i don't know you know maybe
that's that's
one solution but you know it might limit
your portability depending on what your
targets are
but no i mean pointers pointers are not
good like
in general pointers are pretty bad
they're too big
because usually you don't need um eight
bytes
to represent where something is usually
you know 16
bits you know so two bytes or four bytes
is plenty um and so it's pretty
you know you're you're bloating out the
the credit cash footprint
of everything you do by having these
larger
things pointers don't save you can't
save a pointer off to disk and
assume it'll be valid when you load it
back in right so you have this
translation process go to
indexes don't have that problem indices
just save just fine
right um
uh it's harder to validate a pointer
an index is much easier to validate you
just say look is it
is it less than zero or higher than the
total number of things i have
if it is then it's invalid a pointer you
get it and you're like i don't know
you know i don't know if it's valid or
not um
assuming that you're actually using the
benefits of a pointer which is that it
could be placed anywhere and not inside
a penned memory area so
uh i i think you're right on target i
mean
i don't like using pointers for things
that aren't
pointers like that that aren't like i
allocated a big chunk and i'm trying to
say where it is if that's what a pointer
does
that's what i use them for so you know
most the time
in my code when i'm using actual
pointers
a lot it's stuff like the code you see
on the screen where it came from an
index originally and i just
turned it into a pointer to do a lot of
stuff off of it but i usually don't
store that pointer
so like you notice entities they work
with like ids or something
we just don't use pointers as the
primary thing a lot
so so i don't i don't think you want to
use
pointers anywhere where you didn't
actually want a pointer
right um for permanent storage for you
for things that go into structs and
stuff for
actual code you use pointers all the
time in the sense that you first like
you know you load the id's
address and then you offset off the
pointer that's great i mean you can do
that a bunch like you see on the screen
here
but yeah for for tracking things you
know i don't store pointers very often
if i can avoid it
so i think you're right on target i i
wouldn't change a thing
i guess the only thing i would i would
the only thing i would add to what you
had posted really
is i think your emphasis on the bad null
pointer thing
i don't think that's the really the
interesting part because i still like to
have
a zero element for null anyway right
because i like to be able to know is
something pointing to something or not
right
so i usually reserve index zero for null
um so i'm it's not that i'm
trying to avoid that and per se although
that
it does give you new options you can
always have the null slot actually be
there so it actually does something
uh so that you don't have those problems
uh so there's all that it's fine
but i love all the other benefits of
indices they're smaller
they can be saved to disk or transmitted
over a network without translation
like ids are great for a lot of reasons
that don't have anything to do with null
so so yes to the thing you said but also
add on all the other stuff
is it possible to replace entire web
stack by c
uh well
i mean no because the front end has to
be written in javascript right i mean
you could
what you could do is you could write it
in c
and like compile it to javascript right
but at the end of the day the only safe
way to ship things currently for the
front end of a web stack
is javascript
so
when your zero slot is reserved do you
loop start from one or zero then your
choice
uh usually what i do is i let
the zero be valid but just have all
things in it that don't result in
anything
so like if you're running a physics
update or something it has no collision
volume and it has no velocity and no
position and whatever
so it just ends up doing a zero plus
zero equals zero update on it
so that you could loop over it if you
wanted to
but you don't have to so you can just
start everything from one if you want to
because you know the first one isn't
valid
or not valid but isn't important
what would you say to the idea that
pointers can be better because the
compiler knows to prefetch the targets
of pointers
this is not the case with indices as
there are no pointy semantics there the
power understands
[Music]
so um
i guess stanislav what compiler are you
talking about and which circumstance are
you talking about
where it enters prefetch
instructions
can you give me an example of some code
that you think would have a compiler
insert a prefetch instruction
would be would be my first question
i have others
like if you if you actually want to talk
about that part specifically because
uh we certainly can but uh i would first
need some code that you think
like can you post a godbolt that shows a
compiler generating a prefetch
instruction of the kind you're talking
about
and and this will be the last question
because uh i gotta
i'm i'm gonna smoke some meats today i'm
gonna
i'm gonna be doing some barbecue and i'm
getting hungry so i want to go
downstairs and
and start the smoke or
okay we'll i'll if i can remember
filiodelski
i'll point i'll post some pictures to
hashtag food on the molly rocket discord
where did stanislav go
okay here we go i cannot give an example
it is just something that i've heard
other people talk about when they give
counter examples for using these
well okay well then we need to ask those
people um
i mean
first of all do do does that even happen
like
i don't compile with clang a lot but i
can pretty much tell you that msvc
does not insert prefetch instructions
so i don't really know what what
that means
it doesn't sound logical to me
but um
so if we were to say that we were using
like
the most modern version of clang which
does all kinds of ridiculous
stuff in it right and and i guess
like we're like you know small structs
so it's really tiny and it's and the
compiler would really want to issue a
prefetch
maybe i don't know
about it but like
trying to think of what would convince a
compiler if it was going to do something
like that
um i'm not optimistic i like
my first thought is that i don't think
the people that are saying that probably
know what they're talking about but like
you know just to be fair let's not
assume that
actually you know what
um so let's see here so we have a small
struct
right that just got like an integer in
it um i don't know why this is returning
it's supposed to be turning it and um
so we go through here uh at each point
through i'm gonna take this sum let me
recall this sum
and i'm just gonna add whatever the x is
that's in the struct
right um and so we're just going to loop
over these and go
uh
oops
um
[Music]
there we go and let's see what we get
here
i'm gonna get rid of osaka
um so here's our asm
right so like
i don't even know what i would do to
this code to get it to issue a prefetch
because remember in order to want to
issue a prefetch
this thing's got to be tiny right
we've got to be wanting to prefetch
things that are pretty far
out or something
uh
i'm not sure
like without some idea of where the
compiler would ever do this i don't know
i've never heard of a compiler inserting
a prefetch before that you didn't tell
it to insert
right um but that doesn't mean it
doesn't happen
so let me just try to answer the
question this way
since i don't know how to provoke a
prefetch
um i also i'll be honest with you
prefetching
almost never helps so like i don't even
know if i can write a situation where i
would prefetch
because it's pretty hard to find a
situation where you want to do a manual
prefetch
once in a great while you do but it's
actually quite rare
right um but what i would say is
if we can find a situation in here
where you actually have a thing where
compounds to prefetch
but an index would not have the compiler
done it
i would want to see that and ask why
because the compiler knows when it
fetches from somewhere
whether it was fetching off an index or
a pointer
right
i mean
you know so i i really don't know i mean
we could do something like
yeah like a binary search or something
uh
so yeah you know like we could do
something where
we were trying to go like okay if x is
less than zero go to the left if x is
greater than zero go to the right
um and sum all the way down just so we
have something to do
right um but again i just
i just don't know like
i i i don't i don't know how to make the
thing do it
let's suppose we said there was a ton of
of crap to do here
right um
so now it knows it has tons of time to
prefetch as well
right i mean maybe um
[Music]
i mean it even it even auto vectorized
this
for us right like
right it it even vectorized this and
it's still here
[Laughter]
check out that unroll
all right if you say so clang
if you say so but i'm not seeing any
prefetches
right so stanislav my first thing to say
was like
make if someone says that be like show
me the code you're actually talking
about
right show me some code that actually
generates this mythical prefetch
and then show me that the compiler stops
generating the prefetch when you switch
to an index because frankly
i don't see that that would be the case
a compiler knows when you're accessing a
memory location and it knows that
whether it's using an index or not
right um and so it's just not going to
do pre-fetches oh do you want to see an
os there you go
um
built-in prefetch is the way to hint uh
okay so
so built-in prefetch
where do i put it i guess i can look at
that page um
saying this is only gcc so we're gonna
have to switch
so do i tell you what to prefetch though
but if i tell you what to prefetch then
this is a manual prefetch so what
so that doesn't help right
but that that's me i'm telling it what
so i could have put an index in here
right so that's not
it's built in prefetch location optional
but that but that's me telling it what
to prefetch
so this this is not we could have just
put an index in here so that that is not
the compiler inserting it into
a prefetch that's me inserting in a
prefetch right
so that's neither here nor there if i'm
inserting the prefetch then i can just
prefetch the indexed one just as easily
as i can press
prefix prefetch the pointer one right so
so that's not that's just the same as me
doing this
right um
i would think so so that that doesn't
seem
that doesn't seem relevant to me
yeah so that that's not that's just a
prefetch just a regular prefetch
and i could do that just fine so we know
that's not
that can't be it right um
i like so gcc i feel like gcc's code gen
i don't know maybe i don't use it enough
but it seems better than
clang clang's code gen has just has just
all gone to poop sauce
clang just like poops out the crappiest
code i do not understand what is going
on with clang
i don't like it it does really
unpredictable stuff and a lot of times
it's just poop sauce
that's no good i don't like clang
anymore i
i i just don't
i don't even know why it did this why
did it unroll this
that just seems strictly worse that just
seems like increasing the code footprint
but without actually improving the
performance
like i do not know what that i do not
know why that did that
i have no idea i have no idea why this
got unrolled
the vectorization makes perfect sense
the unroll makes no sense at all
to me
because basically like so i mean what's
what's the benefit there's no benefit to
this unroll
i mean look at this code right it's just
mobs and p ads
did the test jump would be free
there'd be no cost to the test jump and
it's always 256 it's a constant
so it's a perfectly predicted jump never
miss predicts
right so so literally
all this did in and i don't know like
i'm not a performance guy
so like you know please someone out
there correct me if i'm wrong
but all this did was just blow out the
cash
this just blew out the eye cash for zero
performance gain
this will run it like the exact same
speed as the one with the jump in it
right
so so i
i don't know i mean you you can go test
it i mean
go ahead and run them both versions but
it should be this should run
it's not just that it should run the
same it's literally gonna do this
this is what the cpu would already have
done
in the other case because test jump
doesn't
exist like the front end just just
appends the instructions
right so so this is actually what the
cpu would actually just do
if you had just written the test jump
right
so so like unrolling it maybe so that
there's
two per loop might have been necessary
i don't remember but that should be it
like at most you should have enrolled it
one
one time but possibly just not at all
maybe i'm wrong let's see so let's look
at gcc looked sane
let's see what it produced and see if i
can see
why something wrong with it
that is why you should have unrolled you
know what i'm saying
um
so whoa okay so 10 24
so that's the jump
so i'll be honest i'm not sure i totally
follow that
that does look weird or to me
good old msvc no auto vectorization
i support that i'm totally fine with
that by the way
so gcc's code is still a little weird
it's not what i would have expected so
maybe maybe that's also not what i want
but
this looked pretty good
i mean yeah
i guess
this is not quite right because you
don't really need to do
that but like it's much closer
is there anybody here who generates the
loop that i'm thinking of
i mean that's pretty good
actually
so this is what i would have expected
it's still a little more than
i i don't think it's i think it's still
too large
but but that's much better
right and so what i'm trying to say is
like so look at this code
so this this
and this those are one
uh fused issue
this is one they are both
going to execute during this like
all of this stuff is on different ports
than these
right so these will just issue right
at overlapped with this so they're free
so once you get to that point why keep
on rolling and this is why i say it
seems still a little
too much because i feel like you could
have just stopped here
you i don't think you needed the second
one because this is
already once you've done this where you
loaded
all of these you can just do this and be
done
right so you add 16 here instead of 32
and off you go
try oh z in clang
no no no i i i want i want it to
vectorize that's the right code
it's just it's just it should only be
it's unrolled it like one more time than
it should have
but it's still fine this code is fine
like that code is fine this code is like
not
fine at all like that i'm pretty sure if
you went and asked a person who really
was good at optimization they would say
this was very bad
like you should not have done that
because this code runs the same speed or
should run the same speed
um this code should run exactly the same
speed
but it's much more efficient in the
cache so
over the long run it will be faster
so so i don't know
even so i think it went to one too many
i don't think this should be here
um i actually should say i don't think
this should be here
right um
all right um
i gotta go i'm gonna go make some some
tasty barbecue
uh so i'm gonna wrap it up for today uh
we're gonna look at the color detector
when we come back
next time uh and we gotta get we're
gonna
make that make that not be bad
uh so that's our that's our goal all
righty
let's see here i didn't even have
handmade hero up
my bad thank you everyone for joining me
for the episode of handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you want a following series at
home you can always print the game on
handmade hero.org and it comes with
source code
you could go write the collision
detector that i was just hypothesizing
and tell me
it was any good that way next week i can
just
find out from you folks whether it
worked uh that's it for today
i'll be back here next week to play
around with that and see what we
actually want to do until then have fun
programming everyone
and i'll see you on the internet take it
everybody