hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete-game
live on stream we have well I mean I
guess it worked yesterday it's all I can
say it was kind of surprisingly easy to
do I was planning on having today be a
continuation of yesterday where we were
trying to reduce the grid size for our
so our spatial grid not our our lighting
but our actual spatial grid that
represents where the lighting it that
represents where the occluders are and
is used for a faster rate intersection
so we did that and we got a good speed
win there in fact and at this point to
be honest were we're getting pretty darn
fast I think we're actually more or less
capable if we turn everything else off I
think we're actually more or less
capable meaning if we turn off debug
collation and stuff like this
I think we just run at 60 frames a
second now and honestly I think at this
point our main the main thing that's
probably keeping us running at 60 frames
a second is going to be more like just
transmitting these excuse me
transmitting these values down to the
graphics card is mostly the problem that
we're probably having at this point
because since we're doing it CPU side
that transmitting is not being done
particularly efficiently right now and
we're actually sending these down as
full floating-point values which is four
times larger than we probably need so I
mean at a bare minimum it's it's at
least twice as large so so we definitely
have a lot of work we could do we also
have quality issues and you can kind of
see like it's not even clear that our
ray Kassar doesn't have some bugs in it
with lane states and stuff like this but
in terms of just visualizing the voxel
but you can see us doing here it looks
like the voxel is producing relatively
correct results you can see a lot of
things like the lighting consistently
responding to where we think it should
be and so I'm
still fairly confident that from here
were in a pretty good position I want to
do a few more optimization things first
but I think we're in pretty good shape
right and so what we're gonna want to do
is we're gonna want to do a couple
things one we want to do a little bit
more optimization over the actual
lighting pipe because there's still some
things in there that we're doing very
inefficiently that we can fix so we want
to do that and then we want to start
working on quality and the main thing
we're gonna do there for sampling is
we're gonna smooth out these samples
because you can see we get a lot of hard
lines on here there's really no reason
for that we can smooth those out and we
should the lighting will just look a lot
better when we do that because normal
lighting doesn't have doesn't look like
that right it doesn't have those
rectilinear patterns so smoothing out
those rectilinear patterns will just
make our lighting look a lot more
organic and the other thing that we want
to do there is we want to see what we
want to do about Flickr I actually at
this point I honestly kind of liked the
look of the lighting so I I don't really
even know how much of that I want to do
because I like the lighting to vary like
that because I feel like having the
lighting vary in that way to mean gives
it a nice kind of like active appearance
and I feel like if it was just static it
just wouldn't be as exciting like having
that light very I don't know I think I
like that look better so I don't know if
I actually want to do that or not
I guess we'll see when we actually do
the lighting quality pass what we think
about it at that point and we'll kind of
go from there
so that's really all and so all I'm
gonna do today I think is I'm going to
go take a look at the other parts of the
pipeline add that I don't really know
how effective they are there's another
thing that we can do so there is one
thing we haven't really looked at yet
and that is to what effect because this
is a pretty this is pretty heavy sim
decode actually that we're looking at
here well that's interesting
do you notice why am i why am i why am i
a guy can't face forwards that's kind of
weird when we go down to entity stuff
we'll see but it looks like nobody can
look we've got some kind of bug in them
in the facing picking you notice that
like you can't face downward anyway
doesn't matter point being when we
actually go and do the quality
improvements to this code that's you
know sort of one separate thing but for
right now what I'd like to do is I'd
like to focus on just the authorization
parson what I don't know is because this
is so simple
like basically the entire lighting pipe
line is now done wide everything's wide
vector ops visual studios compiler sucks
at vector ops like it's SuperDuper not
fast at that and so I'm somewhat worried
that we also may be losing speed simply
because the compiler is not doing a very
good job and so one thing if we really
want to be complete about it is we
should probably compiled through clang
just to see what happens if we compile
at least the lighting code with clang to
give us a metric of what the difference
between those two actually is because at
this point we don't know and so we don't
know how much of our code
is slow for no reason and I think having
two compilers in the mix would at least
give us a little bit of a I just think
that'd be something that we would like
to do for purposes of just knowing how
much it's costing us if anything that
Microsoft's compiler is usually pretty
bad at optimizing around vector ops in
my experience it tends to do weird
things on the loops it seems like if I
had to guess about what's going on it
seems like it massively over estimates
the degree to which you want to avoid
saving registers in a weird way so like
just to give you some perspective on
what goes on and in there so the way
that the ABI is specified on Windows is
basically there's you know some number
of registers and those registers are
both general-purpose and vector are
specified as whether or not the caller
so the person calling a function is
expected to save those registers or
whether the person being called is
expected to save those registers and
what I mean by that is when you know you
got two functions they're both compiled
they both use some set of registers and
one of them calls the other well let's
just say you're talking about the xmm
registers for example there's XM m 0
through XM m 7 when you call from one
function to the other the function doing
the function call already has probably
some state in those xmm registers right
because it's doing calculations itself
and when it calls out to some function
that is doing some sub part of this
procedure
it needs a way of knowing which of those
mm registers might get destroyed by the
person it's calling and so the way that
the ABI is SPECT on Windows is that
certain of those xmm registers are
expected to be destroyed and certain of
them are expected to be preserved right
so any function that gets compiled by
MSV c4 by Visual Studio is expected to
preserve certain registers because it's
conforming to the ABI and when it's
conforming to that ABI what it's going
to do is say oh X mmm these particular
registers I know if I use those
registers I'm gonna have to save them to
the stack at the beginning of the
function and then restore them from the
stack at the end of the function because
I've changed the values and I'm not
allowed to change the values in there
according to the API so after like
saving restore from what I've seen
Microsoft's compiler seems to make
really weird decisions about that so it
will do things like spill to the stack
constantly inside a loop seemingly just
to avoid using one of the xmm registers
it's not allowed to destroy instead of
just saving it once the beginning and
restoring it once at the end it
literally puts a stack spell like inside
a loop which no one would ever do and I
don't think so I don't know it's just
it's just something I've seen so that's
the kind of thing that we may want to
try as well and the problem with that is
just that getting something to compile
under clang versus getting it to compile
under CL might take a little while
because you know they might have
different warnings or one of the other
problems this clang is really bad about
undefined behavior so things like I it's
no secret that I strongly strongly
strongly strongly strongly disagree with
the C++ Standards Committee about what
undefined behavior should be here and is
and clang really likes to take advantage
of undefined behavior to basically
optimize code in ways that's almost
always wrong but they just do anyway
they don't seem to care about the fact
that this introduces bugs and tons of
people's programs they just rather take
advantage of undefined behavior that
really should never have been undefined
in the first place because it's very
clear what it would do on an x86 x64
processor so if the spec had any sanity
at all it would just say this behavior
varies per platform and does whatever
the chip would do when you you know add
two of these together in the overflow
right so one of the big problems and
I've said this many times I think is
that undefined behavior should there
should be no undefined behavior in the
C++ spec right what should actually be
in the C++ spec is just something that
says here's a bunch of behaviors that
were not specifying the exact output of
but we are going to specify that it does
do whatever the processor would do when
implementing that instruction right so
it's not undefined it's defined but you
need to know your platform first that is
what you would write in to aspect that
was saying in my opinion because there's
really no excuse for not having defined
a behavior you should always define the
behavior just define it in something
that varies if you're worried about
platform specificity because that way a
programmer who's writing code to a
particular platform knows exactly what
the behavior will be and that's critical
and they also furthermore know that if
they do that particular thing and then
they want to port to a platform whose
CPU behaves differently that it will not
work so they know now all the
information they actually needed and
that's very important right
so there anyway so I think clang is
terrible for taking advantage of those
things I think the spec is terrible for
having them and I wish they wouldn't do
these things but they do and they create
tons of bugs in people's programs for no
reason because there was an easy way to
not have people have bugs code has
enough bugs as it is the concept that
people would be actively doing things
that would put more bugs into it is kind
of absurd and ridiculous in this day and
age especially when people write into
our programming languages such as rust
where the only point is to have people
not have bugs they like literally adds
nothing other than like additional bug
proofing when that's the kind of thing
going on in the world and then you write
a compiler that intentionally inserts
bugs in people's code just because you
think you could is kind of nuts and
ridiculous but you know that's where
we're at so anyway so that's kind of
annoying and one reason that it might
not be the most fun thing to do to Port
Klang but since people build with clang
people build the handmade hero source
code under clang all the time on other
platforms I assumed that it wouldn't be
that hard for us to do because we know
that we don't have too much weirdness
going on there or somebody probably
would have reported that to us you know
what I'm saying so anyway let's take a
look now at what's going on with our
code here I want to see what speed we
get down to if we were to optimize the
the actual blending code because that's
something we haven't looked at yet and
we spent a lot of time working on the
Ray casting side of things and I just
want to know to what extent now we could
get some some speed winds from
relatively straightforward optimizations
in the actual light blending code so
that's the part that that I want to take
a look at now and so what you can see
here is we've got like fill outlets
border and then we've also got this this
part of the routine here this this T Y
loop here right and so what I'd like to
do is just comment this out and the fill
out light atlas border part here with
the x and y i don't really know why
that's outside of here I maybe there was
a reason for it not sure it could be to
avoid having something
completely but msec doesn't usually do
that so I just want to see what happens
if I remove sort of the fix-up code so
you can see here that actually it's not
quite a quarter of the time but it's
close so we can take an entire second
off the time here if we could figure out
a way to make this code work more
efficiently and you know just looking at
how it works it certainly seems like the
sort of thing that would not really that
would not really be a huge issue to do
especially because so the way that we're
doing this is we're producing cosine
fall-off so I'll jump over to the black
blackboard here and fortunately this is
not really my strong suit I've never
done separable filtering ever for some
reason I don't know why how many of
these did I want to launch too many
apparently so I apologize that like I'm
I'm kind of the wrong person to do this
and it'll probably be a pretty clunky
approach to it but I just want to kind
of point out what's going on here and
then maybe we can take a shot at it but
I'll also point out why I think in our
particular case it's also much easier
than it might be in other cases as well
okay so I've talked about this a little
bit before but I just want to talk a
little bit about what are called
separable filters and why we care about
them so separable filters is sort of
just a shorthand used in digital signal
processing to talk about what is
effectively a process you're probably
already familiar with even just from
like high school math so one of the
things that you've almost certainly done
in you know math class at some point is
you
taken something that looks you know
maybe like this 5x y plus 10x equals
zero
right so you've taken some kind of
equation and like you've done something
where you've like factored it right and
you've pulled out a common term that
exists so in this case like you know 5x
appears in both of these terms because
this I can write is 2 times 5 right so
5x appears in both of those terms so I
can if I want to write this as 5x and
then say well it's gonna be Y excuse me
y plus 2 right and so this is the same
equation but I've written it in a way
that separates the terms out differently
right and then similarly you've probably
also done things where you can break you
know you can do the opposite right so
you could say something like well if I
want to break this into different pieces
and I had this right and I just want
this in in the form of two separate
terms I can look at then I can multiply
it out right and now these things are
completely separate right they can be
processed completely independently and
then there's added together at the end
and they have no dependencies between
them right so separable filters are kind
of a way of talking about factoring
filters into into two parts from one
combined part or more right
so the classic example of something here
is exactly actually what we are kind of
doing in the code and it is to say that
suppose you have something where you're
talking about
a 2d grid right and in your 2d grid
you've got you know the fiber to number
of these right so if I have some kind of
a 2d grid like a pixel grid or anything
else that I want to do some processing
on then if I just want to do processing
on the row so for example let's suppose
we're doing something that we're already
familiar with because this is a cosine
filter where we're using let's start
with something simple like a bilinear
filter which we've done like tons and
tons and tons of times right so let's
start with a simple linear blend okay
so let's suppose that we were going to
linear blend this and we're gonna start
by just saying okay the way we're gonna
linear blini early blend this thing is I
want to take four values right so I want
to take these four values here and I
want to average them together or
something or maybe I want to do
something a little more complicated than
average maybe I want to do something
kind of weighted so like in order to
figure out what I'm going to write right
here right maybe what I want to do is
just take some weights and blend them
together so maybe I want point two of
this value I want point well that won't
quite work point three point three and
then point two right so I'm gonna take
like ABC and D and I just want to take
and the actual thing I'm going to to
produce for this square is a blend of
these so I'm gonna do point to a plus
point 3 B plus point 3 C plus point 2 D
right that's what I actually want to
produce
right so if we take a look at what we're
doing at each individual square as I
kind of marched through here
I'm gonna apply this thing and if we
assume that this continues going AEF
right whatever then on the next square
on B Prime I'm going to do some similar
equations so it's gonna be point to B
this time and then point three c plus
plus point 3 D plus point 2 e right and
so what you can see about the way that
these are getting computed is that it's
just repeating a what is what is
effectively just a very simple you know
it's a matrix multiply but the matrices
are literally one dimension so it's not
for interesting but it's basically a
very simple matrix multiply we're
basically saying look we've got some
weights 0.2 0.3 0.3 0.2 in a literally
like you know four by one matrix and
then we're multiplying them by an input
of ABCD right and we're getting an
output here that is you know this answer
and then we're just purely sliding this
window right this ABCD we're just
sliding it that way and we're writing
out the answer into each individual slot
as we go right
so there's nothing particularly fancy
here and as you know we've used linear
blends so many times all we do is we
just add together mult you know we
multiply each of our inputs by a simple
coefficient it's just a number
users usually fractional because we
usually want them to add to one so we
don't add energy to the system but all
we're really doing is we're just all
we're really doing here is we're just
using fractional values multiplied by
our inputs to produce our output it's
it's all it is very very straightforward
right so if you imagine us doing this
this is very efficient and it wouldn't
really scare us very much even if we had
to do like the entire row we probably
wouldn't be that scared right like I
mean we might start to get kind of
scared if the row was really large or
something but you know at least for any
fairly small size of this thing we're
not going to be too terribly worried
about it right but if we now make the
jump to 2d right because we're gonna 2d
grid here and we but we were just using
a one-dimensional filter excuse me
so if we want to make the jump to 2d
I've been sick for a long time anyway if
we want to make the jump to 2d what we
have to do here is we have to use a much
larger input size right so instead of
just four and it's not even gonna be
four plus four right it's not going to
be four plus four it's actually going to
be four times four right because now we
have to do for this way and for this way
which includes this entire set of values
so rather than doing four multiply
additions we now have to do 16
right so for any for any filter that we
want to run over a bitmap over a 2d
bitmap can image which our light maps
are we have this really nasty problem
that when you go from one D to 2d we we
basically have this you know nasty
problem of way too many F Mads going on
and what we had for our 8x8 right we had
for each of the 8 by 8 we did a full set
of of 64 right so we do 64 times 64 ops
right which is per bitmap per per light
map and we have like a lot of light maps
right so we're literally talking about
4096 multiplies there right and it's
just it's just a lot of math for the CPU
to do so the question is what do we
actually you know how can we perhaps
modify what we're doing because again
it's even in our case especially not
just in the hypothetical ease but in our
actual practical case we don't really
care that we get exactly a cosine
fall-off for our blend you know anything
that's even remotely like a cosine
fall-off would be fine
with us right so we have a lot of
latitude in constructing our filter we
just need something that's fast and sort
of like a cosine fell off because we all
know light doesn't actually obey an
exact cosine call it fall off curve
anyway material properties create much
different reflection characteristics
than that so a cosine curve is just one
of the things that is sort of like what
light would do when bouncing off a
fairly diffuse surface but it's not
correct anyway
so there's no particular reason we have
to do that we can do something else if
we want to so what I'd like to do is I'd
like to take a look to see if what we
can do is change the way we're computing
the math to do what's roughly called a
separable filter although I may be using
that term a little loosely here but I
would like to see if we can create a
separable filter where the idea behind a
separable filter is to just break the
thing into two passes the first pass
does just a 1d filter in this direction
so it'll do like an X filter right and
it writes out what are effectively
intermediate values they're not actually
values that will ever get used by
anybody they're just temporary
computations computed by the first pass
of the filter then we run a second pass
and the second pass goes in the other
direction right it goes vertically and
it picks up well I suppose since I wrote
it this way I'd be that way right and so
what it does is it will pick up all of
those temporary values right and add the
temporary values together in a way that
produces our final results without
actually having to ever do any 2d
operations and the only real restriction
here that we have on how we would do
this is just the fact that both
processes have to be one-dimensional so
we're only looking in our row or our
column right depending on which phase
were in and that we only write out a
single intermediate value that's really
it and honestly those things aren't even
am I out of tissues again
hopefully is I need to get some tissues
prompt salt
okay so anyway we could if we wanted to
broaden the definition even further than
this I mean there's no reason that we
only have to have one intermediate value
if we needed more intermediate values we
could have them and so on but obviously
the most efficient thing is to write out
the fewest values possible and so you
know we would like if possible to make
it so that we keep you know we keep the
whole pipeline flowing as efficiently as
we can so how can we take a cosine
weighted fall-off curve and turn it into
you know something we can use in a in a
separable way like this well we can
start by just looking at what we're
actually computing so what you can see
here is at each position we have an
outgoing vector and an incoming vector
and we're basically just taking those
two things and we're producing a you
know a dot product between the two and
we're you know we're doing that for the
entire matrix effectively so if you take
a look at the way that would map out on
here what we're effectively computing at
the moment is we're basically saying for
each one of these grid locations we have
some vector that represents where it is
on the octahedron now if you remember it
looks like this roughly
and when map to the sphere not the
world's best sphere I admit that but
when map to the sphere it looks
something like you know this so this
here call that a comes here and this
becomes here C and D are here and here
and then this is the exact same thing
but on the backside of the sphere right
so each one of these squares represents
a particular specific directional vector
these are presumably along the edge so
these are ones that are like you know
pointing this way these are along that
edge but they're on actually edges so
they don't the center doesn't point out
there so you know we've effectively got
something like this happening right and
so each one of these slots in the
octahedral map corresponds to one of
these it corresponds to one of these
values here yeah so what we would like
to be able to do is say well okay
assuming that we were going to you know
compute what the the values are here to
what degree do those things have any
coherence in terms of their coefficients
right from from slot slot right
so there's a couple of things we would
like to have be true so one of them is
that you know the the value of something
when when considering the value of the
input cell versus the output cell if
it's the same cell that's kind of our
one value right because we want the
value to come over Asma powerfully as
possible in the exact direction because
that would have no cosine fall-off and
then when we're doing perfectly
orthogonal which to be honest they don't
know to what extent that ever actually
exists anywhere on the map but there are
places where that would be close so like
you know these and these for example
would be very close to zero actually no
that's not true I take it back because
of the cosine clamping at zero because
we don't actually want negative values
anywhere so orthogonal values after the
orthogonal value it should drop to zero
and what that should mean effectively is
like you can only go half way down the
grid right so if we're talking about
this one by the time we got to this one
it's you know it's gone ninety degrees
past the sample point so all of these
additional ones are presumably not there
I don't know so let me think about this
so it's probably something like three on
here so it's probably something like
this region would be zeroes but I'm not
sure so
so that's kind of what we're currently
doing right what we're currently doing
is we're doing those in our products and
if we take a look at what direction from
txt why does it's really this unit
vector from octahedral so this so this
unit vector from octahedral what this is
doing is it's saying okay from a
particular 2d point on the map what
we're gonna do is we're going to make
sure the signs are correct and we're
gonna invert the polarity of some things
occasionally just because we're trying
to cover a sphere but basically all
we're gonna do is we're taking the
absolute values so the magnitude of the
X and the y and we're using the Z value
to effectively cover whatever the amount
of the X&amp;Y was that we didn't fill and
then we're gonna normalize that right so
that's what our actual values end up
being is just the normalized versions of
that sort of of that ketchup if you will
and you know the problem with this is
anytime you have and normalize in there
it's a very nonlinear thing right so
what we've got there is we've got a
we've got this sort of nasty nonlinear
computation that's what's determining
what our individual weights actually are
which kind of makes it a little bit
harder to figure out how we would
necessarily separate them out but at
least for me now is the time where I
just say look I don't really need to be
math star here although people who are
math stars could probably just go ahead
and analyze that analytically right and
say well maybe I'll take a look at what
all these equations work out to be and
you know or maybe you bust out MATLAB
I'm not sure but what I would like to do
first is just dump whatever this wait
map actually looks like right because
that will give me a better understanding
of what I'm actually looking at so that
I can understand the the specific
numerical values in question so what I'd
like to do what you can see here is when
we do build a few slight Maps we're out
putting these light maps into a into a
table that gets stored and so what I'm
going to do is in h h light prof i'm
just gonna dump the table because that
way i can just look at what it looks
like and then I'll have a better
understanding of what the heck is going
on right so what I can do here is say
look after those hmm after those
coefficients are computed which actually
they're saved to disk so it's actually
they're actually loaded not computed
because this is the profiler I'm already
out of t we're gonna have to have like
regular tea breaks on stream hmm in fact
I'm gonna do it now
I realize I'm at risk of patent
infringement on John Blow stream because
he makes tea on stream and you know I'm
I'm sort of like encroaching on that
space but what can you do so after we've
loaded these tables in which you know
and we've got the letting solution here
that lighting solution is going to have
these tables they're just going to be
listed here in this diffused weight map
right and so if we take a look at what
happens after we've loaded it we can
just add into our code here something
that prints out the diffuse weight map
exactly now it's a sixteen by sixteen
which we actually don't have so it's
it's only going to do eight by eight so
I think that was just something we did
to like make sure there's enough space
in case the tables are bigger or
something so we need to print out eight
by eight and then the diffuse weight map
just has the weights right here they are
so what I should be able to do is just
take a look at how the build diffuse
light Maps works and just verify to
myself that was the case you could see
it only loops over eight in either case
so I should be able to just go ahead and
use that so if we just use this
I guess there's two different versions
here there's the sy and the T Y and we
do need to do them both because we're
going to want to print out all the
tables as well as all the elements of
each table so we need 64 tables each
with 64 entries if that makes sense
that's what we're storing here so in
each case here I'm just going to print
out one floating point value I don't
need like a huge amount of precision
because I just need to know like roughly
what it is anything that's within you
know a rough two digit two significant
figures is probably enough we'll say
three just to be even more crazy about
it but it's probably fine so if we look
here at the actual values I'm going to
say map
looking into the map looking at a
particular element like sy SX so for
this particular map that we're trying to
print out I'm going to ask for a
particular element value and what you
can see here is the way that it's
indexing into this thing is it's just
saying look I'm going through each of
the the element values and I'm pulling a
particular element out here now I guess
and that I guess looking at it though I
can't say I understand what's happening
there because oh yes I can
sorry-sorry has a little confused there
what was going on so here's the actual
lookup into the fuse wait Maps I was I
was very confused because I was looking
at this I'm like that's not enough
accidents but it's fine so if we pull
out for the SX X Y here if we pull out
which map we're trying to print which
this is what I'm going to do right here
and I just access them effectively the
same way that they have been being
access to the entire time we're gonna
pull out a particular diffuse map that
we want to print out and then we're
going to access the values of that map
as we go right now this is doing it kind
of a little bit backwards
and I guess I don't I guess I don't know
whether I care or not how this is being
computed but to make it a little clearer
I guess we want to call these the
opposite thing because the way it's
getting computed is the other way round
from the way we probably would want to
think about printing it out so we
probably want to do it this way like the
destination we're going to print out the
map for a destination and then inside
that map we're gonna look up the values
based on the SS X Y right
so what we want to do here is we would
like to treat this as floats and then
just look up the sx s ex version so what
I'd like to do is just say look pretend
this is a float and give me the nth
float because we're not printing these
out wide we're just pretty nice floats
um every time we finish a row go ahead
and return out of the row and then each
time we finish a map maybe print two of
these I would like a announcement for
the map so that we can know who's in
whose particular you know map we're
looking at without having to I just
don't want to have to guess like our
count right so I just want a thing here
that says hey tell me which one of these
were actually looking at as we go right
all right so I'm going to print these
out I guess I'll just print them out to
standard out temporarily because again
we do this is like a this is just random
test code we don't care about what it's
doing it doesn't matter
so we'll just print them as standard out
and we'll pipe them to a file and then
we'll look at the file and that will
just be what we do and end off again
okay so I think I messed something up
here because you can see like a lot of
these things are all zeros so I'm
probably looking up into this map
incorrectly so we'll take a look at this
in a second here but just in terms of
I'm not sure so you can see here we've
got a TX minus 1/4 to look up into which
weight map it is so I'm not sure how
we're encoding this exactly but it's a
bit weird
I guess Pirozhki so I think I know why
so I think probably the reason for that
is because the way we're processing them
wide at the end of things I guess the
way we're doing it well let me actually
just go in there and look in the
meantime the tea is ready
well it's not ready it needs to be
steeped but so here's how these are
actually getting loaded out so you can
see here like it does it does allude and
it's processing these like four at a
time right so the reason that that this
is only happening over two things is
because we we compute each diffuse map
is actually computing like you know four
of these values at the same time so the
actual way that this would look is if
we're actually trying to extract the map
out it's not quite that way and honestly
rather than extract the map that way I'm
actually wondering if maybe what I
should do is actually just compute it
directly because now I'm thinking about
it we're gonna want to play with this so
I don't know that there's any real
reason not to just do this right and
then stop doing the
stop doing the opposite version there
and let's just take a look so if we
actually just did it this way and said
okay we're gonna do 8x8 and then these
we would do the same way so here's us
producing these values and I believe
since these things adjust they would
have to be incremented by one to account
for the apron because this takes into
account the apron this produces the
total W value for everything and then
this would compute the weights right
once it computes the weights we have the
W value and now we don't actually need
to do this we can just produce this like
final value or a new entry might be the
thing to call it and then we can just
print it out right so then after we
print out all of those now we can add
back in our little returns here and then
each time we go through this process of
doing all of the T X to Y X to Y yep so
that prints an entire matrix and so what
we can do is just put the announcement
here of like map % u % u equals and
minus X so that is actually saying that
computes it directly and that should
give us what we need I don't know if we
pull the diffuse Atlas out of here or
not we do okay so I'm just going to move
this down to where we do that
and then I'm going to rob bubbly yep so
I'm just gonna go ahead and just call it
here right and that should give me what
I need oops all right let's go get our
tea steeping I think there's an extra
bracket and now I should be able to see
the actual values in question right so
you can see them here and this gives us
all of our maps and you can see that
they actually look like cosign fell offs
right rapped on to the octahedron right
you can actually see where the values
are and one thing that you might
sometimes want to do I don't know you
might not but sometimes I do stuff like
this where to say okay look so we know
this is like one two three four five
entries right so what we can do is like
one two three four five and this allows
you to see a little bit easier sorry
this allows you to see a little bit
easier what's going on right so do you
see how you can see the shape of the
matrix just you can just see the shape
of the matrix entries a little bit more
cleanly right it's just an easier thing
to see so you can kind of see how
they're shaped as they as they as they
move around on here right okay so I
would hold on a second
all right the tea is now steeping so
we're all good so what we'd like to do
at this point is say okay
looking at these values right in terms
of significant figures and so on my
question is to what degree are we ever
actually using the same values you know
multiple times right because in order to
figure out how we would make this
routine do something sensible we're
going to have to find terms that can be
reused you know I'm saying so in other
words we if we don't ever see terms in
here that are similar to each other then
there's not a lot we could really do to
speed this up we need to see you know
particular values being multiplied by
the same thing or something in order to
figure out how we would more efficiently
compute it and one of the things that I
think is really you know if you look at
at why this is probably going to be
harder for us than it would normally be
and one of the reasons we may need to do
something more approximate or who knows
what is you can see that the shape of
the filter for each individual output so
you know if you want to take it look at
what has to go into square 4 or 4 you
can kind of see like just how different
the pattern of inputs is compared to
something like map 5/6 or you know maybe
map 6-7 they're just totally different
right very very different shapes so you
know if we literally are just going to
use the dot product here to figure out
what we're gonna do it does seem like we
maybe have a bit of an uphill battle of
course what we don't really know is to
what extent we could use fairly similar
values so like we don't really know how
different
actually is in terms of like the point
7s here you know like how often does
point 7 show up there it's it's not
never right you can see that like it's
actually fairly frequently showing up in
that slot so you know you never know
right
even just using the cosine fall-off we
might be able to do some stuff here that
would get us out of that business and
again I don't know I'm just saying like
looking at how looking now this filters
distributed there's you know there it is
again
it's possible it's possible that there
is enough reuse in here that we could do
something interesting
you know we don't know so at this point
it's kind of tricky like I said this is
not my strong suit I don't really do
this kind of signal processing hardly
ever never really done it so it may be
that there's some obvious things that
you could do here that would be good but
you know just looking at it sort of
quickly it definitely seems a bit scary
to me because I don't see a trivial way
that you separate this into passes no
matter what they are I mean you know
that could be anything but I don't see
much opportunity for doing that with the
function as it stands just because I'm
not sure how we would account for how
irregular the shape is you know and I
mean it just seems really it just seems
really hard to conceive so there's two
ways I could think of approaching this
one way of approaching this would be to
try and get something that produces a
sort of somewhat similar pattern but
that's more regular another way is to
see how many times a particular type of
value gets used and where so in other
words
if we were to look at all of the terms
that are involved in if we were to look
at all the terms involved in this matrix
right how would we actually figure out
like like could I just write a thing
there's my tea
all right
all right so I don't really know where
to go from here there's a couple
directions we could go and I'm not sure
which one of them will pant you know
which of those will pan out when we're
generating this pattern of sort of
transmittance we we might want to do
something where we wrap our values and
get a larger matrix just to see what it
looks like you know you could imagine
doing something where we said let's
print out a 16 by 16 matrix for each of
these or something right and well we
only need to do it on the printout and
so here where we're producing these
values we could just say look just just
give us the matrix in its entirety
wrapped so that we can see the shape
better when it happens to wrap around
because it's a little bit hard to see
with the way it is now right so here's
like a better sort of view of what's
happening to the matrix I think
and you know there are some things you
can sort of say about it wow it's just
really Squinkie
so I guess what I would say is I'm a
little confused first of all I'm not
sure what I want to do next but one of
the things that you see that's pretty
unusual is it's weird that even out to
three significant figures you get like
these rows that are like exactly the
same so you know map seven seven and map
seven six are like identical in terms of
their contributions here and that's just
real weird and you see that pattern kind
of happening fairly frequently I guess
that's because of the structure of the
cosine because the cosine has like a
very you know steep fall off it has a
very like sharp inflection and then it
has a very sharp like a very smooth
crest right I guess it's possible that
that as you get to certain incidence
angles the variation in the output of
the cosine when it's you know near near
zero and near one are maybe very you
just don't see like perturbations and
the inputs just don't change the output
much at all so even though these are two
totally different products because
they're close enough you end up with two
three decimal places you get the same
value right so that's surprising to me
it's not what I would have expected to
see but it's what we do see so you know
that's where we're at so yeah so back to
our story so figuring out what we want
to produce here I guess what I'd like to
do is find out you know can we can we do
some kind of a search over this space
and see if there's redundancy in here
that
could just compute things maybe in a
different way sooner they could think of
to attack this that doesn't just involve
changing the function which is the other
thing that we could do and changing the
function again you know looking at how
different this looks I am mildly worried
that changing the function to some kind
of a basic blurring process might just
produce too much error I really don't
know it's possible that just a basic
blur of this thing would be fine and in
which case we're just spending way too
much time trying to do something more
interesting that we don't really need to
do right mm-hmm
so there's one other thing we could try
too which is threshold inconsiderate
amido care anyway and it might be
interesting to see what those values
look like so let's suppose we were gonna
say like look maybe one thing we'll do
is just try to do threshold here so
every place in here that W is greater
than 0.1 F we use it but everywhere else
we just don't and maybe we want to try a
couple of these values so maybe what I
do is I say thresholds here and I just
say that and oops and then I just say
okay that's something we can control
so if we were to just cut things off
what does that look like does that give
us anything particularly nicer you know
I don't know so here's the results of of
this what just happened Oh
oops um yeah sorry about that we're in
the wrong routine the perils of having
two parallel routines open at the same
time ladies and gentlemen
we did not actually want to modify that
um so yeah all right so we'll just do it
that way we'll say look if we're below
the threshold we just get zeroed out
what does that look like so here's the
look of the matrix did I screw it up
again what happened what are we doing if
W is less than threshold W equals 0 if
Debra's of student and tree W / W total
am I missing something
threshold equals 0.01 if it's less we
dump it hmm I guess I'm not sure what's
going on there because at least looking
at this we should have zeroed out W so W
/ W total here would be zero right what
am I missing folks
because like I mean if you're seeing
0.07 there that's obviously not that's
obviously not above the weight threshold
I mean at the risk of stating the
obvious so you would think that that
would take care of it right what just
happened
all right I don't know what to make of
it so I guess I'll go ahead and step
into that routine probably just some
kind of stupid typo I guess soaking up
remedy shhh lie prof and we'll take a
look
so NHH light prof i'm just gonna go
ahead here and run and i'm gonna take a
look at what w is oh whoops I guess I
just somehow wasn't thinking about the
fact that this will decrease the values
dramatically so the problem with this is
since we don't know what the total is we
don't know what we would clamp out here
so that's a little trickier right that's
a little trickier because since we can't
know ahead of time what that is I mean
we can very easily just go through and
make sure that that particular when we
can zero things out and then normalize
them back up to one so that's not that
bad but it does make it a little harder
to say like what that cutoff should be
right so yeah anyway
so if we look at the results here you
know cutting off at the cutting off of a
particular threshold you know it saves
some work so you can see here how you
would be able to skip about two to four
rows most of the time some of them
unfortunately are treated four columns
which doesn't help because when these
become columnar here right it's a lot
harder to skip a column that it is to
skip a row just because of the way that
we're processing is so you know it's not
nothing but it's not really it's not
really super compelling
yeah I don't know I don't know I'm not
thinking of the magical thing this this
is something that really wants to be
explored more deeply so normally I would
kind of break out the the notebooks and
and work on this problem for a while
it's pretty hard to do that kind of
stuff on stream because this is gonna be
something that's very solvable I think
but you know in this particular case I'm
not sure I can really do that
effectively on stream because it would
be like you know hours of me kind of
like noodling with the thing um so just
to try and figure out what we might be
able to do again more shortcutting there
so the other thing we could say is well
you know what if we just consider an
arrow or band and I mean that is sort of
what this is doing right
it's narrowing the contribution rate but
so what if we were to say like
everything like less than 10% is out so
a much stronger so instead of doing
things that are insignificant we're just
saying look we're restricting the
function actually quite a bit that's
post consideration so I guess it's got
to be a little bit different than that
but so let's try here
so it looks like the point on one is a
pretty aggressive cut off already just
looking at how decimated this gets
and I'll go ahead and stop doing the
additional so I can just look at the
actual matrices so realize before when I
said two to four rows it's really just
to write because the reason it looks
like for us because we had extra an
extra print out of the matrix in there
[Music]
hmm
so one thing I would be interested to
know - so I think I'll print this out as
well is rather than just looking at the
dot product for my own edification what
I might do is say show me what the
actual you know in a separate pass
appear that I do for actually you know
we'll do it last so it's so we don't
even have to scroll up to it let's just
put it last so what I'd like to do is
say for a particular one of these what
if we just printed out what direction
things are in so you know maybe
something like this
so one matrix each and well just say
like oops so what I'll do here is just
go through each of these and say look
we're gonna take the incoming direction
which gives us a v3 we're not going to
beat any weights or anything we're just
gonna say that the entry and I can still
do like if entry is positive or if entry
is not zero what I could do is say look
take the entry and just pick out
whatever element we're printing and
we're just going to print that right and
the reason I kind of wanted to see that
oh and you know what we're going to need
some spacing the negative is a problem
here because I don't remember what the
printf format is to leave space for it
is it plus or something that anyone know
know that yes so if we take a look at
what the elements are here this is just
sort of my way of trying to see like
what are the actual values like
components of the vector right
[Music]
so these are the X components of the
vector now and it looks like we need one
more to write this sorry it doesn't
really matter but because the way they
lined up it didn't matter but we'll do
it anyway right looks like I put this
inside the the for loop erroneously as
well no no okay it just prints out every
time through I was gonna say no I was
like I didn't think I did that I didn't
so looking at this this kind of lets to
see what these values are in terms of XY
and Z and that's actually pretty
interesting
so that's pretty interesting and the
reason that I find that to be
interesting is because if we look at the
separate pieces of the dot product right
there getting added together right so
we're doing like in here we're doing an
ad and this this part is a little
trickier because it's clamping the
values so that they can't drop below
zero
which is something that we're gonna have
to reckon with which might be a little
tricky right but looking at those values
it's like okay so they're very symmetric
in exactly the way that we would expect
for X&amp;Y right so it's really and Z is
both so Z is symmetric on both axes
Sophia if you look like actually
actually know all of these because
they're come from a sphere they're
actually all doubly symmetric right so
you can see what all the values are for
for one of these octahedral maps and
they're completely symmetric right
so again while I'm not really sure
exactly how to take advantage of it
there's a tremendous amount of structure
in here
and so when we're doing our
multiplication you know where we're
going to be multiplying the same values
often right because as we do
combinations of each of these there are
only so many different products that we
have to take into account here right so
for an equation for in in terms of
understanding the structure right we
have something that looks like you know
ax BX + a YB y plus C oops
a Z BZ and this although it's being
clamped so we kind of have to understand
that there's you know an operator
happening here of some kind if we ignore
that just temporarily because that's
gonna be an additional fly in the
ointment but if we just look at this
we're basically doing a series of these
you know times our color values so all
of our terms effectively look like this
and each of these is drawn from one of
these distributions so these are the
only possible values that we can have
right
so because these are completely
symmetric if you look at the actual
values that exist here one of the things
that you can see is that there's
actually so there's only 16 possible
values that you can get for Y and among
the 16 possible values not all of them
are even unique to this level of
precision you can see like negative 192
is repeated twice right doesn't look
like there's really much repeated miss
but there's 16 Y values that's all the Y
values there really are and there's just
positive and negative versions of them
right so you can pretty much only draw
from 16 values there's 32 values total
if you want to count the positive
versions of it but it's basically just
16 values and then the positive negative
version right if you look at Z so Z has
20 no oh I'm sorry you know what that's
not even 16 that's only 12 because
actually we didn't get out to here so
it's only 12 twenty four if you count
both there's sixteen here right but this
is actually diagonally symmetric so you
can see when we look at the number
pattern here the 318 one 64 right is
duplicated so the z pattern is like
really easy it doesn't even have
positive and negative versions of these
so the z pattern is like really basic
one two three four five six seven eight
nine ten so there's like ten values and
that's it so we're talking about ten
values here right that can possibly come
in we're talking about 12 or 24 that can
come in here hard to say how you want to
count that
I don't know and if you look at here
what you can see is the so trying to
kind of say this right so if you look at
what's going on here you can see that
the same thing is true about this that
was true about that so if you look at
what these values are it's exactly the
1224 thing again on the other side but
one of the weird things that you can
also see here is some of these values
are like the same value so like these
are the same as these right these or at
least this one is the same as this one
right to these levels or this one is the
same as as this one so like this appears
to be roughly the same set of values
right and so what we see is that the X
like although and this is what you would
expect because this is actually you know
it's a diamond pattern so the x and y
should be the same and they are so
actually these two both pull from the
same set of values right
so when you actually look at what our
inputs to our coefficients are while the
coefficients are kind of a bit wonky the
inputs are actually really regular
there's actually very few inputs there's
as little as twenty two separate values
going in here depending on how you want
to look at it so it's actually a
reduction that's pretty dramatic in
terms of what you would expect if these
were actually completely unique
functions because if you look you know
we've got three of those matrices so we
actually have one hundred and ninety two
values going in right but only twenty
two actual values that we see
differently and if we want to we could
call it thirty four values to give it
the maximum amount of expressivity if we
want to count the plus and minus
difference but right so there's a
tremendous amount of structure in that
input that we're seeing there
and so I don't actually know to what
extent we can take advantage of that but
it's worth noting that we're only
talking about the pairwise
multiplication between each of these
values and the values only get
multiplied interior to each other so in
terms of like what would happen with the
Z coefficient right
we know that the Z coefficient has 10
total values and if we so if we talk
about the total number of products there
are a hundred total products that can be
produced for this term right so even
though we technically have 4096
different products for producing there's
actually only a hundred versions of this
so it's 40 times less right in terms of
this term for this it's not so good
right for this it's 576 for these two
terms so it's like 576 576 and 100 in
terms of the possibilities so the actual
total number of possible terms we might
want need to compute here is you see as
drastically less than this but it's
unclear how we really take advantage of
that given that these numbers still are
quite large especially these so although
we could separate this math out in a way
that potentially allowed us to compute
fewer of these
I'm not sure to what extent we
necessarily care
so
so suppose I was to think about this
equation sort of the other way around
yeah
[Music]
I mean I'm just trying to think out loud
here so suppose you were to say well you
know we've got a matrix right I mean
just thinking about how you're gonna sum
these things together if we're thinking
about how this procedure actually works
effectively what you've got at the head
end is you're computing all the possible
ones of these right this is how we were
doing it originally now we're just
saying look take all the dot products
that you can using every combination of
a and B from our input vectors so you
know a and B are basically drawn from
these 64 vectors that we can have right
and so in terms of a transpose B that's
going to be 4096 inner products right
that we can generate and so out of this
4096 inner products that we can possibly
have which all of which we were taking
then our input right lines up with one
our input lines up with the B it's
basically saying look here's what the B
vectors would have been and so and our
output lines up with the a so we're
trying to basically say like if we had
an input coming on B and we want the
output going out of a you know how do we
produce each of those output values
right so there's 64 and they're taking
64 inputs so I'm trying to think if
there's another way to phrase that I
guess right so I'm trying to understand
if there's some other way that I could
produce that same result by perhaps
saying like
well rather than doing the combinatorics
is there some way I can just do each
half separately and then combine them
back together right so for example you
know could I do instead of 64 times 64
which is 4096 is there some way I can
just do 64 like plus 64 right June and
I'm saying like is there some way that I
could do a process on 1/2 where I pre
calculate a set of matrices that can be
then used by another output set right so
what I want to know there is if the if a
particular input cell right if I know
that that is a transpose B or ax BX + a
YB y plus AZ BZ if I know that cell
needs to be this and more broadly
speaking the entire matrix is just those
where the a value goes you know along
the the output side right and the input
value goes in here right um so if you
imagine this as instead of individual
cells rather just two matrices so just
trying to think this through in my head
so if we were to just try to generate
what each of these is going to be
imagine we just did it for one right so
take take this part out and imagine we
just did it for one and so what we're
trying to produce serious a transpose B
at a particular location right
if you imagined it looked like this and
I want to produce axbx here right then
it's sufficient to put all of my
different a because you know I I have to
give another index here but like so I
want to produce a IJ you know bij here
right and these are of course just
matrices full of those things so if I
wanted to produce
one of one of these results where I have
the color value in each case right so
this this is this then again would be
multiplied by whatever my color value
input is to produce the actual values I
mean it's this is actually just a scalar
so that wouldn't really matter but so
each one of these bitmaps basically
would just have the X vectors here and
then we're going to do that matrix
multiply to produce these these values
right the source of the exponentiation
in terms of how many of these products
we actually have to do is coming from
that matrix multiplied right so for each
of these locations because there's 8 by
8 for each of these locations i have to
do 1 2 3 4 5 so i have to do 8
multiplies to produce this value right
so for 64 slots i have to do 8
multiplies each
or 5:12
so yeah I don't know because that all
that gives you then to is it only really
gives you the contribution from that
particular cell hmm so I'm not seeing
anything yet I think this is going to be
something that's going to require a
little bit more thought which of course
we'll have all week to do in the sense
that you know it'll kind of be kicking
around at the background so I think I
might just end it there today because I
didn't have any good ideas we do have a
nice way of looking at the matrix now
and looking at all the different pieces
of it so let's just leave it there
ruminate it over the ruminate over the
week and then next weekend we'll try to
figure out what our approach is going to
be for looking at how to calculate this
more efficiently because thinking it's a
full second to do this and that's just
too much so go to a brief Q&amp;A now or if
anyone has any suggestions of what we
might want to think about we can and
then hopefully next week we can look at
some strategies because it looks pretty
tough this is this is it's not
insurmountable by any stretch of the
imagination but it does look like a
matrix we're gonna have to think about
couldn't at least the tetrahedron unit
vector function use a lookup table and
lerp sorry I'm I'm not sure what what
problem is that trying to solve what
would that be doing for us I guess is I
just I'm not sure what that not sure
what that would help with exactly
oh yes so that function never gets never
gets called it's strictly used in
building the look-up tables it's it's
it's used to generate look-up tables but
it doesn't get called the actual chain
so just to give you hoops just to give
you a little more of a insight into that
so here's the actual routine which what
we're looking at speeding up so it's
here and so what you can see is it just
loads weights out of this diffuse weight
table and it just does the ops directly
right and so it doesn't ever call that
at all this routines kind of sucks in
separate ways but it's not dependent on
that function because that function has
already been baked into this map so we
are never calling it the problem with
this that we're trying to look at right
now because we could try to improve I
should probably if this back-end by the
way this part could be implemented more
efficiently just as is although it's not
horrible as it is right now it could be
improved right
but what we really want to do is is
tackle how many of these there are right
so you can see here we've got 64 of
these right you can see this is looping
over eight things
this is looping over eight things and
then we've got two of these so it's just
it's a hundred and twenty eight of these
and that's just of this whole block
right it's not good so what I was hoping
for is a way of breaking one of these
out so maybe like if we could get rid of
this loop right by doing two passes
right so then we could get down to more
like 32 iterations of the loop instead
of 128 right
so that we're just trying to break that
squared iteration problem if we can
all right I guess no questions so we
will wrap it up thank you everyone for
joining me for the episode of handmade
hero it's been a pleasure coding with us
always if you would like to file in
series at home you can always peer to
the game on handmade hero org and it
comes with a source code so you can
follow along with it at home maybe you
want to try and figure out a separable
filter that's approximates the filter we
have we're not even a separate I'll just
figure out a good mathematical
optimization to the process we're doing
that breaks some of those iterations
right that's it for today hope see you
back here next week when I will be
trying the same thing myself hopefully
after a week of thinking about a little
bit more we'll have some idea of what we
should be doing till then have fun
program everyone and I'll see you on the
Internet
pinkies everybody