hello everyone and welcome to I guess
what will be a fairly short episode of
handmade hero because well since we've
been on RSI break with the hand
I've just been basically starting the
stream and I take questions until we get
up to a question that seems like it's
one that should be recorded for
posterity and then I start recording and
now we have gotten one but I think we
chatted for like 45 minutes on
relatively off-topic stuff so anyway
here we go
first question of the day that's tech
oriented let's go ahead and check it out
so the question was can you explain
cross compiling and the answer is yes I
can and here I will all right so what is
cross compiling first of all for those
of you don't know what it is because
some people maybe never encountered it
hopefully everyone knows what compiling
is because we've talked about in a bunch
if you don't know what it is go all the
way back to the very first stream and I
explain what it is the intro to see
stream for example will tell you exactly
what it is but as you know compiling is
the process by which we take source code
and turn it into machine code something
that takes the text files that we write
that are the sort of human readable
version of what we want the computer to
do and turn it into actually something
that CPU actually reads now the textbook
definition of compiling is a little bit
different I think technically and I
could be wrong about this but
technically the definition of compiling
usually means something more like
translating something from one language
to another so I don't really know what
the textbook definition compiling is and
I'm not trying to say that this is what
the tax profession is what I'm trying to
say is what we think of it as when we do
it here on handmade here and we run the
compiler what we are trying to do is
take these text files that we have
created that our source code that we can
read and turn them into something that
CPU reads and we've looked several times
on the stream at what X 64 code right
that's the the sort of encoding that the
processor uses that we're trying to run
on right
so what we're talking about very
specifically when we talked about
compiling handmade hero is we're talking
about taking a source file a set of
source files right you know like
handmade dot cpp and everything else
like all the source files whatever they
are and turning them into some stream of
binary right which the CPU can execute
right the CPU can understand this so
this is the human readable thing this is
the CPU readable thing and the compiling
step this is compilation right
compilation turns the human readable
stuff into the machine readable stuff
for us and that's fundamentally all
we're doing member programming right is
we're trying to create we're trying to
create this but typing out a bunch of
ones and zeros would be murderously hard
on us right so we create textual things
that are easier for humans to manipulate
because that's what way more efficient
you know the very first programmers were
actually in putting this stuff directly
right the very first program has
programmed machines by actually putting
in the actual instruction encoding in
binary you know using flip like levers
and stuff right or punch cards later on
but quickly you know we kind of said
that we can make this better by making
something that translates easier
directives things that humans can
manipulate more easily and that's where
the concept of compilation kind of
became central to the programming
process where it's like Oh
instead of inputting the stuff directly
we should input it in some other
language that's designed for easy human
use that can still output what we wanted
to output and and that's you know where
where that comes from
so that's what we're doing when we
compile and the important thing to
remember about compiling is really
there's a couple different stations this
process we kind of talked about it where
technically you know when we say compile
well really there's multiple steps to
that we compile right but then you also
if you remember we linked there's a
linker right so really like the when we
say a week recompile the program well
usually when I say that really what
we're talking about is wery compiled and
we relinked the program because
technically usually it's you compile
then you link and then you have this
thing
right so it's it's really worth noting
that there's two steps here now now what
are those two steps you know if you
don't quite recall from way back in the
beginning well this first step where we
do the compilation that's turning our
source code into sort of a partially
it's turning into partially this right
and why is it partially this well it's
partially this because there's still
some unknowns in the process there's
still some things that aren't quite
known yet at the time when the compiler
runs okay and there's a couple different
reasons for that one is because
oftentimes more than one file is is
involved in building the project and
especially if you don't use like we use
a unity build when people call it on on
the stream which has nothing to do with
the game engine unity it's just saying
that we build everything as one big
giant source file it's kind of a nice
way to do things when you do things that
way it may be a little bit less clear
this is happening but in a in most
people's projects they don't actually do
things that way most people products
there's a the concept of an obj file
that they actually overtly use and what
that means is you know you've got you
know a dot CPP and B dot CPP and C dot
CPP you know I don't know make me up
names here but you've got tons and tons
of CPP files you know there may be like
a thousand of these files right all
involved in the project and the compiler
you typically invoke on only just one of
them and you say compile a dot c p--
opinion too often times a dot obj or a
dot o depending on the operating system
this is the UNIX way right this is the
the windows way right
and so when you compile something you
turn into this object file and then the
object files they all go into the linker
right and the linker produces a single
executable file right so it typically
looks something more like CPP s you know
there's tons of them maybe there's a
thousand of them who knows how many a
hundred of them I'm not sure right they
all come over to OBJ's one to one right
so every individual CPP file becomes an
obj file ok and then all of those files
the linker this is linking this is
piling soca' pile we linked and then we
get an executable right or an 8 a doubt
file or whatever elf binary whatever
whatever you're trying to produce the
thing that the operating system actually
runs right so that's actually what's
happening right when we talk about
compiling when we talk about doing
compilation that's really what we're
talking about is that process and this
we know what it is
we look at this every day this we don't
really know what it is in the sense that
we haven't really talked about too much
on handmade hero but what this is is
it's a partially CPU readable thing
meaning inside it is actually machine
code right so it's got machine code
that's like ready you could send it to
an X 64 and the X is before would know
what to do with it
but it's not quite all there yet because
since there's a lot of obj files
remember those obj files call each other
right every CPP file that we you make
maybe call something that's in some
other CPP file or whatever so if you
have a function right let's say you have
some function foo of X or whatever that
you're trying to call and foo of X is
defined in one second feed file let's
say it's defined here here's the
definition right and then somewhere else
is a call to foo right and some other
CPP well obviously when I build these
things you know when I produce the obj
files those obj files they don't
actually have enough information neither
of them has all the information they
need to successfully have foo get called
because the debt the actual code for foo
is in one place and the actual call to
foo is in another place and those two
things aren't even seen by the compiler
at any given time the compiler is
working at one file at a time right and
so that's where the linking phase comes
in so the machine code that's in the obj
files has what are called like
unresolved symbols basically in them
right it has things in them that it
doesn't really know what it is yet so
let's take that call - foo we're trying
to call foo
right so maybe there's something like a
jump instruction or a call instruction
right for the in the case of a function
call would be a call instruction right
so it's got the machine code the actual
binary encoding for a call instruction
and then it needs to know the address
it's trying to call it needs to know
what it's trying to call into but
it doesn't know what this is it has no
idea because it doesn't know where foo
actually is it's never even seen foo it
doesn't know anything about it other
than maybe its function prototype right
so that remains as sort of an ambiguous
symbol and then it gets fed into the
linker and the linker reads these obj
files and has the obj files have
information that tell the linker where
all those symbols are and what they are
so then what the linker does is the
linker does a couple things it merges
all of these things together right so
it's basically something that allows it
to create for lack of a better term a
single homogeneous thing with all the
code that correctly can jump into itself
and knows where everything is right so
it's that but it actually has a little
more so it's it's gonna bind all these
IP files together but it's gonna put in
a few other things okay and so what's it
gonna put in well what its gonna put in
is on this executable right we have the
result of all of the obj files so all
the obj files are are sort of merged
into some giant block of executable code
let's let's actually call this machine
code so all of this machine code all of
these OBJ's are combined together if
they're you know correctly aligned and
all that stuff to produce machine code
all that machine code is all ready to go
it could start being run right but
typically because this is running in the
context of an operating system there's a
bunch of like header data here as well
right so the linker is not just
producing a bunch of stuff for the CPU
it's also producing a bunch of data that
typically goes at the beginning but it
could go anywhere it's producing a bunch
of other information right that tells
the operating system how to load and
execute this code because remember
remember we talked about dynamic link
libraries right dynamic linking this
concept that well you know I have to
call Windows for stuff but Windows Azure
running when I run we weren't compiled
together I didn't compile my app into
Windows right that didn't happen and so
if you think about it what happens there
is a actual runtime when this executable
is loaded in and executed by Windows it
needs to know how to like patch up some
things in my excuse to that when I do
jumps into Windows code it knows where
the windows code is right so all of that
information ends up having to be packed
into this header as well as some things
that usually they stick on there that's
like for example in Windows there's some
stuff that identifies it as a Windows
executable so there's like a thing like
a mattad value and stuff like that in
there right and it's even more
complicated there's lots more stuff in
here right so it's it's a very
structured file that's a lot of
information so and the linker does more
than just mush the objects together it
also does a bunch of extra work to
basically produce a file that's in the
right format for the operating system to
get the stuff out of do what it needs to
do and start the program running okay so
what is cross compiling well cross
compiling is when you want to run this
process exact when we talked about
compilation linking producing an
executable you want to run this process
but you want to run it for an operating
system other than the one you are
running on so for example let's say I
have a Linux machine oops and I want to
run code on the Linux machine so my goal
is to run an executable on a Linux
machine but I am running on 1/32 this
machine we're running on right now is
win through two machine well it's a win
64 machine right but it's Windows ok so
if I was to set up a tool chain that
built a Linux executable on Windows so
I'm running the linker the compiler and
the linker on Windows but I'm producing
an executable that's in the format that
a Linux machine would expect that is
cross compiling that's what cross
compiling is it's simply the act of
taking one operating system and one tool
chain on that operating system
running it and getting output that you
can then run on some other operating
system okay very very simple so how does
that work was the question and I had to
go through the salaah explanation so
that you could understand the answer was
incredibly simple which is it's there's
literally nothing to it all of this
process none of it has anything to do
with the operating system at all right
nothing in this process has anything to
do with the operating system it's all
just reading and writing files right so
if you want to build a cross compiler
all you have to do is build a compiler
in the linker exactly as you would if
you weren't cross compiling right and
then run it on some other operating
system there's no magic to it right
because all the compiler does is read in
the CPP file do a bunch of work on it
and then output the obj file at no time
does it have to interface the operation
for anything other than loading and
saving files right which we all know how
to do on any operating system really and
you can even use a C runtime library for
that right so all of that logic all of
the code for the compilation does not
depend on the apperance is amin anyway
so if you wrote something that compiles
for say x64 you could go run it on a
PowerPC you could compile that code with
a PowerPC compiler run it on a PowerPC
and it would still output x64 code
because the compiler is a thing that has
nothing to do with the platform it's
running on it's just code that generates
file data right it's just generating
data that it writes out to a file so it
doesn't matter what platform it's
running on just because you run
something code that generates x64 code
running it on a PowerPC doesn't make it
suddenly output PowerPC code right
because you know I'm talking about
literally the process of doing it is
like hey I want to XIII I want to output
a call instruction here right that's
what I want my can power to do my
compiler did a bunch of work it wants to
write out a call instruction into the
obj file or whatever right it just knows
that oh a call instruction I don't even
what it is but I know it's like Oh x5b
or something and then the address is
encoded here or whatever right it just
literally writes those bytes out to the
file so it doesn't need to be running on
an X 64 for any reason in order to write
out X 64 code right because X is before
code is just data it's just bytes on the
disk so as long as the compiler knows
what all of the opcodes are it could
write them out no matter what the host
machine is right so you write the
compiler just as you would if it was
native if it was on the same machine if
it wasn't cross compiling you'd write
the same code then you write the same
exact linker you would you know you
write the same code to link to X C and
just because you're not running on
Windows or not running on Linux doesn't
matter it's the format that you output
the format of the file you output is the
thing that determines what platforms
will be able to run it so if I write a
linker that writes an exe it doesn't
matter if I compile that linker on Linux
it's still gonna write out an exe that
Windows would read that's just how that
works right so cross compiling there's
no magic to it all it means is that the
code for the compiler in the linker were
programmed to output specific format
things that were for a target other than
the one that they are running on that's
it
and so if you write your code well like
for example LLVM you know it's a nice
compiler or whatever I you can just pick
the target because it's got a bunch of
back ends in it one that generates x64
code one that generates arm code and it
doesn't matter whether you're running it
on an ARM processor or an x64 a
processor whatever you compiled LLVM for
has nothing to do with that code path
both of those code paths will exist
inside the actual compiled compiler
right and so at that point if you just
have a command-line switch that says
please generate arm code that just means
that the compiler will now call its arm
code generator which is a piece of code
that knows how to write out files with X
with with arm assembly instructions in
them right arm machine code whereas if
you tell it to run the exit e for branch
it's just going to call some
that writes out x64 machine code okay
and that's it
so cross compilation is nothing special
it's no different than compilation in
fact compilation is just compilation the
only thing that makes something cross
compilation is if you happen to have
compiled a compiler for some other
operating systems format on you know a
different operating system that's all
that makes it cross compiling but the
code for the compiler is identical it
doesn't change at all right because when
you write a compiler that outputs x64
code it will always output x64 code and
if you compile that compiler on PowerPC
and then run it on PowerPC it will
suddenly output x64 code on the PowerPC
and so you've made a cross compiler at
that point just by recompiling the
compiler on a different platform write
compile of ecstasy for compiler on x64
and you will have a compiler compile and
execute for our compiler on PowerPC and
you have a cross compiler that's it
hopefully that answered the question
let's see
let's see I think we're just about out
of time
s I was going to be very short one
because we most the time was off topic
questions today let's find out
looks like there's no other super
critical questions here alright so I'm
gonna go ahead and wind down there is
cross-compiling
in a nutshell oh well ok here's one
that's kind of on the topic just so we
do it's a Qbert Caleb you didn't put a
QQ on in front of it but I noticed it
here he just want to know so why do I
still need Linux to compile for Linux
and the answer is you probably actually
don't but here are the reasons in
practice why you often times have to be
on a particular platform to compile for
that platform reason number one is some
important tool in this some some piece
of this chain is not available for the
platform you're talking about so for
example right I don't think I don't know
if on Linux there is a Windows linker
like LLVM doesn't have a Windows linker
a thing that it doesn't have a thing
that can link to an egg's II so LLVM on
Linux can very easily output obj code
that could be used for a Windows program
but on Linux you may not have access to
a Windows linker right now I assume by
now someone probably has run it like
Ming Ming GW Ming win or whatever has
won so I assume you can do it on Linux
right so I assume that that's actually
the case I don't really know though so I
have no idea but point being one reason
that you might not be able to do
something is because the linker has
never been ported so you might have
access to the compiler but not the
linker or I guess the other way around
you may be a linker not compile but so
in practice you may not have all the
tools that you actually need on any on
one platform so that's one thing can
happen the next thing that can happen is
nobody may have done the work of setting
up all the dependencies so for example
you know in order to compile a program
oftentimes you need all of these system
header files all these dot H file system
header files system library files right
if you don't have all those you need all
of those in order for the compiler in
the linker to grab them when they're
required and so in order to build for
Linux say on Windows
you need to grab all those files and you
need to put them all on Windows and so
that your windows toolchain can access
them right
and so again cross compiling
conceptually is incredibly simple
hopefully it's you know I convinced you
of that but as you know and builds can
get incredibly confusing right
as with many unnecessarily complicated
build processes building for an OS
oftentimes is way more complicated that
needs to be because there's all these
libraries you have to link with there's
all this special stuff that has to
happen for producing executable or
there's all these system header files
like hundreds of system enter files blah
blah blah and you have to reproduce that
whole environment because otherwise you
know the compiler it sees pound include
you know some some Linux header file and
windows you know that's not on your
machine so you do have to do a bunch of
work to set up a cross compiling
environment oftentimes that has nothing
to do with having an actual compiler
that can produce the code sometimes
that's the easy part and the hard part
is all the accoutrement
although like you know other files that
have to get input into the process so
the compiler when you say pound include
this there actually is that that thing
right but that said I would be surprised
if you can't compile for Linux on
Windows I suspect you can are you sure
there's not a tool chain for that I feel
like I feel like that would surprise me
it's probably super janky but I feel
like it's probably exists anyway all
right so let's go ahead and close things
down
all right I don't want to sign into
Google accounts but thank you all right
thanks everyone for joining me for the
lip soda handmade hero it's been a
pleasure chatting with you
like I said we're on RSI break right now
I don't have a specific ETA for when
we'll be actually doing game coding
again but if you would like to join us
for more Q&amp;A style chats obviously we're
still here 5:30 p.m. tomorrow I think
check the tweet but though I may have to
move it up to 6:00 I can't quite
remember what exactly the schedule will
end up having to be for tomorrow there
might be a reason why it has to be moved
slightly but we'll be a Becker shouting
and then next week I will also post the
tweet bot scheduled for next week so if
you've got questions tech questions that
you want answered I can I can feel them
or if you just want to chat like I said
we we do a pre stream I basically take
off-topic questions till the first on
topic question and then I start the
recorded stream so if you have off-topic
questions we cover those too that's
about it for now I'll hopefully see you
all tomorrow
back here on Twitch until then have fun
programming I'll see you guys on the
Internet