okay thank you everyone for joining me
on today's very special handmade hero
episode I don't actually know that it's
going to be very special but isn't
everyday kind of special at the end of
the date like I mean if every day is
precious I i think that there's probably
some kind of weird spiritual book you
could read somewhere that says something
like you need to treat every day as
precious or special or some other
nonsense like this and so I feel like if
today isn't special then really no day
is special and who wants to live in a
world where not every day is special or
that they never have a special day I
mean furthermore why would you want to
have only some days be special when
every day could be special I think it
just doesn't even make any sense so I
feel like this is going to be a very
special episode of Hamid hero just like
every episode of handmade hero is
incredibly incredibly special almost
oppressively special if you will so
special that it's specialness may in
fact render everything else that you do
in your life sort of inconsequential and
dismal by comparison that's not my fault
that's just how special we are here so
let's go ahead and get started because
we have some work to do today it's day 2
65 and you're going to want to unpack
the very special code from day 2 64 into
a directory somewhere if you're trying
to follow along with what I'm doing
because that's the code i'm starting
with and honestly it's pretty special so
here comes our code and i'm going to
compile it and then i'm going to run
nope not like that and then i'm going to
run it using the very special and i mean
that in sort of a different way now
microsoft visual studio so let's go
ahead and get that running here where we
left off is we had made some little
buttons right that we could use to
interact with our profiler or really
anything else that we wanted to and
we we just put those in and we have a
number of things now where we've got
like sort of debug control stuff that we
can use we can pause the game and jump
around and that sort of stuff but we
kind of need to clean a little bit of
this up first of all we have to clean up
the layout thing a little bit because we
never got the we never really did a
proper abstraction for lines that have
stuff glommed on to themselves because
as you can see our first one is
erroneously not indented all these
should have been indented right and
similarly we sort of have a weird
situation where we these are kind of we
can't even tell if these are buttons so
I think what we want to do is just
expand this UI a little bit and make
this work a little bit better just kind
of clean it up now that we know what it
looks like and have some things that use
it the other thing that we might want to
do and i'm not sure if we really care
about this or not well you know we could
do to the other thing we could do is put
that off a little bit and what we could
do is also make a profile top list where
we could base to say like give us what
functions are taking the most time and
stuff like that which is pretty handy as
well right so those are just some things
that we could do I'm not sure exactly
what we will do but that's kind of where
we are at and what all this what this
means for for you the the glorified
listener is that today will be a sort of
a debug profile you I'd a word one way
or the other one thing that I do wonder
is do we still have the ability to do
all this fancy stuff we do that's pretty
cool I really like how we can tear
things off it's like oh do you want
another profile like is this not enough
profiling for you maybe it's not
sometimes you know you just need a
little more profiling so what you can do
is you can just say like oh I want
another profile here let's go ahead and
and grab that off we go and now I think
if I'm not very much an error which may
be I am you can actually these are
totally separate which is kind of
awesome too so I can have two of these
and I can like drill down in one of them
right and it doesn't affect the other
one which is also pretty cool right I
like that a lot um you know it's just it
just means I think we did a pretty
reasonable job on the architecture you
know what I'm saying anyway yeah anyway
uh let's go ahead and and dive in here
so the first thing we need is we need to
add into our debug control we need a way
of putting some some pause like we don't
really have a way to do the pause
control right now and I need to have
that happen so what I want to do is say
well we have these boolean buttons so
I'm going to make in our debug control
wherever that wherever that nonsense is
debug control where where are you at
it's like frame slider like that oops
rain slider in our debug control I want
to make some buttons that go with the
frame slider that makes sense and I want
those to be able to do some operations
for us right so what the first thing I
want to do is make like a pause button
that's that reflects the state of the
the debug pause right so we'll just say
debug state pause is the state of that
so if it's true then it's paused if it's
false it won't be and then in here we
just need a thing which says what kind
of interaction we want to do and I guess
in this case we want to do like set u
int32 in Iraq
maybe and we just say we want to change
the pause to I guess whatever not
whatever isn't right so whatever it
isn't right now is what we would change
it to and we can just say this is a UN
32 interaction oops it means that close
that pensais will just make one of these
so what I'm going to do here just so you
can sort of follow along with what I'm
thinking what I'm going to do here is I
want to make ways of just making these
interactions pretty easy to create so
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
make a generous interaction that's a UN
32 interaction where I pass in what the
type of unit that you and 32 or
interaction is than anything that does
that can can use this function to
generate one so in this case I'm going
to do debug pause you know or set pause
and so in here i'm going to say debug
interaction set pause and that's going
to toggle the paws on and off so that's
all I really needed that to do and
similarly i'll do another one here which
is like let's see I maybe do something
like a set you know to be honest with
you we can even do these fairly
generically like these could be just
like if I wanted to set a value in the
debug state I could just make it so we
pass an address so we could do something
even more ridiculous which is just like
you can just do totally generic stuff
here like set you and 32 which is like
anything that's a UN 32 it can set right
in fact this set element type could even
be written in terms of set you and 32 if
that's what we wanted and that kind of
seems like kind of cool to me actually
because then it's literally just a
straight up that it does that anyone can
use so i can say Oh what I wanted to do
was I want
set a particular thing I want to set
whatever the debug pause value was and I
want to set it to whatever the debug
pause value is not like whatever the
opposite of it is I can do something
like that and I could leverage that same
interaction to make some action buttons
that were like that allowed me to jump
the viewing frame to the various frames
that we actually have like these so if I
want to jump to oops if I want to jump
to the oldest frame then what i could do
is say well set you in 32 interaction
debug ID I want to set a the viewing
frame ordinal and I want to set that to
whatever the oldest frame worried
ordinal is and again that's just kind of
its it's just like a poor man's lambda
right I you know if you wanted to start
using crazy c++ features which I detest
you could imagine making a lambda out of
these for example and you know or some
other kind of a closure if you're in a
language that was had better closure
support and that sort of thing so
something like this ah you get the idea
that's not what I wanted those trees
frame ordinal and so then all I'm really
saying is well you know much like we had
and I guess I should get rid of these
those don't wait what I'm saying here is
that instead of having to make a bunch
of interactions that are specific to
what it is that I'm doing if I just take
a look at like set element type
interaction for example and what that
does I can make this much more generic
by saying instead of set element type
interaction I can just make this be a
set you in 32 interaction and instead
it's just like what's the UN 32 target
like what am I going to overwrite and
one
gonna override it with right and then
instead of having the concept that the
debug element is a separate thing that's
like you know more more specialer what
we can do instead is sort of have
basically binary functions any kind of
binary function can be represented here
relatively straightforward right we can
do void star target and then we can just
sort of say well whatever the the value
is that we're going to store goes in the
other place and off we go right so at
that point I can say okay whatever the
target is that goes into the targets
lots of a set of element it's just
target now like so whatever the value is
goes into the value slot and in this
case we can just generically treat you
at 32 s this way but we'll can have
other functions that take other things
sighs you in 30 tues like so and that's
a lot more generic right so now when we
go in here instead of set element type
we wouldn't even have that one we would
just have sent you in 32 then what we
can do is say well the target has to be
the same instead of the element having
to be the same and then again can test
that generic element there okay so let's
push forward so an element interaction
itself I guess we can still have for the
time being since that's not particularly
unusual we can still put that in here I
do think though I'm going to not quite
replace that just yet because I want to
do a couple of things first so when we
do a set profile graph route that is
probably another example of a place we
could have done a set if this just be a
set pointer right you could imagine this
just being a set pointer interaction so
we could do something like set pointer
interaction and we would just say well
whatever the element is that we're
talking about here we know that it'sit's
grid that's the thing that gets set
we know that the graphs profile root
node we know what that is because that's
what are our graph view information
tells us unfortunately guess I don't
know if I have that in here I can easily
get it right because here's that debug
view so if I want to I can say alright
well we'll get the debug view then in
fact I could even if I want to I guess
do it a little higher up although
there's no really need to do that unless
we're actually in the rectangle in
question so i might as well as leave it
there but point being I can do this zoom
interaction instead by essentially just
saying I want to do a set pointer
interaction that's that pointer
interaction is going to set the view
route grid whatever that thing is let's
see what that actually is I'm going to
look for a set for cloud graph route
here so set profile graph route what I
want to do is do exactly this so I want
to set the profile grid I'm just going
to say hey here's that profile graph
grid I want you to overwrite that with
my grid that I'm looking at right now
and that's all I have to say about that
so this all goes away and now we are
just left with this which is much nicer
right so again that means we can get rid
of some of these interactions oops we
can we can get rid of all of these
really like these are gone we could in
fact get rid of probably even this one
but przemek I'm going to keep going
first so let's go ahead and say what
else we got here so debug interaction
here's another zoom interaction for set
profile graph root right again this is
exactly the same thing as before it's
just this code and we should probably
pull this out anyway this is some common
code that we don't really need to have
multiple copies of right i mean these
we're not getting anything out of that
duplication it's just wasted so here we
are at element interaction i believe
element interaction is probably still
fine like i said we're gonna probably
put that back and i just want it to be
gone for now so i can look at all the
debug errors let's see here element is
not a member what's going on here why am
I not there we go a debug ID undeclared
Jennifer I thought we had debug ID its
graph ID I guess but what were we using
for these interactions before we should
have been able to have a debug ID for
them why don't we have one at the moment
that's a little bit weird we're we
actually using the graph ID in this case
I guess we never made another debug ID
for these guys which we should have
because they have one right they do have
debug IDs it's the stored event pointer
not the sort of n pointer it's the
element pointer is a more accurate one
than the graph so graph truss element
pointer would be a good debug ID like to
do here too
ah yes element is done a number of debug
interaction sorry debugger idea I'm
cardona fire all right graph ID and same
thing here set pointer interaction and
if I not found that's true I'm going to
I'm going to grab these guys and just
pull them up to the top out to where
we've got our interactions somewhere
we're going to we're probably up here
and I'm going to make two of these so
we've got set pointer interaction and
that's just going to have you know a
pointer to pointer unfortunately see is
bad at this c++ i should say c is not
bad at c++ because like i said they
always get everything wrong and so
that's actually one that's going to be a
little annoying as you'll see but it's
okay to do set pointer and set unit 32
and then that's I think I'll we should
need for what we're trying to
what is the actual definition here I
guess we can just use generic well you
know I'm going to make another one okay
debug interaction set pointer I didn't
make one of those decided all right
let's keep cruising here oops yeah and
so this is the annoying part like I
don't know why they insist on doing that
I assume that it has something to do
with the inheritance pointers being
different but it would be nice if you
could have a this is a pointer to a
pointer all pointers are the same size
trust me stop complaining because
pointers you know could be different
sizes in other you know some kind of
weird implementation of some other
feature but I want the version where I'm
saying no I'm telling you all my
pointers are the same size stop your
whining but there's no way to do that
that I know of that is relatively
straightforward anyway so let's continue
here this is the slider ID stuff again
this interaction we can just use set use
and 32 interaction again this is a again
totally trivial I can just say whatever
i'm doing i'm going to set the debug
State viewing frame ordinal and I'm
going to set that to the frame index and
this will no longer pause when we click
but that's okay because I don't really I
never really wanted that I just did that
because we didn't have a way to do click
pause if that makes sense
I'm sorry we didn't have a way to
actually manually pause what I want to
do is like manually pause because most
of time I'm not scrubbing all right so
let's see this is set profile graft
route so this is this is the graph so
what is the actual value their graph
let's see you profile graph Fergus to
scrap wood so what I want to do here is
I want to do set pointer interaction I
want to set the graph wid and I want to
set it to nothing so that it you know
just get cleared
what is the same and also I suppose now
I can just make this this can actually
just come in here and do this okay so
set element type interaction this is
really just to set you in 32 now and I'm
just setting whatever the element type
is and this doesn't need to be there
anymore let's see set pointer
interaction of course yes thank you so
much for reminding me of that and the
problem is so if you just set it to
avoid star because I could just do avoid
star but then you would oftentimes
accidentally forget it and do that what
you don't want so you want to generate
it in the error if you don't do this but
you don't want to have to cast it every
time for no apparent reason it's really
annoying I hate that anyway let's see
boolean button it doesn't take three
arguments
really it doesn't
oh you're right it doesn't so why are we
oh because it couldn't compile that you
and 32 okay that's fine all right can't
convert debug type to you in 32 that
when I suppose is okay pause is it just
called debug Paul's know what's it
actually called we have that pause I
know we do because it's in there pause
duh so let's see set UN 32 interaction
cannot convert are going to be 32 to you
32 that's fine too
something accidentally put a period
instead of a comma and let's see a lot
of modify variable most you submit to
the hydrogen element so this we have to
reinstate which we will so that'll be
fine in a second profile graph root
boobs profile graph root is not
something we need anymore we only need
set unit 32 which is going to do a
simple right it's going to say the
interaction target equals the
interaction UN 32 like so this will
disappear this will cast to au 32 so
they can write it and the Zach same
thing will happen in the pointer case
like so it'll take the target like this
and it will write the pointer into it if
that makes sense all right so getting
down to very few errors now that is
is also fine and so is that and we are
done so that's good so that's all
finished so now all I have to do is pop
back up here and allow there to be a
data member who is the element and never
done alright so let's see if we're still
working we still work like that pretty
well we can still zoom I believe it yet
looks fine what else can we do here we
can now test to see whether our debug
control works at all here's our jump
commands here's our paws so what I'm
going to do there sit pause and see we
stop pause again we keep going so that's
good I can jump to the oldest the most
or the most recent in either case right
should really make what when you're
viewing show up more but because it we
should probably make that be like an
outline across the thing so you can see
what the filled color is anyway a lot of
stuff we could do there to improve it
but basically all good all right so
that's all happy now what I think
probably we should do is I'd like to go
ahead and clean up the layout code now
because like you saw the layout codes a
little bit busted there I am wondering
if now might be a good time to split
this into a second file as well because
we've got like a bunch of code that's UI
code and a bunch of code that's
collation code and I am just wondering
if maybe it's at the point where the you
know the UI code can sort of be included
separately
so I'm thinking anyway and we could sort
of start that right we could sort of
start that and so maybe I'll do that
let's take a look at what would happen
if i was to pull out let's see here so
oops not for quota let's say I was going
to go and copy this file at that age I
copy this into handmade debug you i dot
cpp or something and then i will load
code you i dot cpp let's see here okay
uh so I've got this file now and i'm
just going to start pulling these things
out i'm going to include a handmade
debug you I Daisuke in here I don't know
exactly where I'm going to occlude it
yet i don't care at the moment but i'm
going to start pulling out some of the
code that i would need for for this
stuff to work right so let's take a look
at a given row like that sort of stuff i
want to grab some of these out here so
let's take all of this stuff
and maybe even all of this stuff and put
it out here all right and let's take a
look here interactions I don't know
where interactions really make the most
sense to be we even have such thing as a
variable iterator anymore we do it's in
this nonsense debug draw main menu
should really be recursive and we should
get rid of this this stuff there's no
reason why we to do it that way anymore
I think I was just showing how you could
do it that way or something I don't know
it was dumb yeah a lot of this stuff is
just kind of sticking around I don't
even think we use that debug statistics
stuff anymore either anyway put that in
there I guess I'll also maybe copy this
and make this a place where we can store
the thus trucks okay so here's the
layout code that we have so far and if
we counter the interactions as part of
it which maybe we do also want to do we
would grab these out as well so these
are probably first because everyone else
talks about these usually and these are
all for the collation stuff except for
maybe this and the debug tree I guess we
could also say was maybe well not really
it the rendering of it and the structure
of it I'm going to keep them a little
bit separate for now just cuz do we use
debug string anymore but what is that
that appears nowhere in here
I don't really know what that does or if
anyone uses it anymore I don't think
anyone does you know what we're going to
do here we're going to comment this out
for a moment and then we're going to
delete it if nobody uses it I don't know
if anyone does anyway so yeah so what we
can do here is we could say well this
code you know can include debug handmade
debug you I that H and compile that and
obviously we got up pre declare that and
that looks like about it interaction is
hot is not found that's because we
actually didn't copy that over probably
should interaction is hot and okay all
of you should come over here
interactions are equal also and debug
kick all of that stuff should probably
be in here right so debug that CP
actions are equal and all of this stuff
debug event to text I don't know about
that let's take a look debug IDs are
equal
that should probably just be something
that is included in the H file I'm
guessing right that's probably something
that should be in here so I need debug
get text size and probably debug text
out at like probably text app all this
stuff should probably be in there right
I would be my guess x 0 is this oh man
we still have like highlighting control
escape codes in here who was it that
made me add those that I remember that
was ridiculous but somebody was like can
we make it have like color codes in
there and I'm like what yes but why and
I don't know that they ever actually
provided me a why that I'm actually okay
with but but we did it anyway and now
it's in there clogging up the code okay
so debug get States debug text out at is
that can we make debug text out at take
this now
is there actually anywhere that matters
like what even is the above text line is
that something we even need because I
don't think we need it anymore right yet
nobody uses that goodbye and debug text
out at everyone always has the debug
state when they're actually calling that
so it's just a holdover from the old
days that we were ever calling that in a
way that didn't have all right so now
we've isolated that stuff which is good
that's step one so now I can like sort
of see what we've actually built here
for our system in a little more concise
fashion which is kind of nice right
again people often ask me how do you
divide files up as if there is a magic
answer but there is no magic answer my
procedure is just a divided files up in
whatever way makes it easiest for me to
concentrate on the information I want
some day after Allen Webster is done
pounding editors into the ground with
his raw and meaty fists we probably
won't even ever think about files again
because why would you there's no files
are stupid they don't even make any
sense I don't know why we're still
programming with them it's ridiculous
you'll just be programming along and
you'll say i want to see these four
functions and those will be the
functions you see that's like how any
sane person would have made code editing
if they weren't from 1950 but you know
what are you gonna do anyway point being
since we're still stuck with text the
way i organize files is I separate them
by the stuff that I want to see together
that makes it easy for me to think about
how that system is working like quickly
see it which is a little harder on
stream because I have a lot less screen
space since I have to use a big font in
1920 x 1080 but it's still the same
thing applies alright so the first thing
I'm going to do here is get rid of the
stupid debug prefix that I put on
everything for no apparent reason
and so that was like functions here so
it's going to call that tech stopped
because they all take a debug state is
the first parameter so there's really no
reason for it we know that operator
overloading you know I'm not trying to
they're only in here for this particular
code anyway you know what this why is
this function even here text out at he's
just the same as debug text up so yeah
it's kind of a sure game anyway that
should definitely be in line doesn't
really do anything its translates one
call on to another so yeah these guys
are just these guys are just shorthand
and that's fine okay so i'm just going
to change those quickly and then i'm
going to sort of zoom through and trim
that coat off
there we go
and the last one I think okay again
nothing should have changed as you can
see and so now I want to go ahead and
make this layout system a little bit
more robust so I'm going to take a look
at everywhere where I'm actually using
this looks like there's a couple of the
things that I that should probably still
also be pulled over like this is all UI
code right so this stuff should get
pulled over we've got like what what is
deep quest of interesting oh so that's
our stuff for testing whether you want
to put something alright so this stuff
should get moved over as well like so
and let's go ahead and grab the set a
frame slider draw element drum a menu
well so there's a couple of weeks I
could look at this and I don't know
which one I want to do I guess what I
probably want do for now is maybe not
pull those things out leave those in
here and say that this is just for sort
of the generic UI code at the moment
let's just say that that's true just
temporarily I don't know that I want
that to be permanently true but I'm
going to leave it that way for now so if
I take a look at where we're doing
layout again like I was saying I think
this is the only place that ever
actually opens a layout at the moment
everything else is kind of gets it from
cascading away from the main menu stuff
so what I want to do here is I want to
change this to being something where it
actually initializes this thing a little
more formally right so I want to have a
thing where i'm like oh hey when you're
going to make one of these layouts I
want to want you to specifically call me
so I want you to say begin layout and
maybe I want you to say n layout as well
and this layout obviously has some stuff
that has to go into it so for copying
this information here then probably what
I would need to pass is I need to pass
the debug state I need to pass the mouse
key I need to pass where I want it to be
like the upper corner of the layout and
that's about it the rest of the stuff i
think is not different if that makes
sense so here's the upper left corner
bit there's the mastery bit there's the
debug state bit and then I just return
that okay and that way we can change
this a little bit more freely now and
not have to worry about it so here's
debug state here's Mouse p here's three
uip and we might make that a little bit
different in the future but for now
that's the way that's going to be okay
so that calls begin layout and then at
the end of all of it in case it was
important we would call em layout and so
in n layout we just passed the layout
that we initialized originally so that
does what I wanted there and now
everybody as far as i know is actually
going through this layout system so now
i can clean it up you know tidy it up a
little bit and make it a little more
sane so that it can do the layout that
we want because they like we sort of
just ad hoc did it and now that we know
everything that we need in there we can
just kind of like lock it down if that
makes sense so I'm going to grab the
begin layout in n lae i'm actually going
to move those down so i can look at all
of these guys together so we can kind of
see here's all of our stuff like begin
layout n layout element rectangle and I
don't know so begin element rectangle I
think an N element are the pair there as
well we've got advanced element and so
on so
what I would like to do is start moving
these things into slightly more a
slightly more coherent places so what I
want to do is say if I'm going to do
begin element rectangle then what I need
to do at that point I need to sort of
have an opinion about how I'm going to
store how I move across the system right
and there's two ways i can do that one
ways i can say that when you call begin
i figure out where you should be you
know and do indentation if you need to
do indentation at that point another way
that i can do it is i can say well I'm
you're always going to draw elements
where you are right now and then only
when you like go to the next line will
any sort of changes that you've made
take place if that makes sense and the
other thing that I think where is the
depth stuff here yeah so the depth stuff
is kind of busted as well because that's
just hard coded into the layout right
now and I don't really want people
setting that depth manually which is
what they're doing now so I'm just going
to make it be an underscore and that way
we can know when people want to change
the depth if that makes sense so like in
here we could just say set up like so
right and yet this is I think exactly
the thing that I sang for I've complain
about this in the past and people don't
believe me I'm not sure why they don't
believe me oper Torian people get
absolutely livid when I say this but I
don't know what to tell them you saw how
long that took me to change right so I
have no idea why anyone ever makes
getters and setters for everything up
front instead of just only doing it when
you actually need one it saves you so
much time in development it's crazy
that you would ever do it another way
the only time you ever make a getter and
setter is if you know that the thing
that's changing actually does something
or will do something right if you don't
think it ever will you should never make
a getter and setter or if you don't
think the probability is like ninety
percent right because it costs nothing
to fix you change the name of the
variable you replace all the places
where it gets called to set call and
that's it right I don't know they're
they're an interesting Bunch those
lobster native programmers they they've
got certainly have their way of doing
things so anyway I I just want to do
that because I don't know I I feel like
that hmm I want the latitude here to
know that when we call set depth I may
have to set a flag to say readjust what
you're doing right and I and I don't
really know exactly how that's going to
work like so in this case for example if
we were going to do a system where you
know not now I think about two if we did
a system where where we only actually
start when you call begin element I
wouldn't even have to make a set desk
all right because if I want to do this
yeah if I want to do that I think I
actually can because here's my thinking
what I could do is say ab32 new line or
something like this and it's basically
just a latch that says when you tell me
that I'm supposed to go to the next line
I'll latch that right and then when you
call begin element I'll know that you
know if that latch is set I need to do
my indentation computation and if it's
not set than I don't write and so that
actually seems like I wouldn't I won't
even need you know if you wanted cold
set the depth you just can I think that
probably just works so let me try it
first with that before I unnecessarily
make someone go through an interface
that doesn't actually do anything for no
reason hmm let that seems fine to me so
I'm going to go ahead and set lay out a
new line equal to true on startup and
that way or you know what I could even
do it I can do it with a thought I can
do a line initialized and that way Wow
initialized cannot type program type
program cannot all right so i initialize
and set that to true or rather i'm not
gonna said anything it'll say false and
that way I'll know when the line has not
been initialized so when it calls begin
element rectangle in this case you know
we'll start doing stuff will do are all
of what you know whatever we have to do
here where we do our interactions and
then what we'll do is when we say n
element and we're computing where this
thing should go at that point is when we
can initialize the indentation of the of
the system right so what I can do here
is say alright we've come in here I'm
going to say if the layout system has
the line initialized unset then I'm
going to initialize the line so it won't
happen again and I'm going to set the at
equal to the indentation level that
we're currently at which is this thing
right yeah
so that'll basically say like okay if
the line is initialized the line is
going to equal well it's going to equal
this right it's going to equal the base
corner plus the layout depth and a yeah
and and off we go although I guess I'm
saying in this case going to be X is
that way so that's what's going to
happen to line malicious lies similarly
what I might say here i guess the line y
stuff is okay as it is it's a little
janky i wonder if i should clean it up I
don't know if I don't need to and we're
almost out of time anyway i only got
about 12 minutes left so that's probably
fine anyway that that will do the line
initialize stuff so then what i need to
do is say well if we're doing no line
feed then we just advance the X if we
are doing line feed then we need to
advance the y but we can set our line
initialize to to false and clear it out
similarly we can say that the next y
delta since we don't know what it is we
can make that happen here and so the
thing that I don't know is why I decided
to do it as a delta I'm not one hundred
percent certain uh what the real point
of that actually is I guess it was
easier to do it that way maybe I'm not
sure anyway
so yeah so now we've fixed our
indentation bugs as well look all of
those are gone which is good and yeah
what you know what I might do because
our profile I might make our profile
default to not go behind my head since
that seems like a good thing where is
that code debug that's a QP so this
thing frame slider frame Slatter so I'm
gonna say like okay let's maybe make it
fourteen hundred because well you know
this is the debug system is supposed to
be quick and easy I don't really want to
have to keep fussing with it okay so off
we go of course that makes these pretty
tiny we could store less back frames
certainly if we wanted to but now at
least by default it's not behind my head
which is nice right alright so all of
that's good and this all feels much
better now and I don't really know that
I have anything else say about the
layout stuff other than we probably want
to make our buttons look a little bit
more like buttons that's probably it so
I could do that that's actually pretty
easy where is my button it's not here
here we go debug you lied SVP button sew
buttons are basically these basic text
elements basic text elements are drawing
stuff with debug text out and if I just
said why don't you return me the
dimension of the button I guess
that would make it pretty easy for me to
make the button that I need so let's say
we return the dimension does the element
have anything else in it it just as
pointers to the dimension yeah i'm just
going to go ahead and return just the
dimension itself for now so in here if I
say action button or boolean button I
think what I want to do here is make it
so that i can i'll try the action button
first we'll say that here is the
dimension of the action button i kind of
want there to be more of a border to it
so I want to do kind of a Minkowski
situation here I want to do something
like our to like a border I know
enlargement and so when I come through
here and I've got this dimension what I
would like to do is sort of increase it
by by twice that so I want to do like a
Minkowski diameter on that and say that
why don't you make that bigger I think
I've got one of those right
just called it's called ad radius 2
there we go so I want to add the radius
I want to enlarge that all around and
then when I do get max corner and you
know a justice thing what I want to do
here is just say well i'm going to
offset it by the radius because
obviously I want it to be centered
inside there when I print the actual
text so that seems good you know what I
could do to i could just make this even
more ridiculous why not I mean it seems
reasonable so action button here what's
the highlight what's going on here so
highlights yeah I could just say well
the action buttons get a highlight to
you know why wouldn't they to think
about that how I want to do that and
then there's a border option that gets
set here right and the border option is
going to be like I don't know whatever
the button border is let's say the
button borders like for pixel border and
the color of the back thing is I don't
I'm so totally making this up as I go
along here I'm just trying to give you
what the idea is you know there's a
border color so that I can have that
because everyone likes it when you have
colors and things and stuff and so
there's a border and then there's this
is the the backdrop color and by default
I'll just say the backdrop color is
invisible and so when we do all this
nonsense here and we come up with a
particular size for these things we do
plus radius you know I don't know why I
didn't do a plus radius here but I
should have so that's a mistake well is
it a mistake it's get max corner it
actually should be this it's get Matt
corner- radius minus that
I then want to do a push rekt right I
want to do a push back to fill that
rectangular dimension so the element
bounds I want to actually fill them with
something and so let me go ahead and and
grab the code for that as well so we
have the backing transform here so if I
say all right draw to the render group
with the backing transform draw the
element bounds please and draw them with
the backdrop color and oh by the way you
don't have to do that if the backdrop
color W is not at least you know if you
just don't want one and you pass zeros
for the Alpha it won't draw it won't
even bother recording it we probably
should make the render or do that to be
honest but anyway we'll do that for now
i guess i can still return the dimension
why not but that should do it so let's
see add radius to what are you
complaining about oh this is not
actually a rectangle it's just a dim so
what I actually want to do is I suppose
make the the I want to make the the dim
just add two times the radius
right I was thinking add a rectangle but
i don't i guess i could also just to
this radius is not radius i really want
to call that radius don't i only have
three minutes left highlight highlight
for the action button that's actually
not right so the highlight for this guy
this is this is not supposed to be this
way the highlight for this guy is
actually just supposed to be more like
this where we just have that's the color
that normally is and here's the color
that it I don't know so like that cannot
convert
from floats to that's true so this has
to also take a hot color so we'll make
that happen as well and there we go all
right so not much time left here but
there we go so now we actually have some
buttons which is nice
but since we have multiple buttons on
the same thing we're probably also need
to there's a little work going to have
to do for making sure these highlight
properly that's separate issue though
but soon we can do some more fancy stuff
here anyway alright so that's good and
that's fine place to leave it we're
almost done with all the layout things
we need here so that's fine and yeah
okay and I'll uh I'll leave it there we
don't really have much time for
questions but I'll take a couple real
quick ones if they're quick and then
we'll be cuz we'll go back and finish up
some of that stuff tomorrow and we can
take more at that point
prefer to include your new Casey custom
in the repo yeah I gotta go get it from
the other machine sent me an email just
send me an email
is in sohbat spoilery the witness right
now what is in so about doing that's in
crate that's amazing
long billion could you explain your poor
man's lambda how it works how it is like
a lambda and how it is not so basically
like one of the things that C and C++ do
very poorly even though C++ is kind of
started to try and go down this route
but just not very well is they don't
allow you to defer something you might
want to do to a later part of the
program something that lets say in
Erlang would be stupidly easy like I
want like a co routine or something
where you're just saying I want to like
do a little bit of this and wait or
something things that would be very easy
in languages that support full closures
and stuff like that are like incredibly
difficult in C++ because it just was
never thought through and they don't
give you the good the features you need
to actually SQ them properly so you can
either start using what C++ has four
lambdas now and what a lambda is in c++
if I remember correctly in terms of what
they actually implemented out of
closures was like if you have a function
and you would like to create a little
snippet of code that refers to some
things in that function and then pass it
to some piece of code that you're going
to call and allow it to execute so it's
basically a pointer back up into a
parent stack you can do that right and I
don't know if they can do the thing that
we're doing here I think maybe they
could because i think it well no so my
guess and i don't really know but my
guess is that c++ just doesn't have
enough stuff to make this work I don't
really know I couldn't tell you I have
no idea um I don't know what they didn't
didn't implement in a language with full
closure support what you can do is you
can just write any piece of code and no
matter what you happen to be referring
to it will simply know how to get back
to that stuff right and so you can write
a snippet of code and pass it to
somebody as a like a
bundle and say I need you to execute
this later so to what extent you can
actually do that with the new supa
sizers I don't know I know they don't
support foreclosures for obvious reasons
but I don't know how much they actually
do support so what I did and what the
reason that I say that it's kind of like
a poor man's closure is because what I
do is I say well alright in this case
I'm doing some stuff we're like we're
drawn this frame slider or whatever and
I have a thing where I want to sort of
say if this if I want to do an
interaction that takes place when you
click inside where I am right now I want
to remember the stuff i would have done
a moat the most straightforward kind of
a immediate mode user interface design
would be that I just do it in here so I
do something like you know if mousedown
do the actually a sign frame ordinal
like I do this
right that would be the fully the least
complex version of the immediate mode do
I for this so I'm in the rectangle I see
the mouse is down I just do the
operation this is a little bit tricky
because then you end up in situations
where it's hard to do certain more
complicated operations when that happens
right so I was just kind of showing you
how you could defer things to later in
case you're interested in being able to
do that kind of operation in your UI
coding what I do is I say well let's
make a structure that could remember
some information about what we wanted to
do so I can do it later when I actually
go to process the UI right so what I'm
doing is right here I'm bundling up the
fact that what I wanted to do was I
wanted to take this frame ordinal and
set it to this so it's a poor man's
closure in that sense that i'm taking a
snippet of code and i can't just use the
language to bundle it up because the
language is too dumb but i can make my
own struck that records what i wanted to
do and know how to play it back and so
for some limited set of things that'll
just work does that make sense
thus Isaac do you ever turn on unused
function variable warnings not normally
no woodman see I am currently working on
a 3d OpenGL project and implementing
collision detection I've been introduced
to the idea of changing my vector space
so my character is a perfect unit sphere
which should make detection easier do
you have any opinion on this approach
well my first suggestion would be I
don't think Spears are very good
colliders but I mean I mean maybe a
sphere is okay usually people use a
cylinder for the player which is harder
than a sphere to be sure but you have I
mean a sphere has a bunch of weird
problems like it means that your guy
things that are you know it leads to
some unusual things it means that you
know if I'm if here's the wow that's
really bad ground if here's the ground
right and here is something that I'm
going to bump into and i'm using a
player's sphere well if this thing is
this high off the ground it means i can
only go this far before i hit it but if
it's this high off the ground it means i
can go essentially all the way to like
you know i could go i guess to like
right there i can go like right here
before i hit it so it's really kind of
weird because usually it doesn't make
much sense to have it it doesn't make
sense the player that if this thing
moves up a little bit all of a sudden
they can walk much further in that
direction so my first thought is player
sphere are you sure have you thought
that through would be my first thing to
say I
and there is no warp that's going to
make there is no like a fine like
there's no vector transform your going
to do that that makes a sphere a
cylinder into a sphere so
all right I'm gonna close this up ah
let's see
there we go all right thank you everyone
for joining me for another episode of
handmade he wrote show where we code a
complete game live on stream i feel like
i should say that because i don't think
i said it at the opening i think i just
said that it was special which is true
if you want to follow along the source
code you can always do so at handmade
here org you can pre-order the game and
it comes to the source code so if you
want to do that you can do that it is
right there we also a forum site you can
go to where you can ask questions we
have a patreon page and go to sports
video series we have a tweet bot that
tweets to schedule at you when they
don't reboot my server and speaking in
the schedule i'll be back here 5 p.m.
pacific daylight time tomorrow until
then have fun programming and i will see
you guys on the internet take it easy
everyone