hello everyone and welcome to handmade
here offshore we code a complete game
live on stream we really are I mean this
is the classic case of we left ourselves
with a giant code bomb and now we just
have to defuse it basically last weekend
we made importing WAV files in we
integrated the code for importing and
segmenting WAV files we we took that
from our original asset packing task
code and we weld it into the game so
that now like the running game can just
live import sound we did all of that
work and it was a fair bit of stuff we
had to merge but again you know it was
code we'd already written so we didn't
really have to invent anything it was
just a porting issue really so we did
that work but we didn't have time to
actually do anything with it so we did
all the porting and literally I don't
think we've ever even run the code so
what we need to do today is get started
down the road towards actually finally
that code and making it so that it
imports WAV files properly and allows us
to actually you know use them in the
game so we got two steps to that step
one involves no really new code I don't
think it's just actually going through
and getting the code we wrote working
from last weekend that's just going
through and making sure the wav files
appear to import the actual sample data
correctly and store it into the HHA
files this involves reading one of those
tag files parsing the WAV file directive
looking at the tags applying those tags
to an asset structure and then having
that asset structure point to the to the
actual sample data right and in order to
do that so that there's a lot of things
that we we haven't really addressed in
there but in order to do that
I think the only thing we may not have
written yet is how the channel labeling
works at the moment
and so we kind of have to look at that I
think we have to expand the grid notion
to actually have those things labeled
properly we have to actually prepare a
grid that would have that in there and I
think we made room for that but we never
actually made the grid something along
these lines so we have to write a little
bit of new code to create that grid but
other than that we wrote all the code
and it probably just needs to be
debugged the second step which we
probably won't do today because that
probably what we'll do today is the
first part the second step which we'll
do next weekend is to streamline the
asset system and make it so that it
actually works with page sounds
correctly now because we sort of changed
up how we wanted to do that and so just
reimplemented that sound streaming code
into its final form would be the last
step of that process so that then we
have sounds in the game fairly solid we
can just move on from there we already
did that sort of with textures we took
kind of the old-school way that we were
doing it and we rewrote it to be sort of
a more efficient system there's a little
bit of objec in the system namely that
we don't really do any kind of runtime
packing of textures if there's tiny and
that's arguably something we probably
should have been doing but other than
that we did a pretty good job like we do
what we're supposed to do which is we
keep a bank of textures and we just swap
them in as necessary and that should
keep things running pretty smoothly but
for sound we did not do the new version
right and so what we want to do is make
a fixed block system exactly like the
textures base we'll just allocate a
bunch of bins of a certain size and then
every time we pay Janice and we just
page it into one of those bins or we can
use the kind of more avant-garde
ridiculous system it's probably one of
the weirdest ideas that have had I don't
really know what I think about it but I
just grabbed it on a previous stream and
it was essentially to treat sound it's a
giant streaming buffer and what you do
every time you play a sound is you move
it from the inactive region to the front
if it's not in the active region at the
time this is a really weird system I've
never heard of anything like it it's
probably dumb
but we could certainly try it because
you know sometimes trying dumb ideas
lead to good ideas it's pretty hard to
say entropy is the mother of all
inventions you might say so I guess it's
usually say necessity is the mother
invention I would say that entropy is
the mother of invention and necessity is
just the thing that filters those
inventions by which ones you want at a
particular time not oh there yeah
entropy is the mother of invention is is
almost certainly the correct statement
anyway so let's go ahead and get started
on that we have a pretty clear road to
go down here so there's no sense in
belaboring the situation let me try and
get this out of the way there we go I'm
having cable issues I always have cable
issues on handmade here oh there's way
too many machines and things here it's
not preferable anyway let's go ahead and
get started I'm gonna go ahead and and
open up excuse me the editor here and
I'm going to switch to handmade Hiro and
filled and then we're going to jump into
the debugger I think what I may do oh
right we're not using this to bugger any
more because it crapped out on us so
we're gonna be using remedy also you
know I think we're one behind so I may
want to update yeah we are so there's a
2.0 version of remedy that's available I
probably should switch to that it's got
some pretty important additions made to
it so yeah that's one of those things
that yeah well I didn't plan for that
and I don't have a thumb drive handy
which is an issue if I'm being honest
let me see if I can find one hold on a
second we'll take a look in the into the
magical backpack here in hope that I
have a thumb drive that I can use to
transfer the file because I don't I'm
not logged into to the itch I owe to my
itch I owe account which is where you
get remedy from so let's take a look
here if I've got one in here I hope I do
there's a lot of stuff in this
ridiculous in this ridiculous backpack
here and I never really know what's
still hanging around in there I've got
some business cards that's always good
we've got a pen like thing that has a
screwdriver in it for for accessing like
laptops I think we've got I don't even
know what that is
some kind of audio cable this is this is
like a this is like a treasure trove in
here we've got we've got okay there's a
there's a power bar in there I don't
want to know how long that's been in
there
that's probably not great if we're
honest about it okay so there's a
package of black forest gummy bears
that's that's always good yep not not
what I was expecting
it's fine there's a mouse and then we've
got what have we got in here let's take
a look I thought there was a thumb drive
in here but I'm having trouble
look there's there's a there's a USB hub
that's in there there's there's a ear
ear plugs got that in there so this is
there's you know there's some screen
cleaning wipes ok so there's an entire
keyboard in there so that's good got an
entire keyboard we have a huge set of
cabling we have a microphone
this backpack is a little bit ridiculous
at this point I don't even know why most
of the stuff is in her I think probably
because when I went to for coder Jam I
think I probably left I never it looks
to me like I never actually unpacked
this backpack and so everything that was
taken to allens for for a coder Jam is
still in the backpack is basically what
happened all right so last chance for us
to find okay we have replacement pen ink
so that's good we've got we've got a a
car stereo to head like a you know like
a cell phone to car stereo connector so
that's you know for road trips and stuff
we got two pens which actually would go
with those pen inks we've got a flat
folded Ethernet cable so that's pretty
good right you can just kind of like
keep that's that's in there that's
probably good to keep in there huh case
you need it for something we're trying
to plug stuff in and let's see what's
this here I feel something that feels
like it could be possibly USB I'm not
sure let me see okay oh that's in there
yeah man that was disappointing I don't
see an actual USB Drive in there
anywhere so I think I'm gonna have to go
get one from another room how
disappointing is that like I literally
don't see a single USB Drive in this
entire thing well folks you'll have to
excuse me for one moment because I just
don't see any USB Drive here it must be
in the other room probably because I
installed remedy version 2 on my other
machine on my dev machine and I needed
to get it over there so I probably
brought the thumb drive that's normally
here I'll be right back
[Music]
at least we got the backpack unpacked
that probably needed to happen if we're
being honest with ourselves I'm gonna go
ahead and switch over to this machine
and copy the remedy to or well actually
I guess I don't know what the latest one
is because maybe there's been there
might even be another one that that I
haven't downloaded yet but let's take a
look what we got here oh yeah there is
so there's a - I don't so remedy for
some reason has like the most version
numbers of everything anything since
Windows Windows was a four four digit
version identifier as well so this is
remedy 0.2 0.0 0.1 and I'm not sure what
that necessary like why there are that
many actual labels in there I'm not sure
what that could possibly be referring to
but but you know I guess we'll have to
ask George why there are so many and he
can tell us I don't know affect search
Oh X 13 pixels is on there there he is
so he can tell us why there are so many
I don't know but he must know because he
invented it so all right all I'm doing
here is I'm just updating to the new
remedy there were a lot of pretty
important changes in this version that
that like I'm was really happy about so
I really don't want to use it without
these so I thought it was worth going to
get it so I'm just going to copy the new
version into into our remedy directory
here place and if you yourself want to
get this debugger if you're sick of
Visual Studio or if you just stopped
working like minded you can actually go
to its IO and get it its remedy well
actually just completed for me it's
remedy BG HIO you can click on this
right here and you can buy it and it's
like I don't know 1/100 of the price of
visual studio something like that I
don't remember what the price is it's
like a thousand or two thousand dollars
for the full version I don't even want
to know what it is you could probably
get one for only 10 times that much
I'm guessing visual studio I don't
remember I bought a version of
professional for Maui and it was like
absurdly expensive for such a piece of
junk so this is a bargain price in my
opinion probably the best 20 bucks
you'll ever spend on piece of
development software that's basically
free in the realm of development
software and and yeah it's pretty close
to completely replacing Visual Studio
there's there's not a lot left that
doesn't doesn't work so anyway in here
we have now upgraded to 201 so that's
just I feel like that's probably
something we want to do before doing any
serious debugging because there were
some pretty big improvements to it that
were made including better expression
parsing in the watch window and handling
of there was some problems with
inspecting things that are passed to a
function by value that were compound so
I could be passive struct it was having
trouble with that and that got fixed
which is a pretty big button for me
because I will often pass or return
strux and so I being able to inspect
those is pretty important for me so that
was that was a big one as well okay so
if we start down this route now that
we've got our debugger updated if we go
into the import layer here and we just
look at what was supposed to be
happening we could get an idea of what
we want to start looking at what you can
see is that basically the codes gonna
actually exactly the same as it did for
bitmaps there's really not a lot of
difference there but then what's gonna
happen is we've sort of set a little
booby trap up so that if we saw a sound
instead of doing the normal PNG parsing
that you would do we're gonna do a wave
parse instead so we kept the code path
basically exactly the same we'd not
duplicate it at all
we run exactly the same code path and
then all we do is we have a few places
in it
where we sort of switch out what we're
doing if it turned out that we were
parsing a sound we either turn some
things off returns and things on that we
would normally need so in here we would
expect to go down the process audio
import path up here we would expect to
go in the parse wave path or parse wave
as I like to call it now that's really
most of it the rest of this stuff like
there's a few things like well hey if
you try to put an alignment point on a
wave directive we would tell you no but
most of the other things will execute as
before
the one thing that we didn't do if I
remember correctly is when we come
through here and you see us like find
something that is a sound or is music
what we would normally do in the case of
a piece of artwork is we call this parse
pieces function and what that was
designed to do is that was designed to
say what is the actual thing being
parsed here like ground cover or you
know a head our body image items a plate
figure out what we're actually parsing
and then what it would do is it would
build this grid worth of tags because we
import like different pieces of the PNG
as different assets with different tags
on them right
so the problem that we have here is we
need to do the same thing for sound but
we never actually did it right so when
we actually find a sound file that we
want to update this audio channel tags
grid needs to match up with how we're
actually splitting those channels out
now if you go and look at how we were
parsing those I guess it would probably
an import a process audio import I think
which is right here you can see us look
at what the Mac's channel count is and
it's the size of that grid and when we
go through and import these you can see
that for every channel that we were
going to import we assign that to a sub
sort of looking for we assign that to
a substitute subsequent entries in that
asset grid so if we want them to be
tagged properly on export what we need
to have is that you know we already sort
of set ourselves up for this we put it
right here but this to do is the part
I'm talking about what we need is that
audio channel tags grid at the start of
importing has to be created to contain
on each individual entry a single tag
which is just that says channel 0
channel 1 channel 2 channel 3 right that
is what we need to have happen and so in
some sense this ends up exactly
mirroring the grid import for art the
only difference is instead of us having
lots of different ways that the sound
can get tagged depending on what the
directive is in our case the sounds have
only one directive which is just the web
directive or sorry they only have one
way of importing regardless of the
directive because there's a sound
directive and a music director if we
don't really do anything differently
regardless of which one it is there's
only one thing that happens they end up
with a grid that just says for every
channel use a channel tag that says what
channel it was and that's all we do
right now you could imagine in the
future us doing something fancier I mean
we could do something fancier here right
so we could have a bunch of different
ways that we create sounds where the
different channels mean different things
and then you use a directive that says
which tag grid to apply when it comes in
we absolutely could do that we just
don't have a reason to do that right
there's there's no you know there's no
point we don't have to do that for any
particular reason so for our purposes we
are just gonna do the simple thing but
it's worth noting that if we wanted to
really mirror that process and we
actually had some argument for why we
would need to split sounds into
different channels that got tagged
completely differently rather than just
got tagged with there
channel index we absolutely have the
code path for it
so should we find that that needs to
happen in the future we can trivially do
it at the moment we really don't need to
so we just won't but that's where we're
at so in here with synchronized asset
file changes I'm gonna do it at the top
here but we could actually do this a
little bit more proactively we can see
that happen maybe a little bit later
this import grid tags here is right on
the context so right here what we could
do is initialize it what I'm gonna do is
something like create audio tag audio
channel tag array or something or tag
grid and not to be confused with a grid
which is from Harry Potter this is tag
grid which is slightly different
although no less large and imposing so
on the hht context we've got this audio
channel tags I'm just gonna say look we
need a function that's gonna initialize
those audio channel tags now one of the
things that I think we might also want
to look at just while we're doing this
because I mean we are sort of trying to
get this asset processing to be sort of
streamlined is it's worth noting now too
that one of the things that we don't
really need to do anymore but still do
if you take a look here at what's
happening inside this parse piece is
call so what we use to do and the reason
we used to do it is totally reasonable
the reason we use it this way what we're
doing inside parse pieces is we build a
tag array anew every time we go to parse
a particular thing like blocks or head
right we create these sort of tag arrays
what you'll notice is they're all the
same now now why do we do this if
they're all the same byte we just make a
grids ahead of time because we used to
do is we used to have welded into this
import process appending the tags from
the actual tag markup for that put that
particular file or that particular
import we're not doing that anymore
so if you look at what happens in this
process when we actually don't need to
build different tag arrays for each of
these
right none of these none of that has to
happen it's all totally rote and we just
know ahead of time what it actually is
so we can avoid going through and doing
this on every import of every asset by
just creating them ahead of time exactly
like we do with the audio channel tag
grid again tag grid not hagrid very
important programming concept they don't
often teach that in CS classes I wish
they would you know a lot of people are
currently graduating with a degree in CS
from even reputable institutions and
they still think that at a grid and
hagrid
are the same thing and it's you know it
really creates problems when you take
junior programmers and you try to throw
them into a production environment and
all of a sudden they're you know you
tell them that you need to make a tag
grid for something and you end up with
this like sort of burly groundskeeper or
you tell them that they need to get
Hagrid for something because you know
maybe it's magical or whatever and you
end up with this too you know this this
two-dimensional list of asset tags right
and in neither case are those things
miscible that they're not fungible you
can't use one instead of the other and
so I really want to just highlight how
important it is to to make sure you know
which one of those ones you're dealing
with and you know yet may not show up on
a job interview but it's going to cause
you a lot of problems when you actually
go to do production work at a real
company so in here with parse pieces I
what I'm advocating is I think we should
just go ahead and break this out so that
when we do these imports here what we
could do is just use the context
structure that we could easily pass you
know down to parse pieces we could just
have all of those tag grids just created
at the head end into the context
structure itself and then it would just
provide back a pointer it'd be like
here's the one to use as you go forward
and that would be that so if you take a
look at how the tag system is working
inside the actual call-out where we call
parse pieces to begin with and I can
actually jump up there
so here's parse pea
is inside parse top-level block here
when we go down through parse pieces you
can see the import grid tag structure
here if we look at how that's actually
getting used so if we come down through
there oops that's not what I want to do
let's look at it this way if you look at
how this is working you can kind of see
that in here we well my head's in the
way I'm trying to show you if there it
is you can see that all we do is just
treat it as a pass through right it's
all attack that's happening is it's
getting passed through here so I think
we can just call this something like
template tags or whatever and then what
we can do is just treat it as a pointer
so we can just say all right you know
we've got a set of templates here we
know that we're gonna pull out something
like it so when we come through this
template tags we're gonna say okay in
this case the template tags is always
this we don't have to really look at any
more information than that in the case
where we've got something where we're
not sure exactly what it's going to be
let's take a look at that parse pieces
and see to what extent we even really
need to do it it looks in here right I
mean just looking at it it looks like we
could just insert this particular sort
of token check serial token check it
looks like we could just do that rather
directly and so it you know in fact we
don't even really need it to be internal
here because it's only really setting
that template tags part I think what we
could probably do is change the way that
we're looking at this stuff here and
kind of put that in so you know we're
looking at is default right at the head
end here we could make this part just do
this checking right so this this part
where we actually do the check we don't
really need to call out to this function
anymore I don't think I think what we
can do is just do that right in line and
make that a lot clearer about what's
going on so when we come through here
you can see that the block
is the thing that we actually want check
and so when we come through here and we
see that this part right here would
normally be building out those tags
we're gonna let that happen again ahead
of time and so the import type that we
would normally be looking at there again
so that's this these two these are the
two things right here that we're really
filling out again they don't even depend
on anything else so it's it's a really
good indication that we don't need to
bundle those those productions together
either so if we get rid of this stuff we
can just say all right let's check the
block token we'll see what it is we
don't need to do any of this stuff so
instead what we're gonna do is pretend
that we already had this template built
and so the template tags are just going
to be something off of the context so if
we imagine this context just had all of
this stuff on it right so we have the
import grid tags audio channel tags
we've got the like block tags maybe
something like this I don't know
something like this so we just have a
ton of these you know different blocks
we can have so that'd be like head
that'd be body right you can look down
here character
we've got clever in hand and then we've
got item obstacles plate and you know I
don't know exactly where we want these
to come from or exactly how you know
maybe we want those to be pointers or
you know who knows what but essentially
regardless of how we you know choose to
do that we want something along the
lines of okay we've got art block tags
here are the tags that you're going to
apply in the case where you end up
seeing the head token again none of this
matters and so we just want to again get
the art head tags right and so all we're
doing is we're just keeping this this
result here actually needs to change to
import type right as well again you're
just calling it something else and so
all we need to do here is just
automatically replace these with an
assumption that we already built them
because since they don't actually depend
anymore on the individual thing we're
importing there's no reason not to so
I'm just deleting all these things
goodbye and we'll you know we'll keep
that parse pieces function we'll call it
something else but effectively we'll
keep it and we'll just call it once
startup and that'll be much more
efficient because then we're not
constantly creating these ridiculous tag
arrays all the time for no reason right
because before that's what we were doing
so in this case yeah in this case we
don't really know what this stuff is
yeah I don't know do we actually inside
the h h TS do we actually have those yet
I don't know if we do or not if we look
inside the base game h HT so so these
things are all commented out so I'm
gonna feel free to just go ahead and say
well it was a multi tile import we know
that that's what it will be even though
you know we we haven't actually done the
template tags for it yet that's what it
will be later so we can put the to do
down in the thing where we actually
create those and not up here so that'll
be fine
port type and so that's about it
although I do want to weld the other
oops
do that 10 tags come on art obstacles
and the last one plates
sooo this just lets us take a look at
what the top level block type actually
is and we can now go ahead and weld this
stuff right in there so again all of
these are are actually should be block
token as well so I should just go ahead
and replace those real quick and that
should get us most of the way there but
I would like again to just sort of weld
these in you can see the sub durst of
happening here and so one thing I could
do is say yeah the subject stuff could
also be part of this pipe I guess I
don't actually know if we want to do it
white this way but if you imagine
extending this out to sort of say look
let's put all the things in here so
we've got default music sound like so on
then what we could do is say well maybe
these things are actually nested maybe I
don't really know exactly how I want
that to work but let's suppose they were
so let's suppose these things were were
nested like this and we wanted to do
something where we said okay so all of
these all come from the same
subdirectory maybe that's a mistake
maybe we should have everything in its
own subdirectory I don't know we're
certainly free to do that we could
propagate that subtor switch down a
little bit but I guess what I'm
suggesting is this right so yeah is
default would be true here is music
would be true here and is sound would be
true here I don't know if I actually
want both of those I don't know that
that's actually necessary I might just
want one which is is audio because I
don't think there's any reason to
differentiate between those two but
we'll see in the meantime I do want is
the music to come from the
music Durr and the sound to come from
the sounder because those are actually
currently separated at least the way
that we decided newer assets for the
first part so we do want to look roughly
like that but again I'm not sure whether
we need is music or is sound I'm gonna
take a really brief stroll and see if we
actually care you know we never really
care so I think for now because I don't
have any reason not to I'm gonna have an
is art and is audio and that's it I'm
not gonna have the sound one so I'm
gonna do something like that where we
say look they go in different
directories but they're treated the same
for all intents and purposes here and so
then what I'm gonna do is pull this part
up because now this doesn't need to
happen anymore right that's that's not
part of it and what I'm gonna do is
inside here I'm gonna say this is what
we need to know for audio we don't care
about the parsed pieces aspect of things
because we're not calling that anymore
anyway and so we're gonna do something
like this right so the import type is
audio for both of these and the tags are
the same for both of these in the future
we may change the tags between music and
sound like maybe we'll tag them slightly
differently I'm not sure but for now we
are going to tag them the same because
we don't actually have anything we need
to do differently between them we're
then gonna keep this part here but we
want to have some way of making it clear
that we didn't understand what the block
type actually was so I think rather you
know this import none part here I don't
know that we actually want to error on
it there I think we were airing on it
there just just because right so I I
don't know we may want to do something
more like this
if import type none then we don't need
to do anything right in this case and
well I can still have the invalid
default case show up here but I think
that'd probably be fine and I think all
I really want to do there is when we are
looking at these tags
I want to go ahead and produce an error
that says I didn't recognize the block
right because that's what's really going
on here when we you know have these
different multi tile things whatever you
know that I think that's actually what
we want to have happen so when we come
through here do we get you know one of
these errors we can just say look and
not remember what our thing is it's just
the tokenizer in the block right yeah so
in here I don't actually know that this
matters at all I don't think it does so
I'm gonna get rid of it and I'm gonna
take this error and put it where it
actually probably you know arguably
belongs in the first place which is
right here which is to say if we can't
find you know among all of the different
types of directives that we expect to
see if we can't find anything that
matches what we saw on the file then
that's an error that the block token
that we saw we don't know what did it
you know you you put in some kind of an
art import directive we did we just
never seen have heard of right so I
think that makes just a much more
coherent import path and it unifies
everything together in a much cleaner
way it also makes us easier to read
because basically can see the steps and
I can even sort of you know narrate them
here in a sense I can say you know step
one here right is oops determine the
import type from the block
so that happens then what we do is we
parse the actual contents of this thing
so here actually this is we find the
matching asset file right and then here
we prepare the the grid for matching
which is I guess not that interesting
and then we do the parse so this is what
actually happens at the moment and then
we parse the contents so we parse the
contents of the block doing whatever we
need to do for that and then finally
here at the end that we actually rebuild
the asset contents right and so it's a
pretty involved process but it's
actually not you know that hard to
understand now that it's all laid out
and I think this makes it a lot clearer
how this is going because now it's
really obvious how these things are
getting tagged up and you can kind of
see now that these things are just
shorthand for applying a particular tag
array what that means is that in the
future what we could consider doing is
we could consider just defining these
and it file themselves so if in the
future we just want to get rid of the
concept that these things are hard-coded
we could instead just have you know a
way that we parse these and we create
those tag arrays out of the parsed
contents and then apply them so what
that leaves us now is all we need to do
is have an actual inside the parse hht
part where we actually well
I guess it's probably actually out here
when we do the create audio channel tag
grid again not a Hagrid but at a grid
what we need to do is initialize all of
these so for all of these we need to do
a create call so this is like create art
block tag grid right and we're gonna do
this for every single one so this is
create art head tag grid and we'll need
to pass a few other things to this
probably but we'll find out in a second
what those actually are so here's the
body tag grid and so on and so forth
right so these are all gonna be this way
that and they're all gonna be done like
this I think something like that and
again I don't really know what we're
gonna pass here but probably the canta
game assets
I'm guessing and what are these our
obstacle tag grid and our weight
so I think that's all of them and these
are each just going to create that array
of tags that we expected to see so it's
it's really just us taking this parse
pieces structure and breaking it up
right so what we want to do is
effectively call this and we just need
it to be yet we just need to make sure
that we do it kind of see the tokenizer
is never really used anymore in fact the
only reason we were using it is when we
ran out of tag space we were issuing an
error there so I think the way I would
rather do that is just have this now
raise some kind of an error when it when
it fails that we then just Iran because
now we know that there's no way of for
having a parsing error if that makes
sense
so we should be able to just make this
be something that checks the error at
the end and returns like two or false or
something like that right so it should
be pretty straightforward
to make this work without the tokenizer
so I think all we really needed to do at
that point is we just need to pass the
game a set structure because that's the
only thing that's actually going to be
used here and so these should all take
assets in addition and that's it at the
moment we actually don't really even
need to do that even but you know we
only really need to be so specific here
we don't need to go completely overboard
but anyway so getting rid of these we
don't need type token and we don't need
tokenizer all we need is a pointer to
the tags that we're actually filling out
and then the game assets part here which
is what we're using to like actually
allocate those tag arrays and what after
we do parse pieces again we're not
returning an import type because we're
not doing this determination anymore so
parse pieces as a template for these
things I think all we really want to do
is return of b32 that tells us did it
work right and that way we can also take
that one error that we actually do care
about if it happened and we can throw
that into the process here so you know
when we do all of this part of things we
can issue that error message pretty
directly right and and that should get
us out of the business of passing the
tokenizer around as well so if I just go
ahead and make this a thing where it
says look if if all of these don't
succeed then we're in trouble and we
don't want to really proceed right so in
here where we've got an out f2 that you
can see writing the Airstream
to start with there so what I'm going to
do is I'm going to create an if here
where like if all of these things
succeeded then we proceed with the
import as we would normally do and if we
don't then we we just abort like right
off the bat okay so that should be fine
and again this we don't have a tokenizer
at this point so we're not issuing an
error on that but we're actually gonna
issue an error on is you know the the
error stream directly and so this is
going to be in like error you know out
of tag space and I think we can even get
rid of this error eventually if we
wanted to by just creating these that
start up in the handmade and turtle
context and then we would just always
have them there just something we know
we allocated space for so again just
sort of slowly moving this to something
now that we've seen how it actually
works in practice we can migrate
everything out to things that are less
troublesome and less likely to fail
which is what you want so I think that
should be roughly all we need to do to
you know start things up and now we just
need to actually process this stuff if
you look at where the tokenizer was
happening here I'm gonna get rid of that
I'm also gonna get rid of it here the
tag builder what you can see is the tag
builder is generally speaking something
that's happening inside like one of
these kinds of calls or directly in here
I guess
yeah you can see like a begin tags here
and so those begin tags end tags thing I
guess all we really want to do is just
have it so that those builder errors
propagate outward right I think that's
all we really want seems fairly
straightforward the import body
returning a import grid tag uh to be
honest I don't really understand what
that's doing oh I see you I see what's
going on there so these import head and
import bodies you send them down like an
index for that set and that way you can
put multiple things in there I see that
makes sense so yeah the I guess the main
problem that we're gonna face here is we
would like to return an error message
out from inside of these things and we
don't really want to have to worry about
when it actually occurred so that part's
a little bit uglier and we're gonna have
to take a look at how we want to do that
we would just like to have that be
remember that's kind of we go as we go
up the stack but we'll see what we want
to do there so let's start by just
having it work and again this is the
part right here that we end up with you
know now that I think about it it seems
like we could just check to make sure we
didn't run out of headroom right that
actually seems like the easiest thing to
do so basically if we ever hit the yeah
I mean you know I think about it that's
all we really needed because we can't
proceed anyway if that was hit so we
don't really need to know we don't
really need to know that we hit that
with that kind of fidelity what we can
actually just do is this
right this is more than sufficient so we
just build all these things we don't
even have to look for errors when we get
to the end if we were up against the
limit we want to bail anyway because
either that meant that we hit the tag
limit already or we're about to when we
parse this thing and so that's
sufficient for tracking those errors and
like I said they don't really care that
much about it because this we could
really just do differently anyway having
these tags go through the asset system
in the first place is not really that
necessary because these are templates
they get copied from they could have
just been allocated separately so it's
kind of just a legacy of how we happen
to create these things in the first
place that they even bother to go
through the asset system so I think
that's fine um so I think what I'm gonna
do here is just get rid of that concept
altogether I mean I guess I can leave
the errors in there because why not but
we're not gonna actually look at them or
do anything with them if that makes
sense and so all of this stuff can just
happen exactly what it was happening the
only difference now is the tokenizer is
out of the mix so anybody who is
previously passing that around to do
stuff with it is no longer going to have
to and they can just continue about
their business so I'm going to remove
the tokenizer from these and then inside
parse pieces now all I really need to do
is just break this up instead of each of
these being sort of its own separate if
block inside a larger parse that gets
passed something to sort of switch on
the block the head the body instead each
of these is now just the function that
creates the tags for that specific thing
so for example create art blocked a grid
would be again Taggard not Hagrid I
can't stress that enough that's going to
be one of the calls again the templates
match correctly now it doesn't return
anything it just initializes what it is
you can see that we've got it to do in
here that says to do exactly the thing
that we're actually literally doing
right now that's great I like to knock
off what to do when I can and so all I'm
gonna do first is I'm just gonna you
know one by one split these off into
separate code paths for whichever one
I'm actually looking at so this is the
art head
Hagrid here I guess I can actually do
this a little bit more efficiently by
just doing that right this is the arts
body tag rid bring that up there this is
the art character tag red this is the
art cover tag grid at which we never did
we don't really know how this is going
to work on so there's the art cover tag
grid there's the R cam tag grid there is
the art item tag grid it's V are
obstacles tag grid and the art plate tag
grid so I think that's pretty much that
and all we need to do now is go through
these and actually make sure they work
correctly with you know how they've now
been pulled out so I think all we really
would have to do is remove the import
single tile right I think that's really
all that has to happen everything else
that's happening in here is pretty much
what it should be right it's just it's
just iterating over here that the grids
and setting those things so I think we
should be fine I got to remove the
tokenizer because again that's not
something that we're actually using
anymore so everywhere that that was
previous getting passed down it now just
goes away but other than that think
we're good
so these routines should be able to
operate identically to how they were
previously operating that's it and now
we can also we also have a clear shot at
exactly how we would
implement that the thing for our sounds
right you could rubes know but that just
did oh right because now we can see how
the sound should get laid in here we
want to essentially take you know one of
these where we're doing the you know
sort of the enumeration of the asset
import structure right so we're going
over the entire array we want to do this
same thing now we want to do for create
audio channel tag grid what we want to
do is say alright here's the tag grid
that I want you to fill out loop over
the whole thing and all we're doing is
we're adding you know we're effectively
doing this right we're saying okay why
index X index this is the tag that we're
going to import we'll do a build on that
well actually we don't even really need
to do that I don't know why I bothered
with that this will work just fine so
we're gonna do a builder on this we're
going to then do an end tags call into
here the asset type in this case the
basic asset type I'll be honest I do not
remember how we chose to align those
basic asset types so where are those
defined asset block so I guess it's
these right and so I think as far as
asset categories are concerned I don't
really know what we want here we can do
just asset audio and leave it at that I
don't think we really have to
differentiate so I'm probably just going
to go ahead and do this asset basic
category I don't know if you can get
that as a string you may not be able to
so type from ID v-0 that's not what that
is
yeah I don't I don't think we actually
made a name table for these so I don't
even think that matters so what we're
doing here is just gonna say look the
taggers and Ollie it's always in the
asset asset audio section the begin tags
end tags part here is going to properly
label as asset audio so the only thing
we need to do now is have an ad tag that
puts in which channel I thought it was
so in terms of the channel index we just
want to set that to the combination of
the X&amp;Y index obviously the X index
gives it sort of which channel it is
incrementally but the Y is gonna go by x
strides so we essentially have to do
something like this where we take the
asset that's the that's one entire row
is asset import grid max so we want to
take the Y Index multiply it by that and
that'll sort of give us our channel
index we can make that into a variable
here just so it's easier for us to see
what we're actually doing it's just a
little clearer if I say that right I can
do this
furthermore I can do that without doing
the f32 so we can be a little bit more
explicit like look this is an integer
we're just storing it as an f32 because
that's we do that uniformly for all our
tags you don't have to have like typed
tags so what you can see that's actually
getting created you know effectively as
a u-32 there because it's always gonna
be something linear like that with no
fractional component so in here we would
say alright we're gonna do an ad tag for
the Builder tag channel index with the
channel index in there that's exactly
what we need that will create the entire
audio tag grid which now gives us a
complete set of tag labels for every
import type that we had right so let's
take a look at where we screwed up in
terms of you know whatever is not
getting done here so yeah okay so for
here in end tags for this where we do
end tags this we do still want in this
particular case where we're adding the
tags in here we want to do a check for
the error so I'm glad I left it in there
so what we want to do here is say
look if builder error now we can say
error tokenizer token and i guess
whatever token we sort of ended on i
don't know which one would be the best
here i don't know if we can do a get
token it doesn't look like we can so I'm
think I'm just gonna do it on just error
tokenizer here and say out of tag space
right so we can still check for out of
tag space when the when the time comes
inside here we can also do it but again
like you know that it's kind of nasty
like I wish we weren't really doing it
quite this way it's a little bit
unfortunate that that still happening
right also in terms of passing the
tokenizer right this is still not what
we would want and so to a large extent
we weren't even using it right you can
see us doing an out f2 the errors here
so like we were already assuming we
weren't using that tokenizer but because
we had to call end tags we were feeding
it in there and that was literally just
to the error reporting so you can kind
of see that this was kind of maybe a
positive change to begin with because
we're just you know you're not
tokenizing anything at that point so
that was kind of a false past we really
shouldn't have been doing it and so what
I'd like to do yeah just to make sure
that that that end tags there is handled
a little bit differently right so here
we can just say look if builder error
then go ahead and an out if an error
there where we say out of tag space
and that should that should solve our
problem so now we've got like the
subdural I may have accidentally deleted
that or you know we didn't copy it up so
we do need to put the sub dirt in there
because we do use that later I think
that's all we needed
and then our is sound is music all of
these are just is audio now so
everywhere that that was happening I
think this is actually a plural and
there should be one more I guess I
didn't see it let's take a look didn't
we have one more is sound I thought we
had one more is sound I guess oh you
know what we got rid of it because we'd
already handled that case
alright so never mind so let's take a
look the other eras first so update
asset metadata doesn't take the
tokenizer anymore so that's fine and
then in here we're looking at this
builder asses tag count that's just cut
and paste there we don't have a builder
here we do have the assets which is all
we needed to check and so that should be
the end of that all right so this is
still a to-do in my mind to do kc these
actually can be created once per run
they don't need to be recreated every
import so it's still a little
inefficient we could just call those at
the outset and just use those directly
you could argue we should just do that
right now
I really can't think of not a reason not
to so maybe that would be smarter let's
take a quick look at something so inside
handmade asset in here you know what I'm
effectively talking about is look if we
just want these things to be you know
created that startup could we just do
this right and put the tag arrays in
here that's that's really all I'm
talking about so in other words if we
wanted to
we have done this instead since they are
constant across the run and the only
question is you know this has to kind of
this import grid tags has to be created
has to be defined earlier in the process
if we want to do that meaning it would
have to be in here so I don't know
looking at this to be honest this
actually looks like for the most part
this could actually proceed the game
assets so you know I'll be honest with
you I think if we want to in the
definitions we could actually just swap
these and then be done so we could do
this this and I think that would just
work yeah this piece of information
asset import grid max I don't know where
that's at but we can just put it here
okay so I think that completely solves
that problem for us so if we want to we
can actually just do the right thing
right off the bat
inside handmade asset if we just let
these be defined here on the internal
run of the game then what I can do is
delete them from here entirely when we
actually start up so if I go into the
import code here we can just get rid of
this and put that into asset cpp and so
we already kind of have I believe this
this already kind of switches on this
when we do our in it because it's going
to do some well you can see it right
here it adds like import head room to a
bunch of stuff that would not normally
be there we can see that happening and
so at the end if we want to we can just
go ahead and do this right so that would
get us out of that business entirely and
I think that's probably what we want and
so now we just need to go ahead and make
that be the case so if I now said
okay all of these things are off of the
assets instead like so instead of the
context then we can just get them there
from now on
and they are only created one time so I
think that's all we really need to do we
don't need this call anymore either that
check is now redundant with checks that
are happening on the inside and I think
that pretty much takes care of it so if
we then go up into the part where we
were actually cracking out which type of
block we were looking at and you're
looking here and see where we're getting
these template tags all that we're gonna
change here is when we get those assets
out there in the context we were
previously looking directly in the
context we would now just be looking at
the assets structure itself right so
each time through here we're just you
know we're just doing that but otherwise
it's exactly the same so we're just
pulling them out of a permanent place
that they live for the entire run of the
game and we're not creating them every
time like we were before now I I'm
assuming and there's a couple different
ways we could solve this the problem
we're gonna run into here is that all of
these are defined in a file that hasn't
been included yet what's this is so if
we look at what we're getting here these
are you know because of the way that
handmade dot CBP includes these in order
and just because see is you know and C++
are kind of garbage I you have this
order dependence so the fact that import
comes after asset is a problem if we
either when we do I suspect we'll end up
with some yeah you can see like unload
and get file right thanks that go in
here so I'm not sure how I'd rather do
the pre defines for these but I think
since the asset system is the more
general system what I'm gonna do is I'm
gonna loft the pre defines
I'm gonna loft the four declarations up
from asset not from import there's
really no difference between what I'm
this is again just working around C and
C++ being lousy you know C has an excuse
it's it's from the 70s C++ has no excuse
just incompetence but either way you end
up with the language it doesn't work and
this is part of the cost you pay so
getting these two predefined is one
thing we'll need we need a couple other
things from there you can see them
listed here in its source HHA get file
and so on so let's just look at those
oops in its source
HHA will grab that out here get file
that's this and so again these are you
know all that we're doing there just
saying look these are the things that
you need to do inside the import layer
so get asset type wait is it set asset
types are set asset type there we go I
don't know why this is still an inline
that should not be the case in lines
really just shouldn't exist we should
just get rid of them
internal is sufficient the compiler will
automatically do that for us in pretty
much all cases that we actually care the
inline keyword is not really doing
anything for us so it's just kind of
annoying get a create asset source file
I don't know what it looks like we've
got two of these not sure which one
we're calling I would assume it's
probably this one but I don't know so
let's take a look yeah
and then that get asset call should also
be and I think that's it everything else
should be fine looks good and so now I
think we've got everything in place and
we also cleaned up how we were doing it
previously in terms of creating those
tag sets so that's a good thing too
now I want to go back and actually make
sure that we any of this stuff actually
works at all so now we're gonna start
the debugging runs obviously this
is something we could step through at
the outset just to make sure that we're
creating those the way that we think
allocate game assets is the function
it's called at startup if I set a
breakpoint there and jump into that I
can just you know I don't want to walk
through all of this again and we don't
really have any need to inspect that at
the moment so if I jump down here and we
step to it then we can take a look and
make sure that these are getting created
in some reasonable way so create audio
channel tag grid as we're looping
through those oh it looks like I'm in
release mode too which is not really
what I want so I might just back off for
a second there and compound debug mode
make it a little bit easier to walk
through it because this is you know I'm
trying to do like a clean inspection of
this code to make sure that I don't see
anything out of place and that gets a
little harder to do if the you know IP
is jumping all over the place and I
can't read the source code cleanly which
is what would happen if it was in
release mode so I'm gonna go ahead and
step in to this stuff I want to make
sure that these are cleared to begin
with so as I step in here I want to be
able to look at tags and make sure that
all of these are set to like nothing
right I want to see that there's nothing
in them that they're all set to zero in
in all cases right like everything's an
asset none and it you know it looks like
that's what I'm getting and so that's
good that's pretty interesting so so
George there is a bug here it looks like
the way that traces are stored in terms
of what is expanded is a little buggy so
the IDS that are generated for these
like I don't know if you watch that but
if zero is expanded it goes like that if
one is then expanded it inherits that
pass through it that expansion but then
if you unpack this one the expansion
goes away right because it's using it
looks like it's using only the first it
looks like it's using like the iteration
order or something as opposed to some
kind of stable addressing for which one
these are it's kind of a hard problem in
in a basic I am GUI it may be that they
just don't have a good version of that
inside dear I am going
not sure but in terms of the way need to
build IDs for things like that it does
get a little bit harder and so that's
one thing you might want to look at not
particularly essential but it's an
interesting thing to note so if we go
ahead and look at this what I would
expect to see now is every time we loop
through one of these parts of the grid I
want to add one thing to it so the first
thing I would expect this I would change
this to an asset audio by the way George
nice work on the giving the enum names
here that's really handy kind of an
advanced a bugger feature when you think
about it it's just like helpfully
providing information for you that's
actually not part of the raw display
right it has to go like oh this is one
of these enums let me go look up what
the name of that enum would have been in
the PDB or whatever right so anyway you
can see this getting set up here and
that's exactly what I wanted to see
happen it's creating two tags one that
says it's an asset audio and one that
says there's a channel in there the
channel index in this case should be
actually zero and that channel index
should go up with each time so as we go
through here you can see channel index
one Channel next two three four blah
blah blah right
I wonder that's nice I really like that
you can lock that down so you can see it
like this is one of my big pet peeves
like in visual studio you can't once you
get to here you can't inspect a variable
that's in the loop you used to be able
to and then they broke it and it looks
like normally oh and you can hear - that
wasn't showing up before it just said
not oh because I entered it there I
guess so that's pretty cool like this is
just way better than visual studio like
that disappears immediately right and
it's really annoying so it's pretty cool
that that still shows up like base so
yeah I mean I don't know how long it's
going to take George to get to the point
where all this because there's a couple
things that remedy doesn't have
obviously you need like data break
points I don't think are in there so
there's there's some basic debugging
features that haven't gotten implemented
yet but just based on where it's at
right now and how stable it seems to be
in daily use this is just clearly gonna
be better than Visual Studio like I mean
not to mention the fact that it updates
in real time right like Visual Studio
this value would be sitting there for
like a second and you just wonder what
it was and then it pops in you know so
yeah I would highly recommend ditching
Visual Studio it's a piece of garbage
and we've been stuck with it for too
long
buy a copy of remedy for 20 bucks and
start sending bug reports on the forums
or something let's go ahead and get this
tool to where it needs to be so we just
don't have to ever think about Visual
Studio again I mean it's obviously close
enough it's obviously useful for
day-to-day work it's way better than
windbag now in terms of usability you
know doesn't have all the features that
windbag has but it's like way more
useable and it's really it's been
smoothed out over the past two or three
months to the point where like really
it's just a few features that I feel
like I missed sometimes but I'm no
longer at the part where I'm like
kidding oh there's this bug or that bug
like it's it's really kind of feeling
pretty solid in terms of getting the
work done it's great work really really
really well done so anyway I feel like
this stuff is pretty well taken care of
now and here let's just take a look at
one of the art ones because that was the
one that we wrote anew the audio channel
one let's just make sure that the art
ones are working as well so you know
this just tags this thing as a block
with no tags that seems fine this goes
through and does the import body tags
let's make sure those are reasonable it
does look like they are yeah so I'm
pretty happy with with that that all
seems fine
so I'll just I'll just skip right down
to the the actual important part of
things if we go through synchronized
asset file changes now we're I don't
know if we'll hit any
asset changes on our art you know we
changed a little bit with how the tags
were working but they should still
basically be creating fundamentally the
same tags in the same order I think so
it probably won't I hope actually change
any of our art so I don't think we
should see any art import re triggers
but I could be wrong what we will see is
audio import reet riggers because those
are completely new and we've never seen
them before so let's go ahead and see
how that works we are going through the
top of a block person here we should be
parsing the default block and we are
what oh okay I see a bug right away
those ifs were supposed to have else's
and they don't so that would have been a
bug right off the bat I'm glad we
stepped through that because that would
have been annoying right these are
supposed to we we aren't ever supposed
to get to this case if any of these hit
and so that was just a that's of
straight-up bug right there nothing good
about that so let's try that again I'm
gonna receptor just this point since we
know that was the first time we were
coming through here I should be able to
step right to it let's go ahead and step
through that now we see it's the you
know we skip the rest of this what we
want we can go through here where's my
disassembly window where did it go I
feel like it I feel like it went away I
don't know why it went away but it did
so I want to get that back up there I
just like having that available in case
I need to quickly look at what's going
on it just helps to kind of get get in
there right um can I step through with
f10 oh that's nice
can i oh no I can't
okay so here's another thing to note
since I love the fact that the texturing
to the X 16 pixels watches the stream I
can kind of do live bug reports save me
some time so it looks like when you hit
f10 if you're in the disassembly window
it properly knows to do a single
assembly step but then it switches your
window to the source view which means
your next time you hit f10 won't be a
disassembly step so it'll be nice if if
you're in the disassembly window if it
didn't grab the focus back out I know
it's a minor thing but I'd like to be
able to click in here and just step
through the assembly you now I know I
can do that
using this which is the control shift
f10 but control shift f10 is kind of
hard to hold your finger on so it's kind
of just a lot easier to like click in
here and then go you know for what it's
worth anyway so going through here that
that doesn't matter for us at all we're
not trying to step through the assembly
today so we don't care we could care
less about that
so coming through here into the parser
here we're just looking to see what's in
that default field we got we got that
stuff there's really not much more you
do here it all seems fine get those
descriptions loaded and now we should
just go ahead and skip the the default
case which is what we did right so we
come in here and we get those default
fields and we load this up so that's
exactly what we would expect nothing
weird going on there and then when we
come through here for the next block
what we should do I think is actually
parse apart that work I think at the
moment we're in the intro scene so I
expect to see like a plate or something
probably so we come through here let's
see what we get I'm not sure about that
I'd have to go look at the H at XI to
see what the next thing is yeah there's
a plate right there so we loft up the
art plate tags is the thing that we're
gonna look at that should basically be
like a single tag in the first slot and
nothing else
I believe but don't quote me on that
let's take a look what it shows Asset
plates yep and nothing else right yeah
so great seems to be working perfectly
so far
off we go needs full rebuild is false
because well we probably don't need to
perfect we saw that the file is the same
so we don't need to change it with the
full rebuilds we could come through here
we're looking for tags we're getting
those tags hopefully I mean I don't know
maybe we are hope we are let's see what
we've got here we go Asset index there's
a line points in that's irrelevant I
don't really care about all that stuff
so that looks like that worked fine this
is just copying so I'll be honest with
you I have no idea what this is doing
I mean that that's a harsh statement I
know exactly what it's doing I don't
know why so if you look at what this
loop is doing it's taking the asset
alignment points well it's taking the
alignment points from the that we parsed
and it's assigning them back to the
bitmap but doesn't it need to do that
before it writes the thing out like why
isn't it doing it well I guess now I
think about it update asset metadata
doesn't write the thing out so I guess
it's fine because we actually write it
out back in the we write it out back
here so I guess that's actually fine
surprisingly enough all right I'm okay
with that
so it looks like the art is still
loading properly for what it's worth I
guess again I think we you know at some
point it would be nice to clean this up
if this weren't a thing where I had to
do just two hours a show I would
probably spend a good eight hours or two
two or three days just going through it
and cleaning everything really carefully
and sort of pulling things out into more
verifiable chunks but you know we can
only do so much with with the limited
time of the show so that's kind of where
we're at but we'll call that good enough
for now and we'll wait for bugs to rear
their ugly head to be long further what
I'd like to do now is jump right to the
new blocks and see how they work so here
we are in I think still in the intro
cutscene now this is probably I'm just
guessing if I were to look at this it's
probably this yeah so this is in the
intro cutscene this first when we hit is
this music test that laughs I am
narcissistically tagging myself as the
author which of course is
screw but probably not super necessary
since this isn't even official music for
the game what we want to do is verify
that this gets loaded properly we are in
the right tag block and we are loading
those audio channel tags we're looking
at music subtor so that's good now let's
see what actually happens when we build
the source path I'd like to see if it
actually looks reasonable and it does
one thing while we're on the remedy list
of requested features it would be
awesome if there was some way to get
this whole string
I know Visual Studio does this weird
crappy thing where they put like a
little magnifying glass on it that kind
of sucks so I wouldn't recommend it but
what I would say is like let's say best
of all possible worlds one thing you
could do there is have the watch window
have an option so you know if I
right-click on this or something or I
don't know where options would go
normally but you know let's say there's
a right-click menu or something that has
settings like where is that for like the
call stack for example okay so you know
I'm right-clicking in here and I'm
getting these settings right if there
was the same thing for the watch window
just have a string window and then when
you highlight something like you know or
whatever it shows the whole string
another way you could do it is if you
Pat if you did like I don't know I'm
making this up but something like that
and then it would just make this part
bigger right so so it could fit you know
several line you know it could wrap this
so I can see the whole thing I don't
know the exact right way I've thought
about it a long time but like the visual
studio one sucks because you click it
open and it opens a separate window
which I don't want right I want to see
things in the watch window its modal so
I can't step right which is also
terrible but it is something you want
which is the ability to see a longer
block of text and so I don't know I
would say
when you get a chance I know this is a
lot of work to handle all this stuff in
the de bugger but when you get a chance
think about something like that you can
think of it sort of in the same concept
the same domain it's like eventually you
want to be able to see like images and
stuff right and so it'd be great if you
could have like an image show up in here
if you you know could set the format
like oh it's rgba or something and you
know here's how big it is this with this
height I don't know right it would ship
you know take some space to show that
thing the same would be true for Strings
like how do you make it how do you make
a clean interface for always showing you
know the contents of the thing for when
I've got a few things I want to watch
you know again I don't have a strong
opinion I haven't thought it through
particularly carefully but I do think
there's something there the like here's
stuff I need to view that's more
complicated than just a simple value how
do I get that into a coherent easy to
understand way that lots of different
data types could eventually take
advantage of you know I want to view
sound waves same thing right like
basically providing little widgets here
that you can interact with that more
in-depth view something you typically
want them to still sort of work with the
watch window in some way so they can
constantly be updated as necessary and
so it's not this huge pain in the butt
I've often thought the same thing about
the memory window like I don't really
want a memory window what I want is the
ability to have some memory ranges shown
in here so I can have more than one of
them and have them update as I go right
and so I feel like you know thinking
about how to extend the watch window
into something that has the widgets
built into it is kind of an interesting
concept going forward you know what I
mean and you can even think of that as a
way you know as unifying some of these
things like oh you know I can just do
like that and this shows up in here
makes they're not really be a need for a
lot of this other stuff sometimes right
so you know one of the things that sort
of stuff in Visual Studio forget it
because it's this weird like giant
c-sharp framework that's just a you know
garbage pail when you're with when
you're in an IM GUI setting it actually
becomes not that prohibitively expensive
to just rigidify some block as necessary
you know what when it's visual and then
these sorts of things can just unify in
there it's just something to think about
again it's half-baked I realize that
it's just it's something to think about
that maybe would save you actually save
you time in the long run because instead
of having to constantly think about
things with all these separate windows
and I got a re-implemented this stuff
it's like everything can just go one
through one thing and then that's it
right I don't know just not here no
they're moving away from pine sky
nonsense debugger nonsense going through
here I looks like this is the right
thing I should probably verify that that
actually does exist
oh it says file not found oh you know
what that that might be true we may have
put that in the wrong directory did we
so here's our hand made sources in intro
cutscene that's not where we put the
music and that is that is where that
should have gone so I think actually our
code is smarter than we are
this is not in the right place and it
should be placed here so actually good
work code you caught us let's go ahead
and rerun I think I still got the
breakpoint set there so here we go let's
see if it can find it now that I
actually put it in the right place there
it is okay so that time it worked
we need a full rebuild because it's
never seen this file before so let's go
ahead and go through here here's our
tokenizer parsing stuff we've got
everything that we need I think I hope
let's parse those tags we should get
tagged here there it is title screen
that is the tag that we expected and we
should also by the way this kind of does
it so it it looks sort of like remedy
almost already does the thing I want it
just doesn't wrap right because you can
see when there's actually new lines in
the string it actually displayed the
whole thing right
it just doesn't wrap so that's actually
pretty cool that it already does
it already does take more room you can
see it it just doesn't actually wrap the
text so it's really just a wrap like
right click and hit wrap long lines or
something
what's all that that really needed here
it looks like sort of although if this
thing we're really like this string
keeps going you still kind of want the
text inspection widget so you can scroll
down and like see more of it or
something I don't know again neither
here nor there these are all just like
hey now that the bugger is you know
replacing visual studio what if we
actually started adding features that
visual studio never had and should have
anyway so that all looks fine and the
tag ID is presumably the right tag ID I
don't actually know it looks like it is
title screen there it is
so if we go ahead and assume that the
tags are now correct on this thing the
question is can we actually load the wav
file which is you know the the lion's
share of the work let's take a look so
we go through we find the match we know
that we don't actually have this
assigned to anything yet so we're gonna
have to we come through the full rebuild
path we try to load the file we do it
looks like we successfully got it in
here we now need to do the the checksum
of the file to set it up properly and
then we need to read this into the wav
file this read stream this contest
stream nonsense should really go in here
we don't need this for anything
looks like that's wrong by the way I
don't know if you care about that
like the cursor position is wrong I'm
not sure I certainly don't care but it's
worth noting uh so the make read stream
there when I get that constant that
contents stream back we don't actually
care about it unless it's art such as
probably being here
but either way here's our sound loading
code we get to is audio we need to start
parsing this wav file we come into the
parse wife call and we're gonna try to
iterate the riff section of things
it looks like the header was correct
because we passed the if statement so
you know hopefully this is correct I
don't know how to inspect this in a
different way I don't even know how to
change to hex inspection or if there
even is such a thing because one of the
things that's true about remedy is I
only just started using it so I really
don't know much about how I would do
that so I couldn't tell you maybe it
can't do that but maybe it can and I
just don't know how so I can't really
look to see whether the riff ID is
correct I don't know if it supports this
kind of thing yet no so it looks like it
oh well well
although yeah there we go so it does
actually support that so the riff ID
does look like it says riff so it looks
like we are looking at that correctly
and similarly here is the file type ID
wave so that's pretty cool actually this
didn't used to work in remedy so I think
the latest version I know that George
said he put in a real expression parser
it looks like it's working great because
I don't I don't remember being able to
do that last week so like this is pretty
awesome because that's really handy for
obvious reasons you can see me why I
wanted right there and that's great so
that's that's a pretty big improvement
that and a really really useful one like
that's one that really adds a lot of
value having good expression parsing is
pretty great
all right so at some point I got to
learn I don't know it might actually
have this in the readme I should
probably look I don't actually know the
expression parser works though like I
don't know what else it can do
let's see here oh wow
I get greets awesome thanks for the
greets makes the greets man Visual
Studio absolutely deserves these greets
right here so yeah okay so you see all
this stuff like this is important stuff
right that I don't know and I need to
learn so there's a relative scoping so
like the previous scope or the first
ancestor scope this is awesome by the
way like this is so just to show you
what this is this is really pretty cool
so let's say I'm up here right you can
see that there's this sound struct or
this is audio right and so if I was here
you can see that I can I can get that is
audio when I drop down here I can't and
the reason for that is because remedy
correctly is showing me things that
resolve in my current scope but if for
some reason I wanted to see that it's
suggesting I can just do sorry I need to
look it up again it's suggesting I could
just do hey look up scope just keep
going up so you find it I mean look at
that how awesome is that
so now I can just look up stuff that's
like out here and it will find it even
when I'm in here that's just super
awesome like that's that's just great
right again there's so many great
features you could add to a debugger if
you just aren't Visual Studio and you
actually care about debugging and so
it's so cool to see that stuff coming
coming together because that's just
awesome I mean that's really gonna be
the point where it's obvious you have to
switch where it's not just a case of
Visual Studio is annoying but it'll
actually be a case if you know so you
just doesn't have the features that are
actually good so I don't know like I
should learn that so so probably that
the most important one is carat star
because that says like go up lock
expression will lock it into its scope
so that's like if I go up here and I do
is audio I guess I can lock that in at
its current scope and then go down and
now it'll remain again really awesome
I love it format specifier going off to
the formatting or display currently only
a single for I suppose for this is for
specifying the number of elements
displaying in a rare pointer the syntax
of the for instance where is calm at the
end so that's the same as visual studio
so I don't really need to learn anything
for that that's that's how that worked
before so for example if I wanted to
look at path know if there is a path up
above what is up above something back
here right no there really isn't well
file buffer file buffer is a thing it's
not a string but it does exist up there
so if I do file buffer there it is if I
do this the data array kind of stressing
things out now but let's try it so if I
did that star I don't know I'm really
pushing things here but if I were to do
that can I do I don't know how I would
do this is it that it is that's really
awesome so if I wanted to see more of
this thing I do that awesome
yeah this thing is super cool all right
cool so you can basically say like look
up in the prior scopes find this thing
show me 16 elements of it and that all
just worked flawlessly that's pretty
great yeah
looking great looking really really good
alright so moving along here enough with
us saying how good remedy is we should
probably
in our own code working as opposed to
looking at someone else's code who got
their code working let's go through and
see what we've got here
I guess this properly starts at the
first chunk so we're skipping the first
chunk I don't know if that's correct I
[Music]
kind of don't think it is like I feel
like the first chunk so I want to look
at that that looks like maybe a bit of
copypastas sort of potentially so I just
want to look at the riff iterator code
here and and just see so so you can see
that the header is not the thing that
it's pointing to initially right it
parts of the first one so I don't I
don't think this is correct I'm gonna
say that that's wrong
you don't skip the first one the header
is peeled off as as a separate thing so
I think that's not what we want so I'm
gonna say that that's bad and we're
gonna skip that run through and we're
gonna jump into a new run through that
doesn't do that because maybe it may
have worked but it would still be
incorrect because it would have been
skipping some chunk and maybe that chunk
is not one of the two chunks we actually
care about fmt and da ta but just
because it would work with that wav file
it could easily have not worked with
another where one of those two chunks
was the first chunk and so I'm pretty
sure we didn't want that so off we go
and it looks like it actually would have
failed because it looks like the first
chunk actually is the FMT chunk which is
a format chunk which is the one we need
so I think that's probably important
that we that we fix that all right so we
get the data out and get the format out
it looks like there's some other chunks
probably like an info chunk or something
and we ignore it we come down here and
we've got the channel and sample count
and what we're doing here we're gonna
push
sound on that's the essentially the the
you know D interleaved version of this
thing and we're just going through D
interleaving it right like this is just
a B interleave and so if just a
visualize is actually going on there if
we take a look at what the channel can
actually is you can see that this is
actually a dual channel sound it's
stereo because it's music right it's not
a sound effect so it kind of has
spatialization already built into it and
so that channel count of two means that
we're doing in the interleaved by two we
should be able to watch that to
interleave happen if i look at source
samples using the stuff that we just
looked at sources sorry sample data if
we look at those samples well
unfortunately it starts with it looks
like it starts with silence which is
kind of what you would expect i don't
know where it actually starts being not
silent i'm sorry for pushing 500 things
on to the immediate mode stack here but
let's see so so really there's like just
a ton of silence at the beginning of
this file so d interleaving I would
rather we had some structure art there
I'm just going to assume that it works
for now we really should go through and
try to visualize that if there was some
actual data in there but all we would
would see right now is just writing
zeros everywhere so be impossible to
tell if it was actually didn't relieving
anything or not so if we get through
here and go to the actual return after
these two things have been to interleave
now we'd expect the sound to contain
those d interleaves so it should have
two sort of channels each one is about
7.5 million samples long and there'd be
two blocks inside here when we come to
process audio that's gonna actually
trigger I think the long sound case this
part it doesn't have to worry about
because obviously there's only two
channels not 64 channels which is more
than any
sound should ever have but when we come
through here the max sample count should
absolutely get triggered it looks like
here that's gonna be a pretty low number
compared to the number of samples in
this particular sound so that's the you
know the number of samples that we're
talking about here and if we look at how
many samples
how many chunks we have to break it into
it should actually be substantial so if
I look at total chunk count let's see 57
right so this is a pretty long stringing
piece of music and it's just gonna chop
it up into little pieces and so when it
actually does this it's gonna look and
see what the asset index is there isn't
one currently so it knows it has to
reserve a set of 57 of those when we
come through here we just check to see
if we have enough and it looks like we
do so we're gonna look and see here 470
the asset count then should increase by
that reserve amount that we want there
oops there we go
so as we step over this we're in good
shape we come out here we've got
everything that we want inside the asset
index case because we know we actually
reserved one we should now be able to
split it into blocks the sample count
remaining should now go down over time
as we write out the blocks here's the
total amount we have as we go through
here we write out each individual one of
these
we're not reusing the assets so we
create a new one every time we ask to
unload this audio but there actually
isn't any audio loaded so that's a no op
time so that's only if you're updating a
thing that was already sort of in the
set of known data we're gonna reserve
the asset data size here let's make sure
that asset data size looks about right
that should be double the max sample
count because each one 16 bits it is so
that's a nice that lines up with what we
expect in fact and it lines up I don't
know can you do this no you can't
so I don't think it shows you results of
the numbers but I can do that in calc so
if I just say look I want to know how
big 256 K is which is what I kind of
wanted these blocks to be you can see
that's exactly what it is and so that
works out nicely
we set the Dean of science we pull
everything in and yeah everything looks
fine there we're gonna write that asset
data out so I see a bug now so this is
wrong
this right here is incorrect so what you
can see is what we want is we want the
first asset the first asset index wants
to go in here right but we're iterating
over these asset index C's as we go and
so really what we need to do is outside
the while loop we assigned this and then
we write as we go but you know writing
this every time we'll set the asset
index to the wrong one so that is a bug
that needs fixing
so almost made it not quite so process
audio import had a bug in if the bug is
that we're trying to remember the first
asset index in our chain instead we're
remembering the last asset index in our
chain that's a definite bug so what we
want to do is right before we actually
kick in here when we have the asset
index that we've allocated we set it now
that way as we come through here and we
Inc the asset index each time we're
never going to rewrite that asset index
back out to the storage the file
remembrance so that it won't you know
look it in the future again think about
that now I think if I'm not mistaken
there's a further bug here which is that
this really should be written per
channel because each channel gets a
different asset index out of it
looking at how this goes and and does it
here you can see yeah and this is just
garbage this this stuff is just garbage
this is supposed to this isn't supposed
to be acid import grid divided by eight
it's supposed to be channel index
divided by eight so this this is just
all wrong so let's go ahead and fix it
right okay so what we want to do here is
say that we've got an asset index slot
right the asset index slot is going to
come out of here
and we're going to rewrite it like this
it has to come from the channel index so
what we actually wanted was this right
something along those lines where we've
got the div eight and the mod a split
into those two segments right now
there's easier ways to do this we don't
really have to do it that way we could
have done it differently and you know I
don't know yeah exactly how we want to
do it but that's roughly speaking what
we would do let's actually break that
out oops
into something a little bit more
specific let's say that we've got the X
index and the Y index here so we can at
least inspect them and make sure that
they're right and so that's really more
what we're talking about here so if we
then come back to this routine and look
at it again
hopefully it's more reasonable now I
don't care about this code at the moment
I want to jump right to here so as we
load out this stuff in parse wave we're
gonna soon that work too because I
looked at it and looked reasonable so as
we come through here now I want to see
if we got a reasonable X and x and YX
they should bow
be zero now and then as we go to the
next channel we should get a one here in
a zero here so as we produce that asset
index now we're going to write it back
the asset slot once if we go back and
look at the source file itself so I you
know if I do this and I take a look
inside the asset indices in in chant you
know for channel zeroth there the asset
index should get written back to there
on this line so that's the asset next
that looks right as I come through here
we're gonna do a sample count remaining
kind of clip behavior to write that out
you can see us getting this stuff
created here so the chain equals HHA
sound none and this will determine if we
have to clip it means we will change the
next one so let's see so we've picked
the sample count it should be the total
sample count which is here it should now
get clipped to the max sample count
which it does right so this is that max
sample count and you can see that that
got clipped we set ourselves up for
chaining because we know that we have to
go to the next one since we're not gonna
be able to write the whole sound out
here when we go through here we should
be good to go this is just creating the
total asset data size and yeah reserving
the data in the file writing it out that
should be fine and then we inked that
asset index move the sample pointer
forward and then come through again here
so I think that should be fine as we go
and that'll just loop through 57 times
hopefully finish with no errors we'll
find out if we go looks good all right
so that's correctly we hope loaded our
sound and
we'll see what happens all right
so looks like we got a break here on one
of our assertions you can see up at the
top there's a like a notification here
which is like exception thrown at right
one thing I meant to mention about this
line it does something a little bit
weird which is the color of the line
doesn't change the way that I would
expect it to like I would expect it when
you stop to be read on like an error or
green if it was fine or something and
then orange when it's running or
something but it remains orange even
when you stop running which was weird I
don't know I I'm not sure what how this
lines supposed to work exactly but it's
kind of like a status right and it feels
like it just needs a little bit of work
there I don't know just something to
think about how that's working at the
moment but anyway moving along we're
getting a problem where we try to do a
set asset type here where it's looking
and it seems like this asset maybe
already got added or something else
weird happened so what we want to do is
figure out where that's occurring and
why and see if we can't stop that from
happening
so the first thing to check out is who
were you know who are we saving I and
just to take a look at to what extent
you know this is some old part of our
you know is this something that's
happening as part of the old art
exporting or is this actually something
that's happening as part of our new
sound exporting because I don't know
which one we're looking at so let's pop
back up the stack here which is what I
did to look and see what what we're
exporting so is it art is it audio right
that kind of thing so it looks like
we're exporting art here which means
that we're getting an error in something
that was supposed to already be working
but you know we've we've broken it
somehow and there's a lot of different
ways that that could be
happening we don't actually know where
it's getting this set asset type part
from we should probably look here so
it's getting this asset out of the asset
pool it's looking at the import grid
so I guess my question is what came out
of there so it said it was a plate that
seems eminently reasonable so it has an
asset that it thinks next of type should
be set to null on but it wasn't
so this does at least suggest some kind
of a weird bug happening because it
suggests just to walk through it here
when this asset was initially loaded it
was loaded presumably with type zero
which is to say that the asset didn't
have a type so it got shunted into a
group of assets that are typeless right
ones that didn't have a type assuming
that that's what actually happened and
we can go verify that if that was really
what happened then now it's getting
tagged with a type of plate rather than
a type of zero and there really
shouldn't have been a type zero asset
getting imported there originally so I
would like to go find out what's up with
that so let's take a quick look and see
inside the initial asset startup code
when that set asset type is happening
and again I realize we're supposed to be
done but I just want to take a quick
look at this before we proceed so in
here what I'm trying to say is well you
know you can even see that it's
happening this asset type is getting
added to the list even if the type i's
ID is zero which really shouldn't be
happening you know that's not really
something that's supposed to occur
because you're not supposed to look for
a type zero asset so what I'd like to do
is something more like this
I'd like to take a quick look and see
why if I'm right if this is happening at
startup why did we have asset none
plates how did that happen
like was that just because we had a bug
in the importer originally or is that
happening in some other way and and we
need to go find out how right so that's
what I would like to take a look at
first so I'm just gonna set a breakpoint
cure when we initially like open all of
our existing files I'm gonna I just want
to know what's going on here so you can
see that this is happening at least once
I mean Here I am in the code right it's
actually happening quite a bit right
that's like way too many so I don't know
why we're getting so many assets with a
type ID of zero because how are those
getting written out in the first place
like why were we generating so many type
ID zero assets my only thing I can guess
is that we basically had a bug where we
were creating type 0 assets for plates
or something like how was that happening
I'm really not sure how that could have
been happening
what's the name of the tag list stuff
there it is
so if we assume that these are plate
assets now and which is the type that we
saw before and like before they weren't
or something I'm really not sure what
what was happening there such that they
weren't getting tagged as plates was
there a bug in our original routine I
mean if we look back I don't actually
know if we've got it up here but like if
we look back at the code
yeah we're not can we login probably
can't login it's gonna ask me to like
verify it some nonsense if we look back
at the previous code let me grab some
authentication here I guess
so I guess we have to look at the
authentication here and see what the
authentication is there we go
so if we look into the code that we were
using in the import scheme here right so
this is the code from last time and this
was the code that was importing our art
assets so if we were on a plate it still
should have set it to a set plate right
so I'm not 100% sure where we were
getting that from I don't know if it's
like a problem is it a problem with like
reloading or something or you know I
don't know what's happening there with
Wow why we're getting that because it
should you know if you look at what
should have happened here we should not
have had that issue
um I guess one thing that maybe is the
case I mean I guess I don't know where
exactly those things are coming from you
know maybe they're coming from the font
file or something because we're still
like reading in some older stuff maybe
we didn't properly list
[Music]
I'm really not sure there are some
assets that don't have any types
associated with them and I think font
glyphs would probably be one of them
maybe don't quote me on that but like
font glyphs would be an example and
another example would be the sounds like
themselves they're chunks that come
after the initial chunk if they're
streamed those don't have any it
wouldn't have any type associated with
them because they're not ever accessed
directly their only asset accessed as
chains off of the existing sound off of
the initial sound but I couldn't really
say why those would have been getting
reassigned to a plate
that seems busted so I'm kind of at a
loss to explain exactly what's going on
here the first thing I want to do is I
would like to go ahead and re-import
everything and see if it actually if
this error occurs on a fresh import or
if it had something to do with like an
old like setup that we had like I'd like
to get a sense for what's happening
there so let's just see what happens if
I look inside the data directory here
what you can see is that we really only
have three hhas this one is the only one
that is not built fresh it's because
it's got fonts and we don't support
fonts yet in our new system but we
probably will try to get those in there
as well just so we can kind of have the
complete set of things that can be
buildable at runtime as necessary so
fonts you know we don't have that in
there yet
other than that these two are built
completely from scratch as necessary and
so I would like to know what's going on
there is this some kind of a you know is
this something that happens every time
we import or is it just some artifact of
what
happening in these files and I don't
know so I would like to do that before I
do that I want to take a like a look at
them and see if I can see that we do
have in our HHA edit program we do have
a way to dump these out so if we look in
the dump directory we've got a ton of
that stuff okay so if I do
HHA edit and I do a dump not an extract
which would like get all the bitmaps out
and stuff which I don't want to do if I
do an HHA dump of base game
ehh-ehh and I put that into base game
dot txt I want to then do intro cutscene
dot HHA and put that into intro cutscene
text and then finally test fonts the two
dot HHA and then test fonts if you got
text I'm then gonna go ahead and load up
from the bonus pack the tab view app and
see if there's anything in here that
tells me you know what's going on oops
that was not what I wanted at all nor
that so here's that base game one if I
look at these s assets I guess it's kind
of hard to tell it's not like I can
really quickly look through these to see
if there's like plates hanging around
you know what I mean
and maybe that's sort of maybe that's
sort of something we should add I'm kind
of inclined to do so like for example
let's suppose inside the HHA edit dot
cpp and hey this this would give us a
reason to add that table remember
earlier today as like we don't actually
have a table that says what the asset
type actually is that might be something
we want to add
so in here where we do a right HHA I'm
not ready to H a when we do the dump so
in here where you see us dumping out
these assets we might want to look
through the tags and see what's in there
so you know in here where we do this tag
this tag dump what we could do is do the
tag dump more at the beginning and when
we do that you know in other words here
this is at the you know at the tail I
guess we don't have to really do it I
guess we don't really have to do it
there we could still keep it at the end
but at the beginning you know when we
loop through these assets right and we
grab one of these out of here what we
could do is before we actually print the
line loop through the tags and extract
any information from the tags that we
want to print out as sort of more of a
heads up so you know in here we would do
something like this
[Music]
actually that's not iterating over the
that's that's not right that's doing all
the tags we want just the ones for this
asset there it is so what we want to do
is it's this right here we want to loop
over the asset tags here and I want to
like grab out the one that's the basic
type so in here I want to do like a if
so and I want to grab out the tag this
way
so that will get me the tag and now I
can do something that says like what the
basic type is so inside the file formats
where we've got this basic category
thing what I want to do is have a way
that that gets printed out and you know
this this same thing we've got here
where we got like the name tags right I
want substantively the exact same thing
so I want to be able to do like a global
thing where I do category tag I guess
and then you hear I just want to do like
a Const Z and this is well these can
actually just be in order they don't
have to look like that so in some sense
this is actually more like the one we
have one like that don't we that instead
of tags it's just now I guess we don't
actually do one of those it looks like
we always have them lined up okay well
that's fine too so if we want to do that
it's just this like so and so I just
want to make sure that these are all
like you know represented in here and
I'm just gonna print out what kind it
was the reason I'm doing that is because
it's just too hard it takes too long for
me to like open up each individual one
and look to see if it doesn't have an
asset category that's more what I want
to know and so I just want to go through
and prep this in a way that allows that
to happen a little bit more specifically
right here's where macros would be
pretty handy
see here there we go and now I just need
to turn them into something that looks
like this so these commas are not
necessary although actually maybe they
are so probably what I want to do is
something like this right you can see
why macros would be handy because you
could do all this with your doing the
same thing whenever you're doing the
same thing to every line that's where
that's like really the only place I used
to use macros in canoeing Emacs most
things you don't really need them for
but stuff like this it's just handy
because you can do it one time and then
you know apply it to lots of things at
once all right so after that I just need
to eliminate the asset part of things
here and change this into constancies in
the broader scheme of things really
talking about needing macros is kind of
a little bit of a red herring too
because honestly the fact that we have
to do this typing at all is just because
C++ is garbage C++ is any good you
didn't have to do any of this because
what we're doing right now is manually
doing a bunch of text entry and saying
it would be nice if our text editor
allowed us to automate that text entry
when really we shouldn't have to be
doing any of that text entry in the
first place since if the language just
had the ability to create things like
this from a single list we would be good
to go you can also sort of you know
there's a there's sort of a poor man's
version of this that you can do where
you include you know you can list these
things once in an include file and then
use that include file twice and that is
you know at this point because we've
done so many things with these arrays
it's probably what we should have done
it probably would have saved time it's
just a little bit ugly you know I don't
know how I feel about it it's it's six
of one half doesn't know the other it's
it's really kind of abusing the macro
though the preprocessor but it does kind
of work and sometimes it's just better
to have something that works even if
it's a little ugly than something like
this which is kind of error-prone and
manual and I don't know how to you know
how to really say much about those two
you know trade offs there but yeah
either way would be nice to have text
macros for things like this if you do
want to do them but really they're also
just a kind of a stupid thing because
you should never really have to do a
text macro your language should have
been able to handle that for you
whatever you were doing with a text
macro should have been something the
language could have done right because
if it is that wrote if you can do
effectively a programming operation on
it you should have just been able to
tell your language to do it whatever it
was and the fact that you happen to want
to do it in actual text maybe you want
that option but you should never have
have been forced to do so right like
that's not something you should have to
do that's something that you should have
the option of doing and that's like you
know it's worth noting the difference
between those two things anyway so let's
get category name from ID here and I
think this is what asset basic category
and so all I want to do here is say look
I've got these like category tags
whatever those are and we don't really
know what they are just yet
but we've got these category tags so
we're gonna go through here and we're
gonna look at the category tags and for
every category tag that we see if we
find one that matches the idea that
we're looking for we will return it
right and that's all we were going to do
so we've got this thing called a name
tag and we want so don't know where
that's defined to find here we want one
of those four category as well so we've
got here
category tag I guess is what it is
and that's just going to be a basic
asset cat or a basic category asset
basic category yeah that will allow us
to scan through there and do this in HHA
edit so we can find that name right
we'll be able to call that so I'm gonna
do category here and I'm gonna say that
that in fact maybe we'll do like a nun
something like this or something like
that and then what I'm gonna do in here
in fact I guess what we could do is
actually call it this way so category
tags or category name from ID we can
start by just asking what's the nun
version because that's what we will
assume and then in here we would say oh
the category actually comes out of this
so if we find the tag that has that
particular thing in it we'll go ahead
and convert it right so the way we want
to do that is to say if the tag type in
this particular case right happens to be
equal to tag basic category then we can
do this which is to say we will convert
the value of the tag into a basic
category and look up whatever that
happens to be we will then assume that
that is our new category string right so
I mean here we say the asset index what
we probably want to do then is say what
type it is I guess so we would say
something like category count category
data and then I think we're good to go
oops no commas
got about those commas
why can't we convert between those
that's really dumb like that's how you
would convert between those two things
how do you not know how to convert
between a floating-point value and an
integer
thanks C++ for warnings that are
completely useless all right so now if I
redo these dumps like if I read you that
base game dump when I'm hoping is that
if I look at the assets now as a list
it'll tell me yeah like right off the
bat right I can see what all of these
are and so looking through those you
know it's pretty clear that there's
nothing with an asset type of none in
here right and that's all I wanted was
to get to the point where that was
easier to see so let's go ahead and read
dump the intro cutscene as well so well
in the test fonts there we go so now if
I do tab view on let's say the test
fonts v2 text oops
w bonus pack so all of these have fought
glyph right so all of those are
correctly being loaded as well so the
last one that could be a problem it's
this one see what this has all right so
you know we've clearly found our culprit
the intro cutscene HHA is just complete
garbage so we've got a problem
so it looks like we we have it all it
looks like we either corrupted this file
at some point or it's just broken when
we import plates since all of these
things are plates I'm guessing what
happened is it got corrupted at some
point like it rewrote an asset array
like incorrectly or something I'm not
entirely sure but what I do want to do
is I so let's let's actually push
forward a little bit on this let's go
ahead and run this again with the with
the plates deleted so I'm gonna you know
I guess make dirt temp move intro
cutscene that star to temp and so we put
away that intro cutscene file and now
I'm gonna run and by the way this should
never hit now I'm gonna run this again
and this should reimburse to the intro
cutscene HHA and what I want to do is
after that intro cutscene has like been
saved I I want to then inspect what it
looks like right
this is gonna take a while because this
is the debug build so all of our
importing will be very very slow right
and then we can Reem we can export that
text file and see what's up
this may take a while probably should
have compiled and release mood for this
but that's almost done
remember how big this file was maybe
when I said almost done that was a total
of total lie what was it 300 Meg file
I'll say it's ready to make file you
know it's our intro cutscene assets
uncompressed or just slightly slightly
smaller than like you know the
executable for Unreal Engine
all right so that's gotta be almost done
right I mean I think it was only in the
300 Meg range for all the intro cutscene
stuff I think well I guess we know how
big it was right it was in the tenth oh
yeah
343 so it shouldn't be much bigger than
that it will now potentially add a
little bit more in it because it's got
the sound data but that should be I
think it and then off it goes right so
it looks like that's it so let's take a
look at what that actually wrote out in
terms of of information in the HHA I'm
gonna do a
rewrite of the intro cutscene text file
and then we're going to reload it here
so that's correct
sort of yes so that is exactly what we
would expect to see all of these are
properly now labeled as plates all of
these are labeled as none and the
reasons they're labeled as none is
because they are like chained audio
right so they're not supposed to get
entered into any list if they're just a
chain of this audio now one could argue
that we want to label these better like
you know it kind of is lamed that these
are not really identified anything other
than the fact that they are a chain
sound like maybe they should have some
kind of annotation on them I don't know
what we want to do about that that's
that's a tough call I'm gonna leave it
like that for now but you know in the
future we may want to do something about
that I'm hoping now then if we were to
close this out I'm hoping that now if we
were to rerun this we would not have the
bug that we had before
well I guess we will get this because
these things are rightfully not added to
any insertion as far as an asset type
area is concerned but I'm hoping that we
wouldn't have that plate export conflict
because that looked like some kind of a
bug with the tag array and it does look
like we don't so I'm gonna call that
done for now this is sort of a standing
issue what should we do with this and I
don't know
since these types are contiguous the
dump could just know that right if
chained if you have a chain sound
I'm kind of interested in what this how
we're writing that out like what is that
74 680 95 x2 did so do we actually write
the entire sample count out and then the
data chunk is just smaller that's pretty
interesting I didn't know we were doing
that and I also don't know is that what
we should be doing like should the
sounds just just to show you what that
is right inside the file format where we
write out the sounds there's a sample
count a channel count and a chain piece
of chain information there right now you
don't need to know the sample count
because the data size right the the
thing that actually says in here how big
the data is tells you what you need to
know about the sound so these two pieces
of information are actually completely
useless and don't mean anything right in
fact the channel count is actually just
a lie because there aren't there are non
we don't actually bother with
multi-channel sounds anymore we split
them into separate assets so we could
literally remove both of those things
from the sound footprint and be fine
we just don't at the moment right
[Music]
so I don't really know what we want to
do there I don't know maybe makes sense
to store that sample count redundantly
just so we can look and see well how
long is this thing gonna play for so we
don't have to chase the chain to know
how long it would be in total I'm gonna
say that let's leave it this way for now
and that channel count as well because
that would let you know how many there
are so I'm gonna say like we
accidentally did the right thing there
and I'm just gonna say that's fine
moving forward I might document this
though like so really this is not true
anymore this is the data and we're just
saying that that isn't you know you
don't you don't get to to really buy
that so so I think that's fine that
means we're actually gonna use that full
u-32 this is pointless definitely
doesn't need to do that I guess so I
should maybe was premature if we just
apply this to do just to the stuff below
it like this then it's still accurate
I'm gonna go ahead and say that's mine
let me do this and see if we can still
run so I think we're okay now looks like
we got rid of that issue I'm hoping that
this will now work for sound importing
but we still probably have a little bit
of debugging to do later however I think
we are now properly
implementing streaming sounds in the
asset import and we should be good to go
alright we'll go to a brief Q&amp;A but I
think that's everything let me go ahead
and there we go
I forget the sequel no it doesn't
support that fly it only gets supports
you know the high-powered hermeneutics
graph traversal
any cues
so interesting enough twitch says we
have 90 out of a hundred and twenty five
sub points but I don't actually know
what we get if we have a hundred and
twenty five sub points they never really
make it clear like what you get for
getting more points is it just more
emotes okay so it looks like we could
add like a lot more emotes now
wait okay hold on I get 125 subscriber
points and you get one new emote slot
but we've got so many there's like one
two three four five six more emote slots
that we can fill out right
I just do not understand
I will I will forever be confused by the
twitch email stuff
all right so we have a couple of
questions now while I was looking to
figure out how the twitch emotes work I
think this means we can add more twitch
emotes but I don't really know if that's
true the questions were you never went
to university seem to be but you seem to
be very literate in mathematics how do
you get to this level so I guess what I
would say is I'm not that literate in
mathematics I do think that going to
university is somewhat helpful for
mathematics because it you know you kind
of have a forced clearly laid out set of
time to go through all of you know
several sets of math I guess what I'd
say is the way I compensate for not
having gone through that is I just did a
lot of that on my own so I would just
work my way through books I as necessary
so you know I learned in turn I learned
interval arithmetic from a book I
learned linear algebra from a book I
learned matrix like sparse matrix
analysis and stuff like that from a book
but like I've never really worked
through like hard core calculus stuff
and so my calc is very weak like you
know I understand conceptually what like
you know Stokes theorem or greens
theorem
do I understand conceptually what
calculus of variations does but I can't
really do it right
I understand partial differential
equations to a certain extent but like
my ability to actually work with them is
poor the same would be true of like
ordinary differential equations and so a
lot of those things are just a case of
spent
the time till like actually just work
through them they're like everything
else you know you just have to practice
with them and start to put them into
your head in a way that makes sense to
you and I don't really have any advice
about how to do that a lot of math books
are terrible most math books are
terrible so finding the right math book
can be a big help but other than that
it's really just setting aside the time
to actually study and work through it on
your own try to pick some code to write
also so you get used to like applying a
piece that you know if you take
something like stokes theorem or greens
theorem or ordinary differential
equations or partial differential
equations there's all sorts of code you
could write that use those sorts of
things and so you can easily come up
with little exercises to do that would
help you internalize what you're
actually doing like how you actually
apply those pieces of math to something
useful and so you you will make like a
stronger connection to what they
actually do as opposed to just the
theoretical I know it manipulates the
symbols in this particular way right so
what I would say is you know just spend
the time that's that's really all it is
and beyond that try to get good
recommendations for books that are
actually good that's really all I can
recommend it's really spending the time
it's the same as programming it's
spending the time simplices I got a call
from Gary Walsh Selina Meyers bagman
while you were unpacking the backpack he
said he's jealous and wants to compare
bag layouts I have no idea who those
people are
what are your thoughts on Cody
introspection we're adding metadata to
things like strux useful or you have
another bad obturate idea no I think
they're very useful I don't think they
have anything to do with object-oriented
programming I think they're just good
there's nothing magic about a struct or
a class it's just a way of assigning a
name to a particular layout of data in
memory there's no reason why you
shouldn't be able to access that layout
conceptually in your code the fact that
C++ doesn't allow this is terrible
they're finally adding that in like C++
2037 or whatever they're up to at this
point or at least my understanding is
it'll probably be complete crap like all
of their features are but like at least
they're adding some crappy version I
guess I am 100% in favor of languages
that actually do this well though it's
very good I guess is what I'd say it has
nothing to do with object-oriented
programming
favorite code designed learning
resources I don't know would you use
your from scratch little approach for
machine learning or just use a library
like tensorflow
I really couldn't tell you because I've
never looked at machine learning
libraries before some of the problems
that you'll have with like from scratch
in any domain where you're probably
talking about using GPU or other HPC
stuff is just that you're going to need
some way to access the custom hardware
for it and so unlike situations where I
would recommend learning to do things at
a low level from the start there are
some domains and special purpose
hardware programming is unfortunately
increasingly one of them where that's
really not an option like there's no way
to directly program an nvidia card it
just simply doesn't exist so you are
forced to use some kind of a library
right in order to access it and so you
know while I would say that
understanding what's going on is still
crucial just like it is everywhere even
when you use a library and I would
encourage you to figure out how machine
learning is working at a lower level for
whatever the particular thing is that
you're working on using a library
whether it's tensorflow
or something else may be unavoidable
because you mainly I mean Nvidia and
Apple and various other hardware
manufacturers put specific machine
learning what I want to put this part of
the die is dedicated to you know doing a
crap-ton of large low precision matrix
multiplies for lack of a better term
right which are specifically for doing
things like machine learning via neural
networks and so if you're trying to
target that sort of thing you kind of
have to
use some API that allows you to access
that stuff and so maybe tensorflow is a
good choice I have no idea I've never
even looked at it but you know if you're
doing stuff that requires special
purpose hardware you oftentimes don't
have the option to programming it
yourself so it's not really the same
kind of question as it would be for
something like what we do in handmade
Hiro and you can see us doing exactly
this on handmade Hiro - right we have to
use for example shaders to program the
3d hardware we don't have the ability to
program it at any real lower level than
that you know you could try and write in
like pseudo assembly but even that's not
really the assembly language of the
shader right it's of the shading
hardware it's it's actually sort of a
translation layer so you know that's
just the unfortunate world we live and I
wish we didn't but you know I also sorry
I also can ask answer any questions
about dear I'm Juliet I've never used it
you could ask George remedy BG is using
it he might have an opinion
so X 13 pixels on the chat he he might
have something to say about that and and
no I don't really have any book
recommendations for programming your
math these days cuz I'm kind of wilfully
out-of-date you know the math books that
I learn math from and the programming
books I read as a child are you know
probably not the right ones to I've got
I hoped hope they're not the like I hope
there's better resources now I guess is
what I'm saying if really nothing better
than then the books I read is have been
written in the last thirty years that's
kind of sad
I guess I'm technically not an
exclusively C++ guy I guess I have used
a couple other languages although I
wouldn't really say that I've ever done
enough work in those languages well
that's not true so I wrote a fair bit of
PHP code for web development back in 20
like 2006 seven timeframe maybe maybe
eight somewhere on there it's a horrible
language don't ever use it I guess one
thing I had to say I don't think I've
really had much experience well Pascal I
used before before I did see and also
like basic and true basic I wrote a
significant amount of code and that's
about it I so I haven't ever used like
c-sharp
or Python try to think of any other
languages that come to mind Swift that
people have been using lately I've never
programmed a significant amount in those
languages not like I haven't done a
significant project like in those
languages so I'm not really in a
position to comment on them extensively
you know I'm saying
what's your favorite fairly new language
I don't really have one
because I haven't really used any you
know I haven't used fairly new money I
haven't used rust I haven't used ji yet
I don't know what other fairly new
languages there are that people will
Swift I guess I haven't used those
languages so I haven't yeah I can't pick
a favorite language because I have no
idea what they're like what's your
impression of Seattle after living there
for as long as you have I think it's not
like I I wouldn't live here now if I had
a choice like it's I quite liked it in
the in the 90s late 90s I moved here in
95 I would say probably even up through
like 2010 era I thought was quite nice
the past couple years it's really gone
downhill considerably it's a it's a very
poorly run City to say the very least
and you know some aspects are not
necessarily the city's fault some of
them maybe you could consider to be
federal problems but a fair bit of it's
just just cities city fault as well and
I would say yeah it's not a place to
move to
you know I I'd probably be gone by now
if I wasn't right in the middle of a
bunch of stuff and you know I don't want
to be spending a lot of money and stuff
like that but you know when I'm done
with projects I wouldn't be surprised if
I'm found out of here
come back to Boston uh yeah you know I
guess I I guess I could I haven't really
spent much time in Boston so I don't
really know what I would think of it I
I'm not you know one of the problems of
moving out of Washington State is like
we're a company you know and I feel like
that would mean we'd have to change like
accountants and stuff for tax filing
because I'm doubting that our
accountants here would file Maslak
Massachusetts has its own state income
tax I I don't know if there's a city
income tax in Boston but there's at
least a state income tax in
Massachusetts and you know they probably
don't work with that I would assume I
don't really know though if given a
virtually infinite budget
what would you dedicate your time to I
would probably doing basically what I'm
doing now you know I just would be a lot
less stressed all the time that makes
sense
so in savate just like can somebody
please clip a what in sohbat just said
that's amazing
in sohbat just said it's still valve
that's very very good that's very very
good
inside bodies is truly a national
treasure and I guess he's not really a
national treasure cuz I think he was
made outside of the u.s. he's an
international treasure might be the way
to say it no one ever says international
treasure
all right I think I've gotten through
all the questions probably it looks like
Victorian just in case you just kind of
quickly joined us here we switched to X
13 pixels debugger and it's working real
well you can actually find a link to it
in down below the twitch window there
it's remedy be GHI Oh
20 bucks and it is pretty darn good even
though it's just kind of getting started
it's on version 0.2 but you know it's
it's already giving Visual Studio run
for its money and I think pretty soon
it's gonna be kind of game over for
Visual Studio as a debugger which is
pretty awesome because I'm so sick and
tired of Visual Studio
all right
we don't need this right now
there we go
thank you everyone for joining me for
another episode of handmade hero it's a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along series at
home you always pre-order the game on
handmade here org and it comes with a
source code I so you can follow along
and do your own experiments we are
ostensibly done importing audio I mean
we don't really know but we went through
the code and it appears to do what I
wanted it to do so that means next week
we should be able to just put that into
actual use add some sound to the game of
course we don't really have many sounds
out of the game but we've got some tests
at least so we can at least verify that
those are working properly hey maybe
that means we should figure out where
we're gonna get some sounds for this
game that's sort of another issue whole
together but we'll take a look I'll be
back here next week to do exactly that
until then everyone have fun programming
and I'll see you on the Internet
take it easy to everybody