hello everyone welcome to handmade zero
share we could complete game live on
stream we're the process of pulling out
a renderer for a friend asking for a
friend
hashtag asking for a friend we pretty
much did all the basics yesterday and
the render is separated now so really
what I want to focus on for the next
step is actually fixing a couple things
in the render and cleaning up the API so
this is more at this point this is less
of a let's pull the renderer out which
we kind of did and are in relatively
good shape for this is now more of a
let's go ahead and start looking at some
things that we wanted due to the API and
fix them because now that we've got it
in a cleaner State it's a good chance
for us to do a couple things we've
really been mean do for a while the big
one is to figure out how we want to
handle textures long term I've said many
times that we have a problem with
texture handling that's because we
started off with just software rendering
suffering doesn't really care about how
the textures are set up Hardware
rendering on several different pieces of
hardware does we kind of need to be
power of two's and we kind of need to be
well it's to be fair the power of tube
stuff is not really the most important
part for most of the hardware that would
actually have caused us problems what we
the real big thing is we need all our
text should be the same size that's
that's really the main thing essentially
you can think of it as when you start
doing a draw dispatch there's different
kinds of hardware out there some
hardware like an advanced nvidia part
that hardware can just think about
textures as a per primitive thing it's
literally like a cpu in a lot of ways
where it's just it can just get a
pointer to a texture and just go to town
right so if you want to change textures
per primitive it's really no big deal
there isn't anything special about it
and the fact that those textures are
different dimensions isn't really a
problem on other kinds of hardware
that's not how it works I don't pretend
to know the internals of
a lot of GPUs but in terms of your
mental model it's as if you have to load
in a single texture pointer into the
chip in a sense like into a register set
and then all of your drawing has to be
off of that base right so you can't just
push down texture pointers per primitive
and expect that to work you actually
need to have a sort of restart every
time that you're gonna have that that
change right eye and so when you are
talking about that kind of hardware
you're talking about needing to make
sure that you can access a large number
of actual conceptual textures off of a
single base pointer and the only real
way to do that that we have is by using
something like a texture array which is
to say a base pointer and then we can
index off of the base pointer to get
many different textures but they all
have to be the same size right so
fundamentally speaking we can't really
do much else about it we just have to
say look we're gonna have all these
textures they're gonna be roughly this
big off we go
okay now you may ask
and rightfully so
well who cares right just pick a big
texture 2048 by 2048 why not and just
pack as many textures into it as you
want right and this is called a texture
atlas and then we only need one size of
texture array right now this is not a
bad idea this is a pretty good idea
actually and you can do it there is
however a pretty big downside to it the
downside is either you have to leave a
lot of gap between the things that are
packed in there or you have to never use
mipmapping or you have to write your own
mipmap fetch and blend why is this well
it's because mipmapping in my opinion
and you know I'm not a graphics person
but I feel like I understand this part
well enough to have an opinion on it
because I've done a lot of work on this
particular type of thing mipmapping was
not very well conceived the way that
texture coordinates are computed form it
levels I don't particularly agree with
and as a result you end up in a
situation where multiple textures packed
together or even a single texture that
needs to be paired up with another
texture and not have a seam in the
middle mipmapping just doesn't work in
order to use it you have to do things
like padding your textures with copies
of the things that they're tiling with
and stuff like this it's it's kind of
nasty and so you end up in two
situations you really don't want to be
in and you've got a lot of issues that
you have to address there if you want to
handle these sorts of things properly
mipmapping like just it just didn't
think about a lot of things when they
did mipmapping it was a simple solution
to the problem at the time but they
didn't think about a lot of the problems
such as needing to place textures next
to each other and not have there be
seams
and they also didn't think about texture
atlases really as a thing texture
atlases are harder to solve with mapping
problems in the though even if you had
done it correctly it still only solves a
little bit of the problem you still have
other problems about what happens as
neighboring pixels get blurred together
so sexual alice's is not as big of a
deal it's kind of broken always um so
you know there's a lot of issues I I
don't know what to say about them other
than you can go down a pretty large
rabbit hole if you actually want to deal
with this stuff correctly on handmade
Hiro will be okay with just a reasonable
solution we just need something sensible
texture race will be pretty good for us
for all of our in-game art I think let
guys saying maybe if we just have
everything as a 512 by 512 bitmap we put
it in there we go since we have a stream
on-demand system I think we can lean on
that to make it so that we just allocate
a fixed number of these and we just swap
them in and out as we need to and as
long as we have some relatively good
prediction which you know I think we can
work out I don't think that's too hard
to do I think we'll be okay
so I think we have a lot of options that
other people maybe don't have because we
have a solid streaming system that we
can sort of improve over time and lean
on for solving some of the problems that
you might otherwise encounter I think we
can probably deal with that and as a
result we don't because I think we can
lean on our streaming system I don't
think we'll have as much to worry about
in terms of wasted space if we want to
waste a huge amount of our 512 by 512
bitmap that could be a serious problem
for another game but for us because
we're streaming we only care that we
have enough 512 by 512 to do what's on
the screen you know and so that gives us
some flexibility to be more wasteful in
other parts so it's kind of nice right
like that buys us it means that there's
no cost to the GPU texture memory
wastage that there normally would be
right because we're not counting on
being able to pack all this stuff into
the GPU texture memory for an entire
level or something and just expect it to
work when we're streaming we can always
just say look as long as we can fit what
to stream in for like our current screen
and a little apron we're done we don't
really have to be any more compact than
that and so that can help us with stuff
like you know not having to have a big
texture outlet set system in there which
again bugs things down adds a lot of
complexity and all these other things
that you know we don't really want to
have to do and also that would make the
code slower because it's actually
thinking about all that stuff right so
anyway what we want to do is figure out
how we're gonna move forward on this
though how we want to start moving to
texture arrays because I really think we
do want to and hopefully get a little
bit of the way there today that's what
we'd like to do and you know again this
is kind of like half and half it's
partly because hey we're pulling out the
renderer but it's partly just like we
would really like to be able to do this
right okay so let's start by doing
something really basic which is right
now we've got if we load up two studio
we've got did that close I did I
intentionally did not mean to close this
that's gonna stay up there we've got to
remember this
all right uh so what we want to do here
is we want to take this sort of basic
that's not we wanted this is what we
want to take this basic start which
proves that our renderer runs outside
runs outside the game and works you know
in all the ways that we expect it to we
want to turn this into something that
looks a little bit more like an actual
game screen right so what I'd like to do
is you know render a bunch of these
cubes and then a sprite you know maybe
on top of them in a reasonable location
and then I would like to have them be
textured with textures that we loaded
from disk right and then at that point I
think we're pretty much done you know
we've provided a solid render service
that works and off we go right so I'd
like to go ahead and move down that move
move closer to that goal I also wouldn't
mind making this a little bit more
active here you know something that we
can see a little bit better again I
don't really know what the perspective
is supposed to be for the the game in
question here I asked sort of for like a
pointer just a simple example it was
[Music]
so this was this was what they were sort
of saying was like look it's just gonna
be something like this right get the
bitmap uh you just talking about
something like this right there there
thing was like something like this but
actually 3d right they they wanted they
didn't want it one way to say it is
they were just thinking of something
like this like so artist paints a tree
and we slap it down there right but they
were saying but it would actually be 3d
so meaning like the blocks and stuff I'm
assuming would actually be in 3d so they
they're not they're not ice isometric
the lines aren't parallel right I should
say it actually be in perspective right
which is again exactly what we were sort
of what exactly what we were working on
now what I don't know is to what extent
the person wants to be able to decorate
with actual 3d elements like for example
if you were to take something like this
do you expect to be able to spin around
and have this thing actually look 3d on
the top like this pointy part actually
look like a pyramid so I don't know to
what extent they want additional
primitives perhaps but for at least for
us we don't really have much problem
with additional primitives you could add
additional primitives to our renderer
very easily because we mostly just think
about triangles and I mean quads
anything made up of quads would just
work if you wanted to add triangles - it
wouldn't be hard right so that's
actually not really that big of a
problem either if they want to do that
the only thing is again I don't know how
much they really want to get into
thinking about the 3d but maybe like I
said they were hoping to work with
somebody to make some modifications to
the renderer anyway or to even to write
a completely new renderer that was the
thing they were originally looking for
when I said hey maybe you could start
with ours just so you don't have to do
all that work so if we're talking about
something like this and we look and we
see what
the real you know what do we do if we
want to create a scene that looks like
this but in 3d well first of all they'd
have to use kind of ground cover sprites
to produce a fuzz effect right because
you can't really have a fuzzy effect
like that it with actual 3d geometry you
have to actually stick something with
just basically you have to actually
stick some fuzz up right you can use
displacement mapping to I suppose if you
wanted to but that might getting a
little bit for our field so if you look
at something this you know but let's
assume we're just gonna do flat stuff
for now and then if you want grasses on
there you would plop some some sprites
on to give it ground cover or something
like that that's what we're doing in
handmade Hiro and then you have big
sprites for trees and let's just say
we're not gonna think about stuff like
this because we don't know what they
would want you could just slap a sprite
on there but then I you know maybe what
you actually want is something more like
actual geometry for stuff like this and
you could do that in handmade here you
could just build that up out of some
cubes and that would work right we
render it would just handle that just
fine so again I don't really know
getting further down what kind of stuff
they were talking about but on the whole
when I look at something like this and
someone says we're going for something
like this this is basically what the
hand made here a renderer was already
set up to do so I really don't think
it's a problem right so what I want to
do is move this thing towards just
rendering a scene that looks basically
like that and to do that I've got to be
able to put some textures on the cubes
and so that's all we're really gonna be
doing curious focusing on that and that
will lead us to doing the texturing
better because I would like to do that
as well all right so let's start by
doing some simple things here let's go
ahead and make something that's like you
know render simple scene and this will
just be something that takes you know
the the camera having been set up and
instead of calling push cube we'll just
say render simple scene maybe we'll call
it push simple scene and we'll pass that
group down so this right here will take
the render group and that way we can
just say okay you know here's our little
simple scene let's draw something simple
enough right uh and let's make it a
little bit more interesting so let's
just draw a lot of cubes right let's
start by drawing a fair number of cubes
I will kind of just do what we used to
do in a made hero when we make a good
bunt you just told me they want to
update perfect timing right I got
nothing to do sure pop it up so I'm
gonna go ahead and say let's loop over
an X Y set place these things into the
world and we'll go from there okay all
right so let's say we've got an X index
or just an X you know I don't know how
many of these we want but we're just
gonna make a grid here and by stepping
along this grid we can just push cubes
in here and we'll make those cubes have
a little bit of variance to them
so the first I'm going to do is set the
cube position and that can just be like
X Y Z you know and what I'll do is I'll
say well the x position and the Y
position can just be you know the meter
right and then the Z position will be
something else that we do here and for
the moment it can be zero that's fine so
now we've got a position we have a
dimension the dimension I believe I
think is the total dimension I don't
know if it's a dimension or radius this
is like NY pulling out the render is
gonna be nice because I'd love to go
through and take this opportunity we're
done to like just say here's what the
whole API is right what are what are
things are they are they radii or are
they dimensions right so here's this you
know and just be uniform at all right so
if it's radii
1/2 meter on either side right and then
here I could I could if I want to since
this is a sea library thing I could make
a little bit of variance in the Z right
I could do a Rand and then you know
divide that by Rand Max right that would
give me a 0 to 1 variance in the Z and
so I could then just get a little bit of
variance in there so you can see the
kind of cubes a little bit better right
and off we go
don't ask me why I thought I could set a
negative value for an unsigned just
hubris I guess so there we go and that's
good that's all our cubes we now need a
little bit more for our cubes probably
to actually see them right we want some
color variance in there because we're
not slepak textures on them yet so in
order to get color variants in there we
want to just create a sort of a varied
color let me just go ahead and produce a
color here so what I'll do is I'll just
say like oh yeah I don't know for now
let's just set it to a gray that's based
on the Z value of the thing and win a
minute I'll make a better color I'm
second here right oh right this random
has to be seated properly for us how do
I want to do that well I guess I'll just
override that'll set the seed and that
way we won't get any sparkles so if I
put this in here yeah let me just let's
just try something simple here so there
we go now the color doesn't really seem
to be changing as much as that should my
interpreting that statement wrong Rand
over R and Max and then the Z value
oh that's good hey man if you make a
color and you want to see it one thing
you might consider is actually passing
it to the routine all right so here's
our world of cubes not very interesting
obviously so that's fine so what I'm
going to do now is just say that I'll
put I'll put a very low variance in
there I'm gonna call this like the
r-value or something we'll put that in
here so I'll say 8 plus that is R and
then this will just be you know blue
world for now so there we can see our
cubes they're not quite distinct enough
so maybe I'll give it a little bit more
variance than that in the red Channel
and off we go
so once we've got blue world which is
this thing then the next thing we want
to kind of do here is give it a little
bit of rotation there so we can just see
what's going on and then probably also
put a sprite in there somewhere I don't
know where but off we go and then the
main thing we just need to do from there
honest textures right so if you're
looking here we've got a Waialua Bowl
running we set a bunch of stuff camera
offset near clamp Bubba blah blah blah
right well this stuff we kind of want to
be able to update over time so what I'm
going to do here is going to pull this
out and I put it in here and then I'm
gonna say that our camera orbit we're
just gonna update periodically right so
when we get down here to Sam seconds
elapsed I'm going to take our camera
orbit which is you know the the kind of
spinning around the point that we're
looking at I'm gonna take that camera
orbit and I'm just gonna add the second
celebs to it so we'll just kind of
slowly kind of move around in that
fashion oh my bad that is actually
dependent on the window size
so here we have you know exactly what
you would expect right here is our 3d
renderer rendering a cube scene that is
again similar to the one that we looked
at you know similar to this right and
now we want to start putting in those
textures and we want to start putting in
you know like that tree for example and
we can act like we can actually do
literally you know basically that scene
if we want to because we actually have
some part from handmade here or we can
just pull in we have a tree right and so
what we want to do is is get that going
so in order to do that I'm gonna first
have to find a way to submit these
textures right and so we know that we've
got our current way of doing it and what
I'm going to do is just gonna use the
cart like I want to build this test up
first I'm gonna use the stuff we
currently have and then I'm gonna
simplify it down as we go and update
that API right because we know we've got
the texture app stuff and we need to
kind of like work on that a little bit
to get it to where we need it to be so
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
pull that stuff over in here clean it up
and get it down to something nice and
simple and then in the meantime we'll
also simplify the one that we're using
in handmade hero because they're the
same right so what we need here is we
need one of these render or texture cues
so I'm gonna go ahead and grab that what
we want to do I think is make these be
something that the renderer itself is
responsible for creating for us so for
example when we call win32 in it opened
jail punches me I think what I want to
be able to do is get back from win32
init open jail or whatever does the
rendering for open jail might be you
know you know we've got to think about
this kind of little bit more expansively
perhaps you me but basically we want to
do is have that OpenGL texture cube
maybe be part of that system right so
just I don't know if that's really the
right thing to do I'm not sure yet
but what I want to do is
just make it so that that comes from
somewhere logical so let's say we're in
the OpenGL subsystem here right the way
that would look is let's suppose it has
the renderer texture cube here and so if
you wanted to talk to the texture queue
for OpenGL where you're submitting
OpenGL textures then the police that
that comes from is the same place that
you look for like your OpenGL white
bitmap for example right it's just off
of the OpenGL object and I don't
actually want to quite work that way
eventually but for right now I'm just
gonna push it over there and we'll think
about it a little bit harder about where
it lives once we have a little bit more
information all right you can see us
doing that right here like OpenGL white
bitmap right so if I want to actually
submit a texture to the texture queue
again we did pull out the thing that
does that it's right here so what I need
to do is figure out where these texture
ops come from right and what's
interesting is I guess actually we don't
that's just a copy right so really all
we have to do is just add an OP with the
thing that we were trying to load in
right so here if I say all right I've
got a cube texture I want to load that
in all I have to do is say okay there's
a texture up like upload or cube op I
don't it will do something different
with this in a second but um all I
really have to do is just look at the
renderer fill out the texture up to be
the OP that I want right so is allocate
is true and where is that
right here I got to fill out the width
the height and the data so the width of
this thing we know is cube texture dot
with because we've loaded the bitmap
right there's the height the data is the
cube textures memory and the only thing
that I would point out here is we don't
actually have a pitch so we're gonna
have to make sure that the pitch
actually works here now fortunately it
does but we'll kind of we want to roll
that in probably in a little bit
slightly different way so then if I set
the result texture here the result
texture is going to be we have the
renderer texture cube and this should
really be cube bitmap right
so this cube texture here is what we
want to actually fill out so we just say
like okay it's cube texture
okay and that's the thing that we
actually want to make sure that we
process so then we go ahead and add that
cube op and we put in here that you know
whatever whatever the texture cubes that
we want to cue it on so since we know
that we're doing the texture Q of open
gel that will do the queuing right so
that's how we would cue one up and what
we want is we actually want to queue
that up earlier rather than later but it
doesn't really matter so when we
actually go to push this you know I
could for example just push this in here
and say okay now when we're doing push
simple scene that will pass that cube
texture in here under a texture cube
texture and then I can just say like oh
yeah you know put the put the cube
texture on there right oh and last but
not least when these if these are going
to live in in like the open gel layer or
wherever they're gonna live right then
the texture we need a way to initialize
the texture queue for whoever we're
talking about here so now that stuff has
to kind of move out of the win32
handmade layer but that's great because
that's exactly what I want to do right
so all this stuff this stuff for the
texture apps this wants to be actually
in the the OpenGL sub system here right
we want that part to be actually handled
by the renderer proper if that makes
sense so this right here should be a
call-out right we instead of being in
the win32 layer we actually want that to
be so opengl managed textures right we
she want OpenGL managed textures to be
it's sort of own call and what you can
see here is we've kind of got this is
our OpenGL render commands and then we
have OpenGL managed textures we want to
stop doing that right that's not gonna
be how we do it anymore
we're gonna pull this itself into here
so we're just gonna call opengl managed
textures as a separate call that's every
time we want that to occur
okay so this comes in here as stuff that
actually happens you can see it doing
its its mutex ticketing right it pulls
it off of here and then does the
manufactures then puts it back on so
what we want to do is say okay this
process just goes right there so we
start our ticketing we and by the way
this is all based on the OpenGL sub
system here so it's just it it's all
using sort of the the implicit OpenGL
global which we could now if we wanted
to be more conscientious and actually
pass into these few routines that
actually use it which we may want to do
as part of the pulling out process but
that's kind of a separate issue so what
we want to do here is say alright we
know we've got a texture cue render a
texture kid so the texture cue is just
the OpenGL text okay
and then what we want to do is these two
operations now what you can see though
that's very important about these
operations OS I hope you can see about
them is they are not tied to a renderer
so no matter which render you were doing
you would do these two operations DQ
everything and then Riku the onto the
free list right so what I want to do
again is set ourselves up for success
here add the those in as sort of utility
functions right that you call so here I
would say that first texture op and last
texture op right I want to get those out
here and I want to produce them here
process them and then I'm going to put
them back on to the free list right um
last texture up next equals first free
that chains it on and then texture has
first yes so that changed it on right
okay we go so this is gonna be a DQ and
this is gonna be like an MQ free alright
now what you'll notice about these is
they really want to work with up for
head and tail right they want to first
and last and so what I'd like to do is
introduce the concept here that those
are sort of first class citizens write
struct texture op list right
those are the pending operations they
look like that then these operations
here actually return a list right so
that not quite correct hold on one
second so when we DQ and we'll call this
DQ pending right we pass the texture up
Q that we're talking about or I guess
sorry renderer texture Q and what that
does is it first takes the mutex then it
extracts exactly what we just said we
want it so result well actually it
literally just does this result equals Q
pending right and then Q pending was
first equals zero cubed pending last
equals zero and now it's good to go okay
so we extract the list and then we clear
the list then we're done so we release
the mutex and let someone else have a
party now the exact a sort of opposite
process putting a list on is the thing
we need here so we need an NQ free this
is going to take the queue that we're
putting the free list on and then we're
gonna take the list in question right
again first things first take the mutex
so no one will accidentally update this
while we are updating it mm-hmm
and keep in mind there's different ways
you can do these sorts of things right
there's weight free ways of doing them
where you never actually take a mutex a
lot of times that's not really worth it
if you only had taken mutex for like
three or four cycles or something you
don't have to maybe think about it quite
that hard if you're gonna take a mutex
for a really long time sometimes you do
have thing about that art or if it's
heavily contended
those that's really not the situation
here so I don't suspect we will ever
have to care so usually the safest thing
to do at that point is just use a nice
ticketed mutex be simple about it
because then you're not going to
introduce subtle bugs that are very hard
to find so when you're doing something
very simple like this it's usually best
to start off with a simple ticketing
scheme and then if you really find you
need to do something much more clever
you can look at that later on all right
um
so coming through here we then have the
the free the free is going to do the
operations that exactly say my purchase
that we're doing before what we want to
do is first take the lists the last
thing in the lists next parameter and
put whatever was currently on the free
list chained off of that like so then
what we want to do is take whatever the
the last pointer actually is oh sorry
whatever the first pointer actually was
that one that we've just set with the
one that we just sort of chained on to
we want that to now point to our head
because that's the new first part of the
list right now obviously if someone
tells us to include has nothing on it we
don't want to even take the mutex right
not only do we not want to do this
because we would crash because we'd be
looking at the last pointer which we
don't want to do but we actually don't
even we don't really want to do anything
right and I'll actually just use last
time here that's the thing we would hit
so in queueing free just does this DQ
pending just does this we could check to
see if the queue pending first actually
was nonzero before entering here it's a
slight optimisation it doesn't it's not
perfect because until you take the mutex
you don't know if someone else going to
override it so I'd rather just do it on
the mutex to avoid possible
miscommunication between folks
mm-hmm so I'm just gonna leave it like
this so now we've got kind of a cleaner
a nice clean looking version of this
here are our pending opps we just say DQ
pending on our queue we then say if the
pending well we don't even really need
to do that I mean this is what we want
right we just say all right loop over
all of them do them and then when we're
done this list is the free list now
right done and so that looks really nice
because now everybody who wants to use
these in any renderer who needs to
process a texture queue like that can
just use these so the D 3d render could
use this software renderer could use
this and it all would just be fine right
so that's you know why I want to pull
that part out so that it makes a little
bit more sense all right so let's go
ahead and clean up the parts that will
now be a little bit broken because we
did that what does that doesn't does it
not know that is what is the problem
identify enough found
I just need to tell you about it ahead
of time because I can do that there we
go
okay so now we get to the part where
we're actually trying to push an op on
here we have taken the mutex at that
point and looks like everything here is
pretty straightforward so all we really
want to do here is say okay this stuff
that used to be linking this on here
this is really just now off of that
pending list but everything else it's
the same code we haven't changed any of
how it works right
Oh No why we left that on there all
right um
DQ pending did I mess up the cut and
paste is that not getting included for
some reason who is who's complaining
first of all because I thought these
were now included and maybe they aren't
I guess this is not included by the
win32 layer anymore which I guess makes
sense there's nothing in else in here
that it actually needed so I'm not sure
how I want to deal with that I mean one
way I could deal with that I suppose is
just pushing them up here I'm not sure
how I how much I really like that but
it's eminently doable but point being
now if I'm gonna just double check to
make sure that we're still running okay
on win32 handmade so those textures I
want to still make sure they're uploaded
oh man and the answer is no oh
we're not we're not initializing it I
still didn't do the thing that I said I
need to do so the last thing we need to
do is actually have that initializer
occur right so the texture op Q is
actually down here right this thing that
initializes the Q also has to be you
know something that that can operate in
here so we need this to initialize the
texture cube and yeah like I don't know
there's any particular reason just
looking at it basically when we emit
open gel it could just call this I'm
thinking if we just do it like that
really what we need here is just some
way of allocating things right and so
when we initialize the texture queue I
suppose what I could do is you pass in
the texture op count and you pass in the
memory and then it would just string
them together for you so you would do
something like this
[Music]
you would do something like this and
then you would say that the yeah that's
the texture cue so has however many
texture operations you would like it to
have and has those from here I think
that's roughly what we're talking about
now right and I'm I'm not 100% on board
with that quite yet so there's a little
bit more than I probably want to do in
terms of how that is actually pulled out
what's going on here texture up count
wise I've waited from that cut and paste
thinking but before I finish I've got to
actually make this thing be back the way
it started so here when we have the
first free it's always thinking about
that as having being initialized to the
texture upper right so I just gotta set
that initial pointer so that's I'm not
sure how I feel about I'm not sure how I
feel about that
I'm gonna leave it that way temporarily
but there's some things that I don't
love about the way that would work and
so I'm probably gonna revisit that when
we actually go to do a cleanup pass on
how we want initialization to work I
just I'm not I'm not a hundred percent
sure how I want to do that but point
being this code can now be executed in
here as well right so we can say how
many texture ups we want we can get
ourselves a texture cube and oops
initialize it to allocate memory yet
so we can initialize our own texture
queue in here now and we can also call
the thing that actually processes the
textures so we can also if we want to
bake that into the OpenGL render
commands it could just choose to do it I
don't know like how we want to look at
that and that's again when we clean up
the API we can decide what we really
want to do there cuz I don't necessarily
know what we want to do there and you
know it might be just simpler for the
user if just you call one thing and that
launches your texture uploads you lose a
little bit of ability to to do that
elsewhere but you know whatever um so
anyway as you can see not a big deal it
just works and off we go
and so now really what we need to do is
start thinking about how we're actually
gonna texture these cubes and giving the
user maybe some more ability to control
like how they place things onto cubes
because that would be something that you
would want to do I don't know how much
we'll use of that I'm hand made here
because we could probably just use one
we could probably just use one very
simple tiling method and just have all
of our bitmaps conform to it but who
knows maybe we would want something
fancier than that - I don't know so you
know let's let's just go ahead and and
do a little bit more here I'm gonna drop
in the art directory take a look at what
we've got so we've got a forest block
there that maybe maybe I might want to
drop in there and I'm just gonna grab
like one of them trees these are orphans
is not what I wanted I know there's some
trees in your summer so those are the
grasses yeah so so
so let's grab one of these and like this
this like poofy tree this like poufy
tree here kind of looks a little bit
like sort of the thing that was in the
other one like that's reasonably close
so I'm just going to grab it with with
the magical crop tool that I was having
trouble finding before and then what I'm
going to do is miss Gail it I'm gonna
scale it down to 512 on its longest
dimension and then I'm gonna set the
canvas size to 512 so that it's 512 in
and then just has a bunch of empty space
around it right
although actually I think about it we
probably don't want to do that I'm gonna
take that back I'm actually gonna keep
this tightly bounded and I'm gonna
export it as it is we'll talk about that
later
so I'm gonna go into the data directory
here in renderer test I'm gonna call
this tree test dot BMP there we go
I'm gonna open hmm
I think it's block forest so I'm gonna
open block forest and I'm gonna export
that as well
and we'll just call that something like
that
yeah um and just looking here so this
will be like tests right head test
sprite tree test right and then I'm just
gonna try throwing those in there
not that's that's really all we're
talking about uh so I'm going to close
this down and that down and then I'm
just gonna load these bitmaps so if you
look at this what we want to do here
know why open render test age when we do
a load BMP we really don't want to load
a BMP for any reason what I actually
want to do is just get a texture right I
don't care about loading a bitmap I care
about loading a texture right
and so what I'd rather do here is just
be able to say like get do this every
time you know so that's what I'm gonna
do and I'm gonna say that we then have
like a renderer texture that is the cube
texture and that's like test I don't
know what I call that test cube grass
right so there's our and I'll call this
grass texture let's say
so assuming that we've got a test cube
grass we call in there and and and you
know who knows whatever happens happens
uh what I need to do now is I need to
actually have some place to store this
now remember this is a write back
situation so I can't just do this
because nothing will happen now I could
if I forced a texture management op to
happen right here but maybe I don't want
to do that right it's hard to say
whether I do or I don't you know you
could put this right here and then that
would submit it and this would be
correct
and again we'll have to play with how we
think we want that to go it's nice that
you can do that but you don't want to
have to and so like I could probably
demo both versions but anyway um so if I
go ahead and compile this now so in here
about what we want to do is get the
result we're gonna use and change loaded
bitmap here to render or texture
ah yeah so now we've got our our ground
with the with like the grass texture on
it or whatever right and the only thing
that's a little bit so there's there's a
few things about it but the only thing
that's a little bit like janky now is we
don't really have the mapping on the
cube so it doesn't really make it's like
totally doesn't make any sense right um
so what we want to do is probably you
know make that mapping make a little bit
more sense but then we want to start
sticking like some sprites on it so I'm
gonna do the sprite part first because
that's getting the rest of the API calls
in there which is what I was kind of
trying to go for there and so I need to
load like that tree test bright tree
sooo if I load the tree in here and I've
got this tree texture I can now pass
that tree texture here
and what I want to do is inside here
occasionally I want to put a tree in so
I don't know like how I should really
put a tree and we probably want to make
something a little smarter than this but
I'm just gonna do a rant choice here so
basically like if you know R and mod 10
equals 3 because it rhymes with tree
every 10th Square will put a tree in
there right and then it can exact the
number 10 up to whatever we end up
actually wanted in terms of sparseness
of our tree right not not rocket science
here and so then I can go into renderer
and look at the push bitmap call um
bitmap is in here somewhere right well I
thought it was volume at lying
push rekt no not push rekt push quad so
I guess the only place we actually have
that at the moment is an asset rendering
rights this thing
and so when we actually push the bitmap
on this is the code that actually does
that right and what this stuff mate is
probably wants to be part of the
renderer proper right all of this stuff
so I kind of feel like what we want to
do here is pass the like have a way of
doing this call that doesn't rely on
knowing a particular format for a bitmap
so something that has all of the
contents that you would want here right
so we've got kind of different ways of
doing the transform of the object and
all that stuff I think that's what we
want so let's suppose that we were going
to do that here how would we go about it
so inside the renderer we need a call
now when we push things we need a call
that subsidy does this but that doesn't
rely on a specific data layout to get
there right so in here we would need a
thing that says I'm gonna give you a
renderer texture and I'm gonna give you
all of the information that you would
have needed in this case to produce you
know whatever we're gonna do here right
yeah and so that's a pretty big package
of information like there's a lot of
stuff that has to go into that so for
example we've got the the UV information
here
oh and there's the like weird sort of
one texture okay so if you look at
what's happening there that's actually
shrinking the UV by one that's a if you
remember what that's from that's from a
very old school thing where we wanted
our textures to have an additional one
pixel border that you could fetch
outside of 4pi linear we don't have to
do that anymore because the software
renderer now gets an upload step so what
that upload step could actually do is
move the texture into a bordered region
because that's the prep it needs to do
that's its texture upload which is what
I would prefer because we don't really
want to be doing a one texel shrink on
our bitmaps
at least not for any reason that I could
think of offhand
I'll have to think about that some more
if there's anything that we want that if
there's any reason we want that anymore
if we look at the rest of what's going
on here I think what we can actually see
is that if you look at the dim it's just
the size and the basis P are the only
things that are getting used from there
right so I want to look at at that get
bitmap Tim where is where is that
defined so we've got basis PE size
aligned and P and here it looks like we
only use size and basis P is the only
things we're actually using that min P
is used is it not yeah um so we need to
pass in the basis P and the size but
then we would be able to get rid of this
right so at that point the only thing we
really have a problem with is this which
is we need to know the basically the
texture coordinates for this thing
but I kind of feel like passing that in
perhaps
um so I have a lot of things to say
about this the first is that I don't
think that upright should be a property
of the object transform I feel like it
should be a property of a sprite so I
feel like it should be more like into
this you know I'm saying to you and I
feel like I want to move away from the
notion that the object transform is the
thing that has the upright flag in it
looking at and this is again part of
that render cleanup that I'm kind of
glad we're doing now because just a lot
of stuff that accretes over time in here
and a lot of it we don't really need to
worry about anymore um so basically when
we look at this like we're just talking
about a scale and an offset I and I
really don't know if that is the object
transform could probably just go away
the camera transform does everything we
really need and I think like the object
transform it's it's probably just not
necessary anymore
so I kind of feel like yeah I kind of
feel like what I want to do is I want to
have this assumed you know like that
maybe the size gets passed in so we
assume you took care of your aspect
ratio scaling however you wanted right
the width and the height are a little
bit tricky here because they get used
here but I'm just gonna say that maybe
the men UV and Max UV are passed into
like this and then this goes away all of
this stays the same
yet all of that is all fine the upright
flag is passed in this is all sane
so this dimmed up basis P that's just
the actual position that right
it's the min P right and we could
construct it in different ways I don't
know if like how exactly if we want to
do basis point and we come out from it
we probably do so you probably want to
do like P and size and then like you
know maybe it's like ground point and we
construct it up from there I'm not
totally sure like how what the best
construction is but we'll talk about
that in a second so if we do that then
the min P would just be like whatever
the ground point is we would just need
to move to the side a lot like along the
x axis right and in fact we've already
got the size factored in there so if we
just said look the location of this
thing on the side is just you go
backwards from you just go backwards
along the x axis halfway because it's
already been scaled to however big the
thing should be that seems doable right
and we'd have a negative 0.5 F y axis in
here if we wanted to move it down the
other way I don't know if that's quite
right yet we can talk about that and
debate a little bit later but for now
that's fine I think
so then just grabbing this out and
looking what's actually coming in here
object transform is not a thing right
height is not a thing oops offset is
also not a thing and so we're really
just left with this seal line also not
relevant so just looking at it we would
then say like okay I want to pass this
texture and draw this right I'm gonna
tell you whether it's upright or not I'm
gonna tell you where to place it how big
it is what part of the texture to use
and then if I want it to be colored or -
if I want to skew like differently you
know then then it normally would or
something um so let's suppose that I
create this function don't ask me why
that's there what does this ground P is
supposed to I don't know why that was
marked as a - um so in this case our
height is really just going to be the
size Y as far as I know but I guess I
don't know if size Y is adult 'red in
some way like let's take a look and see
if it was don't want to make that
assumption if we tuned it differently
it's no it's it's just sighs Y so that's
that's all it was
anyway so that's just fine
there's our texture and we're done
so now if I want to push a sprite on
here what I can do is say in our render
test let's put a sprite into the worlds
here's our tree texture it is upright
the ground P is just the P right it's
just the place where we put this thing I
don't know how we're doing our cubes at
the moment again
ap I pass very needed and we can because
I don't know is that the center or is
that the top we had for a while been
dozing the top I want to clear all that
stuff out and have a like a coherent
idea of how we're doing that stuff I
think that'll feel so good if we do it
but anyway so I'm going to say zero zero
to one one right now for the UVs
on that guy in terms of the size hmm
I have no idea how big I want this thing
to be so for the moment I'm just gonna
say like okay let's suppose it's like I
don't know
five F wide and what if tall I don't
know that's gonna be the color and
actually the color on the axes we don't
really care about the moment so that's
just we're just gonna push the sprite
that way I don't like the fact that I'm
not seeing anything suffice to say also
let me just do this every time just do
it so we can see as much as we can see
it yeah so let's go ahead and step into
push right there and see what we're
computing
so our min UV and our max UV look good
to me in X min Y then X or max X X Y
that looks pretty good actually um so
what's the problem why shouldn't we be
seeing something are we here's a
question are we just am I wrong about
where how the how the cubes are aligned
is that there's a ground point actually
to be elevated up are we just like
inside our cube okay so that was the
problem we were just inside the cube so
to produce the ground point here we need
to go up to the top of the cube so for a
ground P it's actually P plus whatever
that this dimension is right so there's
like an H value here that's the height
of this cube it's actually the radius so
let's call it that so we need to go up
by the Z radius another way to do that
would just be say let's pop the Z by the
Z radius and then once we have that
ground P guess I should do it this way
because I want to actually write a
closed form okay um so then we'll just
say okay that's the actual point on the
ground and off we go
yeah okay so the thing is about that
it looks like they're not centered which
doesn't make much sense to me I wonder
if I screwed something up how let me let
me look at this it looks like the that
it's not properly centered whereas this
should do that I in in theory right uh
so no that's not actually true so this
is doing this the wrong way around
so because the sprite is always facing
us if we're gonna do a span out like
that the span out has to happen after
we've adjusted the axes right so we
actually if we are going to do a min P
here we have to actually first figure
out what the axis of the sprite actually
are and then we could use them I believe
yeah and now you can see that there
correctly stationed in the middle of the
cube which is where they should be
right so probably a little too small
there you know certainly doesn't seem
like a particularly majestic oak you
know for if we're being honest about
about it so this is probably you know
more like that or something I don't know
so we're really probably looking at
something more like this seems about
right
so if we want to I guess the other thing
we probably should do is so if you're
doing a game like this you probably
don't want to rotate the camera cause
lawyer arts gonna look kind of crappy so
what I should probably do is just move
the camera which would give a better
illusion of probably roughly what it
would look like because you know if the
tree is just a sprite stuck on there it
just kinda looks weird when you spin it
around right so I'm guessing that
changing the orbit is probably the wrong
thing to do
changing the offset is probably more
what we should be doing um so rather
than doing this I guess what I'd say is
maybe we have an accumulator here
that's like camera shift or T C camera
shift and what I'm going to do is I'm
just gonna add second little apps to it
and then what I want to do here is you
know when we come through and we're
gonna compute the camera offset I'm
going to go ahead and compute that sort
of based on the camera shifts so if T
camera shift is greater than pi
or tau or who cares all those things are
dumb I have a long rant about PI and tau
that I haven't actually posted yet but
like I realized that PI and tau are
actually really dumb and like the fact
that we still use them as dumb and I
felt dumb for doing it after I actually
thought it through but that's separate
issue anyway so camera offset is now
going to take that key camera shift and
I'm just gonna say let's shift the
camera around where we're looking by
like something that's like a sine cosine
kind of a function right so you know
maybe we do like a
cosine F kind of a situation here it
doesn't really matter to kind of move
around the field and then we can just
say oh it's gonna displace it by like
roughly 10 meters either way or
something so we can kind of see the
whole area or something like that
I don't know I don't really care are we
not using camera offset you're not using
camera offset why are we using camera
I'll set well presumably we have a
translate don't we
actually enough to do so I want do it
afterwards
oh it's already doing that by camera ot
it's already right there
so nevermind we don't need to do that
separately um so this seems like a
better test right
and so I'd want to buy us it a little
bit I also don't want to get nauseous
so let's you know maybe calm that down
considerably and and I just want to now
make it so that like whatever we're
doing here is you know just shift it a
little bit so like you know we got
cosine sine that Y translation I want to
be like biased backwards like a bit
because you can see further forwards
than you can backwards and so we're just
kind of covering terrain that we don't
act ok maybe not quite that far
Oh cuz it's times 10
oops
um so yeah just looking at this real
quick sorry
all right so the only thing I really
want to do here is just give us a little
more coverage I'm gonna make this oops
I'm gonna make this a 30 or 25 just to
get us a little more coverage also those
trees are still too small
so yeah
um the other thing I want to do here is
I would like to I feel like the I still
feel like the trees are not quite pegged
to the center which maybe would be what
you would expect because of how they're
grounded but I have to think about that
this is the align point problem and I'm
not sure exactly we'll have to think
about that a little bit bit a little bit
more but so anyway let's let's focus on
one more thing now which is when we do a
push cube I'd like to now get the
texturing correct on the push cube call
so if we come in here and we look at
push cube when we're actually doing this
what I want here is some way of being
more explicit about the texture
coordinates so what you can see
happening is there's literally nothing
smart happening with the texture
coordinates at all they're just kind of
slapped on there what I actually need to
have happen here is when you do a push
cube we need to have the texture
coordinates make some sense now I don't
really know how I want to do that
because I haven't really thought through
how we want to put those on there when
we look at how these are getting set up
to 0 1 2 3 that's like totally wrong you
know so we're looking here we've got our
quads like negative X plus X negative y
plus y negative Z plus Z I actually kind
of want those things to be picked out of
the texture in some kind of sane way and
you can kind of see how I did it here
there's like a bottom row and a top row
and then a midsection area and so I
think what I want to do is just texture
them with just that first row at the
moment just as a start right
and so what I want to do here is
basically have like zero zero you know
we can we can even do it this way right
so that would be one set of T like that
would be top right let's imagine we have
three of these so that that would be top
this would be a wall piece not quite so
let me rephrase that
so this part is actually still this part
never changes kind of got overzealous
there it's just this part that changes
and this would be a bottom right so just
picking out those three segments of that
and so you know this this and this are
sort of like the I don't know what you
want to call it a top T zero like mid
and bot and so like the negative Z side
I think you could just do this and the
positive z side I think you can just do
this I think and then these you know
these are mids but they're probably not
going the right way round meaning it's
probably not t 0 through T 3 and so
we're gonna have to fix that
the texture is gonna be spun wrong does
that make sense if we do it that way
so let me just look at what we've got
here
am I do I not understand what negative Z
means in this case and positive z
did I do something stupid because the
top part should not be the brown part Oh
in less I flipped those two so negative
Z should be pointing downward so it
should have been the Bott part oh but
these are top the texture zero is the
base of the texture one is the top of
the texture so assuming we load them in
in that orientation then this is
actually backwards I agree this would be
the bottom but the way we've got them
packed in there
so never mind so Brown is what we should
have seen hopefully now we will see
green and we do so yeah
so I think that's mostly what we want
there and again like the location of the
tree is roughly correct but it's a
little weird and I'm not sure why so I
kind of want to investigate that
placement that's bright placement we do
need a to sort of shift the tree
backward a little bit because of the way
that it's drawn right you want it to be
pushed more towards the front but I
don't think that that shouldn't account
for the what's happening on the sides of
the sprite so that I'm I'm just not
quite sure about how we want that to
really be set up and we kind of looked
at this before it has to do with how you
take the tree and produce the
coordinates
for it I mean either/or it's fine
like this is something we want to work
out for handmade here anyway so I'm
happy to kind of go down that rabbit
hole afterwards to make sure that we get
our placement on the ground correct
that's fine with me but it was just I'm
just trying to think of it was a little
bit weird there um so I also kind of
want to do I want to do a couple other
things here let's and let's look at
those so the other things that I would
like to do is I'd like to put in a
Krampus head somewhere so I'm gonna go
ahead and push a Krampus head sprite on
here so I want like this to be grass
texture I want the grass texture wall
texture tree texture and head texture I
just want to get those in here and I
would like to do some kind of thing
where we pick maybe which kind these are
to select maybe do a Rand mod 10 equals
three here as well equals wall nothing
really rhymes with wall that's a number
so what I'd like to do is also have one
that pushes a walls on occasionally and
so for pushing it on a wall instead of a
grass well you know what we could just
put them on top that seems fine too so
like maybe we do something more like
this and so we have like a wall P kind
of thing and the wall is you know higher
than that so we just kind of put it up
so we go like whatever the ground P is
we start there and we go up half the
radius of our wall texture right this is
our Krampus and I don't know where
cramps is gonna go probably right in the
middle
Krampus can be floating three units up
and be quite large because I mean these
Krampus don't screw with Krampus
everyone knows that it's just basic
stuff I don't feel the need to elaborate
further
so tree texture head texture
those the names test cube grass test
cube grass tes cue ball test sprite head
test right trees so that loads all four
of those in oh and I got to actually go
use the correct one for the walls
they're also where is Krampus there's
Grampus
I think oh that's good
Krampus needs to be a little further
forward that's put him like one or two
units forward this wall texture is
somehow still getting the grounds
because well because I passed the wrong
one so kind of what you would expect
looks like we're getting some z-fighting
there so I must have computed where
these are placed it wrong how did what
did I do
how did that happen these two things
must be like overlapping so the ground P
it's gone up by the radius
oh it's radius right not total dimension
so whatever this is so this is like wall
radius equals two or something then we
need to go up by the wall radius
so I think we're pretty good there you
can see what happens if you put a wall
like the trees I think need to be bent
more backwards in this perspective you
know what I mean because they don't
really super work when you have actual
geometry in there now granted maybe
that's just something you have right
because the tree is is way too flat down
like it needs to be like kind of I don't
know what the word is but it needs to be
like more eccentric so if you were to
look at what the push right was gonna do
here right so this loop where you kind
of go between these two
you know it would need to just be it
would need to be a flatter more standing
up thing in order to not have that
problem and not sure what you would
really do otherwise to fix it I don't
think there's really much you could do
right I mean cuz you can't yeah but the
Z bias in this case also I mean I don't
know how we want to look at this part
but the Z bias in that case also does
kind of work I think for solving some of
these problems if you allow the Z bias
to be more dramatic you can kind of see
that it doesn't kick in to get really
close as far as things bending up
towards the camera so if you wanted to
make things that we're gonna be you know
not too bad as far as the wall radius
was concerned but you constantly get the
same problem this is mixing 3d and 2d in
this way is just really difficult
because art wise it's hard to pick
things that actually are going to work
okay if you actually allow there to be
the 3d transform instead of just
sticking with a required isometric right
because as those things come more
towards the camera you end up in bad
shape
right and you can kind of see you know
if you now it's kind of correctly
occluding them in most cases right not
all cases but most cases and theirs does
really some other things we could do
there again to continue to increase the
ability for us to sort these things into
place even when they sort correctly
though you can kind of see because
they're so rigid in that sense they
don't really look right even when
they're sorted correctly so I kind of
feel like they need more of the they
need to take more of the transform there
so I'm curious suppose we were literally
going to let's just play with this since
we have an easy case here so let's
suppose we just took the actual axes as
they existed and just used those right
so let's look at what we got here so in
here we have our x-axis and our y-axis
this would be the actual it would be it
would be these two right so if we were
to say in fact I guess I don't need to
if 0 anything if we were just to say
look let's see at a certain at this
perspective right what does it look like
if the trees are just billboards right
and so what you can see here is first of
all you know you could turn off the Z
bias and it should now just work because
they're just literally standing in place
right and you get some Z fighting if
they're right on top of each other but
that's exactly what you'd expect right
because there's no way to resolve those
two you need them to be a little bit
separated in order to know which one it
should be right but now everything slots
into place the problem is they look way
too like cardboard cutout you know what
I mean but they're always correct right
they always look prospectively correct
and they always look like reasonable in
terms of being sorted into the scene and
we stopped kind of using anything but
the Z for that we had a version before
where we were kind of doing a different
sort of lerp I'm interested to know what
that looks like
I don't really remember let's play with
it a little and see here
so that's one that kind of combines the
two together honestly I think for this
perspective that looks really good
actually right I mean I think that's
about as good as you could have hoped
for I'm not sure you yeah I I really
think that looks quite nice for this
perspective right and if we maybe then
at that point crank the Z bias just a
little bit maybe we get to something
pretty usable for what the request was
you know maybe we do maybe we don't I
don't know like normally you're not
gonna like you know your artist too can
make concessions for the fact that we
know that you know you're not gonna put
stuff self-intersecting like you
wouldn't put a tree like right next to a
wall hopefully in that exact way and if
you did maybe we could say set a flag on
it so we know that it's supposed to do
more so that one looks wrong right those
those don't look right when they're
right next to it
unfortunately these look just fine so as
soon as you can if you can get one
degree of space between them it looks
quite nice
so the other thing I'm adjusting is so
as you set the orbit you obviously get
much better if as you get closer to side
on everything would presumably just work
perfectly right because then the sorting
is just it's just correct like you can
just use the 3d right so if for example
you were to say camera pitch equals you
know maybe I don't know how much of pie
we want in here
but once you get down here like you're
just golden because everything always
just sorts properly right so somewhere
in between those two is where the
problem happens and maybe part of its to
like if you were gonna do a game that's
down at this angle maybe part of it is
like picking a reasonable you know just
a reasonable degree of sort of that that
split let me
let me take this a little so you know
maybe you you pick a higher on angle and
maybe you you buy us a little bit more
towards the incorrect axes or I should
say bias more towards the correct axes
in that case
so let's shoot for that let's use this I
like this so far that seems pretty good
I'm getting rid of this stuff
how much time you got left like about 10
minutes
so that's pretty good
the only thing I would say is that the
the amount of perspective that ends up
on the trees when they're down here just
kind of doesn't work very well I'm not
100% sure how I would fix that
and I wonder too a little bit about if
we want the focal length to be different
so that you don't get as much
perspective in this case so like let's
suppose we want to change the focal
length there and and just tweak that a
little bit I'm gonna go ahead and play
with that so yeah there's camera dot
focal length so when we knit the camera
params we're passing the focal length
down just kind of as like a magical
thing I'm gonna make that be like camera
focal length length
it was 1.0 I'm gonna play with that a
little bit and just see what I think
four different lengths here so let's
suppose we crank it up to something like
four so there's a lot less perspective
right so you could see how much less
there is there right and then I i'll
pull back we'll get rid of the fog tempo
just temporarily
and that's because we don't have the
ability to control it currently and so
that's we need to do as an improvement
to the API anyway so if we look at fog
being off and then we just pull the
camera back much further than it was so
the camera dolly is you know more like
you know 40 or something here so we pull
back use a much longer focal length lens
so what you can see there is it gets a
lot closer to isometric right so we can
control the level of eccentricity that
we get when we look at that at that
transform and so we can sort of pick how
much of that we want to go into our
render and I feel like that's pretty
good so let's suppose we play with this
a little bit and just get something a
little less drastic right kind of figure
out where the sweet spot is here I don't
really know so let's suppose we get
something a little less drastic like
that and then we can tilt the camera a
little more right which increases our
ability to be accurate
we can also lower ourselves down a
little more right we can we can keep
that but shift so instead of doing only
the bevel we can actually push ourselves
down slightly so we can we can actually
have a camera offset shift in there so
like in here we could just artificially
drop ourselves down so this this camera
drop shift here
we can choose to like I don't know how
much we should
okay that's obviously not good what
happened there oh that times 10 gets me
every time gets me every time
mr. not gonna do that
so that drop shift is just going to be
you know put us down closer to the
ground but leave the same angle you know
I'm saying
so there everything seems to be stacking
really nicely like I don't see a lot of
errors in that you know you can't stick
a tree inside a wall anyway so that
doesn't bother me at all you also can't
have two trees like that are exact same
plane so a little bit of jitter in your
placement of trees would fix it even if
you wanted to stick them too close to
right next to each other like that would
be fine still and you just can't put a
tree that close to a wall that such it
would stick into it but other than that
right you're fine so I feel like that's
pretty good
so the last thing we do here is just
maybe try to clean this up a little bit
so what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna make a
little thing that's like do we have in
our renderer test code here we have a
seat in each file we don't um so I'm
gonna make an H file I'm just gonna go
ahead and into that H file I'm gonna put
this stuff
and then all I'm going to do here is
just make a thing that's like just test
the scene and all it's going to do is
just have in it so this stuff here I'm
just gonna I'm just gonna put like this
information into an actual like encoding
right so I'm just gonna say enum test
scene element and I'm just gonna say
grass tree wall that's it animus a test
scene element elements and I'm gonna say
like
whatever these things were here so
alright the it's like 40 wide and 50
long or something right so looks
something like that and so in here I'm
just gonna actually and I'll put in a
little like min p-value so that's where
things start and then everything kind of
works off of that right so if I want to
know I can say internal void in it test
scene and cure you would just pass test
scene scene and what that will do is say
okay the min P is just whatever the test
scene Dimension X is right so however
big it is and I we don't care right so
however big it is I want half of that
backwards right I want to go backwards
by half of that I want to go backwards
by half of whatever the test seemed in Y
is and then I don't bother offsetting
the Z okay
furthermore I can actually make the grid
cell radius I could say so you know LM
radius or something like this right
so I could take the element radius as
well the element radius is the thing
that would tell me like where things are
so for example here where I'm saying
like oh where here's the position of the
thing it's like X Y whatever right
although if I just leave it 1 then we
don't have to do that
nevermind so let's just do that let's
just assume the position is always X y
plus the whatever the minutes so if we
just say seeing min P plus whatever the
X is that seems that's better let's just
do that this is just a test it's fine so
that seems fine to me and then that way
we can just say like okay here's the
test scene right and I can stick this
stuff in here
so that way things are a little clearer
it's obvious what's going on
and now all I have to do is actually
iterate over these things in in a sane
way like so and I should be good to go
right okay so now what I want to do is I
actually want to set these set this up
so you know this test scene here I want
to just create that like so and
similarly I can do that in here so I can
load in the textures that we want I can
set the location of the thing that we
want in general I can go ahead and
compile now and in theory this should
still work I might have messed something
up but in theory it should still work
and then what I wanted to do was just
make it so that when we do this simple
same thing the test same thing when we
admit that simple scene so I feel like
we can just do a better job now with
this stuff so what I'll what I want to
do here is say well we always know we've
always got grass but then we can look to
see if there's a tree or if there's a
wall we do this stuff and then we'll
pick those differently so what we can
say is in here we'll look at the test
scene element and we'll say that
whatever was in this cell right the one
that we're actually talking about is the
element that we're going to use and that
way we can say if the element in
question is a tree then we draw a tree
if the element in question is a wall
then we draw a wall right
and so what should
and now is we just should get garbage so
this is just uninitialized memory
basically right and so what we want to
do is actually write because this this
is just whatever was on the stack right
so what we want to do now is actually
set all of these elements so what I want
to do is is take this thing and just mem
set it to zero right or another way to
do that would be just a force to clear
to zero back here so we could say like
that right that would clear everything
to a grass tile so now we got nothing
then what we could do is when we come in
to the unit test scene what I want to do
is just loop for a while I don't care
how many times I'm gonna say while the
wall count is less than 20 and the tree
count is less than 30 I don't know
then we do a random pick or something I
don't know in fact forget that police
random scene element tree give me 20
wall 30 whatever right you see what I'm
saying so we just have a thing here it's
like play some random things down I
don't really want to hear about it just
do it
count right so then we just see look
loop I guess I can just say while placed
equals zero placed is less than count
placed plus plus what I want to do now
just say alright let's pick a random
spot so what I want to do is I want to
take and pick two randoms an x and a y
right so the X is going to be test
seemed dim X the Y is gonna be test
seemed my long so this is going to be a
Rand mob that I'm gonna skip the outside
so there's a one cell apron and then
what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna look to
see whether everything including the
spot I'm on is free so then I'm just
gonna do like a test X equals x minus 1
test X less than equal to X test X plus
plus and here I'm literally just going
through and checking than the the 7 the
9 cells making sure that nothing is
actually in it right so clear or you
know what I'll do like occupant so we'll
just say all right if the scene elements
test Y test X has something in it then
it has an occupant if the occupants
equals 0 then we have placed the tree or
whatever we're placing
and that will make it so that we don't
place things right next to each other
which is what we were trying to avoid
right
[Music]
that's a typo and off we go right so now
in theory we should just have stuff that
is spaced out properly and we still have
some more stuff we probably want to do
there looks like we didn't place nearly
enough of these so there's that so I'll
I'll up that quotient a little bit
wait a minute what's going on how can
those two be placed next to each other
I messed something up oh yeah so don't
ask me how I forgot to type the plus one
in there but apparently I did so yeah
um so I think that's really it I mean
the other thing we could do is maybe
make a we could make some mountainous
some more like displacement here just to
make sure that's why we could do a bunch
of stuff and maybe we will but like we
can change the heights of things I think
relatively dramatically there and it
should be okay and again the main
problem I'm having right now is the
trees not being anchored white as far
down and again that's that makes sense
the we started the sprite at its bottom
right in the center but you really need
to be offset down so that's something we
kind of want to look at some more so you
know we'll we'll have to yeah we'll have
to kind of play with that a little bit
all right
and we couldn't do anything special on
till you 500 No
I also I noticed the framerate looks a
little uneven here and I'm not sure why
I would I would be interested to see
what's going on there
yeah we need to fix the we need to fix
the the winding on the on the walls I
could do that now like I remember I
mention that we're in there now the
question I think you change the meaning
of the code in the NQ free function oh I
didn't mean to could it just be me
typing too fast you are correct
so that wants to take and the cues
depending what how did I mess that up so
bad that's pretty weird
I guess I was really not paying
attention so I'm not even looking at the
right values there so what I want to do
is say look if you're going to ink you
this list then staple the what's
currently on the free list to the end of
it then set it equal to the first one
that's what it should have been thank
you somebody took my name and yet I can
go fix that UV ordering all
I'll take a look
so if we wanted to fix the UVs remember
a saying about these guys we need to
look at the mid the the mid textures so
basically it has to be t0 t0 and mid t1
need to be on the bottom and then t2 and
t3 need to be at the top so when we're
actually looking at these you can see
the way we kind of got them here p0 all
0 1 2 &amp; 3 are all along the top so the Z
the positive Z is all around the top so
p0 1 2 3 right so there they are there
so here where we've got 2 &amp; 3 those need
to be the for each of these all of the
ones that are on top which I can mark
right
I don't know what for coat is doing
there I really don't know what fur
cutter is doing I guess oh I know why
because it doesn't have the additional
thing it's trying to interpret that as
something real I just want something I
can insert here that won't cause any
problems there we go there so if you
look at which ones these are right these
are the ones that are up on top so the
ones that are up on top need to have
need to have t2 and t3 and you can see
that like this one is problem is
probably right way round because you can
see that two and three are here this one
is probably not because here's two and
three but two and three are on like six
so we need to like shift this down one
right so probably we just have to roll
it over so it's like three zero one two
so now two and three are lined up right
so in terms of this one and that's
assuming that these were bound right in
the first place which I don't know so
we'd have to check here's the top two
here two and three right here's the top
one here two and three again not quite
right so again we just kind of want to
roll it over right and so now we're at
least lined up where bottoms and tops
seem to be in roughly the right location
to each other let's find out if that's
actually true
and I should go look at the bitmap to
actually make sure that's true
so let me that looks pretty good to me
let me let me just verify that that's
what it should look like
I mean that looks pretty good to me
so I think that's correct
[Music]
Albus we did not do the texture
generation stuff today instead what we
did is we just used our existing stuff
and made sure we could do all the things
we wanted to do in terms of sprite
placement and stuff and we roughly have
there's something with the placement of
the trees we want to fix that's because
we need the sort of hot spot stuff and
it's unclear how exactly we want to roll
that in here so there's a little bit
more I want to do but basically we're
there and so we can do the texture the
texture generation of stuff we will do
tomorrow I mean not tomorrow next
weekend
are we done with the renderer or will be
maintained both versions I'm not sure
evening by the render but we will
maintain the the software renderer
ventually it just doesn't have some of
the features at the moment so we don't
run it but I'm actually you know what
could you be more specific I'm not sure
what you mean
Hemet here we'll be using that a coupled
runner it already is right we only have
one render now it's that a coupled
version and both handmade hero and this
standalone version now use it
would be helpful in this situation to
use the old-school billboards that are 2
or 3 sprites in a plus or X shape I've
never found those to look particularly
good for something like the tree I feel
like what you could do is make each of
the bulbs have a little maybe more maybe
do that for the bulbs I don't know about
the base I mean I don't know like this
is this is an artistic decision at some
level you know it's not really technical
the technical solution is to do
everything in 3d right the artistic part
is like how do you want to express the
2d with 3d pieces like how are you gonna
do that you know and I don't know like
you got a lot of options our renderer
could trivially support any of them but
the question is like which ones so all I
was saying is like if you were to take
these and stagger the sprites a little
bit more so you had like the different
pom-poms kind of spaced out I think that
might help to potentially but again it's
just artistic questions like who knows
Fillie dusky oh no we're using the
decoupled version yeah we only have
we're only just running just one version
of the renderer handmade hero uses it
and this other project will potentially
use it or not
I'm also not sure I think cuz we rely on
some optimizations there I should also
point out that I think we probably want
to do that I don't really know how much
we would be bogging things down possibly
not at all but I do know that some of
our code has some slow paths in it if
you don't actually have speed
compilation on so if you too much to
attach the profiling stuff to just see
the FPS I would not do that but we can
dump our FPS pretty easily so if you
want to see that we have in here the
second celeste so what we can do is we
can do and output debug string so I
could do
right so we can prepare a little string
here and dump it and when we do that if
we look at the outputs it'll come out
here so what we can do is we can just
take sort of a min/max average kind of
approach there where we can just keep
track of it so second so if we do
seconds per frame I can do like a min
SPF
max SPF and an average of SP well
actually I'm just gonna do min max so if
we do min max here what I can do is just
say like look every time we come through
here I'm gonna look and say the mean SPF
equals the minimum of the ministry and
the second Celeste and the max SPF
equals the maximum right so we'll keep
track of that and then you know every so
often
how about every five seconds something
like that I don't know I have no idea
we probably want that to be more than
that precision but for right now we're
just going to do it that way well you
know what no I could do this let's do
point O to F right and then I'll do is
I'll just multiply by a thousand them in
SP I'm sorry / no multiplied by a
thousand and that should give us
something uh do we did we not include
that I thought we had a min minimum
where are those oats and hand-made
shared at which we did not include so
I'll do it the old-school way
so we're just keep whatever our quickest
frame time and our slowest frame time
work
and then when we look at the output it
should just periodically tell us every
time we've done a certain number of
frames that doesn't look right at all
it's because of the test right
that is not really the max that was cuz
I was dragging and I'm assuming here you
can see we don't hit 60 frames a second
consistently I don't actually know but
that's from but I'm guessing it's
because of our texture changes the fact
the one thing that I really wanted to
fix right because I'm assuming and I
don't know but I'm assuming if we just
didn't have as many things in the scene
so let's suppose we did something like
this I'm assuming we would just be 60
frames second because I'm assuming that
we just have too many texture changes I
don't really know oh we have to have
enough room for the thing to actually
sprinkle all of its sort of stuff in
unfortunately so I'm assuming that like
again that the fixing the texture change
is not a wasted thing like we need to do
that it will make a big difference I
think but we'll see
it's still not perfect so part of it may
be also the lighting poling and stuff
like that little interesting to see one
of the nice things about having
separated renderers we can actually kind
of go to town on it a little bit as well
you can see it's sound of stabilizing
out now at about 60 frames a second and
it actually does look smoother when I
reduce the size I'm pretty sure that it
was not hitting 60
in this case you can also test its
sensitivity to fill rate we can look at
that a second but so so wheat so it's
pretty easy just to get a simple France
for second counter getting more
information is harder if you don't have
a real profiling thing set up but
I did not update for a credit yesterday
so it looks like actually it is doing
fine even in this case so I don't know
maybe the texture changes aren't that
big of deal it seems like it's
stabilized out to 60 frames a second as
well so I don't know we'll see we'll see
I'm not testify right a little bit
so it seems like it's still stabilizing
up to 260 but yeah we have we wait for
the vertical reef refresh right so it
should never exceed 60 frames a second
because we specifically say wait for V
blank so you know there's that as well
why do the frames Jeff sub le when
moving the window so the reason for that
is that it's not that really that
there's a processing problem with it
it's that we don't update while it's
happening right it stops it's not that
it's take it literally just does not
update that's because of the way that
Windows handles these messages so sizing
and and dragging it actually interrupts
your thread so you don't get any more
like pumping through your message loop
right so it's not that it's spamming the
process with messages and taking too
much time or anything if that it's
literally stopping your process because
that's what it wants it's not that
process stopping your thread because
that's what it wants to do if you
instead put this on another thread it
would just keep on trucking right and
you can do that if you want to tip to
just to maybe make that a little clearer
so you know all this stuff that's
happening here right we create the
window and the windows on this thread so
when we're handling messages this thread
will stop when someone starts dragging
your window this thread will stop
because it's the thread that created
this window
that means that this loop here will stop
if we don't want that loop to stop right
because this remember doesn't do
anything so we could be fielding our
messages in some other way right all we
would have to do is start with another
thread so if we want to write inside
win32 hand-made we know how to create a
thread mm-hmm here it is right so if we
want to not have that happen all we
would really have to do is create
another thread to do the rendering right
or to do everything really and so if we
want to do that right you create a
thread here you just say how big the
stack has to be you know who knows how
big the stack has to be I don't care how
big the stack has to be well megabytes
one was fine so one megabyte stack maybe
it's a bigger than that maybe it's a 16
megabyte stack let's go hog-wild right
and in here we can just have the like
render loop or something the startup
thing is the the thing that you would
pass to it and in this case that would
probably just be the window handle I
don't know if we ever need the window
handle again we do so probably what I
would choose to pass here is actually
the window handle so instead of startup
it would do that so it's an H wind right
and then we would get that thread ID if
we need it but we don't really in this
case so what I would do here is I just
say like okay close the thread handle
when you get it back you're done here
right so then when we come out here we
would need to have a thread proc right
which is something that windows can
enter and we would cast we would say
like that window is really this LP
parameter that we got here right because
it doesn't know what we're passing but
that's what we were passing right here
and so then the rest of all this this
stuff that was happening can actually
just happen in the thread proc now this
thread proc has nothing to do with that
window at all like they are unruly
it's a thread that is just looking at
the window from afar right and so at
that point we can just move the thing in
here that actually initializes opengl
and stuff and I don't remember if we're
maybe pushing Windows a little too hard
by doing that on the outside I can't
remember I'm sorry I just I just don't
remember what its rules are about who
can initialize OpenGL from a thread and
other things like that but anyway also
this stuff has to be in there because
we're actually using it so these things
need to be sort of pushed up in here and
if we launch it onto another thread then
what will happen is that thread this
goes
once we launched that thread then we're
good to go so the only thing we need to
do now is win through two process
pending messages can't happen on this
thread because it's got to happen on the
the thread where the window is actually
hanging out right um
I think that's all we would need to do
and then our render would be chugging
along even while windows was trying to
do other junk it didn't like that Oh
nope sorry we just need a while loop
there
all right so global running now that
it's getting set in kind of a haphazard
way externally that's gonna need to be a
volatile right you're gonna have to
always rear up reread that whoever you
are but otherwise I think it's okay we
send it to truth there it is and that we
have to set it to true before anyone
starts doing anything
and so then in theory you've got a
separate thread that's just constantly
rendering right and so then at that
point like if I move my window around
you'll notice now it just it's fine
right and it doesn't affect it at all
well except for the fact that if you
shake Windows thinks you want to
minimize everything because why wouldn't
that be true similarly we can resize the
window now and it also works we get that
black repaint problem but that's just
because windows will clear it we can if
we want to also change that but then you
get a little bit deeper down the rabbit
hole so if we say that there is no
clearing which is this right here
of the window then you won't get the
clear right but I'm not sure how
reliable the black border part is seems
okay so let's call it good enough for
government work but I would investigate
that a little bit more right and so now
you can see resizing has like no effect
on the frame rate so we can just kind of
go to town with that I've started up
movement resizing on the other hand does
and the reason for that is that actually
is creating more work when we resize we
have to reset all of our OpenGL context
and like make sure all the bitmaps for
the back store or the right size and all
that stuff we could speed that up by
just making ones the size of screen and
only using smaller regions of them but
resizing even though now it still were
it works correctly it's still gonna be a
slowdown because of the way the render
is architected at the moment and the way
we're using OpenGL resources but
movement since it doesn't change the
back buffer is just fine so just
hopefully that clarified that
oh yeah if you want to know more about
volatile I would take a look which back
of the archives but all volatile does is
it tells the compiler when it's
compiling code that it is not safe to
assume that the code that is being
generated is the only code that touches
the value okay so if you look at how
this was before hand without the
volatile this was a global variable
called global running and we used it in
a loop so for there's a couple loops
right one loop was here
Wow global running and one loop was here
log Global running right and global
running could get set to false
inside this win32 process pending
messages so if the compiler really
wanted to analyze this thoroughly it
could it would determine that global
running could be set to false which
means that this loop could exit and
technically you don't have to set this
one to volatile technically this one
however it can there is no way even if
the compiler analyzed all of the
functions that are being called here it
would never see any one set global
running to false therefore technically
the compiler could conclude that this is
an infinite loop and that it can never
be set to false and it would never exit
even though global running does get set
to false why because we haven't told the
compiler that global running could be
set by some other code than the one that
you are compiling right um and so once
you have more than one thread of
execution which is what we did the
compiler now needs to be told
whenever one of those threads that is
not the one it's compiling could touch a
piece of memory that this thread that
you're actually compiling and looking at
is dependent upon
um so what that means is putting the
volatile in as a way of ensuring that
when you have two threads that are both
touching the same memory the compiler
doesn't assume that the memory is the
same as when it looked at last time it
knows every time I asked you to look and
see if global running is true or false
you actually pull the memory and you
don't assume that when you're generating
the code if you read it once you don't
have to read it again if you didn't
touch it you have to assume someone else
could touch it and again there's better
explanations that's back in the archive
where I spent more time on it Martin's
posted a good point which is that we
don't actually need to burn time here if
we want to we can actually just use the
get message now so in here where we do
win through new process messages rather
than doing this peek message we can
actually do this as a get message right
so we can do that now we can actually
put that in here
all right so now we don't really need
the skip messages stuff we don't really
need most of this now actually really
what we can do now is just do a straight
for a get message so if we want to do
that here's the get message function and
here's what it produces right so we do a
get message it gives us back a pool
that's whether I believe whether we got
one or not we have the pointer to the
message pointer to the window handle
which we don't care about we will use
any right because any one is fine and
for filtering again we don't care about
either right so we can just do zero and
zero on those so what we can do here is
NaN just loop through here the got
message when it returns if it says here
like oops if it retrieves the message
other than W quit it's nonzero if the
function retrieves I didn't quit it
returned about zero if there's an error
of the return value is negative one
which is great since it's a bool right
so that's kind of fantastic I assume
that if we get an error we should just
exit out so probably what I would say
here is like if get message is you know
greater than equal to zero kind of thing
then we do our standard processing
otherwise we'll be running equals false
always the other thing is since we knew
that quit is the thing we could just do
this probably so basically if it's quit
or an error then just stop because what
who cares we're not going to do anything
if it's not quit or an error
do this right just deal with the message
do we have a message in here you know
okay uh so yeah that's the more correct
way to do that let me get rid of that
and so then no cpu time is being spent
in this it's just sitting around waiting
for Windows to send it a message if
Windows so desires right
could you go over the extra render
thread thing briefly again please I
thought the DC is thread specific and so
the OpenGL RC has to reside within the
same thread um yeah so I think one so a
couple things remember here so it may
look like we're doing multiple threads
accessing the DC but remember that's not
actually what we did so what we did is
we created a window we have never asked
for a DC from that window
so this thread is not using that DC for
any OpenGL purposes at all right then
this secondary thread is the one that
actually binds OpenGL an OpenGL context
to the DC only on it so we're actually
only you we still only have one thread
using OpenGL on a DC okay so you're not
wrong you have to be very careful about
how you work with threads and OpenGL
contexts we're not doing that our other
thread never touches the OpenGL context
and it never tries to bind it to a DC oh
yeah that's a good point
I don't think that's gonna matter much
but yeah Martin's is always a stickler
for platform calls
I don't know the best the only thing
about that is I don't really remember
so Martin's I don't know if I agree with
you though I think really the A's don't
have to be in here do they do the A's
actually have to be in here for any
particular reason now I mean I guess
you're right we probably want to stick
with using a on everything but I think
the macros are now in here so we could
get rid of all of the a entirely right
and actually switch these two L's
because since this isn't in the handmade
hero codebase anymore we can just do the
default thing right we're bound
including windows we could just do it
which might be a little bit cleaner for
people who are looking at it who don't
know what we're doing like I wonder if
it makes more sense to nuke all of the a
stuff and just use the default you know
what I'm saying
so I agree with you that if we left all
of our other aides in there we need to
be consistent but I wonder if we should
just get rid of all of those and then
just put the L in although in this case
it looks like we're compiling and asking
mode anyway so actually you just don't
need an A anywhere right so that's
probably better if we were gonna ship
this sample code off to somebody once we
clean it up you know what I mean
without air/w depend on project settings
whether Unicode is said or not
yeah I agree well that's why I normally
do a butt
but shouldn't it sort of work like isn't
it possible or is it not possible like
is it is there any way to write the code
so that it just works I guess what you'd
have to do is like your strings the
places where you have strings would have
to be kind of wrapped in some kind of a
of a aware cast you know
look we don't have strings in hardly any
locations but there's just a few places
where we do use it so I feel like maybe
we could still use it this would have to
use like W care T right like yeah
there's really no nice way to do that
[Music]
yeah
so I mean we could say I would have to
test this so we could say is this gonna
work no that's what Martin suggested -
I'm not sure yeah I'm not sure how to
make it be okay with just like turn
these into long strings as necessary
does the text macro work I never do this
looks like it's okay with that and so
then really all we would have here is
our output debug string is it's gonna
need to have that same kind of wrapping
so the question is if you select unicode
does the stupid does the windows stupid
stuff actually change the C runtime
library over as well you know and I
don't know but that that would be my
only concern I assume the C runtime
library doesn't change over to being W
cares so it seems like you could never
really get away from having that be an a
it or calling a conversion you know are
we happy with that
all right I'm gonna wrap it up
oh and Martin's is saying well we could
testify defining Unicode yeah I could
try
seems like it worked I'm curious if we
do we should be able to break it here
though so we should be able to see that
compiled if is actually working yeah
so that's good let's see what happens
when we do output debug string here I'm
curious so yeah you can see that it
wants a wide care so I'm wondering like
can I use like a different kind of care
I don't know if what kind of care would
be what is windows so let's see like
MSDN character type pendant on the
Unicode what
so I think if I just capitalize that
maybe that's what I want I want a tea
care right and then my problem here is
that be I'm I need a sprint F that
actually sort of works there right four
wide characters but I assume that I can
if I want to actually do that as well
because I assume that if I actually ask
for like a WS printf a what you know
like a wide version or a tea sprint I
assume that windows provides that for
their stupid Unicode so I assume that if
we look at the wide version or what
would take a tea care here
so here's the version of that that I
assumed we would want is that one uses T
cares so you know when we actually go to
format it would work oh sorry
we we don't want that here actually we
want that only in the one place where we
talk to windows and their magical
awesomeness right string so you know in
here I don't know what this parameter is
supposed to be whether it's the size or
the number of characters I'm gonna
assume that it's the number of
characters because that's the one that
can't that if I was wrong I just use
half the size of the buffer and not
overrun so I'm gonna go ahead and say we
want this type of routine I don't know
where that is defined probably in like
cease well yeah I don't know where that
is
w care dot H I don't know where that's
actually defined because they didn't
bother to tell us right they're like hey
here's the T care routine not gonna tell
you where it is
so have a party right but I'll assume
that if I I'm just guessing if I
actually asked for like W care dot H or
something that it would be in there
maybe C studio
all right that's only C++
so I guess I'll have to hunt for it
let's take a look
although you know I couldn't just do a
search and see where it is
[Music]
oops
he carried out H perhaps I might just
search for it oh wait this is
complaining about something else
thank you for everyone from t care to
character star Const so really I screwed
up I I was looking at the error wrong so
this just needs to be converted as
necessary so how can I do that it's
argument one so it's not the one I was
looking at so I need this to be
convertible to care star but so that
doesn't look like it actually worked
because this got defined to the wrong
thing right because if Unicode was set
that should have been compiled to SW
print death right
so tea care is not actually doing the
right swap why do people make programs
like this is so ridiculous you can see
why I can't stand any of these sorts of
things and don't use them it's just
ridiculous that you would even spend
time on stuff like this it's so dumb
right absolutely ridiculous
so yeah I'm just not sure I'm gonna put
these into the same place we can see
them both there I'm just not sure how
this this appears to be defined wrong
because it should have taken Unicode and
done it I'm gonna look inside t care dot
H so I can see what it's actually doing
and then maybe that'll shed some light
on the subject right so if we come up
here and we add a pound include t care
dot H I'm just gonna look and see what
it does
there we go
I'm so W care T star which is what it
should have been and then a size T and
then a W care for this so I think this
just right it just needs to be wrapped
and off we go so great good fantastic
nice work
great job Microsoft as always crushing
it so that's just garbage and stupid but
now we are at least compliant with
either way that people want to compile
let me just make sure we've got that all
straightened out all right so that just
tests the Unicode miss of it all and so
let's make sure we can be non Unicode
now and we are and that's good all right
I like how they have Unicode and
underscore Unicode right like that's
it's so freaking fantastic yeah all
right so I think we're all good I'm
gonna go ahead and wrap up the stream
you can see why I always write my
platform layer and then put everything
on top of it because I mean it's just
nuts you know you're you're you're
basing all your code on top of something
that was written by but you know rank
amateurs time and it's just it's not
cool so anyway you know we're getting
there I feel like maybe I'd want to
spend one more weekend just tune in
things up here and cleaning up the
render API looking at the texture great
stuff but I'm pretty happy with this and
actually just looking at this
perspective this is kind of what I
wanted hammered here to be like
perspective wise as well probably
although maybe this is a little bit too
this is a little bit too flat on
probably we'll see we'll play with it
ourselves but it may be that this is as
good as we can get just in terms of like
allowing the art to composite well and
so we'll kind of have to see how things
shake out right I don't know like I
really don't know so I guess that's yeah
I mean I'm pretty happy with that I feel
like anyone could use this renderer to
do stuff now it's pretty straightforward
I just want to go clean up that API a
little bit and then fix the texture
arrays so that the speed is high
you know and off you go now we can also
and again you know just looking at this
if we wanted to we could put in both we
could also just look at what rotating
the camera looks like right so you know
we've got the camera shift version
that's happening here if we want to we
could instead change the orbit you know
I'm saying
so like this stuff we could have two
versions so for example we could do V 3
camera off set camera off set
something like this where we just say
all right maybe we just don't set the
offset in that case and we just use t
camera shift as the orbit value in the
other case and here we could look so
this way if someone wants to see what
happens when you rotate the camera you
can't write just in terms of whether
that's good or bad and so it looks like
in this case we kind of need to fix the
way that we're looking at the trees
x-axis though so that's like this is
pretty good like I think we want to
because we right now just assume that
we're sidon and that's just this one
little piece of of the push right call
this part here and so it would be nice
to say like oh yeah what we actually
want to do there is say that we still
want the x-axis to be what the x-axis
would be but aligned to where the
cameras facing right and then this would
be the y-axis that we're actually
talking about here actually goes along
whatever the cross product of that is
with Z up right that's really more what
we would do to support the rotation
right so it's just it's worth thinking
about that a little bit more so we
should do that I think we should do that
so I'm gonna leave it broken and we will
fix that next time because it you know
we'll see it as soon as we run right and
so I would like to go fix that because
that's it that's an easy thing to fix
and we should support the rotation even
though I don't know that anyone should
really use rotation with sprites like
that because they look kind of weird
when they're just floating there but
weak
support it so we should just in case
that's how they want to use I don't know
you know so yeah all right I'm gonna
wind it down thank you for in for
joining me for that sort of handmade
here it's been pleasure coding with you
as always if you would like to follow
the series at home you can always peer
to the game on handmade here org and it
comes to the source code so you can do
your own experimentation as you wish we
also of course have a watch page you can
use to find out what the schedule is I
post the schedule there quite a bit in
advance usually now so you know when
we're gonna be live if you want to join
the live streams and ask questions and
that sort of stuff that's the place to
do it there's also an episode guide on
there you can use to search the past
episodes of animate hero find new
information in the archives if you
hadn't seen in case there's specific
stuff you want to know about someone
asked a question about volatile today
that's where you would do it just put
volatile in the search box you will get
the places that I talked about it we
also have a hand-made here a fun page
that's if you want to support things
like that awesome episode guide they are
made by folks in the community and we
pay for them through the handmade funds
so that's a cool thing to do if you like
to use resources that are built by
people in the community that's how they
get money for them that's it for today
I'll be back here next week
I suspect although I haven't quite post
the schedule yet I will post this soon I
will be back with I think just a final
round of render or cleanup and hopefully
we will get some nice speed wins there
if we do the texture race stuff which I
really wanted to do as well so that's it
hope see you back here for that until
then have fun programming and I'll see
you on the Internet
cookies everybody