okay so today we're going to start off
by talking a little bit about the light
transport that's going in hand going on
in handmade here right now because
i i think you know i don't work on
handmade hero at any time other than on
stream right so although people
apparently think i do which is very
interesting i've noticed there are
threads on things like hacker news where
uh you know people post ridiculous
theories that are like no no casey works
on all the time literally you've watched
me do the whole thing on stream and
anybody who's been here every day knows
there's literally no change to the code
base and you can even go to github and
see each change with the days marked on
it but you know uh yeah that that's too
much work for people on hacker news
they'd rather just post their idiotic
opinions to a giant thread full of
nonsense so anyway today we're going to
look at
light transport in handmade hero since i
don't work on it during the week at all
and we only have you know
two hours or three hours on sundays to
do it um
in general i find that sometimes during
the week like my brain will be thinking
about it though like i'll be like oh
yeah like you know
uh last sunday we did this thing and i'm
like i just realized i screwed something
up right
uh you've seen me do that and hand it
here before we'll start and i'll be like
you know i was thinking about x and i
think we did a stupid thing or whatever
um and so uh last week we got the
lighting to a really good place it looks
really awesome right now but it's still
got some bugs in it i'm you know i'm
quite sure that we've got some bugs in
it we gotta fix uh some of them are
obvious some are probably not so obvious
uh and so what i wanted to do here was
kind of go over something i was thinking
about during the week i was like i don't
think our light transport is actually
correct right now our thinking about
light transport isn't correct and i
think that's where the like blossoming
bug is coming from we fixed some of the
egregious errors in the blossoming bug
those were because you were able to
transport light um
in ways that you shouldn't have because
we we lost the z bounds you saw me fix
that uh on last week's stream we kind of
discovered that's what was going on and
that's all fine but i think we still
have a fundamental error in how the
light transport is working and i think
that's what causes that sort of if you
put a powerful light in a place you get
this like blossoming effect i think
that's actually
not a bug in our code i think that's a
bug in our actual like equations meaning
the code is correctly simulating what we
told it to
and we like there's not like a typo or a
missing minus or that kind of thing like
a bug in the code implementation there's
a bug in the concept like the way we are
doing things has a missing piece to it i
think and again this is just what i
thought this week kind of as it was
kicking around in my head so i haven't
actually looked at it i could be wrong
but i wanted to go over what i was
thinking of
uh and explain it and and sort of also
work through it myself
so that i could see if i if i think i'm
right or not right because it was just
kind of kicking around in my head
so right now in handmade hero i want to
go over the first part of the light
transport which is what happens when you
throw a light source in a scene
and why i think that's roughly correct
and then i want to go over the second
part of light transport and explain why
i think it's roughly wrong
so what happens in handmade hero right
now is that if you imagine like a
top-down view what chan made hero kind
of is it's you know it's a bit uh
three-quarters or whatever but you know
it's
you can sort of see it's mostly meant
for kind of looking down on things like
a doll's house kind of a well doll's
house is probably more straight on so uh
maybe more like a yeah old school
uh you know ultima style kind of a thing
anyway uh when you look at what happens
we don't have really a concept of light
sources in handmade hero because the
idea was we wanted the lighting to be
very diffuse and and sort of like
expressive
uh and soft so we don't specifically
earmark light sources and treat them
differently than anything else uh
anything in the world can be a light
source and it's fully globally
illuminated but
there still is the concept that light
has to come from somewhere so you know
if nothing in the world was emitting
photons it would be completely dark
right something has to start by emitting
the photons so we do have the constant
handmade hero of setting and a thing to
have an emissive material right to be
able to emit photons and that's where
the lighting starts so even though we
don't like specifically say oh let's
count the light sources how many there
are because that's one way to do a
system right like systems that are less
global illumination based we'll
oftentimes talk about okay we allow like
50 light sources per voxel cell you know
that we illuminate and we do we do the
equations for all of them inside a
shader there's ways you can think about
light sources as a first class citizen
we just don't do that at handmade hero
but
the fundamental concept that light has
to come from somewhere is still
obviously going to be inherent in the
system and so if you put something in
like a block uh that has an emissive
property
then that is going to shine light into
the environment and how does that
actually work well we have light probes
right
scattered throughout the environment
um at the moment they're regularly
spaced the reason they're regularly
spaced is because we wanted it to be
relatively straightforward to sample
them
in the shader so when we do our actual
pixel shading uh we wanted there to be a
pretty clean simple way for us to
interpolate the lighting in the world so
we have you know regularly spaced light
probes
and the way that the light would be
gathered from this emitter here
is that any given one of these light
probes will be sending out a series of
sample rays on every frame right and
these sample arrays are distributed
across a sphere
and they're they're relatively
stochastic so it's actually white noise
sampling right now which is not the best
sampling we had blue noise in there but
we actually changed the dynamically
generating samples and we haven't tried
to do something where we can quickly
dynamically generate blue noise uh we
probably should that's like something
that would improve our sampling so at
some point we probably should do that
but right now we're not actually doing
that
and i think that adds more noise so when
we're looking at kind of the final
cleanup pass after we get all these bugs
worked out uh that would be a good thing
to add but again all that's going to do
is add some extra noise using white
noise instead of blue noise is going to
mean our sampling is a little bit less
clean probably but other than that
there's no difference between white
noise and blue noise in terms of like
bugs like the light transport equation
should still work with white or blue
noise you shouldn't end up with like
dramatically different results in the
actual answer
it's just going to be a little more
noisy so
when we send out a ray
sometimes one of these rays hits the
emitter and that will add that light uh
proportional to how many rays we cast it
will add that light into that sample
of our outgoing light map so we have a
light you know basically that light
probe has some number of samples that
it's keeping for lighting and out of
each one of those sample regions it
sends lots of rays and then it sums
those up and divides by the total number
of rays set to figure out how many are
in there and again that's not
particularly great sampling either
there's
potentially ways we could improve that
as well
to get less noise i'm not really very
knowledgeable about sampling theory so
that's why we haven't rolled anything in
there yet is because i don't know you
know i really don't even know
how much better it could be or if it's
worth it or anything like that uh people
who are really good at sampling would
kind of know just right off the bat uh
you know what they should probably do in
there but you know i don't i don't have
any expertise in that area so that's why
we're just kind of randomly just
averaging them right
but you could probably do better things
than that
uh based on knowledge of of certain
probabilities and things like that you
know if you go look at high-end
rendering papers
uh they're typically not going to do
something like averaging they're
typically going to use some kind of
probability distributions to reduce the
amount of noise in the system or who
knows what right so you know again
just pointing out that there's things in
here that aren't fantastic but they're
not necessarily buggy like they're still
going to produce reasonable answers
they're just not maybe going to be as
noise-free as they should be with the
number of samples that have been taken
um now you may wonder well how does this
you know if we're just sending out these
samples and then we're basically just
writing this light back in their
averaged
is that reasonable light transport and
my argument is for this first step it
actually is reasonable light transport
and the reason that i say that is
because these actually these sample rays
if you notice they do exactly what you
would expect photons to do if they were
going in the reverse direction so for
example if we were going to try to shoot
photons out of here and we're talking
about you know fundamentally when we're
talking about light transport what we
want to think about or at least one way
to think about it is
if we're shooting all these photons out
of a light source
the results that we get for lighting
should roughly match what we expect to
happen if we had tons of particles
leaving this light source we shouldn't
end up with answers that are
fundamentally different from what would
happen if we shot out particles from
this light source
so if we shot out particles from this
light source what we would expect to
happen is they would land at these
sample points right they would arrive at
these sample points proportional to some
kind of an inverse square law right
because as you send particles out in
random directions from a light source
like a light emission photon like like
photons from a light emitter would do
we expect them to get less concentrated
as they get further away so in a ring
right around the light source the
photons are very concentrated on that
surface as that ring gets further out
the photons will be less concentrated
why because for any two randomly picked
directions the further out i look at
where the photons go the more gap there
is between them right
so no matter how dense they are at the
emitter
as i get out to one ring well they're
less dense now as i get out to another
ring they're less dense now right and
they're going to be less dense in three
dimensions based on the inverse square
law why because they are actually going
you know a surface of a sphere is
two-dimensional so any paths on that
sphere will get bigger as a proportion
to the square of the radius because the
the the uh surface area of the sphere
gets bigger as portugal to the square of
the radius
so this convection process here
where we're pulling light is going to
work exactly the same way because the
rays diverge as they get further apart
in exactly the same way that the
outgoing rays would diverge from the
emitter
we're going to get a naturally inverse
square falloff of light arriving at any
given point for the exact same reason so
the inverse square law is actually
already captured in our light reception
in exactly the way that it should be
meaning any particular direction will
simply have less light contributing to
that as it gets further away because the
rays will be less likely to hit right
um so it's naturally going to capture
inverse squared fall off from that and
furthermore it's better to do it that
way because if you happen to have a
large light source right
for which all of these you know all of
the rays going out of one you know
little region if they all would have hit
that
you don't want to do something like
apply the inverse square law manually
because light doesn't itself fall off
with an inverse square meaning an
individual photon carries exactly as
much energy across the entire line
as it did when it left right it doesn't
change its energy amount so you the
reason you get an inverse square law
fall off from light ever is strictly
because you there's less area
that the photons are falling on as you
get further away but if you actually do
have
you know a light source so large that
you know all of the photons are dense
enough that they're all still going to
hit
you should still capture the the full
energy of uh the light source in that
patch so you don't want to artificially
apply some kind of weird like inverse
square law falloff that you just pulled
out of uh thin air right because you
really do want to to measure how much of
the light source you're actually seeing
and that's how much energy you should be
getting you don't want some additional
uh inverse squared falloff that's just
based on distance because it's not
really the distance it's the it's the
surface area of the projection of the
light that's causing that uh
uh which the that uh that um
uh
[Music]
feature i don't wanna say anomaly it's
not weird that uh yeah it's that's
causing that aspect of lighting yeah
so in my opinion i don't think we have a
problem here that is generally what
should happen the only thing i would say
is right now we don't have any real
understanding of what our light sources
value actually is we just say stuff like
oh the emission of this thing is 5.0
right
um and we don't know what that value is
now it's okay that we don't know what
that value is because we're not trying
to simulate
a particular real environment like if
you were doing you know
some kind of architectural rendering it
may be very important for you to
actually know like okay this is going to
be in candelas or looms or whatever you
know however we're specifying we get
some manufacturers like explanation of
how their fluorescent light bulbs work
and we know that we're going to put
those into this house and we want to see
how the lighting actually works so we
need to know right like
exactly how much light is being put in
here and we need to simulate that light
you know things like maxwell render or
those kind of things they're designed to
give you accurate results for
architectural previews you know they
shouldn't be using a value like 5.0
because it doesn't mean anything right
like they can't correspond it to
something in the real world that they're
actually trying to simulate
um but it's fine for us to say 5.0
because we only have to tune things
relative we might
want to make that more um
concrete in the future if our goal is to
make it easier for us to sort of specify
real world lighting conditions like okay
the sun's this bright a light bulb's
this bright and we correspond those to
some real world values so that it's
easier for us to balance
you might want to do that in a game for
our game it's doesn't seem like we're
you know it's a very fanciful game the
art is like kind of hand drawn
and cartoony so you know we probably
never need to move past this
understanding of lighting but the point
is
we don't know what that value is it's
just an arbitrary value that we plucked
out of thin air and we can keep going
with that we don't have to but it's
worth noting that nobody has spent any
time
determining what that value actually
means so we don't have a way to tie it
back to anything and that's one issue
you might want to address depending on
what you were doing i don't think we
need to but you know you could
um
so this entire thing i think is fine i
don't actually think there's any
problems in here and i don't think that
we would have any real issues with it
going forward because i think we could
just tune these values once we put in
maybe an exposure equation on the back
end
the exposure equation and this can just
be arbitrary and we tune them with each
other and then we're good right it's
just a tuning process to get a look that
we want when we're happy with the
exposure equation and the lighting
values we just call it that's what it is
and then we know oh our bright lights
are 10 our dim lights are two and we
just that's it right so that's totally
fine for an artistic process we don't
need to correspond these to real world
values because we're not actually trying
to produce anything that matches
something in the real world so it's not
going to really be much of a hindrance
to us unless we just find that tuning
them is too difficult and we'd rather
you know pull some real world values out
uh so that we can just put them in
directly and you know not have to tune
right that's another thing that you can
get but i don't even know if that would
work because when you're talking about
cartoonish art you wouldn't necessarily
know you're like you put in these values
that are from the real world it might
look terrible right because you know
it's artistic and the lighting's gonna
have to be not that real because it's
gonna have to go with the you know the
sort of cartoony feel
all right
um so that i think is fine uh but i
think we have uh a problem in the other
part of the way we're doing light
transport and so that you know
fairly comfortable uh that we're not
doing something dumb with that light
sampling when it comes from an actual
light source it feels about right um and
furthermore i think that would be true
for anything else meaning in other words
if you're pulling light from just
reflective surfaces i think that that
inverse square part works just fine as
well but
let's talk about the part that i think
is not correct here
so let's suppose uh that we
that we talk about a uh reflective
surface instead okay
um because we have other cases excuse me
in the world where you can gather light
like i said we actually don't treat
light sources any differently from
anything else in handmade hero
everything is basically capable of
reflecting light it's just
it's straightforward unbiased global
illumination it everything
just is able to send light so
we don't have any kind of concept of
something being a light source or not
other than when you hit it it's able to
generate photons out of thin air it
doesn't have to reflect them that's the
only thing that differentiates an
emitter in our system what that means is
that when you look
um at
our light probes
uh yes we have an emitter
like so
um and what will happen is
when you are looking at the first time
that emitter has ever been hit by
anything uh the inverse square law
applies so you know we get this sort of
thing uh happening here uh and
proportionally less of the rays you know
from here will hit than here so the
light will be dimmer here than here for
that reason right less light
will be captured in this light probe so
it will naturally have an inverse square
fall off as it goes but
what we do not do right now is
differentiate between an emitter and a
reflector in terms of the energy that's
being provided
so
if we
look at something like a surface in the
world and we say okay
what happens when we have a surface
like this
and somebody hits that surface as a
sample point
yes the inverse square law will apply
meaning i am less likely to hit that
point on the surface with rays you know
or that small region of the surface with
rays as they go further out
that's true
but what happens when i sample from here
is i take the reflectance of this
surface which is something right like
we'll have a reflectance number of you
know
0.7.7.7 or something for like a sort of
diffuse but fairly reflective surface it
just has some we're literally in there
just multiplying by a modulation right
um
so we hit this thing what we do is we
sample from the nearby uh light probes
so let's just say that this one is
mostly dominant here because we're close
to it you know it doesn't really matter
what we get is we look at okay
we're trying to figure out this
particular light probe how much exits in
this direction from this light probe uh
because we're like blending a bunch of
these together right
uh and we send that amount back right
we're basically just saying like look
this is how much
um
this is how much light would go out in
that direction
so the thing that i was thinking is
probably wrong here
is that at no point do we ever actually
try to differentiate
between light that's being reflected in
light that's being emitted
what i mean by that is that the emitter
is itself
something that generates photons
so anybody who is looking directly at
the emitter obviously is going to get
some number of photons given by that
brightness level right like 5.0 whatever
that is we don't know what that is but
it's
abstractly
some measure of the density of photons
that are going out right
per unit area on that you know on that
uh
on the on the emission of photons in a
in a sphere as they you know go out into
the world
anyone who hits it we don't have any i
we don't have any concept of like bias
in light direction we could introduce it
but we don't right now so the entire
sphere is just covered with
this density of photons and i think
that's sampled roughly correctly because
of that inverse square falloff of the
sampling rays you will naturally get
less as you go further out
so you'll be less likely to hit the
light source as you go further out
so that seems fine
but
what doesn't seem fine is that when you
get those results so i hit this thing
and i say oh i you know i sampled this
and uh you know what i see is that in in
coming out this direction right i'm
gonna look back in the opposite
direction and see how much stuff that i
hit so you know maybe this is not quite
right maybe i should be talking about
this so that it would be hitting this
more directly
what i will get is basically that
the inverse squared fall off from this
light at this point
will be sent completely along this ray
again like a repeater
right because at no point did anything
other than this
reduce the light amount
does that make sense
at no point did we ever say oh by the
way
the light that falls incident to this
has to be radiated out
without adding energy right meaning all
of the light that we're going to receive
at a particular point we can't radiate
out more than we actually got
so let's say for example that at this
particular point right
when we cast in you know in these
directions we got a certain amount of
light energy well everybody who roughly
hits from that area will be getting that
same light energy sent to them
but that
and again this is i i'm i'm really not
knowledgeable in this area uh i i
think i tweeted as when i tweeted out i
was like uh it's too bad don mitchell is
not here to explain this to us because
you know i i just i just fundamentally
don't really get light very well i think
one of these days i probably should
write like a full like photorealistic
ray tracer
uh
to get my head
fully around
how you actually think about light uh
you know
the phrase watts per staridian right
should be coming up here and uh i should
have a lot more of a handle on like
what's actually happening quantity wise
so i don't pretend to be very good at
this stuff because i simply never have
worked with it long enough to really get
good at it
and so it's a bummer and one of these
days i need to fix that that's for sure
before i'm you know 60 or whatever i
need to sit down and actually do that
but
uh in lieu of actually having someone
with really hardcore rendering expertise
uh or ray tracing expertise
i'm simply going to try and point out
that
i don't think we are properly accounting
for the fact
that a given surface can only reflect
the amount of energy it received in
total
uh less its modulation meaning like
after it it takes away the 30 or
whatever of light that it's absorbing
right
the remaining 70 of the light that it
captured that light has to go out
based on some distribution
it can't have every direction receive
the entire amount of light that it
received from the opposite direction
right because if you allow that to
happen then what you're going to get is
exactly the i think exactly the bug that
we see which is that on the first frame
everything's fine because you only are
sampling from these light sources and
each probe just got the distribution
from the light source and that's fine
but
if you keep the light source in one
place
it will then basically contaminate as it
spreads outward
because each reflector is basically
capable of reflecting the total energy
of the light source again
so yes it inverse squared fall off right
when it got from here to here but then
on the next frame
this is capable of picking up basically
the entire light source again and moving
it one probe forward right
because we're not accounting for the
fact that it shouldn't be able to
distribute that entire light that it
received it should only be able to to
distribute
that light proportional you know like it
should only be able to redistribute that
area across the entire hemisphere which
means some of it goes back in the other
direction right
uh and so on
so i think what's basically happening
right now is our light probes are
functioning like mirrors they're like
one frame delay mirror so rather than
the light itself
actually getting distributed and sent
along it's actually kept uh and
propagated entirely
from light source to light from probe to
probe as we go
uh and and calling the mirrors is wrong
it's not even they're replicators right
because not only are the mirror would
just send it on its way and not keep it
uh they're worse than mirrors right
they're mirrors that send all the light
uh out in the same direction again so
it's just like bucket brigade but also
they keep it so they show up bright as
well you know what i'm saying
um and so it's this lack of a
reflectance equation happening at the
point that distributes the energy fairly
and without adding energy that i think
is our
problem um
i hope that makes some sense that's just
that's just my way of saying why in my
head i think the behavior we're seeing
of that light contamination is exactly
what we actually should expect because
of the way that we are sampling right um
we are we are not sampling the
reflectance in a way that actually
conserves the energy
uh that is incident to
the point right
um
so that's my assumption and i could be
wrong uh but that's my assumption
and so i think what we're doing wrong
here is we are doing something uh ev
when we actually go to sample so you
know i'll draw it down here because we
you know i've drawn too much crap up
there
um so imagine we have like some close
samples like this we don't really in the
game have this but i just want to make
it a little simpler on us
um so suppose we have some samples here
and uh we are going to do something
where we say okay we're sampling from
this
ray so this guy uh you know is is
sampling basically the light that's
coming in this direction so it can
update this light probe and let's
suppose you know so that's going to send
out a a probe you know in this direction
or something and so let's say there's a
wall you know here
and this is gonna hit that wall right
and so we're gonna have something like
this
or maybe let's make it even simpler this
is an emitter so we'll just do one
bounce right
um so what we would say is okay this
emitter right we have some density that
we sampled at this emitter and out of
this direction which is the direction
we're going to sample we have some
amount of emission coming in here
right now for this surface what we want
to say is if it's you know what whatever
this surface's value is we're expecting
to send light back out into the
environment at like a 70 rate
so we know that whatever comes in here
we have some total amount of energy
that's sampled out of this you know
particular thing and we know that we're
going to send 70 of it back out right
so i would assume although i guess i
don't
and this is the part where it's very
tricky for me to think through
so
if we're going to send 70 of it back out
in this direction and keep 30 of it here
right
uh the 30 is just gone this this just
disappears right uh it can't be seen
it's just absorbed to the material as
heat or i don't even who the heck knows
that's that's actually like you know
welcome to material science i have no
idea what's going on there right but
some amount of the photons are just like
absorbed and do quantum things and
convert to ir or i don't know what they
do
um
so some amount of the photons are just
absorbed 70 percent of them have to go
back out into the environment and so you
know 70 of them are going to go out in
you know in
some kind of a
of a ring
the problem that we're having here is
when they
look when they hit other light probes
like these light probes in the
environment
what i don't quite understand is should
these light probes like how should these
light probes react to capturing that 70
percent right
that's the part that's very confusing to
me so we do want seventy percent to go
out here but we don't want like this
these we don't want all three of these
for example if they all happen to fall
within the texel of that octahedral map
we don't want all three of these to all
have 70
right
um
they each would need to get a proportion
of the 70
i think
meaning that
the photons that come in here
however many you got
they can't all go to each
right
each light probe has to capture
exactly a third
or
maybe these would capture less because
they're further off angle
i don't know
but the total light energy that comes in
here on that on that arc
that's the reflected angle that you know
that uh solid angle
the outgoing solid angle has to
distribute that i would think fairly so
it should have to do something like you
know 20
20 30 right
and right now i think it'll just get
70-70-70
which which is i think where our light
contamination comes from
uh
my naivete and the reason that i'm
saying that i'm not comfortable with
this stuff but i don't really understand
it is that although i'm saying that i
don't really have a solid understanding
for
how you'd actually write the equations
for that
partially because light probes are weird
they're not surfaces they're
kind of just things floating in space
that measure the light that goes through
them
so i'm not sure exactly how that would
work i
because these do have inverse squared
fall off because of the way they back
sample right
uh they're sending out samples and that
averaging process will knock down uh the
amount based on how many hit
and like so would that
should that naturally produce the 20 20
right
um
and right i i don't know maybe i'm not
maybe not explaining my confusion very
well uh so i apologize but
if my argument is correct that just like
by sampling this you're going to get
less sampling as it gets further away
you would expect that to have the
inverse square coverage tells you what's
coming in
uh the same argument should sort of
apply here i mean shouldn't it but i
guess i don't know i don't know if there
should also be uh
what you know this particular thing when
we sample in the reverse direction
i don't know if we should divide
by the surface area again
like like i don't know whether we would
divide a second time
maybe i need to try and think about this
in terms of like individual photons
[Music]
uh because you know it could be that
actually this number because there's
some number here that this already has
that surface area division effectively
baked into it meaning because we can set
this to whatever we want it's just an
arbitrary brightness value it could be
that actually no when you hit here you
should have said how big
of a you know how big does this ray
actually represent
and we're actually going to count that
many photons right because it's sort of
a sample that's a part of us you know
that's that's sort of trying to
reconstruct
how many photons were actually incident
and this could sort of just have that
baked in implicitly in the number so you
know you're never going to see that bug
i mean it's not a bug but you're never
going to see that aspect of your system
you wouldn't think about it
so it could be that in this case you
actually do need to do that and maybe we
can look uh and see
let's think about this maybe we can look
and see if we actually do a little
photon counting exercise if we can
convince ourselves uh one way or the
other about that
i'm gonna take a drink of water one
second
someday we're gonna have technology for
this i mean we already have probably the
technology it's just nobody's building
them
uh for instant erase light boards and
that will be a very good day
when these are just like lcds right
and the pen is actually just like a
uh like a wacom pen basically that
lights that lights the surface you know
that tells the lcd to like solidify
their
someday
or we'll just all be in mark
zuckerberg's horrible metaverse or
something
but of course in that case none of this
stuff would work it'd all just be buggy
and showing you ads all the time so that
probably wouldn't solve the problem
all right
that didn't take too long
okay so let's just count
um
let's do some like basic photon counting
and again this is just for my own
purposes try and like
think through what's happening in this
situation uh so that i could figure out
like where in the equations you know we
have very simplistic equations right now
we're hardly doing anything during light
transport
and the question is like what would we
add if i'm right that this is
erroneous meaning
we're getting light replication
uh because we're missing a surface area
divide right like
uh and just to be clear
when you reflect things off of surface
you also have like a cosine falloff and
things like that i'm not talking about
that i'm not talking about trying to
condition the falloff uh i'm talking
about no matter what we do
how do we ensure that the energy
transfer is correct right
um so because any surface reflectance
function you might want
we should be able to
whatever the equation is we choose even
if it was just purely like it's perfect
like it's not even cosine fall if it's
just it's perfectly distributed if
that's what we for some reason wanted we
should still be able to condition the
equations so you don't get feedback
right we should be able to condition the
equation so that there isn't like an
energy
build up happening
so let's just try some photon counting
and see
uh if there's something to be said
about that
so let's suppose that we start uh with a
light source right
um so our emitter is going to emit uh
some number of photons uh out from uh
you know its surface
and we have our uh collection point so
here is our probe
this is going to be our probe p
and our probe is basically like going to
hit
like so
and let's suppose that we say that
what because you know
we're basically trying to simulate a
large number of photons with a few rays
right
so each one of these hits is going to be
some number of photons comes back right
and i guess i would say right now if we
had to categorize what our actual light
values are that's what they are they're
basically like a
one ray
photon count
so 5.0
is like the photon count
right so when we hit with one ray we're
basically getting five photons back
from that
that ray right
now we cast
i think eight or
we know we cast depending on how we tune
the parameter and how fast we make the
raycaster we can you know if we improve
the speed of the raycaster we could set
it up higher whatever we're casting some
number of rays
uh and then we're averaging them
together right uh so i guess i shouldn't
say uh per ray this this is for
uh all rays
i guess
so if all rays that went out
hit
the light source from one
you know one emission texel from from
one like uh texel that we're sending
raycasts out of for the light probe so
the octahedral map right is wrapped
around this
right we've got one texel we're sending
a ton of rays out here
and we're going to hit with some number
of them
so coming back the number of photons
that we received at this probe
uh is going to be the emitter's number
which is like the 5.0
divided by something based on how many
rays hit right so it's times um the hits
over the casts right so there's like an
h over c term here
so five photons are magical photons or
five billion photons or whatever you
want to call this five
if all the rays hit that's how much
energy would have come in through that
texel if some lower number of that
rays hit we get proportionally less
so we don't really even have to talk
about how many actually hit her we can
just say that's what happened but if we
wanted to put a concrete thing on it
let's just say that for some reason all
the rays hit
so like everything in this bundle
uh of rays that we sent they all hit the
light source so we got back the full
five
uh
magic photon quantity however much that
is
five
uh handmades
of photons right
so then what we're going to talk about
uh as the buggy part because i don't see
so i guess what i'd say is i don't see
how that can really be all that wrong
because we're setting this number to
whatever we want and that seems fine
like it's just
that's
that is just a measure of if every ray
hit this light source you would have
that much light energy and since we're
setting this value to whatever we want i
don't see how there can really be much
of a bug there if we were to claim that
this value was something else candelas
watts watts per staridian whatever
then we would have to think about
whether what we claimed the value was
measured in
was actually correct because it could be
if we said that it was for example uh
watts per steridian or straight watts or
whatever there might be a thing where
you have to divide based on the scale of
the light source in order to make the
units of that be true because they they
might be talking about per service uh
they might be normalized to surface area
or not normalized surface area and then
this could be wrong but because we
haven't even said what it is it's just
an abstract measure of brightness that
we turn up and down i don't think it can
actually be wrong because we haven't
made any claims about it we just claim
that when it gets larger the light gets
brighter and it gets less it gets less
so i think this first this is again me
just trying to reassure myself that i
think that we don't have any problems in
that first gather of light from an
emitter because that seems okay
uh but i don't know
now let's look at the next bounce and
here's where i think we have problems
so let's suppose that this is the only
light source in the scene and we've only
done one bounce
so meaning we haven't run this for many
frames and let the light like flow
around or anything so the only light in
the entire system let's say
is there
and now we have
more probes
right and what we're going to do is
we're going to
cast and some of these casts are going
to hit
right
now
some of these we could easily construct
a case where two of these probes are on
the same line directly into here
and i'm gonna like to make our lives
easier so that we know that the amount
coming back
will be exactly the same right
to make our lives easier here i'm going
to restrict our discussion to just those
two
because i think
that helps us understand part of the
problem
right
and or at least why i think this is
complicated
so let's suppose we're talking about
these two a and b
well we know that no matter what we do a
and b the light probes a and b will have
to produce the same values roughly right
um a is a little further away so it may
it will have some proportion of the
light that's flowing into b right
the ray bundle that comes out here is
tighter
so it let's say b hits
all just the part that would be
reflected directly out of here so b
in this
of its
texel would have the full 5.0 but a will
have less right because some of the rays
will miss so maybe a goes down to 4.0
like it just misses some not that you
can have 4.0 in a system where the
divisor is 16 but you know whatever
um
well maybe you could uh anyway uh but
point being
here is where i think we have
uh the issue right or our understanding
of what's happening with the light
probes is slightly wrong
so the light probes are just measuring
the light flow through that area and so
they by necessity have to basically
we have to have
the amount of photons that are flowing
through the area
has to basically be
um
wait i missed a step
i missed one step uh so
this is not quite
true of the five and the four but the
the point i was trying to illustrate
with the five and four will still be
true but let's let's not forget
so in order these have to hit something
a probe is not something you can hit so
you have to hit like a wall right and
the wall is nearby to the probe
and so we have a reflectance function of
what comes off of the wall right and
what comes off of the wall here is going
to be the the total number of photons
right
that hit the wall which in this case is
5.0
uh in terms of what comes out in this
direction we have to basically take
something that will distribute the 5.0
photons
evenly
uh meaning
5 came in
this way so
and if that's the entirety of it the 5.0
have to go out
some
proportion right
uh
they we can't send out more than five
right
uh we know that most of our services
will have some kind of a multiplier on
them and we should go check this just to
be sure uh but let's suppose there is
like the 0.7 or or maybe there's even
just a 0.5 to make it a little easier on
ourselves so we don't have to have
multiply by 0.7 not that it's that hard
in this case to do
but let's suppose that it's just like a
0.5
so we know that we have 2.5
of our magical like
photon count
going out of the surface
and we can distribute it over the
hemisphere however we want
right now i believe the way that it is
being uh distributed is we uh there's a
stage where we take the uh light probe
octahedron and we take the spec like
it's basically a specular one so it's
just got like the light it's got
literally like the texel that this went
out of is like at 5.0 and everything
else is at zero and we do a blur on that
that's based on the cosine falloff which
produces a cosine falloff diffuse
version of the light probe and that i
believe is the entirety of our like
transport equation right
i believe we made that energy preserving
meaning the total uh sum of the light in
there is the same uh the spec map and
the diffuse map now we can go check that
and in fact we should we should remember
to like check
uh diffuse
power
but i believe that we properly did that
because we knew when we did that we're
like we can't add energy to the system
so when we take the spec mac and map and
we produce the diffuse map we have to
make sure that it equals the amount of
the light that came in has to equal the
amount of light that goes out otherwise
we're basically uh adding energy to the
system
but we can recheck that
uh so then we get in here and we say
well okay so 2.5 are going out um and
you know this gets spread along the
hemisphere somehow so we don't know how
much it actually is uh but whatever it
is let's say 1.0
of it goes out in this direction
b all of the texels in that direction
all hit so it gets 1.0 here some of them
don't so it gets 0.5
right something like that
um
so i believe
so you can see the thing that i'm
concerned about here is that we've
duplicated how many tech like we've
duplicated photons right
meaning there are photons now at b and
at a
uh
b has all the photons and a has
half again
right it's got fifty 50 of the photons
but
the amount of photons we sent out isn't
conserved
now because these are light probes
i don't know that they should be
conserved
because we're talking about how many
photons are passing through that point
but it could be that that
but but how do we like do you see what
i'm saying like that's what we're
measuring
and and you know i i just don't quite
see
where the flaw in that thinking is
because it's like well the this is
talking about how many photons in
general
are going through this area
but you can see how this would produce a
problem potentially right
um or at least i think this could
potentially produce a problem right like
you would assume therefore
that if this sort of thing can happen
well if there's further bouncing that
happens like from here or from here
these will basically be bouncing more
than the total number of photons
right
i mean i don't see any way really around
that
and yeah they're going to get clipped
down quite a bit meaning this same
process will go again so you know it's
only going to send out a subset of them
but it's sending out a subset of them
based on a total number that didn't
actually occur
right
right so suppose yeah i mean suppose
this looks like this
well that wall in the way wouldn't be
good
so maybe this
suppose that it looks something like
this
um and we're talking about like the
reflectance from here and from here
it's both of these are going to be using
we're going to be computing those bounce
equations based on a hundred and fifty
percent of the light
and even though they'll be knocked down
quite a bit again you notice we don't
immediately get this it's very slow it's
like a slow creep
so that may be enough to just slowly
over time because the total number of
photons being used in the distribution
is not conserved
off we go
right
now the problem is i don't really know
how you would solve this i mean
obviously people must because light
probes are not weird
um
but i'd but when light probes can
collect light from other light probes
which you have to do
in a system like this where you know
it's it's real time so it can't just
take an infinite amount of time to run
where each light probe just does the
bounces itself and tries to hit the
light source
um
how do you fix that
see this is why we need don mitchell
here
where is don mitchell
probably has something better to do this
time than this
but
i mean i think
i think i've roughly like
i mean i'm fairly convinced that that's
a problem
that like our conceptualization of like
what the light probes are measuring
is fundamentally incompatible with
conserving the amount of energy that we
actually sample in the system
and and i don't know
i don't know how you fixed that
well
let's go back in and look at the chat
so
did that make some sense
thank you all right space naming maybe
we'll we'll set the light board down
slightly
so
so like
i'm just kind of fundamentally confused
about how to think about light probes
because of that
uh nikita97 that's
that's my
concern what you stated because i don't
feel like i'm very good at light
transport you know i just haven't worked
with it much
i don't want to say that that is
definitely true
um
but that's what
like based on
my thinking about the problem i don't
see
i don't see how it couldn't be true what
we just said
like fundamentally speaking if you
measure
flow of photons through a point
there's nothing to stop you from using
that flow in multiple places right
and
it's
it's an aspect of the discretization of
the problem if everything were
completely continuous you wouldn't have
this problem because nothing could
reflect
like no two surfaces can reflect the
same exact photon
if you're stimulating all the photons
but when you're simulating photons as
bundles
right
you have to use like
a sampling from the average of like some
from what direction you're talking about
and you're by definition not going to
get an exact occlusion of who's sampling
what from where right
so it seems
it seems to me that i i don't see how we
modify what we're doing like
i don't quite get it
like i don't quite understand
what we're supposed to do about that
we could calculate the amount emitted in
the amount received and artificially
dampen the emission the next frame
um
yeah yeah we i mean we could or suck
power out of the system like everything
gets that much dimmer right
like you sum the total
the total sampled amount
and you reduce it by enough to make sure
it stays under the total light level or
something like yeah you could do
something like that
i don't know
um
yeah i just don't know i i
i feel like this is probably something
that it would be good to go read about
right like i'm assuming that there's
somewhere that someone has written up
you know maybe when they were first
working on the concept of light probes
where they've
talked more about light probes that are
hanging in space
i don't know
um
i mean maybe the problem is that really
this is not the right way to think about
it because
because really the problem i'm talking
about is a problem everywhere
and so that's not really the problem the
problem is just the discretization like
you would have this problem no matter
what you did that's always true that
you're talking about the photons that
are flowing through an area or flowing
you know
that are bouncing off a surface and so
really the problem is just that we are
discretizing it so that when we sample
we could sample multiple things that all
are measuring the same flow
and because we are you know averaging
them together into
texels
that aggregate and are sampled as
aggregates we end up
allowing people to gather more light
than they should as a result right
um
because because like if you think about
it
you know yeah like i think there's not
really an there isn't really a problem
with it up until that point like up
until the point where it goes like oh
well i can sample from this light probe
and so can this other point but in
reality those two points would not have
been able to sample the flux because
they you know they're both kind of on
they're both offset from the line that
was that flow and only one of them would
have actually been able to like hit that
light source or whatever but now it
appears like two people can right uh and
so on so it may really be more about
that discretization that it is about the
fact that they are light probes for any
particular reason
right um
right because you can imagine getting
taking the light probes out of this
entirely and just talking about sample
points on like the wall
you have the same problem if you
just count like large
angles
and you say well if there's anything in
this angle then you get all the light
then that would be wrong too
you know what i mean
um
so
we need a way of
we need some way of saying that
the light gets distributed between these
two points you can't have all the light
go to both
you know what i mean
uh evan tech we don't do that we don't
propagate light info between light
probes
but when you send out a ray to sample
what's happening in the environment you
hit something the only way to know what
the inbound lighting at that location is
is to sample the light probes in in the
neighboring region right so you get
information sharing just from that
uh and there's nothing you can do about
it right um
so
the only solution to that problem that
that you know if you don't do that is
you have to do multi-bounce ray casting
which would never be fast enough in real
time right
i wish i had some better ideas here but
i don't
uh
i mean
let's so the original paper that we were
sort of basing the system on and to be
fair we didn't
really do it exactly
um
not exactly
did we save this paper on the hard drive
i don't remember if we did
um
did it was an nvidia paper uh talking
about some lighting stuff
i don't actually know
uh
if we saved it or not but
that's not gonna do it
um
but we should be able to go find it
probably
i don't know
you'd think we would save it but
we might never have
docs
it might be one of these
i think this is it
so this is the original uh paper
uh and we did
you know pretty s you know we did pretty
similar i don't think we quite did it uh
exactly the right way or exactly the way
they did it but it's similar
uh right we did a uniform 3d grid
uh we did octahedral maps
which is what this paper does
and so i wonder if there's
if there's something in here that we
were missing because we didn't really
look
at this
um
[Music]
part of it
i wonder if they discuss this anywhere
so we don't use screen space occlusion
obviously
hmm
[Music]
they don't really talk much about this
part though
okay this is probably mostly what we
care about here
you
so i don't think this talks very much
about that aspect of it
maybe we should go back to the mcguire
paper which we also have on here that
they reference a lot
um
let's just go over and make sure there's
nothing we were missing here generate
and trace n primary arrays from each of
the m active probes storing geometry
yeah we don't
really do this
uh they're doing it so you know i guess
it's possible that that is helping them
avoid this problem if they're actually
doing that
so
so it really doesn't say anything much
about it
you
um
so like this we're also doing
right
oh sorry i forgot to flip it on
my bad
um
the bad news is you didn't miss anything
i i didn't see anything in here
there is
a little bit this uh
so
yeah if you look at what's happening
here they talk a little bit about how
they're doing the shading
and they talk about
uh doing cosine lobe distribution which
is what i believe we do as well
so like
um if we go
let's open a command prompt
uh and open the code
so
[Music]
somewhere in here yeah uh so we do this
this step here right which is where we
convert from specular to diffuse
uh in in here
and when we do that
we
we've have it all
we use the
values we get from our like pre-computed
um
weight buffer which is like this
nonsense
right
and
so if i go
look at that where we build it's
like
yeah
so you can see here we do a cosine lobe
right like that's what this inner
product here right the inner product
between two vectors the incoming and the
outgoing vector
uh since they're both normal that's just
going to be equal to cosine theta
right the direction between them so this
is a cosine falloff weighting scheme
and
that's really all there is to it right
um
and and that's it we do it twice because
first we sum up how much it is going to
be
uh and then we write it out uh by making
sure that that total we we only ever sum
up to the total amount of power so the
entire thing is normal right
um so that we do that
um
right we we do
this
so they're talking about this
a lot uh and and it sounds like they're
deferring any discussion of it to this
uh
which is not great because this is
i don't know some kind of book that we
don't have
which is less good
um
we do have
the mcguire paper they were talking
about but we don't have this book
and
i don't think we can
get a book
can we
we would have to actually order this
book which will take a while
although
did they just put it online
hold on
wait so it doesn't suggest that the
entire thing is available for free but
then on there oh it's the preface
so it's only the prep this is the but
the preface this can't be the preface
it's huge
i guess it's just the preface and the
bibliography
um well so we can't really look at that
right now although i could order the
book and then i could try to read it
online
um
so i guess i'm not sure let's look at
the other paper that we do have because
hey maybe it's in there but i don't know
we could also just order the book and
wait is another option
um so let's take a look
a
light field probe structure
a scene's continuous light field encodes
a spatial angular distribution of
radians for all points and directions in
the scene
uh which is what we want we build an
augmented discrete resolution of this
distribution so we require
discrimination of positions in space
into the directions we discretize space
variation of the light field using a
regular grid inside the scene's bounding
box okay
while this regular structure allows us
to simplify our tracing algorithm
nothing prevents us from using spatial
samples jittered within each volumetric
grid cell during construction and query
time
sure
we we might consider that
that's not a bad idea right like inside
when we
our sampling from each probe we could
jitter the location of the sample right
uh
so that's fine
at each distributed sample position we
store a spherical light field probe yep
a discrete circle slice of the light
fields that corresponds to the local
incident radiance distribution at x from
surrounding scene geometry and light
sources yep
the surface normal
at points
x double prime closest to x prime
in outgoing direction
we
don't
have any idea what that is
so it they're actually storing some
geometry maybe this is what we're doing
wrong
we don't have anything like that
we populate the geometric information of
the probes using rasterization and the
spherical light field slice radiance
distribution yeah
um
uh yep all of our results through the
ladder okay
first bounce somebody contains the
emission profiles then we repeat the
shading to really populate with
additional light balances that's what
we're trying to do because the algorithm
can use rasterization to compute the
probes themselves we do not require a
separate geometric ray tracer sure
section four details are retracing
algorithm that allows to populate update
and query physically based
light transfers
so
uh
that's very interesting that they do
that
and i wonder if one of the reasons that
they do that because i can't think of
any other reason why they do that i
wonder if one of the reasons they do
that is specifically because of this
problem like they're trying to represent
the actual geometry in there because
if you don't represent the geometry you
get this i don't know that might not be
true this let's keep going
so this also uses an octahedron
and that's fine
all right
so i think i kind of understand what's
going on
here it sounds kind of like what they're
doing is they store the surface normal
of the things that they hit
when they store the light probe so that
when they then
you you know
uh
do the lighting computation they can use
that surface normal
to determine how much light would have
come from the target surface
in
relative to
the surface that they're illuminating
and again that might be part of this
part of how they avoid this problem
because there actually are
simulating the light transport more
exactly right
generally speaking every physical
yeah atop a ray tracer
where rays are used to resolve
visibility and a sample rate of quantity
sure concrete array is a half line
with points
yeah
sure
our light field ray tracer first selects
a probe then ins invokes a single probe
ray intersection routine to march across
the geometry defined by that probe
if the single probe routine is unable to
actually determine a hit or miss event
then the algorithm advances to the next
candidate probe and reapplies a single
probe routine
as such the single probe routine returns
one of three possible results a
definitive hit a definitive miss or an
unresolvable exit code
the latter occurs when the ray passes
into a 3d region
that is occluded from the probe's center
of projection
in other words when a probe knows that
it does not have the required visibility
information
at a region of space okay an
intersection for a ray that passes
through that region cannot be reliably
computed using only information from the
one probe note however that by
increasing the density of light probes
stored in the scene we are very quickly
able to guarantee accurate roll space
okay sure
um
the light field ray tracer selects a
probe traces within that single probe
then repeats the process until it
okay um
a line segment in r3 maps to a polyline
with at most four segments in r2
after spherical octahedral project okay
each polyline segment lies on a separate
octahedral face
and the 2d coordinates of the segment
endpoints are the 2d projections of the
intersections of the 3d line with the
three principal axis line planes that
pass through the probe center these
define eight quadrants that correspond
to the octahedral faces
after projection
wait
so
they're actually talking about tracing
the ray on an octahedral map
what
okay that's very different than what
we're doing
and very different to the other paper
okay so they basically are talking about
walking the actual packing
[Music]
i just i'm so confused but okay
um
so most of this won't really apply but
let's see what they do when they
actually get do they talk about what
they actually do
when they get a hit
we now describe three globalization
algorithms the latter two of which are
practical a brute force important
sampling minded color render
morph
and more efficient
a more efficient extension that reduces
the number of ray samples required
by post filtering an extremely fast but
biased solution that pre-filters
liberation reflection only traces rays
for glossary reflection which is also
push which sounds more like ours
and i wonder if the biased part is kind
of the same problem we have which is
that it's brighter it you know it feeds
back over time
um but let's see
um
you
so i'm not really sure
i'm still not really sure i see much
going on here so
i want to ask a few questions
um i think we left this yeah
um so you can see the light leaking that
we're talking about or the light uh sort
of
slow bleeding to everything in the scene
that we were talking about here
um
i'm curious to know
if we were to
when we
like let's say this light is only ever
at 1.0 so
you know it doesn't have any higher
value it can reach
does it still contaminate or is you know
how sensitive is this to the number
right
um
i'm just i don't know and i want to i
want to kind of know what's up here
we should uh we should
i wish we had decided to work on the the
light occlusion problem which you can
see here uh because that's a lot easier
for us to fix but unfortunately that's
uh
not
the problem we chose to work on today we
chose to work on the harder one this is
when you occlude a probe right when
something moves over a probe we don't
handle it right now we just write black
onto it so we can see that it's wrong
but
so it doesn't seem like we really get
that light contamination
you know
i just don't understand
if we set the light value for something
up to a certain amount it starts to have
that contamination effect
but maybe that's just it slowly
spreading its light around
and producing a correct value
i don't know right and like if you had
exposure in here
then this would just adjust
so i really just
i this is perplexing i feel like we need
someone who's an expert in this right
um but you can see how that that you can
see that anything over one has this slow
effect
where it you can see it go and anything
that's not
somehow oddly doesn't
which is
strange because it
should shouldn't it i mean why wouldn't
it
i'm not sure i understand why it
wouldn't do that
right
because if what i was saying was true
like why doesn't it happen here
it feels like we've got some you know
there's just some fundamental yeah uh dr
zul that's exactly kind of what's making
me concerned
right because if
there
there really shouldn't be that that
shouldn't be
the 1.1 times 1.1 is larger than the
original kind of thing
should not be a factor so i'm wondering
if maybe we really do just have a bug
somewhere
that is actually having that exact
feedback problem
although i suppose
we should probably go fix the occlusion
bug
i wonder if we should just do that first
so we don't have to keep looking at the
weird like blackout problem but
so that's just a real stump or
um
we know we're doing cosine lobe and we
know that it ends up summing
unless we screwed that up
we know that it ends up summing to the
correct value
[Music]
of course we are doing
like we are
doing
by linear filtering
but i don't think that would have a
much of an effect
right um
this is the filtering code right here
what
so i will say this is a
bit odd
so we have the occlusion
[Music]
so that occlusion d value
what that is is it's saying that
you know we're gonna we're not gonna
want a sample from
light probes that are in the wrong
direction
so the prox one over
is just letting us know
like
we want our light sample to some
to properly like average across only the
samples that we're actually taking
right
which seems fine
uh
you know
i'm not too upset about that
i don't know
this is a real puzzler
i i really just don't quite know
what by the way are our surface colors
like in terms of our
you know occluders that were loading in
here
like
how much light do they generally absorb
would be my other question right
like
when we are actually adding
uh
occluders
what is the
what is the general reflectance
that we would expect to see so you know
it's this
um here
and here are all the places we add them
so
[Music]
color.rgb
so you know
um
[Music]
a dot 888 it takes out 20 of the light
um
in either case
i don't actually know if i guess that's
using the same color here
and then in the apron
it's darker it's half so we know that
there's a fair like
there's quite a bit of
dampening it's taking out 20 of the
light
on every bounce
in that case and it's taking out half
the light in this case right
so
is that actually happening here i guess
i don't know uh it should be because
yeah i'm pretty sure
that in the
[Music]
in here we are definitely using the ref
hit color right like that's definitely
happening
um
i don't know how that happened
so you can see here where we take the
probe normal
and
we have the hit ref color
and when we take the probe sample here
at the very least we are
multiplying by the hit ref color
right um
so i don't know
don't really see
i
i really don't see the error
i suppose that if it's just straight
feedback right then we should also be
able to predict that since most things
in the scene are 0.8
you would expect there to be no feedback
if we set the light
level
to
just enough
right like uh
so if you assume that we want to take
you know uh 0.8 times x
equals 1.0 right
so we're just saying look if we take 1.0
and divide by 0.8 we get 1.25 which
would be presumably like roughly the
steady state so if i set this light up
to 1.25
we would probably expect
that because every bounce will take out
at least 80 that this would not feedback
right
and it doesn't appear to
um but if we go above that to say uh
even just slightly above that
maybe to 1.3
we would now expect it to feedback on
the interior but not on the exterior
where things were set to 0.5
i don't know if that will actually
happen
maybe there's more getting taken on the
system this would be very slow but in
theory would eventually feedback right
um
doesn't really look like it though
again i'm just trying to gather clues to
what's happening here
we'll try a little bit more 1.5
i don't know so i i so i i can't really
construct a valid argument for why we
have to set the number to something
particular to feedback either
right again which is which is you know
kind of perplexing
unless i'm just like missing something
that looks like it might be feeding back
a little bit
yeah you can see that is feeding back
very slowly
it takes a very long time
is it possible that the color dampening
hits some negative values and adds to
the lighting instead
the color
dampening oh you mean like
these
um
well
i don't think so because they're all
clamped
um
i think
like these are both clamped
uh
i guess i don't know i'm not sure to
what extent those are clamped
one thing i do think we probably want to
do eventually is
rewrite this to be ray bundle based now
that we are always shooting ray bundles
but
yeah we did always have this problem i
believe
um it doesn't now that we are much
faster it spreads much quicker because
you have to remember like
it's very hard for this feedback to
happen
if the
total
like contamination number like the the
contamination speed is capped
so for example in here uh when we used
to say like this was going to be
much lower so let's say this was 1
out of 60 so there was a 1 second of lag
it takes a lot longer for contamination
to occur
so because the light is so laggy you
won't see this contamination
unless you hold a particular
location for a very long time
right and that's just because it takes
so freaking long we can probably set
this up so you know 2.0 was fairly fast
contamination before
i believe at six
um
it's it's simply
not going to be very fast uh when it's
got that dampening on it it takes a
really long time right
so before when the lighting was really
slow you wouldn't have this problem
later we upped it so it's six times
faster now
you get a tremendously
faster contamination right
so something that was not visible is
like very visible
at six times speed
and again that's just because now we can
just run it so much faster
so i don't think we actually had this
problem happening that often before and
part of the reason for that was the
lighting was too slow
right
um
now that the lighting is fast any
feedback effects we will always actually
see them uh whereas before they were
kind of like hidden from us right
uh so you know
uh getting better in a way made us get
worse right it made us made it harder
for us to you know
to get away with things like that
so i don't have
any idea how to progress here i feel
like what we need here is education
uh
and
we need like
we need to have a more solid idea about
how we're computing these equations so
that we have an argument for why they
wouldn't just feedback
you know
i also
would like to know how much feedback
there is in sort of the broader sense of
the term like if we had
like what would this look like if we
just had a exposure curve on here and
like maybe that's an easy thing to add
uh i don't really know what kind of
exposure curve we want to put on here
um because that's kind of a
tough call separately
but you know at the moment we don't
apply any exposure curve at all
and so if we were to go into like how
the lighting is sampled here right we
we do
uh one of these like surface reflect
things
uh i guess there's a fogging factor in
here still
for no real reason
we don't use that anymore
uh but we
we don't really apply there's like a
clamp
in here
right but we don't actually apply any
kind of
uh
i don't know why this is written out
manually either we don't reply any kind
of curve to it right
so we could
uh apply an exposure curve like a really
simple one like a brain dead one to see
what happens
um
like
a
simple exposure curve
oh no
no
um
shader
exposure curve
uh
yeah i mean sure
i like learn opengl
um
so that's reinhardt tone mapping would
be fine
and that's just the color of the color
plus one
uh it's not good
but that would be fine
that would be fine i'm fine with that um
let's let's just see what happens right
first of all can is there a reason why
this was written as three of these like
can we not just do this
does that not work
because i i don't
know why that wouldn't work
yeah so that that seems fine
um so i'm just curious so if we were to
clamp this
uh as it's it over itself
plus one
which again is like just just brain dead
you know
uh brain dead tone mapping
uh
what does that do
i'm just curious
uh it didn't like how i wrote that
well you know what when you don't close
your parentheses
that's uh that's a valid thing to
complain about i agree
i agree shader compiler
uh so here's a tone mapped version of
the output
uh just so we can kind of see but it
still looks completely feedback it's
still totally feedback
right to me like that's not producing
any actual
light
like it's totally not actually producing
lighting there it's totally feeding back
um
so i really think this is just wrong
like i really think we just have a
something wrong-headed about the way
that we're doing it it just it always
floods the scene with light and it
doesn't have anything to do with what
the actual overall values are that you
pick
um
it's just wrong
uh yes beginner questions are okay by
the way although we don't always take
questions while we're actually working
um
but
but beginner questions are definitely
okay
i i answer beginner questions all the
time
so we really do have some yeah and i
just don't feel like i have the
necessary like i haven't
figured out how to think through this
problem properly
so
like we're just not oh i forgot those
skull guys can go anywhere they wanted
to i'm gonna run away from that
um so we have issues here that we need
to address
that have to do with that over writing
that's happening there
and their problem with thinking uh in
terms of like
how we avoid using the same lighting in
multiple places such that it feeds back
on itself and i i literally just don't
have
any idea what it is that we're doing
differently
as far as sampling the light probes go
it could still be a bug but based on the
light board
i'm just not sure it actually is a bug i
mean it's a bug for sure but it's not a
bug of the form like we forgot a minus
sign right i'm still concerned that it's
a bug meaning that the strategy is
busted
we're missing something that's supposed
to happen here
that we're not doing
um
the
other thing i would say is maybe is it
possible that when we thought we turned
off probe to probe transmission that
somehow we didn't actually turn it off
like like maybe that is what's happening
and and so when we tested to see does it
still happen with that
we turned it off and then it turns out
we didn't actually turn it off i don't
know that's that's possible
um
i don't think that's likely but you know
it it's worth checking
so in here right
uh we have a thing we do where we say if
we
hit the uh apron or walked too far
without without finding an intersection
so like we don't hit anything
uh we have a thing here where we can
turn on like zeroing out the hit ref
color and the hit emission so that like
basically it just won't
like or the argument is
it won't be able to
uh sample anything if it doesn't hit a
surface
right
um and
i think we proved that the feedback
happens anyway right you can see it
still happening
uh
so
i'm pretty sure that that has nothing to
do with it
i mean similarly the grid walk iteration
part of things
we can just turn off
right we can just say
you know
equals eight and it will never equal
eight because we're not adding anything
to it so now we know this will only
happen at the apron all rays will be
cast as far as they need to get cast
right
and we still get exactly the same
problem
so i'm pretty sure that probe to probe
contributions just aren't an issue
actually
um
so probe to probe
and you know honestly it seems like we
don't really care about that anyway it
looks like we could just just
not have the grid walk iteration
terminator as well like i don't know
this part seems kind of irrelevant
so it's pretty rough it's pretty rough
um
uh valbus yeah
well i don't know that's i would call
them sampling errors but like i was
saying before the discretization of the
problem seems
like it could be part of it because you
can sort of get the same light probes
light the same
light flow reflected off multiple
surfaces
potentially erroneously
now
to
you know when we
sample
and and you know the like like we don't
keep
the normals which they do so we're not
using the like normal to normal
um
fall off
either
yeah i don't know
oh uh there was the copy past the
transfer pps accumulan can we peak
through again sure yeah of course uh is
this
which which one
so there's this one
uh
but about that may that may not be the
one you're talking about uh can you be
more specific about which one you want
to see i can scroll to it
um
but i don't know which one i
you're talking about like when it adds
or like like this one
here
zero as last args
um
[Music]
but i think that's
correct
right
um this is this
we probably want to rewrite this in
terms of ray bundles now that we're
doing things fairly differently so you
know this stuff is kind of inefficient
as you can see why some of these look
with some of these to do's and stuff
but uh the way this was doing it before
right is the shuffler was picking out
uh
you know one of the reasons i think now
we could switch it to that is is because
we simplified things so much i think we
could switch this to doing ray bundles
and they all cast out the same
before we were casting out one ray per
texel now we're casting out like at
least eight so going as a ray bundle
would make a tremendous amount of sense
probably i mean in some cases it it
wouldn't be fantastic maybe but
i i think it would be
plausible that we could do that
but the point is the way the shuffler
stuff worked
it's been a long time but just my
recollection of it
is the shuffler just picks out which one
was the
was the actual best hit
right
so when you pick out which one was the
actual best hit i believe it shuffles
the value that is the
um
the correct value
uh it shuffles that value to the front
so i believe this is supposed to be zero
everywhere
right
um
i i don't think that's copy pasta i
guess what i was saying i think that's
just correct
uh but you know
i i certainly could be wrong about that
but i don't think that's actually wrong
um
does does that
make sense
um but i'll i'll go you one further and
just say like let's suppose that that
even that that was wrong
uh then it's still probably fine because
the r g and the b for our services right
now are the same we don't actually have
any color
in the reflectance
you know we could we just don't right
now
so i you know
the second argument is just saying which
lane you wanted to pick out so basically
like if you were trying to extract the
first one here i'll show you
uh if you're trying to extract the first
one
uh you
[Music]
yeah i mean well you can see it here
right
you pass a zero to extract the first one
um
one to do the second two to do the third
three to do the fourth right and and
this is easier you don't have to do it
this way if you're not on sse there's
there's faster ways of doing it
on more modern
um
like on avx or whatever you've you've
got like extract
calls this is very inefficient
like i do think we could get
now at this point we could probably get
a pretty significant speed upgrade by
rewriting this code
to be brave
to be wide on raise
because then this entire code actually
unwinds into just its scalar equivalent
and it does four arrays at the same time
right
and that would probably be dramatically
faster
we would slow down a little in the grid
walk because the grid walk would get
slower
the reason for that being that uh rays
that early terminate uh
keep marching so you're but uh we don't
even that might not get that much slower
because you're coherently pulling
potentially this from the same
locations uh which might lead to better
um
cast behavior as well i'm not really
sold that that may not really be true
but um so so probably this wants to get
rewritten um but it probably doesn't
need to be written right now because
that's just largely speed it's not going
to change
the bug you saw the exact same bug after
we were done rewriting it so you know i
feel like we can just save that for but
it would clean up this routine a lot and
be less and it probably would run faster
as well
so we probably do want to do that at
some point
that would be my guess
so
we still would have to
at the very end we'd have to broadcast
out
uh we'd fl flatten down
it's not really broadcast we'd flatten
down and some
uh because we we probably don't want to
cast in the same wide as we're doing our
summations here
um
i mean maybe we do because it is rg and
b
it might be that we could even leave it
and then shuffle them i don't know
uh i don't want to talk about that right
now because that's all performance stuff
it's a lot simpler than the bug word you
know it's meticulous work but it's easy
to do
so we can do that at any time it's not a
big deal just a little bit of elbow
grease so really what i'd rather focus
on right now is our
like the bug right
this is a definite bug
and
it's just a lack of understanding like i
don't actually think what we're seeing
is wrong based on how we've defined
what's happening so it's like i feel
like it's our actual definition that
needs to be changed the problem is i
don't quite see how you change it
uh and and
so so that
that is the real puzzler
uh maybe we go back to the light board
and just see if we can figure something
out i don't know
maybe i go get some more pork skins
fried pork skins and i and i eat those
and i drown my sorrows and pork skins
uh but like i said i mean this is really
just a hole in my light transport
knowledge uh i'm just not comfortable
working with light
uh because i've never really spent the
time to do it uh if i had done a lot
more ray tracing work in my life this
would not like i'm sure we could work
through this problem very quickly right
so the main problem is just my like
relative in familiarity with the right
ways to think about light values
so there's probably just a very simple
thing that we're missing
uh when we're doing the sampling
and
uh
and i just don't know
[Music]
exactly what it is mind mark the thing
that the normal what the what the
uh light probe paper was talking about
with respect to storing normals is that
if you look at what we're actually
storing and we don't have unfortunately
a very good way of visualizing it but i
i can i can turn on
in
debug draw
so
here
so if i draw the actual what we're
sampling the octahedral values
that we store at each light probe uh
this is just a representation a visual
representation of them
and you can see right like each one of
those directions it's i'm just showing
the light and
that's you know that's flowing
uh
along those lines and you can kind of
see that you know until the light
contamination problem it's it's fairly
sane you can see our other bug here you
can see why that the reason that that is
black there's no light flowing in there
uh is because we currently don't handle
when a light source is uh occlude uh so
like a light source surrounds it so
there's a light source right here
uh that's basically like enclosing it
right so that's the other bug but that's
a much simpler bug because that's more
just us deciding how we're gonna handle
that it's not like a hole in our
knowledge
right
let me turn off the light contamination
for one second so i can finish
explaining what i was about to explain
uh as well
so oops
no
stop
there we go
uh so if we turn this back down to a
non-contaminating value like 1.0
and then i run it again
and we show those values again
uh so what the paper
uh what the papers actually do
is in addition to each one of these
normals
they also store the
in that direction
the last hit
uh that they had
well not the last hit the average of the
hits they store what the normal was
that they hit
so like for example in addition to that
we would also store well and in fact i
can even sort of show you uh i don't
remember if we
left this on or not but
doesn't look like we did
because i'm not seeing it anywhere
so
maybe we turned off the debugging
yeah i don't normally we would see the
little debugger on here but i don't
actually see
i don't actually see any
evidence
of the little debug of the little raid
debugger
um why is that
oh you know why grid raycast debugging
is probably just set to zero
to turn that back on
okay
so in the paper i should now be able to
[Music]
show you what i was talking about
um
[Music]
oh that's interesting so do we
do we not
oh right because it's white noise now so
it's kind of just random yeah all right
cool
we would probably have to put a pause on
that so that we could debug it if we
needed to debug it further but i forgot
we changed to white noise so that it
won't be a stable array it will be kind
of an arbitrary direction
so what you can see here right is one of
the samples that's getting taken out of
this part of the octahedral map that
sums into if we look you know kind of
straight down the barrel here you can
see it's that
this there's going to be like a texel
there that's being represented
uh and these are some of the sample
arrays that are getting cast and it's
white noise so it varies per frame
you can see the the
brown the darker brown line there is the
normal that we hit like the surface
normal at the point that we hit
now we do use that surface normal to
when we compute how much light we will
record as coming back into the light
probe here
we do
actually
have that value
used in the sampling
but we don't remember it
so
later when somebody samples from this
light probe they don't have any
information about what the actual
surface normal was the direction they
were going
i think what the paper does is the paper
assumes that
when you're going to sample the light
probe
they check to see if the surface normal
was
was mutually occlusive with the sampling
with the surface normal that you're
sampling from
right so the direction you're sampling
from couldn't possibly have hit that
surface normal then it doesn't use it
right
um
that's my guess anyway
so they they basically store that normal
so they can have more accurate
which you know does that
you know
i don't know
so the other thing i would say is like
maybe part of our problem you know is
part of our problem here just that the
numbers in this system have to all be
less than one always
um because of some aspect of the system
that i don't totally understand which
means that actually we don't really have
a bug we just need to change all of our
light values to be lower and then the
tone mapping curve to be higher and then
we and then it's just we call it a day
because one thing is like why aren't
these lights feeding back
right and and i have no idea so if for
example and i'm just gonna
like let's
let's just go down that route slightly
so
uh let's suppose
um
let's suppose that we oops
um i don't actually need this to be on
let's suppose that we did that so
when we have
when we've have it all
if we were to turn off the lighting
entirely
and so now you know the glove is the
only light in the scene
and you can see it and we have our bug
uh where it includes the light source
right you can kind of see it
literally doing that right
um
but other than that it looks correct and
it doesn't do any light contamination
but
maybe we want that to be pretty bright
right
and so what we would want to have here
is our exposure curve would treat that
lighting as pretty bright lighting
or something
right i don't know i mean this is kind
of
i'm definitely winging it here so i'm
not trying to say anything
as if i know what i'm talking about when
it comes to this kind of stuff
but
um so let's suppose like that was
supposed to be pretty bright and so what
we want to do is we want this to be
mapped to a curve
where uh
you know
you
[Music]
you assume that this light is quite a
bit brighter than it is so you know it's
like
yeah yeah like one is like 10 times the
brightness or something
right like it's just way brighter
uh lighting
than before i don't know what this is
gonna do but i'm just
throwing that out there right
um
so like that is like like the the glove
is like a very bright light um now
because 1.0 is extremely light maybe
it's even brighter than that maybe it's
like it's a hundred right so like 1.0 is
like a super freaking bright light the
brightest light you've ever seen in your
lifetime
it's so bright that we can't even handle
how bright it is
right
well we don't get the feedback problem
but we get the same output
right you see why i'm confused about
this right like it doesn't make good
intuitive sense but you can see
kind of where i'm going with it all
right and now let's suppose we add back
in our standard lighting
which is now going to be way too bright
uh for us
we don't want it to be so bright
uh so we're gonna have to bring those
lamp lights down quite a bit they're at
which is much too high right uh you know
so so i don't know what they should be
like let's say 0.1 or something i'm not
sure
something like this
um
we now get the same effect like you can
see why i'm confused right we get the
same effect that we wanted a very bright
glove
so bright that it's brighter than we
even would want right and i can remove
those
where the heck is my debug draw
octahedral uh there we go
um it's so bright that we probably
wouldn't even want it to be that bright
until we actually have some kind of a
tone mapping going on right um
but we have the exact same thing we had
before but now we don't get light
contamination
like it's massively bright right there
but it simply doesn't cause that problem
right so
something about
something about the fact that the
numbers have to be zero to one
is like
in
there's something fundamental about the
fact that the numbers have to be zero to
one that we don't freaking understand
right
and
so
and and i mean the good news is that
means
we don't really have a bug
in the code but the bad news is it means
we have a bug in our brain
right
uh the bug is in the brain the bug is
coming from inside the brain
uh but
so
so yeah i mean we're kind of fine at
that point
uh no worries i mean the glove is now
too bright so we would want to tone the
glove down as well
uh obviously but you can see what i mean
like there's there's just a fundamental
thing about keeping the values between
zero and one for lighting
i obviously just don't understand that
like like i obviously wasn't
i wasn't thinking there would be a
difference between those things
but there's definitely a difference
between those two things
so
i'm very confused right i just i just
don't quite understand why
and so something like this basically
looks correct right like this looks like
a game that you would play and you would
buy on steam or whatever
um and we didn't change anything we just
remapped our values to be in the zero to
one range and applied boosting after the
fact now of course we have to reduce the
exterior lights as well i suppose i
should have done that
as well because we have like a moon
thing
um
that we like add
we generate the apron there's like a
moon
[Music]
light thing
uh here
that we did and that's like gonna be way
too bright now so i don't know
what that should be like 0.025 or
something
[Music]
i guess
i don't know
um still actually quite bright so i mean
maybe just 0.01
for exterior
[Music]
um and you know that's
maybe about right but it's really it
really should be pretty dim out there
because there's you know i don't know
uh but that's the moonlight outside that
we were adding um which is supposed to
be quite dim right as you can see
uh and that's fine
but uh
yeah i mean we just totally got the
effect we wanted
and and literally all we did was like
renormalize the values so all right so
there's something broken in our brain
there we should probably figure out what
it is
also
our square like light problem got a lot
better as well uh as part of that so
obviously like you know tone mapping
needs to be high on the list of things
we're going to do here
um
because getting that right does seem
like it's probably something we want to
do
but
uh either or
or or
um
yeah whatever
let's let that one
sit for a little bit i don't know what
time it is right now
it's two o'clock
um
yeah
gorgeous light that we don't understand
is a very way good way to describe it um
to be fair we understand a lot of it
there's just some
there's some
so let me phrase it this way
one of the values in our system
is clearly
clearly
either the lighting or something closely
related to the lighting is bait is a is
a
i'm i'm just going to say
the problem is that some portion of the
system is is inherently working as a
percentage
that we did not anticipate to be working
as a percentage
right
we've got a unitless value in our system
somewhere
that we didn't think was a percentage
but has to be a percentage and if that
percentage is 110
percent
then it just grows over time and if that
value is 90 it does not right
um so we we fundamentally have a a
unitless value in our system somewhere
that's screwed up
right
okay
uh but we still have another problem the
darkening uh we know what that is and we
have to kind of think about what we're
going to do to solve that problem
there's a number of ways we can solve
that problem we know exactly where it is
and what it comes from
there's a way we can mute that problem
like make that problem be less bad but
we want to actually fix it so where does
that come from let's turn on the debug
drawing again
i explained it before but let's explain
it again because we weren't working on
it before and and now we are
so if i debug draw the octahedral values
again
so you can actually see where all the
lighting is you know
and i take it one step further and i
draw the spatial grid as well
so if i go into debug draw spatial grid
uh there's just going to be a lot of
visual noise here i apologize for that
we don't have that greater debug vis in
the lighting system so um you know
if we if we take a look at this
uh what you can see is like there's a
big kind of fat light that we just added
here you know we haven't done much work
on world generations so we just threw in
a light
and the problem is that light that you
can sort of see here it's it's this you
know this um
interior set like these are ceiling
tiles here right which we don't draw
because we want to be able to just see
through them
so these are ceiling tiles
and then here this is the light source
right that right there is the light
source
um and you know what i could do too i
could uh try doing a thing where i draw
those
have you ever tried this debug
dross
spatial grid have you tried just like
using the color of the actual leaf node
um because
uh
we must have to store that because we
use it right
um so you know ref color here
uh that
you know that is what that is
and our is emission uh value we could
you know we could sort of put those two
together
uh and and try to make this actually
show more of what the actual system is
so i could do something like instead of
this being a checkerboard here
i could put a thing in here where we set
the color based on that so you know get
component
uh of this leaf ref color and we take e
out of that
that gives us uh the color value to draw
and we would need to use the emission
as well
but what's your complaint operator type
of
really
because that's a v4 that's why
can we do this
i think we added that
yep we did add that um
so if i draw the colors of things you
might be able to see them a little bit
better i don't know if you actually will
or not so let's try to make this work i
don't know why those are all white
though that doesn't seem right
um
well i guess they would kind of all be
white
that's sort of true i need to account
for the emission here
so if i account for the emission
uh let's give that a shot
um
that would show us where our light
sources are pretty cleanly i think
um
we don't have a get component for one of
these oh you know why because you can
literally just type
that probably
yeah
um so here you can see reflectors versus
light sources so black is reflectors
white is light sources
or rather the light sources are colored
based on what light they emit so you
know cyan because it's a cyan light
source white because it's a white light
source
uh so in the world what happens is if a
sample point starts out inside um of
anything like geometry whether that
geometry is a light source or not it
doesn't take any samples
right
and
instead what should probably happen is
it should just
that sample should not bother casting
array it should just write
the value back
right
and so
it's a really tough call i don't know
what we want to do here there's a lot of
ways we could tackle this problem and
i'm just not sure
which one
makes the most sense for us
currently the reason that we just stop
is because we do a pre-check to see
whether or not we're inside anything
right
so in here
once we go to
the full cast this code right here does
a pre-check on every place we're going
to cast from and the first thing that it
does is it says well if you're or if
you're entirely inside
one of
uh the piece of geometry
right now what we do is we just spam
black
into there
right
and we could do all sorts of things we
could do nothing right like we could
literally just leave it alone
um and that would avoid the flicker
problem so like if we just left it alone
uh that would mean that for example we
don't get the darkening as the glove
moves around right so that would quote
unquote solve
that uh
that part of the problem
but you'll notice we do
have sort of
we still do have a bug with the lighting
right
which is that we get
contributions from the glove when it is
like cleanly in between two of these but
as it like occludes them we don't get
much right so we we lose light that
should be showing up reflecting on the
floor is not going to be
so it feels like what we'd want to do
here is we'd want to actually you know
uh treat those samples more properly
now the slow way we the slowest way to
do this would be to actually run this
check on every
sample that we take
and
jitter the sample location
out to
the radius of the
voxel so we would just sample randomly
in the voxel and raycast randomly in the
voxel right
and we would
sum up the number of these that were
inside we would add that much light to
the actual outgoing spectacles
at that point
right
um
and i i just kind of feel like that's
going to be too noisy or too slow i
don't know
but i don't see a lot of ways around
that because as lights
move over
we we need that to be reflected
so i don't know that there's a lot of
ways around that i mean we could do
something where we add light into the
system here
with the forward pass
and that might be better actually
so let's ask a separate question so
what's let's suppose what happens if we
just turn this entire branch off so now
we let the things cast from inside
what does our caster do when you're
casting from inside
what happens
does it just hit the thing and that's
fine
because if so it's kind of cheese
but if that's cheese if that's the
cheese that we have in our lives like
what happens if i try to can i i don't
know i might not be able to really get
this positioned
in a way that
it quite occludes exactly
um but you know these light sources all
seem just fine
right um it's not correct because
they're casting out and actually having
to hit the thing
but maybe for like the purposes of real
time where we don't really want to add
more work
maybe that's just fine
like maybe we just cheese that out
and we just say look it's cheese time in
the cheese corral and everyone should
unbox the government cheese you know
so
i'm willing to do that for now
i would document this for sure
because you know it's totally wrong
but i just don't want to slow things
down too much because
uh
yeah i mean i i think that's
i think it could be very costly to do
something better there and so if we can
do something wrong but that works okay i
think that's probably fine
i'm just going to say
although yeah wait uh now i think about
though that's not quite true because you
know what else will happen we'll get
light leaking through walls
right in fact we probably already had
that happen we just didn't notice
because i wasn't paying attention to it
right so you see how like now the walls
are all like kind of lit uniformly the
reason for that is that in there they're
not they're actually able to collect
light
um
i would however ask why because we
i thought
were sort of
i thought we were saying that you
couldn't collect from a normal
that couldn't have reflected back to you
so actually that may mean that we're
missing a normal
ah no you know what probably we just
don't we just don't test against back
faces
so it probably just can soar out through
there okay
so yeah
we would at the very least have to check
to see whether the thing is an emitter
or not
right
we could let you do emitter casting and
force you not to do other kinds of
casting so let's see
what we think of that
again still cheese just trying a
different type of cheese
more like
um
maybe like a barnyard cheddar
as opposed to something like you know
a danish havarti or something like that
so
let's take a look at what we would do if
we were doing this inside mask here
where we did inbounds everywhere if we
basically said you can't do
um
occluders we would have i'm sorry you
can't do emitters
uh we could do is emitter equals leaf is
emission right
um
uh and then we would say uh that
value
if it's greater than zero
uh
yeah
we would say
and
not emitter we would say something like
not emitter equals
is emitter greater than zero
right
um and knotted which we may have an
operator for
i don't actually know
um
[Music]
that is not
the right variable declaration
uh
i might as well call this by the same
name as it was
so we don't have mr noddington
there unfortunately
uh which
is a bummer
let's find out why whose idea was it to
not have that or did we just call it
something else
like we obviously had an and operator
like you can see we've got all the rest
of them did we just cheese out and not
ever put in
oh you know why because it's not really
not like we're gonna be doing the entire
flip so it's it's really like a
you know it's a till day but
but we didn't implement that one either
so it's hardly an explanation
um
so that seems fine
so actually we can just do an and not
and
we don't have to
really
like
even do the not of it anyway
right
um
so i think that would produce the right
the right lane based equation for
emitters don't stop you but other things
too
right
so it's inbounds and not an emitter and
not
an emitter
um
we should now have
both of those things
maybe
um and
again slightly cheesy
but i think
that would probably
be fine
[Music]
um
so i don't know i mean it's not as good
because you want the
you know and maybe we could combine
these two right we could combine it with
a forward flood fill so we we look at
light surfaces
and we would
write the light surfaces into the light
probes
like at those locations
all right i mean fine
so
uh yeah we could i mean we could have
changed this to just equals right
um you know another way to write this if
someone was asking about this in the
chat we could write it the other way
right
you could do that
and that's just saying if you don't emit
light then you're a positive you know
you're a positive includer
um same
same same
right
um so maybe that's just
an easier way to read that anyway
um but you know you can still see the
problem uh so like if you take a look at
what happens in here
um
like
if i
punch
out to here
you can see that this should be having a
bunch of uh actual light in it um
it's kind of hard for me to hold down
enough keys at the same time here
but you can see like what this
light probe is showing right now i push
out the
um
the light and it's actually enclosing it
and yet
you don't see much contribution right
the reason for that is it can't hit this
thing right it's only able to pick it up
indirectly
and so i feel like we might also want it
to
to write the lighting into the probes
that it
is into the probe into the grid
locations where the light overlaps
um
so like a forward pass that writes
lights
into
things they overlap
i'm wondering if maybe that isn't just a
good idea in general
like suppose
i can turn off the spatial production
uh
the debug draw spatial grid thing
uh doesn't need to be on there
anymore obviously
um i might leave the octagonal values on
while we're looking at this particular
problem but
um
so like
these directions are also now bs by the
way because we're still using the
like
we're using the sphere right we're using
the sampling sphere
um
to draw them but they're casting white
noise so it's total nonsense that we're
drawing right like this is drawing
um
oh wait no it's using the vauxhall so
that's fine it's not that i take it back
that's nonsense i think it's using the
voxel so it's it's just showing the
direction of the box so that's totally
fine
um
so yeah uh gosh the question is just if
i was to do that so suppose i was to
write the light values into the grid as
a pre-pass so any when we're when we're
putting them in the space partition
anytime we see some of the missive value
we rasterize that into the uh
into the light probes
um
what does that do for us
does that do
how do we because i don't know
the total size of handmade hero is
uh
sorry what do you mean what does the
total size mean
doing like lines of code
or
uh
something else
because yeah i think we could get this a
little better by rasterizing the lights
as a pre-pass
i like the fact that with the collision
detector turned off we can punch through
and make a light outside the wall
um
because you can kind of see that you get
sort of a like a blinking effect too
like right so
there it would be worth it in the dark i
think we would get much better results
right if we did this because you
wouldn't get so much variance in the
brightness as this kind of bobs around
relative to light probes you get a much
more constant value which is i think
what we would want there so i do think
it would it would be a good idea
oh how big is the binary
oh gosh i don't know because we don't
really build in a small we don't build a
small version of the binary at the
moment so it's probably quite large
actually
um
so yeah it's
it's around a megabyte
we don't build a small binary at the
moment so it's around a megabyte
um it still includes a c runtime library
even though we only call like one thing
from it so that
also bloats us out
unfortunately
so
so it's fairly large
for no real reason
but about a megabyte
oh yeah without assets i mean we we have
like
tons of like assets are large in this
game they're fairly high res and bit 2d
bitmaps so they're that's no no way
that's fitting into megabyte unless you
do some demo scene coding right
uh which you could totally do and try to
get it down but uh right we don't do any
of that so yeah
but yeah it's about a megabyte
executable
um it could be much smaller than that i
think
that's kind of like very wasteful
size-wise um
we could be a lot smaller than that but
at the moment we're just not
so i think yeah i guess i would say i
think we should maybe try a light
rasterization pre-pass there because we
when we go through them we know when we
hit light sources because we have to
insert them into the spatial partition
anyway
and we know that they're not going to be
sampled correctly because when we sample
to them we you know we don't know what
to do when we're inside them we're not
sure how we would really gather that and
it seems like it'd be faster to do that
forward than it would be to do that
backward
so
what would that look like it would
basically be like for each light source
we step through the voxels and see how
much
uh voxel overlap there is and then we
add like that much of that light source
in but
but
what direction do we add it in
right um
what direction
you know
i ask you
it's 2 30.
do we try to do something with that
today
yeah
yes let's just add it to the left it the
light lights in handmade hero
lights go to the left that's it that's
the limitation artistic
it is a deliberate artistic choice
um
in handmade hero that lights
go leftward you you don't if you wanted
a light that went right
you gotta go use the unreal engine
that's just the rule
okay there are other engines available
if you wanted light sources that shine
rightward then that is why you know you
go use unreal engine or something
because they added support in unreal
five for lights that shine to the right
okay we're just not adding those in
handmade hero lights all go to the left
that's just an artistic choice
that we made
um where and we just think that left
lights that go left are inherently more
interesting
and and visually they're more visually
interesting than lights that go right
and i think
you know that's what differentiates
indie games from you know these big aaa
games
right
um
[Music]
so so that's good
no in all seriousness uh
what i mean to say is that if you look
at how a light is going to be
distributed so for example
we want a light you know we've got a
light centered on the glove and as i
move it around it moves but what we want
to do is make sure that it actually gets
more representation
uh in the light probes that it uh you
know is actually overlapping which at
the moment it really doesn't uh get
and so in order to do that what we want
to do is say well okay if we were to add
light
based on the volume of the light source
and how much it overlaps each of the
constituents here the the light probes
that are likely to see it
um
what what i assume we would want to do
is we would want to have the
light
you would want to add light proportional
to how much of the light
volume overlaps the
voxel volume
for the probe
and
if it
if it overlapped the entire thing you
just add it in all directions but what
if it like only overlaps this one half
you would expect it to
to not add light to the other side
right um
and and that really is the thing that
i'm not sure what i would do like like
it is what i'm saying logical
like like
am i correct in saying you would expect
it not to add to the other side or is is
that actually totally
false what i'm saying
and
and you wouldn't so it's the light that
passes through the area
light should not be passing through the
other direction right because
the the light itself is on the other
side of the volume so you should you
would only expect it to be kind of going
one way away from it you wouldn't expect
to be going the other direction
although you wouldn't probably care that
much if you were
right
so maybe we do something like this maybe
we say that we take the closest point on
the light source volume to the light
probe center
which will actually just be the light
probe itself if it's entirely enclosed
which means that it can just shine in
general
[Music]
or
no i've got it i've got it
what we instead do
is we basically see how much the light
overlaps the volume in each of the three
dimensions and we basically use
that
as
as how much we write into the octahedron
right
because we would know like we know the
overlap in x and the overlap in y
so at the very least we should be able
to do
like
that's the region of the octahedral map
we write into is those t x and t y
values
right
so there's probably a way to do that
like pretty cleverly right um
i probably want to start not trying to
not doing it that complicated because
that's a pretty
fancy that's some pretty fancy footwork
you know what else we could do is just
do this stochastically we could also
just generate random points inside the
light volume
and for a given point then you obviously
know which direction it is
because you can just literally do
the
you know the subtraction between the two
between the light probe
location and the light
the point on the light that you picked
so maybe let's go the stochastic route
first
where we just and it doesn't have to
necessarily be sarcastic it could
literally be regular like we could
literally just sample
regular points on the light source
but let's do that
first
which means
we leave everything as it is we don't
make any changes to this right now
but we do on our path through the light
source we generate a bunch of random
garbage
and we sum those into the light
um
we sum those into the light
specular
by the way
i have a question
does our lighting now by default also
i'm sorry i'm to get off topic here but
does our light basically also support
specular now because we compute the
specular map
and the diffuse map
and i don't know if we send the specular
map down or not
i i literally don't remember
um if anyone actually submits the spec
map or if we only ever submit
um
the
the diffuse map
light
depth sampler
we don't actually use that like we never
implemented that that was going to be so
we did actually even think about that
interesting
so the light color sampler is only
sampling the diffuse map we only we only
send the diffuse map down at the moment
but we have the spec
right so like
when we link the sampler here
so we update both of them
the diffuse atlas handle and the
specular light handle are both submitted
and both are bound
so we do have
both of them
but we just don't
use them this this old this code is so
nasty i really wish we had a way to read
this better we're going to have to move
these out to separate text files i think
is the only real answer i wanted to
avoid having to do that but it's
obviously not going to happen so
so that's fine i don't even think four
coder gets worked on anymore right
i assume at this point it's just not
it's just a non a non thing
uh so
we'll probably have to deal with that at
some point maybe someday we can switch
to that 10x ide thing that seemed like a
pretty good thing i don't know
um
we'll have to see how it comes along i'm
not sure how it's going at this point
but
anyway uh if we have
the
the light color sampler here
um
i guess i'm not sure where the light
depth sampler comes in like that was
something we used to be doing i guess
when we thought we were going to have to
implement the depth part of it but
you know we didn't actually do that
so the light depth sampler is the fourth
one i think that's just the specular map
though because if you look at what
happens here texture two and three
um
the depth is
is
it's not that like that's not
what that is
so i think light depth sampler is
actually the the spec map and i don't
know why it's called that i think we
thought we were gonna do that or i don't
know
why i guess i don't really know
um it doesn't get used
right i'm going to go ahead and say that
that is just specular
sampler
instead
um because i can because i wrote the
code
and i'm gonna just ask the question what
happens if you sample from the spec map
instead of the diffuse map
right i mean why not there's no
particular reason you can't do that uh
it's just at the moment everything
happens to be sampling from the diffuse
uh map now they're the same dimension
um
so this is actually sampling from
[Music]
what is this oct map interiov dim
specular vs uv dim diffuse
so we even compute the specular and then
we just don't use it
i guess so
so at the moment we actually s
compute
two of these but we only use one of them
i guess
we really need to clean this up i don't
know if what the right answer is i
really was hoping we could just keep all
the code in one thing
but
unless i guess i go modify for coder
myself i could modify the source code
for coder probably
to actually format this it's kind of
impossible to read a complex shader in
this way it's complete garbage right
like you don't get any indenting or
anything like that so it's pretty
impossible to actually use
and of course because c plus is designed
by people who have you know collectively
if you sum them all together 0.5 brain
cells there's no way to actually just
like use included here docs here i don't
think so we can't just put this in a
separate file and then say include this
as a string i think like people have
i know people have actually literally
even submitted proposals to do that and
i think it took them like many years to
decide on it and they ruined it or
something so i still don't know if we
ever actually got that after 40 years of
c plus specifications
maybe that's in there now i don't know
um
that would obviously be another solution
to this problem if you could just pound
include a string which is an obvious
thing you would do
in any language
but you know
heaven forbid the c standards committee
allows you to include binary data into a
freaking executable
anyway
um so i don't know that we have much of
a way around this and this is really
hard to read so i'm not sure what we
should do about that we could add
something that just loads these as text
files
or maybe someone can tell me if they
ever frickin got pound including strings
into the freaking language
but assuming they didn't were stuck here
and
uh i just wanted to know like
looking at
some of this we can probably cut out
like
like i don't know what this is supposed
to be but
this is a specular
mixing function
i just don't know that we
i i don't know how useful this would be
to us but it is
a mixing function light v
is the encoding of the
light brightness
light and encoding is yeah so this is we
don't
we can just rewrite this again like it's
just a reflection like let's get rid of
this just so we yeah we don't need that
um again just trying to like
clean this up a little bit so we can
read it
i think standard embed got just like
does anyone know how it's possible that
the c plus of certain committee is as
bad as it is do they have some kind of
pre-filter where they're like
we only allow programmers who literally
have no idea what they're doing to
contribute like is that some kind of
like did they work out a way to ensure
that nobody who ever actually got
something done in their life is on this
committee
i don't know how they manage it it's
like it's kind of amazing if you could
just figure out a way to
to
invert
the quality of this like most things
can't
be as good as the cpos committee is at
at being bad being that consistently
wrong in and of itself is hard because
it almost means you know what the right
answer is and then you intentionally not
do it because
nobody can
by
nobody can randomly be as bad as the
sibo suspect they're more rand they're
more
wrong than random would be wrong right
which means that they actually have a
process that ensures that correct
answers don't happen
right which is a different thing than
just
not having a process that ensures
correct things happen
it's really kind of insane and i don't
know how it's possible
so so they literally have some way
um
of ensuring that good ideas cannot be
added
as opposed to having
as opposed to just not having a
procedure that ensures that good ideas
do get adopted right
uh and and and that it's almost worth
studying because if you could just do
the opposite of what they do you would
have a committee that always makes the
right decision and so there is value
like there's value to studying the sibo
sanders committee because i feel like
nobody else in history has ever come up
with a system that guarantees that they
will never make a good decision
that
that's almost as hard as always making
good decision
it's terrible it's the worst possible
thing you could be but it's also
educational because no one's ever
figured out how to
how to do something like that before
that i know of like no one's ever been
able to make sure that they will never
make a good decision that's that's kind
of hard
in my mind you know
i don't know
i think like sam oburya or somebody
should do a study on the sleepos
committee and be like
well we we don't know who just
we we don't know who to study to find
out how to like
solve success successor the successor
problem
right
but we do know who to study who is
someone who has who has sort of solved
it in the inverse like they've
guaranteed that nobody ever
in the entire history no one has ever
succeeded in the cpus committee at
actually making a positive improvement
that's almost the same as solving the
successor problem because if it was just
random who was succeeding them they
would sometimes make a positive decision
right
another way to say it would be
if you could
you could use the sipa fuss committee
as part of your language design process
by asking them to pick the next set of
things to add and then removing those
from the things you consider adding
right
so
oh yes uh
youngster glenn just said exactly what i
was sort of formally he would got there
faster
if you had enough c plus plus standards
committees all you'd have to do is
design a language so exclusively out of
things they didn't use and your language
would be perfect because they're
guaranteed to only pick bad things
so if you know that all c plus right
like if you can so they really have
produced something very interesting the
sibo's a standard committee literally
has a way
of guaranteeing they will produce only
bad language features that in and of
itself is actually useful because it
means you can always just eliminate
those from what you are designing
and your design gets better they have
done
one thing for you which is produce an
entire spec of things not to do
right
uh inside constant pressure you can read
a file and return an array i mean maybe
i don't know that msvc supports that yet
but it's possible like compile time code
execution you could write something that
would do this right
but i don't know how far they are on
actually providing that implementation
i have no idea right
yeah like meta programming makes this
easy right if you can just do that it's
not a problem but
yeah all right anyway so let's take a
look at what's going on here and see if
i can answer my question though about uh
what we're doing
uh for for lighting
so here in the now properly formatted
lighting sampling call you can see that
we actually compute
um
like the same thing twice
that we don't really need to because we
don't change
the dimensions of these two things so
it's probably
stupid to bother doing that in the
shader we should just say
that the diffuse and specular always
have to be the same
um
but you know we still don't really know
if maybe we want one to be more than the
other you could see like
doing something different
um
right so you know hard to say
we we don't really use c bus plus uh net
builder we basically just use c
uh i'm more just complaining about the
fact that you would think c plus would
be better and i could go use it but it
never is so i don't right i just end up
programming in c because people's is so
freaking bad
but i would like an improved c it's just
you know no one's really made one and do
please do not suggest languages to me
now
i really don't want to have to have a
gigantic flame when someone says you
should check out x and then i have to go
out ranting about how bad x is
uh okay so when we
look at this we
have
basically computed both vectors
but
we only actually and you can see here
we're computing like the locations of
things
but we then need to do like a texal
fetch
and
we're actually
when we are interpreting these we're
actually interpreting the octahedral map
in a more fancy way than i thought
uh
interesting so you can see we're not
actually doing like a
uh a basic interpolation we're doing if
like a
a fancier like radial like semi-radial
hero
do you guys remember doing this
um
[Music]
i don't remember doing this
i don't remember doing this but all
right
um
so i guess we use something better than
we use something better than bilinear
i i don't remember that we did that but
we do that when we interpolate the
octahedral map
and
are all right
i mean
[Music]
i guess i'm proud of us
for that
am i though
so i'm kind of interested now because
now i don't even know um
what happens if we turn that off
because i i didn't even realize we were
doing that uh
we must have played around with it at
some point and then decided oh it's like
better if you do that right
um
and to be honest i really just don't
remember so if we were to
change that to using the old path so we
we just that's just the standard
um that looks like a standard bi-linear
path right um
does that actually matter to anybody
because i can't imagine that it would
and to be completely honest i
don't really see a difference
there right
[Music]
it looks like we can also just sample
once so this should give us like a
completely
so is it maybe maybe maybe we only
reload when we restart but i don't think
so so that means i can take one sample
are we is that my am i looking at a
totally different like path that we
don't call or something we should check
at this fader again because i don't see
any difference between any of those
like this does not look any different
than that really
um
you know not in a way that like i can
perceive like it's probably different in
some way
but um
so when we do sample lighting no it's
calling i mean that's that's the code
path but it looks like we were doing a
lot more work than we needed to because
it looks like if you literally just
sampled if you literally or just use
bilinear
this this would do this would just do
the bilinear sample right here's the
here's manually doing the bilinear
sample
here's doing something fancier than
bilinear
and i'll be honest i just i don't see
the point
um that looked
fine
right um
uh
so you know i i don't know that we need
uh any of that garbage in there i mean
maybe we do
but like
i mean once you actually get this stuff
going it just doesn't seem
i mean i can see that that's maybe a
little squarier
yeah i mean you know
but part of that extra square here is
because we haven't addressed the other
problem with the light
not being added to
the uh other elements right so like
these guys don't really have that
problem particularly much
so i'm not sure that once we fix it we
would even care about that all that much
you know
so i'm not sure
i'm not sure we give a crap
i'm not sure we give a crap about that
um but we can see i don't know can we
see any difference here
i don't see any difference there does
this actually work let's like i don't
even remember if we reload shaders like
let's suppose we said like oh yeah hey
by the way
um
everything is is like red
always that's just something that
happens
in the world
well we're reloading shaders i can tell
you that
um
so
i don't know i mean i don't see a
difference
between the bilinear and the non so you
know what we're just gonna say that
that's
that's it i think i think we're turning
that off
and i don't know like
it seems like it's just fine as just a
regular bilinear sample i don't
i think that's probably fine and this is
i think mostly again like i think we can
fix that that squariness in a different
way
so i'm gonna i'm gonna go ahead and say
like maybe we just don't care about this
stuff
so let's suppose we went here and we uh
grimbled this particular
gronkus here
and this just became
you know
something i don't know what the a value
is doing there i don't know why this is
even returning
[Music]
um an alpha value in the first place
that doesn't really make any sense i
don't know why
why any of this is a v4
um
it's just
stupid um
it don't make no sense anyhow
so
probably this should all be v3s
right
like like what would the a value
what's the alpha value there's no
point to that
so this should probably be all bv threes
right all the way down
um and
because i don't see any point to it
um because what what was what were you
doing with the what were you gonna do
with that alpha right like what was the
point of that there's no point
so let's change this to do a v3 because
we had to amplify it to not do that
which seems dumb
um
so let's go ahead and
[Music]
just remove all that garbage so that now
we just have this
uh and let's see we're probably going to
get a compiler because i probably
you know chunked something out there
accidentally
we'll probably end up at shader
validation failed
nope we didn't
all right
um
so
that's all fine and and
whatever and that's good
uh and if i clean up the indentation
here that
that four coder munged um
we can see
roughly what this code is doing as well
um which is again not
particularly
interesting um
this is just indented too far
for no reason
uh but but now we're good
so we can see the lighting sampling here
is just taking the light sample from the
uh from the eight neighbor
like light probes for any given pixel
uh and because gpus are so ridiculously
fast that's just fine
um
[Music]
uh well no more specifically in four
coder if i told it to indent it would
indent but the problem is it thinks this
is a string
so it's going to do things completely
wrong right that that was the entire
part of the problem normally it just
indents everything for you automatically
and you don't have to do anything right
but in here and we could add a function
that just like moved things around in
here but
really what i want is for to just indent
these as if they were code and
unfortunately there's no way to tell it
to do that at the moment
um
which is partly for code as well but
it's partly c plus pluses fault
for sucking
so anyway uh
when we do this sample we could uh in
addition
take a
uh we we now have the specular sampler
here uh and we could
uh call this instead of like color
sampler i could call this diffuse
sampler
so that it's clear what's actually
happening here right diffuse sampler
um and we would then
change this to defuse sampler like so
uh and i think uh that would give us
this exact same behaviors we had now
only the like nomenclature actually
lines up
so let's think about specular here
because i figured we can now actually
take the specular sample as well we
could instead like and let's just do it
directly
we can do a specular sampler
um
sample specular uv and and now that will
just overwrite our diffuse sampler with
a spec spec
specular sample
which would make everything unpleasant
and shiny if any of this works which it
might not
um but you can kind of see the the
difference there right
so everything is like very reflective
now
um and and nothing is smooth like it was
before
right
um
so
the spec sample is not going to be going
in the right direction right now
uh so we have to kind of change that a
little bit but i would like to change it
just so i can see what kind of specular
lighting we have because we actually
kind of have spec lighting that we're
not actually using it we probably should
right
um
so yeah so when we look here we've got
we're going to sample the lighting right
we do the lighting sample whatever blah
blah
um we need to take the light direction
which i guess is this
so that's
wrong
kind of is it i mean no i guess we would
sample them both from the same place
would we
that that's probably not true
so here's us mapping it into the
octahedron
where we're actually sampling
so the problem here is that you would
you would have two of these right
because one of those gonna be like the
uh gonna reflect off the i vector
right
um
uh
uh sarah croqueta uh you can do that if
you want in four forecoder you would
just have had to have
actually created that function right or
rather bound that function to something
i like manually created all the stuff
that is bound to the keys in my version
so
i don't actually have anything bound to
that
right
it would be very easy for me to add
something like that but but because
literally you never need that for any
reason
um i never added it i ever never added a
binding to do that
i
so
you know we end up in this situation i
could go add one but
really i think i i don't want that i
want to have this auto indented like
everything else so i probably will just
move them to separate files at some
point
probably
um
so you know i don't know but anyway uh
the point is so the specular version of
this uh i think now we would just need
to have the reflection vector the i
reflection vector
would have to be somewhere in there
right um so so at the moment
when we compute this we take
the
[Music]
yeah
right you can actually see it it's like
right here
that that for those of you who
know what you
are looking at um
that is literally the reflection
right um so if we change to using the
actual reflection
reflection vector
uh
we would get this
um which hey looks a lot
like specular lighting now
as you might expect
um
so
right you can see it travel upward you
can even see it smear out across the
surface there
right exactly like a wet surface would
do
um
so we certainly could
now have
um
we could now have lighting that had
actual surface properties meaning things
could be like part spec part diffuse if
you want you could blend
those two together
which seems valuable because you get
kind of some of those nice effects right
like that
um
[Music]
uh reese cyrillic i was wondering about
some of that so i no i would like to
know what you're talking about so let me
take a look you can use a macro like
pound defined shutter code a
pound a
and then on kerastar shader equals
shader code insert shader
here
the shader code
interesting
interesting um
that seems like a good trick that i
might try
uh
actually
um
[Music]
yeah no i would i would definitely try
that
so i'm interested in the um in
we might try that that's a good idea i
like that trick
um
so i don't really know
what to do about this exactly
um
so i think what we probably want to do
is be able to pass down the two
octahedral values here we want one for
each of them so we would want this to be
like the world end is one and the
reflection vector is another
uh and this function would want to be uh
able to be called for either so like
this would need to be a thing that you
could call
right
uh and you would want to be able to get
the v2 that you were using for sampling
here and you want to be able to pass
like both of those in
so you'd want to have a thing that was
like
oct from
or something
uh and we'll you know what after i'm
done with this real quick we should try
that uh
that pound defined trick i like that
solve it with uh
with a macro
um
so if you pass in a normal
i i guess we'll just use r here right
uh then you get oct out
like this
um
that seems fine
uh and then in here
we would just say like v2
oct
equals oct from
world n
right
or
r
right
um and so we could get both now
uh so that we could get both the
reflection vector and maybe i call this
reflected
uh so it's a little clear what what the
heck r is
um
and then we have like
uh the diffuse oct and the spec oct
right uh we pass them both
um
in here
so hard to edit anything as a string so
this is why i want to fix this if i can
it's really hard to edit when it's all a
big string and
four coder doesn't think it's a real
thing
um
there
so now we have both of the uh the two
octahedrals the reflected and the
diffuse and they would come in here as
uh dif spec and diff oct so that when we
look at where oct is actually happening
here
um
it's literally just that one
so i think it's just this
don't ask me why i wrote that backwards
um so maybe that does both samples
maybe
uh i ain't even know
uh but we'll find out
so if we look at you know our vague test
here it
kind of looks right i mean you know this
not particularly accurate uh testing
here but okay
you know
looks a little bit like something
uh not very good but it looks like
something
um so we can here take both samples so
here's the diffuse
uh here's the spec we have both of them
uh and we could use those to produce the
results so we could do like diffuse plus
specular to produce our our results
um and normally what you would do is
we'd have a material parameter here we
don't have one right now but you'd have
a material parameter
that would tell you uh
which you had
right like
whether a surface is particularly
diffuse whether it's particularly
um specular
right
and so for right now we'll just pretend
everything's like half and half
uh because we don't have a
you know we don't have a material
parameter but eventually
uh you know maybe we get a way to send
something in there
to you know say like you're gonna
you know put put those together i don't
know
uh so anyway like i'll just pretend we
have one i'll put it to do like it'll
just be like hey yeah there's like a
uh spec level spec
spec
shift
i don't know what this would be but like
material
it's called material
and for now it's like half and half so
we lurk between
these two
like that um and so this is just gonna
be like it's half and half there's no
rhyme or reason to it it's just that's
what it is
um and if we wanted to we could use that
to like control some aspect of what
these materials look like
as it is this just kind of makes it look
maybe a little bit better because you
get a little bit of a feel like that
just looks a little nicer it just gives
you know a little bit of character to it
um so i can't see that it hurts to just
turn that on everywhere and maybe that's
all we actually ever do maybe we don't
have material parameters because it's
not like it's real spec like it's not
like we're actually computing at higher
enough resolution for it to be like
bounce reflections right doesn't we
don't really do that
um
but it's all right so let's see um
the
shader code thing here that was
suggested uh
let's let's see what happens with the
shader code
trick
so
the select suggestion was to basically
do something like this like say hey
there's something called embed shader or
whatever
and you
include the code and it just puts the
code as a giant string
and then the idea here would be that you
would say well okay
instead of the hear doc version that
happens like this
uh the suggestion was well you just do
that
and you see if that works at all right
i'm not optimistic that'll work but who
the heck knows maybe it will and in
which case if it does work that would be
cool right so now this is our gigantic
shader um that is all included as actual
code and in theory i could come in here
maybe and indent it
um and it would indent although it looks
like it's kind of like far because it
indents to that as the as the margin
um but i could maybe do something like
this and that way it would pull it back
a little bit further and that would be
fine but then it all like indents
correctly which is what i want
so that's like it would be way better if
this actually compiles i don't know if
it will but we'll give it a shot
no errors
um shader validation failed did i
accidentally clip something out
let's look at the errors
um
i
[Music]
don't quite
follow what has gone wrong here
is it
this that it's complaining about
there's no other token pound in there
except on this depth peel
pound if
so
yeah the the pound ifs wouldn't come
through right
so so like that probably doesn't work i
mean i don't know what i don't know what
the spec for the the string eyes
operator which is that thing
i don't know what that does
with this
um
i i don't know
but it does look like it don't work
right
um
probably just because of those i mean
probably it would be fine without those
i guess
i mean we can do the test
like i'll have to undo those changes
because we we need we actually need
those pound diffs like i don't want to
get rid of them right but we can
certainly try
uh to see if it would work without that
so so it is actually the pro that is
actually the problem right you can't you
can't have poundifs in it
um
so like we could try to work around that
a different way
but
i mean we we do need
we we compile the shader in a couple of
different ways right and and like maybe
we could change kind of how we're doing
that
um
so
but for now i think the raw string
literals are all we really would have
and we we just have to go change the
four quarter source code to stop
treating them as strings
um
so
i think that's basically it
anyway um back to our story so i'm kind
of glad that we can put spec in there as
well that's pretty cool
um in my opinion i think maybe the
lighting is still a little too bright
right now for my tastes uh like i think
we might want it like it's not as spooky
as it should be
um like things are just too bright
at the moment
uh let me i'd like to
you know i i like to keep things spooky
uh i i think at some point if you
end up in a situation where you've
de-spooked things to a certain level
um of spookiness that is like
that is sub spook it's less spooky than
it should be
then you run the risk of
having completely unspooky game and that
you know i don't
ever want to really be in that zone
um so let's just try to
keep it a little spookier so first of
all i don't know what we're doing with
the outside
but
i guess
like the garden
[Music]
i don't know what any of this stuff even
is let's be honest um
i don't remember why we named certain of
these things what we named them but uh
i'm curious like okay so if i remove the
lighting from outside it still has like
the flat lighting from moonlight right
um which you know is is what we would
expect um that's probably a little too
bright
probably
uh would be my guess so so that probably
wants to get fixed
[Music]
as well
this looks proper like appropriately
spooky
these are maybe a little too bright
let's go
take a quick look sorry i know this is
not what i said i was gonna do but you
know so you gotta you gotta do things
when you do them
so when we're in
uh not indoors
when we're outdoors like this we add
this light in here uh and it should
probably be just a lot dimmer
um
[Music]
i don't know it should probably still be
like brighter than the apron maybe
or maybe we should just add some light a
light to it if we want um i don't know
uh
that seems better
so i think we're i think we're now just
down to
uh
to wanting this needing this to
rasterize more properly so that we don't
get the splotchiness
um i think it's the only other thing we
want to do and the question is just do i
want to do that now or do i want to do
that next weekend
i think i do that next weekend because
i'm going to want to make dinner and
stuff
so i think we're down to just that the
splotchiness of this we can fix and
should fix
um so i think we're going to want to do
that right
uh i also don't know where we are at on
flickeriness
so is it really necessary to be at six
right now or have things gotten to the
point where actually we don't need it to
be
at six right now and i don't know the
answer to that question
let's drop it to three
it doesn't look very flickery at three
what's it at one am i
seeing this right did we make some kind
of mistake where
like why is it not flickering
something's broken
oh right that i went the wrong way i'm
like it should be ugh
this is this will increase the
flickering there you go
i'm like god that was just weird
so um
so it seems like that is kind of our
flicker floor
right
is like around six so it's it's 10
frames flicker floor
you know
um which would suggest if we if we could
speed up the raycast a little we could
get
probably to this level
which is a little flickery
but is closer
to full speed
it responds a little bit better i think
this should probably be our target is to
de-flicker this which i think we can do
um
i think we can do i think we can manage
that
um so yeah we just need light
reservation i think i'll save that for
next week but i think we're in really
good shape the lighting is so darn good
right now uh and really we just need to
fix sort of the squariness of this like
the response with i think forward
rasterization of the lights is the right
way to start with that
we might need something else in there i
don't know
um
exactly
so i don't want to promise that's going
to fix it we may have to do a little
more work than that
um
but i think that's a large part of it
because one of the reasons
as i've mentioned before one of the
reasons you get these square artifacts
is when the light isn't properly
uh represented
when when you get it unnatural clamping
to zero on your linear interpolation
you get this kind of thing so i could
easily see just rasterizing the light
fixing this because right now we're not
it's not a smooth fall off like it
should be because we're not doing that
right
um so i don't think it's i don't think
we're far from from good uh this is this
is looking pretty awesome
uh to be honest
um
and and i think we'll get i think we can
deflicker this so right now uh our main
problem is if we know if we wanted to
crank the rate count up a little bit
more and don't forget we're on the cpu
moving this to the gpu
would get us a huge speed boost as well
so we we can always just target that as
something we do later as well uh to
solve the speed problem so we're very
conservative right now because we're
doing everything on the cpu side and the
gpu can do a lot more flops right
so yeah
excuse me
um
also you could just run on a faster
machine
you know run this on a thread ripper and
you could
get count or even just a modern machine
from today right
um
and it would it would totally stomp this
thing
um
for sure
so uh
yeah the
the ray
weight is the rate count here if i turn
that up to 16
uh the game will be slow but it should
be about as stable
lighting wise
right so
hopefully now we don't really see in the
flicker which i don't
um
even in here the flicker is pretty
minimal like you would not care about
that much flicker
so i do think if we can just double our
raycast which i think is probably doable
even on the cpu side definitely doable
on the gpu side
i think we would kind of just be done
yeah i mean this lighting is just like
very good now
um i the only thing that's objectionable
is that rasterization artifact or that
lack of rasterization of the light
source artifact
i mean that's just really freaking good
i'm sorry but it is
uh okay
so
now we probably call it a day
and we tackle the
forward rasterization of the
into the light probes
to get a nice smooth distribution for
small moving light sources like that
um
[Music]
i think that's it and then we're good um
i do
want to see
[Music]
what happens if we turn off the lighting
again
now
i mean that's just really good
i mean right i mean that's just like
very good
yeah i mean i so i think we're basically
done i mean i really think we just have
to clean up that you know figuring out
how we get the probes for overlapping
probes like that we just got to fix that
and then i think maybe we just rewrite
that the cast to be based on array
bundles because i think it'll be a lot
faster we may be able to get our 2x
there actually
um
but that is just very responsive
not very much flickr except in the
really dark areas and i'm okay with that
and
just looks fantastic
um
[Music]
so you know like i also would wonder
like so where is our snake
where's where's
i don't
know how this is this this world gen is
stupid and bad
um
and that probably is the thing we'll be
cleaning up
right after we clean up the world
storage because now we know we don't
have 2d we can cut out a bunch of code
from that i mean you don't have 3d
stacking
um but where's the thing that creates
the like we have a thing that creates
snakes in dungeon areas
um
i guess it literally does it right here
so i guess if i wanted to i can just add
this to something else so if i wanted to
add this to
i don't know
like
bedroom a would that just work
and
the snake pattern
is
has a light on it
i think
doesn't it
or maybe it doesn't anymore but i
thought it did
at least at one point
add piece
add piece light
so if it's got a light on it that 1.0
light's going to be way too bright
we already know that
um
but does that add
a snake
somewhere yes
uh so like i said way too bright
but
we know how to fix that
imc best i agree with that
assessment
so the uh skeleton dude of course they
get stuck in the corners sorry skeleton
man
um
uh maybe maybe we should just make them
have less
pieces
um
anyway
uh
uh yeah like i mean i think this is just
this is pretty solid
we really have to get ourselves our poor
snakes they all lock up like immediately
[Laughter]
oh well
um
all right uh i'm pretty happy with all
this i think this is all great
uh i did maybe the standard lighting
when we add this back in now the
standard lighting pattern probably we
should just make those lights less
bright
uh again for because of the spookiness
issue
uh that i spoke about before
uh
and and we can return
to this nonsense here uh
let's
make things half as bright
and go from there
so i think we're all good now
and i think we'll call it a day here but
this this creates some like different
light colors which was just kind of a
nice touch
um
i think this looks fantastic i'm really
happy so basically we'll just fix the
we'll fix the occlusion problem here
which hopefully will get that light that
kind of light
looking a lot better
um
and
and then we'll just assess it might not
if it doesn't then we might have to take
some other steps to figure out what
we're going to do to solve that problem
um but
i think that may just be the bug
that may just be uh
that sort of skipping problem is because
of that bug
that we know about and so i think if we
just fix the bug we may just be done
uh and then and then we move on
so that's it
um
happy
happy fun day to everybody
uh
that's that's all there is
i'll be back here next week to
[Music]
fix that bug
and
we will cross our fingers
that that will basically be the end of
the lighting
debugging
we would like to probably rewrite that
routine to be ray bundle based so we may
want to spend another weekend on that
but but that i mean
hey that we we may actually now have
legit good lighting
um
so
uh so yeah at some point well mine mark
42 the feedback issue is because
something in there is is measured as a
proportion
and we just
weren't thinking about it that way for
some reason right
so setting all of our numbers to be
normalized between zero and one fixes
that issue and
it's really just a bug in our thinking i
don't think we actually have a bug in
the problem i don't think there is a bug
in the program
i don't think there is an actual
feedback book i think it's literally
just a bug in our thinking
right
uh the values are all percentages
and
i guess i just wasn't
i'm missing a place where that
propagates through somebody who knows
more about lighting would just know that
they just be like oh yeah like you
because you wrote this
part of it
this way it means you know the light
values have to all be percentage of the
maximum light value or whatever and i'm
like okay right
but as you can see we can get exactly
the same result just fine completely
stably
so i don't know
exactly where that percentage is
but
yeah
i don't think we have to do any work to
fix in other words i don't think there's
any problem the feedback is not there uh
it's just because of a units issue
um so we don't actually have to fix it
it would be nice to understand it
but but we don't actually have the bug
i don't think
uh while i'm i i don't know i don't
think it's that simple i think it's more
complicated than that
um because it would not explain
like
it doesn't really explain why simply
normalizing the values between zero and
one automatically fixes that or rather
it also doesn't explain why you could
set them to things that were higher like
1.3 and not have the problem right like
so there's it's probably slightly more
complicated than that but i mean that's
obviously part of it because we know
that because it it operates over several
frames it can have that kind of feedback
right so any bias in the system will
produce that but we don't really know
why it's sensitive to
the units in that way
because we now are essentially using the
same values we just multiply by 10
at the end
right so we're still you know we produce
the same kind of light values they just
don't feed back on each other because
they're normalizing zero and one to
begin with
it's not immediately intuitively obvious
to me why
that unit change y representing things
between 0 and 10
versus 0 and 1
has that behavior
obviously it's because
numbers significantly greater than 1 can
feed back
in some multiple multiplicative process
i just don't understand
what
that i don't understand exactly where
that is taking place right
so representing the the lighting but as
numbers being 0 and 1 instead of between
0 and 10
completely fixes the problem even if you
then multiply by 10 to get the exact
same values back
right
uh that's why i say like maybe we just
asked don mitchell
to come solve the problem for us right
um
because he would know and we don't
so
anyway that's it for today
uh thanks everyone
for joining me
i will be back next weekend
when we will try to fix
uh the problem with
lights
uh
inc occluding
uh sample probes
because we definitely have a problem
with that
so i will be back for that until then
have fun programming everyone
and i will see y'all on the internet
take it easy everybody