hello everybody and welcome to handmade
hero this is the show where we code a
complete game live on stream so long as
all of the certificates that certify our
certification are continued to be
certified and don't expire obviously
sometimes you have certificates that
expire with their expiration which
causes of course the expiration of the
certificates that were signed with those
certificates leading to a certificate
expiration at which point I mean all
bets are off because without
certificates you would not be able to
certify that the certificates that are
certifying your certificate are in fact
themselves certified because they could
be expired so one of the things that we
like to do on handmade hero obviously is
just remind everyone out there before
trying to program anything during the
day or evening actually really pretty
much time independent except for of
course if that time is an expiration
date for the certificate to just go
through and check all of your
certificates and make sure that the
expiration dates on the certificates
that you have are not about to expire
because if those certificates expired
then obviously all of the certificates
that were certified using this those
certificates will also themselves expire
which would lead to any certificates
certified with the certificates that
expired from this from the expiration of
the certificate those will also expire
and at that point mostly what you have
is certificates that expired because of
previous certificate expiration
certificate expirations just want to
make sure that's clear just you know a
little that sometimes people explain in
a confusing way it's just wanted to put
it out there in a way that was really
easy to understand that's just kind of a
public service announcement because if
you don't always make sure that you have
the certificates that certify the
certificates that certify the
certificates that are you're using for
certification then one of those things
could expire which would lead to
expiration so I'm going to go ahead and
just assume that everything's certified
today
if we have to recertify some of the
certificates that were used for
certifying the certification certificate
we can do that certainly if you know
either way but for right now I'm just
going to assume that everything's
certified and we'll go from there and if
there's any expirations that happen with
the with you know with handmade hero
we'll we'll address them as we go
all right so yesterday we finished
working around some some Windows issues
that we had because we were using
Windows to extract some font data from
TTF files to put them into our asset
packing system the unfortunate aspect of
Windows is font extraction that we came
across was that for whatever reason it
doesn't like to anti-alias fonts that
are larger than I think it was we tested
it 353 pixels high and so we made a
thing that would automatically do down
sampling of larger fonts to produce an
anti aliased output we do anything fancy
just a simple box filter but we just
used that to make sure we could always
get anti aliased fonts even if those
thoughts were happen to be fairly large
because I don't really know whether we
want to use large fonts or not I didn't
want to leave some kind of mess in there
where if we asked for a large font with
and you know we wouldn't get it or
whatever
so um we went ahead and did all that
which means we now have the ability to
export fonts what we don't have right
now is anything that reads the font text
that we output and that's the only thing
stopping us from having completely
refreshable art path meaning we can
start from raw inputs and reproduce an
entire set of packs that has everything
in it that we might want streaming audio
music spritesheet sound graphics stuff
whatever and all the font information
markup alignment points we got all that
stuff but we just don't have now a way
to read the like glyph positioning
information so we want to do is go in
and add that to our import and then I
think we can sort of do some testing of
the art packing system to make sure that
everything's good where we're at so I'm
going to go into handmade here I'm going
go ahead and load everything up in sign
handmade hero the place where this stuff
happens is in the import file handmade
imports EPP um I would mention just
really quickly we've got someone was was
worried on the github I don't know how
to write I don't know how to get this
thing going here nope that's not there
it is if I look at the issues someone
was worried because the space character
produced corrupt PNG for the space left
what's happening here you have to
remember we didn't make the ping spec
the ping spec is someone else suspect
and there's some weird issues with it I
replied to it here just so the person
would know what's going on according to
the PNG specification it's actually not
legal to make a PNG with a width and
height of 0 now I don't know why because
that's a valid image right like if
you're trying to specify hey what's the
image for the space character right the
answer is there isn't one there's no
data it's empty right so specifying a
PNG with a width and height of 0 is the
right way to do that if we were to
specify it with a width and height of 1
that would imply that there was a pixels
worth of data but there isn't right so
it's not the way I would choose to do it
because it's actually not correct I'm
not sure how we would want to solve this
problem we can't really do much about it
and our reader will correctly read this
PNG so it's okay that the width and
height would be set to 0 for our
purposes so the only question is do we
want to do something about it for the
other programs out there which wouldn't
know how to deal with the width and
height of 0 and therefore interpret the
PNG is corrupted which is correct
according the spec because you're not
allowed to do that but I just don't know
what the other option is one is that we
just don't output a glyph for that
character and so what that would mean is
that we would literally like compact the
table so that you
there's just no bitmap for it like we
have to leave space because we need the
space
the information so it has to be in the
table as an actual glyph entry we just
wouldn't have an image for it I don't
know what to make of it um so we have to
think about that a little bit I don't
I'll leave this up but I don't really
want to do anything about it just yet
because I'm just not sure what the right
answer is here like like I said we need
to leave space for it and so maybe we
can do is just not output any PNG at all
and then inside the actual text file
that we output with all of the glyph
information we'll just leave it as an
empty slot that doesn't specify any
input bitmap and then maybe we can just
make our text processor understand what
to do when it is when it is not given a
glyph for one of the slots in the glyph
table right that's that's all we got
okay so let's go ahead and go into how
this is going to work here I'm gonna
load up one of those files that we
outputted that's just a tenth it's just
a test we did of the font code so if we
look in here you can see all the font
bitmaps there's also an hht that it
outputs and it looks like this we
haven't thought at all about what we
want this to look like we can obviously
totally change this text file to
anything we want and so this is just a
like rough sketch of what it might be so
what I'd like to do is go through and
actually write the reader and then go
back to the writer and modify the output
to fit what we actually decide to read
does that make sense this looks pretty
good but I suspect we need some things
up at the front like we'd like to see
the glyph count probably and we'd like
to see some of that space confirmation
if I remember correctly oops that's not
what I wanted inside the file format if
you actually go look at what a font has
in it
what's going on there font no no there
it is
if you actually look what a font has any
it's got the glyph hat the glyph one
path slash gunpoint glyph can't be
sender height to sender height and
external letting we're not writing any
of that out yet so I think at a minimum
we would want to get that data into our
our system I and maybe that has to be
specified like along with the font you
know or something like this so that's
what I'd like to do here if we look at
what happens when we're doing our
parsing you can see inside this set up
here where we do a parse top-level block
you can see us sort of doing the parsing
for for things like whether it's default
music sound blockhead whatever that
needs to have a thing for fonts shoved
into it probably that's my assumption
but if you actually go look at how this
routine works it kind of argues that we
may have to start breaking it apart and
the reason for that is if you look at
how we've set it up pretty much this
thing is is set up only to really import
like one thing at a time right so it's
gonna go read like one file but we need
it to read like lots of files you know
I'm saying we need it to check and read
a whole set of files and so really this
code right here that reads like a single
you know a single import like let's say
this right here or this right here that
code needs to be we need to be able to
call that like multiple times from
inside a single block if we're going to
do this right so I'm not sure exactly
how I want to attack this but what I
might do first is try to make it so that
maybe we've got separate paths for
separate elements here so that for
example we know the difference between
using you know between things that have
arrays of alignment points versus things
that only have one
or other things like that and so that we
can call like update asset metadata you
know we would call that for each
individual glyph in the font rather than
just having one call like it's doing
here and stuff like this right so I feel
like that's more what we want to do and
in order to do that what we would need
is something that allows us to treat
parts of blocks uniformly such as like
the shared information in blocks so for
example the things that say like what
the name is or what you know like we've
got sort of these things in blocks that
are they're suitable for default parsing
like author description and name or tags
right all of that stuff we need or we
want to be able to be parsed easily by
any of our parsing operations so instead
of having to keep everything in the same
routine what I think we might want to do
is just have us something that handles
those externalities so for example let's
say we took all of this stuff here and
we went down to the end and said look
this group could maybe all be handled by
like a else if handle common fields
right like that
and assuming this was handled by common
fields we just do you know we just let
that handle it in fact we could just say
look if it's not handled by common
fields at that point then we have to
issue an error you know then what I can
do is pull this stuff out which starts
to get me in a better position for where
am I going here for being able to make
multiple of these right because by
getting that code out now I don't have
to leave everything in the same routine
I can just call this from several
different routines and not have to worry
about the paths diverging right
so if we had something like this that
was like handle common fields then what
I would need to do is say okay have a
handle here like that
and then in here I could say handled
equals true so we'll assume we handle it
if nothing gets handled will say handled
equals false up at the top here where we
do handle com of handle common fields we
would need to pass it for example an h
HT fields target - like for it to feel
fill out right and that works for most
of the things we need right so if we
have that we would just need like the
tokenizer
the token and the fields and most of
this stuff would work so like here that
would work here would work here would
work and so the only thing we really
have now is the append tags tag list
that's the thing doesn't work well why
don't we just make that part of it right
why don't we just make the append tags
be part of the fields and then off we
would go right I mean that seems pretty
straightforward and that might allow us
to do some other things with tags later
on in addition maybe if we wanted to I'm
not sure how sensible that really is as
something to do but you know we could
see so if in here we take the attack
that maybe hht fields has that append
tags in it I mean the first question
right is like what is the Pentax you can
see it's just a tag array with nothing
here right so I mean we could make the
part of fields the other thing we could
do is just say well meat you know maybe
that gets passed as well right if this
were like that then we could just have a
pen tags and off you go right so it
seems pretty straightforward for us to
be able to do this and I think that you
know that right there is an easy enough
routine that we can just now call that
you know call that part of the problem
solved
all we would do
the you know tokenizer token the append
tags and the fields right now there's
some nuance here I think we would need
the assets for it so we do need the
context of the hht context past year but
that's not the end of the world
we obviously already bundled that stuff
up for a reason so we would need one
additional field there that's just so it
has some place to talk to the you know
it can have a route to get to the asset
system so not a big deal there so I'll
just put that in there and now we've got
that extracted as something that we can
share for multiple things right so what
that allows me to do is say well okay
now we can start to treat these things
potentially as separate paths right
I could choose instead of having parse
top-level block as a thing I could start
to peel off some of these operations
right so if we look at what happens for
example with is default what you can see
is we're like intentionally avoiding
most of the work that we were doing for
is default we just say don't don't do it
right so I might start by saying what if
we just peeled the default part out of
here and said that's no longer a thing
we're gonna handle that back where we
called parcel up top level block
sorry typing errors I'm still split
unlike my editor it's different on my
work machine now than the one here which
is a little bit crazy
we'll fix that eventually but it causes
me no end to the typing problems so
anyway on parse top level block here's
where we actually call that code what
I'd rather do I think here is just say
okay let's do a little bit more work
here to see whether or not we're setting
the default or not right so if this
thing was the default then we're gonna
do one thing if it's not the default
we're gonna do another and that sets us
up to start being able to actually like
notice realized we could also do this
without knowing the HHA right so
actually I think I think this may be
actually better than what we were doing
because we don't need the HHA to parse
that parse the default block so actually
this code can actually can do this and
now we can allow default blocks to
happen without even having an HHA
specified yet and that's actually more
powerful so that's an improvement over
what we had so if we wanted to do that
what we could do now is called parse
default
and that would allow us and I guess we
don't really even need to pass the token
there that would allow us to make this
routine be a little more sensible so in
here we could say all right here's you
know what we're doing we're going to do
exactly what we're doing before where we
grab the default fields we're gonna loop
over the contents of this block and then
we're going to automatically do the
thing that we were only doing on is
default here right so that case goes
away and now we can just do a check on
the if parsing for the tokenizer and say
look
assuming that we didn't have any errors
go ahead and set the default fields to
whatever we parsed right um so now I can
actually go in here and start pulling
out those is default parts we know that
this will never happen now because it
doesn't exist as a code path so in here
what we can do is actually do the block
parsing part of this I'm gonna go ahead
and just make that out of pieces if that
makes sense so in parse default block
here we're gonna do while parsing we're
going to do exactly this I think right
we need to be able to parse an open
brace though there it is
and we never rewrite this so I think
it's sufficient I believe for us to
literally just parse like to do a copy
of everything that exists in the entire
token stream if that makes sense so
pretty much every time through we can do
that where we and in fact I guess I
could just do it up here right
so if we ever hit the close race then
what we do is require I don't know why
was that an open brace finger fired
there I don't know what was going on
there sorry so we need to require that
open brace I just want to do this copy
here where we actually do everything up
to the close brace token in fact I guess
I could do it this way so this is just
letting me say look I'm gonna parse
everything that comes out of here I'm
gonna get the the tokens sequentially if
I see the closed brace then we're gonna
finish and I'm just going to remember
where that was so I can tell this thing
to copy all of that into the output if
we're rewriting the hht due to some like
edit that our editor did or whenever it
right so then inside here there isn't
any like none of these things are
relevant so it's only this one that
we're doing so we really just have a
close race and then if it wasn't the
close race then we're just gonna try to
handle any fields this append tags will
be zero cuz we're not gonna allow tags
inside here and that should do it
I think I think that's it so at the end
oh and I guess we require some ink alone
so I guess we don't even need the closed
brace here I guess we can even do this
like that so that's even easier right
that all seems good so we come in here
we'd say part Steve a block grab that
open brace we loop through everything
that's in here one at a time if we ever
see the close brace we're done if we
don't we just assume it's a field we try
to process it that way right up till the
end we don't need this really this is
just a require semicolon I believe
because these don't actually ever ask
for one as you can see so it's really
just like every time through the loop we
require semicolon that's just a hard
fact right so I think that works you
don't see any other issues with it so I
think that's all we need and then we
just need to make sure that in here we
only allow the tags field if there was
an append tags so for example in here we
would do this because if a pen tags
doesn't exist then we don't want to
allow anyone to specify a tags field
because obviously that's not allowed for
the person who's calling us specifically
in the default block right so that seems
like it's all good yeah parse default
block is supposed to take the token here
I guess even though we don't really need
to pass that I'm just keeping a symmetry
with this and that's all good right so
now that we've extracted default block
it should also now be possible for us to
extract a second block which is fonts
and called those as a separate processor
as well which is exactly what we want to
do because our parsing is going to be
really specialized in weird because it
just has a ton of data that other things
don't have and we don't really want to
force it through the same path that
everyone else was using so this is
parsed font block the exact same things
are going to happen here probably almost
certainly right it's gonna look a lot
like this but the interior here is going
to be completely different so I think
that's all fine the append tags is
actually a thing now
that we will have to have and yeah so I
think we just want to grab that tagger a
there it is
I think we just want to do it like this
right so what we need to do is add the
fields here that we want for our font we
can require them in a specific order
because these are generated so if we
want this thing to have specific stuff
occur in specific order we can't just do
that for example I don't know if we have
a require call for identifiers but we
might looks like we don't have a require
to identifier I'm gonna add that though
yeah so right here where we call require
token what I want to do is I want to
have a thing that's similar to that so I
want to have a thing that's like require
identifier that basically says I want it
to be an identifier and I want its value
to be this that way it's basically just
calling it this and I guess since we're
using Cara starts and we don't we can do
it like this because we know that there
are care stars always so inside the the
tokenizer now we could just say I want
an identifier so I want to be able to do
require token and get me an in a fire
for sure and then what I want to do is
say also this I think is probably just
that probably not all right so then what
I want to do is say look if token equals
ID match I think that's all I need right
yeah
if this is okay then we're good right if
it's not then we're airing out
right so this way we can say hey we
needed to see this identifier at this
exact time so and we didn't see it so
that's just a hard error you know we're
not gonna go any further so I think we
can do that because now we can just say
look require identifiers require token
and then get the next token I guess
require token like a number or whatever
right and so we here we can say I know I
want to see what were those things that
we had inside our fonts there you know I
want to see one past highest code point
you know what I mean then I want to see
an equal sign and then I want to see the
value that we're talking about just
hard-coded it's got to be these in this
order just make sure we have them and
then what we'd end up with is a bunch of
things that look like this to read
fields so we would say why can I not get
to complete there there go
so you know I want to see this then I
want to see this and then I want to see
and in an integer or whatever right so
what I don't know what the value of that
thing is number right now what you can
see is we're gonna do this like a bunch
of times right so there's you know we'd
be doing this and stuff so you can see
that this is basis a template for
reading fields so what I want to do here
is say why don't we just make that be
its own thing I don't know if we want
that in necessarily the tokenizer part
of things itself but what we can do is
say require field is out here you pass
us a tokenizer
you see what kind of token you wanted
the field to be and what the name of it
was right and that is all we need to do
this entire process for every field we
can then require whatever identifier is
that you want to we can require the
equals we can then require the you know
type of token you want in the field to
be and then we can return it and all of
that just works so then we can say one
past highest cone point equals require
field oh and you know what we can also
require the semicolon okay so in here we
can then require every field that we
want really simply with just one line
say a bunch of those don't ask you why
duplicated that word even though we're
only gonna have it once so we can just
say all right we want to read that we
want to read the glyph count what else
we got stuff in here what is it again
sender descender right we want that bat
pasting back here as well and externally
so at that point you can see how easy it
is for us to just make a template
essentially that says everything's got
to have this stuff at the top and we
know that it's easy to do because our
generator does it humans don't have to
touch it so this part will just should
just work right and we can put those
things in there after those things
you're welcome to put whatever you want
but those have to be there right so that
seems reasonable we could instead of
going a different route and said like
let's put a fixed like thing of like
font data in there or something like
that I don't really care we could do it
either way I don't I don't really care
one way or the other but here's that you
know here's this version of it and we'll
see how that goes
all right so that'll parse the font
template for us if we get past that then
we can start to do work with it
right we can create an array of that
size to hold the glyphs that come in we
can create a code point table for
storing the horizontal advance stuff or
other things like that right so we can
we do whatever we want at this point I
think the only thing we really need
though is this I think everything else
is pretty much not really that important
to have up front and so one way to look
at it is we could also make this part of
the this part where we would do the
require field thing we could also make
that optional for these the order
optional for these things and it's only
glyph count that has to come first we
could do that later too I don't know
whether we care enough but it's just
something to think about all right so
when we're done here and we go to
actually create this font we should be
able to make one of these that gets kind
of stuck into the you know in the font
file so we're gonna presumably end up in
a situation where you know we're not
sending the default fields anymore
we're parsing the font block here and so
at some point I'm gonna have
a thing that's like this right and we
don't know you know how we're gonna
write that out exactly but we do know
that all of this stuff now can get set
so like one past highest code point will
equal something the glyph count will
equal something the ascender height will
equal something the D Center height will
equal something right so I know I'm
gonna need to fill that out and I'm
gonna have to feel that out from these
right all these things are gonna have to
be filled out from here and the way that
I'm gonna have to do that is the
tokenizer has ways of actually getting
the value out of it right you it will
have filled these out already
so in theory I should be able to come
through here and say look just give me
like whatever these things are and
probably I'll have to validate them at
least a little bit so we may want to
like require that they're not negative
numbers or you know whatever else but
otherwise it's pretty straightforward to
just do it's pretty straightforward to
just pull those out so that would get us
the top part of the font like the header
information of it right which says all
this stuff what it doesn't give us is
the horizontal advance or the code point
data that's basically like which you
know what each of the code points
actually is for each of our glyphs so we
need to be able to write this data out
to the file and in order to write down
to the file we're gonna have to actually
produce it ourselves so I think what we
need here is something like this once we
actually determine that we've got valid
data I mean to the extent that we think
we do you know maybe we do something
like this where we say all right and I
put the glyph count first here because
these may we may move inside but this
point this one we definitely never would
so then I'm gonna say okay
the glyph count equals the glyph count
token s32
when this actually gets specified we're
gonna assert that it's like greater than
zero basically right so we'll just say
like if whiff count took necessary to
its greater than zero and maybe we check
the parsing level here as well it's like
we must have lost the sauce beam not
sure I heard her food dispenser go off
so at that point you know she's not
gonna be sticking around
I don't know when she actually left so
we've lost post power we have no more
plus power we're programming on our own
now which is less good but what are we
gonna do yeah must you must persevere
cats gotta eat sometime
all right so we're gonna see the parsing
here you know if the Toth if we if there
are errors in the parse up to this point
then don't bother working on this stuff
assuming that we see the Douglas count
token has a value that seems like it's
going to be in range we'll go ahead and
take that and then we'll try to actually
process going forward so what we would
need to do is allocate space for this
storage using temporary storage here so
first we would allocate the code points
like so and in here we would say HS a
font glyph right and we want this many
of them same thing with this at the
horizontal advance table
I'm sure why we're still saying r32 and
that's gonna be a square great so that's
a that's an N squared table there that's
actually holding for every glyph what
every other glyphs advance would be for
you know if they occur as a pair that
would give us a space we need to store
it and then we can parse each of these
we're effectively looking for a token of
type glyph and if we get that what we
want to see is the code point and the
horizontal advance I'm sorry just the
code point and the bitmap ID for it if
you look here I think we did we
neglected as specify the code point so
if you look here we we specified the
bitmap we didn't specify
unfortunately the we didn't specify the
the code point only the alignment of the
bitmap so we've got two out of the three
things we need we'll have to add one
here which is literally just a number
that is the Unicode code point
represented by this particular glyph
because remember the glyphs are packed
so if you use a total of 500 code points
from the unicode code set unicode code
set for a particular font then there are
only 500 glyphs but there may be a very
wide range of code points covered by
those 500 glyphs so that's a very sparse
array so what we want there is just a
way of understanding for each glyph in
the packed glyph array what's the actual
code point that that glyph is you know
it's mapped to at runtime when we go
here to the you know glyph processing
itself and we parse that stuff oh you
know we load that stuff in what we need
to do here is a little bit complicated
we actually have to process the bitmaps
separately so we have to issue a load
bitmap at will an import bitmap call for
every single one of these lines that's
different than what we
before because remember what we were
doing before is we'd only do for every
block one file ingest so files
effectively mapped directly to the
blocks themselves but here each file is
mapped to a line not a particularly
difficult or weird situation it's just
that's what's going on we also know we
have the horizontal advance so this is
the thing that we're gonna have to parse
an array of numbers out of so that's
another thing we've got to do and so I
probably say let's focus on the glyph
part of things here just because that
part's a little bit better understood at
the moment I and this part is I should
say I mean the opposite that part's a
little less understood this is literally
just gonna be calling the parser this
many times right the N squared number of
times to get that many integers in
followed by a comma so that's you know
that's nothing
oh hello hello all right so I guess
feeding time is over and we've restored
plus power back to the programming
stream which is very important hello
Soph me how's it going do you have
opinions on the code do you what do you
think here let me show you what do you
think of that code right there is it
good to look up at the camera no all
right you can just do your thing if you
need to type you can just paw just paw
at the keyboard at whatever you think is
wrong with it just don't shut off the
machine that has happened before she she
definitely has shut off my laptop before
when I was in the middle of something
and that can be kind of a problem but
you know maybe she didn't like what I
was doing
it's entirely possible all right soft
bean okay all right so we're gonna be
we're gonna be cat lap programming here
which is definitely a little bit harder
I don't know if you can see that's a
good girl she's shedding her undercoat
right now so she is like just literally
producing a cat an entire extra cat's
worth of fur like every day which which
is kind of difficult to manage I
probably I need to get like some more
brushes in here so that like I have a
brush all for whenever she's around
because she really needs the brushing
she's just shedding so much for it's
just this has happens in the springtime
because she get I think because she does
sit in the Sun a lot I think she does do
the coat cycle that you know an outdoor
cat would do even though she's not an
outdoor cat um so it's very okay okay
all right
do you want to programs you want to help
program can you help us program we got
to do this font routine okay we're gonna
do the fun okay
we're gonna do the font routine you can
go look for won't you help us by keeping
watch on the birds outside and then
we'll write the font routine and you can
check it when we're done and make sure
it's good okay okay do you mean to put
you in your seat do you need a lift
gene lift yeah okay
there you go
there we go no all right okay you coming
back over what's it what's the call so
I'm not really sure what puss wants well
she wants to eat my headphone cord and
that's pretty common but I'm not sure do
you want to sit there you want sit there
is that good okay let's just go ahead
and see what we can do here let's see
we're not getting what do you want to do
what's going on you're just you're very
cuddly yeah is there something you need
everything okay
you just ate you just want a nap what do
you want to do all right you take care
of that and we're gonna we're gonna
write this this cliff import routine
here okay
all right sue
like we got a parse the glyphs and those
lists are gonna give this bitmap code
and the bitmap code needs to be imported
separately so we're gonna have to do
like an import glyph kind of a call here
and it's gonna have to take you know
like a bitmap name and that's gonna have
to get loaded out of the file using the
same techniques that we were using
before to load things out of file which
means that we're gonna want to pull that
you know code that checks to see whether
or not something is out of date and you
know that kind of stuff we need to make
sure that that stuff is happening inside
of reusable routine so for every bitmap
we can you know actually do that so
we're going to pass that the bitmap name
and we're gonna have to pass it the
align point like v2 like whatever you
know we're gonna have to pass it this
thing right and for that I mean it's
unfortunate but that you know that we're
specifying these align points in two
different ways it's a little bit janky
there
so you know we may want to write those
out a little bit differently we may want
to write those out as the sort of short
values that we were using before I feel
like that might be better so it might be
nicer if this was instead an actual
align point so maybe I will force it to
be that more something so that we
essentially have when this comes in
notion of what the align points are
actually going to be hard to say but I'm
just gonna say like I think that's what
we want I don't know so I think we want
to do this where we just passed the
align point in and maybe you know if
this were structured to allow many align
points for the bitmap because I don't
know how exactly we want to do that but
it would probably look something like
this right so we have like that one a
line point and and off its gonna go but
we could pass more line points if we
wanted to something like that so I don't
really know but let's like sketch it out
that way for now and we'll push forwards
through it and see what happens when we
actually get there so we know we have a
bitmap file name right and that's gonna
be just this you know thing with the
ping on it that's gonna go get a path
appended to it and then loaded so that's
all fine but then what we also need here
in addition is we're going to need to
we're going to need to pass like the the
context because it's going to need to do
a bunch of asset work in order to import
that bitmap file name so I think we need
something like that and then we can read
this stuff out as necessary so we would
have like here you know a glyph index
that we would produce by requiring a
token here so in this case we would have
a number that needs to get used a number
that needs to get read we would check to
see whether that glyph index is in range
so it needs to fit inside the table
right the universe realized one past
highest code point we don't actually
need to store because we're gonna know
that information we know that like every
time we see a code point we can just
make this be one past it so like in here
when we see the code point we can just
do like if one past highest code point
is less than or equal to the code point
that we saw we can just bump it there
you know I'm saying so I think we can
avoid actually ever specifying that and
just track it since we'll see all the
code points when we go to write the
thing out we're done um so these guys
here look like they're probably pretty
easy to to just use directly so I guess
like I really can make this as simple as
just requiring the glyph count to come
first right everything else
looks like we could do this way and so
those allow us to parse these pieces
here pretty easily and these are just
like oh yeah I need an equal sign and
then I need a number and that's pretty
much it so I think that's all we need so
I want these to persist outside so for
each one of those I would just write it
up here here's the sender height here's
the descender height and here is the
external letting there's the code point
these all get read in I think that's
pretty much it right so when we come
down through here at the end then this
is going to be like not it's gonna
exactly the same code it's just not
gonna have to do any of those export
those unpacks there it can just use them
directly because they're just values we
track now so I think we're pretty much
good to go
so that means the only requirement for a
font is that the glyph count appears
first that means if we wanted to we
could also put that in here somewhere as
a different thing if we wanted to I'm
not gonna bother right now let's just
say we require that and we'll just leave
it that way I don't really care when we
actually create these arrays also I'm
gonna just while we're here because you
know - well we got to do at some point
the context has this temporary
I'm gonna use that to just push the
memory on here because I don't want it
to stick around right it's just
temporary for during processing so we're
going to go ahead and push these arrays
on which allow us to have all the
information we need for processing so
then through here whatever we grab a
glyph we can now say well the code
points for the glyph equal the code
point right whatever that glyph index is
and the horizontal advance which will
come down here we can just read these in
in a loop right so what we want to do
here is say look we need to read one
horizontal advance for every glyph that
there is squared right so we've got the
you know effectively a read index and
we've got glyph count times flip count
we're gonna go through here reading each
of these into the horizontal advance
setting that value so we know from
looking at the actual age of T what that
thing will look like it's essentially
just alright we've got the horizontal
advance token read so we need to require
the equals token now and then we know
that we're just reading numbers so first
we do a require token oops
to get the actual number in and then we
do a require token comma
right now looking through here we know
that at the end it's actually a
semicolon not a comma so we really don't
want to do that if it's the last one
right so we only want to do that you
know if we're in between two what I
could do here is the glyph count times
glyph count say you know don't regret it
tokens again I don't really want to do
that because it's harder to check for
it's just more you know typing or
storage what I'd rather do is just hey
if it's not zero require the token
before you read a number so that way
right you can see that this is an easier
way to write that otherwise I would have
had to say if it works coming after I
would haven't said if read I read index
plus one is not equal to glyph count
times lift count it's just more or save
this value and use it right you know
it's just so this is nice and simple it
just keeps it easier because that way we
know look we only require the comma if
we already read at least one number but
the first number doesn't need the comma
right so I think that's all good that
seems fine so that reads our whole
horizontal advance table so now we just
need to finish off reading the glyph
assuming that the glyph index is okay
then we just need to deal with the code
points the name bitmap name you know
that kind of junk and read you know the
actual alignment thing here now I want
to look just really quickly because I
don't remember I want to go ahead and
load in to the editor here what is one
of those tag files look like in terms of
align points here it is so looking at
this I kind of just want to use the same
format I think probably for what you
know for what this thing is is actually
specifying so if you look at the align
point themselves if I if I go over to
the file format and we look at the align
point there it is you can see we've got
you know
P percent value is the size value and
the type value I don't really think we
need the size of the type for the font
so we're really just storing to you six
teens I think that's it so what I'd like
to do here is in that font hht I'm just
gonna I think I'm just gonna literally
store the to you six teens and then
assume the rest of the align point
values I think that's what I would like
so when we actually do this let's grab
all the tokens that we actually need so
we've got a name token or sorry I should
say a filing token we need this to have
a comma and this is just going to be a
giant list of requirements right so
we're basically saying look we need a
file name then we're gonna need and I
mean I guess I don't even need the word
token after it I could just say that's
the file name and then when we actually
go to pass this thing I can just say
like alright well it's just you know
it's it's whatever the value is I don't
remember in the tokenizer exactly what
that field is called it's just text
right so here we know we're gonna get
the file name we know we're gonna get
the code point and then we're gonna get
the aligned X and the line y
and that's the entirety of one of these
font specifiers so it's just the
filename the code point the align X in
the Alliant
all get rid in and they're not gonna get
rid of this float because float is just
Dicer to deal with so I'd rather not
write so after all of that we should
just be able to validate like you know
whether the glyph index is what we
thought it should be and so on I could
even do this right and so if I do that
then when we when we look at how those
align points are actually packed when we
put those together we can just make sure
that those values are within range so
what I can do is say you know if you
know the code point well the code point
doesn't really matter if the align X is
less than this and align Y is less than
this right not have an S 16 max
we do not we have a u16 max I guess
that's what we actually meant so we just
check to see make sure these are within
the ranges that they're allowed to be if
they're not will issue an error there
and if they are we're good to go we also
want to do a check for the glyph just
massages code around here so this is
also an error and so here what we want
to say is all right I if the token if
the glyph index for the token is wrong
and in here just looking at it I think I
want the token itself just for error
reporting purposes right so I think I
want to do this I want to be able to
report that error specifically on that
token so I want to be able to say like
look if the glyph was out of bounds
there's the error right like
something like that
I I don't know if we need do we actually
use character turns now we don't so I
can get rid of that and so here where we
have those errors I'm just gonna give it
all of the numbers we know so you know
here's our glyph index and here's our
glyph count so that way it should be
obvious like a something specifying like
an out of range whiff and we can't we
don't know what to do with that like
it's obviously corrupt font file font
markup rather so you know fix it so here
we also want sort of the same thing we
want to be able to testify the alignment
being broken and so in here I probably
want this to be the align token as well
I don't know exactly where we want to
air out on this we could air out on
either one individually but I don't
actually know if I care about that so we
may just maybe we'll use the same thing
here and just say glyph has bad
alignment values and again we really
don't expect ever to hit these but we'll
just you know leave them there just in
case
so assuming everything comes in okay
then we can set the code point two to be
correct which is what we want and we can
set the alignment to be what we want so
just a line point for example we can set
up here and so the align points
has to be set to probably default right
so up here we probably want to say look
the type of this thing is that and then
here we want to set the P percents and
the size and stuff like that right so
actually you know probably I'd like to
do is just do one of those set a line
point calls like this and say alright
set this a line point to be aligned to
this it's not going to be well it is a
two-parent right the size is going to be
1.0 and the alignment in terms of like
think where the point is gonna be the
center point and then we will overwrite
that assuming that we see one of these
other alignments here will overwrite the
P percent with the values that we
actually get right so that allows us to
import the entire thing in here and then
all we really need to do is start to
take out some of that bitmap code so we
can call it and say hey we need to
import this like dependent bitmap so
please make sure you've got it and when
we get it back by the way I need to know
the bitmap right cuz this right here
needs to be set so we'll set the code
points dot glyph index unicode code
point here and then we'll set the code
points bitmap here right
so that's the way that's got to work I
think so we'll expect import glyph to
tell us what that's going to be then
finally when we get to the very end of
it all down here and we're ready to
write everything back we can create the
font pretty easily now but we need some
way of like applying tags to it because
remember we got like a tag array and
stuff so we're like you know we're gonna
have to actually do some work here to
tag the metadata and that sort of thing
and so if we look down at what we're
actually doing here when we do all this
processing you can see we can call
update asset metadata right and that
would actually do what we need like you
know if you look at this it sets the
type and and difference the tags and all
that nonsense we need to do that right
so that pretty much takes care of that
matching for us so I think that part is
pretty good to go right what I don't
actually know is where is it getting the
data for the actual where is it getting
the data for the actual asset
so it looks like it's just using it the
asset index rate right here okay like
that seems totally fine uh so I think
what we want to do yeah I think I'm
right I think we want to do is just
break this out and this call
just needs a version that doesn't use a
grid that's just gonna do one asset and
update it that way so if we imagine we
were inside here what would we need so
if this went away right so this thing
has to call out to you know some other
function here right it's gonna call this
thing what else does it actually need to
know in order to produce that result
right and so from looking at it it seems
pretty clear well it means you know all
of the stuff that we were giving it here
right the assets the file and the fields
what we really need to do now is say
well we know that we're not taking a tag
grid so we can't pass that and we do
know that we want append tags because
obviously that needs to go down there
but we also need to pass the grid tags
and and the asset index right because
those are the parts that came out of
this
we should probably also pass well
actually I think that just comes out
here right so if we did that so now
we've got the the asset index here and
we've got the import tag array tags here
I think that allows us to make a call to
just update a single assets metadata in
the case where we are only doing one
which it which is like what we have with
the fonts we're parse font lock for
example when we get down here we want to
do that update asset made of data like
so right so we know we've got the game
assets here we know we have to pass a
source file of some kind so we don't
know what that is yet we're going to
have to to get it we should have the
fields because those exist already we
know what the append tags are so those
are fine I and I don't think we have
this because this came from the grid so
these extra tags just aren't they don't
exist right so I think we're down to
just this we need to be able to produce
the source file that that this stuff
comes from unfortunately I don't we
don't have one so I'm not really sure
how we would do that
because fonts don't come from a file
it's this file which I guess is okay if
we wanted to specify that so let's just
take a look at where that's actually
happening so file arrow right
it's really just used it's really just
used to get that destination file index
which I think we already know right so
[Music]
so do we actually if we were to get rid
of this well let's let's build first and
go from there and so I can use some
errors to guide us in this process a
little bit all right so this is actually
import like grid tag right so that was
wrong work grid tags Thanks
this needs to be told what kind of field
it was there this is probably the wrong
format what's our pusher raidCall again
it's the arena the count and then the
type so it's looks like this
[Music]
it's kept a horror of capitalization I
don't know if code point should be tap
inter capped or not
[Music]
so I think the main problem just looking
at it here what we've what we're running
into
is the fact that fonts don't come from a
file at the moment they're just reading
out of the hht and the hht always gets
parsed so in a sense we don't really
need to do the checking that we normally
do because we're always going to
effectively have an updated version so
it's just if they disk they need to be
outputted if they didn't if they don't
but we don't need to first check that
piece of information because they they
don't have an additional file that we
read so that's the part we're gonna have
to work around that's really just a
plumbing problem I think so we can kind
of go from there quickly let me just
sort of clean up any other as we have so
we don't really have many looks like we
fixed them so that's the part that I
need to kind of get away from here so
update single asset metadata let me just
look now at what I wanted to look at
before so let's suppose that asset
source file was not available and/or
asset file wasn't available like what
are these things actually being used for
right so first of all there's the
modified value right and then there's a
rent but that we know because we know
which asset file were writing to that's
something we could just supply so what
if we said this where we're like alright
that goes back here where it was and
then this actually passes asset file
right so it doesn't have the other file
it just has the asset file what would we
then not know right what what is the
problem there out of that so first of
all it looks like we don't know where to
put the errors so we could I mean
obviously we can't fix that
why can I not go backwards oh there we
go
all right
it looks like we don't know how to put
the source file in there so that would
be fine we just need to pass that would
be the name of the hht which is fine so
really it looks like mostly what we're
talking about here is just the error
stream it's just the air stream in the
name so again seems pretty
straightforward what we can do there is
say all right like pass the error stream
and the source file name right so if we
did that then we could take these out
and just say like the error stream there
I guess we'll call this errors for
simplicity that should allow us to say
okay if we pass those two things out
from inside update asset metadata so
that when we look in here and we're you
know sort of sending this nonsense down
right there
after the asset file will send the base
name and we'll send the errors I think
like that then in here we would not have
to do this anymore
all of these things would just go to
stuff that we passed directly and then
we don't have to worry about it what did
I call that
there and so that way that should give
us the ability to when we call update
single asset metadata here we only need
to pass like the destination file and
what that name would be so I think
that's okay like that seems like that
would work um I don't really see any
issues with that so when we come through
here we know which asset file we are
because this operation we can do right
in right in line so if we get to here we
can grab that by saying whatever the
context HHA index is that should give us
the asset file that we're targeting the
error stream probably would just be the
tokenizer Zehra stream so you know the
tokenizer itself right has an air stream
built into it that it's using that's the
one we would route all of our errors to
so in here we would just need to say
okay pass the asset file pass the error
stream from the tokenizer and then the
only thing we would need is that base
name the base name itself I think is
just this so I think the context itself
has that piece of information and I
think that's everything that we actually
need right
pretty sure anyway so when we call this
we need to get the game assets we
already have them they're just not put
into a convenient pointer so pretty
trivial they're the only other stuff we
now need to think about is how we're
actually gonna update the rest of the
phone info I think most of it is
otherwise fine uh contents is undeclared
identifier that's true I don't know
I said contents and this is the part
where now we need to figure out what the
asset index actually is going to be okay
so now I think we've come to the only
hard problem that we actually have and
it is as follows normally we use the
like normally we have a way of looking
up what the asset index was for the
import on a particular file but in this
case we don't know right look we have no
idea what the asset action index
actually was because we don't have
anywhere to put it right so we've got a
couple different ways we could do this
one is that we can introduce something
in the asset system that itself stores
the piece of information we needed like
hey there's a way to look up a font an
asset name and back comes the index for
that asset right so there's an
additional lookup I don't love that
because we're introducing code paths
just for the font handle which seems
less good right but my assumption here
is that we would rather go with
something simpler so I'm thinking maybe
what we would do is when we load the
glyphs instead of getting back to bitmap
ID maybe that import glyph routine
actually gives us back one of these
right um and we could store the the font
index in there just a thought
the reason that I don't love that is
because it wouldn't allow you to use the
same thought glyph in multiple fonts
which seems like a bad limitation so I'm
just not sure exactly where yeah I'm
just not sure exactly where that data
should come from it seems like we do
want to support the idea that you can
have multiple of these but I'm just not
sure where I would put the information
I really don't have a good idea for this
sorry
so I guess when we Oh
oh wait maybe I do have an idea you know
what I do have an idea I take it all
back this is actually much simpler we
all we have to do is introduce a
synthetic asset file because the asset
files are stored in the hhas
that they are packed into so actually
it's not that hard all we have to do is
say in the asset system when we actually
initialize one of the sources right this
code we just used the base name of the
font so I don't know why I was making
such a big deal out of that because
actually it's really just not that hard
all we have to do is say all right get
us you know font source file this is
synthetic doesn't actually exist there
is no actual source file but that's fine
we don't care we pass the game assets
and the base name the base name is
whatever that block token whatever the
name is that we get out of here so
before the open brace read I just forgot
that we have this there is a name this
is the font name right so that font name
should give us the asset source file we
need so here I'm gonna say get the
source file for this thing and then from
there we can create our font asset and
do all the rest of our work so it really
wasn't that hard after all we were just
being dumb so sorry about that all right
so then in here where we've got the font
source file we can now actually use this
ah there we go
what we want to do here is do that
remapping so like where we actually set
the target of this thing you can see it
here right where we say where is this
thing gonna go you know it's gonna go in
here or whatever right so this is all
we're gonna do we're just gonna say yep
let's let's go ahead and write that into
the asset file or asset source file I
should say so whatever the source file
is here you know it's gonna be written
to this HHA now mandatorily that's where
it goes right and once we do this
process this asset file will now have
the asset index in it as well so we can
look that up of course that asset file
index has to be updated I think now we
can move that logic though back into the
the single writer and just have that be
handled in the common case so here you
can see us doing this part here where
you get the asset index out of the file
and doing the tags so I guess it was
done somewhere else where is that
somewhere else
so I guess it's just in all of these
right where you see it says like hey get
me the asset index so this is where it's
been happening right it tries to get out
of the asset file whatever the asset
index was we and we either use it or
don't so I think this is fine the only
thing I don't know of here is like when
this asset data gets updated I am
assuming that that means we need to mark
it as modified but I guess that would
happen with the tags anyway so I think
we're fine so I think all we need to do
here is just say all right we've got the
HHA font information that's just a zero
thing that we're gonna fill out in a
second
when we finish yeah that can just be
read out of the asset I guess
I think that's all we need so we just
say look is there already one for this
thing it's gonna be in a 0-0 slot cuz
there's only one for a font if we don't
have one let's reserve one for the font
once we do we're good to go so we've got
the asset loaded out now so that means
the font is just the asset font we write
all the data into that and then we can
update it and be done right so I think
that's everything we need to do modulo
actually writing out the new asset
metadata like the glyphs and that stuff
so we do still need to do that one part
but otherwise I think we're okay the
fact that this requires a care star is
bad and we'll have to fix that in a
second because we want to be able to not
do that I'm surprised we're still doing
that honestly so I'm not sure what's
going on there
but we'll see in a second so the HHA
index here that's coastal comes out the
context I'm not sure why we're doing
that this year is
[Music]
font source file Oh God
looks like I've don't ask me why some
kind of weird screenshot just happened
all right
so yeah
so the asset we actually want to look at
the hij part of the font obviously but I
think that's it so now we just have to
look at update single asset metadata
make sure we're passing the right stuff
we need the assets the asset file the
base name the errors the fields the
append tags the asset index and the
extra tags and then I think we're just
about good right seems good
so that update single asset metadata
part there
I guess word I'm not sure what that's
good funny man I've got the asker this
fellow got the H is this Tim the
Airstream got the fields oh that's the
problem all right so I think we need to
actually now just do two more steps one
is to write the actual glyph import
which is really just fixing our existing
code so that it can get munched we just
reuse the stuff we already use for
loading a bitmap but the thing we need
to do here is we don't currently write
out our two arrays so we need to reserve
space for those and write them out if
they don't differ so right now what we
know is you know in this case here we
could do this right and test to see if
what's already in the file differs or
not and that's sort of what we need to
do here oh and another way to do this
would just be like okay
so what we need to do now it you know
when we grab this font out we would also
need to do a thing where we say hey make
sure we compare the existing font arrays
I that are that are in the that are in
the existing font data we need to make
sure that those are not different than
the ones we just computed right so how
we actually do that in this case it's a
little bit tricky because we don't know
whether or not we don't really know that
that's that those fonts have even been
loaded so we would have to compare it
with the file directly right because if
you look at what actually happens when
you do a load font you can see right
here like that's not not what I was
talking about when you do a load font
you can see that it it actually is a
page in that code point data and we need
to be able to know what's happening
there right we we have to be able to
compare that existing file data to know
whether we need to rewrite it you know
I'm saying so I think we're probably
looking at something where we would need
to do like literally this this load so
we would need to do something like okay
assuming that we
assuming that we think we don't need to
update what we need to do here is make
sure we can actually load the file in
right get this data and then do like a
compare right on that data and looking
at the way that this stuff works here
where we get the size total it's I feel
like we almost want to make this code be
shareable so that effectively what we
can do is do this the same way this is
doing it and make sure we fill those the
way they're being filled here something
like that so that we can actually test
them later I don't know it's kind of
hard to say but I suppose the other way
to do it is to read them separately and
then test them I don't know
again it's really annoying this is as
you can see by the amount of work we've
had to do for asset importing the
difference between an asset system that
allows dynamic updating and running from
PAC files that can be updated directly
the difference between that and the
stupid version which is just I can only
read things once and pack them once and
there's no dynamic updating is massive
right it's like a 10x complexity
increase to go from a I don't support
hot updating of the live files to I do
because 90% of this code is from that
right but that's why people license
engines or by asset system stuff like I
used to work on because it's a
tremendous amount of bookkeeping code
just way too much and most of it's just
because art tools aren't made to output
things games can run on directly so
you're doing this work every time or the
engine writer is but somebody is because
the tools don't do it so anyway we need
some way of knowing whether we need to
rewrite it because we don't really want
to rewrite it every time we
and import we only want to rewrite it if
we actually got different values than
the ones that we already stored so what
we'd like to do is say you know compare
those two things what I might say is
like let's just let's just do this so we
need to do a fill rebuild if we do or if
blocks in the file the two blocks in the
file that we actually have if those
blocks differ and so if the asset here
we just do this right like assets asset
file here we just say look let's write a
function that takes an asset file takes
a range of date in the asset file and
then an actual like array we would be
writing out right like the code points
are the horizontal advance in our case
and just returns whether or not we need
to so
so basically that way we can just do
something like this so we now know like
alright we know that we've got the code
point size and the horizont sees we know
we need to dip the ranges out here's
what we're going to be writing to them
if we need to let's make something that
can actually do that then we'll say all
right if we need a full rebuild then we
need to actually reserve that space
otherwise we don't actually have to do
that right we don't actually have to
rewrite the font if those things didn't
change cuz those are the only things
that actually would have depended on
this right so I think we should be able
to do that I'm guessing that would seem
logical to me but I yeah like I said I'm
not 100% certain so the other thing we
might have to do there is we might have
to compare these as well so yeah I mean
another thing we might want to do is say
okay if any of these things differed we
also need a full rebuild so that's just
an another annoying piece of nonsense
again this is where I think I kind of
want to be able to do something where I
say hmm here's the data we would write
just to finis entirety and we just like
write it and then there's a diff fat
that I put in it to do basically exactly
oh this you can see why it's just this
is very very annoying and complicated
and I feel like we could have gotten it
better I don't really want to have to go
down that road now but I do feel like
there's a something there and so if this
were like my day job I would definitely
go in and figure out how to make that
happen but you know it's not so we won't
something like that
yeah I'm saying
that seems reasonable not great but
reasonable hello cat is back so I think
all that's good I just now need
something that says what the sizes of
these things are which we kind of
already know right so this is how big
the code point size is this is how big
pearls Donald Vance size is and although
I don't love that you know I think that
probably is fine for our purposes again
this is not code that users would be
running so if it is kind of janky or
fragile or we have to debug it a bunch
it's not as bad because we don't
actually depend on it to be reliable
when we ship it that helps a little bit
but again like I said it doesn't really
meet kind of my my you know I would do
another round on it I guess is what I'd
say uh so looking at this we then if we
need to do the rebuild here I think
really when I'm saying that I suppose
this stuff can all happen just in
general that that stuff is fine so what
we're really looking at here is in needs
full rebuild that's just when we need to
actually write the font out itself and
so to do that we just need to follow the
sort of the lead of the reserve asset
like space or whatever we call that let
me just jump to reserve asset we just
need to do this where we reserved space
for each of these things now I I guess
we don't do it twice because we just do
it for the total size that we needed so
what we would be doing here is saying
that asset data
so this this asset data that we've got
here we need to make sure that that's
going to hold the entirety of what we're
going to write so we have to pass it the
data size of the code point size plus
the horizontal advance size once we know
that that's safe we're good to go
but there's sort of a one additional
thing here too I suppose
this needs to be checked as well so we
sort of need this to have been computed
already as you know sort of a secondary
piece of information right and so if the
data size was wrong or these things
don't match or the blocks themselves
don't match if any of those things is
true we need to just rewrite this thing
and so that's gonna set the the modified
stuff on these files and that'll happen
automatically which is nice right you
can kind of see that happening here why
this doesn't set modified I'm not
entirely sure but oh well and then
anyway we at that point need to write
these out which is fortunately not so
difficult we know that we've got the
code point size here I should I guess
I'm gonna have to make these be thirty
twos here
we don't support larger than 32 sides
for that data so when we write the asset
data out here what we would do is say
here's the asset file in question here's
the data offset here's the thing we're
writing oops go ahead and write that I
think it's that and then we've got a
horizontal advance size now this is
going to start where the code points
left off but other than that I think
we're okay that'll do all the writing
for us
and off we go again not pretty but I
think that's where we're at so that will
write the font stuff out and look we've
got one too many close friends there
looks a lot good and then we need to
actually implement that block difference
routines which doesn't look particularly
hard to write either so that should be
pretty easy and then we can just focus
next weekend I guess on what what is
this complaining about can I create
import group tag no used to find confuse
available argument eight tag array to
grid tag
all right so let's just quickly blast
this in here if we have comparator here
for a block then what we want to do is
say here's the game assets here's the
asset file here's the data offset and
the size and then the guess what we're
comparing it to right so we need to do
that read and then we need to do mmm
compare which I thought we had you have
something that does this I feel like we
wrote something like this
ha so we have something that says
whether the memory differs or not and
that's what we actually need in this
case so we should be able to do a memory
is equal call where we pass the buffer
you know the you know file value and the
test value I guess are the two things we
should be able to say that gives us our
result so the only thing we have to
worry about is how we would actually you
know how to actually get that data out
of the file so in order to do that I'm
just going to go and again look at that
part that we were just you know for the
load font call that I was looking at
before we're just going to do that same
operation so we say look soon the result
is false try to get the for whatever the
acid is that we're reading here so I
guess we could just pass the asset
actually because it looks like the asset
itself has the file index in it so can
even just do this right but I don't know
I'm gonna go with this for this asset
get the file handle that we're going to
use to load it for the data offset that
you're given go ahead and read that from
that file handle however much we told
you to and put that into our temp buffer
assuming that there weren't any errors
then go ahead and do the compare
otherwise assume that it failed now when
we do this we're gonna need a place to
put this you know the base of the
temporary and so what we'd like to do
here is we'd like to just be able to
have a scratch
right would be we'd like to be able to
do something we're going to say
temporary memory like begin temp
temporary memory because we don't care
about saving any of this we just want to
use it just for scratch so we should be
able to do that just fine here and that
means we should be able to allocate
basically a membe lock to use in this
particular circumstance so in order to
get that file value we can just do give
me something that's the size you said we
needed we don't need to do anything else
with it we also don't need to clear it
like we normally do so we can just say
hey don't don't clear that either so
that's pretty much the entirety the
block clears or a block difference call
we know we've got a temporary nough here
because there's just one sitting around
so we can just say whatever that temp
man was called temporary 'no i that
should do it
so i think that gives us the full
pipeline pretty much start to finish
[Music]
looks like get file handle for is not
declare its we're gonna have to push
that out there we need a version of get
of that get or create asset source file
that doesn't use a care estar so i'm not
sure why it's even using a care star
actually because that's kind of annoying
we want those to be using a name that's
that's a string so I think that's like
an older piece of code so we do want to
fix that but what else do we got here
and then we have to import implement the
import glyph there let's look at what
the problem is here Assaf odd asset so
in this case we know that it's just this
asset
we're creating this asset we need to set
the asset file so when the asset gets
reserved I'm not sure when this asset
file actually is supposed to get set
where it when the assets supposed to get
set so like when you do this reserve it
doesn't actually set the asset to
anything in particular so I'm curious to
know like when that piece of information
actually gets set because we need it to
be reliable if you look in here you can
see that it's got like a file index and
an asset index in file and so I just I
do not know who's actually setting those
things so that's only happening like out
here in write modifications to HHA so I
do feel like that means that that buffer
check has to take something more
specific so here in get file handle for
what we really need to do is just just
get this platform file handle so I think
what I'd want to do is inside block
differs just forget all of this garbage
entirely and actually just do this right
because we already have the asset file
in question when we're here so rather
than going through some roundabout
process to figure out what file we're
going through what I would much rather
do is in here say by the way the asset
file in question is this one here's the
handle you know I'm saying
all right um let's see here so I think
that's it I'm still a little cagey have
how this works how does it know where to
put these assets so like who is setting
that asset and Nixon files getting set
there but file index someone has to set
this right and that someone is kind of
us right
so I mean that just kind of has to
happen
[Music]
so I think we're okay
so I think that's basically it again
very very complicated lots of pretty
tricky stuff happening there and again I
think if we wanted to do a full another
full pass on the asset system we could
fix a lot of that I just don't know that
we will
so because going to a system that's more
generic in terms of how it prepares and
then diffs data is almost certainly the
right way to go but I we probably just
won't do that but that's where we would
that's how we would do the next
iteration to make further improvements
so for right now what I'm going to do is
I'm gonna finish up for today because
we're pretty much done we just now need
to to stuff out the import glyph call
which we don't actually have probably
just you there and yeah that's I don't
actually know what we want to pass there
yet
so that's what we need to implement but
at the moment it's not and then the only
other thing that we have here is we want
to be able to do a getter create asset
source file without needing a null
terminated string I am surprised that
that didn't already exist that's really
bizarre you can see here like you know
it's just yeah just looking at all the
places it's actually used
so you can even see in here like we had
to do a null terminator on here for no
reason right so that we could pass it as
a null terminator is trying to begin
with so I really do think we just want
that to be a string in general I mean
that's really all there is to it so I
think we do want that I'm gonna go ahead
and and make this happen this way
temporarily
and this will just make sure we can pile
okay for now
so what was it supposed to be taking
their on the bitmap ID because that's
the only thing we've got left
oh it is actually it's just an actual
bitmap ID which is kind of a little bit
weird because we don't really use IDs in
here otherwise so I don't love that I
think we want that to be a u-32 you know
not that that's not what it is but I
just think that should be like that
right
so I think that's good for now
that leaves us running okay so I think
that's pretty much all there is to it we
can go ahead to brief Q&amp;A now and next
time we'll do the import glyph next we
go through import glyph and debugging
import lyft will just be like basically
Riemann geing some some code there oh
sorry did I have a typo there
let me take a look yeah
looks like no questions
all right I've forgotten no questions
then I am done I will go ahead and wrap
it up thank you everyone for joining me
for another episode of handmade hero
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow in
series you can always peer to the game
on handmade hero org and it comes with a
source code so you can follow along at
home that's it for this weekend next
weekend I will just be doing cleanup
work so that we can check this off the
asset system off is being done basically
that involves pulling out that bitmap
import code so that it can work for
glyphs or for sprite sheets like it was
working currently and then just like
testing everything debugging you know
making sure we can rebuild your desk
that's just putting it through its paces
making sure everything's fine and and
then I think we're in good I think we're
in good shape I hope see you back here
for that until then have fun programming
and I'll see everyone on the Internet
tickety's everybody