everybody welcome to handmade here oh
sure we code a complete game live on
stream we did the work necessary
yesterday to remember whether or not
files have changed so we basically
snapped the file date on files and then
we can check them later to see if
they've changed what we need to do today
is do something meaningful when they do
change we already wrote the PNG reader
so we can load them but we don't
actually know what to do with them and
so our job today is to do something with
them sure we can call the PNG reader but
what do we do once we get the PNG back
so I'm going to go ahead and load up
handmade asset that's where this is
taking place let's just get that going
here so what you can see here is we left
a stub function here called update asset
package from PNG and the thing that we
created was this check for art changes
this goes through looks to see what
files the platform layer reports they're
being of type PNG and after it's done
with that it looks through them all to
see which ones have changed from the
last time we saw them those ones that
have changed get this call but this
doesn't do anything it's all set up to
do something it's got the contents of
the file right here it's got an arena
that it can use for temporary work such
as loading the file and you can see that
we're all set up here to go ahead and
call like parse PNG for example but we
don't actually know what we're gonna do
with it so that's kind of what we need
to start doing today
and again that starts to get us into the
the zone that we don't really know what
we want to do which is the tags part of
things and so that's what we're going to
kind of run up into today I think so
we'll kind of run up into that and we'll
stop there and then we'll pick that up
the next weekend we're coding we'll
start to take a look at what we want to
do with that with that tag stuff so we
know that we can call the PNG reader
that we wrote and we know that it will
return us an image so this is the raw
image that would come back here we give
it a temporary nough and then what we
need to do is pass it a file and we also
need to have some kind of
an info stream if we care now one of the
things that I'm pretty sure that we did
and if we didn't do we need to do it
right now but one of the things that we
need to do is make sure that we do not
record anything if we don't have a
destination stream so we did not do that
so exactly what I said we need to do we
didn't do we want to do this right
because we want to be able to just not
capture information could come back and
so for example in this case we don't
care about the like debug print out
that's gonna happen here in the info
stream we just don't care about that at
all so what we would rather do is only
initialize the error stream so what we
can do here is we want to create one of
these file one of these file buffers and
if you go back and look at what we did
in test PNG we have like an error stream
you can see right here when we do read
into our file we sort of create one of
these and blah blah blah right but what
we would like to do if possible is we'd
like to make this a little bit more
systemic because this is going to be
something now that we actually do
perhaps more regularly creating one of
these streams one of these yeah one of
these stream things so what I'd like to
do is say well okay so maybe we have a
count and a data pointer or something
like this and maybe when we get to the
end here maybe we do something like
stream result we do a you know make
stream or something like this and we
pass it the count and the data and the
error buffer and then off we go so that
we know that we've got some way of
making these that's reliable and and
that works right so this would be this
would be nice now the problem that we
have here is that the error stream we
actually wanted to use it here right so
what we kind of want to do instead is
a little bit uglier but you know if we
want to do it that way we kind of don't
have a choice
basically if we'd if we weren't able to
get a pointer here we we produce an
error right so we can still kind of do
it you know it's it's still fine it's
just it's not quite as nice so you know
maybe that isn't the greatest thing to
do I don't know but there you go so it
would look something like this and oops
that would sort of allow us to do this
this kind of a this kind of thing here
so I don't know if necessarily better
but at least it has sort of a
centralized way of calling make stream
you know what I'm saying and so that we
can use in other cases and furthermore
this right here is a buffer so we can
actually sort of straight make this even
more straightforward by doing this sort
of thing and then we just do this right
so make a stream out of oops out of a
buffer and some other stream that
captures errors like so and that's
that's all we do right so from here if I
wanted to do that it's pretty
straightforward as well I know that I've
got the contents that I want to to pass
through here so I can make my file
stream by just saying hey make a stream
with these contents and whatever we want
our air stream to be now I do actually
want an air stream here I want a thing
that will record what the errors
actually were and I think I kind of want
that to be part of the asset system
permanently I don't mind that it kind of
just builds up memory forever because I
think I kind of just want to be able to
go back and inspect that so what I think
I want to do is kind of say that asset
source files when they get you know kind
of pushed on to the I know what you want
to call it when when an asset source
file when we become aware of it I would
like to sort of create in here a stream
that is for
all of the errors that are gonna be
associated with that source file we'll
see a little bit more about why one do
that when we when we move further down
the pipeline but basically what I want
to be able to do is I want to be able to
tell the user when there is an error I
want to say here's the source files that
you just tried to import and here are
the errors per source file that are
relevant so that you you know the artist
can know that something you know bad
happened or whatever so I'm gonna go
ahead and make one of these a little
earlier on in the pipe and I'm gonna
pass that here so we basically have when
the when the asset source file itself
is operational it'll have an Airstream
and all of the errors that happen on
this file will go into that stream not
some you know not off into the ether
somewhere so you know I guess we'll put
the thing that loads the images out of
the asset file here but for the moment
I'd like to ping-pong back down to where
we create one of these match structures
you can see us making one here what I'd
like to do there is go back to the
stream start of things and kind of take
a look at this I want an on-demand
memory stream for these errors and you
know I don't really care how they're
being allocated because like I said it's
never gonna be free that's only for
development purposes anyway so what I
pretty much want to do is say okay in
the case where we create a new match I
want to take the error stream and I want
to just make that a new stream that can
capture errors using the same memory
that we use to store the permanent
information for the asset store so it
stays around forever we'll always be
able to go back and see all the errors
on a particular loaded thing for this
run it's we're probably not gonna save
them out to disk because we don't care
about them further down the line but you
know for the most part that's
we're gonna do now air is on this stream
there are none we don't capture errors
on the stream itself if that happens
then you're just Sol there isn't a
central air stream but that's how that's
going to go now we could choose to do
this differently if it turns out in in a
when we actually go to play with this
that what we'd rather have is just a
single error stream on the assets we can
just put one of those on the asset
system itself and vector everyone
towards that stream again one of the
really nice things about doing the
stream stuff this way is you can just
Rivera's errors you want to wherever you
want and it doesn't really matter so
we'll have plenty of flexibility to you
know look at that sort of stuff later
right alright so if we go ahead and yeah
and go from here we just need to make
sure we've got what's going on here
buffer we just got to make sure that
we've got our make stream which I said I
wanted but we didn't actually implement
I'm gonna make one of these here what I
can do is also kind of piggyback these
two since they are the same you can kind
of see you have an on-demand memory
stream here and anime extreme here that
they're pretty similar stuff right so we
might be able to kind of share a little
bit there I don't know we'll see you in
a second so let's take a look when we do
this make stream and we're gonna pass it
at buffer this is sort of a read stream
you know we could say make read stream
here because that's really what this is
doing so if I want to do one of those I
know that we we look and we can't kind
of see what's going on here we don't
have memory we do have errors right
there giving us one of those that's what
I should put buffer here and so then
we've got you know contents and the bit
count bit buff under flowed first last
all of this stuff can stay zero it's
really just this that we need to
initialize right
now you note there's something very
subtle going on here and I'll point it
out do you notice how we did not so so
one way you could have done this
rather than having buffer contents in
the stream itself is you could have
exclusively used stream chunks right you
could have had it so that what a stream
does is it always looks as its first
dream stream stream chunk for the data
okay you could have done that what
you'll notice is because we chose to
have the buffer in here and stream
chunks are just new buffers that can be
pulled in that actually leads to a much
more closed way of running the system
which is nice in that you can return a
stream by value and it is correct if we
had to have the stream chunks always
then these pointers would have to be
valid which would mean that we would
have to actually allocate memory in here
to point to something that stores this
contents so having the first buffer that
you're reading from always be inside the
actual handle itself actually allows you
a lot more flexibility with how these
things move around and where they live
because you don't have to allocate
memory you can have them on the stack
you can have them welded into other
structures that have been allocated and
you don't need to allocate another piece
hanging off of it for the chunks in the
case where you don't want a chained
situation so that's pretty nice and it's
just worth noting so let's go ahead and
finish up we were doing there
we call this content stream okay and so
when we call parse P&amp;G now we got to go
back and look I don't even remember what
this thing took so let's take a look
maybe since this thing's only supposed
to have one thing getting called maybe
I'll just loft that up into the H file
so it's easier to read it's that's
really all it's for I'm gonna put that
up here right the info is optional so
maybe I'll just make that optional and
then we're done effectively I don't know
why why this doesn't take a pointer so
there's not really a lot of reason for
it not to - that yeah I'm not sure
excuse me I need tissue I'm not sure I'm
not sure where I Parsa P&amp;G doesn't take
yeah well you know I don't really care I
guess it's fine so parse P&amp;G will go
ahead and read that content stream and
now we've got an image back again all of
this stuff we don't have to worry about
hemorrhaging memory or anything here
because all of this stuff is in
temporary arena that gets cleaned up and
again this is a really nice way to
program again a lot of people always ask
about garbage collection of stuff like
this memory arena's are a really good
way to have basically all the things you
wanted from garbage collection without
all the unpredictability and weirdness a
memory arena you can just pass it down
say do we're all you're working here you
can allocate whatever you want and we're
done it all gets cleaned up right you
don't care about any stuff and you don't
need any complicated garbage collection
analysis to figure out what isn't isn't
used because you know that nothing is so
it's just a really nice way of like
having off sections of memory and saying
look we don't really care about tracking
stuff here we're just gonna remember
everything that was allocated and just
wipe it all away at the end you know I'm
saying so they're just really handy in
there one of the big way
is that you can get effectively the
mental freedom from not having to think
about your memory there's a lot of
techniques like this that you just once
you get used to using them garbage
collection just kind of becomes a
non-issue because you're like well 99%
of the time everything can just happen
in a temporary arena or some permanent
arena and that's it and you don't like
the the there's a style of coding where
everyone has gazillions of crazy
pointers pointing to everything and they
have no idea what's going on and do you
need garbage collection to maybe try
makes a sense of it
probably yeah if you're not coding in
that ridiculous style you know it
quickly becomes sort of a non-issue just
with a few simple tools in memory arena
being one of them there's others so
anyway but that that aside once we have
this image back what I want to do here
is I want to break this image up into
tiles because again for those of you who
maybe haven't been following along the
past couple days of coding we definitely
have a different sort of idea of how
we're importing art assets now because
of the new art we got so we just want to
loop through these tiles these tiles
what you can see is we tried to make
sure that they were nice and evenly
spaced so that we don't have to load a
lot of metadata or anything to figure
out where stuff is just to keep
everything simple so if we come in here
and take a look I'm gonna go ahead and
select one of these as best I can here
let me try and get that fairly exact
okay so you can see there's a pink wreck
down there I'm gonna just do one pixel
short of the next one because this is
like the whole area here so what you can
see about this this rectangle that I've
got selected if I click on it here you
can see that this is if you go out to
the actual rectangle itself like so oh
that's nice Anna did that really good
it's actually a one pixel border around
the whole thing
so you can see there it's a 1024 by 1024
rectangle with a pink border around the
edge of it right so what we should be
able to do is just step through the
image looking at these chunks and the
images themselves when we look at them
should conform you can see 8192 8192
right they should conform to an even
number of these chunks so once we get an
image here we should be able to do sort
of a like X count Y count situation that
we can determine directly from the we
can determine directly from the image
width and height right so what we need
we do need to be a little more careful
so we'll will I just want mention I do
it now but we are gonna have some things
like this that aren't that way so the
title screen and the cutscenes stuff can
go down a separate path that's just for
large arbitrary bitmaps those will not
be our bread and butter but they will
have to be handled this is kind of fun I
like this I like Krampus a lot Krampus
is great my mom one time tried to say
Krampus she wanted to say that she likes
cramp Krampus she thinks it's cool that
Krampus in the game or something and but
she didn't remember what Krampus was so
she said krump as' and like I feel like
we need to put krump 'us in the game as
well I don't know what krump is is
but maybe like I don't know maybe
crumpets is like Krampus is like weird
younger brother or something I don't
know it's it's it's pretty hard to say
yeah I don't know if someone wants to
file a bug report on the handmade hero
github with market as a feature request
that we have crumpets in the game
because we already have one up there
which is like to put a winners don't use
drugs screen like the old 90s arcade
games had so like something like that
another feature request it might be a
good idea to have a crumpet in there
alright so I'm gonna go ahead and say
that we've got a tile dimension here
that's 1024 that way we can change it
three oops time dimension sounds like
something that like Neil deGrasse Tyson
would talk about on a talk show or
something alright so we've got the
account in the Y count and now we want
to go through them and again like I said
we're gonna have to do something other
than this for the other kinds of bitmaps
so this is actually just one type of
thing that we're talking about here so
we'll probably pull this out into a
separate system eventually what I'm
going to do here meat you know we could
do is have a thing here where we say you
know process tiled import or something
you know that sort of thing so we could
do that and we probably do want to do
that actually that so I'm gonna go ahead
and do that and and that way in the
future because right here I'm going to
do is after we you know parse PNG I'm
gonna want to have a thing that's like
if this is going to be tiled
but then process the tiled import
otherwise you know process you know you
know something like that right
so it's going to look something like
that eventually but it's not gonna look
like that just yet so anyway in here
we're gonna take one of these image
trucks and we're gonna process this tile
import we're going to need probably hear
the game assets the assets source file
and there's the image there we've got
pretty much what we need at this point
to know the pixel region of the image
that we're talking about here so we what
we want to do is see if it's empty or
not right we want to basically you know
analyze this thing to figure out whether
this is something we actually want check
or not now what I'm gonna do is I want
to produce a I want to produce a copy of
this image of the tile into a temporary
buffer that I can then use for well
whatever I want to use it for right so
in order to know whether this tile in
order to figure out what I want to do
with this tile I want to make that copy
probably at the same time I'm checking
now there's an there's an issue with
that
there's an issue with that and that is
that if we go look at how the asset
system is storing things so here's the
asset and when we look at there it is
when we look at the asset we've got this
asset memories header that's pointing to
potentially that you see that loaded
bitmap structure right so the loaded
bitmap structure let me just grab that
here so the loaded bitmap structure has
like a pointer to the memory and it's
got you know the information about the
bitmap there that we loaded in so what
we more or less want to do I think is
load you know we want to load into one
of these and we either want to load into
one of these that already exists that
we've got loaded or we want to make a
new one that then will be used as the
loaded one right so I think what we want
to do is first search to see whether we
have a loaded bitmap that should be used
and if we don't have one then we will
make a new one and that new one will be
provisional so this is a little hard to
explain upfront so I'm kind of just
going to type it in and explain it after
the fact so you can sort of see what I
mean but basically the you know the long
and short of it here is I need to take
this asset source file right and I need
to look to see if I've got
where is here I need to look and see if
I've got an asset that backs this source
file yet right so when I'm looping
through my X and my Y count here I'm
gonna look up this X&amp;Y and go from there
now it's also worth remembering here
that these have to be clamped so we
should probably also put in here
something like this something that could
be shown to a programmer so they know
what's going on if an artist
accidentally makes an image that has
more grid squares to it we could say the
Tao exceeds whatever that maximum tile
count is right so something like this
right so this way if you feed in a file
and the file has too many columns
it will air out do the same thing here
and we knew what these are oops right X
count Max and y count max are just the
asset indices counts so you know this
will tell the artist assuming that we
print these on screen which is my
eventual plan if they tried to make a
file and it had you know twelve rows in
it or something we know that we only
support eight at the moment and that's
arbitrary we could change it to whatever
we want but at the moment we don't have
any plans to support tile sheets of that
more than that in them so when we do
this we want to just warn people when
they put in an image it's not gonna work
now when we detect it it's not gonna
work I'm also gonna go ahead and set the
maximum so that we don't like end up
crashing because you know we'd rather
just print out an error and let the
artist fix it then crash the whole game
right and then they don't know what
happened because they can't even see an
error print out because the game crashed
right so we want to do a little bit of
defensive programming there and say look
this file could have anything in it we
don't know so let's go ahead and check
it for air conditions that are might
happen in practice that are likely to
happen in practice so that we can print
out our usable error message for the
person who made the mistake so that they
can fix the mistake rather than just
getting frustrated with it so we have
the
looping over the tiles now so what we
want to do is look at the asset index in
question here so this is going to be
looking at these asset indices and I
might just go ahead and say that I'm
gonna look at the I'm gonna actually
snap an address to it so I can edit it
if I want to because in the case where
it's it where it's zero I'm gonna have
to assign a new asset index in that case
so anyway if we see that there is an
asset index in question then what I want
to do is I want to gather the loaded
bitmap that corresponds to that asset
index right and so the way that I can do
that is by looking up the asset itself
and grabbing its memory header and then
looking at that bitmap there right and
that's a pretty straightforward
operation for us to do we you know we
can load the bitmap in and and and be
happy so to do that I've got to say all
right here's assets and remember we've
got sort of an array right here of them
so grabbing that one out
so grabbing out that particular asset we
can then look to soups you can then look
to see if it has a header or not I guess
we can also look at it state we could
say if the state equals assets state
loaded then we can sort of use the
bitmap that's actually in there right so
looking at this loaded bitmap here oops
this is the loaded bitmap so what I'm
going to do actually I guess I can put
this out here what I'm going to do is
say if we already had it loaded then I'm
just gonna do it I'm just gonna load it
into the place where it was already
loaded right and one of the things
that's true is we're gonna have to deal
with invalidating the texture cache as
well texture cache is the wrong word
invalidating texture memory because if
this thing was loaded it's probably
already been sent down to the GPU and if
it's already been sent down to the GPU
we need to send it down again because
we've we will be replacing this this
piece of information right well we'll be
changing the one that we actually used
in that case now one of the things
that's a little tricky here is that
we're kind of coming into this knowing
that we're going to make another change
which is to change to using texture
arrays now that we have everything at a
similar size so it's a little bit janky
cuz we kind of want to make two changes
at the same time but I don't want to
make those two change at the same time
so because I want to do it
stages especially because it's on
handmade hero in when I'm normally
programming and I don't have to explain
things as I go I will often make a
number of changes at once because I know
how they're all gonna go and I'm
concentrating fully and I'm not talking
the whole time so I tend on handmade
hero to go slower for two reasons one
because I want to show how things are
done in stages but also because it's
much harder to keep everything in your
head when you're talking the whole time
and you have to do it in you know 2 hour
increments over weekends you know weeks
apart and all this stuff I said it's
doing the whole thing in one day so
normally I probably make a few changes
I'm not gonna do it that way what that
means is we're first going to make the
change of loading the things in and then
what we're gonna do is probably wipe out
this section entirely and go to a fixed
buffer set where we just have exactly
what we say here like we've got you know
probably more like this like we've got
some 64 by 64 is that we use for
particles we got 1024 by 1024 as we use
for sprites and we got 2048 by 1024 by
1024 is that we use for cutscenes or
something right so like and that's
roughly what I want to do that reminds
me what reminds me what is the size of
this thing
yeah so what we'll probably do right is
like will resize stuff like this down to
a different resolution right so like you
know will open up title screen or
whatever so this is the original title
screen graphic and what we'll do is
we'll say you know all of this stuff has
to fit into something that's going to be
oops it's not I want to do
right so we'll use that resolution of
the thing and we'll just say that like
all of our cutscenes stuff fits in to
images that work like that
so again it's a bit of a procrustean bed
situation but it simplifies our life and
doesn't really cost us that much at the
end of the day it's pretty easy to fit
our assets into those things so what
we'll do is we'll fit all of the kant's
of the cutscene art into packs like that
and then we'll take those and those can
be you know the highest size texture
array the 1024 by 1024 s will be the
sprites and then the the they'll be one
smaller one for things that are like you
know particle effects and stuff like
that that don't need a big one 1024 by
1024 might be too large so what we might
do is down sample everything by 2 and go
with 512 by 512 it's hard to say if you
take a look at the actual sizes oops I'm
not supposed to use that everyone
chastised me for it if you look at 1024
by 1024 assuming we store them
uncompressed completely so we don't use
Dixie or anything then the size is is 4
megabytes per sprite right so if you
figure that on a higher end card of like
say 4 gigabytes that means that a 4
gigabyte can have a thousand 24 sprites
resident at a time right
there's no way we're gonna have 1,024
sprites on the screen in different ones
that's just not likely right so we
should be fine to use super high res
artwork if we want to even without
compressing it
we're probably fine and so I would
imagine we won't have to down sample the
artwork we can just use it at its native
resolution and that'll also give us some
nice
bonus is like if we want to run at 4k
our art can stand up to that because it
is 1024 by 1024 so even big things will
still look nice and crisp so that's
there okay now what I said isn't quite
right because we'll probably need to
store some Maps so it's really it's
probably more like 500 different sprite
bitmaps that time so you know maybe that
gets up to the point where it's a little
bit too much pressure I don't know
either way we do need to kind of be
aware of that boundary because on lower
end systems for example we would
probably want to have the option of
loading 512 by 512 sprites or even 256
by 256 sprites because if you have a
graphics card that only has one gig of
memory or has 512 Meg's of memory or if
you're running on some kind of a low-end
platform we one try supporting someday
like a Raspberry Pi or something we
don't want to have to have these huge
sprites in there so we do need to sort
of keep that in the back of our minds
that there sort of there's 1024 by 10 to
4 is the largest on the most powerful
machines that's the size we will load
our sprites in at but that's not the
size that they will always necessarily
be if we want to support lower end
configurations of machines and if we
look at the the quality difference
between the two you know I don't it's
not going to be huge if we open up
something here like here's Krampus
so if we take one of these and we look
at it you know you can kind of see what
it looks like here right if I was to
scale this down to what it would be if
it if all the artwork were 512 by 512
you can see what it would look like it's
it's definitely blurrier right but it's
not it still retains the general I mean
you know you're not gonna it doesn't
look all flowering thing on the other
hand if we do go down to 256 by 256 at
that point it might start to get a
little ugly right so that would be that
right and so what you can see there is
as you get down to that size you sort of
start to lose a little bit of the
quality of the line work there so it is
ugly reduces by 26 some of that could be
mitigated by better down sampling you
know better scaling then cubic something
that was more aware of the fact that
it's kind of a line art cartoony style
for example so there's that but also the
other thing you could do is you know if
you really cared about something like
this you could have your artists work at
this resolution originally or touch up
these these themselves to to fix the
liner we're not going to do that because
we don't care about that at all so we
will probably just say 512 by 512 is the
size the sprites are when we down sample
and that gives us four times the number
in memory in any given time so if we
assume a 4 gigabyte graphics card as our
spec you know this game releases I don't
know in 2020 let's say a 4 gigabyte
graphics card is probably going to be
pretty standard at that point but even
if it's not a one gigabyte graphics card
should be pretty safe now it's hard to
say I don't really know what the Steam
Hardware survey says these days
[Music]
marry now but you know just looking at
here right you can kind of see that that
at one gigabyte graphics card even today
is kind of a minute minimum on Steam
like the total number of people who have
a card less than that who are checking
into the steam hardware survey is so low
it's like 5% total right so it seems
safe to say that in another year or two
which we wouldn't be shipping to any
consumer before then it seems pretty
safe to say that we really wouldn't have
to care much about anything below a one
gigabyte graphics card and that should
work just fine for 512 by 512 sprites if
we have a particularly good cache
predictor that may actually even work
fine for 1024 by 1024 sprites depending
on how we choose to do them
and again that's uncompressed right
that's if we don't try to apply DX TC
texture compression to them or something
like that where we would you know be
able to but I don't think we're gonna
have to do that because again if we just
try really hard to do good predictive
streaming we should be able to not even
have to compress these sprites if we do
have to compress these sprites I would
say palletized might be the right way to
go although that does put extra stress
on the shader so sometimes so I don't
know but anyway because palletize would
probably just work whereas DX TC would
introduce some artifacts into these
sprites probably um alright so anyway
just you know keeping all that stuff in
mind primary display resolutions pretty
interesting here no one's at 4k you
notice the 4k revolution has not
happened yet so everyone's got a
gigabyte of graphics but no one's got a
big big desktop resolution a big primary
display resolution it's pretty
interesting looking down these stats is
you know it's pretty interesting
eight gigabytes of memory man there's so
much memory in systems now like it's
just nuts just nuts I love like like
some huge butts over over a third of the
people have more than 12 gigabytes of
memory in their machine there's so much
memory now it's nuts just nuts
this stuff's looking pretty good - sorry
- the people who still have the old AMD
phenom but I'm guessing those just I'm
guessing sse4 is gonna be here to stay
pretty soon so you're just gonna have to
not not use those car those chips
anymore because I mean you're down to 7%
of the people don't have SSE 4.2 it
becomes pretty hard to justify not
moving to that platform at this point I
wish AMD had not been so slow on the
uptake of those anyway those are almost
certainly phenom syn there I would
assume so anyway yeah there we go
whatever such and so forth yeah so all
right let's keep going here so what I
was saying originally is as we go
through these tiles we take a look here
and we look to see whether we've got an
asset index or not if we do have an
asset index we'll try to see whether or
not the thing's loaded and if it is will
use the bitmap that we've already got if
we don't have a bitmap at that point
what I want to do is use the provisional
bitmap so what I want to do here is say
bitmap equals you know provisional
bitmap now what's a provisional bitmap a
provisional bitmap is the bitmap that we
use to load things before we know
whether we're actually going to keep
them or not
right so it's a it's basically just a
chunk of memory that we're not sure
whether we actually need yet but that's
what we want and so I'm gonna do a thing
here that's like a provisional bitmap
equals I don't know something like this
get provisional bitmap and I know that I
need a tile dim by tyldum bitmap for my
use right and so I'm going to get one of
those
and we're gonna this is just sub code
we're gonna see what this is gonna be
about in a second anyway once I have one
of those what I want to do is I want to
move I want I want to move through all
of the pixels in the source and I want
to see I want to do two things
copy it to the provisional bitmap you
know the place where I might actually
want to use it so I want to do that and
at the same time I want to see whether
or not I think that there's anything
actually in this bitmap okay so what we
know is there's a one pixel border
around everything so we want to actually
do this rather than the full size of the
thing the reason for that is actually a
little bit difficult to understand we
covered it a long time ago on handmade
Hiro
but it's actually critical to have a one
pixel wide blank border around all of
our sprites why because we don't want to
rely on any kind of texture board or
hardware or other kinds of features like
that we want to be able to sample from
the edge of the texture and not have
anything be there now I know this sounds
a little confusing let me just restate
why this is the case it's actually
relatively important to do this to be
able to support software rasterizer x'
as well which we do want to do because
we would like again to update our old
software rasterizer to work with our new
system eventually so it's not a
non-issue it's it's something we
actually want to be aware of for
software rasterizer x' as well so
so what we want to say about texture
borders is just that look let's suppose
I've got an image and you know here's
the image that we're talking about it's
a four by four right and it goes all the
way to the border okay so that's just a
little squiggle well we want sub-pixel
accurate rendering and anti-aliasing on
all of our rendering work that's just
something we set out to do with the
beginning it's much more high-quality it
looks much better than crispy nasty
pixel garbage so what we want to be able
to do is stuff like say okay this sprite
lands at a boundary that's not right on
any of these pixels so maybe you know it
looks like this okay so what that means
is this needs to be spread out among
those four pixels so each of these
pixels gets a little bit of a
contribution from this pixel right makes
sense and how do we do that well the way
that we do that because remember we only
want to fill each pixel once so when we
go to draw this pixel what do we do well
we sample where the center of that pixel
would be right and we buy a linear
filter between the colors that we know
are in the texture to produce the
correct color for that pixel right right
that's how we get sub pixel movement of
a sprite through a pixel grid this is
all old news we've done this animator
before I'm just tryna fresher memory but
what do we do for this pixel well for
this pixel we need to sample this
location and the
problem with this location is that it
doesn't have any information about what
exists out here because it is
fundamentally outside the texture now
what we want to do is support clamping
we want to be able to support the
texture mode that just says if you were
to sample outside the texture just
sample the thing that's inside the
texture closest to you because that's
the most efficient thing for us to
implement the software under it's also
something that's available on all
hardware without any additional
operations you can just say clamp and
you get clamping well we can't do that
here we would have to use what's called
a texture border which is additional
texture of order color so actually it's
called sometimes you can do this thing
called textured where it was separate
text where it colors what we need where
we set the texture for closure zero zero
says if you see a play outside the
texture use this color instead that's an
additional operation we don't want to do
right so by creating all of our sprites
such that there's a one pixel border
around them that's no good
so we just say look if it's a four by
four that means sprites are two by two
effectively right now see we're not
gonna do that it's 1024 by 1024 so
really they're all 1022 by 1022 right
all of these have to be left blank and
the reason that they have to be left
blank is because they need to be able to
sample in between these two to get a
clean result that's just how it goes
are there problems with this approach
yes what is the problem of this approach
mipmapping
and this is where we start to get into a
whole big can of worms that's
I don't really want to cover today
because it's not super relevant but
suffice to say if you really want to do
this stuff accurately you almost need to
do your own texture sampling in the
pixel shader because one of the really
big mistakes that was made when people
originally designed graphics hardware
was they designed mipmap sampling wrong
I hope that's not a controversial
statement I don't think I'm stating it
controversially but basically what
happened is when they created mipmapping
instead of correctly identifying the
fact that textures should be sampled
from the half pixel boundary at 0-0
they made 0 0 B that outer corners of
the texture the result of this is that
mipmapping never properly works for
images it's always wrong and the degree
to which it's wrong has to do with how
many MIT maps down you've gone this
manifests itself in a lot of really
serious problems for when you want to
put tiles next to each other that are
supposed to be continuous stuff like
this there's a lot of really bad errors
that therefore occur I and yeah I don't
know any other way to say other than MIT
bamming hardware was built incorrectly
it's always been wrong it's wrong still
today so if you actually want to support
the correct movement exactly right
with MIT Maps you actually have to do
your own texture your own texture
filtering and your own pixel your own
texture sampling inside the shader and
there's no two ways around that what we
will do on handmade hero for that I'm
not sure I don't know that we really
want to try to do that I think handmade
hero it's perfectly reasonable trade
I'll just say
we're just not gonna go down that road
but it's worth noting that you need to
do that now we can take another step in
handmade hero that would actually create
a circumstance where we thought we don't
have to worry about that as much and
that is border thickening what you do
there is you say all right since we know
that we're probably going to only care
about 128 by 128 to v6 by 2006 512 by
512 and 1024 by 2024 but we're never
gonna shrink shrink these things down
really to 64 by 64 what you can do is
leave a border that is that thick around
the whole image right so for example if
you go into if you go into and you
look at what it's and you look at what
that would imply here actually that's
not what I want
so if we were to take Anna's reference
sheet here and take a look at what this
would actually imply so I'm going to go
ahead and just make a little selection
here so if I pull this out to encompass
the entirety of one in sprite cell
so if you take a look at one entire
sprite cell this is a 1024 by 1024 you
can see a rectangle said down there so
if you were to look at one of these and
I was to read out the entire area of it
right and then what I did is I pulled
this down so that we actually had an 8
pixel wide border sorry
oops
okay and then we just said all right
there's the actual space of the image so
one thing we could do is just say let's
leave that much right what will then
happen is there's an 8 pixel blank
border at 1024 by 1024 there's a 4 pixel
blank border at 512 by 512 there's a 2
pixel wide border at 256 by 26 and a 1
pixel wide border at 128 by 128 so only
when you mipmap down to 64 by 64 which
is getting pretty darn tiny will you
actually end up with a sampling problem
if that makes sense
so we could ask Anna to do that if we
take a look at the way these actually
actually look here
not sure how hard that would be to do so
you know a lot of them just already are
you know so what we could do is just
like print a warning you know about it
if it's if it's inside the borders on so
hopefully that makes some sense to you I
am basically what I'm saying here is
like look if we don't want to tackle the
whole MIT map problem then what we could
say is just 8 pixel wide borders on the
input and we go from there
so yeah that's that's that's all there
is to say about that I so I'm just gonna
go ahead and say let's warned on that so
if we see anything in the in that apron
we're gonna go ahead and warn and and
now I think about it yeah like let's
just go ahead and yeah let's go into
some of that so what we could do is say
look we're gonna copy the whole thing
but if we see anything in that apron
we're gonna we're gonna warn about it
and go from there
now you know one thing that I guess I'm
not sure about is you know we could also
store these things a little more
minimally when we actually put one of
these we actually put one of these
bitmaps in there I could actually just
sort of scan for sizes there's a lot of
we got a lot of stuff we can decide to
do here I'm not sure which ones we want
to do but anyway we want to take a look
and see you know if a source if the
source has an alpha value that's what we
want to know so you want to take a look
at something and say like okay you know
there's a source that we read in from
somewhere like source pixel we want to
take a look and see if the source pixels
alpha channel has something in it so
basically like this I guess the other
thing we could do is shift it down but
we just want to see if the source pixel
has something in it that we actually
want to read and if it does we want to
set all of the you know all of the
different borders of the image should
shrink tear so we can sort of figure out
like what the region is I'm going to
create a thing here for that
do we have a kind of rectangles we have
so we have floating-point rectangles
I feel like that's probably fine hard to
say well alright let's do it this way so
what I can do here is say look we've got
some some bounds every time we see a
source pixel you know in here we're
gonna say that the min x equals the
minimum of the min X and X the max X
equals the maximum all right if you want
no we want that yeah so we basically
expand you know our notion of what's
enclosed based on what we see so if we
read all the source pixels in this will
tell us the bounds of the actual image
and then what we can do is when we're
done with that particular tile we can
now see whether there was anything in it
so basically like if min X is not equal
to you 32 max right or more specifically
what we could say if min X is greater
than equal to max X oops last we go to
right as long as there was something in
the image then we'll will do something
with it
right so if there was something in it
then what we want to do is we want to
issue errors if you're in that pixel
border so if the main X is less than or
equal to you know border dimension let's
say I guess I want less than or the max
X is greater than or equal to the tyldum
minor this - the border dimension
so in other words like if a tile Dems if
the tile dim is 1024 and I want an 8
pixel wide border around it then I want
to know if my my max Y is gets hit on
that gets hit directly on that value
right of of 1024 minus 8 or 10 16 right
I want to know if I'm on there over it
and and similarly I want to know if I if
I've gone below 8 because 8 itself would
be fine but 7 through 0 are not fine on
the other ones right so when we pass in
here the tile dim we also know what the
border Jim is and maybe the border dim
is 8 and here we can sort of say if we
see one of these we can print it out now
as owners is this is going to be I
guess really what I should do is specify
specifically which ones are in and out
laborious ly like each individual one
with a different error message just so
that the artist can tell if they get
used to these error messages they can
actually know what exactly to do so what
I could say here is like tile
something like this you know I'm Sam
and I guess what I could do to make this
a little bit more straightforward is
maybe something like this well but
that's not gonna work because I want to
print out each individual one so yeah I
think I'm just gonna leave it this way I
don't think there's gonna be I mean I
could there's some other ways I could
write it but I think that's going to be
actually the easiest one
yeah
and these are top down because pngs are
top down right so we're looking at it
from the top down I don't and I think
the artist wants to thing from the top
down too so this is probably the right
way to report it right if we're gonna
flip the image you're gonna flip it
later into like an OpenGL texture style
or something like that but I think
that's what we want to do and we can
probably say here that this for this is
also like so what can pass the border
dimension in so in case we changed that
it won't say 8 pixels and actually mean
16 or 4 or something all right so when
we read this thing in now we've got a
way to warn if it if it goes into the
Porter area which isn't technically a
problem like if the game was so run just
fine just there might be some anti
aliasing artifacts so it doesn't it like
has a little weird fringe like an
artifact that you'll see when it nipped
maps down so a 1 pixel border is really
all that's necessary for the highest
level of resolution but as you mipmap
further down you'll get more and more
problems so if we take a look here we
loop through the X you know XY index
stuff we go through looking for bitmaps
when we find one now we're gonna copy
into that or we'll see what we'll do in
a little bit but when we grab one of
these then once we figure out the
borders of the thing that's are actually
in question we know whether we need to
retire it or not and that's when we
would go ahead and write it back into an
asset pack file or who knows what right
so let's go ahead and start implementing
that code path what I want to do here is
create a death pixel pointer in a source
row pointer
the reason I have to do these two
separately is desk pixels we know that
we're gonna produce optimally packed
stuff for our file that we're saving and
this is where I was sort of saying we
kind of get into a situation where I
don't know how we want to how we want to
deal with this for fast for the fast
development purposes I think what we
want to do is we just want to store
everything as 1024 by 1024 is back the
pack files that can just be overwritten
but then eventually I think what we're
gonna want is we're gonna want a thing
that goes through and compresses and
just takes the min/max of the thing and
shrinks it down because we don't really
need to store all the empty space it's
just not necessary so we can probably do
something like that eventually I just
don't know that we want to do it quite
yet because if we do it then we have
trouble replacing assets and we have to
keep a free store and all that stuff now
maybe we want to do that it's hard to
say probably eventually we would if we
actually wanted to lean on this system
and let it be something that people use
after the game's already shipped to put
their own art in or something but hard
to say anyway so what we want to do here
is take a look at the loaded bitmap
stuff
here's that memory pointer I don't know
if we've got a way to quickly get
[Music]
doesn't look like we do
so I guess I'm just gonna go ahead like
this say we've got some bitmap memory
we're writing into our source is going
to come from this image here and so this
is going to be our source for a pointer
and the source for a pointer is going to
advance every time by the width of the
image right so then I've got a source
pixel that's just gonna be the source
for a pointer and I want to advance it
as far forward as I need to for the x
position did I'm at right
same-same with the Y so I've got a Y
index and I know that I want to do tile
dim times image width right so I want to
start there and then as I go forward and
in fact you know I can just pre step
this one as well so what I can do is
just say also you know step the Y at the
exit next times the tile dim forward
that just brings me down to the start of
the tile that's the first tile and then
every time I go on a row here I'm
already at the right place in X so I
just need to advance the source pixel
pointer each time
so that does the complete scan if I want
to write into the desk pixels these are
just direct so once you have once you
have thesaurus color extracted you're
just writing it directly into the other
bitmap and off you go
I don't think there's anything else we
need to do here other than extract it
right so I think that just does the
extraction the only problem is when we
actually need to get like a professional
bitmap we don't have that yet so once we
get in here and we see that we've
actually got something we're going to
keep then we need to actually do the
work of pushing that back through into
the system so what I want to do here is
say all right let's go ahead and and
load up the file formats here so what I
want to do is I want to write this back
to some location and there's two cases
that I might have to handle one case is
where I don't have an actual asset yeah
right so that would be the case where
I've got like an HHA like there is no
HHA on the disk that actually holds a
backing store for this asset it's new so
it's not the case that I'm going to go
back in an overwrite an existing asset
what I'm going to do instead is create a
new slot for a new asset so the h/h a
header for one of these files now
essentially has to get expanded with an
asset count that's larger than it used
to be and the these arrays have to
expand right
[Music]
so just thinking through how I probably
want that to go I think I just want to
kind of pile up the data in a separate
growable file and probably just have
there be something flexible that writes
these out which can then be compiled
down to the existing HHA at such a time
as I want to do that right
[Music]
yeah so I think what I want to do here
once I get one of these is I want to
look to see whether I want to store over
an existing asset or whether I want to
write an asset anew so I think what I
want to do is actually and considering
this a little bit more carefully here
yeah I'm pretty sure what I want to do
is write out the asset here
yeah - enough - an own store so I think
this is what I want to do I think I want
to have one file for each size type well
I mean either day I don't even really
have to do it that way
but I want a half I want to have
basically a file that I use that's just
a backing store for these things that I
just write into and when I if you know
quote-unquote free one or overwrite one
then what I'm gonna do is I'm just going
to overwrite that part of the file with
the new data just like I would in memory
and then when we want to compress these
down into an HHA what I can do is run
something that actually does that
compaction and goes from there and this
could be a pretty nice way to just do
the development the first place
basically we just say look all of these
PNG files datas get compacted into
something that we can read from reliably
and that happens at runtime
automatically the artist doesn't have to
think about it and then when you want to
actually ship a build of the game you
can just run something that trims out
the dead space right and we could even
put a little simple LZ compressor in
there kind of like what PNG had to
reduce the size of our games asset
footprint because at that point it would
probably be pretty cheap to do that so
we could probably do something pretty
nice there it's also my guess yeah
yeah so I'm in favor of that I think
that's good so what I want to do here is
I want to first I need to figure out
what the tags for this thing are going
to be because I don't know what the tags
just thing you're going to be so we kind
of have to imagine that the tags for
this came in in some way that we can use
right the X&amp;Y location the X and X and
the y index have to be translated into
tags somehow so we needed to do here
that's like translate the tile index
into tags based on the name of this file
probably using something passed into
this routine so like that's the part
about the tags I said we had to do once
we have the tags then we have to do like
a right asset data the right asset data
call is going to excuse me the right
asset data call is going to take some
information with it here let's say that
that's going to be probably two parts of
data so we're gonna need a couple pieces
of information here but we're gonna need
the bitmap so you know the loaded bitmap
and we're going to probably also want
something like this like metadata and
data right so when we write the asset
bitmap data out to the file what we're
gonna do is just give it that bitmap the
bitmap should have everything that it
needs in it which is got everything here
although I guess that also has the align
percentage so I guess we really are just
going to have that because it's got the
metadata in it as well so I guess we
have that right out just that and we
need a write asset
and similarly right because we need some
way of associating associating that now
we know the asset index right the asset
index here we've got we need to assign
an asset index so here we need to say
look if not asset index this needs to be
assigned an asset index the asset index
in this case is just going to be however
many assets the game currently has when
it's when it's running so inside the
asset system here let's take a look
where is my asset count yeah so once we
assign a new one of those asset indices
then we know that the asset itself that
we're looking for is just that one right
think it's just asset
and what we do want to do here probably
is well I think we're going to make this
so it can't actually fail so we're
probably going to need to do a max asset
count thing here which will grow that
array as necessary but taking a look at
what we're doing here so we come through
we got the asset index and and all that
nice stuff and once we have that we
should be able to say okay we're going
to write asset tags for this asset index
and yeah and I guess maybe you know now
I think about it that's probably
something we can just do like this
so we can go ahead and say we want to
write asset tags for that asset index
which we assigned a new one to we can
probably also have you know I don't know
if we want to just have this allocate
more space in the array as necessary
here if we don't that's kind of six and
one half dozen or the other but anyway
we need some way to write out the asset
tags here which we don't know and then
we need a way to write out the asset
bitmap here which that's a lot simpler
because we do know everything we need to
know about that so what I'm going to
introduce there is probably just another
way to use an HHA file that has this
information in it so we'll kind of look
at how that's going to work in a second
but we'll look at that look at that a
little later so let's see
almost time do I have left I've got
about 20 minutes
so you know I think I maybe don't really
want to do this this way I think what I
think I'm gonna go ahead and say I'm
gonna get rid of this so I think what I
want to do is we're actually always
gonna go into a provisional pit matter
that we just do a right I think we're
gonna go a little bit of slower route
here and just live with that yeah I
think I like this better and then what
we'll do is we'll flush the asset cache
and force it to reinitialize things I
think that's just better so what I'm
gonna do here is say look we're gonna
we're gonna have a provisional bitmap
here that we use and that provisional
bitmap is going to come out of the asset
temporary memory because we just we're
not gonna keep it right so and in fact
what we could do
yeah I think I'm just gonna do it this
way so we're gonna pass in the temporary
nough and what I'm going to do is is
just say look let's get like a pixel
buffer here and that pixel buffer is
just going to be an allocate or sorry
push array on the temporary 'no of the
tyldum times the tyldum of you 32s so
we're just going to create that pixel
buffer and we're going to use that for
all of our operations so this will
extract the information here as well as
do sort of analysis to see whether it
fits in there properly when we're done
we'll go ahead and write that asset
bitmap out you know based on the tile
dimensions of the thing and you know
that's that's the size that we want to
send out and so what we really the only
thing we really then need to know is
where inside our sort of we're in
you know table of asset sort of
temporary asset storage do we want this
thing to go great so for that I just
really need a notion of yeah like where
the where in the asset temporary storage
these things went right and if we look
the HHA itself has that information so
really what I want to do here is it's
actually pretty straightforward I think
when we get an asset index out if we
have an existing asset index the first
thing I want to do is and you know what
maybe we don't really need to go through
this rigmarole I'll just you know I'll
just reassign it at the end right so
that way we don't keep putting the star
in there so I'm gonna grab an asset
index out of here I'm gonna look at the
asset index and if it actually is valid
then what I'm going to do is I'm going
to look to see what that asset actually
has like so when I look at that asset I
should be able to see in inside the
asset file index I should be able to see
whether or not this file is one of our
compacted or non compacted files right
so I can go grab the asset file
oops and when I grab that asset file
inside the asset file I can remember in
here which one it is that I actually
wanted like what kind it is right or you
know maybe something like that so
basically if this asset file type if
this is an expandable asset file then I
could do it if it's not right
if this asset file is not expandable
then I effectively don't have an asset
index I can actually use right this
asset is is no longer valid and it
shouldn't actually be used for anything
so what I would want to do at that point
is like nerf the old asset file so that
we know that it's not actually one that
we want to continue to use right so in
the HHA itself we want to kind of nerf
this asset so we want to like mark asset
as old or something like that
for this particular asset so we want a
mark asset as old here and we then want
to also say that we don't have an asset
to rewrite anymore so then when we come
through here if we don't have an asset
index what we want to do is we want to
assign a new asset to the asset index
that we have so we could do this
something like this right so we want to
basically say hey let's get a new asset
index that we can use to do stuff and
then once we have one we will fill that
out with the new data that we have right
now the other thing that I probably want
to do here is maybe change this around a
little bit so what I would want to do
here is if this was expandable then I
well actually I guess no that's not I
take you back there we go
so what I want to do here I guess is
when we grab this asset out there is a
little bit more we can't do with it so I
want to rescue the information that we
were using in terms of like alignment
and stuff and probably preserve it
because whatever the artist set up last
time is probably the best guess for
setting it up this time and if they
don't like it they can always change it
but at first we probably want to use
that thing right so we probably want to
store this when we have one so that way
we'll keep that around even if we
realize that the assets old and we're
not going to use the old location in the
file to actually touch that asset we're
still going to use like the metadata
from it that we had originally like the
alignment point right so then when we
come in here and we say oh you know we
didn't get an asset or whatever then we
can say let's reserve a new asset and
then we can start assigning stuff to
that new asset right so we can grab it
out of the system we can say that it's
HHA equals our our HHA and we can go
from there now that's probably something
can do right here
like so and then we can write it back so
now what we need to do is actually set
this stuff up and when we actually do
this like reserve new masa it's gonna
have file index and asset index in that
file that will be set for us when we do
the reserve and so we can probably just
proceed to looking to looking at the
actual HSA data so looking at the actual
HHA data what we can see here from the
HHA assets here we go is the data offset
and the first tag index and the one past
last tag index so the first tag index in
the one past last tag index part of
things we need to set to whatever our
whatever the actual data is here that we
need that comes in from our prefab way
of setting tag information right so
that's the part that we don't know yet
but that we need to put in here at some
point right so we're gonna say HHA asset
first tag index equals something
HSAs at one past last tag index equals
something right and we don't know what
those two are but then we need an HSA
that's a data offset that's what we
actually need to know to write this
thing in and then similarly we know that
this is a bitmap that we're doing here
and so the bitmap needs to dimension
informations and to align percentage
informations the dim informations we'll
just put in here the aligned
informations we're just not gonna touch
we'll set them up here to the default
which I assume is like 50% the mid like
probably the middle right
Just Cause like that's if you didn't
have if no one had ever told you where
the hot spot on sprite was the middle is
probably a good bet now what we could do
is actually take the middle of these so
the middle of the actual image that we
get but I'm not going to do that because
we don't really know that that's any
more accurate we just be purely guessing
that it would be so here we are setting
the tile dim that's going to be correct
so really what we need here is reserved
asset space so this is where we would
reserve the asset space there's two
cases here one is if the asset file
you know the expandable expand a little
bit I think this probably wants to look
like this and yeah and it probably wants
to check to make sure the tile dims were
the same
so what we want to say here if it's non
expandable file or it's not matching
dimensions I guess I can just do it like
this right so if it's not expandable or
either of the dimensions have somehow
changed which we really shouldn't have
happened hardly ever but you know we
want to make sure that we support it if
for some reason it did then we're just
saying like no this is not this the old
asset is no longer available it's just
old data that we can't really use and
now we need to put it into a new place
right however even as I'm saying that
even as I'm saying that I guess now that
I think about it there's no such thing
as a nun expandable file we can always
write new data at the end right so
really I think what we want to say I
think we're just fine I think all we
need to do is say is it a different size
because right I think it's fine
so we just want to say look if we can't
if we can't just romp over the thing
with the new thing right then sure
yeah so I want to say this is this is
really just this yeah so so you know
what I think this is really it's really
this actually it's really just look if
we don't have an asset we need to
reserve a new asset otherwise we can
just say look if the data offset is zero
or the dimensions don't match then we
just need to reserve space for you know
we just need to reserve space for
something that's that's that bit right
and so that will get us data offset in
that'll that'll give us what we need to
write into that file and it will bring
the data it'll give us back the data
asset the data offset we can use to
actually write in there so we need to
set up the tags but then I think we're
just good like this is actually easier
than I thought it was going to be I
think so we just reserve asset space in
that file
like that's so I can get a new asset and
I can get if I need one and I can get
more data space if I need it
and then once I have it I just write it
in there right so I think really that
was all I needed to do and then when I
get to the point where I've where I get
to the point where I want to write out
this asset bitmap really it's not
writing an asset bitmap anymore
it's more like saying look write this
asset data we know it's this big that's
how big the data is so we want to
reserve that much space it gives us back
a place to put it then when we write the
asset data we say hey the asset data we
want is this right it's this big and I
want you to put it here
right so like there's the place to put
the thing at this offset it's this big
here's the data write it out so then
once we do that the only other thing we
have to do is to to overwrite the asset
record itself with the new asset record
and so we would just say hey write this
asset back out to the file from from
whence it came
I think that's all there is to it I
think that just updates everything so
the only really thing we need to worry
about is the tags like I've seen before
I think that's literally it
like that does the whole shebang and the
only things we need to implement is
something that reserves extra asset
space and something that expands files
as necessary - very very simple
operations that really just won't be
very hard to implement I'm going to go
ahead and nerf this for now so that we
still compile wait what
it's the easiest one to define that was
this right yeah and that's supposed to
be X and X Y and X same with the one
down here
[Music]
so we need to grab that out
that's all good there I think that's
that actually yeah so I think now we're
pretty good actually
um here is here's presses tile import I
can pass this all that stuff I think
that's all good and so really what we
would need here are these functions so
that's the asset index we need the
reserved data one
I don't recall asset file and asset
dates I suppose this can could probably
be au 64 but we'll leave it like that
and then these two so I think
that's all we're looking at and that's
all compiling to so these are like
trivial to implement too so these are
really easy which is great
so I think we are now basically down to
exactly what I said we were going to run
up into which is the tags so we're gonna
have to rethink tags next time and
that's gonna be a little bit of a grind
because we're gonna have to really put
on the thinking cap for that but that's
about it like I think we're in pretty
good shape otherwise I think the rest of
this stuff just sort of works I'll go
ahead and go to the Q&amp;A but I think I
think we're in good shape
we rewrite the software rasterizer with
sse4 um I don't know probably honestly
probably what we'll do for the software
aster Iser is we'll rewrite it with
avx-512 and just because it's it's just
an you're not gonna run a game nowadays
on a software rasterizer like that's
just not a thing you do so we've always
only ever done it because I think it's
important as a learning exercise for
people to see how it works because
otherwise you have no idea what your
graphics card is doing it you don't
really get it you know what I mean
so we you know we can't ride it what we
could try to do is once the game is done
we can rewrite the software rasterizer
and we could use avx-512 because then we
can actually do a pretty high
performance one too because that's got
like Lane based gather and stuff so for
texture fetches it actually works you
know I don't think there's much point in
rewriting the software rasterizer with
sse4 because sse4 doesn't have any stuff
that we really need for software
rasterizer
like we wouldn't really gain anything
all that useful there's maybe a little
something here or there that's useful
but it's just yeah so I think the
software rasterizer probably like
avx-512 so it's got Lane based gather
and that's just purely exercise in in
learning and avx-512 the only actual
instruction set that was sort of
designed for a rasterization anyway you
know
and don't feel bad about not having
avx-512 nobody does I don't have it
either I'm just saying when we actually
go to do it if we're lucky
AVX 5:12 we'll be around if we're lucky
maybe it won't be I don't know I mean
one of the problems is that AMD seems to
not be going that direction
unfortunately and the problem is so the
problem with avx-512 is I don't care
about the 5:12 part I care about Lane
based gather right so you still haven't
bounded hash value and check for oh
you're right that's a good point
we should do that right here right so
in here we've got the source file hash
we only support up to 256 wide hash
there so let's go ahead and bound it to
that you can probably do a mod there
because the compiler is probably smart
enough to change it so you could I would
imagine the compiler is smart enough to
change that into an and buy one - I
don't actually know III don't know if it
is or it isn't
but let's just say
I would be shocked if it couldn't do
that it's a very basic transform but my
soul look it's not a performance
critical part of the code anyway so we
could just do the mod how long until
Microsoft tries to force win through to
become obsolete and what comes after win
three to four games
so if I may make a rather dire
prediction
I think Windows 10 is probably the nail
in the coffin for games on Windows is my
guess and I will elaborate on that as
follows
yesterday I was trying to play player
unknowns battlegrounds with Anna the
artist at Mali rocket and Matt Grinnell
a friend of mine from California here's
what happened
Anna tried to plug in a mouse that she
had used on her laptop
it's a razor Orochi Mouse into a PC that
she wanted to play the game on ok upon
plugging in the mouse because I guess
the razor Orochi Mouse has a very high
sampling rate or something and there are
no default drivers for this Mouse I
guess on the PC it was essentially
unusable like moving the mouse only a
little bit like moved it all the way
across the screen even though the like
sliders on the mouse configuration were
not set to like high speed or anything
so it wasn't really usable so over the
phone I tried to walk her through how to
fix this well unfortunately Razer
doesn't distribute drivers for their
hardware anymore in order to fix the
mouse you had to install Razer synapse
the only way that they actually
distribute drivers for Windows 10
anymore she tried to install Razer
synapse and of course it was Razer
synapse version 3 which is the default
download Razer synapse version 3 doesn't
support the Razer Orochi Mouse so we
didn't do anything they just forced her
to create an account and didn't do
anything I then had to walk her through
uninstalling right in mind you when you
try to install uninstall something on
Windows 10 what happens is you type
uninstall into the Start menu it gives
you some uninstall whatever the last
uninstaller was and it just says
uninstall right in the little thing so
she clicks that and it says do you want
to uninstall mumble which is like the
last program that got installed or
something that had a thing called
uninstall and she's like no so I'm like
ah you have to type add or remove
programs and click on that find Razer
synapse in the list uninstall it go back
to the Razer web page download the
download the Razer synapse to install
that that actually identified the mouse
and was able to install the driver ok
that was getting anna's mouse working so
then we tried to play but unfortunately
matt Cornell's windows 10 had updated
and apparently melted down now it just
blue screened all the time and he
couldn't tell why he never got it
working by the way he's a tech
professional he administers websites for
a living he runs Linux servers all the
time he's and he knows everything there
is to know about administrative computer
he couldn't get Windows 10 to run after
like 30 or 40 minutes so we just gave up
and that was our experience playing
games on Windows this garbage is
completely unacceptable and there is no
way that the playerbase
on Windows will continue to grow with
this kind of crap we are talking about
an operating system that pops up a
dialog box in the middle of your game
asking you to reboot
all right it is totally unacceptable as
a platform they do not know what they're
doing and it is only because people love
PC games so much and people like valve
have stepped in to supply something like
steam that it even exists at all we are
hanging on by a thread and Microsoft is
essentially completely ruining our only
existing pseudo open game platform that
we still have that's that's actively
being used I don't think it's going to
last if someone like Sony decided to
ship the PlayStation 5 or whatever they
want to call that with a mouse and a
keyboard and a way to plug into a high
DPI monitor if they just supplied an app
system
I think Windows as an operating system
would be gone I don't think you'd ever
see it again forget it it's a legacy
it's like
os/2 or ms-dos or anything else because
if you could just buy a relatively fast
machine with a consistent hardware
platform that has a mouse and a keyboard
that plugs into it and you can run apps
on it and compile stuff there's no
reason to use this garbage anymore
it is completely unacceptable what they
have done to the Windows platform it is
it is disgusting it is unusable and it
is it takes so much more time to
actually keep your system running and do
anything with it I have no idea how long
because consumers are gonna put up with
this but I guarantee you they won't and
if you ever gave them any other option
to switch to they will people aren't
stupid right the reason they're still
using games on Windows cuz they don't
have another Mouse keyboard monitor
platform where they can compile games
and run games right someone else steps
in and provides that Windows has gone
tomorrow period right that's it I mean
they have done such a horrible job with
this plat
that you know I'm not sad to see them go
either they could just I know love lost
they have absolutely treated this
platform with nothing but disrespect and
it has been a tremendous burden on the
PC community for no reason so as far as
I'm concerned my prediction is that if
and it's a big if anybody wanted to take
over games on Windows as a platform they
could do it tomorrow
Sony could do it tomorrow and it would
be over because Microsoft provides
negative value at this point installing
Windows on your system and playing games
that way is an exercise in futility it
is frustrating it ruins your gaming
experience and they absolutely don't
care when a when a version of Windows
goes out the door is so clear that not a
single person who has any power at that
company cared one bit what the
experience would be for a gamer not one
bit
because no gamer would ever ever accept
a dialog box popping up in the middle of
a game it's absurd to even consider the
validation process you have to have in
place to allow that kind of thing to go
out into the wild it's ridiculous
absolutely unacceptable and I know this
is a total rant but it's an absolutely
accurate rant there is nothing
histrionic about this it is just a fact
that the chain of command there does not
care about games at all period and you
can see it the proof is in the pudding
and the pudding is made largely of dog
feces at this point and that's all I
have to say about that
if I remember correctly STB use lib was
used in one of the episodes was it for
loading PNG assets no so what I did I
think it was on Sean Barrett's birthday
actually is I'd never shown how to use
an SD B lib because we write everything
from scratch so what I did is I made a
we had a thing that you know made turn
fonts into bitmaps and I had done that
using the windows API to take the
thoughts and rasterize them and then we
suck them out of that and put them into
a bitmap right and then what I wanted to
show was hey there's an SD be lib to do
that I think it's called SD be true type
and so I want to show how to use it so
still to this day if you go into the
test asset processor there's actually a
switch so right now it's compiled lib
free because you know hammer here we
don't use libraries that's our thing but
you can steal to this day turn on the
thing that will go through Sean's
library if you want and I thought that
was important because I do think some
libraries are well made and I wanted to
show how to make something you know that
was I want to show how to use a good
library on the stream so that's the one
we did we didn't use I don't think we've
ever used STV image which is the one
that loads pngs but but there is a PNG
loader in NS DB Lib what I did do
recently just a couple streams ago is I
tested our PNG reader against Shawn's
PNG reader because I wanted to see if we
were misinterpreting something and it
turned out that we were we didn't so we
didn't actually ever use that in the
game system but we did run it as a
separate like we compiled it as its own
thing and ran it and that's a pretty
handy thing to do if you have a
reasonable code base that does something
like PNG reading that you're doing you
can run them side by side to see if you
got something wrong because you know you
very well may have and we had we had we
had we were flushing too many bytes in
in a place we were flushing 1x
by then we should have and we learned
that by looking at at Shawn's PNG reader
since you already have deflate decoder
inputted in PNG reader will you
implement implement deflate compressor
for asset files we could we'll see
that's kind of debt we don't care about
that right now but down the line we
might speaking of stupid driver
distributions Sony only has Dualshock 3
drivers for PC packaged with their PS
now software ridiculous DualShock 3 is
which one is DualShock 3 is is DualShock
3 is DualShock 3 the PlayStation 4
controller
what's the DualShock 3 so I don't know
the DualShock versions so he just
struggling with getting that the darn
controller to work ok
my poor friend said when Windows last
updated for her it took 4 hours yeah I'm
not surprised do you think Linux will
take over that seems unlikely also
remember the PlayStation 3 had links for
it no I don't think so because Linux is
just as bad I think you could switch to
Linux and have just an equally
frustrating experience with Windows but
I don't think that's what's gonna woo
consumers you can't really wow consumers
by saying hey you can be just as
frustrated over here as you are over
there oh and by the way there's less
games over here like that's not a
value-add right but if someone like Sony
actually spent some time making a little
desktop and ship that with a mouse and
keyboard I think they could just
annihilate Windows I don't think they'd
have any problem with that right it
there's really not much to it we know is
almost completely unusable nowadays I
mean it's mine barely saves running and
I don't even do anything on this one
right
what would it take to make it more
designer friendly to develop on an
Ubuntu or Fedora platform first so I
mean I don't really think Linux has a
future as a consumer OS I really don't
think so I mean I know a lot of people
constantly think that it's going to but
it's just not and the reason for that is
you can't have a consumer platform
that's inconsistent
the thing about Linux is there's a
billion versions of it right you try to
look for an answer to a question and you
find 50 answers to the question none of
which work on your machine and half of
them involve a command line you know
that that's not sustainable you need a
simple reliable system that people who
don't understand computers can use and I
think that's what Linux people don't
understand you need when you type in
something how do I fix my bla it needs
to come up with one answer and that
answer needs to work right it can't come
up with 15 answers like oh are you on a
bun to 14.1 Oh open up the console and
then run this command to see how many
ethernet adapters yeah look free no no
an artist isn't gonna do that an
accountant isn't gonna do that only a
computer aficionado is gonna do that
it's just it's untenable Linux isn't
even anywhere close to being consumer
operating system it's nowhere close
right now that doesn't mean maybe
something the community couldn't
consolidate and say we're only gonna
ship one build from now on everything's
gonna be on this build we're gonna
simplify everything so you never need to
open a console sure maybe but they
haven't done it in 20 30 years whatever
it's been since 1992 10 12 and 14 they
haven't done it in 16 years why do you
think they're gonna do it now
em SVC does a terrible job with mod
let's see here
so insert some God bolt links
so I guess it won't do it interesting so
maybe we will have to do and with the
minus one
enemy masks are you going to support
more complex languages coding your own
Harbaugh's text shaping equivalent uh no
I think that's probably gonna be outside
the scope of of handmade hero I just
don't have the knowledge of that stuff
that I would need to do a good job so we
will probably try to keep that sort of
thing to a minimum would be my guess but
I don't know maybe we should go the
other way and learn it I don't know
frost you mean the sixaxis ps3
controller ah yeah the sixaxis ps3
controllers are are much harder to read
on Windows due to the way that their
initialization procedure works and
whether they do wireless or wired the
ps4 controller is very nice it just
pretty much just works when plugged in
so our plan to infiltrate Microsoft
macam in Windows I don't know I mean
it's it's miserable it's just miserable
I don't understand why they can't just
ship a reasonable operating system and I
think it's because they just don't want
to you know if they seem to be
preoccupied with all this other stuff
why is there a 3d paint program
installed by default you know what was
wire resources goodies they can't even
ship in the operating system party a
person
what's all the rest of this garbage I
don't want a new shell I don't want an
edgy Windows interface I don't care
about that stuff get that stuff out of
here
I don't want JavaScript integrated tiles
for my weather report or whatever like
that stuff is if you've already shipped
an operating system that works you
haven't done that you shouldn't have
anyone working on anything else until
you actually can ship the operating
system and make it work which they
cannot do apparently
oh yeah and frosting it yeah you need
this us it's a USB handshake thing that
has to happen yeah exactly
for those ps3 controls um is it true you
can't enable the controller through user
land win32 so you've got a B in kernel
mode is that basically what happens are
you sure about that
I guess I don't really know I've never
tried to do that handshake in user mode
alright looks like the end of the
questions
oh I realize I forgot a part of that
story too actually part of the story of
trying to get Anna's computer work also
involved having to unplug the television
from it because it wasn't coming up on
the monitor there the story I told about
was it was actually a a better was was I
didn't even list some of the bugs we had
to work around now that I think about it
too legit to quit isn't a big part of
the issue that the operating system
would need a lot of traction if Jonathan
or someone like you built an OS it would
need a very soon to come out attraction
to incentivize game fairs to bill for
that platform it's hard to say game
developers are pretty used to shipping
on lots of platforms right now so I
don't really know that there's that much
traction that's the problem I think more
the problem is just how big of a project
it is right I think the reason that
Linux Mac Windows is basically the only
games in town now is because it's just a
huge undertaking with not a whole lot of
upside to it right so the only real
reason to do it is because it's gotten
so bad so it's like a frustration based
project you know and it's just hard to
get up enough anger to make that happen
right so I think that's why it's like
all these operating systems are garbage
and none of them have their priorities
straight but what are you gonna do it's
a massive undertaking to ship for an
operating system and it costs a lot of
money and you need a lot of really good
people and you need you have to do a
better job than they did otherwise
you're just making a fourth operating
system that also is crappy right so you
don't you know it's a really big deal
and I don't think traction is probably
the biggest problem
oddly enough I think the the biggest
problem is is really the undertaking it
is a serious undertaking it is it is
something that that requires a lot of
dedicated time and energy from several
people and I think that's just
Brij that someday we probably have to
cross if we want to save pc computing
but it's you know it's a big it's a big
head of steam that has to get built up
there alright thank you everyone for
joining Philip said handmade here it's a
touch recording with you as always if
you want to follow along the series at
home you can as career to the game on
handmade hero org comes with a source
code so you can follow along with it if
you want to try your hand at running out
those asset things you can actually do
that if you've got the source code you
can see if you can do it this week
before I do it it's probably pretty good
practice I while we're at it we also
have a new website I mentioned this
yesterday I'll keep mentioning it since
new people come into the stream we have
a watch page you can go to it's got the
live stream on it when we are live in
the schedule on it when we don't and oh
and of course twitch ads but like I said
we don't actually get any money for
twitch ads so that's just something baby
insert into the stream hopefully if
you're an Amazon Prime customer or
whatever else there are the ads go away
it's also got buttons to hotlink to
things and then we also have the episode
guide here maintained by the fabulous
midlow it allows you to search for stuff
so if you want to see when I'm
complaining about Microsoft for example
you can quickly type that in and see all
of the part parts of it here jump right
to them which is pretty awesome so this
is just a great way to catch up on old
things or fine particular things you
wanted to hear me talk about buried in
the archives of handmade hero that's it
for this week check the watch page for
the schedule I'll be updating it right
after this with once I check my calendar
so it should say when we're going to be
live again
that's about it I hope everyone has some
programming this week and I'll see you
folks next time take your news everybody