hello everybody and welcome to hand made
here of the show recode a complete game
live on stream last week before we left
we were making some changes to how the
movement code in the game worked and in
general we were just starting sort of a
sweep towards building out a playable
game scenario so that we could start to
tune our lighting algorithms our camera
and start to get the art flowing and
stuff like that just trying to build a
working example of how everything in the
game should go because we're mostly
there in terms of game engine stuff
we've built everything under the Sun
that you might need and so now is really
the time to just start finishing things
to a specific state based on the game
because most of the stuff that we're
gonna want to do from here on out will
probably be dependent on what the game
needs specifically and so most of the
things that we know it needs generically
are accounted for there's stuff in place
for whatever those things are generally
speaking so we don't have any particular
sort of schedule or guide for what we
are doing there it's really just
freeform as we sort of work on building
things out we build them out and off we
go so as you can see here we've sort of
got the the hopping stuff that I changed
from the other day in place and one of
the things that obviously we have a
problem with at the moment is the fact
that we don't have the real art in there
yet and so that's one of the problems
that we probably need to address pretty
soon especially because stuff like the
way the hero is assembled right it's
just kind of three random sprites we've
stuck on top of each other here and
they're not drawn at the right
perspective from what we want and I do
have our from the right perspective and
stuff like that so there's a couple of
things that we can be doing there if we
want to start moving towards getting the
art in that's a big one but before we
quite get there I want to look at a few
other things which is getting the camera
and the world sort of construction stuff
sort of buttoned up because right now we
got a lot of weird stuff that we just
have to kind of finalize that's only
half in there we do have camera stuff
like for example if I come over towards
a a look what am I looking for
a overhead overhang right like this one
here and we wait you know the camera
does go and look down to further floors
in fact I can show that a little bit
more effectively if I actually kind of
come up some stairs although I don't
know if we have any here yeah we don't
have any here so we do have some stuff
in there for the camera but we changed
the way that we were doing rooms and
stuff and so the stuff that was meant to
like move from room to room with the
camera isn't correct and more
importantly the zooming like the way
that the camera determines how far out
it should be when it's like looking at a
particular room or things like that
none of that stuff has really been done
and a lot of the reason for it if I
remember correctly is that we need to
start having the notion of what is a
room because when the world generation
system generates a section of playable
region for the game it's gonna have to
say specifically what that is right
because only the world generation code
knows what it wanted the like sort of
visible region for a given set of
playable stuff to be like what a room is
is up to that system right so like if
the game decides to generate like a long
skinny room that connects to things only
it knows whether the idea behind that
when it created it was for you to see a
small section of the long skinny room
and scroll along with it or whether the
idea there was to have it be one large
view where it just zooms out and shows
you a long skinny room that you hopped
from one end to the other off right and
what we would like to do ideally is make
it so that whatever we are generating
for those purposes that generation can
just tell the camera system at the time
when it slaps tough room down that
here's what it wants to do so that's
what we're talking about here right and
furthermore we kind of have some other
stuff that we'd like to do you can see
here like if i zoom out in debug mode
you can see that the camera system still
sort of it does nominal work you can see
the white areas or areas that are
outside of the viewing right if I come
in here we're kind of doing this is the
part thinks it's supposed to be doing
it's what gets lit these are parts or
not and that was just some approximate
stuff we slapped in there but you can
see that still sort of gives you that
impression so you can see the cameras
feel sort of nominally works but it
doesn't really work because this was
clearly a room and so what we want to do
is light that whole room and a
furthermore in addition to lighting that
room we want to make sure that that room
gets zoomed and looked at for the camera
right and stuff like that so yeah all
this stuff again pretty obvious stuff
it's just now is the time to start doing
it because we've got everything else in
place and we have to start finalizing
things now here is an example of two
rooms stacked on top of each other like
I was looking at before or talking about
before rather so if I bring the the
little Dube down here and I hop up the
makeshift stairway that we built this is
the thing I was talking about before you
can see that the camera is still doing
the look down part so if you want to
look down below you to see what's
happening right the camera still does
that stuff so the cameras we still do
have camera control stuff in there and
it does work it's just it has to now
actually get wired up in some
intelligent way that makes sense and we
definitely don't have that at the moment
right we just we don't have any
conceptualization of that um so the
other thing that we're gonna have to
think about too is you know when you
want to look at a map we want to make
sure that you can you know we want to we
want to be able to see some kind of a
logical map that you can look at to
understand where you are in the game and
so that's another strong impetus for
having a notion of a room stored in the
system somewhere that's sort of metadata
that sits on top of the information
about the actual entities right like all
of
these entities here are obviously stored
in the game and and all that but you
know they don't really they don't have
any information about their real
structure they don't have any
information about like what constitutes
a region of play right and so another
region reason to have that region of
play information in there in addition to
guiding the camera and other important
aspects of the game is the fact that we
need some way of displaying a map and
without a notion of what a logical room
is it's gonna be hard to present that
information to the player because the
player needs to know the connectivity of
the rooms in the game and without that
we would have to write like some kind of
AI to try to determine what a good way
was to simplify a giant collection of
entities down into something that is
easy to read at a glance so again rather
than go that route and have to struggle
with it and oftentimes probably have it
be wrong or not what a human would do
what we want to do instead again is
create that metadata while we're
creating the entities so that it's
already in there when it goes time to
draw the map it just knows what was
supposed to be a room and what wasn't so
that's what we want to do so I'm just
gonna go ahead and jump right in on that
task because I feel like we want that
either way let's look load up for a
coder here and get our project going I'm
gonna go ahead and switch over to the
world system and the world mode to sort
of take a look at how I might want to do
this now the interesting thing about
this right we've got this sort of world
information here and the way that the
world information works is it has a for
lack of a better term it has a giant
like world database almost that you
stuff stuff into and pull stuff out of
based on the location so there's a three
dimensional hash table well it's not the
hash tables in three dimensional it's a
one-dimensional hash table like all hash
tables
but the hashkee is 1-dimensional a
three-dimensional rather that we smack
down into something that can be used as
a as a hash so the question is how would
we want to put metadata on top of this
right because one of the problems that
we would have if we tried to make world
data a piece the Broom data be stored
along with the rest of the data is that
the queries wouldn't make sense right so
for example one of the things that we
would want to do let's say to draw the
map is we'd want to say show me all of
the rooms that are in this rectangular
region but we're completely unable to
answer that question here without going
through all of the chunks right and
pulling out all of the entities from the
hash table sequentially right and that's
not what we want to do so what what I
guess I'm arguing for here is that we
probably want some special structure for
the metadata that is separate from not
merged with the entity data because the
entity data is very specific it's
fine-grained we know we only pull tiny
regions at a time and we really don't
want to change that that's good but this
room data is a different beast right
it's it's something that wants to be
stored very differently I think and so
what we want to do is really have a
secondary structure for that now I'm not
gonna start out presupposing that I know
how I want to store that I will probably
just start out storing that fairly
linearly and then as we go I will add
more abilities to store it in flexible
fashion I suspect so we'll see but what
I'm gonna do here is again just augment
the structure I'm gonna say ok let's say
that we have a world room and world room
doesn't necessarily mean room in the
traditional sense like not semantic room
in the sense that it's got to be a thing
with four walls and a roof and a floor
but I mean room as in a playable region
of the game so this might be outdoors it
might be
you know something that bears no
resemblance to a literal room
but it is a room in the gameplay sense
of the term room so it might be a forest
like Legend of Zelda had a lot of rooms
that were forest area right but they
still obey the trishal notion of a room
there's one screen and you know you did
stuff on it and left so if we take this
world room what do I want to know about
this room well I think the basic things
that I really want to know here is I
want to know some of the camera stuff
that we were talking about before we had
put that into the game entity system so
if you remember the entities had ways of
describing themselves as camera
information right so you can see here
there's a bunch of information about how
the camera should behave you can see
here like we've got all this camera
behavior stuff and this was things that
sort of said hey here's some information
we want to tell you about the camera for
a given area inside the room and this
again was for markups like if I stand
here I want to zoom in or something like
that right things like that and so I
don't think we really need most of that
stuff here I think all we really need is
some more basic stuff like the bounds
right so like for example I can take
this world position here and just say
okay let's just make a three dimensional
boundary so a right rectangular prism
like we talked about many times which is
bassists a three-dimensional rectangle
let's describe a three dimensional
rectangle that is meant to contain the
entire room okay and then from there
what we'll say is when we have this
entire room
to find we then want to know roughly how
you expect it to be viewed okay so we
need some hints essentially that the
system that the the game is going to
give to the camera system that says I
want the whole room viewed I want this
much of the room viewed you know
whatever right and so I think I mean the
the I guess the most straightforward way
to implement that it's just to say what
the camera offset is supposed to be
probably although not really so because
if you think about it let me draw this
really quickly because there's a reason
why I think talking about the camera
offset is maybe not such a useful thing
to do in this case so I'm gonna bring up
Milton here
so the camera behavior per room wants to
say stuff like I was sort of alluding to
before where let's suppose I have a long
hallway like this and the player is here
and you know and they're hopping down
the hallway what I want to say is okay
did you want to view that sort of this
way where the camera seeing the whole
thing or did you want to view it more
like this and have it scroll upward
right and those are the two things that
I would think you might logically want
to do there aren't a whole lot of ways
the camera could shoot this you know
that seems like pretty much most of it
so you kind of need to versions there's
a room centric version I guess you might
say and a player centric version and so
what I suspect we would need unless
there's some other you know and I really
can't think of it unless there's
something else to be said here I think
we kind of just can make those be
so you know as I'm as I'm saying this
out loud - I guess I'm wondering maybe
this doesn't even need to be in the room
structure because those things could
still be done quite easily by just where
the player is standing
there's a lot of complexity here not
really in terms of code because the code
is not that hard the complexity in my
head really is about just what the game
wants to do and again part of the
problem there is I'm not a game
designers this is not my area of
expertise as I say oftentimes so you
know if we had a clear mandate from the
designer if there was one about what
should happen here then we just go write
that thing but thinking through what's
gonna happen here there's a couple
everything's so one thing that is worth
noting is that scrolling you know let's
say what if we do have a co-op mode in
this game because you know like I was
showing the other day we even from the
very beginning of the game right here's
you know one hero but if you just push
the start button on like a xbox
controller or you get another hero you
know and off you go so the question that
I have there is just if you were playing
co-op then it kind of makes sense what
you would do if you both you know maybe
you both stand on this Square and then
it leaves the room or something or I
don't know you both hop out and then
like I don't really know to be honest
with you exactly how you move from room
to room when you're co-op it it's a bit
confusing i i mean maybe one player is
just marked as the key player and that
player can leave the room or not and the
other players is confined to the bounds
of the room till they do you know i
don't really know it's tough to say but
there's a lot of ways we could handle
that let's put it that way
but one of the things that we need to
determine is if you were to support some
co-op play which you know I'll be honest
is kind of nice
I said we wouldn't do networking but we
could easily do co-op play right it's
just a question of whether we want to
take the time to generate be able to
generate co-op worlds because they're
different obviously then single-player
world
so if we ever decide to generate co-op
worlds then we definitely have this
other consideration to make which is
that the camera can't zoom on a player
it has to zoom on both players right but
you know again the reason I'm talking
about just to get it straight in my head
like I said if we had Adam and eight
from the designer twine let's just say
we do that I still think we have these
two concerns and so what that kind of
suggests to me is like maybe this stuff
is not as relevant I mean maybe it is
because you both of you can stand
somewhere and then it would do this but
you know as you might imagine it's
really just not that interesting to talk
about specific things that happen when
you're at particular locations in a room
if you're in co-op mode you're never
going to be at a specific location in
the room you're at two specific
locations in a room right
and that to me just kind of argues for
something that's going to be more
generic it's like we either are in a
room where we show the whole room or
we're in a room where we show two
characters who are focused on it you
know - two characters are focused
together kind of a thing right
so I don't know I mean that's all I
really have to say about that I wish I
had some more specific opinion about how
that should work but I don't really know
that I do and so you know if I was just
going to type in the sort of most basic
version of that probably something like
this right
and you know maybe we just eventually
get rid of this uh
I wish I had a more sort of I wish I
wish I had a more coherent view of what
should happen there but I just really
don't so I'm just gonna say that that's
what that is
and we're gonna go from there so my
mouse is currently stuck beneath my
tablet so if I take a look here and I
just say alright so a world room has
bounds and a camera and then I just
again this is if I go ahead and just say
we've got some big set of these in here
that's all the rooms in the game I don't
know how many rooms that are going to be
but let's just say we've got a lot of
them some really giant number maybe
that's a little bit too many let's stay
a little bit less than that I don't know
so if I just say that I've got some big
old thing that just says how many rooms
in the game there how many rooms there
are in the game and there's just that
many rooms and I go ahead and have room
count in here I can just spam rooms into
this and then maybe I can draw those
rooms right so when you go to the map we
draw the rooms that there are in the
game and you know everyone's happy and
it's great and whatever so let's just do
that because we have an easy way to get
started down that path what you can see
right now is when I do this you can see
that we've got a region that we pull
entities out in but I can't see anything
else right so these test rooms that we
slap down here you know they're there
and I can go from one to the other and
when I do go from one to the other right
you can kind of see we scroll through
the world as we should in all that
nonsense but I can't
what actually got generated you know
what I mean I can't actually see the
rest of the world because those enemies
are all packed into the world thing and
I don't know like I have no idea what
other parts of the world there might be
so even just for our own like
edification debugging wise it'd be nice
to be able to see a map at this point so
we know what the heck we generated right
so I do want to kind of go ahead and get
that going as well so I think this might
be a good opportunity for us to do that
I'm gonna go ahead and hop up here just
because now I'm obsessed with hopping
around so that's fine
sorry this is one of the problems when
you actually have a fun movement thing
to do is you end up doing it all the
time
looking excited so I think I've reached
the end of the world I think
yeah so without traversing the whole
world like that we would have no idea
what the world actually was because even
we don't have the ability to draw a map
right now so that's kind of a bad thing
so one of the things I can do just to
start off with to get this system
rolling a little bit and I started to
play with it and see what I actually
want to do here is to just dump all the
rooms that we created into this room
structure so that I can actually draw
them and see what they look like so
that's my first thing that I would like
to do when I go into the world mode a
broom nonsense right we have this add
standard room think here and the
standard room comes back and all that
and so what I could do is inside the
code that adds this stuff here I should
be able to do something where I place
the world's information into one of
these as well right so when I do add
standard room here and it puts the room
in there maybe I just do it right in
here for now so we come through here and
we've got sort of an idea of where
everything is maybe in here I go ahead
and set up you know you can see here
like us setting up some of these Kent
cameras and stuff like that
maybe what I want to do here just say
all right let's go ahead and put a I
don't even know what this oh this is
just well this is the whole room right
here
yeah so this is the room information
right here actually right you can see it
so we actually have all this stuff
recorded it's just not in where we want
it to be recorded right here's brain
type room right so again we have all
this information like we were already
doing it like I was saying before we
just weren't storing it in a way that we
can pull out in any convenient way right
I don't actually know if we do anything
so you can see here right this is the
way we were pulling it out so once in a
while we would use it we would see
whether or not we had a room piece of
information and then we would look to
see what the camera behavior was
supposed to be in that room right so we
had the ability to do exactly what I'm
saying but not in any we didn't have the
ability to talk about those things
separately so that we could do stuff
like draw a map or anything like that
right and so we I think like I said we
do want to be able to do that and so
that's what I'm doing that anyway the
only question that I have right is just
whether this because we already have a
system that can do this based on
locations more specifically the question
is just do we want do we want this data
to still be handled on a regional basis
or or do we want to just like lean on
the room concept and say look
everything's got to go through the room
concept because especially with two
players at a time you're gonna have to
deal with that right all right so I in
update camera for entity movement SOI
person who uses that thing anyway and we
can leave that in place but now when we
have this information here the the
simple grounded collision stuff this
information is exactly the information
we need in order to specify the rest of
the world information so if I want to
say that we have a world room here I
should be able to tell it that
and maybe this has to take that all that
information so I'll just say that it's a
focus on room worlds for now a room for
now but I needed to know the minimum
position and the maximum position and so
what I think I have to do is I think I
have to do this stuff here where we do
make this simple ground and couch stuff
I need to do this effectively with the
trunk position stuff right so in order
to figure out where that's going to be I
need to do a chunk position from from
tile position and that'll give me
I believe that gives me a world position
a piece of world position that I need
let me just verify that yeah so once I
have one of these I just need I just
need some way to pass these down but I
know what they are right because I know
that the minimum like I created all the
entities in here you know so I know that
my offset was negative radius Y negative
radius x2 positive radius X positive
radius line so I know where exactly I
was
right
and so I know where I was the only
question is what's the Z range and I
don't actually know what that is because
the current way that we do it is not
right so you can see we do typical floor
height here and that's just because we
hard-coded that for the room but we
don't actually know that that's gonna
hold for certain in the case of this you
know going forwards so in reality we
should have a value here that's like how
tall is the room and in lieu of not
knowing how tall the room is we would
need something else here right for now I
can just do something like this and
we'll just adjust this manually to
figure out what we want it to actually
be but otherwise it should be fine now
what are the problems that we have with
chunk position from top position is it's
gonna give us not quite the whole room
area that might be fine I'm not sure how
we want to do that exactly we'll take a
look at that later but point being it'll
go from centers of tiles which is maybe
what we want to talk him out for the
room maybe not we want to talk about for
the room it depends on how we want to
talk about rooms whether they have to be
a budding or whether there can be space
between them or who knows anyway it
doesn't matter
point being I'm gonna go over into the
world structure itself here and I'm
gonna go ahead and specify what the
version of this function should be let
me get it out from behind my head there
so in here if I want to add a world room
I just need to well you know I mean it's
literally just gonna be recording one of
these right so it's literally just
saying pass me the parameters that you
wanted to fill in for the structure and
we'll fill them in now why am i doing it
this way the reason that I'm doing it
this way is because I don't actually
want to let the outside people change
the min Posen map
suppose necessarily because I need to
potentially insert this into a spatial
partition leader right so what I'm doing
here is just saying hey you got to pass
me these two in this one we could leave
out I just added it for convenience that
one we could leave out but we're not
going to for now so let me go ahead and
assert here that we haven't run out of
room and again like I said this is only
temporary but I always put the
assertions in even if it's only
temporary the reason that I put the
temporary is you never know what's
really temporary I mean a lot of stuff
happens in game development you never
have enough time to finish everything
it's always a rush and you're trying to
prioritize things we may get to the end
of the game and it's still this
hard-coded array right because it's just
it didn't end up being a high enough
prop a big enough problem to spend the
time on right and so that's one of the
problems that's why I say always put the
assertion in there always do the check
it takes only a fraction of a fraction
of second it takes only ten seconds to
put it in there that way you know if
it's starting to cause some weird bug
memory overwrite or something like that
you might as well do it because you
never know what's gonna stay in there
longer than you anticipated or perhaps
all the way until the end of the game so
it's just not a good idea to assume that
just because you know something isn't a
good way to do something that that won't
end up in the game because some of those
things will they just won't end up being
enough of a problem oops for you to ever
deal with them and if you don't have to
deal with them then you don't and that
goes out in the product and you may have
a little lurking bug in there that
you'll forget about till the very end
and then it will come back to bite you
and that's never good so anyway here
I've I've gone ahead and I've added a
room and so now when we actually run the
game it should build up that room arrays
so we've got a certain number of those
there we wouldn't know because obviously
we're not using that room information
but what I'd like to do now is when I
when I'm doing this I'm just gonna go
ahead and be fatty about it I'm just
gonna go ahead and draw everything that
there is because again there's no world
partitions I'm just gonna loop through
them and just draw them so in the world
mode when we are looping
through all of like our sim region stuff
and doing the sort of well-behaved
things that actually do use a facial
partition after that's done I am going
to go ahead and render all of the rooms
in the game period right so you know you
can see here we're when we are where is
it but you can see here some stuff that
I don't have okay so you can see here
we've got like these volume outlines for
example I'm gonna go ahead and and turn
those back on what you can see is those
volume outlines allow us to draw stuff
like just debug information you know and
what I would like to do is I'd like to
go ahead and draw that debug information
for the rooms this for example is just
some basic information that we were
drawing I to be completely honest with
you don't remember what it was or why we
were drawing it this is the sim region
the region that's getting pulled in and
all that nonsense that's all fine I
don't care about any of that I just
wanted to have it in there so I could
show you what I'm talking about what I'm
gonna do is take this volume outline
code which draws things for us and I'm
just gonna go ahead and use that to draw
the rooms alright now I don't know
whether I need to do that inside depth
peel or not I assume that I should just
go ahead and do so because we might as
well get the depth sorting in there so
I'm gonna go ahead and say that we've
got a room index here the room index
runs from 0 to whatever the world says
the room count is so however many rooms
we've got that's how many I'm going to
draw so in here I'm gonna push the
volume outline and you can see here is I
need a way you know this is just a
hard-coded one here I need a way of
actually specifying what these should be
now the color here and the width are
fine but I need this part to make more
sense I've got a recommend maxed and I
just don't know
to pass up for these two parameters now
remember these are going to be camera
relative and so I'm gonna have to use
the sim region here to make sense of all
that in fact to be honest this should
probably be inside this bracket because
I kind of was looking at this bracket of
stuff that had to do with the sim region
so let's just go ahead and put it in
there so let me grab the room out here's
the rural room I'm gonna say that array
of rooms just give me whichever one I'm
on and then I know I've got a min
position into Max position the question
is how do I translate that and if you
remember this is kind of going back to
old handmade hero stuff from the old
days the sim region knows how to
interpret coordinates relative to itself
and I think that's all we really need to
do here right so what I need to do is
say okay wherever the sim region is I
need a way of mapping something in the
sim region I need a way to map something
out and so you can see that it I believe
it does this in kind of a compressed way
you can see here it does like a relative
thing where it does all right here's the
energy position plus the volume position
and you know it does some well actually
it's it's this stuff here right here is
it looking to see whether these things
collide with the region where are we
doing this
oh I'm in the wrong place
forget everything I just said where's my
cap this is what this is function I want
to be in so you can see here when we go
through this right we've got the the the
entity itself coming in and we use the
location that it is we use the chunk
Delta which is the thing that says where
this particular world block is relative
to the sim region and so that's the same
thing that we want to do here's the
trunk position x y&amp;z right it's a world
position
and we're calling this subtract now
that's the thing that we actually want
to do here we want to know the Delta
from the sim region's origin out to it
and so I want to just make that more
systemic because I don't actually think
I don't actually think we ever pulled
that out because if we did we would have
called it right you can kind of see it's
just not there so what I want to do
because now if someone's gonna be using
this outside is I want to make that a
little more systemic and so this what
effect we want to do here is say all
right
make relative or get sim relative
position I want to be able to do that
and you know it's basically going to
pass this exact same thing except it's
just going to do it like that
so it passes the sim region in and then
it'll effectively do this operation so
in here we have an equivalent in line
that's just gonna return oops don't ask
me why I just did that my brains a
little bit fried today so if you take a
world position coming in here what I'm
just gonna do is say okay perform the
exact same thing we were doing to map
all of our entities in but now you can
call it from outside so if this thing
wants to do a rectum in max now it
totally can all it has to do is just
call this thing twice on the world's min
pose
and the world's max pose and that should
do it
where is our sim region world sim that's
what I actually wanted except believe
that's what I wanted try that one more
time a long time since I've touched this
part of the code there we go
all right so what you can see here is
we've got a little bit of a bugginess to
us here I would have to go through I
probably out of typos in there summer
we're basically correct but just not
quite so we're not getting one of our
one of our lengths is wrong so I'm a
guessing that when I added it in the
first place so add standard room I'm
guessing that that is typo'd and I'm
correct and so all I really want to do
is just fix that and take a look at
these rectangles which now should be
correct um so what you can see here like
I saying is they run through centers of
tiles which is probably not what we want
but we now have exactly what I was
talking about which is the ability to
see where the rooms are now currently we
are clipping so you can see we clip here
we got near and far clip planes there
and so that's probably something it
would be nice to get rid of maybe just
set these to something a little bit
different we could use an infinite I
don't think we ever talked about
infinite for our clip plane we probably
should talk about infinite for our clip
plane at some point maybe set it to
infinite for our clip plane because
infinite for our clip plane would let us
see the whole map where as now as we
zoom out right we're gonna fall out of
the Far clip plane region right as we go
so there's that but oh well anyway
that's all I wanted to accomplish for
getting those room barriers in there and
so now once we have those room
boundaries in there we can draw a map if
we want to right so if we had a map mode
we could just draw the rooms and off we
would go now the question is just
alright since we have the room
information now I
yes there's there's a couple of things
we want to do with that I suppose and
again I guess this gets down to sort of
some design decisions about how we want
to make this stuff go so
I think what we want to say
I think I think we want to have an idea
of which room the players in at any
particular time and the reason that I
say that is just because I think we're
gonna want to have I think we're gonna
want to have stuff based on this a
little bit more well it's just such a
hard decision right because it may be
that all we want to do is that like
literally what I just did
it might be the entirety of what we want
because all we're gonna use it for is
the map for all I know right so maybe we
really just don't want to do any more of
it yet
we've got a way to put them in there and
that's all we really want and everything
else will just be based on entities that
are regional entities because we've got
that ability
maybe that's the smart thing to do you
know I really don't know but that's sort
of where we're at I just I just don't
know the right answer to that question
and so we may need to delay that a
little bit further let's just push that
back a little bit let's go get the
camera stuff working for let's let's go
make the camera stuff that we have in
there currently work better in terms of
zooming out and making sure that it
captures the entirety of whatever room
that you happen to be in at the time
because at the moment that doesn't work
so what we want to do here is is have
like those camera modes and and since we
have those specified at the moment we
could just say look let's just make sure
that those actually work like right now
they don't and we need to have some way
of making sure that they do so if we
come through the world's creation stuff
and take a look at how that's going I'm
interested in making a couple different
things what I would like to do is I'd
like to make
I'd like to make different types of
rooms one that you roam around that's
bigger
that Scrolls with you a small one that
is oom xenon like like I want to make a
couple of these rooms and I want to make
them work reasonably so I'm gonna I want
to figure out how we're gonna start
getting the room building working a
little bit better so I'm just gonna grab
all the code that does this stuff and
I'm gonna put it into a file that I can
isolate and grind on for a little bit
right so I'm gonna introduce a new file
here in the code I'm gonna make
something that's about world building
right so maybe this is handmade
[Music]
something like that I don't know one of
the nice things about file names is you
can you're always free to change them
later
oops
here we go
so I'm gonna go ahead and just see what
I've got here in terms of code because
this stuff is gonna need massive
upgrading because we've never done
anything real for it right it's all kind
of just garbage
it's simply you know we've simply spent
no time on this it's just a routine that
has been repeatedly just kind of tweaked
to do whatever random test stuff we
wanted and we've never done anything to
try and make it functional it's all
messed up and weird right so this all
this code is garbage we just know that
going into it was all just test code
that we were using because we needed
some stuff to do all of our rendering
and asset loading and all the stuff that
we built for the engine and so now we
have to do is actually think about how
this stuff should work for real so I'm
just gonna grab out this code and and
see what we've got here right
and you can see we've got sort of a
begin world change and world change kind
of idea here I'm going to wrap that up
into this stuff because it seems like
it's relevant
with the understanding that I'm probably
gonna want to get rid of a lot of it
okay so let me just build this year for
starters and so what we've now done is
we've room we've basically removed the
roller code so if we run the game it
should just like Fault out immediately
and because the the initial player the
hero can't stand anywhere so when it
tries to add a player it's gonna be like
there's no world I can't um I can't be
placed anywhere right
and so we've completely exercised the
world building code it will now assert
I'll start up that like it cannot do
anything it goes to get the location of
an enemy there and can't do it and so
the off you go right so now what I need
to do is say all right
let's start trying to make this stuff
let's try to make this stuff a little
more systemic so I can actually build a
little world in here let's start trying
to fix the stuff that's rusted about it
and all that good stuff so I want to
make some understanding here just well I
guess before I do that let me just go
ahead and put that stuff in here
there we go I and this is just gonna be
three worlds there we go
an inside world mode if I just call that
in theory I should be fine so back where
we were in here where we would have done
it before I'm just gonna do it
here and that should do it
the only thing that this currently has
in it is this one function you can call
but that's fine so now we should be back
to the existing rule that we had and we
are and that's fine and so here's the
the basic starting point that we're at
and so what I want to do is start to try
and figure out how we're gonna actually
build these things and so I feel like
the first thing that I want to do here
is actually try to I I kind of want to
try to make I want to be able to talk
about stuff without thinking about how
it's actually gonna happen right so I
kind of want to just pie in the sky or
you know pure whimsy if you will I want
to just try to make calls that are
fictitious like I'm imagining I often
say you start with the usage code if you
know what the usage code is in this case
that's kind of
what I want to do right I want to say
let's pretend we have a system for
generating stuff and placing stuff in
the world that is whatever we want right
so I don't have to think about what I'm
actually doing I can just pretend to
call functions that magically do what I
want and then I'm going to look at that
and see what implies for the API that
should be in place for building the
world because if you magically dream of
an API that does everything you want
well that's a pretty good spec for the
ideal API right and then you can deal
with the realities of it later by going
okay now what do I need to change to
make this actually achievable and
usually that change isn't that big on
the other hand if you start by building
a system for building worlds and then
later you try to write to it using the
API that came out of that you may be
very misinformed because you haven't
actually thought about what you actually
are going to do in practice which tends
to be subtly or significantly different
from what you imagine the API should
have been if you're only looking at it
from the perspective of this system
itself so let's start out with the
basics here the idea I'm literally just
going to start with the most
straightforward stuff I'm literally
gonna start just at the beginning and
and go from there
so I don't even know if I want to do it
this way but obviously this game starts
at the orphanage for the the home for
limbless children where all the limbless
children are and so I want to create a
little orphanage layout and the
orphanage layout should be something
that like got the hand made heroes room
where the hand made hit where where the
hammy hero lives and then also rooms for
all the other characters and there's a
lot of other characters in the game who
are little NPCs or whatever that you can
rescue and stuff like that so
the orphanage should be sort of a little
hub area and then we need a way to get
out of the orphanage and getting out of
the orphanage would involve walking out
the door in and into a path for the
forest and then what going out the path
before it should get you into the actual
adventuring area of the game or whatever
so I'm literally just gonna start by
trying to do something like that and I
don't know how I want it to happen but
I'm just gonna start typing things in so
I need to you know I don't know I need
to do something like this where I say
look I need to create a room here and
you know I'm gonna I'm gonna
differentiate I'm going to try to
differentiate between world rooms which
are rooms that have actually been
created and generation rooms and the
reason that I want to differentiate
between these is is fairly
straightforward this is putting the cart
before the horse a little bit but it's
just because I know how these sorts of
things go I've done lots of generative
coding before so one of the things that
you don't want to do when you're making
a generative system is actually make
anything before you know what everything
is that you're going to make and that
sounds a bit a little bit weird but let
me just try to well you know what let me
just draw it for you I find a diagram
always helps because you know we are
visual thinkers at the end of the day
and it helps sue a room in the case of
handmade Hiro implies a bunch of stuff
there's like you know the bounds and the
entities and where they are you know and
what they are right there's all this
information about what a room is in
handmade hero so when I go to make a
room for the orphanage or a room for a
dungeon or whatever in order to actually
create the real room that's in the game
I need to know all of that information
but some of that information maybe dip
pendant on things I don't know yet for
example if I need to create some rooms
that connect to each other I may not
know what the room is that this room
connects to because I have to create one
of the rooms first right and so I may
want to do some things that analyze the
fact that two rooms are connected first
before actually making either room
because maybe it will determine where
those rooms are placed and until I know
where those rooms are placed I can't
make them so rather than placing down a
room and saying okay I'm making this
room
this is room a and then I'm going to
make room B and room B goes here what
I'd rather do is create sort of the idea
that there is a room a and the idea that
there is a room B say that they're
connected and then later on I will
generate from that the actual physical
room a and B this directly models what
happens in say a compiler write a
compiler doesn't often read the exact
line of code that you wrote and output
some assembly exactly right away right
usually what happens is it goes through
an intermediate right this is basically
the I are the intermediate
representation for our world Jen and I
RS are very important because what they
let you do is they let you work with
something semantically first before
actually creating the concrete version
of it that you're going to use and this
allows from our facile flexibility for
example I can create a bunch of these
things that are related to each other
have hypothetical locations about where
they might be shift them around run a
solver on them to figure out where they
should be placed right all of those
things I might want to do I don't want
to move all their entities around I
don't want to even have created the
entities that are in them I just want to
know what entities probably will be in
them and go from there figure out where
they go and then
once I know everything else about it
then stamp the room down right so I want
to make a notion of a generated room but
that is not the same as a handmade hero
room because it's sort of existing in
this in imaginary abstract space I could
call it an abstract room or something
that but I feel like Jen rooms good
because it says in the Jemez system
that's kind of what I want to say about
it I want to be able to say look let's
generate all these rooms and then say
other connect it up and then start
placing them down and maybe make
something happen I don't know we'll see
could be dumb could not be them we'll
find out later it doesn't really matter
right now
so let's say we've got that Hiro's
bedroom here this may not be a very
accurate way that an orphanage would be
constructed because an orphanage
probably trying to maximize the number
of people they can keep in a particular
space because they're trying to you know
accept some a children's they can but
this is gonna be a very posh orphanage
maybe you know this is a this is this is
the the Trump orphanage right it's a
it's a it's an orphanage for luxury
orphans and and it just it has like
gold-plated stuff in it or whatever for
some reason I really that reason is just
gameplay I want there to be enough room
for you to hop around but point being
this is this is probably not
representative of a real orphanage in
any particular way because all of a
sudden people have individual rooms or
something like that which doesn't seem
plausible to me but that's okay it's not
very plausible that many children
hopping around with no limbs going on
adventures in a forest anyway so we're
kind of in the realm of the absurd even
when we just start walking down this
path to begin with um so anyway I want
to do be able to generate rooms here and
I want to be able to generate rooms for
a different for different orphans as
well as like you know a central room and
then I want that path and so on I also
wanted a garden there's a gardener
wasn't one of the in fact there's
there's sort of a rough sketch that Anna
did a while back you can actually see
these I don't have the art for these all
of these characters too
on Mali rocket calm
there is a yeah so the there's a
gardener orphan who does gardening and
basically what happens there is at first
there's no garden but when you recover a
gardening glove for the gardening orphan
she can then go garden in the garden and
grow stuff right and most of these
orphans have stuff like that like this
is a tailor and the tailor can cook you
know so there's a number of orphans and
they have different things that they can
do and so in the fiction here I want a
couple different things as well as rooms
so there's like your bedroom and then
there's the tailor room I don't know
what you call the room in which a fabric
designer or a tailor works so I guess
I'll just call it tailor room because I
have no better way of stating it
[Music]
and maybe I'll just have a couple more
bedrooms here right because there's a
lot of folks in here so we'll just have
some rooms randomly some bedrooms and
whatever and then some additional stuff
here I want to have sort of a up that
forest path right and then I want to
have like the forest entrance or
something and so that's a pretty good
example like if we can make this work
we can probably make most things work
right I mean there's a little bit one of
the things this doesn't have as a graph
cycle in it and so we might want to try
and figure out how to make a graph cycle
and again let me let me sort of say what
I mean by that so if you take a look at
what happens
so let's see that our orphanage looks
like this oops so here's the forest
entrance here's the path here's the
garden here are some of the bedrooms
here a bedroom whatever suppose it looks
based like this
well what you'll notice here is that
there are no cycles in this graph if you
imagine each room is the note of a graph
and each of the connections between the
rooms is an edge in the graph then if
you were to draw the corresponding graph
it would just look like this
I should put em there for main room
right that's the graph and what you can
see here is anywhere that you start on
the graph if you do not retread one of
your edges so if I if I only allow
myself to walk along this graph on edges
I have not already walked on I can never
get back to where I started right if I
start on E no matter how I Traverse this
graph I can never get back to e it's not
possible I would have to retrace a path
in the opposite direction in order to
get back to e right but let's suppose
there was a secret exit here and that
secret exit went to a path that led to
the forest entrance as well now I don't
know why there would be such a thing but
let's just say that there was then the
graph looks like this and now that is no
longer true there is now a cycle and the
cycle is that we come through here and I
could start at E and return to E without
ever retracing my path right so we may
want to artificially introduce something
like that simply because it helps
guarantee that our graph system handles
anything it might need to handle cycles
are the most complicated thing that will
happen in a graph because well graphs
just aren't that complicated but to say
the least
a graph that has no cycles in it is
simpler than a graph that does have
cycles in it and I would like to make
sure that we're starting with something
that has the most complicated case so as
I work through it I know I'm not missing
something
okay so let's just do exactly what I
said
maybe there's a secret path back here
like that or something so maybe there's
a back door and so maybe those things
connect to each other right and so what
I want to do now is I want to have some
way of saying that these things do
exactly the stuff that I said they would
do before so if I just go by this and
say this is roughly how I want it to
behave what I could say is like all
right I would like these things to
connect in a specific pattern right so I
want to make sure that you know the the
main room connects to the hero bedroom
in fact the main room connects to like
all these things right so the you know
the the the main room needs to connect
out to the hero's bedroom the ABCD
bedrooms the tailor room the kitchen
[Music]
so that's all the stuff in the main one
then it's got its exterior entrances so
that's the forest path and the backdoor
path right and then from then on I want
to say like okay I've got the things on
the outside they connect in a specific
way as well so I've got the forest path
connecting to the garden oops
and connecting to the forest entrance
[Music]
I've got the backdoor path connecting to
the side alley
and then I've got the side alley
connecting to the forest entrance right
and again as you as we start to try and
make this stuff work you'll see why
cycles are more difficult because as you
lay things out they become more
problematic certainly but that's
basically what I want to do right
and soon arrow what we need to do is
specify some more information about what
these things are supposed to have in
them right in terms of some kind of like
generation parameters right they need
some stuff and that stuff needs to to be
specified in a way that allows some
future the hypothetical piece of code
that generates things to be able to know
what to fill these rooms with or what
they should look like how they should be
shaped all that kind of stuff right so
what I want to do now is introduce a
concept of like a room spec or something
and the room spec should say how this
stuff should be generated right and so
you know like maybe there's just a
generic forest spec and again I
don't know exactly what that would
entail here or anything like that
probably want it more like that or maybe
you know what maybe it's just like this
and so what I need to do here is tell
these things when I make the rooms I
need to tell them here's what you want
to use to generate yourself so you know
in this case I've got a base forest
basic forest
maybe these are all basic forests for
now and let's tweak them a little later
so all this stuff is basic forest
so maybe something like this where we
can just say alright we've got a few
room specs here and these could those
can be used to generate whatever these
rooms have to be and they're basically
prescriptions about what sorts of stuff
he's allowed in the room and what sorts
of stuff isn't allowed in the room right
so I think that's all of it right
bedroom main room Taylor kitchen garden
done
so again just kind of laying this out
the way that I would imagine wanting to
do it this is probably going to be
something like this and that all seems
fine so when I generate one of these
specifications I'm gonna need a bunch of
information about how they work at the
moment I don't know that there's much I
want to say about them because we
probably can get into that a little bit
later but you can imagine the sorts of
things that we might want to have here
they're gonna be stuff like saying hey
this is you know the type of stuff that
can be on the ground and this is the
type of stuff that can be on the walls
and this you know what I mean
so it's starters we will specify
anything and they'll just be generic
rooms that have no character to the
middle but so ever but eventually these
specs will have to get information in
them and that's how it knows what to
create now all of these things are gonna
have to take some kind of a generator
right and that's just basically a
parameter where it's like hey where does
the memory come from and what where are
we storing all this information and how
am i connecting it to other things in
the world it might be relevant and blah
blah blah right so looking at the API
here we can sort of start to see exactly
what what needs to happen I think and
honestly I think that's mostly it
I guess if I'm being specific here let's
just suppose I went the whole nine so if
we take a look at what I'm talking about
here I'm just saying all right
we've got an orphanage creation routine
it specifies all the stuff that's
relevant to the orphanage now as you
might imagine the game can't just be an
orphanage but that's okay because when
we do this what we can do is when we
pass this back right we can just say
that there's like a Jenner or an
instruct and the general finished struct
has the outgoing connections right so
the room that's the forest entrance is
the only thing that this thing actually
allows you to work with although we may
also want to do the hero bedroom because
that's where the player should get
placed so what we can say is when you
call create orphanage you get app you
know back from that you get the
information you would need to connect it
up if you wanted to and you're going to
want to write because you're going to
need to connect it up stuff later um so
we can say it's like okay the hero
bedroom gets recorded the forest
entrance gets recorded nothing else
really needs to but we could we can
return anything we want here so when you
create one of these with the you know
world generator you get back the
information that you needed about what
was in you know how you might plug into
this thing that you made okay so that's
pretty straightforward hopefully you
understand what I'm talking about there
so when I do create world here what I
need to do is first create one of these
rural generators who knows how that's
going to happen then I'm going to create
the orphanage here and I guess I'll get
back
an orphanage
I'll create an orphanage then what I
need to do is actually have that do a
layout to place where all these things
you know would be and then I need to do
a world generate that would actually
take all the semantic information and
produce the world mode result from there
now I don't really know that that needs
to take the world mode it could be that
you can just take the world yeah that
that may not need the world mode it may
be that that just just does world so I
will say you know I'll I'll just I'll
pass the world for now if it turns out
that we need the world mode later we can
fix that and that's fine I don't know
that we really need the transient state
to be honest
I don't think I'm going to use it we'll
see why in a second
but I think that's it
so what you can see now is again I did
exactly what I set out to do I wanted a
way to figure out where my API should
sort of begin and this seems pretty
logical to me this gives me all of the
stuff that I wanted I can specify what
kinds of rooms I want to be involved I
can have a place where I can talk about
things that need to be in them and then
I can say how there should be linked up
so that it will make a plausible version
of that thing right now in the future
I'm gonna need to expand these I can you
know I can already guess that this would
have to have constraints about
directionality like maybe I always want
the hero bedroom to be connected on the
south side of the orphanage and they
always want the forest pass to be
connected on the north side of the or
Freight or things like that but you know
those are things that I can add over
time and there's a clear place where I
would do them because I have every
logical thing that I wanted to talk
about is being talked about there's the
specifications for rooms
there's the rooms themselves there's
connectivity between rooms and that's
basically what I wanted so far in the
system and there it is so what I should
be able to do now is I should be able
start building this out and actually do
exactly that implement those api's and
make them work so let's go ahead and get
started with that
okay and you'll see as we go yet
basically the the main thing here like
this stuff is pretty logical the main
thing that probably left you expanded at
first is the specs things like how big
rooms should be generally speaking like
what the flexibility is on that and and
just some basic parameters will have to
be specified pretty early on I think
because if we don't specify those we
won't have a lot of understanding in the
generator of how it should start placing
things so that part logic is failing
sooner the other stuff can be expanded
later like what actually gets put inside
rooms and all that needs its own sort of
rich system of specification that will
go in here
and that stuff I just don't care about
at the moment right that stuff that will
sort of start to take on a little bit
later as a secondary system that's sort
of it's it's it's you want to look at
this sort of as a meta multistage
process get the layout of rooms first
and then find details of the rooms
second so that you can kind of tackle
the problem in in two stages so let's go
ahead and talk about the types that we
said we have we know that we have a
world generator we know that we have a
general spec we know that we have a gem
we know that we have a gem connection
now we didn't talk about it explicitly
but presumably that's what connect would
return we just never need to talk about
it at all
so far so we know that we have one we
just don't need to actually expose it to
the users yet of the generator but we
know it's there so I'm gonna put it in
there because it's clear that it's there
and that's what we've got furthermore we
know that we've got a certain set of
routines here right and what we can sort
of see is this will probably move out to
you know we've got we've got to have the
system there's an API for building a
world and then there's actually like the
game logic of what world gets built and
those are two separate things so
eventually we're looking towards right
pulling out like create orphanage will
not live in the world generator for long
once we get a significant amount of that
world generation stuff together we will
make a hard split of stuff that does the
world generation work and stuff that
lays out the specification for what
world should be generated and those will
not be the same right so that's where my
eye is out at the moment just you can
understand mentally you know sort of
what I'm talking about
as I go forward so we now know that we
also in a
to these things we've got a bunch of
code that we've sort of said has to be
there right we know we've got this thing
that generates a spec we know we've got
a thing that generates a room or creates
the semantic idea of a room to generate
right we know we have to get the world
generator somehow we know we have to
have a layout called places worlds and
whatever we need a thing that actually
generates everything and then we need a
way to clean it all up right and just
say we're done all right so here in my
we've got the sort of gemspec thing that
takes the world generator and that's
just something that produces a spec
we've got the general call there there's
something mixed connection I'm not gonna
use Furman too because in our world we
don't really have one-way connections we
may add something like a one-way
connection in the future which would be
like a teleport or something that only
goes one direction but that's not the
same thing as we're talking about here
when we're talking about connecting here
we're talking about the geographic
layout of the rooms and that is only
mutual there's no way to have room a a
but room B but not have room B about
room a they're a budding or they're not
right so Connect is about the spatial
relationship of the rooms connect them
physically not about the topological
connection in a gameplay sense which is
irrelevant to this part of the code this
code is talking about where to put the
rooms
it doesn't need to know whether the
player can get between them or not in
fact we could have people calling
connect with a parameter later on that
says
don't actually make a door I just want
these two things next to each other but
they you shouldn't be able to go through
them right because that is something you
may want to do for example let's say a
room was on top of another room but you
don't want to stare well you just want
to be able to look down into it that's
like part of the gameplay
who knows that's an example of what I
would want to say connect these two
rooms one on top of the other spatially
but don't have a way for the player to
actually get between them right so again
connect in this case is talking about
the physical connection between the
rooms not the actual semantic connection
can the player get there and that's an
important distinction for us understand
what we're trying to accomplish here so
we don't know yet what that takes
all right
I assume now we have sort of all of the
all of the sort of the husk the stubs of
what we actually need to do here and so
let's start by implementing the basic
stuff that we can implement right so
when we go ahead and start doing this
stuff we kind of know that we're just
going to be creating these arbitrary
stuff that these yeah we're just
creating this stuff here and fill in
junk out so what I want to do is I want
to have a good way to allocate this
stuff and if you remember where's our
arena stuff here yeah
this is really good advice by the way
so I assume
[Music]
hmmm this is where not having worked
with this code a long time makes it
tough because I don't remember what we
had implemented yet so we have here
allocation flags and it looks like to me
so okay great
so it looks like we've already finished
this part so if you look here and you
can see this you can see this code just
grows the arena any time it needs to so
basically we can just make one of these
and go to town so I think we're
basically good to go so here's all I
want to do I'm gonna let this thing for
now and possibly for always one of the
things that's generally true these days
is especially lately this was not really
true when we started handmade here oh
it's starting to be kind of true now is
the amount of memory and machines is so
much larger then I would ever have
expected it to be relative to what we
create it's kind of nuts it's a little
bit weird so I'm not sure how much we
care about this stuff or not but in the
future we may want to hardbound the
world generation size at the moment any
platform we're going to run this on is
more than capable of giving us all the
memory that we need to do so so I'm just
gonna let it take as much as it wants
for the time being we'll see eventually
if I need to walk that back for some
very constrained platforms I'm not sure
what the most constrained platform would
be maybe a Raspberry Pi but even like
phones nowadays have like infinite
memory it's weird I mean not for the
crazy stuff that people seem to expect
now in you know like a Unity game or
something but like if for a hand-coded
game the amount
to memory they give you is just
absolutely nuts used to be that the
iPhones were not so much but they're
starting to get kind of absurd in terms
of how much memory they have it's really
bizarre but more power to them if those
hardware manufacturers can keep putting
it in there and I guess they're gonna
have to you can't even run a web browser
with like about multiple gigabytes these
days it's like I just want to load the
front page of cnn.com it's like oh
that'll be half a gigabyte of memory I
guess it's like whatever anyway um so
I'm gonna let this thing grow at the
moment and so I'm going to use the
bootstrap push size thing that we were
here to just create one of these world
generators and so what I'm gonna do here
is just say okay
when you go to start creating a world
I'm gonna say I've got a the world Gen
here and if I remember correctly sort of
the way we did this is you can say the
type that you wanted and the member in
it that's going to be the arena so the
arena is just gonna be right or I'll
just call it memory right so inside a
world generator I have a memory arena
and that memory arena is called memory
on surprisingly and so this will just
create us one of these rural generators
that has its own arena and off it goes
and then we'll just create all of the
stuff that we want for it we'll just be
in there and then we'll just discard it
when we're done and be done with it so I
think we had a way to do that here oops
so in here we sort of have there is one
nastiness we never fixed this in fact I
think we have a bug logged against this
actually don't we do we I need to log
into github on the main hand main hero
machine I'm I'm not I'm quite sure I'm
not in fact but I have it on the other
machine here logged in let me see
yes bug in clear memory arena and what
happens there this was reported by busy
beaver and thank you for reporting this
it's true I will log that as resolved
today presumably we'll see but what you
can see here is this was written before
we used the bootstrap stuff which
allocates the arena inside the arena
itself and so what happens is when you
do free last block and you do this the
allocate memory on exit from the routine
you come back to clear you check this
and this is now an invalid pointer right
so what we actually need to do there in
order to make this be safe is we want to
check this as a prophylactic first to
see whether or not we we are done if
this is the last block because if it is
the last block then we want to break
always so we can actually leave the loop
mostly the same but what we do want to
do here is like you can see where we do
this arena preevning we can say you know
something like exit or this is last
block I'll put a note here
so what we want to do here is say look
if this was the last block so you know
if the if the the arena current block
had the one before it which we're about
to say is a new current block if that is
not valid so if there's if it's as null
right all right you know what I could do
it this way if the if the one that we
will be moving to is zero then this is
the last block and so I'd say if this is
the last block break right
probably not the cleanest way to write
that loop but that'd work and like I
said that kind of has to be in there in
order to make sure that the clear
actually works because otherwise could
free the arena and then look at the
arena which is obviously a bug so um the
other way to write this I guess would be
to just make this a four loop and do an
if the rad doesn't matter all right so
anyway I'm gonna call clear on this and
that'll be the end of it that'll free
all the memory that we use so then we
don't really have to track the memory at
all and we don't care we can just do
whatever we want so then for each of
these I can do a push struct on them and
just get them oops
and I probably want these to be zeroed
when we're doing it as well I don't
remember whether we said that's the
default it is so it'll just get cleared
to zero always so if you look at what
we've got here we have now implemented a
stub version of basically everything and
if I go in and now actually call this
which I don't think I'm actually doing
so inside create world here for example
I'll actually call this now
I'm mr. debugger and that's a good
stopping place - for today so that's
great tomorrow we can base start typing
that in how come I did not hit my
breakpoint what was taking so long do
you see how long that took
what how are we
uh so the generate lighting pattern
takes forever in debug mode off to fix
that good how long that takes but anyway
here we go so you know that's not even
the one I wanted got too many things
called create world so just want to walk
through this here so when we do begin
world gen we do a bootstrap right and so
then what we get back is one of these
guys that just has the memory arena
built inside it so then when we start
doing stuff we just can so then we come
through here we'd like to do a gen spec
right we just push one of those on off
we go right so this just basically just
generates all that memory fills it up
and good to go we then call these sub
functions that don't do anything yet and
then we end the world gen which does the
clear right and now the clear there
should only be like one block I think
right yeah because we didn't use very
much memory right so then there's a
previous that's that's set to zero so
this should be set to one because it is
the last block so when it frees it it'll
see that that's the last block and leave
so that bugs gone
and off we go so that's all good you
know we're we're all happy campers there
and that's a good place to leave it for
today let me go ahead and close that bug
out too
I today is what 444 so I'll just say
this should be fixed as of day 444 and
then I think we will go to the Q&amp;A let's
close in comment
[Music]
any thoughts on mic act enjoining the
unity dev team um I don't have a lot of
thoughts on it other than it seems good
to me unity is used by a lot of people
to make games now and it like the
quality level seems pretty low on a lot
of those games in terms of the code
quality I don't know whether that's
because unities has low code quality or
whether that's because hey the whole
point of unity is that inexperienced
people in terms of programming can use
it to make games that's like the whole
point of icing an engine a lot of the
times and sometimes the point is to save
yourself the work but a lot of times
it's because people who could not have
made an engine can now license one and
use it and that's good I don't know if
maybe it's just because they don't
really know what they're doing
programming wise so it makes it appear
like it's a lot more finicky and poor
performance and all the other sorts of
things
I don't know right but I do know that a
lot of games I play that use unity have
a lot of problems that really shouldn't
be there and I don't know why that is
but one of the problems may be that
there needs to be more attention paid to
how to make it be efficient given that
you know that the people who are using
it aren't necessarily expert programmers
in fact a lot of times the whole point
is that they aren't so it seems like
having people who have a focus on sort
of performance and code cleanliness in
that sense not over complicating things
and making it be designed specifically
to do good CPU level processing he's a
plus and hopefully will lead to good
things because a lot of people make
games and unity so we're gonna get games
made in unity there's no two ways about
that the better unity is the better
those games will be right because the
more improvements you can make to unity
the more those games will be improved by
it right same is true of the Unreal
Engine the better you make the Unreal
Engine the better the games are because
a lot of people use it you know if the
Unreal Engine had better networking code
player unknowns battlegrounds wouldn't
be such a pie
I know sorry to be mean about it but the
networking code in that game
well the networking code a lot of Unreal
Engine games is just really bad and you
know that's like hey if they make good
significant technological advances in
some of those things then all those
games get better and that's better for
everybody right so it does seem good I
don't know you know can he make
meaningful improvements to it he's only
one guy you know it's not like he gets
to go there and change the whole thing
or whatever so I don't know what will
become of it but it seems good you know
it seems like it could have a positive
positive impact right if the parentheses
around the return values for debugging
or just a habit just to have it it
doesn't do anything
so you're talking about this if you
remove those parentheses nothing would
change at all like any at all like
anywhere
I just always got used to reading it
that way and I don't remember why yeah I
don't know I mean technically there is a
thing that makes a difference here which
is that if found task was a macro that
included a semicolon this would make
sure that you got an error so there is
one safety reason why you might want to
do that but I don't know that I've ever
really relied on that to catch bugs so
I'm doing it out of habit there I guess
is a reason you might want to do it but
I wouldn't consider that reason
particularly worthwhile because the
compiler should most compilers will give
you an unreachable code warning in in
release in optimize builds so chances
are you would eventually find it anyway
a debug maybe a debug build wouldn't
tell you because it didn't do dead code
elimination or something but but a
release mode build almost certainly
would find would realize that you had
something after a hard return and it
would tell you so I don't think you
would yeah I really don't think it's a
much of an issue is it a good idea to
use events you got to give me more
context than that I mean yeah events are
a tool right there um it's like asking
is it a good idea to use the
cross-product I for what right like I
mean I don't know so events are useful
for certain circumstances and not useful
in others if you need to be able to
serialize a set of things across
multiple threads events are very useful
or distribute things across multiple
threads over useful you
you need to break up a control flow
pattern to avoid using a callback events
are very useful if you're just spamming
in an event system for no reason and you
could have just called a function that's
kind of dumb so there's you know there's
a lot of different there's there's a lot
of different scenarios there and I
wouldn't say that you can just say
events good bad right you have to have
some idea of like what you know what was
the reason and what are you trying to
solve does an event make sense here
right are we gonna see the new art
assets soon
today was exciting I can't wait for will
join should be interesting um I don't
know like we'll get like everything else
I get to it when I get to it off topic
if you run out other questions and see
is there a way to make something similar
to function overloading I don't know I'm
sorry I don't use straight C so I don't
keep up with the C spec much the C spec
has changed considerably since I learned
it I mean I learned it in the 80s and
the C spec has been revised heavily
since then so whether there's something
you can do nowadays that's similar to
function overloading I don't know I
don't think so but there might be but
I'm the wrong one to ask because I
really don't keep up with it enough I
read somewhere you can pound to find
return and log all your returns that
happen sure you can certainly do that
what do I think of golang I have never
used Galang so I don't know
just as a side note on the Nvidia Fiasco
you had I found that in my case I can
get inside rabbits to crash in the same
way if I use raw input to get ps4
controller data really as soon as I
remove the call that registers raw input
controllers and site works any idea on
why that could happen maybe insight is
using something for intercepting user
input so I guess my question would be
does it matter what raw input
controllers you register or not if any
raw input registration causes it to
happen then I think you're on to
something there if it's only
registration of the ps4 controller that
caused it to crash I might ask whether
you're sure you don't have some other
dependency further down the line based
on the ps4 controller registration that
might be causing it because it doesn't
seem like they would crash on a specific
hid registration but maybe I'm wrong
about that I mean obviously they could
but it just seems unlikely it seems less
likely I know you did a video on trip
relation do you know of any good
resources for cubic baselines what do
you want to know about cubic b-splines
you just want to kind of get better at
understanding how these mines work or I
mean I guess I couldn't tell you off the
top of my head that there's any
particularly great B spline reference
[Music]
yeah I don't really have anything else
to top my head sorry
I mean be splines and and Bezier curves
cubic B splines and cubic Bezier curves
are the same curve a B spline it just
has baked the parameters such that the
tangents of the tangent of sequential
bezzie as line up that's all a B spline
is just pre solving the equations so
that instead of specifying two endpoints
and two tangents you just specify points
and each point is the tangent of the
next point point right like you you
already say that this whole curves gonna
be continuous so every point implies the
tangent for the next point right or the
previous point however you want to look
at that
so I don't know of anything offhand but
there's no other magic to it right it's
not like a b-spline is a different type
of curve it's the same type of curve
it's just a Bezier curve that's had the
tangents pre-baked because you want to
be able to have arbitrary numbers of
points so instead of specifying two
endpoints and two tangents and then for
the next curve making the two tangents
force to be the same length and the same
direction you just pre say that those
are derived from the points themselves I
mean that's that's it
so I don't know I realize that doesn't
help because if you want a full
reference and to see how they work you
work them through and all that obviously
you need more than that basic
explanation that I just gave but that is
the first step to understanding them
anyway it's just to realize that all
those curves are the same they're just
different ways of specifying the inputs
so with a Bezier curve you've taken a
cubic and you said I want to specify it
by two endpoints or two tangents with a
b-spline curve you're saying I want to
take a series of points and construct
bezier curves out of essentially the
latticework of those curves going
forwards and that's all it really is you
know
I shouldn't really say going forwards
because there's actually two ways of
constructing a b-spline you can have
forward-looking not or backwards looking
not again this is like getting into the
weeds and whatever but if you imagine
taking a series of points and you want
to construct a Bezier out of them well
let me just it's been a while so I
apologize if I get something wrong here
because I just I worked with these a lot
in the old days I don't work with them
much today so a Bezier curve right is
going to take four points and it's going
to draw a curve between them by using
these as the tangents and these is the
end points right so you essentially have
like an end point and end point and then
two tangent points right and there's
your curve you tweak where these are and
you change the shape of the curve but it
always gonna hit these two you change
where these are and that changes where
the curve like starts and ends right so
that's a Bezier curve the problem with a
busy curve problem I mean it's not
problem but it's just aspect of it is
you get one curve right it's a cubic in
this case right if it was a Bezier
curves can be arbitrary degree and what
that means is that they can have an
arbitrary number of loops in them right
so if I have a zeroth-order bezzie a
right all of a sudden we're talking
about
[Music]
curves there's so much to talk about
with curves I should probably stop but
so if you're if you're gonna talk about
a curve order then essentially what
you're talking about
it all gets just gets back to
polynomials
you know from math class right oh let me
use it the standard notation here you
know from math class that essentially
you've got different degrees of
polynomial right so if I have a function
and there's a tea that I'm passing into
the function then I can have a lot of
different characteristics of an equation
if I want to have a zeroth order one
then it's just a constant it's like f of
C equals five what does that mean it
means that T is actually irrelevant
right it's not really a function of T T
doesn't appear its T to the zero with
power
it's five T to the 0 and T to the zero
is one so it's just tea anything equals
five doesn't matter I didn't pass in any
number and I get back five right that's
zeroth order right first order I come in
here and I say all right that's five T
plus we'll use something else for T 0 +
5 0 same term here but now we've added
another one and that's linear in T right
T is to the first power it means that as
I increase T I get a smooth even line
increase at this slope you know for this
this part of the parameter right so I
went from something and if i graph these
I get that right just a line constant
line here I've got something looks like
that right or it can go downward either
way second order now I've got F of T
equals you know 3t squared or maybe
whatever you want like seven T squared
plus 4 T 1 plus 5 T 0 right and that's a
parabola right can be like that can be
like that something like this right
and then I got finally that third order
which is the one we're talking about
here which is cubic these can keep going
on but you know cubics were what people
normally use probably since what you
were asking about so I got to T to the
third plus 72 the second plus 4 to the
first plus 5 to 0 right or whatever and
that's a cubic curve right so that's
something that looks anything like this
right Senate cetera I should write this
a little bit differently right and each
one of these can include a shape of the
one below them right so if I just set
these parameters as I reduce the squared
parameter I get closer to a line as I
reduce the line parameter I get closer
to a constant right so a cubic because a
cubic can have a wiggle in it right a
cubic can actually change direction in
and of itself right so a bezier curve
and all that garbage was just to explain
to you like oh hey if I set one tangent
going this way one tangent going that
way I would have a curve that looks like
that right but it can only have one bend
in it that's all it can have so what you
end up with is if you want to start to
fit things that are more complicated
right let's say I want to be able to do
a shape that looks like this well you
know busy he's not going to cut it it's
got too many you know no matter how
imprecisely I fit this I'm never even
gonna get remotely close even that you
know which is all I could do with a
cubic is just not gonna work right
I need a been here and have been here
and a bent here right so I need more and
so the thing that you do with bezzie a
is like if you're Adobe Illustrator or
something like this is you line them up
oops
so here's my first busy a and here's my
second busy a and what I do is I lock
the two tangents so I make this and this
be complimentary to each other so that
when the curve passes through this point
it is smooth right so I make this be the
negative of this so that's how you daisy
chain bezzie ace together to make a
longer curves you just do Bessie a and
then the next as ei locks the two
tangent handles the so basically you
know if this is p0 p1 p2 p3 p4 p5 p6
what I say is all right the first bezzie
a is p0 p1 p2 p3 the next busy a instead
of starting at p4 it starts at p3 so I
duplicate the end point and then p4 is
equal to p3 plus whatever the negative
is of p2 - Pete right that this this
this vector here I set this point to be
equal to that displacement right so my
p4 you know is going to be locked
instead of it being whatever you want to
be it's going to be locked and say that
p4 equals P 3 oops - or we can do plus
doesn't matter which one we want to I
want to go in this direction here right
so I'm gonna say whatever p3 is minus p2
there right
don't do that right we're on transfers
so it's p4 equals P three plus P 2 minus
P 3 minus P 2 yeah yeah so effectively
we just get to P 3 minus P 2 that's our
new point and so P 4 is now not free
right so not only is there not another
point to start the curve because we're
saying they started into the same place
but we also prescribed P 4 so there
really is no P 4 it's just a fan fantasy
right makes sense
great ok and furthermore Adobe
Illustrator does some other stuff like
if you want to have a discontinuity here
so they meet up but they don't have the
same derivative then you let P 4 be
specified that's called a corner right
in in their parlance right Bezier corner
and furthermore you can also say that
well I want the direction to be the same
that the length can change and that's
saying that the second derivative won't
be give this continuous right because
remember this is a cubic you know so
it's got different derivatives right
there's a there's zeroth order just
continuous and if it's zeroth or
discontinuous then we're not even lining
up the points that's one busy a here one
busy a here and the and there's a gap
right so it's discontinuous all the way
up to its actual location there's
first-order discontinuous that's if you
meet these two points right so I want
these two points to join so there's only
so it's always gonna meet it's gonna be
a continuous curve in terms of visually
but I don't care if this points in the
same direction so instead of looking
like that maybe it looks like that right
so when I actually draw the curve I get
a hard bend there these two parts are
fully continuous but this right here has
a kink right finally there's
second-order
discontinuous now I'm gonna write that
and that's the acceleration along the
curve so that means it will point in the
same direction but the rate of curvature
will change at that point so rather than
looking smooth like that it will look
more like that so it'll have it'll have
a kink but the kink won't be visible at
it as a instantaneous direction change
it'll just start curving much more
quickly and then there's third order
continuous third order discontinuous
which is irrelevant for the purposes of
cubic splines because there is no fourth
term so you can't be third order
discontinuous because there isn't
anything past there right if that makes
sense so all of that is my way of trying
to lay the groundwork for you to
understand what a b-spline curve is what
a b-spline curve is is solving pre
solving for how you want to interpret
your points such that a set of points
passed in is continuous everywhere on
all degrees so there are no
discontinuities at all it is as if you
did the thing I said here where you lock
the tangents their direction and their
length so that they always flow
perfectly three order continuous the
whole way and the way this works is it
basically mix a bezzie a more-or-less
it's not exactly that way but it
basically makes a bezel bezzie a out of
four points and starch the interpolation
but only goes a quarter of the way so
you can imagine it sort of starting to
go like well maybe I should say a third
of the way I don't know how you look at
it we start going like this but as we
get to here we then change to
interpreting the curve over the next
four points right and then we use the
next four points and so rather than ever
hitting a point we always move the
framework for words so the only point we
ever hit is the first point or the last
point depending on whether you do
trailing not you can do it the other way
you can say we start with four points
behind us there's two different ways to
do it right and so Abby's flying
formulation is just that it's moving the
frame of reference before you ever get
to one of the points so you are always
off of the framework the whole way that
help
I really like the look of the lighting
you've implemented will the system be
working for any light points I guess the
system right now does not require you to
say what's a light and what's not it
it's just takes all of the light in the
scene and convex it so you can have as
many lights or as few lights as you want
it doesn't care it's not like a normal
3d engine lighting where you have to say
this is a light this is not it doesn't
work that way it just basically says
look everything's a light source in
their receptacle and off we go
long boolean so if I on the same page I
wanted to make sure that two rooms never
touch each other we would still use
connect bus passing a flag of some kind
or would you do something else I
probably wouldn't quite have live that
way it might be a little that way
internally but I would probably have two
different functions just so it's clear
when you look at like repel or something
or I don't know like don't connect I'm
not sure but I don't think we need to
say much about that because I don't know
that we're gonna care I don't know if we
care if two rooms abut or not because I
connect will say whether there's a door
between them or not as long as I don't
say put a door here there should be a
wall anyway even if they happen to line
up next to each other it wouldn't
actually put any way to get there so I
don't know that will necessarily care
about keeping them farther away from
each other but we could we can put in a
repel thing that's like keep these at
least this far away from each other or
something
are there any plans to write tools to
author rooms or will everything be done
in code everything we've done in code
it's a fully procedural game so we won't
be writing an editor where you place
stuff
although someone's welcome to do that as
an add-on if they want to write like you
can you've pretty much got everything
you need for it right because you can
just use the handmade hero source base
to make something that displays the
entities that you put them down right so
it's not it wouldn't be that hard for
you to add one if you really wanted to
do so all right I'm gonna wrap it up for
today
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for live so the hand made here it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
the series at home you can always go to
handmade hero Network and pre-order the
game it comes with a source code and I
update it every time we finish coding
here so that you can keep up to date
with serious and try your own
experiments for example if you wanted to
start building a little world builder
editor tool since that's not something
we're doing you could certainly go try
doing that yourself and make your own
little handmade hero worlds to explore
instead of the generated ones that are
being generated again that's just
handmade here at Oregon so you need to
do we also have a bunch of resources you
can go to there like the episode guide
and so on
I'll be back here tomorrow so if you
would like to finish doing the world Jen
basic pass with me where we're trying to
just sort of get rudimentary stuff in
there we'll be doing that tomorrow same
time same place so I'd love to see you
back here for that until then have fun
coding on your own stuff and I will see
you on the Internet take it easy
everybody