hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we go a complete-game live
on stream I don't know what we're gonna
do today coz it's been a long time
sweeping back we were on winter break
it's been a couple weeks and here's the
thing I'm in the middle of some for
kotor modifications so we also are gonna
have to talk about that sometime soon
next weekend I will be completely done
with them I'm almost done now but I
don't want to go over and cover like how
all the new stuff works just to bring
people up to speed on what's going on so
they can follow until then so there
might be some weirdness and also it's
some of the stuff is half-baked right
now like on this machine I think I
haven't copied the latest one over yet
so it's still the one that we were we
did a stream over the week where I kind
of showed for coder modification stuff
that I was doing so we still kind of
have the the older version here so I
apologize for that but again it's just
it's in the middle of an upgrade and so
we're gonna we'll talk about that a
little bit more next weekend when all
that stuff's done I'll go over kind of
what's in there and how that works now
more importantly though over winter
break this was really the biggest news
and it only just happened couple days
ago so George man horn actually got in
touch with me and said that remedy the
debugger that he'd been working on was
starting to get get ready for primetime
and as you know one of the biggest
things that I find really grating about
development is having to use Visual
Studio it's really just difficult to
work with and there's so many reasons
for that we've talked about it many
times but it's basically like it's very
slow and cumbersome and it requires this
massive install it has a weird licensing
regime that constantly decides it's
unlicensed and you have to deal with
that and all these are things and you
know install sequel server on your
machine I mean it's just it's absurd
right like the the amount of stuff that
you have to go through just to get a
debugger is kind of crazy but you know
there haven't been a lot of alternatives
to it anyway I took a look at remedy
which was the
that that George been working on and I
am pleased to report that it's looking
like really solid and so I thought today
I might sort of go over that a little
bit as a start of warm-up to get us back
into the groove of things and just see
can we switch to that on stream now it's
very reasonably priced for anyone else
who wants to switch with me and so if it
turns out to be you know useful this is
an easy thing to afford much cheaper
than a visual studio which costs
thousands of dollars or something if
you're you don't want the professional
license it is available here here is the
thing so it's remedy BGH IO I don't know
why there's a slash that like it seems
like you should be able to do that but I
don't know maybe not um so anyway this
is the the URL for purchase for some
reason its name your own price I feel
like something like this is worth at
least like 50 bucks or something I paid
50 bucks for it because I was like
that's how much I'll pay easily for good
debugger if it turns out to be good and
it seems like it's gonna be good I
should I send more money but yeah so I
don't know why it's priced so low
because that's basically free
essentially so I would recommend paying
something but also George this probably
should be more than three anyway so if
we go in here we can see the
distribution and the first thing I would
point out is look at how beautiful this
looks right like Visual Studio Lake they
can't even distribute visual studio
without a virtual machine when they do
their previews I don't know if you guys
have seen this but like when they ship
betas a visual studio it comes with a
virtual machine that you have to run it
in that's how bad they are at
distributing software right this which
is a pretty darn good debugger so far
looks as good as Visual Studio it's one
executable that's five Meg's that's it
right and that's just like a sight for
sore eyes right it's like that's
something that you can trivially put on
your machine you don't have to worry
about it
you can check it into your source code
control so you know you
have all your previous versions so if
you want to roll back to a version you
were using before you just can forget
that visual studio use never that's
never gonna happen right you're you're
never gonna roll back to a version in
source control forget it
so again just really really happy to see
that now I'm gonna go ahead and install
the latest version I had put an earlier
version on this machine this is the
latest one at 1:3 and I don't have a lot
of experience with it yet I'm kind of
early in on it
but it seemed to work quite well the
only thing that didn't have yet is like
PDB finding stuff wasn't quite in there
yet so it didn't really work with PD B's
that an X's that are moved that are like
using pdb alt path and moved or archived
from their locations but it seems to
work quite well for stuff that's just
left in place so if the eggsy or dll's
pdb path that it's got baked into it
points to the pdb seemed to work pretty
well
we can go ahead and try it out on
handmade hero so let's let's go ahead
and and and load it up and you can see
what I mean I'm gonna just go ahead and
be an optimist here on four-quarter I'm
gonna go into our bin directory Laurel
it's our Miss directory but our one
that's in the path here you know we've
got MS dev in there for launching the
debugger I'm gonna go ahead and say that
let's just make a remedy dot bat file
and what I'm gonna do here is just make
a thing that calls out to remedy and
let's see here yeah there we go and so
I'm just gonna have it so that you know
let's be optimistic and see if we can't
make this into our daily debugger and
then we don't ever have to see visual
studio again so there we go
oops I gotta have the actual eggsy name
in there there it is and for those of
you unfamiliar with das batch files
let's mention it again percent star is
just the syntax for saying any
parameters that were passed to the batch
file on the shell just pass them through
so this would allow us to you know if if
remedy ends up having a bunch of command
line switches that we want to be able to
use here and there that just allows
those get passed through so you can kind
of think of this batch file as the thing
that like
goes and finds the executable we're
running but also that has that ability
to add flags as well right now here's
one thing I don't know I don't know if
remedy wants to run in a particular
location so what I'm gonna do here is
I'm gonna probably go a little bit
further just just a hair further maybe
well see but this wouldn't and local
eggsy files wouldn't work correctly they
did that so what I don't know is how
remedy puts files on the drive so I
don't know what I'm gonna do here
exactly I'll leave it like this for now
and we'll maybe look at that a little
bit later I also think George is
tweaking some of that stuff now so well
we won't worry about too much okay so
let's see what happens let's say we're
in the W directory here I'm just curious
what happens if I do remedy like this
and then I close yeah so this is what I
was worried about so it writes this I am
doing I and I file into wherever it
currently is so what I think I'm gonna
do for now I don't think that's good
like he should probably change that
because it should it should probably
write that into a more specific location
so what I want to do is I want to kind
of guard against that for now until that
gets resolved in the action in like a
future update so if I come in here to
that remedy file what I'm gonna do is
I'm just gonna guard it by saying look
this thing always has to run in its own
directory and we'll deal with it from
there now that does mean that anything
that you know you pass on the command
line that you thought was gonna be
relative to where you are isn't actually
going to be and that's unfortunate but
you know we'll just deal with that
because it's better to not leave this I
am grave files lying around so this way
we'll do a push T into that directory
will start remedy this way so it doesn't
lock up our command line and then we'll
go from there so here we go and well let
me do that
again so here's remedy again and I'll
close it and this time it should not
have written that file out here right
Matt didn't so that keeps that properly
guarded and and off we go
so that means now you know for if we're
in here and we wanted to start this up
we can just start about let's take a
look at the actual debugger itself so
you can see across the top it's got a
familiar menu system here and I do know
someone how to use it already I play
with it a little bit on my own basically
what happens is in here you can specify
the target information that you that you
want we want to use hand-made here
obviously and so that's in our build
directory back here it's win32 handmade
right and so we can put that in there
for command argument we don't really
have any at the moment for the working
directory we know that we run inside
handmade like so so it looks like that
and one of the nice things is you can
just save your session really quickly
using what these are TG r DB g files you
don't have to make a SL n or prj or all
these weird other different things that
it's hard to tell like what refers to
what so r DB g files just this is the
debug target so you know you can just
save that and have it and you're done
and so one of the nice things about that
is i can just maybe in here in our
handmade directory i might just save
that out you know i guess to the route i
don't have a lot of opinions maybe about
where that needs to go but maybe we'll
put that in the route or what i could do
is i could put that in a debug directory
we've got this nvidia directory and
we've got the MS vc proj directory and
so you know the other thing i could do
is make a remedy specific directory i
don't know how necessary that really is
so i might just make a debug directory
and we'll start putting things in there
in general maybe the in video stuff will
go in there as well so we don't have to
have like lots of directories for this
sort of stuff so once that's in there
oops what did i do wrong oh i got a name
this thing so this is like just wintered
your handmaid let's say so i believe
once you do that if you just close it if
you start it again
I believe you can just go open and then
pick it and then you've got your target
set up the way that you know however you
did and you can switch between them that
way so it's pretty easy to do exactly
like they were an MS vc project or
something like that
it should just work right and that's
really it the key commands he's done a
nice job mapping them to things you
already mostly know so to launch the app
you can just hit f5 and you know it runs
and similarly you know it's got all the
familiar features if we break into it
you're pretty much good to go we can
click on our starting now click on but
you can see the modules that are loaded
in here and you can see which ones have
symbols they're exactly the ones you'd
expect
we don't have symbols installed for the
win32 libraries so we're just looking at
the ones that we've made the handmade
one the win32 opengl one and the other
one through two handmade egg Z right
those are the components that are
running the game at the moment and
they're all loaded which is exactly what
we want so if we take a look at the call
stack for any individual one of these we
got to go to our threads window here now
one of the things that I found a little
bit confusing and I don't really
remember to be honest with you I don't
remember why this isn't hard on when
windbg or MSV see there's some piece of
information that's missing here if that
makes it hard to tell which of these is
our threads and which of these are
threads created by operating system
services let's take it let's just take a
look because I wanted to send this
feedback but I was like I don't even
really know what don't even really know
what the feedback is so if I go here to
win through two handmade SLN and of
course it takes a while to start up
because you know how could you possibly
load that in time and I run this thing
if I go to the threads window here so
you can kind of see like somehow they
get this information right and it's this
name thing I don't know where exactly
that's coming from but that is really
hey
because now I know that these are the
thread procs and this is the main thread
and so it's easy for me to jump down in
there right so that's one thing that
would be a nice improvement around UV I
it's one of the only things I noticed
when working on it I was like there was
something that was a little bit nicer to
use in in the debuggers I was familiar
with already so anyway that's a little
bit of an issue and so you know the
reason that it becomes difficult is
you're kind of hunting through here to
find these things and so you look in
here I'm guessing what it is is that the
other ones hunt upward till they find
something they recognize maybe to be
completely honest with you I really just
don't know but we can see on here that
that this is you know eventually we can
see the one that is ours and we can like
look at where it is and all that sort of
stuff once we've done that it actually
works exactly the same as everything
else to you know you can just run and it
should be able to to break when you stop
on things and so on although that
actually doesn't look like it is at the
moment so maybe I maybe I misspoke there
I didn't have I don't remember having
much trouble getting break points to
work properly
I wonder what's going on there I in the
right place okay
doudou there we go so let me just see
what I can do here let me go here I can
single step through things just fine but
it doesn't seem to really want me to be
able to set a breakpoint which is weird
because I did this a bunch on my own
computer and it was fine but this
definitely doesn't seem to want to
alright so maybe this will be a short
demo like I said it's still in progress
so I don't know although I didn't really
have this problem so I wonder if I've
got something more tricky going out the
pdbs on this machine
let's try setting a breakpoint here if I
look at what my breakpoints are you can
see them right here right this one it
definitely located this one it looks
like it had trouble doing oh that's
because that's not an actual function
that's why so see that works just fine
and so did that so I don't know what I
was having trouble with there and maybe
that's just working out the kinks you
know like I said this is very early
access at this point and this is a
retail build so it's the worst possible
case as well but it does look like it's
having trouble with breakpoints setting
a little bit at least in this miliar
because like for example it couldn't
single step over that line which meant
that it couldn't it wasn't able to set a
breakpoint anywhere in here which I
assume has something to do with again
like that sort of code problem so let me
take a quick look at whether that's
release mode issues or not because I'm
curious natsu so let me go into and
code let's go ahead and open up for
coder here and I just want to change
this build dot back to an OD so it's
gonna be a debug built and then in here
I'm gonna go ahead and run that build
and just have everything rebuilt for a
debug mode I just want to see if it
behaves any differently here I'm not
sure if it will or not but so here's
this restarting same place I'm gonna
step through this and see now if it
still has the same problem with stepping
as it had before and if you remember
correctly it basically as when I got
down to the sound area here it wasn't
able to continue single single stepping
over that and it looks like it's having
no trouble with that sort of thing now
so yeah I want to say that maybe the
problem with what is it doing oh never
mind it just didn't do anything I want
to see that maybe he still got some bugs
with how to figure out where to set the
breakpoint for the next line in a
release mode build that'd be my guess
because this looks just fine and
similarly I'm assuming now I could reset
those break points for what I wanted
before that I was having trouble so I
wanted to set a breakpoint like here
yeah and that works just fine so I there
my guess is there it may not be quite
ready for the release mode builds yet
for whatever reason again I'm gonna try
and put together a big list of things to
send to George's like here's all the
things I noticed so that's one the nice
part about that is if it repros in
handmade hero it's pretty easy to point
him at it just be like here's handmade
hero
go nuts and so hopefully that's
something that can get straightened out
pretty easily so let's go ahead and
continue on just with this a little bit
more so it works the same way as you
would expect in terms of being organized
or Windows which is nice the only
difference is like for some reason
memory and registers are not enabled by
default probably because they're not
enabled by default in Visual Studio and
he was trying to clone that experience
which is great by the way giving people
what they expect is really good because
it just eases their transition but
obviously I'm gonna want those
so I turn all those on first of all and
then these things can be peeled around
exactly as you would expect so basically
like you know you can gather things up
if you want to and they just create
little tabs exactly as you would expect
right and so now it's just a question of
well how do I want to make this window
arrangement work and one of the things
that I actually like that he did here is
he doesn't use mixed mode assembly and
source which is what videos show you
does he does a separate disassembly
window and source window so as you step
through you can see both of them
together
I do actually prefer this that's windbg
style so that's the way windbg works
Visual Studio meant to be work
differently the reason I like that
better is because most of the time if
I'm stepping through the disassembly for
anything serious if I'm stepping to
disassembly just because there's some
weird thing I wanted to look at real
quick then it doesn't matter I don't
care which one I have but if I'm
stepping to disassembly because
something is actually important usually
I'm in and I'm gonna look at it for a
while
usually I'm in release mode because the
disassembly for debug mode is usually
irrelevant right it's it's storing the
stack all the time like you wouldn't
really be looking at this assembly
because it's garbage so it's only if
there's some weird compiler bug you need
to track down or something right you're
usually not really looking at the
disassembly so if I'm looking this is it
the assembly I'm usually gonna be in
release mode and in release mode the
correspondence of the disassembly with
the source is pretty bad like it's
usually not very good and so I don't
really like having it intermix with the
source because it makes it harder to
read actually so I want to be able to
see them both but I don't really want
them interleaved because usually it's
not prepped it's not actually correct it
doesn't actually add to the information
it detraction it so having them both is
great so I can be like okay I see it
thinks I'm roughly around here although
I'm not really you know exactly there
now let's look at the disassembly that
actually works quite well for me like I
like that
and so
I actually agree with this decision and
and I would say stick with that right
okay so let's go ahead and organize our
windows as you know I kind of like to
have the watch window on the side so I'm
going to go ahead and you know sort of
peel over here the watch window and I
don't know exactly how I want this stuff
organized we'll kind of see in a second
but we're gonna want something like this
so I'm gonna want the watch window up
there and I'm probably going to want
things like modules and threads and all
that stuff into a separate window over
here on this side and I'll try to put
the least you know normally I would use
this slot I can't because my head's
there when we're doing a streaming so
that makes it a little harder to
organize but we'll get by right and so
I'm gonna go ahead and put the
breakpoints window over here as well and
I'm going to put the call stack over
here and probably the threads as well
and I usually need to be able to see the
call sack in the threads at the same
time so I might try to do something
where like the call stack is like over
here right and the threads are over here
maybe something like that I'm not sure
right but something like that probably
so anyway the output in the disassembly
can probably go here together registers
probably wants to be over here as well
so we can switch to that I don't know
it's hard to say memory can probably go
over here somewhere
let's say there and modules can probably
go up there as well because these are
things that we use less frequently so
that that's all fine again
don't know if this is really the
organization I'll use but something like
this is probably what we want so that's
all and as you would expect everything
else seemed to work pretty good so up
here you know I can do button and index
and and see it it's pretty pretty good
right it just does exactly what
expect compound types seem to work quite
nicely so a new keyboard controller if I
want to look at it it seemed like I
could look at things just just fine all
of that seemed to be fine and it seemed
like I could step through them and so on
so a couple things I'm not sure about I
don't know if it has the same kind of
problems as Visual Studio like for
example if you're inside a block and you
want to look at something let me see if
I can get to a block that has some local
variables in it that are relevant so
yeah let's see I guess this is fine yeah
weird really just not we need it okay
so audio wall clock would be an example
Frank audio wall clock so if I want to
look at audio wall clock you know here
it is and once it goes out of scope I
want to keep looking at it which in
debug mode is very easy because it's
still in the stack in the same place so
it should be easy to look at and so it
looks like that so that's another thing
I should really be writing this down you
know in fact I'm gonna go ahead and do
that let me just go ahead and and start
a little list here on my other machine
type on the right keyboard if you want
it to actually work so I'm gonna go
ahead and start a list here to George so
that he can get
so okay so far we've found release mode
breakpoints seems body and stuff that
just went out of scope isn't visible
anymore
again that's exactly the same as Visual
Studio so not a reason not to switch
because you have that problem in your
case it's just something that I know can
be done better and so now that there's a
debugger that looks like it's going to
be better it'd be a great feature to
have right
very very nice so anyway as we come
through here I like I said don't think
there's that much to look at I mean just
kind of works exactly like Visual Studio
and there's not really much else you
need to know let's try to set a
breakpoint somewhere I don't know where
we want to set a breakpoint let's look
at some other code in here if I just
open up some code randomly that we've
got um maybe we want to look at some of
entity code let's say you know cuz we
were looking at some of that stuff so
maybe we want to set a breakpoint right
here let's say can I run there yes I can
everything looks good also I would
notice I would point out the
responsiveness of this thing is great
it's not like Visual Studio where you
hit the step button and you can look at
your watch and and you know go get a cup
of tea before it finishes updating like
the watch window it's like right away
which is really nice so again really
nice work on that just demonstrating
what we know to be what we already knew
to be true which is that these things
don't have to be slow it's only if it's
visual studio that's slow so one thing I
would point out is there probably should
be a keyboard shortcut for expanding
this stuff and there doesn't seem to be
so I'm gonna add that to the list as
well so let's say keyboard expand
collapse of
window compounds I don't know what it
should be but like right arrow or return
or something and so stepping through
here yeah again like looking at some of
this stuff you can see it I want to see
how it gets updated and and just make
sure that that seems to working so let's
say I open up match vector oops this
helps if I type it correctly
well I can't how do I edit that or can I
not edit that because that would be
another thing that yeah so it doesn't
look like I can change these maybe I can
only delete them so I feel like they
should be editable so let me go ahead
and add that
and once I've got one of those in here
let's see if I open one it's fairly
large here so there we go
here we're gonna that's supposed to
clear and it did that's good and then
we've got one of them that's gonna get
set although it may be getting set to
[Music]
let's see entity facing direction can I
inspect a particular one so it looks
like it's kind of hard to inspect
variables there like I say entity facing
direction but it doesn't know how to do
that dear F maybe so I think maybe he
doesn't have a parser yet in here so
that's another thing that would have to
go in there um unless I'm wrong about
that you see here T facing Direction so
that's zero that's why it didn't show up
in there
so the weight vector let's see if that
gets updated properly oops again so not
be able to edit this is tough because I
misspell things too often but that
shouldn't be very hard to add I wouldn't
think alright so let's see if this
updates to one yeah it did so I think
that's all good so I'll put in there
what do we want to say there that like D
references after work
so like any and also changed values
should be something like that so I think
that's most of what we would be doing in
here
all that seems fine what I will say is
this stack window looks a lot better
than the visual studio stack window like
you get all those nice parameters in
there I think you can turn off some of
that on a visual studio but I don't
think it's quite as complete the module
name I'm gonna kind of get rid of here a
little bit more because we don't really
need that and since my head is blocking
too much of the screen I think we'll
just leave it like that so we can kind
of see but that's kind of nice you know
that you get all of those on there what
I will say is that they it does make it
so that it's a little bit difficult to
see all of the things that you like if
you just want to see the stack more
concisely it might be nice if you could
turn that off so I don't think there's
any setting for that but that would be a
nice thing
let's see breakpoints still seem pretty
good I don't know so I guess like I
guess what I would say is I suspect that
at the moment there's no hardware
breakpoints and that will probably have
to get added I don't tend to rely on
hardware breakpoints very often I can
tell ahead of time to that this is
probably gonna have to go up here cuz I
can't see it there um get me get me all
my registers yeah yeah I can kind of
tell that that the breakpoint stuff
needs to get more robust to again
probably like I said this is early so
it's probably just not at the top of his
list but basically like data breakpoints
and conditional breakpoints at some
point you got to get those in there
because for you know more tricky for
more difficult scenarios you start to
have to have like stuff for that right
it's nice it's by the way it's nice that
these are separate first step into
instruction and step over instruction
versus line all right so I think I've
got a nice healthy set of things here I
would say probably the other thing that
I suspect that it doesn't do at the
moment that we're gonna need it to do is
casting so like in here right where we
say something like what's a good example
so traversable index is oops well that's
not where we are so let's say we were
here
although it looks like I'm never going
to quite get there how do I don't
actually know how to unset that
breakpoint
ah
well that's interesting so for some
reason it treats this breakpoint as
occurring here that seems a little off I
think there's something off about the
pvb person there Oh duh it's cousin if
zero block I'm gonna be it let's try
this there we go
yeah sorry George that's my fault
alright so in here if I look at color
and I you know let's say want to look at
this as a this x value here if I want to
well I guess I can't really do it but
let's say I want to look at that as an
array of integers or something you know
I'm assuming that you can't put
expressions in here yeah so basically
like this for the same reason you can't
look at like entity era P which you know
we'd kind of need to be able to do or
like in any facing direction was the one
I tried right it's gonna need to be able
to parse those expressions and give you
something for a limited set of
expressions right doesn't need to be
able to do every single one but that's
relatively tricky because you know the
types that can go in here are the types
of the programs you have to be able to
get those out of the PDB and all that
sort of stuff so that's that's pretty
that's a pretty big one
they'll have to happen at some point so
let's see expressions in watch window
forecasting listening arrays so that one
kind of needs to go a little further and
I guess I don't know memory window so
some of these things have right-click
menus so this one had one there right in
the memory window it looks the same so
you can sort of I don't know what oh I
see so if I
oh it's double-click does that work in
here too no
so that's kind of nice that you can set
the number of columns it looks like you
can sort of have some nice highlighting
there that's kind of nice too what's hex
II don't actually think I know what hex
he is
well let's see if we can find out is
hexie just a ski if it's a ski in hex if
it's not like a ski if it's a normal
letter and hex if it's not maybe
otherwise I'm not sure what that is so
for the memory window I don't know
exactly how to how it works let's try it
so let's suppose I put entity in here
okay so it looks like it only does
addresses so maybe you have to do so if
to type the address manually 2 6 2 1 2 3
a 9 5 8 ok I see so basically well I'll
be honest I don't really know what hexie
is still I guess it's sort of the thing
that I was thinking of it shows the
letters if they are letters otherwise it
doesn't yeah ok so I would say this
thing kind of needs to oh I like that
though I would say this thing also kind
of needs to be able to have an easier
way of getting stuff in here because at
the moment like if I wanted to cut and
paste into there how would I get the
value right because I can't I can't copy
this like there's no way to actually get
that value in here right so they're kind
of needs to be ways to you know like
edit those values like
um trying to think of anything else we
haven't really put through its paces oh
and I forgot to put into here to the
like thread window should use last
symbol names found so you can see which
is which and that I think maybe that
this is not zero zero one zero
[Music]
so I think that maybe just about it
and so yeah like looking at it and just
playing around with it a bit I think
it's not quite ready because of just
some of those things like the I would
say the breakpoints in release mode need
to get more stable and then this window
needs to work with expressions more
that's most of it maybe some way to pick
the threads better but that's mostly it
a lot of the other stuff I listed there
are things that I would be okay without
like I could get by and not having to
install video visual studio would be
enough for me like that I would easily
make that trade so I think this isn't
pretty good shape look I'm pretty
optimistic that this would be easy to
replace visual studio with for most of
the things I do without that much more
stuff that needs to happen so that's
pretty encouraging really nice work on
that George that's coming along really
nicely it seems pretty stable hasn't
crashed on me or anything here which is
good you know you don't want your
debugger adding to your debug woes and
everything else seems pretty good so I
think we've got a good list there to
send him and I say we could just call
that a win and we could probably use
this a little bit too for handmade hero
the watch window would really be the
major blocking factor and maybe those
release my breakpoints but but a lot of
times we step with the bugger we compile
in debug mode so I'm not sure that would
matter very much so it would really
mostly be the fact that the watchman is
a little harder to use because they
can't handle those expressions I think
we got expressions in here I think we
would pretty much be good to go I think
that would pretty much do it for us all
right so that's pretty encouraging we've
already got our own editor handmade and
now it looks like we're gonna have our
own handmade debugger too
it's looking pretty good we even have
our own handmade drawing package we just
need to make a handmade compiler I guess
well I guess we need a handmade
operating system too but you know what
can you do
alright so thanks very much George for
all of that hard work there it looks
great we'll send off this list of
feedback hopefully some of the more
pressing ones aren't too hard to add I
don't really know the expression when
the watch window part I mean the nice
thing about that is you can sort of hack
in the you know the basic stuff so just
like basic casting and basic
dereferencing that's most of it right
you don't have to go down a huge rabbit
hole to make some super elaborate
expression parsing blah blah blah right
and so I guess what I would say there is
that like you know maybe starting off
something simple that just gets us
enough so that we can switch then later
you know you can spend the time and do
some more elaborate you know real
expression parsing and do all kinds of
fancy stuff so I'll go ahead and send
that off to George little later I want
to go ahead and polish up that email
it's kind of just little jot down things
as I thought of them and off to clean it
up a little bit but yeah all right so
that's great I'm pretty happy about that
if you're interested in in that debugger
again if you want to purchase a copy
yourself you can into Google type remedy
BG and then hit return that will bring
up this page which is the page on
handmade Network for it which does have
the forums again this is the purchase
link so you can go buy it here and then
again for giving feedback this is the
place so the forums you can go here and
start threads Nicholas Lindbergh also
looks like he was working on it here
he's already got some in fact here's the
I'm GUI ima one that we were talking
about so that's
yeah that's just another like kind of
good example of people already starting
to find these things
so yeah pick up a copy of that find bugs
make suggestions send them back here and
George this should not be free there's a
lot of work that went into this charge
something for it alright so let's go do
some regular programming today cuz I
feel like you know we might as well try
to get our feet wet a little bit here if
I remember correctly we had like an hour
the the streams that we were working on
just before we left for winter break we
kind of gone through here and we had
gone through all of the github issues
that we've had and we try to like you
know clean them up as best we can get
rid of bugs that we we knew we could fix
and so on right and so we've got a few
more in here Martin Smith Zico as he
always does fine stuff for us as well
and so there's a new one here that he
opened Kim was trying to get things
working on Mac but Mac OpenGL is so poor
at this point I don't think it's ever
going to I think we're gonna have to do
a metal version for Mac so I don't know
how much we really care about some of
these OpenGL problems because like I
said OpenGL is kind of not OpenGL can I
think are kind of dead I think that's
just forget about them so we're probably
gonna have to do a metal D 3d thing at
some point which won't be that hard
we've got our render completely isolated
so switching over to a different back
you know backing API is not the end of
the world
so anyway a couple of things that we do
want to do though is I think we want to
talk about the the Downloads the the
different ways that the send all
downloads work now because I basically
went in have the hhas so that they can
be exploited directly now and you don't
have to worry about that so much anymore
and so what I wanted to do as a very
first very simple thing is change the
readme file because now it's out of date
and it doesn't actually refer to what's
going on so you can see here
we have lung that basically says you
know how things are going and then we
need to say here how this stuff should
be set up now this test assets zip
doesn't really get impacted unpacked in
there so we kind of need to talk about
this a little bit more specifically so
we don't need to build the asset pack
files anymore so what we need to say
instead and we also need to change this
right let's see right so that's supposed
to look like this so we just want to say
look you've gotta have the art files in
there so I think that's all good and
what we need to now do is describe step
3 which is like how you set these up so
so in step three we want to describe how
you unpack this stuff so that you know
people can do that and what you really
need in here in the data directory right
is you just need these hhhh a's right
you just need that and all of those are
already exported so you just need those
and then inside the art director i guess
we're gonna need a step for that you
want to put these PNG x' right but i
think so
there's a couple different things to do
here and we're a little bit premature on
this it might be nice to go ahead and
push to get ourselves to a place where
we just rebuild from PNG s 100%
correctly and then we just distribute
the PNG x' and off we go
right and so you know that way you can
do a full art builds pretty easily just
by you know letting the game import
everything or you know whatever that
sort of thing so you know maybe we want
to push towards that a little bit and
say something more like this so in here
we would just say okay let me actually
also look while we're at it I'm gonna
look at what Sun Devil actually has for
us here because I don't actually know
the answer to that question but I would
like to basically I would like to get it
to the point where it's easier for new
people to come on board because we
haven't really done that in a while
and as we are wrapping up engine stuff
and moving towards gameplay stuff
there's probably people who might come
along and want to follow along with that
who haven't follow along with the rest
and it's just if you haven't been
following along you can't really build
the game because we haven't done any
work to make that happen it assumes you
followed us the whole way right if you
want to build the art assets the code
can always be built but the art assets
are like a different story so let me go
ahead and and like just take a look at
the send owl-like downloads here where
is that so Oh Linux multiple desktops
you can't see right now thankfully me
struggling with Linux multiple desktops
which of course I set up and then get
confused by let's see so if I want to go
to my send download
that's gonna be here somewhere
[Music]
and I guess I also have to sign in yeah
and like I said I just kind of want to
know at this point I want to know like
that people can get like up and running
with handmade here and more easily and
so we might just do some work on that
and we also need that anyway because
it's nice to just clean up the art path
there and make sure that that everything
is you know is buttoned up we had some
things we wanted to do there if you
remember correctly we kind of wanted to
make it so that like the mark-up was in
text files and so on okay so let me see
if I can get back to their orders let's
see let's go to the download URL so
currently we've got handmade Hiro latest
art and data and handmade Hiro latest
source code delete a source code just
builds out of the box fern and as far as
I know the latest art and data when you
download it I'm just gonna take a look
at what exactly is in there and make
sure that we refer to it a little bit
more cleanly so we'll get that going but
yeah I think what we want to do then
let's just say that what our goal is
gonna be for the next couple weekends is
to get ourselves completely clean
rebuilding and I'll post a new set of
PNG s where you basically just you just
download a zip of the PNG s that's all
of that and then that will just build
right and what we can do is we can
export those text files like I was
saying that have the markup for things
in them we'd want to do that anyway we
can just lean on that as a system that
allows us to augment the PNG s with what
we need and then everyone can rebuild
them so at the moment it looks like we
supplied the exact art and data files so
okay so this is easier than I thought
so for the time being though what we'll
say is
of the handmade latest art and data zip
must go into the W and made arts and
video and made data directories
right
so that looks good you know can we also
while we're in here talk about how to
unpack the code so if I download the
source code that has like you know a zip
file in it code - yeah so you know what
[Music]
maybe we can talk about this a little
bit differently maybe we can simplify
this a little bit so maybe we say look
the way directories you can try out
through the video first
unpack the and made hero day
you know what is this called go start in
data how's this and so inside that
handmade hero source directory just
looking at that as well so there's like
a bunch of other things in there as well
and we don't really care about those
necessarily so I won't go out of my way
to describe those but so we can say look
unpack one of the sources it's in here
that looks fine battle looks fine to
build the game you know you're gonna
need this installed and you can build it
and run build that bat and that will
build it into W builds and then I run
the game all this stuff is correct right
you have to be in the handmade directory
and then you have to run the executable
that all looks right all right so let's
just leave that for now and then
eventually I think we can probably
simplify things down a little bit by
making it so that you don't actually
have to deal with this directory anymore
you'll just unpack pngs and it'll build
the HSAs automatically into the data
directory as necessary um that seems
fine and so yeah I think that's all good
I think that's all good that way people
don't have to worry about the asset
build at all now and hopefully that'll
just be a little bit clearer for them uh
so anyway let's talk a little bit more
about getting this the PNG stuff set up
kind of more the way that I would prefer
because we've kind of gotten almost all
the way there and we might as well just
finish up right all right let me switch
this back yeah so that's all good and
now we're happy and everyone is shiny
and happy and smiling alright so what I
want to do now is just take a look at
the way this is working so you know if
we run things and we think about how
this is going and by the way this is
kind of nice so Visual Studio we may not
have to deal with us very much longer
that debugger was looking pretty close I
don't want to get too excited because
you know maybe it just won't work out
but you know I'd like to get to the to
the point I wanted
I'd like to get to the point where we
could get rid of it and that would be
just really exciting so you know I'm
hoping I'm really hoping but you know
we'll see so anyway let's let's go ahead
and talk about some stuff that we want
to do here I'm gonna go ahead and set
this back to optimized build for now so
anyway if we go ahead and run the code
at the moment and we just think about
what's going on if you look at the
current situation we have a couple
things that are like I think pretty
important for us to to just address
before we actually go start learning a
ton of game stuff in here
one is the lighting which is that our
lighting just kind of needs to be
probably simplified a little and you
know like right now we even have the
volume set to be too small so you can
see that it doesn't even cover
everything that you can possibly zoom
out to see you can see our lighting
boundary there and so I think we need to
kind of simplify our lighting to not be
quite so aggressive as it is and you
know because we were doing kind of full
like a global illumination and we maybe
need to back off to something that's a
little bit more representational just
because you know we did what we could so
we want to be able to to make it so that
that runs nice and fast and is this
largest
the visible region is always and then
the other thing that we want to do like
I said is address the problem with the
art assets right now which is that we
kinda just haven't quite finished that
process of of storing the metadata in
text files that can be regenerated and
so what I'd like to do is focus on that
part I think mostly let's get that part
straightened out and then let's go
simplify our lighting and then let's
call it a day
because I don't know that there's very
much else maybe there's one thing we
should do which is sound because we have
our sound in sort of a half-baked state
let's finish that out and then I think
we can call the engine done because I
mean we're pretty close right we can we
can make a list of things right now but
it's looking like you know you could
build a game with this pretty easily
we should also reenable our sprite
sorting stuff so like that doesn't
happen anymore with the clipping that we
remember or we have Z bias in there to
fix that it's turned off right now so
you know a couple quick things I think
we do have a couple days of solid work
to do
but we're looking really good coming
back from winter break it's pretty
exciting I mean this is an engine we
built entirely ourselves fully streaming
dynamic lighting infinite size worlds
effectively no loading screens like I
don't know man
like Pat yourselves on the back if you
followed us this far because we've done
like an entire engine from scratch
for realz no joke not a single library
in sight right yeah it's pretty good we
do have to play sine and cosine though
we are still using the C runtime all
right sine and cosine we can't kind
complete victory til sine and cosine are
gone so I don't know looking pretty darn
good I would say and so again just a few
things we want to button up there and
then we can just start focusing on world
building and stuff which will build this
out into a game pretty quickly because
yeah I mean that's mostly what a game is
so anyway I think that's pretty good and
and I'd like to get started on that so
let's start with just the basics here
I would like to go ahead and look into
what its gonna take for us to transition
so basically right now we only have a
way of storing things in hij files I'd
like to go ahead and see what we can do
to transition over to storing things as
sort of textual markup that we can use
and I'd like to separate those out so
one of things I want to do here is say
look inside that handmade directory
we've got art and that I want to
consider as input from the art team so
actually what I'd like to do is not this
right I don't actually want this to be
with the art assets necessarily and the
reason for that is that I would like
those to be separate and so what I think
I might do is start to pull away from
this structure a little bit and make it
so that a data pack is basically two
things it's a set of text files and a
set of PNG files and wav files that go
together and that way we can package up
the text files with the source code and
the PNG s can be shipped separately and
that's just for our purposes because
every night I upload that all the source
code I don't want to re-upload giant
three gigabyte art packs or something
right and so I think that's really you
know mostly the the problem there so I
like to go ahead and do that and push
towards that a little bit much and so
maybe we kind of start to talk about a
slightly different structure that will
occur here and so we've got sort of this
data and those are the HHA files that
come in here and here's the arts and
maybe this wants to look a little bit
more sort of compacted there I'm not
exactly sure how we want to do that
give me a name what do we call these
like source packs it's sort of like you
know pretend you were going to be
shipping and add a mod for handmade hero
what would you call the package you know
it's like a datapack or something like
this but there's two versions of it
there's an HHA which you can just ship
by itself and someone can install it and
play but then if someone wants to edit
that what do you call it what do you
call it folks we need a name we need a
name its source material may be call
them sources and so one of the ideas I
had in here was if we had like you know
sources or whatever right and I make
something here that's like the like base
pack what I was thinking is previously
we sort of had this loose notion and I
didn't really have any way to do it
inside the source code because they
don't really know what to do but before
when we were building things
everything went into the core hij file
right so like you make a local a judge a
file and it would just pack everything
into there but what I was thinking is
what we could do instead is if we have a
directory like sources here then what
that could do is every one of these like
bass or whatever inside here all of your
stuff that you want like you know we
could have our sound
music and you know markup or something
maybe the mark-up goes in the outside
right so inside the sources directory if
we made one of these then you could
imagine other people's doing this which
is like and maybe we even do this just
to make sure that it works right so
you've got sort of these things that are
like sources that you know like this is
the intro cutscene and this is the base
you know game or whatever and when we do
a rebuild each directory inside the
sources directory we would then compile
into an HHA here so we no longer it
would no longer have to think about the
like what goes into the local or it's
like the directory structure on the
drive gets packed individual hhas so
that's easier for people to create their
own additional packs because they just
create the data structure that goes that
the directory structure that goes to
that pack and then it just gets packed
in automatically to one that corresponds
to that directory structure right cuz I
and I was struggling with that I know if
you remember but when we did that I was
like I don't know where should it go I
guess when you create a locally to say
it goes in there
right and so I feel like this would be a
really good way to solve that problem
you know and I just didn't think of it
at the time so it wasn't like I didn't
do it because you know I wanted to do
the other thing first I just didn't
think of it I think this is a much
better way and so if we imagine creating
something that works in this way then I
think we can sort of get ourselves into
that position now one of the things
that's a problem too is that I thought
of that we don't need to do and we can
work around now is if you look at what
happens here the way that I chose to
solve the problem of how to tag things
was by changing the file names but what
I realized is that's not that good
because if the artists want to export
new file names
name things whatever they want and
they're not gonna keep these names right
they're just going to give us a new set
of source files so what we would rather
do is stick that I think this into the
text files right
so when we go into the sources you know
and we look in here the the text files
that would have things like hotspots
we'll just keep the tags in for the
things as well right and so I think
that's all we really need to do a bunch
of busy work there that we're gonna have
to actually do but I think that'll work
quite nicely and so I wish I had kept
the original names on these things and I
may go back and try to find the original
set there too just to see like and in
fact maybe I'll just get that right now
because I think the send owl page still
has those in the old downloads so maybe
we switch back to the old names and we
make the text file do the work right and
again I think that's just a nice way to
to go down that road alright so let me
try that and see if that works
so up here on the download page you know
there's this old legacy files directory
and we've got the legacy art files
download and in that legacy art files
download I think that's got a lot of
that stuff that we would want there and
you know the other thing that I'm
thinking too is we can we can dump that
HHA out into how should I put it into
p.m. geez for the intro art as well and
we can import all those as well I might
not want to do that I might ask Anna to
clean those up for us too because they
were kind of the ones from yangshin
still had like some weird like places
where the Alpha was not what you would
expect and stuff so we might want to
clean those up and because well you know
while we're at it basically
so if I look at the PNG art packs yeah
so I've got the ones with the original
names here the like head body and and
stuff ones yeah so let's just grab those
let's just let's just grab those as well
so I'm going to go ahead and pop over to
this machine put the the thumb drive in
there I'm just going to grab those off
the back and then we can go from there
so let's grab and you can do this at
home too if you're in the mood right
because like I said this is up on the
this is up on the handmade hero download
page so Santa's can be removed that's
good and let's pop back all right so
here's that legacy art file so let's say
we go in here and we go to sources and I
unpack this thing and I say all right
PNG art packs you're going into base
game come on open all right maybe not so
we want to put that into base game art
and if I remember correctly we separated
characters into body and head so we
don't really need this anymore right
those can go and then I'll close this
guy out and so looking at this right
this is the original name for stuff like
that we had in there and you can see
that there's quite a bit of difference
there between that and what we actually
named them to get them tagged properly
which is in here we've got if you look
at our current art directory right you
can see like this is called Black Forest
a one but you know it's not called that
at all I think it's called block floor
grass right and so what we want to do is
preserve Anna's names for these things
right and I think we can do that pretty
easily like I said by just using text
files to describe them and I don't know
exactly how we want to do that but I'm
guessing that
could just it's probably easiest to just
put this in one file I think can you
think of a reason not to I can't really
think of a reason not to
you know the bonus of spamming tons of
text files into the directory because we
could we could do this two ways I'm just
gonna point out what they both are one
way is we have a text file for every PNG
right so basically we would create for
block forest oh one we've created text
filed mirrors block for us so on so we'd
say block Forest a one dot txt and in
there we would put this information so
we would say the block forest oh one has
the block floor and grass tags right in
addition to anything else we want to say
about it the other way is we would just
have a single text file and that text
file would list all of the files that we
want write the bonus of doing one text
file is just easier to work with you can
just open it one text file in your
editor and search for the thing you were
trying to edit right it's it's easier
and quicker
the thing that's harder about it is it
doesn't play as nicely potentially with
say source code control to people making
change at the same time you now have to
like merge those text files together and
so it's hard to say which of those ones
you want to do right since I think
handmade hero is is more of a small team
small focused kind of a project right
it's not a triple-a we have 3,000 people
working on this project like Red Dead
Redemption 2 or something like this
we're literally the amount of time it
takes to watch the credits to Red Dead
Redemption 2 is like longer than it
takes to actually play like the game Red
Dead Redemption 2 because there's just
that many people who worked on it um I
don't know that we really care about
that merge problem
so I think I want to go with a single
text file because that just makes it
easier you know what I mean so let's try
that if we run into problems it's not
that hard to later split it out right
and furthermore we can make our game
load all the text files that are in that
directory and process them so if
somebody did want to make one per thing
they could right so we're certainly not
gonna stop anyone from doing that I just
don't think I'm going to take that tack
so let's see we were going to do that so
let's say inside the handmade directory
we go to the sources here and we say
look there's this base game directory
and here it is and I'm gonna say like
this is like base game dot txt or
whatever right and so it's got you know
information here about what this
actually is and so what I'll do is I'll
incur mention like also a note KC these
are the assets for the base game and you
know base game in game assets the base
game and then we would also have another
one that was intricate scene text and
that would be like these cutscene and in
each of these we just want to list the
pngs this one I can't do yet because we
haven't downloaded pngs for those so we
just want this to occur so what I want
to do is I want to merge this with this
so the way I'm going to do that to make
it a little easier on myself is I'm just
gonna use the command line here because
even though the goths command line is
kind of crappy it still is better than
nothing
it's certainly no Linux command line by
a long shot but still if I go into that
art directory you can see here's all of
the art files that we have right now
with
their names if I want to I can look the
dirt command actually has you can see
here options on controlling how the
output goes so if all I want to do is
just get those names in here I can use
what's called the bear directory listing
which is dira /b and you can see here
hopefully right do you see how it just
lists them all out for me like that and
so if I want to I can do adder /b and I
can dump that into a temp file and so
let me just do temp dot txt there right
and then if I load up that now I just
have this complete list and so what I
can do is start to make the format here
that will describe these and so what I'm
going to do is just make like a simple
format I can use to put the information
in that I wanted to put in about these
and so maybe I say something like you
know there's a maybe I say bitmap or
something like a source bitmap or
something like that I don't know I don't
need to say it's a source something like
this right I guess I don't even really
need an equals there I can just say
here's a source bitmap block for floor
grass right and oh actually guess that's
wrong because this is the handmade art
directory so that's these are actually
the things we want to use for
Association let me back that up a little
so these are actually the things that
we're going to use for Association so
first I actually want to do the other
directory as well so in here let me go
ahead and and kill this buffer let me
look at the other directory so in
sources base game right in here what I
want to do is all of those things in the
art directory
I want those again to be adder /b so it
does that right let me go ahead and put
those intent
temp dot oops temp dot text and so now
if I load those and I just grab this out
these are the ones that were actually
getting sources from so now I can say
all right there's a bitmap source so
load this thing and then I want to say
some stuff about it right and now
remember we've got these this is the
information that we've got for it so far
and so what I want to do is kind of grab
that stuff out and put that in here in
some meaningful way now we're gonna have
our work cut out for us because this
file needs to be able to be resaved and
all sorts of other stuff as well
so there's gonna be trickiness here
certainly as we kind of go forward but
that's just how things are going to go
uh so here's our block floor grass we
know that that is what we want to put in
here so this is basically the tags for
this thing so how we want to specify
this I don't necessarily know but we can
just do it probably something like this
right and that's really it so we might
want other things in here as sort of a
separate piece of information eventually
I don't actually know but we can kind of
look at that as we as we go further so
we've got three other things in here and
we can do all those as well so here's
another source right and you know maybe
we should have named this the problem is
this it's not for coder doesn't know
that this is a code based file so it's
not gonna try and do anything to help us
here with how this works but that may be
fine but we may want to actually also
maybe we want this text file to actually
be labeled with something else so that
syntax highlighting and something can be
kickin so maybe it shouldn't be based
game dot text I don't know that's kind
of a question going forwards how we want
to deal with that so anyway if I take
this a little bit more seriously here so
going forwards let's look at what block
Orphanage oh one actually
was so black orphanage oh one is I think
this yeah so block wall man-made wood
drywall is this one and so those are the
tags that wrong here right and then in
here we've got some other ones and so on
now one of the things that I'm not sure
about is does this actually just want to
be called block and so right because we
kind of have this notion of that their
sources block body character cover hand
head right so I don't know if maybe do
these want to be that way like does this
want to just be this probably I think it
might want to be so because the type is
kind of special right and the tags are
not as special they're matching things
they don't affect the processing really
these are just for information so that
when the game wants to go grab assets it
uses those this is actually like how the
asset is loaded and processed and so I
think I want that to be more specific
right so orphanage two and three we had
in here these two so it's the wood in
the stone so too is the wood and three
is the stone right - is the wood three
of us now
uh so again just copy those in here like
so and we don't need block anymore
because it knows that from the type same
here
so I think that that seems pretty good
to me right I think we can just use that
and that way we keep the filenames the
same we can put all the markup in here
that we need so any other stuff that we
need to put in here it'll just work yeah
I don't I don't see much trouble with
that seems pretty easy pretty easy right
so we have orphan bodies here and we're
gonna have to figure out which all these
are because I don't remember what they
all are right so we'll have to do that
and then we've got the Oh looks like I
may be deleted these a little too soon
oh no I didn't I left them in place
somehow I was smart enough to not delete
those but I so I guess I was smart
enough to only delete the orphan but the
character ones alright great
it's always nice to be smarter than you
thought you were because often times
you're dumber than you thought you were
so it's kind of the rare occurrence all
right so let's see let's continue down
this path let's get all these merged and
saved off into a file and then we'll
parse the file probably won't have time
that today we'll start on that tomorrow
and then we also have some work to do
with exporting the existing markup that
we have which we didn't really do very
much of but we probably want to do that
as well okay so we've got the rest of
these guys in here I'm just going to go
ahead and do the basic sort of getting
them started and then we'll try to
figure out who's who because I don't
really remember which is a bit of an
issue I admit that I apologize but we'll
just have to do it manually sometimes
well not sometimes there's a lot of
times there's a bit of grind to game
development because you don't ever get
things right the first time in fact you
rarely do and so you have to be willing
to kind of go back and and redo things
when there
you know a better way to do them we
don't need a character template in here
by the way obviously because that's just
a lineup thing that we exported so we
could be reference it uh so we've got
ground cover in here let's see I guess I
can just kind of cut and paste this in
here as well you get all of those in
there and all these in there and now
these are all the later part right this
is the part that we were looking at in
the X portion of things right so that's
just here and so these are just now for
our advisement okay so going forwards
also let me while I'm at it let me
finish this part here so let's put this
in there oops those are not hands those
are heads in there so those are all the
heads of all the orphans and finally the
miscellaneous stuff at the end so here
we've got the title screen which
honestly the title screen
I think should probably go with the
intro stuff so I don't really think the
title screen should be in here so I
might suggest that we move that over
into here instead right
now this for stuff like the title screen
we have an import path for those that's
a little bit different
it goes through like just kind of an
arbitrary bitmap path
so I don't know what to call those
exactly maybe a plate I'm not sure but
they're kind of like they're their own
thing so let's think about those we
maybe already had a name for him so
we'll look and see so we got items in
here and then obstacles in here and
again I don't really know if the word
obstacles they're an item and head and
cover and stuff I don't know if those
are all correct they might be they might
not be we got to go look at the importer
and see what it wants to do
but again the files here kind of tell us
so we did use oh and in fact we did use
the word plate so I was right about that
I guess my intuition works the same in
both cases so if we kind of look at all
of what these are here now we just have
to kind of figure out which one goes
with which so some of these are easier
than others obviously in here we've got
like Fred Hannah and and Molly those are
our cat characters and also Krampus so
those we can just use directly so cat
Berman ghost is Hannah and so the tags
on that artist cat Berman and ghost and
then the brown tabby is Fred's
so that's pretty straightforward as well
the gray tabby gives Molly who you saw
on stream if you saw the four coder
streams there we go
by the way I guess I forgot to put the
semicolon there now why I put the
semicolon in I'm not sure just because I
think I like to have things with
semicolons at the end of them having
been a C programmer my entire life
but yeah so anyway coming back here
we've got Krampus which doesn't have any
tags besides just Krampus apparently so
those are all good and then we've got
yes some of these are pretty easy
probably so we just have hat one two
those look like they weren't tagged so
we don't really need to put any tags on
these at all I don't think because we
never tagged them and forest an
orphanage ossicles we didn't tag we
didn't tag the title screen the
templates obviously aren't relevant the
cover never got tagged so we're really
talking just about these here so now we
just kind of need to go look these up
let's do the characters first they
probably are the easiest so we've got
skeleton skeleton broken skillets and
dark and mummy so I'm assuming that this
is wrapped that this is dark that this
is broken
and this is that ones there right and so
those are pretty straightforward because
they just happened to map directly and
like I said those are easier than the
characters which we kind of named weird
things and you know who knows
oops that and so here we go with this
and done now for hands I we've got fire
glove and skeleton so I'm assuming that
fire is this one I'm assuming that bones
is this one and that fingers is this one
so I think we can just do tags Undead
bones dark and here we can do tags
why didn't that's weird
shouldn't this be glove oh it's not a
glove right never mind
it's just our hand that doesn't have a
glove so I take it back it's not a glove
right so I think this should all be
lined up now properly and so we're just
down to orphans now and so those are the
annoying ones because like I said
they're kind of kind of random so body
orphan here oh that's easier cuz we know
which one's the hero since they're kind
of special so that would go in here and
that's that's easier so this is tags
this is an orphan hero and then we've
also got the head orphan hero so you
know that should be it will be tagged as
well so that's good and now we need to
correspond these ones that are more
difficult right oh wait no it's one more
we can do which is baby so oh no we
can't we have to actually look that one
up alright so we just need to correspond
these now and make these tagged properly
and so
if I go in here and look at which ones
are which but you can see like one two
three four whatever I need to correspond
to those now to these so I have to look
for example head orphan one I have to
look at where which head that was so
here's the head orphans and we can just
go oh you know what I could probably do
is sort by size so if I sort by size
these will probably line up because the
sizes are going to only line up right so
if I go here and I scan down to the
first time that I see one of the
characters right character here oh I'm
assuming that then I will get that same
thing although oh wait character hero is
not supposed to be there that's a
mistake
right because character hero is should
have been deleted it's gonna be inside
head hero
so that's that's actually wrong did I
delete so I deleted almost all the
correct character files but I missed one
there we go alright so block tweet we
know these correspondences so we get
down here to body orphan hero body hero
we already did that one so now let's
scan down for the next one head orphan
hero we already did that one as well
head hero so then we've got head orphan
Lambert and head orphan Oh - now they
should be the same and they are right so
that's good so OH - is Lambert
so head orphan Lambert's so I guess the
only real tags here are orphan , Lambert
and those are gonna be the same on the
body
I would assume right because it's just
body oh wait no the bodies are just
completely different we decided bodies
don't go with heads anymore all right so
that's Oh - we've got character we don't
need to know
we've got head orphan Oh six so head
orphan oh six is climb we then have head
orphan Sonny why do these not shouldn't
those line up differently where is
locked floor man-made stone why isn't
that oh how are those slightly different
sizes is that creepy I guess we we saved
it from and it changed the size at
some point that was interesting alright
so head orphan oh one is Sonny what do
we got next Cassidy is Oh for
then we got Carla right
Oh three and then we got head orphan oh
five wait why do say five now oh nine is
Brahm yeah good
so then twelve is oh but that's body but
that's okay we can start doing bodies
now so body orphan tank is twelve so
this is tags equals four Fionn tank I
think right then orphan strength is
ninety four so oh six strength almost
there
then we've got head orphan drew that's a
five
and then we've got a bunch of bodies so
we've got earth which is a one go we've
got Giles who is seven
we've got Dylan who is 12
Taylor that's the body of o2 right let's
see this isn't taking as long as I'd
feared it's a little dry but it's fine
Rhoda it's 13 assume I spelled that
right yeah body orphan dark so that's
our five and Viva is 11
and Slade is eight so I was right there
why did I leave Oh No
but I already filled one in I got braum
wrong how did I do that
it was owned nine right I put it into
eight that was mistake
plus to be there I think slate is
spelled that way right
did I not guess I did okay where is
slate come back here
here we go
okay so then we've got fauna orphan four
and what else
cook body
he's our three so I'm not sure why some
of these are three tab it's like I just
for some reason indented some things
three yeah
so we're mostly bodies left looks like
we've got almost all the heads we're
missing two heads we've got a fair bit
of bodies left to go here alright so
let's see body or from cook angle
stringers hand body orphan fall so
that's 11
so that's tags orphan floats orphan
fall-spring is nine and I should do just
copy that because I'm going to use it so
seven is winter speed is fourteen oops I
said I was going to use it and I didn't
and summer thirteen
we've got Laird at 14 and baby is 10 and
health is 8 all right I think we're
almost done let's see yep I think we're
basically done so then all we've got is
10 is baby this
and it looks like for some reason we
didn't put the hero Oh was character
here that shouldn't have been in there
so I think we've got everything now I
think that's it so that's the entire
markup that associates all the tags with
the correct pngs right and for the intro
cutscene again we're gonna have to put a
bunch more plate files in here as sort
of once we actually get those p.m. G's
in but you know for now we can ignore
that so if we've got those two and we
kind of come back here so now we can see
if we look at the handmade sources
directory we can go to the base game
right it's got this text file the
scissor that's in there we've got three
directories we can put our stuff into
that we want and this title screen I'm
basically saying should should get out
of here
right so that should actually go into
the intro cutscene directory like so
right and this way now what we can do
when we ship the source stuff we upload
the send al can just be a pack of this
source directory here and then people
can download that and use it but we can
also like I said keep the txt files
instead of packing those up we can put
those into a different directory right
now I don't know exactly how we want
that to go there's another way we could
do it right which is that instead of
putting those here in we could basically
say like oh the handmade sources
directory there's a like the txt files
actually goes somewhere else completely
so that they don't overlap so the
sources directory only includes this
stuff and like bass game text and an
intro cutscene text are elsewhere but I
don't feel like we probably want to do
that even though that's a little bit
easier for us to package up every time
you want to upload to send out it
actually not how you would want probably
it for editing when you're actually just
making the game data you know what I
mean I would assume or maybe you do I
don't know maybe because the text files
are edited separately maybe they should
be somewhere else I'm not sure
hmm that's a good question do I like
this better
so I don't really know that's parts a
little bit trickier and like I said the
problem with it is just that you know
you want these text files to be things
that are that we can change and not have
to redistribute the art files on sundown
again because you know they're pretty
big right you look at how much is in
this based game directory right and it's
like 60 megabytes and so we don't really
want to redistribute 60 megabytes of
pings every time we make one change to
the base game text file which is you
know 4k because that can just be packed
up and put in there so you know what I
think I am gonna go and get ahead and do
that just to make it a little bit easier
what I guess I'll do is say okay if we
go out to handmade let's say that these
go somewhere else here and then they can
get checked into source code control as
well and so maybe you know we have
something here that's like markup or
whatever right you know or tags so that
way we have a source is in a tags
directory and this and they're separate
right and that way this can just get get
checked into source code control and
this sources directory can be
distributed as the separate thing that
you download so everything else gets
packed up every day but the sources
don't because they're just too big you
know what I mean and then we would just
vaporize the art directory right the art
directory just goes away entirely and we
just don't touch that anymore I think
that's pretty good right I also would
say that I don't necessarily know yeah
like what we want to do the day
directory long-term and I guess we just
kind of vaporized all this stuff
eventually as well but we'll see so I
think that's more sane I think that's
how I would like to do it and we've got
a couple things we need to do to make
that happen I don't know where we are on
I think I started so I've got about
seven minutes left I think so I don't
know that I really want to do too much
more today but what we can do is take a
quick look at what we're gonna do when
we when we actually come back and and
tomorrow and start on aren't this stuff
so if I go ahead and and open up the
hand made here our source code and we
look at the sorry not the art we look at
the asset directory I'm sorry the asset
loader source code so like I said before
inside here you know these these art
assets get written back these this right
modifications to HHA part is the thing
that allows to do edits and then those
those things get saved and so what we
need to be able to do in addition here
to the right modifications to HHA file
is we're gonna have to now be able to
maintain this that that text file right
so in here you know when we've got the
[Music]
I'm sorry in here where we've got these
tags that we're putting on there we need
to be able to maintain that file now
there's two ways we can do this one way
we can do it is to write an additional
file so we can actually put in here
instead of ever overwriting our base
game dot text file which is something
that we've edited and set up for the
tags that we want to to apply to each
individual bitmap file that comes in we
can either make something that rewrites
one of these and you know puts the
additional stuff in there or we can make
it so that it outputs a separate one
right and the separate one has the
additional things in it that we've
changed when we do our write
modifications I don't know which of
those we really want to do it seems like
if we're going with a single a single
text file we might want to rewrite it so
it would just rewrite the the one that
we have and go from there so again kind
of tricky and I might say you know and
and so we've got this this notion of
like the alignment points and all that
sort of stuff and it seems like we
probably just want all that stuff to
just go directly in here I mean why not
and so when we do that I think we
probably just
rewrite this file and so in addition to
doing rate modifications to HHA what
we're gonna have to do in here is open
up the the text file the tags file for
this and you know and write that out so
another thing we could do here is say
that you know maybe these files
themselves are called tags files you
know you know we could do that or we
could say like you know make a special
things forgot in HHA this maybe is like
a handmade your a tag file or something
like that which is a different thing you
know what I mean and so that we can
recognize what they actually are as
opposed to saying a text file which
really could be anything
we know that the format is ASCII but
it's not really a text file in the sense
that it's not an arbitrary like a CPP
file is also a text file right but
that's not exactly true so if I go in
here I might want to associate this with
like notepad or something right so that
we can actually look at these you know
like that I don't know didn't I thought
notepad I have to update this Windows 10
machine or try to I thought notepad
wasn't it supposed to be able to handle
UNIX line endings one of these days I
thought that was something they were
adding and I know how to get that but
I'd like it um so anyway I'd like to be
able to to probably rewrite those and so
I think it'll probably start by doing is
we'll make something that imports that
and does the tagging properly so we'll
update our import routine here and then
for the export routine what we'll do is
we'll continue the thing that we had
before where we owe and you know what
that would also give us a place to set
our author right so this we could
actually fix now right remember if we go
into the HHA if we take a look here if
you look at these hhas we have the HHA
edit program and that can give us the
info on one of these things like
you know like this and one of the things
that's in the annotations if we say like
jump one of these guys it tells us a
bunch of things like the descriptions
and who the author was in the case of
some of the newer assets like the local
HHA when we look at those assets what we
can see is that the annotation stuff is
kind of set somewhat haphazardly like
there's an author but there's no
description and so that stuff is also
things that could actually get solved by
those tag files because now we could put
any of that markup that we wanted in
there
we could put so for example in here you
know what we could say is we could say
like global or something like default so
everybody gets this so we could say like
off there is an Arab
right and you know actually
and so that way like the author and
description for these particular assets
can get set to something reasonable so
that if you were going to be looking at
them in the future and you just got this
HHI felling you know idea what it was
supposed to be if you actually looked at
the content of the education file it
would tell you where it came from and
you know that it was art from Anna as
opposed if somebody handed you another
HD file made biases like some buddy out
there whose you know doing some mods dan
made here or something like that and put
together separate HJ file they could put
together all through in description
things and then each one of these could
override the author in description if
you wanted to but of course in most
cases you wouldn't really need to
because most of the time I assume that
the art packs won't be heterogeneous in
that way so I think this is better I
think we should go with this and we'll
implement that tomorrow it won't be that
much of a change it's just a slightly
better system than what we had and then
we could finally call it really done
because then we've got a way of building
everything from scratch anytime we want
and we have a clean distribution model
so we know what we're doing and so I
think like we've done our homework here
we've explored a bunch of options and I
think where you've got something pretty
good let me go ahead and do some Q&amp;A
here
let's switch back here and we'll see so
do we have any questions
when utilizing each scheme you mentioned
to the priest ream the single
inheritance scheme how would you
implement functionality to allow modding
of the game's existing entities and the
code handling them such as a physics
overhaul mod which replaces the physics
system in the game well so there's a
couple different things about that which
I think are semi orthogonal but so in
terms of implementing a modding I don't
really prefer a single inheritance so I
wouldn't use the phrase single
inheritance to say what I was talking
about John usually prefers to do single
inheritance as his way of implementing
just single type entities writes meaning
an entity has a type which his does have
so they happen to be implemented with a
he likes having the compiler generate
the jump table for him don't ask me why
he just does okay his prerogative
you know he's shipped two of the best
games of all time so I'm not gonna argue
with it but I would never really bother
with that part I would just use the type
and then make a dispatch table if that's
what I wanted but you know but either
way they're basically the same design so
if you're using that particular design
and you want to mod it all you do is
when somebody ships the DLL that's the
mod they just say I override the
handling you know in that mod it's got
the table of what functions you provide
you're like oh I provide the handler for
entity type blah and then instead of
calling the existing code for any type
block it calls the mob code for entity
type blah right and furthermore you can
compose those if you want meaning the
system can allow you to dispatch to the
old code if you wanted to right so if
the mod code just wants to do one thing
and then dispatch to the old code for
that entity it can just do that that's
not hard right so again pretty simple
and john would have a slightly harder
time implementing that than I would
because since I use just type and
dispatch table it's easier for me to
work with in his case it would be a
little bit harder because you'd have to
because he's using the virtual function
table he asked to kind of still work
with C++ is broken
inheritance system but he could still do
it right if you asked him to make that
code he wouldn't go oh my god I have no
idea how he'd be like okay sure and he'd
go do something similar to what I just
described but with the inheritance
system right or maybe he would say okay
at that point inheritance isn't a good
idea I'll just use the type the type
same exact thing but the typed way that
case you just described right like maybe
he would switch at that point I don't
know as far as replacing the physics
system physics is a system that runs
outside the entity system right because
it has to handle the interactions of
entities so typically what ends up
happening is you don't have an entity
system that has the physics baked into
it anyway so you're going it's sort of
like asking how do you need to architect
your entity system so the renderer can
be replaced it's like it doesn't really
make sense because physics as a plug-in
architecture if you want to have the
physics solver be a plugin that's fine
because usually what entities do is they
just articulate their rigid body and
continuum dynamics out in some way and
then the physics system runs those steps
typically the only interface that you
see between any system and the physics
system is the articulation of the rigid
bodies so like here's where the things
are going to start and then the
simulation then reports back like we're
what collided and the entity system can
operate on that as a result right but
really you don't the physics system
shouldn't really be baked in the NDA
system no matter what its architecture
if that's probably a bad sign if you're
doing that right so I don't think that's
really part of the question
so what does windbg do better than
visual studios to bugger have you
thought about using it in the interim
between now and when remedy is ready so
when DB G does something's better than
something's worse basically the things
they do worse our workflow related they
have a lot of problems with like hotkeys
not being buying the stuff they don't
hunt for pdb files very effectively
they don't load symbols at the times you
would want them to load them they wait
till they do like delay loading and
stuff so you can't resolve breakpoint
names it's a lot of stuff that they have
problems with and windbg it's better in
terms of the debugger it's a lot more
features it's a lot easier to do stuff
like use like symbol
server or to control how symbols are
being loaded at a finer grained level or
to look at what things are being loaded
and stepping through there and figuring
out how that stuff gets bound you can
also force loading of a PDB to it the
file easily and say I want to use this
PDB even though it doesn't match like
all that stuff just works because it's
got a command line that allows you to do
all that stuff
it's got time travel debugging so if you
want to you can turn on recording and
say oh you know I hit a bug and now I
want to go back in time to like way back
before the bug triggered and see what
happened you could do that it's got the
ability to do like remote debugging a
lot more cleanly and kernel debugging
and all these sorts of stuff it's got
like a lot more Pro features along those
lines there's tons of stuff in the
command line that you can do in terms of
just you know basic debug inspection
stuff you can do things like look at
what the process list is as if it were
like see structures and ask questions
about it and all these sorts of things
so it's just a better architect and
debugger just all around it's just much
better the only problem is it just
doesn't have good workflow and they
don't really seem to be serious about
making the workflow better they sort of
are making servitors I tried to maybe
like post and feedback it didn't really
go particularly well I don't think they
care that much about really actually
making it easy to use and smooth not
shouldn't be easy but fast to use and
smooth it's just they don't seem to get
that yet and so I don't know if they
ever will they might be they maybe they
will if they do it could be useful at
the moment still pretty rough it's a lot
like remedy in that there's some things
that I would just consider I can't quite
switch this yet for windbg but it's
alright you know on this machine I
wouldn't bother because we've already
got Visual Studio and it works just fine
so we you know it's fine I probably just
hold out for remedy
getting a bit fancy here but you think
of me hey enough scope defaults in the
hht so you could have multiple defaults
and a file each of which has its own
scope I mean it might be handy I don't
know that I would really want to bother
but it might be like for example like
you know you might say oh let me make a
tags equals orphan default and then put
all the orphan stuff in there right that
seems totally reasonable you know like
there's two ways you could do that you
could just reset the defaults right here
like this and then later you'd set them
to something else and then you could
delete the orphan from all of these I
don't know if we care about that yet or
not it's not a bad thing I just don't
know if it's really save as much I'm not
averse to a blow though I mean it could
safe that could be useful I don't know
you know you could use the d1 report
time flag for CL to see where the
comparison at the time no actually I
didn't know that is it is it actually
useful
so you're singing just say that oh my
god
okay
I mean I I don't know what to make of
this I guess it's sort of
it's a little much you know what I'm
saying I mean mostly what it tells me is
what I already know which is Windows in
the standard library or complete
disaster and ruin everything including
your compile time I mean most of stuff
on here isn't ours why are we even
seeing things called soap method inside
our compile time which has nothing to do
with that right this is why like in my
actual code base at Mali rocket we don't
allow any includes or libraries at all
period because it's just garbage right
it's just garbage
so really all that does is make me sick
I'm not sure I would want it turned on
very often but yeah like just including
Windows at age 4 including the C runtime
library it's just a disaster you know
it's a disaster it's bad code and it
clogs up everything but yeah that does
seem nice right you know maybe I'll
maybe I'll put that in here if we ever
want to look at it again oops just we
remember the flag because it's a little
bit of a non sequitur just tuck that in
there
but yeah I mean God you just look at how
much crap windows and it's like you know
Microsoft you added a flag to the
compiler to tell me that your code is
crap
right like but I already knew that so
yeah a my as was called that flag -
confirmed the fact that Microsoft's
libraries are crap and I could just
print out yes
like we're done with Q's
all right I think we're good so I'm
gonna go ahead and wrap it up all righty
there we go thank you for um for joining
me for lips on a handmade hero it's been
a pleasure coding with you as always I'm
excited to kind of get this stuff
wrapped up because it'll be kind of nice
to just have everything in a nice little
package any bit like hey look it really
works
if you want to following along with the
code at home obviously and kind of what
we talked about a little bit today in
terms of getting that cleaned up you can
always pre-order the game on handmade
hero Oregon comes with all the source
downloads and those will soon be even
easier to use looks like they're pretty
easy to use right now because I did
upload the latest hij stuff so you can
kind of start where we are today and not
really have any issues and the readme
files we're up to date now so it should
be pretty easy for people to get started
but we'll be making that even better as
we go because I think we can kind of
transition to a pretty clean scheme now
that'll make a lot of sense so anyway
that's it for today I'll be back here
tomorrow when we'll do some of that text
input/output stuff just to get that part
of the pipeline cleaned out and yeah
that should be about it and then we can
move on to maybe we'll just throw sound
in or at it because we kind of got to
clean up the the way that that stuff
gets managed in the memory management
now that we simplified those things
maybe we'll do that before we go finish
the lighting in the homestretch though
people feeling pretty good about it
engines looking pretty pretty sweet
alright hope see you back here tomorrow
till then have fun programming I'll see
you around the internet take it easy
everybody