hello everybody and welcome handmade
hero show recode a complete game live on
stream we are going to pretty much do
some cleanup today and testing where we
left off last weekend was we got
everything working that we were trying
to do with respect to rewriting files
and changing the alignment points in
them and so on but we you know we
haven't really put it through its paces
and there's probably some bugs lurking
there it's kind of subtle what we
decided to do I kind of tried something
a little bit different from what I would
normally have done in that we actually
try to preserve the file the way that
the user wrote it which is kind of a
step beyond what you might ordinarily do
and with that comes some complications
and as a result I'm not really 100% sure
of what we did right it's anytime you
kind of do something new like that
you're always experimenting and you have
to kind of give it a little while to
sink in and you'll probably learn some
things about how the code was structured
that later on you'll be like okay
probably this isn't the best way to do
it you know now that I've done it one
time I would change some things about it
to second time and so on
sooo it's definitely the kind of thing
where I'm like yeah we may you know we
may revisit some of that or you know
maybe we'll leave it as it is if it
works well enough and but I would still
say something like if you were going to
do this now knowing what we know maybe
you do it a little bit differently but
anyway I would like to start off by just
addressing some bugs that were reported
in the github because during the week
sometimes other folks who play around
with the codebase will report bugs into
the github and we can go ahead and fix
those bugs just because hey they've
already been found by somebody we might
as well to do that so I'm gonna go ahead
and this was a clean reboot here they
actually replaced the breakers in the
apartment the other day and so all the
machines powered down nice they had to
be rebooted anyway I if we go ahead and
and just jump into the code here I'm
gonna open up for coder
and try to remember what the old hotkeys
were for everything so if we go to
handmade hero here and I build the
project let's just take a look at the
ones that that Kim had explained before
he said that in the Edit edible boolean
edible size we just really quickly
ported those over to being able to use
regular strings it looks like we forgot
a couple of the capital s is so if we
just jump to editable boolean you could
kind of come down here and see these
things here where we do the format
string when we pass we we made our own
printf so it can take our own types and
if you look here this label text is
coming in as a string and so we want
that to be a capital S so that the for
mastering nose properly had a par set
the other one is apparently editable
size had the same problem and so if we
jump to that function you can see just
looking through here it's the same exact
problem right so there's the label text
and we just need that capital S alright
so again these things were written
before we were using strings so we're
just kind of like moving them over to
the new way of doing things which
because it C isn't perfect you know the
the way that I even even in C the way I
do these now is I just bite the bullet
and have some more kind of expensive
ways of doing things but that don't have
this problem saner languages don't
require you have a format specifier
whatever the type is that you pass
that's the type of the input right so
it's it shouldn't really be possible to
make a mistake like this but C++ is ver
args are horrible and you know as usual
a C++ committee didn't see the need to
improve them over 30 years so that's
where you're at so anyway if we take a
look at the last one you mentioned error
apparently is not calling the correct
thing he's probably talking about yeah
okay this would actually how I don't
know I jump there so this one here he's
saying it needs to pass argh list
I'm not sure I did he make that change I
guess because I'm saying like this looks
like it passed it correctly so I'm
assuming that the one in ours doesn't
look like this because the buggy was
reporting that was that we weren't
passing that and so I'm assuming that oh
you know what no he's just he's just
saying we were calling out arglist and
that's that's 100% correct so we should
actually call that because remember we
had to split those functions up okay so
let me go ahead and jump there and we'll
take a look let's see here that's not
the one we're talking about but this one
is and so we have an out arglist
I believe don't we yes so we have one
that we can call explicitly and you can
see it here and so if I want to I can
call this one explicitly I don't know
that we did a pound to find for it but
it looks like we didn't and so you kind
of need to pass the file name and line
number two out if arglist in order to
make it work and so that would have to
happen here as well now there's a number
of ways like I said before that we can
do this and I'm not sure which one we
really want to do sometimes it can be a
little confusing
if you look at what we're doing here
we're putting the args the error we're
putting that actually into the format
string as a prepend and that's something
that we want to do anyway because we
want to put the value of the token in
there and so that kind of informs our
decision as to what's passed to out FR
list out if arglist takes a file name
and a line number so they can tell you
who is reporting it and so in this case
I think we just want to do this right we
just want to say look we're gonna use
this file name and line number to report
the error here because we're just trying
to talk about ourselves having reported
it we don't really want to pass the
error along the location along from on
token that again is just a judgment call
it's a little weird the way we chose to
do this and so you know we support this
idea of every entry in the buffer being
able to say who put it in there but when
it comes to error messages it's a little
confusing
because again you don't know whether
you're talking about the file name and
line number of the person reporting the
error or the file name and line number
that generated the air and you could
pass either one and there's no right
answer it's just what did you want to do
and what did you want to have available
to the code when it's looking at those
things
anyone who's iterating over the chunks
gets whatever one we decide to pass here
since nobody's really using that
information at this point I mean another
argument will be just get rid of it it's
probably not it's not really something
that we should even have just inserted
in the stream if you want it so again I
don't really know what we want to do
there it's a little bit hazy to me which
way this should go now one way of
thinking of it
alternatively would be to say well what
if you know we were trying to print one
of these outs and you wanted to like
click on it and go to where the error
was that seems to suggest a different
approach right and so you could imagine
us saying you know I'm token filename
and on took and line number maybe those
are things that we should be passing you
know directly here right look maybe we
should be passing those you can click
and jump to that line something like
that and that does have some some merit
to it so another thing I might ask is do
we really you know when when we're
recording these here we're just
recording a founding pointer and again
that's less good because it means we
can't extract regions out of the strings
like we were doing with everything else
and so it kind of again suggests that
maybe these chunks want to be using a
string to remember what the file name
was as well again kind of just a lot
wrapped up in there if I go back to how
tokens were working so if you take a
look at the tokenizer here we have the
token type you can see that the file
name is itself a string right so we
can't really pass this as a null
terminated thing because we've kind of
moved away from those notes or made
things so if we really wanted to do that
in order to pass a file name and line
number here of the error we would need
to actually have out F take strings now
again I don't
really no wrong file I don't really know
how I feel about that one way or the
other a changing this to a string would
make the stream truck slightly larger
not probably in a way we care about
because these are not really heavyweight
operations here we don't really use
these chunks in any time of like
hardcore way so you know it's it's hard
to say right like I again not really
sure so it's kind of one of those things
where I just don't know what we would
want to do here and we could obviously
have a wrapper that wraps this constant
string in a way that would allow us to
still pass it and all that sort of stuff
since I'm so conflicted out all that I'm
just gonna say look we're just gonna
pass this for now and I'll put it to you
in here that says look in the future if
we want to we can change stream chunk to
take strings and then we could pass the
on token filename line here right
because we could and we're not gonna be
bad now but we could and so I think
that's all of the changes that Kim
requested it looks like we've got so
there's an error there cannot convert
argument three to stream star now that's
actually just because I'm calling the
wrong function I said I wanted to call
that and just didn't type it in so now I
have and that should be about it all
right so that's really all there is to
what we're doing at the moment from this
I'm gonna go ahead and close out this
particular issue than just say I think
it should be resolved as of day 519 so I
believe
Dave 5:19 and hopefully that's you know
that'll take care of those to the extent
that there was problems with them we
must just not have hit those because we
you know hadn't tested it or something
right
so in here it looks like most of these
are things are not super important
they're not relevant to what we're doing
right now and this test asset builder is
probably never gonna get updated so
we'll probably end up closing that one
out one way or another but we don't
really need it right now
oops this push size bug one I'm not sure
I've really looked at it yet it was
reported as a problem with the size
being spawn size in it and this is in
handy memory data is pushed size
underscore so the core push routine so
let me just go look at what we're
talking about here when size and it
comes in let's see what we're doing here
so I don't the bug reports a little bit
hazy
if the arena current blocks size is
smaller than the specified size in it
this will be a buffer overflow yeah I
mean just for future reference that is
not really like you want to explain what
you mean by this right the fixes are
fine but it's more like I'm not sure
what you mean by this I guess you just
mean in general this situation causes a
buffer overflow so let's see why so the
statement is that if the arena current
block size which is
[Music]
I can't say I'm quite seeing yet so if
you look at what happens when you come
through this piece of code
if the arena has a current block then
it's going to do some calculations if it
doesn't need to do that so if there is
no current block at all then it's going
to do something else so it will always
enter here so I think maybe the right
thing to say was if there is no current
block this would be a bug because that
does look true to me right meaning this
this get effective size for here I think
needs to happen in all cases so I think
probably I guess I can't say why this
wasn't getting called always cuz that's
a little bit strange right I mean
correct me if I'm wrong here but it
seems like we should just call that
always we don't really have to though
yeah I'm not seeing it yet so let's take
both cases separately one where current
block is zero and one where current
block is not zero in the case where
current block is zero it will not call
this so the size will remain zero right
you will automatically enter this case
because since this is true you will come
in here that means that you will use the
original size past you will not try to
do any kind of alignment for it right
you won't do any of this sort of thing
you will then check to see if you need
to do any kind of power of two
alignments to it which is sort of a
separate thing for debugging only and
that would be fine if it's too small for
the arena
minimum blocks well you know a tenuous
you small you're just saying look if
there hasn't been any initialization of
the minimum block size then we are going
to create that minimum block size what I
would say about that again you can see
this is fairly complicated but what it's
doing is just saying look if we aren't
going to do an allocation because
remember if underfloor / checking is on
we're not going to use blocks we're just
going to allocate everything piecemeal
right and so this stuff is is designed
to make sure that you don't aggregate
things together because otherwise they
can overwrite out of their bounds and
not crash so the entire point of
underflow and over to the technique is
not to aggregate so then you'd set the
arena minimum block size to one megabyte
if you were not doing any kind of
allocation checking and no one had set
one you then allocate a block excuse me
you allocate however big this needs to
be or whatever the minimum block size is
right you then allocate it and you get
back the block that you wanted you then
fall out of here and say okay if the
amount used plus the size is less than
the current block size which it has to
be because we or we just did that and
used a zero then we do the alignment
offset which is to say that we call up
two params dot alignment which is
somewhere here it is here and you know
what we in theory are supposed to have
happen here and I you know I guess you
could argue that this is maybe a bug but
I don't know I mean because we because
we're claiming that these things always
have to be aligned to the Mac like that
the memory blocks are required to be
aligned to the max
something you could ever align to right
and so you know I'm not sure if you want
to call that a bug or not but at least
according to our comment that was by
design meaning we don't try to realign
things if we know they're the first
thing in a block that is the most
aligned you're allowed to be you know
you can't be more aligned than a fork a
page we just don't let you do that right
so I think that
I mean I think that you know maybe we
could put another assertion in here that
just says look you know you you know
make sure that the amount you return is
not bigger than that but I don't
actually see the bug in that case let's
try the other ones so let's say there is
a current block when we come through
here we're gonna say get effective size
four and this is I think the case that
was reported as being wrong and you know
I'll add the assertion here as well
meaning you know when we come through
here when it says note the base will
automatically be aligned now we would
have to say that well yeah and the power
of two alignments so we just have to
assert that the power of two alignment
is always going to be less than whatever
the page alignment is which we can also
do which is to say that if we came
through here and you know this alignment
offset shouldn't put us further over so
we can just say look assert that the
arena current block used is less than or
equal to the arena current block size
right I believe it's yeah so we can just
assert that you know once we've done
this
you know something like this and we can
also say that you know we want to ensure
that the page size is is sort of the
maximum there so when you know the
alignment comes in we could assert that
you're not allowed to align to anything
larger than the page size right again
this has nothing to do that with a bug
that was reported and it's also not a
bug as far as I'm concerned but it is
the kind of thing that maybe you want to
just put in there to be clear about what
is and isn't allowed in this case so we
could say you know look whatever you're
going to do in terms of alignment we're
going to require that that alignment be
reasonable and not absurd right so yeah
so you know I could do something like
that I'm not sure I'm just not sure what
the best way to express that would be
again it's really unlikely that anyone
would ever do that but if for some
reason they did that's a problem right
and when we do that alignment where's
the align pattu here it is yeah you can
see here too that this is required to be
a power too because otherwise that code
wouldn't work so like you pretty much
just need to ensure through all of this
that it is going to obey those rules
it's just kind of implicit in the way
that we designed it is you know it's it
has to be reasonable in that respect so
yeah I guess what I'd say is we can add
some assertions in here like we can say
like assert that params alignment you
know is less than let's say you know
1024 right like you can't align to
anything bigger than you know what
with that let's say you can't do
anything other than 128 bytes or less
and we also want to assert that it is a
power to just to make sure that no one
puts any thing in there that's gonna be
really weird we would never do that at
least not on purpose so we could catch a
mistake you know if we made one but
somebody else who doesn't really know
what they're doing who maybe tries to
call this code well that could certainly
backfire right so I guess that's another
possible reason to do so just to make it
a little bit easier for other people to
not do something bad I can't think of
much else other than that so if we do
and is POW to that would just be
something where we would not sure where
we'd want to put that exactly but since
we've got the aligns in here we can just
do one of these where we just say like
is pow - and then we can take you know
input here so if you know we if we have
a value that we want to be equal to
power to I think we should be able to
check that relatively expediently so you
know if I take the value I'm assuming I
can do something like you know take the
value and subtract one from it right and
so if I subtract one from any power of 2
in binary it will set all the things all
the bits before the what you know a a
simple way to say what a power of two is
in binary is it's something that has
only one bit set right and so if it has
only one bit set then if I subtract one
from it I'm going to get all of the bit
to the right of that bit turned on that
bit and all the rest of the bits to the
left turned off right and the that's the
only time I think that that could happen
because any other value shouldn't
produce that same pattern right because
anything else would either have bits set
to the left still or there would have
been a hole somewhere and so you
wouldn't actually get all of the bits
turned on right there would be a stopper
you know or something so and I would
assume i if I take the value minus one
right and then I end it with the value
so I say whatever I had originally just
and those two together right I guess I
shouldn't say and those two together I
should say if I take this and I and with
the knot of it right so I flip it around
then I should get the same value back
right because if all of the things below
it are set to 1 if I flip them if I
invert everything so all those becomes 0
and all the rest of the things the right
become 1 if I end it I should get just
the top part and the top part should be
the same as it was before because there
shouldn't be any other bits set that are
higher than it right so I think that
would work the only question I have is I
guess that doesn't necessarily fix the
fact that well so that could still allow
you to have more up top actually now I
think about it so it's not quite right
[Music]
so I guess I need one additional check
to make sure that you don't have
anything else up on top right look up on
the high end of the value and so when I
do that I would also need to say yeah if
I were to use the bottom part not sure
what the quickest way to do that being
that one's a little harder although it
shouldn't be that much harder right we
may have to go to the blackboard for
this and yes this is something that I
have done before but I'm too old now I
forget everything you used to have a
good memory for things not so much
anymore to be fair I was never much of a
bit twiddling kind of guy people who
live and die by bit twiddling and stuff
are definitely more oh no my my pen is
plugged into the wrong machine somehow
that's no good that's not gonna help
what hmm well hold on one second
okay maybe this will have improved our
situation yes okay so let's let's try
that again
it's a little weird though like why am i
getting do we why am I getting you weird
Oh cuz the opacity got turned down
somehow not sure how there we go um I
must have accidentally clicked that at
some point so let's take a look here and
just let me show you what I'm talking
about
that is not how I normally do it it's
been too long so what I was saying
before is fairly straightforward right
suppose you have a binary number like so
and it doesn't matter how long it is
just any binary number and I want to go
ahead and subtract one from it
right it's gonna carry this way so that
if this was a zero right it's going to
keep trying to borrow till it gets to
here so if I subtract one from this
number I'm gonna get a number that looks
like this right which is that number
minus one right in this case you've got
remember your powers of two here right
so you got this first one is 1 then 2
then 4 then 8 so if you look at what
these values are set to you know this
one's set to 8 because there's only one
bit set it's the 8 bit these three
bottom bits are all set in the next
number one plus two plus four is seven
right which is exactly what you'd expect
it went from seven to one by subtracting
one and so what I was saying before is
that well if you go ahead and and these
two things together you can pretty
quickly tell whether or not this part
was a power of two because if you were
to end
the your result back with the thing that
you had originally you can either test
for zeros here or you can just test to
see if you got the same number again
right
the problem that I'm having is how do I
test to see loops how do I test to see
what these are right because you need
something fundamentally that right here
you know let's suppose that I want to
differentiate here is a power of two
here is something that is not a power of
two right
this one is eight and this one is eight
plus sixteen right I should break these
in some other way this let's say this
one is eight this one is eight plus
sixteen right which is twenty four not a
power of two right so this one has to be
yes and this one has to be know if this
routine is gonna be worth anything in
the checking right and so when we look
at it we need some way of determining
that we don't have this particular
circumstance so again starting off with
doing the subtraction in both cases we
would get the same answer for our
subtraction in the bottom bits right
we're getting it one one zero I'm sorry
one one one with a zero here and the
only difference between the two is going
to be here right so the difference is
going to be in one of them were going to
get a one up here and then the other one
we're going to get a zero so we end up
with these two different values and we
know that this one should yield a yes
and this one should yield and no but we
don't really have any way of knowing
that that's true right we can trivially
check to see whether this part was a
power of two now because I believe any
other pattern that would have occurred
down here for example let's say we had
one one zero zero one zero one zero
one I started one zero zero one if we
did a subtract one on each of these they
would become 1 0 1 1 1 0 0 1 and 1 0 0 0
right because subtracting a 1 from each
of these never propagates up to this
value so if we were then to do the
operation I was suggesting before which
is to say that if you not these values
you would be producing 0 1 0 0 0 1 1 0
or 0 1 1 1 and in each of these cases if
you were to end the value back to the
thing that you started with originally
it would not propagate this number
through right so you will definitely not
match right you will definitely not
match so if you did equals equals value
right which is what I was doing before
you this will successfully tell you that
right so we definitely have something
that tells us if it's successful power
of 2 in terms of those those low bits
right but I'm just not sure whether or
not it works all the way up to high bits
now I guess the answer is are we sure
that that same process doesn't still
work because now I think about it if it
works like this it should work on any
bit so I may have just talked myself out
of it for no reason so let's see what
happens so let's say we were to do it
here again we got these two so if we now
invert them what do we get well we get 0
1 0 0 0 or 1 1 0 0 0 in this case we
want this to be yes and this to be no if
we and this back with the original value
right which was this we do get the the
same value back if we and this we don't
so you know what I just I'm just being
too careful I guess I I did it correctly
I mean famous last words right but it
looks like that does work for any bit
pattern because it just can't propagate
far enough down
you watch me be wrong about that we
didn't exactly attack that particular
verification with a heck of a lot of
rigor there I suppose but you know we'll
see so yeah again you know just a simple
way to say is this thing in power -
that's all you really need to do right
I'm arguing you subtract one from the
value to do the bit propagation you and
it with the non of that and you see
whether you get the same value back if
you do great if you don't then no that's
the theory anyway and yeah so we'll see
if that holds up anyway again not even a
central part of the code that's just
there to provide that assertion so now
let's go through this routine and take a
look at the part that was actually
reported as the bug again all of that
was not what was claimed so what was
reported as a bug was saying look if
current block does exist but the size is
less than it should be right so let's
suppose that size in it comes in as you
know 70 or something but current block
only has a space for 60 because that's
what it says if the current block size
is smaller than the size in it right so
this comes in at 60 this is set to 70
what's going to happen well first size
will be adjusted for the amount that it
might need for alignment right and so
when that happens you can see it
happening here it's gonna say whatever
the alignment off offset needs to be
we're going to go ahead and add that to
the size because we're gonna need that
presumably for shifting or something
like that right so then we say okay if
there's not an arena current block right
which is to say that if we you know have
some kind of a if we have some kind of
situation where we haven't creating
before or we've got this and so this
might be the bug here where this looks
like this is not in bracketed properly
right like I feel like that should save
that because you
even even if that isn't the bug as as
reported there what you can see
happening there it's like hey this
comparison wants to be clearly between
these two things and I don't ever like
eat leaving something like that dangling
anyway because it's unclear what you
meant the or to refer to there and
you're kind of just relying on see
precedence rules to do the right thing
is that actually what was suggested as
the bug it's not but okay so they're
suggesting that you changes to an and
which is something else entirely
I don't understand why you would want to
do that because you want to do this if
you don't have a block or if it exceeds
the size of the block so I I'm gonna go
ahead and say this is just wrong and I
don't know C++ rules by heart so I don't
actually know whether you need this
parenthesis or not but I want it there
anyway
because I just like that to be clear
specifically so I don't have to remember
C++ is precedence rules for operators
why you know why would I want to have to
remember that so if you come through
here you're gonna say look in this case
the case we're talking about the size is
going to overflow this so you are going
to enter this case that means you're
going to reset the size to be size in it
and the reason is because now again you
know that it's aligned so you don't have
to have the alignment anymore because
the alignment should just work
the rest of this just works exact same
way it worked before
[Music]
don't see any problem in here it's so
this was line 146 do I have the right
lines here so that would have been I see
so they were actually suggesting look if
you you want to test to see that this
part of it and make sure you'd call get
effective size for up here but you don't
so I just I fundamentally disagree with
this bug report i I don't think you do
that because this changes the alignment
back to normal so I think you it's
totally fine right if that makes sense
the only thing I'm not sure about here I
see why they want to do that now I think
about it though because this is this
check here since this wouldn't be called
you would really want to do that right
because if they're well even that but
that doesn't make any sense because
you're gonna do this with it so you
really don't have to do that either
so yeah no I think this bug report is
just wrong I guess is what I'd say this
one I do agree with because well no I
don't review with this one either I just
want the extra parentheses in there to
be more clear but this is also wrong so
I guess I would say this entire bug
report is wrong
would be my guess so yeah I'm pretty
sure that there wasn't a bug there now
what I do want to know is there might
have been a bug if this that's totally
separate and unrelated to the particular
bug report that was issued which is to
say that this operator precedence here
might have been an issue so let me check
to see operator precedence or see just a
lot of quick check the table we can also
look at the grammar those are easy ways
to to look but what I want to see is who
gets bound higher of course this this
isn't what I want because it's not
telling me which order these go in the
operators are listed in order of
precedence highest to lowest their
associativity indicates which operates
equal preference in the expression so
let's see highest to lowest means that
this is the most powerful so let's take
a look so logical or goes below these so
that means we should so so I don't know
here's what I'm gonna say the second
issue is definitely not wrong what's the
second issue this one here
[Music]
so the second issue is this one ginger
bill and you're saying you want to be
greater than or equal to but it doesn't
have to do that what this is saying is
if I were to take the current base
position and I add the size to it then I
need to end that value needs to be
either equal to the block size because
that means I have not overwritten it
I've ended at the location where it also
itself believes it to have ended right
or I need to be less than that so the
case where I need to allocate a new
block is specifically the one where I
would exceed the size right want to go
ahead and update this to tell me why you
think that's wrong
maybe the buffer overflow is because you
had a bug in your code so let me try to
let me try to give you a like a more
constructive way we can step through it
how about I just set up one of these to
be in exactly the situation that we're
talking about and then we could do we
could just see right III don't know
does am I the only person who doesn't
understand what the bug report is
actually reporting so what I changed was
not a bug it's just something I would
like to do for clarity so that wasn't a
bug so I don't I still don't see any
bugs in this code despite the bug report
saying that there are two bugs in it I
actually see none and so I'm trying to
figure out what they actually are
and this is wrong at least from the
perspective of what it's saying there
may be some other bug that's different
or something I don't know
so let me go ahead and construct the
case just because again it's educational
to see one way or the other so we might
as well do it so if I just go into
handmade CBP let's say right and in here
I construct the exact case that we're
talking about so the bug claimed that we
were going to have a problem let me do
it maybe at the end here actually now I
think about it just so I can make sure
that the that the memory subsystem has
been started up and has the platform
allocator calls because we're going to
be asking it to do an allocation so I
want to be able to construct a memory
arena that would be in the situation
that we're talking about here right so
let's suppose that I take an arena and
well I don't even need to do that I can
just do this right and let me make sure
that I only do it once so we'll also do
a thing where we say look let's put in a
temporary here where we just say like
persist do still have persist now we
know local persist okay so what I'm
going to do is say local persist do once
that's going to get initialized to zero
so that I'm gonna say look if not do
once will come into this path and now we
can construct this situation right that
is supposed to cause the bug according
to the bug report and then what I can do
is see whether it actually causes a bug
and if it does then we can debug it
right so that you know is kind of a good
way to reproduce the the bug so first
what we'll do is we'll create an arena
and what we need to do is create the
circumstance where as the bug said it
the the current block size needs to be
smaller than what we're going to
okay so what we can do is we can set
this arena you know we know that there's
gonna be a minimum block size for it so
let's test the most common case which
would be that's that no one set the
minimum block size right so let's go
ahead and allocate we'll try two
different things but let's go ahead and
allocate a block that will succeed right
so we'll do a push size on the arena
where we say here's the thing our size
is gonna be the minimum block size for
the arena right - something right so
we'll just say it's gonna be minus-30
right a number that's not a nice even
power of two just to make sure that
we're not you know gonna bias in favor
of a good result so just say allocate
everything except for 30 bytes of a
block okay so we're gonna do that and
then what we're gonna do is we're gonna
leave the arena push params to be
whatever they would normally be and you
know if the bug report had said these
params caused a problem when then we
would want to put those brands in there
but we didn't get any guidance along
those lines so we're just gonna be like
this right um so there's our first test
allocation and here's our second right
and I'm gonna make sizes for these as
well just so we can remember them right
and so now I'm gonna do is just make
something I don't know 50 right so now
we're gonna have something that also
needs to go you know we we need to put
something in there and we're expecting
there only be 30 right 30 bytes long and
50 bytes can't fit in the 30 so it
should if it's working properly
triggered allocation if it's broken it
should hit the bug case that's you know
that's being contemplated here so let's
go ahead and and do that as well
so let's allocate size a here and size B
here right
and now we should get back both of those
what I might do is say look let's change
these two u8 as well so that we can
easily look at them in the debugger -
because it's just a little bit of a
handy thing doesn't really matter one
way or the other we'll do that and then
the other thing we can do is we could
also like memset these basically so we
could say like set I don't know if we've
got a set a call or anything here there
you go zero sighs so now we'll also
clear them to zero just to make sure I
like double check this code should do
that but just to make sure that somehow
this code isn't doing something better
than we would do when we get the memory
back let's try to also ensure that we
got something usable back that we can
also use right okay and so now we should
be able to step through this code and
I'll set it to debug build so we can
watch it we can like actually step
through each individual line and watch
it happen and then we should be able to
see the bug happen directly right at
least in theory so let's go ahead and do
that so why am I not seeing what am I
seeing
missing type specifier what's the
problem ah yes sorry I gotta just finish
that up so we'll set new ones to true at
the bottom so that we won't do it at an
infinity of times accidentally we don't
really need to do that because we're not
really keeping this we're not leaving
this in the game so it's not really a
big deal whether we do it or not but I
just wanted to make sure that so now I'm
gonna go ahead and do MS dev and open it
up here like so and what we should be
able to do is go to that part of the
code I mean if there was definitely a
bug in it we just run it and it would
crash there but since we don't actually
know let's and and maybe there's a
subtle bug that wouldn't immediately
crash we should at least look and do our
due diligence I mean the whole point of
this is to look and see if there's a bug
we don't want to just you know say oh
it's probably fine right um so let's do
the arena oh you know what there's a
problem here which is that the minimum
block size won't get in
initialized yet so we actually can't
quite do that because we don't know what
this will actually be so that's a little
bit harder I guess I'll just say look I
happen to know what it is so I was
trying to be clever there but you know
oops so let's try this and see if we can
get the case to trigger just you know
hard-coded there all right so here's me
running to that location and here's me
going in to push sighs it's going to do
clear to zero in alignment of four which
seems like a reasonable test case so
here we come through this code there is
no current block so it means we enter
here and it means that we're going to
allocate a block size of 1024 x 1024 and
off we go
we're going to only use slightly less
than that so if you look at what's going
to happen here right we've got a block
size that's that's that big we're using
I believe 10 for horotec well actually I
guess I just look at it here right and
so the actual amount left is gonna be
that 30 bytes that we wanted okay um so
there's us allocating it and here's us
clearing it and now we've returned it to
the user right so they've got that now
we're gonna try to do a push size on
test B and this is where the bug is
supposed to trigger right so we come
into the code and we've got a size in it
here of 50 and we're going to now try to
allocate that we do have a current block
and so we're going to get an effective
size back and you can see that the
effective size actually did come back as
something else which means it is gonna
have to be aligned right which seems
reasonable so now we do our test
we say look do we need to go in here and
of course we do because it's going to
not work right it's not it's gonna
overflow so of course we still have one
test we're gonna have to check which is
when this is right on the boundary
because that's also the one that's being
suggested as case so we'll do that in a
second but here we go
we allocate a new block and we put this
in the block and we clear it and we're
happy right and everything
good okay so now let's try them on
that's right on the boundary right so we
know we have 30 bytes left right
and so if I were to put 31 bytes in
that's the minimum I could ask for
that would overflow if I asked for 30 it
would fit right but if I ask for 31 it
won't and the argument here is that I
can ask for 31 and it will still say
that it fits and fail that's what the
bug report is claiming off by one error
right so this should find that case if
that was happening because we know we
got exactly the block size here minus 30
and then we're gonna try and put 31 into
it although now that think about it the
alignments gonna be wrong here try that
one more time we would need it to not
change its size when a line so we
probably will have to change the
alignment here to be one byte alignment
because otherwise this will expand to be
32 at least well you know what here
how's that well no because we need to be
33 this will fit and will work right
without changing the alignment I can't
do one byte over its right I mean well
well no I guess I could because if it's
only aligning the bottom it won't align
the top so that's actually fine that's
fine that should produce exactly the
case that that you wanted right okay so
we come down here to the arena we say
all right let's allocate something with
32 bytes left which we're gonna do here
and then let's go in and see what
happens when we try to allocate 33 bytes
which is one more bite than we would be
able to actually fit into this buffer
right so we come through and we're
hoping our size stayed 33 it did okay so
now trying to again look at the bug that
is claimed so if we look in cubes so we
look at how much
is in the current block used right and
we look to see that block size is this
so if I actually go and and subtract
this from it right you see that we can
fit 32 bytes in here and we're asking it
to fit 33 so this is the closest case I
can possibly construct for the bug that
you're talking about right so now what
you're saying is we won't go into this
routine but of course we did go into 13
and precisely for the reason I said
which is that this has to be higher than
this in order to fail and it is right
why is that the case well the arena
current block size is this which is 1024
x 1024 and the arena current block used
plus the size we're asking for is 1 over
that right which is exactly what it
should have done so not sure how else to
demonstrate the fact that the code
doesn't have that bug that you're
talking about
[Music]
anyone wanna tell me why this bug still
open
try allocating for 1024 1024 bytes okay
when do you want that just as the first
allocation or the second allocation just
out of curiosity I mean I guess I could
try it as either right so here's what
would happen if we do if we try to
allocate four megabytes as the second
allocation so we go ahead and do
[Music]
where's my there it is okay so here's us
doing that so in here we would want to
just do the same we already know what
happens when we do that and so here
we've got a size B which is this and I'm
not sure why this is a relevant test
case necessarily but you can see it
adjusts the size if it needs to here and
then you know allocates that block
exactly as you would expect
so nothing weird there as the first
allocation okay so what you want to do
is I assume retained this do you want
that or that and I'm not sure which one
you want so I'll just do this one first
right so yeah if we go ahead and
allocate that first we kind of know
what's gonna happen here because there's
no block so we're just gonna allocate
that much right it's very predictable
you know nothing nothing much goes on so
then in here where we get size B we're
gonna allocate the 33 but that's the the
block is presumably completely used
right so it would go into there no
matter what you allocated like as long
as it wasn't zero bytes you're done
so I totally
I am looking at the chat by the way but
no one's no one's saying anything in the
chat that's useful
are they here's the same test but with
the 32 so like I guess what I'll say
about this is I mean that is I don't
know what else I could possibly test
they're the you know like the right way
to phrase this I think would be this
seems like a premature bug report like
if you actually had a repro case for it
you should send the repro case so that
we can actually do it because this
definitely doesn't repro right and and
so you know it's okay to put bugs in
that's just like I think there might be
a bug here but this was like kind of an
oddly specific bug report it's
suggesting like you know if you're gonna
put that into a bug report um or that
you should have actually isolated the
bug right but that's not what happened
here this is this is not a bug and there
may be a bug in the code somewhere but
this ain't it right there isn't an off
by one error on that line at least not
the kind that's being talked about so
again you know I would say this kind of
is sort of a general thing that I would
say two things about it first of all
hopefully that was useful just to see
how you would go through something like
that to verify whether you've got a bug
of the kind
yes or not Thursdays if you want to
submit bug reports of something it's
usually a good idea to make sure that
you're actually submitting something
concrete that you know about right
because especially with something like
this it's like well you know it takes a
bunch of time for the person on the
other end to verify that your bug does
or doesn't exist since you're already
there to do that you should actually do
it right and try to get the thing in
there right but I don't know
yeah why is this still open I guess
would be my my larger question so this
should just get closed right I mean I
guess I'll close it myself
so yeah but hey you know it can't hurt
to double check with the that the
alligators working as planned as well
and you know one thing that I would
generally do on a project a little later
on not right now is I would probably
unit test my alligators you know and a
couple other like there's a few small
things inside a game typically that are
like fairly system II things that can be
unit tested and often times I will do
that so something like the alligator
where you you know we didn't have an off
by one error there but you know you
could see having such an off by one
error and the interesting thing about
having and off by one error is that you
know that's the kind of thing that a
carefully targeted unit tests can find
and so one thing that I will often do is
for something like an alligator you know
I'll put things in there that
intentionally probe those boundaries
much like the code I just wrote to check
for that bug and then just run that
right so you know like even though we
stress the alligator quite significantly
in handmade hero right now by calling it
all the time to allocate everything all
that really tells you is that in the
mine run of allocations you don't have
any bugs right but what it doesn't tell
you is in that like point oh one percent
of cases maybe you're just never hitting
them right because you never happen to
allocate anything quite that small or
quite that on aligned or quite that
something right
and so I think that's probably I think
that's probably a good argument right
for a place to put some unit testing in
because it's not hard unit test it's an
isolated system with well-defined inputs
and outputs so that's a pretty good
place to put that testing and it would
look a lot like an expanded version of
what we just did try to pick a lot of
allocations that will force it to do
things right on the edge of what its
defined to do to make sure that there
aren't places where it gets one wrong
oops it like thought it didn't need to
allocate but it did or thought it did
need allocate but it didn't and then we
check a few more things right where you
would kind of go from there now the
reason I haven't so you know I get asked
about unit tests a lot and so you might
ask well if I'm saying that I might
write a unit test or something like that
why not write it earlier and there's
actually a really good reason for that
too the reason for that is unit testing
wastes a lot of time and effort right
and so if your unit testing doesn't find
any bugs it was a complete waste of time
actually right and that's kind of an
important thing to internalize a lot of
people don't think about how much time
things take and whether those that time
be better spent elsewhere so what that
means is any time you spent make writing
unit tests is times you flush down the
toilet that's a given if it finds bugs
that would have taken a long time to
find or that would have slipped into the
project and caused catastrophic failures
on end-user machines it was well worth
it if it doesn't it wasn't worth
anything right and that's just the truth
there's no real way to get around that
hard fact what that means is even if you
are going to do unit testing because you
have specific systems you want to make
sure are more bulletproof because you
think there might be bugs in there and
you are afraid that they will get
released with those bugs you don't
necessarily just write unit tests you
still have to pick when you write them
and there's two things about that number
one
you want to wait as long as possible to
write the unit tests because since code
tends to evolve and change if you write
the unit test too early you'll end up
testing something that you then change
and have to rewrite the unit test for
very important so no wait as long as
possible and two you want to make sure
that you use the information you have
available to guide your unit tests if
you have systems that start showing bugs
that are hard to find that's a great
place to say maybe this is somewhere I
can use some unit testing because now
you have evidence that there are subtle
bugs occurring and rather than spend the
time to debug them raw maybe your tests
can help you right and so if we had had
some subtle bugs with the allocator
already I might have said at that point
let's start doing some testing because
by doing that testing we will make it
easier to get the bugs out because we'll
have concrete things we can step through
it's like oh we don't have to run the
game and wait for it to crash we can
like actually get it to crash like right
away and that's really important right
but also then I'm like okay I'm I'm sort
of getting dual duty out of that
debugging in addition to being able to
debug the bug I have which is unknown
problem so I know I'm not wasting my
time because I'm gonna have to find it
one way or the other I can also do
leverage that time to basically make a
unit test I could maybe run again in the
future to verify I haven't broken
anything right so again stay away from
dogmatic approaches to things like unit
testing and think more carefully about
what is giving you the most payback for
your time and that is a great way to
ensure that you won't spend a lot of
time reading unit tests on things that
actually never end up shipping because
they get deleted or rewritten or that
you don't end up time spending time
running unit tests on things that didn't
need to be attested in the first place
vallabha bla bla bla bla bla right so I
guess that's what I would say
uh and you really need to understand
that much like anything else there's you
know there's very few programming things
there's a couple probably but there's
very few programming things that aren't
useful sometimes and unit tests are just
like everything else they're useful
sometimes so the important thing to
remember is you have to understand what
they do you have to understand why you
are doing them and what the benefits are
so that you can make intelligent choices
about when they are employed and that
statement is pretty much true about
everything in programming and so you
kinda want to make sure that you
understand cognitively what's going on
there and hopefully that captures it all
up last thing I'll say is it sounded
like the bug report for the arena
alligator there was actually a bug
report from somebody trying to compile
it in a language that isn't C++ at that
point I would say just don't send bug
reports if you didn't bother to
reproduce them in C++ right like if you
haven't actually taken the time to
actually verify that the language that
we build in has the bug then you really
shouldn't be submitting a bug report
right because you have no idea it might
be something with that language or that
languages precedence rules or that
languages who knows what that's causing
the bug so it's really inappropriate to
submit a bug report unless you've
verified the bug in the language that
you're reporting the bug in right so I
would say that's probably a bare minimum
if you do wants the report a bug you're
welcome to do so but maybe mark at the
top for me this bug was never tested in
C++ so I can just move it to the end of
the list and never look at it until the
very end of the project right because
otherwise it wastes a bunch of time like
I did today not really getting anything
done and it's like okay had I known that
that bug was never actually reproduced
in the head made here a code base I
wouldn't have bothered looking at it
right not for a long time anyway okay so
I think we're good to go
now with those bugs that one got closed
out I don't know why I I should have
gone back to here though so I thought
think there's anything else we really
want to get right away this one
is a problem on Macs I think that people
were having so we do want to look at
this one eventually I it's probably
something we want to fix in general to
do with the way that we're allocating
frame buffers potentially so we do want
to get that eventually probably these
two both want to deal with that
I'm guessing also you know Martin's
reported a thing here that we should
definitely fix it's it's a dumb thing
we're doing so there are some things
here that probably want to get fixed
this one probably won't get fixed but
that's sort of a separate issue all
right so now we're down to trying to
actually work with the asset system here
and what we want to do is go ahead and
just work with it a little look for bugs
right because we probably got some and
we want to make sure that those bugs are
are tracked down and killed early so
we're not like dealing with a bunch of
stuff you can see that right now we
haven't really done anything in terms of
like saving out the heroes alignment
points to them for the most part so we
got like a bunch of work to do here and
then we have to also put in alignment
points for everybody else now it turns
out our art assets were wrong for the
hero so that's something that has to be
repaired and will repair that a little
later so the head face direction his is
backwards oh well
so we'll fix that in the art assets a
little later and and make that change as
well but everything else we should be
able to work with a little bit more so
let's take a look at what's going on
here let's suppose I open up the editor
here and I just want to start playing
around this a little and see you know if
it works at all basically and so if you
take a look at at the alignment points
here
I'm just looking through yeah this looks
all like what I would expect um just
looking through the alignment points
here right you can see that we've kind
of got one here for the for the body and
then one for attaching the head and what
I was kind of saying before right you
can see the way this work
I would like a little bit more ability
to sort of turn these on and off right
now what I have to do like let's say I
wanted to set up this default alignment
for the body you can see that I can like
edit it here just fine but it's really
hard to see whether I'm putting it in
the right place or not because the heads
in the way now I can go switch this to
something else temporarily
and then place all the markers that I
think should be placed and where they
should be placed right like I don't know
exactly where this should be
but it's something like that probably
right and then switch this back but you
can kind of see how that's pretty janky
don't really like it and so I feel like
I need to have maybe maybe I want this
thing that I'm doing here if you turn
off an alignment point maybe it stops
functioning entirely so that we can just
turn it off temporarily adjust the thing
and then turn it back on right that
seems a little better to me and so I
might go make that change the other
change I think we need to make is now
seems like the right time to go into the
renderer and put our Z bias stuff back
in because as you can see when we
actually put sprites on here they will
interpenetrate the ground and the reason
for that is we're aligning the tile that
we're well I shouldn't say tile
billboards a more correct term for it
we're aligning that billboard hmm such
that we we need it to put the highlight
point at a specific lineup spot in three
dimensions but in order to do that it
may be placed such that the ground right
is it sinks through the ground so we
want to do is create the correct bias
information in z2 or the correct
placement of the quad I mean
whatever we want to do right we need to
make sure that we're doing that
correctly and we put that off until now
because we wanted to have our actual
assets correct first but you can see
that that's a problem right and there's
two problems there the first one is that
interpenetration problem and we'd like
to get that fixed the other one is kind
of a related problem which is that if I
hop in a doorway you can see that I clip
through the doorway as well so figuring
out how to get that Z in there correctly
that's something we really want to get
get right and one of the things about
that that occurs to me is I think that
I've kind of been approaching that
problem wrong sort of this entire time
to a certain extent right because I
think it's actually something that we
can sort of solve correctly if we really
work out the math precisely right and
the reason I say that is because I think
99% of the time right what I want to
have happen is I want to have the
placement of the sprite essentially be a
card in 3d Z wires such that no matter
where I put this head the Z value for
the base of the sprite will be the Z
value where the base of the position was
and then the top of the sprite will be
the Z value that is wherever it should
have been for its height right and
that's why I want to have happen so we
should be able to solve for that and I
think I said we were gonna do something
like that like let's do something like
that so I kind of knew that was coming
down the pipe but we haven't explicitly
formulated it and we should and that
will I think get us to the point where
we can finally see like a robust
completely 3d integrated
2d and 3d thing which is pretty hard to
come by not many games managed to do it
to the level that we want it done here
and we've done a lot of things that get
it pretty close but that's the one we
haven't quite finished yet and I think
we should try to do that now because
instead of we don't want to start
working with our art assets and baked
things into them that are wrong because
we didn't do this part of the process
all right so I think we should do that
today my only question is do we have
enough time to do it
looking at the time I think we have
about 40 minutes so I think that's at
least a good time to to maybe get
started on it
right all right so let's take a look at
how we want this to work so if we go
into if we go into handmade the renderer
right and we look at the Z bias shader
which ships which apparently is actually
in here okay I want to look at the Z by
a shader this is the OpenGL part so
actually we want here right yeah and so
if we take a look at the Z bias I guess
I can just jump to it like this don't
know why I'm doing that if you look at
the Z by a shader what you can see here
is there's this modified Z thing and
it's basically saying look whatever the
in vertex you know is we got to do some
some nonsense here and produce a new Z
right and so what we're going to do is
produce a Z vertex that has this bias
baked into it so the Z value that we're
actually passing gets changed right now
the problem with that is that I'm not
sure that's gonna actually be as
expressive as we want it to be right it
might be but it might actually just be a
pain in the butt because really all
we're trying to do here is specify a
transform on these points that puts them
such that they're effective Z values
fall within specific range for the Z
buffer right and so I just don't know I
just don't know if that wants to be
encoded the way that's being coded here
right that's that's the the touchy part
okay so I'm gonna go to the blackboard
and try to explain what I'm thinking out
loud and hopefully that will give you
some perspective on exactly why we there
we go on exactly why we need to consider
the encoding
wait why does that say Dave 5:18
supposed to say Dave 5:19 right I mean I
wrote it right there yeah I don't know I
maybe I hit a hot key by accident I
don't know what I did
sorry about that it's safe 519 right
great folks I mean it just is I don't
know why that said that sorry about that
I hope that doesn't confuse anyone later
on anyway so Dave 5:19 so what I was
trying to say here is look what's gonna
happen is we're gonna have some ground
point here and we're going to be putting
a sprite card in here but that sprite
card is gonna be set up in a way that
really doesn't necessarily correspond to
what we want to see values to be why
because what we want to do is take
essentially a slot right this is
basically like a little plate of virtual
plate and what we want to do is say this
Z set right so the Z range from here to
here right this would be the maximum
value well shouldn't say maximum value
because that's a little ambiguous when
you talk about Z because depends on how
you want to do your Z buffer on stuff so
let's say this is the closest to the
camera and this is the farthest from the
camera right so if you take a look at
what's happening here no matter what we
end up a lighting our sprite to be
because we may end up having our sprite
you know look like that or something
right its lowest point we still want to
be sorted as if it was here because
that's just how we're saying the sorting
works you get placed as if you're at
this point in space tough right so we
want the Z value to be that 4 here right
and more specifically the way you might
think about it you
is we want this point to behave as if it
were sorted into this location Z wise
right and then furthermore we want this
point to behave as if it were sorted
into this location Z wise and the fact
that they're not even remotely there
doesn't actually matter to us because
what we're trying to do is falsely
present this sprite as if it was in that
location right I mean that's what we're
fundamentally trying to do so the
problem that we have is we'd like to
express that directly but obviously each
one of these quads kind of needs some
way to encode this and we don't really
want to spend a ton of space in coding
it because the more space we spend in
coding it the more expensive it's going
to be right so when we actually send
down triangles we know that we're going
to be interpolating those values when we
actually send down triangles we're just
gonna have vertices that have X Y Z W on
them and that's all we get we could if
we wanted to make our pipeline more
outrageous certainly do something more
complicated than this we could have a
shader that actually takes some kind of
other primitive thing like here's the
plane I want to use for sorting and then
it could output that as additional
things to the pixel shader as necessary
and all these other sorts of things
right so we certainly could get more
complicated than this but I want to try
and keep it simpler if possible because
every step we take in that direction
again makes it more and more unlikely
that you can port this thing to various
platforms it makes it require harder and
harder core hardware and so we kind of
want to manage what we're mandating
because you know if you wanted to turn
off stuff like our depth P
you could just do so and get worse
anti-aliasing right or something you
know be sparkly or something but you
could still run it right whereas if we
do some really crazy stuff that makes it
very hard to do it without a fancy
graphics card scaling it down in the
future might be very difficult and again
it's an educational project not a game
design to just push the limits and who
cares if anyone understands how it works
and who cares we can run it on the
Raspberry Pi someday and who cares and
who cares who cares right so again we
want to sort of say look let's just have
some consideration for what might go on
there and see if we can do something
with just that W parameter you know can
we just make sure or can we try to make
that be enough right okay so if we look
at how the Z bias is actually working
then what's going on here is we're
taking the actual transform of the
object and really all we're doing is
saying well we're going to take the
zooming we're going to go ahead and fake
the z-buffer by doing two transforms the
first transform is gonna be the actual
vertices that we've got the second
transform is going to be the vertices
that we had but with a value added to
their Z so they're going to be
artificially moved closer or further
away if you want to they're gonna
artificially be moved closer to the
camera and then we're gonna take that
modified Z and that's the Z that we're
actually going to that we're actually
going to pass down to the renderer for
z-buffering right so when it actually
does the depth buffer check it's going
to use that modified version instead of
the version that's actually
representative of where the pixels are
okay
and so this gives us an easy way to
change what the Z value should be of a
surface but it also does make it a
little bit trickier for us to figure out
how we would create the circumstance
that we actually wanted to create it's
especially weird because of the fact
that if you think about how the game is
currently presenting the information
that it's trying to present we are
actually adjusting in a sense the
location in in Y all most of the of the
sprite right now it may be a little bit
confusing what I'm saying when I'm
saying that what I mean to say is if
this is the floor tile again that we're
looking at right so you know here's a
wall or something if I'm trying to place
someone in the center of the tile then
the problem that we have is you know the
artwork is drawn to sort of have some
volume to it right so if this is you
know the hero then this position here
they are actually you know sort of
circum circle er region around there
right so that if you look at where this
would be if it was actually a 3d object
meaning instead of having hand-drawn art
we have 3d you know assets that actually
got rendered well the position of this
bottom most part that we're rendering
here so this part right here right
actually isn't displaced in Z in the
world it's displaced in Y right it's
moved in Y this direction so that it
transforms to there instead of here
right and that's why it doesn't clip
when it is actually moved out it's
because it's actually also moved closer
instead of just you know being moved
down which is what's happening now and
so you know that is the operation we
would actually be trying to mimic
is that moving it out in Y and then
producing whatever that Z value would be
now I guess there's a small part of me
that asks the question should we just be
displacing the things in Y to get there
Z and then that's what we do and I don't
really know the answer to that question
[Music]
but I guess what I would say is I think
it's not exactly clear that that's what
you want because if you actually do that
you are moving the actual physical
location of the thing which would change
a lot of other behaviors that wouldn't
work so I think you still need to draw
it there and you just need to come with
a Z bias value that is the Z that you
would have used had you just placed it
to that location right and so again I'm
not sure exactly what that value wants
to be
and I'm as a result not quite sure how
we would encode it so if you think about
some ways we would have encoded it if
you just went pie-in-the-sky
if you imagine looking at this thing
from the front so let's suppose we're
just looking at it like this so you know
this is the ground this is the wall
right and so if we look at this here
you know let's say we're standing on
that right and so I would normally draw
a sprite card that just looked like this
but of course what we actually end up
doing is we draw a sprite card that
looks more like this right we just place
it so that it's on an angle so that it
looks more facing to the camera than it
really should be and then we also drop
down a little bit right so that it
appears a little bit closer and maybe
that's a little bit pronounced compared
to where it would be right but suffice
to say the Z bias necessary to make this
not interpenetrate the ground is
precisely the Z bias that's given by
this interpenetration depth now it just
so happens that it's pretty handy how
this would get computed it's not a hard
thing to compute really what you would
do is you just say well if I wanted to
know the Z bias of this transformation I
could just recognize the fact that this
is a right triangle I know how far I
just placed it down from here because
that's exactly the alignment points y
offset from the bottom of the sprite so
that's pretty straightforward right this
is just that Y offset here right and so
if I want to I just need to be able to
figure out right if this is the sine of
theta here which it is then this is the
cosine of theta here right
proportionally so Y offset cosine theta
well actually that's not quite true
sorry in order to figure out what the
hypotenuse here
actually is I need to do this around the
horn right so this leg right here I know
that H sine theta is going to be the Y
offset right and I'll just call that Y
for now so if I then want to know what
the hypotenuse is well okay that's
pretty easy I just divided by the sine
right of the angle and then I want to
know this value here right so I want to
know what the cosine angle times it is
right so I want to know what you know
what X is basically and I know that x
equals H cosine theta right so if I want
to know what X is x equals H cosine
theta right in this case and I know that
H is y over sine theta I can just plug
that in here and say x equals y cosine
theta over sine theta which hey is just
Y tan theta right so once I know what
angle I am choosing to drop these guys
by because remember this angle right
here right that we're using here that's
it so effectively the angle of tilt
right it's the same in either case so
whatever angle of tilt I want to give
them this would give me if I know the
tangent of that angle then I know what
this Z biased value would be right I
know how far it has to get displaced in
Z in order to be correct right so I know
that value the problem is again that's
really not even how we're computing the
Z bias right now the way we're computing
the Z value is Z bias is an actual
movement in Z the actual movement in Z
means how far do you move this point up
to get it to the correct z value right
after transform
and that part is a little more confusing
to me and not 100% clear on what that
would be because in order to get a Z
value that's the same as this one right
you're assuming that there's some that
there's the plane of the camera right
which is passing through here and so in
order to put this point on the same
plane of the camera and to be fair these
planes look like that right they look
more like this right and so what we're
saying is well we want this point to be
on the same plane of the camera as like
this point is or somewhere around there
right and so what we want to do is say
well that plane of the camera that one
here we need to move this up to that
point but like that point is really not
obvious to me how you encode any
convenient way so like using either the
angle of tilt which I guess you wouldn't
necessarily know so the angle it tilts
probably bad but maybe the angle of the
camera which maybe you could do a
computation a little easier would be an
easier thing to compute but again you
can see why it's pretty tough to figure
out what you would put into the Z there
to make that work hmm and I really don't
know
I guess one way of thinking about that
requires another vector I'm not having a
brainstorm here I'm not having the flash
of brilliance that's how you encode this
in for each vertex into just one
parameter like I said pretty obvious to
me how you would do it if you could just
encode points and say this is transform
this entire other point right like
forget it like you know don't transform
this point I'm giving you transform this
completely other point that has nothing
to do with it that makes some sense
because then you would just say all
right this is the place I want this
vertex to appear like it is it's
actually over here but I don't care
so just transform this one and produce
that Z value and then use that right
yeah then I'm not I'm not coming up with
anything
and another thing that
[Music]
another thing that kind of creates a
problem here is that the location that
you transform to in pixel space is also
wrong you know what I mean you know the
ideal way to do it would be to say
something like I'm gonna tell you where
in the depth buffer you should be
looking in addition so like you almost
want to like draw a quad and say
rasterize this quad and do the depth
buffer testing on it and then write the
pixel right the pixel if you find that
you could have right
and again not not a particularly
plausible thing to do you could
obviously make a fairly inventive
renderer that worked that way but I
don't know so I'm kind of I'm kind of at
a loss to know exactly how I would
encode this so that you're gonna get a Z
bias that's that's really stable and
you've seen on and made hero the
difference between getting something
really right and not quite getting it
right so like for example when we redid
our camera code to like do type
computation of like the fading bounds
and like good interpolation it just felt
so much better you know and there
weren't weird artifacts where the fading
was off sometimes it just feels so much
more solid and so I feel like this is
one of the last parts of the sprite
compositing 2d 3d hybrid thing that's
that's really nasty but I feel like we
can get it exactly right or at least get
it that solid thing that's just like
yeah this is how you do it to have it
really compute well but I'm just not
thinking of the magic answer you know
maybe maybe I got this out the other day
because I had noticed it was around and
I and I put it on the owl the Owls over
there and I was thinking maybe when we
really need to get down to business here
we go right get our little tennis tennis
headband on I don't play tennis by the
way but I associate these kinds of
headbands with people who play tennis so
we just put our TAS headband on and I
think the important thing to remember
headbands is that they help keep your
thoughts in right there they're like
keeping someday secure the thought right
yeah I'm saying they just any of the
thoughts that we're going to kind of get
out through this ring right here those
are being reflected back in giving you
the power of both your thoughts right
now and your thoughts from a few seconds
ago and that you know that's where it's
at so putting our headband on and trying
to think harder about this right let's
try to write some more direct
correspondences here and see if we can
something starts to jump out at us right
so when we take a look at what we're
trying to do here we have this part of
the wall right right here's the wall
here's the floor we we would get exactly
the results we wanted if we just drew
the sprites like this right and we can
do that if you go look at how like we
actually have code right where we do our
sprite transforms I think it's in here I
think we do it in here I don't know if
we'd actually then don't don't quote me
on that maybe we do it in here maybe we
don't let me look at the element code
sorry enemy code and see if we do so in
here you can see us doing our push yeah
so we're calling sprite values for up
right and then we call it push sprites
so you can see push sprite somewhere
here it is you can see push sprite on
you here doing this thing right and you
can see when we create these we're just
not putting in any Z bias at all right
so that's why we're clipping through the
floor we don't have any Z bias in there
at all and when we're creating these so
you can see sprite values for upright
rights right values for upright when
we're creating this the t camera up
there variable is really what determines
how bent the thing is right and so if in
here I say okay the t camera up and I
can that we can just look at this in
practice right so if I say look we're
gonna use that that T camera up value
then we don't need to worry about Z bias
as much well you know that's even that's
not true no I think about it that's only
true at the top right so that's only
true for like this sort of the sorting
that happens like here right against the
wall so I take that back
that's not true even if we set that it's
the bottom when we do that alignment
because of the alignments the bottom
would still interpenetrate through so
it's not true changing it wouldn't be
the case okay so let's go ahead and
continue to work that through and I'll
forego what I was saying for because
it's actually not accurate um but let's
pretend that t camera was directly up
and now let's work through what we would
do to correct the alignment in that case
right because I think that case we could
get correct so let's suppose the
alignment point was actually up here
what's going to happen well we're going
to shift down to bring the alignment
point into shocking that alignment with
the position of the entity on the ground
that will shift this card down like this
right yielding to this much
interpenetration right so right there is
where we would clip out if we wanted to
fix this if T camera up again was not
used so really if the camera up would be
zero I think so it was just straight Z
right we're just using straight Z up and
down uh so if T cam was that's the worst
handwriting Wow
it's just been bad today huh if T camera
up right if T camera up equaled zero
meaning we're not using the up Vector of
the camera which will lie things down
because the camera is looking a little
bit rotated right so that'll live things
down more than they would be if we were
looking straight top-down so if we're
using that bend then what we're gonna
find is as we use that T camera up this
would get wrong but if we have this at
zero then we would literally just be
using the z axis for this right
so Z bias if we just set the Z bias to
however long this distance is which we
know what it is actually it's the
alignment point Y times the height of
the sprite right because that's how far
we're moving it so we would be able to
set the Z bias exactly correct because
this is what it would be right the Z
bias on all four points in fact would be
set to that now once we get rotation
involved there'd be a little more to it
we'd have to account we'd have to do the
plane multiplication to find out what it
was but then it would be correct right
okay but now we get to a much much much
worse problem or at least I think it's
much worse right and what happens is now
if we let T camera up go to something
that is not right so not equal to zero
right even something small like point
one but we're actually more than halfway
to T camera up we're at point six five
because I think what we set our t camera
up that's what we thought was a good
balance of sort of shift as the camera
moves that's gonna lie these things down
a lot flatter so what will then end up
seeing is something that looks more like
this right and now you can see what the
problem is if we were to still set the Z
bias to the values that it would have
been if T camera up were not involved
well then we would be in big trouble
because we'd be setting these values to
much closer values of Z than they should
have been
because we're gonna shift them up way
more than they need to be looking at it
again from the side right the easy case
was the case that we had something that
looked like that and we just shifted it
down right so it looked like that right
all we did is shift it down so all we do
is like take this point and move it to
here take this point and move it to here
there's actually two points it's you
know it's a quad but you get the idea
right we we shift it down like this then
the question is uh hmm okay what do we
shift the Z by to make it appear as if
it was so right here obvious answer
however much we shifted down by in the
first place right we just apply the
negative and that's the Z bias pretty
simple should just work right but now
what do we do when this is what it
actually looks like
and we've lie down right and now we want
to know how will I still see this thing
you know in this case and it's got to
produce a z value that's the same as
this thing Z value well I don't know
what that is unless I project this thing
onto this plane right
did I just accidentally say the answer
to the question
I feel as though I may have accidentally
said the answer to the question
if the thing is I know the plane in Z
that this needs to project to but I
don't know where it projects what if the
Z value
I'm sorry the W value is how we're
passing it down what if the W value I
set is just the Z value the Z height in
world space of the plane to which you
need to project it and then you just
project it in the vertex shader
so in the case of the bottom vertex I
know exactly what that Z plane is
because I know the Z value of this point
right so I know the world Z plane that I
would project to in the case of this so
in the case of this I would just set it
to this it would know this point and it
would find the intersection from here
going backwards in the camera direction
to that plane right and that would be
the actual Z value camera relative Z
value right if I want to know what the Z
value should be for this point well I
want you to reject as if it were well I
don't really know where I want to
project as if it were there I guess
that's kind of a problem where do you
want that back point to project you and
Z I mean maybe you just say that it's
some kind of a well so I don't really
know but I guess you would say the
height value is where that top point
should project so if you want it to
project to this Z plane you would say it
would go right there the problem is you
actually want to see it so you kind of
need it to go more like right there
so do I actually know what I'm talking
about or not well I might still know
what I'm talking about and the reason I
might still know what I'm talking about
is because actually this is the point
you would pass in not that one because
this was the original point much like
this was the original point so you're
passing the Z of this and the Z of this
and this would actually get projected up
to this plane which might be correct
I'm willing to believe that this is part
of the answer possibly not the entire
answer but it's an interesting start
so basically passing the worldspace z
ah
I'm willing to give them try so passing
the worldspace Z point which that you
want to project to and what we can do
there is just pass the actual Z value
anytime we don't want to do this so you
want a bias of 0 because project is
saying project it to the same plane it's
already in right I don't know does that
sound good
I'm gonna go ahead and stop there for
today and I'm gonna say Saturday and
Sunday when we resume I might try it I I
can't say for sure that's right but I
might try that we'll go to a brief Q&amp;A
and I think that's the best I've got
right now if people have better ideas
they're gonna have to they're gonna have
to tell me what they are
what kind of testing unit replays do you
used on 1935 have you used over the
years its automated testing even really
a thing at game studios yeah actually it
definitely is used but it depends on the
studio and what value they place on it
and so on
what I would say is I have written a
couple different systems ranging from
full recording of everything to just
sort of log based stuff that I do use
for more for watching playthroughs than
for catching bugs usually but you can
also sometimes do bugs with them I did
write walk monster for the witness but
we didn't end up needing it because I
later made a system that actually just
told you everywhere the player could go
from a starting point so you don't
really need that kind of testing and I
really haven't seen much else done at
projects I've been on for unit testing
on the 3d animation system I did for rad
game tools that had a complete set of
unit tests for all the core functions
inside like sort of the runtime library
that that I made for it so basically
like the memory allocator the math
routines those were tested with unit
tests so and that makes more sense to
you on a project like that where tons of
studios are using it the more bugs you
can find with unit testing the less
problems for other people so that's
reasonable right so yeah outside of my
personal experience though I would say
that there are definitely studios I know
of that at least have used that kind of
testing I specifically remember Chris
butcher telling me that Bungie was a
huge fan of doing random walk testing so
they would just basically feed random
use
inputs into their games just something
they would do and they just feed random
inputs over and over and over again and
they said they found stuff with that I
don't know to what extent are using that
these days on like destiny but it was
definitely something that they used to
do on at least one of the halo like Halo
Reach maybe and and so on I don't know
what other games but I know that was a
specific case trying to think of what
other unit tests Reeves losing games I
don't know
randomized testing is fairly popular
because again games the hard bugs and
games you can't really it's it's pretty
hard to design unit tests for them so
you kind of need a different kind of
testing you need something that tries a
bunch of stuff and sees what breaks in
it was a unit of the Tri slate things
because usually the units to start
broken usually if the interaction of
units that gets broken you know or
gameplay logic stuff that just turns out
to put you in an unwinnable state or
something that really that you know
doesn't crash or anything and you can't
really detect that's wrong you just need
someone to walk over and go how did the
player end up up on this ledge that's a
totally busted thing and then you can go
look and see if you can find out why
right
can use the 1935 not just yet
gun games for people who don't want to
fuss the flappers through code would you
say STL is a good solution I've never
used it so I can't really say that it's
a good solution because that implies
that I've like assessed it and
determined that it was at some kind of a
quality level or something which I
definitely haven't done but what I can
say about it is it's shipped in a lot of
games right so it can't be that bad
right it's not completely awful because
you know that there are games out there
running on it right now that are running
on millions of machines so it's at least
it must do something right it's about
it's about as good as I can can give
without actually spending some time
looking at it myself I couldn't tell you
whether it was good or not but it
certainly can't be that bad
right
alright looks like we're all done I
don't see any other questions
all right thank you everybody for
joining me further sort of handmade hero
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
with the series at home you can always
go to hammer here about organ pre-order
the game it comes with all the source
code so you can follow along do your own
sort of test on the Z buy stuff you got
all tomorrow I'm not here tomorrow I'm
here back here on Sunday
yet all tomorrow to try out your own Z
bias equations it's a pretty well
isolated thing and pretty easy
experiment with so you know take a look
see if you can figure it out yourself
see if you can make something that
produces nice results with sprites and
sorts them in in a way that's pretty
consistent with everything 3d that we
want to do in the game it'd be a really
good exercise really useful for people
to sort of you know see see what trout
their chops right like see if see if
you've learned something from all the
math we've done see if you can come up
with something if you just want to try
the thing that I said maybe you want to
try figuring out your own and you know
again would be a really great exercise
I'll be back here on Sunday I'm out of
I'm not around I'm I would say out of
the office but I guess I just mean I'm
not around tomorrow and so I will be
back on Sunday until then yeah again if
you do watch I got any further Mali
rocket stuff besides handmade here you
can always click on the little Mali
rocket head here and it will take you to
our other stuff our comic is out now
which I always try to point people
towards since just got released and
hardly anyone knows about it so if you
want comic to read you can always go to
me out of the infinite you can either go
to me how the infinite calm or you know
you can click on it through here and if
you want to find other stuff people ask
about 1935 all that stuff as we get it
it's always up here right we've got a
blog you can even go to news anyway
anywhere on here there's tons of mailing
list sign up places you can sign up for
our mailing lists all that stuff we send
out stuff as soon as we have something
official to announce so trust me as soon
as I want to show screenshots for 1935
you'll be getting a mailing it
I won't sneak them out and not tell
anyone I mean the point of putting games
out there is that you hope people buy
them so that you survive as a company
we're not gonna keep it hid from anybody
trust me so anyway that's it for today
and I will see everyone back here on
Sunday that point we'll get to see
whether or not Z plane projection is
useful or whether it's just a dumb idea
we had our sweatband on so I'm hoping
that that will increase the chances that
it's hardcore but you never know until
then have fun for everyone
and I'll see you on the Internet take it
easy everybody