hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero the show Rico to complete game live
on stream we are I think we didn't quite
finish debugging something that I want
to debug on the last dream on monday and
so today we're going to finish debugging
it it's in the day 257 code today is day
2 58 so if you would like to follow
along at home and you pre-order the game
on a major org unpack that day to do
seven code because that's what i'm
starting with today and here we go let
me first load up our handmade code here
you know what i want to do actually I
take it back I'm not going to do that
I've been wanting to do this for a while
and I keep forgetting I wanted to move
the prj file out of the code directory
and into the root directory like this is
where I actually wanted it to be don't
ask me why I just kind of like that
convention these prj files or something
new that I made just for for kodir but
my convention has in work has been to
put them in the route instead of in the
code directory I just seem to like that
better and so that's what I'm going to
do so here is our system and it's
working actually quite well at this
point and we've gotten it into a fairly
nice state but before we go any further
on our profiler system like making this
a more usable user interface thing here
what I wanted to do is figure out why
we're getting an occasional bug with
code reloading we fixed one of our bumps
with code reloading but we have another
bug with code reloading and that bug is
that if we change the executable so you
know somewhat significantly we can't
just you know twiddling and then change
it we have to like if out a block of
code so that you know it gets rearranged
a little bit but assuming that we do
that and make us a substantial enough
change we can get to a point where the
profile no longer works and we basically
know why the profile doesn't work
anymore but we don't really know what is
like we know the the way in which the
profiler breaks we just don't know
is making it break in that way and so
that's actually what I'm going to look
at today and I'll show you in a second
here oh wait forgot switch to buffer
there I will show you what I mean in a
second ah this in case there's folks who
don't remember what what we're talking
about all right so uh where is this is
it there is it here's the one I was
using so I made this little if 0 block
here and essentially you know this is
playing the cutscene right now I'm going
to switch into like just the simple
world render and then I'm going to
switch back here and I'm gonna well I
guess I'll also make for kodir a little
more tiny just so you can see the rest
of it happening so there we go I'm going
to compile and you can see that during
the code reload everything worked just
fine but the profile is now gone right
and you can see that you know I'm
walking around and the profile is
completely gone and you know I can
switch it back on and it's not like it
depends on the X people directly that
way it just it it's over right so even
moving back to what probably is exactly
the same executable it's busted it's
still busted right so the profiles not
working and so I did a little
investigation on the previous stream and
we kind of know what is actually
happening there but we just don't know
exactly why and the reason that we or at
least the what I believe could be the
problem because we observed it happen in
practice is that when we are
encountering the profile blocks so
remember we write to a debug log and
then we essentially collate that log
after the fact to determine what what
has happened and one of the things that
we compute during that collation phase
is we compute the profiling information
so how long things took and we do that
by adding a begin marker and marker and
off we go now our game is multi-threaded
nominally we don't make super heavy use
of it at this point but we made very
heavy use of it in the software renderer
for example and we probably will make
more use of it going forwards we might
multi-thread simulation in the future uh
we always even in this fairly light
multi threading thing relying on threads
to do our asset processing the
background so that we can stream the
world in
the world assets in and stuff like that
so we are a multi-threaded gang what
that means is when we are cooling the
debug log we have a log filled with
events that happened but those events
are coming from multiple frames and what
we need to do when we collate the debug
log is we need to look to see what um
thread out of the threads that are
running what thread we are actually
looking at for a debug event and then we
know that begin and end blocks pair up
along that thread so you know one thread
may have a begin block another thread
may have I begin block and then the
previous right at the end block and the
other for that I'm in block right and so
we're using those thread IDs to pair it
up now we know what the thread is
because we've already found it right and
you can see this get debug thread finger
so for every event comes and we look at
the thread I diem you say what's the
thread that this is coming from right
what thread is this knee bug event
pertain to and then we look to see do we
have an open debug block on that or
don't we if we have an open debug block
at its begin block I should say if we
have an open profiling block and it's to
begin block we make a new profiling
block underneath that one and say this
is like a child call right this is this
block called this other block right if
we don't then we say this is at the root
it's at the top it's in the actual frame
like this was one of the main blocks
that constitutes our chunks of work
across the frame so it's a root block if
we encounter an end block we do the same
thing we go what is that you know what's
the frame I'm sorry what's the open
block profiling but we're talking about
it close it whichever one is open on
this thread is now being closed by this
end block okay and so that's what we're
looking at here right that's what we are
trying to make work and what we found
happened before because obviously this
is working normally what happened before
when we were looking at why we lose our
ability to look at the profile was that
it wasn't that the profiling wasn't
working anymore it was that during the
reload so when the reload happens we
never get an N block to match the open
block around the reload so for example
handmade
actually gets wind could be too babe TPP
so let me search for frame and there is
so what we were seeing is that this
debug collation block which opens right
this block gets opened and that is
typically going to be in most
circumstances the last block that is
open before a collation event occurs
because collation of debug events
happens inside this debug frame and
operation so typically what will happen
is we'll process all the debug events
and then we will end with all those
events being processed and one open
block which is this block right so that
block is open now we come through here
and we write the this doesn't close the
block remember it just writes in an end
block event into like basically the
first event in our new fresh buffer
because we've you know we're using a
different buffer at this point so we
writes it into a different buffer we
then write a whole you know we just
start writing debug events during this
process we come back up to the top of
this loop we come here and we do win32
load game code potentially right if the
xq2 eyes reloaded and that's the case
that's breaking when it does the reload
at this point right we've got an open
block here etc we called n block blah
blah blah we start we we use the new
executable to generate a bunch of stuff
right all this stuff is going to turn
entered into the debug log blah blah
blah we come back down to debug
collation again right and so now we have
basically a whole nother frames worth of
debug events with another collation and
collation begin at the end of it right
and the very first thing in that buffer
should have been an end block okay and
it should have been an end block using
the same executable information that we
used before right
I've got it in all of that explanation I
think I may have an idea what the
problem is well hmm no you know to be
honest no I don't think I do I was gonna
say that end block will not have a valid
like the the information that end in
that event might not really be valid
because it's going to point to strings
that we can't access anymore because
they got unloaded right but that
wouldn't really explain the bug because
the bug just needs the block pairs to
match and in this case it's not even
looking at the grid for that purpose so
it still seems like the end block
doesn't get picked up for whatever
reason and I don't know the reason but
we do have another bug there I feel like
there's another bug there and that is
that in this this debug frame end
situation I feel like we really want to
do the reload with an empty buffer right
like I feel like we want to ensure an
empty buffer as part of the reload
because otherwise we are going to be
collating bogus data potentially that
just
that just seems true right because we
write in these grids and they get kept
permit they get copied during this so so
I guess what I would say is this part
really the executable reload part I feel
like the excuted will reload and the
debug have to sort of be mated they have
to be working in tandem and that's just
a bug regardless now I don't know that
it's a bug that has anything to do with
our current bug but it is a bug so I
think the correct thing to do here is
actually inside this where we do this
compare file time right I think what we
want to do is remember whether or not we
will reload the executable like that's
actually the thing we do want to know
but then not actually reload it until
later
so here's my proposal this is what I
think we need to do now I guess there's
a risk in me fixing this bug right now
while the other bug is still there which
is that I'm a cover-up the other bug and
that may still be a bug right because I
basically got two bones now if that
makes sense that I know about and since
this is the debug code I guess I'm not
too worried about that because if
there's bubs in the debug code well who
cares it's not even compiled in in the
users the case so i guess i don't care
but it's just worth mentioning if that
makes sense but what I'm saying is I
think what we would actually need to do
is we need to make sure that we flush
all of our cues right so basically we'd
say if executable needs to be reloaded
right if we've detected that's going to
happen we need to flush all our cues
then we do excuse me then we do our
frame end if that makes sense and then
and only then after we now know we have
collated all of the debug events that
we're going to collate can we then say
all right now do this you know I'm
saying and I suppose this stuff can can
happen in here as well so this is
basically like yeah if we come in here
we're going to say the executable
reloaded is it's that this year is going
to be like all right so we flush the
cues we let the debug to its collation
and then if we need to be reloaded we
reload it oops like so and I put this
guy in here right
so I think that's actually when that
needs to happen I'm pretty sure because
if we don't do that then we will have
some errant grids regardless i don't
think that fixes the bug we're talking
about because i don't believe the bug
we're talking about requires those grids
to do the beginning and block matching
so i think we still have the other bug
but this definitely was a bug and it's a
bug we can fix so we should and so all
we really need to do up here is do a B
32 of executable needs to be reloaded
and that X people needs to be reloaded
is just that information right so yeah
that's what's actually going down I
think I also suppose that this really
doesn't need to be up here either it can
actually remove down below right so this
this part here can actually come over
here and my only concern at this point
is that this does mean that will go one
frame without actually having oh no it
doesn't here's the we load it to begin
with you anyway all right so I think
that's more correct I think that
basically removes bugs that we would
have had with the executable code
reloading we're across the reload we
would be unstable so I'm going to double
check to make sure that I haven't broken
everything horribly which again may have
happened so let's take a look again I'll
do the same update we were doing before
and just make sure that we can still
reload the executable
let's see that's the world mode that's P
and in here I can hit spacebar and let's
see so if i do 0 there off I go let's
see okay well that didn't work well at
all that actually just caused me to to
hang what happened build let's break all
there we go so what is going on here
threads we are in win32 fill sound
buffer
so it looks like somehow somehow this
failed in a very bad way
but i'm not sure what happened let's
find out like our game didn't reload
properly so that that is why it stopped
updating is because it literally had
nothing to update all right here we go
so unloaded game code unloads the game
code not surprisingly we then reload the
game code like so I'm going to take a
look just to see what this looks like
here oh right it's a little bit it's a
little bit more sensitive than that
isn't it because it can't load the game
now because the compiler is not done
with it yet so it actually does like a
well this time it will actually work
because we were broke into the debugger
and so this time it'll actually be fine
but right we probably made it yet the
you can kind of see what the problem is
here this is pretty subtle so let me let
me explain this in case you guys didn't
quite catch what happened there so the
problem here is i forgot that we don't
immediately get the game code we usually
wait a frame or two to get it because
what happens is we try to reload it but
visual studio hasn't finished writing
the executable yet or the PDB or and who
knows what else right so there's this
this sort of latency where we've
detected that we need to load a new one
because the date stamp has changed but
we can't actually do it so what happens
is we come through here and the first
time through it actually fails like it
doesn't work right
oh and that explains our bug that
totally explains our bug as well right
because we can't call debug frame end we
end up going all the way back through
this code one more time without ever
having called the collation code since
there was no collation code to call
that's crazy that's crazy so I think
what I want to do here is actually just
force this to maybe be a little more
sane so maybe do something here where we
just go like okay let's try to make this
behave in a in a slightly more
interesting fashion for example you know
load dry index equals 0 load dry index
is less than 100 load dry index and so
let's just try loading multiple times to
see if we can get to load right in here
I think that's more what we want to do
and then if we can't then we you know
we're in really in bad shape right then
we know things are bad what I do want to
do however is move this stuff outside of
it so basically this stuff happens over
here we do this stuff exactly the way
that we would normally need to do it so
really I just want this
okay so this is what we actually want so
here we come through we say all right
you know we assume that the executable
doesn't need to be reloaded we assume
we've already done that if we were going
to do it we do XP will needs to be
reloaded from the detection and we flush
the cues if we have to we then give the
debug system a chance to do the final
collation round or we bail if we need to
I mean you can the blood was like right
here like this was the bug right I mean
that was the bug in fact I guess we
could even maybe get rid of that line
and then it would have worked if we just
didn't do this the problem is will
eventually overflow you know like as if
we need to clear that eventually we
can't just keep regard recording the
emigrants forever but that was the bug
this was the bug right here the whole
time we're staring us in the face and
then if the extra doesn't even really
will just go let's try a few times to
reload it because we there's no point in
going back through the frame because we
can't draw anything we don't have a game
running right there's no game we
unloaded it so I think that's more
correct now and that solves both bugs
assuming we actually got it right all
right so i'ma go to world mode dot cpp
I'm gonna switch this up like so and
it's totally not going to work because I
made some other mistake but we're almost
done and that's what's important let's
see here oh that's good apparently I
just want to load the game 100 times how
about you actually check to see if it's
loaded muratori not the brightest bulb
on the tree today folks not the
brightest so here it's right here right
it's supposed to be assuming that the
game is not bad now win32 unload game
code I'm assuming actually does the
right thing here and sets it to not be
valid yeah so I think that's all we
needed so okay let's try it one more
time try that one more time all right
here we go and so in cure let's just get
back to full mode and that and what is
the problem came up to and renders
unhappy hmm
not sure why it would be did I mess up
something here where we use this
hmm let's take a look what the problem
is so this memory is wrong right you can
see that that's true let's take a look
at where we actually got in here so we
called game update and render we took a
look at what the game mode was and it
was correctly in the cutscene so that is
what we would expect it we do update and
render cutscene and we're calling this
asset rendering code and we get in here
and we just find that the scene that we
actually passed is garbage but that's
actually that's actually true right
that's actually that's actually not our
fault that's just actually this code
being wrong because these variables are
globe our statics and we store them so
that's actually yeah that's not going to
work right because presumably this
cutscene code take a look here in the
cutscene code where we are pointing to a
layered seen star scenes not sure I
guess we decided that that was well you
know what i don't understand exactly
what that does like I don't know why we
needed that do does anybody else
update and render cutscene so it's this
is the stupidity right here right and I
guess this is so in case we wanted to do
another cutscene and so that doesn't
work across reloads right because we're
snapping a pointer to that internal so
that just seems dumb to me and you know
again would be a totally fine program
practice if we had a different sort of
code reload system but since we're using
the simple relatively simple kind we're
not allowed to do that so what we
actually want to do here is say okay in
update and render in update and render
we need to Weiss yeah give this game
update and render cutscene we need to
stop looking at this the scene in
information that we're passing and start
doing it slightly differently trying to
think of what i want to do I think what
I'd like to do here is just use an enum
right because that's very simple
solution if I just say like okay we've
got you know our struct cutscene right
and that cutscene has the what are the
two things we want in here we just want
the scene cat in the scenes so if I just
have seen countin scenes then i can say
cut scene
and then we just do a raid count clear
cut scene and cuts so all i'm doing here
is i'm just making a table so that we
can index into the table that's it and
then i can just say okay cut see an ID
intro and now we're good to go so
instead now of doing the the thing where
we actually store that pointer will just
say that instead of game mode cutscene
having anything else in it it can
actually just have this in fact i can go
ahead and put this out here if you want
to like so and say that there's a
cutscene ID that says which scene you're
trying to play and then in here what we
would do is say okay the cutscene you
know there's whatever the cutscene is we
just say the cutscenes array whatever
the ID is lets us look that one up and
then we just use the info pointer from
then on like so
um what are you complaining about you
are complaining about that well you know
what you don't actually need to be a
pointer for any particular reason and
there we go so in case of the intro
cutscene all we do here is to set the ID
equals cutscene ID intro and there we go
so now we should be safe across reloads
for that as well which is nice so let's
go ahead and double-check world mode
okay um getting there looks like we
still have so this would be looking into
a this would be parsing an element whose
grid we don't recognize which means that
someone's still putting events in there
that we're not that we're from the
unloaded version if that makes sense see
who it is
you
keep a person named event grid of course
I can't see the event grid because it's
already been unloaded hmm that makes it
harder to find I must step back to
collate event records here I would like
to know how many event records there
were how many who were on the very first
one actually I'm not sure how to figure
out where that would be I guess what we
could do is try to do it across a run
where we don't really change the
executable but that we could see which
one's come across so I'm going to try
that because I feel like it would be
easier to debug that way than any other
way so what I'm basically saying is I'm
going to make it start and do it's you
know it's normal thing and I'm going to
go ahead and have it ready to go and
then I'm gonna set a break point such
that I know right when the executable is
going to be reloaded so i'm going to set
a breakpoint like here right and so off
we go
I'm not going to change the executable
at all basically and then I'm going to
see what events end up in that slot so
so yeah so let's see we unload the game
code I'm going to take a look too with
the global debug table so this is our
event index here so there's six events
that got written in there let's try this
one more time
so there's six events that get written
in by the debug frame end system itself
I assume that those are like renderer
pieces of render information I guess we
just look and find out so we're on event
indexes ear so we're basically in the
first six events is what no I don't want
to see that many so let me just look to
see what the first six events actually
are so we could figure out who it is
it's writing in there and can we make it
so that they don't write in there
because we want to make sure that no
one's writing in during the reload
unless there's some easier way to do
that I'm not sure hi I would really like
to see this piece of information please
debug start what on earth is debug start
ah guess get best match asset which of
course is going to be getting called
so here's a thought here's the thought
and you can tell me what you think of
this thought of the thinking behind this
thought what if we were to simply turn
off recording of debug messages inside
the debug system so that we knew that
that was not going to be something that
ever actually occurred across the reload
right meaning inside win32 handmade CBP
across the reload we could say all right
from right here after we've drained
after the queues have drained out we do
something like you know debug stop
recording events or a debug set event
recording true and then after that we
say okay debug set event recording oh
sorry false and then true so right
around that block we don't record
anything and I guess we could even say
like we're not going to record anything
all the way till we finish till we
finish reloading so basically we don't
record anything we let this collation
wipe the entire slate clean so we know
that all the events are gone then we do
the reload and we don't resume recording
any events until after then inside the
actual debug interface code we would
have one branch which hopefully would
always be perfectly predictable which
just determines whether we ever actually
do the atomic add right and so what this
atomic add would do is it would just say
like okay will you do the atomic add the
global debug table here and this is
going to be crazy town so just
let's just assume since we drain out the
cues we don't have to care I think so we
do global debug table record increment
right and so in the global debug table
there's just a thing here which is the
record increment and it's either set to
1 or 0 so we don't really we don't
really add any cost we don't even need a
branch we just don't ever update where
we're writing so we just like sit in the
same position and never actually
increment the event count right and this
wouldn't really work with multiple
threads but because we know that we only
care about this in the circumstance
we're not actually doing the recording
and there are no threads running we
should be fine right now I really only
need to do that here because normally we
can let the debug system actually record
itself that's not a problem we designed
to do that it's fine so really I think
all we need to do is actually do it here
it also occurs to me that this could go
away now so really we could have fixed
this whole problem I think leaving the
code in the same place that it was
before and just having this the ability
to turn it off as soon as we detect the
need and yet and we could leave it
turned off so if there's no if the game
doesn't get reloaded we would just never
turn this back on
so I feel like we can do that as soon as
we detect that the executable nice be
reloaded we turn the event recording off
and then when they see one used to be
reloaded we turn that the the event
recording back on only if the game
actually was running yeah
and then this doesn't need to happen
anymore because event recording would
not be occurring if the game failed to
reload itself all right so all that
remains is just for us to actually
implement this that call which is a
debug set event recording and all debug
set event recording is going to do which
is you know enabled you know is it
enabled or not is this going to say
whatever the global debug table was I'm
going to go ahead and take that record
increment and I'm going to say that if
you told me to enable it i'm going to
set up to 1 and if you told me to
disable it i'm going to set it to 0 and
that's it right now we will no longer
record events if we are not actually up
and enabled which i think will mean
we'll never have a problem with the
grids either that's my guess of course
now i think about it we do actually have
to enable it initially so there is that
meaning this debug said event recording
situation has to actually occur at some
point and I guess that would be pretty
much at the immediate outset of the game
we could do that because the debug table
is configured and up immediately so I
think we could say literally right at
the beginning we're just going to start
recording I don't think there's any
reason not to do that
I and so yeah off we go let's go ahead
and see what our status is now look at
that so lovely our game my date is real
slow isn't it of course that's not
surprising we're not even compiled in
release mode all right I'm pretty happy
with all that I am happy with that I am
a happy puppy at that particular piece
of thing all right let's let's take a
look at our build up batter I want to
see if we work in release mode build
see how we're doing here and switch from
here yeah as I thought so a lot of that
we really actually aren't very slow
we're actually plenty fast it's just we
have a lot of debug code happening so
basically this is all time but as we
start making game code we're going to be
filling up with lots and lots of stuff
so that's what we want to see obviously
we don't want our engine to be this big
piggy thing so it's good that it's it
slow because we're not doing very much
right now like they were not really
pushing anything so which we don't want
to see some really nasty you know long
times on there or whatever all right I'm
super double happy with how that went
I'm a happy puppy so I'm going to go
ahead and I'm going to go ahead and say
that that's that's that's very nice I'm
going to leave that where it is then
tomorrow we'll start working on
beautifying the profiler I'm going to
take some questions now from the studio
audience
am I not whitelisted why did QA y is h
MH bot not there it is all right raso
not sure if this was asked before but is
it worth it to use static cast instead
of a see style cast that does not that
does set a cast dynamic cast and
reinterpret cast if you know that you
only need the first so i'm not sure i
100% understand the question but i will
give you an answer and then you can tell
me whether this is the answer that
you're looking for so the problem with c
plus with regular C casts insofar as one
might consider their to be one is that
you might be using it for different
things right in other words if I was to
take for example here in the code if I
was to do something like let's say
something like this
okay suppose I was to do that versus say
something like this right what you can
see in these two examples is I in both
cases I have done a see style cast but
in one case what I was doing was I was
saying that I believe that this 64-bit
value can actually fit in a 32-bit value
and I would like you to convert it
that's just I'm semantically telling the
compiler I had 64 bits I don't need them
all please just use 32 of them give me
that value now and we're going to go
from there right versus this where i had
a pointer and i still have a pointer so
if there's no information loss from here
to here right I'm taking a probably
eight white pointer assuming we're on
six x64 to an eighth by pointer and I'm
ending up with an 8-byte pointer there's
no difference between these two values
they're the same value at the end no
matter what but I'm telling the compiler
I want you to think of the value in a
different way right so you can kind of
see these two things are actually
different operations one is telling the
compiler to treat something differently
semantically which is this one the other
one while it does also tell the compiler
some semantic information is telling it
to change this user do really a lot
telling it is I'm sorry really it's also
telling it truncate the value so these
two things are not equal at the end of
this even though these two things are
right barring the absurd case of the
multiple inheritance C++ class the
hierarchy like forget that but in almost
any other case these two pointers in
practice will be the same so nothing
will actually occur there and I could
make more examples right if you're a
constant of person you might imagine
something like this happening well
that's not really true let's try
something like this
right in this case I'm removing the
Const so in this case I'm not telling
the compiler to treat it differently I'm
not telling the compiler to cop to
truncate it all I'm telling the compiler
is that I don't want you to complain if
I modify it right the thing that it
points to and so the idea behind C++ is
casting was that because these things
are different we want to provide you
with the ability to be more specific
about which kind of cast you were doing
so that if you actually made a mistake
like you weren't trying to truncate
something you were just trying to change
what the compiler thought the type was
it could give you an error and say hey
you were like let's say I did this right
maybe all I was trying to do is convert
it to signed but I forgot this value was
64 bit so what I really wanted to do was
I was trying to say something like this
that's what I was trying to do right but
what I actually did is converted design
but also truncate the value which was
not my intention so maybe I wanted a
compiler error that said hey you
accidentally truncated the value and you
didn't mean to right so that's the idea
behind the c++ cast as with everything
else in c++ they mess them up and so
they're not really i don't like them and
i don't use them but the idea that you
want more control over the cast is not a
bad one and that's why you'll see me do
stuff like this in my code like safe
truncate and those sorts of things
because conversions oftentimes should be
made more explicit than just a cast so
if you are doing cast that you don't
necessarily feel like will always be
rock solid and easy making conversion
function is usually a good idea I don't
recommend using
c++ as casts but i do recommend
potentially making your own now with c++
is cast there's casts there's one more
thing which we don't care about a hammer
here but you might which is there's a
thing called a dynamic cast right and so
for those who don't know what is the
original poster probably knew what this
was but i'm just good mentioning it
others thing called dynamic cast and
what dynamic cast will do is that anti
cast will actually create an exception
or a zero I don't remember what the
rules are for which of those two maybe
you could control it I don't know I
don't care I don't care at all about c++
as you know but if you tried to cast
something to another something so I've
got a struct a and a struct I'd be you
know something like this if I have a way
to distinguish between these two so
let's say that it's something like this
so I've got a struct foo and I've got a
bar oops and I've got a bar which is a
foo if I then have one of these things
that I'm working with here and I want to
cast one of these things to a bar
pointer right I don't really even
remember the syntax for these two
completely honest with you but if I
wanted to cast this a that I have to a
bar star if I use a dynamic cast and I'm
in a situation where this thing has a
virtual function so you know so it had a
virtual table like so in the case where
it had a virtual table it would use the
runtime type information to determine
whether it actually was a bar and if it
was a bar it will give it back to me if
it wasn't it will give me a zero or
something like this like I said I don't
care I so don't care about that stuff
that I don't remember even the slightest
specifics of how they
works it's all really stupid and a waste
of everyone's time but you should be
aware of it that if for some reason
you're using these things there is
special behavior with dynamic cast that
actually is going to look to see whether
or not the thing that you have a point
the thing that you're trying to cast
actually has information in it created
by the secrets of empire that can tell
it whether that cast was possible and
then the cast wasn't possible it will
create a problem so so there you go
cuber Caleb how exactly did they mess up
casting in C++ well again they just
introduced a bunch of business but they
didn't actually cover all the cases so
for example there is no cast from type
to a lower type that you know has a loud
assertion or something when the value
was too big to do that cast so you still
have to write it so all of the cast all
of the conversion functions I used to
write I still have to write pretty much
we're C++ cast so it's like they added
these couple cases that I guess
sometimes you care about they're not
even the ones I would usually care about
so I never actually used them because I
always have to actually use a conversion
function if I actually want to put in an
assertion or another appropriate thing
there so they're really just kind of a
waste of time it's just a lot of typing
it's like a lot of extra typing that
doesn't actually get me what I needed
and so you know because I'd like most of
us less things they don't actually give
the real programmer what they actually
need to do their job so you're still
going to end up writing the the one that
you used to write in pretty much every
case you cared about right and there's a
bunch of stuff like that dynamic cast
the same way it's like i have x what I
need to do discriminated unions this
doesn't do it works with C++ entirety
system that's the only thing it works
with you can't program it to do
something else I can't tell you to do
that I can't tell you to have a dynamic
cash check a type field to see whether
it matches right so again completely
useless right it's like it doesn't give
the primary power it means you have to
use darkness stroustrup stupid idea of
how programs are structured to get any
benefit out of it right and so again you
end up you never use any of that you
always write your own one of whatever
the thing was that the C++ thing was
trying to do because you actually have
to make it work for real right dynamic
asset returns 0 if it fails yeah that's
what I thought I couldn't remember I
thought there was something like maybe
originally when it was proposed it was
going to throw an exception saying there
was like there's some exception based on
an a cast thing I don't know what it was
i I really don't remember it's the debug
view for bitmaps working again I don't
think
because we didn't debug it right i don't
i don't feel like we have done that yet
I could be wrong but I'm pretty sure we
never touched it so if it shouldn't be
where I can't imagine that it is but we
can check yeah there's nothing in there
I i imagine it's probably quite simple
it's just like with the profiler we just
have to go in there and just finish it
up because it's probably just a little
thing we change like probably if zeroed
it out or something for streaming
evolution is there a library worth to
use in C C++ I could do it with Python
but i'd like to see it's a good question
um I don't know there might be it would
be great if there was a well-designed c
string library but I I honestly just
don't know
spending a lot of time in debug tools
before you need them is it going to be
worth it I disagree so I think I covered
this pretty pretty thoroughly when we
started which as you said I'm spending
the lot of time of debug tools before I
need them but we already saw that I had
fact did need them right no sooner did
we finish getting the profiler stuff up
and running that it became completely
obvious that our xbox controller code
was taking too much time right and we we
already passed that and so the problem
with debug code is you have no idea
whether you need it or not right so
saying before you need them suggests
that you actually know whether you need
them and you never do the chances is
almost one hundred percent that you do
because something like that xbox
controller thing will go completely
unnoticed and then there's half a
million cycles down the drain that well
no two million cycles down the drain
that you never would have known were
missing right so i think we exactly
needed them now we could have actually
built them way back when but i felt like
it was important to have threading
rendering and all that stuff up and
running because otherwise how do you
build the debug system right if you
don't have threading and you don't know
whether your devo system actually works
with your threading or not if you don't
have rendering in you can't display
anything you know what I mean so we had
to get to a point where the game was up
enough to actually put debug code in but
it's absolutely worth it now as for the
amount of time it's taken to do like I
said with that I decided to let this be
more of an architectural expression
because I wanted to show people how to
do that so does it normally take this
long ago you could do my system probably
not because if you'd already done one
before and you just decide to do one
exactly the way that you had in the past
you would just do it and you know if you
wanted to write we've got now like if I
wanted to rewrite what we had now it
would only take me like a day or two
right because I know exactly how I
decided everything should work and you
don't have to explore it but exploration
stuff takes a long time so I would say
don't count that against debug code
anything that we decide to explore like
this will take 50 hours or more right I
know how long he bugs taken but probably
60 hours something like
which one handmade hero takes a huge
amount of time because we don't we do
one hour a day but in the real world
remember that's not that long right even
if we spent a hundred hours on debug
code which might be the total at the end
of the day that's two three weeks of
programming in the real world even if
you didn't get faster because I'm not
talking right which you should be a lot
faster if you're not talking all the
time and you can do it back to back so
you don't have to page in and out what
you're working on which of course is
also a problem so really nothing in
handmade here I mean we've only wet
we're day 22 250 eight hours is like no
hours that's like six weeks of
programming it's like you haven't even
started your project yet and we have all
the stuff we have so again like nothing
that we've done in this code base took a
long time all of it is short if that
makes sense Cuba Caleb speaking of
string libraries what kinds of things do
you think should be in a good string
library you know I got to be asked I'm
probably the wrong one to ask uh I don't
do a lot of string manipulation you know
it's not my strong suit because I just
it's not the kind of code I tend to
write I probably should sit down at some
point think about that because I
probably should just write a string a
library for myself at some point that I
just use and it does everything that I
ever could want but I don't know so yeah
like not sure I think honestly the thing
that I would want out of a good string
library that nobody's string libraries
ever seem to care about is actually
really great performance so like for
example don't allocate strings and
deallocate them all the time you know
try to work with try to do things in
temp buffers really efficiently so
you're not constantly copying things
around or allocating tons of memory and
chasing tons of pointers for no reason
which a lot of C string libraries C+
flustering libraries are disastrous that
way
so that'd be one thing that I would like
but yeah
did ince about just a hand banana hero
you rock inside bot is amazing it's
about i think i would like to quote
andrew chronister here and just say that
in sabah is a national treasure in sir
that's a national treasure that's just
this is true keeper caleb does using
virtual Alec and reserving a lot of
memory upfront count I only really care
about performance at this point I think
memory ranges on 64-bit are very cheap
and so if you can get really great
performance out of your string library
by just doing a big virtual Alec and
going nuts great the only thing that I
would point out is using a ton of memory
probably means your performance will be
bad because you'll be blowing out the
cash all the time so you can't just say
well I'm going to just never reuse any
memory in your string library
potentially because if you start getting
big string loads that might actually put
so there's a trade-off there but yet if
you can make sure that that's not
happening so you're keeping your cash
utilization good then I'd say yeah go
nuts reserve a ton of memory and just go
nuts not a problem at all especially
because a lot of the time string
processing stuff is an offline thing and
so especially if you were talking about
string library that was optimized for
offline processing then you don't care
at all because we're not going to be
running on like a phone or something
where like virtual alkene might not work
so well
kubrick killable I meant using mem
reserved than mem commits that you can
append quickly without the copy well
good luck with that though because that
means you're going to have to call
virtual Alec once for every string and
that's gonna be slow right
all right it's time for me to go eat
dinner I'm really happy with how this
debug system turned out I got to be
honest with you it's going to be pretty
pretty awesome yeah what did I do I
actually know what I changed yeah all
right
thank you everyone for joining me for
another episode of handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
with the code at home you can always
pro2 the game on handmade here at work
and it comes with the source code do
that right here with this little button
this is the forums button if you click
on that you will go to our forums where
you can ask questions about the series
and basically what it means is Martin's
mosaico will answer your question
because he is a beast and answers
questions so quickly the guy should have
his own programming advice site or
something I don't even know but yeah or
a patreon that's like pay me because I
answer all your questions which is
really probably sure what should happen
maybe we should just set up a martin's
fund we also have patreon page want to
support the video series which always
remains free to the public we have a
tweet bot which treats the schedule at
you and that is really it I haven't much
more to say at the risk of jinxing it I
will also say that I am hard at work on
the planning for the next handmade con
so as soon as I have a little bit more
information about that i will be sharing
that with you but it's still going to be
a cup few more weeks before i think we
get everything locked down but don't
fear those of you who thought handmade
Con 2015 was awesome and are wanting a
handmade con to happen again because it
quite probably will be happening again
that's about it anyway that's it for
today if you want to use the editor that
we use on the stream I also been
mentioning this lately don't forget you
can get in early with that as well mr.
fourth dimension from the twitch stream
is actually making the editor custom
editor that we use on handmade hero and
it's pretty awesome at this point so
check that out here if you want you can
just type for kodir into Google + and
that'll do it we are using the five
dollar tier one here so highly recommend
that if you want to use same editor
we're using
and my customization file for it if you
want that is included in handmade here
as well that's about it everyone I will
see you back here tomorrow for some
profileview prettying up and feature a
fying which is going to be awesome now
that we know that our bugs are fixed so
hope you'll join me for that until then
have fun programming I'll see you guys
on the internet take it easy everyone