hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero show recode a complete game live on
stream we have well you know we we're
doing so well at this point I'm gonna
have to think about what the the most
sensible path is forward because the
actual lighting now is working like
really well and you know at some point
we should probably switch over to doing
quality stuff because we have some
flicker stuff we want to address and
then we have some blending hard edge
blending stuff we want to address so
we're we're getting to the point we're
gonna have to make some decisions about
when we switch over to that at the
moment though I think today I'd I want
to keep doing some optimization maybe
today and next weekend and then we'll
maybe call it there on the optimization
front unless there was some major thing
that we kind of wanted to do that came
up if you recall what we did yesterday
we were at the point where we welded
into the grid ray tracer we welded in
the sampling code so now we just have
this one large routine that's entirely
stream together you can see here we've
got the grid ray cast right and the grid
ray cast just goes ahead and does
everything so here's the part where it
actually does the ray casting that kind
of comes through here and then there's
this Parshin here which actually does
the voxel sampling right in line and so
it does the Texel it first figures out
what texels need to get loaded it loads
them it figures out how they will be
shadowed and shadows them and then it
sums them up and it then falls right out
into the part where it will actually do
the blend so you look out here and
you've got the part where it actually
blends things out now I don't actually
know so it looks like this is always a
summation to yes you can see here the
transfer people yes gets not summation I
shouldn't say the transfer PPS gets
bucketed up here and I guess that makes
some sense it's a little bit weird to
bucket it but because the way that this
is working is you can see here we do a
load F 32 for X on this stuff and we
write it out with with three stores you
know it's one of those things that's
it's one of those things that it's I'm
not 100% certain is the say myst way to
do that right so if you take a look at
what's actually going on here cuz now at
this point like I said our our job for
today I guess I mentioned this the end
of last stream but I didn't really say
it starting up here our job for today is
to now just look at the combined routine
and start to simplify it a little bit
because now that everything is in one
place we can start to like get rid of
certain places where things get down
shifted or Swizzle that don't really
have to happen right so some of this
code is just not necessary to do anymore
right also the compute voxel irradiance
at call is now actually not used so we
can also just stick that in here with
the the lighting for the AAB ray caster
so this code right here where we have
the a birria AABB ray caster
all of that stuff is also now kind of
just stuff that we don't really need to
have and we can if we want to remove it
right we wanted to leave it in until we
were sure we were faster we're quite
sure we're faster now so we could remove
it I'm not going to actually take the
step of doing that quite yet because we
don't need to but eventually I'm going
to because the actual way we call this
routine can actually be improved as well
I would suspect but anyway
so if we take a look at how these rays
are getting cast all I was trying to say
is the way this thing is writing out is
the first thing that I was just like oh
wait you know we should probably take a
look at this really carefully but what
you see here is were writing out three
of these which each one of them contains
three plus one right so it's like I
shouldn't say it three plus one each one
of these contains four so we're actually
doing three writes of four floats to do
four rights of three floats right
because we have four pixels that we're
trying to write each one has an RG and a
B I should say texels and we can't do a
three-wide right because the rights that
we're doing are going to be 16-bit bytes
whether we like it or not so we're doing
rights that way by basically loading in
this is RGB R this is GB RG and this is
B RGB right so we're loading in like
sort of a odd kind of chunked version of
these things and then we're loading in
what we computed for the transfer PPS
right so we're writing those like to the
stack and then reading them back from
the stack as is something different than
what we wrote C I'm saying but it's not
immediately clear to me that that's
actually what you would want to do right
so the reason I say that is because we
could instead just maintain like four
values and you know for all I know you
could do four registers I don't really
know what our register pressure is at
the moment but I guess it depends on an
AV X part for example you've got more so
I don't actually know to what extent we
might want to actually do something
fancier here right because loading these
back in is is possibly not necessary and
you know loading them kind of oddly like
that I don't know to be honest it
probably doesn't matter too much
but it's just one of those things it's
like I don't know
similarly this stuff here what we could
do so another way to look at this is
like what we could do is actually
preload in the spec Texel values and
actually some of them up here and store
them out here we could do that probably
a little differently as well so you know
you look at how this is working in this
so you can see what's going on here it's
a it's a linear blend we're producing
the inverse and the regular version of
the blend that we're just doing it here
right and what you can see is the
initial values s0 s1 and s2 creating the
inverse of that is something we can do
like right off the bat right so just to
illustrate the point like if you were to
break this into two pieces right this is
exactly the same equation computed in a
split right and so if we wanted to this
would be a totally fine way to compute
this so if we wanted to we could load
these at the outset right we could then
go ahead and store just the in of
blended version of them and then as we
grabbed a transfer PPS we could sum it
in right and the reason I'm just going
through this is because I don't actually
know how we would make that work cleanly
because each round of this produces
three values and we need four to finish
off this part of the routine so each
time through we would need to kind of
reemerge the values and then up on them
to make this work right
so again I'm not really sure I'm not
really sure how to take advantage of
that but I just wanted to point it out
because it's not clear to me that we're
doing the best thing there that we could
it's just a little iffy right because we
are doing this thing where we're load
we're doing these like tight load ups
here and we have to do them together I
imagine it's probably fine because this
will any bottlenecks this will hit it'll
just ride over them because it'll go out
into it'll like ret out of this routine
and those ups will just be sitting in
the pipeline while we do other
computations to get the next rig has
started you know so I don't know right
so once we kind of move forward from
some of the other obvious stuff I I
start I'll start to take a look at that
I guess right but what I'd like to do
now I guess is focused on some of the
easier stuff cuz they don't see any
particular way to fix that in short
order so I'm just going to take a look
at how we're doing some of these other
things here and see if there's any kind
of obvious things that we can fix so if
we take a look at at this part of the
code here I'm going to pull it up on the
the left side so we can see and then
we're gonna look on the right side here
at how we're filling these out so you
can see that when we actually do our
operations here if we are if we early
out here you can see a storing probe P
single probe in single and occlusion D
right and if we error or not error if we
leave here you can see us doing
conversions to get those things right
and what I'm interested in here is I
would like to know if we could just
simplify this process and try to pass
those things through more directly
because what you can see down here is we
actually know what we're gonna do with
these things right you can see the
absolute value taken of the probe and
single right that happens here and the
regular uses of it here so the x and y
of it
go there the Z of it goes here for a
mask right and so you can kind of see
all of how we're using each of these
things the sample P as opposed to sample
n right the sample P is down here and
you can see that that's actually strided
so it's x y and z as one register with
whatever in the end we don't really care
what goes there because we're gonna
leave it out and then the occlusion and
the occlusion end comes into play down
here and you can see that these just get
load ups but replicated they just get
broadcast and so I'm just interested to
see like what we can do to streamline
this process a little bit more so let's
start with the simplest one so if we're
just gonna if we no we're just gonna
load up this or load up is not the word
at all if we're just going to broadcast
this where does that come from and how
would we use it right so let's start by
saying let's let's remove this naming
convention change so instead of going
from occlusion and inclusion D let's
just make it be occlusion D right so I'm
gonna just compile without that and I'm
just gonna go ahead here and replace
that name just because we welded these
two routines together and did the
simplest possible thing but now at this
point I'd like to start like making them
actually come together so the first
thing that you can see is here we have
probe and probe sample and the single
getting assigned to occlusion D so we
can probably simplify this quite a bit
because if we already know that we had
to produce probe sample n single in a
way that would get used here right then
we can probably make this and this
together pretty easily I would assume
looking back here you can see occlusion
D in the other case that we actually
need to exit is just the negative of
rady single one of the things
that I don't actually understand about
the way that we chose to do this is that
since this is how we always error out
this assignment probably shouldn't
happen here it's just complicating this
part of the routine so probably these
two things because they are known should
probably just go up in here because you
can just front load the loop with that
computation and that way you don't have
to have a dependency on it when you move
down into the lower part of the code I
can't really think of a lot of reason
why we wouldn't do that
so you know I think mostly what we're
looking at here is is more this yeah so
you know we have got this part of the
process to which is producing the normal
and single so you know when we look at
this we know it looks like anyway we're
gonna have to produce this value in sort
of two different ways right we need the
broadcast able version and then we need
the regular version this one is not the
same it's the negative of it right so so
I guess though in that case it's still
more or less trivial to produce because
it's just a negation right so again in
both cases these two values are really
closely related and so I suppose that's
really not that big of a deal one way or
the other so our job here is really just
to figure out how to simplify this down
and not have so much fussing it is a
little bit bad that we have just you
know two sort of ways that that's gonna
work so let's take a let's take a look
at the occlusion D again so that's those
are broken apart so actually though now
you know I guess actually looking at it
they're always broken apart really so
it's really just one
we just want replicated our X and Z in
there in both cases so and looking at it
though I think we still want them packed
because if you look at what will happen
with impact we would want to do this
absolute value in a more we'd want to do
the absolute value wide on the are X's
and Y's and then just broadcast to get
the 1 norm probably would be my guess
and then assuming that they were wide
like that again we would just broadcast
from that one value yeah so I think what
we want to do here is let's just start
by just taking occlusion D and I'm gonna
just start with the simple act of making
a clusion D here be equal to negative R
ad single like this so that we don't
actually have any initialization of it
in here I think again I'm just it's just
a little bit hard to know whether it's
smarter to put it up here or not if you
take a look at what's gonna have to
happen with it the radial value which is
going into the probe and thing here so
the raid erection already gets used here
right and it's just a little weird
because it's replicated out right and
the reason is replicated out is because
it's gonna get used in this way so we're
already taking up a bunch of slots with
this and so it's really hard for me to
say exactly how we want that to go if if
this were actually packed so the radii
actually along a line you can see here
why we don't do that it's well actually
can you well actually actually hold on
let's see where this gets used so I'm
gonna do a search for rady ear and see
what's going on with that you can see
the inverse getting taken there
I wish this my head wasn't in the way so
this is actually kind of interesting oh
my oh my goodness alright so basically
this code is kind of kind of garbage
actually Wow
so I so this is all terrible and there's
a lot of stuff that we could do here so
if you take a look at what's going on
here's us computing sine values from Ray
deep but as you can kind of see there's
no reason like whatsoever that this
would have to get done here
these are constant for the Ray and you
could have done this wide anyway so like
this is kind of just dumb so we have a
lot of work we can do here this is this
is just kind of ripe for for fixing so
if we imagined that our rady was packed
which i think is what we actually want
you could have done this right so this
would do all three of these at the same
time and then you would just use the one
you actually cared about to produce the
normal values and if you look at what
these are doing it's doing it wide again
so like this doesn't make any sense you
know just just bear with me here
so if you take a look at what's going on
you can see like alright we have sine X
Y Z this are being done like 1 2 3 but
we could have done them just like this
if ray D was packed we would have just
gotten those and radius constant so we
don't even need to do this we could do
this once at the top of the function not
only the constant is from a table so we
could actually do this pre compute it
right I mean duh so anyway if you take a
look at at what we were doing there this
is this is just just stupid so then if
you look at what's going on here let's
suppose that we were going to compute
normal XY Z there and just leave it
packed so if we were going to do that we
would just have normal XY Z which is
actually all of these sine X Y Z is
already lamed it's right there so we
just need to do an or with this so we'd
have 1 x and x max 1 and Y mask and an
and not with the Z mask right and so if
we wanted to make this line up all we
would have to do is not so
how come I can't where is this and not
where is that coming from how come
that's not showing up here that's weird
so why isn't that why isn't that jump
weird so and not for some reason it's
not sure that I don't know why doesn't
matter don't really care
oh is it because it doesn't handle
comments interesting yeah it doesn't
have a comments that's what it is
interesting so if you take a look at
here it's the bee that gets knotted so
it's like the Z mast that actually wants
to get knotted and so the and not that
we're doing here if we just wanted to
make this be completely like inline you
would just do like oh you know not this
thing right you know what I mean so if
you did not that thing and put the end
in here then all of a sudden this is all
so wide you see what I'm saying so I'm
just knocking these out one at a time I
don't actually want to do that quite yet
because I wanted to leave that code path
intact so if we assume that we then just
grabbed this part and put it in here for
the moment we need to do this but
otherwise we can then say sign X Y Z get
sword with 1 and XYZ mask like so and
off we go right so at that point we're
just saying we just need to produce an X
Y Z mask here and you can see the
various pieces that we were actually
trying to do it's a little bit hairy
like it's you know it is what it is but
presumably there's a way we can do this
not too horribly wide and so you can see
why I want to do this is because it
collapses to just two instructions
something that previously took six
instructions at the cost of just adding
one not into something else so the
question now is how would you compute
this efficiently and I'm not entirely
sure so the point of the pea chef Bea's
here is to produce the min X and the min
Y in the correct location and
unfortunately oh but you know what
what does correct location mean in this
case hold on one second oh yeah okay so
this actually does a full replicate so
that actually means that this will
produce the correct location for this
thing so actually we can just do like a
select or something to merge these
things together first if we wanted to I
mean I don't know that we do because we
need to do the inverse part here to make
sure that we only get one of these and
that's really going to be the hardest
part
so I'm going to take a quick look at
exactly why we chose to do this way this
was trying to make it as efficient as
possible right because what you could
see is when we are doing our actual
collision loop so this is checking again
since each individual box in a set of
boxes and what you can see is when we
actually do the the hit testing we store
some of the stuff that we actually need
like what the color and emission was for
each of the lanes right and then we also
store the min X and the min Y and the
reason that we did that was just because
we want to know which side we hit so we
know which normal to pick right so these
are really the only reason that we're
storing these is just so we can try to
figure out like what we actually hit
whether we hit the minimum or the
maximum and so when we come down here
all we're really doing is saying look
did we hit a minimum or a maximum right
for this thing and so it's saying if we
hit the and and you can see we use the X
and the y right are the two that we keep
so we're just saying look did you hit
the minimum or maximum of the X right
and did you hit the minimum or maximum
of the Y that's what we're just trying
to do and so what we're doing is we're
just looking to see whether this thing
is equivalent T ray or not and since we
don't know which one of them which one
of the lanes contains the actual value
that we care about we're using the
shuffler to move the thing we hit into
the well and it basically replicates it
everywhere so that we just end up with
one value and off we go
so if we hit whatever this the hit team
in X thing the thing that we actually
hit there it's not I shouldn't say
whether we hit the minimum of the
maximum it's just whether we hit the X
or not right whether X was the thing
that was the closest hit that that's the
way I should say it's not the max is not
relevant because we don't care which
side of the box it's it's the min of the
Ray that's coming in so it was the
closest hit that's what that min refers
to so it's actually just saying look did
the X did the X stop us and then it says
that the Y stopped us and then it says
well if neither the X or the Y stopped
us then the Z must have stopped us right
so that's what we're doing there is just
saving that value or those two values
because it's cheap right we don't have
to compute anything additional
but it's just not obvious the fastest
way to get from there to the normal and
I'm just wondering if a mob mask plus a
load would be faster right like I'm
wondering if we could just do something
more straightforward here so if we
compute the ex mask and the Y mask and
then did a mauve mask
it just seems like we could just load
that in I don't know and then you
wouldn't have to do this you just you
just you just or in the sign
yeah so
I'm just kind of tempted to go ahead and
do it the other way so let's just take a
quick look at what that would look like
so suppose you just did a mauve mask on
these right so although I guess we have
I think we have an actual function for
that don't mean like or whatever I don't
really remember what it is but I thought
we had like some really poorly named
function yeah like this it looks like we
don't so any true yeah so I don't know
it doesn't it doesn't look like we
really have a thing that moves the mask
which we should like we probably should
but anyway it doesn't matter so if we
were to do a move mask on just like two
of these so like let's do the XCOM first
so we'd compare X's we'd compare Y's and
then we could move masks these right and
we know which bit we would actually want
here because again I'm just trying to
see like to what extent this would be
simpler and we could actually also
probably do these so they're both going
to be in the same Lane so if we if we
just take
take these two here and now we have like
a bit for the X and a bit for the Y and
we know that they are in the shuffle
index lane of this so the mauve mass PS
we would just say look if you take that
Mothe mask and you shuffle and you shift
it down by shuffle index you're going to
get the bit that you actually care about
right in the low so if we did something
like this where we just use these
probably like so then this entire path
could be done in scaler if we want it to
right so trying to think of how this
would want to work it'd probably be more
like we want to shift it I'm really not
sure exactly how we want this part to
work right but it would be something
like this so you'd start out and you'd
say like you know extract which one of
the X we're doing extract which one of
the why we're doing put them together
here like whether it was the X or
whether it was the Y and then at that
point you're gonna get an index into a
table of four values and you can just
get the normal right so then you would
just say like okay
get me the normal right so you wouldn't
need to do any of this it'd just be two
comps and then a bunch of scaler now I
know that seems a little bit weird but
because this isn't wide like we can only
do one because we only produce one hit
after doing all the collisions wide
sticking this in scaler might actually
be the right decision
the reason I say that is because if you
take a look at these instructions so you
know let's just flip over here just to
give you a little bit of a background
here so suppose I go into sse and i say
look if we did an and PS like what's
gonna happen there and you can see how
the poor tissue works ignore this line
because this is a memory op so these are
like you know the memory ports that are
I'm sorry these are the memory ports
here 2 &amp; 3 so we're really just looking
at this right and you can see how it
issues issues on port 0 1 &amp; 5 so if we
were doing the and PS is and and you're
gonna see that a lot so if we did a not
PS I guess wouldn't be there but you can
see here we got Pia 1 0 1 5 I don't
remember what not and and not is or if
there even is one I think there is but I
just yeah and NPS there it is 0 1 5
right comp EQ or comp PS is 0 &amp; 1 right
so 0 1 and sometimes 5 are the ports on
which stuff can happen if you then go
look at like what you can do if you're
just using a regular register what you
can see is that port 6 shows up a lot so
if you want to do something like
register to register and or shift I
don't remember what the shift mnemonics
are
do you have that it's like gonna be yeah
left shift logical right so if you take
a look at what you can do if you're
doing register to register shifts or
whatever the let me see what if we've
got any what is the logical shift III
never remember these mnemonics cuz I
never did any Intel CPU programming back
before Cindy at all it's like I never
remember the monix for any of this stuff
so let's see x64 shift
assonance for instructions s al s AR s
HL okay that's what we needed
so we don't care about arithmetic shifts
those are ones that replicate the sign
bit so we really just care about s HL SH
are probably in this case okay so here's
that Shh l for immediate so there's a 31
maybe again port six right so basically
what I'm thinking is that we can
basically just shove all this work on to
port six while other people are
finishing up crap from using all of
ports here one in five right so we may
just be able to get this for free so
instead of like basically like massively
overloading the other ports the two
comps can be done will have to be done
those purpose then everything else could
be done on port six well nobody is
actually using it the only thing I'm not
sure about is the mob mask I don't
really know how bad that is
it's a it's a one you up port zero it's
it's not horrible right so I don't know
it's easy to savings is it not this is a
shift by a register which is not
fabulous so you know and one of the
things that we could do here is actually
just do the and on a register and then
do one shift so rather than two variable
shifts we could do this in the opposite
order and that might make more sense
hard to say if we look at these if I
don't know what a register register
shift looks like here so let's just take
a look so it's a bit expensive but still
on port six so I don't really care I
don't think
so let's see what we've got here um do I
have any other cares of this year so
let's see what do we have for what is
the point of that
so I guess there's a different profile
for just a single bit shift somehow
maybe on other maybe on different
architectures doesn't look like it is
here
that is that's kind of interesting right
so I mean I'm assuming that basically
this is what we would end up with is one
of these which it doesn't have bad
latency it does take three UUP's
but again it's not that bad because some
port six oh I think I think this is
probably fine right and then what we
would do is you just have the normal
table here you would just have the
normals that you actually cared about
right so the normal table you would just
load load out of that so let's suppose
like I don't know why we have the
shuffle table defined here sort of
defining it out side but you know
whatever
so the shuffle table there looks like
this the normal table would look like
this if both of these are zero that
would mean it was Z so you know if we
take a look at how these are going to be
it's like you know X Y Z and nothing
right so Z would be if it was a zero if
it was zero zero was the lookup into the
normal table
if we just had the bottom bit set that
would be X if we just had the second bit
set that would be Y and then if both
bits were set then it's really our
choice and that just means that it kind
of hit like a corner and we don't really
know which corner it hit because we
don't know what the Z value would have
been so we don't know we shouldn't say
corner it hit an edge it may have been
at a corner if the Z value was set
otherwise we don't know so we could
choose to use like an edge but I'm not
I'm just gonna bias towards X and say
it's gonna be X in that case right so if
we want to load out of the normal table
we can do that as well and just say okay
normal table and I'll just make this be
kind of a thing that you don't ever
actually use and just say alright that's
that's the normal tables so now you can
look up into the normal table and just
load one of those and be done with it
right so in here you just load it up and
you'd call it a day I think and I think
that's all we really need right yeah so
yeah so it looks like inverse sign bit
was never implemented
just for F thirty twos I guess or oh no
it's because we haven't actually made
this packed yet that's the only reason
yeah yeah nevermind right okay
also I guess this technically wants to
be an F 32x so I guess we we actually
want that
I'm also not sure that would not
actually be a star there oh and this is
wrong this needs to be initialized every
time through the loop so I'm not sure
but yeah that was a little bit premature
but so when we were actually doing this
this part still needs to be in there
this part doesn't on that part can be up
at the top just so it's clear but yeah
this shuffler has to start being the
right value because I believe it doesn't
get set in the case where we well I
don't know so where is this used
so
so I guess the idea is we just load this
out of here and then we let it fall
through to the bottom where we still use
it which seems kind of strange so you
can see us doing it unpacking it here
for like the emission level and stuff
right but it seems kind of weird that
you wouldn't just do that inside so
right like I don't quite get it so I
feel like this is all so stupid I feel
like there's a lot of stupid stuff going
on here and again it's it's not because
we were stupid really or anything it's
just because we've gone through so many
iterations of like refining this thing
you starting to get to the point where a
lot of it can just be kind of collapsed
down so yet it's a little bit weird
right but anyway okay so rady needs to
be packed and then in here we have the
normal XYZ stuff and so probe ends
sample and single we have to decide how
we're gonna actually feed that out but I
think this is like way more efficient
than this was because this was extremely
expensive and this is not right so I
think we basically just want this and I
think that's by far the simplest way to
get that normal out that we found so far
so yeah sorry so I think we're getting
somewhere on this now again we just have
to decide how our exact we do this for
this part of the things again for v3 we
can just quickly test this to see if
it's doing okay by first of all making
our ad be packed like I said that we
wanted it to be but furthermore we can
also do this this part here by just
doing extraction for testing let me just
again double check I want to see if
probes sample and single
and yeah it looks pretty much like the
r-value there is he's just taken like I
said with with each of these these bits
here so I don't know just for testing
purposes it kind of feels like we
probably need to keep doing things more
or less the way we were doing them it's
tough
I'm gonna go ahead and and put this part
as an if one for now and just
double-check that this is working okay
there we go yeah we kind of need some
better ways to test this but we probably
during the quality round we'll do some
testing anyway so hopefully we'll suss
out weird bugs in there when we get to
that point but so what I want to do here
is I before I flip on this path I would
like to go ahead and get the other path
working the back end working where it
accepts things in the other format so if
we were to look and say let's make probe
and single come through wide then what
we would do is we could still leave this
part the same for you know this kind of
crappy version of this path we would
just move this in here and say okay it's
going to be an f32 for X right I believe
yeah
um and so program ends sample single is
gonna be an f32 4x and so then at that
point the radial which is this we really
just need to load this this rate up as
an f32 4x in order to get this started
right and again this can be done much
more efficiently because we could do
this as a single load but at this point
we're looking at a part of the routine
that's so uninteresting because it's
it's not the you know it's it's not
something that's running the loop and
it's not a particular important part so
we will probably want to sort of clean
this part up later as well but at the
moment we're not going to do that yeah
so then for probe and sample single and
we have rady single here so what we want
to do now is say well that's the rady
that's that's actually the the PAC
tradie value that we would want to put
in here and so if we take a look at
probe sample and single here I'm not
sure why because if this was already
getting set there this wouldn't have to
happen anyway because that because probe
and single already was set to radial
just to start with so this is not
necessary right and occlusion D but in
the same way could just have been done
up here with a sub so it wouldn't really
have to get touched so what we could
have done here is say well okay like
occlusion D the packed version would
also do that right but again I'm not
actually gonna look at that yet because
I just want to do it one step at a time
so here we're probe and sample single
where we're setting the occlusion D this
parts a little bit tricky because again
now we're not actually computing that
anymore but just in keeping with what I
said about taking it one step at a time
I'm just gonna go ahead and try as best
I can to like keep this path working
exactly the same so then in here where
we use our as probe sample and single
I'm just going
go ahead now and start to actually try
to use this properly so in here where we
nullify out these two lanes to be
completely honest with you I don't know
that we care about that so if you look
here and see the shuffle it will only
take the two lanes anyway and iuv
isn't used anywhere else is it well okay
so it's used there right with that Z
mask so the question is how much do we
care about that so we do not use this
anywhere else right so basically we can
leave those lanes as garbage because as
you can see right here we actually like
get rid of them like those two zero
zeros will nullify whatever was in the
UV no matter what you selected out so
this right here can actually now be
replaced with just probin samples single
because we actually just know that that
is what it is I can change it to our for
the time being and go like that right
and we should be fine now if you look at
what's going on here we need to test the
Z value and do a select on that and we
need that to have been replicated right
we need to have the the replication here
but that's pretty easy because we can
just do like a broadcast for X on that
thing and I don't actually know how that
was written yeah with the index so we
could if we want Z we can just say look
broadcast out the Z and off you go
right so at that point it's pretty
straightforward to produce the one norm
which we want to do the sum and the
divide fat parts again it's a little bit
harder unfortunately
just because we we're trying to do a
horizontal ad here and those are just
slow they they don't end up really being
any faster a lot of times than just
doing it manually so it's kind of
unfortunate but what we want to do here
is just say okay let's let's go ahead
and do this um so I'm gonna do an ABS R
is absolute value of R because you can
see that it's being done to all of these
so we might as well just do it once and
then all we have to do is just do a
broadcast for X on our R to basically
some it out right and in this case we
want our abs are because we don't again
want to do it we just want to do that
that some right and when we get to here
this one is this one is just the regular
R so we can just use that right so I
think that's everything that we needed
and now probe n sample single in this
case is just it's just the value it's
just it's just flows directly through
right and so our goal would then be to
also change sample P to to be that next
right and you know in theory that's now
got the correct flow through for
sampling right and again we would really
like some better testing here it's it's
very hard for me to know like to what
extent this is actually correct so at
some point we're probably gonna have to
do some kind of like thing where we put
like a unit test on top of the grid
raycast
just to like try to suss out problem
like finicky problems that won't show up
because if there's a really major
problem we'll see it but if there's a
subtle problem like oh that normal is
pointing the wrong direction with
something like lighting it's so hard to
know if it's right just by look
that like we're probably enough to
construct some really specific test
cases so we can see that's I don't
really know any other way to it approach
it there's really not a lot of ways to
unit test the entire system but we could
like try to isolate just the grid
raycast
and say like okay we know if we shot
away from here it should hit this thing
and it should point in this direction
right and we could construct some of
those cases
- just like test out like okay can we
get each of the normals the right way
what happens if we get a corner like you
know just try to do a couple of those
things just for trying to suss out bugs
in the routine and it's like pushing
structure dart through it basically
right I often talk about how useful that
is so we would just be pushing structure
dart effectively through the pipeline
here to see what happens that's all all
right so let's suppose that sample P was
going to be a 32 for X as well like
let's go see what that would do so if we
look through here for the usages of
sample P you can pretty much see that
actually it's just this is all it is so
so actually that part we don't even
really need - all we would do in here is
just say oh all right we just want this
to happen now right so so that's pretty
straightforward and now what we would do
is look back at where sample P was
getting constructed and for I should
sorry I did that a little bit too
sleight of hand
I meant that so we need probe P single
now to be coming through as an f32 for X
as well and again this is just us trying
to simplify that part of the pipeline so
there's not so much shuffling around so
if we look at probe P single here how
that's getting initialized it's as ray
origin single and again so we can do a
pretty simple sort of fudging here for
the time being of this
so now that we just have the Ray origin
it just gets packed in there as the
probe piece single and that's all we
really need it to be at the moment right
and so let's take a look at where that
gets set so you can see here where we do
probe P single cos ray or it's a single
plus T Terminator II D single producing
this Ray origin here now you can see
that this is actually ray origin single
we're actually creating that same value
so probe P single and Ray are just ago
the same value at the start so we can
make that pretty simple T terminate is
just the T value which we could just be
making wide at this point it's really
easy for us to do that and so this could
be a wide value very very simply and so
r ad single is then the only thing that
we actually would need and you can see
that it's already something that we were
doing that way it's this value here
right
so I think all we really want to do is
now start by probably the first thing is
to look to see if ray D single is
actually used like anywhere other than
to do exactly the thing now and it's not
so if we look at what we're gonna do
here we're going to change and then I'll
just use sort of a new naming scheme for
this just to make it clear but it should
become obvious what we're doing so let's
just make a rady which is exactly this
value and so at the start the probe
sample n single is just going to be the
radii act value right and then here we
would just use the radio packed value
and this t terminate would be packed as
well the Ray origin single I'm just
going to call this ray origin packed and
it's literally this right and this probe
sample P single would just be ray origin
packed right
because we know we need to sort of
produce these values anyway so we can
just stuff them in here and they'll be
sitting on the stack when we need them
the probe sample P single here would now
just be the Ray origin packed Plus D
terminate comes array D packed and
that's all we would really actually need
now the problem here is that T
terminates not going to be correct so
this needs to be expanded out I don't
remember what this was called there it
is so T terminate would start at zero
and then when we advance it so like this
the only difference here is we just
loaded up right so we would just load it
up into a wider wider thing so again in
terms of keeping this without actually
doing any actual work here if we go
ahead and oops if we go ahead and
continue the trend of just putting this
into that format without actually trying
to make it actually do it efficiently
you can see that we can compile the code
as it is at the moment and hopefully we
didn't mess up too much right hopefully
everything's still okay there it looks
pretty reasonable at the moment anyway
all right and so once we sort of do a
clusion D here then we will have all of
them and so at that point we should be
in in good shape so let's just finish
that off so let's take a look at where
occlusion D is getting used you can see
here that it's it's just getting used by
doing a sort of a replication here so
let's just change that to say look let's
grab the XYZ out of this thing like so
and then occlusion D can go ahead and
also be NF 32x right so we can do this
and say let's zero here I don't know why
these are not also being done this way
they probably should be just for
completeness because it lets compiler
see that that's supposed to be zeroed
there instead of like do they remember
how the initialization syntax affects m1
tomates
you know I don't know maybe they do
maybe they don't don't want to have to
think about it so here I can just use
ray deep act so that's a pretty easy way
to set occlusion D in this case again
since we know that this will be what
happens on fallout what we probably
could do is just do this up at the top
so that could just be that it's just a
sub to replicate and that seems probably
fine
that'd be my assumption anyway if we
then look at what happens to occlusion D
here same thing as that we did last time
just going to change this to an F 3 to
4x and off we go
right
so again not really very interesting
just going through the motions of
untangling this code in the way that we
wanted to before and so that should all
be good seems like everything is working
very very well here
yeah so moving on now what I'd like to
do is is try to get some of these other
cases working more efficiently so if we
take a look at how much cruft is
happening in here we can hopefully now
do something much simpler so here we
need to produce three things we need
probe and single a probe sample P single
and occlusion D right the occlusion D in
this case is the same as the normal so
really this could also just be that
right so this is the same thing there so
you know in theory that's that's totally
fine and so in this case we know that
that that's always going to be the case
and we don't really have to think too
hard about it right so we could we could
just eliminate that out of these two now
so really in this particular case we're
just producing two things here these two
values that's all we're doing the probe
P symbol single here you can see when we
produce probe sample P it doesn't
actually get used for anything so you
can see that this is actually kind of a
dumb thing so we can again simplify this
and it actually speeds up this part of
the code too because this was doing a
bunch of unnecessary work since tier a
has now been replicated ray origin x ray
D those are already in stuffed formats
so we can actually just nuke this probe
sample P and when we actually do this
probe sample P single thing here we
can't just do ray origin pacts plus T
ray x ray deep act right and that goes
away so that's pretty nice and then for
probe n sample single although I suppose
I should do this or something and since
that that should really let's do this
that's just organize this a little since
this is all the normal and that's all
not
there we go so yeah so you can see here
right we can we can do all of this this
can all be done way more efficiently
that's this is like gonna be three times
faster than that presumably so that's
nice so then we're just down to this
when we produce the normal XYZ this way
which in theory we're saying works at
that point that is probe sample and
single because it's the normal XYZ
packed which is now what we actually
want and so in theory that's the whole
thing right in theory so now we have to
debug this actual part where we compute
the normal this is probably correct
because it's not a lot I could have
screwed up there but the normal parts
probably wrong and we're probably gonna
have to go through there and figure out
what to do with it right now the inverse
sign bit from part again this is
actually just known so we don't need to
do this but I guess there's no reason
not to do it here I don't know it might
be better to just let this happen
outside and I don't again I really just
don't know so if we took where we
produce radio packed if in here we just
said look give us the inverse sign we
could just do that and pull it's pulled
out so it's really just these these bits
here is is all we would actually need
right yeah so again we got to go to bug
that because it's probably wrong I mean
it looks right here so hard to say I
guess but you know again we kind of need
to put some test cases through so we
don't really know like maybe this norm
maybe these normals are right maybe
they're not but you know with lighting
it's always pretty difficult
I mean here's an example so let's just
see what the chances are that we're
wrong so let's say we just always pick
the wrong normal you know how different
would it look right I mean right like
it's like you can't even tell right
which which maybe suggest that you know
we're kind of wasting our time getting
some of this stuff correct but right I
mean that's it's kind of nuts like it
doesn't matter which normal I I'm
selecting so yeah a little bit weird but
we do want to test this and see you know
what's going on there you know is there
a bogus or not a bug right so so this is
not great
we're gonna have to to
that said let's since I think it's
roughly still the correct number of ops
there let's see how we're doing now on
the benchmark just so I can get a sense
of if I've done anything really stupid
which sometimes happens I don't want to
slow this routine down for obvious
reasons so let me just run HH late prof.
a few times here to see what kind of
noise were getting on the samples and
just just so I can kind of get a feel
for what the speed difference is if
there is one so yeah I don't know where
we were at before actually so actually
that's pretty good
we're still we're still getting faster
and faster with each revision so now if
we take a look at how this code is
working again like I just want to do a
quick spot check to see like where are
we where are we in terms of
[Music]
so hold on a second what the heck is Z
offset here and why is it never used
okay there it is like what's going on
okay
so now if we take a look I just want to
kind of run through this routine and
look and see if there's anywhere now
that we're still using something weird
like a downshift where we or a weird
unpacking or something like that right
so I just want to kind of get a sense
for what the heck you know what we're
doing and and then see if there's
anything yeah just just want to see if
there's anything weird
so yeah so I mean just just cleaning up
some little tiny things so this is
supposed to be one - so you know it
should be this because that's just one
sub instruction it shouldn't be loading
another value so that was that was
pretty dumb that doesn't need to be
pulled out either so like this doesn't
have to happen here at all this could
just be nope not that there we go
this could just be used directly here
because this is the only place that gets
loaded up right so that's a little bit
simpler as well I don't think we need
these anymore we can always add them
back in there not particularly
interesting so yeah so now looking at
what's happening here this looks pretty
bad
[Music]
yeah and these are like these are values
that probably should all have been pre
computed right so the stride XYZ and the
voxel dim part C should be just things
you can load up directly out of your
Atlas so I think that's pretty simple
and the other parts pretty simple so I
think I would want to go do both of
those actually and then there's some fat
we can trim out of here not that's
performance related but just now there's
some like old values when we could name
things better and such things like that
right so let's go ahead and do that
first of all let's take these things
here and put them into the Atlas so
let's go to the light atlas code and
where we actually do the in it's on it's
like make light atlas or whatever right
so in here let's just let's just put
these values in there so you know in
here there's gonna be like you know this
thing and so you know these these will
just be things that we store now in the
actual Atlas itself so that we know that
they're gonna be available at all times
we don't have to do this ridiculous load
impact like they'll just be in there and
correct so all of this stuff can just be
like alright whatever the well I guess
these are just already known so there's
the voxel dim and the tile dim there so
but well you know I'll just do it this
way anyway since they are dependent
what is the complaint oh yes it's 4x all
right so that way we just have those
there and what do we not have one we
have one it must have just been declared
inside yeah get out there there we go
so these two it looks like the light
atlas for some reason is not declared
after the sims ii is that be cut no so
I'm not sure why that's actually messed
up
probably because those sim D things
aren't defined in there so let me
actually just go to win mate handmade
open jail and maybe we'll just include
that right so oh well it's pretty
obvious is that better
this is just annoying see nonsense
there's really no point to it
so those are just in the wrong order
yeah none of that should ever have to
happen but it's just the way see is
finally in win32 handmade and alright so
in the renderer test stuff I'm not sure
to what extent I really care one way or
the other about whether or not we still
compiled that so I made just nerve that
for now because no one ended up using it
so I may just say that's not gonna get
maintained anymore unless someone has a
good reason to do it yeah alright so
moving on now that we have those stored
in the light at lists we should be able
to inside the the lighting code now
instead of having to construct those
values every time those should just be
things that we can load up out of this
out of the atlas directly which again is
just there to save us time right and one
of the things that could do so you know
what I probably should have done to be
completely honest though no I think
about it maybe this was dumb maybe we
just leave that enabled and and we don't
really need Cindy in here right because
the other thing I could do was just this
right those to you you know then you
could just say like F load F 3 to 4x and
say you know load it out of there and
and call it a day right that seems more
sane this I don't know what we want to
do with that this may also be something
we want to load up out of I'm not I'm
not a hundred percent sure what I want
to do about that so we'll like leave
that B for a second but once we put
those in this format then you know we
could just do it slightly differently so
here now we just would say okay these
are going to get set like this
and this voxel dim Forex will do the
same okay
so if we do it that way I think that's
just a lot more sane because then we can
avoid having to like actually make any
concessions in here because it's just
some floats we need to load so we don't
really care if I look at load through
the Forex you can see it's a none
aligned load anyway so those don't even
have to be aligned so we should just be
fine
now if we run I think we're okay and
yeah we should just we should just be
okay and reproduce the same results okay
so if we take a look at what happens
there now we're just doing less fussing
in that exit code which which should be
good and again it it doesn't have a huge
effect right either way but at least is
just getting that streamline so we know
we're not paying any weird penalties
there right and again we're starting to
get like we're getting like really into
a pretty good good place if you look at
at how expensive this is now
we're down in the in the really enviable
place of 4.5 seconds here we started at
seven point four seconds so that's like
a pretty crazy jump down right so now
we're literally two seconds of
raycasting time and and that's kind of
nuts right well not really I guess
because we have to retake we would have
to retake this because the computer
radians so we need to like redo this
computation so you know no we're not but
we're getting very low let's put it that
way I don't know what I want to do next
exactly but I believe the most important
speed improvement is still yet to come
in in the as far as the recasting part
of things and we can talk about that a
little bit I'm just trying to think if
there's anything else I want to do
before we kind of go off in that
direction we could just now remove the
ABB caster entirely because I don't know
that there's any point in running it or
even caring about it anymore so since we
do have it checked in and anyone can go
grab it if they want it I think maybe
now might be a good time to just start
pulling that out as well again this is
just cleanup work it's not really gonna
make things significantly faster or
anything like that but it's probably a
good time to start simplifying so let's
get rid of that because now I'm pretty
pretty confident in in what we ended up
doing let's go ahead and pull this whole
branch so let's get rid of that
and we're again we're only going to
really use the grid path so I'm going to
leave anything grid path related in here
and I'm just gonna remove the ABB caster
right so let's see here we've got the
build still on here somewhere
yep there we go and that probably is
most of it yeah okay and so I think that
gets rid of basically everything that we
need and in in this case here we don't
really care about this part anymore so
we can just you know we can't just get
rid of it so I think now that's all of
that sort of cruft that's gone and we
can start simply everything else more
now too right so now if we go through
the lighting code and also I guess the
ABB stuff like can just be ganked so for
example if there's anything I guess well
you know it I don't see anything
particularly a specific to that though
so I guess we were just using the
lighting box structures for the abbs so
is fine
I don't know in here if there's anything
the lighting boxes can just stay the way
they are this part I think is just not
relevant anymore
so I don't know if anything other than
is light is any more necessary because
we don't need any of this stuff right so
I'm kind of curious about the lighting
box pack thing and I'm trying to think
about what we want to do with that
because we do need the is light but we
could probably do that in other ways
really hard to say so if you look at how
many of these there are there's three
floats each for three values so there's
nine floats they're getting it down to
eight floats would be nice or I should
say eight values would be nice and that
would be pretty easy because if we just
packed the color value in some cleaner
way that would do it
so if for example we said all right this
is six values and then we had one value
for the ref color and one value for the
flags or you know 64 bits total that
would have the light plus you know some
kind of 10 bits per channel 12 bits per
channel pack right so I think in the
future this
I think in the future we can pack this
down and save some bus bandwidth there
right at the moment what I'm gonna do
instead is say look we don't really want
to mess with this at the immediate
moment so at the right now
I'm probably just gonna go ahead and say
you know what this is just gonna be is
light and that's it but I think in the
future instead of for values for this we
can get this down to two right it's
because we have way more in just in
terms of storing lighting values we have
way more than we need there right so
yeah so I can go ahead and simplify this
now that we kind of know what we're
doing so this doesn't need to be an end
anymore that's literally just gonna be a
check on whether or not it's a light
okay
so again just just trying to clean up
some of the cruft here because now that
with ABB is gone we don't need that
extra inline hierarchy packing that's
just a waste of everyone's time so now
let's go and take a look at the full
cast and see what is actually going on
in here so you can see when we call full
cast you can see that there's just a
bunch of ridiculous dancing around and
crap that's happening and what we want
to do is now that we know exactly who's
getting called here and why we want to
we want to have some way of figuring out
what should get passed
to grid raycast and make sure that
that's being done as efficiently as
possible
right because at the moment I doubt that
it is and this is not really necessarily
for speed because at this point we
probably got most of the speed out of
the streamlining that we can so this is
really more just for my sanity like I
don't really like how sprawling this
code became it was unavoidable for the
most part but now that we know what
we're doing so now that we've finished
our exploration it's just a good time to
kind of clean it up so let's start by
just going through and figuring out who
the heck is doing what and why so you
can see here that we've got a box test
to see whether we're inside any of the
boxes so we're just looking inside our
node and we're looking to see whether we
landed inside any of these boxes and if
we did land inside one of these boxes
then we don't bother initiating the cast
and so this is a pretty pretty cheap
pretest and since we know that this is
going to be in the cache too it's nice
because we're about to go do more
testing with it so it kind of pre warms
the cache anyway so I don't I don't
think it's necessarily a bad thing
because it probably helps us out in the
long run there as well something it's
too wasted we don't really know without
measuring it but doesn't seem that bad
so I'm gonna get rid of this because I'm
not sure that that's really true either
way so let's see doing this is inside
test that all seems fine in this case we
probably do want to lurk towards zero
here that's that's true so maybe we'll
little bit later looking at this leaf
index
here this part seems reasonable we're
just checking bounds and ending them
together that all looks totally fine the
only thing I would say is I don't
actually know if like I don't
necessarily know that you would do it
that way so so probably you would just
do something more like like this right
because there's really no reason to
transit this out into a general purpose
register which I don't know if maybe
there is a reason why you would do that
to make it go faster I don't think you
really have any scalar work here to do
you probably just waste the same amount
of time moving it out as you would save
by doing so so I feel like it's probably
saner to do this right but I don't know
so I'm not really sure but it feels like
that's probably this saner way to do
that that way everyone stays locked in
in the eye in the xmm registers inside
this loop and then the loop controls
done in the scaler and that seems like a
better way to make that go then
transiting out each time there's really
no reason to do that because you know
that all of the bits will just persist
through the or and so at the end all we
have to do is just see did any lane come
up saying it was inside and then we're
done right so so I think that's you know
just it's just pretty straightforward
so we know that we're going to want the
Rey origin here to be loaded up in this
way so we kind of know that we have that
when we start so let's take a look at
what we actually pass into grid raycast
here and see how straightforward it can
be in this case so if I go to grid
raycast here I just want to see like
what we're actually doing you can see us
passing ray origin single here and you
can see us passing the sample directions
so just looking at that it looks like
the raid D is never used am I wrong
about that so this is not a thing right
that's just not a thing at all ray
origins single is getting component out
of the Ray Arjun which is actually
something that comes as the part of the
light probe piece so we've kind of
already had that so if we wanted to pass
that as a v3 we could but the thing that
I would like to know is is that actually
necessary meaning is that a thing we
actually want to do or do we like do we
ever actually care about that or not
right and I don't actually know so it
may be that the better way to do that
would be to pass the Ray origin packed
part of things actually you know what I
mean
so it may make more sense to pass the
Ray origin pact here and then to the
extent that we actually want the spread
version of that you know we can always
replicate it out right so so I'm not
sure that we actually want to pass it as
Rayleigh single but it's hard to say
so since light probe P is already ray or
Jin there though we might as well just
just pass that for starters right
because we don't actually need that
anywhere
okay there we go
um and again yeah like I said just
trying to get the cruft out of here
slowly so now if we look at how this is
doing you know we we've run two of these
in a row and then stride by eight and I
do wonder if since now that's the way
that this is going I do wonder if
there's any reason why we don't just
make it do this in one loop so if you
look at how this is going and we move
forward by sampled their hair like this
is just a locked loop that goes forward
in Y and so it's not obvious to me
mm-hmm like if you look here you know
the question is could you weld these
loops together and hard to say right so
the way this is working is it's
producing hopefully you can see what
what's going on here each time through
this we're stepping down Y and we're
doing the Ray casting to write out our
grid values so we're doing a tile at a
time we're doing the Y's and for each Y
we're writing out three times four to do
the the writes here right and so really
we could expand that to doing six and
get do one call for that and we could
even roll this loop into there because
it really doesn't do anything other than
loop over these texels right so we could
just make this whole thing be one
function you know and I'm saying
we could just make this whole thing be
one function and simplify it that way
and it makes some sense to do that as
well because again like I said all of
this stuff is just obscuring to the
compiler what the heck is going on this
is really just doing a straight ahead
loop the reason it's not simpler than it
is is because you have to do this sort
of interior set of eight rays to do the
right out for one row and I just don't
know right so let's imagine that we did
this so suppose you were going to do
more of these at once so what would you
have to do well the transfer PPS value
is just indexed off the Ray and it's the
only thing that migrates out of the
routine in the first place
so in theory and you know let's just
let's just do this for a sake of
argument
I'm just curious and I'll take ten
seconds so you might as well look so if
we run HH lightproof
you know a little bit and just see what
kind of values we're getting out of this
thing it's four point five ish you know
I don't expect to get really any went
out of this but I just want to verify
you know four point five one four point
five two if we were to just widen this
so we just said look transfer PPS is
going to be eight now and we're doing
eight rays at a time as far as I know
that will just run straight through so
there's nothing fancy going on there and
so then you would just say well this
crap just gets extended so it just looks
like that right
and and literally that's that's just all
all we're doing you would do six at a
time and then you would write six and
that's it right so so it seems like I
don't know maybe it's good maybe it's
bad I'm not sure but it seems like
rather than having all this garbage
happen you might as well just do that
because I don't see what the difference
would be it just seems like a waste of
everyone's time
so because you're already doing the loop
that one seems like a no-brainer right
so I'm just curious if that changes the
performance profile at all I don't think
it will but you know I just want to see
if it does and we'll see and actually
that did quite a bit right well that was
strangely variable there though
what the heck why is that so variable
I wonder if did we do something weird
that's just kind of weird how variable
that is
so I mean a little bit hard to save
because that's a little bit all over the
map but it does seem like it actually
sped it up a bit that's getting into
making me nervous territory with that
variable that was those yeah but anyway
since it doesn't affect us negatively
certainly at least we could say I think
keeping that welded seems like it makes
some sense so the only question to me
now is should this whole thing just be
welded together because you could just
put the loop right here and if you look
at what happens here like we could just
make it easier on ourselves and just say
you know if there's any true here you
know we handle the open case in return
otherwise we do the rest of it right and
so we could just do all of this inside
the loop I know it's kind of ridiculous
but we definitely could do that right
and again this is just for smashing down
the code like smush smush smush until we
smush it the maximum amount of smoosh
that we possibly can so again hard to
say I'm not sure what we want to do
there
so yeah so part of the other problem
here is like the debug code 2 is going
to start to get in the way as we try to
make this sort of more straightforward
so this is actually gonna be a problem
and we could we could nerf it for now
but we're definitely gonna start to run
into problems where the debug code is an
issue and you know that's something
we're gonna have to figure out how we
want to get our debug stuff out of this
because we're gonna need to debug
problems when we start to stress test
things and we'll find bugs and we're
gonna have to draw them so that's going
to be that's going to be its own sort of
thing if we were to smoosh this in
directly so the sy loop were rolled in
then the part that's kind of tricky is
this part here
and since the sample Durr is the thing
that you would want there you can see
why I'm so interested in this so since
the sample dirt is since the sample Durr
is just going linearly it means there's
only one thing you would have to do each
time on the rail OOP even so I think I'm
going to leave this for later
that's a fine smush to make but here's
the thing so if we were able to write
these in line and it don't really know
if we can but if we were able to write
these in lines somehow so that as we
cast we just wrote we should be able to
actually just do one loop and at that
point I think it probably would be a win
because what we would do is we would
loop over this and we would use like a
mask or a mod or something to figure out
whether to advance the line pointer and
we could just write these out in a much
more straightforward fashion so I'm
going to go ahead and go to the Q&amp;A but
I'm gonna say like to do can we merge
this with the grid ray cast ray loop by
doing something clever with how we do
write outs so they don't have to be line
buffered I don't know so let's go to the
QA and we'll table that for next weekend
yesterday you change your Simbi extract
functions to use shuffles instead could
explain again why that is better yes
certainly that is if I have my
blackboard okay so if you think about
and let me do like extract British
shuffle so if you think about what's
happening in the actual process or so
you've got like a register file which is
not really a thing I mean the way to
think about it is just on the chip it's
got a bunch of storage for register
values they're whatever they are there's
just a huge bun huge crap ton of them
and you know when you talk about a
register and you look at assembly
language you talk about things like XM
m0 or you know r7 or something like this
and when you talk about these they're
just names that your code gives to
values they're basically just temporary
scratched locations they're a base like
scratch memory that you use and these
names just get assigned slots in the
register file so it like I've said it
before in here me near I'll say it again
saying that there's 16 registers or
something or general purpose registers
on an x64 60 years if you it doesn't
mean anything it's really just how many
register names there are it's how many
names you can use in your code but they
don't actually correspond to storage
locations there are many many many more
storage locations for register data then
there are register names ok
but anyway inside the register file
there's gonna be storage and there's
gonna be storage for different sized
things right or more importantly it's
gonna think it's storing things of
different sizes right so if we talk
about an X mm register that is a 16 byte
piece of storage if we talk about an AR
register that's a 8 byte piece of
storage right and the reason for this is
just that if you look at how the
registers work in x64
registers that are general-purpose
registers are 64 bits that's why it's a
64 bit processor but the vector
registers are all bigger than that so
xmm registers are 64 bytes ymm registers
are 32 bytes and zmm registers are 64
bytes okay
these happen to be a cache line size
these don't exist in basically anything
these exist in almost everything so on
the chip that we're running on right now
we have these registers we do not have
these registers okay so
when you want to talk about a vector
register you are talking about a 16 byte
value and often times such as the case
of what we're doing you are talking
about that as a packed set of multiple
values so the 16 bytes of an X mm
register is usually packed into four
floats so this may be 16 bytes wide but
we're never gonna really use it as 16
bytes instead what we're going to do is
pretend that it's got little like
dividers inside it and say well there's
gonna be one float here there's gonna be
another float here there's gonna be
another float here right and that's how
we get speed up that's how we get
performance improvements by doing sim
decode is by recognizing that by packing
multiple things together into one
register and then doing ops on all of
them at once we know that we can get
like a 4x speed up so instead of doing
one multiply we do four multiplies and
that's four times faster right but now
we have to think about what needs to
happen if for some reason we need to
talk about one of these values
specifically all right so let's suppose
I need to start talking about this f2
value I need to know something specific
about it now there's two ways that I
might need to do something specific with
it on the general purpose register side
one is to branch and the other is to
load right and you know I should say
load store because it doesn't matter
whether I'm reading or writing from
every write up until a V X 512 which
again we don't have this processor in
this machine doesn't even have it so
it's kind of a distant future thing that
you could you can't really rely on it
these days maybe someday you will but
right now you can't and avx2 I think
maybe has some of this but it's lousy
yeah a BX 2 has this so actually some
latex to chips would have some of this
this
might be plausible but we'll talk about
that second so there's two things you
might want to do branch and load and
store so branch is the biggest one if
you actually need your code to take a
totally different code path like call
some different function or or do
different sides of an if the branching
that you need to do you can only do off
general-purpose registers
general-purpose registers and the flags
there the the flags register is the only
way you can actually execute a jump
right so sometimes what we need to do is
we need to move stuff out of here into a
general purpose register and we need to
branch off it let's say or maybe we need
to load or store something off of an
address and you can only really address
off general-purpose registers up until
avx2 I think avx2 added stuff where you
could do loads that were wide scatter
gather but let's not talk about those
because those are a whole nother thing
and we can't rely on them yet in about
five years you probably would be able to
ship avx2 exclusive code and be fine but
right now you still have to always do a
path where you'd fall back so you'd
still need to know about this so if we
were going to do that we need to extract
a particular value and put it into a
different type of register so we're
trying to transit from here to here
right we're trying to say let's get
something out of one of these and put it
into one of these now remember they're
not actually registered Pacific
locations well they are as different
things in a register file but we still
need to do it we still need to move
something from from one place in a wide
sixteen byte thing and we need to tell
the the CPU we're trying to get one
thing out of it and put it into some
other type of register storage okay so
we're trying to change the name of it
and what it means so there's a couple
ways we can do it one you've seen me do
today it's move mask and what that does
is it takes slices of these things it'll
take like the high bit of each of these
and move them into a general purpose
register right that's great for this so
if we want to branch things it's great
we can move out the slot that the high
bit of those which would either be the
signs of the values which sometimes we
want to use or if we did comparison
operations all the bits in these would
have been set
same so it's just the same as getting
out what the comparison was for each
lane so move mask is a way of getting a
four bit value or more depending on
which move mask of use but in the case
of PS it's a four bit value that lets us
extract a very useful portion of an X mm
register into a general purpose register
so that's a great instruction another
one is an extract instruction and the
extract instruction takes one of these
slots whichever one we pick zero one or
two or three and move just the whole
contents of that one block into one of
these general-purpose registers right
and we could also move the 64 bit if we
wanted to - right
so is extract instructions to pull out
30 you know 32-bit 64-bit pieces
whichever piece you want and pull those
out into a general purpose register now
why would you want to do that again the
same reason maybe we want a branch or
load in store out of that specific value
so we want to start using it in a
general purpose register right and
there's other reasons we might do this
too like you saw me do today maybe we
want to move it out there so we can use
port 6 or some other scalar ports that
can't work on wide vectors right so some
reasons okay
but there's one more reason you might
want to extract in it's purely semantics
and this is what so if you understand
all of that now you can understand why I
didn't want to use these instructions
the other day and I changed to a shuffle
sometimes you're just talking about a
semantic extraction and what I mean by
that is look in the compiler this has
nothing to do with the CPU in the
compiler it thinks there's a difference
between this and this right but in the
CPU there is no difference between those
two things
while the CPU does have an old X 80 X 80
7 floating point stack for backwards
compatibility it never actually would
use it so you would never do
floating-point operations on the X 87
stack you're always actually doing
floating point
creations in annex mm register you're
just only bothering to use the low lane
right so if you do single float
operations it's really just loading up
an X mm register with 0 0 0 and then the
float that you wanted right so all
floating-point operations that happen in
X 64 are actually happening wide whether
you like it or not it's just telling the
CPU hey by the way I don't care about
these upper lanes so instead of actually
pushing power through them to get the
results just zero them instead so we can
save power so some ships can save power
by doing that right so we're actually
always using wide vectors even when we
just want to do one float we're using
wide vectors we're just telling the CPU
not to bother computing the upper lanes
right so what you don't want to do and
what I accidentally did in Martin's
pointed out and I was like oh duh thank
you Martin's as usual Martin's catches
everyone's mistakes mm-hmm
basically everyone just needs a Martin's
next to them that like some kind of
autobot Martins thing like that sits
there and catches your mistakes or when
you don't know like the right flags for
crap or which utility to use he also
always knows that anyway so what you
don't want to do is do an actual
extraction to a general purpose register
just to tell the compiler what you were
doing and so what I had written was
something like this right like hey turn
this thing into a float the result of
one of these extract calls right so what
was happening is I was saying extract
something out to a general purpose
register which would have taken one of
these right and moved it out here and
then I was saying turn that into a float
again right so it's just transiting it
through a general purpose register
there's no reason to do that so if all
you want to do is take a floating point
value that's somewhere in another lane
so what I had specifically was this case
for floats I want say this one right
what I was doing was using the general
purpose register extract which would
grab this right out of xmm zero let's
say
move it into some other thing r7 like I
said before right that's what his track
will do and then I immediately told the
CPU to move it back in right so what I
was doing was I was transiting through a
general purpose register just to get
this to move from here to here but
there's actually already a function
right chef PS just does that operation
so if you just do a chef PS to move this
thing down right that's an easier way to
tell the compiler what you were trying
to actually do than the extract call
which the compiler could look at that
and see oh he's just transiting through
a general purpose register why did he do
that I'm not gonna bother let's just
short-circuit that to a shuttle
it could be smart enough to do that but
why rely on the compiler when you could
just do the right thing
so chef PS is a better way of moving a
thing from one of the lanes to the low
lane which is where it has to be if you
want the compiler to start treating as a
float so this is all just manhandling
the compiler hopefully that makes sense
is there such a thing as smashing too
much and causing a power to bail before
during doing optimizations not unless
you're passing that flag that says don't
do optimizations on large functions I
think I don't know though the important
thing is don't guess time as long as you
have a time thing where we're timing
like we see there and also you can
always look at your code you'll know if
you got slower so the important thing to
do is just always time alright last
question will be gained any speed by
moving ahead 16 and doing 12 ops for
pass you know what bill let's talk about
that after tomorrow because I'm gonna
look at that stuff tomorrow and see what
I think like I said I want to figure out
how to I want to figure out how to
restructure those lose potentially
anyway so let's save that for tomorrow
but you can explain what you mean in
more detail to in tomorrow's Q&amp;A and see
if I didn't already answer it tomorrow
okay all right Thank You Rudy for
joining me for the episode of hand made
here it's been a pleasure coding with
you as always if you would like to
follow my series at home you can always
peer to the game on handmade hero org
and it comes to the source code so you
can see everything you for yourself and
play around with it yourself alright
that's it for today I'll be back here
next week to take a look at streamlining
those function a little bit more and
then we can move on to doing one more
optimization that I think will be like a
really big optimization for the actual
speed of raycasting and then we can fall
back to looking at just the diffuse blur
which is taking a lot of our time or the
build we don't actually know which ones
we'll see that's it for today hope see
you back here next week until then have
fun program everyone and I'll see on the
Internet piggies everybody