hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero show recorded complete game live on
stream uh
we when we last left which was actually
a couple weeks ago because we did some
rough term streams
um in between when we last left we were
doing
some code for just we wanted to be able
to
make our collision system we really want
to be able to debug our collision system
uh in some reasonable way and i really
don't know
any way to do that other than by having
good diagramming
um inside the the engine itself
meaning some way to draw what's
happening
because things like collision are just
unfortunately
very uh abstract when you look at the
code
it's pretty hard to intuit what is going
on
by just looking at code so stepping
through
a collision routine in a debugger you're
almost never gonna see
your bugs because they're so geometric
in nature and your brain
can't really look at a watch window and
extrapolate
oh you know this um
here are these three points and this is
their relationship oh they're coplanar
and that's breaking this thing i was
doing
well three points always go planar four
points and their coplanar and i was
assuming they would actually make a
tetrahedron and that's why my collision
detection
didn't work and so now i can fix that
gaining that geometrical tradition
most humans can't look at four points
and tell their coplanar
right um if all you see is just the
numbers
if you show them a picture of four
points almost any human can tell that
they're coplanar
even if they're humans who don't know
what coplanar is they can still say oh
they kind of look like they're all
flat right so your geometric intuition
tends to be the best thing to use for
debugging collision detection
um and our collision detection is
working well enough
um but it looked like there were some
problems with it
um and i wanted to see if we could uh
get some better diagramming in here just
so i can
figure out whether or not there are some
more bugs in it
or as we see bugs that come up
in the course of using it i want those
to not be
super mysterious or difficult and i
think the thing we're seeing is like
this dude
um well okay so unfortunately right now
i'm not seeing much in the way of the
bugs that we were seeing before
um so that's a little unnerving but you
know
i still i just still want to do it i
thought yeah there you go so there's
some weird like it was getting kind of
stuck in the ground a little bit there i
felt like
there were just some things where it
felt like there were some bugs and
you know it's always hard to know um oh
like right there though
so i don't know if i guess i don't know
if those guys have circular collisions
or not
they might not so maybe that's what's
going on there but there's just a bunch
of things like that that i'm just not
sure
what's happening and if i'm not sure
what's happening
then i kind of need um a way oh so like
yeah
like that's
here's an example hopefully
right um
well i mean yeah but i still think that
should probably work
right like when something gets in like
that kind of insight we should be
allowed it should be allowed to get out
of that
right and it's having trouble doing that
now and i'm sure it will be allowed to
get out of it
uh if we do that right but i think it
should have still been able to do like a
roll off of that so
you can see that i just think there's
some bugs in here um
they may not be literal bugs in the code
they may be misunderstandings about how
we set things up you know it could be
anything
but without better drawing there's no
way i'm gonna know
right i just won't know what's happening
and so as we see stuff like that happen
i need some way of getting uh
of getting a visual so that i can debug
it
and that's really the only thing that
i'm talking about at this point
there's also the uh the fact that we
would like to add a spatial partition
but that's purely optimization
so i don't care about that right now uh
what i care about is the ability to do
like you know
uh good debugging right i also like how
our under damp spring goes nuts check
that out
that's awesome this is why you never use
an underdamped pdc for controlling
things because it
goes crazy like that right
and that's just that spring getting too
powerful right
as the frame rate goes down it's an it's
a it's a
uh frame rate dependent equation and you
get those kinds of behaviors as the
frame rate goes down or if there's a
slow frame or something
right uh and it just builds up so much
kinetic energy that it can just like
shoot over anything
right anyway uh
those are other problems though that
we'll deal with later that has nothing
to do with collision detection at all
so anyway that's what we want to do uh
that's our goal
is just to figure out how to not have
that problem
right is that a single oh no that's two
snakes i was like why is there one snake
that long it's not it's two snakes
um so that's all we really need to do uh
but it just takes a while to do
something like that right to put in a
system and
uh we made sort of an idea for it here
where we said all right suppose that we
just have a way of anywhere in the code
that we want to
we can just do a bunch of this stuff
where we just have like hey
here's diagrams right so you say diagram
this diagram that
um and what we want to do here
is we want to just be able to uh
we want to just be able to say any
diagram that we want to make
we can output this way and then we can
look
uh at what it actually drew
later right so it's basically a debug
buffer
is all it is that fills up with uh
you know it fills up with drawing
instructions
and it's really exactly the same
as our render uh like our render command
list
stuff right it just builds up a series
of commands
that you then do and the only difference
between
that renderer and this one is that
render is meant for like actually
driving the gpu
this one is instead meant for
convenience it's just meant for
say whatever you kind of want to draw
as broadly as possible so it's easy for
you
uh and then we'll draw that
for you later by translating those high
level commands
into the kinds of things that the
renderer can actually produce like
lines right
so that's all we're trying to do here
and you can kind of see there's a couple
of things that seem
maybe like they're missing here like it
probably would be good to have
something like this that we didn't put
in there
so that you can change what color is the
thing that you're drawing
you know what i mean um that's probably
a good thing to put in there
and i don't know about maybe line weight
[Music]
um
something like that and so i don't
really know like what are those things
we need but i feel like we probably want
some things like that that would just be
sticky so you can say like here's the
thickness here's the color
or whatever right
um that seems fine
and
yeah i don't think we need to belabor
the point too much so when you look at
this you can kind of see
and i'll pop these two
[Music]
additional functions we made down in
there too so
uh and if you take a look at these you
can kind of see all they're going to be
doing is
cueing this stuff up right there's not a
whole lot to it
uh and so what i'd like to do is just
have some way
of cueing these that is relatively
straightforward again we're not going to
do anything fancy
um so what i might do is say well there
are these phases
right and you know
it's got like begin and end for phases
and i think
sorry no it's got phases and a beginning
end for diagrams and the diagrams
presumably
are like
we will want to be able to isolate
individual ones
you know what i'm saying so we'll want
to be able
and you know the other thing is the
names that go in here
uh i don't know if those
want to like i don't know to what extent
we
use those too much
so i'm not sure if those should actually
be labels like this or not i don't know
doesn't really matter point being um so
what i might do is just say look there's
like a diagram entry
um and the diagram entry is gonna have
like all of this stuff in it
right so it's gonna have the color um
and thickness in it uh it's gonna have
like a uh you know maybe like an
a and a b kind of a thing um
and it's gonna have to have a type
uh and in here we're gonna have things
like what we
said we would draw so we've got like a
sphere
a line um and a box
at least uh and then we have some
special things that are like a
you know these are not actually
i might pop a diagram null in here as
well
uh and then a uh a diagram count
and so in here i would say like okay
there's
probably things in here like a
phase a diagram um
and a result which are sort of pseudo
it's weird to have diagram diagram but
yeah that's what we've got
um and these are the types
of things that can come in to this right
uh
this entry thing and they
just have a bunch of different things
that we will stack up
and you know i think that's
that's pretty much all we would really
need there um
there's maybe some parameter stuff like
this
uh that we would want so maybe
maybe we have like a
[Music]
i don't know a parameter like that
um and maybe these are from two kind of
as well
um or something like that or i i don't
know i mean
there's a couple of different ways you
could look at that uh i think i'm just
going to do
uh a and b or like you know that
uh two points just because i
if you want to be mr always
uh you know lays things out
exactly and i have to have a type for
everything
then what you would do is you'd make a
struct for the sphere a structure for
the line instruct for a box and you'd
put a union in here
to me that just seems like a waste of
time so rather being mr lays everything
out i'm going to be misses doesn't lay
everything out and just uses a generic
parameter
because i really just don't care like i
don't think i'm going to get any
additional
valuable error checking for that so i
just don't think it matters
right so
that's all i need for the basics and
if i go to the actual file here and i
just sort of stick
a global in here and i say like global
diagram
entries uh and you know
i don't know i may not exactly want to
do that i may say that there's a thing
that's like
diagram uh group or whatever
and this is you know
it's got the color and the thickness
that you currently set
uh and then it's got like a entry count
and then it's got the entries um
like this and you know i don't know how
many this has
and no one cares because it's debug
anyway uh
but something like that and obviously
this stuff can be disabled in in debug
mode so we can just say
look if you're not doing an internal
build
then you really don't need any of this
stuff um
and i guess we already have a thing for
it here right
so we can't just disable those uh
by by just making all of these things
not happen
right and i don't know why we didn't
already do that uh probably because we
didn't much care
uh at the time but all i'm going to do
here is just i'm just going to take
these
wouldn't it be amazing if like anyone at
the c plus committee learned to program
someday
and then they would know that this is a
very common thing that people do
so maybe they should just have a way to
define a keyword
that is this thing disappears
when this command when this uh pound
define
happens right
like
you know all of this nonsense could go
away
with one tiny language feature but you
know
we've been waiting 40 years and it
hasn't happened so i'm gonna go ahead
and guess
that it's never gonna because that would
require someone who actually programs
for a living
to be on the c plus committee all right
so by the way i don't suppose
john is watching but if john was
watching
i would love to know what jai's solution
to this problem is because i'm guessing
he has probably addressed this um
because he does program for a living and
he's probably had to write
stupid code like this before uh
and i'm guessing he probably fixed that
but
i don't actually know he may never have
gotten to that i mean there's a lot of
things to do when you're making a
language so
he may not have actually gotten a chance
to address something like this before
but i'd be curious to know what he did
if he did
i might reorganize that slightly
okay um to be honest i guess i'm not
sure why there's a diagram
end because
you kind of just have these hierarchical
phases
right um and so
i think maybe that was just a dumb idea
like if you had to look at what was
going on here you would probably say
something
uh
you would probably
you would probably not do what i did
right like like
that doesn't really make a lot of sense
you would probably say something more
like this
where you say uh there's a diagram phase
and there's like a phase depth or
something
you know what i mean um
where you just say like oh there are
these phases and they they push
so you know i
and i guess what i could say is if you
were going to do a begin end then you
would just make that be hiracle so so
yeah so so let's say
um
let's say that we just have phases and
at the beginning end you can just make
some
like nested diagrams because otherwise
it seems like we've just got extra calls
and those calls don't actually do
anything so
you know um let's just say
that that is what we're doing
or something i don't know
um so yeah
like i'm just assuming we dump stuff to
this thing
and
yeah so i think what we want is maybe
this
right uh and each time you do one of
these it can like set the pen
or something so then there would be uh
like this
um where if you didn't actually want
to set the pen and you wanted to put
text
out you could so i think that's
maybe more like what i'm thinking here
um
by the way before i forget i should
check chat to see if anyone knows if
john implemented that thing
so i guess nobody knows
um all right so anyway that all looks
fine begin end color
thickness sphere line box
point text out
okay um
so i don't really know exactly what i
want to do here but it's probably going
to be something like that
right uh and and so now these
these have to be changed a little bit so
it's probably gonna look more like this
um
i think
all right so let's give that a shot uh a
shot
a implementation shot
um and we could too if we want
uh we could make this a little bit
squinkier
i don't know how squeaky we want it to
be uh but we could make it
fairly squinky by actually making this
an arena that can just have as much
stuff in it as we want
so the other thing i could do is just
this
right uh
you know so that it just like threads
these things
and you can just have as many as you
want so i don't really remember
how this works uh and
i don't really care
but i'm going to assume
that it does things the way i do them
now
even though this code is old
all right so i'm going to assume that
that we can
just do that right uh
and that way we can then just say all
right uh
if enable diagrams and if and just to be
you know
maybe that's more what that should be
but that way all of this stuff uh will
compile out
automatically right uh and i don't have
to rely like i don't have to rely on it
somehow compiling this out which it
might not right
so that all seems fine uh
no real issues there and then in here
where we've got these like phases that
would be what would
what would get pushed on here uh and so
this will need a like a phase depth
uh sort of thing and
i'm not super sure
[Music]
um
i want to hold off for just a little bit
on the text side of things um
because i'm not sure how i want to
reference those
there's sort of two ways i can do it and
i'm not sure
which one i actually
want there's
one that attaches text to the thing
by putting it afterwards that's kind of
you know what let's not do that
let's do it like this so you say
beforehand what the thing is
right and then you do it and you get the
thing so
yeah yeah that's probably it um so
there's like text attached to the thing
and blah blah and no one cares and
whatever
right so it probably looks more like
this
um right
uh you know what i'm saying so you've
got
what comes after it in the list you've
got what is the actual
like text stuff that's going to be here
i don't remember
i don't really remember how this works
when we print stuff out
uh yeah so it's kind of crappy
right um
yeah it's kind of crappy because we
ported it like basically what we did is
we made our own printf
um and so it's not designed particularly
smart
uh right like it's it's not
it's not that good uh and that's fine
so anyway
let's call it that uh and so you
everyone can have
a buffer of text that's associated with
whatever it is they're doing
uh they can have you know whatever this
stuff is here
right and you can set like the
parameters or whatever you want for
what's going on now
whether these are sticky or not is kind
of another question
you know maybe you want the thickness to
or the color to be uh
maybe you want the color to be sticky
but the thickness not to be or
you certainly don't want the text uh to
be sticky
i don't think um so it's a little bit
hard to say
what the rules of that would be and they
might be a little
counter-intuitive but they just kind of
do what you want them to do
uh is is you know i wouldn't be mad
about that
but we'll cross that bridge when we come
to it
so in each of these cases all we're
really doing is pushing an entry
onto the stack um
i should say onto the list it is sort of
a stack but
you know who cares um and so what we're
doing here is like
each time here we just have like a thing
that's like
you know uh push diagram entry or
whatever
or append might be the better way to say
it
uh so there's a this thing right
so you grab the the global thing that's
gonna
track these and the reason that it's
global
is there's sort of two ways you might do
this you don't really want people to
have to pass it through the call chain
uh and the reason for that is it's a
debug system so it really doesn't make
sense to architect around it because if
you were doing that it's actually having
implications for your architecture and
the point is the
deodorant system shut end so normally
what you would do is you'd tack it on
the end
of a like thread context and each thread
would have its own context that does get
past the chain for actual architecture
reasons
but we don't actually do that in
handmade hero because we don't thread
very much
so it's just it's just a vanilla global
um
whereas it would be in the thread
context otherwise
those are two choices there really
aren't any other choices passing it
around would not be a good idea
because passing it around would imply
that you've architected for it and you
don't want to architect for debug
architecting for debug is a very bad
idea because it means that you're making
architectural decisions that affect
the actual performance of your program
so that you can enable debug and you
want the opposite you want the debug
system
to be transparent to your architecture
so that when it compiles out there are
no implications
right and that's pretty important so
okay so
for each of these arenas um sorry for
each of these entries i want to
ask the arena uh to give me a new one
so i've got a diagram entry
and i'm just going to say that
this arena
that i've got here should allow me to do
a push struct
of one of these diagram entries right
and that should give me back
uh what's happening here uh oh
did i oh like it looks like there was
like a i accidentally hit like a delete
thing or something
memory arena unknown override specifier
uh where did we put this in the list of
things
so yeah this this probably needs to be
much higher in the list of things right
all right so uh
now the phase thing i guess
each time through this loop
is going to look like that right
uh so there are the phases yeah
and uh we should have had i guess we
weren't using
i see we had that with enable diagram
still
so i don't think anything in there
really
needs to be in a block for enable
diagrams right um
how about this
so in theory i would think that most
compilers who aren't completely brain
dead if you put an
if zero in here uh
then it will compile all of this out
right i mean that's what we would expect
to have happen
so i feel like that should probably be
safe
um right
like like that feels like that should
probably be
uncontroversial uh so that way you can
put things in blocks that are ift on
whether the diagram is
system is diagramming or not uh
and that'll make it very clear to the
compiler without needing pound if blocks
so that they still get compiled and we
know what's going on
and if we change the definition this way
we gotta compile error and stuff
which is what i would prefer right um
so that that i think is more what we
want here
um so yeah
and maybe this is stupid what i'm doing
i don't know
right um
you know maybe we need a more succinct
way
of uh of of
passing this information uh because i
can think of some other ways we
could do it and you know
there's pros and cons to each the
important thing here is i just want
something that works relatively well
and if it's a little verbose that's okay
as long as i can put everything in that
i want
um i think it's all right uh but you
know do we
maybe want something a little more terse
you know you can see why pushing that
out to a text thing
is maybe not as good because it just
makes the code too long
so it's something to think about
right so you know
meh it's not horrible uh
all right um
so yeah the reason i want that is on
switch
is because we probably want to be able
to turn diagrams on
if we even so there's enabling diagrams
which means
is the code compiled in but then we may
also just want to be able to turn them
on and off at runtime in builds when
they are compiled in
and so that's really what that is there
for
um so yeah
uh this is
not this yes so
is on begin end color thickness text
sphere line box point overlay
um
okay so now we just need to buffer these
up uh as they go and so
i guess really what's gonna happen here
is
each time we do be a begin we need to
push on one of these
and you know so this uh
this is gonna be a clear right so
i think we clear by default
uh if i remember correctly we can double
check that
um but i'm pretty sure like the default
thing
to do uh when you do a push size
uh is to to clear
um so so that will just clear it and
then all we have to do is set
the other pieces now probably everyone's
going to pass one of these
so we might as well just say that that
gets set for you
um and then the other things in here
probably can get set
uh based on what the thing is it's
actually being called
some of them probably can get set so
like the value
um and the thickness right
uh oh sorry the color and the thickness
um the color and the thickness can
just get set from the group because
those
are going to be like sticky right this
and this
uh and the same thing would be
probably for the text um
[Music]
right so you would probably expect to
see something
like this
yeah uh and
since you can kind of see where that's
going i feel like you probably want
this
like maybe attributes right
uh and the attributes for each thing
just are in here
you know what i'm saying uh that way we
can have
attributes on the group that just get
applied each time
and furthermore we can do
[Music]
this
so that we have a default set and a
current set
oops
right so that way we can add one more
command
which is like stick
so if you want to set a permanent thing
you can
uh
so after you set like color or thickness
or text or any of those things
if you want those to apply to everything
uh for the rest of the for the rest of
the
uh thing that you're doing um
then you can you can just call stick and
it will
it will apply those settings right
so and all that is is it's just the
it just takes the global attrib group
that where these things are being
tracked
and says that the default trib equals
whatever the current
attribute is right
that's it um these are now you know
really straightforward the color and the
thickness because they're very simple
they just set uh whatever the current
attribute is they just set it
uh and the text one is more complicated
partially because we don't really have
an arena-based push
of these things at least i don't think
we do and maybe we actually secretly do
and we just forgot um
about it you can see i even have a to do
so it's like we knew that this was lousy
this was the thing i was actually
talking about right
so we knew that kind of sucked um but we
we just haven't ever had a chance to go
unsuck it
right which is fine
so here's uh i'm gonna leave the text
one for now because like i said that one
requires a little bit more finesse uh
let's just do the rest of these
so append diagram entry now
where we just have you know
i mean you know what we're doing here
right uh
there's it's just
it's literally just just stacking these
right so uh what we need to do here
is when we push these on uh we also need
to set the like
first and last pointers so you got these
first and last pointers here that's the
chain of things
that we've seen um and you know
so that's just gonna be like um
this sort of thing
right um
anyway it doesn't matter point being
we're just changing these things on
and each time that we see a new one we
want to add it to the end of the list
and so this the reason that we can't
just keep a push down version of it
is when we go to actually draw these we
we want to draw them in order
like the person who was recording them
wants to draw them in the order that
they were seen
because we're trying to step through the
run of the program in a diagram
at diagram by diagram and you don't want
to see like the last diagram first
or something right so what we want to do
here
is we want to actually uh go through
each of these
and say uh okay
the every time the last entry
needs to point to whatever the current
one we just made is
if there is a last entry already then we
just want to set the next pointer to the
entry that we're talking about
whereas if it's uh if we haven't done
the first one
yet uh then it's gonna set the first one
right so it's again pretty
straightforward we're just
that just makes a linked list of these
things and that's all it does
right um so that way
we can now implement all of these really
easily there's really nothing to it
so we're just going to do this append
diagram entry and each time we're just
going to pass
whatever the type of the thing is that
we were actually going to draw
so each of these will look like that
uh and the only thing that they're gonna
do
is say like hey it's a sphere or
whatever
right uh and we just say well there's a
center i and
a radius right
um and that's it
and then for this one well it's a line
so there's the you know from
and the two uh there's you know
a box
uh and in a and a point
uh and then we didn't really do overlay
but we we need one
and that's just if you want to just if
you're just trying to display some text
that doesn't really go
anywhere on the diagram right
uh so it's just text right
it'll just overlay it on top of the
diagram in like a hud or something
uh now we've got one more thing that
needs to be recorded
this does not that's not a thing anymore
um we got one more thing that needs to
be recorded and
that is the phase
right so we need markers each time we
have a phase
and uh the value that that is
in the phase i don't know if this so
this is really just
you know it may not make any sense to
actually do this it may make more sense
to just say
look there's two points and
this stuff will just have a phase begin
phase end there'll just be a beginning
and end
and that'll just get tracked when you're
drawing it um
that probably makes more sense because
there's no need for that value
uh so it's probably and then you just
you just actually have that stack depth
maintained here
so probably this is better
these don't actually have any parameters
you know
so they can just kind of just be ignored
uh the return value because you're not
going to do anything with it
right so that does a complete recording
of everything we wanted to draw right
and as you can see it's almost no code
right so it's pretty
it's pretty cheap to make one of these
things uh
and that's it right
um
the only thing we haven't done is the
text output and then we can just move to
the drawing phase where we just convert
these things to something you can
actually
uh put on the screen uh which will be a
little more work
because it's you know doing more
than merely recording what the person
wanted to do but as you can see if you
write this sensibly there's not a lot to
it
it's really straightforward to do the
recording part
uh it's pretty basic right
now one thing we might want to do uh
is when you begin a diagram
we should probably clear out
um
like
so the the only thing i'm thinking here
is like
when you actually do one of these
diagrams
we probably want to be able to like
to like keep track of the state right
so i wonder if it wouldn't maybe make
more sense to just
to just actually just record that state
and have the render side track it
that's a good question
yeah i i think i might just do that
so because i think we could just say
well let's just make it entirely run
at that time so you could do this
so either you specify points to draw or
you specify
attributes that you're changing
that makes a lot of sense to me so maybe
let's just do that
yeah i think i like that better uh and
then you just have them
up here
that seems good uh and
these now actually have an entry so like
changing
this stuff just has an entry
like so
[Music]
um
and that seems okay uh that seems better
to me
i think i like that better uh
so this doesn't have to happen which
makes that more efficient
and the structs are smaller so that just
seems like a better choice
pretty much across the board don't ask
me why that's not a pointer and why
didn't it complain about this one
um this doesn't need a return value
because it doesn't do anything
[Music]
um
okay so last but not least is
text it's actually very uh simple
what's happening there also because uh
this seems like it's only ever going to
be just in for the
in the interest of being slightly more
efficient we can also put text i think
in here uh because we know that
you don't really need i don't think i
ever need to specify more than that so
the diagram attributes can just be a
thing that that exists in here because
they're the ones that might be sticky
and you know we'll
we'll play that a little bit in a second
but then the text that way
this whole thing is only ever going to
take the size of of this
uh so six floats
six floats great adventure and
uh
and all we need to do here now is set
this text
uh buffer to something right
now we know that we can do a
uh so if we go to the format string side
of things we know that we can do this
you know so we know that we can do
an arg list format and we can pass it to
this thing
and off we go and and the problem that
we have
right is we don't know what to do with
this so we don't know what to do with
this dust size
dust here these are now known right it's
it's what came in
as the printf uh but these we don't
actually know
what they are because we don't have any
buffer to put these things in
but you know we have an arena right so
what we should be able to do
with the arena and i don't know to what
extent we support this because like i
said
it looked kind of crappy and that's fine
uh but it's just
you know it is what it is uh when we're
doing the push size on here
you know we've got this sort of stuff
where you can do like a
you know you can you can do like
begin and end where you can check like
how much memory
uh you use then you can rewind and stuff
like that
that's what this and temporary memory
does you can see it rewind
uh and reset the used part here
uh and the stupid thing about this is
what you would normally want to do here
is you just push on like a large chunk
like 4096
you do the printf into it and then you
just rewind the pointer back to however
much it actually took
right that's what this would normally do
but we don't really have a way to do
that
right so i'm not going to do that
because i don't really want to muck
with that part of the code there's no
point in doing that this is a
just a debug system um
so if we just make a thing that's like
okay the global has some format buffer
and we'll just
just put it into the format buffer right
um this is an inefficient and stupid way
to do it
but we don't care so uh at the moment
we'll just do it that way
instead and the way that that will look
is uh
you know we'll take this diagram group
um and we're gonna say however big this
is
you can put it in there
and then you can tell us how big it
actually will be
right um and we'll do like a
a push copy you know what i'm saying
uh so a push copy is just saying i'm
gonna give you block of memory and
you're gonna
you know push it on in there
so if we do a push copy we
push an arena
a size a source and then the params
uh we want like
no clear right
because it would be dumb to push a copy
something you there'd be no reason to
clear it first right
so we're going to push on this result
and we're going to push on this
source and we're going to push it onto
this arena that will push the copy on
uh and then we just have to do like is
there a make buffer
or a wrap what does this do
bundle string
so then we can just say
oops to uh
bundle that into a buffer and now we've
got the string
right uh so not fabulous because
this is just inefficient for no reason
but
you know so you can say here if you
wanted to
right uh so that's fine and
now we have a complete recording so all
we really need
is a function that draws this right and
if we so you know we just need some
function that will
we'll dump this down to the render
buffer
um as we go and
the other thing that's the thing about
it too is like we've got all this other
drawing code right now that's in there
for no reason that we could also
like so there's drawing code that is in
the actual
uh collision detector destroying those
little boxes that should all get moved
to this code as well
right obviously um because we don't
need that sort of like hacky drawing
code now that we actually have a way to
record things into a debug buffer and
then play them back that would obviously
be right
what you would do now there's a lot of
stuff that we can do
here
[Music]
and we'll kind of get into that probably
next weekend the things that we can do
here
so one of the reasons i predicated the
diagram stuff
you can see with this like diagram is on
call is we can
make it so that this is completely
dynamic where like as you step through
diagrams it'll just
only turn on the ones that you actually
are looking at that will help
keep the speed high so that people
aren't syncing like
hundreds of thousands of these diagram
calls every frame
only for us never to actually need any
of them because we're not looking at
them
so that way that can always return zero
except for the diagram you're actually
looking at
right so that would keep it to just
diagram begin and end are getting called
uh
to to like say what diagrams are
available but all of the actual
information the diagram just would never
actually happen
unless you uh specifically asked to view
that diagram
so that's you know uh
just to give you an idea of like where
that should be going
it should be something like that so
after you do all of this there should at
some point here now be a call that's
like
you know convert or something like
diagram
you know convert d diagrams
to uh
or render diagrams i guess render
diagrams
you know that kind of thing uh and
that's going to take like the render
group
and it's going to take whatever the the
diagrams are from that
that diagram set it's just going to dump
them out right so dump them out
so yeah
that's basically what we want
uh i'm tired i guess i didn't get enough
sleep last night
which is unfortunate um so
you know we would we would do that and
i'm assuming that like the place we
would put that
is like in here somewhere right because
we've got
this stuff that like uh when you're
running
what is this complaining about
i have no idea what this is complaining
about at the moment hold on
um oh
we don't that's right i always do it
this way
on handmade hero i build i don't build
twice
for whatever reason um probably should
uh so that should crash again here
hopefully yeah
uh so i don't know what
what that's about it doesn't
like this debug record allocation the
call to the debug system here
but i'm not actually sure why
that all looks fine and that looks fine
but this
apparently it doesn't like
our debug system is so terrible um
at some point we should just rip it out
and replace it with something better but
uh
i can't say i see what the immediate
thing is
writing location zero it's something in
the
that actual macro
um like trying to get that event right
because it's
it's it's actually in the debug record
allocation call
that like it's not able to get one of
these events
or something um
my assumption would be that that is just
because this is getting called so many
times that we're actually running out of
these events
you know what i mean um
[Music]
that'd be my guess
uh which is annoying to say the least
uh but i guess we just don't do enough
small allocations
normally to to actually make that be a
problem
for this particular system right
uh
meh so i'm not sure
what to do about that other than to say
that that particular thing where we
record those allocations
is not particularly useful like
what that was used for
is so let me disable this and just we'll
go through it
so what that was used for was
uh oops still running
what that was used for was a pretty
stupid thing
um i think it was just something someone
asked for so we did it
but i don't actually think it's
particularly useful i don't i don't know
that we we almost never use it at least
i don't remember ever using it
but wait did i not just
that was funny i said it's a nine no
nine does not disable uh a pound if in
case anyone's wondering
um so we've got this thing that's like
this and
you can view like how your memory is
laid out
uh you know what i'm saying
so this is all the memory um
in the system and
you can see like who allocated it or
whatever right
so that's all that's doing uh it it
doesn't do
anything else um
it's just this right um
yeah so you can kind of see like where
all your memory is
uh or whatever and i don't know
uh no one cares
um but that's just what it is right
uh and
being able to see this level of
granularity is what causes the
problem because if you do tons of little
allocations in there
the debug system is trying to store all
of those and eventually just runs out of
space to store them because we don't
allocate that much space
to the debug system itself and that's
basically it um
i'm not sure there's really anything
else to it
uh and a lot of that's just because the
debug system is terrible
right there's so many reasons why the
debug system is terrible it's hard to
describe how many reasons there are
um it's just bad in a lot of ways
and it's just one of the things we
[Music]
it's one of the casualties of the way
handmade hero is developed
not being able to spend like weeks at a
time on something where you concentrate
on it for several
hours every day it's pretty hard to do
complex systems well
if you're trying new stuff
and so in this particular case i don't
know why i can't jump to that
global yeah
in this particular case right it just
ends up not being very good
and you know it definitely cost us
something because not having a good
debug system and having to deal with
crap like this is not what you want
but you know there's only so much you
can do
about that so the global debug table
i don't actually even know how we were
doing that we were using that so we
could use that weird counter trick
which i don't really know how valuable
that even is
but um
so i guess what i really probably want
to look at is this
yeah um so you can see here like hey
it's this thing with like a tremendous
number of these like debug events
there's just tons of them
uh and i assume what's happening there
is it's just blowing out
like whatever that number is it's too
many right
um so you know you can
up the number i don't know uh how big
are these things
what a strange thing so it's got a u64
so this is like
eight eight and then
just an unbalanced with a pad eight
eight so that's like you know a 32
and then whatever the heck this thing is
that's gonna be the biggest
probably is a wreck three uh so that's
nine
floats right
so like looking at the
looking at the layout of this it's like
you know it's like nine floats
plus you know 32
68 fantastic number okay
um so 68
of these i don't know this is just
stupid
um the way this is done
but so 68 is
fine so we got 16 times 655
36 times 2 times 68.
uh so it's pretty huge right it's a 142
megabyte
buffer for debug that said it's a debug
buffer so you can pretty much make it as
large as you want and no one's going to
care because it doesn't actually ship
with the game
so i suppose there's that
if we were to make this bigger so it
takes half a meg
does anyone care and does that fix our
problem if so that's probably what we
should do
um but we'll see
yeah so basically if we just let it have
more
you know then it's fine so that's okay
with me
if we take a look at the arenas now do
we see that
stuff happening oh wait no we
but the duh we didn't turn back on the
diagram so we don't know
that yeah we don't know that that
actually helped
oh
false alarm that may not
actually be necessary yet the reason
that may not be necessary is we're not
clearing these right we haven't called
render diagrams yet
right um so we haven't actually called
any stuff so it'll just keep piling up
forever so
that you know yeah that probably
is the problem so we we could we're okay
no need to panic uh i just forgot we
hadn't actually finished this stuff yet
so we wouldn't we would it would just
grow forever right
so all we really have to do here
probably is clear this arena
right um and i'm gonna go ahead and pull
out this is a as a local just have to
keep typing it
if we go ahead and say look clear that
arena you know
get rid of all that um
how does that work
in the debug system though
yeah so you know now that i think about
it i i i maybe
that may be false alarm though maybe it
is a problem because
the debug thing will get cleared every
time because that always gets cleared
so
yeah so that does seem weird also debug
arena suppress
does seem like we could use that as well
so we could get rid of this arena from
the system so that wouldn't be a problem
right
yeah i don't know anyway uh when we look
at this
here it looks like it records the block
freeze as well so the clear would work
um but those things all i thought just
got
freed anyway so so i yeah so i don't
know
i'm gonna go ahead and do this part but
i do think we may have
some stuff to worry about anyway so
let's suppose we do a clear on this
uh so that we do clear out the group
every time
like so uh and so every time
in handmade uh you know update and
render or whatever
not update in render editor although
maybe that does make sense i don't know
you know maybe that is where it should
be but uh update and render
i'm thinking more like just update and
render
regular like in handmade cpp right
so in uh in this game update and render
right uh when we go through here i'm
just wondering like
you know maybe this happens after we do
whatever this ui nonsense is here right
so we do that and then we clear the
diagrams
and that probably has to be something
that is going to go through this system
maybe that
right so that it doesn't cause a problem
so that'll be diagram reset that'll be
uh
that'll be called every frame and so now
at least we know this will get rid of
uh any things that are you know in the
way
so if i go ahead and make that a one so
now the diagram code is enabled
and i run it now i want to see
like is this actually a problem with too
many of these
i want to know right
so looking at the global debug table
okay i'm pretty sure it's not zero
that seems unlikely um
let's try that again folks
uh
so i suppose what i don't know is
how is that event array index
thing doing what it's doing
um
so it's just a 64-bit value that's split
into two
halves right
so
top one looks irrelevant um
so it is just an overflow right
that's all it is and so now i just don't
know
like is it is that actually expected and
maybe it is
i don't know so what i'd like to do here
is just say well let's find out
let's boost that number and see what
happens
just so i can have some perspective on
whether it actually is an unbounded
problem
uh or whether it's just a uh
yeah so it really feels
well hmm that's a little bit odd though
because that number is the same number
oh but that's just what we put in there
so here's our uh
our new one right
so it really feels unbounded right it
feels like we're doing something where
it's not really that we don't have
enough
it feels kind of unbounded and i'm not
sure why
you know what i'm saying so let's see if
we can figure out what's going on there
if there's some kind of thing that i
screwed up
uh
or maybe it really is just that many
diagrams
you know what i mean
so i guess if you look at what's
happening here i guess it really could
just be that many diagrams because if
you look
it's any time you call move entity it's
doing the n squared check
because we don't have the spatial
partition
right so if it's an n squared thing yeah
that probably just will blow out the
total diagram i mean you wouldn't want
to record
that many of them right
so that does seem like just flat out a
problem
and i'm not sure like maybe the right
thing to do here
is to limit this to a particular entity
you know what i mean
like you know
if we just want to see particular
entities we can
have some way of restricting it because
you know i'm going to want to use these
diagrams all over the place
so i don't really want like i can't
afford to have them
be something that's producing billions
and billions of things
so i need a way of scoping them down
more
so maybe we do something like
um
how would we do this
so we basically need some filter here
and i'm guessing that we just need like
entity filters so
i'm thinking that probably what we want
is like sort of this
sort of thing
so like whoever's trying to do like
pushes
has to check to see what's up
right
uh and then we will just return zero
when the filter says that the diagram is
not necessary at that time
uh and so here we can just say like okay
if we want to actually do the thing do
the thing
otherwise return 0
and we can just turn it off that way you
know what i mean
and so now we just need a way of
articulating what the filter actually
is right
um but otherwise we should be fine
so now if i go ahead and restore to
a optimize build
like so
um
now what we need is just a way of like
you know spot turning it on so
like
i guess we just want this thing to just
[Music]
do
i i really don't know um
but my hunch is we just use some kind of
like an id
so you know something like an entity id
like we have um
we could just say something like
in the diagrams we
[Music]
uh we pass a filter
so you say like i'm gonna begin
[Music]
like
um you pass a filter and you know
everything from then on if it doesn't
match the filter
right or whatever it doesn't pass i
don't know
so you would do like
you pass some value here and there's
like
a set that someone can call
uh and then each time through when we do
these it's like okay we know we're going
to be doing a bunch of diagramming and
so the thing is like
well the diagram filter here
is going to be like you know two and and
there should probably be like
multiple pieces to this like this thing
should probably take
like a care star or something or like a
void star
that's like a
like a type string or something and then
the value so it would be like okay you
know it's this function
and uh
just to like disambiguate which one
you're doing although i guess the
now that's probably not that necessary
because you can just pick those out so
let's let's ignore that so we'll just
say look there's the entity
we're going to pass the id as the filter
and that will give us a way of only
outputting
the diagrams we actually care about at
any particular time hopefully um
and we'll go from there
that seems fine
and the way this would work is now we
like
have some notion of like did you pass
the filter
so in here we've got
a filter past variable um
and like the filter itself
and so in here you would say set filter
just as a global diagram group filter
equals value
and in here you would just have global
diagram
group filter past equals
like whatever this thing is that you're
getting
um if it equals whatever the last thing
was set as the filter
then we use then you can draw
right so at that point
this just works and this is now just
if the diagramming is on right and i
think
then we're fine so now the diagramming
is actually live
and you can run it and in theory
we won't have that problem with too many
diagrams
and now you should be able to sync your
diagram just fine
by turning on the filter for a
particular entity
right um and then what we can do
is just next time uh we'll find the free
f
key there are not many
um oh we've already got one
right so
really all we need to do is go into this
collision recorder thing change this to
diagramming
um and then it will step us through
right
um so that's what we'll do next week is
tie that up to it
uh and then we should have some diagrams
whether we'll find anything with them i
don't know but hopefully they'll
make it clear what's going on um the
other nice thing we could do there
is like we can finally shut off some of
this other stuff so like if we go back
into world mode we don't have to keep
drawing stupid
uh colliders and stuff
um
there we go uh so we don't have to draw
like this stuff
anymore uh because we can now put that
into the diagram so that we only
see the colliders that we actually care
about that are like in the region we're
looking in and all those sorts of things
so that would clean things up nicely so
that when we're normally running we see
the actual
thing correctly which is much better um
just so we have some idea of what the
heck is going on
uh and then we'll just make it so that
as we get you know closer to things that
draws their collision volumes in
uh using the actual uh diagramming right
and then we should be able to see we can
like set the diagramming to show the
glove and then when we get those things
where it sticks on the corner
and we don't think it should because the
sphere roll-off should have solved that
right or that was the hope anyway
we can see why and that's really what we
want here
you know what i mean
all right
so that's it folks
any questions about what we just did
um it all looks okay like i think it's
so the only thing that i would say about
it is
one thing i would probably do if this
was something i was programming in
myself
uh with a lot more time uh i would say
you
probably want to make it easier to
specify the diagrams
so i might make it so you can just like
throw those up on there
if that makes sense
do you know about web view 2 that
doesn't sound
on topic synthesis
[Music]
um
well it's just web view 2 just kind of
sounds like
you know electron for windows right i
mean that doesn't seem weird
it's just hey you wanted to put a
website
content thing into your
like into your app
um that you know i mean we already have
that
but i guess this they this is
microsoft's version of it right
what's the sphere roll off um so what i
was trying to say there was just that
if you so one of the things that we
added to the collision system was
spheres and they don't seem to work
right
because you would expect the spheres you
would expect sphere colliders to be able
to roll
off the side of of uh
like when they hit
the collision normal is going to be
pointing towards the center of the
sphere which means that if you hit
anywhere
to like the side of the center of the
sphere
it should be able to roll around the
corner instead of getting stuck
and you know that needs to get debugged
because it doesn't look it's working
you made it about rewinding a memory
arena does a rewind free the allocation
uh it doesn't have to the important part
about that particular to-do
was i was just trying to note that what
we don't want to do
is we don't want to push some space on
use it for a printf buffer
and then orphan all the space that
wasn't used
because that's just a tremendous waste
especially when you're doing potentially
a lot of these like we would be
so if you put on 1024 because you want
to support
large string printfs and most of your
strings are 16 characters or something
you're orphaning like basically a
thousand bytes in the arena
that you can't use for anything they
just got wasted on that frame
right and yeah it all gets cleared at
the end so maybe you don't care but it's
still a tremendous amount of wasted
memory
uh paging that doesn't have to happen
and so the way smarter thing to do is
when you do a printf like that
you print f into the buffer and you then
record that you the
amount you actually used and it's very
simple it's a really simple addition to
arenas that you know you should do
shouldn't we add spatial partitioning
for collisions uh and such at this point
uh
not until it's debugged so
i don't want to uh so so typically if
you when you're talking about spatial
partitioning for things
the best time to do spatial partitioning
is after you're done with the algorithm
because until you're done with the
algorithm and until you have it
completely debugged and you know that
it's
what you want you may end up making it
if you do before that you
may end up making a spatial audition
that doesn't answer the questions you
actually needed
because you add a question or you change
how a question is asked
when you modify the routine so i would
highly recommend
not adding a spatial partition until
after you're done
with the actual routine because then you
know what you need
whereas until you're done you don't
you mentioned you are doing memory
arenas differently now what are you
doing differently um
so nowadays i lean on the 64-bit
stuff more so a lot of times i'll set up
arenas if they're growable arenas
they grow in linear order
they don't use chunks as much right
because you don't really need chunks as
much when you have a full 64-bit address
space
you can kind of just like grow linearly
pretty much all the time it's pretty
rare to need
anything else so you know you do it a
little bit differently um
in the early days you're mentioning that
australia's got enough attraction you
could probably
possibly look into networking what are
your chances now uh no if you want
networking you're going to have to do
star code galaxy
starco galaxy covers networking um
handmade hero will not so you know
when this comes out you'll get your
networking
um and there's a lot of it
but uh handmade heroes no networking
so
uh why do you forward to clear the
diagram function the header file i
thought you did the unity build system
so you didn't need to that kind of thing
unless the pound include order requires
it
um well there's a couple of reasons uh
two
two or not two do it right uh
yeah one is for the pound include order
the other is just for my own
organization so when i do
uh typically when
i do something where i have to do this
crap because of c
plus um i typically also put the
the non-pound defined versions up here
and that's just so i can see them and
make sure that i remember to do
them both right so
you don't really need them um
you you probably and well i don't know
let me just see i'm not sure what our
there we go
uh you probably don't need them so you
probably
could do this uh right and it still
works
but typically when i you know typically
what happens
is i end up uh putting them in there
when i'm trying to keep them lined up
right
do you know any particular reason why
msvc would optimize a piece of code
better with
slash ox instead of slash o2
um can you be more specific i don't even
remember what
the like i i hate remembering things
like command line switches and stuff
so i don't even remember what that is
uh slash ox
is favor speed
so you're asking why is slash 02
and slash ox you're expecting them to be
the same
because they're both favor speed
or and and you're not seeing that um
or something so i can give a meta answer
because obviously i have no idea because
i don't write the compiler
but what i would do is i would go to
here
right nope not that did i type that
wrong
there we go i guess i typed it wrong um
so i would go to here and i would put in
your code that you're talking about
whatever it is right and then i would
just set this up
to to look at both of them so i'd add
two compilers
i'd add microsoft's you know
increasingly terrible compiler as they
release new versions of it
the latest version of microsoft visual
studio visual c compiler is one of the
worst
i've ever experienced in the
10 in the 30 year history of me having
used this compiler is that right
so like 92 so 10 10
10. yeah in the 30-year history of using
the compiler their latest one is
probably one of the worst i've ever
experienced
it's absolutely horrific um it gets
worse with every version and this
latest version is is
just insane um absolutely
absolutely terrible uh so i'm assuming
that everyone will eventually switch to
clang
because they have to because microsoft
continues to make their compiler so bad
that just i don't think anyone could
use it uh eventually but you know
that's where we're at so you know i
would type in whatever the thing is
that you're trying to do here
you know um and then what i would do
is oops i forgot this thing is to return
something
um i would look and see if you can
narrow down
what the actual difference is between
the assembly language between these two
right um and
so that is that is what
that is what i would do because then you
can find out like
what is the actual diff uh
that that it you know what is it
actually changing
that is making the speed difference
right and then you can investigate that
but i would start by trying to find the
actual difference
and you can pick your exact version of
msvc if you're not using the latest one
but that's where i would start
what do you mean by grow linearly um so
what i mean
is that in a 64-bit address space
you can just pick very sparse starting
points for your arenas so that they have
as much room to grow as they want right
um
that's that's all i mean
yeah and botonder my answer is the same
right it doesn't matter which one of
these produces more
regardless of which one produces the
faster code you want to find out by
doing this
and there's multiple reasons for that
one is you might want to report a bug
i mean we've seen what happens when you
report a bug to microsoft so maybe don't
do that
but you will be able to see what's going
wrong
and then when you see what's going wrong
you can try to change your routines to
work around it right
because you have to remember that when
you when you're asking the compiler to
optimize something
what really is happening is the compiler
is applying a bunch of heuristics about
what it thinks is going to happen
uh to your code but it never actually
tests them
right so the compiler doesn't the
compiler never like compiles and runs
the code to see whether it's faster
it's just guessing that if it applies
the transformations that it thinks are
faster that it will get faster
right that's what it's doing
and so when you ask it for
maximum optimizations it's simply
what it's going to apply are the
optimizations that it generally
thinks are the best but there's no
guarantee that that code will actually
be better
that code may actually be worse for all
we know
right it may be worse than debug in some
really rare cases
because the compiler never checks right
the compiler never checks to see whether
the code
actually got faster it's never running
the code only you are running the code
and you're the one who knows that it got
slower
so what you have to do is when you see a
case where two different flags
produce different speeds and it's
unclear why
you're like how that doesn't make sense
because this one should have is supposed
to be faster
the only thing you could do is go look
you just have to go look
and then when you find out what the
problem is you can try to work around it
by changing your c
code or hand optimizing that part that
got slower
so that the compiler doesn't have to
figure it out right you're
when you're doing code optimization
through a compiler you have to do a
bunch of that
stupid dance where you go in there and
you like you know you
make little changes to your c code to
try and nudge the compiler towards the
right thing to do
right
would be possible to render all of the
unfiltered n-squared diagrams if the
number of debug events was huge
or are there just way too many diagrams
for that um
you know one of the problems so
there's a difference between what's
possible and what's feasible
right so it's probably possible
to render all the diagrams but the debug
system
is not set up to be super optimal
because it's a debug system
right and so the problem that you get
is that you don't actually want to spend
a bunch of time
optimizing the throughput of your debug
diagrams
right so what's
feasible to do and what's possible to do
are very different in this case because
if we don't want to spend a bunch of
time optimizing the throughput of our
debug system so that we can draw
billions of diagrams
which might be very possible on today's
hardware it's just not feasible for us
because we're trying to do
other stuff we don't want to spend all
our time on a debug diagram system if we
did we might be optimizing it for that
kind of throughput right
and for the record like that would be a
cool project right
so if someone wanted to do a really
highly optimized very awesome debug
system that you could use in your games
or whatever that's a great tool
right so it's not so much that you don't
want to make a super highly optimized
debug system it's just that that's its
own
project right and so if you're not doing
that project then it doesn't make much
sense to do it
i think that's all the questions
what you used to build on linux
i i don't know what you mean
what do i use to build on linux i just
use a compiler
i usually use clang sometimes i use gcc
if that's the thing that's installed
do you know that sean barrett is writing
a c compiler are you going to use it i
mean i don't really have any use for a c
compiler so i don't
i mean i program in c
plus plus you know i don't use a lot of
cbs features but i use
you know operator overloading and stuff
like that so a c compiler doesn't really
help me
oh any build system or just yeah just a
sh file same exact thing as i do on
windows just a dot sh file that just
says
like clang and then the file the c file
and a bunch of switches
that's the entire build right
all right
thank you everyone for joining me for an
episode of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding through as always if you
want to follow
the series you can always pre-order the
game on handmade hero.org and it comes
with the source code
um i will be back here next week to
do this actual uh basically we did all
the work for like queuing up our
diagrams
and so now we need something that will
actually draw them
right uh and so we'll just make our
our little like drawing loop uh and then
we should have some diagrams
the hope is that will make it pretty
easy for us to figure out what goes on
with things
like spheres like whatever but i don't
actually know
so it'll be more of a question of like
at that point it'll become a little bit
of a
of a discovery process where we start
drawing things
and hopefully those drawings will help
us discover uh some of the problems
that we might that might be lurking in
the collision code that's hard to find
without drawing
that's it uh i will see you next week
until then have fun programming everyone
and i will see you on the internet
um i don't