and there we go hello everyone and
welcome to a sleepy morning edition of
handmade hero we are getting started
late today because honestly I was just
too tired so I was drinking my coffee
and we were chatting while trying to get
to the point where our brains might
actually function to do some programming
because we do have some programming to
do today and it is not the absolutely
trivial variety we are going to go in
and modify our stand and collision
detection loop to do some new stuff that
we wanted to do in terms of working with
entities that define the walkable
regions and the ground in the game and
of course the reason we're doing this is
because we want to be able to have rich
three-dimensional constructions in our
game even though it is a 2-d game we
want to be able to do things like rooms
on top of rooms that you can see down
into other rooms from and ledges you can
jump off of and land on lower ones again
this is not necessarily because we feel
like this is crucial to the game design
or anything like that
as is typical on handmade hero it's more
about making sure that we don't shy away
from solving the harder problems in any
particular game space and so the fact
that this is something that is raised by
the type of game I want to tackle it
head-on and show everyone how to tackle
these kinds of problems even if we in
the end don't really decide to use it
very heavily in the actual game design
we still want to make sure that our
engine tech is you know top-notch and I
feel like this is the kind of thing that
you know if I were looking at some kind
of a 2d engine licensable thing right I
want to know that it's got a really nice
robust system that allows me to define
these nice 3d things even in my 2-d game
so that it all worked kind of seamlessly
and feels good and doesn't have janky
corner cases where as a designer when
I'm making my game in it I gotta be like
oh I can't I got a hack all this stuff
in and add all these other special
checks to sort of approximate the fact
that it's gonna be in 3d right so we
kind of talked about this yesterday I
highly recommend watching
yesterday stream before this one if you
haven't already because we kind of
talked about exactly what we wanted to
do as our first attempt at at solving
some of the ground specification
problems because a little bit of a
open-ended sort of thing since there's a
lot of ways you could imagine doing it
and there's questions about you know
what do you think would be the most
effective and so I'm just gonna go ahead
and start programming the stuff that we
said we're going to program yesterday we
added all of the infrastructure we
needed to do that but we haven't
actually done the computation on it yet
and so that's we're gonna be doing today
is writing that computation and then
playing around it to see if it does what
we need it to do so with that in mind I
will just remind everyone that if you
wanted to follow along with the source
code and you have pre-order the game
today is day 80 and which is our second
week of programming write one hour a day
80 hours that's two 40-hour work weeks
we are finishing up our second full week
of programming very exciting here on
handmade hero but that means that if you
have that source codes if you want to
unpack day 79 out of it because that is
the source code that I'm starting with
now and so let's see how sleepy we
actually are let's go ahead and bring up
those collision detection routines and
see if we just stare at them blankly
going I don't know what all these
letters and numbers on the screen mean
or whether we actually whether the
coffee has kicked in to the point where
we actually can write some code that
makes sense alright so the first thing
that I'm going to do is take a look at
you know sort of doing an as simple as
possible modification of the loop
because again we'll probably do some
significant upgrades for this collision
loop in terms of robustness and
performance and everything else so we
don't really care necessarily how
efficient this loop is right now as long
as we think we can make it efficient
later that's fine so really what we want
to do here is take a look at this loop
and go well looking at this loop what
can we do to sort of tackle this this
this thing we were talking about
yesterday
which is this right here right we we
want to turn our loop that was looping
on one type of T value to something that
loops on two type of T values we want to
say alright find the minimum T that is
where we would stop if we were gonna hit
solid entities that's what we're already
doing
let's mint this loop to also have a
second T value which is the maximum
distance you could go in the entities
that are representing empty space right
so we're doing our own kind of
constructive solid geometry here merging
things together so that's what we're
doing and that means we've got a sort of
upgrade this T handling so if you look
here on each iteration of the loop you
can see that we've got the T min and
that T min is exactly what we were
working with in terms of entities
getting hit so what we want to do is
introduce another one here I think T max
which is saying this is how far you
could go maximally and obviously at the
outset T max is going to be equal to
zero because at the outset of a loop we
have no idea how far you could go before
hitting a boundary of one of these solid
objects and so if you know I thought of
something else we're probably gonna have
to add for this and it's something
that's pretty good to talk about so
that's good but anyway we'll get that
second and so what we want to do is we
want to look at the entities now and
obviously we've got some that are that
that are operating on T min already and
that's good that's exactly what we want
but what we want to do now is also take
a look at entities that would affect RT
max so we do cat can collide and we go
through and and you know check the
things that we collide against and in
fact I think we probably want to move
this inside this is interesting
early out I guess but for now I guess
let's go ahead and just
and just do this here so we're gonna go
ahead and add that can collide on the
inside so after we start looping through
the volumes and we're going to do a
volume check I guess the way that I
would say it is when we well now you
know what let's make two checks here
because we sort of have we sort of have
two kinds this this is like our early
out if you will right it's our thing
that says do we need to do any checking
on this guy at all and it feels like we
probably want to leave something like
that in place so I guess we'll actually
just do two checks right we'll see
whether there's any kind of collision
that's going to happen here at all and
then we also need to say later
what kind of collision that actually is
so when we go through this what we would
say is all right if it's something that
we can't collide with in some way then
we go ahead and set up the collision
computation when we do the collision
computation we then actually want to do
these tests differently right so right
now what we're doing is we're testing
the four walls of the bounding box for
whatever the entity is we want to go
ahead and do this so that instead of
looking for the minimum T it's gonna
look for the maximum T and I feel like
probably the easiest way to write that
right now is to have test wall compute
both and then at the end we will just do
whichever one is you know whichever one
is the one we actually wanted to pick
now the problem with that is the test
wall normal stuff that's that's gonna be
a little janky because we don't actually
know we need to know which of the two
whether team in test or team
max tests which one was hit potentially
I guess no that's not true that's not
true I suppose
well you know I mean this is what I'm
thinking we have this test wall call and
inside the test wall call right I'm just
trying to think of how to structure this
the most effectively inside the test
wall called what we're doing is we're
checking to see whether or not the hit
was earlier than it used to be right and
in fact you know this this is that test
right there right saying if this test is
is earlier mm-hmm
then we're going to accept it and if we
want to add a thing here that says if
this test was larger than a Tmax accept
it for the t max hit as well so again I
don't know it seems like to me almost
that we want to actually just have two
different loops here which is kind of
annoying to say the least but I don't
know I mean you know maybe that's maybe
that's just what has to happen so you
know it would look something like this
if we were to do it that way right it
would look something like this where we
have one of them here and we have
exactly the same code duplicated for the
max on the other side now I feel like
that's a little bit ugly so I'm
wondering too if maybe we wouldn't turn
this into something that just loops over
data right which seems kind of plausible
maybe I'll I'll give that a shot first
so let's let's you know the way that I'm
thinking about it is basically this this
test wall we've sort of manually made
this a loop over data by repeating the
code and then plugging the data in right
in each individual case and so what I
could do is is loft that into some
actual data right and then just do a for
I loop over it and that would give me
the opportunity to do that for I loop in
two different ways without having
it'd be particularly problematic right
and again since we don't super care
about the performance of the screw team
at the moment that is probably fine we
don't have to think too hard about it
so I'm kind of want to lean towards the
thing that's gonna be the easiest to
type in so let's let's try that right
let's go ahead and say okay if zero this
out seems like a good idea if zero this
out and let's turn this into an actual
for loop so if we were gonna turn this
into a for loop and it looks something
like this wall index equals zero wall
index is less than a rate count walls
you know something like this wall index
plus plus and then we're just gonna do
this once I guess that's technically up
there we're just gonna do that like so
and each wall so I don't know what we'll
call this a test wall I'm not sure
each wall we will loop through walls
plus wall index and we will just grab
out of that all of these values that we
were going to use previously right so
we'll basically say all right yeah we've
got you know the wall min corner X so I
guess let's just do that the wall
relative what are these what are these
actually in fact they're just these so
you know it'd be this right so there we
go we'd get rid of a team in but
everything else would just be in there
and so the test wall is just wall X wall
this is no well X well real X well real
y wall player Delta X wall
there Delta Y and maybe I'll just change
this to be calling Delta X and Delta Y
so on and then got the min Y and the max
lab right
and so we'll call that test well
function like that
and now that allows us today to drive
this this call so that we can you know
and this is the exact same here test
well normal would be equal to wall
normal that allows me to just build a
data structure that will allow this loop
to drive and then we don't have this
code spammed out here so if we want to
duplicate this loop twice it's not such
a big deal right so that also allows me
to move this inside potentially since we
want to do this check two different ways
one with the min confirmation and one
with the Max confirmation so I'm gonna
go ahead and do that as well although I
guess I'll do it in two steps to make
debugging a little bit easier so let's
go ahead and and now turn this into data
so we now want to take all of these
things that used to be actually spammed
out as individual calls here and make
them into data all right like so so
here's all my values minus the min test
so that's gone right and I guess I
should I think I accidentally removed
that entirely
so in here after that Delta Y we do need
T min to be here so we want T min test
to be in there as well so there we go so
that's really all I'm talking about here
right I guess we need that wall normal
as well so let's grab that and stick
that in there so so now we've got an
easy way today to drive this and that's
a good technique especially in
situations like this where you know our
primary concern here is not the
performance right now so we don't really
have to worry too much about how we
structure this we just want to make sure
we structure it in a way that's you know
reasonable and more more or less easy
for us to modify right now and then we
can kind of go through later once
everything's said and done and we're in
a more performance oriented mindset we
can sort of attack this later on because
obviously there's no difference between
these two things if later we needed to
pull this back out into some more
explicit code we could always do that so
all right so there's our fault four
walls and here's our wall testing and
and honestly I think that may just work
all we need to do now is actually define
this test wall and that's that's going
to be exactly this stuff right like so
so we we have our X we have our rel X we
have our rel Y we have our Delta X we
have our Delta Y we have our min and Max
and that's it we have two videos oh
right and we need to remember our normal
which is not something that's actually
being passed so that's actually normal
there we go and so let's make sure that
that is still working at all right so
that appears to be working just fine so
that's all good no problems there all
right and yeah everything's still good
we can walk through things perfect so
let's take this the next step further
let's move test wall into there so that
we're not actually calling it any more
so that we actually just have this
called directly embedded so what that's
going to look like right is this so
inside here we're going to we're going
to actually do this case inside here
right that's what we were doing before
we're gonna get rid of all of this and
we can actually loft some things out
pretty trivially here I guess all we
really need to do is just make these
operate off of that pointer all right so
I'm just gonna go ahead and do that so
all the wall stuff is is this way
there we go and
tea results tea results is it's just a
thing we computed and then team min is
this guy right here all right so this is
T min test right like so and we don't
have to do pointers to it anymore we can
just use the actual value so T min test
like so I think that's most of what we
need to do there so if there's our boobs
our wall there and there and that looks
good so let's see okay so now we've
we've basically collapsed all that down
into a little loop it looks pretty nice
so here we go and that all seems to
still work pretty good go out here test
against all these guys everything looks
good yeah so pretty happy with that
we can still can we still shoot oh man
did we break our did we break our hit
testing for against the Monstar I feel
like we did right it's not doing that
anymore I wonder that doesn't have
anything to do with what we were doing
does it we just didn't test that in a
while
della check yeah so we got out we got a
bug there we should take a look at
someone remind me to take a look at that
it doesn't really matter at this point
because like I said we're still playing
with all this stuff but we should
it probably has something to do with the
fact that we have changed the 3d ness of
everything and maybe that sword no
longer overlaps the guy when it passes
through or something like that but all
right ignoring that moving on so what we
want to do here is also have something
where we test you know in entities that
we would consider inside entities like
those empty space entities we want to do
this testing a little bit differently so
we would basically say you know if we're
testing for an inside entity we do this
right and if we're testing for opaque
when we do this other thing right so
let's go ahead and introduce a second
loop here that we're going to do for
things that are inside entities and that
would be that would be a double if
actually because we have to see we only
do it for things that we're currently
inside if I if I if I think about it
correctly right you you want to find the
maximum T for the for the empty space
entities that you're actually inside so
here's that secondary type of test and
really the difference here is that
instead of T min test we're going to be
using T max test so this is T max test
this is T max test like so and if we
were doing it this way we need to
reverse the sense of these so basically
we want to make sure that whatever the
result is is greater than zero and then
we want to say all right whatever
do me whatever this max is we want to
accept at any time that the t max test
is less than the T results so if we were
going to have a hit that was further
away now
before we were testing for hits that
were closer now we want to test for hits
that are further away than the best one
we've got so far and then when we come
in here I don't know what we would want
to do epsilon Y is the reason we had
epsilon is before us to stop you a
little bit before you got to the wall
and in this particular case I don't know
how much we care about that exactly we
do have a bit of a problem which is you
are never allowed to be outside of these
and so I feel like you know probably
what we want to do is you want to stop
you exactly on one and perhaps do you
know like a fix up at afterwards - to
make sure that your Oh ease inside right
we want to we want to keep you
constrained to the outside to the inside
of these as much as possible so for now
we're just gonna say that this is going
to be T results like so we've already
tested it against zero so we know it's
not a hit that's behind us so that seems
fine and test well normal in this case
we have two of these so we're gonna have
a test wall we're normal
the min side can attest while normal on
the Mac side right we want to track both
of those so we have testable normal min
and Max and we've got our our team in
test and we've got our T max test which
which like guess it's just zero yeah to
start with so there we go we come
through here we do our t max test we now
have that computed and so at the end of
this we actually know both of these I
suppose for these two things I don't
really know exactly what we want to do
it's a good question in terms of these
guys I suppose for now let's let's do
this hand like separately since it's
going to be pretty different probably so
this is the case where we were you know
hitting something that was going to stop
us this is the case where we're hitting
something that isn't going to stop us
that's allowing us to move so assuming
that we hit it we now would say well we
don't need to do the speculative
collision stuff probably we do need to
say that our are hit well normal max is
equal to our test well our max our hit
entity max is going to be equal to our
test entity and our t max is going to be
t max test right
and similarly our roll normal min here
is going to be equal to our testable
normal min now I guess technically so
since we only do one of these loops
I suppose we actually don't need to do
we don't need to have two test sets
right since we can get rid of this right
this is gone
this could really we could just leave it
as test well normal right and in fact
this this that goes inside the secondary
loop so we could just say all right test
of all normal that's just going to be
test well normal right no big deal test
roll normal test well normal
and this guy can do it the same way so
it's really only that outer one that
actually needs to be specified as both
the min and the max all right so we've
got test run or oh man test well my mum
acts like so I and at the end now we
just have to do some thinking about
what's actually going to happen
depending on which one of the this is
and oh I right I needed to hit under the
min and Max as well so that comes up
here's Kennedy Ben max so hmm I guess
what we'd want to do now is we want to
see which of our team ends with sooner
right so what we want to do is say
something like you know pick one here so
we want to say if our team min is less
than our t max that means that we hit
somebody who was opaque and he stopped
us right a solid entity stopped us from
moving so if that's the case then what
we would like to do is we want to
introduce here because T min is going to
be used to compute the actual motion we
want to introduce this thing here which
is a key stop something like that right
and so our key stop is something that
we're going to initialize depending on
which side of this we take right like
that so if the team in is less than the
T max then the teet the stopping value
is the minimum and if the T stop if the
other way around then the T stop is
whatever the maximum when we hit is and
that determines what our can't hit NB is
I guess we'll call it our stop Kennedy
well no our he identities fine right
so our Kida t equals our hit entity min
in this case and our wall normal equals
our wall normal min right
like so max max max and those things can
now move down
I believe meaning that for example hit
entity was and and and well normal those
used to be defined up at the top and now
they're gonna be defined here because
they actually this is where they
actually get used like so on and so that
just allows us to take whichever one of
those we want now we haven't filled in
these two ifs here we're gonna have to
do that I guess we're gonna have to do
that right away let's just do this for
now there we go so it looks like we're
compiling fine we just need these actual
tests so this one right here we have to
test for overlap and this one right here
we have to test to see whether the
entity is an empty space entity and so
we have a way very trivially to test if
it's an empty space entity if just is
whether or not this traversable set flag
is set so basically if this test entity
has the traversable size flag set then
we know we're doing basically a maximum
extents movement test right and then
what we want to do is before we test
against this guy we have to verify that
you were actually inside him right you
have to have been inside the bounding
box in order to do the move and so what
we want to do is is sort of take our
overlap testing that we were doing here
we want that overlap testing to occur
inside the loop and what's interesting
about that is this was actually
something that we probably should have
been doing in the loop anyway where we
are handling the overlap in a more
intelligent way so it's kind of
something that probably is good for us
to have been doing regardless and we do
have a little bit of an oddity there
which is that we kind of want all of the
things that you're overlapping at any
given time to have an effect on you and
again this is just you know the the
complexity of really doing motion
correctly in games is it's
it's very very complicated as you've
seen so far we've spent a bunch of time
on it
way more time than we spend on a lot of
different things that we had to spec out
but I don't really want to stop pushing
on a lot of these things because usually
what happens in any particular piece of
code especially when you're working on
something that's relatively complicated
is things get very complex and then you
start to find ways in which they can
simplify down right and so you know
sometimes proliferating out and really
like handling or all the edge cases and
thinking it through and improving the
capabilities of something even though
that ends up with this big messy
nightmare yeah in some cases that's
actually not something to be too afraid
of as long as you are then willing to go
through and go all right now that we've
seen the nightmare how do we turn it
into a pleasant dream right and and so
that's what you know happens a lot of
times in code if you push through it and
so I would encourage people not to be
scared about how ugly some of the stuff
is to handle and you know don't just go
oh let's just go do something simpler
because a lot of times in the end what
we come up with could might actually be
quite simple like we may be able to then
reduce down reduce down reduce down and
end up with something that is actually
pretty simple in the end it but it took
us that sort of circuitous route to get
there because we have to see all the
complexity first before we can have the
insights that make things simpler and
we've seen that happen already on the
stream a couple times in other places so
that's why I would always encourage you
to push through that do actually do go
solve the problems no matter how janky
your solutions end up being because once
you have them all solved that puts you
in a really good position to come up
with more clever streamlined solutions
that still get all the benefits that
you're at a perfect point to be able to
do that once you've seen it all right
and before you've actually gotten solve
them all you don't really have the
necessary sort of perspective and of how
everything really works in practice
so yeah so we want to do here is take a
look
you know let's take a little step back
and just think about that overlapping
bit just a little a little bit so as we
go through our iterations on each
iteration right we are doing this
overlap testing and we're seeing you
know we've got you know what what what
entities are we inside right what what
space filling entities are we re
enclosed by at at any given time and
those entities that we are enclosed in
we want to take a look at those sort of
how should I say this we want to take a
look at those in sort of also a well so
as I think about this more I'm thinking
maybe you don't want to double up that
notion though look maybe we don't ever
really want to say that something that
encloses a space can also be a trigger
we may want those to actually be
separate because they mean everything so
I guess I'll put that aside for now I
guess really all we do need to do is
just pull out oops what did i do did I
hit no I did all right fine
I guess really all we do need to do is
pull out the notion of the overlap test
into something else so that we don't
have to do it multiple times so
basically this this stuff right here
this this testing that's something that
we probably want to to loft out so let's
go ahead and and nerf this for one
second
so that I can pull out the other test
and verify it well enough so let's go
ahead and do that so let's end if this
will go back in here and just say you
know so the oops that's no good what did
I do wrong there I managed to make it oh
right
with our team in set to zero to zero to
max up zero you'll never be able to move
anywhere so temporarily I need to set
this T max to one so that you can
actually move right
there we go so this is the thing that's
doing that actually operates on overlap
right now is right is that moving up and
down so I want to go ahead and do the
overlap test to make the overlap test be
better and so let's go ahead and do that
overlap test because it's got to do on
here that says handle multi bombs let's
handle the multi bombs and then pull it
out into its own test that allows you to
check for overlap really easily right so
in order to check for overlap what we
want to do here is move this entity rect
inside so that what we're going to do is
we loop over the volumes of both things
like we were doing before in another one
of these double double loops right it's
literally this thing right here this
loop right here so we could just reuse
that that verbiage that is sort of the
the way in which we were doing that
testing so what we want to do is test
the what are our two things here there's
test identity so it's a key the same as
it was before
so we've got the two different NDS we
now have the two different volumes and
so what we want to do is make this code
happen and then at the end we say if
overlapped we handle that overlap right
so we'll basically say bool overlap
equals false and we can early-out as
soon as we know that we overlap because
we don't need to keep checking for
overlap so we wanted to say you know if
we aren't overlapped in each of these
loops then we'll do that and that way
when we set overlap to true here they'll
break out of both loops and be done so
here we are inside our volume testing we
can do it exactly the way that we were
doing it before right instead of doing
total volume in both cases all we really
have to do is switch to using the two
different volumes that we said so we
essentially have entity volume I believe
what is it not just volume so we have
volume like so
right oops so we have volume and then
we've got the test entity rect is going
to be hmm the test volume there we go
and now we are looping over both volumes
and testing them both and then we are
seeing whether or not those volumes
intersect and we can actually do it just
straight straight ahead since we know we
breakout immediately upon overlap being
true we can make it a little bit more
concise so there we go
so now we've got a relatively concise
over left check that we're doing here
and so what we should be able to do is
now pull this out into its own function
right so let's let's go ahead and
compile that first make sure this works
okay
rule 3 to forcing value to troops I
typed that wrong and by the way this is
why I hate bool and always type bool 32
I don't like these warnings right I
don't want the compiler to do those
those quote-unquote optimizations there
or lack of optimizations to do those
things that turn things into 0 and 1 for
no reason so I just want everything to
pass through regardless of how it was
computed so all right now we've got that
let's pull it out although I guess I'll
test it first just to make sure that it
still works it does so that's good and
we can go in here and pull that out into
some kind of a function like internal
bowl for you two entities overlap
hmm sorry I was thinking about some
things in my head so I might want to do
something else here which is introduce a
little okay so I had a thought I'll
share that thought with you in one
moment so let's go ahead and pull this
out first before I share that thought
with you so let's say okay we've got
empties overlap we want to do here is
pass in the two entities so we have a
and entity and test entity right and
maybe I'll upgrade the Naaman clay Chur
of this a little bit as well so we'll
call this results equals false and we'll
just do this result salt result and then
return results right oops sim region
overlapped this will now just be if
entities overlap and it'll pass the two
entities in so and again this is classic
compression oriented programming here
right I'm just looking at things pulling
them out when I new I want to use the
multiple times and letting that guide
the design of of everything right I'm
not thinking about the design at all I'm
letting literally the reuse what I want
to call at any given time drives that
sort of upward motion I really like that
style programming I find that it works
really well even early in the morning
like this so now this is much simpler
and easier to read as well we can even
sort of double this up we can we can
almost just say this right like so and
and that makes this loop really nice and
pretty simple we now handle multi
volumes so that's pretty good and I
don't know what we want to talk what
do about this will still leave that
other to do for a little bit later on so
this looks pretty good here what I was
going to say is I wonder if what we want
to do is move our epsilon into here so
we can say that there is an epsilon
basically a enlargement region if you
will in terms of testing whether these
overlap and I feel like we could even
say that there was an epsilon in all
three dimensions I know it's a little
bit weird but this is just thought I was
having and so by default if you ask if
they overlap there is no Epsilon but
later we could make their b1 right and
it's really easy for us to do because
all we have to do is take one of the
volumes that we're using for the overlap
test and add the epsilon to it right and
that enlarges that guy but a little bit
which means that there's now some sort
of fudge in in the overlap there's a you
know at kind of an extra boundary there
right and the reason that I think that's
kind of interesting was because that
would allow us to do that sort of the
overlap to be a little bit forgiving in
those those ones those there's things
you're allowed to move through so that
we can do precise stopping on those
those room boundary guys we can do
precise stopping on them but we can also
figure out which one you're inside much
more easily and so I kind of like that
idea I'm gonna go ahead and stick with
that for now and so what we would do in
here now is we'd reenable this guy like
so and we can set this to basically
entities overlap and what we'll do there
is past entity and testin be like we're
doing four and assuming that the two
entities overlap then we we actually
will use that that Tmax
two to see what the furthest we can go
is inside that entity now what I wanted
to do here is again use that enlargement
region and so what I'll probably do is
say okay we have our overlap epsilon
right in fact I'll just say overlap
epsilon the overlap Epsilon
we'll be something fairly small for now
probably I don't know exactly what it
should be this is definitely something
we'll have to look at more detail later
but basically we'll just have you know
we could even do this you might want to
make a utility function for that you
know something that just spams one value
out to all of things in in a vector but
so you know all right that does the
overlap test go missing a parenthesis
that does the overlap test and allows us
to make this loop more practically we
loop properly in theory now oops I
really need a better typing setup here
I'm always find myself askew in the way
that I'm kind of crammed in here at this
desk all right
in theory now we could actually well no
that's not good at all we never seem to
be able to get past our Tmax what's
wrong all right so now it's time to
debug this I was hoping that might just
work
but of course it never does so let's
take a look at what's going on here just
spot-check before we go debug this make
sure we didn't do anything obviously
stupid so when we're doing our t max
test we need to set our t max test to
zero we assume that that's the minimum
you could possibly move in fact these I
guess are technically T max test 2 min
test these these don't really need to be
out here and neither does hit this right
those are actually these are actually
internal things so these are actually
these are actually like here right and
down here so and this one doesn't have a
T max test and this one doesn't have a
team in
right so yeah in fact and I'm gonna move
over here to this this side so that my
head is not constantly in the way so
when we come through here
and we do these tests we're testing to
see we're accepting the largest value it
looks like which is which is what we
wanted so I'm not sure what the problem
is exactly here it could be that our
entities overlap call is not working
properly I guess we do have another
thing that's kind of stupid which is
that you know we actually probably since
we're already looping over the two
volumes that loop those volume loops are
really set up wrong now that I think
about it right we don't actually need to
loop over we don't actually need to loop
over the volumes
so justjust thinking this through right
so up at the top here and in fact I
guess this can collide is exactly
probably why we're not getting in here
so I didn't really think this through
enough as I need to basically this can
collide is really something to be done
as an internal check and furthermore the
entities overlap check doesn't need to
be done per volume like this right the
enemies overlap check can be done once
for the entities up at the top and so
really this this loop this can be done
all the way out here right that's this
is actually being done up here so let's
let's reorganize this a little bit
that's being done up there and this part
right here looks a little bit more like
it's it's it's its partner there and
similarly this can collide right is is
part of this check here too right
so essentially what we need to do is out
at the top here we need to do that
determination of whether or not this is
something worth considering and then
traversable tells us which one we're
going to do on it so in some sense we
have something that's sort of like if
it's traversable and the entities
overlap right then that's one reason we
might do it or if you can collide right
and so I think the test we actually want
to do is out of the top here we want to
say if it's a traversable entity right
and the entities overlap then we would
do our collision processing or if there
are things that can collide with each
other then we would do our collision
processing and those are the two reasons
that we might start checking the volumes
right but otherwise we wouldn't do that
and I we got to do our our epsilon up
here right so that is really the loop
that we wanted I think or at least
closer to it and then the rest of this
stuff does what it does
right that seems a little more same to
me so let's take a look and now we're
actually working a little more properly
we're but we we don't really have any
places right now that we can test
against our blue line so I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna go back here to our our thing
that creates the world right
here's handmade that's EPP and when we
do add wall I'm just gonna go ahead and
say that we're just not gonna add walls
we're not gonna add walls two rooms past
the first room right so basically if we
have screen index here I'm just gonna
get rid of those walls everywhere else
so I'm going to do if screen index
equals 0 we add walls otherwise we don't
add any walls and so that means that we
should have a world that pretty much
only has those walls at the beginning
right so there's the walls and we are
colliding with them that's good we're
colliding with all the other people here
and so on and then we kind of walk up
here and now we're in a place that
doesn't have any walls right and so
we're walking around and so let's make
sure that we can't go outside of our
blue line and we can't which is what we
wanted that's a good thing it looks
pretty solid at the moment although we
do have there's some stickiness that I
don't like I'm not sure why we're
getting and that feels like we're we're
able to do some things I don't think we
should be able to do so yeah we're
getting some stickiness there right
we're sticking and I believe that
sticking is probably because of the way
that we're doing that epsilon handling
we're not we're because world you're
allowed to go because we're not setting
you inset from this guy from from the
space in the epsilon our sliding stuff
is a little bit more broken let's verify
that that's actually the case and we'll
have to think about how we want to
handle that we still we really don't
want those epsilon in there anyway so
you know that's something that's
definitely on my radar of stuff that we
want to clean up but I don't have a
really good idea of how we want to do it
yet so that's gonna have to be something
we set aside some time to think it
through and do something nice with it
but basically it's this part right here
you know where we basically want to say
this this exact thing that you're saying
for we would still need to do it for the
other side and now you know we get that
sliding which is what we want so you
know I would sense it her this a bit of
a success I think this came out
relatively well it's doing what we want
it to do which is preventing you from
ever getting outside and I like that and
so that's a good start that's a pretty
good start
I think now I'm not sure why we're why
we're stopping in here though that's a
bit odd I wonder if that's just because
what is that T Epsilon the T epsilon is
the same as our o is the same as our
overlap epsilon which is not what we
would want right we'd have to make those
be different in order for this to work
for you to be able to cross through
these properly right well I'm not sure
why it seems odd right I'm not sure why
we can't cross over that boundary that's
definitely a bit janky because I can go
through that boundary I can go through
that boundary in one direction but not
the other direction all right so we
definitely have some bug miss they're
something they'll have to think through
take the stairs
this is stairwell is a stairwell up or
down stairwell down
so yeah so why can we not that's
interesting it's the same we can't go
backwards I wonder if that's just an
order dependency thing too so if we have
a bug and it's just the order in which
these two things were added you can go
from an earlier entity to a later entity
but not vice versa you know what I mean
not sure why that would be though
because since we're taking the maximum
hit is it just an over is it because is
there something weird about the way this
overlap works like you would think we
must just have a simple bug actually
because you would think especially if so
we're in the situation should wrap repro
right here right yeah you would think
that if I made the overlap test very
permissive so I said like oh yeah the
overlap epsilon is massive
right that now we would definitely be
able to pass through there because it
should find that we are enclosed in that
other guy and his team axe should be
very large so the question is with that
overlap epsilon very large why is it not
possible to find a larger team axe there
and I don't know the answer to that
question it's very strange
right and so when we come in here and
we're looking through these walls we
find whatever our team axe test is is
later is less than whatever the result
is for this particular wall we then
accept it yeah I don't know that that
doesn't seem that doesn't seem logical
to me
so I guess what we need to do is is step
through this and see what's going on
here because I don't have it and maybe
it's just the early morning stream maybe
it should actually be obvious what's
going on and I'm just not seeing it that
seems like probably a pretty likely
thing for a sleepy time
for sleepy time programming and we've
got about seven minutes left so I think
we've got some time to step through here
and see what's going on so let's take a
look at pushing forwards through there
so I'm gonna go ahead and do this team
axe test let's see what our what's our
yeah so I don't know if this would be
the best test because of course I think
our team in and Tmax might already be
small but I'm not sure about that yeah
okay so anyway we have our team in in
our team max we're coming through here
to test these wall normals this is
somebody that we're already inside and
so let's take a look what is our T
result equal to ok our T result is
massive which is fine so we accept it
and our t max test is very large we
don't have any other collisions with
that and so that's fine we accept that
as our new t max and off we go and we've
we've set our hit entity rank we come
through here is that the only one we're
going to know we're gonna test against
another one so that's good off we go so
now we're testing against a separate one
it's resetting a t max tested zero again
and now we find a much closer hit so in
theory that will get accepted as T max
test now right but we should ignore that
hit I would think oh no oh yeah that's
it right there
this has to get initialized to what our
current max is that was dumb yeah so
that's the problem right we weren't
initializing it to the best one we'd
found so far so it just happened to be
whichever one was next yeah so then
those are fine and I'm not sure if we
really need to have that permissive
overlap test anymore but let's double
check and see I'm just curious yeah so
that passes through properly now and
still stops in the boundary so that
seems pretty good but you know
it's still a little janky certainly to
say the least
but we're definitely getting there all
right so that's pretty good
and so these now serve as boundaries
properly and so the next thing that we
we will want to do and I don't think I
want to start this today this will be
next week's thing is to actually start
playing with Z levels now because now we
can go ahead and do our sort of testing
against these to drop us down to
wherever the floor would be and that's
pretty you know that's gonna be a pretty
significant code change as well and so
now that we've got this working for the
most part I think we want to kind of
stop and go ahead and and move into the
Q&amp;A so that's pretty good I think we
made pretty good progress there yeah so
so let's do that let's go ahead and and
do the QA yeah what's our what's our
situation here so it looks like this I
think is already handled this we need to
play around X tweak and these two were
pretty we're on the we're on the edge of
solving these two so I think we we might
if we're really lucky we might be able
to knock off this entire thing next week
although next week might have to be
short cuz I do have a business trip
Monday and Tuesday that may make it so
it's hard for me to stream on those two
days so maybe not so it might take us to
them to the next week because we we're
gonna lose some days but we're getting
pretty good on this right so that's
pretty good yeah I feel like like debug
code is a real easy one this is gonna be
pretty trivial if it's pretty rope so
there won't be a lot of fussing there's
a bunch of code to write but it's pretty
pretty trivial this one is as well so
these will be pretty easy ones so we
won't probably get to the the next hard
stuff will be will be coming through
here so we're based gonna have to -
pretty easy guys
here and here yeah so I wonder if we
want to do if we want to sort of break
this up a little bit I guess we'll see
what we feel like doing it since debug
codes gonna be kind of fast one you know
maybe we want to do something more like
that where we do like this because this
is a little more interesting and
involved in the topic and then do audio
then come out to metagame and then and
then kick it through yeah seems seems
reasonable I'm excited about this so
many good things to do so yeah we're
really pushing through the hardest stuff
is really front loaded collision
detection that's gonna be probably one
of the nastiest things that we're
dealing with so yeah yeah this will be a
good block to get done this is the this
is a really hard block easy block this
actually block isn't that hard either
but it's stuff that people do weirdly so
it'll be something they'll have to kind
of cover like here's why you do it this
way and this has some nice benefits or
whatever and then yeah audio is pretty
pretty trivial as well so yeah alright
queue at any time let's let's go ahead
and do some Q&amp;A
can you explain the length of array
macro and the size of pointers so we've
we've this seems to come up a lot and so
I feel like this is something that's
unusual for people or III guess I don't
know like it just feels like some people
have trouble with these they're like
maybe they're not things that they're
used to seeing and so you know maybe
like let's let's explain this like very
slowly and and be very clear about
what's going on just so everyone is sort
of on board with with it a little more
cleanly so the idea here is that in
--see oftentimes I find myself wanting
to define an array right and so you can
see that I do that sometimes here right
where for whatever reason it might only
be temporary or it might be permanent
depending on what I'm doing I wanted to
find array of things and like in the
case of map mouse buttons if we only
know that there's always five button
mice and we're never gonna handle more
of them it'd be stupid for us to go
ahead and make some kind of flexible
sized array and incur the overhead that
that implies when we could just compile
the code to know exactly how many mouse
buttons there were right so I find
myself oftentimes wanting to make arrays
that are of a fixed size but I don't
really want to write the code to assume
that fixed size baked into it I would
rather have the compiler do that so that
if I do in the future decide that I want
to change it for some reason it doesn't
necessarily have to change at runtime
but it might have to change a compile
time so I defined the array to be
whatever size it is that I want to write
the code being able to use that number
now one way to do that is to use a pound
defying for whatever the number is but
the problem is that can break right if I
pound to find something and then later I
change I use a accidentally used the
wrong pound to find in the code or
something or I change which one is being
used for the array size now the code
that was based on that pound of fine is
mismatched with the array so what I'd
rather do is be able to look at the code
and know that it's actually using the
size of the thing that's actually
talking about and so
that's why I used this array account
macro which allows me to pass the array
that I'm working with and directly
compute its size without having to rely
on some kind of pound to find so it
doesn't matter how the person define the
array this will compute it and so how
does this macro work well in C there is
this concept of the size of sort of it's
a compile time directive really it's not
actually a function it looks like a
function but doesn't call anything what
it is is it's a question to the compiler
that says I'm going to pass you a value
and what I want you to do is instead of
looking at the actual value what's in
the value instead of what's contained in
this name like you would normally do
with the variable like if I say foo
normally you know if I say int foo
normally I'm talking about what's
contained in the int when I say food to
the compiler in this case don't think
about what it stores think about how big
it is how big do you think int foo is
and it replaces that this when you ask
that with that size in bytes so when I
say sizeof int foo I get back
four right on a thing where integers are
four bytes long such as our platform
right now now I can pass more
complicated things to it so if I have an
array like int foo five when I ask for
the size of that it will actually tell
me five times the size of an integer
which is four or 20 so I can ask for the
entire size of an array and get it back
the problem is that doesn't tell me how
many elements are in the array it tells
me how big the total array is so if I
want to know how many elements are
actually in the array I need to know how
big the elements of the array are and
divide by that number right so in this
case I'm gonna say size of food it's
gonna give me back 20 if I know that an
integer is 4 bytes long if I divide by 4
I get back the original 5 that's the
number that I actually wanted and so
what this second sizeof does is it says
what is the size of the first element of
that array because that's how big every
element is going to be the elements
can't be different sizes and so by
writing the macro this way it allows you
to take the name
of an array and produce its count
directly by just looking at the total
size of the array divided by the size of
its first element that gives me how many
elements there are right now the reason
that I can't call that directly for the
thing that I believe the person was
talking about here the reason that I
can't call that directly on this is
because C doesn't have a way for you to
basically do this right there's no way
to say how big is this how big is this
array in some other type right now you
can do that now by using a deckle valve
which we mentioned the other day that's
a brand new feature that got implemented
or whatever so I still use the
old-school way because it would work it
works everywhere and doesn't require a
new feature so no sense needing to use
the new feature you don't have to in
some sense so since you can't do this
what you do is you pretend that you
would have an actual value because size
of needs to pass values you can't give
it types you can't give it members right
if that makes sense
so if you say size of you can't pass it
the member of a struct you could pass it
a type just like int and you could say
you could pass a type like game input
and how big that is but you can't ask
hoops you can't ask for just one member
now why I have no idea it makes no sense
to me that you can't do that but you
can't so since you can't actually do
that what I'm doing here is pretending
that I have a pointer to something and
asking how big the controllers things
would have been off of that pointer
because we know we can always say like
size of some value that I might have
like camera P in this case right I know
that I could say if I had a world
position camera key I could ask for what
the size of that was so what I'm doing
is saying pretend I just have a value
which you know in I don't have an actual
pointer to a game instructor but I can
cast zero to it for free right pretend I
have that how big would it be since
see will never actually evaluate this
instruction it's never this expression
it's never gonna evaluate the actual
value of the expression so I don't have
to worry about dereferencing the null
pointer because it's never gonna look at
the value it's just gonna look at the
type because what size-up does is it
says what is the type of the thing on
the inside so since this only needs to
look at the type it says okay well
what's the type of a player to a game
input and looking off that adds
controllers member what's the type of
that right it's gonna go look and say oh
well I know what the type of that is
right the type of that is I'm gonna go
look up at the struct game input right
I'm gonna look here I moved four
controllers I'm gonna see what the type
of that is game controller input okay
that's the type so it will never
actually be reference that null pointer
it's strictly constructing a synthetic
value that has the right type because
that's what C allows you to do right and
C++ it up until very recently so that's
you know that's how that works I don't
know why I've still got changes here
undo undo undo back to the beginning
please
there yeah all right so that's all
that's going on there hopefully that
makes some sense
well the space enemies be used for the
collision optimization you were talking
about in an earlier stream
oh and squared stuff probably not
they aren't super suited to that because
they're more about defining the
locations of things so we could choose
to do that but if we did would probably
break those up more and that's not a bad
idea
like the way like the way that we would
the way that we could envision the
structure of the world is we could start
thinking about instead of having those
spatial things be entities they could be
sort of a superstructure that gets
divided up and is used as a spatial
partition we could go that route so I
don't know but we probably wouldn't use
them if we did go that route they
wouldn't be entities anymore they'd be a
special-purpose kind of structure I
think but that's totally fine and
someone's saying the size of game and
put controllers works for you with G+
that may be because that's a valid
extension in in G + + G + + has
extensions it should have been something
that they allow and see but of course
you can't actually do it in regular C++
right you know I'm saying so that's just
the way it goes but G but good news C++
has extensions and some of those
tensions are good that would be a good
one I think that should have worked
right I think that should have been how
how sighs have worked it just
unfortunately doesn't
I noticed that you tend to mostly skip
over questions past the first question
mark is it because you just parsed that
way or the rest tends to not be much
interesting well I see the whole
question well Mike what my parser does
is it pulls out the question the the the
IRC line from Q : through to the end of
the line so that means that as long as
the question fits in one ir c comment i
see the whole thing if it's too long i
won't see the second part so that
sometimes happens but in general no i
read the whole question and then just
answer the part that I think is
interesting the answer but sometimes I
also just forget to look back in answer
the second part if the question if my
answer kind of goes kind of long I might
just forget so it could just mean me
being forgetful I may have seen it and
then forgot but yeah for things like the
projectiles are we going to extend their
bounding boxes in the z-axis so they
will always hit enemies that are below
them or are we going to handle that in
screen space somehow so I think that'll
depend on whether we want bullets you
know style things to be able to fly over
or under entities like you know I'm not
sure is the answer to that that'll be a
gameplay concern when we actually are in
there playing it a little more and
seeing what we like about that so yeah
and I should add speaking of that I
should add a note to fix that bug we
have with projectiles fix swerved
collisions so when we're cleaning up our
predicate sigh suspect our predicates
are step wrong now and the predicates
are kind of a mess right now so when we
go to do that clean up I'd like to fix
the swords as well
do you dislike templates yes I do
just like templates and I've talked
about that skill times before really the
short answer so I don't have to rehash
it again is just I don't like templates
because I really like meta programming
and I feel like templates are so bad at
it that I just get frustrated if I ever
try to use them I'm like these are awful
like everything you might want to do is
done in the worst possible way you know
and so I probably wouldn't be so angry
at templates if it weren't for the fact
that I actually really like meta
programming and I'm like seriously guys
this is the way you did it
so it really just gets me angry because
I'm like okay it's clear that whoever
made templates has no idea how to matte
a program like they were just like
they'd never done it before they don't
understand it they were thinking of it
from a very abstract you know not I
don't you know not not the perspective
of someone who ships software using meta
programming they were coming in from at
from some weird like language design
thing where which is never a good place
to start and so I just get frustrated
and angry and I'm like ah and so I don't
use them anymore
pretty much at all because of that
how will you handle something like an
explosion that affects all things in an
area then it's not one entity colliding
with another no it is right basically
every time that you handle something
there's no such thing in computers as
something affecting a bunch of things
simultaneously you can only operate on
two variables at once that's just the
nature of a CPU basically right and so
what ends up happening is even if you
have the concept of an entity that's
affecting lots of entities it's still
doing it piecewise so if you do an
explosion that's affecting a bunch of
entities you're still looping through
each of the entities and having them
collide and so you know it would be the
same way that it works right now where
you loop over all of the things that the
explosion touches and update them
individually right and as for the person
who's asking about what I think about
the Vulcan API again there's I've
already answered that on a previous
stream and the not to rehash it again
the very short answer is they haven't
released the API so I can't actually
discuss it in any detail because I
haven't had the opportunity to see its
actual design once I have the API in
front of me and I'm able to evaluate it
I will be able to give a better opinion
about it
but until then it's nothing really you
can say
so looks like we're at the end looks
like we're at the end of the questions
which is good because it's right about
the end of the stream - all right well I
guess I will wrap things up then let's
go ahead and close down good thing here
maybe save our mischief I think I forgot
to do that the other day and so I like
it so the mischief file ends up in the
handmade misc directory it's blackboard
art and so I try to save that
periodically so that when people
download the source code they can open
up the drawings file if they want to
that's the that's the thought anyway so
yeah all right let's go ahead and end
the stream that brings us to the end of
another episode of handmade hero thank
you very much for joining me this this
morning even if it was a bit of a sleepy
morning we did some reasonable coding it
worked out okay so thank you very much
for joining me for the pleasure of
coding with you as always even if we are
a little bit sleepy if you would like to
follow along at home obviously like I
say you can pre-order the game on
handmade hero org and it comes with the
source code so even now before we've
really done much of the game you can
start playing around with it yourself
and learning from the source code
playing around that making your own
experiments in there and changing things
and see how it works that's a pretty
good way to variable things so if you
pre-order the game you get that and it's
updated every night after I'm done
coding so you can follow along with
stuff literally as I do it if you'd like
to we also have a patreon if you want to
support the video series you can always
subscribe to that very much appreciated
we also have a news and forum site
that's got a bunch of information from
the community about handmade hero it's
got ports to Mac and Linux got a great
annotated episode guide I highly
recommend checking out just a lot of
good stuff on there so if you're trying
to learn for the series that's
definitely the place to go we also have
a tweet bot that tweets the schedule to
you newly freshly updated so that it's
even daylight savings time aware ladies
and gentlemen that's how how fancy it is
it changes between PST and PDT
you know no y2k bugs here man so yeah if
you want to know when the streams gonna
be and you want to know in advance every
day what time the streams gonna air and
also on the weekends it post schedule
for the coming week so on that sort of
stuff
that's the place to check it out and you
can also follow that bots on Twitter if
you want to have it sort of integrate
into your feed so that's it everyone I
think speaking of the schedule I think I
may have to to do only three days next
week it may be just Wednesday Thursday
Friday because I will be out of town
potentially Monday Tuesday depending on
how the business trip falls out so yeah
I I would say definitely double-check
that schedule and and take a look at the
tweet bot Sunday to figure out when the
streams gonna be if you want to catch it
because the first stream may actually be
Wednesday next week that'll probably the
end of the bit of the traveling again I
traveled last week and I got to travel a
little bit more this week but after that
should be pretty clear sailing for a
while and we should be back to being
able to do five streams a week no no
problem although people often are very
happy when I take a day off because they
like to catch up so you'll have two more
days potentially next week to catch up
but then after that probably not for a
little while so anyway keep an eye on
that and I think probably I will see you
next on Wednesday so so until then have
a great weekend and I will see you next
week