hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here on the show Rico to complete game
live on stream today we are back last
weekend
kind of took the weekend off we had only
one stream last weekend and because John
blow was trolling us with dota things on
the chat we decided to make a dota hero
generator which actually you can now see
running I cut and paste a result from it
every day I got a hook it up I'm gonna
hook it up to a tweet bot but if you're
interested we've got it it's here and
you can see that it's created some
pretty high quality it's created some
pretty high quality heroes for us with
some pretty great spells a croc with
shrapnel for example always great really
helps with the with your micro I guess I
would say proximity crush really really
powerful for teamfights I think if I'm
not mistaken and then who could of
course forget lumira one of the most
interesting heroes our latest hero with
such wondrous abilities as walrus
bringer bear of the demonic restoration
and of course cursed bolt ransack
chemical dream also I don't know if he
just kind of trips out or something
point being that is what we did last
weekend so we didn't really do any work
I mean unless you count that as work so
this weekend we're back doing what we're
supposed to be doing which is finishing
the lighting for our game system and
we're gonna go ahead and get right into
that today we more or less finished the
part we were working on the weekend
prior and we were ready to move on to
the next part and that next part is
exactly what we want to do today and
specifically what we were doing was
fixing the light distribution and so
what we want to be able to do now is
start to actually do the plumbing to get
our probes into the system draw their
results so we can see whether they're
actually convecting light properly and
that's pretty much all we really want to
do this weekend once we've gotten that
then we can flip over to the GPU side of
things
and worry about how we're actually going
to sample these things at runtime to
light our entities in the world so if I
go ahead and open up our lighting system
again remember we did the the sort of
basic work that we needed to do to just
see that these light probes are you know
happening at all right so if we run our
game you can see this running this is in
debug mode here so it's a little bit
slow framerate wise but you can see that
as I spin around there's these sort of
purple floating points and those purple
floating points are just the places
where we've sort of provisionally have
the level generator stick lighting
probes so you can see at the moment we
don't stick any lighting probes out in
the filler apron regions we do put
lighting probes on the interior and we
put two per tile this is probably
overkill and we probably don't need to
or even want to distribute them this way
and also we probably want to scatter
some light probes out in the outer area
as well although probably not many
because we don't really want to spend a
lot of time computing lighting in the
apron since it's just supposed to be
like a dark inaccessible area outside
the sort of region the player hops
around in anyway so that's what we're
working on right now and so what I'd
like to shoot for as our next goal in
life is embedding is very complicated I
say this very often letting is very
complicated and so as a result you want
to typically break it into pieces that
you can sort of independently verify or
at least nominally working if not bug
free and so that you don't spend your
time trying to figure out where the
problem is let alone what the problem is
when you have a bug so what I want to do
is I want to get us to a point where
we're not
there's no GPU involvement whatsoever
other than just drawing our debug
information and I want to be able to
compute these light probes the colors of
these light probes on the the various
sides of the cube and play around with
that until I can look at it here and
sort of at least be able to argue with a
straight face
that the lighting on the probe debug
markers looks like some lighting you
would actually expect from the placement
of the lights in the world and the
occluders right and the reason I want to
do that is because until I can see that
that looks okay there's no real point in
working on the GPU thing that samples
them because we would have no idea if we
then just get bad results we have no
idea who's at fault is it the sampler
that's at fault or is it the lighting
propagation that's a fault is it the
bookkeeping that's a fault right and so
we're trying to slice this problem up
into chunks because the smaller we can
make those chunks the easier real time
we will have debugging because there's
just less things we have to consider
right and so you know that's just kind
of the case with things like lighting
where we don't have easy ways to like
test it or you know right can't really
it's very hard to write like a unit test
for things like lighting I mean the
Cornell box is like the best thing we've
got so far two piece unit test for
lighting right it's very hard for
something that's an approximate artistic
only solution we know we're not really
simulating lighting the way it works in
the real world that's way too expensive
for a modern computer to contemplate in
real time and so what we're trying to do
here is just say look because this is an
artistic process we will know visually
whether it looks like a usable lighting
solution let's try to figure out ways to
bucket that up into ones we can visually
verify and then after we're done with
that we can progress to the next stage
having some confidence that the bugs in
the previous stage at least aren't
producing any things that will confound
us right okay so what we need to do now
is start to work through the plumbing of
this system and there's a couple aspects
of this that we need to do first of all
we need to actually build our table of
light probes if I'm not mistaken right
now we we don't really have a way to do
that we do know that there are light
probes in our system we are ready to
build a set of light
probes for the lighting system to work
with but to the best of my knowledge we
never actually did any code that
actually puts that light probe table to
use we just have entities that draw
themselves as those little purple
markers that are like these are the
light probes and then we have a light
probe system in the lining that will
iterate over them and try to move light
around with them but we don't actually
plug those together so we need to do
that we also need to actually call the
function that inserts these probes into
the spatial index I don't think we did
that right I think we wrote some code
that does it but we don't actually have
anybody use it yet right and then third
we're gonna have to build some of these
additional support structures so for
example we've got lighting samples right
like this sample table of 16 light
directions that we're using for lighting
although actually I thought that was
this so I'm not sure what this is right
now maybe it glows after this I don't
really remember it doesn't matter
point being we need to go back to the
code that generates the directions to
sample lighting wise and we need that to
remember for each individual lighting
direction which of the light directions
corresponds which of those sample lines
corresponds to which directional
contribution for a probe and at the
moment unfortunately for us we don't
really again we don't really know how we
want to keep this lighting information
stored right it's entirely possible that
we would like to store it in some way
other than 6 light 6 rough light
directions you know what I mean
and if you look for example the paper
that I mentioned the other day which
I'll be honest I don't really I don't
really remember where was here it is I
guess I do remember where was so if we
take a look at like the the paper that I
mentioned the other day that was talking
about light probes and again light
probes are very common thing they aren't
invented by this paper they are like old
right just in terms of giving you some
information about how these things work
when they're used in sort of 3d triple-a
sorts of games and so on you can see
here where we're talking about spherical
irradiance the question is how do you
store these things and in terms of how
they store them I'm not sure let's see
spiracle distributions at the street
clothes would be combined blah blah blah
blah let's see we encode straight
irradiance in eleven eleven ten at 8x8
octahedral resolution so they basically
use a little 8x8 square that I assume
just source the color so I mean it looks
like them and just from looking at it it
looks like they're doing roughly what
we're doing just a little better right
or more more detail right we're just
using six samples they're using 64 right
and that's understandable because
they're trying to eat up GPU power right
I mean they're trying to make the best
lighting they can and I want to say
these guys are in video rights
yeah well okay not just Nvidia but at
least half Nvidia so they're trying to
you know get as much power out of this
as they can and so they're probably
doing you know a lot more than what we
would necessarily want to do they're
also targeting the
latest stuff as much as possible right
um so there but it looks like they're
doing exact what we're doing so maybe
that's fine but I just wanted to give
you some perspective on what some people
are otherwise doing a spherical basis
function the circle harmonics for
example there's just there's just a lot
of ways we could store it that's all I
wanted to say and so I don't know if the
way that we're picking is the smartest
way for us it's hard to say and when we
go to do sampling you know we may find
that it's too expensive to sample or
it's too expensive the store or whatever
and we might want to adjust that method
so instead of using the six faces of a
cube maybe we want to do something
smarter or maybe there's some way we
could do something you know that that's
going to be a quicker to sample in store
so that's all I wanted to keep you aware
of but at the moment we're gonna do it
that way just because it's something
simple and we can visualize it easy we
can write something that just draws
different colors on the side of a cube
for example and that would give us the
information that we need for determining
whether our lighting seems to be working
at all or not so what I want to do now
is just start on that process which is
gonna be kind of slow but we're gonna go
ahead and just take it slow and the
first problem that I think I would see
here one of the things that I don't
super like if you look at how these
light probes are stored we've got sort
of a six wide piece of color information
here and what I don't super love about
it is if you go look at how we actually
use our hits right if we come in here
you can see us doing or our Ray
intersection and we then downshift a
scalar which we're doing primarily just
because we can't do memory lookups and
Simbi it's really the the sort of bane
of the pre a V X 512 instruction set
it just wasn't well designed for this
part of the of the process unfortunately
I that's neither here nor there but
point being when we have to downshift
here you can see what we're doing we
take four rays at a time
right and we break them up into their
individual single rays and then we do
our lookups right we just try to figure
out you know where we're going to how
this transfer PPS is going to work and
you can see it accumulating that PPS in
here and that this right here is the
part the sample point durand X that
point right there is just the thing that
lets us know which one of these samples
it should be added into now the thing
that I think we want to look at though
is that when we sample a particular
direction sometimes those directions are
going to be kind of they're going to be
shooting out towards the corners of the
cube right and one question I have and
I'm not sure like I'm not sure what the
right approach is is how do we actually
want to record sample directions we can
just sample into the face of the cube
that you left through but it might be
smarter for us to just average like when
we take let me just draw this out here
so you know what I'm talking about
so if we imagine we've got a cube right
and we sample some direction but that
direction like let's say we're starting
from the center here right and that
direction kind of goes off through like
almost a corner of the cube then the
question is like you know do we really
just want to attribute to one side if we
left directly through the middle of that
cube sure but if it's off here or here
or worse yet here how come we don't add
any into like these right and so another
way we could choose to have this work is
we could choose to like place this
information like distribute this
information out to the sides of the cube
as like a blending value right so we
could say that you know this one goes
you know 33% to this face 33% to this
face and 33% to this face right now the
reason that I find this sort of
confusing is because we are also then on
the back end going to blend their two
right so when we sample on the back end
and we say okay we have some lighting
information that we generated right so
we did all the sampling and then we
produced a single cube with a color per
face you know here's color zero or is
color one yours color two or something
right and then we shoot array for
sampling the light we're sitting we
don't shoot the Ray we were just gonna
sample this lighting from this cube if
we're going towards a corner we already
do a 33% C zero plus 33 percent C one
plus 33 percent C two right so we're
already doing that blend to produce the
result from those so we you know when we
go to look at the lighting in that
direction that's what we get and so the
question is what produces the best
result here from this process you know
and I really don't know you can see the
kind of problem that you get
potentially with not blending if you
just use equal weighting as you kind of
shoot out through this cube then the
problem is as you get towards the the
end you're causing light that may be
coming from over here to contribute just
as highly to a sample direction that may
be over here right and if I was to sort
of draw this in 2d so it's easier for
you to see what I'm talking about let's
suppose that we have a light probe right
and here is one side of the light primp
so here's my light probe and here's one
side of it I'm looking out this way at
the very edge of this thing right and
also out the middle I'm sampling these
rays and I get some results so maybe
there's a red light here there's a green
light here and there's a blue light here
right well what I would like to do in
the future when I then have a surface in
this area and it's pointing this way and
I want a sample what's the lighting here
well ideally the best result would be
for me to get heavily blue right like
mostly blue light and not a lot of red
light from that right and so if we
assume that this side is sort of also
hitting the blue a little bit right
because this blue lights over here
somewhere this is gonna be blue but this
is gonna be roughly white right so I'm
gonna blend a lot of white in here for
that a 50% white 50% blue for this
sample even though what I really wanted
was mostly blue right now I don't know
that there's that much we can really do
to fix that but again if these things
were weighted then this would get added
a lot less in there so it would be
mostly green and blue that would be
added to this face and this face right
and so when you sample that direction
you get more of it and there being less
light contribution from our because that
would be mostly added here right so this
would be more B this would be more R
this would be more G which is probably
more what we want so I really again
I just don't really know what we want to
do there but just from looking at it it
kind of seems to me like we would rather
have a blended a blended gather as well
as a blended sample just personally so
it kind of seems like this process wants
to look a little bit different you know
it probably wants to look kind of more
like this and each one of these things
maybe this accumulated PPS as we
accumulate in here some kind of a
transfer we would want to accumulate the
way to normalize like we used to and
just wait each one of these by some kind
of pre computed probe contribution so
remember we know like those directions
if these things are going out in and
when we store those rays sample
directions what we would do is store how
they get accumulated back in so like
each of these things right would be that
way uh that just seems better right to
me
and I just think that's probably what
you would want to do so you know looking
at this we would sort of say all right
there's going to be an accumulated PPS
it's going to be something like this
right so you're gonna grab that out
there and then you're going to do
something like this just so we build
that base pointer once and then we
access it off of here right and that way
now we have each of these sort of PPS
ones it's kind of off of the base one
and then we just need weighting values
for these and we're going to need to
remember how much weight we did because
now we do need to sort of renormalize
those values possibly to be honest
though I'm not super sure how much we
really need to do in terms of
renormalization it feels sort of like
that's unnecessary because you know
we're just taking the incoming light and
so if we just always multiply by the Ray
weight it should generally speaking just
average out over time you would think
maybe that's not true but it feels like
it's an unnecessary step to accumulate
the weighting on these things so I might
just say let's see if we can skip it
so I'm just gonna say that because I'm
just not sure and we kind of have to
look at it a little bit more detail but
anyway assuming that we are going to do
something roughly like this what we need
now is a contribution sample value and
so back here where we had sample point
dur index what I actually want there is
just a blending value right so I really
just want something that looks like this
so for each sample point in the set I
have like how it should be blended in
and when you look at these you can see
it looks like we've got sort of sets of
these guys and so what I kind of want to
do is just say the sample like this
should sort of be its own bundle
probably so there should be something
here like a lighting sample light
sampling sphere something like that
right and then these things here where
we have these sample ray bits here we'll
just call these sampling spheres and
we'll make as many of these as we want
so okay you know we do 16 or whatever
and that's fine
and so these are actually just 18 and 6
right I'm sorry
18 18 6 right so for each of these we
have for our sample point in its really
sampled direction and that's this right
here for our sample direction that we're
heading out in we have our like
contribute are like cubed side weight
right
and so for each one of these we want to
go ahead and use the correct
corresponding weight as we go so we're
just like looking up which weight we
need to use here to blend this thing in
and off we go so that's how we would
update and to get the cube side weight
there we just need to go like okay the
cube size cube side weight just equals
whatever our sampling spheres cube side
weight was right and so now we can look
in here where we're sort of doing these
lookups like this we can make this be
based on the sample sphere now which is
better right so now what we do is say
all right when we would normally go to
get this der sample index nonsense here
which you know is the probe index this
this crap here this as you can see light
probe index plus sample point entropy
the sample point entropy is like a fixed
value up here right so the light probe
index plus the sample probe entropy
ANDed with a sample pattern mask is
actually something we can just have out
here if I'm not mistaken right because
nothing in here actually ever alters any
of that so what we want to do is each
time through once we compute whatever
this Dorris ample index lookup value is
that's what we want to go get our
sampling sphere right so that's where we
want to go like okay
sampling sphere spheres plus der sample
index is going to be our light sampling
sphere and so we're just picking which
one of these spheres we're going to use
for sampling and we can generate as many
as them as we think we need to ensure a
fairly random coverage but off we go so
once we have one of those sampling
Spears you can use it for everything so
here for example we would do sampling
sphere and then when we want to get like
our sample Direction we just use the Ray
index here and this ray count right we
need to make sure that we know
that our ray count is always not as bad
right as well actually can see it right
here so we just need our ray count to
always here be yeah so I mean here we
say look all right we've got our
sampling sphere we need our sampling
spheres sample direction that's gonna be
the ray count because that's how many
that we can pull out of that sampling
sphere and then we just send all those
rays down right so I think that's
roughly what we're talking about here
and these are constant so they should be
able to be optimized away by the
compiler into just constant computations
because they don't change their their
you know based on the structure size so
I think that's all we need to do there
and that you know gets us started with
that bit of sampling right now we have a
problem here obviously which is that
when we are actually generating these
sampling spheres we kind of had our
pattern generator here right and one of
the things that you could see about our
pattern generators is our pattern
generator is always generated only
hemispherical patterns and obviously we
don't want that so if you look here
where we've got our generator for 64 I
guess which I don't know why it would be
generating 64 of anything because we
don't have anything of that multiple
I'm not sure what the goal was here I
don't quite know why it looks like that
to be completely honest with you
but either way when you look at for
example for example our Plus on sampled
generator you can see here we're
generating random bilaterals right and
we are then looking to see whether or
not we have anything in the set that's
too close and off we go
and then you can see here like where we
are actually just you can even see us
here we're just using we're using sort
of a method where we generate stuff on
the disk and then we loft it up into Z
to generate a hemisphere right and again
I don't think we want to do this anymore
so I think what we want to do here is we
want to just generate points that are
randomly pointing in arbitrary
directions and then we want to we want
to just keep the entire sphere so I'm
gonna go ahead and look here this this
point where we loft them up just isn't
necessary right so I'm gonna go ahead
and start to cut these routines I don't
really care about these other pattern
generators here I don't think they're
actually being used anymore they were
just as when we were actually sort of
playing with our different options there
I don't think we care about this anymore
I mean I guess I could keep them but I'm
not going to bother well
it would be yeah you know what I'm not
gonna it's just it's just more work
Vince than it's worth so I'm gonna go
ahead and say look we're gonna get rid
of the lighting pattern generator stuff
and just simplify this code down because
I want the Poisson generator pretty much
period so we're just going to do this
and these folks are gonna go away
and then the generate Poisson samples
now is I think we can just use sort of a
regular sort of a regular thing where we
just generate samples in the cube will
normalize that so then we have a you
know some random direction we don't want
it to be zero zero zero so we probably
want to avoid having it be vats one way
to do that would probably be to say like
like this
so we'll just say alright we're gonna
keep trying to generate points assuming
that we've got one that's reasonable
we'll take P and we'll multiply it by
one over P squared to renormalize it
right so you know will normalize P this
way then we'll just check to see whether
or not it's it's valid here and off we
will go so well you know what we were
already doing that never mind
like I but I want to do this first so I
think we still yeah you know what I
think we still want this this way all
right
so valid we're just going to presume to
be true and then we're going to do our
test over the existing points to see
whether they meet the minimum distance
squared that we've set up this minimum
distance squared is probably going to
have to be adjusted but that's okay and
then we record our points in here for
ones that are valid and so that's good
enough for our plus on samples it's not
a good way to generate plots on samples
and we should probably put it to do in
here like the D okay see we could put a
much more efficient plus on noise
generator in here and probably should at
some point because this is like the
slowest possible way to do that we would
get rid of this we don't need any of
these anymore I'm not sure yeah that's
probably all just fine we don't need any
of this and then when we do our generate
lighting pattern stuff in here we can
just say we don't need any of this we
can just say all right
we need to generate multiple ones of
these obviously and so what we want to
do here is I don't know why yeah it
looks like we cuz we are generator just
works in regular values and then we copy
them out so what we want to do here is
say I don't know that we really need to
do bundling of race in some predictions
but maybe we do that would potentially
speed things up since we cast multiple
rays at a time if we always cast like
you know the Rays that go out one side
of the cube we probably could avoid we
could probably process things quicker
because we wouldn't have rays falling
out of the active set and stuff as soon
because they probably tend to hit
similar things at similar distances if
they go in the same direction most the
time so this to do should probably stay
but either way as we go through this
version index thing what we really need
to do here is just grab our sampling
sphere now
so this is getting whichever one we're
working on right now and then this code
stays basically the same so we come
through here and we basically build you
know this this desk up but what we don't
have yet is we want this cube side wait
here as we go through our direction
index right
we want our well interestingly if that's
gonna be 18 though I'm not sure how we
picked that but this generator here
needs to generate like enough to fill
this sampling set right just looking at
this so four times during Dex whatever
this sample Direction here is right
needs to ensure that this has enough of
it and at the moment it doesn't it
doesn't actually right because if it was
18 18 times four it's going to be more
than 64 which means it would require
more than what we've got in this array
for sampling so that seems like a bit of
an issue and I don't know exactly how we
want to do that you look at how the
point count works out here and I mean I
could just say but you do have a problem
which is like this value we don't know
what this should be like if you want to
insert you know 300 points then their
minimum distance has to be smaller than
if you were only going to insert 64
points right so that value we would have
to adjust as well
and again one thing we could do is we
could just spam that many points out
randomly onto the sphere and then use
some kind of iterative repulsion to like
push them to whatever their natural
distance is and that's totally fine too
and that might be something we want to
do because again we can pre-compute
all of these and furthermore I think
there's some other stuff that we
probably want to do here like probably
what we want to do since we know we're
iterating over these sample directions
is we probably want to produce a blue
noise pattern over the sphere that is
the complete set of blue noise samples
and then each one of our sampling
spheres that we take is a slice through
there that picks like the set of points
that would be in the remaining set and
that are all as far away from each other
as possible you know what I'm saying
so that basically we maximize on any
given frame on any given frame we are
always sending out a set of well
distributed rays but also across frames
we are also distributing so we're not
like casting in the same direction as we
cast it on the previous frame you and
I'm saying and as I'm saying all of this
it's making me just want to just do this
correctly the first time and so I think
I will I think that's exactly what I
want to do and so what I think I'm going
to do is just we're gonna make a little
a little generator I think is what I'd
like so like for example I'm going to go
into hand
made code and you know we have like our
little utilities and whatever so I'm
gonna make HH sphere dot CPP and we're
gonna just do this inside there and
we're just gonna generate these things
as a totally totally separate pass on
the system that you can then just like
load in and use right as as just like an
include file so what I want to do here
is like have a pound include that's
something like handmade sampling spheres
IML and that handmade sampling spheres
that INL would just be like the
directions that we've you know
effectively precomputed right and in
there furthermore what I would like is
actually I kind of want that to be put
like maybe right here even and so that
it's you know it's got the information
there but then that will define the rest
of our stuff so in light sampling sphere
here when we're talking about like how
many things there are and and all that
sort of stuff
maybe that that is actually that
information is actually encoded into
that I am L right so like this structure
here with the sample direction in the
cube side weight like maybe those are
just those are actually inside defined
inside handmade sampling spheres and
that way when we change how we build the
sampling spheres we thought this code
automatically adjusts how many rays it
thinks it needs or has or wants or
whatever else right and similarly in
here where we've got light sampling
sphere you know that maybe is just that
and then maybe there's a pound of fine
that's like you know
you know I'm saying to you and so then
that value whatever this value ends up
being can be generated as well and then
anyone in here who was doing in like an
array count on the sampling spheres here
is not going to do that anymore so can't
see anything cuz my head's in the way so
that for example this right here is
actually just going to be oops no that's
not that's not one I take it back
well there must be somebody because we
do there's that mod of it right huh in a
rate cast it should have done one I mean
not in recast right here it should done
one
so it's this right here
right and so that thing needs to needs
to be this alright so that's fine and
what we want to do now is have this
handmade sampling sphere is that INL we
want this to have this piece of
information in it
right that's what I wanted to do and so
we would have like a handmade sphere
thing it'll generate these out and those
will that'll be our sample table that we
use at run time for the sampling if I go
ahead and cut this out and actually make
one of these then we can just sort of
imagine what this should look like it
should have these two things in it it
should have one of these struts and then
it should have like the set of light
sample spheres so it should have
something like this
and so in here we've got our sample
directions and then we've got our cube
weights the sample directions we need 18
of them they're v3 for X's so they look
like this so that means we've got you
know three things of four things right
so we've got four wide X is 4 wide wise
4 wide Z's for the v3 if that makes
sense
and then we've got 18 of those right so
if we were to break this apart we'd want
18 of these and then inside here we
would have 18 by 6
right
and that would close off I think that's
all we really need and then we have that
many of those sampling spheres so I
think that's what I want and if we
contemplate having this I can now
because we've got one now right I can go
ahead and make this thing so I can go
ahead and fix my compile bugs and get it
actually compiling right and make sure
that that's all going to be fine
which I assume it is
so in the cube side wait for the
sampling sphere so the way that this is
indexed is each ray is shooting out one
of these things
so for each ray and then sub ray we have
to know what the weight is for that
thing right so in here we may we're
probably down yeah so this is not not
quite gonna cut it right so for each of
these things for every sample direction
that we have here so however many this
number is here we've got 18 sample
directions but they're four wide so
really we have four times 18 sample
directions which means that we need four
times 18 cube side wait right so you
need you need that right because for
every one of those that you grab you
need to actually grab four of them so in
here where you do like cube side wait
you would have to say all right the
sampling sphere we want to take the cube
side wait and we want to move it
forwards by four times the four times
the rate index plus the sub ray right to
get to the right one which way we're
talking about here and then we can use
the cube side wait from there which
isn't great right but I think that's
what we actually need and for the cube
side wait this doesn't have to be a plus
anymore I mean it's it's this we're
actually looking it up and getting back
an array of six so that's actually a a
dereference for pattern name we know
needs we're not gonna do that anymore we
just gonna generate these offline and
the generate lighting pattern call
doesn't really need to be there anymore
all we really need to do is say that our
sampling spheres just plugs into this
right because that and that's going to
be like something that we output from
our routine so I think that's what we
actually want to do and now I can go
create that sampling first lookup table
and what I'd like to do now is just have
a way of visualizing it so I can see
whether I think our sampling sirs are
any good so if we look here at our and
our startup what I want is show me the
show me the sampling sphere and we did
some code for this I don't know if it
still works because it's like old we had
sort of had some code that would just
draw the sampling sphere and I don't
actually know if that's still in here
anywhere right it might be it might not
be let me take a look
so if it wasn't here it would it would
be drawing the debug lines right and I
don't know if that's anywhere in here
this is so we we have things that draw
our debug lines and that's all fine but
we don't actually have we don't actually
have anything that outputs the debug
lines from our sample spheres so I guess
what I would say is we just need
something that will do that and
presumably that wouldn't be too hard as
far as whether the debug lines are on or
off we probably just need to hard code
that on for now so you know
yeah I think what I do here say look
let's turn debug lines on just
permanently for right now and then I'm
just gonna have something that pushes
those debug lines on there
in fact this looks like the code we want
right basically wait why is it doing a
push cube
I don't know what that codes still doing
in here
so this this actually looks a push line
segment it looks like we weren't using
debug lines it looks like we were just
using push line segments so it looks
like we do actually have the code that
we that we need here right I mean this
is all that code you can sort of see it
so I think we can just use it I think
this is exactly what we want right here
we don't need this stuff I'm not sure
why we have any of this is still in here
this this is not gonna ever be useful
for anyone yes so you can see both of
these here's one that draws them with
little cubes here's one that draws a
little line segments I don't know which
one we want but probably doesn't much
matter so in here I'm going to do point
index here we're gonna take one of these
lighting spheres we'll just take a look
at the first one at the moment but we
may want to wrap this in a four I loop
pretty soon we're then going to go here
and say alright let's make sure knows
that we're going to draw six of these
quads for however many total raise there
are while we're in here I'm gonna do
like sampling total rays per spear and
I'm just gonna say that we're gonna have
like pound two finds that so that we can
look up all of the information that we
want so in here we're gonna have like a
light sampling Rabin Dalls Perce fear
and total raise for serious this is
going to be 18
right and this is going to be like four
times eighteen four four times this and
that way you can just know what these
are um so if I want the total raise for
a sphere I'm just gonna say that so
we're gonna say look we're gonna output
this many cubes there's six faces of a
cube and we know we want light samung
total rays worth of them we're gonna go
through and draw for each one of the
sample points which again is the number
of bundles because we do four per and
then we're gonna extract just the
components there we're gonna use our
debug color table here it looks like
probably I don't really know if I
actually want that color table so for
the moment I think I might actually just
do this but we can do that later for
some reason I actually want that and
then in here we'll do for our normal
we're gonna get the component out of the
sampling sphere so here's our sample
Direction 0 sorry point index and we're
gonna get the comp index out of it we're
then going to push the cube on there
this start point I don't know where that
came from or what that's supposed to be
or why but it looks like it was just set
to be a little bit off the ground which
is probably fine I'm gonna go ahead and
compile this and what we should see is
nothing really because we just got
garbage in there for now but then I want
to go generate some points and see if we
can get them being displayed so get
current quads takes what it takes to
render group the quad counts and the
render of texture in this case it's just
the white texture because we don't want
to put any textures on these things
push cube actually why do we even need
this I think we do push cube yeah push
cable just do what we needed to do so I
don't know think this just this is just
code from long ago just hasn't been
updated ever since we can just have the
push cube do that yeah so that's the
starting location the radius of the
thing is just going to be this I don't
know what else we need there but
probably nothing and now we should well
we're not really gonna see much but what
I can do temporarily to get this working
you can you can see it it's right there
right so I think what I'm gonna do is
just go ahead and write that generator
load it in here and let it look you know
but it looked like it looks alright uh
so if I go ahead and load up h/h sphere
which is this code I know now what I
wanted to generate which is this code
right and so all I need to do here is
just actually make something that will
output this this file exactly this way
so I'm gonna make like a output blah
function here temporarily and I'm just
gonna make this thing print this stuff
out
something like this and so in here you
know we know we want this right so we
pretty much know that this has to be a
power of two right our raid bundles
first fear is like whatever we want and
then this stuff is actually just wrote
because it's sort of calculated right
there right so we'll print out all that
looking at this it turns out this is
actually fine and we really don't
actually need it to be in there but
because we're just defining everything
in that file I think I'm gonna go ahead
and keep doing that because it'll just
make it a little bit easier and it won't
create like a tangle of includes it'll
just like have it in the correct place
and be done with it right but you can
see that it's actually wrote there's now
that it's based entirely on those pound
of fines you don't actually need it the
generator to actually change the nature
of the structure at all but you know
okay so that's like the preamble and now
we get to the actual part that we care
about
which is this table and we need 18 of
these guys right so we just need this to
be inside a four I loop that we're gonna
print out so and then we need to do the
same thing so this is like what we were
estimating there so this is four times
18 of these right so we just need to
print out lots of those this opening so
just looking at how this goes I think we
need an extra bracket set here there
right so when we see 18 of these we mean
18 sets of three right so this is
correct but this bracket should actually
be holding it should be one more bracket
level I think right I think it's that
and then you close that bracket and open
another one for these guys and then you
close that bracket and then you close
these two brackets and just again
looking at this so you're saying like
look we're making one array of light
sampling spheres which is this first
bracket here for each light sampling
sphere that we want to do there is a
bracket so it's this and since we know
we want multiple of these we're actually
gonna put this whole thing inside of for
a loop eventually right that's gonna
happen like this
so each one of these is a light sampling
sphere each one of these right here this
is the array of sample directions and
this is the array of cube side weights
right and so here for example where we
look at these that's gonna be this way
but this is actually going to look like
that that's my argument I'm sticking
with it for now the compiler will tell
us if we're wrong I'm saying but I think
that's roughly what we're looking at and
so what we need to do here is we need to
pass some information to this thing just
some basics right we need to know what
the light sampling sphere count is we
need to know what the Ray bundles for
sphere is right and then when we come
down here we need to loop over those
things so the light sampling sphere
count for example
we're gonna print out that mini spheres
for each of these we need to know how
many ray bundles there are so that's
printing these out right and then
finally down here we need to print out 4
times the Ray bud
which again is is you know computable by
us so we might as well just do this and
that's for our like cubes or our weight
next and so we print out one of those
for each one of the bundles for now and
again I'm not that's the only part that
I really don't like so far about what
we're doing I don't like how much
bookkeeping is of is required in like
the spheres and I think that that's
where something like spherical harmonics
actually works nicely is because you
just have some coefficients and you
don't really have to think too hard
about what those coefficients mean
during most computations you can just
kind of store your stuff in there that
just is kind of a nicer way to think
about things sometimes so you know I
don't like having to store all these
like you know I would rather have
something that you could just somehow
use those normal directions just
directly and that's something that you
know I'm just red flagging right I'm
just saying like you know
[Music]
watch out this looks wrong right uh so
anyway moving on what I want to do now
is I want to I want to output this fear
I know like this and I just want to have
someplace said it's going to go and I'm
gonna pass it this information which i
think is the only pieces of information
it actually needs so we I mean who knows
what we're gonna do how many of these
were gonna do for right now let's just
say it's 16 and 18 cuz I think that's
what we had in our thing before but
don't matter now because we should be
able to just like set these with abandon
and we should be able to make our stuff
work either way right so when we do our
outputs to your IML we need to pass
those two things in and then we also
need like this file like where's this
crap going to actually go so that'll be
like the output of of our thing so let's
do that and so in here we need some way
of saying like what the thing is that
we're gonna try and output in this case
I'll just read that from aargh so I'll
say like you know maybe the art count is
just a thing that tells you maybe
exactly this information so maybe you
need like three arguments to it the
samplings to account the bundles for
sphere and then just where to write the
thing so if that was the case we would
need our our count to be four right and
otherwise we'd like say hey man I'm not
gonna work
something like this
no I'm saying to you and so when we
print out that usage information we just
expect the person is going to be able to
put it in in exactly that way so that
then when we come through here when we
create these things we would say
something like this I you know I mean
wow that's some good spelling today and
I think that's all we really care about
here
and then we can just report an error if
we can't get that for some reason but
this would basically be the entirety of
the function and then we just need to
write the generator the way we want to
write it and this theory would write it
out for us so let's start by kind of
like working our way towards getting
this compiling if I go look at one of
these guys if I just bulk import
everything well we don't need Windows
but if I bulk import everything else and
I just go down here and and we look at
let's say one of these things right so
in here we want to compile our sampling
generator we can do our compile
it's called HH sphere and that's it in
theory that should now get compiled if
we look in here can't find the random
series so you know I guess we would just
need handmade random
and it's handmade Cindy right yeah which
we would have made it anyway looks like
there isn't one of these um so compiling
that's if we then look here you know
this has some residual in there we don't
care about that just quite yet so I'm
gonna go ahead and and nerf that out but
now we should get our oops we should get
our sphere generator you know doing it's
its little thing and if we go actually
invoke it now we should be able to start
like debugging that and getting our
sphere include file written to do that
we could just go to the temp directory
build a chaser deck see it should tell
us this right because we didn't give him
any parameters if we say we want 16
spheres and 18 ray bundles and we say
that it goes to handmade sphered INL or
something like this then it should
generate that file for us and there it
is so we now have it outputting
something who knows if that something is
correct looks like we forgot to indent
some of our lines there but that's ok
and this is basically just a giant data
table right it doesn't do anything else
but it looks like it put out everything
correctly like there's the count and the
mask and off we go and that should be
ready to pound include so now what we
want to do is fill it out with some
actual data try including it and see
what happens if I want to I can roll
that into the build process as well
which I probably do want to do but one
step at a time so here's our generate
lighting pattern call our generate
lighting pattern call wants to have some
way you know of of storing the stuff
that it
creates right so you can see it creating
like temp stuff here but we needed to
actually create real stuff so we needed
to call generate Plus on samples like
this and we need it to actually put them
somewhere after it's done we know that
this temp storage here for example we
actually need that to be a certain size
because once we get told how many light
sampling spheres there are and how many
rate bundles for a sphere there are we
need to start like working with that so
if we assume that in here when we do
generate lighting pattern that someone's
gonna tell us like this right then what
we need to do is we need to make sure
that in here we have four times the rate
bundles Purse fear as storage space that
we can use to like output this data and
furthermore we need to like that's like
just some temp information right we need
to do that for each of these so as we go
through here and do you know that as
well as we go through the light sampling
store account we need to like we need to
work with these things together now what
I'm suggesting and I think this is a
good idea but maybe it's dumb I just
think it's a good idea what I'm
suggesting is I want to change up the
way that we were creating these so
before we were creating each sphere
separately so we we don't consider the
spheres together we consider them as
discrete units and we go from there
but what I'd rather do what I'd much
rather do is take and cover the sphere
with densely sampled points dead densely
sampled blue noise and then extract
slices from it that are all sort of
uniformly distributed to some sense to
some degree
now we know how to do this in a variety
of ways the only thing I'm not sure
about is the slicing right because what
I want to do is take a blue noise sphere
and break it in you know
then pull it apart into a number of
spheres that combine back to the
original sphere each one of which is
roughly blue noise shaped and I think
the way you could do that is just by
always picking the furthest point or
something which is n Square D to a
certain extent the naive way meaning if
we literally if we literally didn't
classify the points at all and just
every pick of a point look for the
furthest point away that might be
prohibitively slow or it might not be I
mean as you crank these numbers it might
be but we know they can't be that high
to begin with because the rate bundles
for sphere has to be pretty low and how
many of them do we really need at the
end of the day so I don't know we'll see
I'll start with a naive solution we'll
see how it goes so let's start with
white noise and go from there
what I want to do first is allocate some
space so I'm just gonna say okay we've
got our vertex storage so these are our
directions all of them and I want to
make a total ray count right so total
Direction count is going to be however
many spheres we have thumbs
however many bundles we have times four
right and then what I'm gonna do is
allocate space for exactly that many I'm
then just going to loop
over each of them and I'm going to just
set each direction completely randomly
first right so in order to do that I'm
gonna do just a standard thing you've
seen me do multiple times before
it's just hey create three bilaterals
that gives me a white noise to a certain
extent to the extent that our random
number generator isn't busted it gives
me white noise inside a cube I can then
normalize that and take you know I can
keep it if it actually the only time
that would fail is if it was zero zero
zero right otherwise it will always
produce some direction I and so all I
really need to do is just guard against
that one specific case and otherwise my
white noise is fine so if here I do
total Direction counts maybe I'll do
this
or this will just go through here and
say okay actually you know what I'm not
gonna do that I'm just gonna do this
okay
we'll go through and say okay if length
squared er is greater than you know or
it's greater than anything because it's
been normalized so if it just didn't
come out to be zero
then we increment otherwise we don't
write so we're just gonna go through
here see the white noise out first and
then what we're gonna do is for each
sphere we're gonna extract points from
here into the spheres so what I'll
probably do is have another thing that
we create here that's something like you
know was this point used in a sphere yet
or not and what I'll do there is say
okay oh and I can use my own because I
forgot me we've got our types in here
all right so I'm gonna go ahead and
allocate another right here which is
just one of these things right and so
I'm gonna allocate all of those in each
one of these as we go I'm also gonna say
like oh okay oh you know what I forgot
to do here got to actually record this
we all try to avoid care here by doing
this so that we'll initialize a table
all to false saying we haven't used any
of these yet and it will initialize all
of the directions to white noise
pointing in random white noise
directions on the sphere right and
they're not really white noise on the
sphere because it's a cube that's been
projected to a sphere so it's really
white noise in a cube projected to a
sphere which is not the same thing it
doesn't matter because we don't want
white noise anyway so we don't really
care what our initial seat is because
we're going to be cleaning that up and
doing different things with it so you
know we can kind of ignore that for now
we then have to go through and create
our individual spheres so now we have
our you know sphere index equals zero
experience less some light sampling
sphere count and now for each sphere we
need to pull out enough vertices so we
need to pull out like we would right
here so here in our sphere index as we
go through what we want to be able to do
is pull out the exact number of
directions that we expect to have which
is this right so what we want to do is
and I'm going to call this bundle index
because it's not a direction index it's
a bundle it's four directions at once so
for each of these are going to say okay
there's the bundle index
like so and then what we need to do is
transform this into something that's
going to pick these in in an actual
intelligent way now the first thing I'm
going to do is to just take them
randomly and that way we can just get a
white noise you know n spheres all of
them white noise again it's cubic white
noise projected so it's not white noise
on the sphere but it's similar it's it's
related to that by a projection function
I just get that drawing and in the game
and then we have to come back here and
start to actually make this do something
intelligent to reduce good noise that we
actually want sliced in a way that we
actually want so going through each of
these what I need to do is first of all
have someplace that these are stored and
so that is something that I guess we
would expect this to probably pass in
and so I don't know how we actually want
to store this that's kind of a good
question but I guess what I'd probably
say is we might just want to do a thing
here where we have something like this
and in here we're gonna want to store
the component information now we don't
need any of this stuff because we're
just printing these things out so we can
actually not bother you know no I look
at it I'm like we don't really need to
store them in actual v3 for X's we can
but we don't actually have to for any
real reason right there's there's no
actual reason that we need to do that so
instead what we could do is store them
as something else I don't know how I
feel about that either way I suppose
what we probably want to do is just do
it like this and say alright you know
we've got this we know this is what we
want to actually print out and so what
we're going to do
is store like or maybe just that
something like this and then these here
right we know how many there are
supposed to be so we just be doing this
right and so maybe this is just
something that gets passed in and that
way in here when we write the stuff out
we just write it out right and so here
in our sphere stores we can just go for
each sphere and that plucks out each
individual sphere store that we want we
then go through here and fill out that
thing and we can do that by just writing
to the sample direction and writing to
the weights so here we would say sphere
sample Direction bundle index and this
can stay the same it would not be temp
though we would actually want to have
like four things that we actually
grabbed here right so we would want to
take these directions here and actually
get them somehow now for now I won't
again I won't bother actually doing that
but we'll want to do that in the future
right but it would look like this where
we grab these things out you know four
at a time and furthermore we would want
to advance by the sphere amount inside
the direction so we'd probably for now
also want to do like this
right now again that's kind of stupid
because you know even at first we
probably want to go ahead and just
simplify that just so it's a little
easier on the eyes so we'd probably do
something more like this we load up a
particular direction that we're getting
our v3 out of right and then each one
through here we just probably do
something like this right and and again
we don't really care what's going on
here it doesn't really matter but it'd
be something along those lines
furthermore in here for the weights we
know that we need six of those as well
at the moment we don't know what they
are so we would just do something like
this
again all good nothing particularly
weird happening here so I think that's
mostly what we want I will probably just
put nonsense into our random seed for
now and I think we're good to go
so I think that roughly does what we
want and so now we just have to fill out
the rest of the program to print it and
I think that'll even leave us a little
time today to start playing with this
but then tomorrow we can pick it up and
actually produce some good sampling
spheres for us to use that that you know
fit the nice sampling criteria that we
would hope for so in here if we've got
our sphere store I'm gonna go ahead and
just pass that along so in here I'm just
gonna say all right when we output this
stuff we're gonna output our sphere
store and then in here I'm gonna
actually allocate this sphere store and
the storage for it into the system so
the first thing we need to add is for
these spheres we need to print them out
sensibly so we've got the loop over all
the spheres needs to pluck out which
sphere we're actually talking about we
then need to go over each ray bundle for
the sphere and pluck that out so that's
a v3 for X and that's just the sphere
sample direction I don't know what we
called that up here sample Direction
mewn rhai bundle index that gives us out
the one we wanted to print and so then
we just need to actually print it using
a bunch of crappy percent s like so
right
and I don't know how we want to do this
we could actually write a for loop it
might not really be worth it but once we
get the bundled and we don't really need
an address or their once we get the
bundle we can just pull out the ones
that we want so I think in this case
where we've got our cindy code here if
you look at how v3 4x works you can see
that we've got an e that a picks out
which one of the three you're looking
for so we would basically say okay we're
printing the first one now then inside
there you've got an e which says which
member right and so that we would look
like that again it just it's just this
the whole way right so I don't think I'm
going to bother with a for loop it's
just more typing that's worth because C
is too frigging verbose all the time but
still not particularly difficult and
that should be fine that prints out the
REA directions as v3 for X's that can
then get loaded back in hopefully as M
128 later on in the process in here
where we have our wait bundle index that
needs to get printed out in exactly the
same way so we've got our cube store
cube that's going to be sphere cube
weights or just weights I think we
called it weight bundle index and then
in here again it's just looking up the
elements of that cube that we print out
one at a time again don't really need
that
and so in here we've just got our 5 4 3
2 1 weights and then I think that prints
everything out that it should right and
so now all I have to do is allocate some
space for that and actually call the
functions we don't currently call the
generator we're gonna have to so here's
the JIT here is that right let's go
ahead and call it
we know the light sampling counts like
so and we'll have our spheres there
first thing I need to do is allocate
space to store the spheres in order to
do that I have to allocate space for the
number of spheres we expect to have
right oops and then I need to allocate
space why is it's having some trouble
with that and then I need to loop over
each sphere and allocate space for the
things that the sphere needs to store
right so for each sphere we just need
two arrays we need a sampling direction
and we need our weights again each of
these is a pretty simple malloc in this
case we're looking at Ray bundles purse
fear times the size of each individual
bundle and in the weights case we're
looking at the number of bundles period
sorry the number of bundles times the
number of rays per bundle right then
when we do our output sphere I just need
to pass this along and now I think this
is ready to run I do think so in our
cube for each bundle you can see this is
actually not right then because the
weights we need to write out more than
that number of weights right so for here
we need to for each one of the
directions that we actually picked up in
there like I don't know whichever you
want to call it I don't want to call a
slice index but like something like that
so for each bundle component we actually
need to compute this
because remember they're just there's
one of these for every ray and there are
four rays per sample direction bundle I
think that's it now so running this
we're gonna have to debug now and so
what I would like to do is maybe SiC
remedy on it so I could step through it
and see what's up in order to do that
I'm just gonna go ahead and call remedy
on it like so and in here I noticed by
the way I don't know I don't think this
is our fault it might be let me just
double check first before I ask ya um I
wanted to mention that it looks like
remedy no longer can take stuff from the
command line for some reason and I don't
know if maybe that's cuz I don't know
the arguments but George are you are you
with us today I don't know if George's
here I was wondering if there was a way
to get remedy to take that I and it
might be that that there's special flags
now cuz remedy has a bunch of command
line options so it probably is no longer
sufficient to just pass that but I'm
curious what you do pass maybe it's in
the docs I don't know but just something
to think about or to tell me about
maybe put it in quotes or maybe it just
can't do that like have the arguments
get passed you know I'm saying to you
so it looks like it just can't handle
arguments at the moment right so yeah it
would be cool because I'm 99% positive
that that used to work so I think it
might just have been a regression went
cuz remedy gained a bunch of powerful
command line features actually you
didn't see you can like drive it you can
add and remove breakpoints and stuff
from the command line for like a running
instance so all this stuff is like
pretty cool and probably what happened
is when that went in the command line
parsing had to get a little bit more
fancy and so it probably doesn't work
with the old thing anymore just for
reference you you might you might need a
command because it might not be obvious
like how to like like if you just send
that crap down it might not be obvious
to remedy what's going on I mean maybe
you could just say if I don't see
command is the first thing then the rest
of the things are arguments I don't know
but something to think about
cuz it would be fine as well if you just
did you know that or something you write
or you know it doesn't really need to do
anything specific but I thought I'd
mention it because I did notice that the
other day it's something I rarely do but
it does seem like it it gets it has
trouble sometimes with that alright but
I don't care about any of that right now
because again not really a problem
it's it takes like 10 seconds to just
put it in here but it was just a feature
that remedy did have so I figured we
might as well report it to get reacted
alright so here in the settings I'm just
asking you to do in the temp directory
I'm asking it to output that handmaid
certify and now I'm gonna start stepping
in and you can see it running here just
gonna make sure that it actually gets
the information that we think it does
but we kind of already know that that
was working it's light samplings ear
count and array bundles Paris here so
these are the numbers we expected to get
we're going to allocate our information
here
then start to generate the pattern so
now we should have fears that kind of go
out to the correct number so like for
example spear 15 should actually have
you know space reserved for stuff and it
appears to but sphere 16 should not
although it might point to stuff anyway
if it's just in that page so it's hard
to tell
yeah there we go so the sphere 16
doesn't that's nice so then we could
kind of come out here and say alright
let's look at generate lighting pattern
that's going to Matlock some temp
storage for the directions it's going to
populate that let's take a look at what
wrote oops again totally fine if I look
at this that's like a sort of an array
of stuff what I should see now is when
we come around will populate the next
one and we do populate the next one and
we do so you know that's all fine
the total Direction counts in this case
should be 16 times 18 times 4 and that
looks about right
yep and so that should just populate our
entire array and then when we go to
print it out I didn't actually step
through that code but in theory it
should just print out all of those
values let's take a look and see if it
did if I go in and here to for coder I'm
gonna close this out cuz I don't eat it
and I'm gonna load out of the temp
directory that IML file they probably
should have s after them so the compiler
doesn't complain I but you know that
looks about right
you know I mean who who's to say but
sure right
so I think we're roughly generating the
correct stuff now and I just need to put
some s in the print out routine but
other than that I think we're ready to
go
and we're just about at the end of the
session anyway so that's a good time to
wrap that up but let's see if we can't
just load these into our render a test
draw them and verify that we've actually
generated some spheres for sampling so
in h h sphere if we look at our
printouts really what we need is just
these things have to be percent FF so
really all I'm doing is like replacing
percent F with % FF just to stick the F
at the end of it
right just pretty basic that's all I
really need to do there and if we if we
were to add this in now to the hand mate
here a build process I should be able to
use that
IML file right I do want to save this to
our debug directory that's HH sphere dot
our GD r d gb that way at when we need
to debug it we can switch quickly using
this menu which I like so if we run Hana
me here now we shouldn't see anything
different because we're using the same
INL files we're using before which
doesn't have anything in it but what I'd
like to do now is replace that INL file
with one that we've generated in order
to do that I'm just gonna for now use
the command line because I want to play
around a little bit more so what I'm
gonna do here is I'm going to run this
command and I'm just gonna have it
overwrite our file so basically the W
hand-made code handmade sampling spheres
that I know that will overwrite it and
so now if I actually build we should be
including it and so you can see we've
got a compile error there oops this
is old news there we go
it's telling me I have too many
initializers but who is that actually
referring to in 8 comma 11 too many
initializers this is a struct what is it
talking about
I don't follow is it just reporting that
error weirdly or something because why
would it be complaining about too many
initializers in something that isn't an
initialization if it was complaining
down here that's what we would expect
but does it look like it is I'm gonna
build from the command line just to
double check cuz it looks like it's only
complaining about it on that line and I
have no idea what that is complaining
about light sampling rate bundles first
fear I mean that should just be an 18
right in other words we're just talking
about that I don't get it
[Music]
oh okay so I guess my first question is
is this just the compiler outputting a
really busted error so for example if I
was to get rid of the actual
initializers in the file so does the
error go away it does so it seems like
it's trying to tell me that there are
too many initializers in here and it
just got really confused about how to do
that I guess I'm not sure so let's go
ahead and put these back in and see if
we can figure out exactly where it's
complaining so we know that we need n of
these sampling directions so for light
sampling spheres let's look at what
we've got this outer bracket here is the
sampling sphere contain like contains a
sampling spirit this contains a sample
directions so for each sample direction
we would expect to see 18 V 3 4 X's 1 2
3 4 5 so we do see exactly 18 let's see
if these look reasonable because we
don't know maybe these themselves are
busted so in this case we've got 1 2 3
each one has four things in it so that
all seems good I'm wondering if maybe
the problem is that because it's a union
it's having trouble with that and I
could see that because it's let me just
jump to 3 3 B 3 4 X here I could see
that because it probably doesn't know
how to initialize that properly for the
v3 for X e values there like maybe it's
just confused
what it should do
and I don't know
[Music]
this is always the problem with C++
nonsense you just want to say I'm trying
to input this data and I want you to
build it into this type please just do
it but that's always easier said than
done
I think that's probably what we're
seeing here I couldn't say for sure but
that's my guess and in order to test
that guess I guess I'll just do this
because that's essentially what we have
here and so if I took out the Unionists
of this and just changed it to that I'm
wondering if now we still get the same
error or not and let's look so here
we're still getting too many
initializers that's actually reassuring
because if that's actually the case that
means it's not the Union it's just
something else so let's take a look at
what actually is happening there for the
light sampling sphere we have four
things that's our guess right we have
three things here if I put it calm in
there even though you don't really need
one I have three things inside this so
that's our guests our outer guess right
and then I need 18 of those which is
what this looks like
again not really seeing where the
problem is it would be really helpful if
the compiler actually output a useful
error for us but it's really adamant
about not doing that and I don't know
why so I'm gonna keep going down this
road I'm gonna go ahead and clip out
everything else
so now we're just working with this and
I'm going to eliminate all of these so
we're just gonna see if we can give it
to do one thing right so again here's
our light sampling sphere because this
is an array of light sampling spheres so
this is the light sampling sphere this
is our guess right no sorry this is our
sample direction we need 18 of them or
no more than 18 of them this is our
guess yeah and this is our guest to
so what am I missing folks what's the
problem
that looks totally correct right I mean
isn't that exactly what we said we had I
guess I'll start start small is this a
guest - do you think that's a guest -
you let me know compiler because I have
no idea there do you know do them that
is or don't you
so it thinks that - guess it thought
that was fine right it thought that was
totally fine didn't have any problem
with that okay so now let's try a guess
a guess needs to have three of these
right so it should look like this
so it doesn't think it doesn't think
that should be happening right it it
doesn't like that it says there's too
many initializers and here it's actually
able for whatever reason it's actually
able to report the error in what looks
like more of the correct spot right it's
actually at least flagging this which is
something so here's our random test it
should have three guests twos in it
here's one of them here's two of them
here's three of them where is the too
many initializers where do you guys see
it because I don't see it
if I double bracket it but you shouldn't
have to do that because we didn't have
to do that before right but it looks
like it wants that extra bracket but
before it was an array and we didn't put
the bracket in right so I mean in other
words if you don't put a bracket there
which you don't why do you put a bracket
here it's totally wrong like these are
both exactly the same thing and yet for
some reason this one needs double
brackets and this one needs no brackets
right now one pair of brackets is
correct because this is an additional
layer right it's an additional array so
instead of just these brackets who knows
anyway stupid garbage no one cares
going back to h8 sphere all that means
is that if that is the in fact the only
problem we just need to spam brackets in
here for no friggin reason so inside our
Vieth are v3 for here I just have to put
an additional bracket set around this I
think for no reason I believe that is
what we learned but who knows
alright so in here I'm going to run this
again to generate a different version of
this file I'm gonna kill this buffer and
let it load the new one in and we'll see
if it thinks that's fine right
it didn't look like it even loaded that
one in so looking at this now we've got
this magical extra one here right and of
course I don't know how many more
friggin extra brackets it's gonna want
us to put into this nonsense because if
that needed extra brackets then
everything probably needs extra brackets
at some level would be my suspicion but
I don't actually know but it looks like
it's still complaining about two main
initializers it's gonna flaming now on
the v3 4x and I'm not sure I want to go
ahead and just again clip this out I'm
gonna try and work this one backwards
now to see if I can get rid of the error
in here and then know exactly how many
more ridiculous pairs of brackets for no
reason I have to add alright so in here
by the way all this is absolutely absurd
that the programmer has to do this at
all it's absolutely ridiculous data
status pecking in C is absolute garbage
and it only gets worse in C++ so anyway
that aside if we compile this which is
the minimal set now we just add brackets
till this works I guess
such a piece of garbage just total
frickin garbage there we go all right
there is our generate sphere here's me
running it
I need this to reload did I put that in
the right place it's the triples yeah
and so we're probably gonna have to
double even more of those now
actually you know what let me save this
one and let me actually make multiple of
each of them now because we're probably
gonna have to double the outer ones too
to
so I'm tempted you just say that this
entire thing is stupid and I don't want
to deal with it so I'm guessing that
rather than try to make C++ actually do
something right at all here maybe I
should just flatten these things down
because this is ridiculous how just take
the things and put them in the freaking
it's just an array of numbers what is
wrong with you it's so dumb it can't
even report where it thinks the error is
and it doesn't need any of these
brackets it should just take the data
absolutely absurd anyway all right so
now it thinks that this is a problem
suddenly who knows why
right just magical the unicorn shot in
the wrong place today there we go yeah
and it can't seem to figure out what
goes on there I'm just wondering if like
we just need every pair of brackets to
be doubled or something like this I I
really just have no idea what it's
thinking none whatsoever
so let's see how could I define this
let's suppose that we need to do this
differently let's suppose that C++ is
just so broken that you just don't even
bother right what would we do well we
need two tables we need tables of
weights and we need tables of sample
directions right and so if we wanted to
do that really we could just not define
this and we could just say that we were
pointing to it because we know that the
data layout would be the same it's just
a large array of f/32 right so in theory
if I make sure that the alignment is
correct I should be able to just dump a
giant array of floats instead and then
C++ could try to get its head
out of its anus and we could actually
program instead of meant handling this
stupid compiler all day long so in order
to do that all we would really need to
do is just this right here's our light
sampling sphere table guess what it's a
giant array of floats because that's the
best darkness trout strips true strips
ugly stepchild can do and so when we
come through here I'm just gonna dump
them all out right I'm just gonna dump
float after float after float and I'm
just gonna dump them in the order that I
know that they should be right so
there's all of the floats for this no
more of that here's all the floats for
this and then we close it off so that
produces the same layout that we want
right it gives us what we actually
needed like so of course they run it
and now what you can see is lo and
behold the C compiler was able to
actually do its job for a change what a
shock high C compiler thanks for coming
to work today and then if I go load up
that file we now see it's just a giant
dump of floats which you know is about
all that that it can handle right I'd
like to put an intern on that so I think
inside h/h sphere I'm gonna add I think
we have a thing called global we can
just put in there so when we grab that
light sampling sphere table what I'd
like to do is also align it I don't know
if we actually have in our platform code
a way to specifically align things I'm
gonna look we don't really have a deco
spec align and we kind of need one in
this particular case because without a
deco spec of line I don't think it's
gonna know what's going on I'll try to
putting that in just to give you some
perspective on that the reason is
because we don't know what the compiler
is gonna do as far as loads we don't
know if it's gonna try and use the line
loads I don't need it to do that because
unaligned loads are just fine for our
purposes but just in case I need to to
put one of these into the declaration of
the variable to make sure that they're
aligned to a 16 byte boundary so that
aligned load Cindy loads won't fault so
I just need this to get that alignment
specifier placed in there and you know
that would look something like this
right
and now what I can do is actually just
print out some ridiculous nonsense here
as well and say okay after you define
the table we can just make this thing
point to this other thing right so all
I'm gonna do is make it so it outputs
the table as this giant floating point
array of garbage and then I'm just gonna
straight-up cast it and that's gonna be
the end of it what a waste of time such
a garbage language alright so now I'm
going to go ahead and generate our our
file again I'm going to compile and I
think we should now be working okay but
we'll see oops put that inside actually
have to go outside and in theory now
that should allow us to effectively
we're just defining it as a giant array
of floats but then we're using it as if
it was an actual lighting spirit table
right so we have to get that cast
working properly what's the problem here
initializing handmade lighting 16 what
should I forget a I did just forgot
something : uh all right so now
hopefully we're good to go
nope not quite ah that should be like
that we just want to point her now all
right so that took way longer than it
should have because we thought
temporarily that C++ might do something
smart some day but it doesn't so why
bother I should have just done the float
table to begin with because we know that
would work so now I think we're good to
go I think we I think we have our
pipeline flowing tomorrow we can
concentrate on actually creating some
useful values in our table for now we
want to see if we can get anything here
printing out or started drawing spheres
sampling spheres and what you can see
there is we've got a sampling sphere
exactly as we wanted there's our points
around the sphere and what I'd like to
do just really quickly before going to
the QA where hopefully all of the
questions are why does c++ suck so badly
and my answer will be because it
requires people who know what they're
doing to make a language that works I'm
going to go ahead and draw all of them
so all of the spheres that we actually
created I'm going to draw them all like
on top of each other right I'm gonna
also kill this buffer so in here where
we loop over
I'm just gonna do it over all the
spheres like that
and so here we're we're just using the
first one I'm going to do all of them
and the other thing I'm going to do is
I'm going to look at our color table and
I'm gonna get a debug color off of the
sphere so we can in the future like
right now we don't expect to anything
else in here but in the future what we'd
like to see is those colors themselves
are equally distributed sort of so we
kind of want to see that our spheres
have that nice property to them as well
right so there's our sphere and that's
exactly what we wanted
I'm gonna lift that up off the ground a
little bit because it's a little hard
for me to see the whole sphere remember
we were using a hemisphere before hand
and now we're actually sampling in an
entire sphere so what is that don't know
what's going on there hold that one
quick second there we go
but I think we're all done with the sort
of annoying plumbing part of things now
so we really just have to focus on
creating a nice distribution now but
there we go right so there's our
sampling and you can cut you can see
it's not very well distributed right now
right you can you can actually see that
I may want this that to be even higher
up honestly
just to get it out of the way
so there's our sphere right kind of
floating up in the middle of nowhere
you can see it's got some big holes in
it right
and again it's gonna under sample
because it's white noise on a cube
projected on to a sphere right so that's
our job for tomorrow I I'm gonna go
ahead and go to a Q and a
have you considered using Julian
language to do any sort of game develop
a I've never been heard of Julie
language I think coder I'm surprised the
cast works as an initializer why are you
surprised
you can always cast a pointer to
anything to a pointer to anything else
because all you're doing is just telling
it to reinterpret the pointer but the
value stays the same so the compiler is
like okay it's the same value right just
copies one pull up it copies one eight
byte value to another eight byte value
that's it so it doesn't actually do
anything it's not actually converting
anything in an initializer it's not
looking at the data at all you know I'm
saying to you
it's just copying the pointer and this
gets not even copying the pointer
because it's just a hard-coded number
where the array is so it's just saying
hey off you go why does he Sasebo suck
so badly good question
I don't know I don't know how they are
so bad at so many things
I don't know it's like in order to
contribute to the C++ language fact you
have to had to pass some kind of like
you know decathlon of of stupidity where
you have to prove that you're stupid
along many axes so that you won't
accidentally do something right
Martin's was asking if we can use seeps
C++ 11 a line as yeah if if that's well
enough supported and you would know
better than I'm Martin's cuz you
I feel like do a lot more platform work
than I do these days but if you think
that's okay I'm totally fine with it so
you're doing saying that in here instead
of a deco specular line you want
this just making sure I get I'm
understanding the request right
just waiting for Martins to confirm
that's what he wanted me to do
what advice would you give to bjorn
history strip a take real-world
programming more seriously right
programming is not a theoretical
exercise you know it's like plumbing or
something like it actually has to move
the water around the pipes like you
can't just theorize what might be nice
and then not look at what the actual
practical consequences of people trying
to do actual work you know are and like
C++ with it's ridiculous set of
undefined behaviors and it's like
hamstrung feature set that always seems
to have something wrong with it it's
just such garbage if you're to make this
a more 3d game how would you go about
modifying the renderer to support
submissions of these would you keep the
single vertex lever set up no if you're
trying to push like large 3d models down
a pipeline what you typically need to do
is do you know how we've got the
textures set up right now you would set
up one of those for the models as well
so you would basically have a parallel
thing to our texture like our texture
cache system right you have a parallel
thing to that for your models and every
time you need to use a model that wasn't
in the cache you would try to load it
into the 3d memory the memory on the 3d
card and whenever you wanted to draw it
you would reference that so so you don't
want to be like sending down all the
vertices every frame like that's not
gonna work so you have to just treat
them like you treat textures they're
basically just vertex textures right
what happened for you to turn on
co-sister RC well nothing happened it
caused me a turn on see below so harshly
I always rant about C++ just stupid
compiler being bad about just getting
data in there right
okay so looks like they want this before
the type although I don't know if it
matters so this what we're talking about
you just want you want that
that's story fine by me
since we're asking off two other
questions is SP IR V in the direction of
getting programmable Isis for graphics
hardware or am i incorrect thoughts on
experimental no SP IR V is is just an
intermediate representation of shaders
it doesn't really have anything to do
with programmable Isis for GPUs you can
think of SP IR V sort of as like clang
IR if you're familiar with that or just
generally when your compiler ingests
code normally so you know I give it one
of these C files and I say compile this
it doesn't just read the C file as text
and then spit machine code out the back
it reads it in it builds a bunch of
intermediate you know data structures
that it uses to like analyze the code
and think about what it should do and
then eventually run something after it's
gone through transformations and bunged
around and all sorts of stuff eventually
it will kick out some machine code when
we say a programmable eisah for graphics
hardware we're talking about a spec for
that machine code SP ir v is like the
compiler internal structures so SP ir v
is saying look let the shader get
compiled into an intermediate format
then we'll hand that to the graphics
card and the graphics card will actually
generate something that map's it to its
eisah so it's really SP r v doesn't
really have anything to do with getting
graphics hardware more programmable from
a direct programming standpoint in fact
it's the opposite of that
it's an insulation layer that prevents
you from actually programming the
graphics hardware right
what do you think about rust I've never
used rust my only thoughts on it are
from looking at the things that people
talk about it doesn't sound like a
language that really has much of a clue
about things I care about it seems like
yet another C++ to me but you know I
haven't used it yet so maybe I would
think it was great but I could pretty
much tell you right now I wouldn't I
would probably think it sucks it's
probably slightly better than C++ though
because most languages are what happened
to Sean McGrath I don't know did
something did something happen to sean
McGrath
August 30th all right there there are
some swears on there yes I should put
that on the stream sorry kids you had a
post from today or yesterday so I'm not
sure ting about what happened to him
maybe you mean something specific I
don't know can you build an entire game
and a data or data oriented mindset well
I do really I'm a CS student and I want
to learn about rigid body physics it
seems resources I've found the internet
are very basic tutorials or advanced
academic papers is there a resource I
can use with a not a steep learning
curve you know there probably is that's
a good question
it probably is but I don't know what it
is light sampling sphere has no padding
then it shouldn't but we can make sure I
mean we'll look right but it shouldn't
really have I don't think but we can
double-check right
you know we don't know like you know we
may have to do some padding on here so
in order to maintain this alignment we
need this stuff to multiply out okay and
so when we do the total raised purse
fear that 18 times 6 that is probably
not what we want right so we probably
want to do here is we probably want to
include you know whatever gets us back
to a 16 byte boundary because I don't
know that we actually are on one at that
point these obviously will always be but
these are not and so that would be the
only thing right so effectively like
whatever it would take to bump us up
properly to the next like aligned number
is what we would want and we want that
either way so like you know this may do
it for us
and then you know the cast might also do
in both cases but we need we need to put
in the padding there either way like
either the compiler has to do it for us
or we have to it and if we do it we know
that it would be good right
so that alignment padding should
probably be there and
well we're thinking about election
powder just put it in there but I I
guess what we would want it to be is
just whatever the next padded number is
so like you know I assume you would want
this again I don't really want any of
this but because it's I don't know if
the compiler will generate aligned loads
like I don't want it to but it might I
just I'm trying to be overly cautious
right so in there we need to pad it out
to make it so that will always be
loading off an aligned value for each
light sampling sphere and to do that we
know that this was aligned because each
one of these is for floats so it's 16
bytes each one of these is each one of
these is not right and so what we want
to do is we want to say well ok we know
there's this many right we know that's
how many there are of the cube side sort
of bundles we know each one has six in
it right and so that is gonna produce
some number that's not a multiple of 16
bytes so we need to do is find like the
next multiple of 16 bytes that it is so
to do that I can just round up basically
and then truncate so I should be able to
just do like you know something like
this to basically say give me however
many of these like floats I would need
to round up to 16 bytes but in this case
since I'm adding since I'm doing this in
F 32 s which I probably want to stick to
these are actually not it's not 16 right
it's actually just going to be like 3
not three kind of a thing so I'm not
sure which way we want to do that for
now I think what I might do is say let's
just make this padding be actually in
bytes which seems maybe like that's more
flexible it's just easier to calculate
really and so in here we would just say
look it's four times the total number of
floats we have rounded up and then
truncated to the to the sixteen right so
we could do that that's one way to do it
another way to do it is to do it in
f-302s which I again like I said I think
it's a little bit better and we know we
don't really need the flexibility so
here we would just add three and and
three and do it just in float so I think
that's what we would want
oops sorry it's not it's not total
raised for sphere it's
it's that I believe
I need like a revert function which I
don't have right now don't know why but
I don't have an old build but alright so
in theory that would do it
that is not right at all
I I'm just getting a little sleepy
alright oops so I think that's what we
want for padding to ensure that we're
always going to be able to be on the
correct line and so in here right we get
off of this member we know we're aligned
we come into this member we have light
sampling total rays for spirit times 6
which is 6 times 4 times 18 right and so
then we need to know how many would put
us up to the next 64 byte boundary and
we're computing that as 3 so let's see
if that's actually true so if we look at
cube side wait it's gonna be 4 times 4
times 18 times 6 that's the number of
actual bytes so we're saying that if we
add 3 that doesn't look right
to me at all did I actually do that math
right
yes I did that math wrong don't program
when you're done for the day that's the
that's pretty much the rules here so you
can see what I did here is I computed
like what the next bump would be but
that's not actually what we want to do
for alignment this is where we are going
to be right and so what we actually want
here is I don't know why I was doing
that at all that was just kind of off in
left field this is the actual number
that we've advanced so far it's four
times the rate battlesphere times six we
want to get up to the next value so all
we really need to do is look at what
it's low bytes are and figure out how
far we have to go to get there right so
it's really just four - whatever that
lobe that low value is right because
whatever that low whatever those bottom
two bits are well bottom two bits of
this value because it's in multiples of
four bytes
whatever those bottom two bits are we
just want to get to the next even
multiple of them right so I believe
that's actually what we want not the
thing I wrote before which was kind of
out of left field
so here we should get so in this case it
said there was no there was no on
alignment there right meaning it thought
this was a multiple of four right and so
when it did the padding again it found
that this value is zero so if we
actually want to not put padding in when
we don't need to we would have to do
this
so essentially what we do is we say look
where are we in terms of alignment if
we're already aligned we don't need to
do one of these if we aren't then we
just need to give ourselves however much
we would need and so to answer the
question it looks like we magically just
picked numbers where that worked so we
don't really need the padding it would
seem let's see if that's actually true
now that we kind of like I have my wits
about me again temporarily I so if we do
four times the the sphere number right
times six its 432 we want to know
whether that's a multiple of four right
because and it is so we don't actually
need the padding unless somebody sets
this number to something else right so
it's good that we put that in there we
do want to be able to check for that
padding but in this particular case we
don't actually need it right yeah
so if we look at those sampling sir you
can see that doesn't have the padding in
there now does that make sense but
you're right it it would need that there
all of her the best cat says the one
thing rest has it makes it better than
C++ no header files that's enough right
there again it's it's not though like
I'm not gonna go through the trouble of
switching everything I do over to
another programming language just for no
header files you know that's just not
enough of a win it's it's good and you
obviously would want that in any new
language because header files are absurd
but you know it's not enough you would
need a significantly greater you know
efficiency boost than bad so and what
will def s that learning curve seems
through the case with most complicated
programming topics this is referring
back to the rigidbody stuff I think how
did you learn these topics when you
started out slowly and just by reading a
lot and practicing like doing stuff
myself you know rigid body dynamics is
pretty bad when I learned it it was way
worse because there were no nobody had
done physics game engines at all pretty
much Looking Glass was one of the only
people that really did anything serious
in that direction so it was really bad
you had to like basically learn it out
of mechanics textbooks that weren't
written in a computational mindset at
all nowadays a lot of that stuff's a lot
easier because you can at least go look
at papers that just are like oh hey
here's how we implement our rigid body
dynamics you can also go look at like
public domain physics libraries even and
just see what they do right so there's a
lot more resources now but I admit it's
always a little hard right it's it's
always a case that when you're learning
something new it's hard to like put
yourself in the right mindset and it's
hard to like know what it is you don't
know you know and you got to muddle your
way through it and kind of like just
work on getting small individual pieces
at a time right so
all right
[Music]
thanks everyone for joining me for those
set of handmade here at sort of pleasure
coding with us always it's not been a
pleasure coding with yarn straw strip in
the C++ gang but then again it never is
what can you do I will be back here
tomorrow when we'll work on our
distribution of our points on the sphere
which is all we really need in order for
us to be happy campers with our sphere
IML file which we can then use for a
lighting sampling with some relative
certainty that it's doing a good job
covering the samples that we actually
need that's it for today I'll be back
here tomorrow hope see back for that
till then obviously if you want to
follow along the source code at home you
can always pre-order the game on
handmade hero dot org and it comes to
the source code so if you want to play
around with it check that out
I'll be back here tomorrow till then
have fun programming and I'll see
everyone on the Internet
to use everybody