hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show we code a complete game
live on stream yesterday we got rid of
the C runtime library and our win32
loader and mostly in our regular game as
well in preparation for what I'm doing
now which is I'm going to be using sine
and cosine today probably to work on our
sampling quality and what's gonna happen
is we're gonna see that we really
probably don't want to be calling sine
and cosine C runtime library anymore
it's gonna be slow it's not gonna be for
wide anyway blah blah blah so we're
probably gonna want to be able to call
for wide sine and cosine or even if we
only call it one wide and then replicate
we're gonna want it to be nice and fast
and not slow like the one that's in the
SE runtime library so we'll have to
start looking at that next week but is
something we always want to do anyway
but it's you know finally at the point
where we actually care at least a little
bit and so that's what we're gonna do
next week probably however today we just
want to go ahead and use our crappy sine
and cosine that come with a see math
library in the C runtime library which
we still linked with the game and if you
remember from yesterday we now know
exactly the six routines we are using
that we didn't write ourselves we wrote
everything in this game ourselves except
for six functions or is it five eight am
to cosine sign floor and ceiling so five
functions I believe I'm not unless I'm
forgetting one so five functions that we
haven't written ourselves and we need to
replace those functions with our own
versus at some point that's what we're
gonna talk about next week for now we
can't still do the work we were going to
do using those functions as is because
we still have the ability to link with C
runtime library basically we can turn it
on and off in the build time so I have
it turned on right now so that the game
code even though the win32 code doesn't
link with it the game code does so
that's where we're at
let's go ahead and push forward on that
so here is what we stopped with I made a
actually I believe it was a stream
request at the end of the show yesterday
was to be able to draw the hemisphere as
a little like a set of points so here is
a stable sampling so we're just looking
at freezing the random number series at
a particular point and looking at how it
you know what the distribution over the
hemisphere is and what you can see about
this is it's a totally reasonable random
distribution over the hemisphere if what
your goal is is actual randomness
meaning unpredictability right
it seems pretty unpredictable the way
these points have been arranged it
doesn't look like there's a particular
structure to them so that's fine but
what we do see here is that it's not an
even sampling so remember we talked
about white noise vs. blue noise what
we're looking at here is something
reminiscent of white noise what we
wanted something more reminiscent of
blue noise which is to say that the
points on the hemisphere kind of want to
be placed in such a fashion as to ensure
that any individual part of the
hemisphere is not too far away from a
sample point right we want to make sure
that we sort of get coverage with our
points so we do want them to kind of
wiggle around and get some sort of
coverage at over the entire hemisphere
by randomly moving over every frame but
uh you know by the same token we want to
make sure that they're spaced in a way
that gives us some kind of a reasonable
arrangement of points in terms of making
sure no area gets on you know completely
unsampled on a particular frame so we
don't want big holes and what we can see
here is we do have those big holes right
and again that's not unexpected for
white noise white noise should be just
as likely to have clumps and holes as it
is to have an even distribution because
again it's it's random so there is no
sort of bias or force pushing it towards
uniform coverage
so we would expect that so what we need
to do is introduce that bias introduced
that uniform coverage constraint or
something
to try and keep it that way so that's
what we're gonna look at today and what
we want to do here is we want to go into
our lighting code we want to go take a
look at that part of the code that
actually does the sampling here it is
and what we want to do here is we want
to figure out ways we can make this
routine generate more interesting stuff
now this routine is can be as slow as it
wants because we're just doing testing
right now so we can just be as slow as
we want here and do anything we want to
do here so we're free to experiment free
to create whatever we want and so that's
what we're gonna do right now if you
take a look at how this is being set up
at the moment what we're doing here with
our normal is we've got sort of a thing
that picks a random bilaterals and it it
basically picks a direction and then
picks a distance how far it wants to go
out along the normal in 2d right so
we're effectively taking this this
process right here what day is today
we're effectively taking a process that
looks like this
where we take a flat disk and you know
what let me draw it a little more 3d so
we can puff it out in a second here so
in the plane you know we've got a circle
and what we do is we're picking a
direction in the circle so we're picking
like a direction like that
and then we're gonna walk out along that
direction a random amount so you know
here here wherever right then we're
gonna project that up onto the
hemisphere right now what that's gonna
do because of the way that it's being
done right now is this gonna concentrate
our sample points more strongly in the
middle than at the end why because we're
walking out along a line in a uniform
fashion right but that line is going to
so that line is going to spread out
those points as it gets further away so
if you imagine two of these right let's
say you were gonna take a bunch of these
and place them like so well let me let
me see if I can draw it a little better
here let's say we took a couple
different lines right if each of these
lines picked like one quarter let's say
so those are our points you can see that
those points remain very close together
but if each of these picked three
quarters you can see that those points
end up fairly far apart right so what
we're gonna end up having is less points
on the perimeter and more points in the
center this was by design right we this
wasn't an accident we meant to do this
why we want to concentrate our sampling
in this region because we know the
cosine law kills samples that are in
this region so rather than doing a lot
of sampling towards the edges we want to
do a lot more sampling towards the
center right and to a certain extent
that is what we accomplished if you take
a look at what's happening here you'll
notice we have a much stronger cluster
up near the top but the problem we get
is that you know even even there where
there's a lot of sample points they're
still just clumpy right we got a big
hole here at
clomp there there's a big clump here
which is roughly at the same degree of a
fan-out is here so what we we don't
really want that we want to see as it
gets further towards the end much less
sample points around that bend right
around that sort of end of the
hemisphere the ring but we want to see
it be even so even like any given band
should be as sparse as it should be
dictated by how far down we've gone
proportional to like the cosine law for
example but we still want to see them
evenly distributed around the ring so we
don't want to see like tons of sample
points on the right side and none on the
left or whatever and that's what we're
seeing here right and again that's
exactly what we would expect to see
because we don't do anything to prevent
pure random white noise clumping right
which will happen so let's think about
what we can do here to try and improve
the situation right all right first of
all let's take a look at how many sample
points we actually expect to have that's
a you know our first step so when we
think about how many samples we'll
probably have you can see that our ray
count here is 16 right which means if we
multiply 16 by 4 we get 64 which means
that the number that we're using right
here is actually accurate that's how
many we think we that is the correct
number we think we should be
distributing so our question now is how
would we distribute those 64 points in a
reasonable fashion right and we do know
also that we want to be casting four
ways at a time we want to keep those
four ways that we're casting at the same
time sort of pointing in roughly similar
direction right
so what I'd like to do here is I'd like
to figure out a way to maybe do some
regular eyes sampling and then maybe
jitter within the regular eyes sampling
now if we assume that we have at least
so again if we if we think we're going
to be sending out four random samples
per actual direction then that means
that we've got something that looks you
know like this right because obviously
if we go ahead and do 16 times 4 we end
up with 64 so or maybe the right way to
say that is 64 divided by 4 is 16 so we
know that we've got 16 primary
directions to distribute and then we've
got 4 you know sort of packets of rays
we're gonna shoot out in a particular
direction that want to be sort of semi
correlated right so what we want to do
is figure out how we can sort of wrap
these around and actually we may want to
start with something because the the
person who did most of the code for
handmade network actually Columbian on
the chat I don't know if he's here he
was asking maybe we could do spiral
sampling right and I don't know let me
see a spiral point or see if I can get a
good I wish I knew what to search for
here spear spiral phyllotaxis is
probably the right word for it see if we
can get a diagram of this somewhere
so yeah this is kind of like it that's
not really what I wanted this is what
more what I wanted yeah so if we want to
take a repeating spiral and kind of put
it down the sphere that is what actually
Columbian was suggesting in its a pretty
good idea actually of a way to quickly
get something fairly abusive it's on
fear just trying to find a good diagram
here yeah here we go
so here you can kind of see a 2d and a
3d version of this here is like a 2d
just looking at a disc right and they're
referring to Vogel's method here which
is the way of like placing these points
on to the disc right and you can see
here how the points are produced in
polar coordinates so polar coordinates
meaning almost exactly what I've written
here right we take a direction and then
we go out that direction by a particular
distance and so in this case we're
creating that direction by taking a
random bilateral in this case we'd find
that direction by taking a random angle
and then using cosine and sine to move
to figure out what it is right so here
you can see what we've got in terms of
the the distribution and I believe n is
the number of points you want to do
right I'm assuming yeah n is the number
of points produced by the sequence theta
is presumably the rate at which you want
to spiral I would assume I'm not sure
though did they define third anywhere
I don't actually see them say that here
we go so figuring out the ideal angle
coefficient right there saying this is
the correct number of radians to use
it's the most irrational ankle I guess
I'm not sure what that means but I'm
sure that if pseudonym 73 were here he
would be able to tell us anyway
we can basically say that taking a
particular theta right produces
different kinds of spirals and I guess
you know we're kind of saying that we
want a nicely distributed one so we're
talking about ones that looked like this
rather than ones that look like this
although as you can see it is a free
parameter we can play with which means
that we don't actually have to think too
hard about it if we know we just want to
get one like this right there sort of
saying there is a there is a rule you
can use to arrive at that correct value
so that's how you would do it in 2d
right that's that's the algorithm for
producing this like sort of layout of
points and then you know the question is
well what do we do if we want to do
these on a sphere and they're basically
saying well you know it's not really all
that difficult to do they use
cylindrical coordinates right which is
basically the same as polar coordinates
but then with a height so these are very
closely related this is exactly the same
as it was so the angle distribution is
the same it's you know but that's
because this value is whatever we want
to set it to right but then the ti here
where we do this is actually going to be
changed it's gonna be changed to use
this zi value which is the height so
it's basically setting the distance we
go out to be proportional to the height
but we end up with a fairly concise
formula again for producing a set of
spiral samples and here's what that
looks like now what you can see here is
it does look like a pretty nice sampling
right it's a pretty good covering of a
sphere without having to actually do
real point repulsion or blue noise or
something that actually produces a true
ran
uniform covering but you know that's
pretty good right we'd be pretty happy
with that for 256 samples certainly now
we only have 64 samples so our sphere
would be more sparse unfortunately and
to be more concrete about that actually
we only have 16 samples but let's try
playing around with this you know I like
the idea I think Lybian had a good idea
here let's play around this a little we
can start with this formula and play
with this value to see what we get in
terms of placement for our 16 points
that we can then blow out 264 using
maybe jitter around the points or
something similar right so I don't know
we could do that the other thing we can
do is produce these using the
cylindrical coordinates and maybe
because we know how the cylindrical
coordinates go we could actually still
use cylindrical coordinates for actually
all of the points and then know that be
based on your index we could know which
four to group that would be close
together right so we could come up with
some rule for tiling these that might be
interesting so we've we definitely have
a lot of options here and you know we'll
kind of see we'll see right all right so
let's start with this what we want to do
here is say okay you know we're gonna be
doing we'll start with just doing this
mini and we'll we'll sort of forego the
sub in next part for now like maybe
we'll just nerf this so we're literally
just doing this part here and what we
want to do now is introduce a little bit
of polar coordinates so what I'm going
to do is I'm going to do a random angle
here and this is corresponding to this
part of the of the series right we want
this P I here we're going to be
producing this this value as an angle so
I'm going to switch to using a random
unilateral here and I'm going to say x
tau 32 right
so basically we're gonna take a value
from 0 to 2 pi and we're gonna produce
that angle right then instead of normal
being this what I'm actually going to do
is say it's going to be cosine of the
angle sine of the angle and then I'm
going to compile right
so that will should in theory anyway
produce 16 points that are randomly
dispute over the Hemisphere in exactly
the same way we were doing it before
right so no nothing else happening here
so there's our 16 points and you know
there they are on the hemisphere as we
would expect and again that's just
changing this into polar coordinates now
so now we have our sort of angle normal
is a probably dumb thing to call this
because we sort of kept that because
we're you know using it the whole way
through but let's let's call this
something a little bit different or
maybe you know I'll start following this
here right so this is this is our angle
value which is this P or R oh I guess
that's the Greek symbol array for for
Rho naught P right this guy so anyway so
we could make it like so and right now
we're just computing that as a random
unilateral but then we will introduce
the spiral in a second there so we've
got the Rho then we've got this this ti
here that value is again kind of
computed off of this so we really want
to start with this value first
so our Z value in this case is and this
Z value will get plugged straight in as
Z I believe but we want this to be 1
over 1 minus 1 over n here like so and
then that's going to multiply
one minus two times I oops and we're
probably have to make that be a float
here right because it's going to be I is
going to be an integer and we want to be
doing these with splitting put
calculations and then we're going to
divide that here by n minus one
and there's the complete equation so we
know that that's the equation for
producing the Z value let's go ahead and
divide that up yeah believe that's right
yeah so then when we want to produce TI
it's fairly straightforward right it's
just going to be the square root of one
minus whatever that value is squared and
again that's not actually T I guess is
that tau these are tiny little letters
yes that's tau so this is actually our
tau value I guess technically that means
this is Zeta right if we're really going
for it nope it's not that's an actual Z
all right so now we've lined ourselves
up with there now McClay Chur which is
good all right so this is going to be
your square root here and it's really
just square root of 1 minus whatever
that value is squared right so that's
pretty straightforward as well so again
this is the the the equations for
setting up the spiral sampling and
presumably here you know if we want to
kind of work this through a little bit
more carefully what's happening here is
just that this is producing you know we
know that this is
the angle so that's just telling us what
direction we're gonna go out so here
we're gonna say how high we are and so
all this is doing is saying well if for
that high here's how far out along the
thing we have to go right so really all
of the complexity here of producing the
spiral has been baked into the height
value right and if we want to we can
probably reverse engineer exactly how
that works too right because we know
that it's supposed to be sort of
producing a stepping around the sphere
right so if you wanted to get a little
bit more fancy you could figure out
exactly what we were doing here in terms
of why we picked these particular ratios
right but for now let's just continue on
with using the prescription for Vogel's
method which by the way
should be here it is
this is the actual method and
unfortunately looks like maybe I don't
know if this actual paper exists
anywhere in PDF form doesn't look like
it necessarily does there we go
so this is the actual paper this is why
they call it Vogel's method is because
Helmut - Vogel right I don't know how
perhaps that Vogel Helmut Vogel
I'm not sure my pronunciation of
European names is pretty poor so anyway
here is the actual paper that introduced
this method so this is probably actually
the correct place to go if you really
want to figure out exactly why the
spiral is computed exactly the way it is
now I don't really care why the spiral
is computed exactly the way it is
because again I'm not really looking at
this as an important feature I'm looking
at this more as like what distributions
that people come up with that are
interesting and Clement stretched this
one it seems interesting I don't really
need to be able to edit this or make
meaningful changes to it so I don't
really care exactly how it produces the
spiral other than in an academic sense
however again we may want to get a
little bit more into it later on in
which case we should decrypt these more
directly and probably read that paper so
taking another look once we have these
values here again this is not going to
produce spiral yet because this value
has not actually been computed properly
so we're gonna have to now actually make
this be our theta value which we haven't
determined what that actually is yet
times our I value like so and we'll have
to define what our theta is out here
right so then we also have our other
values like N and we have our I value
which is you know actually just this an
iterator here and we've got our N
which has to be the total number of
points in the system like so and so the
only thing we need to do now is actually
compute that theta value and then we've
got the full set that was requested here
so in terms of the theta value it looks
like the theta value is actually used
the same in this case so it's the golden
it's the golden angle here times the the
N so if we take a look at how that's
actually be computed this is the
discussion up here right the golden
angle pi times 3 minus root 5 it's
roughly equal to you know this value the
golden is the most irrational angle
defined as 2 pi you know whatever blah
blah blah blah right so what we want to
do here is just put in an approximation
for it cuz I guess we don't really care
to we don't need it to actually be truly
irrational in that sense so what we can
do here is actually just use it as it
appears right pi times 3 minus root 5
should be sufficient for 4 for us so
let's see here 3 minus root 5 so that
should produce the actual value that we
want in theta again we've got the the
number there the 16 which is how many
points we want to distribute and then
off we go now I assume
[Music]
it's kind of interesting right
we don't really modify this value so you
know no matter how many points you're
distributing the distribution comes
entirely in the later section you always
do the golden angle part here right
which is pretty bizarre but that's just
you know that's actually the way there's
this little thing Oh
syntax highlighter so that's pretty
interesting right that's that I think
that's pretty interesting
so anyway again if we take a look at
just how this is computed right we don't
I guess I'm not sure exactly what this
is meant to accomplish here but you know
you can see a range N
I assume this is just saying we're gonna
do this over a number of points so I'm
assuming that's still just i but yeah
point being it's interesting to note
that this angle remains the same no
matter what n is because normally in
most distributions you would alter the
theta based on the n but here we don't
we only alter the placement where how
far out we place it we don't alter how
much we rotate each time which is kind
of an interesting if that's really the
way these work it's an interesting
observation right about how those angles
are behaving okay so now if we want to
actually produce the normal well at this
point we've pretty much got the
information that we need so we can
actually stuff these directly if we want
to we know the angle that we're talking
about here and we know how far out we
want to go so we really can dispense
with all of the rest of the stuff
because we've already computed it all
and just directly computer normal out of
thin air right so using the values
prescribed by the by Vogel spiral
formula we can compute those values and
then we can see how they are arranged
and if you look at them actually there
they are quite nice right those are very
nicely evenly distributed over the
sphere and in fact if we were to to
ratchet this up to the full 64 and take
a look at what that looks like
that is a really nice covering right it
looks lovely
now some things I would observe about
that is it's for a sphere so we do have
a bit of a problem that the formula as
written is giving us miracle data not
hemispherical data right so we don't
really want the formula to behave the
way the formula is normally behaving so
the N value that's used in here is not
really the N value that we want what we
rather want here is double the N value
right and the reason that we want that
is because we want the end to stop at
the hemisphere not the sphere so if we
take a look at what would happen for
example here if I multiply that value by
2 so that we only go run up to half of
it then we get the hemisphere that we
wanted without going without completing
the sphere towards the bottom which is
important right we don't want to have
any points go go to to the downward
facing hemisphere because we're only
currently sampling out away from the
surface not back in to the interior of
the surface if we were doing subsurface
scattering we would want that right but
we don't so there's the distribution of
points prescribed both the spiral as
suggested by Columbian and discovered by
Vogel in the 1970s and I agree that's a
pretty nice start right I think that's
pretty great now again if we go back to
looking at what we actually have to work
with in terms of points here it's
actually it's just makeup and we
actually only have 16 points to work
with here and so if we look at how those
are distributed those 16 points like
this we could imagine taking those 16
points and kind of fanning them out
differently right so for each of those
if we did do a sub in next year and we
wanted to add random jitter to it we
could add random jitter by randomly
jittering the the row and the theta
right or the Z in this case
so what I could do here is take this and
introduce a random bilateral and what we
want to do here is add just a little bit
of jitter so you know we don't really
know how much jitter we want to add
because it's a pretty tough call in this
case we know we're rearranging up to tau
this is an angle right so it's
proportional to tau in terms of how
large it is so this would be you know
[Music]
that would be one tenth of the angle
could vary this would be one sixth of
one tenth of the angle that could vary
right this would be a hundredth of an
angle and so on so I don't know exactly
how much we want to vary it there this
is a height so it ranges from zero to
one in this case so again we probably
want this to be varying a little bit
less than that but exactly what we want
we don't really know let's go ahead and
try those here and so now we would have
actual random coverage around each point
and we can kind of see how that is right
and so those are not spread out nearly
enough as what we would probably want in
terms of getting sample coverage there
so let's go ahead and boost those up a
bit just to kind of spread the mount
more there you can see them spreading
out but again still not really spread
again also now that we've done this we
need to normalize this again in fact you
know what we can do is just just move
this down so that old should we
normalize it for us I believe although
it might not because of the way we're
doing row but it probably should right
yeah so there we go
so you know one of the problems though
that you can see is this ends up getting
back into sort of a more clumpy sort of
problem there right so again we may just
want to keep with the uniform sampling I
don't know it's hard to say but we may
want to keep with the uniform sampling
and then group back together
to produce something more stable I don't
know but it does seem like you know also
one of the things here is we probably
want the angle to vary more at the
bottom than at the top right
so as the eye kind of gets gets further
out you know it's probably something
more like well you know ft 2i over f/32
and times this random or whatever
something more like this so that the
variance in terms of the values
increases as you go right just taking a
look here so let's go ahead and make
those values get a little larger there
and I'm also going to now take the
training wheels off and allow this to
vary so we can kind of see how the
hemisphere is being sampled right so you
can see that this point gets no spread
and the reason that that point gets no
spread is because of this value here so
you know technically we would probably
have to do something where we do an I
plus 1 here just to make sure that you
know the ratio doesn't collapse at the
very top and that way this one can get
some motion as well but again it's you
know it's not fabulous and you can see
also since it can't really rotate itself
in terms of the way it's doing the
displacement the other equation you
don't get good sort of fan out there
either but either or like even just at
this point it's already you know
arguably better than what we were doing
before so that's kind of nice but we
still have a long way to go so I don't
really like the random jitter much to be
honest I think this is kind of better
the question is what can we do here one
thing I'm curious about is let's suppose
we just offset our room
right like we just spun our angle by a
random amount so let's suppose that our
row is just offset is the only thing
that we offset and we offset the row by
whatever we want so it's just tau times
a random unilateral that's that's the
thing so we're just rotating this
randomly what kind of coverage does that
give us right and if you look it's
pretty good right I mean that's looking
pretty good in terms of coverage there
you know I'm saying and if we so if we
were to do 64 samples this way I think
that would be pretty interesting the
problem is again the coherence of those
samples isn't great right so let's let's
go back to pausing this thing for a
second and just talk about what I mean
so here is oh that's wait a second
that's not what I wanted no wonder it
looked it looks better than it should
have looked that's not what I wanted
what I wanted was this
I wanted to pick one random value and
just jitter the sphere around right so
it should look like that always right
but then I wanted to jitter it around
so how's that coverage seems alright
let's accumulate that coverage so let's
see how we do if we were to say you know
let me give ourselves a little more
Headroom here will this blow us up no
that's just fine so what I can do here
is say all right yeah let's let's go
ahead and stage make this stationary but
then what I'm going to do is I'm going
to run this multiple times you know what
and all I really needed to do was this I
suppose
so let's do this 16 times actually 10
times is probably better because I think
our blend rate is like 0.1 or something
like that it might actually you know it
might be 20 so it might be over 20
frames is our average so let's just see
over 20 frames what it will sample right
so you know it's not awful but you can
see that you do get a little bit of a
regular pattern happening here because
you just can't seem to hit a bunch of
these points you know we may also want
to say well you know this this right
here this is the step function so we may
want to do something like this and I
don't know if that'll improve it at all
but probably not
interesting am i doing something weird
here
so I think you know maybe the better
thing to jitter would be to jitter the
actual I value because if we jitter to
the actual I value then we would get we
would move along the spiral which would
give us better coverage right so this is
probably a bad way to do it what we
probably want to do is maybe this what
do you think about this so as we move
through
oh and also we're not actually tracking
this properly because if we actually do
the sub index here the I values are not
yeah are not accurate here so if we
actually want to do this maybe this is
the better way gosh it's really tough to
think about all right so let's
restructure this loop a little bit here
because I wasn't doing it fairly there
because I wasn't updating the eye
properly so let's back up a second
rather than trying to be clever like I
was doing before let's forget about the
fact that we need to bundle these for
ray tracing let's just take a look at
the thing as how the distribution is and
then we'll try to back figure out what
to do about it right and you know what
let's take out these f/32 s because what
I can do here is just say hey these will
just be f/32 so here we go now we've got
I think the the fairer test of this
actual 64 rather than a 16 let's take a
look at that again now that I'm doing it
fairly so there's our 64 points right
and now what I'm going to do is I want
to jitter the I value so this value here
is what I want a jitter so I want to
take a random unilateral to push on to
that that'll basically offset us a
little bit
so here's now the coverage and you can
definitely see it kind of biases towards
the spiraling line right it can't seem
to get it doesn't jitter it's it's
displacement this way which I guess
makes sense right cuz it's just making a
spiral can we move this out of here it's
just making a spiral right it's just
doing that whoa what happened oh I I
moved the thing over to the stairs I
always forget that we do that weird
stare camera thing where are we what's
going on we got issues on this
so taking a look you know it's not the
worst distribution in the world but it's
not the best either it's got just this
heavy bias towards the Rings which you
would expect right that is act not
unusual but it does seem like maybe so
jittering the eye at least is not
exactly what we would want to do there
so I guess the next question is should
we do more of a traditional jitter on it
you know so we could try that
so instead of doing an eye offset value
let's try going back to the kind we were
doing before where we say produce the
stable spiral because this is kind of
what I'm hoping for
so now if I come in here what if we were
just to say normal equals mouths normal
so I just do exactly what we were doing
before and add pure pure just pure noise
into there and again I don't know how
much we want to separate those out
so that seems reasonable right because
those do seem to be growing in a in a
sensible way let's see if we can make
that work here's if there are three
times larger you know that's not bad
it's not perfect there's a fair bit of
nonsense happening there but it's not
horrible
you know that's it's pretty good
what's up the sample count a little more
you know it feels all right you know so
I think that's not that's not horrible
the other thing we want to do here is
remember our I values want to be denser
towards the top than towards the bottom
so if you look at it right now it's kind
of a uniform you know jitter in that
sense right
and you also kind of have this problem
where as the spiral winds down at the
end you kind of end up with some some
nonsense happening there I don't know if
we want to try and fix that either but I
so you know if we wanted to in here we
could make this I'd be more proportional
so the I value that comes through here
where we're getting an index from 0 to n
you know that maybe wants to be shifted
so it's proportional to the cosine right
so we kind of want that to be almost
inverted like so that the the value is
distributed opposite the sort of as it
folds down so what we could do here is
say well you know I don't know maybe we
square root this value or something so
that it shrinks it
it biases back and we can adjust it and
so on
but if you take a look at you know what
happens there and you know let me let me
remove the sampling the over sampling
value and just take a look at one what
you can see there is like hopefully we
could make this sort of shrink back up
to the top by by changing the increment
on I now part of the problem here is
that the theta value then becomes wrong
so it's kind of a little bit tricky to
know how we would adjust that sampling
to put more samples on the top than the
bottom because as you do this equation
doesn't really walk out along the spiral
per se what it does is it knows where it
should put a point for any given step
along the I so they're kind of jumping
around so when we change the stepping on
I you don't get an even distribution
anymore look that's not really very good
right although maybe you know well here
let's find out what happens yeah like
you can see what ends up happening right
as if you adulterer those values you get
something very different so that's a
little bit harder
so I'm not really sure how we would want
to address that I guess one thing we
could do is play with this value as well
but yeah I mean I feel like we'd have a
hard time I don't know I feel like we'd
have a hard time concentrating our
values based on cosine theta unless I'm
missing something obvious I'm not seeing
it now granted I'm not familiar with
these distributions so you know maybe
maybe there is an obvious way we could
do it but I don't know so I may say what
if we just created a pattern that
actually has the properties that we want
directly because we could always reuse
it right so let's just let's think about
that and and see if maybe there's a way
we can sort of say hey let's try
something a little bit different so
let's suppose we went in here and and
you know I keep this guy so it's you
know still there but I'm gonna go ahead
and
make another one here so let's suppose
we did something where we said let's
generate the points that we actually
want so here's the points and we know we
want you know 16 of them or something or
maybe we want 64 of them to start with
right and I'm gonna keep the point count
and then what I'm gonna do is I'm just
gonna say like alright while the point
count is less than the array account
points again the super slow
just doing super super slow I'm gonna go
ahead and draw these in them separate
pass so while I don't have enough points
I'm going to make a new point or just
you know a new point on the hemisphere
and I'm just gonna do that
100% random right so I don't even care
do not care anything about this thing
don't matter what the distribution is it
can be anything at all the only thing
I'm going to do is make sure that it's
only pointing upward because we're not
actually making a sphere we're making a
hemisphere right so that's it so just
purely whatever doesn't matter
scattered white noise not even uniform
white noise for that matter because I'm
not even doing a cube and then just
projecting it onto a sphere so just a
complete crap distribution and that's
fine then what I'm going to do is gonna
say alright let's just figure out how
close we are to any other point right so
I'm gonna say you know I'm assuming
actually missing this points valid if
the point is valid then I'm gonna say
points point count plus plus
oops plus equals point count sorry
equals P and that's going to retire a
point on to our sphere so what I'm gonna
do for test index is say well if the
points testing this value so one of the
ones we've already added if the length
squared of the distance between me and
one of the test points is less than the
minimum distance then it's over so you
know they have to be that close or
something I don't know right so this is
just going to put random points on the
sphere and guarantee that no two points
are too close together based on this
value that we set so that will give us
64 of randomly generated points off we
go then I'm just going to draw them
and that's it
all right so this is just an exercise of
placing random points on a sphere and
then discarding points that I don't want
until we get a uniform coverage now the
key to getting the uniform coverage is
to make sure that the point repulsion
value there that minimum distance is
sufficient so I'm gonna go ahead and
adjust that value now basically until
our routine crashes and that sounds
weird but that's what I'm actually gonna
do so you notice that gets a lot more
random let's go one more time
see you a routine crash because now it
can't possibly do it right we've we've
done it in an effectively impossible
task so we know that our answer is
somewhere like this
so there's our lovely uniform we cover
its fear and it's quite nice as you can
see right it's pretty lovely and off you
go now the reason I want to try it this
way is because now what we can do is
adjust the minimum distance for example
based on where the point ends up height
wise so that things down towards the
bottom of the sphere are spaced further
than things up towards the top of the
sphere and so what we can do is say
something like you know this men
distance squared equals whatever our
normal minimum distance squared would be
times one minus the Z value so that
basically as we get higher up we are
allowed to be closer right and so you
know this is probably not that's
probably more like 1.5 so you know how
close we well how much bias do we want
there I don't know but this way we can
say all right you're allowed to clump
pretty tightly at the top you're not
allowed don't ask me why I said minimum
sometimes and min other times I don't
know there we go
and so now we should be able to sort of
adjust those values accordingly to make
our points cluster more towards the top
than the bottom so let's go ahead and
try adjusting those values towards
something we want so you can kind of see
us starting to get that clumpiness that
I wanted right and I don't know we may
want this to be a higher powered value
too
right like you may want this value to
get squared or square rooted I think in
this case since the higher the value the
more it subtracts out we would want to
square root the value right to make it
clumpy er I believe don't quote me on
that you're wrong about that
now I'm pretty sure it should be square
root right although actually I suppose
if we're this is supposed to be
proportional to the cosine weighting so
there should be cosine less samples at
the bottom so in some sense I guess what
we really want to do is shove this
through a cosine right so what we'd
really like to do is say okay cosine
so the cosine at 0 is 1 and the cosine
at 1 is 0 so we really want that right I
think oh wait no that's wrong
that's not quite right since it's an
angle we need 0 to PI over 2 right so if
Z is 0 then we will we will want the
full minimum distance so we will plug in
0 if Z is 1 so it's pointing strict
straight up then we will have it return
1 I'm sorry it will return 0 so you will
use no minimum distance things can be as
close as you want that I think is
correct in terms of allowing clumping
right so now in theory if we increase
that clumping value I think that should
do it
but don't quote me on that but I think
we should be able to clump more towards
the top hopefully so there's a nicely
clumped distribution right that falls
off quite a bit as it goes now I don't
know if we really want it to fall off by
that much you know like maybe that's too
much and so we may still want to bias
that coverage value a little bit so we
may want to say like look we need a
little bit of separation
so we're gonna always use a little bit
of the minimum distance right sort of as
we go and it will go up from there so
then this has to be knocked back down
again and we have to again find that
value so this force is a little more
repulsion at the top again and now we'll
see as we concentrate those points a
little bit more so it can't quite find
them so it's again something like this
uh so there's our clumping that's a
little bit tighter now right and off we
go so let's try repeating this process
doing the whole sample count thing to do
this 20 times so that will actually see
how our Gajic it is basically so in here
I'm gonna go ahead and initialize that
Hemi Sirius on the outside of this so
now this little buck wiggle around right
and that's what our coverage would look
like over some number of frames you know
so so there we go
and on any given frame you know we know
that it looks like that
so there's one option and that seems to
be a pretty good way to start right I
don't know to what extent we could
really do this
so because we now have to produce
bundles of points right so we could
bundle these points up now but then we
kind of end up with this problem again
of how do we deal with the this sort of
spread on the points and that's a good
question so we kind of got to think
about this a little bit and if we if we
were to reduce this point count to 16
and assume that each of the points was
going to get four random fan outs
happening with it what would our values
be then right
you know that's that's what 16 looks
like
now it's worth noting that distance wise
we're not using a particularly good
measure for distance because we're using
the Euclidean measure for distance which
will change quite a bit so and just to
give you a little bit of understanding
of what I mean by that so if you take a
look at how the distance value is
interpreted there what we're talking
about here is a hemisphere so if we take
two points on the hemisphere I'm just
taking the distance between them like
that which means that if you were to
look at a cross-section of the arc that
kind of contains them I'm looking at
that distance but what we really would
probably like to look at is this right
how how much angle is between them and
that may sound like fairly complicated
but it's really not because remember we
know that if we have two normal right so
if I have a and B and I know that the
length of a is one and I know that the
length of B is also one then a transpose
B is going to be length of a length of B
cosine theta which means that since
these are both 1 I know that a transpose
B is actually just equal to cosine theta
so I can measure the angle between them
very reliably by just looking at the
cosine right I know that cosine theta
will give me exactly
well done exactly what I want and
furthermore if I took the eCos right I
would know exactly what the angle was to
so I can basically pick a minimum angle
if I want to write and use that minimum
angle instead as the comparison function
and that gives me a better a more stable
way to compare the disks between the
points if I want to now it doesn't
really matter but it's worth noting
right that that's something we can do
and since we're gonna do this in a pre
process anyway because it's a slow
process we can trivially do that and
just it makes it clearer what's actually
happening right so what we can do is say
here there's a min cosine value and
that's gonna be the cosine of whatever
the angle is that we think is the
minimum so you know we don't know what
that value is but whatever the angle
minimum happens to be that's what it is
right and then we have when we go to do
our this minimum distance squared
sort of situation that's gonna become
this min cosine and the exact same thing
will happen here but we just adjust the
minimum cosine instead based on where
you are on the actual sphere then when
you come here what we're actually gonna
say is yeah and not that at all
what we're gonna do is the inner product
of these two points and we want to make
sure that that inner product is going to
be less than whatever our minimum is
right so whatever that cosine value is
we want to make sure that it is less now
since we know that these have to be
acute angles we're not letting angles go
past 90 degrees we don't care about
negatives here so we also want to
probably make sure that we didn't get a
angel' that's large enough in that sense
so what we need to actually do is change
the way that this is phrased to saying
we want to be above a minimum cosine now
why is that the case well that's the
case because as things get closer
together their cosine gets closer to one
right so we're actually looking to
maintain things that are wait no let me
say that one more time I may still be
correct
as things get closer together angle lies
there value gets closer to one and we
want to throw those out right so what we
want to look at is we want yeah now I am
correct so we want to look at things
that get above a certain amount right so
we want to look to see is this too high
and so we probably want to phrase this
and say that there's a maximum cosine
value you can have because it's not
really a minimum it's a maximum cosine
value you can have right which means
that this has to be phrased in a
different way this is not actually
correct anymore right
and so the maximum cosine value here
although we do have sort of our
adjustment value which is fine
we need to phrase this a little bit
differently because in this case what we
would rather do is we want that maximum
cosine to get higher not lower right we
want to get higher as we go up the this
fear right so the maximum cosine is
going to be rather inverted from where
it would have been so instead we're
gonna be doing something like you know
1.0 F it's minus the C value so in this
case right what we're doing is saying
alright look if the C value is like zero
okay so we're pointing like straight up
right is that right no peasy would be
one and so that's gonna be the full
angle so that would be zero right our
cosine would our cosine value of
pointing straight up would be zero we
want to use the the fullest possible
maximum so we get the full range as it
comes down right and we are plugging in
a zero there which will give us out a
cosine of one we therefore want to force
very wide angles at that point right so
maybe not 1.0 like still again maybe we
give it that Headroom or something there
but something like that it gets it's
gonna be closer right so then we just
say all right look if you dock in there
and you end up with more than the
maximum you know you're invalid and
we're gonna throw you out otherwise we
will keep you and it's good right so
let's go ahead and take a look in here
and start updating that constant value
and again this is the exact same process
we did before nothing mysterious they're
just using a different error metric for
how or a different distance metric for
how close these points are which should
give a slightly fairer results again
I don't know that it will necessarily
matter in practice it's just sort of a
using the truer measure the one that
would be more is more logical for our
situation so that we can you know just
have a cleaner result there I think all
right so there we go there's our
distribution of points again pretty even
on the sphere and this time based on
angle I want to sort of be able to clump
those towards the top more and I don't
feel like I'm getting enough of that at
the moment so I don't know if maybe we
need this to kind of drop down a little
bit oh that's because I wasn't using it
all right so now let's try to spread
these out a little more again we want to
keep clumping at the top as necessary
this doesn't seem to be producing much
repulsion here so clearly this is not
falling off the way that I think it
should be or something well okay so this
would do a cosine squared fall-off so I
guess technically what we really want to
do is this right so we actually want the
cosine value probably to be put in here
so that the maximum cosine as the Z
value yeah so you know this Z value
right let's talk about this for a second
so this Z value is gonna go I guess I'll
be at that in there this view here will
now go from 0 to 1/2 pi so the cosine
value will go all the way up to 1 as the
I'm sorry will go all the way to 0 as
the Z value gets to 1 and it will be
when the Z value is actually 0 so it's
down at the bottom it will actually be 0
so the maximum cosine is any thing with
90 degrees right so we can kind of
adjust this now by saying you know
whatever this value is that we put in
here maybe we don't we probably don't
want it to quite be that aggressive in
terms of what we plug in angle wise so
let's say we have a minimum angle that
we want to have happen there right so
let's say we want a minimum angle of 0.1
radians oh well that's not 0.1 radians
sorry Oh point 1 pi radians and then we
want to use the 0.4 as the rest of our
sign range right and that's how we're
gonna set up our angle you know it based
distribution there so let's play around
with this a little bit and see if that
maybe gets us more what we were looking
for so am I going the right way there I
just want to make sure before I start
trying to tune this and they're going
right over there
again as Z gets larger
we want our cosine value to get smaller
and that yet and so that's not gonna
happen right cuz we want as we want if
this is 0 we want the output to be close
to zero right so we actually want that
to be minus we have that going the
opposite direction all right so let's
take a look and maybe that's too much
right in terms of of max cosines there
so we may want the thing to never quite
get there right we may want something
more like this
it's still not quite right so yeah we
could say that what am I doing wrong
here feel like this should be okay right
because the maximum cosine value here
you know as we want it to be close to
zero right I mean if we put cosine zero
in the mat cosine would be 1 and nothing
would be over it right I mean let's
suppose we just do this no waiting at
all so that angle still too large
apparently
and that angle isn't so that angle is
supposedly our our neutral angle right
like that's close enough so now if we
actually went in here and said well okay
as you get closer to the top
you should get even lower this should
definitely work because now you have
even more room virtual room to place
these points right at least I would
think so
so I should be able to increase this
value
so it still feels like I should be able
to go a little bit more than that in
terms of repulsion I also think actually
clumping wise I'm you know let me
actually
so that's starting to look pretty good
so three nice two did not work right
that was crashy yeah should write a
little program that just finds out it's
just like for any given value figures
out where the crash point is
2.8
so I also want to try upping the sample
count here so I can see what happens
over several frames like what we end up
with
and I'm not really sure why we are
getting that kind of somewhat clumping
behavior there I don't know if that's
somehow related to the way we're doing
the randomness or if our random number
generator because it's an XOR shift just
isn't good enough that I really just
don't know so it's kind of difficult to
say what should be happening there right
[Music]
but it feels a little off if we do an
aggressive over sampling so much more so
than we would expect in practice how
does that look does it still have them I
mean it's tough to say because it's one
of those things where you're like maybe
that's correct it's really hard to say
it may actually be though that you know
the XOR shift really does want to be
modified because the XOR shift may have
problems with successive values not
producing good pairwise values so we may
want to look at that a little more
carefully right because that could be
affecting us there
yeah it's hard to say so anyway what we
could do now is take a look at what
would happen sample wise if we did
something slightly different which is to
say we could say let's keep the sample
count here as one and then instead what
we'll do here is we'll do 20 samples of
the samples we have with a displacement
so we'll say that the normal equals
normalizer zero of the points point
index and for each one of those points
will do a displacement actually you know
what I I'm just gonna do this way
so if we take a look at this
displacement based method here so we'll
say all right let's suppose that for
each of these points let's suppose that
we did a random displacement around the
points each time and draw what that
looks like and furthermore we can do 20
times 4 cuz that's roughly how many
samples we'll take 4 per you know every
ray will be a bundle of 4 and we'll do
it over 20 frames it's kind of what we
were doing before what would that look
like
if we put a little bit in there oh you
know what that's way too much randomness
though I don't want it that random so
here's what that would look like and
again you can see sort of the random
patches spreading out a little bit there
and so if I go ahead and make those
random patch spreads be you know a
little bit wider you can see that it's
actually relatively good in terms of
coverage there it's not too bad but you
know yeah it could it be better probably
what we could also look at here is this
spread wants to be based on the Z to a
certain extent so we want to you know do
something probably more like this
where we have some current sort of
minimum displacements and then we're
gonna get some amount of displacement
from the sea so that things on top which
are supposed to be clustered closer
together anyway get less randomness
added to the you know less spread to
their samples than ones that are further
down which you know maybe have to get
more so as the Z gets lower we want more
I guess that actually means we want this
kind of a thing right so we get the
maximum when Z is lowest and the minimum
when Z is highest so something like that
not sure exactly how much you know that
should factor in but something like this
seems not too too horrible and if we
take a look at one of these again just
so I can understand what would happen if
whoops - just one of them you know how
bad is it we want to make sure that it's
still fairly uniform for any given one
so actually that's I guess that's four
and so that that really doesn't help us
much with the uniformity if we do it
that way you know so I kind of think
we're I kind of think it may be a losing
battle to do it that way I think we're
gonna have to distribute the 64 points
as 64 points and go from there which is
not fabulous but I think that's what
we're gonna have to do and then we'll
just have to figure out a way to
randomize those much more tightly or you
know jitter them much more slightly than
we were I'm not sure but doesn't look
good for doing him in in sort of a 16
than random 4 way which is what we would
have liked but it doesn't look likely
okay so let's take a look here we need
to adjust this then for doing a full 64
point distribution because this is going
to be too much spread for these so
generally speaking we need a wider angle
we need to make max cosine be a lower
value so the the value inside has to go
up right we have to get the these this
value to be you know higher than it
should be right or I should say higher
than it then it
sorry this values to be lower so the max
cosine will be higher right so you know
this this has to get knocked down I'm
not sure to where exactly but you know
it has to be knocked down significantly
so we can just do a quick test to see
all right so there's 64 points repulsion
wise let's go ahead and knock this value
down a little
OOP that's nope not what we wanted
that's what I meant
and maybe we can go ahead and knock this
value up slightly
all right so let's take a look at this
distribution see every think of it
so that does look pretty nice you know
I think I think I'd be happy with that
yeah and that seems pretty good so what
we could do next time is we could then
try to bundle these into into ray
bundles that make sense right so you
know try to cast like those four
together and those four together
whatever those four right try to produce
segments on this that are you know as
closely you know as compact as possible
to maximize the chances that they
Traverse and hit the same things so
let's go ahead to a quick Q&amp;A and then
we'll finish up that because that's
about all the time we have for today
what do you think about a compile-time
switch to flip between pseudo-rng and
senator Angie to see if it's an iron G
issue I'm sorry I what's a what's a
standard RNG I'm not sure I know what a
standard orangy is
Nixie why can't we use the spiral method
to generate 64 points that we group into
16 groups of four based on direction and
then rotate the spiral 18 degrees over
20 frames to samples the reason is
because that won't cover the hemisphere
like remember how it it produces sort of
steps along and if we rotate them it
will just produce slices like us like a
peeled orange so we need ways of
displacing our points laterally as well
and I'm not sure exactly how we want to
do that yet
but we definitely need jittering more
than just rotation we need to jitter
vertically as well if that makes sense
what about a pre computed sample sphere
that you rotate over the frame period
instead of random Jerry jittery
so again rotation doesn't help us
the problem with rotation is that we
need to rotate on all axes and then a
part of our hemisphere would kind of dip
away right so remember let's say you
take a look at a particular cross
section of your sphere right and you've
got points here here and here
right well rotation does give you the
coverage this way but it gives you no
more coverage this way so if there was
no point in this region anywhere in the
ring on your initial random distribution
rotating it won't cover it right so you
need ways of of doing lateral
displacement as well and so we need our
scheme to have lateral displacement as
well does that make sense
and that's true for the spiral as well
the spiral will never give us what we
actually want unless we jitter the
spirals yeah I mean the spiral is a hard
distribution to think about I feel like
it's kind of not one I really want to
use largely because I feel like it would
take a while for us to intuit it now if
we actually sat down and really studied
it then I think we could play with the
formula and make it work but I'm just
not sure about that off-axis rotation
will cause our points to dip below the
hemisphere so one of the problems is we
need it to never be in the bottom
hemisphere if we do an off axis rotation
some of the points that we're low will
cross into here and that's unacceptable
we definitely can't have that because
then we're casting backwards into the
interior of a volume which we really
don't want to do
hopefully that makes sense so yeah you
know I don't know that we maybe the
right answer is to kind of like maybe
the right answer is to study this the
spiral formula and making a new adapted
formula that's basically the same as the
spiral formula that allows us to produce
randomly spaced points in a specific way
that we want that allows the for the
jitter but I don't know
I mean yet another way to do it would be
to just produce quadrant based stuff
where we just divide the sphere up into
64 slices that we then randomly pick one
point inside right
and that might be good right best allies
the CRTs random number generator is
complete garbage so you wouldn't compare
against that one if you were you'd have
to go get we'd have to maybe implement
one of the PC R G's like from O'Neill's
paper or something because the see
random the C runtime numbers R and our
dinner is like the worst one ever
those are linear congruential generators
which are complete garbage right in fact
I can show you like X or shift is better
than the C runtime libraries one if that
makes sense
where is that this is not what I want
that is not what I want at all no false
incorrect
this is so annoying
this right
no still not right
there yeah that's what I actually wanted
and now so let's see if we can get it
Rand in here
[Music]
come on it's got to be around in here
somewhere folks
you know what forget it
okay are we ever going to actually
so I think this is it
maybe not how is this the is this really
ran this is nuts
this looks more like it there's the mall
there's the ad there's the shift
well I wanted to show you the source
code to it but unfortunately all I would
be able to trace the assembly but it's
just a that's all it is it's a multiply
and add in a shift for a linear
congruential generator so that was the
code right there for it and so it's not
like some good random number generator I
it's just this
right
that's all it is
and you don't need to do the modulus
because if you're just using the entire
number range this this is what you do
afterwards to produce a particular
random between some number and some
other number
so it's just this right and then the you
know the well I guess this is probably
the shift right if you're doing one
that's just used as a power of two then
it's just a shift right unfortunately we
don't have the source code to the MSB
CRT to show you that that's just what
it's doing but that's what the you know
that's what it was right
long believes this intended as a
pre-press a stepper all these
hemispheres your computer for every quad
every frame I'll probably a combination
of two steps a pre-computation step and
then a per quad step and so we have to
keep the per quad part simple but the
pre process step can be as complicated
as we want really could anything be done
with a centroidal Voronoi tessellation
covering the sphere is that too
expensive is a terrible idea I know
that's sort of what we're talking about
like once I've produced these points on
the sphere you know maybe we produce
regions that are sort of like a Voronoi
region for each one of them and we
randomized in between those right so we
I don't know we'll see could we get a
relatively performant blue noise yes you
can do a relatively performant blue
noise I'm doing the simplest way of
producing blue noise but there's a lot
of ways you can do it faster you still
wouldn't want to do it for every quad no
matter what you do but you can do it
much faster than what I'm doing in fact
I even have a thing I talked about that
on my blog in fact when I was talking
about the witnesses grass sampling thing
so I think gets in here
yeah so here is you know the way that
we're doing it in him adhere right now
is this graph and this is the the graph
of it's the same as this graph in this
graph are the same it's just a scaled
version that includes the highest point
right and so here I talk about how you
get rid of that here's the graph of you
know if you if you write the algorithm
properly of how many test points you
need four point inserted then you can
read about that here so it's a slog
entry number ten so all right I'm gonna
wrap things up
thank you for joining me for those sort
of handmade hero so I'm pepper coating
with you as always next weekend well I
guess we won't have to replace cosine
and sine just yet because we still have
more stuff we can try just in terms of
getting our Hemisphere sampling the way
we want it so maybe next weekend won't
have to happen but you know as you can
see we've got cut sine and cosine in
there now we don't know how much more
we'll have to do with it but you know
we're definitely getting to the point
where we want to replace it anyways
because it's you know it's happening
it's being used for real in the code
base now
so we want to get rid of the C runtime
library and that's something that's on
the hopper
but we can do more because we're only
using the pre-computation step now so we
don't really care how fast it is and
maybe we end up only using it the
pre-computation step in case we in which
case we really don't care how fast it is
and it won't force the issue
but either way we've got at least one
more weekend we can do without having to
replace it so next weekend we'll play
around the sampling a little bit more I
hope to see you back here for that until
then if you want to follow along with
source code you can always pre-order the
game on hand made here at organic comes
the source code so you can play around
through OMS your sampling and see if you
can come up with a good hemisphere to
sample for our lighting purposes that's
about it for today hope see you back
here next week
until then have fun programming and I'll
see everyone on the Internet take it
easy everybody