hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero this is the show where we code a
complete game live on stream although
today what we're actually coding is the
thing that will produce font bitmaps for
our game so technically it's not in the
game it's little offline utility to
shove fonts into bitmaps so that we
don't have to do it ourselves I mean I
guess technically we're doing it
ourselves because we're writing the
utility but you get the idea so the the
point here is pretty basic it's just to
say that look we need fonts in the game
we want to be able to have those fonts
edited in a normal font editing package
so that either we can just take free
fonts that we want or purchase a font
from a font foundry that's been made by
a professional font designer and then
turn it into art assets we can use in
the game or we would like to be able to
make our own fonts in a font creation
utility but either or we want to
leverage that existing technology and
not have to make like our own font
editors or force our artists to create
some heinous list of font text markup
something for kerning who knows what
right we want to use the existing tools
so what we need to be able to do is take
a TTF file or an O TF file and turn it
into a series of bitmaps automatically
and remember all the kerning information
that goes with it so the goal of this
font utility is just to take that
information dump it out so that it can
then be loaded on demand as any other
art asset would and packed into hh8
files as necessary as any other art
asset would and that is our goal so if
we go ahead and load up where we were
because we actually did a bunch of this
work last weekend I think we took a day
to do it or two days to do it I remember
how long we've worked on this it was
either one or two days but point being
if we go look at where we were at I
think we got right to the point where
we're just sort of did the flow of the
code and you can see this utility here
it's pretty tiny right and then probably
I'm hoping it won't be too bad
because there's not that much stuff that
it needs to do but if you run it on the
command line you can see that we've
we've gotten the basics started it it
lists how it's used you run the HH font
utility and then you say which TTF file
you want what the font name was inside
that TTF file because I think TDF files
can can even potentially hold more than
one but either way we kind of have to do
that because windows doesn't really let
us figure out what the fonts are and at
ETF I don't think we have to basically
say load this TTFN and then query a font
by name out of the system we can then go
to the next frame which is pixel height
which says okay how big did you want to
generate this font because obviously TTF
file store vector fonts so they're not
at a particular pixel height most of the
time right you can't store bitmap fonts
but nobody does anymore and then finally
we have the care set and that's just a
thing that we have defined ourselves and
what that is is that's a keyword and you
can see it listed here test is the one
we have defined so far and what that is
is says which characters to extract out
of the font because remember depending
on who's using this and we're let's say
that a Chinese person wants to extract a
font for Cantonese or Mandarin or
something right or I don't know maybe
simplified Chinese is the thing that
everyone standardized on now right but
point being they want to extract those
glyphs
now those glyphs are a different set of
code points than the glyphs you would
extract if you were say German and
wanted all of the German glyphs out of a
font right and those would be you know
the standard characters that we use in
English and then also some of the you
know diacritical marks and things that
are you know accents and things like
that that German has that we don't for
example in English so you need a way of
extending the font utility to say what
ranges from a font you want to extract
and that's what that keyword does at the
start we're just gonna support English
because that's the only language I
really know my Japanese is terrible
and my French
is you know also terrible probably not
as terrible as my Japanese and so I'm
not gonna try to do any foreign language
support beyond simply making sure there
are font system supports for people who
do want to do it and then we can you
know move on from there knowing that
when the time comes if we want to
localize handmade hero into some other
language we haven't shot ourselves in
the foot by hard coding our entire
system to only extract one language as
fonts whichever whatever those you know
might be so that's the goal there is to
make it extensible so that as you want
to localize things from country to
country you can easily extend the set of
glyphs that are extracted from a font
pretty trivially so that's what we're
trying to do here and furthermore we can
use different fonts so you know it's
highly likely that the font that we use
for English language wouldn't
necessarily be the same font that we
might want to use for Japanese language
and so on because we probably will find
you know certain fonts are better for
certain languages because the person who
made that font was make was targeting a
particular language for it right and
this is especially true of other things
you know I mean most fonts for example
that are made to be english-language
fonts probably don't have any glyphs at
all for Thailand you know for Thai
language or you know like let's say
glyphs for Vietnamese or Korean right
they're not going to go out of their way
to create characters for languages that
they weren't targeting cuz they probably
don't even know how to read those
languages or what would make a good font
so you probably have to pick different
fonts for different languages if you
want high quality glyphs there are some
fonts out there that are designed to
support all languages but those might
not be the style that you want right so
you kind of need to be able to go and
pick different fonts for different
languages and you don't want your system
you can strain such that it has to use
just one font and that has to cover all
the languages because that may limit
your options for creating richly styled
fonts in various languages or you know
the people who try to read you know your
game in Farsi or something or like this
font looks terrible and you'd want to be
able to fix that but you can't because
you
only use one language one font for all
languages so you got to keep it to like
the few fonts actually support them all
at Sarah Ted etc right so the goal here
is to allow that to be flexible so that
basically as we want to localize the
game should that occur we can make
intelligent decisions based on feedback
from people who are actually native
speakers to that language and if they
say you know this font looks a lot
better we can use that font for their
language and some other font for someone
else's language without having to make
that trade-off of well it gets worse for
one better for the other bla bla bla
right so that's the idea there and let's
go ahead and see where we're at so if
you look at what's going on in this
utility what's happening is when you
pass all those things we first run that
care set like we made it easy to add
those care sets we run those that care
set code which basically says look
putting these ranges of characters you
can see here we include the space
character we include the full set of
typical ASCII right and then we also
added some special code points these
code points are for the kanji characters
for owl and that was just testing to
make sure that we could handle high like
16-bit UTF you can see these are these
are values that require the full 16-bit
range of utf-16 so we want to make sure
that we could actually call some 16-bit
characters out of Windows and get them
obviously we can't use anything higher
than utf-16 because Windows doesn't
support it although Windows 10 might
start supporting it soon I don't really
know but anyway to be able to extract
those fonts out that's what we were
trying to do there getting that done was
just a test to make sure our system
worked for those fonts so this will
create a mask that says here all the
glyphs you should export that then
allows us to call our extract font
routine and our extract font routine if
you look at it here goes through each
individual group Jimmy goes through each
individual glyph and tries to extract it
now what we haven't done yet is actually
do anything with this data so you can
see right
we've done a load with bitmap that
actually rasterized the font we have the
font ready in thought bits to export we
also have filled out our entire
horizontal advance table by the time we
get to into here so technically when I
do this if I was to run this and say hey
and I think we had a thing down here
that actually sort of gave an example
command line so if I was to actually do
you know let me let me extract I don't
actually know what works dragons
liberation mono I don't know so if I was
to actually follow the instructions here
and actually supply you know one of
these things here that in theory should
actually do the full flaunt extraction
so in theory this is actually doing it
now
so all we need to now add to our system
is actually export the data now the
easiest thing for us to do would be to
steal the bitmap writing code right out
bitmaps and then just have a thing that
writes out the HHA that corresponds to
those bitmaps we're gonna start with
that I don't want to leave it that way
and if I get that all done today and it
seems to be working then what we'll do
is tomorrow we'll start on PNG export
because I'd like to do is just keep
these all in p.m. geez so if the game
doesn't have to have to export past one
for BMP one for PNG right so I'd like
our utility to export pngs
not BMPs we don't have to compress them
we can leave them uncompressed but we
should write them out so if you look
here you can see the extraction it says
I'm gonna start 200 glyphs the largest
code point is 3 to 820 that's gonna
correspond to like probably this one
here right a t-33 there uh so you know
but make of that what you will
in theory that actually did all the
extractions but we never actually wrote
them anywhere and so that's kind of
where we're at now so let's start by
trying to dump these bitmaps somewhere
what I'd like to do is expand you know I
know it's already kind of way too many
character way too many pram
this thing but hey that's just how it
goes sometimes what I'd like to do is
create two more pieces of information
that go along with this I'd like to say
I want to know where to write the output
so you know a desk
HHA file I'm sorry I know that's a trade
a file I just hht files so like what tag
file you want it to write out and then
like what directory do you want to dump
the pings you know what I mean so this
way in here I can say give me all of
that so I want to know two things here
from five and six I want to know the
like hht a file name and I want to know
the PNG der name and right now we will
be writing out not pansies but actually
bitmaps but we'll change the p.m. geez
when we when we have a chance to finish
to do that code so if we call extract
font here this is going to need to to
take care of that I might save the
opening and writing of that hht perhaps
two out here so maybe we'll first try to
ensure that we can actually get it so if
I was to say like H of T file equals F
open and in Cure I'd say that I wanted
to do a binary write of this file
not technically we're actually writing
it in text but I hate the text mode in
the C runtime library so I just never
open things in text mode so what I want
to do here is say look give me the hht
file names file there we're gonna F oh
that's not what I wanted we're gonna
open that up
assuming that we could get it then we'll
just pass just the handle two to this so
that instead of passing the filename
will actually just pass a file that's
ready to be written to I just like
handling that outside a little bit
better and then finally we'll pass that
PMG dur name so we will pass that
because it's gonna have to generate file
names in there continuously one for each
bitmap as it goes so I need to print out
an error because we may not be able to
open that file
so I need to be able to do like error
unable to open hht file this for writing
and so agency file name and that just
lets the user know if there was some
problem with writing to the place they
told us to write the hht and then i
could go up here and inside the
extraction code that's trying to
actually strike this font I can have the
hht out
so that'll have to be how that's written
and the PNG der write where that's going
to be now we don't really need to close
this file because it get closed
automatically but you know I'd like to
just keep it clear what's happening here
so I'm gonna go ahead and do an F close
on this just for good measure again
don't really need to do that technically
but we should i and just to make sure
it's flushed right I mean now I don't
really know what the rules are I don't
know if it auto flushes streams when you
when you close but you know just in case
it doesn't so now coming through here
this is where we want to start doing
that work and so we need to start naming
these and I think what we want to do
primarily is just give them names that
probably are associated with the font I
would guess and so if you look in here
you know you can you can imagine some
ways we could name it I'm guessing what
we should probably do is use the stem
name from the TTFN so maybe like just
this like this part of the name we could
use this part of the name but the
problem is that might have spaces in it
now we could sort of we could get around
that by replacing those with underscores
that seems probably more reasonable so
maybe after we actually create that font
maybe that's how we want to do it that
seems kind of reasonable to me
I think that's probably how it should go
so coming up here if you imagine how we
would do that once we enter enter here
we have the font name and what we would
like to do is create sort of like a font
stem name there or I don't know how you
want to phrase that exactly but I would
like to be able to create something like
this named stem so all I'm gonna do is
I'm just gonna create a buffer that
happens to be the same length as the
font name itself and then what I'm gonna
do is I'm gonna force that to be like
something that doesn't have any spaces
or anything else in it at all right
and so what I want to do is say take the
font name and like pass it through to
the name stem here so that we know that
you know it's it's all it's all cool so
let's just do something real quick here
where we say you know source best and
all I want to do is just say well I
guess I can even do it this way yeah I
guess I'll just do it this way I guess
I'll just say look while the source
equals something we'll just copy it
right now I don't quite want to do it
exactly that way because I need I'm
gonna need to be able to check in here I
would like to make sure that we copy the
null terminator I mean one way I could
do this and since I know it's null at
that point I'll just write it but while
we're doing this sanitize pass what I
want to do here is say look if the
destination is you know is how I want to
put this
I think okay so I think what I'd like to
do is let's just convert it to lowercase
first right
so we'll we'll make sure it's lowercase
and then if it's not in the range of
like things we accept so meaning if you
know star dest is greater than or equal
to a or I should say and Stardust is
less than or equal to Z right so if it's
within the range here and you know what
let's even do this a little bit a little
bit squink here what if we do this so
what I'm going to do is say all right if
you're within the range of characters
that I accept so if you're like this or
this then I will allow it if you're not
and I don't know why I didn't just use
the character that I extracted that's
what I wanted so if you're in the range
of characters that I accept then we will
use you directly otherwise we will stick
an underscore in there and that way we
have a name that we know is kind of
completely without weird stuff for
spaces or anything so it just gets
cleaned up and that way all the names
are our bitmaps don't have like weird
garbage in them or whatever so what I'd
like to do now is just say all right
let's say we sanitize that name now what
we can do is produce bitmap names on
demand we know like roughly how big we
need that to be meaning we know that
we're just gonna use the sanitized name
plus the PNG destr plus you know like
the code point number and so on right so
we know how big this thing needs to be
in order to make a buffer that can hold
our file names so you know we know that
we need some some size here
that's going to be the size of the name
stem plus the size of the PNG destr
right plus we're gonna need a slash and
we're gonna need dot PNG and we're gonna
need all that stuff right so let's just
give ourselves plenty of pad right
there's no chance to exceed that so
we're just good to go now anytime we
want we can just say fine let's sprint F
into the PNG out name what our name
would be and we know that it will look
like this right it'll be % s % u dot PNG
right and we may want to do this into
two buffers because we may well I guess
we can just use an address for this so I
guess we don't really need to do that so
we'll get to that in a second but so if
we do the PNG out name here what we want
to do is just say okay we'll do the PNG
out name we'll create that by saying
whatever the whatever the dester is we
start with that we then go to the name
stem which allows us to fill in you know
what the start of the name should be
then we would have the code point and
off we would go right now if we want
this to be padded we could also say that
which probably makes sense so maybe
we'll just leave it that way this is
going to be per glyph so here's us going
through each individual glyph to write
it out so once we get that code point
out this would be what would create the
actual name here furthermore I think we
probably also want to do like a PNG stem
the PNG stem actually is just the length
of this thing right
so whatever PNG out name is it's just
the length of can G destr plus 1 because
you're gonna skip that that slash so we
probably could just do this as well
right so here we just say this is the
part that's like not the derp right
maybe that and we're gonna need that for
writing to our
hht so what I want to do now is just
start testing this out a little bit so
what I'd like to do at first is let's
just write out we know what this should
look like right let's write out
something that that is commensurate with
how we have done our H HTS in the past
so here's our tags files here's our H
HTS right this is what they look like so
what we need to be able to do here is
just put all of our bitmaps in here so
what we want to do is maybe call these
glyphs so that the loader knows that
they don't need to be marked up by
anything so in here we would say okay
you know we want to output a glyph and
then we want to output that base name
like so and so we're gonna print this
out to a file it's gonna look something
like that and this has to go to our hht
file right sorry H of T out so I think
that's correct there yep so we don't
really need anything in the brackets so
I think the glyphs can just literally be
that so we just say glyph name and then
nothing that lets it know that it's
supposed to be imported probably I guess
we may need something in here that says
which code point it is I'm not sure
let's just say that we have to do that
so maybe we'll do glyph index equals %
you and so in here we will we will put
whatever that glyph index actually is so
it basically just says hey this is for a
particular font this is going to be this
particular glyph index right and we also
could associate this with a specific
font I guess is another way to do it
in fact we probably should do that so
maybe we put the font name in here as
well right just so we know what that
font name actually is so that seems like
another good thing to do so maybe in
here we have like font or name stem
right so that name stem right here gives
us that information I think that would
work so then what we can do is you know
push all those glyphs in there and again
I really don't know what the best way to
do the packing for this is I mean
there's another way we could do it you
know maybe this is better see what you
think of this so what if we said oh
here's a font and we tell you what the
font is right so we say it's this font
oops then we say inside the font we list
the glyphs you know I don't know if that
makes more sense because they're so
specialized
and that would look like this and I
really don't care what this is right now
you know I think we can adjust this
pretty easily once we go to do the
reader for it so I'm just gonna do
whatever here let's just say this will
work so here's the glyph index there's
the PNG file only bit right that just
lifts all the glyphs and then we close
it out and that's the end of the font
right so that seems good to me and and
then we can also if we want to we can
put this in here like maybe when we
start writing this thing out before you
know when we actually create it here
oops
maybe we can do something where we just
do
so that'll just print a boilerplate in
there and since we don't really know
what the copyright of this would be I
don't even know if anyone knows what the
copyright of that would be that would be
interesting cuz you can't copyright
fonts so extracted fonts I don't think
you could claim that you copyrighted it
because you haven't done anything I mean
so presumably it's still not copyrighted
but I don't know
so anyway point being this would just
kind of you know put a header in there
for us and off we would go
and maybe we could even do this so what
exactly was the name of this font again
is that it's that Molly bean it's that
Molly bean come on up come on up come on
oh come on you can eat such a small jump
there you go hello how's it going what's
you up to huh did you come to help with
the code are you gonna help with the
code what do you think what do you think
of this code do you think it sucks yeah
you don't like it do you it's not good
enough do you want to look out the
window
there you go you look out the window
alright so the if you take a look on
here right we're just basically saying
let's go ahead and go you know what and
this this can probably bacon the actual
name as well so this would be our zero
right that's the name of the actual
program so as this goes through you know
it should now write out like the data
for the font and furthermore like in
here as we're writing these glyphs out
we're building up the horizontal advance
table we can then dump that table when
we get to the end so we should be able
to say okay here's our horizontal
advance table like so and this is just
you know this would just go in and I
guess it's what is it a squared table so
we should be able to just write it out
as one giant list right so yeah it's
just glyph count cut so so you know I
might store that so that we can just
know that if we're gonna write out
everything in the font it would look
like that and so here I just say like
alright and and write them all out so I
think these are floating-point scaled
actual advance numbers I don't know how
much precision we want there but I'm
gonna go ahead and say we probably only
want three digits of precision there
this is not something that we could
really use beyond that I don't think
if index we need to print well actually
I'll just do it this way the height of
laziness ladies and gentlemen I'll just
say if index then put comma otherwise
don't that'll keep comma separated and
then we just need to say all right
horizontal advance of index print that
out we get to the end we'll stick a
semicolon and the carriage return and
we'll be done right Molly and I don't we
don't scratch the molding
okay that's unproductive won't you go to
your tree here there you go I gotta
brush you I gotta brush you look at you
shedding brush you so much the other day
too you just I think it's your new coats
coming in you get rid of your undercoat
you can't leave your undercoat for the
springtime gonna be nice and cool for
the summertime
that's good
you spot some crows maybe a seagull let
me see much out there but maybe there'll
be something later all right so that's
really all we need to get started and
oops so to lower what's the problem here
oh right this comes in as an int so see
what else we got that needs a file so
that should start now giving us at least
something we can start working on so if
I say this it should give me an error
and now I can say like okay do I have a
temp directory here yeah so let's make
dirt temp font and we'll just say like
okay we need to provide a desk HT HT so
we'll say temp font test h HT and then
here we'll say temp font and we'll hit
return we'll see what we get right so
now if I for example do W temp font test
HH see here's our font file so there's
all of our glyphs doesn't look where's
the that might have been because of the
fact that it's not actually a tab file
yeah there we go
so here's all our horizontal advance
table right so I'm not so it looks like
this is always in even pixels for some
reason why why would that be should not
have been a floating-point value that
seems a little strange
I mean aren't we scaling that value by
something or are we literally never
scaling it that's pretty interesting so
I guess we don't I guess we don't ever
scale it so that's always a pixel value
looks like we're not scaling down which
so are we not scaling at all oh so I
guess we're letting it do anti-aliasing
for us fascinating
well all right then I guess I guess just
don't need to do that didn't realize
that we were always on pixel boundaries
here so I guess we're actually just
doing that and I don't know why we're
we're storing floats in the first place
I guess just you know
um so I guess we don't really have to
worry about that and that's fine so this
looks like it's all outputting exactly
what we want so I think now we can move
on to just worrying about putting the
bitmaps out right now this is not a
particularly pretty way to print this
and one might argue that we should
probably try to make it look nicer and
we certainly could do that so if we
wanted to do that we could just go ahead
and do some kind of a you know strided
version of this so for example we could
say something like you know if index and
index mod 16 equals zero so like every
16 times through the loop we will
actually do a F printf and you know what
we could do this even takes away some of
my fun but you know and what this would
do is say alright look let's every 16
numbers instead of doing this what I was
doing here let's get rid of that and
what we'll do instead is say okay every
16 times will actually print a carriage
return and start printing on another
line right so here we'll do comma and
then carriage return 1 2 3 4 1 2 3 4 and
here we'll just do you know just the
comma right and you may be asking why I
felt the need to put that up up here
well yeah I mean I guess I didn't really
have to I probably could have still kept
it in a more inline way but I felt like
I shouldn't so I didn't anyway so that
would be like a just a nicer print out
it's all that's doing it's not changing
it wouldn't change what would happen
but then you know if I if I run it here
and then type that out now type W temp
font shht you can kind of see right it's
just like out putting it in in a block
of text and you know we could make sure
the block always lines up to by just
saying like look make sure all these are
always two because that's generally what
we have for advance we could even make
them three if we wanted to leave some
space for larger fonts which we probably
will have at some point right and so
there's like now it's just printing it
out in a block and that's just like a
little nicer to read that's all that is
and so that's like probably it right
this is probably legible I'm gonna make
this horizontal advance do a carriage
turn that's actually we could we could
sort of factor that out I guess we
probably the easiest way to do it is
literally just do it here instead right
we could just do it like that I think
that might look a little better let's
try that
yeah
so that seems good right there's our
horizontal dancer a so now that whole
thing is just in there
this needs a closing semicolon I think
right so that should be there and that's
it so now I think we can move on to just
outputting the bitmaps we know where
we're gonna put them which is right here
so now we need like a thing that's like
right PNG and the glyph result that we
have here that should tell us like
that's this right here that should tell
us what we actually need now this extra
data has to be stored into the glyphs
somehow right so I look I think that a
line percentage has to be in there but I
think that's the only piece of
information right it's just the aligned
percentage so that would have to come in
here meaning it would have to be like I
know how to do this but would have to be
something like that right and I don't
know I don't really remember how we were
looking at that piece of information
before but that is something that has to
sort of be written out the align
percentage has to be put back into the
file when it's actually being exported
right so let's just do it this way for
now we'll see what we want to do later
but that's a line percentage x + glyph a
line percentage why that's the alignment
of these of this particular glyph that
seems fine and then we now need to
actually write the PNG out this glyph
result doesn't actually give us what we
need for that so we need to actually
return that as part of this load with
bitmap unless we pass the writing
context to it but I don't think we want
to bother with that
so we want to be able to say here write
a PNG to this file name right and we
want to be able to say what the width is
right we want to be able to say what the
height is and then we want a pointer to
the pixels so we need like you know we
probably would also need a stride
although we may not need a stride I'm
not sure if these things are tightly
packed or not so we probably can just
look first and see whether we need to
whether we need to support a stride or
not so let's take a look and see how
this gets packed out pitch is it no it's
packed so we don't actually need that
and then that out that piece of
information there for the out where is
that actually coming from so we're just
malloc the memory for that right and
it's it's this right here now there's
really no need for us to malloc that
every time that's just dumb we could
just have one piece of memory that we
pass in and I would think I would
probably prefer that because there's no
like there doesn't need to be any
Malik's in here at least I don't think
so if we look at if we look at where the
Malik's are yeah there doesn't need to
be any Malik's in here so what I'd
rather do is say okay let's go ahead and
have out memory be passed in out memory
can just be like the biggest the thing
could possibly be at any particular
point in time and you can kind of see
like max like we know that this is the
only size we have for writing to the
bitmap in the first place so it doesn't
really make any sense to do anything
other than that right that's just that
just doesn't make any sense
so whatever the max glim glyph Tim is
that's all we need for our actual size
now the font bits presumably were
getting created here
yeah here they are so all we really need
to do is say look the out memory is just
going to be whatever the size the font
bits is right because that's also that
size and so when we create the what that
Maxim has to be and we know what the
maximum is because we're passing it
right we're passing max glyph Tim so we
must be setting that somewhere rats
right here so here's the max cliff Tim
right so immediately after that we
should be able to say well just take the
max cliff Tim x times the max lift in Y
times whatever the size of the pixel is
and that's it right you're done so at
that point you can just say all right
let's go ahead and and pass that every
time we extract a glyph and now we're
not allocating memory every time for no
reason right all right so at that point
I think we don't even really need to
know what the pixel pointer actually is
because we already kind of know it but
I'm gonna say let's return it anyway
just because why not
so in here we'll say the glyph result
includes the pixels and it includes the
width and the height of the thing then
inside this particular function up here
where we're going to pass the results we
just need to fill those out that's
irrelevant and this should all just be
known so where do we get all this stuff
from so this is how we computed our
width and height and all the stuff I'm
gonna go ahead and say look this is
outlived its usefulness so this is
actually gonna go up above now which I'd
kind of toy but doing before so that'll
go here and then this stuff can just be
filled out inside so when we do this you
know there's the out without height out
pitch we clear the memory and so on and
and all that nonsense so what we want to
do now is say that it's got the out
memory got the out with
right so now we have all of that data
and then we just need a function that
actually writes the PNG you know I'm
saying so that function oops it's not
gonna do anything fancy it's just gonna
take a width and a height and a pointer
to the pixels and the desk file name
obviously it'll try to open that and if
it doesn't
so like that file can't be opened that's
an error so like will tell the user just
so they know it failed
maybe they typed a director that doesn't
exist for the destination or something
so that's all we need here now we just
need to actually write the PNG out and
in order to do that well I mean we could
do any number of things right but I'd
rather start by just taking we've we've
got in HHA edit we actually have the
thing for dumping the the bitmaps in
here somewhere I think I hope I'm
actually no other is here it is so in
here we can just say look let's take
this header dump that in here you know
any of that here's the right image to
top down RGBA nonsense with the pixel
ops nonsense and let's just go ahead and
run that
I don't think we need to touch it at all
though do we cuz we've already done all
this so we can actually just kind of do
this there we go we don't need any of
this stuff because these are monochrome
right so we don't care about inverting
we don't need to do any other stuff with
them so we're literally just writing
these out one at a time in fact this
whole loop this this whole thing is not
necessary right we don't we don't need
to do any of this so we can literally
shorten this I believe down to just that
so we can just say look write these two
things and be done with it
so I think that should do it and of
course this won't be writing a PNG it's
actually a BMP but we can start there
right so now let's actually try this and
see if everything just dies a horrible
death if I go into that temp directory
and I look at the fonts here then I mean
you can you can base to see that it
worked okay I mean there's the font
right so I think we're good to go that's
all the stuff that we had wanted and I
don't know if this is looks like this is
a one of them is probably had nothing in
it but that looks like all the stuff in
the font I you know I don't see anything
weird going on there so that all seems
fine and you know in theory we should be
able to you know what change a size or
something and it should get
significantly larger so like let's say I
did this you know and restore that you
know there's there's bigger fonts right
dumped out in there and looking at it
you know it it looks like I guess
roughly what we would expect to see
maybe right so that seems fine now what
we need to do is
we need to actually write out a PNG
because this is a BMP and so I don't
know how much time I've got left
actually I guess I have quite a bit I
think I'd like 45 minutes so I may go
ahead and actually start on that so in
order to write a PNG what we need to do
is reverse the PNG spec that we were
using before and instead of trying to
read one we now need to write one so I'm
gonna go ahead and you know open up our
PNG reader here and just look at what we
read right and see what's up
so if we look at the actual routine you
know what's it expecting to see so we're
gonna come in here and say okay let's
read a PNG header that seems easy to
replicate we're going to start reading
chunks the chunks are endian is swapped
it looks like I which which is really
unfortunate
I forgot that PNG is that really true so
P and G is always ending wrong where's
Indian swap yeah so it's just always
wrong that's unfortunate anyway so we
got an Indian swap all our stuff before
you write it out because it's all gonna
be wrong it's all gonna be the wrong
Indian but then we get I it looks like
chunks we need one that's an AI header
and then one that's an AI datte and
hopefully that's it
[Music]
I'm assuming we should be able to set
the compression size to nothing so is
there an uncompressed compression method
let's see what structure was this called
again it's called the AI header
[Music]
oh okay so technically we have to we
have to have a compression method is
that really true so wait is this sick so
if I want to write a PNG alright forget
it if that's the case I might just add
BMP and just say forget it
right because if that's really I don't
really want to have to write out all of
this nonsense for no reason
that just seems dumb like reading a BMP
is not hard so
cuz I don't really want to write out a
fake Z lib stream that basically I mean
it's not that hard because you just
write out as either the stream that's
uncompressed right but it's still kind
of annoying
yeah so it looks like
so the b-type cannot be what's what's be
type-0 is there an OB type-0 what's the
what's the pair it is
so it looks like if we just did be type
zero blocks that's just that's just
pixel data right so in theory we could
do a thing that said the B type is zero
so there's no Huffman on it right so I
guess we could do this pretty easy
because if it looks like B type zero
goes doesn't have any Huffman on it at
all so in theory we should be able to
say what's that actually where's that
actually coming from P type is consumed
it's the comp data this is in the the
actual idaite header right after the I
Det header is the actual data where's
the where's the jumpable part here come
on let's see
here we go
so yeah I think all we do is just store
them as be type zero so all right I'm
I'm okay with that
it's a little bit of a pain in the butt
but it's not such a huge pain in the
butt that I'm not willing to do it so
let's give it a try if we know we've got
a file that has these specs out maybe
I'll just go ahead and try to include it
so if I come up here like can I just do
this and say you know give us the stuff
it looks like that needs memory Arenas
why are those in here these really have
to be in here like why can't they be
is there a reason these can't be like
down here does everything get destroyed
oops
it doesn't seem like it so we should be
able to do this this takes a stream as
an actual hard-coded thing so it looks
like it does sort of need at least a
definition of that it seems fine
all right we're all good
okay so let's give this a shot we need
to start out by writing one of these
things out that's the first thing we
need to do so we've got the file header
and that thing needs to have the
signature be that that bit I guess
there's actually no reason to really do
it this way I guess the right way to do
it and let me just get rid of all this
garbage I guess the right way to do it
is actually just look just write this
right so write that out the whole thing
that gives us a PNG signature right and
I'm just gonna work backwards here and
try to produce this thing let's go ahead
and look at the reader code and just try
to do the opposite of what the reader
code does right so just gonna write out
whatever this thing reads so it's gonna
consume a PNG header that's what we just
wrote out it's then gonna try to start
reading and it's gonna read a chunk
header right so let's just start by
writing that out so we know we need a
chunk header here the question is what
goes in the chunk header and the answer
is well a bunch of Indian swap nonsense
right so we need to basically ende and
swap these two things off of it and we
need to set them to something who knows
what that is
or that then it's gonna try and read a
chunk footer and it's going to swap the
CRC now we don't actually use the CRC so
we don't have to write it correctly but
we may want to try anyway just to be
able to be read by other programs that
do check the CRC but for our own ingress
we wouldn't have to
all right so that chunk header is gonna
read the data for the chunk which is
some length long right and the only
things we actually need are these two
chunks so we should then be able to
write them and their footer right so you
know this is what we've actually got
Jimmy one of them's a ping I had her and
one of them is just the i dot chunk
right so this would be the i dot chunk
here and this would be the AI header
chunk here so this which I didn't even
know you could do until handmade here oh
right I don't know if you guys remember
like I was like oh you can do that I
didn't know um like that that's so cool
I had no idea you could do that I just
don't know when Z added that but that's
pretty awesome that you can do it now um
so in here we need to specify a length
that's going to be one of these long
right so we've got a ping I header this
is the ihdr that we're gonna fill out
ourselves
so we need this thing to be that long
this needs to be the type those two
things need to get Indian swapped so
because we need to write them out in the
opposite Indianness because things I
guess are Mac native or something or
were so we got to swap the endianness
which is a bummer but we do so we do
that and then we write it out right and
so we're gonna f write the chunk header
then the IDR and then we need the chunk
footer
and the chunk footer looks like all it's
got does it have anything else in it
oops it doesn't so basically we need a
CRC we're gonna need a thing that does
this that computes the CRC in order to
write that out properly because we don't
have any way to do that right now but we
can but anyway then we would write out
the chunk footer uh so this is just
gonna be this oops right there's some
CRC here that we have to compute then we
would ND and swap it so that it comes
out right and then we would write it and
that would be the complete chunk right I
don't know what the CRC is supposed to
CRC presumably just the chunk data but I
don't actually know so we'll have to
actually do that then we need to endian
swap any parts of the IDR that actually
matter which looks like a bunch of them
so we're gonna have to set all this
nonsense here
now thankfully we've got a little cheat
code here because we basically know that
we want filter method zero and
interlaced method zero and compression
method zero and color type six bit depth
eight so all that's fine and then we
also know that we need the width and
height to be swapped because we
obviously have those in larger in the
other endian rather so up here we would
say okay let's prepare the eye header so
there's the eye header preparation right
there and there's the swap here's the
chunk header I guess that has to be done
below here because it actually needs to
know the size of is there right and
there's the chunk footer we then write
those out header data footer and that's
the complete header information that we
need so really the only thing that's
probably wrong is this let's make sure
we filled out this whole thing yeah we
did so then what we need is we need the
ID at to actually contain the data like
for the actual file so we need to put
the pixels into an Ida and we need the
Ida to have the right Z Lib header that
tells it like hey this is uncompressed
there's nothing in it right so in order
to do that we need to do this again
right we need to do another one of of
these F right nonsenses here that's got
the header I the you know header data
footer right it's got to look like that
so now we need to do the same thing we
did before which is the chunk
now needs to be set up to be eyed at
instead right and the yeah and the
length is not that so we got to think
about what the length is gonna be right
because we got to actually put its the
pixel data so it's gonna have however
its however big it is right so then
we've got like the chunk header weight
this needs to get there we go so then
we've got the trunk footer needs to have
the CRC computed again and so then the
main thing we need to do now is fill out
the actual i dot stuff that's going to
be in there and that is going to require
us to figure out yeah what that actually
looks like so at the very least we need
the ID at header and the i dot footer
stuff to be correct
i'm guessing that this looks something
like i don't know so let's go back to
the reader and see what happens so it's
reading the i dot chunks out of here and
it's literally just stuffing what's in
the chunk it doesn't look like it's
doing anything else
so this just stuffs these onto the
stream that's all it does right then we
eat them out of here so in theory we
should be able just do it all in one and
not have to do anything fancier I hope
because this is to support people
breaking the file into pieces but we
don't actually need to do that for any
particular reason
so this ID here just needs this garbage
to be set in some way that makes sense
right so we just need it to come through
and see
we basically need to see B final to be 0
and B type to be 0 so like the CM the
scene fo they have to check the F dict
and the F level just need to be like set
to something that works and so it looks
like we're only supporting CM 8f dick 0
so we would just set that right so like
whatever this needs to be for that to
happen is all we needed to actually do
right the additional flags like F nicked
here is 0 F level is that even used so F
levels not even used so F nicked an F
level so additional flag could just be 0
zealand method is a composite of these
things here right these two what is the
F check you don't look at that I'm gonna
have to bounce back here and see what
the F check is cuz I have no idea it's
just the Z Lib stuff so this is the zeal
of stuff so unfortunately we need the we
need the actual Z live info here
oops
guess it's not named to that
so this stuff is all irrelevant we just
need to know like what the so what are
those flags are the flags are those
flags actually let's find the PNG or not
so it does look like maybe those are in
here so where's the I - um
so I'm not sure what that value actually
means so there's the zealand method
flags and the additional flags that's
this
okay so deflate compression and some zi
lib nonsense we don't care about so what
are the what are the additional flags in
the check code like what what are this
so it just does not say so I'm not
really sure what we should set these two
we'll have to find out because we're
probably going to write this out wrong
so I guess I'm gonna have to say like
look we know that the Z lab method for
CM has got to be eight we don't know
what see info should be because we don't
use it so we have to look up like what
that should actually say because I don't
know but it looks like we want to set
that to eight to do
so we want to find something in the spec
we should look a little harder after we
kind of get through this just to find
out like what else is supposed to be
there like because probably we should
set those things to line up properly
with what we're trying to do you know
and I'm just not sure exactly what that
should be yet so we have an IDOT header
that goes in there and then all we've
got looks like is we consume one bit
literally a single bit and then two more
bits and that should be zero so we want
be final to be 1 right because we want
to end so we want to set the first bit
that gets consumed and we'll have to go
see whether it cuz we've got the bottom
of the top because I don't actually know
and then we need to set the b-type so
the rest of the thing needs to be zero
so we're either looking at setting the
highest bit and everything else to zero
or setting the lowest bit so it's either
gonna be that oops it's not what I
wanted it's either going to be just one
or it's gonna be the highest bit set so
it would be like eighty right it would
be like you know like that right and I'm
not sure which it is so we got to go
look at how bits are consumed and figure
that out but that's the first thing we
want that basically says you know the
whole thing I'm Jimmy
the whole thing we're writing out is
going to be one chunk and this is and
it's not compressed so have a party so
we then have a 16 bit length which is
just going to be our width times our
height and I I assume
for I don't actually know if that's true
yeah so just a width times height times
four it looks like these are written out
in just a stupid way that's meant for
checking for no apparent reason that I
could necessarily predict so I have no
idea what the point of that is but
that's fine so we basically have a Len
here that's going to be width times
height times four and then we've got n
Lin which is just that right so those I
you know that can't write out something
that's too large so meaning you know we
may have to break this into multiple
chunks if the thing was too large don't
know if we need to support but that's
the maximum we could do divided by four
is that so if we then square root it
that means 128 528 is the largest bitmap
we could write out if it was square and
it could change obviously if we don't
multi pass this so if we don't write out
like multiple chunks so I'm gonna put it
to do in here just to make sure we know
that in fact I could put an if in here
but I must do for now
why they chose to write the length twice
and have you compare the two I have no
idea incident is having a 32-bit length
which would have allowed you to write
the bits out directly I have no idea it
seems incredibly stupid but I'm sure
they had some reason for it I hope I
don't know
I would ask Molly about a fish you might
be asleep anyway so if we then say okay
we're gonna write out the length that's
how many there need to be then we just
kind of dump this out I think that's it
and then that should just be it I don't
think there's anything else at anything
else so we need to write these two right
Lennon in line and then we need to write
out the pixel data and off we go
so don't know what this is it's one or
the other
so we'll deal with that later but we
have to write the stream byte then we
have to write Len then n Len then we
have to write the pixels and then we
have to write the the footer right okay
so now we get to the thing we're aware
that the length has to be included in
here and I don't know how big that's
supposed to be because I don't know what
it's supposed to include like does it
include the header and the stream by
nanny and everything else and then the
chunk header and footer or does it skip
the chunk header and footer because you
already read those we should be able to
figure that out by looking at how we
were processing it here so what it looks
like is we actually take the chunk data
here
which is
separate from the header right
so I think it does not include anything
other than this interior part so the
length that we're writing out is
literally stream byte and then the
actual length right which we just
computed right here I think that's what
we're talking about where we essentially
do like okay you know take the ID at
feed all the rest of this crap into it
and that's what we're going to be
writing out so then we need to figure
out the CRC obviously which we haven't
done yet and then we just need to write
everything out so we need to write out
literally what I just said oh and we
want this to we want the ID out header I
think no yes yes that's also included so
the ida header also has to go in there
in addition to everything else so then
we just have a giant nonsense set of
this crap where we say like okay and I
could have built destruct out of this
maybe I should so it's a little bit
simpler but basically I just have to
write these in order so you write the I
dot then you write the screen bite then
you write the Len the n Len and then you
write the actual pixels
and then we stick the footer on there
and in theory you're done now in order
to actually determine when we're done
here looking at this you can see like we
do a while loop until it's there's no
more room in the file so it looks like
there is no closing chunk at least not
that we cared about now in the spec I
think there was one meaning there was
like an eye end chunk or some crap like
this that we're just not paying
attention to I don't think but there
might be one and so we might want to
stick that in there for compliance yeah
so just to be like a little more proper
about it I think we want to just dump
out a completely empty one here I don't
know if it needs a if it's gonna have a
footer
let's take a quick look here
so it sounds like it a four byte CRC
calculated on the presetting bytes and
the chunk including the chunk type field
and chunk data fields but not including
the length field okay why not I mean you
knew the length I guess it's because you
want to write the thing in CRC as you go
and since the length came at the
beginning they want you to not have to
have known it ahead of time I guess it's
stupid because you'd want to see our
Sivan yeah anyway so anyway it looks
like we would need a CRC on that one as
well so if we wanted to write that out
we'd be doing this again
like so and there just wouldn't be any
data in it so we would say the chunk
header the length is zero
the type is ions and the footer dot CRC
goes there we would then and you know
what I might start writing this a little
differently like maybe we write it like
that
right because these the things that you
need to fill out uh so I think that
should be good
and off we would go that in theory
writes a PNG II we need access to the nd
and swapping code that this is using but
that seems pretty tame so what I might
do is go ahead and put that up here so
that everyone can use it
right did we also have it yeah we do
type it that in the math library um
alright so who knows what this will do
probably nothing good but you know hey
we got started and so tomorrow that puts
us in a good position to start to
bugging that and getting it working and
because we only got about like ten
minutes left so we probably won't get
anywhere on getting this working but at
least we've got the like it we've got it
sketched out right um so here it so
interesting enough it looks like we've
got some of it right right because you
have like the looks like the sizes are
kind of correct so we're not like
totally off so you know we're yeah so
you know it looks like our ID at chunk
is wrong but our eye header chunk is
correct probably something like that
meaning we got like halfway there so
that's good so you know this this
probably came through correctly but the
rest of it didn't you know like
something something went wrong there I
it would be nice if there was a way I
don't know if someone would complain
about errors in the stream properly like
camp or somebody probably not but no
once no one's probably gonna say what's
wrong with the stream unfortunately
right it's yeah it's just gonna say it's
corrupted so unfortunately we may have
to go look at our own reader code to
determine
call our own reader code and see what
happens which actually can we do that by
the way let's do a Hail Mary first who
knows maybe it's right it's not gonna be
yeah
unsurprisingly um so I think we actually
can use our code can tweet because we've
got one of these things in here like
test PNG which we could build and then
run it on one of these things and you
know step through a nice simple case
there I don't actually remember where
that is but I thought we had something
like that yeah this thing we just maybe
build this thing I don't remember what
that does but absolutely there's yeah
here it is right so in theory if we call
this thing on one of the bitmaps that we
like you know pulled out we should be
able to like step through the code and
see like if we can read it so because
the first step would be let's get us
reading it because that we should be
able to do directly and then we can go
find out what other stuff that maybe
we're not paying attention to because we
don't care if the PNG is correct we just
care if it has the stuff in it that we
look for then we could figure out what
of that is not in there and then we're
done because then you know we were
writing out things that can be loaded by
a third-party tool which we would like
to do that we've an artist needs to go
in and edit like one of the font bitmaps
or something or if we just wanted like
to plug it by open it and or
something we can do we don't we don't
want to be the only people who can read
it right so let's go ahead and make that
happen
I'm gonna do a build of everything there
and then I'm going to open up remedy
let's go ahead and and set the debug to
be
[Music]
Tess P&amp;G the command-line arguments for
what again okay so RGB and alpha out so
we just need like what's a what's an
example file in in W temp thought oops
so we've got liberation mono Oh a like 1
1 1 1 right so there's an input Oh temp
font and then we just need a temp font
out RGB dot BMP and W temp font out
alpha dot BMP let's go ahead and save
that into our debug directory so that we
can you know switch to it again as
necessary loading up there it is so
running it we should get okay so great
you know we air out which is exactly
what we want so hopefully we can just
now step through here and like let's see
how far we get
oops I was meant to step into that yeah
so in here we're gonna load the header
let's take a look at the header see what
it says chunk header there's the eye
header chunk it's backwards cuz Indians
swapped remember from what we would
normally think of it as we're gonna
consume the chunk footer we're gonna
look at this and get all that garbage
looks like that so I'll print it out
flips print it out for us hasn't been
flushed yet though so let's look at it
ourselves
here's eye header the width and height
the bit depth the color type that all
looks good so if we think it's supported
and that's good so now we're gonna go
here and see the eye that chunk
hopefully let's take a look at that
chunk header and just see what the size
is
that looks okay this should be the end
of chunk and we should now be done so
now we're gonna start consuming stuff
there's an IDOT header that comes first
so let's take a look at what that looks
like
oops no okay there we go right ahead
we've got a Z lib method flags of eight
and an additional flags of zero I think
that's what we want
yep and now we'll come through here and
try to allocate memory for everything
that should be trivial because the width
and height looked fine we read the first
chunk so we're gonna load in B final
what does it say it's a zero that's
totally wrong I wanted it to be one so I
guess that's a screw-up
so that's the first thing we need to go
fix and then we're gonna can consume B
type I think I forgot to write that
entirely so let's go fix that and then
we'll restart so looking back at our
nonsense here I'm gonna go ahead and say
that that argues 401 as the screen byte
in here then we've got is it what is it
another what do we consume 4/4 beat for
beat type it's two bits so for some
reason the type here is two bits so you
know who knows I guess you know this is
actually let's just call this what it
actually is on the other side right
so right after B final we actually need
B type to be written as well so we need
like to keep this going here so this
stream bite thing that's the final and
that's B type and in here we just need
to now write that one out as an
additional value okay
so let's save that off and rerun the
program because remember we have to
actually run the thing to update those
those pngs before we try to debug again
because otherwise they won't actually
have been changed so let's jump now
directly down here since we suspect most
of the other things are working so far
let's go ahead and consume be final and
we want that to be one it is that's good
let's consume B type we want B type to
be zero it is we now need to oh but wait
but wait this is just totally not
correct I was why did I freak out there
this is one bit and two bits I'm just an
idiot I did it right the first time
so that was not incorrect I'm just an
idiot so it's it's actually that that's
what's supposed to be right so no I was
I was not I was I was right that this
has to be changed but I shouldn't have
changed that other part okay so let's do
that again
in a less stupid way so let's go ahead
and step through here now again be type
and be final should be 1 and 0 and they
are it should now flush to the end of
the byte which is why again I saying
these these are bit level values not
byte values let's see what the Len value
is that we read in let's see what the
end Len value is that we read in those
are ok we now have to put that out put
that source out there I'm gonna have to
actually jump forward to here there's
not a row there is a run to cursor does
that work oh nice ok great
doesn't make a lot of sense does it
oh so this is not encoded the way I
thought it was what
if you have a Len
all right so I see what I did wrong this
loop is actually totally weird it's not
just let me grab some specific amount of
data it's a little bit more confusing
than that so we do a while length here
and we actually read in so we say this
this just allows us to clamp so we don't
actually read outside the boundaries but
then we actually consume that much data
however much we wanted here and we I
guess we're just using well no I guess
that that is what that's doing so like
why what happened there why did our I'm
gonna reset that so what what happened
something weird happened there I
understand so it was just what I thought
it was but for some reason something
weird happened so if I come through here
I've got a Len oops
of 61 6 right I set use Len oops
to be that we consume that much right
eye that's gonna like copy all this
stuff and then when we get to the end
this is not gonna go down look at all
right what what happened was this even
working before did we screw up this code
path I mean look at that how is that
possibly right
I mean there's just no way that's right
that code has to look like this doesn't
it
where's my where's that that code has to
look like this right I mean it's gotta
there's no there's no way that the that
could have been correct I argue
yeah that's what it should do right
maybe I'm wrong about that but I think
that's correct all right so it looks
like we still have a problem here which
is that we didn't end up at the
destination where we thought we were
gonna so we're still we're a little bit
off look we didn't fill all the pixels
that we thought that we should write so
whatever that Len is the Lyn does not
appear to be correct for the number of
pixels that we thought we had so for
example like it was what 62 16 or
whatever oops
that does seem correct
Oh but we need to leave room for the
filter because every row has an
additional value stuck in it for PNG
right I'm actually starting to remember
how this works now so every row has that
you know that thing that's at the start
of the row that says which filter mode
it uses specifically filter mode zero is
what we want which is to say that you
don't have to do anything to the pixels
but you still need that on every row
even if you're not compressing and
there's no way to tell it not to do that
so we actually do need a thing here
that's gonna actually this this nonsense
and in fact that kind of makes me want
to write these out in a way that would
allow us to do things a little bit
better anyway so for example Jimmy we
could just move this for loop widen this
for loop a little bit later and then not
actually have this problem so okay so
that might be fine all right so let's
just cheese this out for now though and
then we can we can play with it a little
bit more so I'm gonna go ahead and do a
thing here that actually writes the oops
that writes these out in a for loop just
for a second so this is the why we're
gonna go through the entire thing
writing out the pixels here and we're
gonna write those out as whip times for
right so we're going to write out those
in rows and each time we do before we do
we're going to write out like basically
a garbage byte right that's just a like
no filter so we're gonna say like write
out no filter then write out this the
pixels for that row and that's actually
going to be the the data that we use for
pixels and then we can broaden this out
and make it so that we write like one
row per I dad or something that allow us
to have arbitrarily large images so that
seems fine to me
and that would get us out of the
business there hopefully yeah that would
get us out of the business of having to
insert those into the image or something
weird like that because that way we just
write a write them out like interleaved
with the filtering mode I think that
would do it
the only problem there is well actually
don't think there is a problem I think
that's it right all right so there's
that version now let's try this again
and see where we end up I don't know
where did we end up there we go
so we still look like we're under
flowing here somewhere
looks like we're under flowing in the
actual chunk reboot did I mess up the
size calculation there somehow
I did
okay uh let's see here this should now
actually fill the length and hopefully
stop at the correct place let's see if
it actually does there we go alright so
now we can look and see if our reader
can at least read our writer which is a
good start um let's see now it doesn't
look right right I don't see the data
there so we're still screwing something
up there right although I don't know
maybe we've we may have improved the
usability of this in terms of errors in
the stream though nope not quite so
we're still a little bit off but we're
getting closer
alright so I'll leave it there and we
will go to tomorrow will do with the
debugging but we should be able to get
it working that's mostly everything
right so now we just have to go through
and and be a little bit more diligent
about actually getting all of the stuff
written out properly so I'm sure there's
just some stupid stuff that's happening
in here Oh for example every time we
write out a line we have to advance this
so this is actually whatever the pixel
pointer is actually pixels is 32-bit
okay so I can just do this it's actually
gonna do that so that may actually have
been the majority of that bug there let
me let me double check let's just see
hmm let's see if that improve anything
just not appear to have but you saw with
the bug was there right like we were
writing out rows but those rows were not
actually didn't didn't actually advance
so we have to make sure that we move the
pixel pointer forwards each time that we
actually write it right in order to have
anything show up in the file why we
don't see anything I'm not sure because
it looks like we are actually processing
that stuff out
but for some reason we're not actually
getting we're not actually seeing any
data they're not even garbage so
something is still a little bit off in a
way that that data's being pushed
just trying to think if there's anything
stupid we're doing though
I don't think so that still that seems
mostly correct to me alright so like I
said I'll go ahead into the Q&amp;A and then
we will wrap it up looks like info bot
still doesn't doesn't listen to me on
this
and then that never likes listen to me
on that on that channel I have to do
have to do it on the on the handmade
network Channel
the iron footer is missing some swaps ah
yes you're right it is
unfortunately that's not our problem
spatial free I love that vertical header
peak in your for creditor is it a
default feature how can I get it no I
wrote that myself I don't know when or
if how that would be available more
broadly
is the rgba the same for bitmaps and
pngs um I don't remember I think the
answer is no but I just don't recall in
this particular case we literally don't
care because it's monochrome so we don't
have to actually know but we did have to
know when we actually did it originally
well you know the easiest way to tell
just me to look at our code so here's
the test PNG code yeah it's got swap are
in there so I think they're they're
swapped so being BMP is swapped from PNG
do you think machine learning can be
useful in games if yes in what way
mm-hmm I guess I'm not sure like I I
mean yeah I'm sure there'll be some
things you can do interesting with it
right the problem is I don't know to
what extent you really want learning in
games you know like I would think it
would probably something that is it's
more used like offline so like you know
you you might use machine learning
algorithms like outside of the game to
generate stuff for the game but then you
would probably not really want to do a
lot of machine learning at run time
because one of the things that makes
games fun are that there are like simple
understandable patterns that players can
learn about how the game works and if
the game is constantly like learning and
adapting that creates a less fun like
like I don't think there's a lot of use
for that in most games because most
games don't want to adapt to the player
that's like unsatisfying for the player
so in a sense I could see you wanting
that in certain games where if like the
whole point of your game is that you
want the AI to feel more like a human
but in most games you don't in most
games you don't want the AI to feel like
a human you want the ad to feel like an
AI right and so for most games I think
you might want more of an offline
learning it's what you would use and
then only in those circumstances where
you were trying to make the AI feel like
it learned then you could possibly
employ those techniques more like at the
actual time when the game is executing
right
we'll be able to get your current for
coder with the new version coming out
and maybe the sources for yours on the
handmade hero files so know the problem
is my for coder config as of like a
couple weeks ago I now just build it
directly into the Mali rocket codebase
so it's not distributable anymore I also
don't know like I don't think I'll
probably really even be using like it's
mostly just untethered now like I ended
up rewriting like almost all the edit
stuff to be what I wanted and so now I
can just really call my own renderer and
it's probably gonna be pretty pretty
divorced from for coder as a code base
so you know Allen will probably be doing
a lot of the stuff that we did together
that stuff will be shipping but I won't
be shipping an editor anymore because
it's just too hard for me to do that
that would be like another job for me to
try and like like I'd have to start
shipping my own editor basically which
is not something I'm going to do if that
makes sense because I'm not gonna like
support an editor or anything like that
like I'm not gonna do that so I would
say that like these you know a lot of
the stuff that you see coming into for
coder that I made will you know I
contributed the code back so that stuff
should make its way into the mainline
code over time but in terms of me
shipping my own editor version that
that's not gonna happen anymore
I see quite a lot of people moving into
more program software engineering
related jobs after doing some Academical
research not at all focused on Cee
related things physics chemistry etc do
you have any experience working with
people that didn't focus on coding for a
long time possibly not having any real
training in it what's the biggest
difference with people that have a
degree in Cee
or focused on programming from a young
age no I actually haven't ever really
worked with anyone at gas powered games
a long time ago in like 99 I briefly
only tangentially but briefly worked
with someone who was an English major
originally and I think switched to CS at
some point other than him I don't recall
working with anyone who wasn't pretty
much always a programmer
yeah I'm sorry III I have no I haven't
had any any personal experience with
that so I couldn't really say what the
differences would be
do you feel like explicit languages make
people more productive compared to
expressive language is I think
functional programmers program just for
masturbatory purposes um so I think
you're right for starters but I guess I
what I would say is it's a complicated
issue on the one hand if you design your
language to not be particularly
expressive then what you guarantee is
that the programmer can't do anything
too stupid right if you're gonna program
in straight C it's pretty hard to make a
program that's that bad at you know
mapping to the cpu because you have to
work pretty hard to create ridiculous
crap right on the other hand in
something like yeah ml or something you
can type probably ten lines of code and
create something that like is impossible
for a normal CPU to run efficiently
right so there's definitely something to
be said for thinking about the degree to
which your language allows programmers
to create things that are simply bad for
a CPU so you're not wrong that does
exist the problem is that you do need
ways for experienced programmers to use
less code to create more complex things
that they have specifically thought
about how they should work and have a
good idea for write C is to inexpressive
to allow those programmers to be
efficient and so you ideally want
something that's kind of in between the
two that no one's made yet but maybe
someday someone will that's kind of like
hey this language is still very good at
expressing things that CPU should do and
saying how they should do them
but it also allows the programmer to
start lofting up those concepts into
more complicated instructions that allow
the the compiler to do a lot of the
things that the programmer would have
had to have done by hand that are just
wrote and and that it doesn't need the
programmer doesn't need to specify how
they happen every time right you've
talked in the past about understand the
trade-offs and Safran elements such as
optimizing increasing complexity time
constraint in the context of readability
versus futures implemented there are
other things you keep in mind when
deciding how to spend your time um not
really you know I'm not a particularly
good programmer as far as like spending
time on like the highest priority stuff
that stems largely because I'm too
interested in solving problems a lot of
times which I don't really think is a
bad thing it just means that like I
wouldn't necessarily take my advice on
on prioritization right I think you want
people who tend to go off and try to
sort like the concept of Jack shaving
right I think actually you really want
people who like to do yak shaving but
you you only want the ones who come up
with something right so the reason that
a lot of times I think stuff like you
know going down rat holes gets a bad
name is because the people who go down
rat holes never actually do anything
down in the rat hole so they just wasted
their time right whereas people who
actually rattle on stuff and then come
up with a new way of doing things that's
really awesome those people I think are
pretty valuable and so I think you know
it's it's worth drawing that distinction
but in general I wouldn't say that you
want people who are good at like rat
holding and coming up with something
really cool at the end of it those
people are not necessarily the people
you want giving advice for the rest of
the team about like where to spend their
time though right so I think I'm a bad
person to ask about that because I'm
more of an rng kind of person and I'd
like to do those sorts of things
but you know that you only need so many
people doing that and you only need
people who actually come up with
something when they go do stuff you
don't really need people doing that who
just waste their time right so that's I
think probably how you would draw it you
know how you would talk about that
distinction
yeah George I don't know when yak
shaving became a thing rat holing was
kind of more the phrase that I used to
hear around that but yak shaving kind of
I assume I because it's kind of trying
to talk about a slightly different thing
so you know rat Holdings like oh I got a
you know do this PNG writer and then I
end up like spending a ton of time like
researching the origins of PNG and how
they worked and whatever so you know yak
shaving is kind of a term that that came
up to sort of talk about something a
little bit slightly different than that
I mean you don't really need another
term but you know it's worth noting that
there's a different thing there and so
what you actually means trying to refer
to is like the concept that in order to
do something you kept having other
things you needed to do first and so
someone comes in like you know two weeks
ago they were like we need to write this
PNG reader or writer and then two weeks
later they come back and you're working
on like a new device driver for the hard
drive right or something right and
they're like what happened and you're
like well you know I started running the
PNG writer but then I noticed that there
were these problems when I was actually
running things out I wasn't getting the
performance throughput that I thought I
should get so then I started profiling
the hard drive and I realized that the
hard drive was like writing things
really slowly and not exactly the speed
that it should have been and so then I
looked at why that was happening it
turns out you know blah blah blah blah
blah the reason they came from yak
shaving is because it's like they told
you to write a PNG reader and they come
back in two weeks and they see you just
like shaving a gak and you're like what
are you doing right and so it's just
this notion that like from something
that should have been relatively
straightforward they came back and found
you doing something totally unrelated to
anything but you have some coherent
explanation of like how you went through
the steps that actually got you there
right
we don't use libraries on the stream
everything has to be written from
scratch so you could certainly use SUV
image or something else to write a PNG
but you know the whole point of the
stream is to show how to write code if
all I show you how to do is download a
library well bad news folks
you'll be replaced by a is in about ten
years the AI that just uses Stack
Overflow and cut and paste the code is
gonna replace like 90% of programmers in
ten years I guarantee you it's coming
because like a lot of people who are you
know nominally programmers these days
are just a glorified cut and paste
engine and they really don't know how to
do anything other than like pipe
libraries together and cross their
fingers and that is gonna be automatable
I mean we're already getting the point
where programming systems are going to
be able to understand api's and wire
them together that's not gonna be that
big of a deal and so I think they're
gonna get there and so the only
programmers I think that'll be all that
useful are people who actually know how
to do something you know at the lower
level so I try to teach as much as
possible how to do that because I think
those are the only programmers gonna
remain valuable people who are literally
just like wiring stuff together I just
don't think they're gonna be necessary
you know if you go back and look at sort
of what happened as you know robots
automated away manufacturing you know
there's just not as many people
necessary to to build stuff anymore
and that's gonna be true of programming
right as soon as people start automating
it huge swaths of people who are
literally just the dude who puts the
bolt on the thing which is like the
equivalent of like I went and looked on
Stack Overflow and then I like used like
15 packages to print a stupid integer or
something right like those people are
just gone I mean that there's no y-you
know you don't need those people for
anything because they're not doing
anything right they're just doing what
an AI
and I think you know I don't know what
percentage of programmers that is but
it's it's pretty high nowadays because
there's just you know in in the in the
80s or something the percentage of
programmers who were doing something
like that is was incredibly low today I
think the percentage of printers that
are doing that is very very high because
there's thousands of programmers working
on things like Twitter which is you know
a very minor program or something like
that and so you just like what are all
these people doing you know they're not
[Music]
doing like you know all kinds of
hardcore super amazing programming where
they're doing just the stuff that you
can't possibly conceive of how any I
could ever do it it's like that's not
what's happening right and just the
number of them that there are you know
there aren't that many good programmers
right it's just not the case and so at
some point I think that that huge slack
just gets optimized away because there's
really just no meat I mean you just
don't need people who are just pushing
libraries around there's there's no
point the people who are interfacing
with those programmers will simply skip
the programmers and use some kind of
automatic generative tool to produce the
combination of stuff that they want and
they they won't need a programmer in the
loop at all right and so then the only
people I think that will still be around
are the people who are creating like new
stuff the engine maintainer z' the
people who are writing new languages the
people who are working on those AIS I
think that's really all you got left
because you just don't need people who
are just reconfiguring existing code
reconfiguring existing code to do
something else that that code could have
done but that no one had actually piped
together in a particular way that a eyes
will have that under control
that's my prediction anyway and the only
reason I say that is because that's what
happens to every other industry so it's
kind of I don't know why it wouldn't
happen to ours right
you know everyone probably always thinks
that their job is the one that only they
could do and you know
of course anything I can't do my job
it's like mal really you know every
industry that has no robots in it
eventually gets to be some percentage
robots
you really think ours is gonna be 0%
it's a pretty big wager
there's there's too much stuff in here I
my voice is getting sore yeah well I've
read the sequel I mean you know if you
want a really future-proof job I would
work on cogent man I mean cuz that's I I
that's where I think it's going you know
you know I would either specialize in
something that's gonna be very hard for
a eyes to do like maybe operating
systems development hard core engine
programming you know that sort of stuff
that'll probably be like further you
know it'll be later it'll take longer to
automate those away or I'd just get on
the automation penguin and say I'm gonna
make the stuff that replaces the you
know 50% of programmers who are just
googling Stock Exchange and then cutting
and pasting crap I'm just making piles
of crap and be like I'm gonna make the
crap pile program and you can just give
it these high-level directives and say
make me a crap pile that does this thing
and it's like how about this and you're
like sure probably out less bugs and
then the people we're replacing would
have put in there so off we go right
because I just like I don't I just don't
see any way that probably 90% of the web
things I interact with I don't see any
way those couldn't been made by an AI
right like you know the code for Gmail
could have easily been made by an AI and
it would have been better than the code
that that is up there now right the just
the front end right or like you know
that the more much much easier than that
would be like something even simpler
that the page the web page for my bank
my credit-card company right it's just
garbage right it's just it could have
taken a very high-level directive of
what that page
like and generated that code right and
it would have just spit out the same
stupid jQuery garbage into a giant
bloated web page that takes forever to
load and is slow but guess what that's
what I'm using right now so how hard is
that could that AI possibly be to make
right and so I feel like all that stuff
is super automatable now and it just
isn't because no one's doing it but I
think you could easily do that and then
you could just go around and like every
bank and say here you go here's the
webpage here's the entire web front-end
maker for you and you don't have to do
anything else right
and then you can just keep growing it
from there and it's like oh let's add
every let's add restaurant websites
let's add this that's a bat right eye
and you know people are already sort of
doing a version of this like Squarespace
or something like that that's just like
these templates right how hard is it to
go from that to whatever the rest of the
stuff is people normally pay programmers
to do with their back-end right um you
know I'm saying like it can't be that
hard to just start extending those
template base things so just having some
AI that's like hey now I can just make
my own stuff I don't need to do like it
doesn't have to all be templatized right
it can actually think a bunch about how
to like combine multiple things together
into making a new thing and then you
just you know off you go right so I just
I don't think you need most of the
programmers who are doing those things I
think you could just get rid of most of
them right by just starting to build
things that do the modicum of actual
real work they do just do it automatic
automatically you know I just don't
think that's going to be that hard
do you have a standard vector dynamic
array replacement akru also not using
standard we are not using standard for
anything in fact we do not include any
standard library stuff from the c++ side
of things we don't use any dynamic
arrays though either I don't think so we
never wrote a replacement for standard
vector because we just don't use
standard vector semantics anywhere
anyway that makes up
I wish you see 99 with MS vici but heard
it is not so well supported Microsoft's
could it be an issue for programming and
see with Windows um I don't know I
thought I thought MS BC now supports you
99 pretty well actually
but what I would say is window clang
works on Windows now totally fine right
out of the box you can just go download
clang for Windows and it supports C 99
and every other flavor see you might
want and it outputs pdbs and eggsy's in
native window format so you can just
skip the whole MS vc thing if you want
to I guess is what I would say
I mean here okay so guys here's another
thing just make your AI anytime it can't
figure something out just make it post a
Stack Overflow and wait for someone
answer the question right I mean again
that's what a lot of programmers do they
just like you know they don't know how
to do even basic stuff so they post on
Stack Exchange and they wait for a
printer actually knows what they're
doing to tell them so just do that
there's an AI that's a sellable AI right
just make an AI it tries it's best to
solve the thing that you asked it to do
any step it doesn't know it posts on
Stack Overflow the question if someone
closes the duplicate it looks at the one
it was told to look at and tries to grab
the code from there and weld it in right
get working on it do it right
I mean in savate I'll be there soon
alright I'm gonna call it quits
if some guy in twitch is writing is VI M
plug-in that you asked questions to and
it would look on Google or in a database
for code and paste it in on your cursor
yeah I mean right because there's plenty
of things that are just too complicated
and that it's not gonna work for but a
lot of those things aren't things that
programmers are being asked to do right
I mean you're talking about like
fizzbuzz as an interview question kind
of nonsense that's the bar we're talking
about for a lot of programming jobs
there's no way you couldn't make an ai
ai to replace some of those jobs I mean
there's no way like we will make those a
eyes we just haven't figured it out yet
but we will right and and yeah just like
make the thing have the ability to post
questions to the Internet like that's
part of the I can ask to see if other
people will post code for it right do it
get started
someone will make it and you know you'll
be doing the world a favor because we
won't be having like you know sort of
this this weird like layer of
programmers who aren't really
programmers or whatever who are like
kind of clogging up the economy by
sucking down huge amounts of money which
then creates like income inequality for
people who are really not doing anything
that couldn't have just been done by
robot right so it would be nice it just
kind of like even that out and not have
there be like so many really high-paying
jobs in this weird like concentrated
sort of situation another way to say it
would be it helps create a world where
everyone's in the same boat if there
aren't magically a few jobs that can't
be automated right you know because as
long as there's like a sector of people
with automatable jobs and then everyone
else has automatable jobs you're just
gonna like the money just the money
funnel just points straight at the
people with the unavailable job
right and so you just you know that's
just not a good recipe for stable
society
having a bunch of people who can make
infinite money and then a bunch of
people who can't make any it's not gonna
be not gonna be great right so the
sooner we have everyone afraid that
their jobs will be automated probably
the better you know I feel like that's a
good idea and so the number of
programmers who were around in in like
the 1980s wouldn't create enough of a
disruption so if you could even just you
don't have to automate all the brilliant
jobs just automate 50% right automate
75% you don't have to made 100 right but
just get it up there and that's good
enough because that creates the fear and
that puts everyone into the same mental
category because I mean not all
manufacturing jobs are automatable
either right there are still people
working on assembly lines so you don't
have to be a hundred percent just make
sure that they don't feel like they're
untouchable by the wave of automation
make sure we're all a little bit worried
about that because then we will all
probably hopefully I mean that you know
maybe this is a this is assuming too
much for Humanity but assuming that most
people are in the same boat then they
will presumably act together more than
if you have a hard delineation between
like a large number of people who don't
have to worry about this thing and then
another large number of people who do I
haven't thought that through
particularly well so take it with a
grain of salt but it just seems like we
want automation to be everywhere because
since it's going to be certain segments
quite a bit we probably want to make
sure it's going to be everywhere so that
people are affected more uniformly and
we'll want to take steps to make sure
the
society doesn't like implode as a result
all right
okay thank you everyone for joining me
for the lips on a handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
series at home you can always peer to
the game on handmade hero org and it
comes with a source code so you can play
around with it
we mostly made the PNG writer today we
just kind of slapped it in there but
it's probably mostly done so one good
exercise you could do over the weekend
before I do it tomorrow morning is go
debug why it's writing out the stuff
incorrectly and get it writing correctly
that would be one thing you could pretty
easily do that would be a fun exercise
right because we've got the whole
structure there so now you just got to
go look at it and see what it's doing
wrong so I would recommend giving them a
try if you're up for doing some work
today that that might be educational to
you if you're the kind of programmer
who's still working on stuff like that
obviously if you're an expert this is
nonsense what I'm saying but you know if
you're interested in some beginners kind
of stuff to do try to bugging that that
would be a good exercise I'll be back
tomorrow to debug it myself and then we
can see what was wrong with it all
together until then have fun program
everyone and I'll see on the Internet
take it easy easy everybody and I'll see
you tomorrow