hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode a complete game live on
stream we got a little off-topic during
the pre stream and ended up looking at
some weird meal hash stuff that's just
out goes sometimes
today we are going to try to improve our
art pipeline situation a little bit we
kind of decided that mostly the way we
had architected our matching is probably
good enough for what we want but there's
still some subtlety there and so what we
want to do is we want to go through and
decorate our rooms with imported art
textures and the goal here is to figure
out how we're going to import those
textures in such a way that we that they
correctly get the tags and asset types
associated with them that we want and in
theory that's not gonna be too hard but
in practice there may be its some
subtleties mainly all of this stuff
stems from the fact that files on a hard
drive the concept was made a long time
ago it hasn't really been improved much
it's still kind of crappy and so really
basic stuff that you would want to do as
a developer such as associate a few
enums with a file that merged when you
build is totally unlike theirs it's
completely not anywhere you have to
build you do all that kind of stuff
yourself right all you get when you open
a file is just some contents right and
if it's a PNG then you just get the PNG
and there's no way to say like I want to
have a little thing where you know if I
right-click on that PNG I can put in
some some information so typically what
ends up happening right is people have
all these text files they end up
associating with the PNG and that
specifies the extra information that it
actually needs to bind to the game or in
our case but I'm hoping we can do more
so is actually just use a series of kind
of template not C++ template but the
literal meaning of template meaning a
prefab sort of thing templates that you
can basically put in the file name is
what I'm sort of thinking that'll sort
of say here's the way this PNG should be
interpreted and
it will be interpreted that way so if I
go ahead and get started here I could
show you what I'm talking about we did
the work yesterday to make sure that
this stuff works the way we want it to
but we don't actually have the import
story straightened out yet so here is
our orphanage and the walls currently
are red the florists green and the
passageways in between rooms those are
blue you can see that right now right
and so we just want to do a very simple
task we want to make it so that those
walls actually use a texture from our
art set here right which is one of these
like black orphanage right and we would
like the the floor to use this and we
would like maybe other parts of the
floor as we deem it necessary to use
this so like stone and wood we will
ourselves specify you know maybe which
ones we wants and then that will be the
that will be respected by the game
engine it will put them on there and we
pretty much have how we want to do that
but we don't know how to associate the
file with how we wanted to do that so
where's that gonna happen well if you
look at what happens inside the asset
system you can see that we've got this
notion of an import path here where we
can call check for our changes and it
actually will look through this
directory and it will look for any
changes now none of these things are
actually things that our game has
imported yet so all of them will come up
as not found right but we've never
figured out how we're actually going to
import those now in some sort of way
that makes sense we did a little test
where we could do the hand
here and we did you know we did him
import that and the way that that was
working was when you you set wasn't say
in actually no I take that back
we didn't set in the properties anymore
it's just automatic if you create inside
the data directory when you start up the
game what you can see here is there's a
local HHA file if the game sees a local
HHA file that you have started it will
pack new art assets into it so all you
really have to do is create one of those
and if you do create one of those it
will start importing and then if you
ever want to stop and importing you can
just rename that file to like finish
that HHI or whatever and now that's a
finished art file you can distribute and
you could create another local HHA file
to then pack more assets into on the fly
if you wanted to but you know your
that's choice is yours right um so what
happens here is this pretty convenient
because I can delete that file right
it's gone and then if I run the game
there won't be a hand anymore right
let's see it's not there anymore because
that was imported little it's not really
a hand it was a little it was a little
flaming thing we imported it doesn't
matter anyway so that being in there
because we haven't created a look-alike
say it won't run the import we have our
HHA edit utility right and so we can
always that we wrote we can always
create a new local dot HHA and now we've
got one if we now run will run the
import so right now it's importing it's
done importing so now i've got that
little weird thing back right so we did
all the work to make all of that stuff
happen and the only thing that we
haven't done now is figured out some way
to actually associate the things that
get imported with the tags
and types and all that stuff that we
actually want we even put in ways to do
that we just haven't defined any right
so I don't remember what that was called
but it had a name here somewhere it was
like tag array or something tags that
I'm just gonna look import grid tags so
we define this thing called import grid
tags and would import grid tag grid tags
does is it tells you how the image is
gonna be broken up if the image is gonna
be broken up which you know maybe it
will maybe it won't be so we had a way
of doing that and we at the moment don't
have anything for just single big images
right so if we look at what happens say
with with this this is just 1 4096 by
4096 bitmap and when we import one of
these we don't really need it to be
imported as separate bitmaps I don't
think now we could write I mean we could
do that we could break it up into
separate bitmaps I just don't know if we
want to the top pieces and the bottom
pieces
[Music]
I mean we it just doesn't seem like it
makes much sense and part of the reasons
because this is like longer you know
what I mean
and so it just doesn't seem like yeah
it's it's hard to say
I mean on the one hand there are some
additional things you might want to do
like for example you might want to
expand or contract like if you were
trying to make this be a sort of
repeating text or somehow I don't really
know that we want to do that I think if
you just stretch it a little bit or it's
probably fine so you know I would say if
we just leave it at that we just can
just treat that whole thing as one
bitmap right and we already use it that
way so it's easy enough to do so really
there's an import grid tags thing right
but there's also another kind of thing
where we just pass a single import grid
tag and that's all it actually needs and
I think that's the path we need to
implement today did I not I didn't load
our project file if that's the path we
need to modify today because that's the
one that we would use for walls and
stuff like that so process tiled export
is the thing that uses the grid tags and
is fairly complicated here right you can
sort of see if that makes sense we would
want another path here that's like
processed single image import or
something like this that that wouldn't
go through that path right that doesn't
actually need to do that uh and looking
at the like the way this one goes it's
yeah like it's a little bit more
complicated probably than it would need
to be and you can see here we've even
got sort of a stub out for that so we
want to we want to have some notion of
which of those were doing and
fortunately we know we know that by
what's here block would always come in
as one big thing right whereas character
or item or obstacles would come in as
multiple right so I think that you know
it won't be too hard for us to
differentiate between them so let's
suppose we have one here which is just a
process let's say a single tile import
and I want to distinguish this between
so there's two types of images we might
want to load in
one type of an image is one that we're
going to mush down to a single 512 by
512 texture and another is like a flat
image we might use for a cutscene right
so we've got two kinds of flat imports
we might do and that's fairly important
right okay so what I would like to do
here is I would like to sort of grab
this part out probably and see if I can
just reuse it because all of this stuff
is the same and I don't really want to
be doing you know too much of that right
so what I'd rather do here is something
like this let's say I don't know what
just happened there did I actually cut
that properly yeah like can I just pull
this out into a shared piece of code
that actually extracts one of these
things from an image that's already done
you know what I mean and then have both
of these call it so you know right here
where it would have done it it does the
like you know do the rest of the stuff
and right here we're where we would call
it same thing right and similarly we've
got this down sample where we're doing
sort of this this down sample in place
you can see that this down sample just
writes directly to the pixel buffer in
both cases you know I'm saying so the
source in the destination are actually
the same pixel buffer and pixel buffer
so what that means is because you know
we're gonna want to use this for both
routines this is also something that we
would like to have and so if I if I kind
of go like this and make our down sample
by to also something that can be called
on the pixel buffer then that gives us
this and so I think that's mostly what
we want and what we could do to is say
well we just want to down sample it
until it fits probably I'm not sure what
our approach would be there
I'm not sure what I approach to be there
so I'm gonna say well downsample it so
if it's that maybe dumb
[Music]
in fact that is probably dumb but I'm
just gonna claim that I can do it anyway
yeah so this might be more like down
sample until Fitz and and we'll yeah you
know like just you know I'm saying to
you so you can basically give it an
image and say I want this thing to fit
in here so just keep you know reducing
the size till it does um and we could
make that more you know we could we
could do that in a more filter filter
down sampling by two each time is not
the best way to do it right finding the
exact down sample that would do it and
then down sampling would be better you
know what I mean so we could improve
that some day if we really felt like it
as well so we want to do down sample
until it fits and then we want to do do
the rest of the stuff and same thing
here we want to be down somewhat Fitz
and then do the rest of the stuff right
and so this is going to be a while loop
here that kind of tries to get this
thing small enough like so and so
instead of this being a for I equals
down sample to or whatever actually I
can just get rid of this instead it's
just going to loop until the the size is
exceeds the size that we are going to
pack right and as it goes down the the
dims divided and we probably want to
make this handle
rectangles because there's no reason not
to do that so we probably want to make
this a little bit a little bit saucy err
in that sense right so let's go ahead
and say that downsample to it so it fits
probably takes some kind of an image or
something right we we've got just like
image pixels thing so let me take a look
at where that's defined here right here
so we've got this image 3 2 with high
pixels right so in theory inside here
what we could do is say that the down
sample to fit bit just takes an image 32
and says here's the thing to to down
sample maybe we'll say that will write
back or well you know we could do is say
source image and then have the desk
image come back and then we could say mm
the maximum width and the maximum height
and so this while loop here could be
like while the width of the desk image
right which will set up snot at some
point while the width of that is greater
than the max width or the height is
greater than the max height keep on
going you know I'm saying to you so this
image here is just going to be equal to
the source whatever got passed in which
by the way is like a sprite dim right
it's like sprite in my sprite dim here
cuz that's like yeah although you know
the this actually has like a min this
actually has like a min Max X and
everything I kind of feel like you'd
want to just make the image be that
thing we'll cross that bridge in come to
so anyway we do a process single tile
import or or the multi tile imports
you're probably called multi tile import
presumably this takes all the same stuff
except for this that's probably just
going to be like here's the tags that
we're using I suppose is probably just
now and the rest of this stuff is
probably the same so you know we down
sample the image till it fits in
whatever are required tile sizes there
and I feel like we set that
so interestingly enough we meet our
texture array 512 by 512 but we shrank
everything down by 2 so does that mean
it should really have been 256 by 256
like
it seems like it I'm not sure about that
but here's what I will say this so the
texture rate dim is not necessarily
something that we want to base our art
import on because you know we want the
hhas to be the maximum resolution that
you might run the game at to be to
support that texture radium might be set
to something less than that right so I
don't really know what we want to do
there that's kind of a tough question
but I guess like that's sort of more of
a thing that should be defined in the
HHA file format I feel like you know I
feel like that's something that should
be specified and here more
so I don't really know I'm gonna go
ahead and set it to 512 why not
so I'm gonna claim that I can go ahead
and do this where I down sample this
thing I send it off for processing and
then I'm done and basically the exact
same thing would happen here now I think
that means I can if I want to just do
this
so I could build another image out of
that and just do this here right and the
grid tags here would be the tags that I
would pass and everything else would
just work this you know something like
that I don't know what the image is here
that we're even using just image right
so we could make a thing that says like
hey give me the sub image of whatever
this is so we'll just use that separate
region and then we'll pass it to this
that way multi tile import and single
tile import are actually the same and
they both just do the down sample the
foot fit and then and then they do the
do the rest of the stuff you know aspect
of it
Oh
[Music]
so here we need to be a little bit more
specific about how we are doing these
dimensions so in here we need to have
[Music]
something like this
I guess the result gives us that so
we're sort of saying look the result
with is this thing you know like this so
then what we want to do is divide these
and really that may be the backwards way
to do it so you might really want to do
it like this and then assign them at the
end you know I'm saying and then in here
you're gonna loop over whichever ones
you've acted the new ones you know and
this on this one on the other hand on
the the advance is gonna be on the old
ones you know and that would down sample
in place and keep going as long as you
wanted and the source pointer just
remains the same because the the start
of the image is always in the same place
so that's fine but each time through it
would contract contract contract right
and I think that's really all there is
to that I don't think there's much more
to it so this one here we need to make
it you know it's going to look like this
and I think this is just like you know
right image to HHA or something I mean
and it takes probably all the same stuff
tags tags so it's going to look at that
the align percentage part we're gonna
have to make some way of setting the
align percentages and I think we're
probably just gonna have to set them
ourselves so I don't really know I'm not
sure how we would get that information
in any good way so that's that's a
little bit tough
I mean I guess what I would say is I
feel like if the asset actually already
existed we'd want to use that and you
know honestly it looks like we already
did so it looks like we already did
preserve the align percentage so that's
good so that way we could make a little
tool in the game that sets the alignment
points and adjust them and then it would
write it back to the HHA and we wouldn't
have to if you really are tacit it would
just keep whatever your old aligned
percentages which is probably what you
want and then you'd only have to update
it again if you actually wanted to
change it because the artist had like
change what it looks like or something
and that seems good so when we come in
here when we look at the data size the
data size is going to be I mean we
should just make this part of the image
right like there should just be a call
that says how big is the image that that
seems pretty like straightforward you
know you should be able to just do like
something like
pass me one of these and it just does
right and that way I can just say how
big is the thing we're saving you know
and then it'll tell me and then I
reserve them enough space to store that
if I need to and and off I go
translate the title index into tags it's
the name of the file probably using
something past 13 we're already doing
that so that's to do is done it's not
relevant anymore the bitmap dimensions
here we know what they are and I think
that just does it so image pixels is
actually what we'd be writing out here
and I think I think that's it
so I believe that's correct
I don't I don't think there's anything
weird about that so I think we're pretty
much good to go and so that function
right image to HHA is what we would do
in both cases that's what we would do
here and it's also what we would do here
well actually get this call serious we
don't need to do that so we're really
just down to this guy and it just needs
to take this like region oops
and so if we have one of these I guess I
don't really need to set it equal in
that case so we know the width is going
to be the max X minus the min X and we
know that the height is gonna be the max
Y minus the min Y so at well you know
what so here's the thing though without
a stride that wouldn't actually work
you know I'm saying because you can't
take a slice of an image out if you
don't record the fact that the stride
was actually different so it kind of
seems like in order to do it that way we
would yeah we would need to have a way
to do stride in there which we don't
and similarly I feel like this routine
would need that too right because
otherwise it's going to overwrite that
part of the image so yeah I mean I am
not necessarily certain we care about
that so I think I might not bother to do
it that way I think I'd just copy it out
oh and we do so I guess I was one ahead
of myself because the thing that I just
said I needed to do we do great I mean
that's very nice
the only thing is it doesn't copy it out
once it knows how big it is which I kind
of feel like it's what we would want to
do ya know sans here
so I feel like this is not really what
we would want here and this should
actually be like a separate loop that's
what I say so I'm thinking that it's
more like this you know so when we go to
process one of these it actually gets
pushed on here you know what I mean and
this loop does the copy at that point
now I realize that's a little piggy you
know but I'm not super certain that
there's a reason not to do it that way
because that way you extract just the
parts that you actually wanted the down
sample I suppose could be made to do
that as well but again it seems like it
over complicates things a little bit so
I feel like in here where we do this you
know I would just assume do this twice
so when we actually do get one of these
we just do it like this and we don't
need to do any of this work we're just
doing that and this doesn't do any of
this
you know I mean so this is strictly a
loop to check what the bounds are this
is a loop to write out what we're
looking for and in this case we're
actually going to start at the min X you
know what I mean
and the only thing I think we want to do
here is we wanted to have there be some
extra space in the image right so when
we actually go to take it we wanted to
kind of Pat it out right so I mean I
think we want to adjust these for that
purpose you know what I mean
so I think what we'd want to say here is
just that like
we assume this includes the padding when
we actually compute the values I mean I
mean I think that's what we want and you
know we're gonna we're going to create
this image here to store it
I should probably just even make one of
these right I mean why not if you want
to make an image you can just do this
and say well okay seem good that way
those are always consistent with each
other and you can just say here like
what's the arena that you wanted to push
them on that way here I can just say
this is push image and you know the
these are the dimensions
and that should just work right oops
okay so yeah
moving along okay we'll have to resolve
some of those but really want to look at
that just just so just yet so if we're
gonna do this right we push one of these
on there we've got the pixel buffer now
which we can write to we we could you
know we probably should have a get pixel
pointer thing as well here we can call
on this we're just given an x and a y
and it goes but all I was going to say
here was actually that when we've done
when we've done this border stuff I
think what we want to do here is invert
the sense of these and say look if it's
greater than equal to border Jim then
we're good we can just subtract border
dim from it if it's not we issue an
error and it's zero you know I'm saying
and that means that we'll copy that
region which i think is what we actually
want to do there right we want we want
to include the border you know and I
think we weren't doing that we were
extracting without including the border
which is not actually what we wanted to
do so I think this is actually what's
supposed to happen so you know again
I guess I should say since this is the
maximum value you can have if you're
less than that you're fine if you're not
then you need to write set it to two one
- well no cuz that's an interesting
question so in this case max X is set to
what exactly it's set to the one year
act the pixel you're actually on not one
passed the pixel you're actually on so
in this case yeah it has to be less than
it and a half set it but what that means
is that in here where we do Max and min
it's actually a plus one right because
we're saying the max X and the max Y are
actually not are there they would both
be set to the same value if there's one
pixel which means that when you subtract
the two you'll get zero but you really
wanted to represent a width of 1 so that
is why like I have to add one in that
part of it if that makes sense
of course then I think about that's
that's still not right for this part
what I actually want to do here is say I
guess this is yeah this is that what I
really want to say here is look if it's
less than that then you can you can
increment it if it's not then you
actually need whatever that tyldum is
and this this tyldum here right it needs
to be that minus one so another part of
the problem here is these aren't right
either because we need to do the top
corner of the image plus that so we need
we actually need this as well right that
makes sense
we need like that Plus this to step to
the tile and similarly for min X we need
this right so we need to step to the X
in my index tile and then into the min X
min why I believe because these are
actually not absolute they're relative
you know for whatever that's worth so
all right so when that does the scan off
we go and this needs to happen in the Y
exactly the same way so if it's greater
than the border dim here then that's
fine we can just subtract the border dim
otherwise I've got to be 0 maybe I'll
put that first since might as well put
the action first and put the error
message second
and then again same thing here if we're
within the tolerance there we'll just
set our max wide it looks right to be
out by however much the border is
otherwise we have to set it till the
tiled n minus one which is you know the
furthest out we can set it yet another
way there's probably a better way to do
that too another way to do it is to
inflate all of these and then test but
you know six of one half dozen the other
and this one of you means you can use
you thirty two instead of nest
thirty-two so that seems good so that
should extract to a separate image and
then process when we press the single
tile import we need to be able to
specify the source in terms of the
import tiles which means we need the X
index and the Y index to get passed here
so when we Pat process single tile
import we will pass in these are tile X
and X and tile line index right and
those won't actually take on any value
of importance when we're doing just one
but when we're going from a grid they
will they're just there to store which
part of the grid it came from you know
what I mean so in here right this part
has that stored in this tube
let's see what else we got these are
just naming differences let's see and
these are just that so the grid tag
array information here really is stuff
that should probably be separated so it
could be passed as a separate thing is
what I'm guessing
so in here where we have the you know
like this stuff this should be like
import source info or something
something like that so that information
comes off of like another thing that we
could fill out separately as necessary
and really maybe would be more more
appropriate to not have it on there at
all and you just pass it separately
right so something like this where
you've you've got the tags and the info
and off you go right so let's see here
we want to pass those two things when we
write things to HHA which means that
they would have to be passed here as
well like so and so that looks like this
and that means this would also take one
of those and whenever it calls through
to process the import it's going to pass
that info as well right so the grid tag
array I'm not sure where it actually
sets that information
[Music]
I'll be honest I'm not sure what we're
doing here
I mean doesn't even look like we set any
of that stuff so we didn't set the name
the description or the author right we
basically set nothing so I think this
was just kind of a hack to test whether
that thing was working and it doesn't
really look like we did anything with it
right so I think yeah like we just never
did anything here other than test it
which is what this was and so I mean you
know this is about all we would have had
is that so we want to actually start
filling that out I think we've got most
of the flow right now on that import
[Music]
we have source image what else pixel
buffer for downsample yeah so in this
case we are trying to down sample from
result pixels we don't need to convert
those to you for your twos however and
here I think that's a little good pixel
buffer dest pixel this is tile image
pixels and that should work as well I
think I hope processed out import
identify are not found that's true we
can pass the info along here and now we
sort of have to do when we do update
package from PNG is we're gonna have to
make this thing know what's going on now
we should probably just test the code
path that we have right now because they
made a substantial number of changes and
probably broke some things so we
probably should just step through their
I should probably compile in debug mode
as well and just make sure that's
working first but then I think we're
ready to go because I think that
actually yes like I said so I think we
want to just get that debug cleaned up
and then I think we're ready to go with
a single tile import so we can just call
that and pass it the tags that we want
to associate with with it and that will
put things on the walls like we wanted
and I think that's basically it so I
think that's the work we needed to do so
let's just go ahead and debug it and
then I think we're you know we're done
with that and we'll have to move on to
the next step which is getting the other
things but got plenty debugging to do
here so let's just go ahead and get that
going so let's start by looking at what
we ended up with here so we came through
here and I was saying we need to get a
tiled image that can extract these
things and so it looks like we did that
okay so here's our table image 840 by
704 so you know does that does it make
sense with doesn't it looking at these
bounds here it certainly makes sense
that looks like how big of an image we
would have wanted to a certain degree
right so that seems fine and the
question here is you know we're not
faulting on the read so we got the
source code we're focusing on the right
so you know what's going wrong well you
know this one's a little bit of a fish
in a barrel probably because you can see
like I just didn't update the routine to
actually step over the image that we're
working with it's still using tyldum
which is no longer applicable because I
I'm now actually extracting the
rectangle not just an arbitrary tile
dimension and so
you know there's not a lot of mystery to
why that wouldn't work because it's just
totally wrong so if we actually step
over the image itself and do it that way
then in theory we should be in better
shape at least as far as the crashing is
concerned so let's try that out and you
know it's a little bit hard for us to
see whether something worked or not but
you know we'll we'll find out I guess so
it looks like it actually did work to be
honest because that's it right
so it's close to working but what I will
say is it did not it does not seem to
have associated things quite right
because it should show different
directions and it doesn't look like it's
showing different directions right now
so I'm not certain it actually did do
quite what it should have done and we
probably want to take a look at that a
little more carefully one thing I would
be interested in is whether or not
that's an offset problem
I'm curious here
so I think we're reading from the right
place though because if we look at where
we're reading here image dot pixels we
are offsetting by the tile dimensions
and then by the rectangle area that we
want to extract so it does seem in
general that there's nothing weird going
on there right that all seems totally
fine
yeah and then when we do this and we do
our down sample and come through here so
how are we passing the tags
so we did properly extract the tags
right and we're gonna use this on on the
one on this thing properly it would seem
yeah I can't say I really see what why
that would be failing I want to take a
quick look at the hand here so just
looking at what the image actually is ie
I want to open it actually in cube so I
can see without all the Microsoft
nonsense going on there I'd like to see
what the image looks like in terms of
the yeah okay so it looks like let's
just let's just take a quick look at
which one we're getting out of these
four
so there is more than there are more
there's there are more than one of them
right happening there
so when I push up I am getting the one
presumably that well actually do I I
don't know which one of those is
supposed to be the up direction be
completely honest with you let me look
at the because we had a template in here
right it's so it should be that one so
it's down left up right or I guess from
the top down it's right up down right up
left down so let's see right should be
that one and it's actually is that one
but it's upside down
right down
you see it looks like they're just
upside-down right so it does look like
it's picking the right ones but it looks
like they're upside down which I'll be
honest I don't actually know which way
we were orienting this thing in the
first place like I have no idea what the
rotation on the hand even was so that's
a little bit difficult to even say but
we may have a problem there where we're
interpreting the PNG like the wrong way
round
yeah I'm saying
so there's some other things about this
just real quick I probably will move on
to the room based stuff and then solve
this a little bit later but there's
another thing about this that's a little
bit squirrely which is maybe maybe the
resizing really shouldn't do what I'm
doing maybe we should just only resize a
fixed number of times and the reason is
because if some of these can shrink more
that have to shrink more than others
then the sizing that we use they'll be
off so we need to kind of shrink them
all by the same amount if you will and
so yeah like I may want to change the
down sample to fit part of things and
say that down sample to fit actually
maybe you shouldn't do this instead
should just just do the twice to do
Casey
should we really do the down sample to
fit because it seems like that is
actually bad
for like the things you know just it
seems like yeah we it seems like we need
to do this a little bit differently so
what I'm thinking is is maybe we say
what those dimensions actually are so do
we have a V to you in this code base I
don't really remember now
we know what I want to do is basically
ask what the dimensions of a thing would
be like so I want to do a thing here
that would say something like oh well
actually look I basically want to ask
how many times to downsample something
and then maybe pass that in so maybe
what I want to do is this
get down sample count you know and say
all right you know you say that and you
say you say look you don't need to down
sample it at all we're gonna keep going
here we'll say with equal source with
height equal source height we'll just
say keep going until you hit the desired
amount and this could be done
we could do this in close form but
instead we'll just do a loop like we
could just instead do a scan and say
look how many times we're gonna have to
down stable this thing in order to fit
in there then we can just say like
that's how many times we want the down
sample it so that we can down sample to
fit if we want but we'll just say
actually I can just say look down sample
and this is how many times we want a
down sample so then here this is just
like alright for down sample index
equals zero down sample index lesson
down sample account plus plus down
sample index go nuts and it'll just do
that many down samples right that seems
a little bit better because then that we
have the opportunity to be more specific
if we say processed I'll import here and
we do the down sample to fit inside the
sprite thing instead of doing it that
way we could say instead we know how
much we want to down sample ahead of
time and we're going to use that or
something right and so I'm gonna take
the opportunity here to just go that is
going to be different between the two
paths now so we're gonna do them
separately
and so this one will actually do the
down sample to fit call by asking is it
a get down sample count for fit
maybe so here we're just gonna say yeah
look you need to tell us how to fit this
thing in and then we're gonna do that so
that'll do that and then we'll process
it we don't need these because they're
always zero right so a single tile
import does that but the multi tell
import needs to scale all of these
things the same way so what it's going
to do instead is
say downsample this thing always two
times because that's our definition of
what you would do right another way to
say that would be down sample it to make
sure that you fit this thing but just
based on the import tyldum so instead we
could say look the down sample count is
based on this so if you were going to
try to fit a an example image right so
so something that was the tile dim right
just the test image maybe we'll call
this size test so if you were going to
try and do the science test image how
many times would you have to sample that
down in order to get to what would fit
and then we will sample everybody by
that and that way all of the sprites
shrink uniformly and you won't get one
of them that happens to just have a
shape that fits better sampling
differently which is what I didn't want
to have happen right so we can get rid
of this now and say this is that this is
that and these are lows and then we've
got both paths right so I think that's
okay
I don't think there's anything else in
particular we need to worry about there
I and off we go
so John sampling here is the tile image
not the source image and actually this
is not the tile image it's the best
image
I think that's all good we'll see in a
second so let me go ahead and just
verify that that works at all let me go
local HHA and then create one I am a
little concerned that everything's
upside-down like I said originally so I
think we may have a bug in terms of how
we're interpreting our images but that's
you know neither here nor there
um so now what I'd like to do is go
ahead and and import those other the
block sort I'm looking for the I want to
import those blocks that go on the
orphanage walls right so here we've got
a multi tile import we now know we also
have the ability to do a single tile
import and that's what's gonna happen
with these because they don't obey that
same tiling process so if we were gonna
have one of those coming here it would
look basically the same but again it
would it would just use one of the tags
here and so this are not really sure why
we just why we don't just have this
welded in there I think we wouldn't want
to
[Music]
and so here's one thing maybe I did kind
of was a little hasty there so if we
always wanted to just pass a grid tag
array and it just only has one in the
zero zero slot that might simplify our
lives here a little bit
but I'm just not sure I feel about it
I'm gonna go ahead and say let's not
bother with this garbage right now
anyway I would like to know what the
result here is for because no one's
using it so that doesn't really make a
lot of sense either so I would say but
if that's what we're doing let's just
paste this in here and so if we make a
read stream here I want to just have
some way of taking you know taking this
and and using it it we have pretty much
all of the things that we actually
needed the import grid tags part of this
is just exactly right the file part I
think just works
probably
yeah that that seems like it would just
work and so what we really need to do is
just have the way of differentiate
between these based on the name so file
buffer is the thing that goes right here
I believe I'm not sure where that's
coming from though let me back this out
one level so I can look at exactly what
we were passing down there so we're
passing contents is its file buffer
right
so we want file buffer to be what we
made the reason amount of the asset
source file is is match
right
so in here the asset source file that
we're calling is actually that the image
is always image and the tempering is ten
Terina makes sense so if we just get rid
of this now it's just down to that and
we paste that in and I think because the
temporary nough is actually something we
constructed here it's got to be
addressed there so many of the tags has
to be and tags like so and so now the
big problem is just that single tile
import we need to actually determine
which of these we're gonna do right but
if we actually just compile now we
should be fine here anyway and content
stream temporary nough that needs to be
an address and I think then we're good
so yeah so now the question is just as
we go through each of these what we now
need to do is actually make this tag
stuff do something useful so yeah for
starters the import source info we know
that's the same the whole time so really
that's just up here and what we need to
get there is just some idea of
of where we would get you know name
description and author right and
unfortunately we don't really have a way
of doing that we could use the username
of the person has the author in terms of
the name of the asset like a lot of
stuff we just don't have and you know it
could be things that's annotated after
the fact
but I mean yeah like
I don't I don't really know what to make
of that I think we just were kind of
overly you know we wanted and I agree
with this still we wanted to make sure
you could put stuff into the hhas to
annotate them so you know for each of
the assets you can name it have a
description and have an author but we
don't really have that for any of these
things we could name them something
based on the file name we won't get a
get a description out of it so I would
say description is probably not on the
table the author is gonna be an
irreverent ear so we kind of know what
that is
but we don't really know like we don't
know that if someone else was running
the game and I'm not sure how they would
articulate to us who it was who did the
artwork in the first place and I would
assume that PNG doesn't have that
information either which is not great
[Music]
the username you know is something and
so the you know the rest of it could be
sort of in here as a specialized er of
some kind I don't know I mean I'd like
to have a way to stamp those accurately
but I just don't know how to do it
because I mean who knows like that
information is just not there and so we
could have something that likes stamps
that information on after the fact with
like a tool or something but in terms of
having it automatically happen on import
there's just no way to know like I you
know I have no idea how I would get that
it would be nice but it's not really
realistic I don't think so I don't know
I guess I'll leave that for now and just
say to do how are we going to do this
eventually a dialog box and ask you know
like who wrote who made this art asset
that you're importing I don't know uh so
what this part on the other hand we
might be able do something about so
we'll leave that for a second do we have
a Rhapsody in here
[Music]
yeah uh so yeah like you know that parts
a little Squinkie but yeah it's just how
it goes sometimes
so we then want to go ahead and and
figure out the tag situation right and
so here's I guess how we'll do this
let's start parsing out these things so
of the things we've got block character
cover hand item obstacle and title
screen so title screen is just a bad
name so I'm gonna rename title screen
and I'm going to rename it to something
that will actually allow us to know what
it is so I'm gonna call it a plate right
and so what a plate is is a plate is
something that's just like a cutscene
thing or just something that just gets
splattered on the screen that doesn't
have anything else associated with it in
terms of a structure right so we don't
know what it is we just know it's a big
image and we are not going to subdivide
it up or think of it like a mapped cube
or separate tiles or anything right so
we're gonna have block character cover
hand item or obstacles or plate right
and that's what we're gonna do so in
here what I'm gonna do is do this
strings equals pieces and do this this
sort of description on it now I don't
really want this to be giant inside this
nonsense inside this routine so what I'm
gonna do instead is put that decryption
of the name in here and I should say
parsing in the name it's not encrypted
I'm gonna put that in a separate
function just so doesn't get out of hand
because it's gonna be this huge like
disentanglement of art specific stuff
right so we're gonna have something
interior that looks like that
you know and what I want to do in here
is say let's do an if on you know parse
pieces and that will like right into our
tags array and into our info array so we
can basically parse out like what the
heck it is we're doing you know what I
mean and so we'll start with that and we
have a little bit more we need to do
here because we need also for it to tell
us how big the thing is so again like I
said we might want to kind of change a
little bit of how I was doing it I may
have jumped the gun a little bit there
but well-well fix it don't worry so once
we get in here we just need a thing that
will decrypt these properly so if we've
got you know parse pieces that's gonna
return a boolean and the boolean is just
like you know can I import this do I
even know what the heck it is right and
if I don't then we just don't write and
maybe we put an error in there somewhere
where we're just like look I don't know
what the heck this thing is and maybe
that actually goes in here right so
maybe there's like an air stream that we
write to and that air stream you know we
can we can report our errors when we
parse things so in here we're gonna have
into our air stream we're gonna write
like unrecognized type of import artwork
and when we look and we see these pieces
we can now enumerate the ones that we
actually care about so there's block
there's character
there is cover hand item obstacles and
plate I and you know since these have
different import processes that kind of
have to to go along with them there let
me this does not belong here anymore
wait where did hand come I deleted hand
no okay it's right here so if we look at
the parse pieces thing we would want to
see which kind of thing it was and how
we needed to import it and we possibly
need to
we possibly need to switch on that so we
may have to do something like this you
know I mean so we would want to be able
to say here's the multi tile one here's
the single tile one there's also the
plate one where we get you know one of
these things that doesn't get resized
like we just we just take it or maybe it
does get resized but it doesn't get
resized to those limits you know what I
mean
so there's there's basically like one
more of these that's the least processed
version that basically says if you get
this
we don't down sample or we down sample
only once
like what's the res on this thing yes if
we don't sample like one time you know
on those
[Music]
so here we do something like asset max
plate them you know and it would do its
thing there and you know you know maybe
that's the maximum plate them I don't
know so I think that's roughly what
we're looking for
and since all of those now fall in line
with that the next thing we just have to
do is actually provide some tagging
ability for each of these things right
now what I can do is make these pieces
return something like you know you know
import type here and we can have you
know one of the import types is multi
tile one of the import types is single
tile and one of the import types is
plate and then of course there's like
import type none you know I mean so here
it can return one of these
and that way just kind of knows what
it's dealing with so that way when we do
the import it will say like okay which
kind should I import and we can make
sure that everything's set up properly
for that and off we go
so in this case if we want to allow
hands to be imported then what we can do
is say import type multi tile and you
know that's what it will that's the path
that it will try to to take right and
you know when we do this parse pieces
we've got sort of the stuff that's
getting set here the destination info
and the destination tag array those will
get set we then need the piece stuff
which is this and piece count I don't
think we care about
so I think that's all fine and then that
asset struct it's gotta be able to grab
so I think we can make that be the locus
of the parsing as far as errors are
concerned when you actually get one of
these files
[Music]
it just has a stream for that so we can
just pass a stream and so then when we
call this function we need to pass the
assets the pieces and the errors for
that particular one like so and then in
here what we actually want to do is like
you know use this thing where we say
what's the import type and we ask it so
and it tells us so then here we can just
say look if we were supposed to import
it then we will
and I think that should do it
in this case the tags we only have one
of them so when we import that we really
just want to use tag zero zero so and
the same would would be true here I'm
not sure what the other thing that was
complaining about was looks like nothing
so that would import all of the
different hands in theory and we can
already kind of maybe look at that as
[Music]
reason why we need to start thinking a
little harder about how this I mean we
want when this imports hands now to be
able to select the hand that we actually
wanted using tags right and so we want
to be able to do that and right now we
can't actually do that so that's
definitely something we want to improve
yeah
[Music]
so we need to make it a little bit more
we need to make it a little easier here
to define what all these tags are
and I'm not sure exactly how we want to
do that look I don't really want to have
to define these all in different places
but it seems like that would be the only
really weighted well you know you could
just redefine them here every time cuz
you're gonna have to anyway so I guess
you just do begin tag array and Tiger a
and you just do it right in here is the
best way to do it because you're gonna
have to do that anyway based on the way
that I kind of wanted it to work out
going forward all right so let's
actually do the hands then because I
want to do it we got to do this for the
blocks and for the hands so we've got
like a fire hand a glove hand right and
[Music]
and a skeleton hand and so
what I want to do is I want to have
these instead of naming themselves that
way I want them to sort of just have the
tags in the file name yeah I mean
and this again is the part that I say is
so delicate
really
but you'll have to just bear with me
here so let's suppose that we wanted to
to talk about this right so the first
thing I'll say is that's not really fire
even if it was right like it's more like
undead energy or something and
furthermore this would probably not
really be that way like we'd probably
get rid of those and like I probably
have an or move that and we'd probably
just do that with a particle system so
they would animate but regardless of
that part of it let's just assume
because we still need the interior piece
which is like the little like solid part
that's just floating there so let's
suppose that we were going to do that
like I don't know what that stuff is
it's like dark energy or something right
it's like it's like some kind of like
necro energy so this is really like dark
energy one like that's a hand that has
dark energy of one so what that looks
like and I don't know that you know how
else to really talk about it but you
know another way to say it would be
fingers zero right like this is one that
doesn't have any fingers and it has dark
energy this one is has a glove and it
has fingers right
I'm sorry
this one has fingers and it doesn't have
any flesh right so it's like it's got
bones but no flesh I'm not sure how you
would necessarily specify that
probably just the fact that it has bones
so I guess another way to say this would
be a little bit different that's I don't
know what that really is other than like
you know it's it's this dude his little
floating hand and so I'm not really sure
what you call that you know you know
maybe I'll just call it bones and so
that one's just bones that's all it's
got this one's got a glove and maybe
that's really all it's got to right I
mean doesn't have anything else that we
could really say about it although I
guess like I said we could say that the
glove has individual fingers is one way
to talk about that glove so I don't know
so those are just some examples of ways
I could name things and if we always
wanted to have them be one we could omit
that meaning if they were if they're
just binary tags and we don't like have
like a certain amount of them really
then you could it so I suppose another
way to that would be like you know you
could just do it like this and say if
you wanted to add a number you can you
don't have to write
and so then we instantiate an entity if
we added the property to the entity and
said you know this this entity has you
know this this entity has a glove and
fingers it's gonna pick this one because
that's the one that it has if you didn't
say fingers in just said glove it still
picked that one cuz doesn't have any
other options to use but if you drew
another one here that was a glove that
didn't have fingers that would pick that
one instead right and so I think that's
roughly what we want I think so that in
here where we say block you know again
I'm really not quite sure what the level
of asset type should really be I don't
want what just happened at all I hate
this file explorer
there we go that's I'm like I don't want
any of that I yes I just so
in terms of the basic category right if
we stop looking at the legacy categories
although hand is still a valid one you
know it could be that we literally are
talking about this maybe that does stay
in here but you know maybe a block is
just a block and we don't like it's it's
literally just the things that are on
there right it's literally these things
and I don't know so you know we've got
block item character cover item plate
and obstacle and maybe you don't
actually do this so everything you
instantiate just has to have the right
properties to pick something from the
set you know and so four characters
there just in two halves so you got the
bottom and the top which is really just
head and torso right are the two parts
there so really we don't need that so
we're really talking about this and this
and this will still be used at least for
the time being right so will those at
least temporarily the rest of this stuff
would not be used and so then the like
basic category is just which one of
those things you were trying to say what
what that you were using because they
sort of have different formats to a
certain extent but that's basically it
and then when you parse them in it just
uses the back part of the name so it
just says like okay you know parse this
stuff and that's what that's what it is
I don't know and so if we did it that
way then you know then you've got the
tags that try to specify what's going on
and so you know the tag array which is
this stuff that then gets all of the
other things in it so basically you
would have in here all the stuff I just
said so there's something that's like it
doesn't have bones
does it have dark energy does it have
gloves this does it have fingers and you
know whatever else we add and that's
what we would do right I and those are
just the properties that we had and they
would just go into the game and you
would just add new properties as you
want them to distinguish between things
that you feel like need to be
distinguished in a different way than
ways that are already currently in
existence right so I think that's what
you would do so this just ends up being
one past last tag index was two there's
two der tags I guess anything so
basically this just has to be something
a little bit better and then I think
we're mostly done right so what you need
to do here is you just need to say I'm
gonna add whatever the tag is and you
know it's always type ID equals asset
hand and then in here we just need to
say what the tag set is let's just real
quick look at what that is inside the
info structure here so if this is an
import grid tag then I think what we
want to do is just say okay well I mean
I guess I can leave that as it is but
we're just gonna say tag equals end tags
or something and we just say like okay
begin tags you know add tag add tag
whatever write something like this end
tag and it's a hand write and then this
will set everything up for us so we need
to sort of do this where we just like
here's the tags that we're adding this
thing begin and end them and go from
there right so I think that's all we
really need to do and
[Music]
you know we again this can all sort of
be done ahead of time and then just
referenced sort of well no it can't
because you're reading it from the file
name so assuming that you're actually
gonna do it that way then you do need to
begin in tags you need to add the
individual tags the tags need to come
from whatever the pieces are that you're
actually processing here right so the
direction tag in this case we can get
rid of sort of the thing that was doing
the dirt agz bit
and what we want to do here is just say
this is the actual set of tags that we
wanted to make and so the Y index is the
thing that tells us here which one we're
actually trying to do so we're talking
about this right and off we go so let's
think about this for a second that tag
is facing direction its value is this
its basic category is asset hand oh so
wait if that's already set I guess we
just have to set it in two places which
is kind of annoying but we can wrap that
into the end tags bit so that's really
not the end of the world um so when we
begin the tags here we just have to make
sure that we know how many we need which
shouldn't be too hard and then we can
just put the system on and finish right
yeah
and and that should be it so let's go
ahead and make that happen
I want to make like an end tags here and
that would be what would actually do
this stuff and it would also be what
would actually set this stuff and it
would return that so you'd basically
have an import grid tag that's like the
result here you would be returning it
inside here you'd want to say look the
type ID of this thing is whatever type
ID you told me it's also the type ID
that I would set here is the basic
category we could be more explicit and
say that's actually a category because
that's really what it is now the first
tag index and the one passed last tag
index are going to be based on how many
we actually used and here where we do
our end tags you're gonna have to pass
in whatever that category actually was
so this is an asset basic category
category and then we just need like some
little builder thing that lets us know
how many of these tags we actually used
so then we can do begin tags end tags we
can pass asset hand there right we can
add the tags for facing direction as we
go so this would actually look like this
right
and we're really only doing four of
these at the moment so know why we
decided to do that there but let's do
this right
so we're gonna take one of these and
divide out the rotation amount I really
don't like that I think that was a dumb
idea by the way I think it should just
be zero to one
but we'll talk about that some other
time so anyway when we actually go in
here to do the beak in tags we would add
the facing Direction tags it would
automatically add the category tag and
know what that was and so then the only
other tags we need to add now are the
ones that we actually parsed out right
so they're the things that actually you
know come from the pieces structure
right so in here we don't need any of
this anymore although this may be
something that we need to kind of put up
here and begin tags and we're gonna how
to deal with some of that so it's fine
but essentially what we're doing is this
and we want to add the tags that we know
we want to add based on the template and
then we also want to add the tags from
the rest of the parse right and so the
way that this works you could kind of
see here where we're looping through
this and we're doing that scan for
underscores and then we update the
string hash value nonsense stuff right
so probably we really don't want to do
that anymore like we probably want to
let this thing parse and we probably
want to have it parse slowly and pigley
just to make things a little bit easier
on us on ourselves
so I guess what I'd say about that is
this part should probably go and that so
the piece cat stuff should probably not
really be a thing when we go to do the
parse pieces what we'd want to do here
is actually just send in the file itself
the full filename I think so that yeah I
mean that's just it's like what we're
doing here right we want to just kind of
say look you can parse the whole thing
yourself and we're not well we're just
gonna do it many times and it's gonna be
piggy and it's fine
so I would say yeah like since this is
only on import I'm fine with it being
piggy for now so I would say we just
have a thing here that's like hey let's
parse the thing that we get as it comes
in I don't know what all that but we'll
first parse it to get this stuff out and
then go you know further from there so
the way I'd like to do that is I like to
say probably something like this
so I'd like to do something where we
read a token out of the file name and
then use it something like that so we
kind of grab pieces out of the text as
we go and then in here where we do sort
of begin tags
maybe we just say look parse the rest of
this thing uh and add all those in you
know what I mean and then we'll add any
additional tags that we want to add on
top of it and then we'll close it off
right that seems reasonable to me
reasonable to me and so when we go
through parsing these out we'll just say
yeah you know there's a way to grab the
next one of these off of the list and
you know there's a thing in here that
just has whatever the text of the thing
is and we don't have to really think
about it too much harder than that at
the moment but we'll probably make this
a little bit better once we go to do
like sort of something a little more
real but what we can do here is just say
you know there's a there's a source and
the source is going to get advanced by
scanning for the next whatever right in
this case we'll just use underscores
like we were and then we're going to
return
so when we you know parse this forward
what we do is say use the same
construction we were using before to
scan you know through it
actually I guess we don't do that
because here we actually know so we kind
of know what the index is I think about
it right
so as we scan through here we just say
look if the one we're on is is an ending
piece and we don't have to check for
this anymore because we know we would
know when we got there right so if we
see that we've got one of these then we
just remember it right and we say the
result is just gonna be however many in
we are right and the data is just going
to be the same as whatever the source
was you know I'm saying and then we can
exit if we well and then we can update
the source right in there as well so
then we would say well the source count
is gonna be less by however many this
thing was plus the one we're on and the
data is gonna be the same right so the
source is gonna go the sides gonna go
down by that much and the data will go
forward by that much
and then here what we would do is say
well actually I guess we don't even have
to say it we can just do this so if we
never find an underscore we just return
whatever the input is I and advance by
that much at the end right so what we
could do is say something like this
which is to say that look whatever we
find will advance by that
and the only time we won't do that is if
there wasn't any advancement to actually
make right a la guess that doesn't quite
work in the case where you just have a
like a set of underscores so I guess
what you would have to say there it's
just like look if the source had a count
then whatever we're gonna do here do it
right and if it didn't then just return
it and I think that does the right thing
so that allows us to just keep going and
I suppose if we then didn't want to do
anything fancier the tokens we could
actually make these just be strings
themselves and keep it simple I'm not
really sure I want that because I might
want to have numbers in there like I
said so you know I'm you know I think I
want to do that probably and then just
what we'll do pretty much always when we
return is just actually set that value
to one and we'll deal with that later so
I want to do this and then we'll just
return those as we go so as you pop
things off the string
it just goes ahead and gives you back
those values and then you can you can
parse them incrementally and have a
little bit of a party right so I think
that's mostly what we would need to do
and ice yeah I don't think there's
really anything much else to it so then
in here what I want to do is I would
like to parse it so when we actually pop
that off and then we use it later in
here what I can do
is just sort of loop through and say
like that so these are the tags
I'll keep grabbing tokens off the tag
string if the name token has a count
we're good
otherwise we bail any here we can look
for the different kinds of tags that we
have you know what I mean so really what
we do here is just say we'd probably
make one of these sort of things that's
just like a tag mapping so we'd probably
say something like tag like named tag
good name tag right so we'd have a name
and we'd have an asset tag associated
with it right so inside wherever that
tag array
is assets you know we have something and
this is again why C and C++ are very bad
they have no way of just generating this
it should just be directly created from
here right
but hey forty years is a long time to
figure out that language is supposed to
have an inspection name so yeah what do
you do um so here's our name tags and
what I want to do is just say which are
the ones that were you know we've got at
the moment I'm just gonna say that we
have these and I'm just gonna give them
those actual names now I don't actually
want to do rap Z because this is
actually a string constant so if you
look at like something like this I
actually want the constant version that
just defines it in place I just want
this to be a table that's compiled and I
don't want to call anything so I just
want it to look like that right and so
in here where we say like hand bones
like bones would be a tag that comes in
there right and so here what did we call
it just dark energy and maybe you don't
even need to call out dark energy maybe
we should just call it dark
you know I'm saying and so that just
gives us a way of translating between
these two in some way that that we can
easily add to because we're gonna have a
lot of these so let's suppose that it's
just that and so dark is just dark
energy and we again don't have to be
one-to-one like if we wanted to we could
allow either of those in case like you
just forget which one is which right and
so what we want to do here is just say
this array of tags we want to figure out
which one it is and so what we can say
is just look give us a way of switching
between those right so tag ID from here
is the string we just do a for I loop
over the ones that we've got and you'll
notice that you couldn't do this if you
just used an array that had the same
index as each of the things so if we
just made a mirroring thing with the
strings it's not as powerful so you kind
of want this to actually have a mapping
switch you can have more than one string
defined for every ID because you might
just want to have a quick way of saying
oh the artist typed gloved instead of
glove let's just accept that as glove
instead of forcing people to rename
files for no reason right
and so in here we're just gonna say if
strings are equal not know if we have a
lowercase looks like we don't but we
would probably do lowercase here if we
had it we'll just say hey if the strings
are equal then that's the tag ID there's
got to be a nun said the priest or there
doesn't wow what how did we not have a
zero tag ID people who is responsible
for this
that is super terrible now a fan of that
not a fan at all I'm gonna do this here
because it'll work but
I would like that to be zero okay it's
not zero oh well so we do result here
and we do the name tags for whichever
the one is that we're on and we returned
that ID that gives us a way to decrypt
that right and so all we're doing here
is just saying if the name you gave us
matches the name of the table then we
return it otherwise we have no idea what
it is so you know don't ask us so in
here when we say we're gonna begin these
tags we're just going to go ahead and
parse them one at a time and when we see
each individual name token come out
we're just gonna ask you to tell us what
it is please right because the only
things that we're gonna understand at
this point is the thing the the the ones
are in that table like maybe in the
future we'll do other stuff but the
moment we definitely don't so what we
want to do is say give us a tag ID if
the tag ID is not equal to tag none then
we can process it otherwise maybe we
give an error maybe we don't I don't
really know how we want to deal with
that my inclination is to say that we
don't recognize the tag name and maybe
we even print out the tag name I don't
know that's maybe getting a little saucy
but you know we could do it
potentially
I think out F let's just do this so it
would be that right yeah right
mmm the problem with it is we don't
actually
oops sorry the problem with it is we
don't actually have like we want to be
able to just print out length strings in
in the out F right that work that we're
looking at there look in here you know
so like our format string list you know
it's got all this mumbo-jumbo in there
and
but when we print things out you know we
can do
it looks like we can do that right we
can we can't actually read it in that
way if we want to the other thing we
could do is add something here that is
designed to print those specifically but
it looks like we could do that so if we
wanted to again there we can just say
like alright well you know print it out
there it is the problem with that is
that strings themselves this is too
large right so it would not properly
this will not properly get converted to
a 32-bit value because it's a 64-bit
value and that wouldn't get downcast so
what you again have to do is you have to
like remember here this is why again C
and C++ terrible at this if you want to
have a way and do not say i/o streams
because that doesn't solve this problem
iOS dreams are a different way of doing
things but if you actually want to have
a function that just takes a variable
number of parameters there's no way to
push the types of those parameters on
before the types without doing a lot of
really disgusting stuff because again I
don't know who works on C++ but they are
often some la-la land where people don't
actually program stuff for a living so
anyway we can do that but it's a little
ugly so if we were gonna print out
strings we should add you know
because that's just too error-prone in
my opinion anyway so if we look at what
this is doing assuming that the tag idea
that we have on there is is actually
valid then we can go ahead and do an ad
tag and we know the tag ID and the name
token gives us the value like so
so mostly then what we have to do is
just actually figure out the right way
to build this tag array and yeah you
know for every tagging value that we
have we need some way of actually
pushing it on there
[Music]
what is asset oh yeah that's don't need
to say that twice sue I think mostly
what we've got to do now is just make
sure that we've got everything we need
to actually add a raise of tags that
makes sense not sure why I'm not able to
jump to error there there we go
this is actually an array lookup and I
think that should do it now when we are
parsing these we do want I think an
error stream to be passed in so we also
need the asset structure because without
it we would not be able to reserve any
tags right so we got to do that as well
this part here we haven't done yep I
just want to preserve it for posterity
uh so we need to have this obey the
standard way we're looking at it and
this is you know whatever this is do
that in a second and I think that should
be okay so this we know is four and I
think that's everything so we've got
begin tags
and we've got everything else this just
has to be named token text and then
we've got a nice little way to read
everything from the file name and go
from there
parse pieces in this case I don't really
want it to pass the address of a string
what was it trying to do there oh so
that's not an actual string it's just a
care star but I would like it to be a
string so I want to capture that into a
string for it to use right like so so
I'm just gonna do that so that gets us
down to where we could we're within
striking distance of having the parsing
work we just need the tags to actually
be a thing right sue
asset and errors here we've got errors
and we've got assets so we just do this
so really all we're talking about is how
do we do the addition right how do we do
the addition here and so we kind of want
to do like a little builder thing I
think and maybe what we could do here is
just say look we know there's only so
many tags we're gonna allow on here so
we could just cheese out and say like
that's how it works right
like we could just say
buffer them up then do reserves and go
or we could just stream them out I'm
really not sure which one of those two I
want to do let's just stream them out
for now maybe and I guess the other
thing is we may not want to allow the
import to complete in cases where we
don't recognize like the tags or
something I guess we'll cross that
bridge when we come to it so when we do
a begin tag ad tag in this case I'm
gonna say like maybe there's just a
little builder here that that that goes
on right and so maybe you know that is
something that you pass in the headend
or maybe not I'm not sure but let's say
it looks something like that and and
maybe furthermore it looks something
like that
so we've got a little thing here this is
the tag builder doodad and get something
that just makes this easy inside here
we're just going to store the stuff that
we actually need
so probably the assets probably the
first tag index and probably the tag
output something like this so when you
actually send one of these down and you
want to add a tag what its gonna do is
something like this right it's gonna say
give me the tag for the current tag
index and then go ahead and increment
that right then set that tag stuff to
what ever it should
right so for some reason we seem to have
deleted the code where we were setting
tags before but you know it's pretty
straightforward it's just an ID and a
value right so if we quick look at one
of those looks like yeah so it's just an
ID and a value so if it's just an ID and
a value we just assign them off to go
and then we go ahead and well I guess we
don't have to return the tag right so
the only thing we have to do here is
issue an error if we can't right so we
need to check to make sure that we could
actually right but if we can right then
we're done in here where we do the begin
tag stuff this has to actually set that
up so this is the tag builder here the
tag builder well I'll just I'll call
this builder in this case is going to
store the assets because we're gonna
need that it's gonna store the first tag
index which comes from here and I don't
know that I actually want to do reserve
tags so I think this is gonna have to be
more special purpose than that right so
in this case we've got reserve tags as a
function here which like looks to see
whether it can actually do this but
we're actually going to do this as a
two-step process so we're actually gonna
do here is say look the first tag is the
tag count that's just what's going down
we know what the max tag count is so
here we're just gonna say look if the
max tag count would allow us to write
this thing so if the tag has less than
the max tag count go nuts otherwise
maybe not right that's sorry that's
correct tag index otherwise no dice
right and so here you know maybe we want
to do issue an error
but we probably don't want to issue an
error they're actually probably what we
want to do is say builder error equals
true and that way we can just actually
have that as a separate thing that gets
handled later that's the way I would
probably prefer to do it so we add all
those tags in there then at the end what
we do is we finally go to write this
thing out then we can say well the first
time in the tag index is whatever the
Builder says it is right so this is
builder first tag index right because
that's the thing that we actually set up
here we need to set that cur tag index
to be equal to the first tag so this is
basically you know we just start at
whatever the count is and we go from
there when we actually go to finish up
then we just say well one passed the
last tag index is just going to be
whatever the current tag was right and
then we're done when we do this though
we may have had an error so we may want
to in here have some way of issuing an
error out to the stream errors so you
know maybe what I'll say is here we'll
just say when we end you can send errors
down and in this case what we'll do is
when we encounter an error of that form
we will issue it so if in here we see
that the builder had an error on it we
will do out F errors you know out of tag
space or something like this right
and that should let us continue to sort
of just work that and we can make a
thing that maybe in Crete you know
reallocates the tag array or something
like this I don't know exactly how we
want to do that but we can we can
probably work on making it so if that
error can't really happen in practice so
I think that would just work and that
would be the end of it right so that
should associate what we wanted I think
that should associate what we wanted in
this case go in builder and yeah
and I guess I will leave the asset ID on
the end because it just looked better
down there and it was easier so I guess
we'll just do that we could actually
have everything down on that one in fact
if we wanted to in fact maybe that's
what we should do so we just say hey we
do an end tags it looked like that we
pass the rest of the things like we
passed the type and the file name in
there and we just do the parsing in
there right so begin tags doesn't do
anything like it just does that and then
in here we go through and add all the
rest of the tags so we add the basic
category and then we add all these other
things in and the tag string actually
comes in here right so everything's in
in tags and the only thing that's in
begin tags is just just to get things
started by passing the assets in and
that's it that seems fine and I guess we
don't care about that either so I think
that's maybe we needed
might be us so we spammed a lot of stuff
in there let's before ending for the day
because I know we went overtime but I
just was in the middle of it didn't
really feel like stopping um let's just
go ahead and just try real quick
to step through that right cuz I just
want to see I just want to get rid of
the basic bugs and then we'll leave the
rest for next week which is using the
system and finding out if it actually is
what we want or not alright so if we're
gonna do this import let me force it to
re-import everything that we've got so
all the hands will get reread and we'll
see what they do
so in here when we when we go to do
parse pieces I want to see what happens
so for starters it's you know we're
passing in this file name and that's got
a you know plate title screen right it's
got the whole thing in there so the
first thing I want to do is just make
sure that pop token works right so let's
see what happens so here's the result
that it's considering right now which is
to say it's the whole thing it's gonna
look for an underscore it's gonna look
for five characters and not find it but
then it is gonna find it right and now
it's made a result which is five long
plae right that's correct but now we
have to make sure that it correctly
removes from the source is this right
the word plate and the underscore and it
did right so that's good and now we can
look at what we've got and we see we
have a plate well it doesn't matter
because we're not actually using that
path so we we leave and off we go
right so now let's take a look at the
path assuming that works that actually
involves thing we do recognize which is
here and so now we want to do
actually build the tag array out of
what's left right so we look at the file
name that we've got here it's just glove
fingers we want to now make sure that we
build a tag set that has glove and
fingers in it right so let's go ahead
and try to do that we start by creating
a tag builder we're going to add one of
these tags in there right so which is
what we're gonna do here 4:27 we're
gonna add one and then we're gonna write
it in to the tag array which should be
fine we then got to do our parse again
we added another tag there which again
also fine so let's see what we get when
we pop the first name token we get glove
which is what we want let's see if we
could recognize glove though we do so
that's good we then go to add that tag
as a one so it has a glove tag of one
that's exactly what we wanted we now
come back around parse the next thing
out fingers is what we wanted do we find
it we do so we have that one and now we
should get okay so there we've got a bug
we should have gotten for this next name
token nothing right but instead we got
73 which is not a particularly
compelling number to receive you know
I'm saying to you so our our pop token
is busted
and I'm not sure why
that was the case
so let's try that again shall we
it's the first time we enter n tags so
it should be pretty easy to just do that
again
so here's us grabbing glove right
and what's the tag string here is this
right so let's grab let's see what
happens when we grab fingers so here's a
source right we go through here and we
don't find anything oh right
[Music]
so I was a little too clever and you can
see that this plus one is wrong here
right we have a seven and that's all we
should remove so it's just the it's the
last one that's the problem so when we
don't find so we really do want those
two cases I guess I can't figure out a
way to be more clever there as much as I
want to so when we come in here I guess
what I would say is
is the source count well so if if the
source count is valid
you
I think I should not write it that way
but if the result count is valid then
the really only question is do you use
plus one or not to get rid of this or
don't you right and the answer I think
is just you have the one if you can so I
still could be a little clever I suppose
I don't really know if I need to be or
not I mean here's the clever or way I
guess clever is in some pretty
questionable quotes there but you know
what do you do so if we happen here and
jump to end tags unless you if we get
this time so there's our five
there's our our sorry our glove and
there's our end so so that's fine so now
we've imported the glove and I think
we're probably fine when we're done
importing the glove are we stuck
somewhere here no we're still running
there we go
so in theory now - like if we wanted to
put some properties on this glove we
could write it doesn't look like the
facing directions working right there so
I think we still maybe have a little bit
of an issue
I think I mean that looks like we're
adding it correctly but I'm not entirely
sure so we do zero the imported max and
we just set the ones that are in the
zero column with and the why we just go
ahead and set those I don't know it
doesn't look like the facing directions
really being used to pick though is the
weird part and I'm not sure why so I'm
trying to think if there's a reason why
the tags are wouldn't be obeyed in this
case it is the first tag but that should
be fine I don't see why that would cause
a problem and let's see how we extract
them here we do first tag index and Kurt
again this is the one pass so that all
seems legit
oh but we need to advance tag count
itself
so actually Kurt AG index isn't a thing
so actually when we do this ab tag here
it's it's really just this right so as
we go we increment the tag count each
time in the actual asset structure and
then we do one pass last tag count it's
it's really this right and so the
Builder itself doesn't even need that
particular piece of information that can
actually go away so they were just over
writing their the tags were over writing
each other right
so I think that's good and off we go
so now it should import those and and we
should have our different versions of
our different hands there right looks
like we've got a scaling bug in there
but I think now we're pretty good like
that's and I've saw that but you can see
there's like a a weird like dimensional
issue happening with one of those guys
so but I think other than that we're
probably in good shape here and I just
I'm not 100% certain but if we were to
go in here I'm just curious to the
entity set and when we do our rendering
and put in the facing Direction tag here
I'm just curious if we were to do this
what happens right just curious if we
get any better matching there
doesn't look like it
oh yeah
so unfortunately yeah it doesn't look
like that did not work first time
unfortunately I was kind of hoping we
could do a match here on one of these
but it doesn't look like it although to
be fair you know I'm not 100% certain
what we want to do next is actually
print out what the assets themselves
actually have in terms of their what
they have in terms of their tags on them
right and I think I'll stop short of
that so I think we did all the work we
need to do but of course we've got some
debugging to do I think we also did all
the work we need to do for our our wall
pieces because now because that's all
done blocks don't have a grid so really
all we would do there is just this we'd
say they have a single tag at 0-0 that
gets used right we'd say begin the tags
we don't have anything to add right and
then it would just use what all whatever
the actual blocks filename had in it
would be what it would use and then you
know you're you're pretty much done in
fact we could even just try this one
because this would show something on the
walls
it just won't match properly because we
can't add the ability to specify any
properties to it because it's gonna it
doesn't look like our tag stuff got set
properly or isn't getting matched
properly one of the other but this would
presumably import a block that means
that when we actually create the rooms
for example we can at least
now that they are in fact blocks so
instead of saying asset grass here you
know we could just say asset block
instead and then you know if we import
blocks they should in theory show up
right mm-hmm
famous last words um but yeah we've got
a lot of work to do there so I'm not
actually sure and that actually didn't
take very long so I think for some
reason we didn't actually import that
block so I will look at that one as well
parse pieces oops just want to make sure
and go so we do get here yeah yeah so
when we get to the block parser let's
just see what it does I just want to
have some some clue so let's go into end
tags and see oh well that's still okay I
mean yeah it doesn't know what these are
but that actually we know that because
we didn't add any of those tags in but
it should still produce the basic
category correctly so it should still
have added it to that right which is the
asset block so that should actually
still be fine I think right so I feel
like it should still have added
something
yeah so so we did import those correctly
which means that probably our renderer
just at the moment doesn't actually put
cubes down with the texture yeah so if
we just matched on the texture
I guess we're fine it's been a long time
but so we need to actually get the we
need to actually get a resolved bitmap
ID to push the cube down which is fine
so it takes a renderer texture but we
don't actually have one of those we just
have a bitmap addy we don't really know
if it's been loaded so if you look at
like push bitmap for example or word is
push it does an actual check in there to
determine whether or not it has to
[Music]
whether it can actually render in an eye
it's actually this one here right so it
first looks to see whether it can get it
and then it checks it does the missing
resource count so we want to do that and
you can see we've got one here that does
that push cube but we didn't actually we
haven't updated that to actually support
the full set of things can pass the
renderer which we need now so if we
actually do update it to be that way and
say all right here's the actual set of
things we need and the only difference
is that we're gonna pass one of these
instead you know what I mean
then we can use the full deal and I
think that'd be fine don't quote me on
that
yes so we're now at least getting
bitmaps on there but it's picking
something that doesn't have content to
it right so we have to go check to make
sure that there actually is something
good in the bitmap but I think that you
know that's probably just a bud with the
with that asset import that we're
working on right now probably not with
the entity renderer so when we loop
through here presumably getting that
match for the asset category actually
does Ford backs like now we don't
actually know we could check and see it
might be that when we go to do that push
cube we're actually getting an on we
might be getting no match back right but
you know like I said I think it's at
this point it's too late in the day to
keep going so I think I'd stop and then
just pick it up because I think we're
just in debugging land now there is no
there's no more actual code to write
there's just a bugging so if we come
here oops
did not I didn't hit any of those keys
that you're saying I hit so I want to I
want to break there but you're not
letting me why aren't you letting me
oh because I'm not in debugging and we
all know it's impossible for the for the
compiler to tell where anything that it
generated win right so if we what the
heck someone want to tell me why we're
not what is happening
so you're saying it's not possible to
ever have a piece type of cube okay
we're on the line oh you know what I
know what that is
Visual Studio changed it so that if you
if you you used to have to set a
breakpoint
on this line they just keep making this
thing worse whatever
so the bitmap ID here is always zero so
it looks like actually it's a match
failure right so the problem here looks
like that the asset category is failing
like we're not actually getting anything
in that asset category right so when it
says get best match from it basically
says there isn't one um so it must mean
that when we categorize these things
we're doing it wrong so we're going into
here and we're saying get best matched
asset but there is no asset of that type
now is that a save and restore issue or
is that a match issue so what I'm
interested to know is if I was in the
asset system here when we go to actually
finish these off and we do the import
right what do we actually what is going
on with the break points
this thing's gonna be unusable pretty
soon I sure hope someone finishes
assembly view in C GD b or c DB or
whatever that when it's on handmade
network cuz i got a switch off this
thing
it's like unusable alright so let me see
what we're actually exporting here if we
look at the okay so this is a glove i
want to look at an actual block
so I'll do it here
when we finished parsing the pieces oh
well that would be one reason to say the
least we never told it how you would
import a block did we all right so now
in theory we should actually be able to
import a block in theory but again we
have some bug with our tag processing so
we know that we're not really quite
there yet in terms of what we need to do
for importing things and having them
match properly so we you know we're just
gonna get whatever the first thing is
and it looks like we probably did right
it looks like we we actually got dirt
right so it looks like we actually did
get the first one so let's just see I
don't imagine we'll have any better luck
with this than before but let's suppose
we did oh and we can't really hmm so we
didn't put any actual tags on these so
let's suppose we did this just to see if
they're lined up properly cuz I can't
tell with just the dirt ones pretty
pretty straightforward right
so if temporarily I just said like I
don't know these things are just like
right there like non files or something
so we just said like look don't you know
don't process those leave those leave
those alone would we get if we just had
one so we don't have to worry about
processing tags or having the tags be
bad would we would they be mapped
properly like did they load properly or
are they upside down which was something
I was thinking could easily be the case
and it looks to me like they probably
are we set the colors kind of weird in
here so I probably should go fix that
oops so in here we've got these like
srgb linearized things that we were
doing all kinds of nonsense with and so
I think what I'll do here is just say
like look let's pretend that everything
is fine and it's not that at all but I I
feel like we probably haven't upside
down like we're oriented opposite the
way we should be on the PNG versus
textures because they're bottom-up
versus top-down right and so and we're
also blue right which doesn't make a lot
of sense here
it's I'm not sure how we're getting
quite so much light in there it's very
unusual hold on a second I'm gonna turn
on the full speed build
yes so that we got some really peculiar
stuff going on right so we've got a lot
of bugs to sort that's okay that's not
that hard so yeah it looks like it looks
like those are probably not quite
aligned right and the tops versus
bottoms aspect of it I think we're
looking at the bottom so I do think our
bitmaps are flipped right with you know
how they should have been why we're
getting such massive over bright
brightness in this case I don't know
[Music]
it's a little weird
so I'm not I'm not sure what's going on
there and I'm also not sure why things
would be blue so a lot of things I do
not understand about what I'm seeing so
there's a ton of bug stuff in there I
don't know why I'm refusing to stop the
stream today I just I think I was in too
much of programming mood I have like
dinner plans later as well so probably
this is bad
just in general let's see
yeah so so I probably got to call it
quits
um so that's unfortunate because I would
like to get the rest of that working but
unfortunately not in the works at the
moment but yeah that's very close to
working and I think mostly we just have
to go through this stuff and clean it up
and do the debugging necessary because
there's a lot of stuff that has to
happen in there right that's happening
in there now that needs to be done
carefully I do know we do a swap R &amp; B
in here but it's weird that we're doing
a swap R&amp;B and
and we're getting the wrong color image
on the on the way out that's pretty
bizarre result to have and I'm not sure
where that's coming from
it could have something to do with how
we're doing the down sample stuff here
one example of how this would go wrong
is if we were accidentally
if we were accidentally somehow passing
like the source pointer instill it
wouldn't make sense how that could
really happen but yeah but I really just
don't know
sorry so I'm gonna call it and I'll let
anyone who's feeling particularly
intrepid go ahead and debug it on their
own for a while but we'll have to pick
this back up because I gotta go so I
will bid you farewell for today let me
go ahead and close down the stream here
and just say thanks for joining me for
those sort of handmade hero and I think
basically next weekend will probably
just be a debugging weekend we got a
clean that code up do any refinement
that we need to do on it make sure
there's no bugs in there for importing
down sampling parsing the tags and all
that stuff and then get all of those art
in our assets importing cleanly with the
right tag sets reliable and so on and
verify that we can update them so it's
basically just going to be a weekend of
debugging and code cleanup but that's
good I mean you want to do that so
hopefully I'll see you back here for
that and then we should be on I guess at
that point we're gonna have to be onto
some entity stuff and also we'll have to
communicate back to Ana the sorts of
things we want to do with the art in
terms of modifications so we'll start on
that stuff plenty of stuff to do which
is always good hope see you back here
for that until then have fun programming
and I'll see you on the Internet take it
easy everybody