start recording hello everyone and
welcome to handmade hero the show recode
a complete game live on stream on Twitch
no engines no libraries it's just us
here and in our own little typing
fingers now we have a little bit of
residual stuff from the Q&amp;A yesterday
that I kind of want to finish up that we
didn't really take close enough look at
but other than that I think we are kind
of done playing around with the asset
system we had a couple bug things we
wanted to look at so today we're
probably going to get back to
implementing some font stuff we already
did the stuff where we got font glyphs
but we haven't done the work of actually
figuring out what the metrics are the
fonts are so like how we measure letters
and line them up and stuff like that we
haven't started any of that so that's
what I would like to do today but first
I just want to clean up some loose ends
from the QA yesterday because we kind of
slammed some coding and really looked at
it so I want to make sure it's all okay
today is day 1 67 so if you're trying to
follow along at home you want to grab
day 166 of source code unzip that into a
directory and that's what I'm doing
today so if you pre-order the game on
handmade here or look in that current to
file for a day 166 a source and unzip it
all right so what we kind of randomly
through in at the end yesterday was i
think we had like a some kind of a state
spinlock that we were doing there where
we did something like you know this yeah
so what we were doing is we were playing
around this in the QA and we were
basically saying like okay if you tried
to do something if you're trying to load
something and it turns out you we're not
the first person to try and load it if
it was supposed to be immediate you're
supposed to spin lock now there's a
couple of problems with this piece of
code as written and this is why I want
to come take a look at it again first of
all I neglected to actually use this
volatile version there which is what I
had wanted right so that's a little bit
of a mistake say the least but the other
thing that's more important is this spin
lock should only happen if you're trying
to be immediate if we weren't trying to
be immediate we don't want to wait for
the asset right we have
so that that was not at all our
intention so I want to get rid of that
as well and I think that's mostly all
that there was we kind of played around
that in the Q&amp;A we never really finished
it properly so i think that's a little
bit more proper way to leave that code
yeah from where we have it so let's
let's go back to our font thing as you
can see we kind of left in a state where
we were debugging it that's why we had
that black background on the font glyphs
there instead of doing them sort of more
more cleanly where they didn't have the
background obviously so if we wanted to
get back to that what I want to do is
bring up that the test asset builder
thing which is the thing where we're
kind of been doing our asset file spec
stuff and as you remember we had a pound
of finding here so you could choose if
you wanted to use no libraries at all
even in the asset builder you could set
that to one if you wanted to use stb
truetype instead I showed how to use
that and you could set this to zero and
compile that in but with use fonts from
windows we never quite finished doing
our good see here doing our
anti-aliasing so if you look at that
closely it was not anti alias and we
kind of that's where we stopped on the
stream and so it might be worth just
taking a second to fix the anti-aliasing
in the Windows version just for now
because I don't know that that be that
hard to do right so if we're using fonts
from windows were in this path right and
the way that this works is when we
actually created a device context we do
like great compatible be seeing all this
stuff someone was hypothesizing on the
Forbes that perhaps the reason that we
were getting anti-icing is because we
had some kind of a monochrome bitmap
potentially because create compatible
dc0 might not be the same as using
Create compatible DC get DC 0 and I
don't know if that's true or not get DC
0 gives you back the screen DC maybe
create compatible DC 0 just does some
kind of a default behavior so it's
possible that that was creating a sort
of a monochrome backing bitmap and sorry
not having it didn't basically didn't
have any color to work with so it
literally couldn't anti-alias I'm not
sure if that's true so if you take a
look here this is what it was looking
like
I mean not know if you can see that too
well but it's definitely not anti
aliased on there that's the way that we
had it and so if we rebuild our art
assets here I'll just go ahead and
recompile go into the handmade data
directory and then run the test asset
builder again that'll go through and do
it's a little thing extract the thoughts
again and we can see if that actually
changed anything I don't know if it did
it looks pretty much exactly the same to
me I don't I don't see any any change in
the in the degree of anti-aliasing there
that's just my it's just my recollection
so yes I'm not sure so in general I
don't know if we wanted to actually make
sure that all this stuff worked right I
feel like we would have to do a little
bit of work here to actually set up a
bit map that was somewhat reasonable and
I'm not sure exactly how we would do
that so I'm going to go ahead and look
at doing something that will create an
actual bitmap you know that I have more
control over so so we can start by just
trying to verify you know that we have
some kind of a bitmap that's you know
that's going to meet our our criteria
right maybe I'll do a create di bitmap
as well something we could read out of
directly right so here's a create di
bitmap so what that would what that
would do right is that would allow us to
pass a bitmap info structure and the
bitmap info structure would be the same
sort of thing that we've been using for
loading bitmaps right like exactly the
same thing so
all that same stuff right that we had
before like the bitmap info header stuff
all that same stuff we could just set it
now instead of reading it out of a file
like we were doing we would just set
that stuff so we could set all of the
things that we wanted to set here in
terms of how we want it you know what
the width the height was how many bits
there were you know all that kind of
stuff we could set that stuff and then
we would at least know that we had
correctly selected into the device you
know a bitmap that was going to be to
our to our liking so we could take that
part out of the equation make sure that
there isn't a problem so if you look at
create a DI bitmap we would take it a
handle to the device context that would
of course be the compatible DC that we
created here we would pass that header
which is going to be one of these things
we would probably just set this to
nothing to I guess we would just pass
the init to clear everything out I don't
know how I don't know what we want to do
there we might want to clear ourselves
looks like the tricks of shreds of
dimensions if you usage and pointer to
the rabbit in the initial bitmapdata the
format of the day it depends on the beer
boot camp that's not really what I
wanted I actually want to create a
bitmap that I can actually read out of
so I think I probably want more of like
a dip section like we were creating
before right like I want to actually
know that that I can access the bits
myself because if I can access the bit
to myself I could also get get out of
the business of doing this get pixel
nonsense because get pixels super slow
it's an OS call every time we want to
read this and so even though this is the
asset Packer we don't really care too
much up so it is I mean there's no sense
in being unnecessarily slow that's my
feeling on it right so what I would say
is let's go ahead and try to create one
of these dip sections something like
that and I feel like that would maybe
get us a little closer to our goal of
having anti-alias fonts and also we
could
we could at the same time fix some of
that nastiness with the end with the
readout with the with the get pixel call
which is not fabulous so if i was going
to create one of these dips sections i
need to have a bitmap info right and i
need to pass that in here this I you
suggesting we definitely want it to be a
RGB right although type of data
contained the BMI colors so to be honest
this doesn't really matter because we're
not going to even pass a BMI colors
thing so I think we really actually
doesn't matter that's that's like if you
want it so that's if I like palletized
stuff or something so I don't think we
even really care about that but doesn't
matter the location of the D did bit
value so this this thing here ppb bits
is going to give us a pointer to the
actual bits that we can then read out of
right and that's the sort of thing that
I wanted so this is basically like that
you know the bits or something I don't
know we want to call that but we could
just pass that like so all right so
let's see eight section handle a file
mapping object okay that that we don't
need it all right we don't we don't want
any of this stuff we just want you know
a standard in memory thing we're not
trying to do any kind of weird like out
of memory stuff okay so that's that's
not a problem and same thing with offset
so that's that's all totally fine right
so all that is pretty easy right we can
create that and that would give us our
bitmap back and then we could of course
selected in now the problem is this
bitmap info thing here we have to
actually initialize that to set that
bitmap info to stuff that that would
actually be meaningful right because
it's going to use we're passing this in
its going to use this bitmap info to
actually create the Dib section and so
you know we've got to fill it out
meaningfully right so if i click on
bitmap info header here what i can do is
i can start to set these values right i
can just go ahead and grab them all
thank you and set them there we go just
kind of get this going here there we go
and some here you know I mean if you're
feeling kind of feisty if you've got a
little bit of you know zest if you've
got some some life in you this evening
you could even go ahead and do rectangle
kill they're always always a big
favorite it was a big crowd favorite a
rectangular kill so we got to set these
guys up and so you know the number of
bytes required by the structure well we
know what the number of bytes acquired
by the structure is presumably it's just
the size of we know the width and the
height oh wait but this is just a header
part right so it's BMI header these are
actually all these are actually a part
of the header so presumably I can just
do that although I you'll notice they
didn't actually quite to say whether
that size was supposed to refer to the
whole thing or just my part of the thing
so I don't know that's a good question
which one did you want for bi size the
number of bytes required by the
structure would suggest it's just this
but we'll see anyway okay so the width
we should already have access to
somewhere in here we should know that
like we should have some kind of notion
of how big the thing was that we were
drawing in with where are you yeah I
guess we don't know slide 6 so we just
do yeah we don't really do anything so
we just need something here that would
tell us the maximum with that we might
ever want right so this would be like
Max dim or something right a max
dimension so we're just going to have to
do something like okay you know it's
1024 is the biggest character we'd ever
have or something like that all right so
let's see bi planes the number of planes
for the target device it must be set to
1 all right well that's easy the bit
count is going to be 32 presumably
yep we could also do 24 but either way
it doesn't really matter we want
probably 32 so it's you at 32 aligned
would be easiest for us bi compress it
and we don't want any compression we
want to be able just read this out as it
is so that's all good the size of the
image for bi RGB can be set to 0 so I
guess we can set it to 0 like so pels
per meter let's see because you just
five sec device I don't know that we
care about that at all I don't know if
it's an error to set it to zero but we
don't really want it we're not going to
use any colors so we don't want any of
these we don't want a color table for
this bitmap or anything like that so
we've set some stuff there it is we
don't know whether it's going to work or
not we'll see we can certainly run it
but we don't have any idea if it's going
to be correct so let's go ahead and see
what we ended up with there
you know I think that may have done it
though
that is looking anti-alias to me sure is
people so I think that that was the what
the doctor ordered there we just needed
to create an actual bitmap that windows
new is going to be a reasonable number
of bits per pixel apparently because now
it's not all janky so that's nice all
right so if that's the case then we kind
of have another nice thing we could do
right because if we did that we could
put this void bits thing right as sort
of an outside a little outside guy right
and that would mean that now the bits
could be accessed directly so instead of
having to do this kind of nonsense we
could just get the bits out ourselves
right now the problem with that is i
don't know what the actual stride is
going to be but my understanding is the
stride is actually knock is it's always
going to be as long as we're 32 bits per
pixel I think the way it allocates them
is always the same because you notice
there's no stride in here so I think it
always just does like one of those
things where kind of rounds up to the
nearest D word so I think we're probably
fine to just assume that that's true and
what that would mean is that we could
literally read out the bits sort of
directly along the line without too much
trouble right without without really too
much trouble so let's take a look here
at how this is going so really we've got
a little bit of work to do here this
kind of runs through that bitmap width
and height yeah so what we would want to
do is our standard row thing right we'd
want to do okay let's start with the
bits at the top there we'd kind of come
through each individual row and do you
32 pixel I guess that's really only need
equals Rho and and at the end of it we
would just do the row equals the sort of
bitmap width
like that right or I don't know we want
to call it this is the like total width
or the the width of the sort of
extraction area maybe max with something
like that we would want to do the max
with you know to advance to the next row
that's really about it right and so that
in here to read these guys off any
getting to give vidual pixel at this
point is just star right to look at it
and then we would kind of go further
like so so I think that's all we would
really need to do we just now need to
actually store that max width so we want
something that's like max width equals
that 1024 max height equals 1024
something like that and then in here we
can just actually put those in there max
whip right max height right so i think
that's that's reasonable i think let's
see if that works at all of course it
does not release does not appear to so
let's see assuming we got the bits back
which we wouldn't hear and it's a static
so it will be preserved then what we
need to figure out is what did I mess up
in here when we were actually getting
that ex back I feel like this would have
been correct we'd start at zero we'd
kind of go forwards with that and that
should have done it right because this
is still using get pixel but that's fine
right there's nothing foo there's
nothing weird about that that's totally
fine although
no I think that should be totally fine
right so what did I do oddly here if
this is set to bits we set the road to
the beginning of bits we then increment
the row every time through the while
loop by incrementing ah well no that's
fine just using just the size CX since I
see why you really shouldn't be a
problem right it seems like that should
be totally fine so we only increment
height times we only increment with
times that seems totally fine to me that
seems totally fine to me so I guess what
I might say is we could put this guy
back in right there's the get the get
pixel right so this is like our
reference pixel and I we could then say
step through this and see if they don't
agree right we could we could actually
go through here and see what actually
happens I believe we are able to step
through our asset processor pretty
trivially just by switching to this
other sln right I've got the two slms
there the one for the handmade and one
for the asset builder so I can kind of
switch freely between them and so when
we do our load glyph bitmap I should be
able to just you know let me make sure
we're running this in the data directory
I don't want to spew HHA files all over
the place okay yes it is so yeah so if I
wanted to I can run this and I can step
into it so I can see what's going on so
I can come in here and go all right you
know let's run to hear there's the row
take a look at what that looks like it's
zero not super surprising but if I come
in here now I can I should be able to
compare what's happening with ref pixel
write and star pixel
right so I should be able to see if they
differ in fact I guess I could just put
in an assert to that would fire at the
right time right so assert ref pixel
equals star pixel something like this so
there you go our star pixel is not
getting back the same thing and where
are we at X 11 y 26 right mm-hmm I say
very interesting
presumably we are just getting a whole
lot of zero from this even though we are
stepping through some semblance of some
bits that presumably should have been
corresponding to the bitmap that's been
selected into that device context and I
don't really know why that's the case I
am interested I would like to see this
pixel pointer I'm just curious is it
just all zeros oh no now I've done it no
I am mildly clearest is it all zeros so
it's just zeros as far as the eye can
see this is just it's just all nothing
right so somehow our bit bits pointer is
not is not really actually showing us
anything here so I guess the other
question is is it just upside down or
something so another thing I might want
to do is assert a star pixel equals 0 is
star pixel ever set to anything even
after we go through all these know so
basically like we're just getting back
total zeros everywhere I which got to be
honest don't know why don't know why I
feel like creative section must be doing
something I'm not expecting but I don't
know what it would be we're definitely
selecting it into the device context
which means that the Vice context should
be rendering to it would be my
expectation and then I feel like we
should be able to grab out those bits
after having done the text out but that
doesn't
not actually appeared to be what
actually happened right it appears like
it's doing some other thing where where
it's not actually running into the same
bits that's giving us if that makes
sense and I am not sure how we fix that
this is one of those things where this
is why programming with closed in a
closed system is so frustrating look
normally you just step in there and you
just see right but of course we can't
step in there because we aren't allowed
to like see any of the window source
code so we have no idea right like we
have no idea what's going on it's
probably something really simple and
stupid that we just made a slight error
on right not knowing like what we should
have set up here or something or we're
stepping through slightly wrong you know
but there's no way for us to like do
easy debugging of it because we can't
access any of the code that would
actually have been relevant to help us
right which is kind of annoying so I
guess let's take a look at the
documentation for create dip section and
see if there's anything that would give
us a hint as to why it would be doing
what it's doing right look maybe there's
some sample code we can look at that
would show us something that we had
forgot to do right or something like
this what does dip suction the actual
value there created by calling create
dip sites from function yeah that's just
info it doesn't really matter i don't
think so well we could look good look at
bitmaps overview in here and see if
maybe there is something using bitmaps
unfortunately yeah well create dibs
section example that's not what I want I
just want you know I just want a create
dip section well that's what I want to
create dip section instead of get pixels
that's exactly what I was looking for
right oh this is somebody who's like
changelog right so hey they did pretty
much exactly the same thing we did wow
that's kind of eerily this close they
even did that that same thing ha ha ha
yeah so they do create dip section there
they do a get DC of 0 as well this is
like literally exactly the same code
right I mean that looks crazy clothes so
let's see they select the bitmap in they
look like they're sort of clearing or 10
they're copying I guess from one DC to
the other let's see and then they long
and pixels p RG b PB bitmap so yeah I
mean they're doing exact the same thing
right there walking through there looks
exactly the same
I do not know why we are having no luck
there when that seems like everything's
wrecked and we know it's drawing fonts
because if we use get pixel it actually
works so hmm I say so am i doing
something stupid in the loop like that I
just make a typo right here's the bits
pointer it's pointing to the top
presumably I mean I guess it could be
pointing backwards thing if it wasn't
then we just crash right because we're
pointing into some memory that they gave
us so if we were walking the wrong
direction you'd think we just crash
right away so presumably we are going in
the correct direction we're pointing to
the bits pointer we go through each line
we start at the row pointer which we
have here we go for however many pixels
we believe we're supposed to go by
advancing one pixel at a time and each
pixel's 32 bits so it should just be one
u32 is worth right sure feels like it
would work unless there's something no I
don't think so and then at the end of
every row of these we advance the row
pointer by however much the maximum
width was which is how far it should be
to get to the next row right which is
going to be 1024 x 4 so 4096 which again
seems totally totally reasonable so I
don't know I do not know
anyone on the stream got any ideas
anyone anyone I kind of want to want to
know why that's broken I want to know
why that's broken there's got to be a
secret there has to be some fancy secret
that we're not thinking of and what is
it what would it be what would it be I
feel like we could do something where we
would shrink down the size of the bitmap
to something easier to see that would be
one thing and certainly
by the way to anyone on the stream who
says stop wasting time get pixel works
fine for the asset builder that is not
not a handmade hero a way to think about
things you're supposed to understand
what is going on in your code you are
not supposed to go Oh something randomly
works here and some other thing doesn't
randomly work well okay I'll just ignore
it right that is not at all the point
bad we always want if we have something
we don't understand we should try to
understand it right and in this case it
should be relatively straightforward for
us to figure out what's going on because
I feel like we're not far we know we're
using create dip section in a proper way
because we're actually getting glyphs
out the other side right so if i want to
write i can use ref pixel and we know
that ref pixel actually worked right so
when we extract the pixels out of there
we know that that works but for some
reason when we use the actual memory
pointer that create Dib section returns
to us we don't seem to be able to see
anything in there and I feel like we
want to know what's going on there so
the first thing that I would say is if
we actually took let's say we let's what
would happen if we just straight-up
obliterated what was in there right like
what would happen if at the outset we
did something like you know a mem set of
max width x max height times the size of
you and 32 so the whole that map right
what if we did a thing where we just set
that to white right I'm interested to
know what would actually happen so must
get a full on set it to white I'm going
to take that bits pointer that we had so
I'm just windows gives me something back
I'm wiping it with ffs so I know that
when I run it we're gonna get we're
going to start out with a bitmap that
has all white in it and hey let's see
here
fits here we go there's all my FS so now
we're going to watch windows draw it
just did not even touch this thing right
like there was no like no touching
occurred there was no touching it all
right so when we come in here and we
look at star pixel and ref pixel it's
just so this this this bitmap is a lie
right this bitmap is a total is a total
lie right because if it were actually
drawing that glyph we would have seen it
in here right so let's do something now
where we kind of constrict things a
little bit as well right let's do
something in here where we say okay if
the width is greater than the max with
will clamp it right and if the height is
greater than the max height will clamp
it so now we know we can maybe do a
little bit more playing around coming
here and say you know what now this
thing is just 32 by 32 it's tiny so
we'll be able to look at like the whole
thing you know in a more you know in a
more direct fashion right so now if I
come in here I can kind of get a little
bit more of the bitmap on there so
here's our bits pointer I'm going to
copy it in there there's all our ffs and
there we can see we can now see the
whole thing right and I want to be able
to see the whole thing so I know that
we're not missing some of it so when we
come through here and we do our text out
right Hey look it actually drew some
stuff so I think what's happening is
we're in some kind of a top-up but like
bottom up top down situation or
something
where they gave us back a bitmap pointer
that was in the wrong place right uh so
i think i think if i had to guess uh
what we basically have here is a
situation where it's drawing the wrong
orientation from what we would like it
to be doing right and we could probably
fix that by saying this right that'd be
my guess where where are we there we go
although wait well you know what now
that I think about it if it is going
from the bottom up if it is going from
the bottom up
and it's giving us back a pointer to the
top all right I'm going to leave it like
this for a second and I just want to see
if that's what's actually happening but
I should be able to do essentially what
it wants for me right I should be able
to emulate what it's doing right I can
do minus equals max with their and and
do something like this where it's max
aight minus 1 times max with like so
right i should be able do something like
that right so hey it does the fill then
it does the text out and then let's see
what the ref pixel is the ref pixel is
zero the pixel is zero those match let's
keep going here and pixels not syrup
perfect ok there we go Hey look we solve
the problem so let's run this back out
lovely wouldn't you say so if we want to
do this right we would do something like
yeah start the row pointer their source
row kind of a thing put the source in
here like that source Rose stepping
backwards question how we could step
them forwards because they're both going
the same direction let's not mention it
you know no need to you know no need to
bring that whole thing up assert pixel
equals source
+ + source can I get a nope can't quite
get uh what I do there so max aight
minus one that's starting at the bottom
right then as we go in why we want to
step backwards which one are we on here
x equals negative what ah that's not
good see we already found a bug in our
actual code before so when we have our
thing there to kind of pull an apron out
around these guys that's I wonder how
we're going to deal with that I'm gonna
we're gonna have to put a little thing
around here do apron leave that out for
a second alright let's go back to what I
was doing okay so why is 26 x is 6 what
does our bitmap actually look like well
i guess going to be hard to see because
we're looking at their well you know I
could do I can look at source row is
bits max assist at the bottom then
whatever min Y is it's going to have to
go up from there that many right which
seems totally fine x max with then ah
right we're not pre stepping min x
that's all since we're starting at min
acts we just have to pre step min x in
right there big deal there alright
hopefully getting a little closer x and
y right because whatever the row is we
would need to go forward by that many
pixels to line up with this
I all right so whatever the pixel is the
source is those are not even close so I
feel like we've got one other thing I
think we were started at ten minutes
left on the clock I don't remember
something like that so yeah so now we're
pre stepping min why we're p stepping
minacs and we're doing our reads that
all seems good
am I missing anything important here I
don't think so but you never do know oh
man that's no good yeah sorry i meant to
pre step the the source not the dust so
there we go now we're running nicely
there right and so with those assertions
in place you know i can get rid of these
right and instead just do something like
you could to pixel equal star source
right so now just get rid of those and
off we go lovely so now I think we have
successfully converted over to using
win32 properly to get a large data out
there so that's all nice and let's see
let's see oh I guess we should do one
more thing but let's just double check
here if I go back to handmade and run it
we should see nice letters we do have
nice letters but let's just double check
here for a second if we go in and do
this remember we we were sort of we
would do it we were doing the alpha sec
separately so that we can put a black
background on it we probably don't want
to do that anymore because now we're
actually doing them slightly more
correct so you can see it's kind of got
that black background if we actually
rebuild the art assets now with the one
that uses the the alpha level we should
have nice nicely alpha
so there we go so that's good but we
still need to be able to put an apron on
them which we don't have the ability to
do at the moment because remember the
way we wrote our bitmap stuff is we
expect a 1 pixel transparent border
around things in order for everything to
sample properly so that's something that
we still want to have to do so we've got
about 8 minutes left maybe we should
figure out how we want to do that I
think probably what we'd want to do here
is inside sort of this width and height
copy we would want to account for that
I'm wondering if I can merge these two
code paths because they should be
roughly the same in fact you look at
them in there they're very very similar
right so it would be kind of cool if we
could go ahead and merge those and
that's something that maybe maybe it's a
little premature to do today but maybe
tomorrow when we have a little more time
at the beginning we could go ahead and
merge those two code paths and make that
a little simpler so in here if I was to
do it right it wouldn't be very
difficult I don't expect because I could
very simply just say whatever the thing
is we're actually making here right put
the result width and height and all that
right if I do this I could just say hey
we add an apron one pixel white apron
around the whole thing and then when I
copy it in here I could I could first of
all just clear it right I could say hey
I want to clear this whole thing right
20 I could clear it and then when I
actually do my rights in here we could
always make sure that we we leave space
for one thing right so we actually pre
step in one and we in our desk we pre
step 1 pixel in right and think you can
see you can kind of see right the little
like O's
they've got that kind of truncated at
the end there right and so I feel like
if we did things this way or we could
just crash that's also another good
option which you know people should you
know should be interested in all the
time uh let's see here why did we crash
result touch memory result High Times
pitch that seems fine result up memory
moving back by one destro plus one that
seems fine just rule pretty step by what
I suppose in the case where height is
zero that might be a problem but I'm
going to go ahead and oh but it can't
because presumably you always have some
so I'm going to go ahead and just see
what the actual crash was let's take a
look run it brick wall stock up in free
wow that doesn't really tell us it just
tells us that we did have something that
went off but that doesn't really help us
too much so let's see I'm allocating two
extra bytes around the whole thing i'm
doing a mem set of whatever the height
is times the pitch which is what i would
expect because that's the malloc size so
i should be able to memset that size
certainly to say the very least right
the only things i changed here was that
and this right that's it I didn't do
anything else so it's got to be
something in just that pre stepping if I
pre step 1 pixel in right I should have
plenty of you know of leeway there right
that should not result in anything so it
has to be the fact that i did this
incorrectly so the fact that we're doing
we're starting with the result memory
and then we're pre stepping you know
skipping that first row is apparently
the problem right whatever that doing
that was not okay right because
everything else was totally fine so for
some reason if we go the height far down
and then step to back that is apparently
not acceptable right that's like not
enough i and i'm not sure why because it
seems like ah because we are using the
wrong height there we go all good so
that should do it okay so now if I come
back here I'm hoping that we will get a
rounder oh and looks like we do have one
although I'm not sure if that G it we
probably should take a look at what the
glyphs actually are supposed to look
like as I don't really know whether
we're actually still truncating them a
little bit or not but I believe you can
see that o is much smoother now
certainly but I don't know if we might
still not quite be lining everything up
properly but that's enough for today
that's fine and of course i would think
i'm not totally certain but i would
think that yeah we could sort of take a
look if this is ariel right we could
also take a look at like word pad or
something and just see what the oh and
the G are supposed to look like when
scaled up quite a bit you know in one of
these in one of these fonts right so
where is the area lat there's an aerial
so if I scale that up quite a bit that
doesn't look like the same font I wonder
if we're not actually getting the font
that we asked for oh that's because we
switched to Times New Roman or something
didn't we
think we actually did I'll do a double
check that but we weren't doing aerial
anymore something didn't we wouldn't we
do some weird thing where we switch to a
different remember which one it was
rover still doing aerial courrier new is
what we did courier new so courrier new
so so that is actually the G actually
just is flat apparently so that's not
such a big deal i guess but yeah
eventually we should probably check that
a little more closely but that seems
that seems fine alright so let's go
ahead and go to the Q &amp; A there we go
and then tomorrow we can should be able
to extract metrics seems reasonable
seems like a reasonable thing to do if
you have questions please prefix them
with Q colon so I can see them
you should have passed get to c 0 to
create compatible bitmap not create
compatible bc but that's fine you would
still have to use a different method
access quit my updated efficiently oh
okay you're saying if we just if we
didn't care about get pixel we could
avoid having to be the creative section
oops is what you're talking about
because you just get in here if you do
create compatible bitmap and then pass
kept TC 0 mr. muffles 869 hi there I'm
rather new to hand me hero do you ever
talk about your key bindings that help
you navigate more easily yes you can get
that so the easiest way is probably to
go to the forums page so on handmade our
Lord can go to the forums page and
that's got a bunch of stuff like this so
coding resources is where you want a
head and I'm sorry not coding her sis
episode guide and it's the first one
here optional editor intro basic Emacs
tutorial this one's got a bunch of stuff
you can watch and you can watch me do it
that sort of talks about my key bindings
water lineman why is arbitrary padding
required for the glyph bitmap is the
correct method used for retrieving the
actual glyphs size define arbitrary
padding what do you mean by arbitrary
padding garland Oh bloom tell us your
NASA secrets so I don't actually know
any NASA secrets Abner cumbre actually
the moderator here knows all the NASA
secrets actually he keeps them in a
briefcase that is that is handcuffed to
his wrist and he knows martial arts so
basically the NASA secrets are
extraordinarily well safeguarded and
you're really not going to get any of
them people have tried and they have all
failed and so yeah so for as long as
Abner continues to safeguard them in
that fashion they're totally safe now if
Abner quits someday just rage quits NASA
and leaves the briefcase lying around
then you know the secrets will be
exposed and we'll know where the aliens
are stored at you know until then
water lineman arbitrary equals two extra
for width height know so that's not
arbitrary just to be clear that's that's
by spec so again if you go back to the
episode guide you can look at our
rendering work when we wrote the
renderer and when we wrote the renderer
we did some stuff in here where we were
talking about getting things to sample
by linearly correctly and if you take a
look at how we did that we did that
let's see here we did that somewhere
here seamless bilinear tiling so in here
we talked about this exact thing of
wanting the apron and so you can see us
talking about out here getraer and
actually apron is very specifically to
so have it so that we can do our
bilinear sampling efficiently and not
have to have a separate if statement
that looks to see if we're on the border
Amy 95 do you think that this stream got
wasted no definitely not definitely not
basically anytime you investigate code
it is not wasted right because like for
example you saw how i went about
figuring out what was going on with that
bitmap right by clearing it to a known
value first and then shrinking it down
to a size where i could see what was
happening to it that was what allowed me
to figure out what was going on under
the hood so I really can't stress this
enough if you think that that is wasted
time this is not the kind of programming
for you right you want to be just using
an engine or doing something else right
that is exactly the kind of coding that
you should be very comfortable doing
should have a lot of attack skills for
it and you should be able to think of
those things like what I did to debug
that problem we in a black box scenario
you should be able to do those things
that's what i would want from an engine
programmer on my team right i don't want
somebody who just goes oh get pixel was
working in this other thing wasn't in
them just fine to move on because that's
how you end up not having any idea what
your code is doing and you have bugs and
you have people who can investigate
those bugs and you have people who just
throw minus signs into the code until it
starts working and like that's all awful
you always want to know that you
actually knew what the problem was and
that you're sure you actually solved it
that's very important so no that's this
this is exactly the kind of thing that I
want people to learn from handmade hero
right that is the whole point in doing
it is for people to learn that kind of
skill
no more questions if you ask me no
questions i will tell you no lies as the
nursery rhyme goes a better debugger
would have led you to the solution much
faster yes no question about that like I
was just saying on the pre stream a
better debugger would have let me find
that quickly soon in 73 just to clarify
it's okay to delete code that you don't
understand and replace it with code that
you do understand as an alternative to
trying to understand code that you don't
understand yeah I think so um yeah I
mean I I guess what I would say is I
suppose it depends on the situation but
yes in general that sounds correct to me
because for example like when you're
programming the windows api it's a giant
messy black box thing right and there's
no real bonus to understanding parts of
it just to understand it because it's
just somebody's bad code right so if you
delete if you have some windows code
that's doing something you have no idea
what it's doing and you're like I want
to fix this and you want to just delete
that code and then write some new code
that does it in a way that you do want
to make sure you get right and
understand and then you go to plug that
and get it working that seems totally
fine to me right i do that kind of thing
all the time because there's no sense
spending a ton of time debugging code
that you literally don't care about and
don't want to run right that does seem
like a waste of time but if you have
code that you actually want to run
that's the code you actually wanted
that's the time when you have to go say
let's make this work correctly and make
sure we know what it's doing right so I
feel like your statement sounds correct
to me
the up 511 did you turn down a twitch
partnership yes we did turn down a
twitch partnership because there's a
restriction in their contract about you
can't upload stuff to youtube for 24
hours something like this and so I just
wanted to be able to upload the things
to you to immediately and and that was
it so so yeah there was no hard feelings
or anything twitches been really nice to
us and you know there was not like there
was no kind of acrimony I just looking
at the contract was like yeah we did
this isn't really appropriate contract
for handmade hero so we didn't sign it
that that was it so so yeah so we love
twitch and actually twitch does a lot of
nice things for us and has been very
supportive of our stream and the
partnership isn't really a big deal for
us anyway they're like I don't want to
show ads on the channel anyway you know
partnerships let you do stuff like that
or whatever and so I don't have really
you know it hasn't created a problem
neither us nor twitch really is is is
losing something because we didn't do it
so it seems totally fine if that changed
in the future you know we'll try to fix
it but but at the moment I feel like
twitch is happy with us and we're happy
with twitch so there really wasn't any
reason to start arguing with each other
about some contract that neither was
cared if it got signed
have you thought about making a handmade
asset viewer no I haven't but that
sounds like the kind of thing that would
be perfect homework for people on the
stream Carl and abloom Abner always lies
and I always tell the truth you may ask
one question what I don't think that's
how that riddles supposed to go does the
better debugger exist not that I know of
sadly pseudonym 73 the reason why I ask
is that I've written code that I
subsequently really had to write off
yeah I mean sometimes you just go all
right look this code is so awful I just
need to delete it it's not going to get
any better I'm never going to understand
it it's a disaster let's start over
that's totally fine what's important is
that the code you're actually going to
keep you should understand right so
that's that's all soy sauce the kid I
need my case emotes though okay so that
there's some kind of thing where it
would have little Casey heads or
something um you know when the next time
I talk to the guys at which I'll ask him
again you know I feel like if it was up
to the people who I actually talked to
they would just get rid of that part of
the contract and I'm a problem with it
but you know the reality of large
companies like twitch which is like
Amazon now or whatever right is that you
you know I mean you don't even want to
know what the twitch rep guys would
probably have to go through to get that
contract range right like they probably
have to go through like 20 layers of
legal people and like have lawyers site
right so you know I feel like if it was
just up to them they just feel like yeah
no problem you can upload the thing and
we'll change that part of the contract
it's great right but that's not the
reality at a big company and you know if
I were them would I want to do that no
because just this huge big thing you
gotta go deal with and you got enough to
worry about already so you know like i
said i'd like to sign the church
partnership thing so that people could
have whatever it is that that gives you
i don't know what it gives people on the
stream but whatever it gives you you can
it uh but I just it's just not worth it
it's not gonna be worth it for them to
fix it I don't think either and and for
us where we're doing an educational
stream being able to upload a YouTube
immediately is is really important so I
felt like that was the priority
adner coin Bray question were out of
questions but you made my life difficult
tonight XD you know I'm under NDA's like
you you know how it is bro yes I'm sorry
I I didn't mean to create problems for
you Abner I was just teasing I was
trying to sort of mock the people who
are asking you NASA questions as if you
can just tell them NASA secrets that no
one can know I guess maybe my sarcasm
was a little bit too much I think it
hopefully should go without saying that
Abner is happy to talk about NASA with
people as far as it's possible for him
to talk about NASA with people but if
nASA has something that's classified he
can't talk about it he'd get fired or
worse so don't try to make him talk
about stuff did he can't talk about yeah
NDA's are awful but that's just how they
work right and that's how business goes
everyone does it the chat wants you to
play the Vista video again all right
we'll do that when I sign off DGM TV
should I stop using templates for my
containers and adopt void star forever
so I talked about this a little bit on
previous streams but I'll just you know
full disclosure at Molly rocket for our
engine oil containers are meta meta
generated so we have our own is
essentially our own programming language
and all containers go through that
programming language there's there's no
void star there's no templates or some
of that so if you want my real answer
you got a meta program if you want
containers you met a program don't waste
time with templates their garbage don't
waste time with void star it's garbage
meta program for something like handmade
hero where I'm kind of trying to show
old-school techniques when I have to
choose between one of the other I would
definitely go void star but most the
time I handmade here as you can see we
can get away without really having to do
it we can get away by just writing
something that's purpose-built for that
area and by keeping the number of moving
parts like that relatively low we don't
have to
on a container thing too hard but yeah
that's definitely like the next level
after handmade hero which is like
handmade heroes your core competency you
should be able to program like this add
a drop of a hat you should be able to do
it right level up from that core
competency as metaprogramming so
everything after that all of the things
that are problematic right that you're
you're doing coding by hand c++ won't
help you C++ is always bad so you don't
go C++ you go am in a programming or
maybe like John global save you with j
ai and you won't have to ever go
metaprogramming I don't know but at
least until ji is released you got to go
metaprogramming that's just that's just
my opinion
all good all right maybe it's time time
for some Microsoft Vista videos all
right let's wind this down close close
okay everyone thank you for joining me
for another episode of handmade hero
it's sort of pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
at home of the source code you could
always pre-order the game on handmade
here org and it comes with all the
source code and you can play around with
it and do your own programming things
whatever things those might be yeah so
check that out if you're interested this
is a little pre order button right here
we also have some other buttons there's
a patreon button if you want to support
the video series you can always just
pledged to the video serious it's a
super nice thing to do but they're
always free of charge so they're always
available in fact they are available on
our forum site with an anti episode
guides from the community which you can
check out we also have porous to mac and
linux stuff like that there we have a
forum you can ask questions all kinds of
good stuff and finally if you like
watching the stream live you're one of
those persons you like I it has to be
live I don't want to watch no YouTube
videos I want to watch it live there's a
tweet bot that tweets a schedule so you
can always know when we're going to be
live but speaking of that tomorrow will
be going back to 5pm our normal time
slot so hopefully I'll see you guys back
here at five p.m. pacific daylight time
right here on twitch until then have fun
programming and I will see you guys on
the internet take it easy everybody