if anything we should be looking for
technologies that allow us to reduce
latency oh I'm not supposed to be
talking I'm supposed to say hello
everyone welcome to handmade Hiro sure
he could a complete-game live on stream
I so sorry I was in the middle of saying
something about the fact that I don't
like games streaming welcome to handmade
Hiro today we're gonna be working on
some lighting stuff if you haven't seen
it already our comic kickstarter it's in
our last week right now and it's
exceeded that means if you're interested
in checking out our comic you will be
able to get one if you're back our
Kickstarter it's the banners on our
handmade hero Patriots should be really
easy to find I think it's at the bottom
of the twitch thing - I'm not sure
though cuz I never really know how to
get the twitch things set up properly
today on handmade hero I sort of had a
thing that I thought of this week as
often is the case when you know we're
spending a week waiting for the next
handmade hero my brain is still kind of
thinking about things in the background
and one of the things that I realized so
a couple things first of all we were
looking at some code for you know if you
take a look at what's going on handmade
here right now there's a couple of
things that we're wanting to do one is
we just want to speed up the lighting
calculation so that we hit 60 frames a
second pretty reliably the other one is
reduced some of the flicker I think I
have a good idea of how to reduce the
flicker I may want some procedural
flicker in there anyway but I'd rather
have it come from me
adding the flicker then from the fact
that we can't do very stable lighting
because we don't have enough ray tracing
power behind us but what I would like to
do is talk a little bit about the
spatial partition stuff because the
thought of something and I wanted to
measure some statistics today because
they realized sorts of things that I'm
probably doing dumb that we might be
able to do better given the nature of
the architecture of the game so if we
look at our lighting code and we wrote
this HH light prof system to profile
what we're doing with the lighting and
we actually have a way to use like our
old KD tree model which actually isn't
quite a KD tree it's actually like an
a/b tree that just doesn't happen
to use that feature much it's it's sort
of like a binary a a b-tree is more what
it is that happens to always use split
planes that are aligned to axes which is
not really a KT trade and one of the
interesting things that we found when we
put this in and it could just be bugs so
you know we don't really know yet
because we haven't done a lot of work to
really determine what exactly is going
on in our system to verify correctness
what we can see is our old you know
running the stress test on our old KT a
bead KD tree however you want to say
that a a KD tree is six point two seven
seconds the stress test is if we switch
to the newer KD tree model which has a
much abbreviated walk pattern but when
you run it it's way way slower and this
is really interesting but there's a
couple things that I think make that a
rather obvious thing to have happen in
some sense and we should probably go
over them but I also realized one other
thing that I had really been thinking
about and probably need to think about
which is that we may not want this kind
of tree at all and it may just be over
complicated for our needs KD trees are
very popular in ray tracing they're very
popular in ray tracing because I think
they have the minimum amount of checking
you need per note per level of the tree
to descend down to the bottom of the
tree and so at some level it's like well
it makes sense to use a KD tree because
we knew they're gonna be good for ray
tracing probably but for our particular
geometry I also don't know if they're
the correct attack plan and I wanted to
talk about that now
what I would like to do is I would like
to profile our own that you can see how
long is it taking so I don't need to
finish right my point is just the Katie
tree thing we dropped in there was
actually quite bad but that may be
because it's buggy we need to do some
debugging on it which we might want to
do just to verify but what I did want to
do is in the old KD tree case so this
case here which runs in 6.7 seconds to
write over the stress test case where we
just run it over and over to see what it
ends up getting we end up with that
timing and we collected some statistics
which is the total number of tests we
perform I believe is what that is the
partition tests which are tests that
don't tell us a collision they just tell
us like go down this part of tree or
don't write and then we say how many
leaf boxes we've tested so when we're
running this we know that throughout
this test we test and I believe this is
what this is divided by the repetition
count so this is actually not the total
number of tests performed it's the
amount in one run so this is what we do
like on a frame in the game so we test
for every leaf we test we test for point
seven partitions right and in here we
also know that we test a total of five
hundred thousand roughly leaves and we
test a total of two point three million
partitions right and what I was curious
about is I was curious about per Rea
because we don't print out the number of
Ray casts here I was curious to know
what the average number of partitions
per ray is does that make sense
so if I go in to the to the code here
and ice and I ask the and I ask it to
count the number of rays I'm not sure if
it may it may already we I think we were
counting that already potentially so it
may be that that's already here you can
see like total cast initiated is there
so I want to say that really all we need
to do is actually use the data we're
collecting there that previously I
wasn't interested in but I am sort of
interested in it now so when we come
through here and we print these out I'm
going to print out another line here
which is just how many partitions per
ray we actually were testing and then
also I guess maybe Leafs per ray so that
we can just find out like what art for
every ray we cast like how many is that
right like how many is that actually
happening so in here we've got the total
number of leaves tested and the total
number of partitions tested and I should
now be able to do like total ray count
or total Ray's initiated or whatever
right in here like so and
looking at that
hmm so what's interesting about that
though I'm a little confused when I'm
looking at this total partitions tested
is actually a summation
oh it's zeroed every time so that's good
I was like I don't divide by the number
of tests that's okay it's cleared every
time so this is just the ones from the
last test which is totally what we want
like we just want one test worth because
it's the same on every test cuz
configurations identical I believe I
mean maybe they're this I don't know if
the series number is reset every time so
it might not be quite identical every
time but it's like close right so anyway
if we take a look here and we look at
like total leaves tested total printer
tested and total rights initiative if I
just count the total well here's the
total cast initiatives right there
actually so I actually have it total
cast initiated and I just look at total
cast initiated like so I should now be
able to print out in addition to the
existing data information about how many
of these things were testing per Rey
because that will give me some idea of
like whether or not this is the correct
model because I don't actually know what
those numbers are I think we looked at
them a long time ago but we're not but I
don't remember right so this is this is
good information for me so in our fast
version that's actually doing a a/b
testing right so it's actually testing a
fully a/b it's not even doing a KD tree
test so it's doing better than a KD tree
test because it has full bounding
information on these things for this
kind of geometry which is a lot of
little cubes like roughly I mean they're
not actually cubes they're you know
rectangular right rectangular prisms you
might say but you know they're stretchy
cubes we're testing five partitions per
Ray and on average and we're testing 24
leaves per Ray now here's the thing
because our geometry is very grid like
I'm wondering why we're not just using
the lighting voxel as
a voxel containment field like basically
like a thing that says here's we're all
like each voxel node just has a list of
the boxes that are in it and the reason
that I say that is because if we were to
do that then we would in theory just be
able to walk the voxel directly with a
known pattern that had no branches at
all
like the only branch would be in the
leaf branch that we already have like
how many leaves were in this branch
right so if you think about what's going
on there I mean there's some things
about that did that are very attractive
to like if you have a known pattern for
array we could test box wise instead of
ray wise too so we wouldn't have to test
Ray bundles anymore which means we
wouldn't bifurcate ray paths either and
so I'm just really curious if maybe the
idea of using a tree is just inherently
flawed and we shouldn't be doing it
right because if we just used a voxel
and walked the voxel we would already
know exactly the pattern to walk and
furthermore we would know the pattern
for every voxel so like the branching
would be very limited it would the only
two branches you would have would be the
loop that loops over the voxels to test
and the loop that loops over the leaves
so you'd have two loops and no
conditionals at all right
Oh leaves in-plane switch some one was
mentioned the chat that I actually
switched that thank you
there we go um Wow so that's actually
even more convincing for what I was just
saying wowzer so twenty four partitions
per a that's like way too many right so
I think I may just say forget it I know
we spent a lot of time looking at how to
walk walk the tree but sometimes you
spend a lot of time and then realize
what you're doing is stupid I mean
that's the nature of optimization work
I'm not sure we even want to go down
this route so let me explain what I'm
talking about here this is what I was
thinking about let me just explain it to
you visually so that you understand so
that you're in the same headspace that I
am or at least you understand my head
space so if we jump in here to day this
is day five ninety eight so essentially
what I'm talking about is grid
raycasting right and what I was saying
let's just do it in 2d cuz it's the same
in 3d there's not gonna be any
difference it's just a little more
expensive because there's more cells but
let's suppose that you were just doing
this in 2d right so
so currently what we're saying is look
we got a voxel and we're gonna start
somewhere in the voxel and we're gonna
do a ray cast and we're gonna bundle for
rays at a time right so we're doing four
rays at a time and we hope that they
kind of go out in a relatively similar
direction and we know they sort of do
because they're in line with the with
the octahedral map so they're sort of
close but not that close and if you look
at how they actually progress out into
the world what we were doing before is
saying well all right so there's all
these like cubes around right and we're
trying to raycast against the cubes and
so what we're gonna do is we're gonna
split those up into like bounding
syriza's right that split things apart
and we're gonna test against these like
bounding volumes that result in those
and we're gonna like Traverse down into
them to find which leaves we should
actually test against right so with that
ended up being is like we would have an
a a BB and it would have to sub a a B
B's underneath it like so right and that
would have to sub a a B's underneath
that and so on and then eventually we'd
have some lists of leaves down at the
bottom right and they're not really list
they're actually just in an array so
they're just the account and then we
test against those and that's how we
would produce our raycast right now the
problem there is that every single one
of these tests is fairly unpredictable
and random we don't know whether we're
going down the left side the right side
or both so we can't really predict and
preload this the process or is just kind
of sitting there stuttering wondering
which side is going to go down and it
just has to deal with that right
furthermore if we have one Rea that only
would need to go down this side and the
other array that would only need to go
down this side that wouldn't actually
work either
so that's the problem
that we currently have and I don't know
to what extent I can do this but I was
wondering what would happen if we just
for example instead of doing that just
cast one ray and used the loader like we
actually took and loaded in serially all
of the leaves that we need to be tested
by using a grid walk so instead of the
tree we just say no what we're going to
do instead is say we know that we're
going to be casting on nope we know that
we're going to be casting on this thing
and if we were to cast a single ray we
know that that ray would have a
predefined pattern in our grid or voxels
the case may be so we know that for
example you would test the one you're in
the one below it the one next to that
the one below it the one below it the
one next to that right this pattern is
deterministic
we are always casting from the center
and we know all of the Rays because
they're in our sphere like our sphere
cast database right we have that and
we're always pulling from a distribution
that we already know so we already know
the lock pattern right the walk pattern
is known so we can just store a list of
voxel indices relative to the current
index and we know what they are right so
that basically means that we can start
by assembling a leaf list and then we
can walk we can literally just load the
leaf list right so we actually can do
this in two loops one is a while loop
over these right to gather all of the
indices that we need and then another is
a while loop over those indices to check
them but that's it so there's no
descending there's no nested loops we
can literally just do it in two passes
exactly and there's no branches and no
ifs because there's nothing to test it's
completely two-term
the walk every time the only thing
you're testing is when you got to the
end so when I got to the end of this and
when I got to the end of that those are
that only two tests in the entire thing
now I don't know whether it's cheaper to
copy the whole thing or just copy the
index but that's
I really don't know that's a tough call
and I really have no idea what the
answer is we'll probably have to test
both of those and see which one is
faster because they have no idea whether
it would be faster to have our grid
squares store the occupants of the grid
square and as indices or if it would be
cheaper to store them as copies and then
copy them in furthermore there's a
deduplication in a sense in that you can
also if you want to try to deduplicate
leaves rather than test against them
twice and what I mean by that is like
suppose there's something here and you
would have walked all three of these as
you like break acid through it you will
need to test that thing once and I'm not
sure I'm not sure what you do about that
because one ways to just test it three
times there's no cost to doing so in
terms of the complexity of the algorithm
it's just you're wasting time testing at
the second and third times because the
hit can't be any closer than you would
have already found when you test it the
first time but if you wanted to
deduplicate those you would need some
scheme for deduplicating them that would
involve a secondary like bit field and I
don't know whether like that
deduplication then adds an if you know
I'm saying so it's unclear whether you
want to do any of these things like
maybe you do maybe you don't
but I really don't know so those would
be specifics to the algorithm that we'd
have to test out but because that's so
clean I feel like I at least want to do
one thing before we spend any more time
on tree walks which is you just say if I
was to take the current geometry and
dump it into a voxel what would the
general occupancy of that voxel end up
being so let's suppose we took the
actual light lookup voxel and we said
let's figure out anywhere that a
a geometry element that we're testing an
occluder right or a light source let's
find out where any of those would have
entered into the voxel and we'll just
print out like the max occupancy of any
voxel at that point right and then we
can get some idea about whether this
would be efficient or not and then I can
maybe just maybe we'll just do it like
maybe this is what we'll do because
maybe this is a lot smarter and we can
sketch out the routine and just see
today if we think it would be
it requires casting one ray at a time so
that part may be bad right you don't
have to but it would make things way
slower if you didn't I would think
because you'd rather not test a bunch of
things you don't have to test I would
think I mean I don't know so anyway just
a thought
and so if you were to do that then there
are some nice side effects which is that
you don't have to decouple raise to
compute the hit afterwards because you
only have one ray so you're actually
computing on the faster side of things
potentially and presumably that's a good
thing like so presumably when you got
into it's just one seemed off and not a
bunch of selects at that point so it's
possible that this routine gets faster
in the lighting act code it's possible
that in the raycast code like this stuff
could get a lot faster because rather
than doing all these selects you're just
storing one variable which is who the
best tier a hit was at who the best
index was rather that you could then you
know look up at the end or something so
I feel like maybe it's got some promise
I don't know hard to say and so when you
do these you would do exactly the same
thing that you do here except you would
you would collapse on tier a so you
would have to do a min on tier a each
time at the end of this is what you
would end up actually doing and so again
like I don't know if
maybe that's not as good because when
you do the min on tear a you'd have to
know which one you did I guess what I'm
saying is there's a mob mask in here
that wasn't in here before right and so
that's a thing maybe is bad right and
again these this code is so touchy that
I'm not sure I can make a strong
prediction about it either way so again
I think it would just be something we'd
have to test out so if we imagined like
what this raycast routine would look
like like if I was to do it the other
way round right so imagine we took this
thing and said look we're just gonna
like change this up a little bit so
instead of that raycast routine there
it's gonna be like a different one
doesn't use the stack it doesn't doesn't
use that stuff right so in here we would
just say okay there's going to be a
thing that's like a grid raycast or
something and it takes the the Ray
origin and the rady unduplicated so
you're just calling like one cast each
time right and when we go through here
and we get out the you know this
information we would be doing the same
thing here this total cast initiated is
it looks like it's a little low so those
numbers are a little false because we're
actually casting for rays at a time so
that should have been so these numbers
are not as bad as they seemed they
should be divided before so it's more
like six partitions per array right and
and like less than one leaf per Ray
right I mean sort of because it's times
four so so that's actually not that bad
right it's not as bad as I thought it
was gonna be so we'll see so maybe this
isn't as maybe this won't be as good as
I did them because if you look at that
it's only doing it once per ray cast
right which which is not as good so
really you want in in terms of total
Ray's like we would want that to be
times four fact I could do that I'm not
sure how we would want that because
these are sort of different so maybe the
right way to do it is to say look this
is like four and
as you know one you know and we could
change that to be called total raise
initiated as well total raised cast just
to make it clear what was happening
there
so anyway inside something like this
when we come through it I'm gonna get
rid of the debugging for now because if
this debugging would have to be
different so we're gonna save that for a
little bit later and I'm also going to
get rid of the branch here because we're
gonna write a completely new one so this
can all go away like so and yeah so when
we look at what would happen here there
would be two phases of this so one would
be a phase where we loop through all of
the you know all of the stuff in the one
is we loop through basically an array
that tells us what to cast so we would
do something like this this is like our
walk index or something and we would
have an array so in here there would be
a thing that's like which which grid
square to load if that makes sense so in
here we would have a like you know a
load index pointer you know I'm saying
and it would be like our block table you
know we would get that out in here we
would basically say like and you know we
could we could even write this a little
bit more cleanly where we just say like
do
you know wild walk count you know and so
on so each time through here we'd say
like okay you know at the end do a sub
and a step out in here we would load off
of the load index so we do like a load
index plus plus and this would be what
we'd actually be loading here right so
each time through here it would give us
some index to load and so this is like
the leaf index that we would get and we
would just copy that leaf index into our
testing stack now we can either copy the
index or the actual data I'm gonna go
with data for now because why not so
when we load this in we would just like
place it into the l1 cache in the right
location right like roughly probably
using the right buffers so we'd probably
just like stamp it out in an xx xx YY YY
ZZ ZZ pattern right so in here what we
would want is something roughly like
this where we say okay we are going to
have like box information here so we're
going to have like you know box mins box
Max is right and I don't know what the
size of these is gonna be exactly but
you know something like this will clean
this up as we go and then we would also
need probably the ref colors I don't
know I mean like I said we could also
just have index e indexes that we're
flattening out here so we could just do
the index ray and then load for a time
later but I don't know it's again hard
to say um so then we've got like ref
colors and emissions right so no it
would be something like that I don't
love this I feel like I feel like the
way that we do emissions is not very
clean feels like you shouldn't need to
do what we're doing so if you look here
you can see what happens
it does this nonsense where it says like
alright like take the probe sample
normal in the mission Direction right
and do some nonsense with it and then
combine those two it feels like we
should be able to send back something
better than that but I don't know we
should look at that later anyway we know
we need to send these back and I think
we need the normal two so it would be
something like this right so these are
the things that we would have to load
and we would load you know them four at
a time and that looks you know a bit
large but again like in terms of how
many realistically they're gonna be
there's probably not going to be very
many of these that we actually touch so
assuming you touch like maybe 16 of them
or something if you're talking about 16
times 3 times 4 that's 192 so you know
at some level keeping even eight of
those is miniscule right so reading and
writing these is basically just gonna be
like one cycle anyway for the most part
you know what I'm saying it's just not
probably a huge deal
so doing the gather here is not awful I
don't think I don't think right famous
last words
um so yeah so when we look at at writing
these out basically like I don't know
what the most efficient transfer methods
gonna be here but you know in terms of
like getting these boxes it's solution
right like box what is it called
there's some name for this stuff boxes
it's solution boxes leaf index is what
we're loading here so we're loading in
one of these lighting boxes and this is
our leaf Sumi and what I want to do is I
want to take the leaf data so everything
that was in the lighting box itself I
want to take the leaf data and I just
want to like unpack this stuff into
sim D format right and I want to pack it
for this specific process or that comes
after me so in this case what I want to
do is say alright like if we take and we
load out of the leaf the Box mend the
box max the ref C and the pack dots is
light value and leaf container can go
that's not a thing anymore so we'll deal
with that later but so we're gonna do
something like that and so if we wanted
to then start packing these what I want
to do is say okay the Box min like each
of these things is we're gonna be
writing to sort of sequentially which
means I may want to do this slightly
differently I may want to say like walk
index equals zero walk index lesson well
count writing this routine well is gonna
require some thinking about what the
assembly looks like so again I'm not
gonna think too hard about it now I just
want something not totally terrible so
we'll see but again like I want to do
this correctly it just in terms of
theoretically and then we'll think about
how to like structure the walk ideally
that's at some point late in the future
okay so I want to do box min walk index
and as the walk index goes up I'm just
gonna be like addressing these like
sequentially so actually like looking at
it this way it's gonna be more like this
right we're gonna be writing to these as
f 32s
so we're storing out to memory and then
we're loading them up wide if that makes
sense so I'm gonna look at this this box
min as if it's f 30 twos I'm going to
assign to them sequentially each
individual like box min part right so
what I want to do is I want to say let's
look at this as if it's an F 30 as if
it's a well I guess actually I don't
even quite need to do that I can
actually use the dot syntax here so I
want to assign the I want to assign the
every
every four I want to move on to the next
one and I want to address the like you
know for modded element of it right so
again all I'm doing is just on i'm
Swizzle indies into a cindy you know
friendly format that's all i'm doing
here so you know i'm gonna take whatever
the x component is and i'm going to
stick it into one of these like so right
and i want to do that for each of these
so we could also do like maybe this is
our you know primary index and our
secondary index something like that or
our lane index so primary index just
walk index over for welcome next mod 4
so i've got our primary index here and
our walk index here like so and then i
just want to assign each of these so i'm
unspooling these into place right and
we're probably gonna want to do these
with actual cindy ops right so like I
said the problem with that is we're
gonna have to do like for wide loads so
we have to like queue up for indices
load for and go forwards which is harder
so we're not going to start with that
but we may have to get to that when we
actually try to optimize this for real
but we'll see so if we're talking about
that then we'd need to like load these
up so we've got box max here and this
actually I guess isn't the case because
that's determinable later so nevermind
with that it's only ref color that we'd
actually need to store it there and
emission right so yeah and these could
be stored much more compactly these
could be stored as a single packed value
so like the emission value like an RGB a
select these
like at some point this crap has to get
worked through and we can do a lot
better job compacting down the light
information to some encoding that's not
so unwieldy as this particular thing is
but that's sort of a separate discussion
we don't have to care about that at the
moment also this isn't hit ref color
it's just ref color intermission so
here's our ref color like so that's
called a ref see and then finally down
here we would just have that like
emission and the emission yeah is again
is this this would be dot X dot e
actually this is the wrong way around
right it's that way oops accidentally
give equals so this is more like that
and that should give us what we need and
for the emission that's just gonna be
the standard because that's just an f32
for X so that's just gonna be the
standard where we just say look whatever
this thing is we either provide a 1 or 0
I think is how this was working at the
moment so it's like if it's a light it's
1 otherwise at 0 is all that we actually
do so this loop would be all we actually
need to do and this part here could be
loaded up better like I say so this this
doesn't need to be an if and at the
moment it really probably won't even be
an if it might actually just be done
with the seam off or something but but
this doesn't have to happen because in
the future I think we can pack these
better this should just be packed like a
8-bit RGB emission value or something
like that is what we should have
something like this
I mean that's my thinking anyway we'll
see so once we unpack everything into
these then all we would do is do our
actual test by counting how many of
those we had so when we do our loading
well this is actually so this is not
true so we would have a separate walk
here right which is the while that that
loops over like it's not this is not
quite right so that's a lie this walk
index would tell us the leaf indices
come out of nodes so there are two
layers here right for each of the things
we do have an unpredictable brand like I
said there's the one here which is just
it's a known number that you loop
through so that one's a fairly
predictable branch it only misses the
last time but this one is the
unpredictable branch like I said there's
two there's that one and then there's
the one that's here which is we don't
know how many of these are going to be
although that's not really that never
mind okay so in here this is what we
actually need to do for wait a minute
let me just make sure we got this right
this is not necessary so that wouldn't
be the case and so it's just this one
here is the only thing we actually need
to do so we would be doing this and that
all goes away like so and then this part
here is still the same I think well
actually it doesn't have to be this part
can now be done in scalar or done
outside by assembling multiple hits
right so yeah
yeah and we could do we could keep we
could preserve the structure of the
routine if we want to by just looping
over each array so we could do this but
it seems better to just call it four
times and get the results back and like
I said since you want this to sort of be
done as part of that ending code I'm not
sure how we want to deal with that like
this kind of has to now move into the
external code you know I'm saying like
this part here now has to move into the
code that actually calls the ray caster
or you can have it be two-stage but it's
something like that right so you know as
those come out you then you then load
them up as four things so again I'm not
sure what we want to do about that but
like this part here right just becomes a
little crunky ER because yeah you have
to deal with that part so I'm not sure
what we want to do about that I'm gonna
leave that temporarily and just think
about these for the moment so assuming
again that we're only doing one this
right here is like the leaf loop so this
is just going to be like looping over
the leaf indices of a particular node
[Music]
so it's like this we pull one out we
pull out whatever the grid node is that
we're talking about here and that grid
node so this is our lighting grid node
this is all it is is two things it's how
many of these there are and an offset
into the list right and again I don't
know if they should be in directed or
not maybe they should maybe they should
I have absolutely no idea so let's
assume that they are undirected for now
like I said so this would be you know
start index one pass last index and then
be loop and this is telling us like what
in that array those are going to be so
then our leaf index is like solution
spatial leaf indices and it's just this
right so we grab one of those out we now
have our leaf index we look it up and we
copy out right and so again like I said
the thing I don't know is should those
just be flattened and I have absolutely
no idea whether they should be flattened
or not maybe maybe not
totally don't know have no idea
furthermore it may be that not only they
should be flattened but they should
actually also be likes whistled so that
you load for a time and then you write
but I mean then what would you do for
nodes that don't have four things it
wouldn't work like because you are
wasting precast at that point so unless
you had an average of four things for
node that which I don't think you will I
mean maybe but that doesn't seem like a
good idea I don't know
that's a little temperamental I'm not
sure what we'd want to do there if you
ended up having an average of four
things four no typically like either
zero four eight
we're not uncommon like discritization
x' then that might not be bad because
then you could just like Swizzle them
once the beginning and not have to
Swizzle them here so I don't actually
know about that part either I'll put
that up here
and one of the interesting things about
that so now that I'm thinking about that
maybe the answer is that's just what you
do because if you load four boxes at a
time from the walk and that's just what
you do you don't need the second loop
because there's no needs to save them
now right to heck with it I'm just gonna
say that's what we do so if we make that
concession and say we're at four zero
four or eight boundaries basically then
this comes into the middle now right and
this loop is just look we walk over some
stuff we've priests whistled this crap
already so basically this happens at
tree construction time so we're still
gonna do this right like that still
happens but it happens at tree
construction times so in like build
spatial partition for lighting in here
what we would actually do is do the grid
build right we do the grid build here we
cross our fingers and pray we don't blow
out the cache doing that but assuming
that it stays in l2 which should be 200
physics K which it probably will most of
the time maybe might not do that but we
do walk the grid in order so we may get
enough for you sunrays I don't know
doesn't matter we're gonna do it anyway
so in here we would say okay we go
through the welcome to season leaf
indices and we literally just load this
crap out directly
so in here when we say look we have a
spatial grid node and that spatial grid
node is what we loaded out of the walk
table we're then going to load leaves
directly out of that node from our
spatial you know grid leaves so this is
a direct walk rather than you know
in other words this is this right so we
basically say like look load this thing
out of here and we're gonna like test
that crap a bunch of times now so inside
the leaf we load up the box min in the
box max directly like so and then when
we do this stuff and we're doing like
the Hadamard products with the invar ad
here this Inver ad is actually the thing
that's duplicated not this right so in
Brady is like load opt up right so this
right is load up up from this rady here
you know I'm saying and so I mean we
could have it passed us a 4x but I don't
think there's any point in doing that at
the moment because it has to be loaded
up either this we can take because we
know it's that way but this is actually
just a single one so this is like you
know single ray D instead and then here
we load it up we do a load up right so
at that point yet in fraidy is the thing
the next M so this all stays the same
like all of this right this is all
exactly the same
I don't know what close enough does
nothing so I'm not sure why that's there
anymore that would have just been
getting thrown out by the optimizer
anyway as useless but so in here we
would we would then what we need to do
is figure out what we're actually
storing here as far as like our team in
T max stuff right and I think you can
just do exactly the same thing and then
at the end we're just gonna load out the
one we actually care about I think
right so in here we loop through and we
just say none of this is necessary so
we're literally just talking about the
same crap as before so like we just go
into this thing and say we're keeping
exactly the same crap as we were keeping
before oops oh it's already there so
we're keeping this exact crap this exact
crap is exactly what we're keeping all
of this stuff right yeah and off we go
yep so then when we come through here
and we've done all of the selecting like
we now at the end the difference is that
we now have like a instead of having
four different rays that all need to
have an answer we now actually have like
one ray whose answer is spread across
multiple values now the good part about
that is like the the good thing about
that the good thing about that is we
don't have n weigh loads in SSE so we we
have to process these see really any way
to look up their lighting values so
that's actually a win the thing that's
not good about this is figuring out
which one of these to pick is actually
non-trivial because actually getting a
specific one out is hard and it gets
easier using later versions of the
instruction set but as for just sticking
with SSE one and two I'm not sure what
we have for extraction that doesn't
involve like I just don't know if we
have
I don't know if we have a lot of ways to
do that that's not gonna help us
yet suit I'm probably not explaining
this cuz I'm thinking it about in my
head and I'm not saying it which is not
helping anyone I'm just trying to figure
out how do I what would be the quickest
way for me to get the results to be what
to use a comparison to get what the
results actually are because once we
leave the for wide path we need to know
which of the four was the minimum right
that's the tough part
and so needing to figure out which for
which of the four was smallest is the
problem that we have and I'm not sure
how we get that to happen efficiently
it's not really something I've done in
ssee hardly at all and I don't know like
what if we went a little higher up what
if we let ourselves go up to like four
point something right is there some way
that we can extract something
numerically so those are all immediate
so no those are all oh that's not an
immediate but that's it that inserts
that value right so that doesn't help us
either here let's do this
and I'll look at three I mean if we have
to add three I guess I wouldn't cry
about it but so let's look at swizzles
[Music]
moves miscellaneous --is and general
support I guess I don't know I'm just
trying to figure out what I might be
able to do here to get something out
that wasn't based on an immediate and I
there may just not be away cuz if that's
if that's the case then it's like a
switch statement or something right
which is not not my favorite it's in the
faster part of the routine it only
happens once so it's not the end of the
world if that's what has to happen but
it's just it would be nice if we didn't
do that but I'm not sure if there's any
way to not do that right like I'm not
sure there's any way to tell it like hey
don't do that
shuffle it instead or something
yeah I don't know so I think what I
would have to do at that point is I'd
have to just do unless I'm missing
something I have to do something with
like a table or something right I mean
or I guess I can do a store in a load
using the mouth mask value so like if I
do the move mask you know if I do have
move mask PS I can get the high bit
which means that if I do a comparison I
should be okay so basically like you
know if I take the min what I want is
the min and do I not have a min
seriously
there's a min what are you talking about
I mean you can definitely take the
minimum of two things and it produces
the result on the other end why am i
open i had these checks still I'm like
what are you talking about
sorry so I can do a max and a min like I
can do these to figure out like which of
the T values is the one we're gonna use
right it's just kind of expensive and to
sketch out what I mean like why I'm
saying that it's kind of expensive to do
is I've got T ray and there's four
values in it so if I do like tear a I
would need to first Swizzle it right
like I need to do something where I
would say like look do a shuffle on tear
a where we produce like you know 0 1 0 1
&amp; 2 3 2 3 or something and take the
minimum and then because I need to take
the minimum I need to make sure all the
values have gotten their minimum taken
so I need to I need to get the minimum
of the four wide elements you know I'm
saying so in here I would say all right
you know shuffle T array to give me you
know the there's like you know 0 1 I
guess it doesn't really matter because
you're wasting a lot of ops here but I'm
not sure how you would do it unless you
just do bulks of these at a time which
maybe we need to do but we'll see so
imagine you do this where you just like
look I want 0 1 0 1 and I want 2 3 2 3
out of this or something right
and when I do these two what I then want
to do is take the minimum of those so
like this is the mins or this is the min
like 0 2 1 3
right so it's the min a piano
so I would need to do that first and
then once I have that minimum I need to
shuffle it one more time like you know
like this basically and that would be
this actually that because I want to
take this and I want to move the two
three down into the zero eighth position
so it's lined up with the other one
right and so then I would do the minty
right routine min is just mm or I guess
that shadows it but min P s min a B then
C D so then you have a team in value and
that team in value tells you what the
lowest one was and if you do a comp EQ
at that point you're gonna get out like
which of what you're closest which one
was the closest right so you would
basically do like teaming you know
teaming mask equals mm comp EQ the tear
a with the team in that would give you
zeros in all the lanes and ones in the
one lane that was the minimum now two
things could be the minimum so it's a
little bit tricky there but after you do
this copy Q you can say you know the
output mask that we get is going to be
the mm mauve mask of team in mask and at
that point we now finally have a thing
that tells us which lane to extract
right and
at that point we can if we want to load
it so we can f/32 load stuff now and
again it's it's not great but I think
that's how you would have to do it so in
order to produce the correct versions of
each of these things you would now have
to use the mask now to be fair I think
you can still do the rest of the
computations pretty easily so it's
really just that one extraction of like
well let's see so what were these doing
down here let's just take a quick look
so in terms of all this stuff where
you're computing it I feel like a lot of
that stuff
in scaler you probably don't have to do
it this way I'm guessing
that's a little bit hard to say em but
again if you look at this extraction
that was happening down here like that
doesn't have to happen anymore so like
this can just occur like directly you
know what I mean
so yeah so if we were to do this
directly just want to see what we
actually need so the t hit value here is
just whether or not this thing was equal
to f 32 max which at this point we don't
care about exactly here where we have to
do the get component that doesn't exist
because we already know that that's the
emission direction we already have that
information so that's not particularly
interesting either right this here is
literally just that one if so it's
literally just hey when we get the
actual T min value out of this thing
which is the part that's a little bit
tricky because we have to extract it
using thing but you know like all of
these extractions it looks like we were
already doing them right so in a sense
they're not more expensive they're the
same so in here we would do I guess the
same thing right we would just say look
if if this is not equal to T ray
whatever the tier 8 values ends up being
like the scalar T ray like so and then
in here where we do like the get
component and all that stuff we can just
do this thing we can just do these in
one wide because although it was nice to
do them too wide this is the expensive
part of the operation and it only works
with one wide so I'm not sure we were
really saving anything I mean you save a
little bit but most of it not really
because you got to do this and that's
the part that actually cost you
something so I think that's probably
okay I mean here's the hit P that you
have right so you've got the hit P here
and it's just going to be that value so
it's just the Ray origin
plus the T ray x TD
and that value the sample n is the hard
thing like it's this ridiculous nonsense
here and so I think that's a lot easier
to compute now because all you would
really need to do is see which of these
things is the higher value is it the X
the Y or the Z right I think that's all
this is saying so when you look at what
the normal is you would all you would
really need to do is look at which value
was highest and that's something we
could do probably a lot easier than this
would be my guess so I'm thinking what
we could probably do there is something
much much much more straightforward so
we could probably do something like if
we computed these values the same way
that we're doing it here so we do this
Center and the radius and we look at
what the Delta value is between the
center you know it's really the inverse
radius that we need there I guess or is
it
so I guess yeah all we really need to do
is is do this computation which I
suppose is not that hard right it's just
this so we would need to compute those
two values and then we would need to use
that radius to compute the inverse
radius so this this code would work
exactly the same way it just would
wouldn't have to use it wouldn't have to
worry about the fact that there are four
different values so when it comes time
to get down to here you actually
wouldn't probably do that you'd probably
do something like this hmm you'd
probably say like if the scale D is like
less than er so you've got I mean what
are all the comparisons here that we
were doing right like here they all are
so those are the comparisons you're
doing you're doing like X s and y XS and
zy less than X y less than Z Z less than
excellent you're right so what you'd
probably do is you just do like you know
normal bitmask right and you'd say just
put all these together like
so you'd do these comparisons where you
do each of the you do each of the
comparisons and then you just like grab
the bit mask out and load right so it'd
be and in fact since you've got you
could probably do that more efficiently
with a single mouth mask just by doing
like putting those in like some lanes so
you could do like x one of your vectors
could be like X x YY and the bottom
could be y zy X Z and then you'd only
have the Z ones but you wouldn't even
need them right probably
strictly out of curiosity are we just
are we totally missing an absolute value
here I think we are
so I think this code is missing an
absolute value right because we haven't
tested like another thing we have to do
when we do our lighting quality pass
right is we have to test all these
things and make sure that we're actually
we don't have bugs in the test case and
I feel like this is missing an absolute
value because all of these comparisons
are not quite right they're only going
to work if you're on the positive side
or the negative side of both right you
can't be comparing these things if you
don't have them absolute valued first so
I feel like you would have to end them
with that mask before so I'm gonna say
like I'm gonna say like we probably are
gonna end up vaporizing that case
because I think doing this in scaler is
probably the right way to go but I don't
know right so that's hard to say so
anyway in here we would do a normal bit
mask and I guess we just need to know
like look we need to know two things we
need to know the signs of these things
and that's one move so like the sign
mask would just be one you know move
mask of the like pact XYZ vector and
then the comparator mask the like or the
greater mask that's going to be like a
mauve mask of a comparison between like
pact XYZ and I need to know like the
comparison between like XY and Z and Y Z
and X probably but once you know those
comparisons I don't know that you need
to know whether like transitive property
wise I should be able to determine from
just three comparisons shouldn't I
I might need one more but like you know
you could imagine doing like this is we
pack one with like X Y Z X right or
something like that and we do like X Y Z
X and packed like Y Z X Y or something
right or Y Z X Z I don't know but you
can see that us getting the extras one
in there but point being once we get the
sign and the greater than in theory we
should then have a way to use a lookup
table to generate the correct normal and
and it in right I would think and so I
think all we have to do at that point is
do two loads right you just do like base
normal or you know you do the normal and
you do like normal table and the normal
table just has this mass in it so it
takes those compares and gets us the
normal and then the sign table right
oops just looks up the sign mask and
applies that right well they're actually
so
[Music]
I think it's always the same so we
actually don't need that we just need to
know I mean I guess we still would want
to load it this way so that we could
Hadamard park them and not have to like
build that up but we might not even need
to do that all right so we would do
something like this and that would get
us our hit normal again just a sketch of
a routine we would come through here and
we would see whether or not this thing
needs to do it's like moon color dance
nonsense here we would say all right
like we can compute this we know we
already have that the hit ref color is
again an extraction so I think this is
like a getcomponent
based on that this would also I guess be
just a getcomponent
exactly like we're doing here this is
the the team in index here the emission
value again the same thing and then the
rest of this just just does its thing
right so then you're left with the
transfer PPS that you actually wanted
um I guess I don't need to initialize
that because both paths do it and then
you have the actual raycast light value
you asked for right and you just have to
actually do something with it and that's
what you would return I guess that's the
only thing and you wouldn't pass these
down like that wouldn't happen none of
this would happen you would just do this
cuz you're now like not lined up for
anything so you might as well just give
back the value and let someone else deal
with it right so I don't know like I
don't know to what extent this is better
or worse but you can see why I'm
thinking that this is a better routine
because I mean if you just look even if
the simplicity of it it's just a lot
clearer how you optimize this thing
because now you're just doing this one
fast loop and that's it right and you
only just have to make sure that that
runs as fast as humanly possible you may
do a little bit too many computations in
there so that's not great but you don't
have any real like issues beyond that
the one down shift is scaler just
happens when you pull have to pull the
index here which is annoying and I'm not
sure if there's a more efficient way to
do that right but that be the entirety
of the raycast
at that point
so and I would say that based on that
that looks worth doing to me because
it's so much more clear how this routine
runs and there's so much less stuff
happening in it the only thing that I
don't like about it is that I'm not sure
how to quickly get that T ray out of
there
[Music]
so I'm not 100% sure on that part and
I'd have to think about that this may
not be the fastest way to do that either
basically like a horizontal compare you
don't want to do horizontal compares
right like they're not they're not
favorable in Tsim D is bad at this so
it's an issue right and again I'm not
really sure what I would do to try and
get rid of that there are some ways you
can I mean so
so if we allow sse3 we do have shuffle
epi8 right and shuffle epi8 is extremely
good at doing things quickly so but I'm
pretty sure you can't do it if you don't
allow SSE is that ssse3 what what is
ssse3
oh it's the supplement sorry
it's the supplemental streaming Cindy I
don't think I ever internalized the fact
that that was an SSS SSS
III as opposed to an sse3 but evidently
it is
there's pea chef be right there right
okay so yeah if we take a look at the
shuffles they're like I think that's the
only way we could really do something
fancier there I think so if you imagine
like using ssse3 which I wouldn't
necessary be averse to you because I
believe that pretty much like at this
point if we look at scheme hardware
survey for like getting what our sse
platform would be here it's always
moving upwards you know and we don't
plan on shipping anytime soon you look
at these and it's like okay so ssse3 and
even foreign two are like almost
complete coverage like no one is doing
that and furthermore you look down here
and you're like wow like we could even
go up to a VX if we really wanted to and
we probably wouldn't knock out very many
machines by doing that so avx2 kind of a
stretch at this point so going eight
wide not necessarily a thing or using
some of that as a c4a
looks like not-so-good but in terms of
this stuff we could totally do that
right so if we wanted to do a shuffle
using epi8 shuffle which is a pfb
instruction right yeah if you want to
use the PFP instruction then we probably
could actually do something here because
[Music]
what we would do is we would mask so we
want everyone to get the value that
comes or we want to put in a known
location that we can I am m8 out we just
want to get that value and so if we just
used the mask to produce a shuffle that
put the correct value there trying to
think of how you would do that it's
still kind of confusing oh well okay
[Music]
yeah I'm still not sure like exactly how
we would do that you would have to take
and do a mask that would tell you like
you'd have the ones in the correct lanes
but then you've they're in the wrong set
of lanes like you want it to be down in
the predictable side
so I guess what you would do is you just
do a load I mean is that really the
fastest way to do that so I mean I just
hear me out
so suppose I wanted to take this min PS
here right and like I've got what the
minimum value now actually is at that
point I want to shuffle everything into
position so I don't have to do weird
extractions so in other words what I
want to do is then say all right instead
of get component on any of these things
I want to be able to just get directly
the value by using an immediate so I
want to be able to do like this you know
what I mean where I just have an
immediate which is always zero right so
that's you know so I can basically say
like look hitbox max right I'm gonna
extract just the zero value out of it
you know what I mean so that all of
these are just direct and they don't do
anything weird right and furthermore I
actually don't even need to do that
because I can just leave them in here
cuz I'm gonna do computations and now I
know they're at the bottom right so I
don't really have to do those I could
just at the very end when I want to
actually get one of these out I can do
it so I can actually just do these
directly knowing that everything is just
piling up in the bottom Lane right so
what I was saying is in order to do that
I could imagine having a packed table
where I would basically do like okay
after you did this right you then have a
16-bit mask so you've got you've got 16
possible values you can just load up
like your shifter right your your your
shuffler you would say like shuffle
table like your min your min shuffle
table is whatever the the mask was so
this thing
right that you then just apply so you
just do an epi eight shuffle right on
each of your actual things so hitbox min
hitbox max like all of these just
shuffle themselves so that now you know
you just have the right thing in that
way you know what I'm saying to you um
you don't even really need to load it
this way because you know it's the same
value so you can even like this thing is
actually like a it's like a it's like a
one like a prop it's like a propagate
right which I don't know that we might
just want the load to be one to be one
go so you know we might not do that but
you know it could be a more compact
table if you wanted to because it's the
same in each case so when you grab the
shuffle table out like so I think then
you just have everything you wanted
right so your team in is now like mm
shuffle epi is well it would just look
like this and that would just give you
like everything that you actually wanted
there right and we don't need this mask
anymore because it would you're only
using it for that one extraction that
you then grab out similarly like this
min PS we don't really care about here
right so it's really that so we do this
crap in order to get the min value here
which we then comp and output and at
that point we just say okay now
everybody shuffles against that shuffle
that we loaded out with that mask right
and then all of our computations can
just happen in normal like wide space
and everyone's fine with that right so
this still is
just the standard wide version and we're
just not using like it so it's still
doing skits doing it scaler but we don't
need to actually move it to scaler first
for any particular reason you know I'm
saying so at that point when we actually
do when we actually want to use any of
this stuff we then have to move it out
to do this part and that would be the
first time when we actually move it out
and I think that might be where I'll
stop today because I think tomorrow's
when I would actually get into
implementing this right we don't have
much time left I guess we got 15 minutes
maybe um so yeah but like I'll just keep
cleaning this stuff and then I think
we'll stop
so all of these would always be zero
right so these would always be mMmmm
tracks and we really just have a nominal
HR issue here because I wanna be able to
extract this and we just don't have a
way of talking about those easy but I
think that's basically it so we would do
this that's not that bad we'd have a
shuffle table we'd we'd do it
we'd go I think we can use the table for
most of this stuff so this would all be
table driven basically and that'd be
that
so I think that's good I don't have a
problem with that and what we could do
here is say like look this is also gonna
be you know an LFO and then at the very
end we just have another Elif and what
we could do is just say look we're gonna
do the trance the transfer PPS bunch of
stuff here oh well you know I guess I
can't quite do that
because we don't like I want to actually
test the faster version of that but I
suppose we don't have to do that like if
we want to we can just return well no I
I really do want to test the faster
version of that so I guess we're not
gonna do an LF there I take that back I
guess what we're going to do is more
like this so in here
what we would do I guess is just heaven
if use or I don't know this would be
lighting use old Cady or use old use for
rays or something like that right and in
here then at the end of that I'm going
to put this and then we're just gonna
call it grid ray cast and we're gonna
call grid ray cast like four times right
so it's like
this and then we let everything happen
and then we let everything happen
normally right so this would just happen
by doing a get component to cast the
different sets of rays so this is the
Ray origin this is the radio we get a
zero out of it right like so which is a
little unnecessary and necessary slow
but it probably wouldn't make it look
too bad so we can still probably do it
that way just until we delete whichever
one of these paths we've determined is
not the right path to continue going
down so here I can just say look we're
gonna cast four times that'll produce
the transfer DPS and then we can still
finish up here right and then if we
decide to vaporize all these passes we
would then just go in here and like
clean up the flow so that we're doing
the most optimal flow from the top part
down to here right but I think that's it
and that's so much simpler than the rest
of the stuff that we're doing it's
suggest it I would say the only chance
that this is wrong is if going for wide
on these is a bad idea
but even if it was then doing the load
pack Swizzle thing ahead of it and
feeding it into this thing probably
would still work so I feel like I feel
like this is probably okay you know what
I mean
you
so that's that's what I'm thinking and
it's much simpler right so the simpler
routine is the easier it is to optimize
that's just generally the case right you
don't have to work as hard so that would
be a nice bonus that we would get
they're just a lot less moving parts you
build most of stuff ahead of time which
is what you want when you're optimizing
like the more stuff you can do that
doesn't have to happen on the fly the
better so I would say yeah that just
seems like what we want right
[Music]
like that that just seems good to me
so I think that's good I think
unfortunately it's gonna take us a long
time to test this because in order to
make this work we have to do a bunch of
extra stuff right we have to add the
walk tables we have to do the work of
distributing the cast like the actual
pieces and then we have to actually run
the routine right and debug it so it's
gonna be a long time to test
unfortunately that's a bummer but based
on the sketch I would say I'm relatively
happy with that right so I'm totally
willing to give this a shot and I think
it's when I was thinking about the KD
tree I'm like it's not even very good
for our fit because we know all our
stuff is access aligned bounding boxes
and it's like Katie trees are really for
narrowing in on arbitrary like
distributions of density and stuff like
this and we don't really have that like
we have fairly uniform distribution of
density and we know that everything is
sort of rectilinear because that's just
the way our game works so it's unclear
that we really want a Katie tree anyway
so I'm I'm more optimistic about this
than going in and working on the Katie
tree walk
so I think I'm gonna I'm gonna try it
Thanks what we're gonna try and then if
it doesn't perform well then we'll
regress back to the KT tree we're not
gonna delete it but I think that's what
we want
flighting is really simple until you
want to make it running real time yeah I
agree if you just don't care how long it
takes then ray-tracing pretty much gives
you the answer you want without a whole
lot of work but
I think we can probably go to QA because
they don't think there's anything left
to do we're just gonna implement this
routine I'm trying to think of how much
time I get 10 minutes left well you and
I could do I could vaporize this for now
and what we could do here is say look we
won't do grid cast here yet so that'll
stay out of the way turn a null value
and then what we'll do is we'll go do
the part where we actually need to fill
Jimmy we can sketch out the part where
we actually need to fill in the spatial
partition so in here where we need to
build the actual grid we can go through
this whole thing right
and so inside the grid build what do we
actually need to do well we're probably
gonna have to step through the boxes so
we're probably doing something like this
right and in here where we step through
each of the boxes what we need to do is
find all of the grid squares that that
box touches and put them in there now
the reason this is kind of a pain in the
butt is because we actually don't know
ahead of time how many boxes are in each
grid square and so we're gonna need like
an intermediate way of chaining these
things together and then unpacking the
chains into compact arrays for ray
casting because anything we do here we
can be a lot slower here because it only
happens once anything that happens on
the raycast has to happen like hundreds
of thousands of times and so we really
don't want to do it in there right we
want to do anything expensive on the
view here so it's okay but we do have to
do a little bit of work there right and
so here we would go through like the
node indices and we would unpack them
sequentially and when we actually figure
out where these things go node wise
again that's going to be something where
we determine the actual node we don't
need this all we would do here is say
look I guess these bv3 used probably so
it'd be something like this so we take
the men in the max of the boxes and we
now know you know we would have a v3u
for where those were in the voxel for
the min and the max we would step
through each one of these you know to
fill the voxel right just a standard
voxel fill right of a region and so we'd
say you know Z is mid note index Z Z is
less than or equal to mid note index
oops max node index Z and we do this for
each dimension so that would give us
everything oops
that would give us all of the locations
touched bite like that could possibly
hit this box we would then store it so
that we'd have to like chain for
whatever this location was right so if
we pass this new voxel location that's
somewhere in here we'd have to chain
this box on to whatever that was right
so the the solution we'd want to access
that node index we'd want to chain it on
here and then when we're done with that
we would loop over all of the nodes
right which would be however many was
the X times the Y times is e total and
for each one of those we would need to
sort of undo that chain right now we
know ahead of time how many of these we
actually need and we could pull it out a
temp memory potentially I mean I don't
know if we want to do that or not but we
know like the total leaf count at this
point and we can sum it because we know
here's how many there are
so when we go to the nodes then what
we're really doing is we're just saying
here's our you know leaf index currently
which is going to start at zero we go
through each of these nodes and we loop
over however many they have so we're
gonna need like a thing for the node
where we would get that out and that'd
be the same as this you know so we would
get one of these out we would do the
chaining here however we want to do that
and then in here we would say all right
for each of these we need to loop over
all of the lighting boxes that we
chained on to that and this could be a
linked list of some kind right it
wouldn't probably look like this because
we'd probably chain off a u16 since we
know that they are that way so we'd
probably do something more like look off
of these UN 16 after the off of the node
we grab a you 16 that's like the first
in chain and then we say like chain is
not equal to like chain and or something
you know this kind of thing and honestly
this probably has to be this way because
we're gonna go look this up right we
would then say all right which box is
this thing
and once we get that we can do like next
in chain as a thing that would we would
train off the boxes so for each of those
then this is where we actually do the
work so once we know that this thing is
going to be packed we would pack it here
um and so when we do the packing we're
doing packing into this thing and so we
would need a like a pointer basically
that tells us where we're packing how
we're packing right and we need this to
be
so actually we don't pollute the cash we
just waste instructions because this
doesn't have to be aligned so actually
we just pack this linearly right we can
just pack this linearly and all we have
to do is store how many you need to load
but we don't actually need it to line up
like we don't you can just load extra
boxes off the end of this thing and we
just have to make sure we Pat it so we
need to do like a wild leaf index mod
for at the end here and and write
garbage in there you know what I mean
but but other than that so these these
would just you know I'm not sure what
the best way is to produce something
that cannot hit it may be that this is
bad because if you pass directly through
the origin it would technically be
considered a hit you don't I mean so
that seems bad it's never gonna happen
like in any way that we would care about
but it does seem like maybe you would
want to avoid it so what you could do
here too is Pat it out with something
that you just can't really hit so like
you know something that's like off in
the stratosphere might be the right way
to do it right so it's like an inverted
box that's off in the stratosphere and
you know you'd never hit it or I guess
you could even do it this way
that might be the easier way to make
sure that you never hit that thing I'm
not sure like we should just put it to
do in here this like what's the best
can't hit me box for our actual box
collision test so if we do it that way
this would be everything that we need to
and and we just need now way to do the
chaining sensibly right but I think
that's it so I'll end it there but we
now have everything sketched out so now
we just got to actually do the
implementation there is one thing I
didn't do which was the walk stuff and
the walk stuff is literally just doing a
Rea walk like we can even do it just
offline we don't have to get fancy and
figure out what it would be for every
one of the Rays we store in our array
table we just store like which table
index it uses for its walk and a lot of
those would probably be the same I mean
maybe maybe they won't be but if there's
any duplicates we just remove them and
then that way we just load directly
another table what what we're walking
and that's it so I think that's good we
can go ahead and go to Q&amp;A now
could you use a couple of M's horizontal
subs to do your horizontal compare um
possibly yes
and in fact if we do decide that we can
use a sse4 we probably have a couple of
different things we could look at which
like I said lose using the steam
hardware survey it looks like sse4 is
probably pretty safe to use so we have a
couple things horizontal things that we
could use right so if you imagine that
is our actual target then we actually
have a bunch of stuff here I mean so so
if we want to just use SSE for point one
that is the entire instruction right
I mean that's the thing so I think like
we could just say look man let's just
use it and we can always have a slower
path later if we decide we really need
it but that I mean that's the
instruction it does the whole thing so
you know I can just say like literally
do min pause EP u16 and get what I need
right cuz if like SSE AVX avx-512
eventually you get far enough up there
they've got the actual correct
instructions that you wanted them to
have in the first place it's just a
matter of how far up you're willing to
go along there if that makes sense
so if we want to we can say you know so
I'm not sure which if I have to prep it
for this though by do it because it's
not a PS right so I don't know if
there's a min pause version of that it
looks like the only thing they've got is
the 16-bit one so I'd have to kind of
like put it into that format first
so I take it back that may not be quite
what I want cuz you want the min pause
PS right which apparently you can't get
because they only have that for just
that one instruction which is hilarious
but so maybe not we could make that work
we can pretty trivially turn our RT
values into 16-bit values that's not
that hard so we could just do that
instead we we'd take the team in the
team axe and and we'd bracket it so we'd
say look we know we don't carry any like
this thing is only so long so we'd say
map into that range
so first multi-verse converts a 16-bit
and do the min pause EP 16 right so we
just it would just be this
so we just say multiply this first by
what we know the maximum hit value is
and we would change this to be whatever
that maximum hit value was and then we
would do a min pause epu 16 that would
get us back our min test we would then
use that to shuffle everything right so
instead of this we would then have like
shuffler equals some shuffle of the min
test which would just move the correct
values around that we need it to use for
this yeah so we could do that too I'm
just not it's not sure like this part of
the code is not the part that runs the
most often so the the most often the
thing that runs the most often is this
right so this we need to make sure is
very very fast this cannot be slow this
part here is it two instructions is it
ten it will make a difference but it's
unclear how much of a difference so it's
unclear that you want to if if this part
of the routine could be made twice as
fast by switching to SSE for you
definitely do it if this part of the
routine can be made twice is passed by
switching the SEC for it's unclear that
you care yeah I'm saying you might just
want to stick with the simpler case
when it comes to game dev engine dev
what you believe is the hardest part to
implement lighting editors etc I would
say probably like infrastructure is the
hardest thing
so like the the the circle that you draw
that is what is the storage format for
both editing and runtime how does that
get processed edited saved shared
optimized that the infrastructure part
is by far the hardest because it has all
of the worst things it has to be edited
so it has to be flexible it has to be
looked at broadly because optimization
often pulls from multiple things to
produce the output assets you actually
need it needs to have fast turnaround
time so that artists can see their work
in the game it's massive because it
includes the sources it's way larger
than the game by many powers like a
hundred times larger than the game if
the game is twenty three gigabytes then
the source you know assets for that game
are probably like you know twenty three
terabytes or something right so it's
like thousand times bigger
how do you switch that fast me
navigating into code and typing am i
fast I mean this is me doing the arrow
keys and then I go into typing and start
typing I mean I don't know I don't know
it's not very far
uh-uh are we getting raided we're done
how can we get raided by John I was
gonna go raid John though what what are
you doing
when am I gonna have lunch
unacceptable unacceptable this is
completely unacceptable
alright well hold on one second let me
get a drink or something because yeah
you know what hold on one second
like let's let's end it here and but
I'll keep the stream going and I'll
think about it I'll be right back but
I'm gonna get at least a drink then