hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero show recode a complete-game live on
stream today we are going to have to do
some serious work actually or aggressive
side get started on some serious work
that we will probably do a couple days
on it is something that we probably
won't pursue to the enth degree because
you can get really really invested or
involved in this kind of problem it's a
it's a very hard problem it's a computer
science II sort of problem and it could
be something you could spend a great
deal of time on so we probably will try
to take some shortcuts and not do a
complete full solution to it just for
brevity's sake but it is gonna be
difficult regardless even with some with
some cheating and short cutting and that
is specifically we would like to lay out
some rooms for our game and we would
like to maybe do this in an automated
way or semi-automated way so that we can
create random dungeons and random worlds
and things that get laid out according
to certain things we need to be true
like what's connected to what and so on
so I'm gonna go ahead and show you what
I'm talking about and then we're because
we basically did all the work to set
everything up and we even put in a
little version of the code that doesn't
really work it's like sort of a just a
placeholder that just slaps things down
sequentially instead of actually obeying
the instructions that it was given so
we're we're basically all the way done
with ever all of the surrounding stuff
that we need and now we just need to
implement the the sort of core routine
that does the real work for this
particular part of the problem so if you
look at what we've got in handmade
worlds in here you can actually see if
we have a create orphanage call that's
an example of user kind of code and by
user I mean sort of the game design side
of things obviously we are both the
implementers and the users of all the
code in handmade hero so it's not like I
mean some external party that we're
shipping it
- but you can see here that I've sort of
laid out the stuff that I want it to do
I want to make some specifications for
how rooms are we haven't gotten into
that yet because that's sort of when we
get to room generation which is a
different thing we've said the rooms
that we want and then we said at what
connections we want between those rooms
you can kind of see that here we've
we've created these connections that
leaves us with a graph and it is a you
know a lot of times you hear different
terms like directed acyclic graph things
like that we do not have one of those
what we have is actually an undirected
graph the reason I say that is because
in our world things are spatially
connected so that means that if you can
get from A to B you can get from B back
to a generally speaking and so when we
talk about connections in that way we're
talking usually 99% of the time about
bi-directional edges in the graph two
rooms that are connected can are
connected in both directions so if
you're thinking about something like a
directed acyclic graph that you may have
heard that first term directed we are
not directed furthermore a cyclic is
talking about the fact that you don't
have cycles in the graph you don't have
any points to be points to see points to
D then points back to a write that is
also not true of our graphs we're
talking about graphs that can have loops
in them that can do all sorts of things
so we are not directed we are not a
cyclic we are just a graph in all of its
glory and what we want to do is try to
create spatial structures for these
rooms organizations in actual space that
will obey the same connectivity that
we've requested in semantic space in
just the sort of idea of the graph that
room a texture and B corrects Durham C
connects back to room a or whatever we
just want it to try and lay something
out where that can be true right so
that's what we're trying to do here now
if you look at where we're at we
actually like I said did all the support
code so actually we've kind of got
everything working and if you look at
sort of what we've got here in terms of
rooms you can see the room we're in is
the one that's
running the lighting right now and then
we've kind of got just rooms laid out
and these are all the rooms that we
created all those rooms through our
furniture and what you can see happening
right now is that the layout routine
instead of actually laying this out the
way that we requested it's just hard
coded to just stamp the rooms out in
series and again we did that just to
make sure that this whole pipeline was
working the creation of the rooms and
slapping them down once we said where
they were we want to make sure all
that's working because then we can just
focus on specifically the task of
figuring out how they should be laid out
right so that's what we want to do now
now in order to do that we need to come
up with some strategy for how we're
going to actually make that work and
this is going to be really difficult
obviously because let's take a look at
sort of why this becomes I'm gonna go
over to the blackboard now and we'll
talk about sort of first steps and
things we can start to try obviously one
thing we can do is try to just look
online for layout algorithms I'm not
gonna do that and the reason I'm not
going to do that is the same reason that
I don't do it on streem generally
speaking until after we've poked at
things a bit and that's that I like to
try and show how you attack problems
when you don't know the solution to them
or can't find a solution because that's
a very important part of engine
programming if you're just gonna program
things that people already did before
that's a separate thing it's still
valuable to do and doing research is
very useful I always research a problem
before I actually go implement something
but a lot of times I find that the
things that I'm researching are not
sufficient and then I have to go develop
my own solutions so on handmade here
we're probably not going to encounter a
lot of things that have no known
solutions to them because we're trying
not to get into that kind of
super-advanced technology but I do want
to mostly teach people how they would
start pushing in those directions when
they do want to do new technology or if
they simply want to have the fun of
developing their own algorithm which is
you know programming is supposed to be
fun at least it used to be before there
were 12 layers of you know nodejs
running on top of god-knows-what in you
know spamming all throughout the cloud
and who knows what's happening so
I want to take a crack at this first and
then when we sort of think we understand
the problem a little bit and we've
played with it a little bit if we are
unable to see good solutions that we can
do then we can go take a look look at
the literature and see what's there
but again normally just to draw the
distinction there I probably would read
the literature first in most cases there
are plenty of programmers who don't so
I'm not suggesting that you have to do
that I generally do and then I generally
go write my own algorithm anyway because
I want to do something slightly
different but you know I was informed
typically by what's happened previously
because usually you can least benefit
from seeing what other people have
experimented with even if it doesn't end
up being something that you wanted so
here's the problem that we have
specifically because you can think about
this layout problem and I'll just say
this is well actually I should say let's
call this specifically inter room layout
because later we'll talk about intra
room layout which will be different
that'll be like what happens inside a
room and so we need some way to talk
about those two separately so maybe we
could call this also you know world way
out as opposed to room layout I don't
know but you know what I'm talking about
not placing things inside a room but
placing rooms relative to each other so
the problem that we have is you could
imagine a layout algorithm that worked
perfectly fine for certain types of
graphs with certain types of constraints
on them that just took whatever the
first room was right this is room one
and then when it found room two it just
said well actually we wouldn't even go
that way
we'd start with just some room actually
we could pick it at random whichever
room we wanted now I think about isn't a
three room one right but whatever the
refreshments put down we then loop over
all of the connections to the room and
we say what real predictor it says oh
there are three rooms connected to it so
it just says ok start here put the first
connection here
the second connection here and the third
connection
they're right and that's how it lays out
the rooms then it moves to these and it
says okay I know I've used this side but
these two sides are free so tell me
where my connections are okay here here
you know in here if there's three again
whatever and then when this guy goes
special care has to be taken to make
sure that if I put it this way it
wouldn't intersect this room and so we'd
probably end up with a system that just
literally started placing rooms based on
connections and the only thing it would
do is not place a room off of an edge
where it determined there was already
something there that was blocking it
right now that would get us pretty far
okay that allows us to lay out rooms
that are not particularly complicated or
that don't have a lot of cycles in them
and things like this it would work for
basic things so what we need to focus on
most of the time is when does that break
right why do we need a better algorithm
than something that just simply goes in
order and doesn't do anything more
complicated well there's a couple ways
that can break the first way is the
simplest way and that is that if I say
that this room right here has 12
connections it's like okay 1 2 3 4 oh I
can't put any more in I failed right and
so there's a notion that we may need to
dynamically grow you know we may need to
dynamically resize a room to make more
ability to connect things so there's
sort of an implication here that we
probably want to allow the layout
routines to grow rooms when they need to
put more exits on them now we could also
make that be manual right this could be
a manual process and it's just a bug if
you don't do it if you don't provide
enough room size to connect things but
you know it may just be a more robust
algorithm if we allow it to resize rooms
so that if they need more X's they can
get them so that we don't accidentally
create you know bad worlds or mistakes
or errors in there that we then have to
recover from so one simple way we can
fail is just we can't fit any
things on a room right and the diner
sizing closer to that so that's like I'm
just gonna list them here rooms too
small that's the simplest kind that's
pretty easy to solve we just go oh if we
need more we can just we can see how
many exits it has and make the room
bigger right closely related but much
more difficult to solve is no space for
rooms right and now this can be caused
in all sorts of ways I put down a room
right I start connecting rooms to it and
then I find that something about these
rooms let's say there's already room
here already room here this room is
supposed to have connections well
there's nowhere to put right there's
literally no way to put anything there
any rooms there so what we would have to
do in that case is rethink how this was
laid out right we would need to stop
putting it there and start putting it
here or something
so that it could continue to grow right
and you can see that that's a very
complicated problem because you don't
know ahead of time when you're laying
out rooms what will eventually create
these sort of problematic regions for
you and so it's very hard for you to
guess as an algorithm what you should do
and you get into things where I believe
these are were traditionally called rip
up and replace routers let me to see if
that's true I remember this from
literally back in like this eighty
for my dad used to work on chip layout
stuff when I was a little kid and he
worked at Digital Equipment Corporation
and they were the people who made like
the deck alpha for example which was the
fastest processor in the world at the
time actually I think well it was it was
the highest megahertz processor in the
world at the time and I'm not I think
maybe I don't know it was a CPU that
broke the gigahertz barrier I think
really early or was very high I don't
remember much about them but they were
like super super high clock rates like
they I don't know it might have been too
early for gigahertz but it was like you
know PC processors were running at
pretty low clock rates like 133
megahertz at that time and these things
would run out like 700 or something and
you know it was it was a pretty cool
processor but because Digital Equipment
Corporation is kind of on the way out
and it wasn't really pc compatibl it
didn't really go anywhere you can look
it up here if you want more information
about it I don't remember much about
them other than they were like
supposedly pretty good at the time you
know compared to the other things you
could get and yeah you could see here
there's the V's sixes and sevens
breaking the gigahertz barrier that was
in 2001 I don't know if any other
desktop CPUs had done that at the time
AMD your Hertz chip was well after
because it was the it was actually I
think people from the duct alpha team
that went over there and actually did
the gigahertz version I think or were
involved in it so anyway he did that had
nothing to do with what he was doing he
was not in the prostitution proper he
was actually in a division that made
tools for chip layout which digital
cooper corporation used and one of the
things that you want tools to do is to
lay things out for you because you know
you you make these gates like processor
gates like you would think of oh here's
an ad adding circuit or you know here's
the thing that does a floating point
multiplier right or whatever and then
you want
these things to be laid out sort of
automatically that's some level there's
too many of them and you don't want to
lay them out by hand at first anyway a
lot of times people do go back and
manually lay them out by hand apparently
sometimes to get better performance but
there's machine algorithms for doing it
and I believe at some point they had
this thing called rip up and replace
routing I don't remember what the actual
terminology for it was it's not that
kind of routing it's this term right and
and they used to use that term a lot I
was too young to understand what was
going on back then but the problem is
basically the same as the problem that
we have here actually we are basically
just doing ship layout that's what this
problem is and the chip layout people
just got to it a lot sooner than then a
game designer would because game design
back then in those days you know there
were 20 30 40 50 rooms or something like
this and games like it's work or
something right maybe dungeon would have
been bigger ran on the mainframe I don't
know a hundred rooms I have no idea how
many interactive fiction games had at
that time I should know I just have
forgotten and you know those things were
designed by hand and there was no need
for automated layout when you're talking
about laying out a hundred rooms and
those rooms are not procedurally
generated there's no reason why you
wouldn't just put them on graph paper
and type them in right that's how things
were done back then but people designing
chips on these sort of high-end
workstations and all this other sorts of
stuff at that time we're dealing with
you know way more stuff and they have
the same problem they have circuits and
those circuits have connections that
need to be obeyed and they need to get
them all laid out on to a piece of
silicon it's fundamentally
two-dimensional and every time you need
to cross over something to get to
something else that's costly right
that's something you don't want to do
ideally all of your trace
just flow and nothing hops to hop over
something else to get to some other part
of the chip so when you're doing layout
you're trying fundamentally to solve the
same sort of problem as close together
as possible for the things that you're
trying to connect the connections go
direct they don't have to hop over other
things they don't they don't take huge
long circuitous trips through the
silicon etc etc right and so their
problem is a little bit different from
ours the reason they're problems a
little bit different from ours is that
we're talking about probably
fundamentally less connections and those
connections are abutment style
connections they're not traces and so
they are talking about you know dealing
with way more connections and those
connections can go long ways and cross
you're just trying to minimize the
amount that's happening right really
long traces are just bad for performance
you don't want to have to have these
really long traces running through the
silicon that's just a waste right and
slows the chip down reduces the the
maximum clock rate and all these other
sorts of things because the distance
that the electrons have to go through
the substrate is at the end of the day
going to be a problem for you and so on
right although nowadays I guess it's
mostly heat but I don't know not a
hardware designer so I can't speak to
that so fundamentally speaking what
we're talking about here is something if
we want to start addressing those kind
of problems we need something probably
that can try to do layout specularly and
when it finds that it cannot lay
something out in a way that's chosen
tries again right we want something
smart enough to go oh you know what I
couldn't quite get this thing to work so
I'm gonna like stop trying that and I'll
try something else right and that's
pretty complicated that's the most
complicated kinds of things to write
typically in software are things that
understand trial and error in a way that
cannot be directly brute forced now what
do I mean by that well brute force
sometimes it's like hey I'll tell you
what why don't you
tell me what two numbers when multiplied
together equals 536 right justjust I
just want to know what it is
and so there's elegant solutions to this
problem or more elegant solutions to the
problem right certainly one of them
would be just recognizing that it's even
in dividing by two and telling you two
and the other number but another way to
do it would be like okay there's a brute
force solution to that problem and it is
easy to write right it's for right all
the numbers here for all the numbers
here up to that number
you know if they multiply together to
equal the number that I wanted whatever
the target is you know that's it that's
the result and so two for loops that
loop over all the numbers produces an
extremely inefficient and completely
unnecessary how rhythm but it is obvious
how to write the brute for a solver that
solves it
it is wasteful but it works right once
you get into sort of two-dimensional
style problems like this it becomes
almost impossible to figure out how you
would write such a brute for a solver in
such a trivial fashion because any room
can be laid out anywhere right so there
is no 2 for loop kind of a version of
this thing because there's an infinite
number of places for every room so
there's not really anything could do
about that right but it doesn't mean we
can't try to go down that road it just
means we need to introduce new ways of
discretizing into brute forcible pieces
the things that were previously infinite
right so for example like we were saying
before we could say all right
everything's aligned to a grid that
discret eise's things quite nicely which
we've already started to do and we know
we want the flick anyway that's a good
first step to we could say oh rooms have
certain configurations of exits in them
and can grow in either direction in a
very predictable way so when we go to
a room we know we're iterating over a
finite number of understandable things
that can happen here right and then we
can start to build up the equivalent of
those brute force for loops for the
layout now the problem that we then will
run into is the same problem we would
run into for the other case once we can
get it down to something as discrete and
clear as that which is it will be slow
but that's probably okay because once we
have a slow functioning algorithm for
the layout we can probably look at ways
of making it faster within the context
that we've received right and one of the
things about that that we can you know
start to look at right is there's tons
of ways that this problem might be able
to be partitioned so for example when we
start to look at certain things here we
may know certain things about like say a
dungeon a dungeon may have certain
characteristics that we just know are
true for the way that we design them and
then we can start to like talk about
floors of a dungeon being laid out say
separately right so each floor of the
dungeon gets laid out separately and
then they get like attached together or
something like this and then that
dungeon gets placed in the world
somewhere and then that gets it right by
breaking the problem down into chunks
like that we can greatly reduce the
number of brute force permutations that
need to happen to lay any one thing out
and furthermore every time we gasket
eyes something like that into pieces we
also reduce the necessity for the brute
forcing to iterate because if it just
can work on the first time out there's a
lot less route for it cycles to go
through so not only are we reducing the
space of searching we're also increasing
the chances that one run through it will
actually just work without having to
brute-force very much in the first place
so when I'm thinking about this problem
of how to layout these rooms I'm
appreciating how complex it is and then
I'm sort of looking at okay first step
can I turn it into a brute-force problem
because that lets me understand the
problem right
get a functioning version that just
takes too long to run and that's a good
that you know don't let that scare you
that's a great place to be right because
having something that works but too slow
that changes the problem too and I don't
know how to solve this problem too and I
know how to solve this problem but I
don't know how to solve it efficiently
and that's a great first step so never
be scared about that never be scared of
writing an algorithm that you know sucks
right don't be scared of that if the
only algorithm you know is crap get that
working anyway because once we have the
crap algorithm working we can we can
start to set our sights on how we're
gonna make it not crap right and again
that moves the problem from a harder
domain to an easier domain making
something faster is easier than making
it at all right because we at least know
we've got something to fall back on and
we know that we at least understand the
problem to produce some solution you
know even problems that are incredibly
hard np-complete problems or np-hard
problems even those problems you can
usually implement solvers for because
usually the problems you're giving
inside those contexts don't fall into
the actual np-hard cases and so again
just implementing something that works
lets you start to gain that intuition
and see what's actually happening for
the inputs you care about and are
actually using and then at that point
you can tune the algorithms to figure
out how to actually run fast enough to
do something you want traveling salesmen
impossible to solve technically right
and I think polynomial time well I
should say that we know of right but we
still do it all the time right we still
we still write things like bus
algorithms that say we need to pick up
this many people and drop them off this
many places we still write solvers that
do it why because we can always do
something usually right when we look at
the actual problems we need to solve in
those spaces we can usually write
something that gives us reasonable
answers we can use and so
again you just have to understand that
no matter how hard the problem seems if
you're just willing to take it in those
baby steps you can start to be in good
shape okay
but all that being said I want to move
on to actually working on this year
pardon my allergies and given what I
just said just to give you some
perspective on the mindset I'm going to
with I want to try and figure out some
ways to turn this into a brute-force
algorithm but that will generally work
and then what I want to do well I should
say will work for any input that can
technically be laid out right it might
be possible to create something that
literally couldn't be laid out so I want
to create something that will work for
anything that could technically be laid
out you know assuming that that's
possible and then the other thing that I
want to do is I want to focus on making
sure that as I'm building it I have an
eye towards impermanence right because I
know ahead of time even just looking at
the basics of this problem I know that
this will not be the kind of problem
that one-pass will solve so I know
fundamentally speaking I am NOT going to
just have this thing that lays out in
one pass and there's the map I know it
will encounter struggles and it will
have to backtrack it will have to say
oops that didn't work erase what I just
tried and try again
and so I am fundamentally going to need
some fungibility there to allow the
algorithm to try multiple solutions to
various parts of the layout problem and
since I know that that's gonna be the
case I know I can't structure my
algorithm as a simple input to output
sort of path it's got to have an
intermediate representation that's
fungible and that can be queried against
and stuff like that right so we're
talking about a very rich I are here for
what this thing is working on where it
has to be able to say
let's try a room layout let's try
another one did that room layout
interest like this layout could I put
these two room layouts together blah
blah blah blah blah blah blah that's
what we're talking about here so it's
gonna be something it looks more like
the internals of an optimizing compiler
or something where it needs to be able
to kind of like fuss with the tree in a
couple different passes and things like
that it can't be something that it just
expects to read in the inputs and write
out the outputs because that's not going
to cut it for what we're asking it to do
I'm quite certain so that's what I'm
looking at as I'm going into this as you
can see we already have this sort of
layout function here that is the layout
function that doesn't work it's not good
we don't want to use it so now what we
need to do is sort of figure out how we
can start to convert this into the thing
that I was talking about which is going
to be able to do sort of the brute force
the kinds of kinds of operations that it
wants to do all right uh so let's talk
about this we know that as we loop
through our rooms here and we're laying
them out I know a couple different
things about this game first of all I
know that I can count on the generator
for the game to give me completely
connected spaces or a set of completely
connected spaces now what do I mean by
that well there is no point for this
game to ever create anything that isn't
connected to the game right in some
sense this resembles the concept of
garbage collection if you've ever read
about that you've got all these pointers
to things different structures that
point to each other and the garbage
collector looks at it and says Oh from
the code I can't ever reach this set of
data anymore
therefore it's garbage therefore I can
recycle it right that same concept is
true of our room connections if this
layout routine is handed something it's
got a bunch of room connections and it
creates sort of some islands where the
player starts over here and there's
literally no connections to this other
set of rooms well we know that that is
just never going to happen right
so we know that from any room we start
from when we do our layout we will be
able to get to every other room that's
just otherwise there'd be no point in
creating it now there are some cases
where we might not want that to be true
let's suppose we have some kind of a
teleportation that happens where there
is no connection between the rooms but
you can like step on teleporter and it
warps you there right then we know the
same thing that I just said is true but
there are a couple different starting
locations everywhere there is a
teleporter is a seed potentially right
so what we know is when we start the
layout we can just say that our layout
starts from a few specified starting
locations and then everything else is
reachable from there so we don't really
need to do much else in terms of
analysis beyond just saying start it at
the room you tell me to start on and
I'll lay it out right that's all we
really need to do so I'm gonna go ahead
and just give zero this out because we
don't really need it anymore and I'm
gonna go with something that starts the
way that I just said I'm going to start
with a room that says like okay
laying out room and I'm going to say
that I'm starting with whatever this
room is here that I'm trying to lay out
is going to be just the first room in
the series and while I have a room to
lay out I'm going to lay it out right
that's about all there is to it and I
always want to kind of spread out from
where I am now I'm gonna probably not
want to do this honestly I don't really
think I want a recursive function
normally when you're doing this sort of
thing you might make it easier on
yourself by creating a recursive
function and a recursive function right
is just it's not magic a lot of people
think that there's sort of this
difference between recursive functions
and non recursive functions but there
isn't they're the same I all that's
different is that the compiler happens
to have in it
a way of managing a stock right and so a
recursive function is just a weight I'll
be using the compiler stock management
instead of your own stack management
right that's the only difference between
those two things it's not like recursive
functions magically let you do something
without a stack it's still there so the
only difference between the two is to
lean on the compiler stock generation
for you now I don't think I want to do
that and the reason that I don't want to
do that is be for the exact same reason
that it's easy to use a recursive
function to lean on the compiler stack
because it's already there for you and
it's implicit it also kind of limits you
because that stack only obeys the kinds
of operations that the compiler
understands so the compiler just only
understands call a new function or
return
that's all it knows but I don't
necessarily want to limit myself to that
I may want to do things like check
pointing parts of the stack and
rewinding directly to them to try new
things and undoing things along the way
and all these other sorts of things and
I'll be honest I just don't want to deal
with the complexity that I think that
will introduce if I tried to make a
recursive function have that happen in
the sort of return path by setting some
variables to tell it what to do on the
way back up and you know you couldn't
implement it I don't want to I'd rather
just go with something that I implement
myself um so what I'm gonna do instead
is I'm gonna create my own stack and
that way I can operate on that stack
myself what I'm gonna do here is just
say that I've got something like a Gen
layout or gen room stack or something
and all this is gonna be is like a
linked list for now that just points
back to whatever the previous one was
and then what I'm gonna do is I'm just
gonna sort of allocate on right as I go
I'm gonna have this sort of like thing
where I just add to what I've got and
you know if you look on here we've got
this temp memory and I'm just gonna use
the temp memory I know it gets cleaned
up and you know where's my um I'm using
this for world Jen right for the room
generator I'm gonna use it here as well
so I'm gonna say let's start the
temporary memory situation happening
here at the end I'll clean it up like so
and then everything in here can just
allocate to its heart content on that
stack and off we go
right so what I want to do is I'm gonna
make a very simple little thing here
that just says gin room stack and what
I'm gonna do is I'm going to allocate
one of these off of the temp memory I'm
just gonna get myself an initial thing
on the stack actually you know what I
don't even need to do that now I think
about it
I can do this in here
and what I want to do is I want to make
it so that I can just create stuff off
of this stack all I want in fact I could
you know I might just go full pull here
and say let's just make this a thing
something like this and then I'll just
let this thing I can just push and pop
these on so that when I'm walking around
rooms I just can deal with it right I
think that's pretty much all I want so
I'm just gonna go ahead and make one of
those I think the in it for this really
doesn't need to be here but just for
clarity sake I'm making one
you basically just give it the stack
that you're trying to initialize you
know what I don't I don't even care
about that the entire initialization for
this thing is just this right because
the only thing it needs is memory and
everything else is zero so it's pretty
simple that's just how you initialize
one of these and you're done so I'm
happy to leave it that way
again the simpler the better for
everything and clear to zero is always
the initialization I would prefer and
that's pretty close to that so then what
I can do is say all right what I want to
do here is just have my room stack
essentially be like utility functions
that let me walk my rooms easily so you
know I shouldn't deleted that yet
because I want to talk about it
so this Jen first room here that's the
first room that we've got in our set of
rims so what I'm gonna do here is just
say like push room onto my stack and say
I want to you know edit this room like
herb not edit this room but I'm gonna
start looking from this room so we'll
take the stack and push it on
right and then what I want to do is
while we're laying out room rooms here I
could I could have my while loop
effectively have some kind of call that
says you know hey as long as my stack
has things on it I'm gonna keep doing
stuff and so I'll pop a room from the
stack here and that'll give me the room
that we're talking about and I don't
know that I necessarily want to do it
that way I may want it to pop a room
stock entry because there may be
additional information on there so you
know there's a couple different ways we
could do that right that would be
another way to do it right in that way
if we want to put data in here that's
more than just a room we can so I might
leave it that way for now and we'll see
but I don't know hope springs eternal so
maybe we just do that so when we pop
this room off of the stack what I want
to do then is I want to say all right
push connections for this room so or
push connected rooms or something like
that right so what I want to do is say
look every time I pop every time you
look at a room I know that I'm gonna
want to look at all the rooms that are
connected to that room right
and so what I'm doing here is just
saying let's go ahead and do that we're
gonna lay out these rooms and off we go
now when I'm laying out these rooms I
have a fundamental problem which is that
this will loop forever because if rooms
are connected to each other then I'm
just gonna push the room and then I'll
look at the next room and push we push
the room I just left and then I'll go
back to look at that room and we push
through I went to and I'll just keep
pushing each other forever so I need
some if statement here that's when I go
to look at a room that's on the stack I
don't want to do any press I don't want
to lay it out and I don't want to push
on its connections if it's a room I've
already said I'm done with right so I
only want to look at new rooms that I
haven't looked at yet and then I can
connect those rooms up right and so what
I'm gonna do here is I'm gonna say all
right let's go ahead and see when we're
doing this when we're doing this work
here let's go ahead and tag rooms that
we've processed with something that lets
us know that they have been processed
right and so what I'm gonna do is
something that we've done many times
before I'm just gonna have a concept in
here called a generation index and that
generation index is just a tag that lets
me know whether I have visited this room
in a particular pass of something right
and so what I want to do here is say you
know whatever my generation index is
here let's say it's one I want to know
if this room's generation index is equal
to my generation index if it is then I'm
don't need to process it if it isn't
then I do so I will set it as having
process and then I will push this
connections on now normally I would make
this thing push connected rooms I would
make that be a thing that we actually
have on this room stack I'm not actually
gonna do that the reason I'm not gonna
do that is because we need to look at
those connections first and have some
idea about whether or not we need to
grow the size of this room and there's
going to be stuff that we need to sort
of figure out here right so this is a
little bit confusing potential
and the reason it's a little bit
confusing is connections for a room we
sort of need to know where they are and
whether our room can sort of obey them
well or not and other things like this
and again this is where we start to get
into the real complexity of it and it's
gonna be very difficult right because
whenever we layout rooms we know that we
have connections between the rooms but
we don't really know how the room should
be placed in order to make those
connections all line up fundamentally
speaking you know the challenge of
laying out the rooms is specifically
figuring out where the connections go
that's like the whole problem right and
we've also said that one other thing
that we want to do here is make it so
that we might get make rooms larger if
they need more connections right so
rooms that have tons of connections
probably need to be bigger rooms that
don't don't right so that's that's the
fundamental problem that we're looking
at here and so now the reason that I say
that this probably doesn't want to be a
function is because I know I'm gonna
have to loop over the connections here a
bunch of times anyway I don't probably
need to have this be utility function
because I can just do the pushing in one
of those loops okay so this right here
will walk all of our rooms and if we
wanted to we could still do this this
sort of layout here that we're doing but
yeah this will walk all of our rooms and
mark them and then terminate right so
this will like mark all the rooms if we
wanted to like I said we could just kind
of put a you know create some space for
the room in there but again that's not
really something that we can do quite
yet be it would just be another sort of
incorrect layout pass that we'd be doing
so now we need to start to get to the
logic of this where we're gonna sort of
look at the room connected to figure out
where this room should go alright so
we've got this genuine connection and we
know that for every room we
which connections are in it and in fact
we've already kind of done that here you
can see looking at the first connection
of a room or whatever so I don't know do
we loop through connector we don't um
since the first time we're doing this
but it's basically just the same as this
code here right all we want to do here
is say for everything that's connected
to this room we want to do something now
the simplest thing like I said was like
okay we're just gonna push whatever the
room on like other room right and we
probably want utility function of this
because if you look at how this goes you
can see that the general connection
points to a connection there's an A and
a B we don't know which one of those we
are so we point to a connection it's got
a location right and then it's got an A
and a B and that a and a B basically
says oh you know I'm I'm these I'm a
connection of these two rooms which room
were you
who's asking me I'll give you the other
one that's who you're connected to right
so we need a thing that basically says
oh if you're coming from room a then
this connection goes through and B but
if you're asking me from room B then it
goes to room a that's a really simple
function
so from a particular connection we just
want to know let's say okay if
connection a equals from room or maybe
I'll say B that's a otherwise B and for
good measure I am going to assert that
one or the other was true you know I'm
saying so in fact you know maybe I will
do it this way so basically I'm saying
okay
I'll assume the result is a but in the
case where the connection a is the one
I'm talking about
then I will say the result is actually P
but what I do want to do is say that in
the case we're catching a is not the
from room
I want to assert the connection B is and
that's just a way of saying look I don't
want people calling this function on a
room that on a connection and a room
where that room doesn't appear in the
connection that's just a bug right so we
want to be warned about that and that's
why I wrote it this way instead of the
more simple way because we actually want
to do something in that case and I want
to make it clear what was happening
there so we'll assume that we're
connection B if we are then we just
return any and everything's fine but we
want to assert that we were if we're not
if we're actually connection a then we
override it and we don't need to assert
in that case because we just did the
check so we know that we are one of the
two rooms right and off we go so I mean
we could do another assertion here we
could say assert connection B is not
equal to from room and that would only
be the case
if the connection was was fully porked
like it's like a connection from room a
to remain but hey it can never hurt to
having a surgeon in there worst case is
it doesn't fire so anyway and I could
note that here so when we're looping
through these connections we can do this
get other room call here I I know I want
to take a look at the connection so I've
got a gen connection and then the other
room is just get other room on that
connection from the room that I'm in and
then I could push that other room so
this will crawl out like a spider web
all of the rooms connected to the first
room that's in the set right and again
we may want to have multiple starting
rooms for the crawls that could happen
it doesn't really matter we'll talk
about that a little later so once we do
this now what we're faced with is the
fact that we're doing crawl but we still
don't know where to put the rooms right
and what we want to do here is say okay
when we're coming through these
connections all of the connections that
don't currently have a location have to
get placed somewhere on to my room and
we need again this is where the brute
force stuff has to start to come in in
the case of a simple layout that can't
help but succeed then we would just
always place connections down and we'd
always work like if it was just a long
chain of room a connect strand B
connects dream see connects to MT
connects from e f g h i j k then just
placing the connection in a brute force
place every time would just work right
and we'd be fine but we're not gonna
have that we know we're gonna have more
complicated room connection to apologies
there and because of that what we needed
to do is we have to have
way of trying different permutations for
where the connections are so we need to
be able to try put this country on the
left side put it on the right side put
it on the top put it on the bottom right
and if we only wanted to have rooms that
would have four connections to them that
would be the entirety of it and we could
start there right we could totally start
there if we wanted to and I think maybe
we should start there right we should
start with something that just does that
right and then what we could do is move
from there to something more complicated
that allows rooms to grow and have more
connections as necessary and also allows
rooms to grow too to make a connection
work that would not have otherwise to
work right and again those are going to
be really complicated operations to do
so starting with something simpler than
that I think is obviously best but you
know that's that's just how it goes
sometimes so here on the jhen room
connection with the room con stuff we're
reliefing over the rims again so what we
want to kind of do here is take a look
at those connections and figure out
whether or not they've been set yet
I'm gonna do the same thing on the
connections so now we've kind of got
this data about the the connections
don't ask me why this is in the wrong
place paired to this one that's a little
bit better there right should probably
look more like that
so if you've got a volume in a
generation index on each connection and
so every connection we can also know
whether or not someone has tried to
place it put it down somewhere yet or
not right and again we may on to use it
maybe we don't need it maybe we do we'll
see as we start to go through it it
might be that we can just look at
whether or not the other room has been
processed yet or not because that would
tell us I don't know
so looking at this I think maybe we do
want this because you know no I you know
I think I'm I think I don't need to get
I think let's just let's just leave that
out here's my proposal so what we do is
we'll put down the room and then we will
wait to put the connection in place
until we go to place the other room and
when we go to place the other room if
both rooms are placed then we put the
connection somewhere in there a button
right because that's all we really need
to do in this case
so that seems good to me yeah I'm fine
with that uh okay so now what I want to
be able to do is I want to be able to
say when I'm going through these rooms I
want to be able to check to see whether
I can place a room summer or not I want
to be able to do some unioning
operations so things are gonna get a
little bit hairier but that's okay
and I don't mean hairier like Space
Harrier like I don't mean like this kind
of hairier right I'm not doing about
this kind of hairier because that would
be awesome
I'm talking about hairier like like when
something is hairier like that kind of
hairier like something has more hair
like this right so what I want to do is
I want to figure out like when I go to
place this room I want to look to see if
the connection to the next room has been
placed yet so so when I get other room
I want to fundamentally talk about two
different things here
if the generation index for this room
that I'm talking about that's on the
other side of the connection if I've
already placed that room then I'm gonna
go ahead and deal with this connection
and place my room if I have not placed
the room yet then I'm just gonna push it
on for further I'm just gonna push on
that room as a further consideration but
that's it right and in so doing I will
try to work out like so honestly I might
not even do that here I might say that's
gonna happen in another pass so I might
actually do it like this yeah
and now that I've said it I guess it was
it was a little curse there now that
I've said it looks like this can just be
a utility function because I'm going to
want to do it this way anyway
and in fact I don't even really need to
do this because I'm gonna check it when
we actually go through on the stack so
it's not like a big deal whether I push
it or not really it would save a little
work to check it here but that's about
it so I guess I'm I'm wrong about that
[Music]
so I think I will just make that a
utility function so here all I'm going
to do is going to take these room this
this function right here and just make
this a little utility function so that
people who use the room stack can just
do this so from a room it'll go through
it'll figure out what it was going to do
and which rooms are connected to it that
are not already in part of that
Generation X it'll push all those rooms
on and then it's done so I do want to do
that now you may ask and rightfully so
why bother why bother checking the
connection index in in one of these two
places couldn't we only check it in one
the generation index the answer is not
exactly so if we didn't check the one
here then it would never cause a bug
because we'd always be checking that
room before we process it but it is
inefficient because it will lead us to
push many more things like five six more
things on the stack every room every
time you process a room then really need
to be pushed right depending on how many
connections there are so it's just
wasteful and it makes our stack have to
be much larger because again we're gonna
do that and you have to understand the
way that a stack works when I push five
connections on to a stack I'm then going
to process the last one as the next
thing I do that may push five more
things so this stack actually is having
lots of fat pushed on it if we don't
cull by the generation that's early so
we're just wasting a lot of space and a
lot of effort pushing things on the
stack for no reason so it's better to
call it here for performance and modesty
honestly and then here we need to always
check it because even though you would
saying well if you're chucking it here
you don't need to chug it here because
everything that's on the stack obviously
hasn't been processed yet but that's not
true either because remember as we go
through the things on the stack popping
them off we are processing rooms and so
two different rooms that got processed
may have both pushed the same room to
which they are connected onto the stack
and then that room got processed once
and will then come up again and we don't
want to process it twice that'd be a
huge mistake because we put the room in
place now and now we're over placing it
we're putting it moving it again and
possibly breaking the layout we had
before and that all kinds of problems
come with that right so we need them in
both places really to have a reasonable
routine I would say so off we go so if
we know when we're in here that this
room is on our generation
and so what we can sort of do here is
ask ourselves the question for all of
the connections to rooms that have been
placed
what would the shape of this room have
to be in order to contain all of those
connections right I mean that's
fundamentally what we're saying here I
realize that maybe a little meat you
know I'm working this out in my head
visually right and you you may not be at
the same place right now when you're
thinking about it especially because you
don't have to actually type in the code
it's you're allowed to be more lazy than
I because you can just go ah okay seal
type it in I don't have um but what I'm
saying here is well okay I've got two
rooms they both got placed they both
have connections to this other room that
hasn't been placed yet
now that room comes up the question is
what is the minimal shape that will
satisfy these connections and the answer
is just an infinitely thin room that
goes from there to there right that's
the information I want to start with
similarly let's say there was another
room here that said it had a connection
what is the minimal shape of room that
would fit these connections well it's
this right so I want to know what that
shape is before I start guessing what
the shape of this room should be
see I'm done with this right so
fundamentally what my brute-force
algorithm will break down to and I think
this is kind of cool right is the thing
that tries to enumerate all of the
places that the connection could go on
the rooms that are connected to the room
I'm working on so this would be really
simple to say the least if all I had to
think about was what if all I had think
about was specific connections on these
rooms but that's that's not true
I actually know that I can place a
connection anywhere on a room and so the
only limitation on where I place those
connections is if this room will
intersect like other rooms right so it's
actually this I don't know anything
about this other than let's say I have
these three connections a B and C and so
my algorithm has choices it can make it
could create a room that looks like this
to connect these rooms right it could
create a room that looks like that to
connect these rooms right that B here
here and here
instead of here here and here so one
would be the same but but these would be
different right
it could even again still like let's
assume a more creative arrangement of
these rooms right now it has the option
of doing other sorts of weird kinds of
room connections I suppose possibly
however this has to be a little bit
closer I suppose for those right you
know we could create rooms that look
like that
if we wanted to satisfy this or whatever
right so I think what this boils down to
here is in numerating shapes of rooms
that touch other rooms and having a
bunch of trial and error as we try out
different room shapes to make that work
okay because the only parameter in the
system really is the shape of each room
and where those rooms touch you know you
even for a given room shape it can slide
a little bit but that's probably
arguably the least interesting part of
it right so we're really just talking
about how do we want to shape these
rooms and that's almost the only thing
we really need to brute force is the
shapes of the rooms and then once we
know the shapes of the rooms we kind of
just know what's going on right so what
we want to do is basically have a number
of places on a room that we could
consider putting a connection and then
we want to sort of iterate over the
shapes of the rooms that we could then
have now we actually have more we can
play with during a given placement phase
because actually we're not restricted to
just changing the shape of the current
room we can actually change the shape of
any room that we want to as long as it
doesn't violate any of the previous
things that we said we were going to do
so for example it is always free to grow
an existing room into empty space right
I mean we just we can just do that there
is no it will not violate any previously
placed rooms and connections to grow a
room into space that is unoccupied so
that's kind of cool as well again I am
interested in discretizing the
problem I don't want a really continuous
version of it so one thing I might say
is maybe to start with at least we will
talk about rooms only being able to grow
in a very controlled very specific
fashion so for example we could just say
that rooms are always a multiple of some
fundamental room size so for example the
Zelda room I think is 17 by 9 is the
tradition am I wrong about that
just gonna go ahead and look at one of
these things here so you can see like
one of the screens here it's like that
this doesn't actually have one you know
what I guess I need a screenshot
we did this before didn't I write this
down somewhere
so you can sort of see here 1 2 3 4 5 6
7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 looks like 1 2 3
4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 maybe so maybe 11 by
15 something like that right um and you
know we can sort of figure in our world
we will do something similar to this
like there's sort of a fundamental room
size ish block doesn't really matter
what it is but maybe it's something I
don't know I said I said like 15 by 11
so maybe we might say something like
okay let's just say 5 by 5 is like the
minimum block size and so all we're
really gonna do here is we're gonna talk
about growing things in a 5 by 5 fashion
so when you talk about a room you're
talking about a 5 by 5 block and you can
grow the room you know in some
controlled fashion
right so I can add five by five blocks
to my room and I can add them anytime
there's empty space next to the room so
if I want to make a connection and I'm
having trouble doing so I can just add
five by five blocks to my room to add
more space for connections if that helps
me right so let's just say we do
something like that where we have a
fundamental block size and we just only
grow based on that size and you know
that's just that's that's life right so
that is you know a reasonable starting
place for that again we're still gonna
have a really hard job to do in a second
here because the problem that we're
gonna have is how do we figure out how
to backtrack in the case where we can't
figure out a solution so I'm gonna
ignore that part for now and we're just
going to try to work with the part that
we don't where that isn't the case
okay so again we push your connected
rooms and now we're looking at the rooms
and we're trying to figure out which
connections we actually need to maintain
so here is the case for connections
we'll deal with and what we want to do
is sort of look at where those
connections sort of minimally have to be
sort of the space in that we're looking
at right so I'm going to do something
really simple here to get me started and
what that is is I'm going to do a union
and then an intersection I probably
flipped away a little bit to serving
staff to explain this but if these are
the three rooms that I need to connect
I'm first going to Union them together
right like so and then I'm going to clip
them out so I'm going to create this
outer rectangle here and then I'm going
to clip that rectangle so that it does
not actually contain these rooms so I
will then clip it off here here here
there and I'll just be left with this
and you can see why I'm doing that right
because that tells me a location I can
place the room makes sense it gets me a
starting location a reasonable area I
might want to place the room here I'm
saying
trying to think if I need to something
more complicated than that but don't
think I do
at least not the moment
yeah so I'm gonna do that and
furthermore what I'm gonna do is when I
do the initial unioning I'm actually
going to include an apron and the reason
I'm going to include an apron is because
what I want to also kind of get out of
this for free is let's say the only room
that I have at all is one one room
that's in place that I'm connected to
well when I do a union intersection on
that I'm gonna get no area back like
it's not I'm gonna nothing if I instead
include an apron when I do the Union so
it's actually like that then when I clip
the room out I will actually be able to
see that there's room around my
rectangle right and I don't again know
exactly how I want to do this because I
don't know if I yeah it's pretty it's
pretty tricky if I was to do a complete
clip I would end up with a set of
rectangles right like let's say I took
this case I'd end up with a set of
rectangles so here's the Union
and I know that if I produce a complete
clip of it
I would get something like this right so
I just get tons of rectangles out of it
right tons and tons of them way too many
and that's not gonna help me that much
right but that's what happens if I do a
complete clip so what I really want is I
more want just what happens with the the
largest possible rectangle that doesn't
intersect any of those you know what I
mean
so what I'm looking for here is I really
don't want the complete clip technically
what I want to do is I want to make a
rectangle that will include the largest
portion of the clipped region or that's
not really true I want to create a
rectangle that touches still touches all
three of the of the rooms that I'm
talking about but that still forms an
actual coherent rectangle right that's
the thing I'm actually looking for and
that's harder to do the reason that's
hard to do is because it's highly order
dependent and I'm not sure I immediately
see how you jump right to that
conclusion right it made me the case and
and let me just show you what I mean in
case you're having trouble visualizing
that so let's suppose I start like I
said knowing that the area that encloses
all of the rooms I'm trying to connect
is this big rectangle right and here are
the three rooms that are occupying that
space well if I look at say this room
first and I say well okay I gotta make
sure that I don't intersect this room
well there's three different ways I
could make myself not intersect that
room
one is I pick this edge and I clip to
that edge that produces this rectangle
one is I clip to this
and that produces this angle rectangle
and one is I clipped to this edge and
that produces this rectangle only that
one is the one that I want right now
what I'm guessing here is that this is
part of our brute force each one of
these has four sides that I could clip
to if the brute force iterates over
those sides I get four times four times
four possibilities right
that's 64 possible ways I could produce
this rectangle only some of those ways
will connect the rooms in fact it may be
the case that like if with three it may
be the case that only like one or two
possibly can you can see that there's
like let's say we were doing with only
two you can see that there's two ways
you can do it that way and that way or
that way so it's at least three ways you
can do it four ways you can do it so
there's four possible rooms that would
still obey those two connections that
are rectangular right and so you can see
that that gives us that's actually not a
problem now think about that's a good
thing that gives us four tries if you
will to lay this out each one leaving
different space open each one possibly
creating a solution to the problem of
not being able to lay it out because of
self-intersection
with other rooms on the map right so
this is part of our brute force
specifically what we want to do is have
some number right
some trying number that gets plugged in
here so that of the valid options that
we have there we will take the first one
the first time we try laying this out
and then if it doesn't work we take the
next one and we use our try number to
sort of advance us through those
possibilities right this is a really
nasty kind of a thing I remember so
there's a set of algorithms called
metropolis algorithms because for some
reason they're named after the manager
of the group of people who actually did
it
so actually metropolis I think was like
the least involved person in terms of
making the algorithm nevertheless it's
called the metropolis algorithm anyway
we actually try to figure out who
actually invented it
there's any one of these things of PDF
oh yeah right here
there you go
wait no no no that's that's a tutorial
where's the original all right Thank You
caps lock you're killing me you are
killing me here people all right I have
the original paper on my machine I don't
know where to find it I'm sure it's out
there you can go find it the fact that
they called the metropolis Hastings
algorithm on Wikipedia suggests to me
that probably Hastings is the guy who
actually did the work if you find the
actual paper you can see who else's
names on it anyway point being it's
called metropolis Arum but it doesn't
actually involve a guy named metropolis
other than the fact that I think he was
the manager of the group or something
like that anyway so in that algorithm
you're trying to iterate over
possibilities and you use some things
involving probability to determine which
ones you should try first and then you
accept things on a randomized basis it's
a long story but point being it's a very
effective algorithm for very hard
problems that's all you really know
about it the case may be but what I find
hardest about it to implement and what I
suspect we will find hardest implement
as we work on this algorithm is very
specifically the fact that as you deal
with a changing world structure as you
try to brute force ways of laying it out
it's hard to understand which what the
state space is of possible trial and
error in a case where you only have one
world config and you're just pigeonhole
trying say these 64 things well it's
very
easy to understand that stay space it's
64 possibilities out of which say seven
actually work so you know you have a
sort of try number of seven zero one two
three four five and six are the six ways
we have seven ways you can lay this
thing out and you're done it gets much
harder when you start talking about well
when I make some other change now if I
revisit this room it's caz other
possible layouts because things
different things have moved right and so
it becomes much harder to understand how
to generate and manage permutations when
you don't have a stable way of talking
about what those permutations are
because those permutations are dependent
on the arrangement of other things in
the system that are themselves changing
that's one of the reasons why you
eventually usually use randomization to
help get you out of a bind because hey
if I just pick a random one and this is
metropolis algorithm relies heavily on
randomization for this very reason and
other reasons if we can't talk about a
stable distribution well we can still
talk about a randomized distribution so
we just say look we know there's seven
ways this could be laid out at this
particular time I'll randomly pick one
of them and I'll just trust that next
time if I happen in the same bind my
randomizer probably won't pick the same
one so we will try something different
or maybe we'll pick the same one but we
wanted to try the same one this time
because hey we know that sometimes
things move and this becomes different
what that really boils down to for us
he's really just saying look when we go
to bleep for its brute force this and we
try a bunch of stuff we probably don't
want to just accept the first thing we
find we want to accept the nth thing we
find and in the case where we only find
one thing obviously that's the one we
will always accept but in the case where
we find multiple things we want to
randomly probably randomly pick between
them I don't suppose that was a very
good explanation of what I was trying to
say I'll try to say it better a little
bit later when we get to it I think I
could say it better now recall those two
four loops I was talking about right
that's the traditional definition of
brute force where you can enumerate all
possibilities we're already saying we
can't enumerate all possibilities so
what we're doing is we're eliminating
certain possibilities right the problem
we have is that we don't even really
know how to stable e iterate over all
possibilities we know how to make
changes and then iterate over
possibilities within those changes right
but once we make changes to some part of
a layout then the brute force search
that was trying to search all the
possibilities for some other part of the
layout now can find different things so
we can't even remember what things we
tried on this part because they may not
be the same anymore so it's really hard
to do a real brute force test when you
have such a large state space because
you're actually talking about things
that change what possibilities are
available as you go hopefully that helps
clarify it a little bit alright so what
I want to do now is I want to go through
all of my rooms I'm going to Union them
together to produce a room geometry area
that helps me understand what I'm
looking at here right
and so what I want to do is is generate
that Union volume right I want to
generate a thing that sort of unions
this that this this stuff up so I'm
gonna create a Union volume and you've
seen me use this guy many times before
he's coming back he's making a big
comeback all of a sudden which is the
inverted infinity volume it's has such a
great name for such a simple concept
that's something that includes nothing
but it includes nothing in an infinite
way so that as soon as you try to
include something you just get that one
something and you'll see how that works
in a second here you've never saw the
previous episodes where I talked about
it I'm going to start with the nfinity
volume I'm going to go into here where
we talk about these rooms connections
and I'm gonna say every time we find one
that's already been laid out I'm going
to include it and so here we can sort of
say look here's the two rooms I want you
to Union these two for me give me back a
union that we've got and and off we go
I could make this because we know this
is sort of the kind of way we use this I
could you know I'm not gonna bother the
optimizer will take care of it famous
last words I'll do it like that so I'm
gonna Union these two together and get
back a result so then I know that I've
got this I also kind of want to do a
grow operation on this here and not the
kind where the feds come because you're
using UV lights I'm talking about a
thing where I can expand one of these so
I want to like do one of our our add
radiuses or something or like you know
row by radius and what I want to do here
is just say look I want to take this
volume and I want to grow it out by one
in all directions okay so I want to
basically say hey I want an apron of one
pie
everywhere around this thing that I want
to make that expansion so that when I do
the union I'm again even in the case
where there was nothing to union I get a
little thin one layer sort of apron
around the room that I can then process
right okay so now what I want to do is
talk about that clipping procedure right
so once I have a union volume what I
want to do is I want to go through all
of the possible permutations of clipping
this thing and that will give me where I
might be able to place it potentially
right it's hard to know exactly but
we'll see so let's say I go ahead and
start clipping this thing so again like
I said for any given room that volume
will be able to clip it and technically
we're 3d so really that volume will be
able to clip it on any of six sides so
we actually have a choice of one in six
for each of these clippings that we're
doing and so yeah that gives us six
possibilities for how we might layout
the room and each of those six
possibilities again compounds with other
possibilities that we might have and so
we may need to do like I said multiple
tries on this so in order to do this way
we sort of have a cascade of connections
in the rim that we have to process I'm
not sure how I want to structure that
loop exactly I might just write the
brute force version first
and I suppose one thing that's probably
true so
connections are going to have some
information on them that requires them
to be a certain type of connection I
would suspect so
each connection is going to say
something like I can be up or down left
or right forwards or back or you know
north-south-east-west
up or down right and I that connection
will not be allowed to be in certain
configurations a very large number of
our connections for example won't be
allowed to be up down connections up
down connections have a special semantic
meaning usually I'm going deeper into a
dungeon I'm going upstairs to a bedroom
I'm doing whatever so typically speaking
connections that can be up and down will
often either be required to be up and
down or just very rare if they're
included in something that could also be
sideways so I think to a certain extent
we know that it's not really gonna be
six it's usually going to be two or four
for the vast majority of things because
we're just not gonna allow things to be
all six directions almost ever would be
mice thought about that right but let's
suppose that we are going to do this
part and go through all of the
brute-force iterations I don't know
exactly how I want to do this but what I
might say is
I might do a really cheesy version of
this first just real just real garbage I
might do something like this where we
just say yeah okay let's place this room
we'll just recurse down and do the brute
force on each of the connections so you
know we'll say the first connection and
we're gonna place this room I'm gonna do
it recursively here and what we'll say
is like yeah let's just return when
we've actually been able to place it so
in the event that we can place the room
we'll just return true or something you
know
so what this boils down to is we're
gonna take sort of all the junk we had
before this is going to be okay so we're
gonna get a given connection here and so
we sort of have two possibilities one
possibility is that we are trying to
place this room in this volume and there
is no more connection to process there's
no more connections to process at all
right so if there are no more
connections to process then we just can
place the room in the volume meaning one
legal placement for the room would be
the whole volume that we're given and
you know what we're just screwing around
at this point trying to make some basic
thing that's just what we'll do right
now we want to do one thing beyond this
probably because otherwise the rooms may
end up being too tiny up in the simple
case like I said when we have that apron
right we sort of know that when we have
that apron if we only grow up I went you
know we could there's other stuff we
could do here that would make this
happen I'm gonna go ahead and say let's
try it this time if we just made like
the size of a room be the size of the
apron that we add to the room that might
be a cheesy way to do this at first so
I'm just going to do that instead
yeah
so what we want to do here is say look
let's take a look at the the volume for
this rim you know what no I talked about
so I'm just trying to think here when we
do the apron thing
it's a pretty it's not quite as it's not
as nice as I was hoping it would be what
I wanted to do is just end up with just
a shape that is something we can just
use the problem is you don't really know
once you've gotten down to it you don't
really know what part of that volume you
do and don't care about using so for
example let's suppose that I just even
even just one by one by one is not
really good enough because let's say
that you have the top and bottom parts
of the room there that you've expanded
to one you have one you know looking
basically a room above the U and a room
below you
size-wise when you then get down to the
very end you're going to have a room
volume that's actually three rooms high
even if you you know probably and you
don't want to create one that's three
rooms high but you don't know whether
you actually may be needed to be three
rooms high in order to connect the rooms
that you're talking about so the apron
thing doesn't really work so I think we
need to talk about it a little bit
differently I think we need to just do
it this way where we say all right we're
gonna Union the volumes and then we're
going to intersect the volumes and
that's it and then we have to do the
growth at the end to try and put forth a
room that grows out to some reasonable
size as we go or something right so we
we will go ahead and say place the room
using that volume and so then when we
get to the end here this volume very
well almost in all cases needs to be
grown somewhat because it may be zero
with zero height and so on right and and
we need to account for that
right
in the case of rooms that well really in
any case we also don't really know what
amount of room we really need there
either and so there's sort of this other
kind of minimum requirement feature that
we want to pass down that I'm not sure I
fully understand so what what I mean by
that is when we look at a particular
room option and we say here's where the
room will connect to this other room
there's sort of an interval there that
says well it could be anywhere from here
to here and that interval is non-viable
right so to give you a clearer picture
of that what I mean to say is when we're
trying to track this piece of
information and I want to lay out
another rectangle that lines up in a
nice way with whatever this thing is
here that I'm trying to line up then
what I'm saying is when I go to place
the next room I know that I could place
the next room
such that anywhere that still touches
this side can connect to this side so
let's say the first place I can place a
door is here and the last place I can
place a door is here well that means
that anywhere that overlaps this
interval is acceptable so the room could
be this wide but it could be as little
as that right so let's say I'm here and
I want you know maybe there's another
room here I know that I don't have to go
this far I could only go that far so
it's
still would work to place the room here
and I just wouldn't grow it out into
that region so when we are clipping the
room we need to understand minimum
boundaries as well as maximum boundaries
because those things are important as we
go down and I'm just not sure it sounds
like the kind of case that we really
want an interval for so we want to
basically say the maximum is this the
minimum is this so once we clip it if it
goes below the minimum we're out of luck
right meaning if somebody else came
along and said well the furthest down
you can go is here then it's like that's
not a legal configuration because it
will no longer touch this side which
means that the permutation that had it
connecting on this side is no longer
valid well excuse me so that suggests to
me that we yeah we need that sort of
minimum and maximum bounding rectangle
and it seems like that's just okay
what that does sort of suggest to me
however
[Music]
what that actually suggests to me is we
don't really need the Union in phase
however it's simply not necessary so
when we come through here this is just
not necessary when we go to place the
room we can simply talk about the
constraints on that room so we can
simply say look we're gonna start with
two volumes and what we really just need
to do here is go through the connections
and clip the volumes to those
connections right and we're just going
to permute how many of those we actually
want to do each time through so in this
case here we're gonna say alright the
minimum volume the minimum dimensions
for each of these along each of these I
don't know if I may actually want a
struct for this I'm not sure but I'm
gonna think I think that I probably do
so what we want to do is say here's the
minimum X and here's the maximum X
values that we are allowed to have and I
suppose that informs my Gen volume thing
a little bit actually now that I think
about it because
we could just make the Jen volume be
mins and maxes and then this would just
kind of work right and I think we
probably want to do that because then we
can make all of this be nice and the
reason I said is because if you think
about what happens X can't Y count Z
count those sort of things the problems
is when you start to talk about those
it's weird if they become negative which
is what would have to happen in cases
where you're talking about it's like
mins and maxes are a lot clearer to talk
about in those cases I should think so
let me just think this through a little
bit more I'll see how I want to do this
so in the police room context here
assuming that I have a connection what I
want to do is I then want to say for all
of the possible ways this thing can be
connected right
and I can just say there's a direction
we know there's six directions that we
can connect the thing you know and so
for each of those six directions I'm
just going to say you know if the mask
value works and so what that'll be is
like connection direction mask and you
know this sort of thing and I can make
that a utility function so it's clearer
something like that so if it can go in
that direction then we will try
constraining it and continuing no it's
going to be reference this here so
assuming that I can do that in this case
here you can sort of see I just want to
look and see if it's legal to go in that
direction and if it is then I need to do
some work here if not that I don't see
that second um
so assuming I can go in a direction what
I need to do once I know I can go in
that direction is clip the legal
possible places for the room to that
particular direction right and what that
means like I said is twofold
it means first of all the min and the
max of the direction in question
whatever the the dimension in question
is has to be clipped and this is you can
sort of see now why I'm saying I kind of
want my gen vine to be a little
different I think what I want to do here
is I want this to look more like this
because that way we can make this be
something that just happens a little bit
more automated with the mins and maxes
right but but we'll get to that second
so once we know a particular direction
we know that we want to set the mins and
maxes to line up with that particular
rooms thing furthermore I may actually
want to do it like this oh and you know
what else I could do here if we do
something a little bit creative here
right you can see how we can get
arbitrarily fancy
and so that allows us to have the volume
be pretty expressive there and I think
we probably want to look more like that
and less like the count XY thing hard to
say now because this is discrete we also
have to make that decision of does the
max is it inclusive of the max or
exclusive of the max my guess is we want
to be exclusive of the max so a min and
Max is the same value is actually a zero
sized room not a one unit sized room but
again that's something that will shake
out I just when you're starting to talk
about things like clipping clipping
becomes a real pain in the butt if you
usually have all these like ones in
there where you wouldn't normally want
them to be if you don't take some pains
to make sure that you say you're
exclusive of one of your dimensions one
of your direction one of your Maxima
either the the minimum or the maximum
what if your extremum put that way so
that seems pretty good so assuming that
we had a gem phoneme that looking more
like that instead of like this then this
can also be automated to a certain
degree here so that as you come through
the directions we can actually say
something more like oh yeah the number
of German let's actually talk about this
instead as like a dimension and we're
going to talk about three dimensions and
then we're gonna do min max or something
so we may be able to automate this a
little bit better right
who knows
but anyway regardless of how we do that
the process is still the same what I
want to do here is say that the volume
in which the room can now exist again
needs to be clipped further so what I
want to do is say all right once we know
what this is we know for the room that
we're talking about which is to say the
room the students or the room turn out
not the room we're placing but the room
whose connection were we care about we
know that if that room is currently
present that we have to clip to the
right so we want to do here is look and
see we want to do this exact process
that we're doing before where we get the
other room that exists there so I'm
gonna come through here and say 10 room
other room keep this moving get other
room connection so I know I in this room
I want to know what the other room is so
I'm going to get that other room if the
other room generation index equals the
generation index that were on which
actually since we mark ourselves as we
come through here right right here it's
just to say the same generation index
meaning I just want to know that the
other room is the same generation
indexes me that means it's been placed
if it hasn't been placed I don't care
about this connection because it it's
just not a room that we even know where
it is yet so we don't really have to
worry about it in some sense maybe if
we're looking algorithm would think
about whether or not it has extra rooms
it has to place and maybe do something
with them there but we're not gonna get
go down that route yet so if we know
that this other room is a room that we
actually have to deal with then what we
know is it's gonna have to clip up to
this room and we have six ways we can
clip it to sides in each of three
dimensions right now we only have to do
that if this connection was marked as
being legal in any of those directions
so that's a help certainly
but what we want to do is once we get
down here and know that we do want to
clip we need to clip that portion of it
so let's say that we're talking about
the zero dimension which is X and we're
talking about the zero side which is min
right that's what I wrote down here
right this is right I so when we're
talking about the min side when we're
connecting to that side
we know that that means the maximum of
this route of the room we're trying to
place the volume in which it's legal
cannot exceed that minimum right so we
have to do a clip operation here where
we say if the in vol that we're talking
about here and and I guess we should
like I said we want to sort of generate
a new one here if the new volumes
maximum in the dimension we're talking
about exceeds for some reason the
minimum for any reason the minimum of
the dimension of the room or clipping to
right so the thing we're placing it's
got to stop at that minimum so let's
just clip it like so and now we know
that volume is is done right it's been
clipped
now we can short-circuit this process as
well by making sure we don't continue
down a road when we don't have any
volume left we could also make this
simpler by saying look we don't allow
rooms smaller than four by four or
something anyway four by four by one so
we could say more is minimum volume for
a room right
something like that
and so that could just say look if we
end up in a situation where this thing
is just too small then we're just not
going to do it right so here we just say
the result is well the new volume mid
max X minus the new volume in X right
something like that the difference
between these two things has to be
greater than or equal to four or
something another those attractiveness
so we can just say look if it's not at
least one high and 4x4 wide then it's
just not you know a room we are going to
allow right and that's fine so off we go
don't ask me why this for Nexus they are
so now we lift your okay we clip the
room to it and then we also need to make
sure that the room understands that the
opposite thing is also true so this was
the part I wanted to get to to see
whether we need additional information
in here because I wasn't quite being
able to think it through probably
because uh talking coding at the same
time is somewhat difficult but what I
wanted you there is just say okay look
if I have a room and I'm saying that
this is the site I'm going to try a
connection on what I want to do is say
well the legal volume for this here it
had better in it had better know that it
can't go below here or or it can't go
the minimum can't go past here and the
maximum can't go past here further down
the line right and so I think that's
like I said I think that just requires
an interval I think that requires for
each of them having a min and a max for
the entire volume right meaning once I
have to say that the maximum has to be
can't go below this other value I think
I just have to do that there's really no
other way to record it right so this is
fine for that first part which is to say
clip the room to being above here but
that's not sufficient for the rest of
the process right so if we have this gen
volume we need to effectively pass two
of these I think
so there has to be a min vault in a max
wall and the min vol and the Maxwell are
based is saying what are the minimum
values and maximum values of the actual
volume itself which itself is minimum
max I guess but we need essentially
regions for each of them right and so
what we could say instead is what is the
volume of space that the min can occupy
and what is the volume of space that the
maximum can occupy right and we can do
that which is a little it's I know it's
a little confusing but I think we can
just do that and that's all we need to
do so in this case what we would say and
we have to be careful about how we name
these because again we have to actually
think it through what we actually mean
by them but assuming we say that the
minimum volume is where we want the
minimum to go and the maximum volume is
where we want the maximum to go I think
we can just say it that way and that's
fine so meaning the maximum value we end
up using has to go in between min and
Max of the max volume right okay
so then what we need to do is we need to
do this on both of them
so both the min and the max volume must
be clipped nothing can go beyond these
values now right they have to stop so
the maximum value of both the min and
the max cannot go beyond the room in the
one we're talking about
then we must further clip the min and
the max more specifically each of them
very carefully so now instead of
comparing them to the same value we will
actually compare them to different
values so the minimum volume is the
place where the min can go we know that
the min is now no longer allowed to go
past the maximum volume value of this
guy possibly with an apron right
possibly so there might be some you know
so we probably need to leave space for
walls right if I guess what I'm saying
and so we can't in fact you know we can
just do it you know there's a there sort
of like a interior apron I guess you
would say and we could just say look you
can't any connection has to be at least
two in from the outside or something
right like that's just what we're saying
or even just one right so if by chance
the maximum value here has exceeded you
know the interior apron right you know
you've got a problem or something with
that okay so let's just talk about what
this has to mean so for this connection
again we these are not the correct it's
not these it's not dim sisterly but we
know we're going to be looking at things
that look like this
so what you can see here is right I
would just be setting up saying that
says the minimum value cannot go past
the place where I would have been able
to make a connection and the maximum
value cannot underflow the place where I
would have been able to make a
connection and I can if I want to be a
little bit more specific about how this
is going right so when we talk about the
sidedness here again that's actually
something that we have to obey because
these will go the opposite way we will
do the opposite of these two things
based on the side right so I'm really
gonna need to talk about dim brackets
like that the sense of this operation
has to switch depending on which side
we're talking about and I don't know if
I'll be able to quite drive that
entirely based off of the based off of
the index or not but yeah it's a little
bit nasty but that's what I have to do
right and then when I come down here I'm
going to have to do this for the other
dimensions the one that we didn't do
this operation on right so this
operation is done on the actual
dimension this one is effectively done
on the other dimensions right it's what
we're going to do here and so
essentially there's like an other gym
happening here so we don't do it in the
case where we are the dimension that
we're trying to do the connection on and
the reason for that is because that one
actually gets clipped we do do it on all
the rest of them because now we know
that we have to fit that aperture which
is how whatever the sort of facing side
of the room is that we're trying to
connect to we've got to keep our room so
that it can touch it right and
furthermore we probably have more work
to do there we'll think about that a
little bit later but it may be the case
that Z always has to be handled
specially because maybe we can't really
you know if two rooms abut like this we
may not have stairs and stuff that do
whatever that is so we may not be able
to create cracks like that it may be
that if Q things connect on the side
there's Z minimums have to coincide like
that just has to happen so there may be
a lot less flexibility in terms of
placing rooms if there is a room that's
high maybe we never have rooms that are
high and it doesn't matter but if we do
then that's you know something to think
about
I so this part now needs to get worked
out so in the case where we're talking
about the in the case where we're
talking about the minimum sign of
something then we know that this is the
value that we're using but if we're
talking about the maximum side then we
have to do the opposite clip so really
what we're talking about here is two
different ways of doing this check
and so in the case where we're talking
about side zero that's what we want here
in the case where we're talking about
that side one we actually want this and
in this case again it's it's the
opposite sense of the check right so if
we were clipping to the far side Master
and Commander style then we need to sort
of say let's let's clip to the max that
of the men and of course we're clipping
the min so we're moving the min up so
that it's got to be past the max of the
other room that we're clipping depending
on which of the sightedness once we do
there once we do that then we can
continue to place the room and and so in
here again yeah we sort of have the min
and the max are starting out being
allowed to be anywhere they want to so
this is an infinity volume it just
contains everything and then and in fact
I suppose we can simplify that procedure
a little bit and then we can go from
there
so once we have
one of these working we can just say all
right the MINIX
and the min Y and the Minzy all of those
will just be equal to x3 2's 32 min and
all of these are Sri max so the infinity
volume just contains everything you
could go as far as you want in either
direction and then we can do that clip
volume there and I'm not sure exactly
how we want to do that
maybe we just returned a volume I'm not
sure I don't think we're gonna do that
I'm gonna leave this place room for now
we'll probably change it later but I'm
gonna leave it that way for now but so
I'm also gonna just pass pointers here
let's keep going behind my head fine
I'll just go over here okay and so when
I pass down those two sort of room
interval areas that sort of figure out
where I could go I assume all this stuff
you know we've gotta have to debug that
and make sure that it actually works but
then once I'm done with that then we can
know that we've got the completely clip
thing and off we go
what we're gonna be able to do at that
point is just say well once we get down
here we know we finally had a way to
possibly place this room so what we can
now do is say and doing this clip here
this is a little bit hard what we want
to be able to do is say if we were to
create a volume from the min and Max
what would it end up being so we need to
basically say like something in here if
it's of the form
[Music]
get maximum volume for and so when we go
to do the room placement thing what
we're going to do is say look for this
test volume here this is the maximum
volume you can have so far given what
we've got and we'll go from there
trying to think of how
we're gonna play with this a little bit
[Music]
yeah all right anyway hmm when we do get
maximum volume for here we're gonna say
like all right here's the places where
the minimum can be here's places where
the maximum be what's the biggest room
we could do and then we're gonna say all
right if the biggest room we can do is
still too small this is a dead end we're
not gonna be able to place of volume so
just stop
if it is big enough keep going and then
finally we'll get down to the place
where we're like oh hey we've got no
connections left we have room for we
have what we could place three minutes
let's place the room all right so when
we do minimum directions room I realized
too that this is not quite right if this
was zero and this was zero you would end
up with absorbing shows right let's say
that it was on zero and that was on 4
that's 0 1 2 3 that's 4 10 minutes or so
that okay so that's fine so this would
all be correct so now I need to actually
implement this function to get maximum
volume 4 and I think I'm only gonna
really use that in the early out case
but we'll see in a second so if I know
the min has to can go anywhere in the
min and the max can go anywhere in the
max then making the biggest volume is
actually really easy it's really easy
because that means that well I just want
to pick the most minimum minimum and the
most maximum maximum and that will be
the biggest volume right so the min X
should come from the min X the min Y
from the min Y and the Minzy from the
Minzy and the same is true of the max I
just take the maximum oops from the max
volume and there we go and that's the
biggest volume that I could have right
and if that volume the biggest possible
volume that I could possibly have if
that is not big enough to make a room we
know we failed if it is we know we can
place a room there right now the problem
is we
want to go placing a room in the entire
volume why because that volume may be
the whole entire space right let's say
we're talking about the first room well
there's nothing to clip so the first
room will be the whole space the second
room will be half the whole space
because the only place that we can't use
is the place that like one side of the
other room clipped right so we place a
giant room right and we don't want to do
that we want to place rooms that are
only as big as reasonably necessary for
what that room is supposed to do so
we'll probably have some information
coming from the room spec a little later
on that lets us know how room big this
room wants to be in general we'll use
that for now what we want to do is say
look place a room in the maximum volume
if the maximum volume is too big let's
shrink it down right so that's sort of
what we want to do all right but it's
not as easy as it sounds because we know
that the min and the max volumes have to
exist inside an integral so we can't
just change them arbitrarily what we
want to do here is we want to go through
those intervals and say okay we know the
min can be between here and here we know
the max can be between here and here so
as long as we're picking legal values in
there let's figure out what we can
actually use and so like I said it gets
a little bit harder then because what we
want to do is shrink the min and the max
down to a size that's reasonable without
allowing either of them to go past where
they would ordinarily be where they're
sort of boundaries would prevent them
from going and so we don't really know
offhand what the right way to select
that value is but we can sort of start
to figure it out right
we know how should I put this so we know
that we can try some different locations
that we have I'm going to draw up the
cases here these are
so let's suppose that we have min and
Max intervals that say where are min and
Max values can be if we have already
determined that this is a legal way of
placing your room then there is one
thing that we are sure of and that is
that the minimum minimum is less than
the maximum maximum why because if it
wasn't there would be no volume in this
volume at all meaning if I have an
interval that contains the minimum and I
have an interval that contains the
maximum it had better look like this
because even if they're overlapping it
still better look like this because this
part and this part cannot cross if they
do there is no range at all so I know
that I'm fundamentally looking at either
something that looks like this
something that looks like this or
something that looks like this where
they're just coincident right so in the
case where these things are coincident
then it's pretty simple any answer is
okay right
I can pick the center I can pick the
side I can pick this side doesn't matter
any answer is okay if I just want to
make a smaller thing inside that
interval I'm done right but in these
other cases it's a little bit harder why
is it a little bit harder well because
when I go to pick the length of this
thing if the length of this thing you
know looks like that that's how big I
want it to be well that is not a legal
place to put it but that is right so we
have to pay more attention to where we
place the thing that we're trying to
place in order to make sure that when we
restrict its length right we don't
restrict its length in a way that makes
it impossible for it to actually still
satisfy its constraints okay so let's
think about how that's gonna happen
what's gonna happen here is we're going
to be passing in essentially a max size
okay
and that max size is going to be the
size of the thing that
trying to to put in here now we can
detect these cases by looking to see
whether or not there are gaps in between
these things right and what we can do is
we can have different strategies for how
we want to align them so for example one
way we could do this that would be
pretty cheesy but would work and maybe
isn't exactly how we would want to do it
but I don't know maybe it is
who's to say is we could just use a like
min preference so what we do is we'd say
all right place it here to start with
check to see whether the maximum still
falls in the region if it doesn't then
just move it as far as would be
necessary to make it do so right done
because I know if I could place this
thing at all then that would have to be
the case right if I can't do that then I
really can't place this thing and so I'm
kind of done right at that point I just
have to say that the room placement
didn't work right so what I can do here
is say look I'm not gonna use this part
here this part isn't necessary right
instead what I'm gonna do is I'm going
to go through each dimension in my room
and see whether or not I can actually
place it fairly or not right so I'm
gonna say let's start with a volume this
is the final volume for the room that
I'm going to be working with maybe I do
call get max volume maybe I don't I
think in this case I don't need to so
I'm gonna start with the final volume
and I'm gonna go over each dimension in
series because the code for each
dimension is the same right I don't need
to do anything differently at least not
at the moment like I said it may be in
the future that we actually need to
treat the Z dimension especially in
which case we got to change the way
we're doing it and off we go
but so let me get down here to the final
volume we need to set the min
for a particular dimension and the max
for a particular dimension and so what I
want to do is I want to say alright
let's set the min for a particular
dimension and maybe you know what I'll
just do these with some variables that
are easier first so we've got our min
volume our max volume that again is the
largest it could possibly be right the
room cannot be any bigger than that and
so then what I want to do is I want to
see how big is that volume is it too big
is within the range of legal volumes for
the room etc right so then I can say all
right let's say the max minus the
minimum is that greater than the max dim
that I want and I'm just gonna say here
look I don't want rooms that are bigger
than one unit high at the moment I don't
want rooms are bigger than let's say I
don't know thirty in either direction
maybe 60 and 30 cuz we tend to be wider
this way probably not quite that but you
know something like that
so as we could do like hey since it's
probably a sixteen by nine display maybe
I want things that aren't any more than
three of that in any direction I don't
know but something like this so then I
see look what's this what's the status
here right well okay if I can't make
that work then I'm gonna say all right
let's set the minimum equal to the min
wall well they are dias let's set the
maximum equal to the min plus the max
allowed Tim so now I know that I'm I'm
compliant because I'm the largest the
rim could be and so I'm gonna shrink it
down from there right
I could also check here to make sure
that I'm bigger than the minimum but
we'll do that in a little
in a second so now I set it to the max
allowed dim and then I got a check all
right am I still within the legal area
so then I say like okay is the max
greater than or equal to the maximum of
all use minimum location that's allowed
to be and is the maximum less than the
maximum volumes maximum it's allowed to
be and if it's both of those things
right then I'm okay so this is like you
know a legal location to be so I
probably should do is this I'm really
looking for the chain condition so I
want to say okay if the max is less than
the minimum it could be or the max is
greater than the max could be you know
it can't really be that because we're
already saying that we're we were bigger
than that so it's really just this this
is the only one we can really be so
assuming that that ends up being the
problem where so the max has now dropped
below what it can be what we can do
instead is say all right the max equals
maxval max dim let's reset it I'm sorry
at the minimum let's make it that
minimum and then we'll just set the
minimum equal to be the max minus the
max allowed in then we'll say all right
if the minimum is now greater than or
equal to whatever the we set it it's
range could be this is illegal
because that's just result so the result
tells us whether the room is valid we'll
assume it's valid and we go through all
of these tests we may find that actually
we can't really do it if that's the case
all bets are off
once we figure out what we've got here
when we get down to the bottom I'm gonna
set the final volume min and Max here
like so once we actually know if we did
get a valid room out of it we can
actually set the room like so and then
we're actually done and so at that point
I've just sketched out the routine that
does that work of trying out all those
possible different things and again this
is just the start it's pretty
complicated obviously and we're gonna
have to debug it because there's
probably bugs in here given all the
ridiculousness I just did but that's the
basic idea of brute forcing all the
different attempts at creating like sort
of connections for the four connected
regions for those rooms one part of the
strategy and again we're not done yet
because this is only trying to find a
possibility given what we're going
through when it can't find one at all
for a room we have no backup right so
basically you know in here
this will fire because we will create a
topology and the order in which it
happens to lay them out won't work and
then it will fail right and so what
we're gonna have to build as we go is
now the thing that happens when a room
placement fails
figures out a strategy for backing up
and trying other things right what I'm
gonna do right now because we're at way
out of time I took way too much time
there apologize for that is I want to go
ahead and do an if here where I just if
deaf that out and go back to the
original really quick because now that I
know I definitely want a parametric way
of talking about room volumes I don't
want this anymore
so what I want to do is I want to go
through the code here and get myself
back to sorry about that get myself back
I call the cursors in my internal code
base that's why I accidentally typed
cursor there so in what I want to do is
get myself back to the same working code
I had before because I want that test
code to be known good I want to go ahead
and make it so that I can use the new
vert the new format for the room volume
right
and it looks like we don't have mins and
maxes for these yeah so we have s 32 max
we don't have s 32 min but we know what
it is right right oh no that's that's
not true it is it's actually that right
it's gonna be the maximum value I mean
it's it's the max plus one right so it
would roll it so so this is you've got
all the way up to the point where you
would have rolled the value right and so
then the minimum is that roll over so
I'm pretty sure that's it's correct I
hope that it interprets that value
correctly and doesn't sign extend it but
I don't know if it will or not so we'll
have to double check that that actually
produces a very large negative number
the way I wanted it to and and not the
other way around but that's sort of the
definition all right um I keep going
here okay so yet here we just have min X
min Y min Z and here we're gonna have
max X and to do that really we just have
to do title X plus ty y plus write tile
Z plus 1
so that's you know really very very
simple and we can make fancier versions
of this as we go
all right
and so Title X just now actually equals
the max X right and then is in volume
now just needs to know its greater than
the min and less than the max and it
doesn't need to do any plussing anymore
and I'm not sure that you care too much
about this stuff but I'm gonna make it
happen anyway just so we can run it
again
and so now what I want to do is before I
end for the day is I just want to make
sure that we can still use that version
and produce actual the same sort of
stuff we were producing before that's
all I was trying to do there and so just
making sure that still works looks like
it does so I think we're good there
hopefully and now we'll go to brief Q&amp;A
mmm-hmm long boolean thinks he caught a
type though and probably did because I
typed in that stuff pretty fast he
thought it was a round line when he
mm you're probably not there right
you're probably talking about like here
or something oh I know what you're
talking about the world yeah we're in
the wrong code that's what we're in the
wrong file there we go
let's see so yeah this part I mean like
I said this part we're gonna have to go
over again but I might as well do it now
if you want to look at it there weren't
any other questions that when I just
looked there
so the minimum locations maximum value
that and that that looks right
[Music]
I mean you might be right
I'm just not thinking through but that
looks like what I had intended to write
is this the code you're talking about
did I just did I miss one or something
it looks right to me
assuming I'm thinking it through
properly which you know with this kind
of code it's very it's very like obvious
geometrically what's going on but it's
like one of those cases where typing
into code doesn't work at all like code
does not represent these problems well
at all because they're visual and
geometric and so it could be that I was
thinking it wrong but what I was trying
to do it looks like I mean that looks
like what I was trying to do to me but
when we actually go to debug it we'll
find out right you might also been
thinking about this code let's look at
this code if the max is greater than the
max that it has to be truncated
this needs the minimum there as well
[Music]
so this really I think this should
happen for the max and the minimum so
this this is actually wrong I mean it's
not wrong it's incomplete which makes it
wrong am I am I right about that
so both volumes have to be clipped and
they have to be clipped to both the min
and the max right
I'm pretty sure
yeah
you
so this code yeah we need to fix a
little bit so this should be if the max
is greater than equal to the max it
needs to be pulled back
[Music]
I think only if it exceeds right and
then if the max in the other case is
less than or equal to the men then it
needs to be pulled in right and then the
same thing goes for the mins if the min
is going to exceed that maximum it's got
to do that right and if then if the min
is going to drop below the minimum then
it's going to have to come up to the
minimum
so I think that's but we'll debug that
tomorrow I mean we'll step through that
with a fine-toothed comb tomorrow big
muff of one
why didn't you place important rooms
randomly then generate rooms to join
them this seems more efficient than
generating all the rooms up front before
placing them we can do that right but at
first I don't think we really want to
because that's suggesting that the most
important thing is making the layout
algorithm easy not the most important
thing is having the gameplay determined
by a room placement a room series that
is good for gameplay right so I guess
the Pat answer that question is why
isn't every room important why are you
making the player walkthrough
unimportant rooms right so if we have to
generate connective tissue we will but I
would like to avoid generating
connective tissue unless it's necessary
so the best possible layout for a set of
rooms is to only put the rooms in there
that the player actually needs to be in
right and for every room you have to
generate that the player didn't really
need to be in but we're just doing it to
make the layout work that's actually bad
so in my mind I would rather have a
layout algorithm that gets as close as
possible to only using the rooms that
the gameplay generation actually thought
should be there right at least to me
that's fairly self-explanatory you know
if that makes sense
looks like we are good on questions yeah
all right so I think we're good on
questions so I can wrap it up all right
thanks everyone for joining me for the
upside of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you want to follow along the series at
home you can always peer out of the game
on handmade hero Oregon of course it
comes with the source code so you could
do your own experimentation on it and so
on
maybe you over tonight before I do it
tomorrow we'll want to run in debug the
first steps of the room layout solver I
certainly would be good practice and you
know that all the code is kind of
sketched out there and maybe if you're
feeling really frisky you could go ahead
and start putting in a thing that does
retries when it cannot place a room so
it knows it's reached a dead end
some way of trying a different room
placement right we could do could do so
yeah think about it give it a try
until tomorrow I'll be back here same
time same place until then have fun
programming on whatever you choose
program on and I'll see everyone on the
Internet take it easy everybody