all righty hello everyone welcome to
handmade Hero show Rico complete-game
live on stream we did yesterday we
changed our lighting to now be able to
iterate over sort of a hierarchy during
its ray casting and we now have to build
some kind of a hierarchy because what we
did is we made the like simplest
possible hierarchy which is just one
node that contains all the other nodes
so now we want to do is make something
that will create an actual hierarchy of
nodes where the Harkey will you know
hopefully prune the the list a little
bit and then from there we have to start
working on how we're gonna actually
efficiently traverse it and all those
other sorts of ancillary concerns that
we're gonna have once we get to that
point so let me first just bring you up
to speed on where we are if we go
through here and take a look you can see
that we've got sort of our this is sort
of flat face lighting that we're working
on here we are we're actually doing
interpolation at the moment and you can
even see it sort of occurring like in
here you can see those color washes
occurring as the lighting kind of falls
off as we go down towards the bottom
what we haven't done yet is actually
made any world generation code that
knows how to put the interpolation
points in so we actually even have a
system where we'll be able to get rid of
this banding entirely and make that wall
appear flat if we want to by just
placing the points properly and putting
in a post past a post filter on the
light so we've actually we're in a
really good place to make some really
good lighting in a bit here and I'm
looking forward to that
but at the moment our primary concern is
speeding this number up why because even
though this appears to be running at a
reasonable frame rate right now it's
still not it's not 60 frames a second
it's more like 30 at best case which is
not good enough for what we want to do
and second the real problem is this is a
toy scenario normally there'll be a
bigger it's going to be a wider you know
more stuff here and more depth
potentially to it like two layers down
and so on and this number will fall off
a cliff at that point as the eight
because remember it's N squared so
adding every additional element makes
our performance C
sniffing not just a linear amount worse
so our real goal here is to really
linearize that number get this down to
60 frames a second and have it so that
we can have our full world size running
through the lighting without hitting
that N squared part of the curve that
really tanks the performance that's
really all we need to do here once we're
done with that we're actually in
position to just have the world
generator output some really good
lighting stuff I think and we'll start
playing with that to try and get some
some nice lighting effects in there
because we already sort of have and I'm
really happy with how this is turning
out actually we already sort of have
indications that's that's gonna be good
I mean you can kind of see some pretty
interesting lighting effects happen like
you get sort of these blue tinges on
things when you get the blue bounce
happening you get nice shadowing happily
happening here so you know as you come
around corners it illuminates what you
can see and so on so there's just a lot
of stuff I think we're gonna be able to
do and furthermore all of this lighting
is like fully it's not based on you know
just light sources anything can be lit
up here you know we can have each
individual tile can be lit and
illuminating light and so on so I think
that's gonna be a lot of fun to play
with and I think we'll have get we'll
get a lot of visual quality out of the
game that that'll be worth it so I'm
pretty happy about how this is coming
out but again really it's all for
nothing if we don't if you can't
linearize that and squared lighting
because we're just not going to be able
to get it fast enough if we don't doing
and the problem there again is no matter
how optimal we make our lighting
calculations if they're n squared
they're just going to be too slow right
at the numb at the end that we're using
it just by itself the N squared miss
approaches the speed of the processor in
a bad way so it's just it's not about B
we can't say oh well N squared is okay
because our end will always be small
enough that we can optimize the core
routines to the point where we can still
do it it's not that way the lighting
numbers will get too high and it's just
nothing there will be nothing we can do
so off we go and what if you remember
correctly what we did is we already
modified everything to take this to take
higher keys into account but what we
don't do right now is actually ever
produce more than one box so here is our
build spatial partition for a lighting
function in which you can see is all it
does is called a split box function that
does nothing right so what we want to do
is we want to have this split box
function do something intelligent and
then we want this add overlapping boxes
call to go ahead and produce the the
correct split of stuff into those boxes
okay so that's what we want to do there
so what I'm gonna do first is I'm going
to say well okay what we want to do is
when we when we split a box let's just
say that when we split it we produce a
split that's even that that's at a
particular let's just say that all we're
gonna do first is let's split our boxes
in a prescribed fashion so for example
when we call split box here maybe we
just always split along the x-axis then
the y-axis then the z-axis or something
like this so we'll literally just do
something super stupid that doesn't
actually try to find a good place to
split it just splits without regard for
how good this would is in a predictable
way as a way to start things off so if
we take a look at split box here maybe
what we do is when we do builds a
spatial partition for a lighting let me
call split box we just pass down
something that's like dimension index
right and so what we do here is we say
okay you know we've got three different
dimensions that we're going to want to
do you know this is the x axis this is
the y axis this is the z axis something
like this
and I probably don't actually need the
switch statement I'm writing it out
longhand first but we'll probably able
to actually do this with indices in a
second here when we look at what the
code looks like so probably not actually
that bad but what we need to do here is
say well we've got a P for box a that we
need to figure out a P for Box B a
radius for box a in a radius for box B
that's what we actually need to produce
here and so then we can go ahead and add
these I'm gonna make a function that
actually adds a box oops
we're I'm gonna try to anyway something
like this and when we add a box to the
lighting solution it's just gonna push a
new one on in exactly the way that was
doing this before so it's gonna add this
is the result here and so what I can do
is I can assert in here that we haven't
overflowed our box count and I guess we
actually have an array here that we can
use this is a box table so what we can
do here is we can say all right we can
go ahead and remap this box when we
remap the box what we could do is we can
add an address for this box into the box
table so solution box table results
equals result so it just Maps itself
directly in there and and off we go
right so let's see here so yeah we have
there's a couple kind of messed up
things here which is that we have sort
of a dual mapping of these things we
don't really need the this part here we
don't really need to take up space in
the main box area so it's a little bit
iffy let me just
to show you what I mean the way we've
got this is it's a little bit it's a
little bit tough so I don't know where's
our box references here so let me just
I'm gonna put this up at the top here
all right so there's two separate things
there's box storage and there's box
referencing because we have two sorts of
arrays that we're working with here i1
stores the actual box data and the other
stores references of the Box data and
the reason we did that because remember
from last dream it's because we want to
store continuous ranges of references to
arbitrary boxes as we sort these things
out and this makes things a little bit
confusing so it might be nice to
actually have a way to talk about them
separately in a nice clean way and so
let's just go ahead and actually try to
figure out if we can do this in a
reasonable way you can see we've got
this this one here we probably want to
do something like this but we do oops
so what we want to do here is say okay
there's such a thing as adding a box
reference and that does not in increase
our box count at all it just increases
our box reference count right so there's
a box table count which is a separate
thing and then there's a box table and
those are not the same things right
they're different things and so in order
to do something like that we want to say
is let's say that our box or maybe we
call this a box ref count so we say that
our box ref count needs to be less than
the box table size the result is going
to be the Box ref count incremented and
then we don't actually return any kind
of a box itself we're just gonna in
return that reference and what we do
there is we say all right whatever the
box is so this is a box storage index
whatever the box index in the actual
storage array you were trying to store
we're gonna store that here for the
result and we're gonna return you back
where we stored it right so that add box
reference there is what we're looking
for so then we have add box storage add
box storage actually gives you a new
actual box and that's gonna increase the
box count itself it's not gonna it's not
going to do anything with the reference
to that box it's just saying I'm
producing new box storage for you and
here is the here is the index for that
box storage right so what we want to do
here is say okay we've got the the box
count incremented we've got the the new
box that we're going to give you and you
know actually I guess we don't even need
to get it all we're doing is reserving a
bit of that for you so now what we can
do is we can be a little bit cleaner
about this so for example when we go to
build these things before we were kind
of doing this nonsense here with the
like child count truncation blah blah
and all that crap we don't really want
to do that yet I don't think but we want
to do instead is we want to say all
right let's go ahead and figure out what
the
the child range is here and let's say
we've got a you know first child index
child count so we've got a range of
things that we're going to loop over
here and we want to go ahead and put
those things Jimmy we want to go ahead
and sort those things into sub arrays
right so trying to think of how we want
to do this here because this is pretty
complicated actually the question is how
we store these things while we're
working with them I'm tempted to kind of
do this as a sort of a merge sort thing
where we just swap indices around where
we just have a buffer in place with all
of the things and as we go down we as we
go down we keep partitions of stuff and
on the way up we merge them back
together I'm kind of thinking that's a
good way to do this
yeah I mean let's think about that for a
second right so if we were only doing
this along one axis so let's say we only
did it along like the x-axis it would be
just a straight merge sort to sort
everybody along the x-axis and we could
partition them as we merged we could
just bucket them into the number of
buckets that we wanted from left to
right or any other way we wanted once
you have them in that order you know you
could do a second merge sort to do them
in Y and a third merge sort to do them
in Z it doesn't seem like a great way to
do it but you could
mmm I'm gonna push forward I'm really
not sure exactly how I want to write
this so I'm gonna let kind of push
forward a little bit on it and just see
what's a reasonable way here so we'll
see and we'll see how it goes so what I
want to do here is I want to be able to
first of all let's let's use this call a
little bit more wisely here we'll use
these these two that we've got right so
we've these are our three calls that we
now have for working with boxes in fact
you know what I might do is put them up
here so they're easier to read so that's
how we get a box that's how we add a
reference to a box that's how we store
an actual box right so that's relatively
straightforward and yeah hopefully
everything's fine with that we could
also just have a thing that allocates a
block of box storage
I'm not Vox referencing yeah but I don't
know exactly how we want to do that yet
so we'll take a look at that a little
bit later uh so anyway if I go down
through here and I go to my stuff box
call so when we do build Fitch parts for
lighting before we branch into it what I
want to do is say let's add box storage
for the route box index like so and
assuming that we initialize this on
entrance where we've got our box rough
count equal to zero then zero becomes
our route box index which seems like a
good idea anyway
I'm good even get rid of this and just
know that zero is and we don't do any of
this stuff order to get this box back
what we can do is say all right we want
to get the Box table we want to get the
box
although actually no sorry this is box
storage we need to add box reference to
go so we're adding storage and adding
reference to that storage right then we
can get the box back and now we've got
it so now we have a rep we can reference
it and we have it which is what we want
we can then set it up and I guess what
we want to do here is say well alright
we've got the this set of boxes that's
in the box storage at the moment and we
want to be able to sort all of those
boxes we could also make it so that if
we wanted to our root box could just not
have an index so the other thing I could
have done here and I maybe we want to do
this I'm not sure is we could say that
instead of a root box index there's just
a lighting box here like that that isn't
included that we just start on and I
don't know if we want to do that or not
that depends on whether we ever need to
reference this box which we probably
don't so we could actually get away with
something like that and maybe that's a
smarter thing because then that way box
storage starts out without having any
non sorted boxes in it I don't know so
I'm not gonna do it yet but it's just
something to keep in mind yeah so anyway
thinking this through so then what I
need to do is the tricky part about this
is we then need to start running over
the boxes and partitioning them into
split pieces that then themselves get
further split and in order to do that it
seems like I need to create a temporary
array full of references that then gets
sorted on the way down which maybe
that's the most efficient way to do it
I don't know so we'll find out before we
add this box what I'd like to do is snap
a copy of how many of these we have can
change that to you 16 since these are
all you 16s here so what I'm going to do
here is say first you know actual box
equals 0
actual box count equal solution box camp
and so this is our range of actual boxes
right not including the fake boxes we're
going to add for our you know
hierarchical for our hierarchy so when
we come through here I can then say
alright this boxes child count is the
actual box count and its first child
index is the first actual box and we are
setting the radius to a faux thing that
we know and closes everything but if we
wanted to we could sweep if we were
going to waste time about it
we could sweep over the boxes here and
look for the actual bounds maybe that's
a good idea to do I don't know
so let's actually maybe let's actually
create the bounds because who cares
we're just playing around at the moment
so if we were going to do that then what
we need to do is a very simple process
of bounds checking what we need to do is
say that the box position will just be
the min P plus the max P times 0.5 so
just the middle of that region and the
the radius of the box is just going to
be sort of that standard take the half
of the diameter of the of the total min
max P right so then if we want to find
that loops if we want to find the bounds
of that we just say v3 and then P and
you know what I think we actually have
the our rectangle code might actually
have all this stuff in it already
because I feel like we did this we have
in for our inverted infinity rectangles
here but they're only for sorting and 2d
it looks like we never did the 3d
version of it
yeah so we never did the 3d version of
these it looks like which I'm not sure
why I would have thought that we would
have but it looks like we never had a
need for it so we have like a rectangle
3 does it even have a union function
yeah we didn't for some reason we didn't
even have a union function for a
rectangle three and I don't know why
that is that's unfortunate but Hawkins
dad one yeah I mean you can see here we
have like a very few we have very few of
these so that's unfortunate but I'll go
ahead and add it anyway so really you
know this is just a case of having one
more thing to iterate over so you can
see here we've got you know X Y Z's
and all it's doing is just taking and
making sure that you always take
whichever the farthest is in any
direction so the lowest X highest X
lowest Y highest Y lowest Z highest Z
and that produces a rectangle that
encloses the two rectangles that you've
added and so all I want to do here is if
I go through
the first actual box in the actual box
count here and I just create one of
these rectangle threes we'll do this in
a second
so Center half dim is exactly the the is
exactly the kind of rectangle that we're
talking about here where we have a a P
and make this root box
okay there we go and so when we go ahead
and create this all we have to do is is
use the bounce that I can do get center
on this bounding box and then I can get
radius on this bounding box and so this
will just loop over it do the Union here
of whatever the box we look up is and I
think that gives us what we want
so I all we need is this in front of the
inverted infinity rectangle the magic
inverted infinity rectangle and that's
just one that is has like literally
infinite opposite directions so it's
like the encloses nothing so anything
that you put into it it'll immediately
snap to that when you do a union and
then it will keep growing from there so
we want one of these again for rectangle
three which we can do really trivially
it just involves adding one more of
these to the mix
all right so I think that's all we need
oh it looks like it looks like these
actually use actual vectors here which
makes sense not sure why the other one
doesn't
there we go
and okay so we may have called this get
half dim not sure or maybe there is no
one of these let me so let me add that
as well because I'd like there to be one
of those in rectangle three as well so
we've got get get where's my rectangle
three code
yes so for whatever reason we never had
to get radius we only had getting the
dimension so let's go ahead and do that
so there it is does not take one
argument I agree with that do we not
have safe chunky ellipse to use what do
we are there we go all right so back to
business now so once we know what the
bounds are for this thing then what we
probably and we want to add in the
references here as well so for each box
I think we want to do a ads box
reference like so and so we go through
here adding the references in we go
ahead and take the union of this box
with our global box so that now we know
we produce the root box's size as well
and then we call split box on that box
right and we're gonna go ahead and do
the whole thing so we do root box first
child index root Buckshot camp and you
know what maybe we don't even do that
maybe this just doesn't have anything in
it yet
you know or maybe it just doesn't yeah
maybe that just doesn't have anything in
it yet and we just passed these in first
actual box actual box count so we come
in here and say all right do those two
we add these box references and we want
to assert here as well that the solution
box ref count equals zero and then at
the end it equals the actual box count
because again we just want the first
block of these two to line up and in
order to do that also I guess the root
box here has to be added after we do
that because the root box is gonna be
after those initial guys are done so
that's right here yeah mm-hmm and maybe
we just do it like this so we say all
right coming in here we want there to
have been no box references added
because there has been knows her our key
setup yet and we want that to be true we
then say okay let's go ahead and snap a
copy of how many boxes there are at the
outset those are our initial or actual
light boxes that that are not hierarchy
you know sorting nodes or anything like
that we go through them all and we say
for each one of them let's add a
reference to that box that just makes
them be zero to whatever and we Union in
their size so we now we know how big
this box is we then say let's add our
root box because now we know what it is
and then let's split this root box in
half so that we can split it into two at
least two pieces so it can be broken up
in that way so again we don't know how
many pieces we wanna break them to we
could also break them we could also do
more of an octree where we break it into
eight chunks right if we wanted to so
it's really hard to say how we want to
do that we could do it either way and I
don't know so we're going to find out so
we do split box here here's our split
box call and what we could do now is say
alright this is going to give us the box
that we're trying to create because
we've got one for it and it's going to
give us the range to go through of four
boxes oh it's a solution boot box just a
new box yeah and then it we were sort of
saying we'll pass the dimension index
which in this case will just be zero so
start with the x axis it will be fine I
guess
okay so then what we want to do is we
want to be able to split things into two
halves based on whether which side of
the thing maybe their Center lies on
let's say so what we're gonna do here is
we're gonna do that loop over the sub
boxes and so it's gonna be very similar
to this but it's not going to be quite
exactly this right that's gonna be just
slightly different now and then we're
gonna go from there
so what I want to do here is I want to
loop over this is the first rough index
and this is the ref count basically so
we're gonna loop over first ref index
and we're gonna go to this is our box
reference we're gonna go from the first
ref index to the first ref index plus
the ref count like so and we're gonna
classify each of these by where they are
at the moment now there's different ways
that we could try to do this one of them
takes more storage and then we actually
need to use so we can talk about ways
that we could avoid doing that and let's
just let's just go ahead and look at how
this is about how this is gonna unfold
and what we might have to do here just
so everyone's on the same page
I'm so spatial partition in place so
what we want to do here is say all right
let's say we've got a region like this
box and there's a bunch of stuff in it
and what we want to do fundamentally is
split it into two halves so we want the
things on one side in one half and the
other side and the other half and thing
half is wrong here because it may
actually be lopsided who knows we're not
even guaranteeing half miss here or
anything so what we want to do is we
want to go ahead and say what is the way
that we will track where people are in
this so that the next time we call it
and we say split this one into these two
halves we know which elements were
splitting right so we know how to track
on the way down well what we've got at
the outset is we've just got an array
that has a reference to each of these
like number zero one two three four all
the way to the last one and what we're
gonna do is we're going to loop through
these indices and say okay box zero
which side is it on now the problem that
we'll have is you know if they if we see
that it's on the the in like the inside
the one that we're gonna keep as the
first set of indices let's say then we
would be fine but if it was on the
outside we don't have a place to put it
right because we don't know how many in
indices there are so if this was not
supposed to be here how would we know
what to do with it right
we wouldn't so that creates kind of an
interesting dilemma for us so one way we
could do it is say well if it's supposed
to be in we just skip it because it's in
the right place so far right and then we
go to the next one and we say okay is
this in the right place no it's not then
we remember that we could put something
here and we continue on right
then when we find something that is
supposed to be in we move it down right
to the next one this is not a
particularly efficient process and it's
good it's kind of ugly and it's exactly
like the old you know should you merge
sort in place or not and the answer is
you can do it it just becomes really
onerous so what we probably want to do
again is have some kind of temporary
buffer that we just use that we can ping
pong between right where we just write
our indices into it and then we only do
our address on the very end right that
seems like a saner way to do it to me
rather than having to use as temporary
buffers because it'd be pretty easy for
us to just have two large scratch
buffers that are just sitting around not
doing anything
that's not really very costly to us it's
pretty simple for us to do so you know
for example if we wanted two of these
here like something like this where we
could pass those down that might be a
more interesting way to do it right and
then only on when we're actually 100%
positive that we are done with our
splitting then we will actually add the
things add the the boxes to the list
right so that seems a little more
compelling to me that that seems good to
me so let's just assume that we're gonna
do that so let's go ahead and slightly
modify this routine instead of calling
add box reference we're just going to
use and in fact that actually makes one
nicer thing which is that we don't have
to do any assertions on the box ref
count now we just don't care because
whatever even if there were existing box
references in there this will still work
so what I want to do here is say okay
we're gonna start by saying that scratch
a is the that scratch a is the the table
we're gonna start with so we say that
scratch a box index equals box
index and this first actual box thing is
not really that necessary anymore it's
just this right so that should be fine
so we go through here and say we go from
zero to the box counts we add all of
these in then when we actually start to
go do stuff we don't care anymore
because we're never going to look at
that again and when we come through here
we just say like okay here's scratch a
and scratch B and we know the actual box
count is the number we're doing for
scratch scratch a so when we get once we
call in there into slip box then so this
is slightly different what it's actually
doing is it's saying okay we've got a
source and a desk
Coop's hello capslock an account and
that's all we need so now we come
through here we say all right we don't
need to use box rests anymore so that's
kind of nice so we can just use box
index or I guess it's sort of scratch
index or a source index that's why I
guess what it would be called so going
through our sources we knew that we
start at zero now and we know that we
have a source count that we've been
passed the boxes as they come out are
just references to the boxes based on
this source value so the source is going
to give us the box to load we can load
that box in and we can process it as
necessary so the way that we're going to
do this is we're going to write into
this the the scratch buffers and and
pass those down in in some kind of nice
way right that's that's our goal here
okay so let's figure out a good way to
do those two partitions shouldn't be too
difficult to figure out how to do that
nicely so let's do that
and
we probably want to do a thing where
we've got two different rectangles here
so we've got a rectangle three for a and
B and then what we're gonna do is we're
gonna do a classifier here to figure out
whether we're in a or B and we'll talk
about what that's going to be in a
second and we're just gonna say alright
bounds a and bounds B are both going to
be tracked separately and they're going
whichever one of them is supposed to get
it we'll get the box now if we want to
be if we were gonna be super cheeky here
we could actually put the ternary
operator on this but we've gonna have
other things we want to do in the if
statement so I'm gonna leave it as an
actual if statement okay so we're gonna
expand one of the bounds depending on
which one it is
and then when we're done we're going to
do a split box call for each of the
separate children that we're talking
about here like so
don't ask me why I put that there
that's not my man okay so what we want
to do now is we want to pass down sub
regions to these guys so we know we need
to have something here that's like count
a and some array here and then we need
the sort of swap space for this thing we
don't know what this is and then we know
we've got like sort of a next dim index
it's got to get passed here in the next
name index is pretty simple we know we
only have three dimensions so the next
dimension index is just whichever the
next one is so it'll go XYZ XYZ XYZ so
this will sort of be like a KD tree at
first it's not quite a KD tree because
they can be a little bit overlapping but
it's you know it's similar to the KD
tree right so we will play with that in
a second and at the moment we we're just
gonna leave it as is alright so here in
child a and child B we've got to be able
to do our sort of same call we were
using to add boxes here so you can see
we add box storage for these two and we
add a box for them once we know what the
child box is then we have to actually
initialize it so we have to say what its
bounds are for example so we know that
it's a p value is the the center of
bounds a and we know that the radius is
whatever the radius is for bounds a and
the seen is true for box B
so from there we now have to sort of
start to figure out how we're going to
build these arrays because there's not
much else left to do the split there's a
slit plane which we have to figure out
and then there's the way we're gonna
actually align these arrays to work
properly and that's a little bit harder
we probably need to pass one more thing
down here as we go but that's sort of a
separate issue so what we need to do now
is every time we we do these let me here
we're gonna need to count B and array B
there we go so there's a couple
different ways we can do this
right and we have to kind of figure out
how we're gonna make it work we know we
sort of have a destination buffer that
we know we've got two buffers one that
we have to read out of that tells us
what's going on and one that we're
trying to prepare that we can write into
right so when we come through here where
if we were reading out of the source we
can't touch it but we can do anything
that we want to the destory
and we know how big the destory is as
well so what we could do is write to the
top and the bottom of the dest array and
that would probably be fine
so yeah I think that would just work
since this is going to recurse though
we've got a it's it's pretty tricky
where we place these because when we
call it again it's exactly like merge
sort so do you remember our merge sort
how this thing worked right it it did
the it did the two like calls on the way
down and then it had to do this sort of
copy out and we just decided not to
ping-pong I think at that point because
it was too complicated then we were like
let's just leave it simpler it's exactly
like that it's a pretty tricky function
to figure out exactly where we want
these things to go so as we push them
down we can take less space to do it in
because we know we we know ahead of time
how many we have so we know we can do it
in the subset of the array that is the
actual space we were previously using so
that part's not really a problem so let
me see let's just see what we can do is
first thing time let's just see how it
goes I'm not sure so if we go ahead and
say we're gonna line these two things up
into our output array so we know how
many there are on the source count
therefore we know that the desk will
only have this many in it because we can
only write will only ever write as many
as we had total so if I have two counts
here here's my count hey I guess this is
you 16 count a and count B I start with
both of those being zero then what I
want to do is say in the case where I
hit either of these two things I'm going
to increment them because I've got a new
one in that bounds and what I want to do
is I want to place the reference
whatever reference this one is and and I
should probably snap that reference here
so here's the box Ref
right that's that's the reference to the
box whatever value it actually is so I
want to place that that reference into
the destination at a particular location
so in the case of a I probably want to
say okay it'll go into it that box
reference oops sorry will go into the
bottom of the destination array going
upwards so it'll start at zero go zero
one two three four five six seven as
things go into a if things go into B we
can go from the top down so we could say
all right desk count B as a subtraction
from the source count minus one right so
we start at the source count - want the
last element array and we go backwards
by count B and store them there and as
we go we just count B backwards so we're
like fill them in backwards from that
top and then at the end we have our
array sorted into two halves right so
once we have our array sorted into those
two halves then when we come through
here to make them go what we know is
that the destination if we if we use
this source here we know that our entire
source array can now get destroyed
because we've moved things into the desk
where we don't need them anymore so the
source array itself is now completely
erasable so we should be able to do is
pass the source array as the destination
because it's it's not useful to us
anymore I think I believe that just
works and at that point we're pretty
much done all we need to do is our
classifier and one other thing which is
the termination condition so let's start
with the termination condition so let's
suppose we come in here and source count
is less than the minimum source count we
want in an area so let's say
that oops
so let's say that we want no more than
four boxes but if there's four boxes
that's a plenty so if that's that's a
plenty small enough so if we are
entering split box and we have four or
fewer boxes then what we can do is say
let's make this an actual box that
stores that like sort of a leaf a leaf
container right it's going to contain
actually the actual boxes themselves so
at that point what we do is we say
alright the parent box is now a real box
a real terminator of the of the tree so
underneath it will be only actual boxes
it will not be sub pop tsa's anymore and
will actually just store those boxes in
here directly so what we want to do is
say that the child count equals the
source count we want to say the first
box index equals whatever the current
box ref count is and then we just want
to add box references for for this this
source here right and so maybe we'll
just have a call that adds box
references in bulk like so in fact maybe
we do it like this and if we look at
what a lighting oops that's good if we
look at what a lighting box has to have
in it we can see here that we've got P
and radius those will already have been
set by the parent routine we have
transparency which is not relevant for a
parent box lightnin C's not relevant for
parents boxes at least not yet
child count first child index they're
going to get set and then we've got the
pad there which we don't care about
right so this should do it for there and
that leaves us just with the classifier
so what I'm going to do with the
classifier here is I'm just going to say
we've got two things we've got the
direction vector for classification
so here's the list a class direction and
what that's going to do is that's just
gonna say okay the classifying direction
in fact again like I said this is
actually going to be trivial for us to
do without a switch statement so let's
do it
so the classifiers Direction is just
going to be one in whatever direction
the dimension index is right so we're
just going to say all right if if the
dimension x is zero the classifier is
one zero zero or it's the x-axis it's
the y-axis if it's one it's the z-axis
if it's two and there can't be can't be
three because we're gonna wrap at that
point so that gives us our classifying
direction and then what we want to do is
we want to take whatever this whatever
this parent box is p-value it so the
center of this box and we want to say if
you're on one side or the other of it
that's going to be the classifier so
what we want to say is just okay the
inner product of this peeve out of the
center of the box with the classifier
direction that's the classifying dot
product like that's a classifying
distance let's say right that's how far
you have to go before you're on the
other side of the classifier right then
what I can do is do the same product and
just say okay if the inner product of
the classifying direction with this
boxes the test boxes P if that's less
than the classifying distance then you
end up in your your a range otherwise
it's in your B range right and that's it
so that's really all we need to do we
can there's some fat in here that I can
even in this thing we could say to do KC
don't produce child boxes that aren't
full so you know what we could do is is
put a special case in here that that
that sorry that don't have numbers so
you know if count a and I guess you know
there's no reason not to
do that now so if count a is greater
than zero we process this path right if
count B is greater than 0 we passes this
path right I so you know don't bother
going and creating an entire
classification box for something that
doesn't actually have anything in it
because of all of the things wet in one
side then we can just forget that
classifier and try a different
classifier the only problem with this
with this process is we don't have a way
to bottom out on it yet
so in theory the problem we we would
have here is we need to know that at
least one thing will get split or we can
get infant infinite loop and I'm really
just not sure how to do that at the
moment unfortunately
so if you have a bunch of boxes that all
have the same XY and Z position so
they're right on top of each other and
then they'll never get split right so
I'm not sure exactly what to do about
that you need like a fallback case that
catches when you have ended up in that
situation but I'm not really sure
what it would be
I think you just don't split it
basically if you've tried each split and
you didn't split at all then you just
give up
I think so you know what I think we can
we can do that here I think what we do
is say so I think what we do here say
all right look we're gonna assume that
if something has more than four elements
that we will be able to split it what
we'll do is we'll say while it's
splittable so while we still think that
it's suitable we're going to do this
loop in here and what we will do is
we'll check in here and we'll say if
count a is not equal to is greater than
zero and count B is greater than zero
then actually do a sub split otherwise
keep trying right and you know maybe
what we'll do here is even say okay for
attempt zero attempt is less than three
plus less attempt
so something like a in fact you know the
other way we could do this is say
[Music]
something like this so we'll save that
splittable as false we'll say if the
source count is less than equal to four
splittable equals true else guess we'll
just do this so we'll assume it's
splittable if the source is count as
greater than four we try to split it and
if we split it we set splittable equal
to false and we break out of the loop
that'll work right we break out of the
loop and then we fall through here and
we see if it's not splittable then we do
this right so I think that works okay we
could even do this a little bit reversed
just say was what equals true
or I guess was not split that's true
that's what I actually want it's not
split it's false so we assume that the
thing was not split if we did split it
then we set that to false so that this
will not execute right so I think that
now we'll handle it so that we attempt
to break it on all three axes if we
don't break it on any three we're just
like all right it's just what it is
right so that seems pretty good here's
our classifier we classify then we do
our split and off we go
so what we really need is this add box
reference this thing to actually work
here and then I think we're good to go
now this routine needs a little bit more
because remember we need an actual
parent box here that can have references
in it so what we want to do here is make
these references actually be coherent
and so what I want to do is actually go
ahead and say child box a index here
child box B will actually just have
these at so what I'm going to do is add
box storage here
directly and add bucks reference in this
case is not what I want I just want to
get these things to be exact lookups so
now I have the two references that I
want to store so now what I do is I'm
going to say add bucks reference add
bucks reference so we know that there's
two of these I'm going to add the two
box references in in fact I guess I
could do add box references too
so in this case I'm gonna say alright I
still need to do this right and in fact
now that I look at it I guess what I
could do to is this could actually just
this could just be this could just be
this right because now what I could do
is to say well the source count and the
source are just the correct things to
add normally right but and in fact I
guess I'm allowed to destroy the source
array as well because the source rate
doesn't get used for anything else so
actually I guess I don't even need that
what I can do is say when we come
through the source array here we know
the source array was greater than four
to begin with so what I can do is just
destroy the source of rank actually get
rid of this and say all right all I
really needed to do was say that the
source count now equals two and that the
two first things in it are going to be
child box be a at and child box be at
right so this now becomes always correct
and the only difference is here is
whether or not the child count is
overwritten or whether it's overwritten
by the splitter or whether it just uses
exactly what it was passed right so I
think that's relatively fine don't ask
me why that was a : there there's a
shift key issue I guess um let's go
ahead and compile this here so in this
case array a and array B are just they
come out of the counts right so
arrey a is actually always the
destination we can see that here and
array B is always the destination plus
the source count from a so those are
pretty easy I think that's supposed to
be first child index and so what we need
here is got one other issue so what we
really need is the way to do the add
references which we can just make here
so here is add box reference so make it
add box references and so what we want
to do is say the result here is going to
be whatever the box ref count was the
Box ref count gets added by the count
and we have to assert that the Box ref
count like light data with or I should
say the array count for the Box table
plus the amount that you want to add or
should say minus the amount that you
want to add
yes well I'll do it the other way so the
box ref count here plus the count is
less than the array count right and I
can prevent wrap around here if I want
to in the test by just making it be
slightly larger so if the box reference
count plus the count is going to be too
large then we'll get an assertion here
too so we know we haven't overflowed
anything there we'll grab it the result
out we will increment the total
reference count and then we'll copy and
this is literally just a copy I guess
you know what do it like this because
we've got to do two different accesses
here so that's the copy there and so
this is a fairly complicated routine
here so we're gonna have a lot of issues
with it and we want to try and get it
down to something where we can verify it
a little bit better so yeah this is
gonna be a bit rough we'll step through
at once and see if we can clean it up a
little bit but again anything where
you're dealing with all these indices
and arrays and moving around it's pretty
easy to make mistakes so it's gonna be a
bit of a nasty routine to get working
properly that's just the nature of the
beast and that's okay so first thing is
first let's go ahead and get a
breakpoint in where we want to be here
here we go
all right oh and good thing I would like
to do is let's go ahead and turn off the
debug so looking through here we start
off by saying how many boxes do we have
the answer is there are 77 of them we
make bounds that are basically including
enough the opposite of everything the
opposite of everything it sounds like a
bad novel so what we do is we loop
through each of our boxes and we say all
right we're gonna start by taking
whatever the scratch a array is you can
see there's nothing in it at the moment
we're gonna widen the bounds to include
whatever this is and we're gonna write
the first index in there which is taps
v-0 so you don't see it happen
and now we've created a bounds that just
include just that first box then we're
gonna go to the next box write the index
in and then widen the bounds again and
we're just gonna keep doing this as we
fill up this array when we get out we're
gonna have an array that goes up to 77
as you can see the 7th 7th entry it
stops there so we have boxes we have 77
boxes 0 through 76 and all of the boxes
should be included in these bounds which
looks like it roughly they do so that's
good we're then going to create a root
box here which is what we're doing like
this we get the root Box index and that
index is 0 as you would expect it to be
because it's the first box that has an
actual positive reference to it we then
go ahead and get that box which gives us
back hopefully our root box and we set
its p value it's a P and radius values
so here's that root box oops that's good
I didn't want to launch an H what you
know what universe do you think I wanted
to launch an HTML window out of here I
have no idea
don't ask me ladies and gentlemen
Microsoft filler studio ok so in here
we've got p value and in the radius
value that radius value looks about
right
because you can see that this appears to
be about negative 6 to 6 and about
negative 3 to 3 which is exactly what
this radius would indicate and it's got
very close to 0 as its enter so that's
all good we're then gonna go in and try
and split this thing we're gonna pass
the scratch a as the source so we come
through here and we look at the source
count which is 70
in the source array which has all of
those indices in it and we looked and
see that it's greater than four which is
exactly correct because it's way greater
than four we look at the classifying
direction which should be one along the
x axis and is we look at the classifying
distance and that's zero which it should
be because it was a fairly balanced it
was negative six to six so it's zero was
about about right and then we create
bounce for a and B that include nothing
and count so for them that include
nothing we start with our first box
reference and we grab out that box and
we look at what that box is here it is
and we looked at the Box reference I
think that's correct
all looks reasonable hard to say for
sure but nothing jumps out as being
wrong we take the inner product versus
the classifying distance and we see
which side were on in this case we're on
side B of it and does that make sense
yes because we're looking this is
greater than zero less than zero would
have gone into here so then we're gonna
add to the very end of desk so if we
take a look at desk 76 or I guess we can
just look at 77 worth of desk what we
expect to see is this add to the back
end so we expect it to be added here of
course I guess now I'm thinking about
box zero we wouldn't know if it was so
that's a should have probably written a
garbage value into there first just now
so we could verify that it was but oh
well
now box B should get widened a bit I
don't know if we ever looked at those
bounce or Acuras bounce a why did they
stop advancing to the next one when you
hit return I just don't understand it it
used to be so easy to use for that and
now it's horrible I don't understand it
but there they go so there we go that
expanded box B to include it and now
we've got incremental box count B to say
that there's one in there we're gonna
classify the next one that one also went
in here so now we should be able to see
that get written in here and it does
expand again and off we go
it looks like we're writing most of that
side now we're gonna write in here so we
should see that box ref getting added
here it does and off we go let's go
ahead and jump to the end what we should
see is this whole thing should now be
filled and it is so that's good we
should have a count a and account B that
if we're lucky you're pretty similar and
they are that's not too bad that's split
you know that's a reasonable split it's
not perfect split a perfect split would
be half and half but it's you know
pretty good pretty darn close so that's
good we go to the next dimension index
like so and we look to see whether we
got counts we did on both cases so now
we're gonna add box storage for these
trial axes we're gonna split them and
see what we get so here's our child box
a our child box a looks reasonable
me we're gonna go ahead and split that
and this array should remain probably
unmolested in the range that B counts on
so that's what we really want to focus
on here so count a was 34 which means
we're looking at this value right here
when we run this split box we hope to
not see any of that get modified and
it's not so that's real good so then we
come through here and now we're gonna
rely on these being valid they are and
then they change out from under us which
is fine and then we're going to write
these two into our source array 78 and
145 are our two children oh our break
statement our breaks team is gone so we
found a bug we I accidentally deleted
the break statement there this needs to
stop once it has a split it needs to
stop sorry about that
one more time so what should happen now
when we split two of these guys we go to
the break statement we recorded the
trout count whatever it was and we
record the first child index as whatever
you know wherever it was able to add
that reference this says that the first
child in mix was nine I'm not sure that
that is correct
because the first time through split box
there shouldn't have been any oh no
there could have been cuz you would you
could have hit this case without
splitting so that that seems okay so all
right so now we're doing those splits
and yes so I don't we're not quite
working here it's that's interesting so
we've got some definite bugs happening
but they're not it's not a full bug it's
like the split initial split is wonkey
or something
[Music]
so I'm not sure what's going on there
that's pretty weird uh but that's okay
so what we want to do now is start
debugging the actual splits to make sure
that we split this thing correctly and
that's easier said than done because
it's kind of hard to draw these things
sometimes but what we want to try and do
here is maybe get a mode where we can
actually draw some stuff that indicates
to us where these things are and what
the splits were so that we can go from
there because what we don't know yet is
we don't know whether or not also what
I'm just thinking about this is you'll
notice the run speed it's running at 30
it's running at almost 60 frames I mean
almost 30 frames a second but it's not
an optimized mode right we had it in
debug mode so hey if we got this working
properly I guess the reason it's running
faster is because it's only doing half
the lighting though but but yeah compute
light propagation taking a lot less time
now I I guess that's probably though
probably not because we did a good job
speeding it up yet it's probably just
because it's not actually doing the
correct light propagation anyway so the
problem that we have now is twofold one
we don't really know how we're splitting
these things or if we're even splitting
them correctly so we could just pre
producing a bogus tree that's all messed
up and who knows and it would be easy to
imagine that happening because our
indices we have all these indices and
stuff running around and it just it
becomes kind of complicated right so we
don't really know what's going on there
and furthermore we have a secondary
problem which is that we don't know if
the Ray caster is working properly
because for we only ever tested it with
just one spatial node that had two nodes
below it I'm sorry that had all the
nodes below it so for all we know we
could have produced a very good split
that actually is constructed properly
and
raytracer is just screwing up so we kind
of have a nasty problem here if we don't
actually know who screwed up and that's
a problem so let's go ahead and see what
we can do about that this routine was
not necessary anymore there you go uh so
yes so what we're gonna try and do here
is is get this get this code try to
figure out how we could draw something
or inspect this code in a way that would
allow us to know that it was working
somewhat correctly and then the other
thing we have to verify is that this
code out here is also working properly
as well right so hopefully that's the
case this is looping over points so
that's not really a problem
this raycast is working on boxes so we
have to go verify that's okay
when we actually get the boxes back it
gives us a pointer so hopefully that's
fine and we never really asked asked
asked for those boxes again so in rate
cast recurse is really the place that we
care about here we go through these
child indices here these for the source
and we ask to get the box there which
should do the dereference for us
everything else looks like just works
fine
if it's got a child count then we
recurse again using that box if it
doesn't we record the hit that seems
reasonable
[Music]
it's not a great way to do it but it
seems reasonable so when we actually
okay so I know exactly what the bug is
so the bug here is that we're not
actually using the we need to do the
interior check we need to do the check
to see if we're inside a bounding box so
this little cleverness here is not going
to cut it I so let's go ahead and back
that out we need to fix that bug first
that's just about my cleverness was too
clever I said it might be too clever and
it was uh so let's go ahead and fix that
where where is my
yes so when we do it we do it on the
root box right that's our first one we
loop over everything in the loop then
the root box the Box you're in you'll
never hit it with array because you
start off inside of it so that's why it
was only checking the side that we
weren't on because that one would get
hit by the Ray eventually right yeah all
right
so let's try this again so what we want
to do here is say okay when we loop
through these in our ray cast we need to
do a check for that so we come through
here we do a check to see whether we're
hitting it what we want to do instead is
make this be to make there be two ways
to check this so in this case this is
the case for something that we're not
inside and we need another case for
things that we are inside so if we are
inside a box we would just have to rake
cast recursive so we need an if here
that's a we need one more if
unfortunately which is not really what
we want but that's just what we're gonna
have to do so basically I guess you know
what I guess the way to look at it is
more like this well
okay no no this isn't as bad it's not
quite as bad as that so what we want to
do is actually do it here right we want
to say if box child counts and inside
box we do something other than what
we're doing right now so if the Rea
origin is inside the box then we have to
recurse this box no matter what because
we don't know when we hit it right we
could in it at any time
so I think that's the only real change
we have to make here so if this is a box
that has children and we are inside it
we have to consider its children
automatically we can't raycast it
otherwise we can read cast against it so
the question here is for this light box
what is the inside box call for that and
in order to check that we need to do
something like box key box radius and I
feel like we had a function for this
that we never really pulled out and
should have
[Music]
all right not really
so all right inside here in the
rectangle three stuff I want to do a
thing that's like it is inside a
rectangle where we basically pass you
know a P a radius and a test so this
would be is inside rectangle Center half
dim sort of thing and then we would do a
test here to say all right
relative equals test minus P so then we
know that it's it's centered around the
origin and so then what we can do is
just use three absolute values to test
the test at versus the radius
so I hope you can see what i'm doing
here i'm just essentially using the fact
that once i make the point that i'm
testing
relative to the origin i am in a
situation relative to the origin of the
bounding box like so i can just test it
versus the radius to see whether i'm
inside right so that's all i'm doing
there
so I don't quite know if that's going to
fix us entirely looks like it sort of
did we still have a long ways to go
debugging wise so I'm not gonna be
particularly excited about that yet but
at least that fixes the basic problem if
we compile an optimized mode
well one nice thing we can say is we're
down to looking sort of 60 frames a
second dish here not quite there yet but
it's it's better than it was so that's
kind of nice and so we're you know we're
getting we're getting closer I guess
than we were before
and let's go ahead and take a quick look
to at what we can do how bad we are off
of our off of our game here if I set
this up to something else
all right so here's a more realistic
scenario for the game that has a lot
more entities in it as you can see and
you know we're getting within striking
distance actually right this is not an
acceptable frame rate but it's like it's
even sort of playable like I can control
the character and stuff so that means
we're not that far away and you can see
that it's actually doing lighting
everywhere like literally everywhere
it's like you got bounce lights on the
ceiling and everything so there's no
trickery here it's just doing its thing
it does look like there's some things
that look a little buggy to me like I'm
not sure that that should be lit right
now maybe it should be I'm not sure but
so we may have some bugs lurking in
there like I don't know like that so I'm
not sure so we probably have some more
work to do our indices we may have a few
things messed up where we're not
tracking indexes properly or something
like this so yeah but getting there
because now we're writing running
lighting on literally this whole thing
here and and it's not an impossible
framerate to conceive of getting down to
faster so I think we can go ahead and
improve our stuff more from here and we
should be able to maybe get to a place
where this is this is all right all
right so we'll pick that up again
tomorrow not tomorrow next weekend
for now we can do a quick Q&amp;A
Jackson Benin yes I love sushi
oh wait we've got 30 minutes till Q&amp;A
wait but it says it's 115 isn't that the
time when did I start I thought I
started I thought I started at 11 and
did a 15 minute countdown there
I could be wrong about that
Brian this is a generic question but for
example ad box storage demonstrates this
IC asserts are used to find exceptions
in debug mode what would be the way to
handle a fail to start in release mode
assuming in release mode it is just
stubbed is it a case where most if not
all problems would be found during
testing and not needed to make changes
release um so asserts are only for
things that you that you are sort of
stating you will never allow to occur in
release mode so things that are kind of
possible to happen in release mode but
just unlikely you don't really want into
cert 4 you want an error handler right
so generally speaking release mode
asserts you know eventually get compiled
out we are actually leaving asserts in
in release mode I believe and it's
actually these two things that would
turn that off so technically you know
this is the mode that doesn't have any
asserts in it right so this is actually
an assert free mode this is what a gamer
would actually get on their actual
machine or something right so there's
different meanings of release mode you
can often have assert still compiled in
in release mode and so if you take a
look at assert and what that actually is
doing you can see it here it's it's
actually not predicated on whether it's
OD or o2 it's predicated on whether
handmade slow is set to 1 or 0 so
hopefully that makes some sense
I what was I gonna say about oh one
thing that I think we should have done I
forgot to do is inside the lighting code
what we should do here is the time
function for compute light propagation
we should also take a look at what the
cost is for build spatial partition
because now we've got you know sort of -
two things that can take time and so now
we can sort of see like hey that spatial
partition actually is pretty free
it just doesn't cost much compared to
anything else we're doing so that's good
to know that it's not wasting any time
right but it's good to verify that fact
so we know that we're still spending all
of our time raycasting which means we
can spend more time building better
spatial partitions and that won't be
something that really wrecks us
performance wise which we kind of need
to know right all right next question
couldn't you have just used a stack or a
queue to do a depth first search or
breadth-first search you would knit the
stack with the route box and then
splitting just adds to it if the stack
is empty you're done I'm not sure what
you mean like use it for what so that
you don't have a recursive function
right are you talking about removing the
recursion or something else Brian well
we need to go through each assert call
and eventually add ways to handle
failure cases are only when we rent an
issue down the line and fix those
specific failures I asked because I had
to source my code but then wonder what
the property handle for us know so I
guess what I'm trying say is if you're
adding an assert somewhere where you
could actually fail that's
not in assert like not in that's an
inappropriate place for an assert
asserts are four things you don't expect
to fail so we don't expect to handle
more than 64,000 light sources
we're just saying the game is not meant
to do that
and if you make something where it does
that that's an error right we're not
going to handle it period if instead we
were saying well sometimes you will and
we just want to warn you that you've
done that then that's an inappropriate
place for an assert what we need to do
is have an error handler that just
clamps the value only does lighting on
64,000 and it puts up a little icon to
say hey you've made a level that's too
complicated or right or something like
that I noticed how you barely have any
code keyword highlighting in your editor
do you not like that um I don't know I'd
say I have a fair bit right there's like
all of that is all highlighted and
comments and constants are so there's a
fair bit
Jefferson Ben and do you wish you never
started sushi game thing um yes and no
so one of the problems of the sushi game
thing is that I did all the artwork
myself I feel like that it would have
been cool to not do that I guess is what
I'd say I am a lot more capable in terms
of making art myself now but I didn't I
just shouldn't have bothered and
probably the game would have maybe come
out good if I hadn't bothered because I
could have spent my time learning to be
a game designer instead of that and then
I could have made the game be fun you
know
maybe so the problem is I think you have
to kind of pick and choose what you
actually want to do and I think probably
that part was a mistake on the other
hands I don't know maybe I can art
direct things better now because I know
all that stuff it's really hard to say
counterfactuals are hard you learn a lot
from everything you do and it's really
hard for you to know
so I'm not sure someone says like I have
here for example but I'm not sure an
example of reference to what oh no I
don't care for that kind of a level of
Sanatana that's more than I need like I
don't need like function names to be
highlighted or something or anything
like that it just gets distracting if
you have too many different colors on
the screen it's I don't find that to be
particularly useful anymore have you
thought about making a stream to recap
your code kind of looking over it and
explaining it to catch people up who
can't watch it all yes actually there
probably will be those after the
products over so when we finished and
made hero and like we're like this is
the code it's over we're not changing it
anymore then then we could do it that
that like you know that's where we could
say this is this is a good time to just
sort of go over the code and tell people
how it works and why we did it that way
yeah let's see started slightly
increased and went on for long usual no
we didn't start late I said it 11:15 and
we did the timer so this timer starts at
11:15 the problem is that the we had
questions that overlap so that's just
how that goes like I keep the stream to
be two and a half hours that's how long
it is
so there's 15 minutes of pre stream if
the preaching goes long it eats into the
episode time and then we have 15 minutes
of questions at the end can you add
partition boxes ation or is that not
valuable no we absolutely will have to
add that that's why I was saying it's a
little hard to do because it's hard to
draw partitions in a way that's really
clear what's going on in them but we do
we definitely need to add this and
eventually we you know next time we'll
probably have to because we're gonna
have start debugging those and make sure
they're getting built properly
all right
how close are we to finishing who knows
it's a project for educational purposes
for you know the people watching so it's
mostly about getting educational content
onto the stream and given that like
usually I make decisions about whether
to go do something based on whether I
think it'll be useful in that way so
hard to say the frame profile UI is that
custom made on stream it looks good
yes that was custom made on the stream
the frame profiler is kind of awesome
actually it's really very powerful so if
you take a look at the way it works is
you can actually pause the game
profiling anytime so the game will keep
running but the profilers data stops
updating and you can go to any given
frame and see where like what that frame
looked like so you can actually get you
know sort of sub like you can look at
like if there were spikes or something
you can look at like what was happening
over time as well you can also look at
other things like thread information so
if you want to see how like multi thread
was was happening or what was happening
on there you can drill down kind of in
in that way as well you can look at
frame stacks so here's like the past
frames drawn as stacks there you can
kind of see like okay so something
happened in here input processing went
long why did it go long like you can
drill down into it if there were sub
regions you can see like message
processing getting the mouse position
crap like that you get the idea
so anyway some of those are more useful
than others mostly we just use the top
list because that's gives you almost
everything you need the other thing we
never really expanded much on we didn't
really try to get it to a place where
it's super useful for finding stuff so
it's we don't really use it much but in
the future we could upgrade it a little
bit and probably make it more useful but
yeah it's a good profiler we've never
done the memory version of it we should
at some point probably because it
wouldn't be that hard
do you think of functional programming
to ask this I've been asked this many
times so you should probably be able to
find a answer in the episode guide
all right so let's go ahead and wrap up
since there are no further queues it
looks like thank you everyone for
joining me for another episode of hand
made here it's been a pleasure coding
with you as always if you would like to
follow along at home you can always peer
to the game on handmade hero org and it
has the source code included with it so
you can do your own experimentation
that's about it for today I will be back
next week to basically work on the
actual optimization part now of getting
a spatial partition and a lighting
algorithm tuned so that we can try to
actually run at 60 frames a second with
you know with with a full sized level in
there and it depends on how we and we
necessarily want to do this since you
can see the fact that we were able to
build the spatial partition on the CPU
in a trivial amount of time that means
that one of the things that we could
consider now is running the Ray tracer
on the GPU itself we do have that option
we don't necessarily want to do that but
we could do that and so we'll have to
start thinking about whether that's
appropriate or not so we'll do that
we'll start making those decisions as
well the other thing we could do is
continue to run it on the CPU and just
run it on the CPU parallelized
and sim dies Dre so we'll see that's
about it for today until next week have
fun programming and I'll see you all on
the Internet take it easy everybody