hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete-game
live on stream we are gonna finish Cindy
optimizing the lighting today and
that'll be nice cuz we don't even know
how well we did yet we haven't even seen
how much Cindy optimization will help us
we're totally in the dark about that
actually
and as someone pointed out on the stream
just now also I don't think we've ever
realty threading with the sim decode yet
either right if I'm not mistaken
yeah that's still turned off so we don't
really know anything about what this
will look like when we when we run it
right now it is I believe slower than
the non Cindy version I would assume
because we still downshift to a loop on
the interior but I guess I don't really
know if that's the case since we never
ran it the other way so what I could do
is run it multi-threaded now and see
what our say this is success what people
were wondering about I agree that's an
interesting data point as we finish here
just to see what the difference would be
so running in Oh - if we take a look
here what we've got Oh someone's angry
ooh what is the problem compute like
propagation so it looks like box surface
index is coming back well I guess we
don't really know what it's coming back
as cuz this is an O 2 mode so in O 2
mode we're getting a weird result there
let's take a look at that
so what happens here right is four bucks
for a box surface index we are actually
talking about the thing that's returned
from the ray code which is not the same
as in that case I mean it is the same
meaning but it's not a loop it's
actually something that just determines
but that's that's like reporting back
here which which one it is
so box surface index here is something
that comes out of the Ray results so
it's this thing here we've got Ray
bracket for the box service index is
accessed off of the individual one we're
looking at here and when we find that
we've got a hit which is determined by
this get box call here oh so there we go
so this box index this is a problem here
so we're not actually this won't
necessarily return zero for zero
I don't think because box 0 is not a
reserved box I don't think we probably
want it to be would be my guess
and we probably want that to be clear so
if we take a look in here right this is
always gonna return a valid box because
box zero is gonna be valid I so you know
I don't know how exactly we want to do
this it's a good question we'll have to
play with it a little bit but let me
just go ahead and insert a value there
temporarily so that we have a clear way
to do that so in here where we that's
not where we want to be I always start
talking before I actually get to the
place because that's just easier to have
the flow of the narration of the stream
so it's like sometimes I'm on the
totally wrong file and I'm like here in
the thing and it's like well no we're
not hearing that thing yet that's where
I want to go it's not where we're there
yet
so here in the file where we define the
results if I go ahead and put a B 32 in
here that's just like hit or whatever
right then what we can do is when we're
actually checking this when we come
through and set it right then we we can
just set all of these hit values
here and we'll play around with how we
want to track that you know when we undo
this loop down here we still got this
one loop down here right right here we
still got this one loop right here that
we got to get rid of when we today when
we get rid of that loop that's a good
time for how we want to broadcast the
results of the hit back to this routine
because that'll tell us what's going on
right so we hear really all we have to
do we're looping over the sub rays what
we can do here is just get rid of all of
this stuff pretty quickly we can just
say like alright I think box service
index and and the Ray position here
those Serb both inside this right so in
fact even this is so really all we have
to do here is just do this if Ray sub
ray
hit and then we know we can just rely on
in here if this is true we just have
result C index hit equals true now
probably what we'll do instead is just
report back the mask so we don't have to
do any work right and then the outside
code will be the thing that actually
looks for the mask or something right so
you can see that this will we're just
doing this as a temporary plumbing
procedure and we'll get rid of it in a
in a second when we actually clean that
up right so all right let's take a look
at what happens here in the o2 version
here's the o2 version
and so what what so I guess that bug
which would have been happening all the
time was a pretty big one right because
now we're running at 30 milliseconds but
I don't think we're doing any less work
did I enable the so just that looks like
that must-own oh I okay there we go
that's like I must have been able so
let's see that again it's like I must
have enabled the multi-threading and and
I had I just forgot I had um so okay so
here's the single threaded sim D version
running here right so there we go
and this is doing again this is doing I
think all 64 raised right so this is 16
casts of 4 raised each this is the full
64 so when we turn on the
multi-threading oops this is the full
version that we were trying to run that
speed before and now with Cindy it
actually is running it at 30 frames a
second which is not as good as 60 frames
a second but it's getting there right so
you know we're making improvements here
we've still got a lot more work to do so
I think we'll get a lot faster than this
eventually and I think we'll also be
able to reduce some of the flicker
further because there are some things I
hadn't tried yet regarding flicker as
well so you know we're definitely
getting there on lighting and we're
still retaining a lot of the kind of
fancy features that I didn't want to
get rid of so that as we sort of use
this lighting more in the actual game we
can have cool stuff like I like the fact
that we still have subtle bounce like
blue light that bounces off of surfaces
and red light that bounces off surfaces
and so on I just I just kind of like
that and so I think as we improve the
lighting which we will do like that's
just really nice I mean I don't know I
think it's pretty cool when you get into
when you get a light near a wall and it
produces that bounce color I don't know
it just feels really good and kind of
brings the game alive an interesting way
so yeah I'm pretty excited about the
potential of this going forwards as we
clean it up and improve it and you know
I just think it's gonna be pretty sting
and we still don't really know exactly
how we're gonna use the lighting in the
render time either so you know right now
I mean that just looks good even right
now that that in there that lighting
just looks kind of good but we haven't
even done a bunch of stuff that we want
to do that you know we could do for
during render to maybe smooth to smooth
it out and make it more continuous
across continuous services and stuff
like that so that we can have both the
sort of nice articulation that these are
blocks which we're getting but also a
little more coherency in the light when
when they when there shouldn't be brakes
which we can play with and again I don't
know if we actually want that it may
turn out that the art style really wants
to be discontinuous across blocks but
you know anyway so looking good but we
got work to do let's go ahead and finish
but I'm happy that we're at 30 frames a
second already that's kind of a nice a
nice turn so if we come through here and
we take a look at our ray cast through
we're I'm gonna move it to the other
side so that my head is not taking it
part of our our code view there so if we
take a look at what's going on in here
I'm gonna go ahead and take this code
out now that I'm pretty sure we're doing
a reasonable job of that so we take a
look through here we can see that we get
down to this part of of the loop and
this is where we have to downshift the
part where we know we actually retire
right so what this is is this is when at
least when this is when all of the Ray
have have decided they don't need to do
any finer grained checking is what
happens here now there's thing there's
different ways we might want to do this
and it's difficult to know which one
will be better or worse and we're gonna
have to probably try them both because I
don't really know which one to do so one
way we can do it is we can only
calculate Rea results at the end so we
won't record ray hits until all Ray's
have gotten down to the appropriate
level of granularity for their hit
testing that's one thing we can do the
other thing we can do is anyone who
passes the masks without the bound check
who passes the masks anyone who passes
the masks records they're hit always and
does not use more granular you know what
why am I
I'm just flapping my gums at you you
have no idea I'm talking about let me
draw a diagram then everyone knows what
I'm talking about so previously here's
what was happening I have a sample point
and I'm sampling out through the world
like so and I've got boxes right as I go
through the world I check these boxes
that I hit this one no I didn't did I
hit this one no I didn't did I hit this
one yes I did I hit this one yes I did
right and then we only record the
earliest so if I hit this one first I
record it and then I hit this one and
throw it out because it's too far if I
hit this one first I record it then I
hit this one I overwrite it right but
I'm always gonna end up with this one I
was gonna end up with the closest hit
that's just true right however one thing
that we introduced was the fact that the
bounding hierarchy has its own record of
what the lighting is generally speaking
and this is a technique to reduce the
by saying look you don't have to
traverse the whole hierarchy and get the
lighting if it's too far away we'll just
give you an average of what the boxes in
that area tend to give off lighting wise
right so if we were to do that which is
what we're doing now that means that
like this light sample would be recorded
instead of this one here on the box that
we that we actually hit the sort of the
parent box would take precedence because
we never go down and check the lower
boxes we just use it as the hit that
once we go multi-threaded is no longer
the case once we go multi-threaded if
there are two rays and one or multiple
rays and some of those rays hit the bus
box
and other rays don't then what we will
do is if any of those rays would have
hit it at a time when we should have
traversed it
we will traverse it for all the Rays so
if one of the Rays really should have
used the average it won't because we're
doing them as a bundle and we choose to
traverse that part of the hierarchy or
not based on whether anyone needed to
not whether they all needed to right so
given that fact we then have to figure
out well okay is that the right thing to
do
should we preserve our old behavior
where we recorded the hits and don't
traverse for those rays or do we allow
them to diverse because hey we're gonna
do those checks anyway it's no extra
work for us because we're gonna check
all these rays as a bundle so we're
gonna do the checks and just throw them
out if we were to use the the hierarchy
one so the question is just do we want
to use the hierarchy one because
obviously that could reduce very and
since it's using an average from an area
instead of
using the individual hits which could
vary more and the other question is do
we really even care because how often
does that even happen right and I'm not
sure it would happen a tremendous amount
if we were passing rays that were cast
from different starting locations but
since we're passing rays that start from
the same starting location it's a lot
less likely pretty much what has to
happen is array has to shoot directly
that way in another way a to shoot this
way and when this rake hits and this
rate hits that length has to be too far
and this length has to be close enough
right so this one would go through and
this one wouldn't have gone through
right but now they both go through does
that make sense so I don't know which of
those two we want to do fortunately I
don't think it's a big deal to do either
really so I guess we should just test it
either way so for example one way we
could we could test it right now right
we could go ahead and say all right we
record hits like this and we just go
anybody who did a hit here does record
the hit something like this and then we
do the recursion after the fact
young-sam
and it looks like we break in any case
don't we right we had we had it like
this this break is actually just here
there's there is no we're gonna get out
of the loop we're not going to keep
going
because when we're checking these axes
we don't need to check any more axes
once somebody hits because if somebody
hits either we will descend right or we
will record the hits I guess
wait that's not really true is it
yeah that's not really true so that the
break statement really needs to go there
I think because if we're gonna descend
from this box then we definitely don't
need to keep checking but if we're not
going to we don't know which raise have
finished and which ones haven't so I
think that is the more correct
interpretation we can break out there is
an early out here which is if all of
them are true right so basically if so
if every one is true when we're in the
hip case that would be a break I believe
that's actually valid I don't know how
often that happens we could count that
branch and see whether we even want to
bother checking but I think that's more
technically the case so again that's the
situation here and the question is well
all right do we want to do this
effectively up here which is record all
the hits for anyone who was I guess not
close not in the close enough bracket of
things
so basically if you were not close
enough to descend and you had your mask
set then you would record this hit and
let it be primal right that's not right
at all is it I thought that was right
apparently I'm wrong close enough to the
seriousness of Tmax
well I guess technically box child count
would also have to be in there right
technically we'd have to do this
I don't think that was the problem not
necessarily apparently was so I think
that is what would actually be required
to make the program work the way it was
supposed to in the previous version
right and I just don't know how I feel
about it one way or the other I feel
like the added complexity probably isn't
worth it so I think what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna stick with the previous way
for a while anyway so I think we'll
stick with this and we'll fine-tune this
a bit more and then we'll take a look at
it later and see if there's other stuff
we want to do here all right so taking a
look here at how this goes we need to
work on this part of our code because
this part of the code is garbage it's
complete garbage right now so we want to
figure out a way to make it less garbage
and the way we want to make it less
garbage is this is just a loop that
takes preferences here like it basically
takes the values we actually want versus
the values we don't based on the mask so
if the mask is set then what we want to
do is take results and replace the ones
we have with the new results if the mask
isn't set we want to leave the old
results as they were so we want to do is
hoist these out one at a time into the
results structure that's going to be
used as the raycast result report so
probably what we want to do here is just
leave the mask value as it is because
the mask value is the thing that's gonna
tell you which rays hit and which rays
didn't right so our hit in the raycast
results I think that's just one of the
things that we need is the mask here so
what we'll do at the outset is in the
result and again we will
do the thing I start to do the other day
it's which is to change this from a zero
one two three thing to just being all
packed in one and I don't know if we
should make this be a return or not
probably we should
I'm guessing this should look more like
this now just to give the compiler the
understanding that you know the values
that are coming into this are irrelevant
you don't have to know what they are so
don't worry about it
and so we can see to inline this routine
into the code on the outside and just
merge them together we could do that for
it later as well we could just copy this
in anyway here's our raycast results and
so we're going to start out by setting
the hid value to f-22 or zero right so
we just want that to be clear and we
want that to be clear because that's the
only thing we actually need to report
back in the case of no hits we don't
need to tell them that's other stuff so
then we need to do is have these other
ones here they all need to be the same
right they all need to be done the same
way but what I'm gonna do is I'm just
gonna start again one at a time
so these are all gonna be brackets for
for now and then we're gonna move them
out one time into actual correct Simbi
so the first thing I want to do is say
all right let's up update the hit valued
differently so the result hit value that
we're gonna end up add that return
statement so the result hit value here
is just a thing that needs to get word
in so essentially what we're doing is
we're filling out the things for which
the mask was true so what we should be
able to do is just or the mask in
because it's sorry our result zeros when
we get a lane that comes through is as
all ones we just want to slot that in so
we want to just merge those results with
what we already have
that should be the entirety of the
update step for the mask and we
definitely don't need to do it inside
the loop because it will get all of the
lanes that should have been merged we'll
just merge with that one or operation we
don't have to do it per Lane so that
should completely finish that right that
that should be done at that point
and if I go through here and I just
double check I don't think we have like
or equals operator or any of that stuff
at least I don't think we do so I should
go ahead and find the x equals sorts of
stuff and just make sure we have
versions of those so here's like you
know plus equals minus equals x equals
divide equals and what I'll do here is
I'll just like grab one of these and
then down in here where we're actually
doing those those binary operate ups
I'll put those in here so here's and
equals and here's or equals and again
we're just using it the two-tier state
system so that it we only have to write
the function once and we can get the
pops out of it so make it easier for
people to pour it so now we just need to
do the temporary port work here
like I said make these B bracket Abel
like so yeah so here's my recast
function we're gonna do ray cast result
ray equals ray cast and get rid of that
and then when we're looking at the right
here this subarray thing is just going
to loop over for temporarily and then
it's not gonna loop over anything in a
minute here so now when we want to see
whether something kick again we can
choose this out again by just doing em 1
28 q 32 here and looking at that sub
value to see whether or not the hit is
recorded and then everybody else
oops we don't need that we can just use
an e right oh well
mmm I don't really want to do that
because that's a floating point 5 moment
so we're going
that way so in here everything else can
just be you just move the index over to
the end and then we're good and I and
again we're not gonna leave it that way
that we're just gonna do that
temporarily as sort of like a stepping
stone so here we are with that code and
that's all fine and now we have to go
ahead and push that down a bit more so
the next thing we can do is target
result T right here so we want to be
able to hoist this out of the loop I
want to get let's get over here
we want to be able to hoist this out
because again result tear a is something
weird is keeping for ourselves so
there's no reason to keep doing that by
slice because that doesn't even
communicate with the outside world so
you don't have to worry about the code
in the outside so what we want to do
with result T ray is we want to select
the lanes of T ray based on the mask so
we want to do a thing where we do like a
select function where we take the old
version of result T array and the new
version of of T array and we take them
based on the mask right so we're
basically saying look this is what it
was this is what the new computation is
if people hit take the new T values
right so that makes sense so there's a
couple weirdnesses about this and I'm
not again this is why it's a little
confusing so yeah no I think mask is
right so close enough is the thing that
tells us whether the T ray is less than
the T max that we don't care about
because that's just a thing that
determines whether we go down the
traversal or not
so if anyone was true and close enough
we would never get to this part of the
code so we're strictly looking at masks
here is the only thing we're looking at
so I think we're good right I think
we're good
you know what I just realized too this
isn't quite correct so close enough if
someone someone has to have hit to have
been close enough as well right so in
here we need to - all of this has to be
true as well so close enough technically
let me let me just back this change out
temporarily let me show you what I'm
talking about
I just noticed this is just a bug you
make sure okay here so this is running
it's running okay right like I mean it's
still producing lighting but it could
have some subtle bugs in it right we
wouldn't know we don't have any really
thorough test cases yet to see whether
our lettings working the way we think it
is but if you see here this close enough
value this is just checking this one
conditional really we have to do these
together right the mask has to be true
and this has to be true because anyone
who didn't hit shouldn't participate in
the any true close enough check so this
is really more correct I believe for a
traversal
you know I don't see much difference
there but I believe that was just a bug
right okay so back to our previously
scheduled program so we here what I want
to do is update t ray by doing a select
on it and I want to pizzette pass result
t ray the mask and the new T ray so I
want to do a select on those and then
that's the exact same thing we'll be
doing down here Jimmy that same select
is what we'll be doing down here as well
so in fact we can just write these all
at once if we want to you know we could
just say all right you know we need a
replicated version of the source index
and we need a replicated version of the
box index and whatever and we'll go
ahead and and make that happen right so
we'll do that in a second but first
let's just talk about the Select and
make that happen
so if I compile now the thing that we're
missing is just that call so in here we
have to implement it what that's going
to do is going to take two of these and
the mask value right
and it's just gonna do a simple
operation on them right it's going to
say okay if I start with a I know that I
essentially want to take and knock out
the lanes of a where the mask has ones
right so what I want to do is end it
with like the inverse and it just so
happens that that actually exists as its
own operation
so when ends up happening is you do an
end with the knot of a and then you end
it with B so whatever comes in the first
parameter here gets knotted and then it
ends with this so I'll be honest with
you I have no idea why you would call
this and not instead of not and maybe so
that you don't confuse it with knotting
after you do the entire end it's more
like and not a first I don't know I
don't the name is confusing but you know
you can see which one it does by looking
at the description here it knots the
first parameter and leaves a second one
the same so what we want to do is in mm
and not PS here and that and not takes
the mask as the first parameter because
that mask value is the one that needs to
be knotted and then it will take the a
value as a thing to end it with
similarly we need to do an and between
the mask without knotting it and B right
because that's going to knock out the
lanes of B that don't have one set in
the mask and then finally we will
combine them together with our or
operation and off we go
so there's our select and it just does
exactly what you would think right so I
think that's all we need to do there it
go and head and compile that here we go
maura meets at that p-value there okay
so that's the Select function and in
theory now if we implemented that
correctly we are now no longer doing
piecewise ifs on that we're just doing
the lanes as they go which is good right
and now what we want to do is we want to
do that for the rest of these so the
first thing we have to do is make it so
that these can be accessible as you
thirty twos essentially like we have to
have a way of loading you thirty twos so
what we want to do in here is say all
right those result values that we're
setting here at the outset we need to
have a way of romping in like actual
yeah like values that aren't floats
because we need to be able to return
those and we can't return those as
floats really we want these box indices
and stuff like that to be regular
integers so what we want to do here is
just say alright we've got our F 32 4 X
4 box index and our F 3 - 4 X 4 our box
surface index and then the rate p value
part I'm going to leave and we're gonna
do that second second because that's an
actual v3 so we already have a type for
that one
so do that one separately but these two
are both going to be done the same way
effectively that hit is done right so
thinks these are going to be laying
combined really we do need to clear this
now because we need to or things into it
so we can't really have any one's
sitting around in there so as we come
through when we or things into that oh
no no I'm wrong we do not need to clear
it we only need to clear that first line
because we're always checking the hit
value first so that's okay on the
outside of the loop it will never
process the lame that doesn't have the
hit value to set so that's all right
alright so our box indices now what we
need to do is when we come through here
we're going to use these these box
surface index values here in the source
index right so what we need to do is we
want to have a way of updating these two
the same way we updated the other one so
we want our our result box index we want
that
and this we want these to both be
selects that just select the right one
now box surface index I don't remember
exactly how that got set
yeah I'm gonna have to look at this a
little more carefully because we want to
know which one we hit here and it should
be the same for everybody so it should
only depend on the axis index it should
never actually depend on the CE index
I don't think and it doesn't look like
it does
oh yes it does because rady
I see ok I'm ok with that
all right so anyway this will get
selected out of this properly here so we
just need to write the equivalent of
these these select statements will work
just fine
because the you know these are the same
type at that point so we should be able
to just run these directly the question
is whether these values themselves are
actually initialized properly up here
and I think that they are so the only
question is how do we get it in there
right we just need this to actually be
initialized this way but I think we can
just initialize it that way
without really doing any other work at
the moment so what I can do here is I
could just say alright the Box surface
index u-32 value will just initialize it
this way and then it just kind of works
right I think that all just works based
off the see index now and we're pretty
much done we could also do this a little
bit more cleanly by saying you know in
here if you want to access this as
something else you can so for example
there's a u32 version oops that you can
access so for example we can just say
like that get it out and that's probably
a nicer way to read that and it's clear
what's going on when you're pulling or
pushing in those values in that way so
that's probably what we would rather do
there I'm guessing so all right
[Music]
right so source index has never actually
been loaded source index here is like a
non replicated value so you can see here
we've got two source index and we need
that to be something we can load in here
so we need to replicate this value
across so what we need to do is we need
to pass this in you know we need to do
something like that where we can create
one of these out of an integer value and
it's gonna have to do that load that we
were doing before so when we create that
mask right you can see this set one PS
happening here this is really exactly
what we want to do so we want this to
happen if you know we don't actually
have to do it like that I guess but
that's that's what we want to do in our
load so where we're doing our f/32 for x
call here we just want to make an
equivalent call
and instead of having if the amass value
it's just whatever it actually is so
then we have the result the result P
equals the casted value and then we
return it that allows us to load up that
in and do our mask operation on it so
again that's just replicating that value
out so that we can use it so now we need
to be able to pull those out fortunately
we just added a nice way to do that so
we can just do it like this and then I
think we're done and now that loop of
course we're not going any faster even
if this loop was cause problems because
the loop is still there right that
doesn't look good
so
I thought we had done everything exactly
the way we were doing it before but that
may not be true
like I don't see anything particularly
different happening here
what's to go wrong so the select call
appeared to be working properly for
everybody else we select the box index F
of that where is our you know our our
hit is checking here we won't call this
unless this comes back as true so I
would have thought we would have been
okay there let me take a look at what
happens
so our box index is definitely
completely nuts right I wants to take a
look at what our values are so here's
our array so here's our hit values hit
not hit not hit hit here's our box
indices completely ludicrous yeah so it
looks like the Select is going backwards
there am I wrong about that we want to
select from this to that based on the
mask
did I not write it that way did I
somehow read backwards or something like
this which would be pretty terrible if I
did so we are masking the knot of the
mask with a and we roaring with it now
so that looks right let me step through
that code I'm not sure I see I don't
immediately see the reason so I feel
like it's just safer to look let me turn
off multi-threading again
so that so let's take a look here's our
mask this is the thing that told us what
hit so one hit zero two and three did
not and let's just take a quick look to
see whether we think that's actually
right so here's our tear a value that we
computed oops the wrong thing there so
in here we've got you know 19 5 4 so
negative 14 obviously didn't hit you
know whether 19 or 7 hit I don't know
but I guess we could look at our bounds
check here's our X's and Y's
and you know yeah I could believe that
these two are pretty close right
yep so this is the only one that passed
the bounced check so that does look
about right
you know it's not ridiculous that mask
seems plausible to me so let's see what
happens here is our result kirei the box
child count here is two and I guess
close enough did not trigger
so why didn't close enough trigger what
is the result T right here oops I'm
sorry what is the T ray so that seems
wrong doesn't it because oh no it's
right because it's five and this is six
so now we shouldn't Traverse that's
correct so this did it right that makes
sense so we're gonna go ahead and do our
select here and we should select five
nine two into the result tra yeah and we
did so then we should mask in the hit
right here and we did then we should
select in a box index this is just
garbage right because we don't need to
initialize it except in this slot so
this slot should now get a valid 534 oh
oh boy oh boy let's get that on there
okay so I don't know why it would
surprise me that I can't get correct
values out of something when I don't ask
it to actually write the value back you
know I'm saying yeah
suffice to say I expect better results
this time yeah all right I wonder if we
should just have a thing by the way
I don't know you know what I'm not gonna
do it now
all right so back to the normal speed
here is the same thing running but now
with selection there so the selection
has only one piece that's not working
now and that's this right here so what
we'd like to do is we'd like to get rid
of that as well now now to do that we
really don't have to do anything other
than what we did here the problem is we
don't actually have what we did here
right we want to be able to call the
same thing we want to be able to call a
select function that'll just select the
appropriate parts of the mask that
picked the Ray p4x instead of the array
P here I and you know not do any of that
stuff so we'd like to be able to do that
and we would like to be able to do it
the sax aimed way fortunately we should
be able to do it by literally just
replicating the Select function but
using the Forex version instead right so
if we come down here and we say okay we
want to have a v3 it's gonna get masked
by a scalar mask though so we don't
notice this one does not become a v3
because we want to mask every dimension
of a and every dimension in beat by the
same mask so we don't have a different
mass for x y&amp;z with the same mask for XY
and z so the result function I mean the
result value here is just to distribute
that mask operation over all of them
like so so that should do the same
select right in either case now I just
need to come down here and make this
actually be a 4x okay
so now I believe we have the fully
functioning version which doesn't do any
weird looping through the scalars on the
out on the inside of the raycast but it
definitely does do weird looping
upstairs on the outside of the raycast
so that's definitely something we could
start to address as well now of course
we don't really know where the time is
getting spent necessarily because we
can't sub profile it here so we may need
to gather some information to find out
what we can do at this point in terms of
of optimizing that right meaning we
don't really know how much this is
costing us versus this and one of the
problems is we call this enough times
that it becomes kind of costly to
profile it at all right
but if we look here so you know it's not
nothing but most of our time is
definitely spent in there now another
thing that I'm not sure about is how
much the startup cost is so you know the
other thing I could do is just let's
just take a look I'm assuming the
startup cost is negligible I really just
want time this block I mean this can't
really be very much time I don't know
why I'm bothering so let's suppose we
times block which I have named real food
flavor just to let you know that it's
made with all natural ingredients and so
yeah that startup cost is not
particularly high right so this part
could be optimized quite a bit but I
don't know that we really care if that
makes sense so now we're down to just
looking at what is a completely sim deed
routine here I believe and yeah
I don't think there's anything
particularly odd going on there so what
I would point out however is that we're
still not nearly as fast as we probably
should be even with just that one
routine and the reason for that is we're
not sampling the hemisphere in a smart
way so what we actually want to do here
is do this slightly differently what we
want to do is have our sample hemisphere
function also be Cindy and we want it to
produce four rays that go in the same
direction so this function rather than
doing this needs to produce four rays
that all go rough
the same direction so they'd start with
a random bilateral set that goes one
direction or something and then they'll
perturb that or write a number of times
with small perturbations so we knew
they'd all cast relatively coherently in
the same direction so if we take a look
at how that would happen what we would
want to do here is say okay sample
hemisphere we can already see if we take
a look at sample hemisphere you can see
how it produces a sample D that's that's
for wide here and then it gets loaded
like this so what we can do is we can
say also why is I don't know why this is
getting produced every time it's the
same right it's up that's that's not a
that isn't very so we want to do is make
this be actually produced directly so we
want sample hemisphere to be something
that just directly produces a v3 for X
and let me just get rid of this and that
will generate like essentially a ray
bundle that we know goes in a reasonable
direction away so if I pull that down
here so you can look at it what we want
to do is take this and change it into
something that that behaves that way so
in order to produce this v3 for X I
guess I'll start off with doing
something pretty basic I'll keep the
load as it was
something like this and then I'll just
say these and then we'll flatten it down
in a second here so what I want to do is
this process is probably fine for each
one it's like you know what let me just
do this as a loot for now and I suppose
actually I can just
so what I want to do is I want to go
through and produce each of these I'm
going to do this by having a basis that
is a random bilateral that I pick up
here I'm going to normalize that and I'm
in normalize it again I don't that's not
really what I want to do I would rather
not have to normalize the first one I'd
rather normalize it at the end but I'm
not sure if I can really guarantee
because I don't know the length of this
I can't guarantee that I'll be close by
on the next one so it's a little bit
difficult there so what I want to do
here is I want to take the basis and add
it to this other vector and I want to
make this perturbation relatively small
right so point one or point two
perturbation
and then I will record that so now in
theory we should be casting rays that
are semi coherent and you know they they
can traverse similar parts of the
hierarchy in theory anyway now we
probably want to draw this at some point
to here in T that we actually are
because we don't actually know if we are
but we can see you know we can see that
this is well I don't want to stand close
to the stairs okay so we can see this is
what like 22 is on the clock and we
should be able to see a difference I
would think if we swap to just doing
completely random bilateral here right
so if we were to say instead that we
just use a complete randomness a ssin
we should be able to see some difference
here at least in theory in performance
but I don't actually know that we will
yeah you can see that so you can see
here that we're getting like about 30
right something like that 28 29 or so if
I change it to be more coherent that
number drops down quite a bit actually
it takes about 6 milliseconds less 5 to
6 milliseconds less to do and again the
reason for that is just the number of
box checks that have to happen at that
point is pretty substantial because when
we cast rays in opposite directions
they'll check everything in the whole
hierarchy right because this one if two
rays go in opposite directions of each
other then we'll have to check all the
hierarchy on that side and all the
Harkey on this side rather than only
checking some of the hierarchy on one of
the sides if they all went that way
that's what so when you bundle rays
together you only really get performance
out of your spatial hierarchy if those
rays are somewhat semi coherent if
they're not coherent then you kind of
lose all the benefit that you would that
you were trying to get out of it right
so now we're yeah we're obviously in in
better shape with our lighting it's
running much more nicely than it was but
it's still not probably fast enough
right so we're not we're not quite there
yet in in terms of cycle count right
we're not typed quite there yet - what I
think we could probably say was
reasonable to do at the moment now if we
think if we improved our sampling like
maybe we are I don't know because the
loop the number of rays here is you know
if you could somehow drop it down by a
dramatic amount you know we would get
dramatically faster right so depending
on how our say or maybe not whoo that's
very interesting data
so that floor is not as high as I would
have thought it to be
that's pretty interesting
so yeah I mean maybe that is sort of an
argument for cleaning up the code around
this as well I'm not sure we could
certainly do that I mean there's not a
lot of reason not to at this point let's
go through this though one more time and
just finish up what we were doing here
so the first thing I want to do is I'm
gonna get rid of the four X's on things
because now everything is done for wide
so we don't have to call something for X
right so if anything in here still has a
4x on it I'm just gonna get rid of it
looks like we mostly didn't but this one
for example does just get rid of these
here
Oh
so that all looks fine
and I may just go ahead and reinstate
this too because it seems like a good
idea
so this radiative value here
I feel like we could just do
well I'm not sure like we could just do
this in Cindy now because why not right
so if we take a look at this right this
is just to select between two constants
like positive and negative one right
so really you know we could just have
some constants here and just do this and
type this thing entirely wide as well
seems worth doing also we could get rid
of this loop too if we wanted to because
we could set the number of children and
have it be a known amount you know so
that that could be a fixed loop I don't
know if the compiler is smart enough to
unroll the access index bit here
you
I also think the way we wrote this down
here is not really necessary so since
the close enough part had to be masked
already this is really not necessary
this can come down here so basically
this can look essentially the same as it
used to
so yeah
where do we go from here
that's the question
and I don't really know the answer one
thing I would like to do is take a look
at what it did here so I might want to
just say let's step in here and see
okay
so it didn't unroll the loop
it did not unroll the loop
I'm just looking at the assembly here
and seeing what I think
because it looks like it goes ahead and
does this jump jumping or he does the
code right here right
so some of these also I don't know if
unaligned moves will hurt us at all
there you know some of these things we
can force the alignment of and I'm not
sure what we want to do about that
exactly
you
you know but mostly it seems reasonable
right I mean so I'm not yeah I don't
really see much to do here that's yeah
it all seems pretty reasonable I mean
one thing that's true
I guess I don't really know is should we
try to simplify the loop for the
compiler a little bit you know and I
don't know because like you know looking
at the speed of the routine and just
wondering like do we want to do stuff
like just say look you can always do
this you know you don't have to you
don't have to do these you know those
are early out conditions but if they
make it worse for you you know don't do
them and and I don't know right it
doesn't look like there's a particularly
big difference between those two like
one thing you could say is it looks like
they are kind of superfluous right like
so those are not maybe necessary in the
first place so we can kind of simplify
that a little bit we could even get rid
of this one as well so you know a lot of
these if statements aren't really
necessary so you can see that that one
does make a difference so having that
branch be tested is good this is I guess
enough work right that if you early out
on it you get a win get a good good win
there
but you know maybe these aren't and we
might we might want to check to make
sure that's true like we might have to
measure it really carefully to see if
that's true
because we're not really testing this
very sensitive here but it looks like
for example these are just not necessary
because maybe the number instructions
that are done here just isn't
significant compared to the overhead of
doing like the move masks and stuff like
that so you know there's that so the
rate value here that we're selecting
also this is not necessary to do every
time so one other thing we might want to
consider is just moving this out so for
example this value here because we kind
of did this before right we can just say
like alright just compute this
based on the Delta value that we do
outside right so we could avoid doing
the select on that which might be nice
by saying
all right compute the Delta by taking
the results oops not result tear a and
then just compute it here so you know go
ahead and write go ahead and and produce
that hit value on the outside so you
don't have to do it every time you know
that's probably a little bit of a win
probably not significant but it's a
little bit of something maybe you know
it's also something that we could just
do outside right it doesn't have to be
done here at all
it can be done in the returning code and
we because we don't really have to
update that value so you know out here
in this when we get the stuff back we
could do something more like that in
fact we don't even need to do the Select
right the Select is superfluous we can
just do that
and then go back to doing what we used
to do which is store the T ray in the
actual thing that we return you know so
then we've got the Ray origin and we've
got the Ray direction which is this and
that should produce the landing point
properly for us on the outside so then
really the result T ray just becomes an
actual thing and off we go
and that is certainly nee be called T
ray anymore either cause it be called T
whatever so yeah so we can again we can
just kind of fuss with that a little bit
do those computations on the outside
they don't really seem to help or hurt
us much though they they seem to be kind
of largely irrelevant so it's probably
not really worth looking at that much
but that is that right so and this of
course we still don't really know if we
care about it or not
yeah it seems like we're pretty much a
Issa as these guys jump around we
probably want to produce some kind of a
lighting test if we're gonna optimize
this further where we can produce a
reliable like you know environment where
there isn't anything moving so you know
if we were to do that so I can take like
the snake and not add the snake then
nothing is moving so you know the speed
of the computation is not dependent on
on anything because no box values are
changing so all right so couple things
here
so if we wanted to it looks like we
could probably do this code more cleanly
as well you know we could do this stuff
in Cindy if we wanted to and in fact
there's a lot of stuff here that we
could start to improve it's kind of hard
to say but you know just looking at it
I do think quite a bit of this stuff we
could we could make a lot better than it
is right so I don't know how much this
is affecting it currently and I don't
know so you know we could drop we could
first of all pull sample Hemisphere hand
in here we could make this loop just be
completely welded together as well and I
don't know to what degree we want to do
that but you know we certainly could so
for example if we took sample Hemisphere
and we just brought that directly in in
fact what I could do is finalize this
sample Hemisphere so that sample
Hemisphere is
is properly Cindy as well weld that in
here drop the raycast in and then clean
this up and the whole thing could run in
Cindy I just don't know if it like based
on what we're seeing profile wise you
don't know that that really helps us all
that much but you know we'll see I want
to take accumulate sample and move that
down for starters I think because I
never really liked it being outside
anyway we only did it that way because
we didn't previously integrate skylight
sampling in but we do now so I'd rather
have a way of saying okay let's let's
actually make this do something
reasonable so here's accumulate sample
and it's passing you know sample point
index here for desk sample index so we
can just replace death sample index
everywhere we see it with sample point
index solution is solution so transfer
PPS is the actual light color so in here
where we take the light color that would
be matte and then we have our normal to
light so I can just make that be normal
to light and then this accumulates the
sample right
so that's just the yeah building that
code in there and similarly you know
this again also could be done you know
just looking at this this sub razor to
force so I'm just looking at can this
whole thing collapsed Cindy fairly
easily and I think it you know pretty
easily can the confusing part is the
fact that we've got a different number
of surface point index loops to do and
that's why I saying like one thing we
might want to do is just say that that
cubes always have a fixed number because
that would help us as well in terms of
getting less indirection happening in
that loop so maybe we just say hey look
we're gonna fix the number of sample
points per side to just be for always or
eight always or something like this and
I don't know if that's smart or not
because we may want to do something like
well it's it's not always the same
number per surface because we don't want
to sample the undersides of things as
much as we sample the tops because you
could see the tops you can't see the
undersides right so in terms of have the
lighting is sampled it really does seem
like we would want to have a different
number per per surface area so that's
kind of a tough kind of a tough part of
it what are you gonna do to see how we
want to how we want to proceed on that
so okay so sample Hemisphere let's go
ahead and Cindy eyes that while we're at
it just for fun so in order to do that
what I need to do here is just make it
so that we create these all at the same
time so I want to start out by
replicating the basis vector and then I
just want to do an ad at the end I guess
seems like it I'm not sure that's really
the most efficient way to do this so I
think if there's some smarter thing to
do there
I mean really I guess we want to just
have a normalizer zero function that
works across all of them which wouldn't
be that hard to do so if you take a look
at what normalizer zero does and really
normalize your zero is kind of iffy here
we don't really want to do normalizer
zero we always want to have in a valid
ray we don't ever really want a result
of zero so normalizer zero is kind of
dumb to begin with and it's there just
to prevent us from actually doing it
divide by zero but tired but it's
unclear that we wouldn't rather just
check for zero and then not cast that
ray like replaced that ray with a better
ray right
so let's take a look at this oops if I
wanted
I could say replicate the basis value
out to everything right so we start with
the replicated version and then what we
want to do is make a version of this
caught this thing right here that just
computes the value directly and also
does this part directly so it would say
you know okay then result plus equals
this or rather equals so you can do it
like this right so we do take the basis
vector replicated out to all four lanes
and then what we'd want to do is take
separate randoms for each of these I
don't actually know why we're there we
want every off on our number of closes
closures here one closure to the sbr so
the next thing we want to do is be able
to take different randoms for each one
of these so we really want something
that creates you know four different
random vectors and then it does the rest
Sindhi wide right but we really do we in
fact what we really would like is
something that could actually do a
random a wide random so that we don't
have to keep calling random bilateral
every time right so we'd really like
something that just was a wide random
number generator that just generated us
for packed random floats at the same
time because there's not a lot of reason
not to have it do that right so really
what we like is something more like oops
f-22 Forex or before I should say really
what I'd like here is something where we
did v3 for X you know Delta e and Delta
x equals random f/32 for X you know I'm
saying what I'd like is something that
does this so that I can generate random
values into here and generate them all
at once so not to keep like calling and
stuffing in that way which is you know
which is annoying so if I did something
like this you know we can make this be a
temporary thing and then eventually
replace it with a real one later then
what I can do is say okay do exactly
this function that we've got here do
that and then do this and that can all
be done wide right so we can write an
inner product function that operates
wide we can do a normalize function that
operates wide and then the other
operations in there we already have so
that would be the wide version of that
I'm going to get rid of the sample table
bit probably at the moment well I don't
know we can leave that in there for now
suppose case you want to fork that as
well so then really the only part that's
a little bit weird is the fact that we
do one vector first as the basis
but I'm not sure there's really any
other way to do it because you're gonna
have to you want to start with the same
value for each of the four vectors so I
think that's just how that has to work
so if we were going to expand out on
that now it's not what I wanted
oh yes it is and probably this can just
become random bilateral and it takes a
4x series in fact we could just make
such a thing because this is all we use
it for so it's kind of annoying because
one of our things doesn't actually want
that one of our things wants to use it
separately so yeah not to think about
that code a little bit maybe there's a
way to more cleverly do that so it's in
the eyes Bowl I mean maybe you just
generate them and then you know do the
normalization by pulling them out of the
red I don't man and it doesn't doesn't
seem great
to be completely honest with you but so
let's go ahead and pretend we know what
we're doing here and this for now will
not do any such thing it will just call
the thing four times like like just a
dumb routine would know you know no
actual optimizing there no no attempting
to make it any better than it was so we
do need the random series to come before
the sim D
and I'm not sure that must be done in in
our platform go do is a Cindy in here
now where is the hand made some use in
the napkin I don't know where that
actually is concluded oh it's in shared
now I could actually just put that stuff
inside handmade random instead so you
know maybe that's a better way to do it
I'm not sure probably not but it's hard
to say so here we go we've got a bunch
of stuff that's wait what do we really
not have a replicate for the v3 4x I
thought we did though it's called 2 V 3
for X not anymore so now we need these
actual functions because we don't
actually have them and then I have to
deal with this part so basically you
know what based on that - that sort of
tells me that I do really not want to
have to deal with the with pulling this
having pulled this out here so what I
can do is inside handmade random I can
make I can make this a courage down here
so now all I really need to do is
implement the functions we don't have so
if I go into him its MD now I can add
these functions that we need so
normalizer 0 is 1
and the other one that we need is the
inner product
oops
and so these are going to depend on some
stuff as well they're going to depend on
having a square root so we'll see that
in a second we'll have to add that but
otherwise we should be fine so we want
to do here for the inner product this is
pretty straightforward we know all about
the inner product we've done it many
many times so that's just going to be
taking the components of these and
multiplying together right so you've got
a dot x times B dot X plus a dot y times
B dot y plus a dot z times B dot Z and
then we're just gonna return the result
so again it's exactly the same so you
know if we go over and look at the math
function if we take a look at our inner
product call here it's it's the same
call it's the same code it's just doing
it for wide and if we take a look at
normalizer zero the same thing would be
true except now you can see where this
is gonna get a little bit Squinkie or if
we come down in here where we're
returning a v3 for x you can immediately
see where the problem arises and that is
that although we can do this pretty
easily length squared obviously is just
exactly the same as would be
same exact code the problem that we're
gonna have here is this is a conditional
and we don't want conditionals and
there's that square root that I was
mentioning before but it's okay again
because we know that we can actually
turn this into a mask and then only
update based on the mask right so what
we're gonna do is we're just gonna do a
select bulk here
from results mask and then you know the
actual normalized value so what you can
see here is we're just gonna do take the
length we're gonna compute the actual
normalized version and then we're gonna
do the mask based on Jimmy we're gonna
do the mask based on whether or not it
passes the conditional and if it does
vests conditional then we will use the
result otherwise we watch so that
normalizes all four at once and only
actually updates the ones that that
weren't too low to use now the square
root value again is gonna we're gonna
have to have a square root because we
don't have one right now so that has to
actually get updated and you can see
this as an inverse square root so we
actually have the option of doing an
inverse square root but we don't
probably want to and let me talk about
that a little bit here we've covered
this before it's worth mentioning again
so here's a reciprocal square root
that's one over the square root and I'm
gonna pull up another copy of the Intel
and turns this guide here like so and
then I'm going to show you the actual
square root okay so what you can see
here is that the reciprocal square root
is like way faster than the regular
square root function
so you know even if you're talking about
a particularly fast CPU here it's like
three times slower to do these
then-then-then to do the reciprocal
right so doing a regular square root
cost three cycles at doing a reciprocal
square costs only one and you already
get the reciprocal so not only do I have
to spend the three cycles even on the
fastest possible case but I also have to
do a div afterwards to do one over right
and that's another three cycles so I'm
talking about six cycles worst case and
that's the throughput not the latency so
best case scenario I've got other things
in the pipeline it takes me six cycles
whereas here it's only gonna take me one
cycle throughput so you can see that it
really is very beneficial to use triple
tour through it the problem is it's not
right the reciprocal actually doesn't
give you the real reciprocal square root
it gives you an approximation to it and
it tells you the relative error here for
the approximation 1.5 times to the
negative 12 right I so the question is
can you use that reliably or not to
normalize the value or is the thing that
you're using going to be wildly
inaccurate when you try to normalize it
and it turns out that it's not actually
normalized right so it's hard to say
it's really hard to say and in a lot of
cases you probably need to be able to
determine which one you actually want in
our case I think I'm gonna say we can
use an approximation when here and what
I want to do is call this a procs
normalizer zero and the reason I'm going
to use the approximant is because I feel
like in the case that we're using it now
we don't care for a little bit off
sometimes we would for this we don't for
raycasting we
care at all it doesn't even need to be
normalized our rape test would work
whether it was normal or not so the only
case we actually care if it's normalized
is actually at the end where we're we're
we're doing the dot product to find out
how the lighting fall-off works that's
the only place where the error could
actually accrue so I think we're okay
using the approximate value here so
that's why I'm doing it that way
so to do an approximate square root what
I need to do is I need to do the divide
here's the one value and then I want to
divide by the approximate square root or
rather multiplied by the approximate
inverse square root of the length
squared and that's you know the whole
shebang so that's really all we're
talking about here so the only thing we
need is that approximate inverse square
root value because we don't actually
have one of those for our four-wide we
don't actually have one of those for
anything really we've never written that
before but to do an approximate in risk
square root again it's very simple
because it's already in there it's
already in the chip so we don't do any
work we just ask the chip to do it for
us right so looking back here you got
our square PS all we do is pass in the
value and out it pops cubes so that's
really all we're talking about here
right pretty basic now the thing is I
believe
I don't remember if there's a refinement
call in here I don't think there is I
think you just refine it yourself if you
want to so I don't remember if there's a
refinement call but let me explain what
that is and then I'll explain why I
don't think we care in this particular
instance but so sometimes what happens
is if you do approximate computations
those approximate computations can be
followed by fix-up which will improve
their accuracy and sometimes you want to
do it if you care about getting the
lecture so is this cheap enough that you
just do it I I don't think there's any
refinement to be done here I think you
can do refinement yourself I don't know
if there's any point to it so I'm just
going to skip that part of it and we'll
just use the approximate in risk square
root here anyway
all right so taking a look here what we
want to do is push this those are that's
a scalar so we want to smush those
scalars first and then multiply by the
vector cannot convert - that's a good
point and there we go alright so taking
a look here we don't have this anymore
we only have the aprox normalizer zero
and then the inner product here is
result an N n is not load opt up so we
need that to be bigger right we need
that to be replicated so we can do the
wide product so
and we need the inner product here
what's gonna produce a float again -
this is this is just zero and off we go
so again this is also a mask situation
so this is just going to be a a mask and
then we need to select based on the mask
and now we're wide
so yeah in theory if we didn't mess
anything up that's the sample hemisphere
function right and it's pretty
straightforward and now it's operating
in Cindy instead of what it was doing
before which is not operating in Cindy
again we want us we want to go through
this after we're kind of done with it
and and do some checking to make sure
that we're still doing reasonable stuff
everywhere we never really checked it in
the first place so we would like to do
that eventually so the last thing I'll
do is I'll just drop this down into and
you know what I don't really care about
this anymore we'll put the sample table
back in will write it new because it
would ask me new anyway so I'm gonna get
rid of the sample hemisphere function
here and I'm just gonna go ahead and
drop that in so that we can see it in
place which is right here and what I'd
like to do there is yeah just go ahead
and take this value here like so and so
narrow we've got these here we're not
using the x axis and the y x at the
moment we're only using the sample point
and so what I can do is I can just load
that up here and leave that be it's
never gonna change doesn't it doesn't
change in the loop because the sample
point is the sample point it's normal
it's never different so when we actually
do this hit check here we can do sample
point in like so and I think that's
that's it
I agree and so this Delta and that tilta
hardened out the same Delta anymore I
can actually get rid of this anyway get
down there and so that seems fine
and again so now we're just like further
welding that routine and I think we're
now in pretty good shape 70 wives right
so we're now running our lighting at
actually well above 30 frames a second
so that's pretty nice right whereas
before we were running at it maybe 15
frames a second and we're actually
closing in on 60 frames a second
lighting CPU side right not using any
GPU for that at all uh so I think you
know that's that that this could work
out you know maybe we'll just leave the
lighting on the CPU and just leave it
that way for the foreseeable future and
if someday we want to convert it to GPU
afterwards cuz you know once once we if
we have something that works we can
develop the rest of the game with it
right and then we can always come back
and decide to do a GPU version later if
we decide that that's what we needed
right so I think we're we're okay with
that I'm gonna go ahead and go to Q&amp;A
and yeah if anyone has any questions
about what we did
off we go and I saw someone asking about
how much CPU it takes to do so if we
take a look here at the CPU cost here's
how much CPU we're taking and you can
see if we go to the profile so so
actually the frame display is taking
quite a bit of time there
so actually yeah
you can see we finished you know the
lighting gets finished actually pretty
quick
it doesn't even yeah it's not even
pushing that limit yet so we could we
can we're within earshot of 16 I think
actually just looking at this we need a
framerate counter that will we need to
put in a frame encounter that will work
if we turn off profiling and stuff like
that right because for all I know we
actually are running at 60 frames a
second if we turn off all the rest of
this stuff so if we went you know full
bore I don't know how much overhead
there is at the moment with other stuff
because we don't have a like once we
turn everything off we don't get a
framerate counter you need like a low
overhead very simplistic framerate
counter so we just know what our frame
rate is when we were in full bore mode
like a frame rate counter that could
ship with the game so users could check
their frame rate that kind of a frame
rate counter not one that relies on our
debug system doing all kinds of weird
stuff excuse me
but anyway yeah like you know we
definitely need to reduce a little more
flicker but it's it's pretty cool this
is getting pretty cool in my opinion and
the other thing I guess we should
remember is that the flicker is worse
the worst flicker will be when there's
the least lights in the scene so a
single light moving around illuminating
the whole scene is actually the worst
possible case for flicker so you know
there's that
what version control system do you use
so i on the for this the version control
system is actually github because people
who peer to the game get like access to
the github they people wanted that so it
checks into github every day after we
finish but that's only for this project
on my own personal projects i have a
custom version control system that i
wrote and that's what i use obviously
don't use github my development machines
are not connected to the internet so nee
lasts a question he well wasn't really a
question it was a request he asked if we
could look at the profile and yes we can
I guess if we don't have handmade slow
on we won't get a debug still have to
turn handmade slow on as well well I oh
no I won't so okay I can I can take a
look at at this with using that so if I
put the thread view on what do you want
to know was if we drop the rake
countdown what happens here profile wise
thread you know thread wise so you know
here's what it looks like
let me go ahead and inside the lending
code drop the breakout down to four we
got it
so dropping the Ray count down to four
so yeah I think it's just we're miss
we're just missing the 16 frames a
second there I guess is what's happening
so the frame with like you know if we
turn vsync off I guess is what I'm
saying so let's suppose we turn vsync
off I suppose we would see what would
happen there
so here's the swap owner of a call if I
was to change that to zero so that we
just lets it swap immediately you know
that would I suppose tell us what was
going on there I don't know maybe it
wouldn't
you know that's just kind of weird so it
looks like
I don't know why that's not showing all
of our frames there that's weird
I'm not sure why
I'm not sure why that's happening it
does it looks like just the rendering
actually takes that time I mean that's
just the slowness of sampling the
lighting I guess yeah I mean look so
we're running at 16 under 16
milliseconds if we just don't draw if we
just don't draw the world we're running
it the lighting just fine right
so if you take a look at that profile
you know we're a ok so it looks like the
problem comes when you actually need to
render you know what it's actually
sampling the lighting that that pixel
shader I guess is just too slow which is
fine because we could speed that thing
up that's not going to be a huge issue
to make that thing faster
there's tons stuff we can do for that so
yeah I don't know like if we want to
check out the actual slowness per ray I
guess you just crank the ray count up
and get rid of the drawing you know so
you know then then we can actually see
you know that's should be dominated
entirely you know by the light
computation time
so yeah
nice PC you cast the input value in the
youth reach Forex letter to a float why
is that
that's just C syntax for forcing it not
to a adult or the value so if you take a
look at what's going on here you're
passing in au 32 but there is no set
call that sets a sim D register to a u
32 this is purely because Intel's
intrinsics are kind of dumb the
processor doesn't care the processor is
going to load bits in so the unfortunate
part is Intel just didn't decide to do
the intrinsics right so they have mm set
and you can see the set of calls here
that you use and what you'll notice is
for for things that are going to use an
m1 28 why do I not see the PS calls here
where are the set calls there we go I
didn't have sse one checked that's all
so if you look at all the values that
are if you look at all the things that
are available here right you can see the
options that you have and what you'll
notice is that if you look at the
intrinsics you've got for producing an
EM 128 which is the floating point type
in the C compiler you can see that
you've got like set R which sets them in
the reverse order you've got set 1 which
sets them in the forward order and so on
but they all take floats now there is a
call which takes integers so if you want
to load it and you could here it is
right set 1 epi32 now that's call we'd
like to make pass an integer the
unfortunate part is it returns a
different type it returns an M 128 I so
in order to actually put that into our M
128 these are the same concept to the
CPU they're both just the register but
what ends up happening is we would have
to call a cast instruction so we then
need to do a cast to convert our I so
you can see here convert our I value to
a ray right it's purely C type nonsense
right so when I did instead is I just
said hey look pretend the bits I'm
giving you a float they're not but
pretend they are mister compiler and
please load them and then it will so
that's what this is doing it's just you
know basically telling it to reinterpret
this if you use like C++ style casting
you can use an actual cast declaration
for that you know like reinterpret cast
and static cast those kinds if you use
those but I don't care for those we just
introduce complexity that doesn't
actually do anything how does a the mask
replace an if in the Simbi instructions
so it replaces an like this we've gone
over this before so you can actually
search for this in the hand made hero
episode archive if you want but it's
pretty quick to explain so I'll just
tell you
so the way that sim D works and the
reason I didn't go over this for this
because we've gone over it multiple
times before so you can go back and read
this if you want so we've got lane zero
lane one lane two in lane three okay so
normally you have something like a float
which we call an f32 and handmade here
oh that's 32 bits and this represents
one value like 2.3 F right or something
well in a Sindhi register we've got four
of them so we've got four floating point
values each of them at 32 bits right so
we've got 32 32 32 32 so in toto we have
128 bits in one register that packs for
flows together for 0.32 point one nine
point zero
eleven point seven I don't know right so
he's got some floats in here
these are floating point values now what
happens inside a normal processing
operation when we were using conditional
branches is we say something like okay x
equals two point three F but if
something happens right then you know x
equals four point seven instead so that
would be fine but once we go Cindy we
can't do a conditional branch because
what this was doing in the code was it
was literally skipping this instruction
it was telling you the processor to just
jump right over it well since this if
conditional will evaluate potentially
differently for all four lanes we can't
skip the assignment because if we did
the ones that were true wouldn't happen
and the ones that were false so all the
lanes that were false would end up at
the right value all the lanes that were
true wouldn't up the wrong values the
end so what we do instead as we produce
a mask that is the result of this
conditional slotted into lanes
and what that mask has is it just has
exactly the same thing 128 bits and it
just has ones for all the true values
and zeros for all of the false values
right so if the conditional would have
evaluated to true on a particular Lane
that Lane gets ones all ones and if the
conditioner would have have evaluated to
false gets all zeros and hey this
instruction set was designed together so
as you would expect the conditional
instructions in sse actually produce
this exact mask so we don't have to do
any work to make it would we just do a
comp less than or whatever we get a mask
out of it so then what we have to do is
just bitwise operations to produce the
result we wanted we want a result here
right and we want to take two things
like let's say we were doing exactly
this right so we want to take two things
where we had some other values here you
know we've got four point seven that was
supposed to be set so we have an input
value and we have like our new value
here four by seven four seven right and
all we're gonna do is we're just going
to do an operation a bitwise operation
to produce a result so that we get this
value in the case of the false and this
value in the case of the true well what
would that be it's pretty
straightforward right all we have to do
is or these two things together after
ending each respective one with the mask
value in the correct way so to preserve
values in the input we would want to end
with the opposite of the mask because if
the mass was one we want to take the new
value so we want to knock out all of the
values here where there are ones in the
mask so that's why we did an and not on
the input on the first value we call
this value a and that pertain for the
new value we just want to add with the
mask directly because wherever its zeros
we want to knock out wherever it's once
we want to keep so we just do a regular
and with the master the new then we
order those two together and only
one of them has survived because one got
him and and one got a man not so only
one of these two values didn't get
cleared to zero so then we just order
the bits together and we get whichever
one of them wasn't in the result and
that happens for every Lane separately
right so that's how we do a conditional
essentially what we do is we run both
sets of code the if and the else right
we run both sets of code and we just
keep whichever part we want based on the
mask value and like I said we went over
this and a lot more value back a lot
more detail back when we talked about
Cindy originally so if you want kind of
a slower walk through you can get it but
the idea is just to use that mask so you
just say you know the result always is
equal to a and not mask or B and mask
right now this is a fundamental Cindy
operation it's usually called select at
least that's what I usually call it and
you may ask why isn't that just in there
the answer is because the ternary
operation it requires an A a B and a
mask and SSC doesn't have ternary
operations really uh so what ended up
happening was it just wasn't in here at
that but it does eventually come in
later here
I don't remember where it is
now do you remember what it's called
I I never use it because it was like
sse4 or something which I don't use soon
I think the installed base will
basically always have it so I may start
using it but I'm sorry I just I I'm
blanking on the name of it but it's
there
it's there somewhere
I thought it was there somewhere
here's someone suggesting a better one
which is an XOR of the end and the XOR I
don't know that's actually true but
that's not what I want to know I just
want to know where that SSE select was
I think Fabien wet
wait I totally spelled his name wrong
there had it on his reference didn't I
seem to remember it being in here I'm
just trying to think of some code that
I've seen that had it in there so I
could look
I feel like this heaven in there
somewhere
I must be wrong about that
I blend blend that's what they called it
that's what I'm thinking
or not
oh come I can't get that
P blend VB it's in there
Oh cuz fit manipulation was set
oops sorry about that so yeah so as you
can see the subset we return here and
have it sse3 doesn't have it here does
that but once you get up to sse4 you've
got blend instructions so you've got
blend V and that's the the phrase I
couldn't think of its blend I don't
think of it as blend I think of it
select but you know whatever you know
call call it whatever you want so this
is instruction which I never really get
to use but which does what you want this
is actually the instruction in question
you know that's how it works and I'm not
sure exactly how it knows what the mask
value is because true ternary
instructions I thought were only added
in avx-512 so I don't actually know how
people end VB knows this I guess I've
never used this instruction so if we
look at the actual intel architecture
manual
this is probably everything hello
all right so if we take a look at the
Intel architecture manual we should be
able to find you know essentially what
what that instruction actually does and
how it does it again for those of you or
maybe I'm familiar with this so it's
fret to set architectures obviously have
concepts of how their structures are
laid out and if you have instructions
that generally can take two registers
those are binary instructions if you
have instruction take three registers
those are ternary instructions and two
in order to say mask a and select from a
and B using masks see that requires
three instructs three registers which is
ternary so the question is how is it
doing it because I don't think they had
true ternary instruction encoding in SSE
for now maybe we'll find out that they
did and that will be the answer but if
that's not the answer then what has to
be true is that like oh it's a secret
way that it works like you always have
to have the mask stored in X M m0 and so
we always use that register as a mask
isn't right um so I'm just curious to
find out that's why I'm looking this up
yeah that's not gonna happen
all right
so here's the until architects remember
manual we know we are looking for the
documentation on people and V and so
where is why am I not seeing any
highlights now forget it I'm just gonna
go look at it directly so we know it's P
so it's gonna be in here so let's just
go grab people and V so please here's
people in V P blend V be uh
and hey it looks like I guessed
correctly so the answer is it just knows
secretly that XM m0 is the mask so it
take it's still a binary instruction it
takes XM m 1 and X mmm - so you can pick
a and B but the mask has to be stored in
register 0 which means that the compiler
has like a constraint on where it can
output that so it's register constrained
there where every select operation will
be fighting over X m m0 is the place to
store the masks and you know hopefully
that's not a big deal because usually
you're masking you're kind of using the
mask as you go and so it won't be a huge
deal but you know that's how that works
I so yeah there's there's your answer
I guess right simply because I kind of
knew that they didn't add Turner
instructions to later so I kind of
guessed they had to use a fixed register
and so I could have guessed 15 or I
could have guessed zero I guess zero
because I thought it probably was more
likely than use zero then the dead then
use the bottom than the top but that was
a purely wild guess so I just got lucky
on that one
so there you go so what you can see here
as well so let's take a look down here
so what you can see is this one starts
so once once you get up to
AVX there's it looks like they actually
do have turn areas here so it looks like
maybe you don't have to wait for avx-512
you can actually have the fat looks like
a ternary to me right xmm one two three
and four select byte values from XM 2 +
XM m 3 using masks specified in x + 4
and store into XM m 1 so that's actually
a quaternary instruction if that's
really the case I didn't realize they
had it quaternary instructions again I
don't ever get to program these
instruction sets I never get to use a
vxr8 VIX - someday soon I will you know
it's you'll be able to ship games on a
VX soon I would think you don't know
where we're at on that
so I guess I don't know where to get
that data oh here we go we can see items
here so so maybe one of these has it
here we go here we go here we go uh so
it looks like you know sse3 is becoming
a really safe bet right doesn't look
like anyone in the recent times was
coming on Steam with those sse4 looking
pretty good so I could probably start
using that blend v instruction and not
really worry about it right
AVX you know looking pretty good at
ninety percent not too bad uh I don't
know about avx2 cuz they're not showing
it here so I'm not sure how to know that
one but AVX is looking kind of good
right like I could imagine saying all
right let's just go EDX go eight wide
why not right if everyone's got it then
there's no reason not to go eight wide
and that would double our Ray count if
we went eight wide right so that would
be kind of nice too I'm surprised to see
that number that high I'm a little
concerned that maybe that's not very
accurate but who knows maybe people are
updating their machines so I so yeah you
know it looks like sse4 is definitely on
the table it's getting down to the noise
it looks like there so I don't know just
something think about
and - thank you - Fabien for using that
blend construction and so we could
remember what it's called
that's cool but why does the light
flicker even when the cube is not moving
it's because of the sampling right we're
using randomized sampling so every frame
we get different results back from the
sampling right could we ship with this
before yes I we might be able to you
know maybe we should change this to a
Texas you know what can you see in task
managers GP YouTube I didn't know there
was a GPU tab and task manager when did
they add that do you just mean do you
mean this column or is that do you mean
that or
I don't know if I can I don't know that
I can expand on that like I don't know
that does it have a oh I didn't even
know it had one of these that's cool
I mean they're not not much surprising
here right
and I assumed that if we just get rid of
the rendering right you can see that we
no longer max out the GPU
Jimmy tips on talking with
non-programmers about programming
related concepts no I don't think so
- you bought T how does your profiler
work does it hook into the compiler no
it just times the code using RT TSE
could we compile 1xe with sse4 that
falls back to see - if it's not present
on the cpu or would we need to compile
into several exceeds no we could do that
the way you would do that is you just
come you know you have two routines you
have the SC for one in the SVC to write
to one and you just at the beginning you
patch a pointer that points to the right
routine based on your check of the CPU I
don't know what the best way to do that
nowadays is one way to do it would be to
just call the SC for a routine if it
doesn't fault call the SSC too routine
but not sure if that's really the best
way you might didn't you want to check
the CPU ID instead if yeah it's hard to
say
all right let's close up shop for today
Thank You Evan for joining me for them
sewed a handmade here it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along series at
home you can always peer to the game on
handmade hero organic comes the source
code so you can play around with it
yourself I'm see I guess this is it
until next week so we'll be back here
next weekend when we will clean up the
lighting some more and maybe take a look
at some sampling options that we have to
reduce the flickering a little bit and
the other thing we should probably do
now because it's about time that we did
that since we're running at 30 frames a
second at least is to actually do a
little bit of world gem that will use
the lighting and just kind of get the
whole pipeline going so we've got kind
of a little world set up that's that's
actually you know it's big enough and
has lighting on on the trees and stuff
as well like you know get get to the
point where we actually are using it for
real so we can optimize in the real
scenario from here on out so we'll start
that next week until then have fun
program everyone and I'll see you on the
Internet take it easy everybody