hello everybody and welcome to hand made
here sure we code a complete game live
on stream we are going to probably move
up a level in complexity with our
lighting today so what we have done and
I guess I should go ahead and run it
here to bring everyone up to speed on
where we are we did a simple test of the
Ray casting and used it for debugging
and what we have running now as you can
see is an example where you can move a
light through the environment and it
will do a fairly perfect radial
interpolation on services that it does
hit and then a simple like you know
binary like on/off kind of thing
for shadowing which again is not
something we actually wanted you know we
don't actually want to use that effect
in the lighting it's not something I'm
going for but this was basically a test
to ensure that we could get reliable ray
casting results and it seems like we've
done that pretty well so I feel like
we're in a you know and a good we're in
a good place right now in terms of
feeling confident that our ray caster
isn't completely broken and it's also
running plenty fast enough at the moment
this is not even multi-threaded right
now this is entirely single threaded
that that's running which is kind of
great and it appears to be running nice
and nice and 60-ish so basically we're
in a good position now to say let's take
the next jump up and start trying to do
the lighting a little bit more
realistically this is again also
computing the lighting every frame
rather than using an average over a few
frames which we'd like to do and so what
we want to do now is sort of start to
move towards that more complex more
complete solution and we have you know
sort of three things we want to do two
of them I think aren't so hard one of
them is potentially hard so the three
things that we want to do number one we
want to start averaging across frames we
set ourselves up to do this so that is
really just a matter of debugging
we've already pretty much figured out
how that will work and we know what we
want to do there namely our voxel is
already set up to
able to save across runs and we will
just save the voxel and average it in
the only thing that will be tricky about
that is making sure that the voxel
copies itself to the correct location
during center of simulation jumps so we
have to do that particular piece of the
code but that's the only thing that we
really need to do to get the averaging
working so we want to do that that's
number one and we might just do that
right off the bat that may be the four
because we can do that even with this
right we could take this solution here
and just smooth it over time and we
would see like a some lag on that shadow
right and a smoother like a gradual lag
on that shadow or something right and so
you can imagine that that averaging step
is something that's pretty easy to do
and we could totally do that the next
thing that we have is we've got to do
indirect bounce real indirect bounce and
convection that's a little more
complicated again but nothing tricky we
already have the Ray caster we already
have a way to sample from voxels so we
kind of know exactly what we're writing
there again it's not particularly tricky
it's just gonna be a piece of code that
says look when you hit a particular
piece of the geometry you're gonna want
to look up in the voxel what the
lighting is there and and put it back
right and the final thing that we need
to do is the one that's really
complicated and it affects both of these
things which is that if we just do a
basic addition into our lighting voxel I
don't think we're gonna get very good
results we would like I mean maybe we'll
get okay results but I think we can do a
lot better than that because basically
our voxel allows us at 60 frames a
second quite easily as we've determined
to interpolate quite a bit of
information and so the other thing that
we need to kind of solve and this is the
one that's that's a much harder problem
and a much more broad I think is how do
we best store and update this lighting
information because we have a will have
a fantastic amount of information coming
into the system basically an
embarrassment of riches in a sense we
will have
between four - like shouldn't say
between four eight twelve or sixteen
depending on what we can get away with
in terms of speed new ray casts coming
in at each voxel right or at each light
probe and then spread out to voxels
let's see how we want to do it we will
have the previous frames complete
information and we will then need to
decide how we want to combine those
results to create the new lighting for
the the subsequent frame and while we
know some basic things about it like
okay we can obviously mix these together
with a simple linear blend that updates
it over time or whatever else right we
we we don't have to think very hard
about how to blend values necessarily
but what we don't know is how are we
storing these and how are we
distributing them about the voxel and
then reconstructing them what we've got
in there right now is essentially like
four light fields with a normal and an
intensity / light field basically right
and we know that that's something that
can interpolate one light exactly right
we can do a very good job interpolating
a single light source exactly we proved
that by having a perfectly spherical
fall off that reconstructed exactly even
though our voxel is not even close to
the resolution that would be necessary
to do that
so we proved that that field
reconstructs exactly per pixel even
though we're not storing it anywhere
close to per pixel but the question is
once we introduce sort of a rich
lighting environment where light is
coming from everywhere the floor the
ceiling the walls right it's bouncing
around what is the actual fundamental
way that we combine these values right
and so that's the part that I feel like
we don't really know or at least I don't
really know and so that's the part that
I'm not sure what to do about and so
when we look at what we're doing going
forward I think those first two things I
listed are just a case of rolling up our
sleeves and implementing them there
isn't a lot of mystery there we know
what we're doing and we have basic
solutions in place
just need to be like wired up and
debugged and improved right and that's a
good place to be but well we
fundamentally don't know is a whether or
not what we've got right now for the
voxel is the right thing to do right
because there's other wait you know we
could we've we basically know our voxel
is a way of storing literally eight four
element things for reconstruction so we
know we have a lot of power there we
just don't know what to do with it and
so we may find that like okay we need to
fall back and do something like
spherical harmonics or something like
this because it turns out that there's
really no way to update for light fields
in in a coherent way and you need
something else to do it maybe we need to
just figure out like how it's feeding
time for the puss you coming for food
plus the puss is unsure she's kind of
she's kind of hopping over into the food
bowl she's looking around and so we
don't really know and and that's really
it's unknown things are the kinds of
things that that usually take the
longest because they take some
exploration to figure out so that's the
complete picture for what we're doing
this weekend and who knows how far we'll
get on it but like I said the first two
or maybe there was to start with because
we can we know that we can just kind of
get to work on those and produce you
know some some usable code just by like
focusing on on debugging and improving
what we already have and that's you know
might as well get that done first
because we know we can do it and then
once we have those done just focus on
like okay now that we have all the
inputs the system how do we make the
system actually work well so if we jump
over to the lighting if we go ahead and
look at this code the first thing that
you'll notice is that like that test
code we've got it in this thing that's
like where it's a test cast from probe
right so this right here so what we're
doing curious were just you know doing
literally a test piece of test code
we're casting here by clearing the voxel
then stepping through each of the light
probes in the system of which there are
many we're doing a test ray cast to the
light source
and then in addition to having some
debug code in here which were we don't
have enabled right now you can see here
that we're basically turning off the
test case but you know it's there for
when we need it for debugging I in the
case where we have not hit anything
we spread out the lighting information
that we have and call it a day now
that's not even what we would want to do
even if this is what we were trying to
do permanently we would want to spam out
to the voxel and we would want to put
like negative lighting in there if you
couldn't see this one to say that there
was a shadow coming in this direction
but again like this is not what this was
for this was not trying to reproduce
lighting accurately or interestingly it
was just trying to show us definitively
whether or not the ray casting was
properly working and we in we did have a
bunch of bugs it did its job nicely like
we were able to find our bugs in a much
faster way than if we had tried to roll
this together and been wondering whether
the lighting was working or not and you
know trying to see from kind of subtle
stuff so what we would like to move to
now is the actual lighting calculation
here in compute light propagation so
what you can see here is this is set up
for multi-threading and I guess I'm not
sure so is this how was this compute
propagation work so this okay so we
basically had this set up to see if we
wanted to be basically turn it to single
threaded is what that was doing but
anyway this right here this compute
light propagation is what we're looking
at and what the compute light
propagation is doing is it's building a
bunch of work structures those work
structures are for multi-threading the
lighting and what you can see is they
all kind of will call called down to a
workhorse routine which is this one here
which is the actual compute lighting
propagation now they should probably be
called something different so it's a
little easier to see which one is which
like this right and then if I go to
compute light propagation we should
probably have that work thusly so you
know we can see which one is which just
makes it a little bit clearer so anyway
what we want to do here is make sure
that the
these are working well and it looks like
do lighting work wait a minute so what
is going on here with with do lighting
work do lighting work as what exactly
sorry we haven't looked at this in a
while ah so this callback here yeah
there we go so anyway this I don't know
why we don't just wrap this thing up
actually like I'm not sure why this is
doing a separate call out like that that
seems unnecessary I'm gonna just take a
quick look at platform work you call
back just to see what that actually is
doing so it's just a platform work queue
and some data I don't know why it passes
the work queue exactly I don't know if
that queue is actually used hold on a
second let's see so it's not so if we
wanted to what we could do here is not
have this double call which I think
would be better so what we could do here
is just make this itself be the thing we
call like that that seems a little bit
better to me and then we would get rid
of this and here we would just cast down
so our our lighting work in this case
would just be the data getting casted
cast down right and if we did it that
way then this code right here could go
away and we wouldn't have that extra
call that you know that the compiler is
probably gonna weld that just fine but
I'm just not interested in having that
extra work there and so here instead of
calling do lighting work this will be
like compute light propagation work and
now we've we've kind of rerouted that so
anyway let me just see here oops what
that was about
I also don't know why data is
highlighted as a type there that doesn't
make a lot of sense but I guess there is
something that's data I don't know
anyway mmm so if you take a look at
what's going on here
we now have our rate caster here which
is just a thing that does ray casting
and we have our compute light
propagation work we've debugged the ray
caster compute light propagation work is
the thing that we haven't really worked
on now we used to have it working in the
old scheme and the old scheme did not do
voxel based lighting so we kind of have
to change around the way that was
working in a sense but in here we would
like to we would like to sort of start
by taking stock of this routine figuring
out what we're gonna have to do to get
it to where we want it to be and then
making those modifications so the
superstructure there change should still
be fine we're still gonna grab a work
structure right and we're still gonna
figure out which lighting probes we want
to calculate given this work structure
so when we get these light probes and
they come into the system here what
we're gonna want to do is say alright we
still want it sliced by work Pro but
that's how we're gonna distribute the
work so we still want this
superstructure to be in place now
furthermore I'm not sure - to what
extent we need to pre-filter that list
but we'll work on that later
meaning we you know right now we're
gonna like we're gonna do ray casting it
for the entire light probes and all of
the light volume we can pre-filter that
at push time so I'm just gonna assume
that we can slice the the work up pretty
much uniformly and that we won't have to
do any sort of work stealing or figuring
out that work actually didn't get need
to be done in certain places so I think
we can do this pretty straightforward
also I feel like I'm hitting the metal
on my shirt here
take this off there we go all right it
was just it was clicking on the metal
you know I'm saying I know that's
happened before us I want to make sure
it's not annoying people so if we look
at what's going on here we're gonna
cycle over the light probes and again we
already kind of have our test cast
routine you can see we were doing the
same thing here right we're cycling over
the light probe so all we're really
talking about is to be multi-threaded
we're slicing it so each thread works on
a subset of the light probes that's
that's all what's going on here much
like here we're pulling out the cast
direction by grabbing whichever light
probe it is that we're talking about
here and then what we're trying to do is
cast for rays at a time we're just gonna
cast those rays in in directions based
on our random table so what you see here
is we're not gonna actually target the
light source necessarily I mean one of
the things we might we might target the
light source with one of our ray cast
every time or something or you know
periodically we may check the light
source but since generally speaking we
won't exactly know which light sources
we even want to target or anything like
that it makes it a little bit harder so
here's what I would say about this if we
assume that we have some set of light
sources that are that are known coming
in maybe we want to loop those in here
but for the moment what we're gonna do
is ignore that part of it and instead of
having the the light sources be
specifically targeted off the bat we'll
sort of we'll probably roll that in a
little bit later or maybe we won't I
don't know we'll see maybe that's
something we'll do on on one of them I'm
not sure but what you can see here is
we're gonna compute a ray origin here
and we're gonna compute a ray direction
by saying well however many rays we want
to cast here this is actually a ray
bundle count but what we're gonna do is
we're going to grab out for Ray's to
cast and go from there now what I think
I want to do like I said is I think we
want to try targeting lights or
maybe a little bit more than we have
then and and that's just a way of saying
look we know that we've got a pushin
light caulk here where we can put lights
into the system and we want to support
an arbitrary number of light sources so
we don't want to do anything that
assumes there's only one two or three
lights we want to assume that there
could be hundreds of lights we want it
to be but what we'd like to do is say
look we want a way of targeting the
light source occasionally so what I'm
going to do is suggest that perhaps this
routine needs to be changed a little bit
and instead of calling this array index
right we're gonna call it or a bundle
index that's just true regardless and
what I would like to do is proceed here
what we're gonna do is say ray Direction
is something that will have some start
up to it
so what we'll do is we'll say at the
start right our Ray direction will
target some light sources so at the
start we'll fill it with four ray
bundles that are all designed to like go
towards light sources that we no amount
as a way of sort of introducing a little
bit of bias in the system towards
hitting a light source and then in here
what we'll do is we'll take the Ray
direction when we're sampling this and
we'll just move this to the end right
and so and I'm gonna get rid of this to
do because we're gonna take care of that
today as well so after we have done the
work on all of our Ray's right what I
want to do here is basically update this
at the end and what I'm doing there
right is I'm just changing sort of the
fundamental way that this is working by
saying okay one of the things that's
always free to do in a for loop is
update at the end instead of the
beginning and then it's free for you to
make the first run of your for loop do
something different right so in this
case we know we want to pull things out
of an array of sampling directions and
in this case what we're doing is saying
look the first time we do that instead
of pulling it out we're gonna use some
special thing that's not in that array
or something like that and that's how
we're gonna go with it so then we have
like here our sampling sphere with the
sample direction there right
and then that'll kick in later and so
what we want to do is just say the the
REA bundle count is going to be the
thing that we're using here I don't
think that's actually you know this will
not necessarily be accurate anymore
because if we have one startup one it
means we'd be skipping some in the REA
bundle but you know you get the idea so
that's something we can do very easily
and I think we probably do want to do
that and that way we can say well the
REA bundle count is actually you know
it's maybe this right but we would need
to pad that sample direction with a fake
one at the end anyway so that we didn't
fetch off the end of the array so I
think this is still probably roughly
what we would be doing I don't know
we'll see
so anyway excuse me we need to set up
all these parameters correctly and we
need to get our sampling sphere taken in
put put in as well yeah I suppose I
could do is write into the sampling
sphere itself like leave a space the
beginning and have it cast so you know I
could do that as well because I just
don't think we want to bother with that
all right so I think we're gonna leave
like this
we'll see we'll sort of work out as we
go so anyway in terms of which direction
we're going to be sampling here you can
see our Duras ample index here that's
just something that we're using to
figure out sort of a stochastic version
of the of the sphere that we're gonna
use this is so we don't always cast the
same direction every frame and kind of
averaged over a larger sphere and so
this is that look up here and then we're
gonna you know use that this the
particular sphere that we pick out among
many of our random stirs that we have
and remember we've got a thing that's
like this sampling spheres that we
generated and these are gonna have other
information that we need we're gonna
have to like update our generator
program to do exactly what we need now
but we basically have this code written
as well and we verified that that sphere
is accurate so we're you know we're in
pretty good shape with with that stuff
all right so what we're gonna do is
we're gonna go through the Ray bundles
we're going to basically raycast from
the Ray Origin ray direction here and
again we're updating that ray Direction
every
through here to a different rate bundle
we're going to go ahead and see what we
hit we're gonna compute that this way
right I don't know this is actually like
a boolean like did we hit or not so I'm
not sure why that's called t hit
necessarily but it's fine anyway so we
come through here and we go through and
do our sub raise and our sub raise here
just look to see this is this is a thing
for pushing debug lines if we want to
debug one of them we can do it this way
but at the moment we don't really need
to worry about that code so what we're
doing here is saying all right if we hit
right so this is the thing that tells us
whether or not we hit
if we hit we're gonna try and do a
lightning look up if we didn't we're
just going to go ahead and put the moon
color in there and that's all we're
gonna do and again this code probably
needs to be improved a bit to work with
some kind of notion of localized ambient
lighting you know we might so cuz we
might want to do something like that I
don't know if we actually need that or
not because in theory you should always
hit something if you cast upward you
should hit like a done unfortunately but
at the moment we don't really put
ceilings on our rooms so you can see why
we may want to it depends on how we want
to solve that problem if we always put
ceilings on our rooms then this just
always kind of works if we don't then it
doesn't so we kind of need to have some
opinion about that and if we decide that
we don't want to put ceilings on the
rooms then we need to have some notion
of localized color that basically says
like for each light probe this is what I
would want here as an ambient color
value in the case where you cast upward
and don't hit anything right so you know
basically we could pretty trivially have
it so that if you look you know if you
look at what we're pushing on there in
terms of light probe information in this
right here it would be pretty cheap for
us to just store an extra piece of
information which is basically the
emission the emission angle or something
and you know basically a vector that
points towards where the
ambient light is coming from if any and
then a color value that should be
modulated in so it would be pretty cheap
for us to just have that be a thing and
I don't know whether we want to go that
route or not but that's something we
could certainly consider so again like
so just sort of think about and we'll
decide how we want to tune that lighting
a little bit later the ambient lighting
is not super important to us right now
but when we're actually going to kind of
finalize the lighting at the very end of
this sweep we probably want to sort of
get in there and artistically think like
what do we want to have happen here now
thankfully this garbage doesn't have to
happen anymore this this update for this
way that we were updating things doesn't
really have to happen but we do need to
do some updating so let's go through and
sweep through this and feel like figure
out what we kind of want to do here so
if you look at what happens on the case
where we do get a hit you can see here
that we have a probe sample position
that probe sample position is basically
saying where is where are we actually
hitting like where did we stop and then
the normal is what was the normal on the
surface at the point where we stopped so
this is basically telling us like the
surface we hit and it's in the surface
normal so that we can compute how the
light should have been moved right we
also know what the reference color was
for that occluder and that's basically
telling us like okay what's like the
average color of the texture at that
point or something and we haven't really
set those up yet I think they're all
basically gray or something so we will
want to go in and tune those as well
but we know that they will come in here
eventually so at some point we will get
that piece of information we then also
know what the emission was on that rate
but I don't actually know why we're
doing it quite that way that doesn't
really seem like what we want because
services won't really have a mission
anymore I don't think in that way
because lights are pushed separately
from services so
so I don't really know how we want to
treat that I guess we do because when we
push in lights they need to basically be
boxes as well so I suppose we do need to
do that the only question is why the
sample ref color can't have that
included in it well let's continue
thinking this through a little bit more
and we'll go from there so let's see
what we need to do here so in terms of
figuring out what the lighting actually
is we're gonna have to do a light probe
query at this point right and the light
probe query is going to be some kind of
a voxel situation where we do the gather
exactly like we would normally do it in
the pixel shader and some interpolation
between them right it's gonna be a
little bit expensive but that's
basically what's gonna happen and we're
gonna you know we're gonna have to call
something like this that won't exactly
be this let me see if if light probe
irradiance is still in there yeah it is
so we left this in there but it's not
actually a valid thing like we don't
actually want this v3 light six stuff
that was for when we're going to do
cubic Direction stuff and we kinda
decided that we're not storing that
anymore so we wouldn't actually want the
light probe irradiance in there and
furthermore the light probe variants
like wouldn't go in here either
right you know this this is not what
would actually happen this is the actual
lighting information and it's the
entirety of the lighting information now
so this stuff here like light probe
position is still the case but light
preparation is just not so that's
actually there anymore so we can
actually eliminate that entirely if we
want to right we can actually just get
rid of this entirely and so we're not
gonna be returning it as something like
that right instead we're gonna be doing
is just like you know
some kind of light value is gonna come
in here we're just gonna get you know
how much light should we have actually
seen bouncing off the surface or
whatever right so we're gonna want to do
something like this and then we're gonna
want to do the reflection so it's hard
to say exactly what we would want to do
in this case but we know we've got a
probe sample and so it'd probably be
something like this like if you assume
that we are bouncing off of this surface
so we know the surface normal we know
what direction it would be because it
would be like the reflection vector here
so we'd have to compute the reflection
vector around this surface normal which
we can do what is the light coming in in
that in that direction right and so we'd
want to just do like get you know
compute box the lighting or something
like this something like that I don't
know but we're gonna want to basically
pass this in where we say here's our
sample location here's the normal at
that location and here's the vector that
we're trying to sample out towards we
may not actually need this
in fact then I think about it we
probably don't we just would compute the
reflection vector and then say this is
the direction we wanted to know about
you know that's not really true because
this is diffuse to a large extent right
and so I guess what we would say is I
don't really know so I guess we would
have to have since we don't I don't know
if we would need material parameters in
here for this that's really kind of hard
to say I guess but since we're computing
the lighting very coarsely I would say
you know we probably just want to assume
that surfaces are diffuse so maybe we'll
do this for now right so we'll just say
look here's the lighting location here's
the hemisphere that it can gather tell
me
what you know what do you see and we'll
use that so then we would go in here and
and do exactly what we would expect here
right this this is all pretty much
exactly the same I don't know where
emission direction was coming from it's
so the REA direction
with the sub rate in particular it's
saying it's the negative of that so yeah
that's just doing the cosine fall-off
it's all that's doing and that's fine as
well so yeah I mean that's all okay I
think and then that's gonna give us back
what the lighting transfer should have
been at that point right so given that
we have a couple different things that I
guess we would need to do here and in
terms of how to interpolate it all again
this is the part that it don't really
know so now we get down to the part that
I'm not sure how we want to do it's it's
pretty confusing so if you look here
this is how we were doing the update
before it's just a straight linear blend
that was doing like the sort of an
accumulation where we were just you know
accumulating everything into this this
accumulator using weights that were
specified as part of the sampling sphere
but that's not we're gonna be wanting to
do now right and this is the part that I
don't actually know what we should be
doing we need to spread into the voxels
so here you know basically the test or
you know test cast or whatever it is so
the test cast from probes right you can
see that we've got the spam voxel thing
happen in here where we just like put
forth lighting information into our
entire voxel what that's doing right is
just hard writing the result so it's
just it's just writing the result in
literally and like I said that's not
really what we need to be doing long
term we need to be doing kind of
averaging and so the spam voxel part and
in fact this part right here maybe wants
to come out into something a little bit
more specific so this
is gonna be like a spam voxel call
itself so here is our actual spam box of
call and these are gonna be called like
spam box a slice or something right and
so what we're gonna need to do is every
time we finish one of these things we're
gonna have to spam the the voxel with
the information now what I would like to
do is since this is expensive spamming
the voxel I would like to basically
accumulate the voxel with the transfer
PBS inside this thing right and then at
the end spam the voxel so I'd like to
like local accumulate and then spam the
voxel at the very end so it would
basically take place out here so like
the spam voxel part would happen here
right so I'm going to move these up
because I want them to be used from the
actual lighting code which is right here
right yes so the spamming of the voxel
wants to happen in here and the get
voxel index and that stuff like this
stuff is all kind of garbage we're done
with it now I think I don't think we
want any of this actually so this is yet
this is all kind of incorrect there is
the UVW part we do maybe need a little
bit of that stuff now but of course that
will happen that'll kind of happen
inside here so we're we're doing this
work we will need one that actually does
the UVs as well and that's just gonna be
for the for blending but we'll deal with
that in a second all right so I think
that's what we want this to look like so
we'll have our spam voxel slice which
does that part of it and we'll do we'll
have our spam voxel which does the other
part of it and so the spam voxel here is
just going to say we need the solution
and
the you know the spam position basically
and so we'll pass Casspi to spam voxel
and then it will do all of the spamming
here it means the the test like all this
nonsense so that it can actually record
like whether it's for having the right
place and all that sort of thing but
other than that it's just a direct pass
through and you know we probably won't
be able to leave it like that forever
because it's probably gonna be a little
too costly to have all this
configurability in there in terms of
what the compilers gonna do because this
is pretty much the the hot path like
this is the the spiciest path in the
whole game it's the thing that costs the
most runtimes so we're not gonna be able
to do all that ad infinitum but you know
more or less this is what we're looking
at and we can sort of leave it like this
until we go to do our like full
performance optimization right alright
so let's start cleaning up the compilers
and move towards actually running that
stuff for real here in the irradiance
part of things we want to just get rid
of this entirely it's not anything that
we actually need so I'm just gonna get
rid of the irradiance stuff it's just
not necessary also set light probe
position is now also gone I believe
because we're just pushing light preps
on not setting their positions anymore
since we don't have storing that stuff
we can actually also pull the light
probe assignments pretty sure we just
don't want to ever have to deal with
that anymore the solution we came up
with was was pretty much far superior
you know it also I feel like I'm too
loud in my headphones I'm annoying my
own self can that be fixed
I'm curious oh it does so it actually
affects what I hear well that's annoying
can't you do something about the can't I
do something about that yes I can't
oh well let goes on anyway
assuming that I don't want to ruin my
own ear but get my own ears with this
I'm gonna have to figure out some way to
fix that not really sure what to do
about that but anyway so in in the in
the spamming right
we can now spam from inside the other
routine which is good and I'm just gonna
start cleaning up the compiler is on
that and then we also have to actually
figure out what we're gonna do for the
blending inside the spamming and maybe
we'll use our current test version to
figure that out all right so we need the
right bundle count here this is
something that targets the light source
part of things we can actually use the
debug light for that right now if we
want to so if I inside the lighting code
here take the debug light P which is
well in here here is the information in
question and yeah so well I guess part
of the problem too is that it won't
actually hit the debug light yes so
we're gonna all right so so here's what
I here's what I would propose we do I
would propose that what we need to do is
take this in two steps I'm gonna put so
in here I'm gonna take the direction to
the light source right I'm gonna take
the direction of light source here and
compute that by just taking where the
light is and subtracting delight creepy
right I'm gonna see the Ray direction
here with just four of those
like so and I don't know that I actually
need those to be normalized but just in
case I'll normalize them here it won't
be expensive it's only done one time the
right bundles so it's not too bad and
plus we're not going to doing that in
general so what I want to do there is
say look we have to start we have to put
the lights into the actual casting space
because otherwise you can't ever hit
them and so what I'd like to do here is
just say well let's go ahead and first
of all try to get the lights into the
system so that we don't pre-code where
they're coming from
and that we can do in our test cast
which will debug that part of it which
would save us some time because it'll
make it easier for us to to figure out
why can't where's the enlarged box at
all there we go got to put this one with
our sort of bundle of things we do all
right
so I think that's what we want to do
first is get the lights into the REA
castor rather than having them be
outside in the debug thing and make our
test code work with that so I think
that's mostly what we want looking
through here what is the actual
complaint on on this guy ray index its
ray bundle index that's all
and then spam Vox look here yeah is what
we we actually want to be doing we don't
want any of this stuff so we're just
going to be basically spamming it with
the transfer PPS ray and so we know the
light probe P we know the transfer
photons per second that we want in there
you know the light solution and what
else do we need like position light
color spam position uh-oh
so okay that's for our fall off so again
this is where we kind of have to figure
out information we don't actually have
right and this is why I say this is
going to be pretty come pretty confusing
but that's okay so for right now yeah
I'm trying to think of how we would do
this so you can see here why I'm saying
this is going to be the hardest part of
the problem so we want to be able to set
our voxels to have nice fall-off and so
we want the fall-off to be computed
based on like where the light was coming
from and so they get a nice sort of
lighting continuous lighting sort of
thing happening from there right and so
what that means is we need to produce
information about that that we don't
actually have right because we're
getting light from everywhere and not
just from certain lights and so I feel
like that's the tricky part and we're
gonna have to like actually have some
kind of a lighting position information
in so I think we're gonna literally need
that this stuff here like we're gonna
need the like light see and the light
key to actually come into the system and
it's gonna be worse than that
it's gonna actually be like a yeah it's
gonna actually be it'd be worse than
that but we'll see that in a second
we're gonna actually need like some kind
of a structure that tracks these but I'm
starting to sort of get it now I sort of
get what's gonna have to happen so
that's probably okay all right so moving
on what's wrong with our spam voxel here
let me just get that one correct oops
just want to I just want to clean this
up in kind of reverse order so the
transfer PPS right needs to be added
the light see is not actually there so
looking at this code it's that and so in
here where we actually compute the
transfer PPS it's like you know
something like this so if we actually
average like the location that the light
is coming from and the amount that's
coming in we could actually use the
amount to weight the direction as well
you know what I mean
so in other words like we could say well
what's the total like what's the what's
the total amount of power that's in this
thing right you know like maybe
something like this something like that
where we get the total amount can we do
this do we have RGB in our Vic 3 by the
way
we do so if we look at our red green and
blue and say look the total amount of
stuff that's going through here that
maybe is our waiting so we say like look
some the light the lighting that we're
getting incoming but wait the directions
right so the light or wait the locations
that it's coming from right so then we
would say all right you know this light
position is now some kind of a weight
here and we're gonna want to sum that so
like you know maybe this is like
actually this power and like total power
or you know plus equals this power so we
know how much it is and we can invert it
right so like power M equals zero or
power coefficient something like that if
this power is greater than zero then the
power coefficient is one over right we
just basically wanna do that we have a
utility function for it it's called safe
ratio zero and so what we can do is just
say look let's take the safe ratio zero
of the total power sorry I said this
karmic total power take the safe ratio 0
of 1 over the total power and that's
going to be the coefficient that
normalizes our position to an to a
location right and so that's we could
average the positions of the light that
were coming in weighted by how much
light we see coming in from there and we
could you know we could use that right
now that's actually not a bad averaging
rule I I'm like thinking in my head I'm
like oh that seems pretty reasonable but
again the only thing that's not good
about it is it doesn't tell us what to
do when we want to start making this
higher fidelity because remember if we
only had one like field so if we were
only if we were only providing a single
light field then okay right then it
makes sense because basically what we're
saying is look this is the best we can
do to approximate an incoming light
position and an incoming light amount
and then we can basically just say okay
you know spam the voxel with that
information that we've received how
in this particular case we know that we
could store a lot more information in
the back so we could store multiple
incoming light directions at every voxel
position and the question is what would
we then do so if we knew we could store
more than one we would need to do
something here that allowed us to take
whatever information was currently in
the voxel and say well or or I mean not
not so but information is in the voxel
but like of the Rays that we cast when
we have information about lighting
directions we would need to be able to
split the lighting directions up into
like at least four separate pieces of
information for the lighting directions
that we would then use right and how we
keep track of those four is pretty
confusing
yeah so that's like that's confusing we
could do something like having the
sphere information tell us that we could
keep a list of the highest power things
we saw gosh you know I just really don't
know
I just really don't know how we're gonna
do that I think there's a lot of
different ways we could try it but none
of them in my head seems like an
obviously right choice so I just don't
know anyway what I do know is that our
light information here yeah it's gonna
have to look something like this we need
the total power to be summed like so for
each light index there and then we we're
going to need some way of doing this
stuff here so light sample and sample
ref color here light sample is not a
thing that we actually have not sure
where that came from it's probably was
in here so we probably need this light C
to actually be called a light sample and
then that'll float through properly in
here so I think that's all we really
need and then we should be okay except
for the fact that we have actually
written this function yet and then we've
got this light position here right which
is perhaps if appeared that's actually
true so we do need the probe sample P in
this case to be sort of consistent so if
we have the light coming from the moon
we need that to be set so we kind of
need this to basically look more like
this like the probe sample P it needs to
be set outside and it needs to be set
from the moon location like wherever
that's going to be and we don't actually
know I guess where that's going to be
but like we need there to be like a moon
P right and so where we actually set up
the moon light we need you know
something here that's like where did you
think the moon actually was right and we
don't know but it's probably like way
the heck up there right and in order for
the fall-off to work properly the spam
voxel is going to have to have more
information in it as well so for example
if you look at what's going on here this
fall-off equation is not going to be
correct like the moon's not gonna have a
fall-off it's just gonna be ubiquitous
right so we would need this to also be
something that gets passed in there so
for example like this coefficient would
have to be passed as part of the
lighting information so for example like
light fall-off that would have to come
in here right and the light fall-off of
0.05 F or whatever would have to be
something that was just set as a
separate thing so you know who knows
what we're gonna set here I don't really
know but like let's say we set the light
fall-off to that in this case and we set
the light fall-off to zero and the other
case or something like that right and so
the fall-off factor would also have to
be averaged right across these runs so
we'd have like at this light fall-off
and it would get summed
again just doing a simple summation here
not particularly clever or anything and
that's just producing the rolling
average of how these things should be
falling off with distance and those are
things that we can set again in the
probes I mean in lights when we push
them on if we want to again it's just
like some light parameterization stuff
we're gonna have to decide as we start
between the lighting its arbitrary and
we can do whatever we want there we can
even have other kinds of equations if we
need to it's pretty flexible and that's
not like it's just a little computation
here that's not too expensive so what
we'd like to do here under the power
summation stuff the same exact way we're
doing it before is we need to take that
fall off and just normalize it out like
so and you know maybe we do these in two
steps that we can actually see so like
light P you know times V equals power
see light fall-off times equals power
see that way we can see what they are
before they get passed when we're done
bugging again not gonna do anything
different in terms of the actual code
generated but it's just something we can
kind of expect a little easier and that
will give us all the information that we
need now and we just kind of now need oh
and we need this fall-off to actually be
specified here somewhere right
okay so now that's all good and in here
we need this to be passed as well so the
light fall-off comes in here and the you
know this is a really cumbersome thing
to do but I'm just doing just base
leaves adding this one parameter and
again we don't really know that this is
the way we're gonna want to do this but
you know we're just trying to get things
working in a way that that makes sense
and produces reasonable result so that
we can worry about the speed of things
sort of as a second pass down all right
so we need the light fall-off to be
passed here and in this case we know
that it's just always 0.05 because that
that particular routine is the test case
which just is always going to have the
same fall-off specified for it it looks
like this is a little unhappy right now
I'm not sure why what did I forget to
pass we have the letting solution we
have the spamming location oh well it's
not spam P it's cast P so I suppose
that's probably the issue there we have
the lighting color the fall-off is
correct and then the test case passing
down so that's all good
and here we know that the irradiance
stuff is gone so we just need to delete
it and that should be fine
and
[Music]
I guess that's it yeah so now the only
thing we really need is a way to produce
light samples and then we would actually
be done quote-unquote although like I
said the hard part is still coming up so
what we need to do here is just have a
way of sampling the lighting instead of
in the shader in the actual outside code
right so we need a way to sample this in
here and so let's go ahead and get
started on how we're gonna sort of do
that but though actually at the moment I
might just return nothing and focus on a
sort of a separate part of this problem
so maybe I'll call the sample game
sample and so maybe we won't actually
implement this quite yet because I might
not really care about that part yet
we'll see in a second let me take a look
here what is the problem here that is
the problem this was supposed to be
transferred it wasn't so that's just a
hasty sketch of how this routine might
look but what I'd like to do is fall
back to our test case first so because I
think there's some things now we can do
in the test case having with the fad
that will help us out so the first thing
we can do is put the lighting into the
actual red cast and like I said that's
gonna have to happen because we
currently have the test cast hard-coded
to just use a hard-coded light position
but we now want the lights action be
coming from the environment and having
as many as we want and so in order to do
that let's start actually putting those
lights into the the the casting
hierarchy correctly right so that's
something that we want to be able to do
now so when we push a light in here we
want to actually push those lights using
the push light call and pick them up out
of the system using the push light call
and so the way that we want to do that
is you know inside there we may want to
put them in a separate array it's it's
hard to really say I'm guessing that we
probably do so that we would have a
split where we would have you know
occluders and lights would sort of be
treated a little bit separately and the
reason for that again is because we
probably want to sort
bias ourselves to shoot towards light
sources sometimes when maybe we wouldn't
ordinarily have done so and there's
different ways we can do that and you
know I'll be honest I'm kind of
interested in thinking about that a
little bit one of the things we could do
that is not something I really am super
familiar with I haven't heard of it
being done before but I'm sure someone's
done it is we could actually raycast and
then bend rays towards light sources as
a separate thing based on sort of the
spatial hierarchy calling a little bit
this is sort of a strange idea but you
know let me draw it out for you just
just to give you some perspective on
what I'm thinking because it's kind of a
weird idea but I'm a suspect
it's not weird enough that I don't think
someone's probably tried it before I
feel like someone probably has try this
form you know maybe it's stupid but I
feel like not totally ridiculous why is
my cord is all messed up here use the
drawing tablet enough all right so
so if we take a look at how this is you
know working essentially what we're
gonna have is we've got a spatial
partition and we know I guess I should
say spatial partition name of Lights um
and I'm not sure exactly how we want to
look at this but effectively what we
want is we know that lights are maybe
somewhat rare throughout our scene
unfortunately meaning that you know the
chances that you'll hit a light source
when you randomly cast array might be
kind of low because you know in certain
scenes there may only be four or five
lights you know maybe in some scenes
there's hundreds of lights and you'll
definitely hit one if you just randomly
pick directions you'll hit one pretty
quickly but there may be other ones
where like the entire light is just
coming from like one candle or something
or you know torch that the hero is
holding or something like that and in
that case most of our rays will miss and
so we won't be able to pick up that
light sources as much as we we should
right and so if we want to bias towards
making sure that we at least sample the
place where the light is actually coming
from what we need to be able to do is
know that for a given location where we
might buy us towards and if there's only
one light in the entire system that's
fine but if there's ten lights in the
system but one in each room then the
lights that we cast on particular room
want to bias towards the light in that
room and so on right and so all I was
saying was if you imagine how the
spatial partition looks you know you've
got something like this if we imagine
top-down and maybe we're casting rays
from here right and there's light
sources maybe like here here here and
here
right and all of these are may be
spatially partitioned maybe this room
right has solid walls so you're never
gonna hit these right and so we'd like
to know is if we're casting rays from
this location
when we want to buy us our rays we want
to bias them towards this light source
but we don't know that right so what we
would like to do is perhaps make use of
our spatial partition to say hey what
are the lights that are nearby and maybe
only bias towards like these too but
bias towards like this one for example
because the chance is that you're gonna
hit that one or actually pretty low you
know what I mean so what we'd like to do
is have a way of bending raised towards
light sources based on the spatial
partition and what we I was thinking we
could sort of do is something like well
what if we just look up in the spatial
partition what if our spatial partitions
stores like the closest light source at
each level of the hierarchy or something
like that or like some kind of a way of
producing that information
I'm not sure exactly what I mean but
like imagine that as we build our
hierarchy of bounding boxes at each
level of the bounding box we store what
the light source is that is most central
to this one and then as we find probe
locations we expand down to the point
where we or we look upward from where we
are until we gather some fixed number of
light sources that we bend towards does
that make sense do you know what I'm
saying
in other words imagine for each light
probe we look at where the light probe
is in the voxel and we walk upwards from
the voxel I'm not voxel spatial
partition we walk upwards through our
parents until we get to four light
sources and then we go gather what they
are is that stupid that could be pretty
dumb
so I guess what I would say is it's not
dumb enough that I don't think we should
try it but you get kind of what I'm
saying right so in other words we would
just we would just find a node that
contained the first node that contains
four light sources and why four because
that's how many we cast in a packet we
would do eight if we you know we're if
we were doing something else if we were
doing avx2
so we just however many we cast in a
bundle we'd look up that many but I
guess what I'm saying here is like so if
you imagine in our lighting work here do
we even use these I don't think we use
these anymore either
all right so we'll probably we can get
rid of a lot of code here eventually so
if we assume that we've got our lighting
is kind of packed into a this array of
boxes right so you have this lighting
box set here and if we look at the
lighting boxes right our spatial
partition is like built out of these
things and these are you know the these
are sort of the the things that we push
on for occluders and also what we could
push on for light sources and all I was
really suggesting is well if we actually
said you know maybe instead of like
emission right here we would basically
just out reference we would basically
say like things that have actual light
sources associated with them can like
reference those as a separate thing and
then when we sort of go up the hierarchy
maybe we say look we just store in here
instead of an f32 for admission and a
texture index like maybe you like forget
that we've got the you know P the radius
in the ref seat what if we just said
like all right there's you know a you
thirty-two of like four lights right and
as you sort of build the spatial Harkey
you propagate the lights upwards so you
know how many lights you have and so
what we would do is we'd walk up the
hierarchy till we get to something that
actually has all four lights right and
you can imagine doing this in sort of a
Squinkie er way if you limited the
number of lights to 65,000 which is
seems pretty
reasonable you could imagine saying
something like this where you just said
like look there's a you 64 that says
what the lights are and what we do is we
pack 16-bit indices four of them in
there
so as you come up you can just say look
if any part of this thing is all zeros
which would be a pretty easy thing for
us to test I guess I don't know why we
couldn't just do that as well just test
to see whether any of those are zero and
if they are then we know we have to keep
walking up the hierarchy further to try
and gather more lights to bias towards
right just an example we could go one
further and if these lighting boxes were
even spammy err we could do something
else where we just said look we keep
which for directions we have in fact so
we could do something like this where we
basically say like hey yeah there's like
a
something like this so we just say look
we take these lighting boxes we
pre-compute the bias directions towards
light sources and we store them into the
hierarchy and that way you just look up
in the hierarchy where you are and you
immediately know where your bias
directions are so we just do that as
part of the Box building pass one pass
through the hierarchy to just build
those right and then every point that
actually looks up in the hierarchy just
knows by pulling that out and the only
reason I put that in there you know and
it would look like this right and this
can be a you 16 as well so it would
really probably more like this so the
lighting boxes would just have this
information as a primary component and
then in cured that would actually just
yeah it would just store the sort of an
out-of-band light bias look up right and
then inside the lighting solution itself
we would just have as many of those as
we wanted like a buffer full of lighting
bias directions because we only need as
many as there actually are containers of
four light sources pretty much so I
don't actually know the only thing I'm
not sure about is what do you do sort of
on higher-up pieces of the Harkey but I
guess you don't care once you have
forward you don't need anything above
that no one would go above it anyway so
I think yeah I think you don't care in
fact this only really needs to be stored
at the leaves I would say so you really
can only have as many as you had leaves
in the first place and you don't need
even close to that many because the
lighting directions will not vary per
leaf so but point being you kind of know
we can get rid of a lot of this stuff
but we know that like you know if this
box table here that we have we know at
the very least that even though it's
quite piggy we could introduce a thing
here that was just like look we've got a
crap ton of these things and we could
even get rid of this if we had the thing
be that big because you could actually
just store it you you wouldn't have to
push them on you could literally just
know that you look up your index and
you'd get it right so this kind of gets
simpler and simpler as we go yeah and
really all you have to know is that the
number of occluders and I don't know why
I still call this light data with but
the number of occluders can't exceed
this value but other than that you're
fine
so alright so I think we're kind of
slowly walking into it here so if we
have the light directions to search in
there then really all we need now is a
way to encode whether something is or
isn't a light and so I think that's the
only thing that then needs to get looked
at a little bit more carefully and so
when we're actually putting these things
in here we need some way of saying that
information like is this a light or
isn't this a light and what we could do
here is like the ref see for example we
could just say all right
maybe our maybe our we just have like
some kind of encoding to mention or
maybe we just have a boolean right look
maybe we just have something in here
that says and so if you look at what's
going on this is nine values here right
and this is a tenth value so if you look
at like oops more speed joke yeah so
we've got three vector threes right so
that's three times three times four
bytes so we've got 36 bytes
being used up there plus we have to
- byte fields which gets us to 40 and so
you know 64 is a cache line we want
these things fit in the cache line we're
in no danger of like falling out of it
we could try to make it a little bit
more compact but I don't know to what
extent we could really do that
effectively we could certainly just keep
it at 40 we wouldn't have to grow it if
we didn't want to because although this
would have to be you 16 this certainly
doesn't have to be you 16 so we could we
could probably easily say that the child
count is you know we don't ever split
into that many so we could also say like
that
and that would be fine right so we could
sort of chart start chopping it down to
that and then the ref see instead of
being a reflection color is actually
just a thing that tells you where this
thing is the light or not the color of
the light right so if the is light is on
this thing is the color of the light is
light is off then it's the amount of
reflection that's going on right and
that'd be it so here when you push a
clue Terp
obviously like is light is set to zero
like so and then when you're pushing a
light source on his lights should be set
to true since this one's a u8 actually I
guess these two are both you eights
those should be set separated when
you're pushing a light source on we just
need to do sort of the other thing here
where we would you know where we
actually pushing that on actually know
so here is the push cube call but we
don't actually want to push a cube when
we push a light so that's not really
actually what we want and let me go to
the push cube call and let's let's take
a look at where that one actually was
there so this is what we want so push a
clue tur and push light or actually the
same pretty much so I'm gonna I'm going
to put those up it's not push Q at all
so it's really this so what we actually
want is this right here this code
exactly and because we don't want to
actually we don't do any of this this is
just wrong so what we want to do is when
we do push light we want to have this
video mission right it's RGB emission it
could be whatever you want and so in
here we would encode that information
here's the P here's the radius and
here's the mission right and then this
right here we would want to set these
two to zero but now we're setting this
one to true right or to one effectively
right and we don't want textures here so
we just really want that like that's
pretty much all we want and when you
push a light on that's what it should
look like and so in here let's see the
hit emission stuff so we'll we will work
with that in a second that's what we
want to be working towards let me just
figure out the rest of this stuff here
so source count when we do split box
here what does source can't actually do
in this case do we actually need to use
16 error like why is this what's this
doing the source count and the source
does the source get reduced here or what
happens source count too
that's all we actually want to do
wait that's not gonna work so wait how
did this thing work Wow so it actually
needed they use 16 even though you can't
actually keep that many children I don't
understand
oh wait no so never mind this is just as
the split box and either it comes up
with two or it comes up with some number
probably pretty low so I think I can do
what I was gonna do which is just keep
those like this and so here I'm gonna
just assert that we didn't lose any
information there and go from there
and so here with hit emission that's the
part we want to work on in a second
what's this part here oh so for push
light so in this case we just want to do
like whatever the emission was we would
multiply it now we don't really have to
do that right so we could actually just
say like to do KC probably can just use
RGB for admission and encode that
directly when we create the empty right
so that part should probably just be
something we can change in the future we
don't need to do that kind of little
dance there but alright so for now when
we do the hit emission cure right we
don't actually want to store hit a
mission because the ref color actually
would tell us what we need to know there
so we don't we don't have like an
emission scalar so what we actually
would have here right is we just need to
know is this thing a light source so
it's effectively just selecting like a
boolean value for like whether the thing
is a light or whether it isn't D'Lite
right because that's what we need to
know on the outside and because well is
that actually true what do we do with
hit right color yeah I mean I guess it
is true so we need we just need to know
that fact right
and so I guess we just want to store
that as as a mask
I'm gonna guess I'm just gonna go with
yes so when we actually do the raycast
result here like instead of a mission
being like a I mean base is gonna be a
boolean right this emission like it's
gonna be is a mission right and so in
here we would have like this selection
is still correct in a sense but this
emission value that we're loading up
here is actually gonna be like is light
right and so what we want to do there is
say look we've got an all ones vector
and an all zeros vector I think right to
be happy round I know if we actually
have 0 so I'm not sure I'm not sure if
we actually have a thing that would do
this but what we want to do here is for
the box right we are loading up the
information for this one box and it
either is a light or it isn't a light
right so what we need to do here is when
we actually hit it and we get the hit
emission value and here we're going to
be setting that value like this so this
is a mission is going to equal the hit
emission what we need to know here is
basically just a 1 or a 0 that goes in
and so you know it can basically be like
a emission coefficient so I mean it
really still is the emission value in a
sense I mean we could actually even just
keep calling it that but it's just gonna
be a 1 or 0 that's it's right whether or
not you're you're gonna have that or not
and so if the is light is set we want to
load a 1 in there right so it's kind of
like this
it's like that right and I guess this is
already specified so we want something
like this where we just conditionally
load one based on which one it's going
to be and so it kind of makes me think
the box wants to have that as an f32
I mean it's alright so I maybe kind of
take it back I feel like we kind of want
to load that as an f32
maybe right so in here we would say like
is light is actually like an f32 so
would either get set I mean it's just
it's wasteful I don't love it but you'd
really don't want to be like boolean all
over the place yeah so I take it back so
[Applause]
I guess we're gonna do it that way I
realize it's not the best thing in the
world but I want to be able to like load
the thing fairly directly from there and
maybe this is dumb because hey you could
just use a conditional move into a
register and then load the register so
maybe that's yeah maybe it is dumb I'm
so torn right now you can see how I'm
vacillating here but I guess we could
just do this with a conditional move so
it's not that big of a deal right but
basically in here we could say all right
look we need to first figure out what
the f32 is which is like is a mission
and is a mission is just going to be a
conditional move that's like look is the
thing a light if it is it's 1.0 if it's
not it's 0
right or something like that and then we
can just load that thing in via the
standard load I don't actually know we'd
have to look at what code this generates
but this could be bad that's all the
reason I'm saying it so I don't really
know we want something that's going to
generate efficient code for that loading
and I don't really know what it's going
to be let me look at the f32 4x here
so that's what I actually wanted so I'm
I just don't really know what I want to
do there but something that does the
equivalent of that which is gets one in
there or zero in there and then that way
on the way out we know what is and isn't
lights based on this and then that way
in the outside right where we get this
emission back it's just a multiply which
is what we want like we don't want to be
doing like if statements in here we just
want to be doing
straight ahead computations so we really
want like a 1 or 0 that like turns that
on or off right and we may want to do
something that like does a 1 minus for
this because we may want a not sample in
the case of a light we may not want to
do the light transfer here that that may
just be wrong and so in a sense we may
want to say like oh okay
yeah this and also this ref fall-off
part right I think what we want to do is
just just roll the emission into that
right so we want to say look whatever
the emission was if it was set to 1 so
it's going to be a light we want to you
know do this instead if it's in fact and
you know what we could actually do this
a little bit differently even we could
just say like yeah the ref fall-off is
the no no all right it is the way it
should be we're gonna say look if this
emission was set to zero then we're
going to use the the ref fall-off times
the how to market this this term will
come into play and it will do whatever
the reflected light is whereas if
emission was 1 then you hit a light
source so we're gonna provide just what
the light source color was right so it's
basically like a toggle that emission is
just a toggle that says which of the
side of the equation we use and that's
how I think I want it right all right so
I think that's roughly what I want to
have happened there and we can sort of
get a little bit further down that rat
hole in a second but for right now what
I want to do is focus on the test code
here and really work on the test code
before we start to try and use the
propagation version
and the reason I want to do that is
first of all this is just using the
debug light P what I'd like to do now is
switch to using that as a push call and
let's get that working properly as our
first thing we do right okay so in world
mode where we look and we have the debug
light P or whatever it is right see that
here in this call to push light you can
see that's actually what we want so we
want this push light call here to come
back into existence right and what we
want is for this thing now to work with
with our system correctly so this is the
light that we're pushing into the system
this is the location that we're pushing
it in and the radius right so now we
actually have a push light that's
pushing into the system and it's putting
an occluder in there that we should be
able to actually like the occluder now
would actually exist I don't think we're
drawing it at all but well you can see
it right you can see that it's including
the light source right because it's
there it's blocking it and when the hero
hops up so that it hits the light source
right it's it's actually putting the
light into it right and so on so we're
in good shape there like like we know
that that's actually being pushed in and
what we want to do now is say like okay
that's not an occluder right we know
it's a light because it's got the
lighting thing set it's not an occluder
it's a light source now we need to
actually like track that information
okay so in the test cast from probes
part of things right I'm still gonna
cheat and use the debug light position
to know that's what we're casting
towards but instead of doing any of this
stuff now we're gonna do this a little
bit differently so before we were doing
is say look the hit is whether or not we
got to the light source before before
intersecting something but now what I
want to say is okay we don't know we
just know that we did a cast that hits
something and so now what we want to do
is say is that something a light source
right so now what we would do is say
well hit for example what we could do is
just use alright is that emission value
one or zero right
so for example I can just do that right
so now we're just saying look is the
thing we hit an emitter or isn't it
right and now we would not actually be
testing anywhere else also I want to get
rid of this secondary bounce thing
because we're not Randi's that was
something that's someone asked us to add
in as a test we don't want that in there
so anyway now we're saying look we're
not gonna cheat and just say did we hit
the light source or not we're gonna do
is expect the ray caster to tell us if
we hit a light source or not and now
let's debug that right and so now we
need to do is go figure out you can see
it's like totally not working right
right you can see it's like all kind of
weird now so what we want to do is now
get this working so we need to figure
out a way to make it this work correctly
for the debug light and this will give
me an opportunity to debug having lights
in that hierarchy which is exactly what
we want right so when I actually hit
something we need this emission value to
be coming out correctly just want to
make sure I wrote this code drop really
that that does look correct doesn't it I
think so I think so I'm going to turn on
the line drawing as well and in this
case I want to the line color should be
based on the hit does it
yeah it's based on the hip and so what I
want to do here is make it so that it's
clear whether we're hitting the lights
are so now what I want to do is make it
so that if we hit something
this is backwards so I'm going to change
this to hit to hit light when I reverse
the meaning so if we hit a light source
that was here so if we hit the light we
will say hit light gives us a yellow
otherwise we get a plaque if we hit the
light source well this is now hit P is
always correct so that's good well know
if we didn't hit anything it's not
correct so if if we have a cast that's
like just too far right so if we if we
have a cast that that just went on
forever we wouldn't necessarily have a
way to draw it so what we would need to
do here is say well if the cast he hit
equals f32 max then what we would need
to do is say you know we didn't hit
anything but that shouldn't be possible
you know what I'm just gonna get rid of
that case for now because we were aiming
at the light so we're either gonna hit
the light or something else right so if
we don't get anything that should be a
bug in fact this right here is just a
bug so I guess this should act this is
what this should do this case should be
like something very bad happened right
this is an error right and so then here
if we hit the light then we spam the
voxel otherwise we don't and I think
that's all we really needed yeah it's
what is it actually
t ray sorry so that is something now I
can debug and look at right so now I can
look at what's actually having their eye
pattern lighting off so I can actually
see it although actually it looks like
it's working now that I've kind of
recoded it properly to talk a little bit
more correctly about what it's doing I
think we just had some some typos in the
code there so so I think that just
worked actually we don't really need
alright so the light is now coming from
the axle from the actual voxel and we
should be able to have multiple lights
with multiple shadows now also by
spamming the spamming a different part
of the voxel alright which we could we
could interpolate multiple light sources
here as well but anyway that just shows
that the test case is working ok and
that the emission stuff is working ok
and we know the difference between an
emitter and occluder now right which is
what we wanted so I think that's all
good and now if I were to take out that
so this this now becomes sort of the the
next the next thing we might want to try
now let's try tracking the lights so we
don't actually have to ever set the
debug light we can just pick it up from
what's in the box all right so we know
that's working what we don't know is
this value here right so what we want to
do is discover that we want to discover
that from the voxel I mean why do I keep
saying voxel we want to discover that
from the spatial hierarchy so in terms
of which light source I would want to
bias towards in the the spatial heart to
hear what I need to know looking at the
lighting is I need to be able to sort of
crawl down that spatial hierarchy that
that partition and I need to be able to
you know get down to my leaf node and
figure out what the light is in that
leaf node and so I think I guess I'm not
sure I think the way we were doing this
here you can kind of see all it does is
it basically just like uses this box
that to see which one's as it kind of
goes down so I'm pretty sure we can kind
of just gank this routine and find our
closest one really simply so let's just
kind of grab this guy this is not really
that necessary but like I don't really
need to cut copy part of any of this but
so if we wanted to say like
get leaf for p4 spatial leaf for P and
we pass in a position right what I want
to do here is say well we probably don't
really need a box sack for this because
we can only be in any one box at a time
so we would just open up with children
look at which one pick one go down it
right we don't have to ever actually cut
use both sides because a raycast needs
to consider both sides because if it
doesn't hit something in one side has to
go to the other side of the spatial
partition in our case we're just going
down one at a time so what we can really
do here is say look there's just one box
we don't need a stack so we can
basically just say you know that so we
start at the root box and then all we're
really doing is saying let's traverse
down what we want to do is go through
the children of this box and see which
one we're in right so we just need a
like a way of determining whether we're
inside this box I and then executing
this carrot I believe probably also want
this
right so what we do is say all right
here's the position we start at the root
we go in and we see for each child that
we have here we want to pick out a new
box that's the one we're in so we would
get the box here and we would say like
if inside right and off we go like that
kind of thing right now what we do want
to do is you want I guess to accept also
a case where there isn't one I suppose
so
because if we ask for something outside
the Harkey you would get nothing I would
assume so here we would probably do like
we start with the results children I
guess cathica how we avoid infinitely
looping here look if we loop over
everything and haven't found one that
we're inside then we have failed right
so we maybe do this perhaps so
essentially what we want to do here is
say okay start at the first child index
one pass the last child index we loop
over all of these we look to see whether
inside this box right assuming we are
inside the box if the box if the child
count is valid then we need to descend
so we just get out of the loop right
and we set result equal to the box in
question otherwise we actually just
returned the box directly write
something like this this doesn't look
great
something like that I'm not sure that's
very good let's think about this a
little bit more there's probably a
cleaner way to write that you can see
what I'm trying to do here there right
if we need to keep going we keep going
if we don't need to keep going we just
leave I guess this is the only return
point so we could actually just also say
this in a sense because everything else
is a failure
[Music]
I don't know I don't think too hard
about that at the moment but this is
basically what we're looking for right
so if we did a get spatial leave for P
we need an inside box like it is inside
kind of a thing here for these boxes and
I guess I don't know like the lighting
box here is a P and a radius so
basically what we need to do is figure
out like are we inside this thing and so
that's pretty easy for us to do we
already have an is is in rectangle right
so we can also we can already do this
and we just need to construct a box here
and that's pretty easy for us to do as
well cuz this is it right so it's just
that so I think that's all we would
actually need to do there it's not as
efficient as probably we would like but
I think that's it and then this we just
need to pass the position to its
position two and I think that would get
us which whichever spatial partition
were actually in at the time right so
that just returns to the leaf to us and
we're good to go so that means that if
we wanted to take the test case right to
the test cast from probes and we didn't
want to cheat and use this debug light P
thing here what we could do instead is
say look get us whatever the leaf were
in like so I don't know why this is this
would be that so we just say look get us
the leaf and then we'll get the deep
we'll get like the location of the light
from the leaf right so the the place
that the the place where the lights are
supposedly at for this leaf that we're
tracking let's skip those right and so
what I can do is say if we are actually
start tracking those right and we go
into
the lighting code here and we look at
how is proposing we store those right
this right here would be the lightbox
actually the lightbox target P or
something like that so this would be the
target positions for the lighting or the
the places to try to aim towards and
there'd be four of them for every you
know their before of those for every one
of the leaves that we would store and we
would look it up
using just wherever whichever leaf we
were actually in right so we could get
the box index and in fact I guess the
box index is sort of what we want to
return for the leaf itself we don't
actually need this information so I
guess it's more like this right and then
what we would do is say okay the light P
that we're actually interested in is
just the solution target P for that leaf
index right I think if you do a depth
component on that yeah
that's right isn't it I think that's
right and so that would be a way that if
we were actually building it we could
get them out pretty trivially and what
we need now is to get that actual leaf
location what did I actually call that
function so now what we would do is say
well the results I guess so in this case
right I guess this is starting to look a
little bit more sane here so we're going
to say look we assume the results of
zero while we don't have a results we
would go to the like parent here and
we'd say
like this parent first child index
parent oops first child index plus shout
count so that gives us our range we
assume that there is no more parent so
we could also say like wild parent and
not results so parent pickles box so in
either case here if we're inside we
break and the difference is just which
one of these two we do right so it's a
little bit of a nasty loops not not the
world's best loop in the world but you
know it sort of works a little bit maybe
so I think that gives us the cases that
we need and off we go
so now get spatial leaf for P peas
undeclared that is true we need the
light probe position so here's the cast
P that's what we're actually looking for
here and now we can sort of comment that
out and get the light position directly
from our spatial hierarchy and that's
what I actually want to do here we only
have a few minutes left but let's try to
actually put that information in now I
mean you know why not so how are we
gonna do that you know we've got this
sort of box splitting nonsense going on
so how are we gonna figure out where the
lights are and all that all that garbage
right so let's take a look at how that
code is working currently and see if we
can reverse engineer something or sorry
reverse inject I don't want to call it
something in here it does because right
now if we did this it wouldn't work
right right now if we did this we'd get
nothing because this stuff is just going
to be zero and so the location of the
light source is going to be zero right
there will be a light it'll just be it
like zero zero zero or something weird
like that
and the shadowy be computed from there
but the other part won't be I guess is
that right let me see what's actually
going on I don't know exactly what's
gonna happen there so so I guess if I'm
honest I'm not sure why we were seeing
the light move I'm kind of weirded out
by that I guess that's because I get
well you know I don't really know why
that's because I guess it depends on
whether you hit the light that seems
buggy to me I'm gonna go ahead and
finish what we were doing but I think
there's just a bug in there I don't know
I don't know why we're seeing what we're
seeing here that doesn't make much sense
at all I don't love that all right so
anyway I'm gonna go look at the split
box how this stuff works so you can see
our build spatial partition for lighting
call what this is gonna do is it's
running through all of the boxes here it
takes the total bounce right so this is
basically like how much space do I'm
actually taking up for the entire set of
occluders it then goes and says all
right let's go ahead and start splitting
these boxes right so it takes however
many boxes I guess we actually have
total and it says split them up right so
I guess in here what it says is when we
go to do a split box call assuming that
there's more than four boxes because
we're gonna store four boxes per leaf I
guess we go through some attempts and we
look to see like how to divide them up I
guess with some rectangles assuming that
we find some way of categorizing that
cleanly we go ahead and do the split box
and then we go through right
so I think all I really need to do there
is pass down
I'm sorry pass up information
information on the lighting right so in
this case if the source count is greater
than four we try to split if the source
count is less than four then we know
that the things inside us we want to
look to see if there's any lights right
so what we want to do is say look do any
or any of these things that we actually
have in terms of our children here which
I guess is is this yeah here's our
children so I'm not sure so we're moving
that point around - okay this is a weird
way to do this but all right um so what
we're doing here is we're saying look
for each of our child boxes is is any of
these alight right so it would be this
and if it is we want to put it in to
like our our light tracking if you will
and so if assuming that we found the
light here what we need to do is
propagate that information to all of the
nodes right so we need to like know
which lights are closest for any
particular situation and it's hard to
say I'm not really sure exactly how we
want to do that it'd be pretty trivial
for us to just for to store any four
lights that are
in the vicinity but it's considerably
difficult more difficult for us we would
have to do something more clever if we
wanted to actually get the closest way
each time so maybe we don't maybe we
want to actually insert these lights
which seems costly and I'm not really
sure I want to do it because it'd be Oh
N and the number of lights which I don't
want
so probably the better thing I mean the
Oh n log n in the number of lights which
seems bad and I think we probably just
want it to be the initial Oh N
build the o n log and build we don't
want another n log and Pass
I'm not sure so let's do this let's just
say look if there's a light in here
I'm Jonathan get well you know we still
but we can't really do it as a as a in
line here because we need to put back
propagate it down as well so all right
so I don't really know how to do this
without doing it as a second pass that
will actually work cleanly so really
hard to say but it seems like what we
would have to do here is actually have
the lights in this case be sort of
handle as a separate pass right so after
you split them you would go through like
this and you would say you know if this
is a light then you need to like insert
the light and when you do the insert
light it would flood through each of the
each of the levels of the spatial
partition right and figure out if it was
close further or figure out if it was
better than the lights that currently
were in there I mean and so thinking
through how that's going to work it's
yeah it's pretty nasty
the first light gets that gets inserted
would be the closest light at all points
in the hierarchy so you would touch all
the boxes the next one would be you know
like half or something depending on how
where the lights were and you would
touch less and less presumably if you
had a way of guaranteeing that you
couldn't be the closer light but that's
yeah this just seems terrible
so I don't know I don't know how we
should find that piece of information I
mean another thing we could do is write
them into the voxel so basically like
we're just storing the closest lights in
the voxel and you aim for those but
again even there you're talking about a
kind of a hard a hard thing to know
I'm not sure I think since we're out of
time what I'd like to do is table this
for tomorrow and relook at it then cuz I
feel like I want to think about this
some more and there's a lot of things we
could do here and I feel like we need to
kind of draw them out and go okay which
one of these is the most likely thing
again we could just not do this at first
right we could just use stochastic
sampling and just like see you know if
we hit the light source we hit the light
source and if we don't we don't and that
would work fine it's just not as good
right so our lighting is gonna be
flicker more flickery or more or
flickery and less you know likely to
pick up the lighting features than if we
do some sort of biasing towards lights
occasionally so it seems like something
we do want to but it how to actually
quickly determine which light sources to
biased towards is sort of something that
it doesn't seem exactly like there's an
obvious way to put it into the spatial
partition nicely in a way that's pretty
cheap to do
like the query for for closest lights is
a little tricky and there's just a lot
of ways we could do it and I just don't
have I don't have a solid idea which one
so I'm gonna go ahead and not do that
and so we're just gonna leave it as it
is right now and we'll pick it up later
what I could do although what I could do
here is cheat again and say look we know
what the D we know we're getting the
debug light in here so what I'll do is
I'll just put that in here just to make
sure this code is working because we
could get that good working properly so
ignore this right and instead we're just
gonna do this so we're gonna like loft
that thing up right into each of these
so for every box wherever you would have
looked it up you're you know you're
gonna get the target that's the debug
light so we're just spamming the debug
light out to all box lookups and so that
way we could just verify that this part
was working correctly and it does seem
to I'm going to turn off those test cast
bits there because it don't actually
want to see those and then we're gonna
go to QA and we'll think a little harder
about how we want to insert those lights
in the future so the test cast here I'm
just gonna get ribs I'm just gonna get
rid of that
and I'm gonna leave it like this so this
is now correctly executing the test code
but again we're not actually doing the
lookup so we're ignoring the look the
lookup will always return the correct
thing as it is going there and so we
need to figure out a way to actually
make that that table be filled with
correct answers all right let's go ahead
and do a QA
you know what I should do - while we're
starting this up
I should see about does this thing log
into twitch I don't even know if it is
if it is I should see if we need to raid
anybody after this you know I'm saying
to you how do I do that again I know
there's a way to do that okay follow
channels nope nobody streaming Johnson
streaming a bunch lately but he's not
streaming now so I cannot raid him just
find you check see you're returning zero
sort of results in the function you
created to find the box oh thank you for
that we don't actually use that at the
moment but we do want to do that so just
you know we don't want to have to go
hunt that down - someone already spotted
it because we're when we do actually
make it work we we would be kind of
grumpy about that so thanks for that
cash yeah if we'd probably spend some
time back and go wait why isn't Rick Oh
cuz it's zero right so saves us that
which is good
not sure I relevant but the problem
seems related to important sampling
lights in Montecarlo rate racers exactly
that I mean that is literally what we're
doing this is a Monte Carlo ray tracer
and it is trying to use some direct
light light sampling to improve the
results I the problem is we're not so
the Monte Carlo important sampling part
of things that part is more about
figuring out how to wait the results you
know whereas that's not what we're doing
here because we haven't gotten to that
stage yet well we're trying to just
figure out how do we want to look it up
right and so Monte Carlo rate racers
also have this problem but probably a
lot of them just use a separate spatial
partition for the light lookups I doubt
they use the KD tree for that although
maybe they do right I was just curious
we can use the same one it's hard to say
you know but what a typical Monte Carlo
red tracer will do is on every bounce as
its tracing out array it will randomly
pick a number and if that number comes
up you know heads or whatever it'll
shoot towards the light instead of the
bounce direction you know the direction
it would have chosen because it's
already got to pick a stochastic
direction in terms of sampling the BS DF
or whatever that's doing you know and
it'll like randomly like biased towards
the light sources or hot regions in the
scene what lessons you learn from
implementing Hammad heroes debug
inspection system I don't think we
really did I guess what I would say is
we have the only real reach thing I
learned about that was you can't really
work on stuff that complicated on stream
it doesn't really work we would need
another hundred hours to get that to a
place I think was really good and
probably I would need to be thinking
about it more deeply and not talking all
the time right so I think we could do a
good version of it but I'd need to like
think about it off stream I don't think
really complicated
architectures lovely that works
particularly well on stream that's the
only real lesson I learned from it it
just it just doesn't lend itself well
you need a more concentrated thought
time any other cues
there is a follow-up question okay I'm
waiting for the follow-up
are there any performance impacts to
storing large arrays of data as static
global constants no there there are not
I mean sometimes you don't want to do
that because you want a little bit more
control over about when and where those
things are created and initialized right
and when you store large arrays of
static Global's then those are going to
be done at you know load time by the OS
loader that's like partitioning your
memory space and you can't like place
them where you want them you know you
couldn't have a base address with
virtual Alec if you wanted you couldn't
put them near or far from something else
you don't really know how they're gonna
be aligned necessarily and let's use an
alignment specifier and blah blah blah
right so you know sometimes it's and
also they won't show up on your memory
if your memory allocator tracks things
they won't show up there because they
didn't get allocated quote/unquote by
your allocator they got allocated by the
system this allocator at startup so
there's reasons why I don't generally do
that I usually if I'm gonna have large
sort of arrays that are declared in C
I'll stick them in a struct and then
I'll allocate that struct just so it
goes through my allocator and usually
again that's just because it's nice to
not have a huge amount of data segment
space just getting created there unless
you really need it so sometimes you'll
do it because like in the debug system
for example you really need it to just
be a globally accessible variable or
something then that's fine but a lot of
times I just won't do it that way not
because there's this like some kind of
super bad thing but just you know
Jesse Meyer is a non-tree apart of
difficulty of the inherent limitations
of C you originally had to implement
various meta programming tooling or was
the ideal system you want just
inherently complex yeah I would say it's
both of those things
it is both complex and C doesn't do it c
/ c++ doesn't do it correctly so it is
both of those it's both both of those
things are true G's OpenGL unfortunately
yes
I probably wouldn't have done that today
but when we were showing how to
interface with a 3d card at the time
OpenGL was probably the best or I
thought was probably the best solution
the reason for that is just because I
wanted to have them have it be as likely
as possible that people could follow
along on their own operating system and
OpenGL at the time ran on Windows Mac
and Linux subsequent to that Mac which I
know a lot of people develop on for
reasons I'm not quite sure but they do
OpenGL look doesn't really run on there
anymore you can sort of run it but it's
like really deprecated and buggy and bad
and Apple specifically said don't ever
use it right there like don't use OpenGL
we're not supporting it anymore you have
to use metal so given that turn of
events I probably would have just used D
3d and and certainly if someone's like
writing a game that's not for
educational purposes I would say
definitely don't use open Jill I would
say use D 3 D 11 on Windows and use
metal on Mac and don't bother with Linux
because people don't buy games on
and if they do they can use like the
valve translation layer that does D 3d
translation or something right
you add lights separately or bundled it
with other objects in the scene like
lamps for example so they're probably
going to be a mixture of the two we will
probably have so right now entities can
specify that they have lighting on them
right so we will probably do something
where some entities like lamps or other
things are just set to have an emitter
on them and then that'll just happen or
something right and then in other cases
we may because again it's the it's an
artistic intent issue right so in other
cases we'll probably add lights to the
system there may be there to help with
with just coloring in areas in ways that
maybe don't really have a reason to be
there like there there may not actually
be like a physical thing creating the
light you know what I mean
because it's a fairly whimsical
environment it's you know it's cartoony
it's not so you know it's not like we're
doing something where we where we really
want to like push the realism and and
have it look really like a real scene so
we probably want to put in lights that
are not really there sometimes and stuff
like that
not a question we just want to tell you
I lost two daughters twins due to a
freak accidents and binging handmade
here helped a lot with managing the loss
during the hardest time you helped with
more than you probably think
okay so not sure how to totally respond
to that because that sounds very
horrific kind of had like this this
vision in my head of like The Shining or
something and you know like they'll -
two twin daughters with the crazy blood
flowing through or something like that
that was very scary and I guess I would
say I'm very glad we could help with
that but I guess that's not me right
that's just trying to prove
I suppose that's just saying look there
needs to be something that you can take
your mind off of something that horrific
and if we could do that for you that's
great but hey man that that ain't me
like there's nothing I can do about
something that bad right I guess I'm
just providing a good diversion which is
more than fine by me I mean if I can
help in some small way with something
like that then I'm I'm thumbs up but
yeah that sounds terrible I guess is
what I would say I've never had children
so I can't really relate directly right
but you know I can I can imagine that
that that's probably one of the worst
things that can happen to you as a
person right
humans are are pretty hard bound to
their to their offspring right that's
like a pretty primal survival instinct
so there's nothing you can really do
about that like your emotions are gonna
be really really violent in any case
that's that's that bad we should have
some kind of a distraction stream like a
not thinking about lost stream we can
have handmade hero loss diversion
programming
do you think the current trend of
dedicated ray-tracing hardware is the
right way to go for GPUs solving the
lighting problem is there another route
you would like to see I guess what I
would say is I don't necessarily know if
having dedicated ray tracing hardware is
the way to solve the lighting problem or
the right way to solve the lighting
problem but what I would say is we don't
know what else to do right
so I don't know what the right solution
to lighting is you know as you can see
it's just really difficult to make it
work
I think if Nvidia had an idea a better
idea they would do it so I mean the
reason they're doing what they're doing
is we don't know like light gets
transmitted along Ray's ray tracing is
the only thing we know about that solves
the lighting transport problem in a
general sense we don't know what else to
do if someone comes up with something
brilliant that turns out to be like way
better we would use it right but we
don't know and so I certainly don't have
some other route I would suggest because
I don't know what else you do you know
stochastic ray tracing is the only thing
we really know how to do it's the
cornerstone of all production rate
renderers for like high-end stuff you
know that renders movies and whatever
like nobody does anything else so it's
pretty much all we got and so it may not
be good just because it's so slow but I
don't know what else you do so just
throwing a ton of hardware at it and
crossing our fingers is possibly the
only real path forward and the good news
is that it's a incredibly parallelizable
problem
so you know when you think about
something like rasterization there's
like order dependencies and things like
this ray-tracing has none of those so
you can literally just throw tons of
hardware with no communication
whatsoever at a rate raising problem and
it just gets better right so the good
news about ray-tracing and the reason
why maybe it could be a right solution
in in the long run is look you can throw
62 chips each with 300 cores into a
machine and have them all rate race and
none of them need to talk to each other
about anything right you've got a
problem of how you distribute the scene
geometry out to them and how they
actually get information about like what
textures they're hitting and stuff and
that's a problem but it's still fully
apparent they don't need to talk to each
other to do it right like nobody needs
to synchronize or like they just need
access so you're just talking about how
do you replicate information across a
wide network of computing elements but
if you can you're done because if you
can get it replicated out to enough
things they will just run in parallel
and they never need to talk to each
other and that's a really powerful
element of ray-tracing that that it has
that not many other things do right so
that's the really nice aspect of
ray-tracing is it's it just works but
you know beyond that it's just a really
brute force thing
bowlinator says I really like the
platform and renderer setup you have if
your renderer needed to load files for
shaders of something or had to allocate
a lot of stuff would you reimplemented
civic functions in the renderer or would
you pass your platform api struct to the
renderer initialize and use the ones you
mean if executable implemented I think
the answer is for the most part I don't
think a renderer should really be
loading anything so I would probably try
to do that stuff with feed-forward so
meaning I would want the platform
independent stuff to do the loading and
I would want it to pass it to the
renderer I can't think of any reasons
why you can't do that like you should
just be able to do that always so that's
what I would do in terms of allocation
though I would say that should all live
inside the renderer and the reason for
that is because the renderer may need to
be doing a special-purpose kinds of
allocation so when the renderer needs to
do things like allocate texture space
and stuff like that that should be
happening inside the renderer because
it's the only thing that knows what kind
of memory and when that needs to happen
so I would say there's a slit there
resource loading should go through the
standard pipeline because it needs to
take advantage of the multi-threading
and different sort of scheduling things
so you really want that to be in the
platform independent part of stuff but
everything else you mentioned I think
wants to go in the renderer all right
I'm gonna go ahead and wrap it up we
definitely have our work cut out for us
tomorrow although everything kind of
went reasonably today we kind of have a
problem of that light source yeah not
sure exactly how we're gonna do that but
we're gonna we're gonna have to think
that through so I'm gonna wrap it up for
now let's go ahead and close this down
thank you everyone for joining me for
those sort of handmade here oh it's been
a pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow on the series
at home you always peer to the game
handmade here or it comes with a source
code so that you can follow along with
it I will be back here same time same
place tomorrow to take a look at that
lighting and how we're gonna actually
track what direction the lights go in
inside the spaceship partition or maybe
we'll introduce some totally separate
way of handling it but either way we're
gonna do something related to that and
I'll be back here tomorrow to do that
until then have fun programming and I
will see y'all on the Internet take it
easy everybody