everyone and welcome to handmade hero
show recode a complete game live on
stream I am going to start today by just
mentioning something very briefly
because I get asked this a lot of
handmade hero and I thought that I would
just kind of give this specific example
so people understand why I take the
position I normally do on a lot of
things so if you remember a while back
on handmade hero while we were trying in
the middle of trying to work Visual
Studio popped up a dialog box asking us
if we want to fill out a survey and so
we did fill out a survey and we
mentioned a bunch of things I was like
here are all the things that are
problematic with Visual Studio and you
know there's a big long list of them for
the way that we use it which is just as
a debugger so we didn't have any
feedback about like project editing or
any of those or text editor because we
don't use like that but we use it to
step through in the debugger because
it's the most efficient debugger right
now on Windows so that's what we use and
so we filled out that survey now oddly
enough and this was somewhat shocking to
me because and I suppose but to be
honest bowed slightly well at least for
Microsoft they actually called me and
wanted to talk about it so that's a good
thing it's the first time they've ever
listened to anything to the best of my
knowledge from somebody who was trying
to give them feedback so I guess that's
a plus I but one of the things that
happened is they were like could you
update to the latest version and I asked
like could because they were like you
know some of the things that you're
talking about we want to be able to help
with and they said that like they now
have in the latest version ability to
take a trace of the state of visual
studio so you can submit bug reports
more easily or things like that so it's
like okay so as you know my normal
policy is once I install a developer
tool I don't update it till the end of
the project and the reason that I've
said many times for doing this is
because usually it
so it goes very poorly usually the tool
gets worse when you update it oftentimes
the update breaks things and so on and
so what I thought I'd show you is this
is what happened when I went to go
install the latest version I clicked on
there update button and it couldn't
update itself right it's incredibly
simple program Visual Studio all it is
it's just an editor and you know it's
just a it's just an editor that's all it
is right you know it should be an
executable on a drive that's really all
it would have to have two or three
executables maybe one for the compiler
once the linker one for the IDE but of
course it's not because the way that
it's developed is is this huge sprawling
mass of millions of com components and
dll's and c-sharp and SQL server
I'm not joking there's actually an SQL
server that gets installed just around
Visual Studio and as a result even
something as simple as updating the
application is fraught with peril the
chance that an update will succeed on
Visual Studio is is almost zero most of
the time when I do it it doesn't work
and that was exactly case this time so
I've only tried to update at one time
and here's what happened right so what
did I have to do exactly what you
normally have to do in this circumstance
I had to get rid of the whole thing and
reinstall it again from scratch which
thankfully worked sometimes that doesn't
even work but it worked this time but
that was just a cautionary tale and sort
of more examples of what I'm talking
about nowadays it's just not safe to
upgrade your development tools it will
cost you actual work hours that you
could have been doing something
productive to update your tools and of
course as you will see when we start
using Visual Studio we don't get any
benefit in this case there's perhaps
some benefit to the developers of the
software because now we can report bugs
whether or not they fix them I don't
know so whether or not they'll ever be
any benefit to us is questionable but
there's certainly no immediate benefit
to us because they haven't upgraded
anything that we need so yeah word to
the wise
don't ever update your developer tools
if they're working leave them as they
are because the chances that you will
get anything improved is
very low and the chances that something
will break very high alright with that
public service announcement out of the
way I'm gonna go ahead and go pop over
here to something that was brought to my
attention on the pre stream but I wanted
to wait till the actual stream to take a
look at it because I think it's probably
something that we that everyone out
there will want to download if they're
on an nvidia card like we are at the
moment which is that i have been
previously using n sites plugin for
visual studio now I don't like the
insight plug-in for visual studio not
because I don't like n site I'd like
insight I just don't like the plug
individual studio I don't like using
Visual Studio I only use it because it's
the only debugger that I really have on
Windows that I found that's effective
but I would much rather have a
standalone application purpose-built and
more reliable hopefully than visual
studio to do graphs debugging an insight
if I remembered correctly and I could be
wrong with this used to be that way and
then they changed it to only having a
visual studio plug-in and I've never
cared for that but you know it was the
only way to use it so that's how I used
it but it was brought to my attention on
the pre steam that they have just
released a new standalone debugger for
NVIDIA cards and profiler and that to me
sounds absolutely fantastic that's
exactly what I would want I don't know
if it's any good because I haven't used
it yet but I'm assuming that it's
probably at least as good as the visual
studio plug-in hopefully and it
certainly looks better than the visual
studio plug-in I don't know if that's
any indication of the screenshots so I'm
pretty excited about being able to
replace that so I'm gonna go ahead and
download that as far as I know there are
no special criteria for you to have to
download it other than having to have an
Nvidia card I don't think there's
anything else you particular would have
to do so I'm just gonna go ahead and
give it a shot here at you can see it's
just developer job and video.com and
select graphics I hit the download now
button this downloads list on the side I
assume is all we really need I don't
know we may have to update our graphics
driver because it may
we work with the latest version of the
graphics drivers so that's probably fine
because I think that actually has been
getting updated anyway by itself I'm not
quite sure what's installed on this
machine at the moment in terms of auto
updating drivers but I feel like Windows
10 tends to install those I could be
wrong about that all right well I take
it back I thought it was something you
could just download apparently you can't
I do have one of these so I can grab it
by logging in on the machine where I've
got a password I don't remember one at
the moment so all right well here let me
see if I've got that here I don't
understand why they do that sort of
stuff it doesn't make a lot of sense to
me seems like you just want everyone
getting your program right I don't know
why I put up barriers like what what you
know they're obviously developing on an
nvidia card isn't that what you want
I don't know so let's see if I can log
in over here on this machine I think I
might have the password because I think
we had to do this for the original one
don't quote me on that but I'm gonna try
I seem to have a password written down
here let's see if I can log-in i well
it's not it's not having a problem with
my password but it is having a problem
with their login window which apparently
just doesn't work on Chrome oh it's
always an adventure isn't it folks
let's try Firefox
I am now trying to log in on Firefox
and I I cannot login on either of these
browsers and it's not it doesn't like
disallow my past or anything it's just
you just can't login I don't know what
to say is it just broken I don't get it
folks well I guess that's the end of
that for now I mean like it's not even
the dialog box won't even accept it it
just won't work well I wanted to try it
I couldn't try it I tried to login
I couldn't log in let me see what
happens on this one so if I'm on here
and I do login
so here's just me typing in ya see it
doesn't it doesn't do anything this
login window doesn't do anything so it
doesn't matter I guess it doesn't matter
what platform you're on you just can't
log in period so what's the deal what's
the deal folks hey NVIDIA do you know
how to programs website hey here we go
access is denied for this document
interesting it looks like someone forgot
to set their access control origin let's
take a look at what happened parser
blocking cross-site script is invoked by
a document right guys don't you know how
to do web programming what is wrong with
you dear Nvidia how do i refresh that
guy here we go
let's get that login window go in here I
also like you get to hear and it's like
all the stuff goes away where is there
okay there's ah so let's take a look at
who the offending person was here so
we've got assets dot Adobe TM Adobe DTM
com
so they maybe they must have made this
site in like one of those like crappy
--the site maker things there so where
is that guy let's see here's the so yeah
you can take a look at these here so
where were these scripts getting
accessed yes so you can even see here
these these these scripts don't have
they don't have access control origin
set right so you can't you can't yeah
these these scripts are not you can't
cross sight these scripts if these
scripts were stored on invidious site
they would probably work okay right but
they're coming from Adobe DTM comm and
you can't execute things across site
like that unless you put the access
control origin header in the response
headers so I don't really know why they
ever thought that login would work on a
modern browser because you can't
cross-site script like that
I don't without installing a plug-in I'm
not sure of any way to let that to force
it to let me add the access control
origin header in there you can like you
can't install plug-ins for both Chrome
and Firefox to do access control allow
origin by default and then you don't get
because it's a browser side check right
so what happened what happens is when
the browser goes to execute a script or
access anything really it checks to see
whether that thing came from the same
domain or not and if it doesn't come
from the same domain it looks in the
headers to see whether it has an access
control origin header that says that
it's allowed to execute it and I assume
that's what's going on here although I'm
not 100% sure because
this part it seems fine this is just an
old certificate but it's not expired
it's not out of compliance yet I'm not
100% sure that I've seen this exact
error before
because that error this is just an
advisory and isn't that specific one
so this document here filled through the
local storage property for window axes
the nine for this document
where is handler dot J s actually from
you can see it in here so here's where
we're here's where it's at right so this
get window is returning the window from
the window handler right and then
they're trying to access this local
storage which in theory exists at this
point so it's it's not telling us that
that's an illegal line of code right
what is telling us is that it's not
allowed to access it so basically this
handler dot J s which I don't know this
came from developer done the video calm
I'm not sure why it's not allowed to
read it actually because my cross-site
assumption here I guess I guess the
problem was that it came from CDN auth0
I guess because I looked at the Adobe
one I thought the Adobe one came up here
but I guess that was just me looking at
this one erroneously I jumped to
conclusions
I looked up at this one but actually
this is not this is not the problem
right so it looks like this is actually
the problem and it isn't involved Adobe
one but they are they've moved this off
0 Minjae s that's on a CDN Deezy off
iframe dot J's is not on the CDN so
those are coming from two different
top-level domains I don't know whether
or not that specifically what it's
complaining about because it's not
saying exactly why it simply says that
the access is denied so it could be
because of that or maybe it's not but
let's take a look at the headers there
so again none of none of these have
there's there's a lot of weird stuff
going on here in fact this is this is
this is kind of this is kind of borked
in a lot of ways so I don't really want
to go down the rat hole of web program
you know we already kind of have so this
is kind of worked as well because as you
can kind of see here this is not an
e-tag resource but it's it's age is very
high right so this resource for example
if it got updated the CDN would still
possibly push a really old version or
the browser could cache it because as
you can see the cache control is
allowing it to keep it for quite some
time but this is not a tagged file name
so typically like what you would do in
this scenario right is if you have
something like a script that's being
pushed to a CDN and it's allowed to be
cached on this on the client side
typically what you do is you set the max
age to something very high but then you
tag the name so that if you ever need to
change this javascript you update the
name to a different name right and off
zero Minjae s maybe that's tagged like
maybe the zero is the tag but don't look
tagged right so I don't know about that
this this looks pretty questionable so I
don't even know if we've got the latest
version of this it could be that one
problem we're having is that we're
getting served an old version of
something out of the CDN for example
right but it's hard to say so so I'm not
really sure about that exactly I'm not
sure what the problem is if this is the
latest one and there's just a you know
mistake there or what's going on but
anyway so it's a bit it's a bit wonky
even to begin with but it also doesn't
have the access control origin header
set on it which means that none of these
you know none of these things here are
going to allow cross-site scripting of
any kind so I'm not sure how that would
even be meant to work in the first place
necessarily it's hard to say
where is this other guy DZ off I frame
and keep in mind I'm not a web
programmer so take everything I'm saying
with a grain of salt here here we go so
DZ off iframe yeah also doesn't have it
also doesn't have the cross origin
headers and it's an in an iframe which
means it needs another header as well
the iframe also needs a spot a special
thing to tell to tell it that it allows
cross site hmm so this is this is rough
so I think our best bet since I don't
think we're going to be able to edit the
source code here because the source code
isn't the problem it's the access
control that's the problem which means
that in order to get this to work we're
gonna have to inject some authorization
in here in order to click on the login
button and so what I need is I need a
way to allow the cross site scripting
you can see I mean it's definitely a
cross-site problem even if I fail to if
I fail to diagnose it 100% correctly we
at least know that it is a cross-site
problem because you can see that it's a
dom exception on access denied
right for the particular document so I
don't know any other way that that could
occur it's not saying that it can't find
that property it's not saying that
something's wrong with the code it's
literally just saying that you're trying
to access the property of a window
that's a that's not in the same access
ring as you are right and I don't know
any other way for that particular to
happen other than cross-site me but
there might be right it might be some
more if you were a web programmer you
might know some more subtle way that
that can happen so the question is
chrome allow cross-site script access
so you know the question is can we just
use some simple way to turn it off right
and and see what happens so let's see
here so if we disable web security
it looks like oops we go
if we launch with this flag looks like
maybe it will do it so let's let's give
that a shot just to see if maybe there's
a way that we can make this work and
then I'll do it on the other machine and
actually login I don't know if that
switch actually works it's on stock
exchange so you know roll the dice but
if we go to Google Chrome here let's see
if we can find the startup there's
chrome Bugsy so in theory if I go ahead
and close this out here and we do
kromaggs see and we do a paste for
disable web security you know off we go
so stability and security will suffer
that's a good sign it looks like it
probably took our advice right and it's
doing that so now let's see whether or
not we can get to the login screen so
I'm going to go ahead and
prophylactically open up the developer
tools here again that's f12 if you don't
know if you want to do this at home on
Chrome it's also in here in the more
tools area right this developer tools
thing here ctrl shift I I guess also I
hit f12 but I guess it's either/or so
now if I type some stuff in here and I
click login let's see if anything
happens nope still problematic so we
really just don't know what the access
denied for this document thing is
telling us here what's the issue if that
if it wasn't that if that doesn't turn
it off you know what is it so let's take
a look over here in in the sources tab
again and let's let's bring up that line
of code so you can see here that it's
it's presumably not getting the new to
the new cookie storage part of things
the other thing I mean I suppose we
could do is the is the this storage part
I mean can we just
can can we simplify this in some way I
don't know but let's take a look at
these values just you know as they go so
window handler is not defined hmm
so maybe this is just a regular bug do
you think
I don't think so this is I think that's
just the top level being grumpy with us
I think this probably I don't know
enough JavaScript to say I'm not a
JavaScript programmer at all right so I
have no idea but I'm assuming that
that's just the fact that for whatever
reason we're not like the exception
throughout of this or something here's a
question can we just get right in there
and break right if I'm in there can I
look at it oops didn't mean to do that
definitely didn't mean to do that
okay so if I break on that line but no
no no no luck there so I don't really
yeah I guess I don't really stand this
this probably takes more JavaScript
know-how than I've got to know what's
going on here here's the dis pointer
right which is the thing that's that's
active in here if I open it up we can
see what's on it right and it wants to
add these two it wants to add storage it
already added warned which is probably
why that one's there right here you can
see it here it is and it never was able
to do the storage line now I'm not sure
where window handler
I don't know this syntax this require
syntax right this looks like it's trying
to say include this thing or something
right but I don't I'm not familiar with
I've never used that in my very limited
amount of JavaScript programming time
right
so what required does in general I
couldn't tell you so we might want to
look up JavaScript require and see what
it actually does it looks like I mean as
far as I can tell it looks like it's
exactly what I thought it was which is a
way to include a module and it looks
like it's maybe no js' so in terms of
the answer of why this isn't working
no js' is a very good first first step
because
you know it's no js' that's pretty much
guaranteed to not be working
particularly well so when we come in
here and we see that this thing
presumably should have done this require
I guess this didn't actually properly do
whatever no js' nonsense was actually
supposed to happen to get the window
handler executed now again since I'm not
a JavaScript programmer I don't know why
so again since this is kind of turning
into can we actually hack around the log
in to Nvidia developer site and when I
say hack around I don't even mean hack
around like not log in I mean use our
legitimate log in with their buggy login
code I'm just gonna try coming back here
and seeing if I can set a breakpoint on
that particular piece of code in order
to and unfortunately it seems to have
gotten rid of that though where where
did that come from I was gonna see if I
Chi said a breakpoint and so we could
just sort of step into it you know and
see what happened when we when we did
that but I don't actually know it might
be that until I do login it doesn't oops
not join
let's try login all right
so when we go to do our login here let's
see do we have some information so
here's that DZ off Moodle iframe bit
right that this is the thing that's
getting loaded for the login and I'm
just going through here and looking to
see what actually gets loaded here so
here's that initial off zero Minjae s
bit it's a minified piece of JavaScript
right it's well it's been like kind of
compressed down to a certain degree
anyway let's see about that here's
here's some of the other pieces there's
that DZ off iframe part what else we got
here
symmetric here's webpack so this is some
way of I get I don't even know what this
is but I guess this is this is the way
of serving stuff compressed it looks
like as a as a as like a bundle of eight
billion you know JavaScript files for I
don't don't even get me started on that
but you know all right
so yeah I don't remember where we were
in here there's that cross origin
authentication bit where were we on the
where were we I don't remember where we
were where I wanted to set that here it
is
so it's hand lured up so here's where
ideas for future reference it's the web
pack source helper storage handler j/s
and it looks like it even remembered my
breakpoint so that's kind of awesome
right now whether it actually did
anything on that breakpoint
I don't know so yeah because it should
have right but maybe it only executes
these once it gets to hear it but it I
mean correct me if I'm wrong but it
should have already executed that it
doesn't look like it did which is a bit
confusing so you can see like it never
actually executed this line of code
according to the breakpoint but in order
for this code to work it would have had
to write and so I'm a little confused as
to when this nominally got executed
because all global variables should have
been executed right before they are used
at very least so I'm not super certain I
understand why that breakpoint never hit
I mean maybe that's just a bug in the
debugger and it really did get called
but of course if that never got called
that would be a pretty good reason to
say the least as to why you would not
have it defined when it gets here
because we're pretty sure at this point
that it wasn't right
it's supposed to have a window handler
thing in here and it definitely doesn't
right so let's go ahead and do this one
more time and you can see that we do
break here just fine right but Wow
so there text inputs pretty broken there
so yeah if we take a look at this here I
don't know that's just the VM that's not
a meaningful location that's just saying
here I think so
if we look at where we were evaluating
this it is trying to evaluate it right
here so I'm pretty certain that this
never got initialized right but what I
don't know is why it never got
initialized because again that looks
like it should have been the case now
let's find out if if well here's okay so
here's an interesting question what
about these other ones
the text input is horribly broken
I'm only typing w once but it puts it
there twice oh the web world so what's
interesting is like for example this
this doesn't new on this this is just
like reverse engineering how this
program programming language works right
so what's interesting is they do a new
on this one so this require here didn't
create one of these right in a sense
because they still had to make one of
them so this window handler I'm
wondering if there was a reason like if
if that actually means that in order to
get a window handler does that mean you
actually had to do this
so that's pretty interesting to me man I
don't know what they did you can't even
type in this thing it's so broken so let
me do this Warren here I'm going to do
the same line as was above so this is
even more fascinating so at this
location I cannot do Warren even though
they did Warren that way and they
clearly it worked so it must be that the
top level can't access those things
properly or something because you can
see that this worked just fine or at
least it seems to have worked just fine
right so I wonder if that's even further
[Music]
evidence I guess that I'm just not able
to use the top level to actually do any
testing on this
I don't get it I don't get it
I really don't so another question is
what if I just got rid of this
can I just get rid of it
I mean does that actually count is is
that will that actually modify that I
mean we could find out right actually I
guess let me do that here oh it already
brought me up here so here's our little
like you know attempt to overwrite
wherever we are
well we won't really overwrite it I
guess I don't know exactly what the best
way to do it can I do a console dot log
actually or something like that
JavaScript console output console dot
log log so if I do that I'm wondering if
there's a way I can tell it I want you
to do this thing prop you know is there
reinterpret this file please kind of
situation but I don't know if I can I
probably can't can I
so all right so let's just try it so it
didn't actually allow my change right
you can see that it's you know it still
thinks that it's the old line here so it
doesn't quite allow me to it doesn't
quite allow me to actually replace a
line of code with the line of code that
I wanted so let's see if I can do that
you know who knows chrome edit
JavaScript and continue so let's take a
look
[Music]
so do I just have to save it
let's see
hmm so that seemed to only be editing
things from the top level though like
that didn't seem to allow me to actually
change this I'll give it another shot
and we'll see so let's say I do a
refresher and oops you know I also
wonder what would happen if we just
loaded this site directly
look if we just did that because that's
a lot simpler right
oh hey so even though that's pretty
weird
what's with the air here no it's just a
post so even though that's pretty
interesting
so so when we use this as the only frame
because we're not in an iframe anymore
that code will work interesting
again that suggested it is the
cross-site they set the cross-site Flags
run on the iframe because iframes have
to have specific stuff set to be cross
frame let's try that over here and see
if I can actually log in right instead
of of using the pop-up if I just log in
instead so let's see this iframe there's
the source let's grab that out
I copy it
my username password in hey hey I think
that actually logged me in let's find
out
so now if I like refresh the page in my
logged in sadly not it doesn't seem like
it ah well you know I tried I tried
really hard this is the this is a case
where being knowledgeable about
JavaScript would help because I'm pretty
sure this is not hard to work around I
just don't have that experience right
like I don't know all of the ways in
which people mess up their code and so
when I see a bug like that unlike you
and C or something where I often have a
pretty good idea of what's going on in
JavaScript I'm like I don't know what
that error comes from right I have no
idea because I just don't have that
experience and I'm not I'm not fast I
with the language you know I don't know
what a require directive actually
doesn't know DJ s I have no idea so
let's take a look at what happened here
cuz it did it does allow me to proceed
but it must not set the login cookie or
it sets the login cookie but for the
wrong site or something let's see here
it seems like maybe like because it goes
to a register callback and but it
doesn't it doesn't seem to actually done
anything useful for us you know
hmm
what if I inspect this guy right here
and paste that in there
ah I did it okay so let me tell you how
I did it so I did go ahead and put this
in its own frame like this I put in my
username and password and did the login
which brought me to a callback
but that callback didn't do anything so
I cut and pasted that callback URL into
the iframe on this page so I basically
went like this looked at this guy right
found the iframe here and I pasted the
callback in here that actually did set
the cookie properly and now I am logged
in ladies and gentlemen the fine power
of modern technology at our disposal the
future of software no less the future is
me having to learn javascript to log
into a frigging web page alright let me
go ahead and copy onto a thumb drive
this program that we wanted to use oh
man there's gonna be a man on Mars
before the web is even barely usable all
right let's see here which one of this
it's put on there and hope this works
looks like it's still writing and now
it's done at long last ladies and
gentlemen I am proud to drag I guess the
nvidia n site graphics installer to our
desktop i think we've earned it here we
had to go all the way in and all the way
back out again should really put vodka
in this thing forget coffee let's see if
it works we may have to also download
updated drivers hopefully those are
available to everybody and not just
registered developers but well i since
since this thing's got the cookie set
hopefully that that's the only thing at
that point
this doesn't seem to be going too well
here we go that all seems good and again
I don't know if this includes the graphs
driver so we may need them you know what
let's go ahead and just find out which
ones we even have cuz I don't know
388 13 and actually let me just look at
its it said specifically which version
it wanted you to have here required and
video display driver which is this okay
so yeah we're like definitely not up to
date here so we want this one let's get
totally fine totally fine
yeah it's cool don't worry about it bro
I know how to program JavaScript now not
really so let's see if I can grab that
from here because I am logged in over
here there it is
yep perfect so thankfully didn't have to
go through that again it remember the
cookie thank God for cookies right or
more specifically I suppose you know
thanking God God didn't really give us
cookies Paul Newman gives us cookies so
thank Paul Newman but either way thank
you old bearded white man for for giving
us cookies because without cookies they
would have had to go through that whole
thing again although now that I know how
to do it I could do that pretty quickly
I suspect all right will we be able to
actually run this profiler before the
episode is over that's that's the
question at this point right but we're
sort of on a mission so I think you know
I think we're gonna make it we've got a
while I got an hour
okay
off we go actually I probably shouldn't
have launched that from the D Drive but
you know too late now I accidentally
double clicked
I'm also going to put these in here I
guess
and when this is done I'll put it in
there as well
hopefully our system is compatible
it's thinking about it all right so we
got a graphics driver that's good a 3d
vision control driver I don't know what
that is I don't any of this stuff is so
let's just get rid of those I don't want
an experience and I don't want physics
so I think we're good with just graphics
driver and audio driver that's all we
want right
oh so people say in blocking cookies I
don't I do block cross-origin stuff
though but I thought we disabled that
with the other cross-origin part right
like this so here in settings
well of course actually doesn't matter
what this one's set to because I
downloaded it it didn't work on the
other one either
yeah so no I'm definitely not blocking
cookie thing I block these which you
should always block because that's
basically just advertising tracking
right so if your site doesn't work with
that thing on your super busted right
because you should never need a
third-party cookie if you wrote your web
code properly you never need a
third-party cookie for any legitimate
purpose right you're just being sloppy
but we allow full cookies from everybody
else right and that's the same that I
haven't said on the other machine and by
the way all other logins work just fine
so no it pretty much is their code is
messed and I think the reason their code
is is messed up is because I think
they're trying to do cross-origin cookie
it absolutely is cross-origin
it's a cross-origin bug I know this
because on one hand the handmade hero
site I have to because it gets served
from a CDN now I specifically had to
make that work I'm not a web programmer
and our site does cross-origin properly
so I can pretty much guarantee you that
it's not me it's them if people allow
cross-origin cookies all right I mean
maybe you just want to be tracked by
advertisers and stuff like that but you
shouldn't and there's no legitimate
reason for it it's never something that
you actually want on because any piece
of code that was written coherently can
set its access control properly to make
it so that that's not a problem right
it's not hard anyway let's see like I
said if I know how to do it it can't be
hard uh so let's see here it looks like
we're all good let's go ahead and
restart
you
hello so every time you reinstall
graphics drivers that breaks
unfortunately yeah again modern
computing it's fantastic so now in
theory after all that work hopefully
this will we'll actually be able to
execute find out so here we go
oh and godling said do you want shooter
debugging I think that's only in the
insight visual addition but I so like
maybe they updated it I don't know but
at least in the old version there was no
shooter debugging anyway shader
debugging doesn't work on 1080s
on well on effect um you know ten series
graphics cards they didn't support
shaded debugging anyway so we didn't a
state a debugging the old 600 series did
and maybe you know maybe they added it
recently I don't know but you know when
we were when we installed it a few like
a month or two ago it didn't it you
couldn't debug shaders anyway so let's
see here here is our Nvidia insight
graphics if I like can I put that down
here yeah so let's see if we can launch
that
of course I don't know how to use it but
let's try builds I mean through your
handmaid that's not the directory I want
handmade data and that should just work
I think probably hopefully not actually
sure
so
[Music]
does that mean that it just couldn't
connect to the process or does that mean
it couldn't send the error report let's
hope it just means it couldn't send the
error I mean that it couldn't take to
the process and that it sent the error
report I guess I don't know what to say
[Music]
so what it mean is that it was that was
at the end of the it's at the end of the
fun or maybe I'll try making a project
here's that legendary startup time
so
[Music]
it doesn't even look like it knows about
my process
do I have to link with a special
something or I should probably read the
documentation maybe there's something
obvious I'm not doing let's try saying
new project handmade hero okay well you
know what let's actually try to put this
in w w and made where would this go and
made Nvidia and made hero
so here is a our project it's pretty
spiffy and I'm getting a feeling that
this is gonna be exactly the same as
before but you know is hope springs
eternal
so there's 132 handmade the working
directory is handmade data if I'm not
mistaken there are no command-line
arguments automatically connect is yes I
guess maybe we should set that to no and
see if that helps us if we connect
subsequent so that's good
[Music]
oh man so no it was actually saying it
can't send the error report so not only
is the program broken but the thing that
reports how the program is broken is
also broken
well what if we set the working
directory to dislike build or something
let's just look at the welcome page for
a while since that's the only thing that
works it's got a nice this is nice I
like that design it's like a little like
wireframe with a flat shaded polygons
there
so here we got some I mean I'm basically
just I give up at this point on the
world vol bus as far as I know not have
the CRT oh you think the fact that we
compiled without the CRT is what makes
it crash because it needs the CRT to be
there for some reason
she tells q says I think you're getting
the nvidia experience after all yeah I
kind of feel like it maybe run the
profile as an admin so those are both
reasonable theories I don't feel like
you have to be an admin makes a lot of
sense but we'll try it link it with a C
runtime library might be harder I don't
know how easy it is for us to restart
linking with it but we can try anyway
let's go ahead and load that project oh
but we're gonna have to so first we're
gonna have to substance is substant
drives or per user so we've got to
subsidize under the admin user so here
we are an admin no dice and so let's try
the other thing that was suggested like
is it possible that it's just because we
don't have C runtime library installed
and I don't know that could be here's
the build up app for the C runtime
library if I just forced it to be in
there that is just just the snow default
Lib I think if I get rid of it I don't
know if we can compile that way though
it might be multiplied to find symbol
problem I'm not sure so that should have
the C runtime library back in let's make
sure because we can't actually check to
see one time libraries giant bloated
pile of poop and so let's just take a
look at whether it actually got stuck in
there I don't think it did so there's
one through two handmade and you can see
that the executable size doesn't seem to
have changed so I don't think that
actually did it
hmm so what I probably have to do is to
put a - empty D in here as well as get
rid of the no default Lib I know I still
think that's probably not doing it it
doesn't am i doing something wrong
because I feel like normally it makes
the size of this cutable quite a bit
bigger if you actually link to the C
runtime library and it's not looking any
bigger oops so I'm not sure that it I
actually can get it to do that I will
have to see if maybe I mean maybe that's
the case we'll see but I got to convince
the compared to a queue that guess the
other question is is it even writing it
dependency Walker can't even load it
it's not a good sign
so there it is gone we've got - MTD
specified and no default lib is gone
unfortunately dependency Walker it's
just a bad day for computing it's just
you know trashed unfortunately
and I'm not quite sure why like it
shouldn't take this long for depends to
load in executable it must be having
trouble with something I just don't know
what does anybody still open here
besides Cortana look at this nonsense
so I couldn't tell you why that's I mean
that should have built with the C
runtime library in there it sure doesn't
look like it did
why on earth we can't run dependency
Walker I don't even want to know but you
know welcome to the future if I come in
here to visual studio I guess if I step
in
I can look to see where we are I mean
yeah you could see it's not it's not in
here so it's not it's still not linking
us with the C runtime library and I
guess the reason for that is because
even if we're specifying this switch
because nothing in here is asking for
the C runtime library it just doesn't
get it right it doesn't get pulled in so
I don't know standard i/o and malloc and
stuff are in here right I mean there it
is
so I feel like that should have pulled
it in if we didn't explicitly turn it
off but but it doesn't so I'm not sure
how to force it to link that in it
really doesn't seem to want to and I'm
not sure how to tell it you know to to
force it in there because as far as I
could tell that should have told it to
put it in there right so I don't know I
got nothing
I'm not sure how I would tell it any
more explicitly to do that well that was
a complete waste of time
so there we go
Wow all right fantastic wonderful great
love it
windows it's great it's fantastic
Mountain software it's wonderful the web
great good everything's super wonderful
this is this is apparently what will be
running cars in the future is this kind
of mentality as well so that's good I
can't wait to walk down the streets with
that happening so I guess that's see it
for handmade here today while I'm here
maybe I'll delete standard i/o and
malloc tat H I don't know why they were
here
we're we actually depending on those in
some way so we're just left over so yeah
great good wonderful fabulous mmm I'm
gonna go to your head and go to
questions and answers I don't have any
answers for you other than it's hopeless
give up now the future of software is
doomed don't bother
yeah we could try with the with the
entry point but we don't really bypass I
mean okay so maybe just the fact that we
defined this one bypasses the entry
point but this is so it probably just
maybe the linker just removed all the
dead code that could be why right so if
we did this I don't really know what the
boilerplate for win main is offhand I
haven't typed it since the beginning of
handmade here I probably
all right so that stuff will now make us
not the entry point right so if I do
this now in fact maybe I can do this so
that in theory should build it there it
is look it's that's what we needed
perfect it's five times its size so now
it's the standard so maybe that's fine
all right so if I load up this situation
again and I load the project that way it
should be shouldn't be like right here
yeah so here's the project and I hit
launch resounding success
hey that one's sent though before we
couldn't send it that one we actually
were able to send so that's something so
what ain't that it's not administrative
rights it's not because we weren't
looking with a C runtime library anyone
have any more really fun guesses
- usually anything like medipartner to
make modern OpenGL more tolerable yeah I
do
use a generator to generate like the
function loading stuff
what is the editor you use the
simplicity of it appeals to me as
someone who used to work on a UNIX
kernel back in the day it's called for
coder and it was actually written
specifically as like a result of Alan
Webster watching me previously use Emacs
which is kind of a pile these days on
stream and you can get it here at for
coder h2o
it's at the incredibly expensive
spensive price of $12 which is a bargain
by any stretch of the imagination and I
highly recommend it
it's programmable in C and it comes with
my config as well so if you just want to
use mine you can but it's programmable
and C so you can program it yourself
in C without having to learn like Lisp
or something like you would if you were
using something like Emacs or some other
proprietary scripting language or Python
or C sharp or whatever so if you're a C
programmer and just wants to program C
you can just program C and it's pretty
nice that way does it still work with a
visual studio plug-in of n site that's a
good question
let's try so if we were to take our
current builds and try it here now to be
fair so the answer is no and but my
other question is since we updated the
graphics driver do we have to update n
site again and I don't know so is there
an update now button or do I have to
turn on updates reboot you know update
oops that's not what I wanted you know
update again I don't know right
wait where's the thing there is
extensions and updates so interestingly
it's not in here
what what does that even mean
what is this garbage I don't know what
any of this stuff is and I certainly
didn't install any of it oh boy now I've
done it
I don't okay I hit the what do you need
to know I hit this button just get rid
of it I don't need you to open up some
other window why is it what is happening
in the world why is it opening this I
don't need like I just told you what to
do I don't know or want to see any event
all right fantastic
anyway I'm wondering if you have to
update insight so what I'm gonna do here
is I'm just gonna turn on automatic
updates that start up true true and true
hit okay and then I'm going to see if it
can update itself because we don't know
if updating the graphics driver may have
that's it now again what did I say it
was opening this thing never update
anything right
and this is why cuz everything gets
worse it doesn't work here's a check for
updates button it doesn't do anything oh
it does does it here get latest version
download here it's gonna it's gonna make
me log in again
it's an update what is wrong with you
okay it's fine
inside Visual Studio I'm scrolling down
I'm clicking downloads I'm downloading
it now
I'm putting the thumb drive into the
machine
and now I'm copying the file over to the
thumb drive I'm waiting for the right to
finish before pulling the thumb drive
out so as not to corrupt the right
and now I'm placing the thumb drive back
into the main machine
so now we know that that option is
completely worthless because it doesn't
update itself anyway so these can stay
false and we just go to the website when
we want a new version cuz we're gonna
have to do it anyway in the entire
process we'll be manual good to know all
right are we having fun yet
programming is wonderful such a great
occupation so here is my visual studio
edition I am going to double click on it
I'm going to allow it to continue to
destroy my development environment since
everyone else has today I don't see why
it shouldn't be given a chance as well
then we've got I don't know this HUD
launcher thing is we can play with that
possibly we might want something that I
don't know but let's go ahead and now
see if we can do what we want to do
before or if we're just permanently
screwed now nope
so yeah I guess if anything if there was
anything that could convince you of why
you never update your development
environment we started the day having
the ability to debug our graphics and we
ended the day without it and who knows
what will ever get it back probably not
but maybe who knows so there you have it
we have spent two hours trying to update
and our features regressed that is
pretty much exactly what I said
happens and it happened that's about all
I have to say for today there's really
nothing else you can say it's as if the
universe just wants to reinforce the
point don't ever touch your deaf
envelopment dev environment people it
can only make things worse and that is
the end of that I'm not going to take
any questions because there's really no
point I think you pretty much saw what
there is to see here
maybe we'll be back next week maybe we
won't maybe it's time to just take a
week off because honestly that was a
disaster and exactly everything that is
wrong with software today we started out
with the fact that Visual Studio
couldn't update properly then we had
Nvidia couldn't download stuff because
they have their site set up wrong and
then the software that we try to
download doesn't work anyway so that's
pretty awesome on so many levels
everybody just out to absolutely win
today fantastic it's great yeah I'd get
a day job somewhere and just kind of
phone it in if you want to be a
programmer don't actually care about
software because it will absolutely
destroy you spiritually because
literally no one else in the world is
even remotely interested in doing a good
job that's it for today I'll see you
back here in maybe two weeks take it as
everybody