hello everybody and welcome to handmade
Hero the show we could a complete game
live on stream we are going to do some
sampling fixes today we were right in
the middle of it last week and we didn't
really get a chance to finish so we've
got a couple things we got to do and one
of them actually will probably lead us
to do something that we have wanted to
do for a long time to kind of put off
and it's gonna happen which is to get
rid of the C runtime library why because
the only reason you know we still link
with the C runtime library at all we
almost don't use any of it but if you
look at what we actually do use here and
in fact we can go ahead and take a look
it's pretty easy to see oops so if we
you know look at our build that bad file
what we can see here is that you know
when we're compiling the code we are
still using just a pretty standard link
line right we don't have you can you can
see here I mean I guess one thing I
would say is it's a little misleading
because normally what happens when you
link a program is you're supposed to say
the things that you actually want to
link with and you can kind of see us
doing that in other places so for
example you see here when we build the
win32 loader we've got common linker
flags is one of the things that's there
and if you go look at what common linker
flags has in it you can see that common
linker flags has all of these libs on it
right and so you might think well okay
we can look at common linker flags and
those are the libraries that we're
linking with so there we go that's what
we must use but it's not actually true
and the reason that's not actually true
is because the C compiler makes some
assumptions about what you're probably
trying to do and those assumptions mean
that it will automatically link at least
two libraries usually that you didn't
ask for one is kernel32 and you'll
notice on here it'll 32 is not on this
link line right yet if we actually run
depends which I don't actually know if
we have depends on this one
or not yet do we have dependents on this
machine we had it on the other machine
that we used to use but I don't see it
on this one yeah I don't I don't see
depends on this one at all let's just go
ahead and download it because I think we
want it depends so if I grab this guy
here 2 2 6 4 X 64 and we'll just go
ahead and grab that out here so we'll
have it there we go if we go ahead and
run this we can I ask about what we're
actually linking with and we did this a
long time ago on handmade hero but you
know it was way at the beginning so you
know it's something that's kind of
ancient history now because we only did
it just you know very briefly at the
start to take a look at how the linking
was working but if we take a look here
on win32 handmade egg Z and I open this
up hopefully if assuming that it works
okay
who knows what this is talking about now
although you know the modern linking
environment of Windows which is
absolutely disgusting in horrendous you
can still if you collapse this stuff see
the actual libraries we depend on in
what you can see here is kernel32 is
there and it's always gonna be there
unless you do some really weird fancy
footwork there's actually some ways you
can not use it but as you've seen me do
in Windows you can use a thing called
get proc address to get the address of a
particular function in Windows and in
order to do that you need to have the
function load library and the function
get proc address because you need to be
able to load library the thing you want
to load that the place you want to get
the function from you need to call get
proc address to get it right to need
those two things well
in order to get those two functions they
have to come from somewhere and you
can't use load library and get proc
address to get them because those are
the ones you need to get functions so
kernel32 is the minimum requirement to
link with on Windows if you want to then
link with everything else right so we
don't have to link with any of these
dll's
on the command line we could load them
and then link with them dynamically at
runtime if we want to and in fact we
already do that with a bunch of things
in OpenGL just because the base OpenGL
live doesn't have a bunch of the
functions in it that we want um but we
could also do that with all of these so
for example when mmm DLL we use time to
get paired from that if we didn't want
to link with win mmm that live anymore
in the command line we could just make a
call in there and get that function out
right we could do that and then we
wouldn't see this on our depends anymore
we would still sort of depend on it
because we do get proc address on it
but we could gracefully handle failure
for some reason win mmdillho wasn't
there we could just not call time begin
period and run as normal and we probably
still be fine right so this is just
giving us a little bit of perspective on
what we're linking with but we don't
have to go through these except kernel32
which we would need forget proc address
and load library so that we could link
with everything else dynamically instead
of sort of more statically like we're
doing here
it's still not statically linking
because we are still using the dynamic
link library but it's static linking in
the sense that we link in hard bound
positions that the compiler generates to
link with these libraries using the libs
that are listed there and so it creates
this automatic dependency where our
executable won't even get to our first
line of main if those dll's weren't on
the system so for some reason OpenGL
wasn't on the system for example we
wouldn't even get to our first line of
main we just get a linker error from
Windows that basically says hey you
don't actually have the DLLs that you're
man if it's not really a manifest but
that your executable says that it needed
right so you can still then do it if you
want to get rid of kernel32 as well and
have nothing here it's just not really
recommended and basically what you do is
you do the same thing the kernel 32 Lib
would do to get the address
of where the kernel actually is you you
have to use some knowledge about how the
stack is set up upon entry into your
program to like go grab I shouldn't say
stack but the segments and stuff are set
up in order to go grab the address of
certain tables you can use to jump to
things like get proc address so you
still can't do it it's just probably not
a very good idea and you always know
kernel32.dll will be on the system so
there's really no reason not to link to
it right so anyway that's currently what
we're doing here so you can see that
well okay there's there's one thing that
we're linking to that that really isn't
quite right you know that that that we
didn't specify here but it's added so
that's added because it pretty much
knows any program linked on Windows
unless you're doing something really
crazy is going to link with kernel32 Lib
right I mean that's just a given
you kind of need it unless you're doing
some crazy gyrations to avoid it
everything else you may not need if you
never call anything in any of these
libraries you wouldn't need to link with
them and also like I just said you could
choose to do get proc addresses linked
with them instead if you'd like so you
have a lot of options of not linking
with these so kernel32 is really the
only one that it knows and so it
includes that one implicitly so we don't
except to specify back here you can see
if we look for kernel32 right it's not
there and that's because it just shows
that one in the link line automatically
now there's another thing it shoves in
the link line automatically and that
something is not actually shown in
depends you noticed it wasn't there
because it's actually completely
statically compiled in what is that
that's the C runtime library we've
talked about before and what's happening
there is when we link this line right
here so you see this - MTD we have told
the compiler we would like to statically
link with the C runtime library using
this switch and it is automatically
adding that Lib to our command line so
if we wanted to get rid of the C runtime
library right we could but we need the
switches to do it so we need to
affirmative ly up instead of all this
does we could get rid of this right now
in fact if we did
we would probably still compile just
fine and so you can see there there we
go
so without the minus MTD it's actually
still totally fine and we're not
specifying any other - M flags as you
can see but what will happen then is
we'll simply just get a different flavor
of C runtime library but it's still
gonna silently link the C runtime
library in right so if we take a look in
here and I look at at that win32
hand-made again with depends this time
let me go ahead and make a oops that's
not what I wanted go ahead and make a an
open width here can I do open with I
can't
why is there no open with usually
there's a little open with all right
well I guess I can't do it that way I
guess I have to launch depends first
there we go so if I come in here and I
drag this guy back out this is now
linked without that - MTD switch right
yes thank you so much so if we take a
look at what we've got in here now oh
this actually looks like it still did
link statically so I don't well it may
not have or I'm not sure it looks like
it still did link statically I don't see
it should list it should lives it should
list a runtime library here if we were
looking to dependently to it so let me
actually try to provoke it into doing
that I don't know if we have any other
switches here that would stable that I
don't think we do though let's take a
look a linker switch for dynamic
- MD let's try that okay and now if i
refresh this here I'm just hoping to get
the dynamically linked version for you
so you can take a look at it there we go
so you can see here if I take out that
switch that says please compile the C
runtime library directly into my
executable basically copy all of the
stuff that we need directly in there it
will go ahead and link dynamically to
one so now it'll try to look for one
right and that you can see is added a
new dependency I won't belabor that
point too much you can see it happen
this is actually the thing that happens
when you see people need to install the
visual C runtime as an installer when
they ship their executable that's
because they did this if they had linked
statically with it they wouldn't need to
run that installer right now there's
reasons sometimes you can't links
ethically with it that have to do with
memory allocation and shared libraries I
don't even want to go into that stuff
right now it's a whole gigantic mess yet
another gigantic Microsoft puke fest but
what is important to remember here is
the part I was trying to demonstrate
that no matter what we specify here
doesn't really matter what we specify
here we're gonna get some see Ron time
library one way or the other all we were
doing is passing the right switches to
make sure that it wasn't dynamic but
we're still using their library we're
just having it copy it in and build it
directly into our app to eliminate
possible compatibility concerns that
would arise by shipping without that
right but I actually want to use all our
own code and only call functions that we
absolutely have to that you know that's
one of the whole points of hand-made
here it's sure how to build everything
and we more or less have but there's one
or two things that we haven't built
ourselves that we're still calling and
they're basically math routines so what
I want to do now that we kind of do that
little diversion there is I want to show
you what I mean by that by actually
asking to get rid of the C runtime
library so for example if I say get rid
of C runtime libraries switch or
no see runtime library switch em SVC we
should be able to find a thing that says
you know here's how to not link with the
C runtime library that's actually not it
so I'm not sure why it brought up this
page unless this page has a link to it
on there because it's actually not an -
M flag
I don't think ya know none of this is
what we wanted these again are like I
just said these are the things that
choose what flavor you want so you can
have debug or release and you can have
static or dynamic
so like the MD and MD D are the DLL
versions but you know release or debug
and then MT and MTD are like release
into bug versions of the C runtime
library that are linked in statically
but there's actually a link earth switch
that's like no C runtime library and
that's the one I want to show you I'm
not sure why it didn't come up on the
search so I got to go hunting for it but
that's what we want let's see here what
else could I say no CRT switch there it
is this is the one I wanted
uh so this which is goes to the linker
and essentially what it does is it says
hey I if you know you were gonna put
extra stuff on that line that you
thought I wanted just how about you
don't that way it won't specify things
like kernel32 or the C runtime library
and it will force us to include them on
our link line ourselves and then we can
do is just not include them on the link
line and then we won't build them into
our app and that also means that it will
give us a link time error for any
function that we did not implement that
we were still calling which allows us to
know what we still depend on right like
right now we don't even know what we
call on the C runtime library because
it's getting silently linked in without
our request so if I go ahead and grab
this no default Lib as a start what I
can do is inside the common liquor flags
here I can place it now I'm not quite
gonna do it in the common linker flags
just yet what I'm gonna do instead is
I'm gonna copy some of these flags down
because the win32 handmade part for
example might be able to be made free of
the C runtime library fairly easily for
example and so we might want to do that
one first but anyway after the link flag
if I go ahead and put no default Lib
here oops that's funny copied kind of
more than I wanted there if I go ahead
and put no default lived there and then
I take this - MTD part out and add it
just to here right so just to our our
compiler flags for the the game code
which is which is actually using the C
runtime library potentially I'm gonna
kind of split the difference there right
so now we won't have that these will
actually be parts that are common and go
from there so now if I build what we
should see is any place that I was
calling a function that was relying on
one of those implicit libraries in the
win32 portion not this because remember
this one doesn't have no D folio so
handmade hero's DLL that has all our
game code that's can still call
any default library thing well anything
in kernel32 we can call anything in the
C runtime library if it wanted to write
and it would still link just fine
but now the win32 startup code and the
opengl part that that part that we build
is a separate piece that is now forced
to only link with its self and things we
manually specify right so now we can see
here unresolved external symbol errors
for everything that we didn't do right
so all the things that we didn't do here
are aren't are there so luckily if you
look at what all of these show they're
all kernel32 things right and so the
fact that they're all kernel32 things
means a lot of our troubles have nothing
to do with the C runtime library right
we can just add kernel32 Lib to it and
off we go
right when we then compile for our win32
handmade stuff we're left with only some
very small problems right some very very
simple things here what are these things
well these are things that are actually
I really wish compilers didn't do them
they drive me nuts but it's a growing
trend a growing extremely annoying trend
actually in compiler development which
is that every time they go to compile a
program they have certain patterns that
they look for or places in the code
where they will call a function from
their own C runtime library without your
permission or acknowledgement and just
expect to have it linked in later so
they basically force the use of their C
runtime library because the compiler
itself is now technically incapable of
actually outputting code that runs on
its own it's actually inexorably linked
to its own C runtime library so like
Microsoft's compilers literally can't
produce code that just runs it can only
produce code that runs with its C
runtime library now that may
sound like there's no way to do it but
there is because all we actually have to
do to try to get around this problem is
a set some compiler switches that make
it much less likely that it will
generate those functions and then be for
the functions that it still does
generate that you can't get around put
in versions of those functions into our
code that we can then use to pretend
that we're linking with the C runtime
library even though we actually aren't
so we'll basically stub them out and
then the C runtime library is gone now
we can do that actually pretty easily
with there because what you can see is
if you look at these functions what
we've got there's only two that actually
do work so here we've got GS handler
check check stack Security check cookie
and security cookie right those are all
just stupid stacked checking security
nonsense that Microsoft puts in there
because they think they're creating
something that's more secure now if
you've ever paid attention to how often
windows gets hacked you would know that
it's not any more secure but hey they
wanted to feel like they were doing
something so we can actually turn some
of those off now check check stack is
not quite that check stack is actually a
useful function at least if I'm
remembering which one of these are which
I've replaced these so long ago that I
can't quite remember but check stack is
actually required to probe the stack
when the stack is built into chunks and
we can talk about what that does a
little bit later but we can actually get
rid of it
in a separate way because it's it's for
doing something that really doesn't
super need to be done anymore now the
computers have infinite memory so you
can also kind of ignore that one as well
but we'll talk about with all the means
that will leave us with just two
functions that are not security and not
stack probe based which is memset and
float used now memset is just used to
clear memory right and so that's a
pretty easy thing for us to write our
own version of and in fact we don't call
it ourselves anywhere we use it our we
use our own zeroing functions so all we
really have to do to fix the memset
problem is to provide our own function
that clears memory and that will do it
right
similarly float used
is actually just there as sort of a
really weird it's an on it's not a
function first of all it's actually just
a variable it's like a global right all
it is used for is to pull in some
floating-point stuff from the C runtime
library as necessary I believe it's my
vague recollection it's been a really
long time is that it's there to let the
C runtime library know it should set up
the FPU state or something I think at
the beginning it's it's it's really kind
of irrelevant and we don't really care
about it so all we actually have to do
there for the unresolved symbol float
used is just to find our own float used
that gets rid of the undefined external
symbol but we don't have to do anything
it's not a function should I put a
little stub value there that's it right
so this is actually pretty easy to deal
with right very very easy to deal with
in fact we can do it right now and go
from there so for example the ones that
are relatively easy to use the GS
handler and the check stack and the
screen check cookie security cookie
those we can get really really quickly
and I'm gonna point you to something
that is by far rather than you saw how I
just had to search through the MSDN for
that and I kind of know what I was
looking for right or whatever so it miss
little easier you might ask is there an
easier way to do that there actually is
and it's thanks to Martins if I remember
correctly he actually put a post on
handmade network that Cole that grabs
all of these things you want and puts
them into one and let me try to point
you to it will try to get the actual
address up here remove see runtime
library and this is absolutely fabulous
I go back and look at this myself
anytime I want to do this in fact
because it's literally like he has put
every last thing that you typically had
to go through and you had to hunt
through MSDN to find it all he put it
all in one place and he walks you
through it bit by bit
actually right so you can kind of see
here everything in this post I would
highly recommend reading I'm not going
to go through the whole thing right now
because
I don't actually need to but you should
read this whole thing right any talks
see here I'm talking about exactly the
thing we just did for example so that
will jog your memory and then he's got
like all the rest of the switches in
here as well um so if we take a look
down let me try to get to the section
that I'm actually was interesting so you
can see here so there's a bunch of
features that you go in right there here
you go
allocating large arrays or structures on
the stack greater than four K right so
what happens here you can see he's got a
great example as well which is this
inside wooden main surgery start at the
beginning he shows the example of making
something that's like larger than four K
now why it is larger than four K matter
well the reason that larger than four K
actually matters is because in the when
the C compiler is actually creating your
codes you've seen me do a bunch of
memory stuff where I allocate memory and
then we use the memory and whatever and
we reuse the memory and all that stuff
right so we do a bunch of manual memory
management and so the reason that we
don't rely on anything in the C runtime
library for memory management is because
we did it all ourselves and you saw us
do it so that's why that doesn't happen
but there's one piece of memory we
haven't been managing ourselves that's
been implicit the entire time right and
that is the program stack so whenever we
call a function there's these local
variables in here in there right well
those local variables have to live
somewhere they have to live in memory
somewhere we didn't allocate it in fact
the compiler doesn't give us the option
to I wish it did but it doesn't give us
the option to manage our own stack
that's really not on the table so as a
result what you have to remember is
every last local variable you ever
defined in a function as well as the
implicit local variables in the function
like saved registers during calls to
other functions and that sort of thing
all in a stack pointer all that stuff
that stuff is all getting stored in
memory the compiler is allocating right
so when you start your program you
actually and compiler is allocating is
not quite the right term it's not like
it's got a memory allocator in there per
se but it's memory
the compiler is responsible for having
allocated so the compiler has to have
generated something that allows this to
work properly right so how does this
actually work well because in the old
days memory was expensive right and you
didn't have very much of it the way that
this is typically done is by allocating
what are called guard pages and then
having faults on guard pages produce
more memory so what happens is the
compiler will structure your code such
that as the at the beginning of the
program your stack which is actually I
believe prepared by Windows initially if
I'm not very much an error in fact I'm
not near when you when you create a
thread in Windows you actually give it
stack size that happens at the beginning
so the initial thread that you get
created in in Windows is going to have a
particular stack size associated with it
and what's going to happen is your
program is going to reserve that memory
so it's going to say hey I'm gonna
potentially use this much memory here
but rather than actually allocate it as
used what it will instead do is just say
well I'm gonna reserve a range of memory
that I could use but I'm only gonna
allocate the first little bit of it and
then what I'm going to do is as I use it
if I find myself going into the part of
it that I haven't allocated yet I will
then allocate that part so it kind of
dynamically grows the allocation and
commits it into actual Windows managed
memory rather than just being a chunk
that would be reserved to eventually use
as it goes it does this often times in
4k pages why because windows manage
memory in 4k pages that's the size of a
page of virtual memory so you start out
with a page of say 4k and as you use
more of that and go into the next 4k it
allocates that next 4k for you to use so
your stack kind of grows and in ads
pages on to the end as
necessary right well if you were to
touch memory more than four K away from
the end of the page then you would
actually fault because the guard page is
just one page at the end of the stack so
in a function any function that has more
than four K of local variable store
declared which you could see Martin has
created here he's created an entire 4k
variable which means that this function
takes 4k plus the IP point of storage
the register storage all that stuff
right so there's a little bit of
overhead there so this uses more than a
4k page what it will do is it calls a
function right here called check stack
and what Matt function does is it will
probe the stack in 4k jumps heating
those guard pages one after the other
making sure that however many 4k pages
this thing used in toto for its stack it
will probe out there pulling in those
pages so that way you won't right past
it as you actually use your your stuff
right um it's a very simple concept it's
just it's antiquated and weird and
stupid and we don't need it anymore but
it's was very very logical and efficient
at the time that it was created right so
that's what check stack does is is
actually a probe that pings out in 4k
steps pulling in those pages and pulling
them in is wrong sir allocating them
basically by hitting the guard pages
right that's how that works
so how does Martin's recommend getting
around this he Beck recommends getting
around this very clever way because one
way he could have gotten around it right
is to write the check stack function
because we could do that and I'd done
that in the past actually granny has
some stuff that ships without the C
runtime library way back in the day we
just implemented the check stack
function so I had my own version of
check stack that when link in that does
the 4k probe that's just what I did
right but Martin's is like well why
bother right we don't really need that
pattern of stack allocation right so
instead what it could do
is just tell us give us a large stack
right so what it says here for example
is I let's just ask for a 1 megabyte
stack right let's just ask for a
megabyte stack completely reserved so
instead of you know asking for a 1
megabyte stack and reserving a 4k stack
right that and that we then have to
constantly reserve reserve reserve
reserve just allocate a megabyte and
reserve that make it like it's a
megabyte people like no one will notice
your web browser to display this page of
Martin's telling you about reserving a
stack a stack of 1 megabyte is taking
hundreds of megabytes just to display it
right so it's irrelevant so what you can
really do is just go how much stack does
my program actually use instead of
telling windows to reserve that much
stack and then do these little tiny
increments just in case so we can save
some memory forget it
let's just allocate it in a big block
and reserve it and be done right so
that's what Martin suggests here and he
tells you exactly what switches to use
and it's a great idea and it's exactly
what we should do right so the first one
we want is this one right here and that
is again telling the linker hey when you
tell Windows what to do with our stack
tell them reserve a megabyte and
actually commit the megabyte right don't
reserve a megabyte and commit a little
tiny bit and then bit bit bit bit bit
too bit right with guard pages just do
the whole thing and then it's good right
so that's what we go let's let's put
that in here so I'm gonna go ahead and
say in common linker flags because we we
can even though we're not removing the
see runtime memory from our regular code
yet this is something we will want to do
so I'll go ahead and put that in here so
here's the stack part and again we may
find that we if we blow out the stack if
we have some weird recursive functions
or some big functions these can just be
increased right 1 megabyte no one will
miss it these days 10 megabytes no one
would miss that either 100 megabytes
probably no one would even miss that
that's how much largesse there is so if
you
want to have some giant functions with
giant variables we could probably expand
this and get away with that just fine
we'll start with this and if we crash on
stack Headroom then we can fix it at
that time but these are just these
aren't magic constants they're just the
amount you wanted to reserve so if we
just increase them we should be able to
get more memory pretty much directly
right okay so if we go ahead and compile
this now we will still have a problem
because we haven't told it not doing
insert these things yet all we did all
this does is it tells the linker to give
us that reserved part but the compiler
still thinks it needs to do this so the
other flag that he says is GS - and GS
nine nine nine and and and and the nine
which are telling it basically hey look
we're gonna give you a giant stack stop
worrying about it you don't need to
insert all these calls right I don't
actually remember what the GS nine nine
nine does so I want to just quickly look
that one up again so I can tell you what
it means exactly it's been a long time
since I have looked at any of these but
I'm gonna go ahead and put those on here
and now when we compile in theory both
of our things should not have any of
those right and you can see that they
don't so now we're down to just the mem
set like I was saying and the float used
so GS - is the one that gets rid of the
those stupid security cookie nonsenses
itself like you know if I just have that
one on you can see that it's only check
stack the stack probe that's there so
the the GS nine and a nine is the one
that tells you hey you've got plenty of
room don't insert the sack it's actually
I don't know just what the nine nine
nine and a nine part is though I don't
know if that's just like the maximum so
I just want to look up so I can recall
what that actually does there so
see if I can find it here
Visual Studio stacks switches come on
Pilar options con folks well there it is
control stock check in calls G size
option is the advanced feature stock
purpose sequence is right we just talked
about what that was the default value of
size of the size of one page okay so
basically this is just this number is
just telling you here is the size of a
functions stack footprint needs to be in
order for you to think you have to probe
so I guess 9 9 9 9 we're just the value
Martin's chose of like hey look
nothing's gonna be no functions gonna
ever have something that many bytes of
stack anyway so that'll just disable it
right so but if you wanted to be
cheekier about it you could actually
specify Oh anything that's bigger than
32 K I want it to still do a stack probe
well that you could do right you'd pass
that value there so that's all that is
Sarris Wanda I could not remember what
what you were actually passing here in
terms of a real value so what it is is
the size of the stack for that
individual function that has to exceed
before it inserts the check stack call
at the head alright so that just leaves
us with memset and float used right so
memset and float used are just two
things that we can reproduce ourselves
and one of the things we can do there's
a couple of different ways we can do
this but the easiest way to do this is
to actually just look at the see runtime
library which I hope we actually have
installed because I think I tried to but
I remember the new Visual Studio
installer is like even worse than the
old visuals to the Installer which is a
temp I know they have a team at Visual
Studio that works on making the
installer worse with every version and
that team is one of the best teams at
so they do some amazing work the
Installer now is probably one of the
worst things that I've ever seen and so
you know they that's where if you're
wondering why Windows isn't getting any
better it's cuz they took all of the
talent off of Windows and they put it on
to making the Visual Studio installer be
extremely large and error-prone and
buggy and do a lot of things that you
don't want to do and just version after
version they really knock it out of the
park so good job guys on that anyway
what we wanted to do here is go take a
look at our dummy project and see if we
can get it to show us the source code
for these things because that way we can
see exactly what the compiler actually
thinks we should be doing right in other
words the compiler is generating this
code expecting to see runtime library to
have that code supplied we are trying to
just basically copy whatever the the
specification is for it and implement
one ourselves so I don't know if this
will work because I don't know if we
have that available but we're gonna try
right so okay good so we can see exactly
how it's defining memset right it's the
exact code that it's using to define
memset is this right so we're gonna go
ahead and and pull that out here into a
special function what I'm gonna do and
this may seem weird in fact maybe I
should kind of do it I'm trying to think
of how I should show you what's gonna
happen here
let me kind of try to do it the whole
way through
so for starters if I was to go through
and place this in win32 handmade right
which might make some sense at the
outset remember we would probably want
to put this in a shared file because
it's going to be used by both people
because both of the compiler will
generate memset calls in both our DLL
and in our executable right but anyway
inside the memset call let me get rid of
this stuff here
those are just some some static code
analysis markup stuff that they do there
here's what the memset call is supposed
to look like that's the function
signature it was expecting so let's
suppose I supply one of these memset
calls here right because I'm like well I
know that it wants this memset call so
if I just supply it here it should be
able to get it and what's better is well
you know I can implement a memset call
it not that difficult right I'll just
take you know a target pointer and I'll
set it to equal the destination that it
said right and then I'll just take that
size and while the size function while I
still have bytes to clear right I will
go ahead and write those bytes into as
part of the BEM set now it's weird that
this takes an int but I guess that's
just a standard C runtime library
definition from it because we all know
that memset only sets the byte values as
it goes it doesn't write 32-bit values
and an int as a 32-bit value so really
what we're talking about here is a cast
effectively to this value so you know we
we have to convert it to something that
we can write value wise there so I'm
just gonna assume that we can use the
value directly and that we won't sign
extend it again since we're only ever
gonna use this to clear to zero I think
it probably doesn't matter but either
way I'm gonna do it that way in case it
was expecting it to not sign extend or
who knows what or sign truncate I should
say so anyway we're gonna go ahead and
grab that value out we're gonna look at
the size and we're gonna keep going
we're gonna romp over the memory that it
gives us with that value until we're
done right so we have a mem set function
but what you'll notice is now when I
compile it it's not gonna gonna help
right the reason it's not going to help
is because the compiler has sort of
reserved the concept that this mem set
function is an intrinsic right so it's
actually it knows that it wants the C
runtime library version and we haven't
given it the C runtime library version
so it's very upset with us about this
right so
the question is what do we do now well
for starters we do have one problem
which is the memset function here is not
defined as a fee function which it wants
to be right so technically we want this
to be in the in an extern see because
the memset is suppose to be in the C
runtime library that's not in the C++
run runtime library so it's supposed to
actually be an extra it's just a C
function not a C++ function gets name
mangled and all that sort of stuff right
but it already had C deckle on it which
means that for all intents and purposes
that just automatically happened right
so this will again not really help us
get anywhere I just want to point out
that that's technically supposed to be
the case right but this this right here
there is no other part of C that we care
about for this for the function
signature so even though extern C would
have made the function compile as you
know as if it was being included from a
C thing or whatever
that's it doesn't matter the C decals
the only part we care about which is the
way that the function is mangled and
called so how do we actually get this
memset intrinsic to it to be linked well
it turns out we can issue a pragma that
lets the compiler know that this is the
function that's looking for right let me
see right here if if this shows us in
there
this is not exactly what I was looking
for
and neither is that
you can see these here this is the thing
we just implemented right well point
being what we need to use is this pragma
intrinsic here that lets it know that
the intrinsic R that this intrinsic is
something that we're actually going to
define so in my recollection anyway we
still need this fragment trinsic I don't
think it's actually still going to be
enough because there's not a step that I
think you usually have to do but point
being if we specify this here like so I
believe that that is required as part of
it but like I said I don't think it
actually works the reason I don't think
it actually works is because I think
there's one more step if I remember
correctly when I had to do this
originally that you have to do I don't
really remember why you had to do it
I shouldn't say remember I never really
quite figured out why meaning I don't
know why the compiler actually cared
that it was done this way because I
couldn't figure out any logical reason
for it but maybe there was one I don't
know
so what I had to do in here anyway
and I'm pretty sure yeah you can't no no
placement of the intrinsic function
helps you if I remember correctly yeah
if I remember correctly there was no way
to actually get it to do it here that's
what I remember anyway what I actually
had to do to get the compiler to be okay
with me defining my memset is it had to
be in a separate file that was compiled
as C that's just I I do not know why it
felt like that was important because it
should only really need the code for it
but it must have some kind of way that
it's doing something important there I
don't know so I'm gonna make a handmade
MSV C function that's re file it's gonna
be straight C and I'm gonna put it in
there like so now when I compile of
course that function isn't being
included anywhere and that's by design
so we're not going to have the memset
but what I'm gonna do is I'm going to go
into our bill
and then in here where we're actually
doing it I'm gonna specify in addition
to the win32 handmade I'm going to go
ahead and specify this file as well so
in handmade code we've got the handmade
MSB C which is just a stub for if you're
complying with the microsoft visual
studio compiler you need this thing
right and then when you actually do it I
think you can get this thing to work now
that's just what I remember but you know
don't quote me on that because I don't
actually remember the way in which you
had to make this happen but I'm pretty
sure that was it cannot be defined of
course I've never done it on this
compiler either this was only on 2012 so
I could be how do I convince you um I
feel like that's correct
what don't you like I remember this
being extremely annoying when I had to
do it as well
[Music]
hmm so Martin's must have solved this
for us as well right I could go look at
my code to see how I did it
it's just was a trial and error process
as all I remember that's for other stuff
so this is what I tried to do
it's exactly what Martin's was doing as
well which doesn't bode well I hope this
is not a thing that happened that means
you can't do it now
that would be really bad oh that's why I
just had it wrong I put intrinsic here
not pragma function okay sorry my bad
since this is a separate file now I
can't be using you eight anymore but
that's fine okay yeah I forgot sorry
it's not pregnant trinsic it's pragma
function that's that's my bad so okay
I'll forget so Y memset returns the
destination I don't know I didn't even
realize that it did I don't think but
you know it does so there you go alright
so I believe we are good to go on that
front now right
and so yes we've we've gotten to the
point where we now have the MEMS that
replaced and then float used again is
just something that we should be able to
again you can just go look at Martin's
cuz he's got all this down but I'm just
kind of showing you the steps that you
would have gone through to do it
yourself
I feel like we should be able to find
float used somewhere
in the math libraries how come
don't you have to be able to call that
hmm
so I'm gonna go ahead and look if I go
into the definition here this is in VC
runtime string so I'm gonna go ahead and
take a look at the path to that I want
the I want find in files where did that
go
somebody know where that went did it not
used to be here
there is they just moved it out into its
own submenu so I want to go ahead and
see if we can find this this is not yes
so that's not the C runtime those just
the header files the C runtime layer
library so I'm gonna go ahead and see if
I can find if it installed the C runtime
library so we can look Wiccan we can
just grab the source code ourselves
right so let's go ahead and do find in
files can this know is there a reason
why it won't let me actually all right
well that's fine we'll just do it the
other way so what's gonna paste this in
here I want to see if it's got the
source code so it looks like it sort of
does anyway I mean here's the CRT source
directory so what I'm going to do is I'm
just gonna take that source directory
I'm just gonna ask Visual Studio if it
can just find me
oh whoops I no wonder it's pacing that
in the wrong area there we go I'm just
gonna look if it can find any reference
to float used itself because if it can
then I can look at it so here are the
results that it gave me you can see one
there see one here and one here they're
all in the same file so that pretty much
gives us exactly what we wanted
there's that definition of it again we
don't really know what Microsoft plans
to do with this value we just know that
it really wants to pull it in so we
should just be able to leave it there
and we don't need to extra and see it we
can just leave it as in float used I
believe now it's a very strange
declaration pattern to be honest with
you I don't even recognize that how it's
why it's set up that way I don't even
know what that is in
bliss Utley meaning if we have literally
this I don't think that would compile
with it yeah it just seems kind of weird
yeah I don't know so I would just write
it like this and I believe that's
sufficient and there we go
so now we've got the C runtime library
basically completely out there is no
more C runtime library in our win32
portion and we've got the wind main CRT
startup situation so let's talk about
that a little bit here so if you take a
look in here where we started out do you
see how we've got a wind main right for
the entire time we've been programming
we've been starting at wind main and one
of the things about wind main is that we
can't actually that wind main actually
isn't an entry point to your program if
you're actually getting called directly
from the operating system what's
actually happening there is that the
linker when it builds your executable
because it assumes that the C runtime
library is being linked in it actually
calls a secret function that you don't
know about called wind main CR key
startup this one right here that sets up
the C runtime library stuff first
then calls your wind main so this wind
main is actually only a prototype that
is created by the C runtime library it
doesn't have anything to do with Windows
it's the C runtime library that defines
that function win means CRT startup is
actually what's been getting called this
whole time when our program starts and
we just didn't know about it right so if
you take a look in here if I go to
definition of well let's do it the same
way we used to
so if we take a look at these entry
points here here we go just scanning
through
so you can see here there's like a bunch
of stuff that it's doing so main CRT
start up let's take a look here this is
really annoying
I should just step into this actually
can we build this program this I can
show it to you
I don't know so now in theory I can step
into this right here's our wind mane see
it looks exactly like the wind mane that
we had before and what I want to do is I
want to see the external code right I
would like to see what that actual code
is that's higher up on the stack
although it looks like it doesn't really
want to show it to me but hopefully I
can coerce it to do that by getting to
our by getting to our return statement
and then if I if I put in here
for this assembly here we go there's our
ret so this will hop back to the next
function so this is what actually called
us so you can see not Windows this is
the C runtime library I don't know if I
can get this to tell me where we are
there you go
XZ common dot INL is actually where we
are right again this is just code that
that got inserted by the C runtime
library into our project we didn't ask
for it's just there we come back up out
of invoke main and now we're you know
still still rockin I don't know where we
are here let's take a look common main
seh seh is structure exception handling
so this probably sets up the structured
exception handling stack for us or
something like this right but anyway
let's keep going
in fact now we've got a valid stack
which is even better so I can just walk
right up it SOT common man that's what
got called and then here we finally are
right so you can see here here is our
actual call pattern this is actually
where we came in we then went to here we
then went to here and then we went to
the thing the dispatches to our win main
I know it's kind of nuts right so what
we can expect is that actually this is
the function that would actually be
getting called right
w win main CRT startup is where we
actually expect to enter and if we take
a look we can search for that and you
can see that when we link we actually
have the ability to specify what
function we want Windows to jump to
first and by default it's gonna be set
to you know whichever one of these you
can find right but we could tell it
whatever we wanted rather than telling
you what we want we can just pick one of
these and use them and we'll get jumped
to right so win main CRT startup will
just work if we just you know specify
that the linker will find it and call it
or we could specify entry until it where
to call now we kind of want to know what
the function signature is to it but it
looks like it's nothing right
there we go wait why is this like crashy
I can't like okay there we go
so what we want to do here is just find
out is there anything particularly weird
going on with what it needs to get past
and I don't really know like I said
because I don't remember but I all we
want to do is find out what this might
take as parameters now this looks like
it doesn't take anything as parameters
right looks like it's not getting
anything there so in theory what we
should be able to do is actually just
use this as iteration directly and if we
do that then we should be completely
good to go here so in here if I say all
right I previously had this I'm not
going to have this anymore so basically
all of these things are gone what I'm
gonna have is this exact thing here and
I'm going to go ahead and rid of that so
if this is my actual startup code and I
compile it now what I will find is any
place that I needed to use something
there you can see we had our instance
there I'm not gonna have that bad
information right
because that was stuff the C runtime
library had prepared and passed to me
but that's okay because actually hey if
your Windows programmer you actually
know where to get this stuff instance is
actually something that we can get
directly by calling get module handle
for example and so we can get our
instance out just fine right no problem
no I don't actually
want I want to just be win main CRT
startup that's all I really wanted there
I don't know why entry point must be
defined as complaining here because this
is our entry point and so I'm not sure
why it's mad at us about that
but again one of the weird things is
this is not what I expected the startup
code to look like signature wise to be
with you so that was a little bit weird
so I am kind of wondering if we've got
that right but I think we should be able
to see you slash entry it's the
difference between these two
where is the function signature I just
want to see the function signature what
do you expect to have there that's all
I'm asking
no I don't I just want the definition of
this can't you look how do you search in
just and I like how Stack Overflow is
like I just want MSDN search does this
work
Wow what is it doing
hello
I don't even wanna know anyway I just
want to know what that function should
be before I go any further just to make
sure that we've got it right and
unfortunately I can't actually see I
don't even know what this is supposed to
be it's like text they paste it in here
or something I don't even know anyway
let's do it it says the entry option is
an entry point it's not even text wrap
like what is this what is going on
Microsoft the function must be defined
the standard call calling convention so
that wasn't happening start with that
LP void starts so yeah this is when
creating him oh that's a managed image
the parameters and return if I depend on
if the program is concept vision what is
the future is recommended you have to
link or set the entry points the see Ron
Tillery essentially correctly and see
but doesn't say what
it doesn't actually say what the in
classic fashion it doesn't say what the
entry point difference would be let me
go ahead and look at subsystem and see
if it somehow defines there so Windows
application to say what the startup is
the native code win mean for W in Maine
is defined for managed code witnesses
default yeah none of this this is all
but that's also again that's for if you
haven't now this is really annoying this
is really bad
the documentation for Windows used to be
good and now it's not
so I'm just curious here also what would
happen if we kept this function
signature
yes so all I'm really trying to do is to
have it fine to this right I want it to
be able to find this guy um let's go
ahead and move this inside an extern and
see block and try a couple more things
but what should have happened in that
documentation right if the documentation
we're good is that it would have told us
what the function signature needs to be
exactly like here is what I'm going to
look for how would that's not there I
don't know it's a very basic thing you
know a linker should tell you and yet we
can't find it
so if we don't define this it says entry
point must be defined
hmm so I'm not really sure I really
don't know what's going on there but I
mean I guess there's no reason we can't
just tell it if it really wants it to be
defined we could just tell it what the
entry point is I mean we could just say
this right and then see what it says
sorry
oh so did we not ever specify subsystem
windows and it just wants us to maybe
even though the default is supposed to
be subsystem windows maybe we have to
say so I don't know what to make of that
so there we go I don't know do you think
maybe now we could get rid of this line
I'm not sure so I guess the subsystem
windows kind of has to be there even
though it's supposed to be the default
maybe like when you turn off the default
Lib stuff it doesn't know that it needs
to be the default anymore and you have
to put it there cuz now I can get this I
can put this back in there I also don't
know what the difference is here so it
looks like it doesn't matter what I
asked for for parameters there either
which is kind of interesting can I do
this now assume that was our problem was
that the subsystem Windows needs to be
there for reasons that are not mentioned
in the documentation but there you go ok
so now we can see whether that works
properly as well because we don't know
we may have broken something critical
all right so we have to see if we can
actually work but you know as you can
see we're running just fine now all
right so now we've completely gotten rid
of the C runtime library from our from
our win32 startup code but it's still
being linked into the game proper so the
game DLL still relies on something
potentially from there so what I want to
do now is I finally want to get to the
part that I was going to talk about for
probably for next weekend but I wanted
to do this weekend we'll do the sample
set but then for next weekend I think we
want to do this so if we take a look
here if I move the no default live up
into our other line as well so now
neither the game nor the
nor the win32 lair will have the C
runtime library right so then they don't
have it then you can see the problems
that we end up with
listed in the link line just like before
now some of them are what we expect so
we don't have check stack or Security
cookie because remember these are on the
common line so those those will again
get rid of that for us right so all the
the common linker stuff that gets rid of
the stack problems still takes takes
place memset and float used are
problematic because again those were
only in the win32 part but since we made
a separate file for them we can just
take that and again make that be part of
the build line so I can put that on here
and here and just link that stub in that
defines those parts and then we're good
right so that's fine then we're only
left with a few things and you can see
them right here there so now you know
100% what we actually use in the C
runtime library it's just three
functions right those are the only
things we didn't implement ourselves and
they're the transcendental math
functions sine cosine in atm
so if we want to get rid of the C
runtime library what we have to do is
replace sine cosine and a tan two and in
once we have those then we can literally
be library free like there were
literally no libraries used in hand-made
here at all not even the one the
compiler tries to shove in there without
your permission which is pretty cool but
that is something that again I said we
want to put off just a little bit
probably till next weekend but other
than that it's all all of the stuff has
been removed now we can if we want to
take a look at what those functions do
right if we go ahead and
we go so we need we've got
Coase f sign F write an 8 and 2 F if I
go to the definition of these here you
can see hey they didn't even bother
implementing a non double cosign they
just call their double version and then
cast it down you know oh well if we take
a look at the definition of that one we
can check and see what that's actually
doing looks like we should maybe be able
to do another finding files
alright or not let's see if I can find a
tan too okay on the right place
so it looks like the source for those
maybe isn't in there so I don't know we
can step in and see where we go like I
did before but it may be that they just
didn't provide the source
[Music]
it's right there what is the problem
Oh initialize local variable I don't
care what the value is fine
try three all right so now if I step in
here and we take a look at this looks
like it's not gonna let us see it so
I'll go into disassembly there we go so
you can see here that even though it
didn't want to tell us about it it's it
is right there right so let's go in
there take a look how many jumps does it
take to get to the cosine code so here's
our cosine code I and as you can see
it's an absolute disaster I mean it's
just nuts right so this again you know a
lot of times people may ask why not why
don't you link with the C runtime
library the answer is because of stuff
like this right like you just that
there's no way that you actually needed
to go through all that preamble code
like this is the actual code for cosine
right and honestly it's probably way too
much code for cosine for our purposes so
we can probably get that down even more
but in order just to get here we went
through like three or four jumps or
something we just want that welded into
our code directly for starters and we
don't want it to do any of the error
checking that it's normally gonna do to
look for like infinities or whatever you
know stuff that it has to do because of
the C runtime spec but that we know
we're never gonna encounter like we know
we're always gonna be passing it valid
reasonable values within a certain range
and so it can be optimized much more for
that so again there really isn't
anything in the C runtime library that I
would ever call that I don't think has a
bunch of cruft in it that I actually
want to get rid of which is why I don't
like using it so anyway there you can
see what happens with the cosine call
and again we can get a better version by
switching this to optimized right so it
would get better than that but it's
still gonna have problems in it again
just due to the spec stuff there and
there's also if you really want to use
Simran Pfizer's there's somebody's their
switches you can specify that tell it to
use better versions like don't worry
about like float consistency or whatever
it's said it's better but even if all of
that were true even if we had a good
inline cosign we still wouldn't want to
use it because we want to do our cosines
for wide anyway and the C runtime
library is never going to do that
because it only takes one float in and
Palouse is one float out right so back
to our regularly scheduled program why
do I mention all of that well because as
we narrow in on our sampling here we're
probably going to want to start calling
things like science and cosines
potentially because we're probably going
to want to do some things with our
sampling that involve producing more
regular patterns and things like sine
and cosine may be necessary to do that
because like one of the ways we could
produce a fairly regular pattern would
be to have a hemisphere that we generate
and use you know that we rotate
potentially which would require a sine
and cosine at the head end or who knows
what right
so it's hard to say we don't know
exactly what we're gonna do here but as
we go forwards we're getting to that
point where we really would like our
math library to be wide as necessary and
we want to stop using this stuff anyway
so that's where we're at
I'm gonna remove the no default Lib for
the moment from here like so and then
we're just going to go ahead and put
that back in once we have those
functions because we're basically
library free at this point all we need
to do is just that one little bit and
we'll be good to go
all right so that's all good and it
feels nice to kind of clean all that
stuff out and so hopefully we can finish
those up maybe next weekend or do
something like that relatively soon
until then I just want to go here and
play around with the Letty sampling a
little bit so we've got our sample
hemisphere function oh well actually
it's not a function anymore it's just
welded in right uh so when we compute
our lighting in lighting test there it
is
so when we do compute light propagation
right in here we set up the work
functions they get called into this
function that's multi-threaded and in
here we create samples for our rays that
are generated here right so you can see
us creating random bilaterals and random
deltas off those bilaterals for our rays
I and what we want to do is we want to
sort of work on this sampling pattern a
little bit now what we did to start
working on the sampling pattern and if
you remember is we just need a little
piece of test code that actually draws
some sampling right and you can see that
here doing it's doing it's a little
dance we're not using this yet this is
not this salmon patty it's not going to
use it's just getting drawn and so we
want to do here is we want to play
around with this a little bit and get
this to look like what we want it to
look like right so pause for a moment
let's go ahead and not look at that
quite yet and instead look at the thing
that generates these Hemisphere sample
points which I believe is down here
somewhere
right there so this is the thing that's
currently generating them and you know
we've got a bunch of cruft in here we
can actually remove as well because we
don't care about it like for example the
entropy counter we were using we're
playing around that stuff we we're
replacing the sampling now so we can
like we can basically ditch all this as
we go so I'll you know I'll do that
first so you can see here we do this
random series we don't really care about
that anymore the random series that's
getting passed in here we could just see
it at once at the beginning if we want
to because we're not using stables we're
not going to use stable sampling anymore
we're still gonna use randomness so we
don't really care about this we can put
this out here we can also just use the
entropy from the actual entropy solution
itself I don't remember what this is
called just called series like so and
then we can do the same thing we're
doing before where we just place it back
bit later so this just returned just to
pure randomness in our samples and just
gets rid of this stuff because we're
gonna replace it in a second so we don't
really need it hanging around in there
right
and the frame counter can go I don't
remember
oh you know what that brings up one more
thing hold on one second one thing
you'll notice we're running the game and
if you remember we replaced that we did
the we replaced the C runtime library
startup with our startup so I hid all
that for here the app is still running
right why is the app still running we
hit alt f4 well the reason the app is
still running is because actually the C
runtime library used to call exit
process to actually close our process we
aren't calling math which means that our
app will just stay running forever in
the background no one will know it'll be
hidden and tiny but it'll still be there
so what actually has to happen is inside
the win32 entry point now because the C
runtime library isn't calling exit
process for us we have to call exit
process that's pretty simple right
not very difficult it's gonna tell us
this return zero is unreachable code
it's right but you know I don't really
know why it does that because the
function has to return a value so I
don't know that's kind of weird but it
does that but yeah I don't know what to
say about that it's a pretty unhelpful
error message so anyway in here now when
I run my actual program and I hit alt f4
it will exit out now I want to check
really quickly that if we are in debug
mode it still realizes that that's
unreachable code and we'll see oh you
can see here actually so in debug mode
we have seal F and floor F are actually
called as well and the reason that you
don't see those I guess in the optimized
version is because it's actually put the
intrinsics in
so for them so that they don't actually
call out so I think probably if I did
that we might be able to get it around
that I'm not sure looks like not so
that's another reason that we want to
replace those with our own calls because
it looks like actually CLF and Fleur F
will want to do our own versions of so
that we can compile in debug mode now
I'm not sure exactly where those are
getting called in the win32 lair
it's in handmade render which is just in
our rectangle drawing routine right so
actually those you know we could replace
those pretty trivially and maybe we
should but you know maybe we should
leave them for you know it's a coelom
floor you can basically use with convert
PS and various other things you can do
in there that aren't too tricky so but
we won't go down that rathole now I'll
just continue to build with o2 although
the other thing I suppose we could do is
in handmade intrinsics I'm just not sure
if you could do this
like to force it to use it but it
doesn't look that way it looks like it
doesn't want to which is unfortunate
because I would like to for now be able
to compound diamond and force it to do
that oh well it's alright we'll replace
it soon enough so we need and I can
write this down these are the five
functions that we actually need so
that's what we will have to replace in
order to run completely library free
technically CLF and floor f we don't
really need to replace because compiler
can replace them it just in debug mode
it doesn't necessarily do it so there is
that but they're so simple we might as
well just replace them because why not
and plus we might want them to be for
wide at some point and that way if we
have our own versions they would be for
wide so that we can get Cindy support in
there which I think would be worth it
right so I think that's good what is
this company about
how did we get a crash here
access violation reading location tell
me more
is there a reason it's not showing me
that there we go I'm like I just want to
see the instruction pointer please so
it's it's looking too so this is
misleading right this is just because
it's in release mode it's telling us
it's on this line but it's not really on
this line because this is a mob that
looks like it's doing something more
substantial
I'm assuming this is talking about the
well you know maybe it's loading the one
I'm not sure what exactly this is
loading
let's find out
so of course it's so frustrating to try
and use this debugger in release mode it
doesn't know any of the things that it
itself did so you can't ask it anything
that you might want to know like hey
what might have been here like what did
you put on the stack or what did you put
in these off this base address or
anything it's it just never wants to
tell you any hints cuz I think it just
loses all the information when it
creates the PDB for some reason so it
wouldn't be that hard to like track
through here it would just create a lot
of datum the PDB but I want you to do
that like I I don't care harddrive space
is not expensive give me all of the
information please so in here I can't
say I see
[Music]
I do want to see what's the next mmm
so it looks like to me that this is
actually a divided by zero that's just
not getting masked my guess is that we
need to set up the Cindi unit to not
fault on divide by zero however what I
don't understand is how its managing to
produce a value that looks like that
because 1 over 1 plus distance squared 1
plus distance squared the distance
squared would have to be negative in
order for that to create a zero right so
I don't really understand how that's
possible
oh this is scalar code what am I
thinking so this is not never mind this
is not divided by zero you can see it's
a div SS so it's not actually going to
do these lanes nevermind
we're good so it really is this mob
somehow this mob we were like returning
an invalid thing to iterate over in our
lighting boxes I guess I try to hit that
again there we go so somehow
ah I wonder how many people on the shot
figured this out already the sharp
people probably did probably one step
ahead of me I'll give you a second I
wish I had more coffee
we forgot one thing this is not really
an alloy of shame because this is pretty
tricky so if you remember in order to
get rid of the C runtime library I said
oh well we're gonna have to change the
stack thing is cuz you don't want to use
the stack check probe blah blah blah
right well one sort of caveat to this is
that the stack right is specified on our
build line here right this is where we
did that that tells the Windows loader
that our initial thread gets that much
it doesn't tell the Windows loader
anything about subsequent threads
because subsequent threads don't go
through the windows loader they go
through us calling kernel32 directly so
what's actually happening here is when
we get to a point where it's just a
little more than 4k of stack space needs
to get used we trigger it again I can of
course now I can't
well I'm trying to but I can't seem to
trigger it anyway when we get to a point
where more than four K of stack space
needs to be used by the lighting
functions we were overflowing the stack
is what was happening now why was that
happening it's happening because inside
win32 inside the win32 handmade calls we
create our worker threads right and here
in our worker threads you can see that's
the only place we do it right that's
that's the entirety of it let me jump
into it in here this is the place where
the rest of our threads will have their
stacks set up inside the create thread
call inside win32 and one of the things
that you have to look at is inside this
create thread call there's some stuff
happening that suddenly becomes relevant
when you are managing your own stack
like we are no results for create thread
great good job guys inside the create
thread function you can see there's a
parameter called DW stack size and what
DW stack size is is the initial size of
stack in bytes right so we were passing
0 here which means that it uses the
default size for the executable which is
specified in you know who knows how it's
specified right but here we go the
default size for the reserved initially
communi stack memory is specified the
ex-people file header thread or fiber
creation fails for enough memory to
reserve or commit the number of bytes
for the default stack reservation size
used by linkers one megabyte specifies
the different default stack reservation
size fall through the fibers use the
stack size statement in the module
definition file the a persistent rounds
up blah-blah-blah-blah-blah
right so that right there is is probably
what we're seeing right the initially
committed stack size I is is probably
still very low so for whatever reason I
strongly suspect this - snack doesn't
alter the commit
sighs for the thread it probably still
uses it for the reserve sighs maybe I
don't actually know but I suspect that's
exactly what's happening to us
right so in here in our crea thread we
probably want to pass an actual megabyte
value here so that we have plenty of
room right for this function do we have
the megabytes yeah
so if we pass one megabyte so that each
of our worker threads has a nice big
stack I suspect that takes care of our
problem unfortunately we couldn't really
get this problem to trigger one I
personally I thought it kind of was
triggering reliably before but hopefully
it won't let's see here so now what we
should be able to do is set that stack
size correctly now that I can get it to
trigger I I wish I knew what I could do
to get this trigger loudly we can see
whether that was actually the problem or
not so let's see what it was looking to
to address here
we can also see what how big our stack
actually was right like how big of a
stack we actually would need like I
don't know what we create in terms of
stack reservation for compute light
propagation
over time so I don't know what we might
need in terms of stack space here it
doesn't seem like we would actually need
that much so it could be that I'm wrong
about it
because it's only gonna enter into here
let me double check that here's our
thread proc this won't require much
stack right it's not doing anything
fancy there this one doesn't either
right there's nothing weird on the stack
here I don't know how much that would
necessarily put on the stack but
probably not very much there's a fair
bit of stack space getting taken up here
but a megabyte it's just not very likely
so I may be wrong about this one because
if we have a megabyte of stack reserved
it should not cause a problem I don't
think but I guess we'll find out all
right so let's take a look at the actual
code here and try to suss out what the
problem is there we go so let's start by
taking a look at some of our registers
here I don't know why I think we just
maybe haven't looked at the register
windows in a while because they're not
up oh don't don't do that
there we go let me just go ahead and put
these guys in here see
that looks like everything we need for
now well that's cool all right so if we
take a look at what we're seeing here
you know we've got so you can see our SP
our IP is this is where we are in the
code right this is where we are in the
stack so we're using our BP to address
and that is a stack address for sure
right because let's go back to the line
here already X this value here is
presumably an offset because it's it's
pretty tiny right that's that's not a
particularly large value our BX here is
you know clearly a real base pointer and
you can see that it's basically a stack
aligned value right like these are this
is the stack and here's our B key so you
know you can see just by looking at them
that's what's going on and then this guy
right here is a fixed offset amount
which is presumably the address of some
you know constant we know or care about
there so what we don't really know here
is if we were to start looking do we run
off the stack particularly early or what
exactly happens here let me see if I can
pop this on here
I also don't know how this memory window
would display basically
memory that was it illegal
what would you say okay good so you know
this would be if we were gonna hit a
protected region so for as far as the
access fault is concerned we this is
what we should expect to see so I'm
gonna go ahead and take a look at this
region again cuz I don't really know why
it's looking there or what it's looking
for I don't have a lot of information
about what it's trying to get I'm gonna
go ahead and try to take that value and
just see that on stack so there we go I
also need a little more room here let's
just get a little bit bigger there in
fact you know what maybe we'll move
memory up to here so because it's my
head's kind of blocking part of it and I
might want to see so again we don't
really know where we're looking here or
you know how how we might get back to
civilization
we suspect
yeah we suspect that this is
am I
am I missing something here
oh I was looking at the wrong value I
was looking at our BP and I should have
been looking at our BX hmm so our BX is
not off the stack right
this is stack our BX is actually a real
pointer that probably got allocated by
somebody right because you can see here
these are this on the stack for some
reason I was looking at our BP not our B
X and so this is not off the stack this
is actually gonna be an address of
something we don't actually know what it
is an address of let's take a look at
what solution is 1 f FC 3 is 0 so it's
actually this it looks like that is
trying to access right it's trying to
access off of this solution points here
uh and so let me just take a look it's
using our BX as a base pointer and you
can see that that is the solution so
we're starting to piece it together here
this is our DX plus solution plus 18 Oh
20 H right that's what it's actually
we've got so far
now our DX I'm guessing is the hit point
index value that it's talking about here
probably modified to have some kind of
an offset baked into it I'm guessing so
if you look at hit point index
well I can't look at hit point index but
if we look at maybe how big a hit point
actually is so for example size of
lighting point
you can see that 60 see here I don't
know how many hit points we've got all
right so it's not that yeah so if each
one of those is size 60 the lighting
points
I can't say why RDX would be so high
so what we would expect to see so maybe
it's not this line maybe it's a
different line that's looking for there
although I mean it looks really
suspicious so oh x3 C is 60 right
there's there's oh x3 C right it's in
heck for whatever reason assembly
language code uses H suffix for hex
rather than Oh X it's just a language
convention so you can see here if doing
an I'm all in the RDX
so our CX is hit point index that's the
hit point index right for sure and so
the hit point index is way out of bounds
it's totally wrong right because we
don't have that many hit points so it
looks like we've got a bug where we're
returning hit point index here that's
just bogus because RDX is then becoming
a value that's totally wrong it's
producing 60 times that which is giving
us the offset so this line is happening
here this is correct that is presumably
the offset of the beginning of the
points array but this is garbage it's
just wrong it's correctly multiplied by
60 to give you the strip the stride but
that hit point index is almost certainly
garbage so if we take a look at where
that's coming from
again I'm not sure why this would
necessarily be something that's
happening strangely after the changes we
just made because we weren't seeing this
happen last time so in theory the much
more likely culprit would have been
something to do with the stack size or
setting up the SSE so it could be that
we have an SSD setup difference that
then creates this problem which we'll
find in a second but at the moment
anyway we do want to take a look and
just see here do we have some kind of
problem with our hit point index that's
causing this to occur right but anyway
so in here where we get the hit point
index what we do is we look to see
whether or not we had a hit on a
particular Lane and then the hit point
index is just we loop through how many
hit points there were for this
particular surface index right
and we you know we just use the base
pointer the the hit index the base hit
index so unless the lighting boxes
themselves were wrong which you know
maybe they are it seems a little weird I
guess what we could see here is let's
take a look if we can shouldn't quite
exited yet see if we can find some of
those other values again just using sort
of the laborious back tracing there
there we go what I'd like to do is take
a look at the hitbox information here
so here's where we are the information I
wanted to see was this got unrolled
so the information I want to see was
here this hitbox information I don't
know if I can still recover it but I
want to try um so if I ask for hitbox
unfortunately I can't get it directly I
don't know why it jumped back down there
thanks that not like I wanted to yeah
fantastic
so apparently every time I type into the
watch window it'll jump back down there
so I want to know if we can get this
information out I don't know if that's
reasonable to do because you can see
when it pulls out the hitbox here it
goes into ECX but then we overwrite ECX
without having saved it so you can see
right here we kind of romp over it with
other information probably because the
hitbox doesn't really need to be used
after that I guess it just uses offsets
into it like the light index which is
probably fine so you can see here this
is trying to load out I think those base
values I don't know if they persist they
might so we could take a look here and
see what these are let's let's see if we
can get some of those values why does it
do that why would it ever think I wanted
to jump back to the current line that
doesn't make any sense I'm trying to
read something here
so possibly that's you know the value
there I want to look at our attendee
comp against for oh it's because this is
probably an unrolled loop so let's take
a look at our ten D as well is that
actually still current
hard to say they're just a lot of code
unrolled here
so yeah not really so
you
oops
so I wonder if we can figure out what
box surface index was as well so it
looks like it came through in our CX
originally
I wonder if there's any way to cover
that ah here we go
so this will help us quite a bit
potentially this is not this is not
really it
I don't think though this may be this
may be some fake news find out well box
index looks valid enough so that's good
[Music]
so box surface index here is 0 6 4 2 now
6 is not a valid box index right so if
we look here at what hit it says
everybody hit it says these are the Box
indices and those are reasonable box
indices so this if this was if this is
actually correctly the values which
again we don't know if it is right we're
just guessing here these would all be
reasonable Rea distances you know that
could be these would all be reasonable
box indices two of the Rays hit box 333
and two of them hit box 321 these are
all reasonable hit masks which are all
ones right basically uh but that that is
not a reasonable box index a box index
of six the boxes should be 0 1 2 3 4 5 6
is totally not ok because 6 a box index
of 6 is off the end of the array now we
have one off the end of the array but
it's used as a cap so if this will look
at 6 &amp; 7 7 is not in the array 6 is okay
just let's look at five or six at
maximum so do we have a bug back here in
our raycast that we just didn't know
about
somehow we uncovered by doing our stock
changes there do we somehow have a bug
where this is producing the box surface
index incorrectly and I don't know so
here's some code where we produced the
Box surface index the question is is
there a way for this code to produce a
value of six so axis index that moves
can be too
yeah this is totally busted what did we
do here did we did we accidentally flip
these two
I feel like we may have accidentally
flipped those two do you think
maybe that's not actually true maybe our
bucks surface indices are like weirder
than this right let's take a look
because that would just be a straight-up
bug that we just didn't know we had so
if I go ahead and look at get box
surface so this code right here I mean
it's I mean you can see right the way
we're doing it is a little weird but no
I guess that is that is correct
that's how we're doing it so the access
index just gets shifted up one and then
or we are in the positive all right
so back to the question in hand though
so if access index if access index is
just shifted up
by one then effectively what we're doing
is we're just multiplying that value by
two so if give me zero one or two then
the maximum value that should be able to
have is four if we were in positive then
the maximum it should be able to have is
five because positive is either one or
zero right now maybe we're
misunderstanding how that code will work
[Music]
maybe the less than zero is somehow
producing something other than that and
I'm not sure so I'm just curious assert
positive equals zero or positive equals
1 and then maybe assert this is less
than six let's just see if we can fire
either these two asserts because I don't
know how else we're getting what we're
getting without it if that Ray return
value was to be believed somehow a six
got shoved in there right we don't know
how but it did
now unfortunately as before we don't
have a hundred cent reliable way to
trigger this unfortunately
I will say this is awfully suspicious I
don't love the fact that I seem to not
be able to trigger it once I put the
asserts in that's a little frightening
way too soon to say we're hitting a
compiler bug here but there we go okay
laughs that was just a little unnerving
okay so we know that we're hitting this
here suspiciously we're getting a six
and yet we have no idea how we would
actually be producing a six because
unless we've messed something else up
which we you know maybe we have in our
array cast function here oh that's the
IFFT zeroed case that's the old one
those asserts will get us nowhere
this is what we're looking at okay so
this is our bar this is our actual box
surface call right this is the different
one that we were doing there and this is
just taking replicated zeros ones twos
threes fours and fives I and placing
them directly in here then it does a
select on the box surface index so the
question is what does it clear it to it
should be cleared well I guess
technically it doesn't have to clear it
because it's not going to return unless
the lane actually got hit it doesn't
matter right so unless we're actually
whoring in the hit mask which we only do
there then the hit lanes should never
trigger otherwise right so we only
really need to care about it here when
we do our select for the box surface
index we're producing the box service
index here so how on earth are we
getting in a situation where we're
getting a six out of things that can
only or in constants between zero and
five
because I'll be honest with you I'm not
sure how we would do that pretty bizarre
so let's take a look and see if I can
put a search in this part of the code
since I'm putting them on the wrong
particle before oh and I only
you and I could also do here so you do
this so if you hit this lane trigger the
assertion just so it's a little easier
for us to see so if we hit that lane I
want to make sure that box surface index
is actually within the valid range 0
through 5 and it looks like normally it
appears to be just fine
lo and behold so what's going on can I
access any of these variables no of
course not
so what is happening I all right so
we've got some building of this guy
right X mm
movemove there's a lot of moving going
on here
so here where we set box surface index
up you can see here we did our and not
and then our and and our or so it looks
like X mmm 0 was our box surface index
and if I go ahead and and kind of take a
try to expand it out see what what it
says you know here's the here's the
values that it appears that it thinks it
has right five one seven one that's what
that that's what it's getting so this
Lane would be junk is that the lane
that's actually triggered and it is
right so that box service in Nexus 7 is
just totally that's just totally garbage
so we must have written this code very
poorly that's my bad I must have done
something very stupid here that I just
wasn't thinking through or something
right now I don't really know what that
would because this isn't particularly
complicated code but I must just be
thinking about it slightly wrong yeah I
don't know what or maybe when we mask it
in I don't know but let's find out what
the mask is first of all so we can
determine this mask here you can see
what it must have been because we do a
move and ends with this then and not I'm
sorry and not with this and then an end
with this then we do an or to smush them
together right
so it must have come from xmm three
originally the mask right because we
moved it in here then we did the smoosh
and the smoosh on 0 &amp; 3 and then we wore
them together for our final result so
the X mm 3 register must have held back
in some historical times must have held
the value of the mask now the question
is where did that come from and can we
still get a hold of it might have gotten
destroyed it might be gone you can see
that it's constantly being used here
so it looks like it's kind of been
destroyed
oops however the move mask of it may
still be right I don't know if the EAX
ever got trashed here it may it may have
been mmm so unfortunately I don't know
how to really look at the mask for this
particular time however I guess what I
can do
so there is a way this could happen if a
box had no size
right if I assume I can't access these
yeah so if a box had the same min and
Max value then two of those could be
true at the same time right
Steve ugh info is just garbage
so I guess if I look at the disassembly
here
I don't suspect I'll really be able to
get much out of this but we can try
let's see re X RDX
yeah
so this box anyway would not have a team
in value in a team X value that would be
equivalent like that's just not on the
table
so if I look here when I'm actually
doing the comparisons
here's the the compy Q's here right for
is obviously team in because it's the
same on all of them and then the Box
maxes are like x-men's to sorry 8 10 6 &amp;
and nine
it looks like because that's where the
comp is going but of course you know
what then they're gonna get destroyed
but you know we can look and see what
these actually were I guess that would
tell us the masks so it yeah I don't
guess yeah I just don't know how often
these things were used again a lot of
these just got reused again so that's
not really gonna help us
so the thing I want to know is whether
the tea box whether any of these can be
true at the same time right because if
they were that would give us the
opportunity to create larger values if
you or in for example you know let's say
you took four and you ordered in two
then you would get six right if you got
one two and four all or it in together
then you could get seven so this code
presumes that the teaming cannot be
hitting multiple boundaries at the same
time but actually that's not necessarily
the case I suppose right if it hit the
corner just on that in theory that would
just work
so I think basically what we're seeing
here is this just isn't a good way to do
this
unfortunately because it almost even
though it's almost always correct if you
literally just hit the corner like an
edge of the box then the teaming value
could work out just right so knowing
which box we hit which which side
is more complicated
also what is the point of this I mean
this is an and with zero what exactly do
you think you're going to produce right
I mean that's that's just dumb so we
start out with zero right and then we
want to select a box index by seeing
which one of these things we hit when we
take this mask value we almost have to
keep like a running mask as we go to
make sure we only ever use like one of
them so once a lane turns on it kind of
has to be turned off for all other ones
so
I mean I guess we really want something
like this so we start off with a BS mask
value that says okay here's where one's
go once something goes there then the BS
mask has to be updated with an and not
right I think which we can make into one
instruction right we can put an and not
in here but we're then saying like all
right
once we've masked any lame that came
back true here cannot we cannot use for
the next one we have to mask it out
that seems right to me so I'm gonna try
that and see how we do so again this
then becomes an update of BS mask
and I think that should be okay now
there's probably a clever way to do that
but like I said we want this to be in
for starters at least and and not like
so and we already have that function we
just don't expose it so inside the Cindy
stuff we have and not you know it's
sitting right there but we just don't
have a way to actually access it so we
want to have a thing here that's like
so I don't really like the convention of
having the not be the thing that it
should be called not and or something if
it's going the other way so I feel like
since the first parameter is the thing
that gets knotted I want mine to read
the other way round
right and if we look at the Intel
intrinsics guide
here you can see that a is the thing
that gets knotted so it's really a knot
and not in and not so I think I'd rather
write it that way you know just say just
so it's clear suing here we're gonna do
that knot and all the way down or and
not sorry all the way down like so and I
think that's what we need there what is
the problem
yeah sorry so now we should get the
correct box index I believe in all cases
even cases where we have them not going
although I'm Sam wrong we should be able
to make that work now I probably messed
something up here
oh yeah yeah this is not at all what I
wanted to do sorry I so what I wanted to
do is keep a running total of all the
things we had masked in and I didn't
quite do that right I wanted BS masks to
actually be the thing that gets Ord
together and I'm not actually doing that
here right so it's not quite correct
this and not supposed to be here not
here and I'll show you what I mean by
that
so the BS mask has to be all the lanes
that were ever true so every time we do
it we have to take the new mask value
that we were going to do right and we
need to append it to the BS mask there's
a couple different ways we could do that
trying to think of what the most
efficient way to do it is the most
concise way of doing it in the code
right but we need to keep the knockout
values there what was happening here is
you know later you could turn a lane
back on that you know a previous one
you're only doing just the immediate
previous and the immediate previous
isn't sufficient presumably right so let
me make sure maybe I'm wrong about that
but let me just make sure here so the
first time we get BS masks here what
we're gonna say is it's gonna have true
in the lanes where we could actually
write where T min and T max are where T
min is equal to box max right we're
gonna or in the one based on those lanes
then what we're gonna do is say all
right we're gonna knock out that Lane
just those lanes that we use in the
previous time and prevent them from
hitting and then this will tell us which
ones are there yes you can see it loses
this information then pretty much
immediately right because now this might
just be zero yes so that this is not
sufficient and not at all what we wanted
so let's try that one more time so
really what we want to do here right is
we want to build this thing up
piece by piece right so let's start with
the mask Building Code and the mask
building code is pretty simple it's just
an or so as we go each time there you
can see this would build up the mask
that is what is allowed in essentially
right I'm sorry
what has already been filled so so lanes
that have already been filled are are
now have ones in them at this point
right and so what we need to do now is
just actually remember what these mass
values are so what we can do here is say
you know something like this so maybe
we'll call this the running mask so
probably it actually this one like this
oops
and again there's probably better way to
do this that we could think about if you
thought about it one more carefully I'm
just gonna do a the basic version first
so the running mask just gets these
things ordered together and I'm going to
pull this mask out like so so there we
have that written a little bit more
succinctly there so we start out with
nothing in the running mask and the this
mask is set the first thing right and
then each time we would update the
running mask as such right then when we
need to actually write to our box
surface index each time out so for
example our box surface index here the
first time well the first time it's just
equal to zero so we actually don't need
to do anything for that the next time
what we need to do is say okay the Box
surface index we will orient a one and
we're gonna end that with this mask but
we also need to knock out anything that
might have been in running masks right
so the and not actually goes here
here where we say this mess that we're
going to or in cannot have any lanes in
it that we're already handled so that
just continues down as we go like so so
we start off with zero the running mask
actually doesn't have to get updated in
any particular way here we can just
start it out that way so that's what was
true the first time right so the first
time we start out we assume zeros
everywhere and we say okay if there's a
zero in a lane it will remain there if
the team in equals the box man and what
is considered that filled then we go and
say okay now let's look at box max
update with box max but don't do that
don't actually use anywhere that would
have been knocked out by the running
mask then update the running mask same
thing again same thing again same thing
again same thing again so now we like
keep that running tally now at the end
we don't really need this last one
because the running mask doesn't need to
be used for anything at the end so the
final one actually it's not relevant
right but otherwise it would have been
so I think that actually now correctly
does the thing we want to do we should
probably step through it and look we're
out of time but let me just check
through the assertions here
seem safe
yes I'm not I'm not seeing any really
problematic stuff happen
so that should be good so that code was
just not really correct and then not
sure why we weren't having problem than
before but I guess we giggled enough
stuff with changing the C runtime
library out that we were no longer
getting the same amount of padding or
something where the stack was just
getting messed with a little bit too
much or who knows what was happening
there right so now we can see is this
code is you know probably quite a bit
slower unfortunately but at least is now
I think correct and speed wise we didn't
really take a hit for that it doesn't
look like so that's kind of a good thing
as well so I guess it wasn't slower in a
in a way that really affected our
profile dramatically which is kind of
nice
alright alright so I'm gonna go ahead
and wrap up for now and tomorrow we will
finish changing the the hemisphere
sampling and then we will have to
because I probably will want to use sine
and cosine for that then we will have to
move on to the C runtime library
replacement which again is not super
complicated we just have to replace
those math functions but we have to do
some talking about how would you replace
those math functions in order to do that
so let's go ahead and go to brief Q&amp;A
can we use six separate bits to
represent hits with each box wall and
then take the highest bit to determine
which individual box we'll use we
definitely could
I'm not sure how we would necessarily
get that bit pattern out though
so you were suggesting using LZ count
epi32 so let's take a look and see what
the compatibility is on that
hello
where is this function
dude dude that's an ATX 512
we can't use that it won't run on
anything I was gonna say I'm like well
you know I pretty much always use just
sse2 so maybe it's in four or something
I just haven't looked because that's
like I've never used that function and
that's why you know but we still could
do something like that where we process
it after the fact I mean the your idea
is still valid because we haven't
thought much it but we just kind of
slammed this in when we needed it right
we didn't think a lot about how we
should do it so it's it's worth thinking
about that what you're talking about
though it's possible we could do
something where we just or in bits that
don't overlap and then later when we
pull it out to do our access then we
could do it so for example we could use
bits can in the exterior code right and
pull it out that way you know so so I
feel like that would work
returned the original destination what
in just in memset are you talking about
mem said or I don't know what you're
talking about
ginger bill said return the original
destination oh yeah this is the
compilers just calling this we don't
really need to we could return zero here
and nothing would happen but yeah we
don't want to leave a time bomb in there
someone cut and pasted this code and
then used it as a met they would be
unhappy so I agree ginger bill
uh-huh we shouldn't leave that like that
it's better to have it do the right
thing in case anyone actually cares
I meant to return the original
destination I just didn't actually type
that in
[Music]
would it be better to make hemisphere
sampling ization in an actually
hemisphere with dots rendered on it
yeah probably possibly I don't know that
we have any way to really render dots at
the moment I guess we can put little
cubes down there the other way we could
do it is truncate those lines so for
example inside handmade lighting right
to make it a little easier to visualize
for in the way that you're talking about
what we could do is say something like
this
so you know something that was a little
potentially easier to visualize like how
you're saying would be something more
like this right and that way you don't
have those those like pin cushions in
there and you can you could you know we
could shorten those up a bit I don't
know if you want to do push cue but we
could even do push cube so in here we
could actually try that by putting a
push cube in here and draw a cube
[Music]
in order to do that I'd have to
basically do this so we'll just call get
current quads with you know however many
of these we were gonna do something like
this and then you hear we could just put
on those those cubes I suppose so we'd
say alright creep bitmap looks like it
needs a bitmap ID for that well can just
call this one the position would be the
start point plus the one point F times
the normal reduce the cube I don't know
what that should be really and then the
color value so in theory I think that
would probably work I guess get current
quads you might not really need to call
that because the push cube function
probably calls the quad function
correctly
anyway fact I don't know does the
line-segment one do
yeah so I'm not quite sure whether we
actually need to make sure the space is
reserved or not but we can so there's
like the cube version right and the
height is value is a little misleading
there but that's because our cubes are
kind of done in a weird way because they
were made for floors originally but but
there's like more what that's about so
that would be a hemisphere sampling
where you could see it a little bit
better in the hemisphere and if we want
to here we can stop the series so if we
want to you know we can intentionally
not use one that's changing so we can
see just our basic distribution
statically and so there you go right now
since you know this is again this is
picking completely randomly you can see
how it's not particularly well
distributed right and that's what we
were gonna do today but then we kind of
got sidetracked on debugging in C
runtime library both of which are good
but what we want to do is we just want
to even those out a little bit more I
wonder could this be made a little lower
let's see a little bit better
so there you go so what we want to do is
we want to unclamp this right we want to
make this a little bit more evenly and
so that's where it's going to be
tomorrow is just just unclip it that
that was it
we're not using this yet anyway so we
just we want to get it straightened out
here and then I'm going to move it into
the the code proper Martin's why do you
do star unsigned care star and at Val
instead of unsaid curv al in mem set so
there's no reason if I think it through
so if I am calling unsigned care to
truncate a value that was an integer it
should just work but sometimes I force a
reinterpretation like some by default if
I'm not thinking about it hard I always
do the address version so that it won't
do some weird sign signed operation that
I don't want because even though I
programmed in C since I don't even want
to know how long like 20 years or
something um I don't remember when I
first started programming C it's
actually probably 30 years so I've
program C for probably something like 30
years still I don't really have an
internal model of it's dumb sign extend
stuff that it does right because the
intuitive way I would think about it is
just not the way that seed ever does it
ever for me so I tend to like Overgaard
against having it ever do anything if I
could I just tell it never do anything
like I'll tell you what to do like don't
do it but I that's why you see me type
that is because I haven't thought about
it at all and I'm just don't want the
compiler do anything stupid
right but in that case you're truncating
an int to an 8-bit value so I don't
think it will ever do anything straight
it I think it will just take the bottom
eight bits I
all that's always I think
off-topic what harm do you think could
happen if you click on that yellow flag
to upgrade MSB see no breaking change
has been introduced since this new
machine just lots of power upgrades um
so generally speaking if you have
something that compiles your code okay
I never upgrade it until the end of a
project I had to switch versions of MSB
see here because we moved machines but
normally I would never do that you know
pretty much ever right because a lot of
times it just dies right it's like we
upgrade it and it just doesn't compile
our code anymore or it like introduces a
bunch of new errors we have to go look
at or it like you know who knows what it
does right so why it doesn't give me
anything to upgrade it that I want and
also pretty much every version of MS we
see gets worse than the one before it so
it's not a good trend right so yeah like
unless you have a reason to upgrade you
never upgrade that's my policy
unless you know exactly what you need
and you're sure you're going to get it
and most the time nowadays it's all bad
right like Windows gets worse every time
it upgrades so I would never upgrade it
if I could avoid it right and in fact I
do avoid it on my work machines because
they're not plugged into the internet so
they can't get to Microsoft upgrade haha
but yeah I I never up to anything if I
can avoid it take everything off the net
and never update it and hey you have a
much better life because stuffs breaking
all the time with these stupid updates
that they don't debug and they don't
test right and then you have to live
with it fluid else key is the snack size
set on the command line for the entire
stack or for each stack frame it's for
the entire stack of a thread so it's not
it's not for like if you have more than
one thread you get more than one snack
but each function doesn't get the whole
1 megabyte each function get
however much it needs out of the one
megabyte
Martin says another thing to mention
when using slash stack to get 1 megabyte
Sacre's forget programs that all threads
also will have the stack size the
default it could be an issue if
somebody's creating keeping hundreds of
threads live that's true if you wanted
to minimize the number the amount of
memory you're using per thread you would
run into a problem there for sure
although I would question why you were
doing that but you know how scale though
you once said that in your products you
don't include windows @h how do we go
about doing that it's exactly the same
as you saw me do with the opengl stuff
you just cut and paste the function
prototype into your own code and then
call get proc address to get the address
of it out of the dol and then you don't
need windows that age right because
windows that h is just a giant
collection of function prototypes and
structs that you could just define
yourself the ones you need so you don't
need anything in Windows H other than
the exact stuff you call so you can just
copy it in and be done which is what I
do
I hope this is not too far I've talked
recently I've thought about a hook based
execution memory management system where
you allocate memory you can tell it in
the next line when it should be freed
there would be as many hooks as you like
for example after frame hook level load
hook or stuff like this
the hooks internally would be a
collection of lambdas so they can
capture the address that you want to
free when the hooks run what do you
think of this idea um I don't like it
that's like how it was done in the
witness and I don't like it
the reason I don't like it is because if
you know when memory is supposed to get
freed then you should be doing it in an
arena and you should have those arena's
be tied to the things we're talking
about so for example if you have memory
that gets freed every frame there should
be a frame arena and any time you want
to allocate something that gets freed at
the end of the frame you allocate it in
the frame arena if you want level load
stuff to be freed then you should be
allocating it in the levels arena and
the level arena gets freed when the
level goes away the witness did this not
exactly quite the same way you're
talking about but it had basically that
where you'd basically hook stuff up
where you'd say free this it like the
end of the function or something right
and I just I just don't like that
because if a function needs its own
stack then give it its own stack that's
only memory arena right and if a frame
needs it then give it an arena
that's what arenas are for and that way
you don't have to track each memory
piece individually right there's just no
point to it just get the memory in a
chunk for that just put all the memory
together that goes with that thing and
then free the whole thing at once so
you're not looping through all these
callbacks or god knows what else right
what are your thoughts on using macros
and C to make writing certain repeated
patterns shorter eg encapsulating
shimmie common patterns like pound to
find do FN for int I equals 0 I less
than n I plus plus F um I'm not averse
to it I think it's kind of too weak to
be that practically useful I prefer more
strong metaprogramming than that but I'm
not averse to it the problem I find with
it if you try to use it too much in
practice is that your ability to debug
the code tends to go down because
debuggers too often times don't do a
good job of stepping through macros they
typically won't really show you what you
need to see so as the macros you're
talking about get more complicated using
the debugger becomes more difficult so
that is the thing I would say to watch
out for there but Clemens mom since
you've worked at Microsoft would you
recommend working at Microsoft nowadays
for a new graduate um I guess what I
would say about Microsoft is like most
places that you could work that are
large companies I think it's less a
question about should you work at this
company and more about where you would
work in the company I think Microsoft
Google Facebook you know any of the
places that grads probably look at these
days
there probably are places in those
companies that are good to work at where
there are smart people doing interesting
things who will teach you something and
it'll be nice the question is can you
find those places right so I think
that's really the thing to focus on it's
not should I work at Microsoft it's can
I find a place in Microsoft where you
know where it's not just a dingus
festival you know and it's like there's
actually smart people doing smart things
I mean I bet the kernel team at
Microsoft is an amazing place to start
working after you get out of college
right there's probably some really smart
people there and they're probably doing
some interesting code I don't know maybe
not but I would guess right on the other
hand like the team responsible for the
Windows 8 Start menu was probably like
the worst place you could ever imagine
going or something right it was probably
about how to like line up the right XML
code to load the right like thing I
don't know right so I think that
generally that's my perspective on
working at large companies is it has
very little to do with the company and
has way more to do with where you are
and I
your life that's not helpful because
it'd be way better for me to say
something like yes like go work at
Google don't work at Microsoft or
something cuz it makes it easier but I
don't think that's realistic
I don't think companies generally are
good or bad unless they're very small
you know a very small company that has
10 employees is probably good or bad
right to work at but a company that has
over a thousand employees which all of
these companies do I really just don't
think you can I really don't think you
can make that determination I think
every team at those companies is
probably good or bad to work at and what
you have to do is figure out how you're
gonna suss out whether a team that you
might work on is good or bad but the
good news is and to put like a silver
lining on that I think what you could
say is take a job at Microsoft if you
get that offer right or just take
whatever the best offer is whoever's
paying you the most or whatever right if
you get multiple offers coming out of
Grant after you graduate to work at one
of these comfortable larger companies
take the best offer you can find and
then try to move around right when you
get there try to sniff around spend your
time your spare time you know do your
work during the day whatever they want
you to do do it and try to do it well so
that you have a reasonable reputation
sniff around and find out where those
good people are find somebody you like
and you trust you know do the networking
and then try to move to that team you
know think of your first six months or a
year at whatever company you go to as
you figuring out where to be in that
company and then go there because it's
very unlikely I mean maybe you know it's
possible I said Twitter I think at one
point maybe I don't know it's possible
that a company like Twitter literally
has no people working at it that you
would ever want to talk to or learn from
right it's possible but it's probably
not possible at like Facebook Google
Microsoft any of the really big
companies that have researched you know
serious research teams
it's probably just not the case that you
can't find some good teams there there's
gonna be good teams there and good
people on those teams and so I'd say I
would say that your perspective I'll
just be like go there and look for that
and then try to move there because when
you first start working your first job
out of college anyway there's gonna be
plenty of stuff you just need to get
used to like having a nine-to-five job
and not studying you know stuff at night
stuff right just getting used to you
like finding an apartment like you know
your first six months to a year you're
you've got life things to deal with
anyway trying to pay off school loans
and you know doing what you've got all
this stuff you're worrying about so you
know don't worry too much if you're in a
group that sucks right if you're in a
bad position there it's okay it's your
first job it's not necessarily gonna be
your dream job anyway it's fine
so just make the best of that I would
say and then spend some time get on
those company aliases that are like
research talks that people come and give
and when there are people presenting
stuff internal to the company also get
on those internal aliases read them see
what looks interesting go to those
people talk to them after their lecture
just make friends as best you can you
know some people are good at that symbol
are bad you know if you're bad at making
friends I apologize it makes it harder
right networking is a big deal but
trying to make friends try to find out
where those things are and then then see
if you can make some friends with
managers and people who are in those
departments and say can I come over and
work there how could I do that I'm
really shouldn't what you're doing
trying to make that move happen I think
that can work out for you because again
I there may be some companies that are
just so lousy at what they do that
there's literally nowhere there to work
that you can learn from and that may be
true but most of these companies that's
not true
so most of these companies are going to
have groups in them that are good and
you just have to find them and so I
that's I think the optimistic thing you
should focus on is that you know very
few of the
these companies once they reach a
certain size can get away with having
literally nobody could write like
there's gonna be good teams there
somewhere right and so you just got to
focus on finding them in and you're
gonna be one of the only people doing
that right because most people like you
know thinking about let me figure out
how much X comma X ml I can generate in
a day for this Windows Start menu most
programmers today like that so they're
not looking for they don't want to think
about memory management right so you're
you're not going to have to worry about
everyone wanting to work in that group
or anything there's a small number of
people who want to do serious work every
day and want to learn in if you're one
of those people who prioritizes that you
should be able to make those friends
make those connections get moved over
within a few years you're not gonna have
to spend ten years working at Microsoft
to find your way to a good group I don't
think if you're putting in the effort to
do so if you just go there and do
nothing then no you're gonna end up in
something where it's like XML all day or
whatever and that's just gonna be your
life right but if you're proactive I
think you can in most of these companies
move because again a lot of people
aren't gonna do that and a lot of people
are thinking more about career
advancement making more money right they
want to get promoted or whatever else
right just don't worry about that part
worry about how do I get to a good group
right and and then you're if you're not
doing what they're doing right they're
trying to be upwardly mobile you're
trying to be laterally mobile and get to
a place where you can be happy and
productive and be interest in your job
and learn from those other people so
that's what I would say and based on my
time at Microsoft I would say yeah I
don't like what that company does but
there are good people at it right and so
you know when you first start working
there do I want to work you know on the
sorts of things that they tend to do no
because I don't really like it I don't
approve of a lot of it
but as a first job or a place to go to
learn things are there places inside it
where you can do that absolutely and it
may be less true today than it was then
because when I was an intern at
Microsoft the caliber of people there
was way higher probably than it is now
just even as a function of its smaller
size remember the smaller the company is
the easier it is to have a high density
of good people when you get up to a huge
number of people it becomes a lot harder
to have them all be good right or the
ratio gets lower but do I think they've
somehow gotten to a place where there's
literally nobody good there no I I
really don't think so
I think they're just the good people are
far outweighed by the people who really
don't know what they're doing
but that's okay for a first job where
you can learn just go hunt down those
good people and they're there Microsoft
has a large research department too so
you know you can go do more theoretical
things there too if you can stand a
sideways move into that somehow is
another option too right
because they do a lot of research there
which is not the same as product
development it's so a lot of
opportunities and I would say that
that's the thing to focus on figure out
you know do a due diligence test first
is the company I'm going to literally so
bad that there's nobody good there and
nothing to learn right that could be
possible it's not true of Microsoft even
today I'm fairly certain right but you
know maybe some other company it really
is that bad okay
maybe then try to avoid that job but any
of the other jobs Google Microsoft
Facebook etc I think they're big enough
they've got teams in them that know what
they're doing somewhere there are people
there who know what they're doing
find those people try to work with them
and I think you'll be okay
do we still need a separate translation
unit for them as fees stuff in my
products I had no problems having it in
one unit um I just I remember there
being some reason it has to be in a
separate translation unit maybe for
dll's or something I was having trouble
so I don't know we can play with it
later if we really want to but I found
that I had to keep it in a separate
translation unit and it had to be C and
it wasn't so much that had to be
acceptance that it had to go through C
now it may be that that was only for
Visual Studio 2012 it may be this one
longer the case right but I that's what
I recall so that's a lot can I tell you
and yes it sounds like Neil and just
talking about asking like him for
example of where to go in facebook or
whatever so yeah this is exactly the
case if you happen to know through like
handmade here or somewhere else if you
happen to know people who you you trust
who work at these companies who you know
whose opinion you value try to see if
they'll help you see if they'll help you
figure out where to work right because
if you've got a friend at Facebook who
you know has similar programming
opinions to yours then you can ask them
hey do you happen to know where the
places are in here that might be
interesting to me right where would you
go where did you decide to work are you
happy in the division you're in if not
where would you go it when you can are
you gonna try to be somewhere else where
would that be right
and so sometimes you can look out and
have a friend at Google have a friend at
Facebook or maybe just someone online
like through the hand made hero
community like have a network or
something maybe you can find someone who
already works there right so there you
go
John Blow says you are so jealous that I
get to go to GDC next week and see all
the great talks yes yes John I of course
am although you know I think you have to
put into perspective that as a new
person in the game industry you just you
just don't really know you don't have
very much experience shipping games and
understanding how to develop games so
you can benefit a lot from those
advanced level GDC talks that you're
gonna go to that'll tell you all about
the stuff you need to know you know I'm
saying so I feel like yeah you just have
to bring your notebook and and and make
sure you take copious notes on things
like for example you may not know I I do
notice that in braids and in the witness
there were like no microtransactions and
so I feel like you've got a lot to learn
about microtransactions and I pretty
much guarantee you there's gonna be a
lot of really great talks about that at
the GDC because you know as you know
from going to the GDC games are not
about making games it's about making
money
and microtransactions are a very good
way to make money alright folks I am
gonna close down the stream here or I'm
gonna try it too anyway let's go ahead
and close this
by the way I don't know if we can get
this link into the into the annotate
into the annotation somehow but again
just to remind everyone martins has this
guide that martins made is just
absolutely fantastic so everything that
we did about removing the C runtime
library you don't have to go back and
watch my stream to figure out it all out
he has already put it everything we did
including the stuff that we were not
looking online for is all in here and
very well documented it's probably the
best guide I've ever seen for this and
it's a guy I wish was around when I
first was getting rid of the C runtime
library cuz it would have saved me a lot
of headaches actually so I highly
recommend this everyone should read it
it's very good
and any time nowadays that I am doing
this and I don't even bother going to
Emma Stan anymore I just go right to his
guide it's that good so definitely check
that out it's it's the best guide for
this that I've ever seen it's got
everything in one place it's it's great
alright thank you everyone for joining
me for an episode of hand made here it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always I will be back tomorrow same time
same channel when we will go ahead and
do the things that I want to do today
when which I ended up deciding to get
rid of runtime memory instead but I'll
go ahead and do the distribution of
points on the hemisphere thing which was
my last things I want to do there with
our lighting sampling so hope you join
me for that and then next week we should
also have a little fun doing the sine
and cosine stuff that we wanted to do so
that should be fun too so hope see you
back here either tomorrow or next week
for that either way have fun programming
and I'll see everyone on the Internet
take it easy everybody