hey everybody casey muratory here i am
looking to do some videos for promotion
of our kickstarter we're doing a
kickstarter from yao the infinite book 2
our graphic novel series if you like
cats and space or just cool graphic
novels please check it out the links in
the description below and i asked around
what i could do that would interest
people and one of the things people said
is please go over your streaming setup
because people thought the lighting
looked really cool and that the sound
quality was really good and first of all
i'd like to say i'm delighted to hear
that because it is a super cheap setup
the lighting and sound proofing of this
setup are about as cheap as you can get
the whole thing is probably 120 bucks
total and i wish i could say that there
was something magic to it but basically
all i did was do the simplest possible
thing and just follow some cinema style
procedures to get good lighting so i can
show you how it's done let me show you a
video from my point of view so you can
see how it's set up what you can see
here is it's just led strips stuck to
moving blankets in a cube around where i
stream the key light is kind of a large
horizontal light to sort of evenly light
the face and then the fill light and the
rim light are done sort of vertically so
that they give a good contour to the
face and believe me my face needs all
the help it can get so if you've never
done cinema lighting before just go
watch a tutorial but once you kind of
know how to place lights for cinema
style lighting uh really all you gotta
do is get yourself the moving blankets
and some of these the moving blankets
will cost you 40 to 60 dollars for a
full set you can get four or six moving
blankets in a set usually you want to
get some kind of heavy ones if you can
because they deaden the sound well but
you hang those up however you can it
depends on the room you might have to
spend a few more dollars if your room
doesn't have really anything to hang
them from you may have to buy like a
curtain rod or something one or two
curtain rods to hang them from so your
price will go up a little bit but if you
have a room you can already kind of just
like clip them to something or tie them
to something you can save the money i
use actually little tiny clips to clip
them but you know whatever works for you
uh you get yourself some of these and
these light strips you have to buy ones
that you know won't have a resonant
frequency with your camera because
that's something that can easily happen
uh i found that these particular light
strips that i'll link in the description
below don't resonate with cameras like
high quality cameras so those are ones
that i like to use but if you can find
one that doesn't resonate with a camera
that's really all you need now inside
each pack of these i'll open one up so
you can see it essentially what you're
gonna do is you're just gonna take this
piece that it comes with right it's just
a basically a roll you can see there
it's basically a roll of led lights and
it's got a little like ir receiver on
the end of it all you do is you just
plug this into a light socket and then
you take the little handy uh remote
control that they give you and you can
just set the lighting to whatever you
need it to be the remote control has
tons of settings so you can make it
brighter or darker you can make it
different color lighting so you can have
you know different themes and so on and
let me just show you
what each of the lights does in my setup
so that you can get a sense for them but
then you can also feel free to play
around with this it doesn't have to be
set up exactly the way i have it
so first let's just isolate just the key
light which is the one that's
illuminating most of my face
so first i'll turn it off so you can see
what happens you see how most of the
light is now gone like i'm basically
entirely in shadow it's like spooky
casey right
um and if i isolate it so if i turn off
all the other lights you can see it's
actually totally usable kind of by
itself but it's just kind of boring and
it's a little bit shadowy it's just not
that great and one of the other things
that you can see is it's the one that
reflects in my glasses you may say oh
why is that happening because i don't
know if you're like me i don't like you
see a lot of youtubers that use those
circular lights i really don't like
those because it shows up in their eye
as a little circle and it just looks
kind of spooky so i actually like this
much better but you might say well in
your glasses it kind of does a nasty
reflection
yes that's why normally i don't talk
this way i'm normally doing this because
i'm doing programming so it's set up for
this direction and you can see that i've
placed the light so that they don't
actually do
that reflection for when i'm actually
doing my streaming so you do want to be
careful not to place your lights in
places where they're going to reflect
off something that the the viewer can
really see
or if that is going to happen you could
maybe make them a little denser and a
little dimmer so that it looks just more
like a natural light but again that's
something that you usually have to worry
about because when you set up your uh
your streaming setup wherever you're
gonna normally be pointing you can
usually place the light so that doesn't
happen
okay so that's the key light and setting
it up is really easy again i like it
large so that it gets a nice clean wash
over the face without it being too like
pinpoint
let me go ahead and turn back on the
other two lights so there's that fill
light
and there's the rim light uh and if i
now turn the key light off you can see
the other two lights very clearly and
i'll just turn each one on and off in
series so you can kind of see what they
add so first here is the fill light
which is kind of giving the the side of
my face that's not doing the sort of uh
sort of blue rim lighting uh it's it's
giving that side more contour right
because otherwise you wouldn't be able
to really see that side of the face and
then the uh the rim light right is just
trying to do uh that sort of uh blue you
know i don't know filmic style lighting
on the side to kind of give it just more
a little more drama to it right so
without that you kind of lose that now
you can see them both with the fill
light i'm sorry with the key light as
well if you'd like here is uh each one
turned on and off individually so the uh
backlight or the fill light depending on
how you want to call that one you can
see that one turning on and off there
just so you get a sense of what it does
for the contour here's the rim light
turning on and off
right
and again there's with both of them
so really that's all that's going on
it's just led strips stuck to moving
blankets that are around me it's an
incredibly cheap setup a hundred and
some odd dollars is about as cheap as
you're gonna get for something that
looks this good most of the other kind
of lights you buy are really clunky and
you'll spend a lot of time and money
actually mounting them as well because a
lot of times they don't have really good
mounts or they're flimsy or they're
gonna take up space on your desk another
really great thing about this setup is
it's kind of all out of your way it's
just a little sort of curtain setup that
sits around you and it doesn't take up
any space on your desk it can't fall
over uh there's nothing weird that's
gonna happen now the other cool thing
about this uh with this setup you kind
of can make your own lighting
environments you can program these leds
to have multiple settings so for example
i can go like switch them around if i
want to have red you know light on my
face or something like that i just can
you know i can have a blue
light or whatever i want to uh i set
these up to do a standard dramatic film
style lighting because that's what i was
looking for but you can actually create
anything you want and you can also
remember the settings because the
program like you can program the
settings into the remote control and it
will then reset to those when you want
so you can get your streaming setup and
maybe you have one or two of those and
so on
that's really all there is to the setup
as far as mic and camera is concerned
the mics don't matter much you can get
really good sound if you have this kind
of isolation with the moving blankets
you don't need to spend very much money
on a microphone i actually use a
microphone that's a couple hundred
dollars because i happen to have had it
from a long time ago it's a really old
microphone but you can use a cheaper
microphone for sure and still get really
good audio quality
camera wise i don't have any tips this
is an expensive camera it's a sony a7
and expensive cameras make things look
better better lenses just make things
look better um a 35 millimeter camera
back with a good lens is gonna make
things look better
this lighting will make things look
really good even with the webcam but
it's never gonna look as good as if you
get a real camera the lens so i wish i
could say there was a way to do that
part cheaply but there isn't the
environment you can do dirt cheap the
camera i don't have any tips that's why
i didn't post a video saying here's how
to get a really cheap camera set up
because that part uh you're on your own
if anyone knows better ways
i'm all yours but
with this lighting setup you should
still be able to use a fairly cheap
camera and have it look good but it
won't look this good that's really all
there is to it you don't have to do
anything complicated just put up the
moving blankets stick the led strips to
them and then tweak the led strips until
they are the right brightness and the
right color for the look that you're
going for now you have to make sure
again don't get led strips that might
resonate with your camera so always
order like one set of led strips first
and make sure they work with your camera
before ordering more i've definitely
seen led strips that will blink really
nastily they like flicker like a
fluorescent light against the camera and
you don't want that so make sure you get
ones and i'll put the ones that i use in
the link below and i'll also put the
moving blankets in the link below that's
really all there is to it again please
check out our kickstarter if you get a
chance uh it's a great comic
about cats in space and a lot of other
cool stuff uh book one was awesome and
the print looks awesome and so i think
book two will be just as good you can
get them both from the kickstarter
that'll be in the description below too
that's it put your questions in the
comments and i'll answer them and yeah
have a good time with your new streaming
setup