okay this is a lecture that I originally
gave in I believe it was 2007 so it's a
long long long time ago at this point it
was about seven years before I started
handmade hero I and I guess it's ten
years to today maybe a little little
over ten years so it's I think it's I
think this talk is actually a decade old
I'm not 100% sure about that but I
believe it is and the circumstances
around which I gave this talk was that I
had gone back to Boston Massachusetts
which is it's I didn't grow up in Boston
but I grew up in Massachusetts I had
gone back there and I had gone for
reasons I don't totally remember to a
local sort of game developer group that
they were having there and I had met a
fellow there whose name was Philip Tong
I don't actually know exactly how to
pronounce his last name
I don't think I've ever actually heard
it pronounced but he it might be Tana
might be tan
he ran a group at MIT called gambit it
was G am bi T and it was a group that
was specifically sort of partnered with
the Singaporean government and I don't
know the circumstances under which they
ran this exactly but it had something to
do with the fact that Singapore wanted
to encourage game development to occur
in their country more so than it was
already and I do think at that time
there was also things they were doing to
try it like a favorable tax status or
things like this to try to encourage
game companies to set up shop there
probably because they perceived other
countries to be starting to have good
game development industries and they
maybe didn't have that and thought that
there was stuff that they could do I
remember actually South Korea doing
something similar around that a little
earlier actually but sit very very very
very similar so there are a couple
countries that we're doing this sort of
thing those the two that are aware of
but I think it was kind of a common
around the world as game development
started to become a little more popular
and so what the Singaporean government
had done in this particular case is they
had one of their sort of initiatives was
to work with MIT to create something
which was effectively a program for
students who I don't really know how
those students were selected back in
Singapore but I assume that it was based
on you know attitude for computer
programming or art or other sorts of
things that were you know game
development related these students would
go over and spend time at MIT during the
summer working with various game
development technologies and being sort
of taught how to make games by people
who were set up at this as part of this
program that's about really all I know
about it but I believe it still exists
to this day I could be wrong about that
but it was still going for quite some
time after I gave this lecture anyway I
met the fellow who was in charge of
running that that operation and he asked
if I would come and give a talk to the
students there and there's only you know
a handful o students there it's fifteen
thirty something like this so this was
the talk that I prepared for that
occasion and it's only ever been seen by
those thirty people or however many
people were in the room that day the
just the people for that program but it
was one of my favorite lectures that
I've ever done because it was very
personal and about the topic that I
actually cared about
unlike most lectures that I give which
really aren't there usually on a
technical topic that's not really that's
just kind of abstract and so this topic
was very personal and in fact it was
basically the the mindset that led to
handmade hero was encapsulated in this
talk back in 2007 and the talk was
specifically you could say talking about
the same all the same things that I
tried to get across with handmade hero
are in this talk already and this is
sort of where I was already thinking
about this and having this opinion kind
of at that time and it just wasn't until
seven or eight years later that I
actually started handmade hero but it's
the same basic idea so that's the
that that's the context of the talk to
you well and it's called how to open a
black box so I'm gonna go ahead and give
you the run-through of the talk now as
closest I can do it to how I did it back
then but it's been 10 years so the
chances that I'll remember exactly how
it goes are pretty low but I'll do my
best
alright so in the industry we have a
term called black box and you've
probably heard it if you've ever been in
programming circles essentially what it
means is it really is a little bit wrong
because black box
you know maybe is different from orange
box a different from purple box it
sounds like you're talking about the
color of the box's exterior like how was
it painted but that's not what we mean
we say black box we really mean is
opaque box we mean a box you cannot see
into so the opposite of a black box
would be something that was transparent
box so it's really opaque box versus
transparent box is the important part
and the key to it is that you're talking
about when you use the term black box
something that you don't really know how
it works right and there's two reasons
you might not know how it works one
reason is that you simply can't so for
example a closed source piece of
software that is too complex to really
be reverse engineered by you in a
reasonable amount of time you might say
this as a black box because there's just
no way for you to know what it's
actually doing another reason you might
have a black box is that you simply
haven't taken the time to understand the
system yet but you certainly could right
and those are the two times you might be
talking about something as a black box
in one case something really truly is
completely opaque to you and you will
never be able to really know what's
going on inside specifically because you
simply don't have access on the other
hand you can have a situation where
something easily could be understood by
you and you could investigate it further
but you're choosing not to do so right
so let's talk about what a black box
might be like in the case of a video
game today as so something that I don't
think I mentioned the time because it
really wasn't necessarily something that
would have been in widespread use but
something like a game engine like unity
or unreal
you might think of as a black box
because you maybe don't really know much
of
how it works but you're going to use it
or maybe you're using some kind of a
game development library so something
like a load texture call you may
understand conceptually what a load
texture call does in the engine you know
that it loads a texture off of disk and
maybe brings that texture into memory
and all you really know about this black
box is that when you make this load
texture call you are going to get back
this texture that you store it on the
disk it's going to come into memory and
you can start using it to texture
services the reason we might say this is
a black box again is because you don't
really know how that happened you don't
know how the texture was really stored
you don't know how it might have been
compressed or decompress you don't know
if was transcoded on the fly you don't
know whether it was loaded on demand or
delay loaded or whatever happened you
don't really know much about the
implementation
you just know semantically I said load
texture I got a texture the same would
be true for the play sound call maybe
you hear sound out the speakers you
don't really know much about how that
happened
maybe there's the physics call like
apply force you don't really know how
the physics engine works but you know
that when you apply force the like
bouncing ball starts bouncing around or
whatever right and these are examples of
game code on the left side all of those
things that I said and the game on the
right side and that's how you would
conceptualize these things if you have a
black box as an engine in between you
think of the left side the play sound
the load texture as the code for the
game and you think of the things that
happen the results you saw as the game
and there's a black box sitting in the
middle what is that black box well it's
the game engine and you have no idea how
it works right it's completely opaque to
you you just know semantically you'd do
something and something else happens on
the other end hopefully that makes sense
so that's the second kind of black box
in most circumstances now it certainly
depends on the particular engine you're
talking about there are closed source
engines out there but say take for
example the Unreal Engine my
understanding today is that unless
there's a particularly unusual
circumstance when you are using the
Unreal Engine you actually have the
source code to the engine as well so if
you didn't know how it worked it's not
because you couldn't investigate it's
because you simply haven't investigated
on the other hand there are
circumstances where you don't get access
to
and source code so you may be using an
engine in other cases where you
literally have no way of knowing
outworks the semantics are all you will
ever get but in either case as long as
those two things were true one of those
two things were true you would have one
of these opaque boxes you did not
understand okay so what I'd like to talk
about today is why it might be important
for you to understand what happens
inside that black box and who the types
of people are who probably should learn
what happens inside that black box and
finally give a motivating example to
show what exactly the results are and
why it's a it proves to be very useful
to have a complete understanding of how
game engine code works if you're you
sort of in this category of people who
probably should care right because I
don't argue that everyone should care I
only argue that certain people should
care right so the topic that I want to
talk about that motivates these things
is normal mapping and normal mapping is
hopefully something that most people are
familiar with today in the black box
sense so in the semantic sense it's
something that even an artist someone
who doesn't do programming probably
understands at least semantically now
because it's part of the job so even
though a normal map is a very technical
topic at some level it has become so
commonplace in game development that
even people who don't program must know
what it is and must know how to make one
even if they don't necessarily
understand mathematically what it is now
a normal map for those of you who may
not quite know what one is it's a very
simple concept the idea is that when you
have a three-dimensional object that you
have created it is necessarily built out
of pieces that may not encode all of the
information necessary to say the the
sort of Ferenc of the surface the the
textural aspects of the surface that run
along the surface that relate to how
bumpy is or sort of how it reflects
light
if you
right so there's a lot of information
that we need to encode when we talk
about modeling a 3d object and so we end
up with a series of maps that sit on
that surface and then encode this
information information like how
reflective how shiny something is
information like what the reflected
color is so what colors does it absorb
what colors does it reflect and finally
information like how is is displaced or
how it has like little fine lit levels
of bumps or sort of defects in the
surface that will cause the light to
catch in those areas and that last part
is typically encoded these days with a
normal map a normal map is something
that says I'm gonna pretend that I know
more about this surface than the
information I actually have in the
three-dimensional model I'm gonna
pretend that I know lots of little
microscopic well probably not
microscopic still macroscopic but very
tiny little surface changes little bumps
little little pieces of information
there and what I'm gonna do is I'm going
to use a two-dimensional texture like I
would use for other things and instead
of encoding things like color in it I'm
gonna encode those little fine little
bumps so that way when I have something
like skin or something and I want to
have every little pore of the skin
represented there I don't actually have
to have a three-dimensional model that
has every pore in it actually running at
runtime instead I can just have a map
that captures those pores and I can put
that on the surface as a map and we get
that fine geometry there okay so that's
what a normal map is now why do I want
to talk about this topic well the reason
I want to talk about this topic is
because if you go back to sort of the
the turn of the millennium if you will
we didn't know anything about normal
mapping really in the game industry it
was a pretty new concept and although we
sort of knew about bump mapping because
bump mapping is a topic that's much
older and I'll kind of try to explain
the difference between those two things
a little bit for those who don't know
but although bump mapping was kind of
well understood because I believe it was
Jim Blinn who originally introduced it
introduced
you know in I don't know the early 80s
late 70s something like this
it's bump mapping had been around a long
time and what bump mapping was is it was
sort of a similar concept to normal
mapping it was much earlier and what you
encoded in the texture map was just
height it's like a height field it's
like mapping a height field onto your
object and what the renderer would do
that you would be using in this case is
you would take the information in the
bump map those Heights and at render
time
you would do a sort of differential to
figure out how the normal should Bend
based on the height map now this is a
reasonably good technique and it had a
lot of nice applications back in the day
but it's got drawbacks and specifically
since it's based on a difference there's
only so much bend you can encode because
since you're not encoding directly the
way the surface is pointing like you can
with a normal map as a normal map
actually encodes a normal week or it
encodes the direction the surface is
pointing a bump map can only get you so
far now to give you an analogy of why
this is true imagine a height map right
probably you've played with a height map
before if you've ever done anything with
game development a height map just says
at every point in the world how high is
it well if you want to make a perfectly
sheer cliff you can't do it with a
height map because it has two points
that it's going to interpolate between
right and it knows this one's this high
and this one's this low it doesn't know
it should be perfectly flat so it makes
it still a little bit slanted the same
thing is true of a bump map it only has
those two points to deal with it doesn't
know that they're supposed to be a
perfectly flat peak there it thinks they
just should connect them with a line
just like it would everything else it's
exactly the same thing as a height map
you cant encode it perfectly normal maps
therefore are much better because what
they encode is the actual normal if you
want something to point directly to the
side you just encode at this point it
points directly to the side and so it
gives you a lot more flexibility there
to encode what's actually happening with
a surface you don't need any more
information you don't need to try to
guess what's supposed to happen because
it knows at this point the normal should
be exactly this so it's a way of storing
more directly what's going on and these
sorts of things are starting to slowly
get introduced around this time into
game development because there have been
research papers on the topic and so on
and so forth right
now what I've got on the screen right
now is an example of why normal mapping
is so interesting so if you take a look
at these two meshes they're half of a
face if you take a look at what what
you're seeing there it's it's like you
know how oftentimes really model one
half the face then we mirror it this is
one half of a face and you can see a
little white line that shows the the
white direction that's coming in and
what hopefully you can see here is that
although the left and right sides are
completely different numbers of
triangles so for example on the left
side there's 31,000 triangles in that
mesh and on the right side there's only
894 right a massive difference in the
number of triangles the two meshes when
rendered look almost identical except
for their profile edges and what I mean
by that is if you look at something like
an actual geometric feature the eyebrow
the nose the ear along the profile you
can see how rough the 894 triangle
version is it's very rough right but on
the other hand if you look at the
interior it's still just right it's
perfectly smooth everywhere in here it
doesn't look rough at all and that's
what was so powerful about normal
mapping is it allowed you to encode
these really nice clean normals into
your mesh that made it look like a
really high res model even though you
were rendering almost no triangles and
this was really powerful so the only
problem at this point became how do you
clean up the silhouettes and even if you
didn't clean up the silhouettes it still
just looks great and what you can see if
I move the light around is as I move
that light around you can really see
that it responds just like it should and
again the only errors you see are really
along those silhouette edges they just
are they're just too rough but all of
that lighting is captured beautifully by
the normal map right so that's really
why this was so important right is we
can get so much fidelity into a very low
resolution model by leveraging this
technique now
what I want to try and illustrate here
is that normal mapping is a good example
of something that it didn't even exist
right
this I believe as of 2007 which was when
the lecture was given normal mapping was
completely ubiquitous more or less at
this point right so when I gave this
lecture and also obviously today which
is even later normal mapping is not
something you probably think about at a
low level it's something that you just
take for granted and you treat it
semantically just like the black box
game engine code that I was talking
about back in at the beginning of the
lecture but if you imagine it back in
2002 nobody knew how to do anything with
it it was completely new it wasn't even
in game engines yet nobody had any idea
how to do anything with it we didn't
know how to make them we didn't know how
to initially encode them we didn't know
how to even get the artist him to work
with them right and so what I want to
kind of illustrate is that it by taking
something that now we do take for
granted as being in the game engine if
we go back in time right every single
thing we take for granted now at some
point in time was a new frontier and
people needed to push on that frontier
in order to get it to the point where we
could use it as if it was a black box
and maybe not care as much right all
right so here's what the challenged look
like back at the turn of the millennium
acquisition of normal maps where do they
come from
right projection of normal Maps how do
we get them on to the models that we
need sampling of them so how do we take
the projected version of them and figure
out what goes on what right
there's encoding of them how do we store
them and how do we use them at runtime
there's post-processing how did they get
cleaned up and this is all at the head
end this is when we're making stuff
right and then we've got the back end
part of the process how do we decode
them at runtime how do we shade them you
know how do we write shaders that use
them so in this lecture I'm we talking
about this part and the reason I'm gonna
be talking about this part is because
it's the basic foundational part the
rest of it is actually very interesting
as well and in fact one of the things
that I worked on that I was particularly
proud of in this time is we had in our
code I think arguably the very fastest
by several orders of magnitude normal
mapping capture system that people had
made and so that first part was really
exciting too but in order to get to that
part you have to understand the basic
parts first so we're gonna focus on that
in this lecture maybe I can do another
lecture later that talks about the other
part of it because that part was pretty
exciting as well ok so here we go let's
start by doing a little bit of
mathematical warm-up because one of the
things that certainly and I can this was
not part of the lecture when I
originally gave it because I didn't do
hand made here at the time it was 7
years before I started it or eight years
I'm not sure how many but one of the
things that I get asked all the time all
the time I get emails from tons of
people who asked this I get asked it on
stream all the time it's how important
is math for game development and my
answer is usually gotta be a little bit
equivocal I the answer is not at all or
it's crucial and you must know it and
the the difference depends on what kind
of game programming you're doing it
always always always matters what kind
you're doing if you are dealing with
physics or graphics or any of these
things math is fundamental and you must
know it you must know it very very well
and you can't be scared of it and so
suffice to say when we're talking about
something that's really graphics
specific and in this case we're talking
about pushing a frontier math is
absolutely crucial and you must know it
so what I'm gonna do here is I'm going
to run through some mathematic
maybe those of you out there who are
sort of new to game development aren't
gonna get what I'm talking about and
that is okay I'm trying to give you a
little bit of the flavor of the way that
we think about these things and some of
the basic math that's required of you
when you do get there so don't let this
scare you off the fact that this math
may be a little bit difficult for you to
grasp I'm not expecting you to get it
all I'm expecting you to go oh I see
this is why we say mathematics is
important for game development and this
is why we say it's involved in what
you're doing so what I've written here
is an equation it's a very very simple
equation to a game developer who's used
to working with math but it may be
completely foreign and bizarre to
somebody who has only had high school
math hasn't had linear algebra and so on
what it represents is a spatial
transform it represents taking some
point in some space and moving it or
rotating it scaling it doing something
like this and we would all recognize
this very quickly P is the standard
notation for a point a point in
three-dimensional space for example like
the kind we would care about in game
development P prime which is on the left
side our standard notation for something
that happened to P afterword right so P
prime is is the new point that we're
getting right it's a point that has
moved or transform to scale in some way
and P was the input so think the
right-hand side that just P by itself
that's the input P Prime that's the
output and this big R that R represents
a matrix it represents a matrix that
will move our point rotate our point
scale our point so P prime equals R P is
a way of stating something very simple a
new point P prime comes from equals a
transform our operating on an input
point P P prime equals R P now here's
what it looks like expanded out on the
left you see P prime it
is a vector because this is
three-dimensional if it was
one-dimensional it would only be one
value X but because it's
three-dimensional it has three values XY
and Z you can notice each of them has a
prime because they are new values that
I'm talking about here that are changes
to P so I have concise or to work that
into the notation where the XY and z are
also the primes they're the new values
of x y&amp;z I'm talking about in the middle
I've got the same old equal sign again
mirrors this equation exactly then I've
got my transform our it's a bag of
numbers I have no idea what these
numbers mean yet I'm not even going to
talk about what they mean I just know
they're a big old matrix of numbers a b
c d e f g h i okay and that's
intentional now I am someone who's
worked with graphics way too long so I
have meanings and I have preconceived
notions and all sorts of things that I
apply when I see a three-dimensional
matrix but right now we're not talking
about those we're gonna pretend we just
don't even we're not even thinking about
these like that yet
we just know there's a big bag of
numbers in there and then finally we
have P on the other side that's our
input again three dimensions because the
three dimension point XY and Z it tells
us where in space this point is okay
this is the simplest possible transform
equation it doesn't even involve
movement it only involves scale rotate
shear that's really what this is going
to involve why because the matrix is
three dimensional
for a three-dimensional input and in
order to encompass things like
translation or projection things like
this we would have to have a four by
four matrix that's a topic for another
day you not to concern yourself with
this just suffice to say all we can do
with these equations mathematically is
all we can do is rotate scale share
those sorts of transforms okay all right
so
what I'm going to mention now and again
it's okay if this is a little bit too
much for people who haven't come to the
math right now is to think about what
does this bag of numbers mean because if
you see something like this and you've
never had linear algebra for it you're
gonna be very confused right you gonna
be like I don't know what's going on
here I have no idea what's happening
here right but once you start to learn
more about how matrix multiplication
works how a matrix multiplies a vector
in this case on this side of the
equation here we have a matrix times a
vector what you will learn is that
matrix multiplication is a very rote
process you can learn how to do it it's
very simple we've actually take a times
X B times y C times E and we add them
together then we do x times D it does
right there's a rote process you use
again don't mean to worry about it now
it's not the focus of this lecture at
all people who don't get it it's okay
someday you will if you work on this
kind of programming for a living but for
those of you who get it you know how to
do matrix multiplication you've probably
seen it before you've definitely had it
if you've gone to the knowledge of a
class in college if you've ever worked
on the 3d graphics textbook they've gone
through this so it's something that's
pretty common in 3d graphics however and
here's the part that I kind of want to
get to in this lecture even if you've
had the basics of linear algebra the
basics of 3d graphics programming a lot
of people for whatever reason don't
really understand how a matrix really
works internally and some people don't
know how to interpret the numbers in a
matrix they just think of them as
something that does a particular
transfer may read in a book somehow
somewhere how to make one of these
matrices so they know how to make say a
rotation matrix by using a formula that
they've looked up in a book and they
know that if they multiply the matrices
in this format like I said before that
they get a particular operation that
occurs okay and that's all they know so
what I want to focus on here is a little
bit deeper understanding let's say you
do know how to do that make sure because
we don't really understand why or how
it's working so let's take a look at
this diagram here here is a set of
points defined like the p value that i
was talking about the previous equation
so imagine any one of these points is
just the p value so we're gonna take
every point in the object and we'll do
this transfer
every single one of them to get a new
object right now it goes a lot of times
people are used to thinking left to
right so because that's the way you read
but in math oftentimes we go right to
left more often because we're solving
equations so we want the thing on the
left side to be the one variable we've
solved for right so that's why it looks
like this so we're really reaching it
right to left okay the inputs on this
side and the outputs on this side the
arrow goes that way that's just how it
works in mathematics when you solve
typically by convention so the new point
we're getting here is a rotated object
as you can see here right and the input
is this object now each of the axes I've
highlighted here I've highlighted the
x-axis in red the green is the y axis
and the z is the blue axis and what you
can see over here is we take this input
and it's around the world axis system
it's just the basic axis system they're
aligned when I apply this transform now
I have transform the object you can see
that it is rotated itself away from
those world axes okay and what I've
written here is I've written R sub W
this is just it's free for me in
mathematics to put a little subscript on
something and say I'm just gonna denote
this rotation matrix with R as a world
rotation matrix W and I'm using that
notation to say this is something that
places an object into the world okay so
it takes an object that's at rest and it
puts it at some orientation in the world
you can see that happening by the
diagrams P prime is the new object
that's been placed in the world so now I
ask the question how does that bag of
numbers in a matrix which maybe you've
seen before but haven't thought too much
about and those of you who've already
watched the handmade Hero series should
know the answer because we've gone over
this but maybe you haven't what do those
numbers mean well what I'd like to
emphasize here is that actually there's
a very specific structure to something
like a matrix that rotates an object to
place it into the world and in fact you
can look directly at the numbers of that
matrix and pull out specifically what
the axes of the
new object will be because they're read
straight off the columns the columns of
a matrix are actually the new axes of
the object after it's been rotated
believe it or not some people go through
their whole programming crew not even
knowing that they just learned that this
is how you make a rotation matrix out of
some book they never really thought too
much about it and in fact this was an
interview question I don't mean to
spoiler it I won't even say where the
interview question who actually gave it
but let's just say a valve interview
question actually involved asking the
candidate these questions and you would
be surprised at how many people can't
give a very good answer because it's
common to learn to use something without
really knowing how it works
even in graphics programming ok why why
does that happen
right I've basically just told you that
if I look at a 3d rotation matrix the
three axes right of the XY and Z world
coordinates I've just said that's what
happened like I just said that but why
does it happen that way right why is it
that these three axes appear in this
matrix in this fashion why is it that
that's what that equation does right
well the answer is because I can look at
matrix multiplication as producing a
very specific result here okay so what
I've done again for the benefit of those
of you who maybe haven't done enough
with matrices yet I've written out how
the matrix multiplication works I
alluded to it before I take a B and C of
the matrix here and I multiply it by x
y&amp;z of the input point and I add them
together you can see it right here ax
plus B y plus cz that's how I get my
first row of my resulting point next row
same thing but I move down one I use the
next row of the matrix but the same
input point finally last row of the
matrix same input point and you can see
very easily here how the math works out
anyone who's gone to even a pre-algebra
class can understand this side here so
again
it's very easy to understand these
things it looks intimidating when it's
presented like this or like this because
you aren't familiar with it perhaps but
once I write it out it's very simple
right these are very simple things that
don't involve anything there isn't even
a squared term or a square root or
imaginary numbers none of these things
are involved right very very simple so
let's concentrate on that left side
because everyone can understand that
left side and what you'll notice here is
that if I look there's a very specific
structure ad and G the column of this
matrix always multiplies X be e and H
always multiplies Y C F and I right
always multiply Z if you imagine pulling
those out you can start to see exactly
how this operation works I'm not really
doing a matrix multiplication I mean I
am but I'll have to think of it that way
instead I could think of it as the input
x coordinate multiplied by a new vector
the input y coordinate multiplied by a
new vector the Z coordinate multiplied
by a new vector what's this doing it's
just moving me out along these three
axes right that's all I'm doing you can
see it very clearly here if I reduce the
notation to just talk about axes here's
my x axis in world space y axis in world
space z axis in world space the X input
multiplies the x axis the Y input the y
axis the Z and put the z axis that's why
these are the new axes it's all very
simple if you go look at the scalars
right very very straightforward so you
can understand very easily how these
things are working you don't even need
to think of it in terms of matrices you
can just think of it as multiplying each
vector by how far along I want to go and
that's it so here's a diagram if in case
this is not easy for you to mentally
conceptualize what's happening
geometrically right if I have an X
vector in world space right like I said
I did I want to go X distance along it
that's what my x-coordinate will mean in
the new coordinate system right
same thing with Y along the y axis the
same thing with Z along the z axis so
effectively I'm building my new vector
right I'm building my new vector out
this way I'm building that by just
stepping along each of the new axes and
that's why I can look at this matrix and
say these are the new axes of the object
all right let's do it one more time here
is the matrix it's the exact same matrix
a b c d e f g h i right same packet
numbers even if i want to it could be
the exact same matrix equivalent but
this time we're gonna look at it
differently we're gonna look at it as
doing something different okay another
way to conceptualize it let's suppose
that I wanted to say this was a camera
transform right so I'm handing you a
matrix and I'm saying I'm going to use
this as the transform that map's the
world into a particular camera space so
that I can render it again still the
three dimensional matrix I'm just gonna
use it for a different purpose how can
we interpret what it does now I know
this is foreign concept but remember a
three by three matrix can be used for
all sorts of purposes so how I choose to
use it will determine the questions I
might want to ask and how I get those
answers if I'm using my three
dimensional matrix to place an object in
the world then the numbers in the matrix
are interpreted a specific way not
because the multiplication is done
differently but because how I use the
results determines which numbers are
important and why right in terms of my
understanding the three-dimensional math
will always be the same but the results
that I produce are always based on what
I use those results for and so how I
want to think about the numbers of the
matrix will change based on what that
matrix is doing
and this should be obvious anyone who
thinks about it because matrixes are
just for everything so obviously I can't
always think about a bag of numbers the
same way because that bag of numbers is
going to be used in many many different
contexts so I must learn to think about
the numbers in that matrix based on its
use so same kind of matrix 3x3 still a
rotation no changes in my requirements
for the matrix but now I'm using it for
something different I'm using it as a
transform that will transform the world
into a particular orientation for
rendering how do I interpret the values
well we have to start by saying the
operation is now reversed I'm starting
with an object on the right-hand side
that is somewhere in the world for real
and what I want to do is I want to move
it into a space where it's aligned with
a new set of axes so let's suppose we're
talking about the object that is the
camera this is the object I want to view
the world from well obviously what I
know about this then is that the camera
transfer must set that object aligned
with the world axes because once I
render everything must be aligned with
the world axis because I'm going to
render down the world axis system right
so the act of rendering a camera
transfer must move the world into a
specific space that is the camera space
so that the world axis and the cameras
are now aligned at the start they won't
be aligned and afterward they will be
again right to left reading because
we've solved for the left hand side all
right what do these numbers mean well it
might be confusing and surprising at
first but actually the opposite thing is
true of a camera transform as an object
transform a camera transform is read by
its rows each row gives the axis in
world space of the camera that will
become the aligned camera after the
transform is over so
you can see we've got a read access for
the ex a yellow I'm sorry a green access
for the Y and a blue access for the Z
and here you can see where they are
placed in the matrix just by looking at
the matrices numbers you know those axes
straight off if you know this is a
camera transform those are the axes why
why is this the case why is it that the
x axis of the camera goes of the row in
the top row the Y x2 the camera goes in
the middle row and the Z acts of the
camera it goes in the bottom row again
it's the exact same equation is with the
worldspace one how is it that the
meaning can be looked at in these two
totally different ways just based on
whether I was using it for one thing or
using it for another thing right well
the answer gets back to the exact same
scalar equation and again it's because
matrix math only does one thing so if I
use it for one purpose I have to analyze
it one way and if I use it for another
purpose after you analyze it another way
but the scalar math can't change it's
still a matrix multiply and it still has
to produce the exact same results
because the underlying computation
doesn't change just because I mentally
wanted to use a matrix for something
different so let's take a look at these
scalars over here how can I get an axis
out of ABCDE F and G H I and why would
they mean the camera transform I don't
understand let's do the same thing we
did before before we observe that we
could produce structure out of this
unstructured set of scalar equations and
they're not with equations they're
computations really because we're
talking about just this side there's no
equal sign anymore out of these scalar
expressions how can I produce that
structure well this time what I'd like
to do is think of it as a dot product
instead write a dot product is the thing
we were actually doing to do the matrix
math ABC XYZ ax plus B y plus cz the dot
product is exactly that operation now if
you've never heard of a dot product or
I'm sorry to throw the term at you but
again the math incredibly simple if I
have one vector X Y Z and another
vector ABC I'm literally just talking
about multiplying the X's Y's and Z's of
each and adding them together that's it
again so simple it's pre-algebra you
don't even have to solve an equation
nothing involved it's just
multiplication in addition that's it
that's a dot product well if you take a
look here you can see that those dot
products are in each row every row is a
dot product so let's take a look if we
were to isolate our dot products what do
we get these are the three dot products
we get ABC XYZ d e f dot X Y Z and G H I
dot X Y Z right those are the dot
products I get which means effectively
what I have done is I've taken each row
of the camera transform and dotted it
with the input point that produces
exactly the operation we want for a
camera the input point measured along
the x axis of the X row first row of the
matrix the input point measured along
the Y row the input point measured along
the Z row now for those of you
unfamiliar with the dot product you may
be like well ok I don't understand what
you mean by that would even mean by
measured by err why do I care that I'm
taking three dot products I believe you
because I can see that these are three
of the things that you said it's three
of these things right but why does that
produce a camera transform well in order
to answer that question we have to get a
little bit deeper into the mathematics
but let's go ahead and do that I just
said a dot product is this equation
right if I have two vectors the X the Y
and the Z get multiplied and added
together and we notate it this way a
transpose B now why do we notate it
trade transpose B what does that mean
well transpose in linear algebra means
to flip something around its diagonal
okay and you can actually see that here
this and this are both three-dimensional
vectors but one has been
flipped it's been laid on its side right
so you can think of this as a transpose
B because this is how we normally write
a vector vertically X Y Z right and I
don't want to get too bogged down in the
linear algebra there are actually
reasons why we write a three-dimensional
point or a 3-dimensional vector lined up
like that and there's some minutia there
if you wanted to get into it
it's not relevant to our current
conversation but let's just say there's
a reason if you go deeper into the math
Y summer vertical and summer horizontal
but if we were to take vectors that we
all would be considering vertical and we
lay one down on its side
that's a transpose operation we're
taking it and the rows become columns
and the columns become rows since
there's only one column it becomes a row
when we transpose it so we say a
transpose B for a dot product we say
that because we're lying this one down
on its side and this one is still
vertical all right
so you can see this operation drawn out
for you here it's very simple hopefully
it makes good sense when I take a vector
a and I transpose it I'm laying it down
its side column to come rows rows become
columns and you can do this with a
matrix to anything that is a
two-dimensional grid of numbers like
this you can do it too right and by the
way there's multi-dimensional versions
of this but again we don't care about
that for our purposes we're totally fine
with just these so here we see a
transpose B written out you can see that
a gets transposed to B does not they
multiplied together just in that very
straightforward way that all of matrix
multiplication was working as even if
you didn't know it you've seen me do it
a couple times already right now and we
produce as a result the dot product the
result that is the dot product it's one
scalar it's a single value each of these
multiplied together and give us a single
value like five right these were more
compound values they have three values
in them five seven nine three two one
whatever but this result here it's one
value so it the dot product by its
nature is contractual right it brings
things together and reduces their
dimension
okay so how does this produce a camera
transform it was very easy to see in
that walking out along the axis form how
multiplying vectors by scalars produced
the worldspace transform hopefully that
made sense to everybody but the dot
product is a little harder to grok why
would that produce a camera transform
why does that produce the basis well the
reason is because the dot product
actually produces a very special version
of the law of cosines and I will walk
you through what that is because it's a
little hard to understand here is a dot
B at the top hopefully everyone
understands that this is what we mean by
that and again that's just the notation
we use we write it like that to
represent this scalar multiplication and
addition okay we write it like this if
we're gonna be a little fancier cuz
that's the more matrix like notation
this is the more informal notation but
what both of these actually compute and
I'll show you how they do it what both
of these actually compute is the length
of the input vector a the length of the
input vector B multiplied together times
the cosine of the angle between the two
vectors believe it or not that's what
they produce so this single scalar value
produced by this scalar equation
actually has all of this meaning length
of a times length of B times cosine
theta all of that meaning is wrapped up
right in that one operation how how is
it possible what right well it turns out
that you can actually see this pretty
easily if you actually just look at how
the equation breaks down right it's
actually not that difficult to see how
it works right and so what we can do
here is we can see that if we were to
take the law of cosines which is this
equation up here and again I apologize
for not proving the law of cosines to
you but unfortunately that would be a
whole different
ballgame right proving the law of
cosines or where that comes from we
start to get deeper and deeper down the
rabbit hole of math but anyone who's had
high school geometry or trigonometry
sorry will have seen the law of cosines
already I've written it for you at the
top it's a minus B so we take two
vectors we subtract them we take the
length of a minus B squared and we know
that the law of cosines says that that
equals right the length of a squared
plus the length of B squared minus two
times the length of a length of B times
the cosine of theta that's the law of
cosines right a fundamental property of
trigonometry well if we just work these
two equations out so I'm going to move
this stuff over to the other side I'm
gonna divide by the two right or the
negative two in this case look at what I
get I get length of a plus length of B
minus the squared length of a minus B
over two and if I simplify this equation
I get the dot product on the left side
what's on the right the exact thing I
said the dot product produced so just
using the law of cosines from your high
school trigonometry class you can see
exactly what the law of cosine says your
dot product will give you all right so
hopefully you believe me there and I
apologize for not proving the law of
cosines to you but at some point you got
to stop math has axioms and eventually
you're gonna hit a wall somewhere I
chose to stop it there I would encourage
anyone who really wants to drill all the
way down go look up the law of cosines
it's great extra reading to accompany
this lecture all right so why does this
help us with our camera transform well
the reason this helps us with our camera
transform is because if you look at what
this equation does a very special result
will occur if we know one of our axes is
unit length okay so what we know about
world axes is usually we keep them unit
length if we want to rotate something
all the axes stay length one right we
don't scale we don't stretch or shrink
those axes they all say unit one they
started out you know an x axis 1 0 0 y
axis 0 1 0 z axis 0 0 1 right
so we tend to know that our axes have a
length of 1 that means the dot product
with one of the axes whose length is 1
that length term disappears we get just
the length of the the first input right
times the cosine of the angle between
the two vectors and this is very
powerful why is it powerful well think
of what happens when we actually
construct the geometry of the situation
here is our B with length 1 this is an
axis right this is gonna be one of our
world axis let's say then we have our
vector a it's any length it wants to be
it's just an arbitrary point in the
world or an arbitrary vector whatever we
want
well this forms a right triangle here is
a right triangle right here we can
choose to drop the perpendicular down
from this particular point that we've
stretched out to along the vector a we
can drop that perpendicular down and
what we know is that where we would land
once we have a right triangle we can
basically compute anything we want just
using our standard trigonometric
functions right because we know the
ratio of this leg of a triangle to the
hypotenuse is cosine theta we know that
the ratio of this leg of a triangle to
the hypotenuse is sine theta basic high
school trig so if we take the length of
the hypotenuse which is that vector
we're inputting length of a and multiply
it by cosine theta we would get how far
along this axis we would be and that's
exactly what we want it's a measurement
of how long how far along this axis I
would travel to get to the point where I
want to be for this coordinate in this
axis right remember stepping out along
the axes this is the reverse process
it's saying let's say I was already here
how far would I step along B to get to
the be if coordinate right if B was the
x axis the x coordinate
of this input a so that's how we get
back to understanding the camera
transform a camera transform is a
transform that measures points along
axes so we look instead at the rows of
the matrix because those are the
elements that will dot product the input
again let's do the measurement here is
that same point but we're doing the
reverse process now we have three axes
we want to measure right the Z prime to
X prime the Y prime we want to measure
along our camera axes where is this
point what would its coordinates be in
this axis system right mm-hm
and I guess I'd this is one of the
things that you don't remember after
giving a lecture for 10 years I guess I
didn't draw the measurements but point
being
each of these dotted lines measures
right how far I am along this axis and
gives me those results so that's how I
do the analysis of the camera transform
now one of the things I'd like to point
out is if you look at the two structures
that I've just told you you can see that
they're very complementary in the case
where I want to talk about world
positioning I'm in columns in the case
that I want to talk about camera
transforms which is like undoing a world
position I'm in rows these are
complementary these are very
complementary structures right in fact
they're the transpose remember I said
what a transpose was it's taking vectors
that were standing up and lying them
down or vice versa
well if I was to transpose this whole
matrix right if I was to transpose the
whole matrix I would do nothing but lie
down my vertical X into XE lie down my
vertical Y into a horizontal YC right
y W becomes Y C lie down my vertical Z W
into a zc transpose
in matrix just transpose each individual
vector Rose becomes columns columns
become rows right it just flips along
the diagonal so what you can see is
actually if I want to talk about
changing a world placement right a
camera transform being our see a world
places being our W if I want to change
an R W into an RC or an RC into an R W
in very real terms these are inverse
operations my our W my world placement
takes an object and it puts it somewhere
in the world my RC my camera transform
pretends I'm looking at the world from
an object and takes the whole world and
moves it back so that it aligns with the
world axes those are inverse operations
we typically write the inverse of a
matrix as the matrix negative 1 to the
negative 1 power
that's inversion well guess what in this
case it's just a transpose and this is
why if you've ever seen some something
say for an orthogonal matrix its inverse
is its transpose if you've ever seen
that statement this is why because if
your matrices consist of nothing but
unit axis system then just transposing
them produces the inverse operation
there's no mystery to it we just did the
whole thing so what I would like to
point out is that if a matrix in the
past has been more of a black box to you
and you didn't understand how a rotation
matrix works or you didn't understand
why the inverse and the transpose were
the same a kiss rotation matrix now you
do it wasn't so hard right it wasn't so
hard to take the black box of a rotation
matrix and get inside there and see
what's really going on now we know and
there's so many things we can do now
that we know we can construct those
matrixes directly right matrices
directly we can extract pieces from them
trivially we just know oh someone hands
you a camera transform I can just grab
the top row out now I know exactly what
the
axises of the camera in world space
right all of that understanding is now
just all in our brains and accessible to
us at any time in the pipeline we can
just go in there and and know that all
of this stuff is at our fingertips right
not to mention how much easier it is to
debug these matrices once we know what
they mean all right so that's one black
box that we just opened and now there's
no mysteries there there's no mysteries
anymore we get it right and that's a
beautiful thing and a powerful thing so
now let's move on to the second black
box there's only two in this lecture
that was the first one this is the
second one I told you were going to talk
about normal mapping now we're going to
talk about normal mapping all right so
normal Maps like I said there's a huge
amount of information that you really
need to understand if you wanted to
write your entire own normal mapping
system soup-to-nuts right but we're just
going to focus on one part of it now and
that is how do we store them then how do
we use them right so let's pretend we
already have some way of getting these
things how do we store them how do we
use them all right
let's start with lighting because the
only reason we care about normal Maps in
the first place is so that we can light
our objects better we want to capture
the lighting of lots of little bumps
little very sort of micro detail along
our surface we want that lighting
information to be affected by our normal
map that's what we're trying to do just
as that's the entire point of having a
normal map in the first place right and
what you can see here is a simple this
is a simple illustration of how lighting
works in the real world we have some way
that we're looking at a surface right
and I've drawn a little eye here and you
can see that from the surface we have a
vector that points towards the eye this
is where the person is who's viewing it
right it's where the camera is and
furthermore what you can see is I've got
a surface normal that's a vector that
points in the direction of the sort of
tangent to the surface right so the
surface is running along here and I've
got a direction that points out directly
out of that surface at this one point in
order to understand the real lighting
equation at the surface what we must
understand is that all of the light from
everywhere is coming in and parts of it
depending on the exact structure of the
surface the material everything like
this even from behind the surface in the
case of subsurface scattering things
like this all of the lighting is coming
into a point and then certain amount of
it comes out at the point and that's
what you see and that's our real
lighting works in the real world for the
most part if you have a bunch of photons
that come in they hit a particular point
and some of them scatter out your eye
collects the ones that scattered out in
the direction that comes towards your
eye and that's what you see now there's
a little more to it than that your eye
is actually a lens so it collects
actually a region of photons it collects
a a conical region of photons which is
not the same thing as a single line but
I can only cover so much in a lecture
all right so how do we compute this kind
of lighting well a simple Lamberson
material as they're called is one that
assumes that a light that comes in let's
say from a point is radiated equally in
all
directions so when it hits the surface
it's going to bounce back out it's gonna
bounce back out at the viewer the same
no matter where the viewer was right so
it doesn't matter where I'm looking the
surface always bounces the same amount
of light out right but that's not
entirely the whole story just because of
some elements of the of how things hit a
surface I'm going to cover in just one
second but the important part is as I
hit the surface I'm going to bounce
light out at the viewer and I don't have
any particular equations that talk about
how this surface might want to prefer to
bounce light in different directions
limbering materials are not common in
the real world most real-world materials
have very uneven distributions of life
they will bounce light much more
favorably in one direction than another
but again that's a topic for a different
lecture we're not talking about lighting
very much here except as it applies to
normal mapping to kind of give you a
little bit of the flavor so I'm not
going to go too much into that right but
the point is if I were to look at the
material from up here or look at the
material from over here I'm not going to
expect the materials properties itself
to bias towards shining more brightly
one place than another okay that's about
it
now if the light moves the same thing is
true right so no matter where I put the
light I'm still shining out in the same
direction as well however all of that
comes with once with very specific
caveat and that caveat is that the light
when it bounces off a surface more of
the light is able to reflect out in
terms of how it hits the surface based
on the angle this is just a sort of a
how should I put this this is a aspect
simply of the differential geometry of
the situation so according to Lambert's
cosine law which is from 1760 so not
exactly a recent development in the
field of computer graphics as you might
imagine it simply says that if I imagine
a patch of the surface no matter how big
I choose to make it it can be
infinitesimally small or just an
arbitrary size what you can see is the
shaft
a light that would fall on that surface
right from a light source if the light
source was the same size over here right
or over here I'm going to get a
different size of the shaft of light
depending on the angle as it rotates
down that same thing that I showed you
back for when we were talking about how
to measure the edge of a triangle that
same thing is true right the right
triangle that I form right here is gonna
say that this right here by the law of
cosines is only going to be proportional
to the cosine of theta as wide as it
would be if it was straight on okay and
you can see I've kind of like created
that that version of the diagram here
and you can do it a couple of different
ways right I put the triangle here you
could put it off to the side however you
want to put it right so anyway we get
back to the exact same thing that I
showed before right this thing that we
learn sort of as we went in and examined
the dot product this is actually already
a piece of information you would
encounter when you just start doing your
lighting right so again one of the
things that I would emphasize is that
understanding one black box typically
applies to another black box because all
of this stuff is interrelated and you
see the same things coming up over and
over and over again right okay so if we
take a look at what's happening in this
equation we get the exact same thing
that we got before and that is
specifically we want to know in this
case we want to take the cosine of the
angle between the two vectors right
which is this angle right here we want
to take the the angle between the two
vectors and we want to find what their
actual measure is going to be right and
in order to do this I'll be honest I
don't like the way I've drawn this here
at all I'm not sure why I drew it that
way maybe I wasn't thinking correctly
when I actually drew it but let's
pretend we just ignore this diagram here
ignore this diagram pretend it doesn't
exist maybe I'll
to fix this diagram for further video
but what we want to do is we want to
compute based on the law of base based
on again that Lambert's cosine law we
want to compute how much light should be
leaving the surface in a particular
direction
that direction is based on the normal
write times the based on the normal
direction and the light direction if we
take those two directions and
dot-product them together right we will
get that equation that we talked about
when we were opening our first black box
length of the first times length of the
second times the cosine of the angle
between them now since we know that we
could for free if we wanted to or maybe
not free but we know we could condition
these things properly so that the length
of our normal vector and the length of
our light vector we could make those be
normal if we wanted to we could
normalize them right certainly if that's
the case we could use the dot product to
trivially compute the cosine of the
angle between them that's exactly what
we need to compute Lambert's cosine law
which is a fundamental law of all light
reflection and we're going to need it to
produce our lighting equation right so
if we take a look at going back to the
1990s right now we're going way back in
history here we're going back almost 30
years right if we go back to how
Hardware shading worked in the late
1990s it looked like this right there
was a vertex pipeline and that vertex
pipeline could be parallelized so we
maybe had multiple vertex pipelines it's
hard to say depending on the
circumstance but basically what you did
is you issued a bunch of data to the
vertex pipeline and the vertex pipeline
would transform your vertices for you
right some hardware could do this some
couldn't sometimes we've still done on
the cpu how does that came a bunch of
triangles and those went to rasterizer
engines and how many of these again were
dependent on the card but those would
rasterize the triangles into individual
little pieces right and then each of
those pieces will get handled by a pixel
pipeline which would figure out what
color they should be and that would
write them to the frame buffer this is
how
now if you looked at where this was
divided most of the time in the mid
nineties to the late 90s the CPU
typically did this part and the GPU
typically did this part this was because
floating point math being very expensive
just hadn't really gotten miniaturized
yet to the point where it could be done
in sufficient quantities on the on the
GPUs by the GPU manufacturers it hadn't
quite gotten to that stage yet so they
still were only doing the pixel pipeline
it was usually done with fixed iterators
and stuff like this so the floating
point math just wasn't happening yet and
the vertex of pipeline requires floating
point math can't really be turned into
fixed point very effectively all right
so what this looked like was we
specified triangles as a series of
vertices right and here they are here's
an example those would get passed to a
rasterizer which produces a set of
fragment values right which is places
where on the pixel grid we need to
process and the pixel pipeline would go
ahead and figure out what to do with
them right so in here we've got a
smaller number of things right 0 1 &amp; 2
and that changes into a larger number of
fragments 0 1 2 3 4 5 whatever right
okay so for a typical goro shaded
pipeline what's Karoshi shading you may
not even know what it is anymore it used
to be a very common terms not so
counting or cos nobody does it
goro shading was one where basically if
you take a look at this there was just a
color at each of these points right so
when you specify these vertices you
could specify a color and then when you
would interpolate the points it would
just figure out what the color of each
of these was by figuring out where it
was sort of barycentric ly in this
triangle and it would be all sort of do
it like an average weighted average of
how close it was to each of these points
right very simple interpolation of to
figure out what the color was okay
so for agarose shaded pipeline again
we've got this information here telling
us how to get to a particular point like
I showed you with the initial transform
right we've sort of got this idea that
if we had for example coordinates of our
triangle and we were using those
coordinate
to produce some kind of a world space
movement right the same thing might be
true of the colors inside a triangle so
we might have coefficients that are Bary
centric coefficients meaning their
relative to the triangle we might add
the same exact thing again this
structure where I move along each one
the rasterizer might be doing this to
compute the colors that it would then
send to the pixel pipeline okay
so what you can sort of see here is that
amusingly enough you actually would end
up getting into a situation where you'd
use the exact same things you saw when
we first opened our black box just our
very simple black box of how matrix
transform for rotation works both of the
things that we talked about there that
construction of moving along a series of
axes and the construction of dot prior
to two things together those actually
form the basis of how we would start to
do agarose shading pipeline how we would
move from agarose shaded pipeline where
we're just interpolating colors into
normal mapping first what we would do at
the vertex stage is pass down some
information about the normal of the
surface times the light right in a
simple crochet 2 pi plane then the
rasterizer uses the standard movement
along the barycentric axes to produce
interpolated colors and then we output a
pixel this is a non normal mapped
pipeline right so if you imagine I want
to produce these colors over here that
are the lighting values of my surface
all I have is inputs here what I would
do in a very simple sense is just have
normals at my vertices I would do the
dot product for each of those normals
the interpolation would take place in
the rasterizer and the output the pixel
output would just be the interpolated
color I mean that's it right so that's a
very simple it doesn't really do any
normal mapping right but it does go
ahead and produce a lit surface that
just only lights as simple interpolation
between the vertices so the more dense
your mesh the more this would capture
the lighting of the surface but the
sparse or the mesh the less information
there would be because
the less times we would be doing those
dot products between the normal and the
lighting right now there's an obvious
problem with the guro shading pipeline
and what you would see immediately if
you start to look into this further is
that if all we were doing right is
interpolating the multiplication between
these two then you get some pretty nasty
results here right if all we do is
interpolate the the result of n times L
then if in the middle right if in this
case for example we have a situation
where the light starts on this side and
ends on this side so we have L 1 is out
here in l0 is out here so maybe we're
taking two vertices of our triangle and
one side of it has one type you know the
light relative to one vertex is pointing
this direction but then this vertex is
on the other side of the light source so
it's over here the interpolation between
them is going to pass through a place
where it should have pointed directly at
the light we're never going to capture
that because the dot product of this and
the dot part of this are basically going
to be the same potentially and it's not
going to be able to capture that
difference right so we get into another
problem here excuse me but we're going
to talk about that a little bit later
right
I don't again not sure exactly why I
chose to do this draw this here because
it's not exactly what we mean but you
know a ten years ten years you'll forget
some things about electro spit that way
so let's ignore that for now and I'll
come back to in a second so the big
thing that happened with normal mapping
and the thing to remember is that what
we were able to start doing with normal
mapping and the reason that it was going
to become such a particularly
interesting thing is that once the
hardware was able to move this equation
again this is the normal dot product
with the light which is just that thing
that tells us what lamber shion's cosine
was right numbers cosine law once that
didn't happen hat have to happen at the
vertex stage anymore things started to
get interesting and
thing that made this possible was an
innovation in hardware and the
innovations probably the wrong term it's
just more of getting more power because
you know you want to do this in hardware
the question is just how right how do
you make the circuits for it well what
they did is they introduced something in
hardware called dot three and what dot
three was as a blending mode which did
the dot product per pixel so at every
pixel on the screen or per fragment if
you'd rather think of it that way
fragments and pixels were basically the
same at that point but per per fragment
what it could do is it could do this dot
product at the fragment stage what that
meant was that now you no longer had to
just take your lighting equations and
compute them at the vertices you can
actually compute sort of part of the
lighting equation down here per pixel
and that meant at every pixel you could
track that light source you didn't have
to interpolate the results of the
lighting you could interpolate the
lighting itself and this was huge the
reason this was huge is because now at a
bare minimum you could do functioning
goro shading is one that just
interpolates the result of the lighting
across the triangle Phong shading is one
that at least captures the fact that a
high light could occur inside a triangle
right and that's that thing I was trying
to say before where if you have this and
the dot product is the same on either
side the dot products going to change
dramatically right here but if those are
your two vertices and all you have is
those two points to interpolate between
you're never gonna catch that that high
light but now you could if you wanted to
right because instead what I could do is
tell the rasterizer to interpolate both
the normal and the light and then the
pixel shading pipeline will dot-product
them together okay all right so now what
we can do is we can do Lambert's cosine
law every pixel and this allows some
tremendous freedom right in terms of
computing our lighting so now what we
can do instead of accidentally producing
the exact same cosine the entire way
across because we're just interplaying
this one value that's already been here
right what we can do is start to look at
it as actually producing
new cosine value right that will give us
more light reflected when we actually
hit that middle point even if it's
inside a triangle and this is crucial
okay so a phone shading pipeline doesn't
actually require any normal Maps it just
requires you letting the rasterizer
interpolate the normal and the light
source like so again this is being
interpolated in the barycentric fashion
which we didn't really cover too much
deal in this lecture but it's exactly
the same thing that I showed you
originally when we were talking about
that sort of combination of axes to
produce a point we're just doing that
and it allows us to interpolate values
over a triangle so that we know what the
values of that are at any point in the
triangle alright so the last piece of
the equation that we're missing is this
term down here which is the
normalization term the reason we have a
normalization term is because if you
take a look at how these work
these don't give us normals back
necessarily okay
and that's a problem because we know
that we said we wanted the the light
source and the normal to be unit length
vectors so that our cosine so that we
could use the dot product compute the
cosine the angle between them if they're
not unit length and that equation breaks
down because remember it's length of a
length of B cosine theta if we need
length of a and length of B to be 1 so
that we just get cosine theta out well
we don't really have the option of doing
that anymore so the problem is we need
an extra term in here we need a term
that corrects our dot product to produce
a more normalized result and so what we
can do here in the case of a pixel
shader is what we can do is we can
actually normalize the light source
right in the pixel shader if we want to
and that that solves that problem for us
but what do we do about the normal to
the surface well we could normalize that
as well
so if we wanted to do a functioning
pipeline we could choose to normalize
both of them right we can normalize the
normal and normalize the light source
and that would be fine but if we want to
move to a normal map pipeline
well we don't have to worry about that
anymore why because the normal is gonna
come from a texture anyway right so this
is where we finally get the normal
mapping pipeline that we sort of
stumbled upon once dot three texture
mapping was available and that is that
if we interpolate with a light Direction
across a triangle then we can also just
read the normal from a texture because
since we can read things from textures
we might as well read the normal out
that would allow us to vary the normal
across the surface as if it had a lot
more details than the mesh would imply
so that's what this looks like we have a
vertex at the vertex we specify where
the light is that gets interpolate
across our triangles which are built up
of vertices we normalize it at every
pixel because you know it's gonna become
non normal as it interpolates but then
we just read the texture to find out
what our normal is all right so that's
really all we need to know in terms of
how shading works so hopefully that
gives you a little bit of background
about how a normal map actually gets
applied at the shading stage we take the
normals out of textures we specify the
lights at vertices and then we dot
product those two things together the
light getting interpolated across the
pixels to produce Lambert's cosine law
now obviously if you wanted to do better
lighting you could use that information
to produce more than just Lambert's
cosine law you could look up into tables
you could use cube maps you can do all
sorts of things to produce fancier
lighting that has more real surface
properties but again that part doesn't
really matter I'm just showing the
simplest possible normal mapping
pipeline but the lighting equation can
be extended in in all sorts of ways so
how do we encode normal maps right how
are we going to encode these normal maps
well as you might imagine the simplest
way to think about this it's just to
think about in the world right there is
a triangle that I'm trying to encode and
it presumably has a lot more information
along its surface that I'm actually
gonna coat the vertices if I was to only
record
at each of these vertices then inside
here any perturbation of the surface is
no longer recorded as flat so the goal
of the normal map is to say let's take a
texture map and let's place this
triangle somewhere in the texture map
however we want to map it again that's a
topic for a whole nother black box but
let's place it somewhere and then inside
there let's use all of the texels all of
the information in this texture to
encode what the normal is so what we
want to encode here is do we want to
encode that at a certain UV in this
texture map we have a certain normal
that corresponds to some point on our
mesh okay
so again looking back here at what we've
got
we're just interpolating the normal in a
way that's going to read it from a
texture and they're going to be here's
the Texel zero texture one it's so so
forth it's going to read from those
points in the texture map and
interpolate between those so what we
will pass down is just UV coordinates
that say we're in the texture to look
those will get interpolated here and
pulled out as a Texel which represents
our normal okay so now let's put this
all together imagine we have a surface
here's like one I'm going to look at
just a slice of it here's one vertex and
here is the direction of the light
source you know if we imagine the vertex
is here here's the direction of the
light source if we imagine the vertex is
here right and of course we're going to
shade this whole surface so along here
the light is just gonna point up towards
the light the whole way right as we
interpolate between these two vectors
what you can see here if you Madame
what's going on here is that the input
to our vertex again is very simple it's
just the light in world space - wherever
the point is right so you can see here
p0 is at this location if I want to know
what the lighting vector is I should
pass well it's very simple it's just
wherever the light is - wherever the
point is so our input to the vertex
stage is very straightforward
the rasterizer stage we know we're
passing a texture
that's very straightforward we know it's
gonna trip late the lights we passed
Sears fromthe do anything else and the
pixel stage is rote
it's just that dot product right and
then we have to normalize the light so
it's very simple to pass the light
direction in okay and you can see here
if I were to rotate the surface okay
it's pretty straightforward what happens
to all of my values if I was to change
the orientation of my surface I could
multiply each point by a rotation matrix
just like we showed beginning I could
multiply the normal by that rotation and
I would rotate everything in the surface
okay so producing new lighting points is
very straightforward but let's look at
this if we have a texture map okay that
encodes our normals what are we gonna do
here because this vector is a problem
for us
we can't go rotate every value in the
texture map right because it's a
statically stored texture map that's
just sitting on the GPU we made it and
that's on there we don't want to run
through every frame and rotate each of
those normals to properly point in the
direction they're pointing now that the
object has rotated so when we want to
move an object around we got a problem
right however we can solve this problem
really easily if we know we can't change
the texture what if we just changed the
light to pretend that the light is the
thing that moved and not the texture
right because remember as Einstein would
tell us I don't know if you would really
tell us this but everything's relative
instead of rotating my object couldn't I
just rotate the light in the opposite
way for example if I was to look at this
diagram and say well I'm not gonna
rotate this object like this instead I'm
just gonna rotate the light over here
right and leave this the same
I could do that couldn't I right I could
do that so if we look at what happens
instead of trying to bend the normal or
something like this to accommodate the
direction the light should be going
instead what I can do is I can just
imagine that if my normal has to still
point in the same direction it used to
point well let's just move the whole
world so that the light is just where it
should be and that's exactly what I can
do if we take our equation over here
right and we say I want to do the
inverse operation on the light location
where the light would be if I had
rotated my point by this matrix right so
I'm applying this rotation if we just
work the math out we get our inverse
times the light - just the original
input point and that's because our
inverse and itself will cancel right the
inverse transform times the transform is
just going to be nothing and I've
already determined because thanks to
opening that black box at the beginning
we know the inverse of just a rotation
matrix is its transpose we know that if
I just transpose this matrix times the
light I will get the operation I'm
talking about right so if I just perform
this operation first and then subtract
the point away I will get the equation
in that original space right in that
sort of transform space even though I'm
no longer multiplying pH times that so
now I just have a way of producing this
information my LH becomes my newly
oriented light source and I just
subtract my pH from that so again this
is a really interesting thing if you
think about it by understanding all the
stuff we understand about matrices now
we can trivially solve this actually
relatively problematic situation we
would have encountered by death going eh
I know I don't have to always transfer
my objects I could just inverse
transform the light and that's the same
as transforming my object off we go and
it's trivial to compute that it's just a
transpose I don't have to do
computation is just flipping some
numbers around right so again we get
back to understanding these matrices
leads to all sorts of other
understanding that we can apply and this
is where we get to understanding object
space normal mapping which is what I've
just described it's normal mapping where
you take a light source you map it into
the space of an object and then you read
out of a normal map the direction the
normals are going and you multiply them
together all right so that's a pretty
easy way to understand basically
everything that's involved in object
space normal mapping now let's go to
something a little bit more complicated
if we have deformable surfaces right
which are characters stuff like this
which you might want to use normal
mapping on a lobby space normal mapping
if you just have a say crate flying
around in the world well you're done
right obviously a snore mapping takes
care of it transform the light into the
space of the object by using the inverse
of the objects transform encode the
normals in the normal map as just
normals in world space all right I
should say object space in this case
right whatever the objects rest
orientation is execute the pipeline as
written and you're done
dot three takes care of the rest however
let's suppose we have a character if
services are deforming what do we do now
now we've got problems because
deformable surfaces cannot include
normals and have the light bend to meet
them anymore because the whole surface
itself is deforming which means that any
individual piece of the surface now has
a different opinion of where the light
was if the normals can't bend right this
seems to be a pretty tricky problem
right so if I imagine a deformable
surface let's say you know a part of a
character's arms the elbow is bending
well if it's highly bent then we get a
surface like this and this is how the
normals are supposed to read if it's not
bent much at all that same surface may
have normals that look more like this
this becomes a problem for us even
though these are the same normals
encoded in the texture map potentially
we need to know that their orientation
and world space Bend you know is having
the
then applied to it so what are we gonna
do right how are we gonna solve this
problem and you can see here if I've
shown you the normals at the vertices
here the normals at the vertices change
right as we Bend all right so the key
here is to go how do we find a way to
encode the normal maps in such a way
that we could still use them even if the
surface is bending and it seems a little
bit like a intractable problem at first
but if you dig a little bit deeper you
realize actually we can probably do the
same thing we did for objects that don't
deform just by treating the transforms
more locally instead of having an object
space transformed what if we just
thought about transforms that existed at
the vertices because that's what's
deforming all right so how do i encode
this normal how do i code that normal
right there well what if I had a frame
of reference at each vertex and I
encoded the normal relative to the
interpolated frame of reference that's
in between those two vertices right so I
have a frame of reference at p0 I have a
frame of reference of p1 and I know by
interpolating those two frames of
reference a1 favourite reference
specifically for that very point on the
object and I encode the normal just like
I use the object space just the just a
resting object's frame of reference to
encode the normal in the object space
sense I'm gonna use this specific
interpolated frame of reference to
encode the normal here that's what I
write into the texture I write into the
texture whatever the values of the
normal would be in this interpolated
frame of reference right well if I did
that then what I could do is say all
right at every vertex I'll transform the
light into the vertices frames of
reference and then I will know where the
light is in an interpolated frame of
reference so that the normal can still
be in its own space on
and it can know where the light would be
relative to its frame of reference right
so the light here LF is where the light
is in this frame of reference
interpolated so the normal would not
have to bend it's a little bit
mind-boggling right and I've hand waved
everything how do we build vertex frames
of reference right how do you even know
what that means well the answer is we
have to develop something that is a
rigorous way of defining at any given
point on our mesh some kind of a space
we can map things into that will
interpolate properly across the surface
of the object and that's exactly what we
did back in the days when normal mapping
had to be sort of created what we did is
create something called a tangent space
and what a tangent space is is it's a
full three dimensional axis system
interpolated over the whole object that
encodes the tangents to the surface the
normal and a full frame of reference
around the normal now we know one part
of it we're going into it pretty
well-equipped on one axis and that axis
is the z-axis right we know the normal
is pointing in a particular direction
which we've been told every vertex has a
normal when the mesh was made we know
that one
so the question are is what are the
other two axes so if we look at what we
have to do we know what we have to do is
take the light in world space we
subtract the point that we're given
whichever point it is right
that'll give us that vector and then we
need to map that into a local tangent
space and to map it into a local tangent
space we need some kind of a transform
and we'll use the inverse
transform right of whatever this vertex
space is we know one component of as a
normal we don't know what the other two
components are all right so what we are
looking for if we were to take a diagram
is that at a particular vertex of our
mesh we want to produce a vector a and a
vector B such that they form a nice
little orthogonal well it's not really
necessarily orthogonal shouldn't quite
say that yet but a nice little tangent
space basis here that we can use for
mapping our light source in so that when
we want to work with our normals will
always be in the space the normals were
encoded even if our surface is deforming
how're we gonna do right how're we gonna
start from this and get there well it
turns out we have more information than
we think we don't just have the normals
we know that the normal map itself has
to be applied to this mesh and in order
for the normal map to be applied to the
mesh we also know that the U coordinate
and the V coordinate of the texture map
has to be applied at all the vertices so
we actually know what the frame of
reference is in the texture right
because we know the U and V coordinates
so we have another piece of information
we can use to form a basis that aligns
with the way that the surface has been
mapped by the artists textured over it
right so what we can use is we can use
the direction that those u coordinates
and video coordinates are going in order
to produce a tangent space for our mesh
now you see I've notated it here with
something that's going to be very
unfamiliar with you and bit outside the
scope of this lecture not to cover the
general version of it and that is the
gradient right this is the gradient
operator what the gradient operator says
is it says the direction of change
basically right the direction that
you're going and there's a lot of ways
that you can use this
very often it's a very very important
operation to understand we're only going
to focus on one particular application
of it in this lecture and again it would
make for great additional reading if you
want to go find out more about it but
for right now we're going to talk about
one aspect of it and the aspect of it
that we're going to talk about is very
specifically figuring out what direction
u and V go so that we can align our
coordinate frame with how the texture
moves across the surface which will
produce a nice solid basis for
interpolating our normal map okay so
even without knowing what this operator
is and let's just pretend we don't even
know there is such an operator let's
pretend we don't even know enough math
to know that a gradient is a thing we
have no idea we don't know what that is
and we don't care we just know what we
want it to mean what we want it to mean
is that I say grad U or whatever I'm
saying here this symbol U means the
direction in which U is changing right
or grad V is the direction in which V is
changing right more specifically let's
say I imagined I'm standing on the
surface of my mesh and I'm going to
increase just the V value I'm not going
to touch you at all what direction do I
walk along that to keep you constant but
V changing or vice versa I'm going to
change you right where do I move across
the surface to change you and only you
and V stays the same so you don't need
to know what a gradient isn't you don't
need to care actually right in order to
look at this particular circumstance
here all you need to know is that I'm
gonna define that operator that way
let's not even use the term gradient
we'll just say we're gonna use this
operation here to mean I want the place
where only this thing
changes and the other thing doesn't
change okay so if I take a look at this
equation what I have written out is a
statement of exactly what I just said
for you I am going to say that a some
scalar times the first UV right whatever
it is in the in imagining 0 1 0 I should
define these terms a little more
carefully here
so because I drew the diagram we haven't
so much about it I have p0 right and
then I have p1 out here and p2 out here
right I have this if I take the vector
from P to P 2 or from P to P 1 if I take
those vectors so I would subtract p2
from P 1 for this vector I subtract P 1
from P for this vector I would get a
change in UV if I subtracted the you
coordinates I would get a change in X Y
Z if I track to the x coordinates right
so if I subtract the UV value at p2 from
the UV value at p1 I get the change in U
as I go from from p0 to p1 the same is
true of 2 so I have two basis vectors if
you will going from 0 to 1 and 0 to 2
and I can look at the change in UV
coordinate and I can make a vector so
this is in UV space right it's on the
texture map you can think of it that way
so if I write this equation some scalar
times u the UV change from 0 to 1 plus
some scalar times the change in in you
from 0 to 2 change in UV from 0 to that
left hand side represents an arbitrary
combination of these two vectors right
so I can take an arbitrary combination
any scalar I want any scalar I want of
these two Delta's if you will and I can
say I want that arbitrary combination
to come out to be equal to a unit change
in you and no change in V that's exactly
the thing I said I wanted the direction
in which U is changing and where V does
not change at all okay now why do I want
that what does that do for me
well once I know the a and B that
produce this result I can use the same a
and B to produce a combination of the X
Y Z Delta's to get me my gradient new
direction right because the combination
of these two vectors that produces a
unit walk in you I can just look at the
XYZ and go that's the direction in world
space where that would occur as well so
now I'm left with a simple task of
solving what is a two-dimensional
equation two unknowns two equations
here's the scalar
right all I'm doing is multiplying au 0
plus B use au 0 1 plus B u 0 2 equals 1
AV 0 1 plus b v 0 2 equals 0 right here
it is
I have two equations in two unknowns
that's high school algebra everyone can
do it
here it goes right there is my solution
for a solving for a plugging back into
the other equation solving for B here's
my B plug back in to solve for a and
here we go I won't belabor the steps
because again this is high school
algebra everyone's had to do this at
some point if they ever went to high
school right that's it so now I know
just from high school algebra I know
that these two equations are how I
produce the a and B values that would
tell me gradient you dumb deal I can
repeat that process for V right same
exact thing now I just have a C and a D
and instead of solving for ones
I solve for zero one off we go look
familiar it should it's exactly the same
right the only difference is the terms
are swapped because if you start with
zero one you get different multiply
through as one zero but it's exactly the
same process and produces nearly exactly
the same results right so now all we
need to do is apply these right
we just need to apply these through and
as we go I don't know why I wanted to
call that out specifically I think I
just wanted to say that you'll note this
is on the denominator of all of them
right oh well you know what I may have
mentioned in the original lecture that
that was the determinant of 2x2 matrix
but you know what that's too much we've
already covered too much math I'll
simply say if you want to read about
determinants this might be a motivation
for you to do so again additional
reading related to this particular topic
alright so that's how we could produce a
tangent space very easily by doing those
twos equations we'll get a U and a V
which we combine with our n to give us
an idea of how the surface is changing
in that area that will be stable as long
as the UV map is stable which we know it
has to be because the artist had to make
a continuous UV map along those
triangles in order to not have seams in
the texture anyway right so here's I
believe this again was just the
determinant part this is the term of the
matrix so again I believe that for
additional reading so with this we can
build our tangent frame here is what it
would look like right Delta u Delta V
I'm sorry gradient u gradient V and then
the N right the normal that we already
had now oftentimes this space is
normalized I'm sorry orthogonalize so
these things will not all necessarily be
orthogonal to each other they won't
produce a standard unit frame where
everything's at right angles to each
other so sometimes people normalize
these sometimes they don't there's
reasons to and not to again not really
relevant to the electric
this point but point being this is where
you start and you can choose to
normalize the sir choose not to know
it's depending on what you're trying to
write but here's our tangent frame we've
got it again simple math high school
algebra we can do it alright so now we
know how to encode we produce those
tangent frames at each vertex we
interpolate the tangent frame to the
point we're trying to encode right again
just by doing that standard barycentre
composite and then we map the normal
into that tangent frame and store it in
the normal map very very straightforward
and so now we have to come back here and
look at what we're doing this was our
pixel pipeline right and the only change
we have to make because remember this
has to stay the same because the
hardware can't do anything else this is
all it could do at that time we didn't
have programmable pixel shaders really
we just had I mean there was they were
slightly par they're more like crossbar
so you could sort of just route things a
little bit so this is all we could
really do there wasn't much we could do
and by the way even this we couldn't
really do you had to look it up in a
cube map that's a whole another story
but basically this is all we can do in
the picture study we weren't
programmable shaders like they are today
where they have lots of flexibility so
the only thing we can really modify us
out here good thing we can write so all
we have to do is we just take that light
and instead of doing the inverse
transform by a stationary object
transform that we were ewing before now
we just do the tangent frame that's the
only modification we have to do now it
costs more on this side why because we
have to produce those interpolated
tangent frames interpolated in that
along the triangle because again we're
we're not really gonna interpolate the
tangent frames along the triangle we're
gonna interpolate the transformed light
but as we deform our surfaces we have to
deform our tangent spaces with them so
there was more work to be done here
during deformation but other than that
this was all we had to do right so
that's tangent space normal mapping
soup-to-nuts here's what one looks like
this is a tangent space normal map of
the head that I showed at the beginning
the half head right and what you can see
is when you encode a normal map in here
you get kind of exactly what you would
expect
all of the information that is that you
see as lighting in here is encoded as
sort of three-dimensional offsets and
the convention when encoding a normal
map is that you encode a normal map as X
Y Z RGB right the X goes into the x
coordinates into the are the Y goes into
the G the Z goes into the B now as we
got further along and shaders got more
able to do more work
it became unnecessary to store all three
because you could actually just store -
and generate the third because since
it's a normal once you get to values you
can generate the third right it's pretty
cheap to do that but you know originally
we didn't have the option so you
actually destroy all three and so if you
take a look at what this looks like you
can see it's overwhelmingly blue because
most of the time the surface doesn't
deviate much from just the normal normal
direction it's a slight deviation you
can see red where it starts to point in
in some direction XY z-- right you can
see green in one where it starts to
deviate Y wise right so you can sort of
read as you can see it's a very logical
thing as it was placed on the surface
okay so that's how normal Maps how it
was determined at the time but again
nobody knew how to do any of this stuff
people had to work out every last little
detail right everything from how you
figure out what tangent spaces are to
even that you wanted to do that to how
you did the dot three how I mean the
hardware people had to figure out the
dot three was even useful right and put
it in the hardware I need to figure how
you were gonna use it and all these
sorts of things right
all of this was unknown and now today
it's all known okay so what I want to
really emphasize here if you take a look
at all that stuff you can see how every
little single black box every little
piece that you choose to look into
repeats itself and affects everything
right a very simple sort of analysis of
very simple matrix math at the beginning
it repeated again in
and again and again and again inside
that normal mapping stuff and even if
you didn't understand anything that I
just said hopefully you could see that
repetition and those echoes all
throughout there right because pushing
forward on one thing and learning how
that thing works there is almost never a
time in game engine development where
everything that you learn and all of
those aspects that come together to
teach you how something worked don't
come back again and again and again and
if you've done enough of these you will
have a toolbox capable of pushing beyond
where we even are today right and that's
exactly what happened back in those days
there was no normal mapping people who
understood how these things worked and
pushed forward and did experiments and
apply the knowledge they'd learned by
digging into things people had already
figured out created a whole new
technology which today we take for
granted that is not the last time that
will happen it will happen many many
many more times before game development
is really understood we are probably
still at the infancy of what a game
engine can do and the game engines that
you can license today or use are a far
cry from taking advantage of all of what
the knowledge of math and the world and
physics and everything have to offer us
but we just don't know what it is
because we haven't pushed out there yet
not to mention a bunch of the new fields
deep reinforcement learning these sorts
of things coming to fruition now in
terms of AI or other stuff what did
those have in them go take a look tons
of matrices dot products threshold
ingredients all of these things they
come up everywhere
so what I really want you to take away
from this lecture is not any of the
specifics I don't care if you know
anything about matrices or normal
mapping after having heard that what I
care about is you understanding how all
of this is interrelated and how always
no matter where you are game development
is so early right now that there are so
many black boxes out there to open ones
we don't even know exist yet that you
could find and when you open one you see
a ton more right and we don't understand
any of these yet and when you open one
of those you get a ton more and we don't
know how to do any of these right yet
and when you open one of those you'll
get even more and every single one of
those will teach you something and
furthermore will lead to questions about
whether we even know how to do that
right yet or could it be better could it
be faster
could it be higher quality right could
there be more to do there that would
lead to more features more flexibility
things we didn't even know we could do
yet or that we didn't know we could do
with this right and the answer is almost
always the turn is so this is really to
a large extent probably that is what
game development looks like right now
and if the general attitude
unfortunately goes from the claim that
it was the 1990s which is every single
game developer was pretty highly skilled
in black box stuff if it goes to
something where game floors don't do
that anymore and you just take what you
are given and assume that's the end of
the universe that can be explored this
is where we'll end up and I don't really
think that's a good place to end up I
think we've only scratched the surface
in what games can do on any front
whether it's things like visual quality
that we've pushed pretty far
there's plenty further we can go but
more importantly on things like
artificial intelligence right how
stories work in games how a game network
does networking all of these things are
incredibly hard technical problems that
we've only scratched the surface of and
I'd rather see us keep pushing forwards
I want to see it look like this before
I'm dead and I want to feel like when I
die people are still looking to make it
look like that and that someday way in
the future we'll get all the way out
there right because black boxes are just
things that are waiting to be
improvements right and so anytime you
look at something and say I just use
this and I don't know how it works
it's kind of like accepting a limitation
that we shouldn't accept and accepting a
small defeat instead of pushing for a
victory so that's what I wanted to get
across with this lecture and I hope that
I've done a little bit of sort of
opening of one of these or two of these
in this case black boxes for you so you
can kind of see how that goes it only
gets better from there those are simple
black boxes and pushing through a really
hard black box is probably one of the
greatest feelings you can have in
development where you open something up
and you really figure out how it works
and you push the tech forwards there's
really nothing else like it so if you're
the kind of person who thinks that sort
of thing would be exciting or
interesting and you like knowing how
things work you don't like accepting
just use something someone else made or
just this is how it goes you don't need
to look into it if you don't like
accepting those answers you're the kind
of person who this sort of programming
is for and I highly recommend you look
into it there will always be a job for
you if you're good at this sort of thing
because so few people have the fortitude
to do it and spend the time to get good
at it so that's my lecture how to open a
black box I hope you enjoyed it and if
you're interested in this sort of thing
please look into being a serious game
engine
grammar it's a great place to encounter
a lot of really challenging problems and
with that I will take some questions