okay we are back with the Q&amp;A please
remember to put at sameera tori or when
you when you do a when you ask a
question so I can quickly see that
someone has asked a question and isn't
talking to someone else on the screen
and I will start taking questions now
let's see a brain cruiser says do a
segmentation error I am going to get to
those I think in the mainstream I'd
rather save memory out-of-bounds writes
for the mainstream but we will
definitely deal with that and memory
protection chronolog in asks me oh you
know what I should probably turn off the
infinite KC's I know you love seeing the
infinite cases but you know really do we
need infinite cases infant cases sounds
like a bad thing to have in the world
will you explain how negative numbers
are encoded yes well I will try to if we
have time tomorrow I would try to
two's-complement
is how they're encoded I don't know that
I don't know that I want spent too much
time because it's not that important for
people to know but I will kind of
mention it in passing at least
chronodragon what would be the
difference if you C++ classes instead of
structs well really nothing at first if
you just declare something as a class
instead of a struct it doesn't actually
lay it out any different in memory but
it can start to be different once you
start to have things like virtual
functions in there because once you have
things like virtual functions then the
class actually has to have a thing in it
potentially that lets it know what kind
of of which class you actually
instantiated so there's a thing called a
V table pointer that gets shoved in
there so basically the only thing that
happens with C++ classes that doesn't
happen with structs is the compiler
starts inserting crap that you can't
control it's one of the reasons I hate
C++ actually is because the things they
added all do stuff in a way that you
can't control like I actually don't mind
the concept of virtual functions it's
really the implementation of virtual
functions that I think is crappy so if
C++ had instead been about building
features that allow me to control how I
wanted to do virtual dispatch I'd
probably love it and I think that's
hopefully sort of what Jon blows doing a
little bit with his languages is going
more like giving you the control to do
those things and that would be better so
you know yeah does the order of variable
equations affect their memory packing
yes basically instructs it always does
so in a struct if you declare things in
a particular order they have to go in
that order
they could be spaced however the
compiler wants what they have to go in
that order on the stack you know I'm not
sure how much leeway the compiler gets
on the stack I think like local
variables to a function like when you
declare things on the stack I don't know
the compiler may be allowed to or to
rearrange those I don't I don't know if
it's under any particular obligation to
keep the ordering that you have it might
be but I'd have to read the spec to know
for sure so I'm not sure show a
segmentation error I will in the
mainstream
we will I'll show one whether we like it
or not I'll make a mistake in the
mainstream that causes us to seg fault
at some point I guarantee it why are
there 18 columns in the memory window
the reason that there are eighteen
columns is because that's how big it
happened to be I'm pretty sure that
actually if I just ran this code if I
were to resize this this thing that
would just give me more yeah it just
gives me more columns and you can do
things in the memory window like you can
change it so that it's it's spaced by by
eight byte things instead like these are
64 bits at a time right and so I just
had it on the the lowest kind which was
one byte per so that we could see each
individual byte of memory but you can
hoist it up and see bigger things at
once if you want to and this over here
also shows you what the ASCII values are
of things and so on and you can change
that here like ANSI text Unicode text so
okay so it is ANSI I always say ASCII
because that's the encoding I think of
but it's actually the ANSI standard
which is ASCII and then revised or
whatever so yeah that's the text of the
slide you can change it to Unicode if
you want etcetera etc let's see this was
asking engine chapter for the stream why
you use chair and short if they get pad
to 32 bits like in anyway so the reason
for that the reason that they are 32 bit
ins is I'm sorry the reason that you
might declare smell has a short instead
of an int is because it's kind of trying
to think of how to explain this
so you will pack things sometimes and
you will not know the size of things
other times so typically what you're
doing when you use care short and int is
you're programming the logic of what you
wanted and you're living the compiler
more flexibility to do fancier stuff so
for example let's say I was going to use
things and I knew that none of them are
going to be bigger than 16 bits then
what I will do is I'll define them as
short so the compiler knows I don't care
about anything else so that if on a
particular target platform it could pack
them efficiently or do something more
efficiently it will now there's a lot of
places that this could come in handy
right like you could imagine doing like
wide sim D operations or something like
this that could do eight at a time
instead of four of a time because it
knows our 16-bit instead of 32-bit you
could imagine if this structure had no
like let's say this structure had no
things that were 32 bit so it thought it
was only ever going to be working with
32 with with 16-bit values it might
decide to pack it differently I don't
know we'll find out in a second here
size of project yeah so you can see if
there aren't any things like I think the
convention typically and see and I don't
know if this is is definitely the case
in the spec or only optionally the case
in the spec but something that typically
happens with most C compilers that I've
seen is if everything in a structure
happens to be a like a certain like a
certain size or smaller then that
becomes the size for the packing so
basically if I have you know one care
and and three shorts or something in
there right then typically it will pack
a it will pack it down to two that to
the size of shorts where the things are
aligned is shorts and furthermore I
believe that it's ordered so that the
packing actually only only happens when
things come after smaller things so I
believe we can do even that potentially
I don't actually know if this is true
but I'm going to say here if this is if
this is possible so I believe we can do
something sort of like this
oops
doo-doo-doo sorry this is the perils and
live coding ladies and gentlemen so you
can see this is actually six so it's a
short that's two bytes plus two bytes is
four now if each of these were aligned
at two bytes it would be six eight so he
respected to be to be eight
but you'll notice it's not it actually
did pack it as essentially three shorts
it did damage part one segment and then
one and two each only got eight bits and
the reason for that is it basically it
seems like it typically only bumps up
the alignment when you have something
that follows so that the thing that
follows will not be unaligned to its
natural alignment whatever it is right
so like if I go ahead and do this it
should you know it should I would think
bump it back up I don't know if actually
did oh you know what it wouldn't because
they're aligned properly so what I've
actually what I'd actually have to do is
that if I wanted it to be to be back to
eight right and you can see that there
and the reason for that is basically
what the compiler is doing it's going
okay I'm at the beginning a thing short
that wants to be on two byte boundaries
basically I'm trying to do it so that's
fine to buy boundaries a care ok that
can be one byte I'll make one byte then
it goes oh this needs this is a 2-byte
thing so I want to line out two byte
boundary again but I'm off because this
was only one byte so I'll add an extra
byte of padding and then do it right and
then when it gets to this one again it's
going to do the the thing where it's got
the one byte pad and then you know it
pads out the end of the structure so I
could sneak another one in here if I
wanted to without changing the size from
eight I suspect yeah I don't think I
mean again I wouldn't care too much
about the vagaries of this typically you
know it matters when it matters and it
doesn't most of the time so it's good to
kind of know what happens there but when
you actually care about how something is
packed you almost always use the thing I
just talked about where you turn off the
compilers options and then you pack it
yourself so you actually go in and
actually say exactly how you want it and
you turn off the the optional packing so
I think that's how C packs things it may
be in the spec because most compilers
I've seen does that so it may be
required
does it that way but I don't really know
if you want to know you should
definitely check the the spec for see
okay let's see in case you weren't aware
the twitch stream doesn't stop when you
kill the webcam video yes that is fine
it's I'm not actually stopping the
stream I'm stopping the recording of the
stream because I post them in two
different chunks that's all it's
happening I leave the stream on so the
stream is still going there's no
shouldn't name be any break in the
stream
what is the arrow operator explain it
yes I explained the arrow operator if
you want to go back and watch the
archived video hopefully that'll happen
uh let's see I understand it do I is
there any particular reason that the
memory watch window shows 18 bytes per
row okay covered that actually tries to
any arbitrary but nevertheless little
any nough seems backwards or at the very
least harder for humans to interpret the
byte code why didn't big envyus win okay
so idiocracy is asking why didn't big
endianness become the thing instead of
little m unis conversely a sony is in a
world where little nes is dominant in
xa6 why would they make things harder
for everyone by choosing big engines for
the ps3 lot of stuff in that question so
the first thing I would say is I don't
know why big nd in this lost and little
endianness one I can only hope that one
is even the right term we don't know
there could be a ton of little endian I
mean a ton of big endian machines that
are about to come out who knows i really
hope we're done with that and
everything's little-endian from now on
but what I'm going to do so the reason I
think it one is probably just because
hey that's what arm and Intel are that's
what maybe that's what Intel happened to
do which is very prevalent so when arm
started being used for like phone os's
they just picked that because both Apple
and both both Apple and the PC market
we're all on little endian and so they
probably figured oh and just be easier
to use the same nd in this on our phones
operating systems as we do on the other
thing because I think arm like I said I
think arm is a switchable architecture I
think you can choose what endianness you
want to build it as when you actually
design it when you license the
architecture from them so I think it
could have gone big I mean but it didn't
and thank God for that so basically we
have little endian now everywhere Wyatt
won I think it probably was just because
of x86 I expect this because what it's
what was on all the desktop machines I
don't know that there's any
particular reason why it's better what I
will say is that the reason why it's a
little bit nicer even as a programmer
and I know you said it's a little more
confusing to read the reason it's nicer
even as a programmer to me is that you
can cast things properly and they would
they they will work so for example let's
say I've got something just to give a
really simple quick example let's say I
have something that is an int and I say
int x equals 16 or something right now
16 fits in a byte just fine
so let's say I now have I want to do
short y equals equals you know this ooh
ah I have no idea what hotkey I just hit
but holy crap that is crazy it's now
showing me like non-printable characters
how do I make it go away
all right I don't know we'll deal with
that later but yeah yeah I do not know
this editor in case you couldn't tell
so if I want to cast this value if I'm
going to cast X to a short right and
then I want to have a care and it's even
smaller and so I want to cast you know
to that I'm going to keep casting these
things right like that now we all know
we've covered very extensively that that
I can I can easily fit eight bits of
data into an int I can easily fit eight
bits of data into a short I can easily
fit bits of data into a care because it
carries eight short is 16 and into 32
but when I do these casting I'm
essentially lopping off parts of the
value technically even though I only
used the bottom eight bits I technically
had 24 extra bits in this integer right
so what this does is this lops off the
top 16 bits what this does it lops off
the top 24 bits right so what we would
expect to see is that all of these
values are equal to 16 correct here we
go
X Y Z all equal to 16 all good right
that'll work just fine on a big-endian
or little-endian architecture right but
what is a little trickier is if I were
to have a pointer to memory so let's say
I have int star X well in star X pointer
let's say equals the address of X right
if I now go and say I want a short
pointer of
Poynter to do that and I'm going to cast
it like this right if I were on a big
endian architecture right what has to
happen here and think about it think
about it carefully I don't want any
shoddy thinking about it here when I say
think about it I want the real full
thinking about it right on this little
endian architecture the pointers are the
same and the reason the pointers are the
same is because we're pointing to the
smallest value so if I cast from a
bigger value down to a smaller one
there isn't any work to actually be done
it's the same pointer I'm just reading
less values instead of reading four
values at that pointer address I'm
reading two in a big endian architecture
I couldn't have done that and the reason
is because the pointer is pointing to
the largest value I'm lopping off that
value so I can't keep the pointer there
so when I cast it down to a smaller
pointer if I wanted to get the same
value if I want to point to the right
digits I'd have to move the pointer
forward by two bytes in order to get it
does that make sense so I don't love
that I don't love the fact that you have
to do that in bighetti and so I don't
super like that I've heard other people
say that that's actually better because
it helps you eliminate bugs or some I
don't know I don't have a strong opinion
bottom either way but honestly I like
the little endian and I don't have a
trouble reading it so you know I'm a fan
I'm her little Indian I'm glad that's
the one but you know do I do I really
care about it either way not that much
I'm just happy to have I just prefer we
always always have just one so that
we're always on the land unit or
big-endian whichever the prevalent one
is now finally why did they pick it for
the ps3 don't know honestly the reason
that they chose the processors for the
ps3 and the the ps3 processor and the
xbox360 processor were chosen largely
for economic reasons I believe I think
it was mostly that Intel did not offer a
processor option for as low a cost as
IBM Motorola that sort of the consortium
that was making the power pcs and so I
think it was really just an economic
decision and those happen to be little
endian so I don't think I think it was
basically like the economics trumped
perhaps the ease of use of it and I also
think at that time Sony was maybe a
little less concerned
about the the barrier to entry that is
posed by them making odd decisions on
their platforms and same perhaps with
Microsoft to some extent and I think
both of them are a lot more conscious
now about how important it is that
programmers be able to just use the same
code that they were using and the least
amount of hassle to get things onto a
platform I think they're kind of aware
that that's important now because in the
old days console programming was a lot
about programming everything 100% custom
for a console and getting every last bit
out of it but nowadays you know consoles
are so powerful and PCs are so powerful
that there's a lot of stuff that's about
whether the game was good and if someone
makes a great game but doesn't
necessarily know how to program on a
console very well and they can't get the
thing to your console or it takes too
long or it means that less games are
ported to it that can be mean that you
lose the war that console generation
right so I think console vendors are a
lot more aware now that like there's
people making games who maybe don't know
how to optimize something for a console
and they just don't make games that have
the kinds of things in them that you
would need to know how to do that
optimization for and that's fine and
again even though I'm about to teach a
thing that's about how to do all those
kinds of crazy optimizations and stuff
uh you know while I think programmers
who are serious about programming should
know how to do a lot of that stuff it
doesn't necessarily mean that people all
have to know it and game designers who
can only just barely program they can
make great games too and all that stuff
is true so while I'm really into the
low-level stuff and want to teach a
bunch of that stuff as part of the
course it's also true that that's not
the only way that things can go and so I
think that nowadays I think people who
ship platforms appreciate that there's
all sorts of programmers out there and
the best course of action is usually to
enable them all you want to have the
people who are give you the crazy
awesome tech stuff on your platform and
you also want the people who like barely
only know how to code but hey they had a
good idea and did an interesting game or
something or even they're just an artist
and it's not about a game or game design
it's about an interesting art project
sort of that's pretty and cool
those are good to have too and so I
think maybe nowadays they appreciate it
but in the ps3 days they were just
coming off the ps2 where they totally
reign supreme no questions so I don't
think it was really on their radar of
thinking to go what will be easy for
people
let's take a look here sorry if I missed
it but aren't the sizes of short int and
long determined by the CPU and memory
architecture rather than always being
16-bit story to bits etc yes technically
they are just not on anything that we
work on so it used to be the case that
they would be quite variable nowadays on
everything you program they are exactly
what I said they were 8 bit 16 bits 32
bits so yes it is true that they could
be changed if you were on an
architecture in the future some kind of
future machine but on the architectures
that we will be using they are always
these sizes after the pragma on the
struct you could rearrange the equation
so it's 11 bytes but on three of the
four 32-bit boundaries in sorry sorry
Jimmy I don't totally understand that
question
after the pragma basically will do
exactly what you tell it so it will
basically reserve only exactly the space
that you tell it so if you say int it
will go 4 bytes forward if you say short
logo 2 bytes forward regardless of what
it would have done otherwise how do I
feel about functional programming I
don't feel much about it I don't do a
lot of functional programming is there a
difference between combining multiple
statements into a single line the
resulting code or is it just to save on
typing mostly it's just to save on
typing although C has requirements about
what is and is not an expression and
what isn't is not a statement so there's
a limit to how much you can combine on a
single line for example a for loop or an
if statement can't really like there's
things I'm having a really give an
example because it's not a great example
now think about it but it's it's a
little wonky like expression oriented
things like adding things and casting
things you can glom rate as much as you
want but there's other things that
aren't quite that way and so there are
places where you kind of have to break
you have to break this it into multiple
statements because of the way it's
written is there a particular reason you
cast a projectile pour into a Kara
pointer instead of an int yes the reason
is because I was trying to add bytes so
the reason that I casted it to an int is
because I did this expression I did size
of projectile I was trying to add this
amount so I said like the pointer it was
a you know care
to our pointer right I did something
like this I had a projectile pointer I
cast it to a Kara star and I added three
times the size of projectile size of is
always returned in bytes so if I am
adding 30 times the size of that I have
to cast to a pointer that's eight bits
that's one byte long otherwise this math
is wrong if I had instead cast it to a
short then I would need to divide this
value by two because I'm going this
pointer when I add whatever the number I
add is will be multiplied by two
remember I said whatever the pointer
type is see adds that multiplication in
there for you it adds see adds this
hidden times two if it's a short if it
was an int it would add a hidden times
four so I would have to divide by four
so what I wanted to do is just do the
simplest possible thing which is go okay
one byte is what we're on so you will
now just literally add the value I told
you without doing a hidden multiple
multiplier and that's what that was um
doot-doot-doot is there a difference
between cabañas I don't know about the
packing I'm pretty sure it just puts the
variable at an address in memory that is
a multiple of that variable size yes
that's sort of what I kind of went over
or tried to say but maybe that's not how
it came across to do maybe I'm
misunderstanding it sounds like you guys
kind of worked us out a little bit short
care int care will be so I don't
understand that one brain Cruiser will
QA continue when you start the main
series yes there will always be a QA
after the main series I'm new here what
is the goal of your stream and are you
streaming stuff like this again yes go
to if you want to see the full action go
to handmade jirobo RG and you can see
the whole faq and everything there and
that'll tell you what the stream is and
when the stream is if pointers are
always pointing to one byte why are
there why are there ever any types
besides unsigned care so the answer is
again just convenience an our kid the
reason for that is that C was trying to
help you out it's trying to basically do
a little hidden multiplication for you
there so that you know
that you're always kind of moving by the
right amount and we will use that to our
advantage to kind of eliminate some
typing in the mainstream so it's good
that it allows you to point to other
values so yeah even though they always
point to the first byte anyway
conceptually they may be pointing to a
larger thing like a projectile and you
want the convenience of being able to
say like just add one go to the next
projectile I don't want to constantly
add to type plus size of projectile I
want be able to just type plus one and
go to the next one couldn't it also be
to make emulation harder
oh so you talked about the platform's it
might have been I don't know I doubt
that was really a concern but maybe
yesterday you said why oh I plant to use
Visual Studio for debugging only we what
we'll use instead and since I am more
used to it
well the vigil so you can power make it
harder to go with you oh I'm sure you're
saying no I will I will still be using
visual Studios compiler and debugger so
what we've been doing will be basically
the same in the mainstream the only
difference is I'll be editing in good
new Emacs
the reason I added in that is I'm more
comfortable that as the editor and I it
works on all the platforms so when I'm
programming when I show how to do the
platform startup code on Mac and on
Linux you'll still see the same Emacs so
it'll be nice and consistent in that way
I don't have to learn like each
individual platforms thing like I don't
when I go to program Mac I can still
just use Emacs which I like since I've
done a lot of cross-platform coding in
the past I've done a lot of work on
other platforms I program on Linux every
day in fact even today so Linux I like
having the same editor on Linux as I
have on Windows so I don't have to
relearn editor shortcuts and stuff like
that for every platform similar to what
are these D word word Q word things in
the win32 api I know they're type test
so I guess I'm asking why they exist so
the reason they exist is because
actually the the question that was asked
earlier about intz being you know aren't
they sort of platform dependent the
answer is exactly that when windows
started everything wasn't the same size
so there are platforms where things were
16 bits an integer would be 16 bits and
platform at least I believe that's true
don't quote me on that but I thought
that was true that the standard size on
16-bit windows might have been 16-bit
and then the standard size of an int
when they went to 32-bit windows became
32-bit and so what they needed to do was
make sure that those sizes were
consistent depending on which
kind of code was being compiled so they
wanted to say Oh a word is 16 a D word
is 32 always no matter what you're
compiling on and so we'll see that in
the mainstream I will actually define my
own types to make sure we can always get
the amount that we want so yeah you'll
see a little bit more about that we'll
cover that a little more detail but
that's why they did it in Windows not
really directed related to the cognitive
stream but do you think C++ has beaten C
as this android game programming and if
so why given your preference for C and
John's very builders like f C++ yeah C++
is typically what's using game
programming and people use it to varying
degrees I even I don't really like C++
very much but I still compiled in cpsc
PPS in C++ because there are some
features as us less that I do take
advantage of from time to time and
you'll see me do that in the mainstream
and so so I definitely think C++ is what
people use in game pregnant even people
who like me who program mostly C like
still usually use C++ if that makes
sense
so so there's really no reason not to
use C++ and that may be the reason the
main reason that it was beat that beat C
is because it's only adding features and
you can choose not to use ones that you
don't like how do you psychologically
deal with not having visceral results or
something you've been programming for a
long time uh well that's interesting
question I usually try to make little
things along the way and like the stuff
that I was showing you in here where we
looked at the memory window and stuff in
some sense doing that sort of stuff with
your code is actually a good idea
psychologically because it helps you get
into the habit of running things that
don't have visual results and seeing
that they're doing things and tuning
certain things of them and so I would
say yeah like use the debugger a lot
look at what you're doing run it time it
do things that sort of turn non visual
things into stuff that kind of has a
tangible result that can often help you
should really put a link to the hand
made to your website and at which pages
description well I tried to in the bio I
don't know what the description is I
guess I'll try to look at what the
description is because I don't even know
I'll write that down but I don't I don't
you know I'm not a I'm not a twitcher I
don't know a lot of these things I am a
programmer so I'm kind of learning this
stuff I will I will try to put that in
there I'll try to go find that
let's see what do you think about rust
or game development have you tried out
yet no I have not tried out rust I don't
really have that much interest in new
languages to be completely honest with
you because at this point I tend to do
my own sort of C meta programming most
of the time and so I kind of programming
KC Lang a lot of the time anyway if that
makes sense not sure you covered pointer
dereference but that would solve some
arrow operator questions people were
asking yes so that's true probably cover
point reference a little bit later but
yeah what what the what that poster is
referring to is the fact that if I have
something like projectile star test and
I want to treat it like it wasn't a
pointer anymore I can dereference it
this way which makes them which is more
useful when you have things like
pointers to pointers but I would rather
cover that a little bit later later on
if that makes sense but I'll make a note
to cover pointers to pointers at some
point so that we can kind of talk about
that a little bit more when I said the
twitch page gription I meant the bio I
think I don't know much about search
phase user but the link should probably
be somewhere on this page so I did put
it like like all I can say is I did put
it there I just don't know how to get
twitch to show it anywhere else I'm not
that knowledgeable of that sort of thing
so yeah
quantum placeand says in the past videos
you seem to dislike Microsoft
substantially why do you think a what do
you think of many of their new open
source free initiatives announced
recently um I guess what I would say is
it's nice of them to release the
compiler for free because it makes it
easier to do this casts I don't have to
tell people to buy something that's two
hundred dollars so that's good I guess
the reason that I dislike a lot of
Microsoft things is not because they're
expensive I don't
I like programmers getting paid for
their work like I don't think there's
anything great about free software in
the free beer sense I do like software
freedom and I think there's some cool
things about that but I don't I think
programmers should be paid I mean it's
how I make a living I want people to
have to pay for software just like they
pay for other things because it's the
only way you can pay people to make it
and to spend a lot of time on it and so
real
the thing that I don't like about about
about the most of stuff that Microsoft
does is it's low quality now I used to
like Microsoft a lot more because their
stuff they shipped was high quality
I thought Windows NT three three five
one was a great operating system for its
day I really liked using it I thought
using Windows was a lot better than
using Linux you know around like you
know even even up through Windows XP
even I thought was a pretty good
operating system and it did it was very
handled a lot of hardware and it made
programming on that Hardware work well
but you know for the past I want to say
decade or more they've been shipping
really lousy stuff I mean their
operating systems are lousy now don't
like them they're buggy they they're
very unreliable they introduce things
like side by side assemblies that make
it impossible to ship code reliably ever
if not a day goes by that I don't try to
like run a game that someone sends me
and it doesn't run on a machine because
like the VC VARs 32 wasn't installed
properly for the version of the compiler
that they use to build oh so it's like
they've lost Microsoft has lost sight of
what it means to ship a platform they're
in this like shipping consumer products
thing and they're just it's a disaster
now they don't ship a stable platform
for developers anymore and so that's why
I'm disparaging of them a lot of times
is because the product is lousy now and
the product used to be much better and
so it makes me sad because I liked
Windows Windows with my home platform
and now Linux is my home platform my
most of my machines now run Linux and I
my laptops run Linux and because you
know I feel like if I'm going to have
something that isn't reliable like that
I might as well use an open-source
alternative because that way I don't
have to be entirely beholden to
Microsoft when I when I do things that's
about all the questions I think if
someone has a question that they that I
missed
please re retweet it or whatever so I
can see it but it looks like we have we
have caught everything that was in the
question so I will wrap up the the Q&amp;A
if no one's got another question I'll
wait another couple minutes just to make
sure
let's see doot-doot-doot no looks like
everyone everyone is done for the
evening
all right everybody well thank you very
much for coming it has been a pleasure
chatting with you as always and I will
see you tomorrow probably around the
same time but I will tweet I will tweet
the actual time on the handmade hero
Twitter stream and on the senior Ettore
Twitter stream if you would like to know
you can follow those streams you can
follow those Twitter streams Twitter
accounts to find out when the next is
going to be but tomorrow will be the
last intro to see before we get to the
main stream so please join me and we
will talk about control flow tomorrow
will basically talking about like if
else while do four function pointers
that sort of stuff and also a little bit
about the preprocessor and then we will
be starting on Monday with the actual
game so things will be quite a bit more
accelerated on the actual game but
hopefully this primer if you didn't know
any C but you know or may be familiar
with some other language hopefully this
primer has gotten you to the point where
you will be pretty comfortable with that
if not we'll do some catch-up streams
maybe but we'll figure it out so thank
you so much for joining me and we will
be back tomorrow
you