okay this is the question set for the
first enter to see video I am going to
take a look at the the stream now and
see if there are any questions that we
should answer right off the bat let's
see there is a lot of stuff there
Abner colum Bray how many videos do you
think you'll do before you actually
start coding the game so the game will
start coding on Monday and I guess it
depends what you mean by coding the game
because I will on Monday I will show you
how to do some things which is basically
the minimal Windows wrapper necessary to
run a game and so that might that'll be
about a week probably of me showing you
all those things and then we will move
on to actually coding the game the week
after that but you may run long I don't
know I haven't done many of these I try
to go very slowly because I know it's
stupid and probably boring for a lot of
people but my goal was to make something
that honestly fairly beginner people
could watch and so I would like them to
have enough information to be able to
take the things that I've said go do
some studying on their own and
understand what happened and so it will
go much slower than it would go if it
was a lot it's not going to be me live
coding a game it's going to be me live
teaching how to code a game which is
very different and it will take longer
arr GT what libraries do you plan to use
in the game development none absolutely
zero there will be none it will be 100%
from scratch
Xavier wreck what about Emacs plus Bing
W Emacs will be the editor used during
game development I will not be using
Ming yet I will be using a Microsoft
Visual C compiler but the one that you
can download for free works the same so
you don't have to pay for it let's see
here oh I'm sorry I didn't mean to leave
the
leave that window up let's see what's
the a in output debug string that's a
good point I did not cover that I should
have covered that so the a and output
debug string refers to the fact that is
taking an ASCII string and I think I
will actually leave a note to myself
explain what the a is next time so that
we will explain we will talk about that
next time I yes basically at one point
during Windows history they decided to
change from asking to Unicode because
they wanted to start supporting foreign
languages that could not be represented
using an 8-bit character set and I'm not
going to go into much detail about what
these things are because I'd rather
explain that next time on the main on
the mainstream so when this happened
they decided to switch to a 16-bit
encoding for Unicode and basically what
that is is it goes from 8 bits per
character to 16 bits per character now
the problem with that is that it's
completely incompatible with anything
that uses ASCII and the reason for that
is because there might be zeroes in that
string and in ASCII Z which is the
format used for C 0 means you've come to
the end of the string so they couldn't
really use Unicode by just passing a
Unicode by just passing Unicode to
functions that were supposed to take
strings and have it work which is what
happens with utf-8 a more modern Unicode
encoding made by the plan 9 guys because
they knew what they were doing unlike
the people from Windows who didn't
basically it means that all of the
functions and windows had to now be
multiplied so that they could take both
ASCII versions and Unicode versions of
strings now of course they didn't want
to make everyone have to now call new
functions they wanted old windows
functions to still compile so what they
did is they made all functions actually
be macros that switch based on whether
or not you are compiling in Unicode or
in ascii mode now this happens to
default to compiling in unicode which i
don't have a problem with that's just
what the what that's what Visual Studio
did when I created the project but what
that means is if I try to pass an ASCII
string which is what I had wanted to
pass
because I want to go look at it in the
debugger later and show you how the
string works that was something I was do
I will do on the next string I didn't
want to have to actually make a Unicode
string there so instead of going and
changing the compile type to be unit to
be asking said a Unicode what I did is I
bypassed the macro because the macro is
just output debug string and in fact I
don't know if you can do this in here
here you go look at that which sometimes
windows sometimes the IDE actually works
you can actually see what happens here
do you see these two function
declarations if you're a beginner you
may be a little loss because there's a
little bit much in here but they're just
like the kind of things we talked before
remember the void this is a capital void
because windows defined their own but
long story anyway here's that output
debug string and here's that output
debug string again but with a W after it
a stands for ASCII W stands for wide it
means wide character and wide character
was the 16-bit characters because they
were bigger there was 16-bit instead of
8-bit so if you look here there's then
an if def Unicode if Deaf's we haven't
covered yet but what they basically are
something that says only do the next
part if you're compiling in a particular
you know if this particular thing
evaluates to true and so this case if
the Unicode simple happens to be defined
if it does we're going to make output
debug string mean output debug string W
and pound define is a thing that
basically does word substitution again
these are all things recover much later
but if it's not then it will define it
to output Devo string a so you can see
that the actual functions are actually
all here so when you look up output
debug string you'll see a function
prototype for it in MSDN in fact I can
do that right now if I want to go in
MSDN and say output debug string you'll
notice that I actually get a function a
function declaration for it a function
prototype for it that looks like there's
a function called a perturbation but
there isn't that's just the name that
actually is the macro that resolves to
whichever one you were building on and
so I said well I don't want deal with
that right now so I'm just going to call
a directly because I know that will take
the ASCII string which is what I wanted
so that I don't have to do a pound two
five of Unicode oh they didn't want to
talk about that at that
their time hopefully that answers the
question for you now I got a scroll back
I'm sorry
twitch makes it very hard to answer
questions in a good way
so I'm going to scroll back here and
take a look
what is damage okay recursive Casey we
solved that okay how often will you do
these videos these videos will be every
week night at 8 p.m. Pacific Standard
Time until the game is done and I will
take some nights off if I have specific
things I have to go to or something like
that but in general most weeknights 8
p.m. there will be a programming stream
and I will explain every last thing
there is to do in making a game ok there
are doing ok
OpenGL DirectX or what so that's
interesting someone I think is asking
whether I'm going to use OpenGL or
Direct X for the game the answer is
neither I will be showing you how to do
all of the rendering yourself it will
not be 3d it will be 2d so it will be a
sprite based game it will be a high-end
sprite based game and it will be a very
very intricate codebase because a lot of
things I want to cover so it will be a
pretty cool 2-d game I think but it will
not be 3d and I had a lot of reasons for
that one is because I think that really
wants a separate series and so what I
wanted to do was do a 2-d game first to
show you all the stuff involved in
parting again except for the 3d math and
then we'll do the 3d math you know in a
separate series if that turns out to be
I really want many years from now and
this one's done it's going to be a while
but anyway yes so no DirectX no OpenGL
it will all be things that are
completely what happens at Apple on
every platform you will be able to do it
booting fresh out the BIOS on a
Raspberry Pi if you wanted to with
absolutely no libraries no nothing so we
will be we will be coding as low level
as you can get let's see fgc hype is
this the same visual studio set appears
you've the witness yes although I don't
edit in Visual Studio yes is the same
setup I used for coating on the witness
I don't really program much on the
witness anymore I'm just doing basically
maintenance work now and optimization
work on occasion when when there are
things that I can do in the code that I
wrote but I'm not programming on the
witness at the at the moment other than
a few chunks of time
basically yeah just support code that I
wrote for them that this stuff is gold
even to see some programmers sanction
kind of stuff oh well thank you very
much for the kind words I yeah
I really hope some people find it useful
I you know yeah thank you very much
are you going to be using the windows
and what up and gel for the game okay so
for the actual game again
no OpenGL no DirectX it'll be completely
raw and it will be all platforms so I'll
show you how to do in a Windows first
because that's the thing most people
have but I will do a adjunct week at
some point for Linux Mac OS X and
Raspberry Pi at least I don't know if
I'll do Android I definitely won't do
iOS because I hate closed platforms and
I refuse to deal with code signing so
that's not going to happen but other
platforms any platform where I can
develop and deploy an application
without getting it code signed I will I
would probably show you how to do
platform code for okay and see not a ski
windows API I'm sorry to understand some
of those I would say goal meant if
you're running testing the console can
the aperture missionary capture used in
some way okay idiocracy asked if you're
you running test that's a P in the
console can the output of output debug
string a be captured or youth in some
way the answer is not really
output debug string I only used it
because it's the most straightforward
thing to use when I'm doing a little
demo like that where I'm just trying to
focus on showing you very very basic
things output debug string is basically
a special-purpose call in Windows that
is specifically for debug output so it
will not show up in the console however
there are programs which capture it
sysinternals for example if you know the
sysinternals suite and if you don't you
can just go in here and search for
sysinternals and you will see this guy
here this internal suite is basically a
thing with a bunch of stuff that you
probably would enjoy if you are a
low-level kind of fellow and one of them
in there is a thing that will capture
the debug stream from running
applications and so if you would like to
see the debug string from an application
that somebody has shipped or that you
have shipped and you are not running it
into bugger or can't run it in the
debugger for some reason that is how you
would do
now we will certainly cover a bunch of
things about how to do debug coded all
that stuff we will probably not use out
but debug string for very much but when
you are in Windows it is a great back
backdoor hack thing to just I really
need output something quickly without
doing much work so it's really good to
just know that's there I actually make
another note here also backslash n
because I didn't play with that one so I
want to talk about that as well okay how
much will you be relying on Windows
Pacific stuff for future parts none
absolutely none
only the week of Windows programming or
- however long it takes me to show you
the minimal window shim to run a game
will be Windows everything else will be
non Windows the game itself will run
assuming that it has a flat address
bitmap to do its rendering to an a-flat
address sound output stream as well as
an input that consists primarily just of
a joystick state and eight keyboard that
is it so every last little thing we do
besides the platform weeks which will be
very brief and mostly involve just me
showing you how to get the platform out
of your way what do you 100% applicable
to every single platform now and forever
as long as you can render to a bap
let's see here's a good talk on ANSI vs.
wide oh ok who's saying someone was
saying I sang ASCII ANSI I should be
saying ANSI not ASCII I don't know if
that's actually true I'm sorry I've
always thought of the a is ASCII but it
may be very true that it's actually ANSI
meaning an ansi standard for ascii or
something like that
the a in output D by stirring a instead
of the W so I don't know I may have
misspoke there and you should definitely
look it up if you care I I don't think I
care at all but um let's see here um
ANSI C if you don't want to get tied to
Windows STL trying to think there's
anything I haven't covered in version OS
yeah these videos on of it okay
someone asked if we will post a list of
these videos on the website blog okay so
actually the answer is yes there is a
site it will be announced on Monday to
correspond with everything it's called
handmade hero org and you can go to
handmade hero org and it has absolutely
everything about the game it has a way
to email me if you have a question
outside of the twitch chats and things
like that because I won't only see them
in twitch chat so you know if it's
something important and you really want
me to cover it you know you can email it
there you can get to the Twitter stream
for it which will say when we are live
starting Monday's you can get to the
archive which is the YouTube channel
that will have them all and eventually I
watch a special page for that which
break them into lessons so you can view
them and learn there is a live button so
that you can get to the twitch stream
anytime if it you know if it's if you
think it's going on you can get there
and there is the game which if you want
to support this product you can
pre-order I
there's nothing yet obviously it won't
start till Monday so unless you're just
trying to give me $15 for free at this
point I would say wait to click that
button until you've seen if the series
if you like the series and want the game
but the nice part about the game is it
will come with all the source code and I
will be zipping the source code every
day so if you want to practice with me
at home or try experiments in the code
the reason that this pre-order is here
at all is just because instead of wait
until the game is out I thought that
people might want to code along with the
series and the game comes with the
source so so I figured that would be
something that would be good and so you
can you can pre-order it if you want to
you can also notice that there are the
platform icons here they will light up
as they are ready I don't know if it
will be a game that's allowed on Steam
or whatever I don't deal with any of
that stuff so I can't speak to that but
for the other ones I do plan on
eventually doing the the various
platforms that are here and they'll
light up once we do the platform layer
for that thing so this site if you
bookmark it should just have everything
you need and you don't have to buy the
game or anything to view the videos the
archive will be free for everyone
forever and anyone can take the whole
course and watch the whole thing so
let's see you're doing this so the
people saying thank you thank you for
watching this is a project I really
wanted to do and I I'm super I'm just
super old-school and I really love
old-school programming and one of the
things that's true about me is I was
kind of born a little too late to really
be an old-school programmer because by
the time I was old enough to be in the
game industry no one really does super
low level programming anymore but we
still do a fair bit of it and it's it's
the type of things that a lot of people
on engine teams and stuff do and I just
I really wanted to how to preserve that
tradition in some sense and show the
stuff that I know and and you know I'm
not even the expert on a lot of things
that are super low level and so I was
kind of hoping two other people would
see it maybe do live streams of the
stuff that they do and low-level coding
that they do and it kind of just I don't
know I really wanted to get some of this
stuff out in the out and it's just kind
of all sort of you know weird apprentice
e out stuff that you learn by going to a
game company in programming with people
who program for a long time or you know
just trying to piece tough together
yourself and I mean I I had to learn
entirely by myself because there was no
internet at that time and there was no
documentation or stuff really to use so
you kind of had to occasionally find
books where you could and you know just
just do it that way and so so this is
basically a kind of a goal to kind of go
back to the style of coding
was done in those days while still
modernizing it and going here's all the
things that I value as an old-school
programmer by managing the memory myself
writing my own renderer things like that
that I think are good for people to know
and to do is exercise to become better
programmers anyway like I think even if
you're going to go program something in
unity or you're going to go program
something using a premade engine or a
bunch of libraries knowing all of these
things makes you so much more powerful
because you can always go down there and
fix things if you need to or you can
always escape from them and do your own
stuff when you need to and it just
teaches you a lot of things that just
make you more aware and better
programmers so I'm really excited about
this project and so really I should be
thanking you for tuning in so thank you
so much for watching it the fact that
100 people on the stream is amazing and
I thank every single one of you for
showing up it's awesome thank you it
makes me feel really good so anyway keep
going on the thing it won't be just on
Mali rockets ok I think I answered those
questions this is pretty neat but you're
not just taking this so seriously
really oh it comes with a source awesome
goodness thank you okay this is just
podcast though okay so I think I've
answered all of the questions now will I
still be doing the podcasts do you mean
the Jeff and Casey show we do the Jeff
mk2 show on weekends that's Jeff and I
get together and do that for fun I mean
as you know it's our little fun hour the
Jeff encaged show is where we just say
anything and be stupid for an hour and
you know let off steam and stuff so of
course we will still be doing the Jeff
and Casey show that's that's
non-negotiable that thing will go
probably forever that thing will go way
past the point where anyone wants to
listen to it anymore because we largely
do it because we like it and so yeah
I may hear some earlier recommendations
were larger font
okay so larger font meaning for in here
is that is that what we mean by larger
font because that seems like something
we can totally solve
where is that that is I don't know where
that is environment fonts and colors
fonts and colors so if I go into text
editor and I select a larger font let's
say a font that's that big you know what
let's address something else right now
this font is awful hook me up with some
liberation monitor people look me up
there we go
and I must see liberation mono that is
that too big though I feel like that's a
little big let's try it slightly smaller
ready 11 okay and the other windows all
text tool windows I don't know if this
will work but we can certainly try
liberation mono 10 I'll make it 12 okay
everything is bigger now and I'll wait
for the stream to catch up a little for
you guys to tell me if that is big
enough output window possible can you
just hold crit and use the mouse wheel
to change it
serene dig into lower southern commit
timing edge font kids something with
decent kerning readable alright so it
looks like everything is good now so I
will save this and I think that answers
all the questions in the stream so that
will be it for tonight and I will
hopefully see everyone again tomorrow
also at 8 p.m. for the next installment
where we will do some more fun window
stuff thanks for joining everyone yes I
should wave goodbye goodbye