Okay
Assuming this is working
I would love to welcome everyone to this
Pestering basically what I wanted to do
Is I am planning on
I'm starting a project on Monday
Which is probably very ill-advised and I appreciate that but I'm
Planning to start a project
Where I am going to show how to code
A complete game in C
Which is a pretty big undertaking
And
I thought about it whether it was a good idea for a while and I wasn't sure but I finally decided that I really wanted to do it and I always want
I need the directions to have like a documentation
But you can basically
Or documentation say
Like a live recording of like cures everything that we did to make
An actual games you can play from scratch
And so I don't know how that'll go nobody make care about that at all until the game is pretty far along or something like that
That but I really really want to do it
And so I'm going to be starting that
On Monday but before then I wanted to practice the streaming to make sure that all of the stuff is going well because
Computers of course as you know are oh so reliable these days
And so I kind of have a feeling that there will be plenty of
So what I thought I do
Is spend a couple days
Doing test dreams where I will at least do something useful
Which is explain how to do C programming on a computer
Because
I mean
Let's face it lots of people don't know how to do that
And if anyone wants
What's to follow along as I program the game
NC and go through all the explanations
Of why I'm reading the game code that way
I won't be wanting to stop and explain little things like what is the question mark operator or
How does
Is the staff work or something like that unless that's exactly relevant topic
At the time so I was hoping to basically do
A couple streams that I could archived and just put up on the website that's like
If you don't know how to pronounce it all if you literally have no idea but would like to watch the series
Go watch these couple videos that'll get you up to speed
I'm just what's going on so you can start to follow and granted you'll still have to do a bunch of work to practice and learn how to program at Aldi
Because if you don't know any programming
You're not going to be able to just jump right in but at least I'll get you started and then you can presumably
At least start to follow the videos and understand
You know the majority
So
What this video is going to be
It was going to be literally showing
How I would start
To program Siana machine and how to do some of the basics
I forgot
So this is not a Windows machine cuz that's the most common
Programming machine that people are going
And have
And
The thing that you have to do right off the bat which is actually kind of annoying and you don't have to do this
If you're on Linux but the thing you have to do on a Windows machine issue has to find
A c compiler
I'm currently you don't have a lot of option
Even though llvm which is, one other platforms
Is
Sort of able to build seen out it's not able to actually do the entire process so what you have to do
Is you have to go
Get something called Microsoft Visual Studio X
And this is basically a free version
Of their you know thing that they're there
Professional
C programming environment and you'll see when you get to this page
They want to give you a lot of other stuff
But you really don't want
When you look on here you can see stuff like oh.
Team Foundation server
And
Since you're just someone is trying to program C at home you probably don't have a team or if you do they probably don't
Don't have a foundation or don't want their Foundation to be comprised primarily
Or something for Microsoft anyway I certainly would
And they're also going to try and give you things like this
Express for web which is something that you use
To program
Like you know if you want to do web deployment you know asp
P.net and other things like that
What you want to do
You're the one that you actually want to get
Is this one here which is Express 2013 for Windows
Which is the thing that actually lets us compile C++ which is what we want
So I'm going to start that downloading
Or at least I'm going to go through this this awesome
Crazy
Circus here that you have to do to download
Los Arcos
And now we're going to kind of have to skip a little bit of this process only because there is a challenge response that they do
Which people will have to do on their own I obviously
I can't tell you how to do
You will have to basically
Install the Skype
Loading identity provider
Okay so yeah you will have to go through and you'll have to fill this out
Unfortunately you'll have to get like a Microsoft
Login of some kind
In order to get it
But once you get it it will allow you to install visual studio and you will be able to do basically Sub sub
Definitely what I'm about to do
After you get that in
Install it'll probably make you reboot your machine which I also can't do on a live stream of course because if I would have read them
Machine
But after you do that
You will get
A newer version
Essentially
Of this particular product this is the older version that was installed on this machine
Visual Studio 2008
And as you can see we've got stuff on here which is kind of not actually stuff I can open up
Obviously I'm not allowed to
To show you any of the secret Witness
Things that would that would be very bad for him
But what you can do
To actually start programming
In this particular Department you should go to new
And you go to Project
And what that'll do is that will allow you to create one of their dummy projects which I'll show you how to build
Only for a little while because we'll kind of immediately get off
What advice does the brings up
A giant window
Full of all of the things
That you
Could build with this
And most of them are things that we are not concerned with
Are you can see there's a bunch of template things for you can use for. Net you can see there's all sorts of things here MSC which is like an
Antiquated Library
And you don't care about any of these things the only thing you want to do is build a win32
Application
Tinder two options
One is for win32 console application
One is for win32
Project
And the difference between these two is actually extremely rudimentary
All it is is for some reason way back when they actually did
The original version of Windows they decided to segregate
How you built
Basically applications that can run from a command line
Which is something we'll look at me
Future and ones that are actually more like apps like it have a window
And because they did that
You have to build an app as one or the other
And this is actually something that's basically impossible to get around there are workarounds for it if you really care but basically there is no
No way on Windows
Unlike say on Linux or Mac Off
There is no way to actually build something
That both
Works from the command line
And work
From
In the standard application mode
But
We don't have to talk about that too much because we're going to be building a game and games don't really have
Have to do anything from the command line
Inside of a
That's right away
So
What we're going to do is Select win32 project which is what setup for actually building a
Sorry I got to enter a name
So we're going to call this
We're going to call this
Okay
And what I'll do is I'll bring up this silly little wizard
And The Wizard is basically asking a bunch of stuff none of what you want
So what you want to do is just check empty project so that it will get out of your way
And what kind of gives you another option here to do other things like the console application dlls which are separate issues.
Saclibrary switch we don't need
Worry about right now better things you might want to know
And we'll go to Windows application which will basically just give us
Our own
Furtive
This will basically give us our own sort of
Dumping Ground where we can put stuff in and build it
No the way that Microsoft Visual Studio works if it has this thing called a solution Explorer
And one thing that will often happen to you when you're developing is it will go away so you will get something
That's like this or perhaps you'll get something that's even completely blank
I'm so that has nothing in it like this
And you can get back to the solution Explorer Thing by going to view solution
Explorer now what is a solution
You may ask what was the problem
You may also ask him that's a very valid question
But the answer is there wasn't necessarily a problem
Unless you consider the problem being that Microsoft makes it very hard to build things
Solution was just something that they started calling a project at some point
Answer
Really a solution is just their word for a thing that you are going to build it's like a basically
A list of things that need to get built and how they're going to build them and so instead of having an intuitive name like
Files Explorer project Explorer it's called solution Explorer
And you have to go to it when you go to the solution Explorer
You will basically get something here
That works a lot like
You know the file explorer in Windows
It's hierarchical and you can collapse it
And they made some folders in here but we don't really have to care about these folders very much
And we can have our own folders or rename folder
So if we wanted to rename one of these you know we could go in here and call this
Whatever we wanted and that's fine
But we need to do to in order to start building something is Axe
She have some files in your
How to build
So that it will know
What we are
So in order to do that I'm just going to right click on this and going to add
And I'm going to take a new item
So that would have make a new file basically
That we can actually build
That will pop up a mess of Windows stuff
Because there's all sorts of things that you might want to do you might want to make an SQL script file
Class diagram
Those might be good things to me
But we're not going to make those right now
Instead we're going to make just a straight-up
CPP file
Okay
So basically I was ripped into the name done I so basically we just have to
Give RC Fallon name and add it now we will have a blank file that we can start typing into
And that is what we will use
To start programming in
Now
Programming UC has not Advanced much over the years unfortunately
Obviously C &amp; C++
They're both pretty old but
You know I think C++ was sometime early 80s
I see was you know a good decade before that I want to say
And yet
Just the same even though they're so old
The way in which you actually enter
C code into a computer and the way it is actually built is still
Almost the same
As it was back then you basically just have
Text files
Their basic clean old text files less complicated than something that you would type into Microsoft Word like they
They literally don't even have annotation right there just
Robotics
And that raw text
Is then
Interpreted
I'm by the tools
To do the things that we need to do
And that's done with the
Compiler and stuff that will be talking about
Basically just understand that nothing we're going to do is going to be anything other than entering text
Enterkomputer
Okay
So
The first thing to do is to say well okay we haven't actually done anything here
This is some text
In a file
And
What you wanted what you will notice is that this basically every time I type in here there's a little yellow bar that sort of appears
And that just tells you that these are new lines that you have type since you have saved
And you can see that I've got a little
Star there
That now adds to it just like in most applications that says this file has been modified since it has been
Can save now if I want to say that I can just go to files saved
Peppa Pig or I wanted some shorthand I can hit control s
Right and there it saves it and you'll notice that the yellow bars now changed to a green bar
And what does a green bar mean when a green bar is basically something that lets you know
That is saved there was still a change recently there
And I believe although I am not a frequent user Visual Studio that
It will basically remove the green bar
Once we actually
I'll be
Inter working program
So that you know what changes you've made since the last time you bought
Your program
So let's say
I want to actually run the process
Of making something out of this text file
Well the thing that you do there is you say build solution
And Bill solution will go through everything that we have in here
It will actually
Do the work necessary to make this in
To a program
And we'll talk about all those steps
In a little while
So when I hit build solution
You'll notice that if I did not have an output window open it magically made one for me
It just pops up there's really nothing you can do
About it
And
What it does is it
Prince out
What happened
When it tried to build the program
So it starts out by giving me a line which says what was trying to build
So it says build started
Project test
No that's what we wanted you can see in here we've essentially when it created are automatic
Project for us
He created the solution called test
And it put inside one default project which is called test in the reason I call a default project you can see it's bold
It's because
You can actually go in here
And there's a thing called set as start-up project in
Some of the things like this
There's basically a notion of what the project is you're going to build
When you build a solution because we could actually stacked other products in here that build other programs
Which we don't all want to build and other sorts of nonsense like this
Most of that is not really necessary when you're doing development unless you start developing a very large and complex project
But if you're just building a game by yourself it's on like you'll need to ever do anything
Like that
And I often don't build anything anything from here so
What are things were at carburetors how to build things without using
That's it
Cast of the project that we will build when we do build solution and so what this was telling us here
Is it was going to build that project
And there's a configuration line
Which is debug win32
And what the configuration mean
Is basically what sort of build it was trying to do
Because as we'll see later on there's actually multiple ways you can build the same set of C code
Some of them are designed to Target different platforms for example you may want to Target a 32-bit copy of
Windows
Or 64-bit copy of windows
And that would be part of the configuration
You might want to be trying to do things that are based on
Deep like a debug developer build so something that has a lot of test code compiled into it
Special menus for you the editor for the game or something
Might be built
In this mode but then there might be another build called release
Or retail depending on how you do your naming
Team which will build these things out and so basic configuration
Is something that affects the way
In which these text files
Are actually interpreted by the various things that
That we do in order to get to an application that that
Is somehow different from the other configuration
That we might be
So now the next time you can see here is compiling
And what that is is compilation
Is the general term
It's not a particular specific term although we actually use it to mean something specific
That's a very general term that technically means
Moving something from one format into another
Basically
It's sort of like
A translation in some sense a compiler is something that parses
A text file typically
It turns it into something Samantha it understands the meaning of that text file what we were trying to do that text
And then it turns it into
Some other thing that we wanted
Now in this case
What is going to do is we're actually trying to get it
To produce at the end of the day
I'm an actual program that we can run an executable something that you would click on in Windows to run like with the little eye
Icon. Exe that thing we want build that thing
In order to build that thing
Basically the the text code that we write
Has to be translated into something that the computer can run
And that is what the compilation step does and there's another step
After compilation that we'll talk about
But the compilation step is basically in charge of doing the majority of the work
To translate
Are text file from something humans read into something that a CPU can read and specifically
Often times
A specific process
The compilation will be
Compiling from a text file into say x86 to
X64 code
Something for the actual CPU
That you were trying to Target not abstract
Stop
Given that
After we we see the compilation lineman of the compiler
Started and we now go to a list of what files it's actually
Compiling we only have one file which is
Just test out CPP
And so not surprisingly it tries to compile that file now you will note
In front of all of these
There is a little
Number within with assertive
Greater than symbol
And
What is
Is totally Irrelevant for the most part 2 what you're going to be doing for development it's not really something to pay attention to
But just in case you're wondering
If you are on a machine
That happens to have a lot of processor
So if I go in here
If I basically just that use the hot tea
One of my favorite hot fries
Control shift escape to bring up the task manager
You will notice that this machine
Have a lot of processors
In this thing called CPU usage history
There is one of these for every logical processor
In the machine
I'm a logical processor is or shouldn't say lunch process
Crap that's the wrong word
Deluxe compressor is not individual processor
If it's only a logical unit that can run code
And there's two different kinds of these
And we might as well talk about them now if I'm going to talk about them
Certainly more
Out later on in the actual series
It's not in the center doctors
Basically the word processor is divided internally or as we are computers about internally honestly there are actual physical processors
So most people have one physical processor in the machine obviously
But other machines have two or three or four maybe
Even dozens
A processor
I'm certainly not consumer boxes but you know
Certain server types my
I have 32 processors
The machine
Who's physical processors obviously are chips they were made by Intel they're stuck in the machine they have a nice big old heatsink,
Grandpa from overheating
And when you power on your machine they are what executes everything
Graphics code or things like
The networking which is sometimes on
Car adjustable chips
The CPUs what does all the work but
In addition to being
A physical unit
The CPU itself is actually divided internally
Into processing unit
Which actually can run code sort of separately
Those are typically called course
So inside a single CPU
You might have four chords
For a course or something
And you will see these often times advertising Intel advertising and of course more course is better but what is a quart
Accor
Is basically something that is capable
I'm doing the work
Stand-alone CPU for the most part it is something that would have been a CPU in the old days when CPUs could only
Execute one thing
Time
Now you have processors capable of executing multiple things at a time
Each one of those units is
Call Decor in
And the chorus typically have a bunch of things in them
They have units capable of doing
Maddox they have units capable of doing every other saying all these hurtful things
And then they will talk to the memory in your system will talk to the
The bus go talk to all sorts of things to do their job but
Biologic or
Is the things action of the computation
Even that
It's still not really
What you might call a logical processing unit
Nowadays and the reason for that is they subdivided that even further
Down two things called hyperthread
And of course
Hyperthreads are basically
A thing where
A processor
Score
Is actually able to maintain this
State
Of multiple cores
As if it were multiple cores
Even though is only capable of executing anyone given Court a time so for example
You think of a CPU core as being able to remember say what it was running where it is in the
Program what the state of the things it was operating on these sorts of things
We'll get into all those aren't detail later
But
Cory's basically doing this work of running an application
That core can actually store multiple of those States
Almost like a multitasking operating system you can think of is, there's the taskbar and it's got different tasks
That it has
Wella Cork and actually sort of do that testing
Insertive sent itself
And
Even though it's only running one thing at a given time it could keep safe for additional
State
But it can really quickly switch to
And so what happens is
Those actually show up often times in the operating system as a logical processing unit
Because to the operating system they sort of look
Like a processor
They are effectively running something
Even though only one of them are particular court is actually inflated a given
Another word to talk about their
But
I am from two tangents I thought I'd mention some of that way booted up here
So how's it going to see there a lot of logical bussiness as they are not this many processors
In the actual machine
In fact
I don't actually know
If I can go on here
I think
If it's actually will tell us
What kind of processor it is
Yes
It is a Xeon
It easy
2 processor box
Although it doesn't actually tell me how many threads for plumbing how many cores for processor it actually has
We can go look up what a w5580 is
And we could see how many it has
But I think it's probably only got maybe
4 / I don't know I'm not really sure
But anyway each one of these would would correspond basically
To one individual one of those hyperthreads and it would show me basically
How much usage that particular thread is is getting
Right now
So hopefully that that gives you a little bit
Perspective on this
I wonder too
You know what
Nowadays that kind of attitude
I wonder if there's any way I can get more information
About things like hybrid
Like I say even show hyperthreads I feel like in the old days you could
Chicago Bears
Didn't say whether you were showing
Clusters of large compressors out of
I do now
Doesn't
Doesn't look like there's much here
For that
Alright well
Anyway that is not really relevant what we're doing so I'm going to skip it but maybe later on we will
We will go try to find out how to how to get a little more info
Thanks anyway
So there a lot of Pastors in this system in when you build something
Obviously compilers can get a little slow and if you have a lot of things compiled they could take
Sometime it's a one of the things that compilers do is they are more
Threading sometimes
Depending on which one
Talking about
And they will try to compile using more than one
Lots of passing it so they'll try to use
More of a CPU resources faster and what this little thing here
Represents if I remember correctly
It's been a long time since I've ever really use my things that just to let you know a sequence number of basically which
Sort of
Spawn of the compiler
Was reporting this message because you may have multiple compilation
I going
Multiple different
City is doing compilation and I believe that basically just tells you
Which Wonder
Which one you're looking at that time
Time so if we were to do more complicated
Population with multiple files you might see two stories for is going on there as it's cooled off jobs
Any more complex fashion but for the moment we're only seen ones because it only had one failed to compile
And did not bother to lunch at
Search for Threads to do that
Anyway
So
This is the father was compiling and we will see here the first time we got an error
And what an era is is an error means basically it was trying to read the text file that we gave it
And it did not like what it found now that is unsurprising cuz I basically just typed a bunch of gibberish in here
But we can do is when we double click on this it will tell us where the problem is
It will then stop basically what it's doing
So when you have errors it will list the errors that it found
It will list them up usually to a certain number of errors and use that as well but after it gets hurt
Compilation
And it will basically just reports
That it failed the compilation and you can see it says 1 errors
This year and it says 0 succeeded 1 failed
And Alexis know if they're ones that it skipped because it didn't thicken
Need to do any work that's what it
It also save a build log for
Which are pretty useless most the time but
If you want to look at the build log basically it saves an HTML file
That has sort of
A a lot of what happened in the building for I guess for posterity or if you want to do some kind of thing for you
You saved the logs are doing
Maybe you are running these
In some way that you're viewing remotely there's there's reasons for build logs but we're certainly not going to
Okay
So that rather exciting process there where we just hit build and we get an error
Is what we're going to be doing
In order to produce an executable and in order to get to the next step of actually producing
Beautiful
What we are going to have to do
Is we are going to have to give it
Some code that actually
Understand
And
Basically I'm going to type
In some rope code now
And I'm going to explain to you
Certified it does it start of the simplest thing that we can possibly type in
To get to the next stage
In
Here it is
Set
If I now try to build this
You will notice
And don't worry we'll get to this
You will notice that what it does is it gets
That's if we were before we got to test out CPP
And it actually was
Able to sort of moved past that
And move on to doing other things now
He tried to lock the Microsoft resource compiler
And that was because we have a resource files
Singing here and it created
This project for awesome
A resource compiler is nothing fancy
It sounds a lot better than it is you're like a resource Camp I like it to pile my games resource with that
Not very likely
And you probably don't want to do that
Myriad reasons but
What the refractive actually does is the resource compiler does things like packing up an icon
For your application
And sticking it in somewhere
Where the
But where Windows could find it in the executable so that I can display it next year schedule things like that so that is something that you do need to know how to do
Eventually
The right now we don't care at all obviously didn't actually do anything so to finish that up but then it got to the stuff that I actually want to talk about
Which is linking
No blinking is
Is linking
Is sort of a
A backpack
Tennis compilation
Process
Now what we could do
You know compiler certainly could
Take a text file and it could directly make an X
Skittle out of it if that textile contain everything that needed to Define their stupid butt
What usually happens more often
And
Harley for legacy reasons at this point but
You know
What can you do
What happens more often if you have a lot of text file so you know the code for game could be hundreds of thousands of lines of code
Kodak
It's a lot of PCP files that we're going to
Learn how to write here
And
In order to
Quote on quote save compilation time
And various other reasons
What a dolphin wants to do is be able to compile each file into an intermediate file
Doing one part of a compilation process one part of the bruising
Deleted file will basically be
The process that takes the text and turns it into mostly
Code to see if you can actually put their a bunch of things that aren't quite done yet
Windows intermediate files
Don't always have to be updated they only have me updated when the particular Source found that they came from changed
So for example this test ICP If I don't change test at CPP won't have to recompile testout CBP if I had tons of them
Other files productivity bar. CDP all these other files
Guy sings just one of them you would only have to do the recopilation
I just one of them
But
Does all of them have to be pulled in made into an executable at the end
They basically have a second stage
The compilation process which is called blinking
And that's what this line does here
And what Lincoln is about is licking is about Gathering all of that process
Sing together
All of us intermediate files
And
Basically resolving the places
Where is Bay Point to each other
So I made you a bunch of things in test out TPP
That are going to
Call out and and or reference
2 or or use data from
Older
CPP file so I can pile
And
Since the compiler is only looking at each individual CPP file as it goes in
Found them
It can't resolve those references
It can't tell
Where the things are that things are pointing to because it's only seeing one individual files so what the Linker does
In this link stage
There's a thing called a liquor that gets executed
Separate from the compiler
And what it is
Is it is something that gathers all this together
Resolve the references
Packages into one EXE
Which you can then ship
Now when I say which you can then ship
That was the good old days
There's a lot of reasons why you can't actually just you
Thanks to Microsoft in their Tyler's Pursuit
Lawmaking building applications complicated
But
I'm going to hold off on that for now
So that we can focus on just the basics of the process in
It's a lot to absorb
I don't want over complicated
More than it already is
So in the linking stage
You will see that we've gotten to our next Air
And that air is this line right here you'll notice that it doesn't give me a line number and that is cuz Microsoft Linker
Is not particularly good
I don't know if they fix this and one of the more modern versions but
Even as of 2008
Their liquor never bothered to tell you where your errors are so all you get
Is which function
It was referenced in
That makes sense
So basically you will know you will know very little you'll know like what file maybe May
Made the error possibly and you'll know what function
What's causing the problem or things like that and we'll kind of get to what all those mean and how to stop them out later but basically you get very
Cryptic message for a blinker fortunately
Most of the time winter errors are simpler airzooka Power air so it's not too hard
To figure out what they mean
So
Look at this error
What it says is unresolved external symbol underscore winmain at 16
Referencing function
Tri main CRT startup
And then goes on to tell us that that was a fatal error
So there was one unresolved external
And now what that means just what I was just saying and unresolved external
What external means in this case is external to the population unit in which it was being used
So when I compile test at BP or something
It's got a corresponding file
That the compiler produced at the Linker isn't pulling in
Things that are external to that file are called externals
And when you see one unresolved external it means that it came across one of these
Couldn't resolve the couldn't find any
Actual definition of that anywhere else in the other file so what can I do it can't finish linking
Because it can't figure out
What it was supposed to do there
So again we get an error
This time it says 2 hours but really it was only wanting her
But that's just the way I guess it
Decided to print it out and not sure what the secondary is but hey
What you going to do
Anyway
Nobody gets now that we see what I look for areas we can start to the bucket
So
What actually happens
If you think about it when you run an executable
There is
Something kind of complicated but has to occur
Which is that
Windows
Is actually the program that's running on your machine
So the processor your machine is executing windows
And now we have built something that we would like Windows to start executing
But windows and our program
We're not linked
Together right
This linking stuff that I just explained where hey we can write some stuff and it pulls out together and it references each other and everyone's happy
It makes sense if we typed in all the code
But if we only typed in some code
That has to be started by windows are started by some operating system will
How does it know where to start how does it actually get started
And the answer to that is basically that
The linking process
Even though it seems like we're going to finish it here in a minute
Is never actually really finished
In an executable
Unless what you're building
Is the whole operating system
If you are building a kernel
You know that runs the entire machine then and some sense you've built the entire program in Lincoln can resolve all external
And even that maybe isn't
Totally true because even in that case there is a bios in your computer and that by us has to know how to
Load something
And start executing it which is the colonel that's on the disc so you know it's complicated if you actually want to go all the way
Way down to the bottom
And open up the Russian nesting dolls all the way down to what's actually happening
In your machine when you actually turn it on
But
Assuming that you're already running a program
Like Windows that's enough free system setup
To run executable content
The question is
How does Windows actually know where to start how did they know what to even do with this file
Any answer is that executable file format
Executable jar files on your disk just like a bitmap or anything else
The executable file format is basically set up in a way that Windows understand so that I can open it and read it
And read out of it information
That tells it
Where to actually start executing
So when Windows wants to run some of your
Code if it's we can load that file into memory
Do some work on it but it needs to do
Which will talk about again
In a little bit
And then it will use information that was put in the Goodwill by the slinker in fact
Which Talbot
Where in the Bible we wanted to actually start executing sewing memory where should it actually
Jump to
To actually start executing and tell the CPU here's where the code is go running
Any answer to that
Is
The way in which we tell the Linker
Where we wanted to tell Windows where to start
Is it we use a predefined name
And we name something that name
So that I can find it in our code
Now
That's not entirely true
Because we actually could go into the Linker itself
And there are settings which we could modify that would tell it to use some other name
For example through here
But most of the time nobody actually does code that way most of the time people just use the default name
And that default name name
Is actually
Well
I'm going to stay at Twin name
I will see you in a second it's not actually women but I don't want to spoil the surprise I'm going to say this with me
And what you can actually do if you
You're not going to probably remember a lot of
The stuff that I'm saying and I and I totally respect that I don't remember all the stuff all the time
Either
I always am looking things up
Ion msdn which
If you type women into your Google search box
You will get the first hit
As this site called msdn. Microsoft.com
Which we are going to be using a lot
As we learn to program C in Windows because it is basic Repository
For all of the stuff that is Windows specific
About program
And since we're going to be putting you in this for awhile that matters to us
Because we are possibly going to have to look things up at least in the first couple weeks
Look up things that tell us how to interface with the offering
Now in here you can see
The definition
We met in the documentation for it tells us a bunch of stuff
If you are beginning c programmer you will understand none of this and that is okay
One of the things I am definitely going to do in the series is go over things many times we're going to go over things in depth
You don't have to worry about the fact that a lot of the stuff that we're going to do may not be completely understand if you understand
Able to you at the moment I will always try to explain as much as you need to know then
And then we will go into more detail later as necessary because I don't want it to bog down
I do want to get bogged down fairly often but it don't like it to bog down
And
You can also email me anytime you have a question and we will try to work those questions into future
Editions of
Web series
So
This right here
Is what it's called a function prototype
And we're going to be dealing with these a lot
But basically what it does is it
Tells you
The way in which
A particular piece of code needs
The star Texaco
And we'll get into a lot of
Stop with these later so I won't belabor the point the basically this is the predefined entry point
That we will be getting called at
When we start executing
And so if we want to Define it in RC program
We have to basically do something like this
We have to go in and Define this
Just the way that they didn't hear
And
When we Define this
The Linker will now see the symbol this win main symbol
And it will know that that is the place
That we wanted our
Are execution for Windows
Now if I go to build again and you'll see there's a there's a shortcut to a here which
Ff7 so it's good to learn this was you build programs a lot
If I build it with S7 you'll notice one of the things that happened here
Before we get into two eras
What is going to happen series
Save the file automatically I don't know if you noticed the green line to the yellow line turning green
One of the things that happens
By default in the setup for
for
For Microsoft Microsoft Visual Studio
Is it when you build something it will save files that are unsaved
That's actually something you can change here in the tools option
If you want to
I change that stuff there's there's things in here that
That affect things like that
I don't have it remember exactly where that one is I think it might be in documents
But I don't know
Build projects I have no idea where it is
You will have to hunt for it my friends because I have no idea where that actually is
But
Etsy
There it is before building
Save all changes
And you can set that other things like don't say whatever so
That's just a custom my picture liking but you will notice that is why you have to save the file
Before I go
So if I hit that 7 it feels the file and you will see
That we have gotten some errors here
And the errors are because we have started to use Windows specific thing
And windows specific things aren't defined by default
In our secret
So what we have to do is we have to bring in something sad to find
Again don't worry too much about this because we're about to discuss it in detail
I just want to finish this one process first
Before we go back here
So I have done that
And now you will see
And I suppose I will have to remove these
To also
How to put those back
Things I wanted to talk about this
I was hoping they would be allowed
So
That did a successful field but I want to break it into two parts because I can't leave these in declaration
Gyms in there
Until
If I want Taxi
So
Miss particular definition
Basically uses a bunch of words
Windows has to find them
We're going to talk a lot about how we Define those things are things later but
I wanted to display nuts
Quickly
These things are all stuff that Windows defined that are specific to Windows
They're all things that you won't probably ever actually see if you're programming in a higher-level language
I've never really programmed in C sharp
Specifically
So maybe some of the stuff still creepy
Through that's entirely possible
But a lot of higher level languages
Obscure the underlying things that are happening in the windows code
And so you never will actually see them
But when we are apart of me and see it specifically when we program in low-level see that we want to directly interfere
Face with Windows as much
Possible to avoid any sort of
Intermediaries
We will have to deal with a lot of bees
No I'll get in touch with you specifically mean in a in a bit but you will see where it's like this LPS Easter
Now what is LP sturmey what what does that mean
Even an experience
Free programmer who's never programmed in Windows before
Would not know what LPC
Mr met so it is not the fact that I haven't explained
What this definition is or how any of this stuff in this file works that is why you don't understand it if you're beginning
You got a friend
This is actually complete gobbledygook
28 experienc programmer
Who hasn't actually ever prevent windows before
Because these are things that Windows made up
They made them up
To use to reference specific things in their operating system
Which we will have to enter
Interesting
For example
Is a running program
It's something that refers to running program and LP stir
If something that is a pointer
To a string like a string of characters like some text
For example
And you will notice something that occurs in these that is kind of frustrating
These weird little H's because hey
Instance
Well that makes some sense that English right I mean
That makes no sense to use an instance of a program
Str that kind of makes me like a string Str stream MX
But like LP and age
Repeated over here
Okay pre Vincent previous since that makes sense instance that makes sense
CMD line command line I can read this evening if I don't understand anything about programming language
But these weird little things here H&amp;M LP there's are confusing
Where do they come from
The answers they come from something a long long time ago in Windows history
Called Hungarian notation
If you want to know if that's racist well it probably is it's just nobody ever
Complain about it being racist
Because most people
Aren't racist against hungarians I don't think they are not a typically
Oppressed class during Washington State
So probably no one got upset about it but to be honest with you it's pretty racist to call Hungarian notation
Call Victoria notation is because the guy who introduced it
What is Hungarian
I think it was Charleston money I don't actually know I don't remember who it was but
Hungarian notation
Is
The sort of
Antiquated at this point I hope
Notion that you should prefix everything
That you ever typed
Into a programming language
With some characters that tell you what the thing actually is
So some kind of notion of what the thing is
Key in this case was pointer
I think L was long
Meaning it was it was a pointer that was into memory in the old 16-bit days that was outside the PayPal
Cuz I mean program
Mark 16 bit Windows I don't at this point my memory of what LP stand for
Completely.
They just handle it means something that you would use to talk
Two windows
It'll take me about something and you will see these littered everywhere they are super annoying
Because they really just do not helping me make things harder to read
Cannot emphasize enough please don't do this is a terrible idea
What can I say no you will see in modern code
Some people still do a variance of this
They will do things like
IP Foo if something is a pointer to food which will talk about a Wild Bill's um Foo or something cuz I'm
Number which is if you're doing object-oriented programming which we are really cover so
Don't ever find out what that is but
You can go watch someone else's track on Ustream Belinda
Anyway
That's what these annoying things are and you can pretty much ignore the most of the time although if you know how to read it it does help you if you just had
Happened to
Try to decipher something in Windows that's
Somewhat obtuse maybe you can use that
To help yourself
So there is
Anyway
If I said I want to talk about before we get into explaining exactly what all this code does
And how see
Work sort of
At a basic level
Is these things right here
So
What you will find
If you actually look at Windows code as you will see that there's a lot of annotation in it
There's not actually designed to be processed and see necessarily but that is designed to be processed by something
Say a documentation system that also reads the same files
Or was called the middle compiler which is a thing that is used to produce
Secondary files for
Object linking and embedding and all this other windows crap
We don't care about any of that stuff but
You will see things like this
Annotate some of the functions that you call and they see what this means
In
Is it telling you what direction
The data is flowing
No it's not actually something we want to have in here when we actually Define it is
It's strictly for their header file
But when you see it when you look at them sdn you will see it there and that is what that mean
Means that this is something
That is going to Windows using pass
Into windows
As opposed to an out parameter which is something that would be passed
Out to you back from window
And we will look at those
We will see those working Mini
Things we go through
Getting a windows program
So I'm going to go in here and delete those because you don't want to leave those in
I guess I've never actually tried before to leave them in I was kind of hoping you could
Just so that you could just
So where we build we now have a successfully
Building
Program
And
What this does is this means we actually have produced
And I will file and if we want to
We can actually run the executable
So in here you can see there is build solution
But in debug in the debug
Menu
You will also see that there is a way
Play to actually run the program
Which is start debugging
And that will actually run our program
Africa
That was our program
Did you love it
I know it's right side
So nothing strange but that actually did run our program our program doesn't do anything so it just started it
And then I deleted it
But you can also see hear some debug information that was printed out
Buy the actual startup code
Which is telling us something I'm sorry but that's exactly by the butter
Wichita keep telling us some things for example
It's telling us that it loaded
Pepcid AC unit
Let's get information for it
Hey buddy some other things
Depends on
So yeah she did Runner program
Isn't that a
Well let's complete that before I slam whatever
Does
With one
Simple thing that we can actually
Morrissey
Very exciting
We are going to run this
And oh
Oh man I get there
Everything
So as you can see now the program but as I modify everyone lying to it and now it's actually prints out
As part of Its Behavior
To the debug output
It prints out of string
That we wrote
Craigslist
I know that you are all very excited I am very excited as well about this
And I think
It is safe to say
That once I explain how this works
You are so on your way to create a game with Windows
If you can print something out of the debug window
How much more work
Couldn't even be to make a game
Certainly not much
Well
Maybe it's a little
I'm sure we'll be able to
In Future rapper
So
Now that we have a working windows program
Even though it really
Very much
Let's go through and see what everything did
I'd like to start first
With the things that I typed in
But couldn't actually be called by Windows cuz it was just a sub box didn't do it I could do anything and wasn't in the format that it wanted and terms
Blinking us
What this is
Empty
Is a function death
Now hopefully most people have
Are coming from other programming languages to have a passing familiarity with
What function is
So I won't belabor the point too much
Paisley what a function is
Is it something
It's sort of a reusable piece
Summer program
It's something where I can put some code in I can I can put some stuff in that it can do
And then I can use it
Anywhere I want to
So anytime I want to basically go do the things that the function does
I can do what's called a function
Call
And I can call into it
Now without actually
Explaining
The signature quite yet
We can actually see this in action
By moving the line that printed stuff out
Into
My function that I defy
Find before now when I run
You will notice I no longer get
The printout
You know
It's not there
Too bad
How do I actually do it well
I just function called that function
And now the thing is that it does
Get done where the
Function call
You can see now
Carpenter
Seriously what function is it something that holds some code for us
In a way that we can reuse
Encoding is about
We use a lot there's a lot of stuff encoding that has to do with sort of
Building little pieces then work together to make a program
It's very very difficult
If you were to sit down and write the entire program in one function
That would be really really difficult to do
And it's a lot of reasons why you would not want to do that
Which hopefully with my parents we go on but
That is what function is and now you'll notice our function
How to draw the parts to it
The first thing it has its word void
What the word void means there's this section before the name of the function
Images fear
This section here
Tells us if the function
Returns anything
And what that means is
When this function is called by somebody when someone asks it to do the work
Does it provide anything back
Two dots
To that call or to the person who invokes it
And it's actually more ways
But you can actually have that happen than just this
This is the most basic way
What void means in C
Is basically nothing
It's like saying
I don't
Provide anything
I am not going to give you something
When you call me
So the void in front of food just says this function produces no value for its color it does not act
Chile return
Anything to the person who called me
The next part of our function decoration
You can see here
In parentheses
Is another voice
And what that is is sort of the opposite of The Return part
It's what does this function expect to get
From the person who called it
So what
Things are going to be sent
Down to this function in order to get it to do the work that it needs to do
And as you can see it also void which means nothing
This is a function that returns nothing and takes nothing
And of course
That makes perfect sense given the fact that
Outputdebugstring
Just print out of string
It doesn't need anything to do it
So
That is our function
Apps that you can see these little plus and minus is he related to collapse functions if you're trying to
So
After that
Which is basically the thing that tells us it's called the function prototype
Piper the function signature
This right here
This is called
Prototype
And what it does is based
It defines the circumstances
If you will for how the function
Just called what does it take what does it return
We then have the function body
This part right here is a function body oh and I will note
This right here
DS2 of flashes
What is something that says
I'm about to type some stuff that's just a note to myself it's a comment
It has nothing to do with the code
But if that's something
You know what to do with my thought process
SOC allows me to do that anywhere I want to
C &amp; C plus plus have to start with comments there's this kind
Which are bracketed by these little guys which is a lot like HTML a favor program HTML you know
You've got these two things
Right if you can use to enclose things and quotes
Enclosed things as a comment but doesn't actually process
So that's something that doesn't there and that basically says from here everything ignore until you see one of these
Right so can be multiple lines and all that stuff
This kind is a kind of was introduced with C++
And what that does is it says ignore them to the end of the line
Get to the end of the line
Star-Crossed
And that's just a sweetie cut down on some typing it means you didn't have to type one of these at the end
It's a little convenient
It's not really that important but you'll find it's more convenient
I just typed
So anyway that's the Prototype of my function in this is the body
The body of the function
Is what it actually exit
So when this function is invoked
This is the code that will occur
And everything in between these two curly braces
Are things that will occur
So all the codes we put in here
Will occur
On invitation
The function
Principal right
Not much to it
And you can see
You really don't need much else understand what our function actually does the code Inside the Box
Office Depot
Because all it does
Is it called another function
A function we didn't Define
Call output debug string a
And I'm going to check out the as
Anyway as you can see
When I want to call the function
Syntax actually looks something like
The Prototype
These parentheses here
Most likely to find what I was going to take
These parentheses
Contain the things
That I'm going to pass
To the function
So in this case
I didn't take anything
Equity Bank Spring
Takes a string
NC
The way that you define
A basic string
Just a simple spring
Easy book quotes
Double quotes
Anything in between the double quotes
It's part of the strain
So
This is a string that I have made
And I'm passing it to Alba TX train so that you can print it out
Apple TV screen is a function
That works
With the operating system in order to actually send stuff to our debug output
Which
Betty Buttercup Frozen Prince over here
Now we'll talk a little bit more about that although debugging services on Windows is probably not something we're going to cover into much detail
But I will talk a little bit more about how that stuff works
More in-depth after we kind of go through in are more comfortable with just basic
Sexy code
Okay
So after that function is called
You'll notice there's a semicolon
A semicolon is a weigh-in see of telling the compiler that you're finished with a particular logical line of coke
Now it's not a particularly useless piece of syntax
Not particularly useful
Pizza syntax it is a relatively useless
Pizza Center
A lot of things just don't need semicolon
In a lot of languages only semicolons once in awhile or end-of-line 2 limited license
Understatement
The beastly all doesn't see in C plus plus is what the compiler know
That the things on that line
Other things that were part
Of a logical piece of code have now concluded
And so there might be more things on here that are part of this logical line of code and we'll start to see more of those later
The base of a semicolon says that the end
And that's called a statement
One line of code like that terminate by semicolon
Because it could actually go on for longer
The End of Line actual end of the text line
Doesn't really mean anything
MC plus plus
It's not like python or languages were white-faced mean something
In general like this
Whiteface here that I use to indent
To put this thing
So I could see that was part of the function more easily
That's really my decision
She doesn't care she just doesn't care about that
Cimorelli it doesn't care about this white space
Basically the only time Serie to care about white space
Would be if you were to insert it into something it was supposed to be a single name
Whiteface does breakup name
NC and so basically output debug
String a
Would not work if I were to compile this you would see that it would say that it doesn't know what output debug is
And the reason is because I Saw the space and thought that was a complete name that it's just hard to look
And see what it means and it can't do that
Something to get rid of that and go back to where we were
So anyway that is basically
How a line of code look
NCAA
Inside function
No
Let's go down to a more complicated function over here at the one that Windows call
So if you look here it's got a whole lot of decoration on it a lot more than we have here
Got something called in the beginning that we know
That is the place
Where the return value goes where the thing that comes back from the function
His place
Miss
In this case
10th and C is a special keyword
It means editor so much like Boyd is a specialty word in seed
It tells it nothing
Isabella keyword that says an integer value
He's going to come back a number
Basically a whole number -5
Something like this
Is going to be returned
From this function
To whoever called it
Whenever they call it
Call back
Is a piece of syntactic icing
Which
Actually expands to something else entirely
It is what we call a macro in C
And we'll look at those little bit later on when I dive into this windows at age 5
And basically what it does is it expands
To some special decorations that are used
Only in Windows
Only for this particular Windows called
And it's decoration
That tells the Linker
And the compiler
The dysfunction is special
It is a function that must adhere to a special convention
Because since Windows was not compiled as part of our program and our program is not
Compile this part of windows
They will have to agree on how functions are called that makes
They will have to agree on a
And we'll talk about that little more when we start to talk about exactly how she actually generates
Access code
I think I'll probably be next
Next
Xvideo
So anyway
Put that in the back of your mind for now but suffice to say this is a special macro that we're going to look at in the future that
Tells
The compiler and the Linker
That this is a special function not like our run-of-the-mill function and then it has certain constraints that have to be met
Why does the pile
We then have the parameters to the function the things up a collar provide these are things that are being
Passenger the function that the function can use
We didn't use any recent void here
But women uses
A few
It has access
The first one is HSN
Is actually just a handle to ourselves
What it is it's basically a handle that we can use
When were talking to windows again if we should do to talk to Windows
To refer to our running program
So for example let's say we need to do something that is very window specific everyone knows their service ever going to ask the windows car
Hey we need you to do something to a running executable
We need you to tell us about the memory this using we're going to we're going to access Addie bookkeeper
Reducing stuff
And where specifically referencing
This copy our copy in memory of our executable code
That is what this handled does
Is a handle that a lot that we can pass back to Windows to refer to ourselves
Turns out you don't really need to
Actually remember this or use it for
Because most the time you can get if I back down
I will cover that way
Free Vincent you can completely ignore is Legacy thing
You will never need it in game programming is basically something
That you needed to use in older versions of Windows sometimes
In order to do things
That had to do with previous runs of your programmer things like this
Previous versions of your program that we're running in memory
This right here
Much like this string
But we created this
This is the first time you've actually printed store
Miss LP store LP command line
Is basically
What
Got sent to us
When We Were Young
No
The interesting thing about that
Is although it's called LP command line
It is referring to it as if we're going to call something from a command line
Which we have not talked about yet and you may have no idea what it is
But
I will show you briefly
What it actually is if you go into
All programs
You can go to a thing
Call accessories and in accessories
There is a command prompt
If you go to that you will get this thing
This is a command line and we will be talking about how to use it later
But what allows you to do is it allows you to run things like I can run notepad for example from it
He loves you to run things and you can pass
Stuff to them on fear that they will receive
Nekros I tried to pass that if you like I don't know what you're talking about cuz notepad doesn't
Want to hear any of that
But when you look at this you'll think of LT command line
Well
I don't need that cuz my things not going to be called from the command line and we just talked about the brave genius episode
The fact that
We're not going to be building a console application or command line application
So I don't care about that well not exactly true
If you go in here
And you open up something let's say
Notepad itself
Can I go to property
You will notice
But there's a bunch of stuff in here
Well this target line
Simon Says Target
It actually allows you to put the command line after
So it's entirely possible to shift Windows programs
Are not run from the command line it will never be no one will ever run them there
It's still take a command line
And so it's important to know that that's there
I know there's other ways to get that
We'll talk about
And finally
Anchorman show
It's basically a parameter
But just back again
To this disorder properties
I don't even know if it
Still there
I'm just going to see if it is
Vans
No
Teeth
Hotels compare
Purity
I don't know what that is
Can you list it for legacy reasons no almost no one ever uses
Best butt
There's still a drop-down that says whether you want to run a particular application minimize or maximize or just in the normal window
So that it would open
If it wasn't told to do anything specific well
That gets passed to you right
Shear n Comanche
And that is basically a number
That corresponds
To which of those things was selected and we'll look at that in
In a little more detail later it's not exciting but you know
Might as well if they're
Play me those are things that we are passing me start up and then we have another function body just like we had up here
And we call function just like this. A function in that function is our road
And it does apathy books
That is
A complete C program
With a function calling it even
But that you don't quite know everything about because there's things in here
Dinner
Define dusk
And so the question becomes
Well
You know if I was to do this
Far Western just run that
You will notice that I couldn't do it
Because it says
Who identify was not
Found
Cuz I deleted
That from my program
And
When we get to the
Welcome
I should mention weather thing
You may wonder if this point
Since there was no Foo why wasn't that a linker-error instead of a compilation error
This is the compilation there remember I said in the past the Linker is the thing
That gathers things up into one
Peace so that they can essentially be
Taken
And and made into and have their references sorted
We combined all point to each other in the proper way
You would think of that era would come then right
Why does it come drink compilation
Because it should have come at the step when people try to resolve reference as well the reason for that
Iams this is actually a good thing to bring up
I'm happy that
Better that I remember that
What are the reasons
But that happens is because C
And C plus plus are languages in which you are never allowed to use something which has not been defined yet
NC
There were looser restrictions on this
And so it some things and see would work even if you didn't
Define Minuet in C plus plus date
Titans that down they tighten the ratchet on that
So you always have to find things before they are called
Since this isn't defined it can't be called
Now that many leaves you wondering if you can't
If you can't actually
Call something unless it's
Define well how are there ever unresolved external symbols
The answer to that
Issy allows you to do what's called a forward declaration
Functions are split into two parts essentially
They are split
Into a declaration
And the definition
Now definition is the full thing
It's the full function
It has the Prototype and it's got the body so it actually is the thing that you need
If you want to run it
But you could instead make just what's called a declaration and a declaration
Looks like this
It is the first
Don't you just love the pretty green,
They're so lovely
Anyway
Inside here
We basically have the same exact stuff that we had here
But instead of it actually
Providing the body it just
Put the semicolon and ends if they still use that I'm done
Semicolon marker to say I'm not actually tell you the body
I'm just going to tell you the signature
And
Once you have that signature
You will see that I can actually build
And you will notice that now or compile error has become a link error
And the reason I care is because now it's legal to call the function during compilation
And it the compiler will just assume
That since it has all the information used to call the function which is the signature knows what it needs to pass it knows what it will get back
It just goes ahead and does
The compilation that started to
Producer call and leaves
Essentially marker that it says hey
Linker
When you find this function
Please pass it in here because I would like to call it
All right
This is quite via the laryngitis seducing
Stream I'm going to have to talk quieter
Anyway
So
We actually fully defined our funk
So we have a fully buildable program
But
Could find this function
And for that matter you to find me this stuff
You'll notice that these things in blue
They're automatically being syntax highlighted by
Visual Studio
Bee stings in blue
They are keywords they're built into the
Tyler you can actually type these in
Alongside the brackets
The semicolons the parentheses
These are part of the language
They will work anywhere they will work on any c compiler that you ever want to use
But all this stuff
Where did that come from that's not mistaken power units is not turning blue is not a keyword
I can tell you that
And neither is this guy
And we need to find that function somewhere to come from
The answer is
Vista find that phone
So we're going to get to the last line here
And then we're going to wrap it up
For tonight because I want to try to keep these two roughly an hour
And we are about an hour
So
Okay
This is a line which says
I want you to go find this
File
Is actually a file name
It could have a complete path if you want
Whatever
It could be out the full on
In anything any filename you want to put in there
Although in general
Most the time you use for its lashes even though you're on Windows because forward slashes work for includes no matter where you are
Where is backslash enjoying working windows with us
Hey play think it's a filename any phylum a drive you can include and really all it means
For all intensive purposes
Is go get this file
Inspect the entire contents of it
Right here
I'm so this essentially makes
Are very simple program
That's only a dozen or so lines long
It actually makes this a very long program
Cuz it goes and
What's this file
I should tell you how to do that
If you right click on one
And knows where to find it you can go open document and it will jump right to that file
I just got a nice
So this is Windows. 8
Which is the file that we included
Let me not look like much
It may look like a bunch of gobbledygook but relatively minor gobbledygook if not
It's absolutely massive
And the reason for that
If it's all just a bunch of more includes
That's going to include this
Right it's going to go down here
And it's going to include
This
All of these things
Right
Who knows
You got to go interpret all the crazy stuff I don't even know what it's including
And all those things include more things happening things
Have included them as well this one includes this one
So there is a huge nightmare
Amazon closes with this Alexis I don't actually needs to be open but
Anyway
Pound including this town and close Windows 8 foot pounds includes all kinds of stuff
From the operating system
Include files
And those include files are designed
To Define
A bunch of functions like these
That you used interface with Windows and a bunch of special macros
And types of other things that will get into next week
That are designed for you to be able to read
Steve information
From Windows as well
And so
That
Define this
That is hard to find
All of these things
And that is why this is a complete program
Cuz without it it would not be
Orange
No I think that's a good place to stop
Because the next step here is we're going to start to look
At exactly how this program works
I'm going to step into the Assembly Language it was actually generated
We're going to look at how linking actually works
Where talk about the C runtime Library
And
We're going to look at why I said Win Maine
With actually a little bit
Of a of a
Misdirection
Why it's not really the entry point for your program
Even though I said it was going to be
Went to the program and it sure seems to have been the end
All that
We will get to tomorrow I believe
As we
Further continue
Our introduction
2 C programming on Windows
I hope you have enjoyed this
Stream
And I am going to stop the recording now
But
I will continue to take questions
On the
On the live stream
And I will split those
Into a
A separate record