okay we are back with a Q&amp;A from day
three of the test stream which is
learned to code C on Windows and I'm
gonna go to the chat window now and I'm
going to take about 20 minutes of
questions so let's see what we've got
somebody says they teach nothing of this
in many colleges how do you feel about
the new programming workforce well you
know I am I am a grunty kind of lusty
person and so you will often hear me say
disparaging things about the workforce
or web programmers I will criticize them
in this sort of thing really that's that
is unfair of me and I know that it's
true when I say those things because
there's nothing wrong with the modern
workforce that's just totally the wrong
way to say things and I think there are
probably just as many smart people now
as there were when I learned to program
and I know there are many people who are
great programmers nowadays as well and
so I don't have any problem with the
modern workforce mostly what I have a
problem with actually is modern
conventions because a lot of these
people like you were saying they go to
college and they are very smart people
and they learn what they are exposed to
I would know nothing of any of these
things that I am teaching you if I did
not know people who knew them I was
fortunate to know experts who knew these
things and that is the only reason I
know any of these things I would never
know any of them if it weren't for those
experiences and so the thing that I
think is the real problem and one of the
reasons that I'm doing this dream is
because we just need to put this
information out there smart people who
know who understand like the importance
of performance oriented code and and
writing code that works well and is
reliable and those sorts of things they
are going to understand all of the
importance of these things of knowing
how the computer works and understand
the security implications of memory and
understanding before its implications of
memory and all those sorts of things
they're gonna understand all those
things there's programs out there that
are way smarter than I am I'm sure but
if they've never had the experience
they're gonna be very very hamstrung
there it's gonna be very limiting what
they can do and they're gonna be limited
to programming in Java abstractions that
never let them achieve the full
potential that they could be achieving
their programs will always be slower
their programs will always not be able
to do these things and that's
unfortunate and I that does upset me too
some degree because I want everyone to
be able to be as good at programmers
they can be and when they do use
abstractions I want them to be it there
I want to be their choice
what abstractions they use I want you to
be able to choose them because I choose
abstractions all the time and the reason
that I still program and see is cuz it
lets me choose the abstractions it
doesn't force them upon me and so I
think a lot of the problem these days is
that a lot of the languages the modern
languages and a lot of the modern
methodologies are just wrong they're
just bad methodologies and it's
unfortunate because a lot of these
languages add features I would want you
know I want a lot of these things even
garbage collection which I often rail
against I really hate garbage collection
I don't mind the option to have garbage
section I love to occasionally turn on
garbage collection maybe if I'm doing
something where it might have been
appropriate and it will save me some
time if I'm testing something whatever
and I just want to use it there's
nothing wrong with those things those
things are great if you know how they
work you understand what they do and
you're you're using them in a
circumstance where you know that the
pitfalls of those things will never harm
you they're great and so do I want to
see languages advance to the point we
can do all those things yes I just don't
want them to leave the old things behind
because the old things are very
important and being able to know what
the CPU does and control it is very
important so yeah I'm really excited
about John's new language too like I
said because he's starting to think
about adding some cool things to the
language but still retain all that C and
C++ stuff where you can actually write
you know with pointers and do things
like that but you want to do all right
let's see what else we got here Wow lots
of Paul success left fleet density I
couldn't agree more I don't even have a
ps4 though yet so how am I gonna stream
density I don't know I'll have to buy a
ps4 a pendo x2 the instruction pointer
memory address to get it in visual
studio Oh seriously is that all I had to
do was that this is me not knowing how
to use the memory window please tell me
that's true
please tell me that's true let's find
out if that's true Carl and oh bloom you
may have saved the day if that's true so
what am I doing here
let's see doo doo doo doo doo doo doo
doo one of the things that's a problem
is when you're doing these streams your
mind is concentrating on the explanation
and not what's going on on in the thing
so it makes it a little harder for you
to to think of stuff that that may have
gone wrong and so I really appreciate it
when people
tell me what's going on here let's see
it's that that really problem oh yes
dude thank you so much all right that is
great that is fantastic so it turns out
you can see your code that is awesome
that's such good news so it did not
prevent me from executing it that's
great
ok good good good I'll have to put a
little correction on there and just I
forgot the zero X so I guess yeah Visual
Studio just didn't know that that was
hexadecimal I guess it thought you know
when I did that oh you know what it
could be - is it because is it because I
changed the mode would it have normally
known no it's not so I don't know so I
guess you just always have to put the
zero X so it knows its hexadecimal for
some reason I thought you could just do
that yeah oh well that's great thank you
girl and Oh bloom thank you very much ok
that's great
do any schools get this right how much
will you have well I have to learn what
to do is cos I don't know chronodragon I
do not know if school got this right I
didn't go to college I've never been to
college I've set foot on a college
campus when I went to visit the
University of Washington once and and
and I guess I've been to I went to
Princeton once but yeah and I went to
MIT once so I've been to some college
campuses but I never went to school so I
don't know I don't know how bad CSA is
I'm sorry again try and do the stream
try to get this information out there
that's that's the best I can do and if
you're having a bad time with your CS
class in college I'm sorry yeah I don't
say it's nice outside my areas protists
what happens in college is I really
don't know let's see what languages do I
use for metaprogramming see I write C
programs that output C programs not a
question but has flowing tools tools
options text editor general heart count
line okay okay okay
thank you post good ism for telling me
that I'm gonna copy that off just into a
quick note here I don't want to address
that I don't want to do that right now
since we're have limited time before I
run that time for the Q&amp;A so I'm just
gonna paste that in on my laptop and I
will take care of that before next time
thank you very much
okay warning track says how big will the
adjustment be for a web programmer like
me programming web scripts involves very
little memory management compared to the
warning track it'll be a big adjustment
for you there's no lie about that
thinking about memory is a big change
but that's what the whole series is kind
of about is learning to to work that way
and so I don't think you'll have any
trouble following it because you'll
always be watching me do it so you don't
have to know how to do it first you'll
always see how I do it
so you'll be able to kind of learn just
by watching oh here's all the stuff he
does with memory and why and I think I
hope I hope people will be very
pleasantly surprised at just how little
work it actually is to manage your own
memory I think people think it's this
huge ordeal and that we're gonna spend
90% of the time doing this memory we're
gonna spend 5% of the times with memory
I'm gonna talk about it all the time in
reference to why we did certain things
certain ways but it's gonna be so simple
you'll be shocked at how simple it is to
do your own memory management all of the
people who say garbage selection in this
garbage collection that oh my god
managed memory for me reference counting
all of those things are actually very
easy to implement yourself when you need
them in the limited cases where you do
most of the time you don't it will be a
big surprise I think you will be very
pleasantly surprised at just how easy it
is it's not going to be this huge
problem now the thing that will take
more getting used to is the pointer
manipulation because I'm going to do a
bunch of stuff where I manipulate
pointers to do the rasterizer to do
rendering and that's where stuff and
that may take you a little while to get
used to but at the end of the day if
you're a web programmer you've probably
dealt with an array before something
that's indexed you know locations
indexed by a value that's sort of what
memory is right it's just locations
indexed by a value so if you understand
how to use an array you're not gonna
have that hard time following what I do
with memory it's really not gonna be
that hard so I think you'll do I think
people who've only ever done script
stuff will actually be pleasantly
surprised at how little stuff they
actually have to do that's my hope
anyway we'll see if turns out to be true
let's see how useful is it to study
cache oblivious data structures as
inspiration for domains of glia such as
then end bows trees I have absolutely no
idea to be on honest with you I have no
idea I don't even know what that means I
don't know what a van and Boas tree is
sorry if you want to send me an email I
can find coverton if you can't restrain
my guests but I would basically say if
you're if you're working with data
structures that are supposed to be
it's critical like you're really
concerned about what their performance
is gonna be then the phrase
cache-oblivious is terrifying
performance is all about cash management
nowadays all about cash management I
mean the difference between like a
memory system if you miss a cache badly
and you fail out to main memory you
could be talking about something like
two hundred four hundred instructions or
something depending on the pairing and
what you're implementing and we're
talking about instructions that that
might do sixteen multiplies in one
instruction or something the amount of
work the CPU could do in the amount of
time it takes you to fail out to main
memory is staggering nowadays it is
staggering so the concept that you would
have a cache oblivious data structure if
what you mean by that and they gonna
said I don't know what you were
referenced so maybe this is not what
cache oblivious means this kha'zix but
let me just say the kind of that you
wouldn't be aware of the cache
performance we're not care about the
cache performance of something is
terrifying now if you're doing if you're
structuring your stuff for something for
some other reason and you don't it's not
super performance critical then it may
be fine
it's certainly good idea to study data
structures in an abstract sense to
understand how they work and what their
trade-offs are in other senses like
order notation and things like that so
it's still very important but when it
comes down when you're actually talking
about something that it's in performance
critical part of your code you always
need to be aware of the cache stuff and
honestly if there's one thing that I
would say if like people ask me Casey as
a programmer what is the thing that if
you could improve your own sort of
skills at what would it be it would be
that like I am still not a great
programmer when it comes to cash
management and stuff like that because I
often do a lot of code that is not quite
as performance critical as it should
it's not quite as perfect as it should
be
I only go a certain level I'm not like
you know Jeff and Fabian the two guys
who do - now for example at rat
game tools they are like super good at
cranking it all the way down you know
like their code is is way further along
in terms of like cash management stuff
than anything I'm gonna write and so you
know I would i would probably say if i
could magically without changing the way
i code or something magically get that
knowledge boost and and have like just a
great feel for for the cache coherency
of things that that would be the thing
I'd probably add so it's always really
important
how do you meet experts I have no idea I
was extremely fortunate in that I just
happened to meet them I was interning at
Microsoft actually and I met Chris
hacker who some of you may know he is
the guy who does spy party which is a is
a very popular indie game right now you
can check it out at spy party comm I
think do I have that right let's let's
take a look at that spy party spy party
calm okay
I don't know why - so right now so this
game right here is made by a guy named
Chris hacker and I met him when I was
entering at Microsoft he actually at the
time he doesn't do that much low-level
programming nowadays cuz he's working on
it on a game and that game is more about
game design and stuff like that he's
working on a lot of other things and the
rendering and that sort of stuff he's
working on other things so he's not
working on operating system code but he
actually used to work on code that was
actually operating system stuff in
Windows at Microsoft and I met him and
he happened to be working on this is
even before Windows 95 shipped he was
working on a thing called win G which
was like the first way that games were
ever really able to run on Windows it
was to allow like fast bleeding and
stuff like that so he knew a bunch of
game development people and he was a
good low-level programmer and stuff like
that so I actually met him and I met a
bunch of people through him and if it
wasn't for that I probably wouldn't have
known a lot of these experts and you
know I'm very fortunate that I happened
to run into somebody who knew that sort
of stuff at that time and I'm very
grateful to Chris for for that sort of
introducing me to that network it's it
really made a huge difference in in my
life
programming there's no question about
that so yeah and and he chris has done a
lot of really cool things too in in his
career like he was one of the guy who
did the the incredible creature system
for spore the thing that lets you build
the creatures and all that stuff and
animate them even though it didn't know
like what the morphology the creature
was could build it yourself but it's
still allowed to animate them that was
all him so he's just done like some some
pretty cool stuff and and he's doing spy
party now so yeah you should you should
go check that out and if if you're in
the mood
you could even support him I know
there's a PayPal thing on his thing to
where you can you can buy the game and
it's it's you know it's still you know
in alpha or whatever but you can throw
him some cash
let's see in light of memory performance
do you use linked data structures ever
nowadays so yes I still do use linked
data structures and you know like I said
I am NOT the most cash optimal guy I get
things fast enough to be good and to do
what I need them to do and when I need
to optimize something maybe I will go in
there and do stuff that needs to happen
to reduce how you know to basically
reduce the cost but no I will still use
LinkedIn structures all the time because
sometimes they're more efficient for
other reasons or sometimes they're just
more more easy to use conceptually and I
know that the performance is not
important at that particular point in
time and I'd rather have its flexibility
in terms of growing things and that sort
of stuff um let's see I'm a big fan of
linear algebra will we see some uses of
it and will you show us how to use it in
graphics so lord lord eldon 1992 oh
sorry if i'm not pressing that right I'm
glad you're a big fan of linear algebra
I am also a big fan of linear algebra
it's one of the few branches of math
that I actually know a little bit about
like I said I'm not great at math linear
algebra is not that necessary for a lot
of the stuff we're gonna be doing in 2d
now I mean obviously everything is
linear algebra at some level because if
you solve more than two equations at
once which you always do you're gonna be
using linear algebra at the base level
anyway so it's a little misnomer to say
that it's not that much it is but the
real hardcore linear algebra stuff tends
to kick in in 3d most of the time so it
won't be that linear algebra intensive
in the mainstream I don't think now I
could surprise myself and paint us into
a corner where we really want some
linear algebra action going on and if
that's true then we'll bust it out but
for the most part I'm expecting that we
will be mostly like if you've got high
school trig under your belt you will be
able to understand most of the stuff we
do because you know vector and matrix
stuff at the basic level
that you need for 2d can really just be
thought of as trig most of the time and
the extent to what you need linear
algebra stuff is you know it's it's it's
linear algebra but it's it's unfair to
really even use that term because it is
not the kind of stuff you know it ain't
gonna be doing you know oh like yeah I
did the singular value decomposition of
this thing right like to me linear
algebra gets into more serious stuff and
and we will not be doing that stuff we
will not be taking the Jacobian of the
matrix we will not be doing any of the
things that I would classify as linear
algebra in the proper sense will we be
grading your own starts to replace STL
well we won't be replacing STL but we
will be using all our own data
structures Paul six will there be
network program as part of the game
probably not if we did do network
programming it would be as a as after
the game is already done basically it'd
be like oh now we're gonna add network
support to handmade here oh but I don't
want to address that early on primarily
just because I don't know how long it
will take me to program things when I
have to explain them all the time it's
hard for programmers to even ballpark
how long it takes them to finish things
when they don't have to explain them so
I don't want to add more complexity I
want to do a really great 2-d game and
show you everything you need to do that
but I don't want to start adding things
like networking and 3d support for
example I didn't want to add those until
if if anything if we were going to dress
them to address them after the game was
already done so that I could focus on
all the things you need to build a great
game at minimum and then as we want to
add things that aren't required for a
great game because we've all played
great 2d games and we've all played
great games that weren't networked so we
know that it's not necessary to have
those things to build a great game and
so I wanted to since the goal was to
teach you low-level programming and
teach you all these other things I want
to make sure you can spend a lot of time
on that and not have to spend time
teaching about like the network model
and all those sorts of things in UDP and
all that sort of stuff but you know
we'll see how this is the the series
goes if people are hungry for more after
it's all done and it's could be a long
time people so we'll see if people are
still watching the videos by the end
right you know I'm not averse to adding
those sorts of things that that's what
people would be interested in how do I
feel about a language like rust I know
nothing about rust never seen it do you
plan on reviving the Mali rocket forum
to something similar for this project I
would love to I don't know if
have time but that is a big thing on my
list of things to do so you believe me
it is something that I would like to do
I loved the Mali rocket forums and I
wish PHP BB had been better because
they'd still probably running today if
it weren't for all the spam and problems
that I was having with it what do you
think about learning to program in C
with a CL I operating system with things
like GCC and compiling manually Visual
Studio authorities are nice but I've
heard option opinions that programmers
should at least have basic experience
command-line we will be doing all the
compiling from the command line I am
only using the IDE right now because I
wanted to show people in introduction to
C on Windows and I didn't want them to
have to deal with the command line and
the separate editor yet but that is
probably something we'll get to this
weekend and the entire stream starting
Monday there will be no code editing in
Visual Studio and no compiling from
Visual Studio Visual Studio will only be
the debugger people so hold on to your
hats cache oblivious algorithms are for
taking advantage of cache close to
optimally without knowing cache sizes
okay so like yeah like I was saying
before I don't know cat what
cache-oblivious means I've never seen
that term before so if that's actually
true that they're about that then I
would say that's good because you can't
always know the size of the cache
obviously because it changes each
individual processor changes so if cache
oblivious just means don't know the size
but you're aware of the cache and you're
trying to optimize the use of it then
that's great
yes by all means you should study that
it's only it's the only thing I was
trying to say not to do is to be unaware
of the cache now I don't know very much
about the latest research in cache cache
data structures or anything like that
and I don't pretend to and one of the
things you'll hear me say a lot on this
stream is that like you know I program
the way I program I know how to do what
I do effectively but I never am an
expert in any one specific thing usually
there are a couple things that maybe I'm
an expert in but for the most part like
most of the things I just know it as
much as was necessary to do a good job
on stuff and so I don't pretend to know
what the best way to do thing is so our
cache oblivious data structure is good I
have no idea don't even know if they are
never looked at them it sounds like a
good thing to try and for things like a
PC where you can't guarantee the cache
size like you can on a console it may be
a very important way to program in the
future because if you think about it you
never know what that capsule is going to
be someone might run in something on a
machine where the cache is much smaller
than on some other machine and so if you
can find effective ways to make things
work well without knowing those
things that does sound like a pretty
good idea so yeah I would say they're
probably probably good a reddit thread
related to my question what is the
question sorry I don't know what this is
is this personal for chicken only board
the bitter truth okay so I don't have
time to read this reddit thing sorry
maybe we can look at that later send me
an email are you uploading these streams
to YouTube yes if you go to handmade
hero there's actually so if you go to
handmade hero org there is a archive
button and if you look on the archive
button all the streams are there usually
the day after they air it takes a while
for YouTube to like process the videos
and stuff but they're usually up within
a day so you can follow along the day
after pretty easily
so yeah if you just go to handmade hero
that's that's all you need handmade here
org let's see doo-doo-doo-doo
doo-doo-doo-doo what's the general plan
for growing graphics through the stream
we will be drawing the graphics the
screen using the pointers that I just
demoed this evening in fact we are going
to be writing to it by just get in the
pointer to memory and and we are going
to do that so that's that's how that
goes
we are going to do let's see we
explaining game designs while developing
in the livestream no not really
I will be sort of saying what we're
doing in the game design and why but I
won't be trying to do game design
alright it is almost 7:30 by the clock
in fact I think it just ticked over to
7:30 so I will be in fact we're down to
three only three questions so that's
excellent I think it'd be a good idea to
choose a friendly URL for the YouTube
channel before the launch okay I will
take a look at that mostly well actually
properties API design yes alright so I
think that is the end of the QA if you
have questions that were not answered
and you don't want to wait to answer
them in tomorrow night's Q&amp;A there is
also at handmade hero comm I've started
him a hero org handmade here
org there's also this email a question
button you can click on that to email
some
in so that it will be in the queue and
maybe we can sort of start using that as
a good way to queue up questions for for
q and A's thank you everyone for joining
another live stream it has been a
pleasure it was great to see you all
again and we will probably do streams on
tomorrow Saturday and Sunday normally we
will only be doing weeknights on the
main stream but for this because I'm
sort of trying to get the streaming
kinks worked out and make everything
work pretty well I will be practicing
all weekend as well so there should be
two more streams one on Saturday one on
Sunday watched the Twitter feed at
hand-made underscore hero com
I start at handmade underscore hero on
Twitter if you want to know when those
are going to be so thanks everyone for
joining and I will see you tomorrow