Start recording
Okay we are
Going
So
I have one piece of news to announce
Thanks to some people who sent me this
Because I did not know
It turns out that almost as if
They wanted to support handmade here of directly
Microsoft decided yesterday
To announce that they were releasing the professional version
Other IDE
For free
For small teams
And if you are practicing at home by yourself you are
Sort of the definition of a small team
And what that means is you do not have to use the visual Studio Express
You can actually use
Something they call the Community Edition now I
Try downloading it and it is installing in the background here
But as far as I can tell it actually is just a regular
Visual Studio
2013 and that is pretty awesome
Because that means that for the whole series proper starting Monday assuming that this works
I will be able to use the exact same version of Visual Studio as people who want to follow it home which I think is awesome
And you may wonder why I didn't just use Visual Studio Express and the reason for that is at least
In previous versions of Visual Studio Express
There was some things you couldn't do like view the registers
Spy in the register window and stuff like that just a couple things that I wanted
They were really going to help
Me to explain a couple
And so I'm really hoping that this pans out we'll see I'll play around with it a little bit
Tonight and tomorrow and we'll see and hopefully this will work out and we can all be on the
Same package so I'm pretty excited about that
And I hope they got music and totally ignore what I said yesterday about
Installing Visual Studio Express you can actually go on in and get this and if you want to get it it was really easy to find
And actually they I guess it's
Definition of a half but it's just Visual Studio
. com
And this is right here free developer
So you can go on there and you can get that and you just download it and install it and it didn't even require the little
Me creating an account thing that they required before and I don't know if it will after it's done
It didn't it didn't require that for downloads
Alright I have to learn John blows Mike discipline where he mutes whenever he drinks
For now you're going to have
Have to actually listen to
I apologize for that I just don't have the
The scales yet
That comes with being a professional
By Monday I will I will have it
Alright let's pick up
Where we left off
So I'm open up visual studio again
And I have my visual studio
Set largely because of this project
I switched it to this
I have mine set in the options
There's a thing called
Startup
And under environment
And what it says here at startup you can pick what you want to have happen I said it to load last load and solution and remember the solution
When is the thing over here
The holes all the product that you want to build
In a particular go
So I said it to that so that when I open it up we'll be right back where we
Left off
Here you are this is the code that we
Saw yesterday
And if you remember from yesterday basically what we learned
Was
That these things are called functions
They have returns which are things they provide back
The people who call them
The call
They have parameters but you think they take
That are passed in
And then I have a body which
It has stuff in it and we haven't really learned how to put anything in it
Other than just how to call function
That's it
And we also learned some of the windows minutiae
The fact that this is the entry point where Windows starts your program
And this is basically something that
Takes the contents of a file
And dumps it into your file so that you can import things
That other people have written or things that you've written yourself
Anyway that you find more convenient
So that's what we did last time but
We still have a lot to cover here because we haven't really gotten into the meat
Of how you write C code and we haven't gotten to them into the meat of how to really write Windows code
So
I guess I probably will save a lot of the windows
Stuff for Monday but I want you to leave C
Some of that some of the things that
All right
So in this particular program as we stand now we sort of left off where we were calling this Outlook debug string
A function
And when I ran the program which you can do by hitting F5 or you can go in here to the
Today
Build start debugging
It printed something out to the debug
And this was a Windows function that did that we have no idea how it works we did not implement it
I distinctly told you that if you call it
It will work
But there's a little piece at the end of it that we didn't cover unless you stayed for the Q&amp;A
Last time
And that is
That a
Is
It's her dependent to the name of the function
How to debug spring mix
What does the a mean
Well the answer to this which I will I will kind of go into the Morty town that was it
Back in the day Windows only worked
With standard ASCII string
And I'm going to show you what a standard ask me string actually isn't that some people were suggesting in the Q&amp;A yesterday
The aiq Stance
Nancy
As far as the windows nomenclature iskcon
Actually be correct
Dancing in a sphere basically
Two sides of the same coin
After use is the earlier version I believe
But you can see
If I actually searched
You know what
We've been using Chrome
Let's stick with one bro
So if you search
For asking
And it's spelled ASCII
If you search for that on the
On the internet
You will get something that looks like this and it's basically a description
Of a way to encode the letters that you would normally use
In a Roman alphabet
In order to
In a way that you can represent them with numbers
And so here's a little
You know primitive ASCII chart
If someone has made and attach the Wikipedia page
And basically what these things show you is they show you how numbers correspond
Two letters
It's a standard scheme
It shows you how that works and that's not particularly easy to read ASCII table so I'm going to try and look for an easier one to read hear this
Looks pretty good
So here you go you can see here it says ASCII value
And one of them and I don't know if I can
Blow this up a little bit
Can I make it
Any bigger
Wow
That's a browser science4you right there
Not even know what just happened
Let's see
There we go that's what really
Okay
So if you take a look at this table you can now see
That it's got a number a bunch of numbers down the side
0 1 2 3 4 5
And as it goes there all corresponding to at these early numbers
Some fairly esoteric stuff
Like the backspace key you know things that that probably would be Escape key but as you get up
Into the higher numbers you can see they start to translate the things that you would actually typed like a space
Like parentheses
The numbers
There's
The weather is here and then the lower case letters
And basically all this is is it's a way of saying
Well
In a computer
The only thing we can really deal with his numbers
And you kind of see that as we go through the series everything is always numbers
And you basically always have to boil everything down to members and so
Early on
They had to figure out a way to represent human-readable text because that's something if you just want to open all the time
Better figure out how to represent that using numbers so they did the logical thing
Which was to start
Laying out what is almost a cipher if you will a way of translating numbers to letters
Stop
I'm going to do something in the divider now
That lets you see
How this actually works
And it will uncover a lot of stuff that I'm going to teach you over the course of the neck
Hour and so it's a pretty good introduction
And when we are done with it all
You will finally see why the a has to be there
Because I will type back in
To why there's an a instead of just making it look
Like that which is what we tried to do original and if you remember just to as a refresher
If we compile it like that
We were getting an error
The error was
Cannot convert parameter 1
From Cox care to LPCwstr
We don't have any idea what that means
So we will
So
I am going to do something
The first thing
In fact that we have done in the whole series
It involves
The debugger
Actually butter
We were running our code
In the debugger
And what that actually means is that in
Instead of loading it as an excuse to build away windows are normally loaded
We're actually sort of loading our code
To run it
Under start of the offices
Of a tool that is designed to help us find
Problems with
And that is the bugger that's built into Visual Studio that is why I'm hitting start debugging
To start to bugging
Instead of
Saying something
Run
And what this allows us to do is when we run things under the departure instead of RR code just running willy-nilly and doing
Whatever it's going to do it allows us to
Inspect
How to program runs
And watch
How it works
So that we can
Figure out what it's doing wrong since you can imagine once you get into fairly complicated
Scenarios
It could be pretty difficult
To figure out what's happening in a complex program
And all you see when you try to run it is that it doesn't work
Will you need more information
So what I'm going to do
Is that something called a break
And what a breakpoint is
Is it something that says I want you to run the program
Until you hit this line of code
And when you get this line of code I want you to stop
And I want you to freeze the state of the program
All of its memory
All of the register the CPU say everything about the program
I want to freeze so I can look at it
Milk it
Okay
The way you do that is by hitting F9
And it hits a breakpoint wherever the the carrot is the
Things that you would type
Or you can click kind of over here you can see I can
Can I put this thing
And I put the Little Red Orb next to a line that has a break
That is one way
I'm sending a break point and it's a way we'll use for now we'll learn some other ways to separate
In the future
If I now do at 5 to start the bugging you will note
Okay you won't know anything until I put the AC back in because of course
Once I remove a terror and we start running program you will note
That there's a little yellow arrow and if you can see that I'm extremely little arrow that comes up
Over the line that says basically this is where the program stopped so it's exactly what I want it to it went to the
I set the breakpoint on and it stopped
Now
I'm going to
Close these windows over here
And the reason that I'm going to close them is because I don't know which of them will come up
By default for you
And so I want to show you how to get some of these windows back
In case you were sitting there at home trying to follow along and going where are those windows
So there's a couple ways to get Windows in Visual Studio
You can go to view
And you can see that there's a bunch of Windows that you could open for me
Here
I believe they no longer put the debug windows in there I think
They put them in here yet
So there's two places
There's ones that are in here under View and then there's ones that are under debug under windows
And the ones that were too concerned with Robert of bugging you're obviously the ones that are in debug
And the one that I want in particular
Is something called watch
Now what watch is
There's four of them because
You know they
Thought you needed multiple which you often do but didn't
Give you
Infinite of them I don't know why there's only
Someone got
The memo that they needed more watch windows and the only way they could forgot to do it was to make four of them
So there are four of them
We're just going to open one of them
And now here is our watch window
And what this watch window does
Is it allows us to type in
The name of something that we want to see
In here
And
It will show us what the corresponding
Value is
So what I'm going to do
If I'm just basically going to take this
String
For the moment
I'm going to take this ring and paste it and imma see if it
Nevermind
So I'm going to have to hoist this out or something I didn't quite want to talk about yet
But I will talk about it in one second
Something I can
Could do this without
It's kind of a tricky thing to go in just the right order
Alright so what I've done is I've captured the string out to a variable and I didn't want to talk about those yet
Twitter
What I'm going to do is I'm going to show you what the actual value of this string actually is
When you look at it some of these things will be confusing to you because this is like several
Steps in if you want understand everything that goes
But
What I wanted to show you was we can actually inspect the actual value
Of this string
Now even though we set our fonts big
I feel like this font
It's still too tiny and people were saying
The fonts are too tiny to see so I'm going to break
1 second
And see if I can't make that a little bigger as well
Because one of the things that the people are saying as they had trouble
Same thing so watch windows
Can I set that
To the same font
That we had
Before
Masters of alphabetical order
Unleashed themselves Liberation mono
11 point
I have to restart the application
Totally worked
Okay hopefully that's a little bit easier to see
So what I have done is I have asked
The watch window
In a way that will get a little more for my Ruth later
To show me
What this string looks like when you actually look at it numerical
And you can see here what it's done is it gone through each individual character of the string
And it has shown me the actual number
But it actually is music
Cat 410-410-5115
And if we go back to the little table there that I had out
And you know I cannot tell between these 84 is the number we've got here
And you can see 84 corresponds to capital T and hey guess what
That is exactly the first letter
That we wanted
So these things these strings
When you define them and see
What is actually doing the compiler will take
What you have typed
Inside the quotes
It is actually going to go through and eat it if it'll character will be translated into the proper
ASCII value that represents that particular
Character
Now
That's all well and good but up until the end we get to to something right here that's a little wonky
Backslash in
Now why is there a backslash in and you'll note
If I
Fight in a leftist program run to completion when we look at this line
There was no backslash in it
So what's going on there why don't we see a backslash and everything else got print
But not the backslash end
Well
The reason for that is because backslash and is actually a special code
And if we go look at
The string all the way down to where the backslash end
Actually
Curse
So you can see here
We got printed.
Which is the end of it there but then there's a 10
There's no backsplash in even in after the compilers done with it it doesn't have a backsplash in either
So it's not just a print out that doesn't have it back session what happened
What you can see now that I've I told you
But these are a sneaky code
What you should have been able to do if you want to jump the gun at home
Is you can go look at the table and figure out what that is
So let's go do that if we go here too
You will see
That it is
Right there
Data link Escape
Which
Honestly is
Not what I would have called it I would have called it
Put carriage return
15 but I guess there's
Crl you know what
I'm going to have to call weird on that
Now that I think about it
That is not what I would have expected
This is a mystery ladies and gentlemen
Why has it inserted that character
I have absolutely no idea why I did that
I would have I would have expected
What I was expecting that
I would have expected it to insert
This character and this character actual
But it did not do that
Instead in
Even for the best
Even though it is a backslash
I am I am
What's the word I'm I'm thoroughly confused
By what HS
And I'll be honest with you I have absolutely no idea why it would do that that does not make sense
I'm going to try I am actually going to
Switch temporarily
Into debugging mode for real so I can see what exactly is going on here
Been a long time since I've ever actually looked
At what happens
When you do some of these
So I'm going to
Check out these cars
So what these lawyer to do
If you are not confused by them as I just
Is when you insert a backslash
In the middle of an actual string
What does it takes the next character and uses it as a special code to Output characters that are not easy to type on a
Keyboard that don't have a direct
Assertive
What's the word for it
That is a problem right there
So
This
Tripped me up something fierce
I was looking at the Octo okay
Q
I thought I was going to have to start the very second stream of the series with like I have no idea how to program which would be very unfortunate
Play Saturn's office table is I didn't bother looking at the order so we have decimal hexadecimal and octal
What they've done is even coated the numbers in different bases
So let's ignore these right here
I guess I was just doing it instinctively correctly but then when I scroll over here I switch to reading the aqua calm because like like me
We said before we lined up to correctly with 84 I didn't read 124
Yeah I don't know
Show me this table is trying to be helpful
But including them in different encoding
So this is decimal which is base 10
The kind that we're normally used to reading it's all I really wanted to talk about
We do want to talk about Paxil hexadecimal we probably won't talk about. Too much about what's a little later
But since it came up because I got confused
I will briefly say that it is a simple way of encoding numbers a little more concisely
By making it through this base 16 instead of base 10
A little bit more about what that means you can completely ignore it for now
It was just a trip me up cuz I start looking off till which is base 8
And you can see that it Go 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 instead of using 8 it goes right to 10
Right face ate so you don't expect
Alright let's ignore that
Thankfully it did what I would have expected
What I thought it was going to originally witches insert one line fee
So if we look at the number here its 10
And untan it is line fee
Just what I would have expected
Okay so let me continue to explain what I was going to explain
That was that was a close one ladies and gentlemen
I fight I know there's going to be a lot of debugging on this
Honest honest program
But I was hoping to not have it happen
Just to insert Escape codes
So anyway
These Escape codes are basically there to put things in that we wouldn't be able to type directly and the reason that we can't type them directly is the
Because what I was trying to do when I originally typed this
Is in fact
You know I can even give you a quick little demo here let's say I was going to Output to line
So I wanted to Output
This line this is going to be Line 1
And this is where I feel I'm 0
And I want to see these two lines
It's right if I were to run that
You can see well
Try it again
If I were to run that
You do not actually see line breaks
You just see the word line 0 and the word line one but then it stops and there's no line break in between them
And the reason for that is because the debug output actually doesn't assume that the thing that you're out putting is supposed to be it
You might want to put multiple things on the same line that come from different
Cost of a function
So what actually does here is it requires us to pass it
Something that indicates that should be a new line
When we actually won new line
And so that is what the backslash and is it just been searched the character that would normally be inserted
If you were hit return how you may ask
Hit return
Right why is put the return in there cuz I can type return
Well if I try to build that you get an error which is newline in constant
And the reason that you get that error is because he actually does not allow you to use
A return character in a string
String is all have to be on one line or if they're not one line they have to be escaped in it in a special way and you can't
Never actually in bed the return character in them
It's just not something that the syntax allows
So what you actually have to do
Is you actually have to use
Decode for it and those are called Escape codes
The backslash doesn't know you may ask
How do you print out a backslash because I maybe wanted to do something like print out
Something like this
Which is like a line 0 / line one or something
That's what I want to print out
What you can see it's actually giving me a warning unrecognized character escape sequence
Because what it does anytime it seems the backslash is the compiler tries to read the next character like I said
To turn that into one of these at the characters from the table
And since it cannot do that with L because that is not something that's easy to find
She does not define backslash L2 actually map to any App Protector
It gives us a warning and said I don't know what I'm supposed to do with
So when we actually run that
You'll notice that it just gets rid of it I mean get rid of the backslash entirely cuz it did not know what it should do with it
So if I wanted to put an actual backslash
You just put your backsplash
So you could always actually get a backslash in there if you want to
It's just you have to take two of them because it's going to look at the next one
I got to do a scapegoat and so two of them is how you tell it no really
I want it back
All right
Back to our story
So
Wendy went in here
And I was looking at this
Went down to the end of it
And we looking there's a 10 at the end it freaked me out for a minute because I looked at the table expecting to find 9 feet I did not find it
But it turns out I was looking at the wrong column so
Happiness
Basically that is just one of the characters that refers to a new line and remember I saying is I said so
Insert one of these cuz I didn't quite remember which was which is not something that I ever deal with
Daily basis
But basically there's two characters
Which sort of have to do with
Advancing lines
If you will
There's 10
Which is new line
Which is a Line Feed and there's 12 which is formed
And there's also 13 miscarriage
Write this all of these
Basically there's different conventions for how things are formatted
And
13 + 10
Or actually used differently by different operating
On Windows the convention is normally
But you need a 10 and a 13
To actually create a new line
One of them goes to the next line and one of them goes back to the beginning of the line
So basically 10
Certificate printing out lines moves you down to the next line but leaves the cursor where it was if you will
And then 13 actually goes back to the beginning of the line I believe that is the order that they would actually go in
And so the way that you encode the other one
Is actually backslash bar
From this again
Please run my program
Hello
Some reason
Why have you locked me out of my program
Well
I suppose visual Studios going to crash really off and on us we might as well get used to it
Little dialogue is act
Don't know if I believe you that there is a modal-dialog active does anyone see a little dialogue
I do not
Yes
So
Basically since we're in a circumstance where we can't actually rescue
Visual studio for a cell if it's time to push it another thing on the stock
Which is what to do if Visual Studio
Totally freezes or hangs on
And let me be honest
Bissell happened to all the time
It is not exactly reliable
I mentioned control shift Escape last time we got that task manager
Ctrl shift Escape is your friend
Control shift Escape
Allows you to bring up this thing called prophecies
In which you can find
When you when you want to kill something you can find the name of the thing that's running
And force it to shut down
Which is exactly what we wanted
So if I go in here and I look I believe they called Evans now yes
Devon is the name of Visual Studio when it starts up
Microsoft Visual Studio 2008
If Deb and is misbehaving even right click on it and you can click end process tree
And if you do that
It will die
Which is exactly what we needed
So
But you can just restart it and hopefully you didn't lose
Much in the way of work
I believe we should be able to open our project and things should be saved
And they are so that's all good
And now I can get back to lesson but that is a very good thing to remember
You'll have to do it a lot
Control shift Escape
Brings it up
And then you can find them in here and you just hit end process tree
And you can restart it
So that's good
If anything pops up on you
It's a good estate
You don't have to beat them
Escape code
Just go to Waze embedding things in the strings that you couldn't normally
Only type and only thing that I was trying to say here just completing us
Is it both of these two things
The backslash are in the backsplash
Are both there
To allow you to encode your 13 and 10
Which are things that you need for new lines and the convention is
The backs are black / n
Which is 1310
That is the convention on Windows for how you end the line of the debug output doesn't require it
But for example if we were going to save these to a text file that you're going to open
It would require these
It's called crlf sometimes
Taxes are backslash type in C is 1310 and ASCII code
Etc etc
But if you were on for example Unix
Systems
You don't put the backslash are
The backslash are is actually not required on Unix systems
They use just backslash into
Actually do the whole go to the next line and return to the first character like you can almost imagine
Like a typewriter
So on Windows you did both of them
That is one of the reasons if you've ever loaded a file in Notepad
In windows that came from a Unix system
All the lion feeds are gone and stuff like this
That's because text files even though their format is pretty standard
Text files actually do differ from platform
Platform
Okay
So that's all minutiae but I wanted you to be a little comfortable with the fact that this is all numbers that really cuz it's going to lead into this artist
Going to do
I'm very happy to say
We did not
Hit a weird surprise with it with the backs at our backs I said that made me nervous for a minute
So what I'm going to do now
Is it going to move on to talking
About this outfit ebooks
And why that was actually a and then I'm going to leave this Miss careful when you're the thing we used to
Inspect because that will ducktail nicely into exactly what I wanted to talk about after that
Which was variables and
And data
Okay
If we go back to our situation here
When I
Call this apathy boxer
It is not actually going to send some pretty string to anybody right the string is just conceptual for our bed
We saw what it was internally it's all of these numbers
So what's getting passed in some sense
To the thing that's being called
I'm looking
You know
How and why things are passed
But what is actually passed is a series of numbers and no series of numbers that we seen are all based
ASCII table
That table
Is what tells
The computer essentially
All of the code that was written
What's conforming to that table so when the when the code in Windows goes to actually do stuff
With the things that were passed in it's going to translate each number
Ask if it was from that ASCII table
And
What happened was
Way back when everything in windows with a ski
Back in the 16-bit days
But then
Eventually they found because Windows internet
Product product
And the international computing
Need to start being able to represent things
Like languages like say Chinese for example which maybe has more glyphs
Then can fit
In a standard and coding
I bet you know that you would have like you know a simple encoding like asking you may have
Tens of thousands of characters potentially that you need
Coats they develop something called the Unicode
Which is a different standard
For how you encode characters and it supports a lot more things than just that simple ASCII table if you look at the Accutane
That we were looking at here you can see it only goes up to 100
I think other people are saying that but the age you're actually first to answer which is another standard I guess you know first
Dancing put a standard which is a c I believe + the dish
I think perhaps hard in there I'm not actually sure
Weather VA Center Assyrians
Totally relevant for any of the things we talked about
Point being
They think Laguna code so they could start to address markets where people want to be able to save text
In their native languages which makes a lot of sense
But in order to do that
You could no longer
Have Windows working entirely in these asking Kota string so what they did
Where's the X
Spend it
To using
And encoding
They can support a lot more characters
Emily did that
They changed all of the apis and windows to accept these new character strings they were called
Wide characters
Encoding was called utf-16
We can actually search for that
My sizing
Definitely paid off her so you can take a look at this here if you want more information on it because Wikipedia page
Utf-16 was the encoding
That they decided to use her windows and at that time I don't even know if utf-8 existed in might have
Don't quite remember exactly Plan 9 the operating system
I believe those are the guys who invented utf-8
And switch to it in there some reasons why it's a lot better than you utf-16 but
At the time when does the side to go with utf-16 which meant
That all of the characters were encoded
Differently
So
If I was to
Call the actual output debug string function
That was
For those why characters
If I was to actually compiled it
Trying to pass a string that's encoded in that format
The C compiler since the compiler knows what type of string this is
It actually tells us right off the bat
But hey guess what
You cannot actually pass this kind of string
To this particular function because it's encoded in ASCII
And I wanted something coated in those wide characters
And that's all well and good
But
You can see there's a little bit more to the puzzle than just that it's
It did just that simplex
Which essential noticed that it doesn't actually complain about Office Depot string
I called out 50 bucks
Complaint about a w
And that's a little confusing
So
What's going on there
Well the answer is because when they actually made that transition and they went
Doing the
The asking Coatings to be doing the UTSA
16 coatings
They didn't want to break all the code
It was already written
To the old API
They wanted you to be able to
Call the same function
And they want you to be able to just convert the strings
And go from there
So I don't
Really know what the rationale is necessarily behind that
I guess it's just so you would have an easier time putting your code I guess you know you just replace the string and you wouldn't have to replace all the calls
With new calls but have different names
I'm not sure but anyway what they decided to do
What they decided to actually use what's called a macro
In a macro is a way of basically
Leasing strings
NC no I'm actually going to show you that macro even though you don't quite have to understand it completely yet
Maxi shirt
To hear
You can see this little block of code here
What does block of code does
Is it basically
Says well if I'm compiling for unicode
Then I'm going to make out with d-box during the word in all the code me out 50 bucks and W but if
I am not in Unicode I'm going to make output debug string
Convert to Output debug
Hey
Hey was the thing that I call directly
So what's going on here
Well what's going on is it
When you actually create a project in Visual Studio
It's actually set
To which one of those things you wanted to use
Unicode
Or ask
And that macro when windows that it gets inserted in here that macro
Watch me do some stuff that changes
Which output debug string we will call whether or places this without book deduction a or Apple
Ww.w
The default for a project when you create it is actually to use utf-16 to use the wide character
So what did was when I did that thing remember yesterday I did that thing I said new project
When it created that product for me it's set all the settings
Which will go into a little bit but not nothing too much
It said all the settings for our project
To basically be unicode
So we end up calling effectively this
When we just type output Street Buxton.
That's what it's actually doing when it goes to compile and of course that's
Not going to accept the type of
When we want
So what I did yesterday when I kind of slightly said oh I can fix that but I'm not to talk about exactly why yet
I just changed it to output device because I don't actually need to go change all the settings of my project to be unicode
Because I know that all is going to do is do that aw switch
So what I've done is I just done the aw switch manual in the code and now every
Everything works right now I can
I can call my function
And I can have it print out what I wanted
So hopefully that makes a little bit of sense to you I realize there's a lot of information there to absorb
I will take a quick milk at but then we're going to die
Right in two more stuff hopefully this is not too much
Or too fast
Okay
So
Let's talk about what happened to you
Well obviously when you are programming
I said some things I was like oh yeah you know we call the function and we did that in here was the function and
Call Dad and then I typed a string in here and it kind of passed it but I only talk about how you pass things or
Even like what these things were when we kind of went over what they meant I didn't really say what they actually were
And so what I want to talk about now is variables
I think
John Lewis Joe King
In Twitter the other day I think he asked her on the Twister even said what's a variable
And I I was I was joking then like we're not going to get to that for a while and I was I was
Telling the truth
We didn't cover it yesterday but we're going to cover today
So basically the way computers work
Is
You are essentially always having the CPU the central processing unit the thing that you buy from Intel most
The time or sometimes
Arm these days I'm
I don't know exactly who's going to stop it
Apple or somebody like this Fab Sauron who fabarm chips
You know when your Android phone or iOS device
That's Central Processing Unit the thing that actually does the work
Inside the computer that thing
Is basically just an engine
Manipulating
Numerical values that's what it does
It sits around all day and operates on numerical values and it has a gigantic store called memory
Any of these numeric values
It pulls them inside to the processor operates on them things called registers that puts them back out to memory
And that is all it does
And we're going to talk a lot about that model and that way of thinking about things exactly what the CPU actually is doing or at least
Mostly what the CPU is doing an exceptional level
As a good way to think about most of what you're doing when you're programming but for the moment
The only reason I want to point that out
Is because
If we want actually have the CPU do stuff for us
We need to start thinking about those numerical values
Cuz all we're going to be doing everything that we type in code is just
Coming up with basically ways of telling different ways of telling the CPU to manipulate
Those numbers
In some way that we want to produce an outcome
So
NC
What we can do is weekend at anytime ask for some
Space
For a new one of these number so I talked about it
Which I said was basically number value
I can basically aspirin and which is some number value I can give it a name
So I'm going to call this
Integer
And then I can basically say
Semicolon
And that is a stand-alone
Statement that will basically say give me space
For a single numeric value
And I convinced start doing things with it that look a lot like math right I can say integer equals 5
And that will make
This name you know that I reserve here I can that will make that people
I can say integer
Equals
5 +
5 and it will actually do the math year 5
That sort of thing
I can even do integer equals integer
+ 5
If I wanted to
And I can so I can refer to it in here and the reason that I bring that one up before I go through and talk about
Please no more detail
Is because one of the interesting things that happened to me
I learn to program before I learn to Bath
I was 7 when I learn to program and I haven't really learned math yet
And I shouldn't say math because I was I knew like addition and stuff like that
But I hadn't learned
Algebra
We didn't have algebra until I was in like
Sixth grade or fifth grade or something 5th grade maybe I don't even know
But it was very very long
It was years after I learn to program that anyone ever taught me algebra
And so
I grew up thinking
The equals means assignment
Because encoding
What equals mean
Is it mean at least in C
Is equals means takes a value that's on the right hand side
And make the thing on the left hand side become equal to that value
No that's not
What it means in math
In math
Equals music with balance it means that the two things on either side are equivalent to each other so you could never write
The statement
Is completely meaningless
Integer equals integer + 5
We all know that can't be true because if you were to actually do if you know algebra if anybody out there know some algebra
You know that I can subtract integer from both sides and you would get that
And I'm sure there's some people out there who know a lot more math than I do I am not certainly math expert
You probably know some kind of
Algebra somewhere someone invented where 0 does equal five
Anderson special things you can do in the sides of our other stuff like that but that you learned
Certainly in 5th grade
You could not have 0 equal to 5 that is not going to fly
But it's okay in programming because equals doesn't mean math equals what it means is assignment
It's basically a copy
It means copy this
Over to this
So it doesn't matter what's on this side
You can refer to it just fine and hear what it will do is it will use the value
From right before that line so basically integer here
Will just mean whatever integer was back up here so in this case the last thing I did is I I made it equal to 7
Right I sent you a 7
So this line will effectively read
83 + 7 + 5 or 12
That's all that's going to do
No harm done
And so let me tell you it was really
Really hard
For me to learn algebra it took a long time for me to learn algebra because I had
No idea
See what they were
Talking about
All
When they would write this stuff up there
They would write things
We're supposed to solve a right you know
You did right stuff like you know too
2 *
A equals you know
You know a + 6
Or something like
They write that on the board and I do like
What is administered
Doesn't make any sense at all that's not you can't you can't even
You should put to tighten 2x doesn't go on the side where you talking about single
Single expression
It was it was a mess
But anyway fortunately eventually learned that there were two different equals in
I'm not going to save the day so I can do math now
I couldn't do it
Back then
So basically here are some lines that I'm going to talk about now so that we can
Get a little bit
Further in our
Discussion here I am going to use
That
That's a procedure that I said before
Where I'm going to set a breakpoint
So we can see what this code actually does
So this first line here like I said this is basically telling see that I want
Space
To basely represented number
And I'm going to use this watch window again I'm going to start now to talk about the watch with it for real and teach you how to use it
Kind of gloss over before cuz I didn't want to get into it
Anyway
So in the Watchmen know what I can do is I can type the name of any of these things
That I have reserved space for that happened to be
Around where where I'm looking
So integer
I can just type it in
And it will go figure out what the value of integer is
At the time when the program has stopped
So you can see here you have a integer equals 5 on this line but I've stopped on the line and the Wade the bug
Honeyworks is it will not actually execute the line you stop on until I ask it to it
Reese's before
The execution of the line so if the yellow arrow is on the line that means it has not actually
Did that line yet
So what you will see and this is very important
I want you to pick very close attention to this
What you will see
Is that there is a value in here that appears until we're in
The program
You can toggle back and forth
Petrini's there's a there's a little bit of a
It's little bit of a cat
Been here the time
Talk about perhaps later
Maybe maybe not
Freeway you will know that there's a value in here that appears nowhere in the program
And the reason that there's a value there their prisoner in the program is because if I simply asked for space for something
Then if I have never actually put something specific into it
Then the actual contents of it
Can be whatever they are
There is no requirement for the compiler to do anything with that value
Other than reserved space
So it could literally at this point the program
Be anything
No that's not entirely true based on the population settings that are set up
For this particular program is true
In an actual shipping executable that you would ship
It's not quite sure yet
But I'm going to save why that why that's the case
For a little bit later
So anyway suffice to say the compiler could do anything at once with that value as long as it reserved space for us
That's the only thing it's required to do
And so it can be any value and it is any value
Now
When I actually
Go through these lines
It will actually start to obey the things that we asked for and actually put the values that we told to put into that
That space now what you will notice is it stopped here I don't want to have to keep
Setting a breakpoint
You know I could celebrate point there and then run to it
Right so I could take a hit at 5 to continue running the program till the next breakpoint which is what it will do
And you can see that it is a Sci-Fi to it just like we asked and the watch window turns that
Read for you so you can see the
Change this the last
You actually
Look at the program
But
Since what you want to do into bugging very often
It's just go through the lines of code sequentially and see what they're doing while watching stuff in the Watchmen
You know Kim can actually shortcut that process by using step into
And step over
Are in the debug
She can see down here to step into and step over this also step out
We'll talk about what all those are in a second
But the one that we need right now is actually it will actually cost
You could easily
I'd only want right now is step over which is at 10
And what that says it says anytime I hit at 10
Do whatever is on the current line just do that
Nicosia
Right
Where were 7 now
Just like we wanted 5 + 2 is 7
And we've moved to next line but it did not run any further so it did not do this integer + 7 bit
Which is what we wanted now if I could have 10 again
You can see that is taken integer which was 7 and added 7 to it
Which became 14 which is exactly what we expect
Everything is half
Secure is simple math executing
MC
Very lovely
And we have now learned how to inspect the
Values
That the compiler is actually
Music about that the code is actually using when it run
Now I know this may sound strange
But actually
You will find
But there's not going to be a whole lot more to the math that we do
Then what you see right here
One of the interesting things about sea
Is it's a very low-level language which means there aren't tons and tons and tons of differ
Types you have to learn into the things you have to learn there's actually only
Very few things are dropped
And in fact
By the end of BB sessions will have touched on Moses
So
This is actually just a pretty
Yo this is not actually toy code in any in any particular way
You will see me when I'm actually go to the game I will be doing exactly this I will be doing an integer all the time
I will be doing math like this all the time and I won't
Assign 5 to Something in the sign
7th right away cuz it doesn't make very much sense
But
Basically this exact process is how we will be doing meth
Very much like this
On integers
So what I want to do now
Is just throw a couple other things
Before we
Before we go
Any further which is to sort of say
Has a little more meaning than just a number
There are in fact
Several different ways
I can say number
NC
I can say
Care
Which is something that is
I can say short
Which is something that is medium
Which is something that is large
Now there's also other kinds when we get to 64-bit programming but
At the moment rolling pretty bit so right now this is a see what we're looking at
I can also add some things to
Which
I will do
So we have
No a larger set
I'm going to
You at the end of these
So I can talk about this
And maybe
Assateague
Okay
So
Fixing what I've done is I've defined a bunch of these kind of variables just like the number I do
Fine before but I used a bunch of different keywords
When I did it
And so what do these different keyboards mean
So
Hopefully most of your
Somewhat familiar with binary but maybe you're not
So I will simply say
If you're not for me to fire you may want to go
Learn a little bit about it separately cuz I'm not going to cover it in detail
Basically computers
Always work in terms of bits
In a bit
It's a zero or
A1 it is the simplest possible thing you can pretty much do
It has two states
Basically is
Honored is off
An Indian in the actual computer in the actual see if you at selfies typically
Correspond
Actual
Electricity levels or things like this
Is actually a high-yellow or things like that
The basic computers are always operating on bits 0 and 1
And so what you like
Wonder
Is it computers always use your own one
How do they ever actually represent values like 10 or 30 or 60
Let alone 4 billion
The answer is you just start screaming that's together it's the same way that we represent things
Decimal
Intestinal we have you know 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9
Those are the actual numerals we have and when we want to represent something higher than 9
We don't invent a new symbol
What we actually do is we just
Put A1
Further over right so we say oh okay I had 9 I want to go to 10 I don't put some other value
You in here right I don't start saying it's V
What I do instead is I put a one further and I go back to zero and I start over two three four five six seven eight nine and then
And if I wrap that
I go
What exact same thing happens in binary
If I want to represent
Say the number you know
3 in binary
Well
Basically if I have zero in binary
Right that is still zero if I have one in binary
That is still one but now if I want to go to 2
I can't put in a two because there is no to so what I have to do is put a 1 in the next lot
And start over at zero again
Right so now I'm at 10
10 in binary is actually 2
So if I wants three will I screw the next number
Which is
And that keeps going so if I were to go up again just would Raptor 0 just to grab 08.21 brenau it 100
100 binary
Obviously is
Sounds like a super huge number
But it is actually just for
So
There you go you can count in binary
Sex
Sunray
So what you will quickly learn
You can start doing this
Out to more detail it is you need a lot of ones and zeros to represent the numbers you might want to represent
Back in the program
So nobody ever for the most part
Writing language is anymore where you have fundamental data types
Such as the ones were talking about like ants
Where they have fundamental types that you're going to start talking about better one bit
It's very very rare
Most of the time one but things are aggregated up into bigger things
The smallest thing that people typically talk about these days
8-bit
Together
And that is what care is
Chair is basically 8-bit
So this is
Now if you think about what 8 Bits me
Right
It basically means
That we have something that looks like this
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8
Brett
That looks like that
So it'll take you awhile if you're going to turn up
To see what the maximum number we can actually represent is here
But there's a short way to do it relatively quick way to do it if you have a calculator handy
And the answer is
If you were going to do something in decimal for example if if if you
If I said you were going to have three decimal digits
That's right so you know one decimal digit would be 0 through 9 so I could represent 10 things that way they say
Hey if I was going 2-0 through 99 that's
100 things essentially
And if I have three decimal digits are 0 through 999 which is a thousandth
What is the rule there
That we can use
To quickly determine for some number of decimals
How many there are
Well it's always the bass
Which was 10 right base 10 is the decimal system
It's always that raised to the power of the number of digits
So for example if I said three digits right and I said there were thousand things that represent wealth at 10 to 3rd power 10 x 10
10 * 10
For you to see why that is it's because
Basically if I do zero you know
I do my 0 1 2 3 4 5 thing
And I got up to 9 there were 10 things I could enumerate by counting to 9
If I then add another numeral
Right if I add to numerals
I was such a thing I had
10 possibilities here and 10 possibilities here
And I can pick any combination of those right I can I can have
La3 here and a six-year whatever one here and I here
So they multiply
Adding another decimal digit * 10 all the things you could have done
When you start it
And so
Basically raising something to the power
Carrot is a symbol used for that when you were typing because when we can't actually put a superstar
You can't even put a little superscript
Three that's how we do
That is a sin tax usually for doing power in
When you're typing an ass
Not concede
So anyway when you actually do that
With with eight things you would get to
To the 8th power that tells you what the max
And all you can do is now I happen to know
What do the 8th power is I don't blame you if you don't but if you program in low-level code
After awhile you will very quickly
Start to learn what the powers of 2 are and you can start to recite them
1 2 4 8 16 32 64 128 256 512 1024
4096 8192
And
At some point you're just like you'll stop
But
For the most part you've learned a lot of them just because they come up so often so I know that to the IS 250
So basically with 8 Bits you can represent
Different values
Now I want to say
Very clearly but that does not necessarily mean
That those values are 0-2
Right
Is that what that means
The answer is no it doesn't necessarily mean that
And the reason is because of this guy down here now you'll notice
I had two different things that both use care one was care and one was Care on the sign
What do those mean
Well what those mean is
Whether or not
I would like to represent
Negative values by default if I say care
I am talking about potentially negative values
If I say Care on side I'm only talking
About unsigned value
Unsigned values
This would be 8-bit
Unsigned
Also 200
6 values
But
This actually is 0 to 2:55
That contains
That would let me represent all the numbers from 0 to 55
This guy right here
Tell me other hands this guy
Cannot represent those
What she actually does is he ghost from -128 to 127
Anything other than that
If I try to go up to 128 it would not work
No
Can't do
Literally never have
Point being
You know
You cannot actually
We're going to use
Mathematical
So this can represent -28
And basically they both represent 2 and 36 different values
But they just represent them slightly differently because one wants it to handle negative
And one wants to handle only
Positive so you get more range
On the positive
I'll talk a little bit more about
About that later
These guys are exactly the same thing just
Borbet
So if I were to go here
50 Cent
This is 16 bit
That's a
65536 different values
Again
The power of two to six
And this guy is 32 bit
Or 4 billion
That's not quite for a billion
There's some noise in there I don't remember
Exactly that's higher powers of 2 that I can
It's roughly around 4
So
These are just ways
Of me asking
To essentially
Reserve a certain amount
Subspace right I need enough bits
To hold a particular type of value
So if I want to be able to store relatively large values I can ask
If I care that they are signed or unsigned I can specify that
If I need negative values for sample I use this one
Funny negative values
16-bit side use this one if I wanted
Jenny 8-bit
But I actually want the full range
255 and don't care about
Negative numbers that I can use this one
And that
Is really all of these do
They're setting me up to start to do things
With those
Now the math that happens on these
Obviously
Is affected by which one
So let's say for example I'm going to
Define
Mother suck here
I'm going to find a test value
I'm going to say
Test equals
And then the next thing I'm going to do
I'm say testicles 200
And the next thing I want to do
PSA test
Protect plus one
I'm just going to add it to add one
To that value
All right
Let us
Run the program I have mentioned yet
If you are in the middle if you stopped here on a line like I said in the booger
You may wonder how do I recompile my program restart
Shift at 5 so F5 runs the program shift at five stops running the program
So you can get out of that new assuming visuals
Senior housing crash
You can get out of that
Pretty quickly
Anyway
So if you get off at 5
And go and stop on this line we can now ask to inspect test
It's not initialized anything like I said cuz we didn't send it to initial value or anything
We can step over that line
We get 255
We can now step over this line and you would expect potentially to see
Which
Is what
35 + 1 is an
Boom
Exactly what we get
Everything's good right
Well
What would happen
If I go back here and I change this to a care unsigned
Now we know that only contain
8-bit
So I have said it
To essentially the maximum value
Vatican hold
When I get here
Decided to 2:55 or what we were
Expecting
But then when I try to add one to it
Game over
Be right back to zero
And the reason for that is because the way that arithmetic
Is defined on the actual CPU most
X Factor that depends on exactly what's going on in the sea
CPU there's different types of adding or saturated adzan
Wrapping a dressing like this
But the way this actually defined
On the CPU that's in this machine and the way that is Define to work
NC
Is it when you add 1 to a to a number which is already at
Highest value
Instead of
Being at the highest value which would be called a saturated
It does not do that wraps
It goes back to zero so basically it's like 0 to 2:35 and then 0 again
75 and 0 keep going at it for him so I could add one all day and I would go right back up
Go around the roundabout
No this is sometimes called an overflow
About the term that you'll see used time
It overflow is a term for when you are at the maximum value and then you wrap that value you over
Overflow over and go to the lore value overflow gets used for a number different things so
I wouldn't get too hung up on the term because
There's a lot of things I could refer to
Tell me about call back and you'll see that said
It's that overflowed value
Okay
So
What I wanted to do with this is just give you a little bit of a base
For how these things work but
And anyhow you can do math on them
That's all well and good we now can
Inspect the program we can kind of see what's going on we can see that there are real sort of boundaries to
The things that we are talking about on here at they are stored as actual bits and when we use up more bit them
We have received the effects of that
And so on the sofa
No there's something big that that I need to talk about what just how negative numbers actually work
Which is a little complicated
You notice I use an assignment for the stuff that I didn't want to deal with negative values that cuz they approximation
I'm going to hold off on that a little bit
Instead I'm going to do a little peas for tomorrow because I said we're going to do some Assembly Language tonight
And I would like to do a little bit of that
So what I want to do before we go any further with 300C
Just
Using this just the simple math
What I want to do before we go any further cuz I want to introduce you
To understanding
What is actually happening in the code because we actually have some stuff now that we could understand
So I'm going to show you
What it does and how to understand what it
And by the way this is again a big reason why I'm glad
That. Microsoft has
Released this thing this Community Edition
Because I think there's some stuff in here
That will help people
That is not necessarily
Present in
Okay
So if I stop a program on a line like I did before it was using the same old breakpoint thing I had a v I ran there
If I right click on that line
That I was on there's actually thing you can do down here called go to disassembly
If I say go to disassemble you will see that everything freaks out for second
But if I look at it closely I can see that my coat is still there
Here is the code that I've typed in but they're just all this other stuff
All lying around
Crazy right there's all sorts of crap in here
But what this crap actually is
Is this is actually a textual representation
Actual machine code
It is actually being executed
Actual processor
And believe it or not
STDs that is maybe to look at this and read this
I actually do this often
Doodlebug problems
I believe it is essential to be able to at least
Rudimentary read it
And
If you're anything like me
I think you will start to feel
What is Big sense of connection to your code that you don't ever feel any other way
When you actually understand exactly what the processor
Actually doing
Instead of just the sort of vague abstract
Symantec things that higher-level languages
Encourage you to work it
Yes those abstractions can sometimes help you get work done faster but you lose a certain connection to what's actually going on in the code
It is very unsatisfied and sometimes
Actually hampers your progress
So I wanted to get
Down and dirty very quickly and some schedule a little Assembly Language teas and then
You know tomorrow when we start talking about actual C code in a little more detail besides just
I'm going to actually start
To show you some more of what all these other
So
Let's take a look
What I want you to do if you're following along
Cuz I want to go into the debug windows
And what you're going to do is you're going to find the one that says
Register
It's this one right here
Now this is
Awful awful awful window
It is
Absolutely terrible
You can tell they spent no time on it
But what are you going to do it's the only way to really get a clean registered
To display this this and other things you can do to her
When you right-click on that you want us to this not much in there
At the moment
When you right-click on that you can actually go and you can ask her all kinds of good stuff
Messi Flags America
The flags register Alexa
Let's do everything
Alright so you can see this
Crazy window if you enable everything
He's basically representation
What's called the registers
Of the CPU
And the way I CPU works is basically as you go through
The code
That it needs to ask
It is given very simple instructions
And those are
Instructions
Basically boiled down to
Going and getting some memory
Pulling it into a register which is the thing that it can work on its inside the CPU
They can actually operate on so it's taking a little piece of memory
Put in the thing called a register
If then has commands I can operate on those registers to change the values of them
And then it will have to manage that put those registers back out to me
You got this big old huge memory for gigabyte gig 16GB government using your machine however much your machine said when you bought it
How much you stuck in there if you build it yourself
All that memory
Beasley gets pulled into the the CPU
It gets moved into registers
Which are there not very many of them it's tiny there's
8 16 32 of them something like that there's a small number of registered depending on the CPU
Where can I see Starbucks can work on those
Does values and put them back out to memory
Everything that happens to computer
Basically Works in that very simple way to the few of the things I can do but for the most part almost everything it does
Is based around just it's it's almost like this just machine
That's just sucking in memory
Spitting memory back out
And in inside she's registered at our training through it to do operations on it does this obviously very fast and operates on tons of memory
It's all going to these registers
Android modify in there
Now
What I want you to look at is I want you to look at this line of
Assembly Language right here
Basically what this is doing
Is
It is going to do our
R test equals 255
Testicles Test Plus One
Right if these are two lines of code
Going to do this
Is it legal to 55 first
And then it's going to
To try to increment that
So what you can see is
There's a number here in the assembly
What that number is is that is busy where you are in the actual code so you have to remember
Last week I explain the fact
That you essentially when you compile a program and Link it you end up with this
With the sort of file that's all the Cove inspected Windows loads that code in
Right
And
When it actually has that
Code in memory it's going to eventually point the CPU to some of it
And it's going to start executing
Right there
When it starts extra in that code I mean that code is actually somewhere in memory exist
Somewhere
In memory and this is basically telling you where in the code
You actually are is an address
In memory of the coat and we will get into what memory and addresses are in all that sort of stuff but this is basically you can almost think of it
Add a line number it's not exactly that
It's almost like a line number that tells you where in the actual code you were
There are some things that there are some reasons why you might want
But mostly we're going to look at right here
Is this
Mov
Now what is it movie
The way that machine code is printed out so that it's easy to read
Is
When is actually being a simple CPU there is no movie in the CPU
Hopefully it's actually working on binary encoded
Things that tell it what is rocks
I do but for human readability the way
Things are printed out when we ask for a disassembly which is the actual code that are
Thing is executing
What it does is it will use
Again like much like the ASCII table
Uses a table
It has been called mnemonics
Which are basically these little short hands
The best way to look at whatever the actual machine code is whatever the actual instruction is it's going executed and turn it into a human readable
For Mama for stance removed
Is it mnemonic that says
I want to move
Memory from one place to another
Got taken out again say The Voice
Anyway
Basically what it is is Mom is a command that the processor can execute
Which takes
Some value
What you can see here 0 ffh
We'll talk about that second and music
To a location
0 FSH
I wasn't going to Super get into this
Vetpoint
Where where it's probably good to start talking about it
I will I will
Mentioned briefly
How do I get to that crazy athlete a while I use the same app
Acetate overlook
Not the one
This one here we go
So when I clicked on this one before you remember I got confused cuz everything's different kinds
Well
The other kind that was in here I said hexadecimal is this
You can see hexadecimal is actually a way of basically saying
Okay
I want to represent numbers
In a more compact notation
And you can look at them here they're lined up exactly with with the decimal so 0 1 2 3
9 when you get to 10
I said I'm going to 10
You actually just go ABCDEF
Which allows you to represent 6
Steam numbers
Before you actually get to 10 its base 16 like binary was base 2 and decimals base
10 this is actually base 16 what it means that you go 0 to fnu go 10 through 100
Right which is down here and so on
Now we'll talk a little bit more about that cuz
You should probably practice that a little bit I don't want to believe in the fact that pointing at you some more compact notation
Production
And so you might ask yourself well alright
Sub-Zero ffh
What is that I'm telling you it is a hexadecimal constant
Especially
Since you probably only just
Heard me briefly
Say out what would I suppose you would never know it is thanks but if you hover over it
Visual Studio actually translate the hexadecimal value
The age of course is not part of the value best
The thing that tells you it's
Hexadecimal
FF is actually the value
So if you look at that it will translate at 5:40 to 2:55 so for now you can actually cheat and just use that but we'll talk
A little more in the future episodes that you can be more comfortable and you can actually just read these things
To be honest
It's not that important to read hexadecimal super well
Because I am terrible at reading hexadecimal
And I'm still okay at programming so it's fine
But it's good to know.
What are bases
So anyway
You can look here and you can see 55:9 you can also do some stuff you can do some experiments
In this watch window if you right-click it's got to hexadecimal display option to Nestle's pretty common use for C programmers
That's when you can see here it'll give us a thing o x
Is the notation that c uses
0h is the thing that Assembly Language uses
0 axis wait use its OCC is actually the hexadecimal
Too much about that
I don't have much too much
Too many things into your brain at once
So we'll talk about that a little bit
A few tracks
Piping
This is the 255 know you'll noticed that's what we were going to sign so the 255 is actually just a concept that appears
Herein
The Assembly Language code and what's going to do is going to move this constant
It's going to move it into the location
Specified by Tess
We're going to ignore the bike torn apart for now because I don't want to talk about pointers to next episode but
You can see when we execute this light assembly again using the f x
Step over it
You can see that it move it should be 5 and just as we asked
Remove this value to hear
Pretty simple right
Know what that was
Is that was a memory to memory move
What that means is that it never actually went into the registers that I was talking about it just went ahead and moved the 255
Which was actually in the code itself right
It move that into this light pointer but it never actually occupied a register with it and what that means is that if I go and look at my
My registers here
This is actually the printout of the registers
You will notice that that value the FF does not appear anywhere here cuz it never actually got moved in there
In
The next statement
You will see move ZX
That is actually going to move it from that location
The test location that BFF
He was actually going to move that
Intuit actual register and the reason has moving treacherous cuz it wants to add one to it
In order to actually do math on things
The process generally has to move them into register
Torso
Step over that
And now you'll see
Tax
Which was the destination register
I'm going to try to explain why it's called the ax
That is a topic for much further down the road but being that the register call Dax
And now that register
Has that value that we tried to move into it
Now we're going to do
Is we are going to add
2X
Right we are going to actually
Say we want
Anchorman
By 1
There we go and you can see it
Rap just like I said it was going to
On the fs
Because basically that was at 2:55 it has to go to the next
The next binary
Is that make sense
And then it's going to move
The result
Back into test
So sure is interesting part
That I want to just heard of leave as a tease for next time
Because all of this is obviously very confusing to anyone who hasn't
You'll notice that the one
Is still here
So when I actually have the FF right
We ended up with a hundred hexadecimal now there's no way to switch this into binary mode
So unfortunately I
Show you that but that's 256
Right if I actually go in here and ask to see
What
Holidays in hexadecimal
You'll see this 250
So we went from
FF
Which is 255
To 100 which is 256
But
Remember
That's what's supposed to happen when it was defined as an integer which can display very large values
I still have it defined
As
You know as only 8-bit slide so how you know what's going on there
This picture actually record is 256 so this next line here
Which is going to take a register and move it back into test
Beltline beer should set testicle the 256 right into
2 Chainz beat the physics I don't know what's going on
What's going on
I've no idea
You'll see when we step over
Actually you will see
That in fact if I look at test afterwards it is zero like it was supposed to be it did in fact rap
And you can see that again
But back up for you here if I go to
Disassembly and leave chest open
You can see I move
Value 55 in there as we said it would we then
Do the ad in the register which does not actually change the value of 10
And then we move it on back
Well
What actually happened there
Is
The registers in x86
And exit
51st and Vincennes
Orvis this particular register is 32 bit
You can see that even in hexadecimal has a lot of characters there right
Register happens to be 32 bit
Why
So what happens when you rap
The lower eight bits of it like that
It still is able to store that value just fine to go all the way up to 4 billion no problem
But
You're also able in Assembly Language to reference
Smaller parts of this register
You can pull out just that bottom 8 Bits right there
Which happens to be 0-0 and that
It's exactly what Al is
Al is basically the reference to eat
Which says only pull out
The bottom two bit
And you can actually see that kind of in here
The a is the important part is register a
A
Be
See
D
Right you can kind of see that there's ABCD registers
But the way that you refer to them actually if you refer to eax
Vs Al for example the way you add to that to the Peace of today
Actually tells you what portion of them like how you want them to be treated for that dick instruction
So in this case the processor didn't actually have to do any extra work
To make sure that we got the the value that we were expecting to get
By only using a pissed because it could just do the math
And I think it was 32 bits and then just take the bottom two bits of it and who cares what the rest of this value was because
We're never going to see it
Okay
So
Fire expect you to understand much of what I just said
Because we are going to go into that into a lot more detail soon but I just wanted to give you a brief
Taste of what's going on there
So you can see the even though you probably don't understand a lot of things and I said memory and I said registers and I said these things
That are are we haven't really covered in much detail so you're going to be a little confused about what they are and they're going to be kind of new to you
Even though that is probably very confusing I hope you can still follow the very basic part which is that
In this language
We have written something
Assign 255 to value
Add it to 1
Isaac we add one to it and assign it back to its
That was very understandable hopefully to most people who are watching
But I hope this secretive instructions was also relatively
Easy understand cuz there's only 4 of them
All it did was move across into something to memory move memory to register register move it back out to the memory
So hopefully
You can see that there's really not that much going on in the CPU for code in C code in C translates into relatively
Small
Code on the CPU and
I will be able to explain to you
What is Assembly Language code does
In great detail
In the next episode and you will
I think fairly comfortable with it
And throughout the whole series
What's the actual series proper starts on Monday
We are constantly going to harp
On
You know sort of
We were cussing out here to a rule which is always know what is actually happening in the machine
And a lot of people think that's really hard to do
And they also think it's very slow to understand those things
It's pretty slow to program a low-level language all these things I've actually seen things to that effect
Of course on Reddit someone posted the
Handmade hero thing
There was some snide comments to that to that effect I guess
It's really not true
There's really not that much code that gets generated from coal when you write it
And that's almost a good thing
If you're wearing something that's fast and efficient
There shouldn't be that much code generated from what you do because you should be
Doing very directly the things that you're trying to accomplish
And you can layer things on top of each other so you don't have to write things multiple time
But each individual piece that you write is actually very easy to understand
It's very simple to understand
What happened to the CPU especially for programming and see because it is a low-level language
But even when you understand the C code
You can sort of translate that's even some higher-level languages
I don't really like for them in the style of language is because I don't like all the things that they put between me and the processor
Since I happen to know what the processor typically does when I do things
I'm not even Assembly Language expert so I don't you know
The guys at rad who a lot of people who I work with at Radford sample they are way more assembly than me you know they are
Are there total assembly
People who know it in and out I know it basically because I think it's good to know and I divide things that way and I like to understand
And the performance of code through it and I like to understand what the CPU doesn't that sort of stuff
So even with just a relatively basic understanding of assembly like what I have
It's actually very easy to understand what the CPU does
When you write C code and that allows you to always be very
Closely connected
With what what the process of doing so that you
You can write
Efficient good code and you can understand what I can do bucket easily it it's just really this nice connect
What you have when you always understand what's going on and I think part of being a good programmer
Really does involve knowing
What's going on
It's it's not about writing a few lines of PHP code
And then
You have absolutely no idea what's going to happen right like
It goes through tons of layers of code that you didn't write you have no idea what they're doing
You know maybe there's bugs that maybe there security holes oh I got it slow why is it so we have no idea
All of that stuff
I find it very limiting and frustrating
And so contrary to what people say about it being tedious
We're taking too long to program
I actually find that I am very fast when I program in C
And I don't really find that there's that much of a value and using those hello languages unless literally all you want to do
She was type a few libraries together
And have them do some
Which is what a lot of people doing some of those languages
And that's fine I don't think there's anything wrong with doing that
But when I'm actually getting down to business and I want to write some serious code that doesn't cool stuff
I don't want that stuff in my way
I want to know what's going on
Everywhere
So
Hopefully that is giving you a little bit Taste of assembly and end
Next session what we're going to do is we're going to really dive into that and see exactly what all those things mean I'll explain
Binary and hexadecimal
In a little more details to understand it I will also explain
Two's complement which is how you do negative numbers
And then we'll look at this assembly again and hopefully
It will be very clear to you that time
What's going on in from then on
I will always refer back to the assembly just briefly whenever I show you something new since you never have to be worried about it
Ever again you'll just be used to it you'll just be there
And you even if you never learn to write a single line of code and assembly that's totally fine
You will still always be in power to know exactly what the CPU is doing
Whenever it's actually code on your behalf
And with that I think I have
Probably pushed a little too much for one episode
So I am going to stop there I'm going to stop the recording
And then I will read the twits
Chat starting now
So if you have questions you would like me to cover
Please go ahead and put them there
And I will cover the
Thank you very much for joining me for this
And I look forward to seeing you tomorrow and in the Q&amp;A right after this if you are still