hello everyone welcome to handmade hero
sure--we code a complete game live on
stream we here at handmade hero have
been informed by none other than
Jonathan Blow himself that Valve has
announced new heroes for dota and as you
know you can never have too many heroes
for dota apparently dota just got two
new heroes a void spirit I'm told and
something called Spitfire spin fire spin
fire snap fire and something called snap
fire I don't know what how many heroes
that brings it to but what I can tell
you is I'm sure it's not enough so I
feel like today on handmade hero what we
should really be doing what we should
really be focusing on instead of
programming our game is generating new
heroes for dota and so what I'd like to
do is just go through here and just make
a simple command-line utility we can run
anytime we need a new dota hero and that
way you know anytime valve needs to add
Heroes to their game they'll be able to
do it so let's just start with the
basics here I'll do the simplest
possible thing so I'm gonna go into the
handmade directory and I'm gonna make
like a dota directory here and we just
need a simple really simple program that
can get us started right something that
just prints stuff out and so if we go to
the like for example in our code
directory you know we have utilities
like this like we have a little HHA edit
and we have like a build that does that
so I should be able to just do something
effectively similar to that so I'm gonna
do a copy from our code directory of the
build that back into this dota directory
here just to make a little oops sorry
we're gonna I have that alias time I
work machine so I'm used to being able
to hide CP whether I'm on Linux or
Windows and so we just need to take this
build up at and
and make it so that it just builds this
one utility that we're going to want all
right so we'll start there and we'll
move out from there so I'm gonna load up
for a coder and what I'm gonna do here
is I'm just gonna load this build that
bad there's way too much stuff in here
we don't need most of this so all I'm
gonna do is just take I'm just gonna
grab a single build line oops I don't
really I want to get rid of those I'm
just gonna grab a single build line for
building one of these command line
utilities and we're just gonna use that
and in fact we really don't need most of
these compiler commands either but you
know for now I guess well we'll leave it
at that okay so let's see we've got the
HHA edit is probably the closest thing
or the HH fonts maybe maybe the HH edit
right so we really just want this is all
we really want you know what I mean
so so this should pretty much do it and
we also don't really need to we can just
build it in this directory that seems
fine too
I mean we don't really need to build it
into the build directory you know what
actually we won't think about this why
don't I just build it in the handmade
here a directory begin with I don't know
let's leave it standalone just seems
better so a lot of this stuff we
probably don't need this stuff either
but you know we'll we'll trim this down
later to something a little bit more
standard so let's delete all of this so
really all we're gonna do here is just
have a single compiled line and what I
want to do is just make it so that it's
going to compile just this dodok erosion
dot cpp or something or maybe just DOTA
hero dot cpp and so that will get us
what we actually need i suppose again i
can just cut and paste the ones of these
and then i need so really I think we're
really talking about something this
simple at the end of the day we'll just
do just a really basic compile and just
let it take care of everything for us
right that seems good so why even bother
to copy that I don't know that's because
like that's why it'll be fine so let's
go ahead and load that up doe to hero
dot cpp and this will just be a standard
like basic standard io like the
old-school way program here well we'll
just include who-knows-what from the C
runtime library god only knows what its
gonna do but you know what that's fine
and we'll just do it you know we'll do
it old school I'm still gonna want my
internal cure because I like to put
everything is internal but other than
that we'll keep keep things pretty
straightforward all right so when we
have our main function care I'm just
gonna return zero because it's always
gonna succeed when you ask for a random
dota hero you know I don't want it to
ever fail to make a new dota hero so
then that printf here I just want to say
you know this is our like dota hero
generator and you know I don't know what
the version is version one point some
stuff a beta let's say and then what I
want to do is just I want to build this
thing right I'm gonna make a little
project file for it so that for coder
just knows that it's something we can
load and build so out here I believe
I've got the project file so we've got
the things on this machine I'm just
gonna add one for this so this is I
don't know what we're calling this but
we're just gonna call this dota hero
from for the moment I guess and we'll
get it asleep at that so that's handmade
dota and this will be like dude a 0 prj
and then that's it I think we just need
a project file and then it will manage
it for us and it'll it'll all be good
again you don't really need to do that
part if you're not using for coder I'm
just doing that so I have it I can load
it quickly and switch to it quickly and
it'll automatically build it for me so I
don't have to like run it from the
command line and stuff like that ok so
if I do a dota he rode up here J that
just needs to tell it where that stuff
is and again that's just the same as
this handmade prj file like this thing
here and so again we don't really need
to give it any directories just say we
build out of this directory and load the
files from that directory and it'll
automatically load it all for us so now
we should be able to now anytime we want
to work on our dota generator in case we
don't make it as awesome as it could
possibly be today we should be able to
switch now build and it should in theory
build for
and off we go uh I don't know why it
says it there's a fatal Inc error there
what happened did I mess up the build
somehow oh is that that weird thing that
happens with four coders sometimes where
you can't wear it if you have something
inside the build like if your product is
inside the bill directly did Alan ever
fix that
I don't know cuz I don't really do that
anymore but if that's the case I will
borrow something from the old build back
because I don't want to have that bug
that that's a really bad bug and as far
as I know it's never been fixed
it's Windows for some reason like Alan
was using the the windows directory
watch so he just opens the directory and
says watch this directory and he gets
notifications that's wave knows the
files changed apparently in Windows if
you do that sometimes it fate like
people can't open the file handle it was
really weird and I looked at the code
myself it didn't look like there's
anything wrong with it it just looks
like Windows does that and I I don't
know I've never had a chance to ask
someone on the windows team what's going
on there I have I have no idea what's
going on there but it's pretty weird all
right so anyway that's fine we'll just
do it that way so now it should just
work and I think it does in here I'll
get rid of these and so now when we
build it builds into that handmade
directory I'm sorry the handmade build
directory and so we should be able to
run dota hero from there and it we
should get it now since we pretty much
just want to see what it generates for
us I'm gonna also in the batch file just
run it so in here I'm just gonna run
dota hero that eggsy right and that way
like when we run it it'll do it'll just
actually run it in there so we can just
build and see how our hero names are
going all right so that's good enough
for boilerplate we don't need anything
too fancy so what I want to do in here
is I'm just gonna run a little loop and
we're gonna generate some dota names
right so we're just gonna say look
there's a hero index I'm going to run
that to a hero account
for now we'll just hard code it to give
you let's say to hero names because
that's how many valve announces but
later on maybe we'll have it take an
argument where you can just say how many
key rows you want and that's how many
heroes you'll get because you know we're
a full-service institution here so what
we want to do here is we want to say
alright give us back a hero name please
and and and we'll go from there
so let's do that let's just do and I'm
not sure exactly how I want to do this
but I think the way I want to do it is
with a simple string with a simple
string concatenation stack so we'll
probably do something roughly along
these lines we'll just do care star get
0 name and for right now you literally
just call that so we'll say hero name
equals get here our name and then we
want to print it out so we'll say like
you know here's the first hero name like
so and normally I don't really like this
kind of string I'm a counted string kind
of person but because we're doing this
as a standalone utility that uses the C
runtime library I'm just gonna go with
the fact that we'll we'll use the
null-terminated strings because it's
unfortunately just they built that
assumption into everything
sadly all right so if we assume here
that we just say well the hero name at
the at the start we're not gonna do
actually generate a name we're just
gonna say that the hero name is like
void spirit or whatever it is right so
now what should happen tubes that's not
what we wanted it all there what just
happened there
can I type something stupid in we got
back our void spirit name we returned it
oops yes we did hero in this gotta love
those see print oh there we go
so that'll print out void spirit for its
spirit which is you know not
particularly useful so now we need to do
is we
to find a way to generate these and
we're just gonna do some simple stuff to
generate them and the first thing I want
to do is we want mmm now if we just want
to generate something random that'd be
one thing but we want to do is we want
to generate heroes that sound right that
sound like these these dota heroes right
so what I want to do first is I want to
like grab all of these words in here and
I want to start breaking them apart so
ideally I would like a list I can cut
and paste and the problem here is I
don't know if that's actually doing it
so I was kind of hoping I could find
some sort of a list that would be like
just cut and paste a bolt you know and
I'm saying um and I'm not sure it looks
like this might do the trick
like if we just kind of grab that like
this I'm thinking maybe that would help
and let me just see what that ends up
being if I paste it yeah yeah yeah so
that seems pretty good so if I just go
ahead and paste that in here right what
I want to do is take all of these pieces
right and I want to break them up into
into chunks that I can recombine and
make more of right so let's just quickly
take a look at the well quickly I mean
there's a lot of them here so and I'm
gonna be that quick but all I want to do
is start to look at these and feel okay
yeah Warriner I'm just just trying to
get a feel for what's going on here
looks like chaos and I doom dragon is
that what or is it doom and Dragon
what's the okay I don't even know that
spaces didn't get doom and dragonknight
okay there we go or a spirit or shaker
elder titan husker io Cooney cuca is it
just me or does that sound like some
kind of like a weird racial slur that
would be you know cancelled by now but I
don't know whatever a kunkka is I let's
see what else we got Magnus Mars those
are probably just single words right I'm
gonna go ahead and guess yeah and then
Night Stalker
on the night Phoenix Pudge pudges I
remember Pudge sand king slardar spirit
breaker probably yeah spirit breaker
spend tidehunter timbersaw tiny treant
protector or just Trent Trent protect or
what's a Trent I don't know but I guess
it needs protecting tusk underlord
undying wraith king okay so those are
the first sets of heroes there then
we've got let's see and time age oops
what's going on
anti-mage there we go so we got
anti-mage arc warden bloodseeker bounty
hunter Broodmother links drow ranger
ember spirit faceless void gyrocopter
juggernaut lone druid yes
luna medusa meepo meepo Marana monkey
king
morphling naga siren NYX assassin pan
goli or pan goli a I don't know if is
that the French is that the French dota
hero raised or Ricky shadow fiend I'm
guessing that's shadow fiend and not
shadow and fiend as two separate heroes
yes
slark sniper spec is it just snark and
then sniper yeah Specter templar
assassin
terrorblade troll warlord Ursa vengeful
spirit venomancer Viper and Weaver okay
so we've got
almost all of them in now we just need
this let cap it's a not so many of these
things there are okay
ancient apparition beam we've got that
rider Shen crystal maiden dark seer dark
willow isn't dark willow from Buffy the
Vampire Slayer
yes so anyway back here dazzle I assume
is a single named Kuro dazzle death
prophet disrupt or Kanchan trous enigma
grim stroke invoker hero what is that
yeah keeper of the light less rock lick
am I missing something or no that's just
a very long thing lick Lina lion
nature's prophet there we go
necrophos over Magi Oracle almost done
outward devourer puck pugna queen of
pain Rubick shadow demon shadow Shaymin
silencer gaia wrath mage storm spirit
techies tinker Vizag or visit warlock
Windrunner winter wyvern witch doctor
and zeus holy cow okay so now what I
want to do is we want to take a look and
see if we can broadly categorize these
name
I'm just gonna open up the same file but
in a different window here I want to try
and broadly categorize these names into
types like basically like patterns that
occur frequently in the like in the dota
naming convention so that we can obey
those names right and I'm gonna be
breaking apart these lists so what I
want to do first is I want to just make
I'm gonna make a separate file here for
these and just put them all in there as
strings probably and the reason I want
to do that is because when we're
generating names we may generate a dota
name that already exists like we may
generate Beastmaster and if we do we
don't want to print that out because the
point is this is supposed to generate
new dota heroes not ones that already
exists so what I want to do is I want to
make a file
I suppose in here and maybe we'll even
make this be a file that we load and so
in our dota directory I want to make a
like some kind of a text file like
existing heroes dot txt or something
like this and that existing Curos file
will have all of the current heroes in
it and we'll leave them there right and
that way we can load this file in and we
can load all of these heroes and then if
we accidentally will we'll use that list
to compare against to make sure that
we're not going to print out a hero name
that already exists right so let's just
do that as the first thing and then I'll
show you what we're gonna do for for
categorizing these so the way I'm going
to test this and we want to be able to
load these lists in and I want ways to
load these lists and easily because
we're probably going to use these lists
for lots of things right but what I want
to do here is let's just do this where
we say okay when you call get hero name
there's a little switch right and we
just say if switch equals zero
or actually let's do it equals one I'm
just gonna do a real simple thing here
where we say like okay when we get back
to this avoid this result here we're
gonna return on the second time through
dazzle mansur which is our one of our
new heroes or whatever and so what I
want to do now is make it so that when
we actually print this out you can see
like one of our things is void spirit
which is a new here actually we got an
ad that it I don't think that was added
in here was it so we need void spirit
and what was the other one
snap fire right okay so now that we have
a list of all those dota heroes what I
want to do now is make it so that we
won't print out void spirit so the first
time we call this we get void spirit the
next time we call get dazzle mansur and
we'll keep getting taoism answer so just
to test to make sure that we will have a
hard gate against ever printing out a
dota hero that actually exists I'm gonna
do that test okay so what we need here
is a way to load file lists in base like
lists of things so I'm gonna make like a
string list thing and all this is gonna
be is just a giant set of strings right
it's just gonna be a thing that has like
tons of strings in it and that's all it
is right so again C really doesn't have
great ways of doing this stuff but
that's okay this is a quick and dirty
utility I don't mind doing it crap away
right so anyway I'm just gonna have in
here a string count and then I'm gonna
have a pointer to a pointer which is the
strings and that way we can just say
that we have some way of loading one of
these things and we load it and then we
know that we can pick random things out
of it and those random things will you
know then be accessible to us so we can
we can check so if I want to make sure
that one of the hero names that comes
back is not going to be one of the ones
that's in the existing dota list I would
need some way of doing that so I would
need like you know existing heroes
equals load string list and I would need
to say
in whatever that that list is there and
in the build-up bat you can notice this
really needs to be run in our actual
data directory so we kind of want this
to do this sort of thing right we want
it to to come back to the main directory
and then run it so it'll have access to
its data files so the existing Kiros
text file we want to load that in and
then what we want to do is every time we
get one of these heroes back we want to
say if we want to do an if here right
technically I think I guess we want to
do this as a while but either way we'll
we'll figure that out it's like in fact
I can do it this way I guess like that
so basically we will just try to
generate these heroes and when we get
ones that already matched we'll skip
those we just won't print them out right
so I just want to say if string exists
in so I can just say take this existing
heroes list I don't really need the
address so if I can just do it like that
actually I could pass it it's by value
because it only has two things in it see
if this string that we get back exists
then I don't want to print it out right
like that would be bad so we want to
basically do that say if it doesn't
exist then we print it if it does exist
we skip it and this needs to be
something Curia that just returns you
know to or true or false I guess I'll
use the regular pool here just because
this is the seal of runtime library
program so I should probably stick with
their convention and not go outside of
it since we're not in the hand made hero
code base at the moment um so there's
our string list here's our string and so
all we need to do here is just loop over
these now again if we were worried about
performance we would want to do
something clever here like a hash table
ER thing we're not we've got so much
compute power to spare this is not going
to be an issue so we're totally fine to
skip that for now all right so we look
at the string index we just loop over we
know exactly how many we have because
the count is right it was right there
I may just call that just straight up
count because you're not gonna be
anything else in here
so it should just be back so we're just
gonna loop over each of these and we'll
basically say the results equals false
and we'll assume that we don't find it
then if we do we'll say result equals
true and break so we'll say if strings
are equal and I guess I could use stir
comp here I tend to not to like to do it
because it's kind of a weird function
but I'll use it for now and we'll see I
might decide not to later and pull that
out so in here we've got lists of
strings we've got our index so that's
our string comp right there and that
that'll prevent us you know the equals
zero is when it actually matches which
is kind of confusing but that's how
string comp arcs it was made for doing
ternary compares so you do less than or
greater than depending on the order
that's so you can use it for sorting so
anyway now what we need is a way to load
these things up the trouble with loading
them for us is the size limitation we
don't know how many there are going to
be until we actually until we actually
spin through the entire file so we can
make a dynamically growing set here or
who knows what we can do it depends but
I'll figure something out on the fly so
here's our load string list function and
here is the file name so that's where
you want to do it what I want to do here
is I just want to get the file open and
in this case we're gonna read it as non
binary so we want to read the file as a
text file because we're that is what it
actually is so we're gonna say all right
let's get this file in here let's loop
through all the lines if we can't get it
I'll just print a simple diagnostic
message I'll f print F to standard error
just in case those are getting routed
separately but I'll just say cannot open
this file
so that's just a thing that you know
we're printing out as a courtesy in case
one of the files is missing in the
future and we're just why isn't it
working right and that's why so the
string list will still work the program
will run but there won't be anything in
it and that won't obviously be good but
so what I probably would want to do here
also I suppose is fill it out with one
thing so maybe I'll do the count here
equals one and the strings list here is
like the error string set or something
like that and so I'm just gonna make a
little thing here which is like error
string set like this maybe so that way
if anyone if we didn't have a required
file it would just print out error
everywhere just so you could see and the
rest of them wouldn't like divide by
zero and craft because we might divide
by this number at some point and so I
don't want to ever actually have there
be a zero there in fact I might even go
so far as to say do this so that's
always you know they're always valid
right so there always has to be one
there if that makes sense and we could
also Pat it we could do that so it just
wouldn't put anything out I don't know
how we might do it but well we'll figure
it out so anyway that's all good and
what we need now is some way of actually
F reading these lines so I'm gonna just
do total cheese here again cuz I don't
care so we're just gonna do an F gets an
F gets again for those of you unfamiliar
with because we don't use the runtime
library on handmade here oh but if you
don't know what it is you can look it up
here it's pretty straightforward all
it's going to do is it's going to give
us a line of the file that's that's all
it's going to do right and so we just
want to read these a line at a time so
when we do this F gets here you have a
string a number in a stream write the
number is just how big the the buffer is
so it's literally just like this right
and then the stream is just where it's
coming from and then we put it in there
right so each time we read one of these
things out we're good we're gonna sort
of get the the next string in the file
and then for each one of these it should
tell us I think
[Music]
so there's an e off f e off will be set
what it gets to the end so in here we
can just do a while loop right we can
just do like while what does this return
an ons are going to turn the case of the
end of file indicator set the string of
set so we want wall it's not f ef we're
just gonna read we're just gonna read
lines from the file and then when we're
done we close the file and call it a day
right and that's it
so I think that's all we really need
there and then we have to figure out a
way to actually store these and that's
how we'll get data into our program so
where's our errors here syntax error
oh hold on one second there is one thing
I would like to do there's a thing that
prints like full path names in here
isn't there I don't remember exactly
what it is and call them Diagnostics I
want those
let's get those let's get those in here
and debug and stuff like that so I would
like to have this stuff probably there
we go so anyway what is the complaint
here we've got a care star arrow string
shouldn't that what's wrong with the oh
that's that's all just a semicolon look
that looks fine but the semicolon
doesn't alright so now what we need to
do is actually put something in here
besides this and so as we read these
things in what we need to do is we need
to figure out how many there are so
here's one thing we could do we could
just count and read a second time it's
the other thing we could do if we wanted
to in fact let's just do that like why
not right that seems pretty
straightforward actually so what we
could do is just say alright like hey
we'll just do this
that's how many we have I guess
seems reasonable go back to the
beginning I'm playing it pretty fast and
loose here folks and I apologize that's
just the way it is I guess uh I don't
know if if that's clear that that Effie
off there so we'll take a look at that a
second but maybe we just do it this way
count the strings allocate the memory
fill them in I could use it dining
everything growing array but I don't
know why bother I don't think I care so
this seems fine so what I could do here
is just say all right we then know how
many there are so the count equals the
expected count now or actually I guess
they're I still want the count equals
zero and every time we read it maybe
I'll do a result count plus plus there
so we'll do strings result count plus
plus equals malloc however big the
string is and then we'll copy it in
write something like that so this would
basically just say look I'm going to get
the address of the pointer that we're
putting this one into we're going to
malloc some memory for the string and
then we're just going to copy I think we
can actually do this right I think
this is actually a size key not up so
this would read one in it would tell us
how big it is
we would then allocate space for it and
copy it in I assume that would be fine I
don't really know but again I don't
really care and I don't care if there's
bugs in this program it's just made to
generate dota heroes it's not
mission-critical I would never use any
of these functions if it was so that
should be fine so let's just copy it in
there like so and that should give us
our strings hopefully right but again I
don't actually know we also need to do
that but I also don't actually know
about that effie off so we've got some
stuff we have to do there oh and one
other thing obviously I need to actually
allocate our string array so I need to
allocate space to store those strings
that's about it yeah okay
so let's actually go to bug this and get
this working and then we should be often
and running with every with all the
basic stuff we need we need a
concatenate er but that's about it
uh so let's see dota he rode eggsy let's
load it up in remedy I should have
updated my remedy oh wait I did update
my room buddy and what a what a good boy
am i let's make sure that we run it
however in the W hand-made dota
directory let's step in there let's try
to load the string list let's see how
many it thinks are there spected counts
121 okay if the memory see what we get
in our buffer that's exactly what we
want
biggest the buffer it's eight long
that's exactly what one two three four
thousand eight yep that's as F what we
want - that looks good everything looks
good here let's see what happens when
we're done I just want to take a look
now at the result and see if this looks
right it should be 121 and
these should be like some strings I
don't know why we're seeing that period
there one two three four five six seven
eight
oh the I know why it's gonna include
that backslash n so I think we probably
want to trim that so like I think we
probably want to do something like like
do the null termination ourselves so
when we after we do this mem copy I'm
just gonna trim that back so I'm gonna
get rid of those backslash ends there if
that makes sense so yeah I don't know
exactly I want to do that but maybe what
I'll do is just something like this this
is kind of wasteful but
I may even do this right here and so all
I'm doing here is just getting rid of
anything that I think is gonna come in
as part of that F read that I don't
really want right I don't want those in
there so I'm just gonna like clean that
buffer out first and you can see that
now it's actually working so now we're
preventing void spirit from coming
through and we're loading our string
lists properly right okay so step two
now we have to actually do the real work
here that was just basic stuff no no big
deal there but what we need to do here
now is we have to actually go through
and take like the the pieces of these
that look like they mean something like
that the ways that these happen to work
out we need to try and break them into
sort of component parts right and so the
first thing I want to do is let's focus
first on things that are two English
words welded together right so basically
like you're taking like a noun and a
verb and you're putting those two things
together right so because I see a lot of
that like I see a lot of that
Beastmaster brewmaster Nightstalker
you know bristleback war runner clock
well clockwork not really Earthshaker so
let's start by removing those hero names
and making those be in the generator as
ideas right so I'm going to call that
for for lack of a better term at the
outset I'm gonna call that like a
primary noun so we're gonna have a list
of these primary
nouns and the primary nouns are going to
come from specifically these sets so
like beasts and brew and I'm going to
separate the master part of that out so
meaning this will go into our secondary
list and we'll see how that goes I'm
going to make all of these the lower
case because well assuming the
capitalization will happen at the end
right
so here's war and we'll separate runner
out to the bottom right I don't know if
a bristle is technically a now because I
but it is I guess the thing on a yeah
Clockwerk is a little bit more tricky
there because I'm not sure what I guess
that is sort of the same so I'm gonna
I'm gonna treat it this way for now if
we have to pull it and do something a
little bit more fancy there and later
maybe we will but we'll just leave it
that way for now right um so again just
just break these out really straight for
just scanning the list Omni Knight is
kind of a different kind of name so I'm
gonna skip that one
for now and and we'll look at look at it
a little bit more
let's see and I'm being kind of fast and
loose with these so it's not a
hard-and-fast English rule really it's
it's more of a kind of more of a general
sort of trend they're you know I'm just
trying to I'm it's sort of a loose
criteria that roughly works right all
right um what else we got gyrocopter I'm
gonna I'm gonna give that up I'm gonna
give that a pass because it sort of
seems like it could get in there into
that set I'm gonna say those are as well
honestly just kind of clean that out
there Lancer as well not really
Mansur is already in there isn't it no
it's not
it's so crazy how many of these there
are that are this pattern though right I
mean you're seeing so many of them in
there
[Music]
not really
death profit probably if we're honest
about it it's pretty close it's pretty
close right don't know about grim stroke
that might be a bridge too far yeah I'm
gonna go with YES on that one and I
think we're almost done
I think we've got almost all of them
alright so our first way we can generate
a hero name is going to be by using
these two lists and that'll get us
started I'm gonna go ahead and open up
we have that primary noun file right so
there's there's primary noun up text and
I'm going to call this like secondary
action maybe verb something like that
and we're gonna put those in here
right
I should double-check that we can have
that we don't add things to the list
that aren't actually don't have any
length so maybe something like this yeah
I'm saying let's just get that going all
right so now what I want to do is get
these lists up and loaded um I don't
think I care about global variables here
at all so I think I'm just going to make
all of these things accessible to
everybody so I will probably just do
this and everyone can have these alright
so we're just going to load these up
right at the beginning of the program
here and that way we'll have all the
stuff in there so we can have our
primary noun text oops
and our secondary verb text file right
those should get loaded
oops I didn't actually include that
string list structure before I started
actually using it let's fix that
and now we should be able to actually
generate some hero names so what we can
do first is we just need some way of
picking a random number and then we can
just pick a random one out of each of
those lists and put them together right
so what I want to do is I want to say
okay the result is going to simply be
equal to concatenation of two things
first I want to capitalize the first
letter
right of a get primary noun and I guess
this is like just random from primary
noun something like that
so I want to capitalize the first letter
of it and then I want to confirm the
secondary verb okay and that's the most
basic rule that I can have to generate
something new and so those are the
functions I need and hopefully they are
not particularly hard to implement and
again we don't care about memory or
anything here we're just in party mode
so everything is on the table and it's
fine so we've got concat and i want to
do like a care a care b thing where we
can cat and not concatenate two strings
together and the slowest stupidest
possible way again like really really
dumb here okay
and so we're just gonna use Rand and
we're gonna mod with random acts I'm
gonna since I'm going to be calling Rand
a lot though I think what I do want to
do is have an actual function for it so
that we can replace the seer and a bunch
of the C random number generators
absolute garbage so we may want to
replace it with a real because this is
all about random generation right so we
probably want to actually have a thing
here that's like get random count or
something like that where you pass in
the counts and it gives you back a Rand
mob bat right
just this and so when we do random from
list I just want to do like a get random
count on the list counts and that's the
care star I'm going to return so the
result here is just list strings plus
that value and I return that result it
was sorry I can't see my head's in the
way there we go right to capitalize the
first thing I just need to do like if
star a so like if there is something in
there I and we don't really need to do
this probably but I just need to do like
to upper so that that thing gets
capitalized right and that's it
maybe something like that we probably
could just do that because if it was 0
to upper wouldn't do anything so we
probably don't really need to check star
a but you know I did anyway right so
here we do this result what I want to do
is I want to make it safe for you to
pass anything that you want in so I'm
going to do like if a and B we can cat
else if a we return a else if not we
return b right and I think I guess
that's just this right and so all I want
to do here is just you know take these
two strings and I want to smoosh them
together right I don't know if stir cat
will do that for me but I only care cuz
it takes 10 seconds to write so it's
fine all I want to do here is just say
all right
Ln equals sterling a beeline equals
sterling be result equals malloc Ailin
plus Pilon plus a null terminator right
result Aylan plus feelin zero that puts
the null terminator in and then I'm just
going to mem copy these two right so we
basically got into our results in the
first part we're going to put a
and into the second part we're gonna put
B right
so to upper I think is like a some kind
of a like cared dot H or something I
don't really remember what it's called
where is that remember what it's like C
type or C C type that's what it is
what's problem here oh that produces an
int not anymore it doesn't so I'm just
gonna pass this through here because
it's just gonna do it in place and it's
fine alright so as you can see we're
already sort of generating names that
are 100% dota2 since we're trying to
test it here I want to kick us up from
to right but basically like we're
already kind of done I mean those
there's no way you can tell me that like
those are not phantom doctor and life
assassin and gyro hunter are totally are
totally things that are going to be in
DotA right like there's no way there's
no way that war assassin isn't a valid
dota hero okay and we haven't even done
anything yet so we're off to a good
start right like like off we go mmm
humans aren't so creative after all are
they all right so I was going to push
this a little bit further now there's a
lot more we could do with those because
remember that we could also have a few
different rules for how these come
together even using the ones we have
already and so for example what I might
want to do is do a split on those two
words and and generate two different
types of results from it right so what I
could do is something like this I could
say like give us a switch on a random
count
what was it get random count and I'm
just gonna say give me like two
different possibilities here right so
there's one there's possibility one and
there's possibility too right
and so what I want to do here is inside
these I'm gonna have just two different
ways of concatenated the same crap
because dota does that for their heroes
they have two different ways of cata
naming the same crap right one way is to
capitalize the first name and then stick
the other one on the end of it another
way is to insert a space and capitalize
both of them right so it looks like that
now what I want to do here is I don't
want to have to sit around type in this
crap all the time so what I'm going to
do is just say well alright if you give
me multiples of this stuff I'm just
gonna stick them all together so a
concat of three things is just a concat
of the two back ones concatenated with
the final one that way i can just string
these together like a freaking party all
the time right and I can just keep on
keeping on right and all I have to do is
just do the last one
I don't know how many of these were
gonna have but that's probably enough
right there are languages I think it's
called currying there's a language
feature named for this and of course C++
didn't have it because you know why
would it have a language feature they
don't put language features in C++ so
here we go so now we can do things like
getting a space of the names now one of
the things that you'll notice is when
you look there's times when we'll come
up like timbersaw is the name of an
existing hero but we didn't match it
against our list because it's got a
space in there now right so what we
might want to do is when we do our
string exists in what we might want to
do is collapse those two strings down
first into something that will get
matched just based on the like just
based on the version that doesn't have
spaces June I'm talking about so I may
say like sort of existent like like that
and if we run here you can see we're not
randomized so we're getting at that
number five timbersaw every time what I
want to do now is I want to make sure we
don't get that so what I'm going to do
is I'm gonna compare these two strings
to my own string compare but that string
compare is gonna be based on the the
versions that don't have spaces right so
what I'm going to do is going to start
with two pointers a and B and what I'm
gonna do here is say that we're gonna
loop through them
so while star a and star B right
what I want to do is skip any spaces so
while star a oops and star a or a zero
is not equal to space I'm sorry is equal
to space
actually I suppose that does itself
right that's all we need
so while a is a space skip it while B is
a space skip it so we're just skipping
over right we're just gonna skip over
the spaces wherever they should occur if
a is not equal to B then we so I'm gonna
assume true
let me start I'm gonna say assume they
match right oh sorry
so assume they match the outset loop
through here if they're ever not equal I
assumed that they've failed right and we
break out of this loop if the result is
ever true then we break out of the loop
and return right it's a little bit
squeaky but I think that's basically
what we want now I want this here to do
a to lower on these guys so that also if
we capitalize something and they didn't
or whatever we're not going to consider
that similar and these are on the we go
there we go
I may have accidentally created an
infinite loop there though I just
realized I didn't put the plus plus in
there that's my bad sorry infinite loop
yeah I know where that is
there it is okay all right so each time
through here we have to increment our a
and B which I forgot to do right all
right so thankfully now we got rid of
our timbersaw which is all I really
wanted to do there but as you can see
we're still also always generating the
exact same hero's what you don't really
want to do so I would like to do an SRAM
time or something here like you know so
that we're gonna get different ones I
don't remember is it clock there's an
easier way to do this I don't remember
exactly what it is but I would like to
go ahead and close this
I would like to go ahead and have a good
way to s R and just to seed the random
number or something time no that's what
they do
so that's time dot H and that means you
know as we run it it'll just change over
time unsigned int is that really a
problem so what's a time T these days so
I think I probably just have to cast it
and I'll be fine okay WindSeeker is
excellent be stranger war stealer timber
master it's very good alright so
something weird happened here
why is war stealer inter caps did ice I
screwed something up didn't I
somehow whoops so what happened there
why why did I how did how did that
happen like that shouldn't be possible
right it should only capitalize when
when we insert a space it should never
capitalized when we don't
and all of these are lowercase right so
how are we how did it do that um hold on
a second
if I don't s ran do I get one of those
gyro answer number eight does that so I
want to take a look at what happens on
number eight there because I I obviously
screwed something up and I just want to
fix that real quick before we put in
some more rules and some more words
right um so okay in here what I'm going
to do is I just want to skip to number
eight which is actually number seven in
our case so I want to go till the hero
index is there which is right like that
and we'll skip in here so let's see
where we go we return a random value and
we end up in this case where we do a
concat on these two so I'm gonna just
let this thing get its results back I
don't know what those results are so it
got you'd actually got back Oh duh I'm
not copying those stupid me so I need to
actually copy those when we do
capitalize first I should actually copy
them because I'm modifying it I actually
just returned it directly that was
pretty stupid actually so my bad we
should just have a clone here right
so in this case all I'm gonna do is just
say okay Len equals sterling a I'm also
do the whole nine here and I don't
really need to be defensive here but I'm
going to anyway
just cuz and this is basically the stir
copy
routine or something it's a C runtime
live every team that does but I don't
like using this new runtime I worry when
I can just write it myself most of time
because I who knows what they're doing
in there right so we say it's always a a
gigantic mess so I'm just going to
allocate this guy and do the mem copy in
and try not to make order my parameters
wrong okay so I think we're good now
I'm gonna turn my s R and on again just
for for fun and looks good right
bop clock hunter blood hunter so
what I would like to do here is there
are a few things like verk that maybe
shouldn't appear as separate last
sections so in that secondary verb list
we've got some things that maybe
shouldn't be there like mansur and
lancer and stuff so i'm gonna separate
those out into a slightly different one
so i'm gonna do secondary suffix or
something like that and all I'm doing
here is just picking out ones that I
don't want placed as a separate second
word right copter probably back
writer Lancer and man sir so I think
that's good right okay so I think that's
fine and then inside the dota hero thing
I'm gonna add that tubes I'm gonna add
that to our list so in here we're gonna
have string list secondary suffix I
might label what these are I'm so like
all right um and so this here the
secondary verb should maybe just be
verbs and we should separate secondary
nouns as well so that might be it to do
on the list a little bit later but for
the moment I'm just I'm not being - like
I said it's it's pretty loose because
the dota names are kind of ridiculous so
you know if we call them something
ridiculous if anything it's like it's
good that we did that not bad right
um so I'm gonna go ahead and put that on
there right and so now we won't see
those but I want those to be on there so
what I want to do now is in my list here
where we do random from secondary verb
so in here where we were doing the
concat with a space I don't want that
but what in here I want to say you can
grab from secondary verb or from you can
grab from secondary verb or you can grab
from secondary NAT suffix right so I
want something like this so you can
merge those two together right um
and so what I'm gonna do here is I'm
going to say let's suppose that we can
look across many of these lists if we
need to and and merge them together and
so that way we can kind of create random
numbers that are that are going to be
spanning more than one set I don't
really know whether I will want the
random to pick which one of those is
going to do and
then pick or whether I want to pick
across the set that's a hard decision
right I don't really know because you
could see here what if we did something
more like this like get secondary verb
or suffix right something like that or
maybe we just call this like a secondary
ending right and what that does is it
did it said look give me a give me a
random case here and what I want you to
do is decide either use secondary verb
or use secondary suffix and so then what
we can do is then if we know we can do
any it's like any secondary ending is a
thing that we that we want right and off
we go
okay so now we should see those like
anytime we're using something that that
has a concatenation like here we get
tide copter right but we should never
see copter on its own on the outside and
that's all that was designed to prevent
right okay so now let's add another type
of dota pattern in right so here what
I'd like to do is say when we have a sec
when we have a separate secondary word
there I'm gonna say that there's a set
of things that can happen on that
outside right so so we've got secondary
verb let's make secondary noun as a
thing right so secondary noun patterns
are ones like king or something like
that right and writer would actually
should have been one of those
potentially but I don't know things that
could get stuck on the end I don't know
how we want to treat this exactly but
we'll see so secondary noun will add
these things in there that we're
supposed to be and we'll put chaos and
dragon in those so we'll take those
names and we'll split those out into our
primary noun list and off we go right
okay so I'm gonna go get that primary
noun list back and what I want to do
here is just grab all of these it come
out how did Earthshaker not make it into
that list I don't know
right but I'm gonna grab all of these
and all of those folks are coming in
there right
- shoes we're gonna have to look at a
little bit separately there's a lot of
these we're gonna up our dota abilities
considerably here I think a vengeful
spirit
sorry that's technically not one because
vengeful spirit is that's not a noun at
the beginning eventual as a descriptor
right so I suppose like lone druid and
vengeful spirit really shouldn't
shouldn't be in there because those are
not nouns
those are descriptors and we want to
handle those a little bit separately
right so I just want to be careful there
let's see Outworld devourer really is
one of those ones that should have a
secondary thing we'll look at that one
in a second as well I think Shadow Demon
and Shadow shame info on that category
sort of storm skywrath mage i guess cuz
i skywrath i think i want to handle
skywrath separately so we'll we'll make
that be a separate thing yeah so I think
that's good
alright so I want to create a new one
here which is the secondary mound right
and secondary nouns are things that
should only go in that second position
right and we don't know that like we may
find that we actually just allow all
nouns to go into any slot and that's
better but for now I'm going to keep it
the way dota kept it right just to keep
with their naming convention for now
right
so I actually also want to put shaker in
here I don't know how we missed it but
we just we did so in secondary noun
we've got night already
we need Titan commander oops
stalker breaker protector king warden
void spirit sorry there fiend assassin
warlord maiden demon
Shaymin and wyvern all right
now all of these are things that can
just loop right into our primary noun
list right I and what I'd like to do now
is just incorporate now if we run it
we'll get some bonus because we've got
some new fake flip doctor okay
did I like I should put spaces on that
denied ah yeah so I've got some spaces
in there which I should probably trim
those because those will end up putting
in some extra yeah so that I was like
that shouldn't have had a space and in
that one if it didn't yeah
oops okay let's try one more time okay
so here we got a bounty back we got the
Kaos assassin
we've got winged capture some of these
probably should be we should require
spaces between them I don't know how
we're gonna do that because I'm not sure
what the rule really should be but left
to look at that but anyway crystal
mother bat mother very good heroes
obviously venom hunter spirit man sword
Rowell answer very good these are all
timber shakers clearly an excellent hero
a life back I don't know about that one
but wind copter certainly I mean
obviously but anyway we need to put
these in here now so those are secondary
nouns are now need to be incorporated
into the generator as an idea because we
don't have we're loading the secondary
nouns I think or are we we're not even
loading the secondary now so we need to
load them in and then we need to use
them for something right so we need
secondary nouns oh there it is I put
them there
so did I actually load that list yeah we
did so we have a second as loaded they
just never get used for anything and so
what I want to do here is where we do
this secondary verb I want to also have
secondary noun right so much like we had
get secondary ending I want to have get
secondary word as a thing or I should
say get final word so it's a word that
ends the thing so it can be one of these
secondary suffixes or it could be one of
these secondary nouns right and so
that's going to be our get final word
call and we'll do that here okay so now
we should get some of those yeah like a
venom Shaymin we couldn't have had
before now we can have a venom Shaymin
we can also have a crystal Titan
couldn't have that before we can have it
now right
alright so we've got some good stuff in
there
and we're definitely improving our dota
heroes but what you'll notice is we
still there's still some obvious
restrictions here because dota has two
things
at least that we don't have at all right
now like you wouldn't a monkey king how
do we miss monkey king don't know how
that happened
anyway so dota has some things that are
that are that we don't really do yet
right and first of all they're ones that
are like there's some of these things
like queen of pain keeper of the light
those are rarer or nature's like
apostrophe s right we don't really have
that concept in there but those are
pretty few and far between so if we
never generated one of those no we would
probably bat an eyelash because there's
very few of them right but what you will
notice is there's a lot of like single
word sorts of things in here and we
don't have any chance of generating
those and there's a lot of those so
someone might look askance at our at our
system for not having some of those and
so what I'd like to do is try to come up
with a strategy for generating some dota
sounding short words like that and
that's gonna be the hardest part I think
of our program because this part so far
was a cakewalk right it's not very hard
to generate things that sound like dota
names so I think we'll pass that test
with flying colors so what I'm going to
do is I'm just gonna separate these out
here and what we're gonna start to do is
we're gonna look at these these are
words we're gonna attack a little bit
separately because they're closer to
what we've already been doing and we
just need a little bit of upgrades to
handle names like that but what I want
to look at now is words like these where
they're kind of a little bit more small
simple syllable words right so I want to
try in and get some of these together
let's look at these so let's try to make
ones that are sort of nonsense words you
know that feel a little bit like
nonsense words anyway and maybe we can
try to get some of the
somehow right
terrorblade is actually one that we can
handle this way but let's keep looking
here so just trying to grab some here
that that feel like the kinds of things
we could do probably just looking at how
they tend to make these names you know
so like so I guess what I would say is
like there doesn't seem to be a lot I
can really I can really get from those
so the problem that I see with this
right is just that I I need a way of
generating nonsense words like slardar
that sound like they're from dota but
I'm not sure what the actual thing is
that make something sound like it's from
dota
I'm gonna go out on a limb here and see
if I can literally just not do anything
and have it work
so I'm gonna do the following and this
is I am just pulling this out pulling it
straight out of the posterior here my
friends so I'm gonna break these into
pieces that I would call sort of like
consonant-vowel if you will
oops that was not what I wanted
consonant vowel dot text and all I'm
going to do here is try to pull out of
this list the consonant vowel chunks
that I think are interesting so for
example na JA ki ro ha go slow
[Music]
Klee Lee and right you can see what I'm
doing here right
we already got no no we don't nee J me
and we've got key so we just need
reading their flaws already in there
oh it's not me Ron nah me nah nas in
there
I don't think rah is it's not um we'll
stuck stick a ba in there for good
measure a lay in there for good measure
Pro a foe oops
Allie's there
nos there too
ra's there stay there
no and cause they're right that's not
all right so what I've done is I've
broken the sill up there like the
syllabary right of these names in DotA
and I've kind of like just kind of
gotten their nonsense names split up a
little bit so those are consonant vowel
sounds and then these are just going to
be like raw vowel sounds right and
there's and I guess dawn would be one
maybe and we'll leave with that and so
these are just gonna be raw bowel sounds
so are maybe RR n KN kz
there's sort of ones that are foul like
ER and I don't really know what I want
to do about those so we'll take a look
at those later but we'll just leave
these in there as sort of more raw
sounds so I'm gonna make another file
called consonant only and this now we're
gonna have to start to try and work out
how this will happen and and this is
again I'm gonna be tough these are this
will be the toughest part of this
program for sure if we can manage to get
something I don't have a lot of time
left but we'll see how we do so alright
so this is for our nonsense names so
we've got consonant vowel and just
consonant and if we go into dota hero
I'm just gonna put those in here
maybe spelling that wrong and I
apologize but we need those two lists
here
oops alright so now we have oops
consonant text apparently is not there
oh I think as I called it consonant only
my bad okay so for right now what I'm
going to do is when we call get hero
name I'm gonna really quickly if zero
this out and I just want to focus on
just those names for now and then we'll
add them as a third case so what we're
really gonna do is this right we're
really gonna do get nonsense name for
now and so I will eventually turn that
on but at the moment I just want to
practice these only so what we're gonna
do is we're only gonna have the nonsense
names for now and that way we can just
try to get those working so let get
nonsense name is gonna have to do
something and this is going to be the
hard part of the program so here we go
in result and I'll say alright let's
just start by saying it's you know I
don't know what we're gonna do here but
just let's make sure this is working at
all we're gonna say give me a random
from consonantal only I'm sorry from
consonant-vowel a random from consonant
and a random from constant vowel again I
don't know I have no idea that's going
to do only sorry and it's not awful
right it's not a honestly it's it's not
that past
[Music]
[Laughter]
honestly if you told me there is a girl
called magna or slots key oh okay so I
thought that's gonna be the hard part of
the program it's not oh man okay whew
I'm gonna add a couple more in here like
n D D D
maybe kale and LK I don't know see how
those do at all
pretty darn good and so I'm gonna say
that there should also be a vowel only
[Music]
that's just I suppose vowel only is
really just like if you want start with
over a or something but I'm gonna say
there's a vowel only as well and that's
just like a IOU for now but we may like
want that to be a little bit more
ridiculous uh so basically like that was
ridiculous I mean I guess it's way
easier than I think it is I was thinking
we have to do that we have to do
anything just like make up a ridiculous
collection of syllables and it sounds
like a total name I guess I shouldn't be
surprised
all right so off we go here's vowel only
and good news so I'm gonna go ahead and
say that the nonsense name now will
just have a switch for what it wants to
do here where we'll just have a couple
patterns oops we'll just have a couple
patterns that we use and we'll see which
if any of them if they all tend to work
out I don't know let's let's make like
five patterns I'm just again apparently
pulling stuff out of your butt is just
fine for doing two names like right
because they pull them out of their butt
so I guess I can pull them out of mine
or my computer could pull it out of
there but just fine too
all right so we're gonna take and we're
gonna say let's make our nonsense name
is gonna have some stuff in it here and
that's fine and then I'm gonna make a
bunch of these so we already know that
this one works right that works just
fine but what about some other ones
right what about some other patterns
here that we could use right let's just
make up five of them right um and
honestly to be honest though really we
could break this down into two
categories so we could instead of doing
five here well I mean maybe we do yeah
like maybe we do like consonant only
like vowel only consonant vowel or
something I don't know which
III don't even know I I'm sorry I have
no idea what I'm doing what I was gonna
say though is so what I think we should
do in addition is after we generate this
we should roll like if you roll a random
let's say there's a 1 out of 10 chance 1
out of 8 chance something 1 I attend
chance that whatever complete crap we
don't we generated there will cat on
itself so like with one of these
ridiculousness is right so once in a
while and it looks like we didn't
generate any there sadly new that's -
yeah we'll get one of these you know
kind of things it looks like maybe it's
only really appropriate for ones that
start with consonant-vowel so not ones
that start with consonant only I'm not
sure we actually want to start with
consonant only so I might get rid of
that entirely right alright so I think
that's probably good I don't know if
that should be capitalized inter wide so
I don't that any shouldn't be
capitalized in that or not but I think
we're good ok so now if we let this go
[Music]
right we can
we can get a really respectable look
looking set of done' names now right I
mean I defy someone to know the
difference between this list and an
actual list of dota heroes right so
that's pretty good I'm pretty happy with
that right but what I would also like to
do is get some more like possibilities
in here once in a while so these was
what I would call maybe Core dota names
once in a while I'd like to go nuts with
it and just say look what if we had like
nonsense name and then a final word as
well right so every so often you know if
you did a get random count here like
this sort of thing every so often I'd
like to see maybe it's a little more
frequent than that I'd like to see a con
cat with a capitalized first get final
word on these guys right so a nonsense
word but then a real noun right I mean a
real ending that we concatenate on to
whatever the nonsense word is
regenerated right and so that way you
know you can get stuff like dock bar
protector which we wouldn't have gotten
before which i think is a good addition
to like the set of things that we can
have right you know what I mean I
thought we took Virk out of the set of
things that were final word didn't we
say that we weren't supposed to have
that
oh this is wrong this is get final word
is supposed to be verb isn't it I think
we screwed that up yeah because like
virk and stuff like the secondary verbs
we're supposed to be they're not the
suffixes yeah yeah yeah yeah I messed
that up sorry that was my bad
all right so this is a pretty
respectable list profit I feel like as a
secondary noun I feel like that should
be in there so that's looking pretty
good so now all I want to do just to
make it so that it's a little bit more
powerful we can do a ton more stuff with
this obviously but I want to just add
our own words in now right so we're just
gonna add our own set so let's see in
this list for example we've just got you
know it's obvious what's here like so
you know let's just make up some words
that sound like they go with this list
right and we should put a lot more in
there but I just want to go through this
list and put them in there that should
really be here
all right
so really this should have been here
[Music]
we should be adding like way more words
than this but I'm just trying to do like
a quick and dear dirty you know job here
I don't know if that would really work
also alright so I don't know if we made
it better or worse we made it better
sellers should really be stealer I think
thief should be in here
sure controllers not that good
I think our job here is done
I feel like Forge it's gotta be in here
somewhere
am I wrong about that feel like we need
a forge
I think I think we're good
here's $100 Hiro's valve if you need
them I think there's maybe our mix is
not perfect like we probably should
silencer also looks like more of an
final noun like
[Music]
Forge might want to be Adam all right I
don't really know
there you go that's what we've got
I don't suppose John's probably still
here but hopefully we can send him some
of these quality names now so that he as
a game designer who I know would like to
be able to design games like dota won't
have to come up with all of these
awesome hero names himself right so I
think that's pretty good
just making the fake get look like yeah
that's that's all I did for the fake it
I just looked at the stuff that that
they were generating and generated stuff
with the same pattern right sent or were
litter was that generated at some point
are you capitalizing the original source
strings no not at the moment
oh wait you probably were telling me
that back when I was yeah okay nevermind
did making the fake it look similar to
this yes you also need the one word type
names like doom or silencer the problem
is I don't know that we can really do
that because that we just have to add
those words right so I don't know how we
would do that because it has to find a
word in the English language that could
probably be a dota hero and use it and I
don't know that's while something we
could try what was the point there is no
point to this
other than we needed more dota names
Linda's memory macros sure yes we can do
those so the Linux memory macro problem
I all I know about it is this pusher and
push size need to have the pound pound
on them I and push it and I'll terminate
can't that's all I know so I will make
that change but I don't know anything
else about it since obviously I don't
compile on Linux if that makes sense so
looking at the push struct push array
push side loops so looking at these so
basically you're just saying push struck
needs that push array needs it and push
size needs it that correct that says
here push truck pusher a push size push
on mill terminate should not have it at
all I guess
are you sure it shouldn't have a comma
with that after it does it does it you
sure doesn't have to have this I think
we need it to have that don't or maybe
not all right
so pushing a null terminate is trying to
pass its entire set down here with the
comma
oh it just needs that probably right is
that sufficient
and and we don't want the comma I
thought you did need the comma you can't
just do that Kenya yeah you can't you
can't do that you have to do that that's
the only legal one that I know about
right
is that is that good up encoder well I
guess I can check this in and then we
can fix it if that's not good enough
right so we'll just say like off we go
um someone wanted to see the main
function again of our duty hero
generator so let me just jump down there
here it is
and here's the get here on you
do you think it's a worthwhile exercise
learning to program for Gameboy or some
other constraint platform or is it too
esoteric specialized to be transferable
well I guess what I would say is it's
definitely a useful thing to do and I
think you would learn a lot from doing
it the question is not really if it's
transferable this the sort of the stuff
you learn a lot of it is stuff you can
apply and it helps you understand a
platform and stuff right the question is
just is it the most efficient way to
learn because there are plenty of things
that are just plain specific to Gameboy
that you'll be learning that really have
no bearing on anything else and so I
don't know I I would say it depends a
lot on how much time you have to spend
and how much you care about maybe
learning some things about a platform
that you don't really need to know ever
so it's kind of a toss-up have you ever
programmed an emulator no I have not
I programmed a few like cycle simulator
things in the past that try to like take
some like assembly language code for a
particular platform and determine like
what the CPU will do with it but those
were just to like do performance
analysis they were never designed to
actually simulate the behavior like that
and actually produce output from it you
know what I mean
will I be streaming beta j ai I don't
have a beta ji I would be happy to play
around the downstream though sometime
for sure I had me I don't know how to
program in ji so you know would be kind
of a learning experience right so I
certainly couldn't do much right but
would you put today's achievement on
your CV this is my CV alright if you
don't think that a hundred perfect dota
names is a reason to hire me I just
don't know what to say I do think it
would be nice to hook this up to a like
a little Twitter posting bot so that it
just generates a dough to name a day
I mean I assume I may not really know
like if I went to twitter.com and I just
you know signed up and I said it was
you know whatever the heck it is
let's just let's just see
so what I need here is I need to make an
account I guess that could tweet out a
hero every day right
and
okay
hello
so it never asked me what my handle
would be why not
what's my handle
weird so it just doesn't you don't get
to pick your handle anymore
that really sucks
man Twitter just gets worse and worse
like it never asked me what the handle
was it just it said what what name and
it just like randomly concatenated my
name I guess you can change the user
name
all right so I've created an account
called daily MOBA hero
so I guess Twitter allows you to change
it so that's fine so we now have daily
MOBA hero and let's just tweak one of
our names from today I think let's see
what we should have Forge maiden I think
is going to be it
and so we'll just go ahead and and make
that happen there I will hook it up to a
Twitter bot later today so that it just
tweets out one of the things that this
thing generates every day right and and
that'll be that
all right folks it's happening we're
good to go so I'll get that worked out
as soon as I can and and and we'll go
from there
let me wrap it up for today because I
mean I really think it would be a crime
for the world to not have our daily
mobile hero available
maybe tomorrow you should show us how to
hook her name's Reptar I'm not gonna I'm
just gonna use the command line to like
probably just a cron job right that just
sits there and posts it that's all I'm
gonna do yeah two weeks to generate
plausible looking portraits to go with
dota hero names which approach would you
take I don't know that's probably not a
two week thing unless you just wanted to
hack together some like AI image
libraries or something in an API how
might you distinguish between functions
that do things in place two already
allocated memory versus ones that do the
same thing on freshly allocated memory
for example an image processing function
that modifies that memory in place
versus one that returns a modified image
so I just in api's I pretty much never
do that I never have the API allocate
the memory I always have the memory get
passed in and then if you want it to
allocate the memory you just do a
secondary call or something that makes
it allocate and then you pass that
that's pretty much what I always do can
you show us how to hook it up is it hard
I know you there's just command-line
utilities to tweet pretty sure you don't
really have to do anything if you want
to write your own it's a huge pain in
the butt because you got it right ooofff
which is a nightmare so I would highly
recommend not writing a twitter bot from
scratch because then you're in like the
OpenSSL territory which is terrible but
if you don't mind using curl or
something then it's pretty easy
alright alright folks that's it for
today thank you everyone for joining me
for another set of handmade hiris Oh cut
recording with you as always we now have
something that generates dota hero names
which is pretty much the coolest thing
that you could have at the end of a
programming stream so congratulations
folks I will be back here next weekend
when we will do our light probe work til
then have fun programming everyone and
I'll see you on the Internet
take it easy everybody