hello everyone and thanks for joining me
this is not an actual handmade hero
stream we will be getting back to
handmade hero shortly but I wanted to
give a overview of an internal tool that
I wrote a long time ago
many years ago at rad 4 basically
debugging video codecs it's the kind of
thing that's if you've ever tried to
work on something like a video codec
then you kind of know that a regular
debugger doesn't work very well for it
because the things that you need to
figure out and see are very hard to get
the debugger to actually show you and my
point of doing this demo is really not
to show anyone how to debug a video
codec or anything like that because I
think that's a pretty specialized field
of inquiry certainly but rather it's to
give a demo of what I think were some
pretty cool things we made for this
purpose to show in a sense just how I
don't want to use the word bad but just
how little debuggers have actually done
to get us what we need to to plug things
if you think about what a typical
debugger provides today it's basically
exactly the same thing but a typical
debugger provided in 1975 or something
in 1985 let's say it really just doesn't
have the ability to do almost anything
else now some debuggers have added a few
features that are new and are good such
as being able to step backwards or
checkpoint runs in memory this is a
great feature and I'm really glad that a
few debuggers have added it gdb and
windbg being to that I can think of but
if you think about how little you can
really point to that they've added in
20-30 years it's kind of too bad because
debugging is very important software
today has just as many bugs if not more
than it used to and furthermore one
thing we
for sure is that software today is much
larger and more unwieldy than software
was back in the 1970s and 80s because
computers today are much more powerful
and can run much larger software and so
what I'd like to do is just show what is
possible even with an internal tool that
has not had you know many man years of
development behind it or anything like
this and just to try to provide a little
bit of inspiration for people working on
debugging tools to say look there is a
lot we could be doing to make debugging
faster easier more powerful and able to
find very difficult bugs in as easy a
manner as we are currently finding
simple bugs we just need the tools and
no one's really providing them obviously
I'm hoping that the rad debugger comes
online soon and that it will have some
of these rad has all the source code to
this tool because I wrote it for them
and of course the techniques that I'm
going to show in here are not rocket
science it's not like you have to have
some kind of crazy knowledge of weird
algorithms to do it it's just a question
of having sat down and doing it so I
think even just showing what some of
these are it should be immediately
obvious how people who are making
debuggers could add these to the
debuggers and furthermore this tool i'm
gonna show you is not itself a debugger
which means that if you were
implementing these sorts of features
inside the motor itself you could make
them even better than the features that
I made because you actually have process
control and access to the debug info
which is not something that we had when
we were doing this particular tool
because it was meant to run alongside an
existing debugger that was doing those
things all right so that's really the
only point of this stream to sort of
provide an example of what sorts of
things you can do if in a debugger if
you actually wanted to and so let me
just go ahead and and sort of show you
how this thing works
and I wouldn't recommend using a wait or
not
hache we go I honestly wouldn't
recommend the UI to this tool it's not
good there is one part of it that's good
most of it's awful so I'm talking more
about the features here oh I didn't know
there was a I whiteboard already okay
well we'll clear that I didn't know
let's clear that out
yes clear the entire whiteboard so
anyway I wouldn't recommend the UI at
all it's not good so don't try not to
take any inspiration from that if you
can it's it's it's mostly bad there are
a couple things in it that are
interesting and I'll point them out but
other than that I think most of the UI
is just a bad idea and also as you'll
see it's one of the reasons I'm not that
into visual programming it just ends up
especially if you already know how to do
non visual programming it just ends up
not being that good alright so let me
start by explaining what mustache
actually is so I'm gonna open up just
our regular editor here this is for
coder and I'm going to talk a little bit
about what mustache actually does so you
can see in here you'll have two I'm in
the middle of some for coder upgrades
which will actually do some streams
about to have to excuse my horrible
colors I have some debug color set to
see if my new syntax highlighting
implemented works properly but so yeah
the colors ain't great but if you look
in here you can see a example program
that I'll sort of point out how mustache
is designed to work so basically this
entire program is just a regular program
it's anything you want so you you can
imagine having your own program whatever
it is doesn't matter and the only thing
that makes it mustache enabled is just
including this one header file if you
include mustache client dot H you get
all the features of mustache and again
this is really important I'll just harp
on it for a second if you're gonna make
a debug tool it has to be easy to use
and there's nothing easier to use than
literally just an h-file that you just
include don't make me link with the
library don't make me open a DLL don't
make me do anything just include one
thing and then let me access all the
features I've said it a million times
it's just that's very important and that
way you just have to copy one file into
your project mustache client @h and you
just pound include it when you want to
use it and that's all there is all right
so what features does this mustache
client that H give you well the theory
behind mustache was printf debugging is
really great in one way right you all
know printf debugging right it's when we
just start dumping things to printf and
then we try to find the bug by seeing
what we print it out and figuring out
like where the crash happens is that
right right
well the observation mind mustache was
printed debugging is actually really
good in some sense and the thing that
it's really good at is it provides you a
log of what happened and this is
actually something that debuggers are
very bad at right a debugger show you
know you're stepping through it your
brain is the thing that would have to
remember the log of what happened and if
you're talking about millions of lines
of code having executed you can't watch
all that so the thing that printed the
buggy is really good at is sort of
creating this log of what happened but
then the question is well why don't we
just always use printed debugging that's
so great and the answer is because
modern programs are way too complicate
you couldn't you just have reams of
printf and it would just become exactly
as complicated as having a step through
the whole program that doesn't get you
anything the thought behind mustache was
what if mustache could build a printf
that was actually far more powerful and
did two main things one it could print
anything so not just text it could print
images it could print matrices anything
that you wanted to that was structured
it could actually print that so instead
of just a blank log of stuff it could
print data as well and that data would
be understood that's thing one thing too
and that solves the problem of how do I
printf an image right you know for just
using a real printf debugging an image
is just a stream of numbers you can't
it's
huge its massive you can't make any
sense of it right well if you know solve
that problem this way so datasize solved
this way but think to which is
complexity how about we make it so that
the logs can be spatially queried based
on the memory that they affect so for
example let's suppose we could do a ton
of printf to say what happened to things
but as we were doing them we said which
pixels were being operated on and then
we could just query that one pixel so
instead of 1920 x 1080 times every step
in the process being how many printf so
we have to look at which would never
work instead we just click on the one
pixel that's wrong in our video and it
would just show us all the things that
happen to that pixel right then it's
like shooting fish in a barrel oh I see
it went through this transform and that
transform was wrong or something right
does that make sense so that's the idea
behind this tool and so you include
moustache client and then what it gives
you is a printf called stash F here
which you can see and stash F itself is
a thing which implements printf in a way
that provides all these features so for
example you can use it the way you would
normally use it meaning if you just
switch a printf to a stash F it would do
it right so you don't have to do
anything different there but then it
also has some other things you can also
see some things here where we talk about
you you can use it to like get input
back or things like that if you want to
like a scanf as well but that's sort of
a separate thing and nautically relevant
you can also do like nesting in groups
and stuff like that so it has a few of
the things but mostly the power comes
from being able to do stash chefs like
this and you can see here that when you
do a stash if you can say I'm going to
print something like a matrix here and
then you can pass all these sorts of
things to it that are like more
complicated so you can pass like the
width and height of an image or
rectangle and then like you can pass
some plain data in so here are some of
the planes of the image it'll gather
those up you can say like what format
they're in like you nor more whatever
right different kind of styles of things
that you want to talk about
pixels and so you do some of those
things you can issue break points which
are basically saying if I get here stop
everything and wait you know in the tool
when you're viewing these things and
then we also have some stuff like I
saying for tracing it's I use the term
deep memory for it and the reason that I
call it deep memory is because basically
it allows you to write to the same sort
of pieces of of the log it allows you to
say look as I move memory around I'm
gonna tell you where I move the memory
to like if I do a mem copy I'll do I'll
tell you that or I'll point to the
memory that I'm referring to and then
when I printf into that if later you're
ever trying to inspect something that
touches that memory go pull all of that
history back so I can see all of the
steps that the data went through to get
to where it was and so the way that that
works is things like this so this thing
is a stash F that says oh here is a
chunk of memory and I'm transforming it
to this other chunk of memory and you
could pass these two things here that's
specified it right and so when anytime
you did a stash if that related to
pieces of memory together it would know
it could search back through that chain
again for some reason we were really
probably overly specific about always
making everything go through stash F so
there's like one function it's just that
one probably wasn't really necessary we
probably could have called this stash
copy and not how to imply that to things
that happen on the same line or related
you can see why there's some things I
say like maybe don't copy the user
interface either the API or that because
this was not a shipping project this was
internal only so you need other things
you can have diagrams here right like
here's ability to just draw on top of a
diagram on top of the of an image right
you could you could just say like hey
I'm gonna start drawing on top of this
thing that I just output right like here
and things like that so you know it's
got other features in there
that worked printf based where you could
basically use like OpenGL essentially to
draw things to it and it just goes on
and on right so you know lots of things
you can stash F and so on so this is all
again just regular code you could do
this anywhere in your project you could
just call the stash F thing and that
would be it
and again the only thing you had to do
to enable that was include mustache
client now mustache client again is just
a header file that influenced this stuff
right so it gives you all of the structs
you need for this and then it has the
code necessary in to do socket
transmission right out of here and it
worked on like it worked on the win32
and on xbox360 um I don't know that it
worked on PlayStation ever it might I
can't recall whether anyone actually
tried it we probably did but don't quote
me on that so anyway once you have a
program that supports mustache and it's
going to do the the debug output to
mustache and you want to use it then the
way that it works is you run this little
server and in fact this window is not
really that necessary in a sense what
actually happens and you can't see it I
could make it so that you could see it
in a second here let me unlock this
taskbar there you go so you can see that
it creates a little mustache icon up
here that just sits in the SIS tray
right and then if you run a program like
that mustache client test that we had if
you run a program like that what it
would do is it'll actually them I have
no idea what that is about okay
it's basically completing it couldn't
find one of the source files maybe I
didn't copy it over I'm not sure but
anyway once you run one of these things
it runs and if this thing was running
then what it would do is it will it will
capture all of that output so you don't
actually have to
you don't have to be aware of mustache
really in general just kind of sits
there and captures everything that you
dump to it now this had input and output
and breakpoint testing in it so you can
see that this program hasn't completed
the reason is because it's actually
waiting for mustache to tell it it's
okay to complete but if you were using a
program that wasn't testing and putting
output or didn't have him input in it it
would have just completed and mustache
would save the data and in fact we can
if we want to just kill the app and
that's fine and then I can run it again
if I want to I can run it as many times
as I want and so on right now all of
those runs actually get captured by
mustache okay so they're sitting in here
waiting for us to use now again I said
the who I isn't great let me show you
how it works what happens is you draw
these little nodes here look I just drew
where I wanted this new node to go and
then you can pick what kind of node you
actually want on a big process list and
of course what process list does or it
maybe I shouldn't have made it quite
that big what process list does is
exactly what it sounds like it does it
lists all the process the processes that
have that have been run right so here
they are and you can see all the runs of
this program remember I ran it three
times well here are the three runs right
and each of these processes is
selectable you can see like I've got
them and it tells me like when they were
run right it's pretty straightforward
hopefully this makes good sense to
everyone
now I think there's a way in here you
could filter like if I only wanted like
a particular thing I could type like
client
oops star client star and then it would
show me only things that match that
pattern I don't have different I only
ran like one executable name so that's
never gonna do anything but if you had
like lots of different acute herbals and
you wanted to just focus on runs of one
type of executable you could filter it
there which is kind of nice right um so
now like I said this is one of those
kind of crappy visual programming
language things and I don't ask me why I
made it this way I don't have an
explanation it's just I don't know but
what you could do is you can
any output of an ode to like the input
of any other node right so in this case
I'm you know this thing is like a picker
essentially right I can pick these
processes from the list and then this
node is a thing that displays data about
the process in question so anything that
you connect it to it will look at what
process ran it and tell you about the
process so this is nice right and I wish
the buggers did this in general this
just saves all of the runs that I did
right and it tells me what they were
really right says you know here was the
process here's the executable that got
ran here's how big the excuted was what
the date was it when I executed it
what machine ran it because this is this
supports tcp/ip discovery and stuff so
if you ran this on another machine it
would connect to this mustache server
and give it the data which was nice umm
you know it tells you what hardware was
running on and all that sort of thing
right it tells you how many threads
output it to mustache as well in case
you were curious about that or whatever
so again even just I haven't gotten any
of the features of mustache that I
really want to talk about yet but even
just this I don't have a debugger that
does any of this right I don't have a
debugger that just sits there and
remembers runs of programs and allows me
to like know what the output of was of
the programs even to the console of
multiple runs I don't have any of that
right so even just this basic first step
is like way better than any debugger
that I have which is not good right this
should just be par for the course
computers have like infinite storage and
infinite memory these days like remember
everything right and mustache did it
remembered absolutely everything you
ever did
you could go right back to the first run
of 2 and see everything that it out
put it in you know why don't we have
that that should just be how did buggers
work I'll buy a bigger drive I'll keep
throwing 8 terabyte drives that you
store my data right ok
so but that's not that interesting right
because you know all that's telling me
is some basic things about a run
program what I want to do is start
looking like what that program actually
output right so we have a node called
listing and what a listing node is is a
node that if you hook it up to any
process that you've selected right then
it can tell you what that thing output
so this is the actual output from that
program so every time that you called
stash F this is what was there this is
all the stuff that was was in stash F
and so what you can see here is that
this program and actually all of them
stopped on that line right and I can
pick these programs separately and we
can see them and you can see like so if
I jump back to this program for example
I don't know if it actually one of the
things that's kind of annoying about the
way that mustache happened to work is we
didn't patch in an exception handler to
it so if you control seed and it hadn't
flushed the buffer yet you didn't get
the buffer so there's a couple things
like that that like aren't great but
what we would do is in our program we
just put a like a catch-all handler
around the whole thing and call stash
flush in the case of a crash so when
these where I control seed it we may not
have gotten the data which is less good
but that's just yeah that's just how it
goes sometimes you could do better than
that you could do better than what we
did so I believe here where we're
outputting these things this program is
paused you can hit f5 inside mustache
and you can see like it will output like
there's that's how you continue the
program and again that was if you put
stash breakpoint that's all that is is a
thing that that's there to try and let
you Brittany oh stop in mustache when
you want to stop in mustache because we
would have situations where we were
working on Bank where we're like okay we
want to get to this frame and then stop
in mustache so that's what that was and
the little red bar is what would tell
you that it was like this was a thing
where we stopped now you can also drag
this little weird nub here over to look
at information about the thread so when
mustache outputted this information this
was the process or that the thread was
running on so for example this is
running on processor to processor means
logical processor so in this case it
means core to obviously there's only one
trust sir in this machine and this was
the thread ID which is thread ID 58 now
there's only one thread in this test
code I think if you don't call the
thread test which I don't think we did
so it's always gonna be thread 58 but
the presser jumps around because hey
Windows can jump us around anywhere it
wants to we didn't try to lock down an
affinity or anything so here's all the
printf and as you can see like by
default all mustache will do if you just
have a listing notice just give you a
printf that's not very interesting but
it is you know what mustache does right
so you got that basic in there and it's
a little bit better than a printf right
I can collapse things right and stuff
like that there's some weirdness I don't
remember all the key combinations
there's like some key combinations you
can use to like collapse stuff and not
have to do what I'm doing here weird to
like scroll back and forth and I really
just don't remember what they all are so
some of this stuff is is you would want
there to be mouse input for and we don't
have it so I apologize for that I'm
gonna get into situations where I'm like
I don't know how to fix this thing and
so that's my fault
but point being there's a bunch of
things that can sort of do that you that
are different from a regular printf but
that's not that important it's it's fun
to have collapsible things but and
they're good for certain situations
certainly but that's not one of the more
interesting parts of mustache certainly
so there's a couple of the things I
might go ahead and show you I as well
here so this was one run of the program
right and I don't know what the status
of this is here but let me see if I can
recompile mustache client
test dot C as well so it needs
it needs like what like windsock so I
don't remember windsock lib windsock
what's wind socks library handle anyone
inside is it w sock 32 W sock 32 maybe
yeah I'm not sure okay and then we just
need like you know user 32 and Oh add
that be who's the registry yeah get
adder info hmm
maybe we need the others ws 232 there we
go okay so I can compile the moustache
client on this machine you may ask why
do I bother we already had a running
version of the moustache client well the
answer is because I kind of want to show
this other feature I may not remember
well enough how to make it work
but I'm gonna show it or attempt to show
it to you if I go to moustache client
test and in here I say like oh yeah you
know the the the define foo bar is the
thing one I'm gonna make that happen and
then I'm gonna recompile this this
client and then I'm gonna run it again
right so now what's happened as you can
see we have the one from ten minutes ago
that's there and then we've got this new
one what I'm gonna do is I'm actually
not gonna switch the processes now I
could right I can switch the process
list to get to the other one here right
and then I can you know do my f5 or
whatever like that I'm actually not
going to quite do that what I'm gonna do
instead is going to leave this one set
looking at this one here I'm gonna make
a new process list to grab from here and
a new process node as well and I'm gonna
select the new one in here so that way
I've got both of these now I could also
just use this latest process boolean you
can turn on and the latest process
Julian would just automatically pick
that I wouldn't have to have a process
list and that's what you would do if you
wanted to just always have your the most
recent run of the program in one of your
flows so you know that was also a common
way that it was used but we'll ignore
that for the moment now I'm gonna go
ahead and here and say alright there's a
listing and the listing is just like the
one we had before but now it's being
driven by this note so now I've got two
different listings right okay now the
reason I was saying I want to have two
of these two different runs of the
program and have a different compile is
I believe there is a thing and again I I
may just be like up it doesn't work
nevermind um there's this thing called
sore stiff and what sore stiff does is
if you hook up a process to it and then
you hook up another process to it it
tells you what the difference was
between the two runs okay so you can see
here what actually happened between
these two things so you can say like
okay there were two missing files
twenty-one lines matched five different
Spurs were found these files were
missing when we tried to do them and we
switched out these versions right so
used to be the old mustache client test
and now it's the new one right I yeah
who knows right okay of course it does
I I don't make any I don't make any
promises that this thing will run
reliably wait how come it didn't yeah
there we go try that again all right so
anyway uh what is it what is it doesn't
like the scaling on that that's
interesting it doesn't seem to like is
that is that who is who is having a
problem with scaling one thing I will
note is that this thing is a lot more
crashing it should be because I had to
write all of the graphics by hand
because Jeff didn't want me to use GL
for it he felt that like GL was too
unreliable so this is all hand written
in GDI so like the stuff that actually
renders images and stuff is written by
hand and it's in a short period of time
so it
pretty error-prone even the clipping and
all that stuff like had to be written by
hand it was not fun um anyway so there's
like an entire custom graphics library
just to support this thing which was and
and is you know anytime you have a
little off by one in there it's you know
it's not great anyway so I don't know
why I'm getting that problem it looks
like this that diff node is buggy so
anyway um again apologize for all the
bugs and all that stuff whatever point
being the interesting thing about that
was and the reason that I wanted to
bring it up was because another thing
that I wish the buggers always did is
just save all of my source files from
that run and mustache did that so inside
the mustache file in addition to all of
the data it also saved all of the source
files so that what you could do is if
you needed to know what files had
changed between the two you could do
that now we never really built out full
different utility which would have been
great that was kind of one thing I
wanted to do and just never did but you
could easily see why this would be good
if you have two runs of a program and
one of them works and one of them
doesn't you can just quickly see what
were all the changes right and so that's
all that I wanted to point out there and
so I just think debugger should always
do that in fact I don't understand why
PD bees don't store all the source files
they obviously should in my opinion I
have no idea why they don't because that
way you wouldn't need to worry about
paths to source files the PDB would have
100% of the source that was ever used to
create that program because if if the
compiler could read it it can be in
there right and so the only things that
PP wouldn't have is like libs
if the libs didn't have source in it but
put it in the libs to put all the source
in the libs right put the source in
there every time you compile the program
put all the source into it into the
debug info right that's that's what I
would do
so mustache did the best it could to
sort of have that for you but really
again I think that should be the
debuggers job all right so let's move on
to the actual like more useful features
for stuff like this
okay so let's suppose that we want to do
something like in you know in
one of these listings I guess I'll look
at this one here let's say we want to
take a look at like this what's a good
example large image diff test let's say
so if I go ahead and create a thing that
does an image diff I'm not sure I'm
going to do this right so you have to
again bear with me but what I want to do
is I want to see the difference between
two images so what I can do here is say
like alright let's grab two images off
of this listing and so you know maybe in
here I could just say grab this one
right and one of the weird things about
moustaches nodes remember their settings
so I think if you just do that it keeps
it so I can actually grab these like
semi-permanently like this and then
disconnect them right which is kind of
weird but that's how that works
anyway I can also just have it be live
and then when I switch these off I get
different images right whatever so
anyway these things show the images and
of course you can zoom in on them right
and look at them however you want to and
it's all alive and nice and all that
nonsense which is fine and then what you
can do is the data that comes out of
those I don't know if this works right I
think it does maybe yeah I don't know
maybe it doesn't maybe it does this was
the first one and this was also the
first one you can see zero right but if
I switch it to the next one down it'll
show me all the differences between
those two images right so I can just
come down in here now and look at a
particular place that's different and
you know off I go right which is pretty
nice and one of the nice things about
this too is that again this is all live
so if I wanted to I could make this
thing here say always use the latest
process you know forget this just use
the latest process and then every time I
ran the program this would automatically
update for me right but this because
it's not connected anything would always
diff off of this image so I can store
or old images right in the mustache
whiteboard and just always get discs off
them and it all just works right which
is kind of nice and again you don't need
any additional storage it's just that
one directory of mustache files keeps
everything you don't need it doesn't
need to be able to get back to your
executable or any of that stuff it
packages everything up into the runs
alright so that's how that works right
you can see why that would be kind of
nice right you can see stuff these dips
also have some stuff like the peak
signal-to-noise ratio the root mean
squared error stuff like that and you
can also crank this multiplier so this
allows you to like go down to like this
is the actual difference right but it's
kind of hard to see if there are some
differences that are not very high so
this multiplier just let you crank up
those differences to make them visible
right and again that was a nice thing uh
so the other cool thing you could do
with that is if you wanted these
differences to be displayed against the
back of an image because what you see
this you're like well I don't really
know where those are as far as it's like
we're on the on the video frame they
were right um so there was another thing
to do which is called a node overlay and
again I apologize if I screw this up I
don't remember much about using this
tool and the node overlay could
basically say well look take whatever
the image is that I give you here like
let's say this one and allow me to pipe
in another image to show as the image
that was on top of it right oh I guess
this doesn't allow that though I thought
that you could do that the problem is
this has this is not transparent so I
guess that's not true I don't remember
how we did this then I think there was a
way to do this but I guess that's not it
[Music]
all right
forget that I don't know how to do it I
don't like I said I don't remember so I
couldn't tell you uh let's me disconnect
that there how did we do that
I don't think there was some other magic
thing maybe maybe that's not how we used
to do it yeah I don't know all right I
apologize I don't really know I'll try
some of the things in a second and show
you those anyway um so let's talk about
a couple of things before I go down to
the actual more interesting features
than just image diffing and live stuff
like that so one of the things that I
thought there was one and only one good
UI feature of mustache and that was
these things here so let me show you
what those are in case anyone out there
is actually doing a visual programming
language or node-based thing these
things are awesome so here's how they
work if you click on the middle one it
will drag anything in that set of nodes
right which is awesome so if I want to
move this collected set of stuff I just
do that right and it moves everything
that's connected to it that's super
handy if I do this it moves it and the
downstream nodes so it's the same thing
here right but notice it doesn't pick up
this because those are upstream you'd
have to travel upstream so all of the
things that are descendant from it can
be grabbed this way similarly any
antecedent node can be grabbed with the
other one right this was just a really
easy way to reorganize stuff I don't
know why no one's done it I don't know
if they just never thought about it but
it's super handy maybe there is some
tools that do it I don't know maybe
maybe you the blueprint in Unreal Engine
does it I'm not sure anyway that was one
really cool feature that I highly
recommend any visual tool do and it was
pretty cool
all right anyway there's a bunch of
things you could do for whiteboard
roll and I'll show you some of the
neater ones as well since we're on that
topic so let's suppose that really all
you wanted at the end of the day was
this image diff well and maybe a couple
other things too like I want you know
this listing and that dip or something
and that's all I wanted to see well the
base whiteboard kind of has everything
on it
but you can also have other whiteboards
so here's like another whiteboard and I
think you can name them so here's my
fubar whiteboard right and what you can
do is you can just grab pieces from your
existing whiteboard and make them into
their own layout so these are now like
and I think you can also I thought there
was some way to to like toggle sorry I
don't actually remember don't remember I
think you could shut off these ghosts as
well I just don't remember how that was
done uh so anyway um if you take a look
maybe it was something up here oops I
don't know I have no idea anyway uh so
you could create your own custom views
where like you know you create this big
weird graph that gives you something you
want and then you could just flip over
to a different view these were all they
weren't cloned they were actually the
nodes for real so any edits that you
make back here would work when you
switch back here it was a really nice
way of basically having some custom view
panels that just worked um and if I
remember correctly this actually works
Cross monitor too so if you have another
monitor right oops
how do I get what's going on here there
we go so if you had another monitor you
could go ahead and put like two
different moustache views one on each
monitor so here's the live updating of
of number two right
but then if this one's on number three
right then you edit them separately so
you could pretty much just have this
your your your console setup exactly you
want it with many moustache views
showing lots of different things at the
same time if you want to and that was
pretty awesome again something I wish
the buggers could do and they pretty
much can alright so moving on to more
features so a couple different things
and again I apologize for not really
remembering how most of this stuff works
uh so here's a note overlay and it's
coming from this image source here what
if I want to start talking about pixels
in there and looking at them in more
detail right so we have this thing
called a pixel inspector
and what a pixel inspector does is it
takes a particular X&amp;Y location and
tells me more about it
so if for example I wanted to know in
this particular image here let's say o
and actually lets me do it to this one
because this one's hooked up to an
active so I can swap them around so
let's say I take this thing here right
and I want to know more about a
particular pixel location now this is
going to expose a bunch of mustache
features at once and so you'll have to
kind of bear with me as I walk through
them in series could be a little bit
hard to understand everything that's
happening here so let me zoom in on this
this note a little bit right let's move
that out of the way as well
all right so here's my pixel inspector
uh and you can see like it's coming from
this listing I can pick different
matrices here right and I get different
results and what you can see is if I in
here was to take the x and y's that i
want to view here it will tell me for a
given x and y-coordinate it'll tell me
what the information is about that
particular pixel for that particular
image now it's annoying to try and pick
pixels by hand sometimes you want to do
it that way but sometimes you don't so
we have this thing called a pixel picker
and of course you could wire it up to
anything you wanted so you can have like
an XY coordinate you can see here and
now as I move around any particular X Y
it will tell me what that particular
pixel was and it'll tell me all about it
so this is the transform the colour
transform that's going through which is
the unity transform but you could go
through y UV transformer so you want to
it's telling me what 32 by 32 block it's
in what 16 by 16 block what 8 by 8 and
then the actual pixel location it's
telling what's value is in real and in
you in eight just you know cuz these are
things we want to see again this is for
video codecs so you wanna information uh
and now I can show you I think the
overlay the node overlay a little bit
better
don't ask me why it didn't work with
TIFF I don't remember but I if I go
ahead now and say Oh take this image
source here that I'm doing make that be
from the overlay take the pixel picker
itself trying to remember how this works
it's one of those things right you know
the beginning when I said don't clone
the UI for this this is why I've done
this horribly wrong so the overlay takes
the pixel picker so yeah this is one of
those things where you're just like I
know there's a simple way to do this ah
this thing no that's just the outliner I
really wish I could remember what what
the heck goes on here there's so much
stuff in this program it's ridiculous
and I and trying to Morelos that there's
let's see so there's all of that stuff I
was pretty sure I could do it with the
things I had here
pixel picker pixel inspector outliner
and how did you get them - like overlay
one of these things does it see pixel
outliner doesn't have any any way to to
drive it there huh second I'm going to
do some weird stuff here so here's the
pixel picker I'm I connected to the
outliner it's program is so nuts right
so that does exactly what you would
think it would do Oh
right the node overlay is coded such
that you don't have to hook up an image
you're just hooking up anything from
that node yeah so all I have to do is
just drag like the X over here put that
on top and then it shows up right and
since the node overlay overlaid the UI
for the nodes as well as the nodes you
can see I can get the picking happening
there as well yeah yeah okay like I said
don't clone the UI anyway so I can go in
and look at like particular ones here
and I can look at like this winner or
whatever right and I can look at the
pixel pixel inspector and I can see what
the status was a fat node and all of
those sorts of things right and so once
you set these up the way you wanted like
I saying you could get to a nice point
where you did all your crazy wiring
which is the part that I'm not I don't
think was very good I think you'd rather
just maybe write some expressions or
something that say what you want and
then it puts up just a UI that just lets
you do that you know but anyway you have
to do your visual programming your
program a thing and then you can get
what you want which is here I can like
do pixel inspection this way and also I
can have as many of these inspectors
running as I want so I can inspect the
same pixel location if I want to for
example on some other image or things
like that right okay so again still not
that it's nice to have all this stuff
live again if I just run the program
this would all just update and all that
stuff and I can again diff with old
things and all those other sorts of
things are great but again still not
really the most useful parts of
moustache even though all of them should
be things that you would want in the
debugger the far more interesting stuff
comes when you start to look at the like
if I go in the the what's the word for
it here if I go into the the listing
looking at some of the the features that
allow you to sort of work with data
associated with memory and so one
example of that is a thing called an
m-space and what an m-space is it says
the thing that allows you to associate
printf with regions
of like in an image so for example if I
go here and I say like show me you know
I'm gonna I'm gonna pick an m-space here
so this let's go ahead and say grab this
M space that I've got and pipe it into
here it should tell me that I've got a
title for it I don't know why I named it
filet filet and ribeye were the two I
named for some reason and it's a 1920 by
1080 output is what that M space was
maybe I'll move this over here I just
put this in line with it and then if I
want to this thing can be viewed if I'm
not mistaken as sort of its own thing
don't necessarily route recall how that
happens I think it just works like this
so if I'm looking at this M space you
can see what's on it here and if we take
a look at the image that was paired with
it so like here's the M space there and
I'm gonna take one of these image
sources like this one oops
and I'm going to go ahead and pipe this
guy to that so there's that image source
coming through there and then I'll
disconnect it so it's just permanently
listing that one and now we're on this
other one here so here's the image that
the program printed and here's the M
space that was printed after it which is
basically just printf that can go to any
part of the image and it happened that
this one was going to print this one
prints regular tiles of stuff so you can
see the M space here you can see the
image source I've overlaid the M space
onto the image source right and so what
I'm gonna do is I'm just gonna zoom in
and you can see the logs start to appear
where they went right this is actually
just a printf log so you can printf
anything you want into an image and have
it show up at that place on the image
and this is super powerful because like
for things like video
impression for example it shows you any
time you had bugs in a particular case
like let's say you add case 13 if your
motion compensator was busted you could
just print death into the piles that
that thing actually affected and then
you just zoom in on the one that was
wrong and look at the printf log and you
could see exactly what happened right
furthermore n spaces I believe are
queryable so for example if you go ahead
in the pixel inspector here I don't know
if you can do this probably not nope you
can so if you look at the pixel
inspector you can actually look at all
of the things that are actually
connected back stream so for example if
I click on this particular pixel I will
get all of the M space logs that have
ever happened in this chain to that
location right so I can just say like Oh
tell me the m spaces that overlap this
pixel and it will print them out for me
right and again that allows me to keep
stacking this up if I wanted to so for
example if I wanted to look at multiple
M spaces at a time I could also do that
so for example here's another listing
node we'll grab the same oops grab the
same process here and I'll go look at
what we're doing fillet here we'll look
at rib eye here for example if I wanted
to have that one show up as well
off we go and you can see that that's a
different one and it's at a different
resolution and again there it all is all
shown in there and so now if I'm like
zooming around here I'm like picking
what effects these pixels you'll notice
that there's nothing from that one right
there was nothing in there but as I come
back here you can see now there is so
this shows all of the M spaces that
could possibly have affected that now
sometimes there's things like node
overlay it's just taking up space well I
can choose to turn this off and so what
I do there is I just say toggle node
hidden from inspector and then it's gone
right
so I have ways also of controlling what
shows up in the inspector if there are
certain nodes that I don't want shown in
there
that makes sense okay um so again really
kind of handy the way that that stuff
works and you kind of get this really
nice sort of ability to just zoom around
images and and find out what's going on
with them and all sorts of stuff like
that
and so on now the other things you can
do is you can start to use features that
analyze the data if you want to and
again my memory is really hazy on how
these works so you'll have to forgive me
but let's suppose I want this image
source to be analyzed in some way there
are other nodes that do that and I don't
really remember what they are so minimum
and maximum is an example node and so if
i hook this up it'll just tell me right
for the node that I was looking at
here's all the minimum and maximum
values that there are now there's a
reason why there's like XY z-- and Z's
of these I think that's because we just
sort of had this notion that things
could be for wide we want to know so
those are like RGB or XYZ depending on
what got fed in I guess again don't
really remember how this tool worked
very well um so you know you can you
know do stuff like that the other things
you could do is is you could put in like
actual just stuff code so if you wanted
to you could say well take you know this
thing don't ask me if this is gonna work
I'm just randomly trying this I think it
might I don't know but like okay I want
to look at this image but I want to look
at the image does it work No
I'm sure if it does or if it doesn't oh
well this is an image source so maybe I
just need to do one of these or
something I don't know
all right maybe not so again you'll have
to forgive me I don't really remember
how a lot of the stuff works all right
so this thing knows it's a one of these
as an input but I guess it doesn't
output an image I'm not sure but anyway
inside the input field I think you can
just type stuff yeah so if you wanted to
change something that was coming in you
could put a like a scalar value in there
or whatever I guess I just don't know if
it can flow through the pipeline you
would think right but maybe not so for
example if that's like I don't know if I
can inspect this yeah so I don't know
that seems kind of broken it may be that
I just never quite finished those I
don't know so I'm not really sure what
that note was for since the polymorphism
of the types was maybe not as good as it
should have been because it should have
been able to flow through and maybe that
maybe I just didn't get around to having
him anything slot nice idea but I don't
yeah gonna maybe it I'm not sure what we
ever would have used it for possibly we
never really did use it it doesn't look
like it really works um there's this
thing called controls and controls is
just something that allows you to
specify some values again don't really
know what this was used for but I think
in some sense it's if you wanted to have
stuff that was sort of controlled from a
central location so for example if you
wanted a lot of nodes that had a boolean
like let's say or even a float so let's
say that you wanted all of your
inspector nodes to use the same pixel
scale so what you could do is you could
wire up something like the pixel scale
of all of those nodes so you can see
here like I'm looking at that right if I
was to sort of change that value it
would change in that node lister as well
right and so that's what that was for I
just don't really know if we ever used
it much
all right let me try to think if there's
anything else in particular recent
element an element gather I don't think
are particularly relevant they're just
things that gather things out of a
listing and the pixel picker outlining
profile report all that stuff is these
are for debugging only like that so this
is just that how mustache is running at
the moment right you can see what it's
finding its time on which is not
particularly relevant so I think that's
most of it let me see if there's other
things that I should be looking at here
just to show some of the other stuff
stat test image span test so let me look
back at the moustache client code and
see if there was anything else in there
in particular that is worth looking at
so if I look at the image span test see
what that does no that just yeah that
that's just working with pitches and
stuff are we where's the deep memory
test so the deep memory test are we not
calling it oh it was turned off hmm
so I'm gonna turn all this stuff on and
see what happens
like I don't know we've come to the end
of the demo but I don't really know what
this stuff does so let's try it
alright so here we are back at the
process list right and yeah maybe I'll
clear this whiteboard
[Music]
and we'll just go ahead and run this
again mustache client test here's this
latest one here's the process here's the
latest process I guess I don't really
need the process list for any particular
reason at the moment and let me make a
listing so we can look at it so here is
an example of mustache input so you can
see it started doing the same thing I
was doing before and maybe I'll start to
use mustache like so we can kind of see
how you might use it in practice just
you get an idea of it right so maybe one
thing I do is I just have my like latest
listing right and that thing is just
going to be this node and it's gonna be
this node at about this size let's say
and I won't go over that thing here and
what I'm gonna do here is I'm gonna do a
node interface lock and I'm going to do
a deselect of it there we go wait like
that no that's not what I want then this
what I want
I don't know what some of these things
do all right well I don't know anyway
point being a top of the interface
lock-on which means that I can always
like interact with it in this view and I
believe if I go back to the main view
you can see that that's tracked
separately so it's actually any time I
flip back here this guy's UI will be
active and maybe I can open up the
thread information here you can see
where each line of output came from -
which is kind of nice
so here when I run the program I get all
of my debug output and you know whatever
when we get to the input one thing I I
don't actually know how the input stuff
works or if it works I'm gonna skip that
part cuz I'd literally just don't
remember I think you could input values
- mustache I want to say but how I don't
know you can see here it's asking for
input that's what the blue line means
right
I do I is there like a type this in sort
of anyone anyone no I got nothing so I
think you could input values here
don't ask me I'd have to go read the
source code so I'm gonna skip that and
just hit f5 here's an example of a
breakpoint
right like we said hit f5 again here we
are at the structured art stuff gonna
print that in and so one of the things
too you can see in fact here at the
structured art test let's go ahead and
create another view here for a second
and what I'm going to do is in a size
this node differently again really using
the power here of mustache like this is
the same node and all of its state is
the same but I can position it and edit
it differently which is really nice
right so I have different views for
different purposes and different sizes
and all that stuff is just kind of
really handy um so anyway inside here
what I'm gonna do is say look I want to
look at the latest image so I'm just
gonna do that
and do it like this and as I run the
program right because remember the
program is halted now oops what resize
this guy
oops maybe like that there we go um soon
as I run this program I can actually
step back you can see it kind of animate
through but also if I say specific line
false so you can see like on here
specific line true alright maybe I don't
remember I thought there was a way I
thought there was a way to do this where
it always picked the last one maybe it's
this way
yeah so I guess if you want to when we
go back to the default whiteboard here
where this stuff is is hanging out um so
I guess maybe this is the way you were
supposed to do it I'm not sure again
it's been a really long time since I've
used this program I'm surprised I've
remembered as many things as I did and
the UI is pretty bad so if you connect a
process and then you say I want to find
the most recent line you can just attach
that this example here you just say I
want something that looks like this
right and I'll be darned if I know how
this worked but I think this would
basically match any time it got the line
that looked like that so that's not all
right
this actually is a search for something
that looks like that line so basically
if I ran the program again it would find
that line that's not the thing I
actually wanted I guess oh wait no it is
look it found frame nine wow I don't
even know how it did that all right so
yeah that is what I wanted never mind
man this program is nuts all right so
anyway now I've got the most recent
element here I actually don't need this
in this in this particular view which
I'm not sure I think I just called
delete on it maybe doesn't does that get
rid of it now that gets rid of it
entirely try that more time so I'm going
to say recent elements and I'm gonna
grab this process and I'm gonna grab
this line as an example line and then
I'm gonna patch that through to this
image source
right again super-powerful program just
horrible you I needed like a lot of
Polish anyway so here's that image
source node now right and as I run you
can see that it updates every frame and
more importantly let's say I kill this
executable like it's gone now right if I
run it again what you can see is that
search is very powerful this is a
totally new run of the program it
figured out that that was what I was
looking for and is now showing me the
most recent line that looks like that
line right so again pretty cool I don't
know what this is complaining about but
I guess it doesn't know whatever that
thing is
I guess those things were I guess some
of those things were if zeroed out
because they were never implemented I
don't know I have no idea what this
thing is this looks like it might be an
infinite loop so I may have to just turn
this one off the hypothetical
compression example let me just
recompile this here we go
and
[Music]
um so yeah we'll get that just fine that
just keeps dumping images till you run
out of disk space okay that's that maybe
shouldn't okay
I admit that I should not have enabled
that so maybe I just want this one I
don't know here we go oops nope no no
alright there we go so I'm going to run
through to the deep memory test here's
the deep memory test I don't really know
what it does but I'm gonna try to figure
it out all right so if we come back here
and we look at this listing that's got
the deep memory test in it so what I'm
gonna do is I'm just gonna inspect that
image so here is an image source node
and I'm gonna look at that particular
image which is this and see if this
stuff works still I have no idea and I
may just be using it wrong as well so
who knows but here's the image source
right and let me go ahead and grab a
pixel picker and get one of those pixel
inspectors going we'll put that here and
we'll put this here and I'll just grab
a pixel inspector and we'll do it like
that and we're gonna inspect this image
all right so again don't really know if
this works or not we're gonna find out
it may or may not work so here's me like
scanning this image with the pixel
inspector I don't see it reading any
deep memory out of there so I guess I'm
not sure if the deep memory stuff just
didn't end up getting moved over from
the previous version of my session I
know this stuff worked but I also maybe
just am NOT doing it correctly
and it doesn't look like there's a node
specifically for that it's not that I
can find
yes I'm not sure I'm not sure how to get
I'm not sure how to get the deep memory
stuff out so I don't know if maybe the M
spaces were just we were using those
exclusively and we stopped using the
deep memory so there isn't a note in
here to view it anymore or something
like that I really can't remember it was
working at one point but I don't know if
it's actually working anymore I'm
assuming I can't do this is an M space
yeah
so I don't know I don't know what the
deal is with that it may be that that
got pulled out and for some reason
wasn't in there or maybe that I'm
forgetting the way that you actually do
it again because the UI is so janky it
may be that it's just like yeah you need
to do this other set of things didn't
you know
and then you can actually see it if you
look inside what the code says it looks
like it's going by eight by eight blocks
right and just yeah it's pretty clear
what's doing it should have just yeah I
mean that should have just been able to
gather this stuff up when we look at a
particular image so I'm not sure
unfortunately like I just don't remember
the code well enough to really remember
what was going on there or I'd go look
I'm pretty sure whiteboard where we at
plot process bla bla bla bla bla
yeah I don't see any I don't see
anything forward and so I don't know not
sure where it goes there was a previous
version of mustache that definitely had
deep memory implemented and I thought
this one did too but I may be we replace
them with M spaces because that's all
that anyone ever used and then I never
made the node to actually look at deep
memory which is unfortunate because deep
memory is cool although it basically
does the same thing as M spaces but just
for more generic regions of memory so I
guess I just never got around to
implementing that which is unfortunate
let me just go ahead and real quickly
double check that there isn't anything
that I've missed I would have liked to
have dem in the deep memory I don't know
if I have an older version of mustache
maybe I'll have to go look for one and
see if I can find it so I assume that
the image markup stuff if that stuff
works or not either
I could have sworn this stuff worked I'm
creeped out right now
so here's one thing I will say for sure
is that I know that the pixel inspector
would show all the transforms that stuff
went through and so at least with
respect to the EM spaces you could print
out all of the and I mean you saw this
kind of working but you could print out
all of the transforms that it went
through as you went through decoding a
frame and just see them all listed which
was made it obvious where your bug was I
guess the deep memory version of that
never got implemented or I just forget
how to view it which is too bad anyway
so I think that's most of it and like I
said this stuff just got stored take a
look here you would make a directory and
then you just run it there you can see
these MRF files this is the one where I
let that thing start storing images so
of course they get pretty big pretty
quickly but that's all it is and you
could send one of these MRF files was a
run of the program so you could also
send these MRF files around and that was
kind of nice so if you know if it broke
on my machine but it was if it was
Jeff's code that was potentially the one
that was causing the problem I could
just send him the MRF file and he could
view it and vice versa right so once you
capture a run it's yours to keep so to
speak and so that was also really nice
you just create a directory on your
machine and just let it fill up you
could even put in an external drive oh
whoops
you could even make an external drive
for it that just like you know you had
some huge you know two terabyte drive
that just sat there holding all the
moustache runs you know in asti you
would go what was the other file there's
an MWF file
so I think that's everything and again I
apologize the demos not particularly
smooth because I've forgotten how to use
most of it and it was a pretty janky
program but basically all of those
features like being able to track things
over time automatically having
everything remember how to organize and
lay out all your data so that when you
run a program multiple times you just
get it again the searching through the
logs for stuff and then showing that so
that you could always like pick out
different things you wanted to grab like
all of those things are features
debuggers could just have like there's
really no reason not to and there's also
no reason that the UI has to be janky
right if you sat down and tried to
figure out what a good design for the
I'd be I'm sure he could come up with it
it wasn't really the focus at the time
right because it wasn't a commercial
product but it's it's not like it's some
huge you know we'd have to imagine some
great leap of of computer engineering or
something right to make that happen
I will go ahead and and do a quick Q&amp;A
if anyone has questions about that but I
guess what I would say is that was just
stuff that was made in the course of
actually developing and so I'm
pretty sure that it's not the kind of
thing that would take that long to add
to a debugger that currently existed
there are some architectural things that
I guess are kind of hard that you have
to have to make an investment in like
storing the complete state of everything
all the time and all the source files
and all the data that got outputted and
all that stuff that is some work it's
not that hard and coming up with a good
UI is obviously also something that
would take some real work because that's
refinement and polish and thinking
things through in a way that's it's not
about programming it's about figuring
out the right way to expose things to
the user so that's also its own thing
you know but again the basic idea that
you can just do stuff like I
have an array of vertices and I want to
printf a log and say which vertex is
affected at any time and then later just
pick see a 3d version of a model pick
that vertex and see the history that is
as easy to implement as what I
implemented here for images right so
this same concept that ranges of memory
can just get tracked and then you just
tell me what the range of memory is and
I can go back and query all of these
printf and the printf scan have things
like 3d data or images or other stuff
it's all doable right any not that much
time you know 6 months of work you could
do all of this stuff right and so I
would just really encourage people to
start thinking about how much power we
could be putting into a debugger and
that we're not right so you know that's
the situation
what enter do I use I use for coder by
Allen Webster called e vu I've been
wanting to get into helping write video
codecs I thought about katrinak to a v1
but libo a.m. is a big bloated mess and
requires a lot of knowledge of vp9 is
there one you would recommend or would
want people working on so I'm not really
a video codec person I'm kind of the
wrong one to ask about that so I
apologize
I only ever really worked on and I
wasn't a video codec person I did
develop the half pal filter for it was
the one thing I did that was like video
codec related and it's a very good 1/2
pel filter I stand by my work on that
one but I didn't really do much else I
did the D blocking filter which is was
kay but it was really not a that great
it was more about what we could do
without taking any cpu time and that's
less relevant today than it was when
Bing - his first made think - was made
to scale to like 4k in software on you
know older machines and so what you
could do was limited and this was on an
Xbox 360 it also had to do 1920 by 1080
on that platform very cleanly as well
which is another hard thing cuz that
that CPU was not particularly powerful
anyway so but ignoring all of that I'm
just not really a video codec guy that's
not my thing
and so I don't have a lot of strong
recommendations about that what I would
say right is that I don't I don't think
the world needs a lot of work on the
existing video codecs I think what the
world needs is someone to sit down and
go how do I make a video codec that's
reasonable right like it's pretty good
but it's like you know 2,000 lines of
code or something right like the problem
of these video codecs like mp4 and stuff
like or you know that's more of a
container format but you know like AAC
and h.264 is they're like insane there
are these huge ridiculous like massive
investments in source code just to even
look at all of the crazy cases I was
like it would be nice if someone was
just like look this isn't the smallest
codec it's not the fastest codec but
it's a codec you could use like it
produces reasonably small video that
people could use and it's like in each
file right or something you know like
that seems like the more the thing the
world could actually use because oh my
god like this stuff is insane
you know and because I think the world
already has gigantic complex codecs
that's like mp4 and vp9 and all that
stuff right and the world already has
alike I want to pay a middleware vendor
for a really fast codec that's optimized
for every platform and has good support
on everything from Android to
PlayStation 4 to Tendo switch that's
right and so it seems like the only
thing I don't know that is like give me
an H file that has a compressor video
compressor that sort of works
it's like decent I don't know I don't
think there is one be nice or someone
would make one you know I just want to
include some video in this thing I don't
want to think about it too hard I don't
want to like build 18,000 files I don't
want to like deal with all that you know
poo shoes do you envision using a single
debugger or one for single single
stepping through the program and another
like mustache with more complex views I
kind of want it all together and the
reason that I want it all together is
that mustache requires you to augment
your code with calls to dump the data
right but there's no reason you couldn't
just ignore that and actually in your
debugger take the stash F calls like the
things that say here's what I want to
dump that could just be entirely in the
debugger I could just go into a line of
the debugger and say at this line dump
this data to my log then you never have
to touch the program and the program
doesn't even need to include an H file
or anything right it's just a program
could be a program you didn't even write
it could be a program you have source to
and you could say when you get to this
point in the program jump this region of
memory based off of these registers or
something right and then you could have
all the power of mustache without even
having to touch the source code right
and furthermore if that debugger store
run information you could even go back
in time and logged data from a run of a
program that didn't even have logging at
the time it was run right so I feel like
putting this into her actual debugger
could be way more powerful than mustache
even if it only supported the same
features as mustache having those
features accessible from the debugger
makes it more powerful right have you
tried the debugger like let me go ahead
and point this one out I've heard of
this one but I don't think I've ever
used it I have never used it I mean I
would be happy to try it it's just that
this kind of thing is usually not that
necessary for debugging programs that
you wrote this is more of a like reverse
engineering debugger it looks like right
so I don't know like it's probably
pretty cool and I think it would be a
good good program to use potentially I'd
have to try it and see what I thought of
it but I'm suspecting that it's not
really designed to do the sorts of
things that I would do with a debugger
right it looks like the kind of thing
for reverse engineering like you're
saying and reverse engineering isn't
really where like I don't need to
reverse engineer my own programs because
I wrote them right in what year was it
made moustache 2011 maybe marry SAV is
it using regular GDI or GDI + it's using
a regular GDI basically I wrote a
complete like image system for it
which I can show you it's not rocket
science
[Music]
so basically here's the Cindi operations
that I'm like I made like a thing for
operating on for wide floats in Cindy
and then what I did was yeah hold on a
second
you'll have to bear with me while I
remember where this stuff was so when we
did paint we called in to traverse
display window
I think Traverse display window might
have been refreshed display window you
know let me go ahead and load let me go
ahead and make a quick project file here
so I'm gonna put like I don't I don't
even remember hold on a second I haven't
updated for coder on this machine so let
me go ahead and and do that real quick
here so if I load up my for a coder
custom layer master does it like master
dot text or something mastered up here J
alright so if I make it mastered up prj
which we've never done on this machine
yet delete this here I'm not sure how
that works just racist right yeah okay
so the projects that we currently have
on this machine are like you know
handmade hero and that's in W handmade
handmade up proj there was handmade ray
and that was in a handmade raid approach
and then there was no there's meow hash
which was in yeah hash type proj so it
looks like that's everything and then
I'm just gonna add mustache and I'll put
that in here and that was in apps
mustache and we'll just call this
mustache dot proj I guess that seems I
guess good maybe yeah
so then inside mustache I'll just make a
project file for it and that way I can
load everything up and do searches and
stuff like that so if I do a mustache
dot prod file here I don't really
remember how this works but it's
something like this and there we go so
now I should be able to do like searches
and stuff so we can look at that source
code so let me go ahead and switch
project here shouldn't that of did I
mess it up again you have to forgive me
I'm in the middle of doing a bunch of
changes to for coders so I just I I'm
not really ready to do stuff like this
at the moment but I did make it
I made a double you mastered up here J
right did I did I organized it wrong or
something the string constant string
constant there's a name and a file
I mean I feel like that should have just
worked right it looks right to me but uh
[Music]
but I guess not it's gonna read w
mastered up ROG but that's good that's
what I want
took a nice it's gonna look at look for
an open brace string constant Oh yep no
comma all right so maybe now I've done
the right thing yeah there we go all
right so if I load mustache now I should
be able to jump around everything so I
don't know let's see here here's that
refresh thing okay so does it Traverse
just right display window then that we
were doing yeah
all right so in Traverse display window
we should be able to look at some of
that drawing code now and like I just
I'm going to look out I'm going to see
if I can find something that looks like
it's doing some drawing and then I'll
show you what that code looks like this
so you get you were you were wondering
about how it was running that fast on
just straight to the eye so let's see
here on something that's going to render
like an image source so here's the image
node right and let's see it's got
inspect work create work render work so
blitz scaled so that's something that's
dealing with an image right so here's
blitz scaled and here's what that
routine looks like right so yeah all
right so basically what you can see here
is I do the basic setup work right I
look here to see if I need to do aspect
ratio scaling oops sorry about the
swearing there we'll just scroll that
off unlike on hand me here where I'm
trying to be clean but I'm working
professionally I swear all the time so
anyway in the code here you can see me
setting up the image transfer and then
I've just got two functions that I wrote
one is blit one-to-one which does an
exact copy you can see it doing it here
and then there's lit sampled and there's
more swearing and you can see that
working here and what you can see is
they're all just cindy code right there
just like hey let's just process for for
color values at a time right RGBA we
load those in and we we write them out
right and I think I mean yeah if you
just write this stuff sanely using Dib
sections through regular GDI just
Cyndi's very fast right I don't I don't
even know if this is multi-threaded I
mean it might have been but I don't know
I guess I can find out
No so it wasn't even multi-threaded that
was single-threaded performance it's
just if you write cindy routines and you
do them reasonably smart you can just do
it how long did probably take you to
write I don't know exactly it was at
least six months of full-time work I
don't understand why using GL DX is not
an option for an internal tool like that
well the reason was stability so Jeff
just didn't like what open gel would
sometimes do in terms of multi-monitor
support or destabilizing a system
because the graphics drivers were bad
and so on since this entire thing ran on
the CPU you could guarantee that was not
screwing with the graphics card at all
and all that had to do was if GDI could
just manage to get the buffer to like
get handed off to the graphs card that's
all I had to do that was why the
decision was made wasn't my decision
that's just that's just why it was done
that way and no it was not ever supposed
to be released why do you not name this
meows - I don't know it's a good
question will you upload this to youtube
yeah probably
and also I turned on archiving on the
twitch stream now so you should be able
to get back to those are you still
getting feedback - the wind debug dev
team on Twitter for where it's still
lacking its current state did you still
like it better than the vs debugger so
two things one I was a little nervous
about the feedback situation because a
lot of the responses from the windbg guy
it kind of sounded like they weren't
really that interested in making it work
well like I'm like
you know there needs to be a hotkey for
setting a breakpoint and they were like
yeah we used most of the hotkeys that we
have available or something like they
were weird answers that kind of sounded
more like they had a particular way they
want it to work and they weren't super
interested in it necessarily feedback on
like hey there really needs to be hockey
for this like it's important maybe make
rebind double hotkeys or something if
you have a different opinion about what
needs to be hotkey but like you know so
it seemed like maybe they weren't that
interested in feedback they were only
kind of like interested in minor
feedback like there's a bug crashes here
or something like that so I'm not super
optimistic what I will say is I do like
it better than visual Studios debugger
from the following standpoint it doesn't
install sequel server on my machine for
example right I just copy the directory
and it works if you actually want to use
visual Studios debugger
it installs massive amounts of
unnecessary things in your machine
requires licensing to run that can just
stop working at any time without your
knowledge and without you necessarily
knowing why even when you're a paying
customer this happens it's just not good
right and so I don't like the experience
as much as using Visual Studio and I'm
not really super sure based on what I
kind of heard from the window bug people
that they're really all that interested
in making it good in that sense but
because it is usable and isn't an epic
disaster that makes it better than
Visual Studio in terms of just what I'll
learn to live with right and the hope is
that you know someday rad ships won and
then I'll just buy that and I'll use
that right because there's so much
better debugging out there to be had and
we just need that to come along but
really that's the main thing is just
windbg preview is usable like I can
debug with it and so I think I just
would rather do that than half
to deal with Visual Studio because it's
Visual Studio is so broken at this point
did you add those new features too for
coder yes during the stream Ryan Reese
said I'm still on the fence about that
unusual interpretation of the
compilation model the everything is in
this header file I'm interested if there
are any downsides to it um well I guess
what I would say is I don't necessarily
know that everything needs to be in a
header file for everything right it's
just something like this if you're
talking about something that's just
designed to be a debug port then yeah of
course it should all be in the H file it
should be a tiny H file it should do
everything right if because it's the
easiest possible thing to include into
your program right um that doesn't
assume it's right for everything it just
means for this sort of thing I can't
think of any downsides to it and if
there are they're drastically outweighed
by the simplicity of just being able to
copy one file into your project and then
be done you know you don't have to worry
about linking and you don't have to
worry about dll's or copying things
around with executable you have to worry
if somebody changes it it's not going
out to a web site to do something or any
of this other garbage or package
managers or github or any of this other
stuff it's just I had an h-file worked I
copied into my program I was done right
and that's very good
I think c64 debugger had a pixel to code
features like mustache um I don't know
what c64 oops I don't know what c64
debugger is Oh No I've lost my I've lost
my earpiece I got it like put a new
earpiece on in fact why don't I just do
that now do I have that your pieces no I
don't I need to do that because this
earpiece got so loose that it just comes
out all the time I need to get the new
one for it what I was gonna say is c64
debugger I don't I'm not familiar with
but what I can tell you is there are
graphics specific debuggers which do
some of the moustache stuff they're not
quite the same because they don't really
allow you to printf arbitrary data out
to it I don't think maybe they do but
for example pix p IX the graphics
debugger from Microsoft that was like
for DirectX debugging it would at least
allow you to see like everything that
touched a particular pixel in the
graphics output right so that's
something and that was similar
did you use GDI functions for stuff like
spline drawing or did you do it yourself
I feel like I would have called GDI if
it had it because why would I have
written it myself so like for fonts I
think I just called GDI
to draw the fonts cuz it could do that
right fast it can't deal with images
fast very well at the time anyway
let me see if I got any what else we got
here
why do sometimes use the end and not
pointers yeah I used to use references
more and here's the thing I don't think
C should have dot and arrow I think that
was dumb and so I used to use references
so I could just use dot everywhere but
then eventually I would just like forget
it like I might as well make my code
like basically C compilable for C 99 and
just use pointers like why not
it's just I'm fine with it right so I
used to still use ampersand for that
reason and I wish that they just would
make it so that dot worked for pointers
but you know they don't want some well
like the vertical text on the left in
your fur coat or build is really cool is
it available in for coder or is it your
own customization that is my own
customization the for coders stuff that
I've done is pretty advanced at this
point so one thing that you'll notice it
now knows is it knows when things are
functions or types that are user-defined
for example I implemented that yeah the
stuff that says like what if block
you're in if it's off-screen and what
function you're and stuff like that
stuff here I'm printed all that also
this jump thing I implemented too that
like finds everything in your program
and let's go jump to it the project's
which are all that stuff so I
implemented a ton of things over the
past two weeks that's when I was on back
from break but haven't been back on
stream none of it is possible to share
with you at the moment because I had to
modify the for coder core to do it but I
have resubmitted the changes back to
Allen so at least in theory at some
point you will be able to have these
features that time is not now but when
Allen
has a chance to integrate my changes
into his codebase and she ships a new
for coder then you could have the
changes I also did some other stuff like
search now works so you know when you do
like sizeof it'll highlight all the ones
in in the view you know stuff like that
that wasn't working for I also added a
feature that's super crazy
I haven't finished some of it yet but
I'll show you it's really strange so
let's suppose you're in here and you
want to do some math basically this was
because I was really tired of this
garbage like having to go to some other
tool to do math I was like I don't
really want to have to do that anymore
so what I did was I just made it so like
okay you know if you're in a comment and
you want to do I just want to know some
stuff I can just do it so if I want to
know what 9 how many pixels there are in
1920 by 1080 right I can just do it and
it just tells me it just it just does
the math for you right and so if I want
to know like how many bytes that is I
can do it that way or something and well
okay maybe maybe not why does that not
[Music]
clearly I have broken something alright
so again like I said not quite done yet
so that's weird
this stuff was working i'm the other
machine I wonder would something must
have broke with comment lexing
what's going on here sorry this is not
really what I supposed to be doing on
the stream interesting so something
broke with comment lexing but I'm not
sure what it is so I guess I've got a
new new bug I got to go look look at but
anyway it has all the basic stuff in it
so you can also assign variables so like
if you want you can do that and so then
like in here you can do that right you
know I'm saying and so the idea there is
just that from then on I can just make
it so that I don't ever have to switch
away anymore when we're doing that stuff
on stream I can just put it into the
comment and the nice part about that is
it can remain in the comment so it's
just there like real like oh this is
when we did that thing and here's the
answer and then I don't have to like
deal with it anymore
right why this lexer thing is not
working properly I'm not sure so I got a
look at why that is and furthermore it's
a little bit weird cuz it looks it
looked like it was not even sensitive to
what else you might do so I'm not sure
I'm not sure how that's possible
yeah it's very interesting so
something's weird about that but I'd
really just don't know what it is it's
like it only wants to Lex that one
what's going on there that's gonna be
interesting bug to find I can tell you
that right now
is it just five times five is it just
that there's a bug you know what it's
probably is there's just a probably a
bug in the multiplication term parser
where it's not asking for an ADD term
next to it so it's probably just the
parser that's all it is yeah
as far as the parsers breasted we'll fix
that later
so yeah ignore this for now it's not not
really ready for primetime but it will
be at some point and yeah don't ask me
why it's busted I don't know probably
the parsers messed up let's see
we should probably change it to shunting
yard anyway I think right now it's
actually was building the actual parse
tree or something stupid like that I
don't know it's a long story
how would you port a game from Windows
to Mac Oz when the code bases and see
any resources to share Thanks yeah I
know so it's weird right it just doesn't
look like it it it doesn't know what to
do with concatenated multiplication it's
very strange so like that's correct but
that not only it just can't figure it
out it's like I don't know what's going
on so I think the parser is broken is
what's happening there so I'll have to
look at what's going on there I don't
know what is happening
yeah I mean again I don't even know if
parentheses work or not yeah it looks
like that it looks like they work with
parentheses so it looks like it's just
the parser for the term for the
multiplicative term it's just not doing
the right thing after it oh the colors I
haven't tuned yet that the colors are
garbage I'm gonna
they're just debug colors to make sure
that I was seeing the right thing that
all right
no it's not a problem with the asterisk
being part of a comment it's just it's
just gonna the parser as far as service
crap it was got kind of threw it in
there the math expression parsing
extremely cool can implement it with the
current customization layer or is it
only possible with the open with the
source available it's only possible with
the source available not because of the
parsing you could do a math expression
parsing because I implanted that myself
and you could do that you could do them
at yourself
but the problem is twofold you don't
have a way to actually know when you
need to reparse the buffer I added that
and the other thing is you don't have a
way to draw text that isn't part of the
buffer and I added that so the those
things there right because remember
those aren't there so if you now go back
and look at the file right so that file
was something like uh s to be painting
test dot CPP right it doesn't it just
saves that and it doesn't insert the
answers right they're just floating
phantom answers
ya know the colors aren't permanent
don't worry the colors are just there
because I was trying to debug I want I
didn't have a chance to actually go tune
the colors and I was just trying to make
sure that like all my parsing stuff
actually worked right
anybody else well good
oh right somebody that's crucial right
how would you port a game from Windows
to Mac offs when the co basis in C so
you know a lot of that just depends on
how the code was written originally so
the way I try to make code work across
platforms if I try to isolate all of the
parts that are actually specific to the
platform and you you know hey make sure
we've done that very specifically you
can go look at it and you can see how
it's very it's very walled off you're
not allowed to have any win32 code
outside of the win32 file you know and
that's the way that I do things so the
first thing I would do if I had to port
an existing game from Windows to Mac Oz
is I would go through the code on
Windows and try to pull out all of the
window specific stuff into its own
separate area like its own separate file
that I could then replace with MacOS
versions that's how I would go about it
you know there's there's not a lot else
you can do but that's a good way very
similar to that one good way to port
something is to say alright isolate all
the windows code then on Windows still
not on Mac us go get SDL to write they
ask the simple directmedia layer to
write an STL layer that replaces the
Windows layer so that you can still
compile it on the windows layer you
isolated and on SDL - and run it on
Windows under STL - and now you know it
runs under SDL - which also runs on Mac
now you can move it over to Mac compile
it with SDL - on Mac and get that
working and off
right so you can kind of go through
these stages of like isolating the parts
that were actually specific to Windows
right wouldn't you cover the Raspberry
Pi
well we won't really do anything with
other platforms until the game is done
right like when the game is released we
will then go and look at other platforms
like Raspberry Pi which I don't know
what it might not be the Raspberry Pi if
that's not the most appropriate platform
at the time I'm assuming it still will
be but like we'll find whatever the most
appropriate like you know single board
little computer is and we'll look at
that which will probably still be a
Raspberry Pi of some kind the Raspberry
Pi 5 or something you know but if
there's some other thing that's more
popular at that time we we do that other
one instead do you know how the calendar
and date are implemented in games I'm
not sure what you mean do you mean like
we're talking about like games like
Animal Crossing that try to do like
different like special things on
Halloween or something Nathan dearth
I've heard a lot of people complaining
about C++ which has me worried and
looking into other languages is there
any problem continuing to use minimal
C++ like you do currently can new C++
features hurt you
I think it's probably relatively safe to
continue using minimal C++ like I do I'm
certainly not too panicked about that
specifically I guess what I would say is
there are two costs associated with C++
that I mean certainly worried me and are
you are right to be worried and they are
as follows number one because C++ is
designed primarily by people who don't
actually you know do real game
programming for a living they don't tend
to add the features that are necessary
for real game programming and so at the
moment C++ is lacking many features that
you would obviously have if you were
trying to make a language that was good
for this if you contrast C++ which just
had 30 years to make these additions to
for example jei which John has been
working on for only a couple years you
can already see literally hundreds of
features that he has added that C++ it's
not added and again the difference there
is you've got a working game programmer
one who's very good making features for
what they do
and so the biggest cost of using C++ is
a language design paradigm and process
that basically doesn't take your needs
into account right so that's the biggest
problem right so as a result every year
your programming gets worse compared to
what it would be if you could have a
language that would add features that
were necessary to allow you enable you
to write better code faster so that's a
huge issue and it's been happening for a
long time so it means that if you
compare what your code quality should be
today under a C++ that was guided by you
know design principles along
Road versus what they did choose to do
you know the the difference is kind of
somewhat staggering if we were actually
to think about what we would have today
if if you know if it had been shepherded
in that direction
so that's very concerning because it
does mean that there's a lot on the
table and it also means that your
ability to write effective code compared
to say working in other languages that
remember Shep maybe we're shepherded
better like c-sharp or something it do
you take a hit and so as a result you
know there's reasons why you might not
want to use c-sharp I mean I don't use
it right because I don't want the extra
layers of indirection that are inherent
there and I don't want to have to worry
about certain aspects of it and so on
the problem is every year the C++
committee continues to make bad language
design decisions you get further and
further behind languages that might be
making better decisions who have
problems because they were rooted in a
systems programming language to begin
with but there's they're getting better
and we're getting worse right because of
the design decisions and that's a really
bad situation right so that's thing one
and thing two is that even though you
don't have to use the poorly designed
features that are coming into C++ they
do hurt you in one very important way
which is they are complexity that gets
put into the compiler and that
complexity yields more bugs for you
right because the amount of effort
that's put into the compiler is finite
there's a certain amount of work getting
done on clang and a certain amount of
work being done on Visual Studio because
those implementers must implement the
poorly designed C++ language features as
they come out that is time they're not
spending debugging the optimizer
improving the optimizer debugging the
debug info debugging the code Jen
all of that is not going into giving you
an improved product because you're not
using the C++ features right so there
are definitely two very real ways that
the poor design direction of C++ affects
everyday programmers who you know know
better than to use it but in the sense
that you can still write C code and it
compiles properly you're not hurt that
much in that sense my hope is we won't
keep having to have this discussion my
hope is that we can reasonably move on
to ji or something or there will be more
languages coming about with the system
programming angle to them and C++ can
just go off and die in a corner right
like I I don't think it's productive to
constantly relitigate the C++ thing it's
not a good language let's just accept
that it's not going to be a good
language so let's just focus on what
will be like let's try to get to
something that is right and then people
who think C++ is good for some reason
you can still use it right it's still
there but those of us who don't think so
can can have something to move to that's
what we really need right what we really
need is an alternative because sitting
around complaining about C++ isn't
really gonna help we've been doing it
for 30 years that's never gotten any
better so like what we need is in what
we need is a way to move to an
alternative that we can contribute to
and make good would you see that Hameed
here a platform layer for Windows and
OpenGL is at a shipping State now I mean
I guess what I'll say is games have
shipped on worse probably but is it the
ideal thing that you would ship with
definitely not so you know it's probably
possible to ship a game on the handmade
hero platform layer but I wouldn't
recommend it because we haven't done
some of the finishing work that you
would want to do for a final product
even just basic things like keyboard
layout support and stuff like that we
haven't really addressed and so I think
there you know in order to have a
quality experience there's things we
would want to add and there's notes to
that effect in our platform layer at the
moment in fact do I have an opinion on
the rest no not really I haven't
programmed in rust
I've added some fancy file hungers of
the platform layer notify whether a file
has changed etc and for every new
function I just added it to the platform
API struct is it that simple yeah it is
exactly that simple
how's 19:35 going pretty good I've had
to divert some attention because meow
the infinite will be launching soon but
but pretty good
you will hear hopefully more about it
in the not-too-distant future have you
ever used embedded Lua do I have to pay
on Luigi no I I don't I have not used
those things for programmers what do you
think skill is most what skill do you
okay I see you're saying for programmers
what skill do you normally think is most
commonly lacking and are there any
practicing methods people should use to
become better programmers yeah I mean I
think I've sort of answered this before
but I'll just it's pretty easy to
summarize I think the primary problem is
that people don't actually look at the
results of their coding practices that's
really the thing that I that I would
like most people to do I mean
dovetailing on to the the previous
discussion about C++ that's my criticism
of that language design as well people
aren't taking the results of their
programming practices seriously they're
not looking to see whether the things
they claim prevent bugs actually are
preventing bugs they're not looking at
whether or not they get more code done
that has less bugs in it in the same
amount of time there's just a lot of
things that are sort of stated as fact
but that have no actual basis in reality
and that's a problem and I think what
every programmer can do to help
themselves get away from that is to just
actually look at your actual what when
you adopt programming practices look and
verify
that they're actually saving you time
that they're actually catching bugs you
know don't just type Const into your
code see if you're actually having bugs
related to modifying things that you're
not supposed to modify if you're not
then you're wasting time with that right
and those are basic things that
everybody should do everybody should
know at this point if you're experienced
programmer at all
where do your bugs come from and which
programming practices actually help
catch them and which don't because it's
different for everybody it's not the
same when people say that this is a good
programming practice that's usually
ridiculous because usually at best it
can only be a good programming practice
for a particular programmer or for a
particular team right but I would say in
general like that's really the thing
that programmers should focus on that
they focus on the least is actually
assess 'lord the practices that you're
doing helping are they doing what you
thought they were doing when you adopted
them and it's really important to
understand it's really important to
understand that there's just a lot of
dogma in programming and it's not useful
right and so when I talk about things
that I have found to be good programming
practices what I'm talking about are
things that I've found are effective and
I've looked at them and they save me
time relative to the alternatives right
even that is not good enough or
shouldn't be good enough for you you
should be taking the things that I say
and say oh okay Casey thinks this is
good so it might be good but maybe my
brain doesn't work that way and maybe it
doesn't help me to do that thing and so
what Casey's saying to do is really just
a waste of my time and this other thing
works better right learning to be able
to do that analysis is critical because
it's totally fine to go look on the web
or listen to this stream or do whatever
else to learn about the possible
techniques you could use because people
other people are gonna have thought of
things that you won't think of but
what's not
is assuming that they're right just
because someone on the web said it right
because that doesn't matter like Derrick
we don't have the kind of science right
now necessary to prove that a
programming practice is good or bad and
furthermore I suspect it differs from
person to person right kind of like what
diet you should eat isn't probably
universal like people from you know a
particular country a particular genetic
lineage probably want to eat a different
diet than other people because humans
are different right and programming is
the same way this the same set of
techniques is not right for everybody
and you want to learn how to actually
assess how you are programming and then
you can test out these techniques to
find out which ones I use are good for
you
which ones someone else uses are good
for you and that's how you become a
better programmer
how do I become a bigger programmer an
excellent question it's difficult
question on the discord how are your
compiled time so fast I've compiled sort
of programs to sewer linkage to Windows
and others are saying they're compiling
handmade hero on a pc + SSD and getting
quite slower compiles is your computer
just that much faster I don't know I
mean it depends on the SSD drive
potentially or the computer this is a
pretty fast computer at this one but I
don't know I mean one of the big
problems with visual studios you don't
get much of a build profile out of it I
don't know if there's switches now that
you can get more of a build profile but
it's kind of hard to know where the
time's going see time tells you the time
for any individual step of your build
but it doesn't really help you in
profile the internals so it's kind of
hard to know you know if Visual Studio
compiles at a certain speed on one
machine and the last certain speed at
another it's hard to know exactly what
the slowdown is is it you know related
to this or that you know ginger brill
says the issue is that the vast rated
printers don't know anything about the
scientific method or learning from
empirical data to improve their scale if
people actually treated computer
sciences an actual science would help a
huge amount I would broaden that to not
just good programmers most people don't
understand the scientific method they
don't understand that when you call
something science that's just an
arbitrary term only things verified by
the scientific method are actually true
right or I shouldn't say true repeatable
and repeatability is what you actually
care about in the world and so there's a
tremendous number of things also that
are branded science that aren't science
because at least in my mind they don't
follow scientific method scientific
methods the only thing that actually
matters the word science is irrelevant
scientists are irrelevant it's only if
you've done the scientific method - its
completion that you actually know
anything right and the same is true of
programming right
and unfortunately for programming I
would say we're pretty far from being
able to really
by the scientific method for real right
so you can only really do kind of a
loose version of it anyway but you
should try as best you can to actually
do experiments and see what the results
are to the extent that you can but I
would say that one of the big reasons
that computer science can't really touch
a lot of areas that we would like it to
is because the scientific method just
really can't be applied really in any
way that we know about yet how do you
reason with people heavily invested in
programming dogma I don't I just don't
work with those people right do you know
of a way to get rid of order dependence
and see I thought about actually parsing
the code but that seems quite annoying
that's the only way I wish there was a
way in situ to fix that but as far as I
know there isn't
I wish C had had a function keyword I
think that would have solved just about
everything but unfortunately you know
function keyword and maybe a different
casting syntax and then it wouldn't have
been really a problem right you wouldn't
need forward declaration really and
stuff would have just worked probably
but you know it didn't and it doesn't so
that's just the way it is again same
thing you know C++ could have fixed this
they chose not to they chose to focus on
all these other things that don't help
hopefully again there'll be different
languages in the future like Jay I
doesn't have order dependence that's a
great start
right
can I have an opinion on the overuse of
virtual methods in C++ in the V table or
head not really I don't have a problem
with virtual methods and virtual tables
as a concept because that is one way you
can do dispatch tables my objection to
the C++ version as with everything in
C++ is it wasn't implemented properly it
should have been implemented as an
optional feature that you could enable
you could say I would like you to
construct a virtual table here is the
things I'd like to put in the virtual
table and here is the member that I
would like to use to point to it right
that would have given you the ability to
have multiple virtual tables per struct
if you wanted to it would give me the
ability to have copied the virtual
tables around it would have been the
ability to store an integer and to use
that to look up into the virtual tables
so she could have had archie TI
implemented in your code rather than and
see again my complaint with c++ is
almost never about the things the
compiler is generating it's that that
thing was not interfaced properly the
same is true with virtual methods it was
just a poor design all right I'm gonna
wrap it up soon here got but we got lots
of questions I heard that in the classic
serious same game they implemented the
multi gravity for the player to move
along the walls do you know how the
multi gravity works
I'm sorry not familiar with serious Sam
and I'm not sure what multi gravity
means in this case what is your opinion
on formal verification do you think
there are any applications of it in game
programming I guess I don't know formal
verification is certainly interesting
but the problem with it is that it's
pretty limited in terms of what it can
actually verify a lot of times and it
tends to not be really great with user
input so the kinds of things that we
might want to ask regarding formal very
kind of things we might want to formally
verify in games tend to be very hard to
verify so it's tough to say what I can
say is the broader idea that algorithms
can be written
foreclose the possibility of bugs I do
think as the loot has a loose
application games I would point you to
the collision detector I wrote for the
witness as an example that was an
algorithm specifically designed to
possible to have movement bugs out of
potato certain layer of the game code
and I think that worked very well
again it's not totally formal
verification but it's a kind of
verification or a kind of formality that
can be imposed on the code in a looser
sense that does have a lot of
applicability in games so I you know as
a partial answer to your question
there's you know there's something the
DMD compiler can tell you which lines of
source code take the longest to compile
so unsurprisingly I suppose to templates
yeah
unsurprisingly all right looks like we
are done I'm gonna go ahead and wrap it
up thank you everyone for joining me for
this special presentation of moustache
on handmade hero I will be posting
stream schedules soon I'm not sure
exactly what we'll be doing stream wise
I may try to stream some of the for
coder development that I've been doing
because I'm finishing that up in the
next couple days I may try to stream
some of that in which case I'll be back
pretty soon if I don't decide to treat
me that I may not be back till next
weekend we'll see but I'll be posting a
few scheduled fairly soon as soon as I
forgot exactly when the streams will be
so stay tuned for that and again they
always they'll show up on this handmade
hero watch page here when the stream is
not live it puts a little schedule there
for us
so you can know when we're gonna be live
there's also of course the handmade hero
Twitter feed but yeah that's just kind
of a disaster so just use the watch page
that's about it for today thanks for
joining me I hope that anyone out there
working on debuggers can maybe think
about adding some of those moustache
features to their debugger because
there's a lot of good stuff in there but
it's kind of not really useful for the
majority of the world at the moment
because it's just in this little
internal rad tool and it wasn't really
polished to the point where it could be
easily accessible by people either so I
feel like getting that stuff out into
sort of the real world it would be it
would be pretty good so that's it thanks
for joining me I will talk to y'all next
time until then have fun programming and
I'll see everyone on the Internet