mega green lightning i'm glad you're
hyped for the kickstarter
everyone get hyped for the kickstarter
you have the link now you have no excuse
meow the infinite
finest all ages cats and space graphic
novel you will ever see
books one and two available now from the
kickstarter
it'll blow your f in mind
you wanna know something
you see that right there
[Music]
that
it's an effing space shark
this book has sharks in space
it'll blow your f in mind dude it has
sharks in space
you know what that is
that's a distress message from an f in
space sheep there are sheeps in space
okay
it's like princess f and leia was a
sheep sending a message it's right there
if that doesn't make you back
kickstarter i don't know what to say to
you