ok hello everyone and welcome to a
special edition of handmade hero this is
not actually part of the main handmade
hero in that it has nothing to do with
game programming but what I wanted to
show today was I'm going to add there's
a little utility that I have that I've
been meaning to release for a long time
I kept forgetting to release it and I
never you know I don't ever like
actually having to use anything like
github or any of these sorts of things
but of course since there were so many
people who asked to have a hand made
here at github and we have the one right
now that if you know if you pre-order
the game you get on that special github
or whatever now there is a way to
actually have things go up there
automatically since I have a little
script that just pushes our changes to
it so I was like finally release the
thing I should do it so I wanted to give
a little brief demo of what it is it's
very very simple utility but it's kind
of useful and especially useful for
people who maybe are in situations where
they work on larger teams and have
problems with their build times and
stuff like this so this is a utility
called see time and you can see here
that I've typed it into the command line
here and it printed out its little usage
information and what this utility is
designed to do is this utility is
designed to give you some perspective on
what your build times actually are and
how much time you're spending sitting
around waiting to have your projects
built if that makes sense so you know
typically when ends up happening if
you're somebody like me you're extremely
extremely careful about your build times
and you make sure that your build times
are always very very small and so for
example you know if I have a build time
that's getting to be 10 seconds or
something like that I think that that's
probably a really big problem and I
should go look at why the build is
taking so long and make sure that it's
like stays well below 10 seconds you
know I consider that emergency however
there are a lot of places out there
which don't seem to have very much
respect for how problematic lung build
times actually are and they have these
turnaround times for doing full rebuilds
of things that are like in the not just
in the minutes some
times in the hours and I think that is
like extremely extremely problematic and
obviously there's lots of people who
disagree and I like that is someplace
that I just do not see even remotely
eye-to-eye with those people if if you
ever have a build time that goes into a
minute long you've done something
horrifically horrifically wrong because
you can compile massive code bases you
can compile code bases that are hundreds
of thousands of lines even millions of
lines in much less time than that so you
have to kind of ask yourself how did you
let it get to the point where your build
times are taking that long and why do
you not see sort of the really
deleterious effects if that has it's
something that really stops the flow of
programming it makes it so that testing
various things becomes very very
difficult for programmers to do and even
if you've got it so that you can
recompile little portions that's not the
same because there's plenty of changes
you might want to make and that affect
large numbers of files in your system
and if you've basically put in place
this negative reinforcement so that
programmers are incentivized to make
tiny changes to small parts go base but
massively disincentivize to change large
parts of the code base well you've
basically ensure that you will never get
improvements that cover large parts of
the code base that's what you did right
so you have to be very very very careful
about build times and I really wish more
people were and so this utility is kind
of a thing you can use to help gather
information about your builds make sure
that you stay honest about your build
timings and also be able to perhaps use
to demonstrate to people that build
times are a problem if they don't
believe that they are or at least so
that you're not just randomly saying
stuff like well I think our bill takes
too long or stuff like that so let's see
how to use this tool in practice and
what I've done like I said is I put it
in the handmade hero build now and so if
you take a look when you if you download
it from send owl if you're if you've I
thought so you normally get it for or if
you go to the github if that's where you
normally get it from if you already
bought a handmade hero and have X to it
it's in there already so you just you
have it and after the stream I will push
it and it'll be up there well I guess
actually technically me
it's tomorrow that it gets pushed I
don't know whenever the next push is by
the end of Monday stream at least it'll
just be in there and off off it goes but
I also put it the the notice on it puts
it in the public domain so you can also
feel free to grab it and put it out at
that point so it's it's not protected by
the handmade hero license it's got a
public domain license and it can just be
free for everyone to use so if you take
a look in the handmade directory it's
gets in there there's the seat I'm
directory it's got the the single see
file source code is all it takes to
build it so you can also modify if you
want to but let's take a look at how to
use it so the way that it works is it's
exactly analogous to block profiling for
an application but it's for builds so
what you do is you basically put a begin
and end pair around anything that you
want to time and instead of giving it a
name like you would in a normal block
profile or you just give it a file and
that file is where it stores the timings
and it will store those timings forever
so as many times as you run that build
it will update that timing file with an
entry for having entered so it's
literally if you've ever used a block
profiler even like the kind we made on a
handmade hero you already know how this
works it works exactly like that and
I'll show you how we do that here by
just adding it to the handmade hero
build as we go so let's open up for it
and I'll show you what we have right now
for our handmade here a build right here
is our project and when I normally build
it right that's what we see over there
there's a hameed setp korean lie right
that's the build happening but you'll
notice even right off the bat there's
kind of this this annoying thing of like
I don't know how long that build took
right just yeah i mean i know that
handmade heroes build process is not a
problem we always make sure like i said
i'm very diligent that i keep it short
but even I because we never talked about
see time normally my builds at work I
always know exactly how long every build
takes but if you look here I have no
idea how long this bill takes and that's
a common situation for a lot of people
to be in is they don't really know how
long their build even took they have no
idea right and sometimes your build you
know your compiler may have a switch you
can turn on may be printed out but if
you have other steps you don't know and
if you compile multiple things you might
not know how
long it takes right so there's all these
kind of things where you don't
necessarily know depending on the tools
you took a pic or whatever you may not
even know what your total bill time is
which is a problem to begin with right
so see time and at the very least solves
that problem because what you can do
it's all go ahead and load up the build
up back here is our build a batch file
this is what does our build so what I
can do now is I can say well okay i
would like to record the timing for this
build so what I'm going to do at the top
of it is I'm just going to type C time
begin and that seat I'm begin call
allows me to basically say I'm starting
at a timing block right just like a
normal timing thing with now I need a
place to put it and normally uh it you
know I have a directory in my build
system where I just put all of my timing
files so normally i would have a record
to that but i'm just going to go ahead
and put it in here you can see the the
normally I believe we run the build from
directly out of here I'm just going to
put the timing foul on there and we'll
just check them in and we'll keep them
around because there's no reason not to
they don't get that huge you know maybe
they're 100 200 k after two years of
programming or some like that but it's
not like you really care how big they
are they're not onerous right so what
I'm going to do is I'm going to say C
time begin and I'm just going to say
like handmade hero dot ctm okay and and
that'll just keep our timings in there
and off we go and then at the very end
when we get down to to the very end of
the thing I'm just going to say to you
time and I'm going to pass it the same
file right so basically that's just the
beginning the end block for the
profiling and now when I build right you
can see that I now know exactly how long
my build takes because at the end of
that profiling block it'll tell me how
long to build went in right here for
example it says 1.3 27 seconds so I now
at least know unlike before how long are
build is well are billed for handmade
hero takes 1.3 seconds to to occur and
you know that's mine perfectly
comfortable like I said like anything
under you know two three four or five
seconds I'm okay with that when it
starts to crawl up towards 10 I'm
nervous right heaven forfend that things
come comes back and says 24 minutes or
something like this that would be real
bad but yeah that's
that's a separate issue so anyway so
that's how sue time works and every time
you build it'll do exactly that so you
can see I can build this multiple times
and it just keeps saying you know cure
town is so first of all at least if you
do nothing else with it at least you
could know how long your build is and
always be aware of that which I find
helpful just to begin with but it has a
few more nice features and I'll go over
what those are now so here we are in
this directory and if I do a directory
you can kind of see in fact I guess I'll
isolated for you there it is that's the
file that we created the handmade here
at ctm and obviously if you want profile
multiple blocks independently that's
pretty easy to do you can just do see
time and you can commune Oh put it put
it put a separate beginning and pair
around any particular parts that you
want at a time and then they will be
recorded into a file like that once you
actually have one of those files you can
start to ask questions about it so for
example if I want to I can say well why
don't you tell me some things about that
block right and what that does is that
basically gives you a dump which says
okay how many times did you actually get
complete timings and a complete timing
is one where the beginning end pair
actually executed so if you have a begin
and you never get to the end because
maybe the batch file crashed or
something like that that would be
incomplete timing and those are not
counted because they don't know how long
they took so if you have a begin
followed by another begin it will count
that first again as an incomplete timing
because you don't want it to you know it
has no idea what it is and then it'll
give you just the basic statistics how
long was the slowest build how long was
the fastest build how long was your
average build and how many total seconds
did you spend in builds for whatever
these these were marked and we'll talk
about this successful part in a second
because we haven't quite gotten there
yet and then these are not particularly
useful yet because we haven't really
recorded more than one day's worth but
after you record multiple days worth of
timings it will actually start to fill
in these graphs so you can kind of see
over time how you're built has been
progressing and in the all this up here
where it says all these graphs show you
how your build has been over the
lifetime of the project and as you know
you can see here like this will go up so
days between first and last timing is
zero because we haven't had multiple
days as that gets longer it'll say like
oh 200 days have elapsed between the
first build in the last
old recorded by hand recorded by sea
time or something like that right it
also gives you this recent one which is
just one day per bucket here and that's
the last 30 days right so you can kind
of see how your builds have been going
recently and how many this is how many
there were each day and this is how long
each one was taking and this is the
average times here no sorry that's is
this is the worst times here is what's
recorded in these in these buckets right
finally the end is probably the most
interesting number that you care about
which is how long have you been waiting
for your builds and so for example I
been running see time on our current
product at Molly rocket and the base the
the the the base build for that project
has been a total of two hours spent
building it over the course of the past
year and a half so that's just an
example of like how much programmer time
did you actually lose over the course of
a year and a half or whatever waiting
for builds because they couldn't test
something and had to do something like
try to pipeline other changes with her
right how much was it actually impacting
their ability to test changes now you
know right so that's a pretty
interesting number the other thing that
you can do with it is you can say well I
would like to get this out into some
kind of a graph that I can use or maybe
run it through an analysis tool or
create a presentation based on it and so
what you can do is you can pass minus
CSV to it and what it'll do is it'll
give you a little thing here which you
can actually use if that's just a comma
separated list of stuff so you can
import this into something like Excel
and you can find out you know more
information about it or maybe you can
import it something like tableau like
some kind of data analysis tool which
allows you to create graphs or
investigate the data if you're someone
working in a large company and you want
wherein facialized maybe you collect a
bunch of these and you want to pull them
all into something and look at different
programmers timing files versus each
other or I don't know what you want to
do but you could do that and obviously
you can also concatenate these together
if you want to run multiples together
and run through something you could do
that as well I should probably include
an option to not have any headers on
them but
I haven't done that yet it's pretty
trivial I'll see if you wanted to you
could just take the C file and get rid
of it right so the other thing you could
do in here is if you remember if i go
back to the stats if you take a look at
what happens here it'll say timings mark
successful and you'll notice that's all
it says it doesn't say anything else
well this successful part is based on
when you call see time end what it will
do if you would like it to you know
obviously one thing that I can do if I
wanted to record different sets of
timings for different types of builds is
this seat I'm begin could include here
like something like % like build name or
something right so I can have different
sets of timings for different build
names and that would work just fine but
what doesn't work so fine is if I wanted
to have different sets of timings for
whether or not the builds succeeded
because obviously a build that like ends
early because of an error is a different
sort of beast than ones that go to
completion because it may be timing less
stuff right and when you call begin you
don't know whether this build will
succeed or not so it's not like you can
create a separate timing file for it and
so what see time does is it allows you
to actually pass an additional parameter
at the end when you finish the block
that says did this block actually run to
completion or did it fail somewhere in
between and the way that you can do that
and I actually document that inside the
seat I'm file so you can actually see it
here is that oops here's the seat I'm
file right here what you can see here
this is what I recommend is basically in
the in the das batch file or whatever
you're using when you do your build you
can figure out whether there was an
error or not right and I don't know if
to what extent we do that here we don't
compile the simple preprocessor anymore
and we don't compile the asset builder
so all we really do is this right here
where we do this this build and then
this build after it and so you know what
I might want to do is just say well
let's not count though
30 to success or failure maybe you know
I don't again it's hard to say whether
we'd want to time those as two different
blocks or how we'd want to do it this is
all up to you it's exactly now it's the
profiling a program you have to kind of
decide what you're trying to gather
statistics about but let's say that once
we do our build here for our fur for the
majority of the code on handmade hero I
want to capture whether or not that
actually worked ok so I'm going to
capture the error level that came back
from CL and then what I'm going to do is
I'm just going to pass that to here so
that if the build failed it will be
known that this was a fail build versus
a succeeding build so now I build it
here and I'm passing that to see time
and so when I say hey I want the stats
you can see that I don't actually get
any yet because it succeeded but if I
was to go into handmade see and break
the build intentionally which I can do
here like by inserting an error for
example and now I build well now there's
an error and if I look to see time now
you will see that one of them was marked
failed and you can see that the failed
build is quite a bit slower than the
successful build so this will keep those
two timing segregated and like I said
that's necessary because there is no
other way for you to have fixed that
because you need to give it some file
where you can store this information and
that's just unfortunate an unfortunate
reality of batch files I suppose maybe I
could run a little service or something
but I wanted to keep this a very simple
easy to port utility that anyone could
move to another platform if they wanted
it for like their linux builds with
their mac builds or something like that
I didn't want to start having services
and named pipes and all these other
sorts of things I figured you wanted to
have a file and so in that situation
obviously you need some way of having
the file include more than just that
information and that's what it does
currently eventually i could see
extrapolating that more two-timing
different parts and keeping them all
circulating the file but it just hasn't
been much of a priority because most of
the time really what you just care about
is how long did the total build take
that's it and so it hasn't really been
worth it to try and put in other things
and so I never did and so now if I go
back to this and it succeeds then again
you can see when I come up here it tells
me that information five and one right
and so here's the total time we spent so
far as you can see it continues to go up
and so this is that number that really
that you mostly care about and again if
I go back and take a look at sea time
dot c you can also see in here that if
it's something that you would like to
this is the public domain notice like i
said you don't have to like this can be
freely disseminated now once it's out
there yeah that can be freely simon
modified however you want to use it in
your products and that sort of stuff
what you can kind of see if you take a
look at this here it's very very simple
program there's really not much to it i
don't know how many lines there are but
738 lines i guess it's very very
straightforward it relies on almost
nothing but the sea runtime library
however unfortunately and I don't know
if this is something that really can be
fixed because I don't know if anyone
ever really updated the sea runtime
library much to fix it unfortunately
there is a little bit of a basically
platform required stuff here so you can
see in here that it includes windows.h
and then it's got four functions right
sorry five functions that's because I
don't know of any way to get high
resolution timing information out of the
sea runtime library so at the moment
that's why that's the case and it's set
up to basically allow you to port
because all you have to do is port these
five functions which should be
relatively easy to do to the operating
system of your choice however that is
the current hold up due to as to why you
couldn't just compile it directly
without doing reporting on a platform
other than windows if somebody does
happen to know I don't keep up to date
like I don't even use the c runtime
library in my projects at work as i
mentioned before so I don't keep up the
date with it at all but if someone who
is more updated wants to port it to the
sea runtime library if they do have high
resolution timing information now where
I can say you know at the start of the
bachelor on the end of the batch file I
can get really accurate times you know
millisecond times of when we started and
ended then you know that would be cool
to add obviously so that this would no
longer depend on any platform specific
stuff but at the moment I don't really
know of a way to do that without going
through the operating system specific
piece of information but that's the only
you really need to worry about if you
want to deport so you could do that and
again if you do want me to reincorporate
other ports if you do one for unix or
something let me know and i'll try to
merge it in here at some point so that's
about it there's not like I said not too
much to it it's pretty straightforward
it should be really easy to understand
if you want to go in here and modify
anything and yeah and that's just about
it I feel like probably one thing that I
should do and never really did is I
think currently because my builds are
always a couple seconds I didn't
actually add something that if the build
took say an hour and 45 minutes it
doesn't actually print it out as such it
would still printed out as a number of
seconds and you can kind of see what i
mean by that you can see that where is
it here here is minus end so you can see
when it goes to do this right here it
prints out this see time and it says
what the the seconds were right and
there's actually a function here called
print time that will take seconds and
turn it into something or so i take
milliseconds and turn it into something
useful print out wise so I feel like
that's probably something that I should
do maybe I should have done it before I
printed it but you know like I said I
don't ever run build to take that long
but now this is out in the wild people
might be running bills to take like an
hour and it's going to print out the
number of seconds which is going to be
not probably what you wanted so maybe
that's something that I should fix I
suppose I could fix it right here on
screen it wouldn't be particularly hard
so the way that would work there's a
function in here just called print time
and I guess I'll go to it so you guys
can see what I'm talking about so if I
if I jump back up here you can see we're
at sprint time you can see it's a pretty
stupid function are you right here it's
really really dumb but it can handle you
know even builds that took a week it
would tell you that and so you can kind
of go in here and and and leverage that
code so if I if I just take this out and
put that in here like so we should be
able to get something that that prints
out the milliseconds and something that
you could use even if your build is
really really really really really
really really really horrific we bad so
if I was to do that I could get rid of
this here and just put that as the pre
amble essentially and then come in
through here rearrange this so that I
call this separately so here's my my
standard out let's go ahead and fix that
there and so here's that seat I'm call
here's the % s I don't need to pass this
anymore it's just going to be whatever
the the timing file name is and that
should basically give me something that
printed out in a way that's going to be
friendlier for people whose builds take
a long time so let me go ahead and
rebuild that here let's go in to see
time if you want to rebuild see time
it's very very simple here's the
build-up bat as you can see there's
almost nothing to it the only thing it
needs to link with is the win mmm and
that's because it tries to use the high
resolution timer like I said so if you
hit build it should be straightforward
it shouldn't really have any problems
there shouldn't be a lot of errors or
warnings or anything like that and what
comes out of it here is that seat I'm
executable if I copy that see time
executable over to our Miss directory
where we keep our batch files I should
now be using the new see time and so if
we were to now build handmade hero again
we should see it print out the new style
which is 1.7 seconds instead of s and
there you can see that's the case I
probably should include a space after
that there but that's about it so let me
try that one more time build and copy
and and there we go so now that will
also print out in a little bit nicer
fashion it'll do you know oh your build
took two hours 45 minutes you know
whatever heaven help you if it days ever
shows up in there but that's about it so
that is see time like I said really
simple utility but it's one that I find
it's a lot of fun it's so easy to add to
your build if you wanted to you could
probably even do it if you're one of
those people and and you know heaven
help you but if you're one of those
people who actually tries to build from
within visual studio you should be able
to use one of those custom build steps
so I've never tried it myself because I
honestly I would probably rather you
know I I probably have to
I probably rather program with with the
standard template library then I would
want to have to build my project with
this thing but if you are in this this
environment and make your build using
the solution Explorer you can probably
add it as a custom build step I would
assume I don't actually know because
like I said that's not something I ever
do but presumably in here if you were to
look inside the project properties
usually there's a way to figure out in
here how to add sort of special special
things and so I don't know like um you
know maybe and and please take this with
a big grain of salt because I don't
really know what you know the right
places to do it but here's custom build
step and I suspect you could probably
put it in here here's build events I
suspect you could probably put it in
here but I have no idea so take a look
at your documentation or try to figure
that out if you're interested in it but
I suspect you could probably get it to
slot in here reasonably and so if you
don't use if you don't happen to use
some kind of a bill that executes sin
the shell that shouldn't preclude you
from still keeping track of your build
times if that's something that you are
interested in doing so that's about it I
will briefly take Q&amp;A but I'm assuming
that there really aren't any questions
and answers because I I wouldn't imagine
that this is particularly confusing but
i will take a quick Q&amp;A if there's
anyone who has any questions about this
that I maybe forgot to do cover
frosting into time to see time build all
right that's just getting that's just
going too far let's see in so far says
lipsy has clock is that not good enough
for timing what's the resolution on it
let's let's see i see one time library
ah let's see cost-efficient what I'm
saying so I think I could be wrong but I
believe I tried this and the answer was
no that at least on windows at least
with that version the compiler or
whatever it was pretty it was the clocks
per second was not high enough to be a
useful timer but I could be wrong about
that
what is clocks per second
do we know you already look at that
I don't know so I guess what I would say
is I don't remember it may have been
that I only tried time and maybe time
was the one that wasn't good enough and
maybe clock would be uh so I don't know
I guess what I'd say is the source codes
out there so if anyone wants to play
around and see if they can get something
I would like it to be you know at least
10 millisecond granular or better you
know preferably it be millisecond
granular it doesn't have to be more than
that because these are builds so it's
not you know it doesn't need to be any
more than that so it so first as
positive clocks per second is is 10 what
is that he's a million so that would be
fine if that's actually the case
well so I suppose there is one other
thing so I suppose yeah but but this
could probably be this could probably be
fixed as well I'm guessing yeah I'd have
to look at it like you can see that's
sort of the way that this works right is
that when it does the it uses the date
stuff too so but that could probably be
ported as well so yeah if it's if it's
guaranteed to be a million clocks then
that should be fine and this could be
replaced with that and it wouldn't need
time get time so I'm guessing that that
would be fine oh and pharrell choices
that it's 1,000 clocks per second well
but that's still one millisecond greiner
so that would still be enough that would
still be enough like I said so so I
would be fine with porting to that right
it doesn't need to be more than a
millisecond granular certainly it's just
timing a build and so it doesn't have to
be I would like it more than a second I
would like to be higher resolution than
one second but you know mid blue cool
stuff if we poured it to linux would you
be cool with us packaging it up for the
arch user repository and then hopefully
have it promoted to the official
community oh yeah you can do it out its
public domain now man do whatever you
want with it
elvin I tried the custom build stuff in
vigils to be before it's terrible yes I
don't ever try to build anything in
visual studio because it's awful but if
you're somebody who does I presumably
then you're okay with it and I think you
can put other things in there because i
remember back the last time i worked on
a project where I had to use visual
studio you could put things in there so
it does have custom build steps yes it's
janky but it does work Sean McGrath is
there a seat I'm time to calculate how
much few time ads for build and by
extension a seat I'm time etc no there
isn't but what I will say is you'll
notice that see time is very careful to
make sure that it takes the absolute
least amount of its own time into
account now that that necessarily helps
you but you can see that initially on
entry it'll snap the get clock right
there and on begin it will actually snap
the get clock again so what it does is
it takes the get clock as close to the
end as possible on begin and as close to
the beginning as possible on end so that
you're not counting morrissey time than
you need to although see time takes very
little time to execute so doesn't really
matter would be possible to time
compiling and linking separately
certainly if you do them separately in
handmade here we do them as one pass so
no because there is no where you can't
look we are not able to get inside this
C compiler to instrument it right but if
you do it as two different parts to
compile and a thing you can just wrap
each part in a big separate see time
begin and end and then you can compile
them separately and then you can time
the separately if you have long build
times how do you find out what is
causing it that is a total other problem
right if you have long build times and
you can put C time blocks around
different things to find out which part
is taking long but once you get it down
to acidic part then it's just a question
of why is my compiler slow right and at
that point really only the compiler
vendor knows you can do tests and try
like turning things on and off and
seeing what it is but it's pretty tough
by flinger are you essentially packing
the run data into a file and updating it
every run yeah it just basically rights
to the end of the file right so just it
just writes a concatenation at the end
of the file every time that's all it
does
dinger bill on unix machines mock
absolute times the best crepe France
counter is on windows there's no co2
touch with high precision timing yeah
but like I said doesn't need to be that
high precision so if clocks per second
is generally a thousand or higher we
could probably use that because it's
just not that important to get you know
millisecond or better timing i just
don't want one second granular because a
lot of my builds take you know point
nine seconds 1.2 seconds and i want to
see that right
so no crown have you tried standard
chrono dude anything that has STD colon
in front of it like should generally be
considered something you never ever want
to use for any reason like ever times a
thousand STD just means bad code like it
STD stands for like like I don't know
probably like sucks too I don't know I
don't know how to change STD into
something that means the code is awful
but I'll think of a good acronym for
that and that's what you should think of
it as SED just means really bad don't
call
grumpy giant 256 clock is no good
because it counts from when your process
started oh that's a good point duh
that's why I didn't use it yeah I'm glad
that I'm glad that Richards got my back
here yeah right you can't use clock
because you need an a time you're
running the program twice you need it to
be an actual time so that's why I was
calling time yeah clock doesn't help you
right sorry I forgot about that clock
can't help you because you're calling
the program twice so you need to know
the actual time like what time it is in
the real world and so that's why I had
to use a time that was actually higher
resolution but that meant real world
time if that makes sense you see here
yeah so you can see that I call time get
time instead of instead of a clock or
time for that reason yet okay thank you
for yeah duh
all right so it looks like that is all
the questions so I think that's it like
I said this will be up in handmade hero
if you want to grab it I can also dumped
it in a paste bin on Twitter if anyone
wants to grab it from there but it
should be widely disseminated at this
point so anyone who wants to keep track
of their build times and make sure they
actually know what they are and / or
know how they evolved over the course of
their project this should basically do
it for you and at the other point is we
will now have that built into handmade
hero so we can also see the other thing
that it does that's kind of nice as well
you'll notice that it has that sort of
thing to where you can see how often you
build something because in addition it
always keeps track of how many times you
built it so when you look over time you
can see you I built like this may times
and then I went down and didn't build
much during this month or whatever so
that's kind of fun to Colombian if you
use see time during a daylight savings
time shift does it take into account the
extra less hour um well the so that
question is actually punted to the
operating system which may be you know I
wanted to keep this program simple so i
use the operating system to tell me what
a day is so you can kind of see on here
that it does some stuff where it it you
know assume some information about how
long a day takes and stuff like that
which is not particularly great so not
not really when it does print out dates
it does it correctly but this could be
improved like probably what you would
maybe do here is when you get day index
you could you could actually like this
could be done better i guess is what I'm
saying you could I do do file time to
local file time here which accounts I
believe for daylight savings time
correctly assuming the operating system
does which you know there might they may
have bugs as well but I don't really do
it in here so this could probably stand
to be improved and what you would do
there is you'd probably call this every
time on
index and then you'd use a you would use
some kind of a basis for that so so no I
mean the answer is no at the moment
to think about that so if i wanted to do
that correctly so you can see basically
day indexes just use the only real
reason is is just to see roughly how
many days there are so it's not really
used for anything particularly own risk
and obviously this part is correct so
when I say see time CSV and I asked for
one of these as I call it oh wait I'm in
the wrong directory so if I come in here
and I want to see like see time stats
for folks are a CSV for handmade CPM if
I want to look at these these are
printed out as you can see they're
roughly correct in terms of what time it
is here right those are when we did the
build 340 p.m. you can see that that we
probably did the build about 20 minutes
ago right and that's what that is so
these are all correct as far as the
light savings time and all that sort of
stuff assuming that the operating system
doesn't mess it up what doesn't take
into account those things properly is
like I if you do this right this thing
when it says one day per bucket is
actually using quanta of a day which is
not the same as as routing that day to
the actual calendar day and if you
wanted to make that happen I think it
would be relatively easy to do I just
have to think about exactly how you
would want to do it you'd probably want
to do something like here you can see
where i call first day at last day I I
take these day indexes and
I guess I mean I guess I did it
correctly it looks like so if I just
came in here this would probably be
sufficient you just have to do this
you'd have to take you'd have to like
truncate down to the closest day so I'm
just sort of talking aloud here because
I haven't thought it through but it
would be something like this first you
would go in and say well you know I've
got a file time in a system time here's
how I map those together so I've done a
file time to system time and now I know
you know the all of this information
about the about the file right let me
get over here into this file so yeah so
now I know all this information I know
the year I know the month and I know the
day right and what I can do now I say
well let's get rid of the hour the
minute in the second we'll just nuke
those right so be going here and say
okay so let's say the hour 0 and the
minute is 0 I believe these are zero
based let's find out yeah these are
these are zero based right no no no they
look one based are they well let's see
now 0 minutes second so those would be
those would be zero based so I believe
you know that would zero it out and put
it at the base of the day and then I
would just need to go the other way
round so I need to now convert it back
if that makes sense so then I would go
and say okay let's now that I've gotten
it routed to a physical day in my local
time whatever that is then I can go
ahead and say all right now will convert
it back over so we've got that system
time else critter system time too
file time and then we can do you know
local file time to file time and that'll
convert it back so that would convert us
back to some kind you know an arbitrary
actual point in time and then we could
get a we could get the information out
of that I think so system time file time
file x file time does that make sense so
that would root it in one of our local
days map it back and then I guess since
we're subtracting we don't really need
to convert it from local to local
anymore because we're just looking at
some kind of an absolute piece of
information here so I think at that part
point you can just do this again I think
uh so that's my guess that's my guess
you know whether that's right or not I
don't know but that seems like it right
so basically what I did here is I just
said like okay I floor it to a
particular day and then then actually
look at the the quad part of the file
time and convert that to just however
many days there are so that they're
they're based off of it right and maybe
that's a little more correct probably it
is I don't know that's that would take
into account you know things like leap
seconds if you cared I don't know that
anyone does but I think that's probably
a little bit more correct if that makes
sense uh let's see here though
a wait a minute so this needs one more
thing which is the a64 you large integer
part here with the quad part that thing
actually needs to come out of the file
time
yeah let's do that hold on a second one
more thing that right so after we do
this conversion our file time now has to
be converted out to whatever we were
going to do with the with the a64 so
this part can stay the same instead of
converting these this way do this these
are actually going to come from these
two pieces right why am I still building
handmade hero I have no idea so that's
that's all you would do there and it's
not going to change anything from our
print out right but that might be more
correct if that makes sense so I don't
know Colombian is that roughly is that
roughly what you were looking for
because I think that's basically correct
Clemmy and indeed that's what I was
thinking okay so hopefully now that's
that solve for you if you care about
those and i can put here like note kc to
help keep things aligned with the users
local conception of day we have the
operating system floor to feel local
days here right all right all right so
i'm going to go ahead and wrap that up
and like i said that'll be in the
handmade here repository now so so there
you go and i think when we just double
check to make sure we didn't break
anything we didn't and so that's all in
there and I will push that out to
everyone tomorrow all right that's it
folks thank you for joining me and I
hope that if you had any you know if you
had any bills that needed timing that
will no longer be the case after today
and I'll see you tomorrow for some
handed here did you use everyone