let me say one more thing before we
leave pre-press so one thing that can
really really screw you up and it
definitely screwed us up until I figured
it out
is when you are actually going to build
your release PDFs so the actual thing
you will be handing to the printer so
final your final pre-press your I don't
know what you want to call that but the
actual one PDFs that you're gonna call
you're gonna say to the printer okay go
like run the presses with these trying
to preview those PDFs and PDFs is
usually how the printer wants them cuz
got all the pages in order so there's no
like weirdness there right we had a
bunch of problems where we'd preview
them it looked all wrong and all this
stuff you have to make sure that you use
a PDF reader that understands embedded
color profiles and this is actually
harder than you might think
to find here is an example of sumatra
version 3.1 - which is only like a few
months old it's not very old if we were
to look this is actually now the
infinite right here so if i were to open
up meow the infinite in that and i don't
even know if I actually can but I'm
gonna try and see if Sumatra can
actually open it no you can't so
nevermind it's too big for it so let me
just use a test PDF then so if we were
to load a test PDF in it what is this
thing well this test PDF is a PDF that
was designed specifically for figuring
out whether your PDF reader is embedded
profile compliant so what it does is it
embeds several color profiles in two
different parts of an image and you
expect to see this right and if you see
something like this you know that your
system doesn't actually support that
right so it's kind of just an easy way
of testing it I wish I had had this PDF
when we started I would
have wasted a day try to figure out what
the heck was wrong I just didn't think
of it for some reason
so even recent very recent PDF viewers
may just screw up color profiling and
this is how you know what you want to
see is sumatra 3.2 this is the very
latest version the one that was after
three points so only the very latest
version this is what you want to see and
as you can see now we get the correct
image so we know it's actually listening
to those color profiles they also happen
to fix the fact that they can load large
pdfs now so it can actually load you
know the infinite so here is our color
pre-press file but unfortunately i can't
actually show you it in the old one but
if i was to be able to load it up what
you would see is that a lot of this
stuff like this looks great right it all
looks really good it would look really
pretty ugly like when you go especially
to some areas where the blue liked alt
like this right here that green would
all be messed up there's there's like
all kinds of stuff that will just look
absolutely horrid if you are not using a
viewer that understands how to take an
ICC color profile for CMYK and action
sway it properly so just be aware that
is something you want to make sure you
don't screw up I think that literally
did cost me a bag cuz that's like
thought I was building the PDF wrong and
you know you never really know what's
going wrong so caveat that keep that in
mind
make sure you have like a test PDF like
this color profile test you can search
for that online as well if you don't
have one but just get one of those
that's sort of like canary in a coal
mine kind of a situation that'll tell
you if your previz process is busted
because otherwise you'll waste a bunch
of time trying to figure out why our
colors are wrong and it turns out it's
because the program doesn't know how to
do it right