fundamentally speaking a cover for a
book and the book it's the same process
there's no difference between the two
you're still probably printing them on
the same press you're probably still
using on the same processes you're using
the same papers but the difference is
usually you make all sorts of different
choices for the cover so it's not like
there's a special cover thing that you
make it on a different machine or
something like this it's a similar
process it's just you've chosen all
these other things that you probably
would never choose for the average
interior page of a book I mean you might
choose it for some special interior page
but you wouldn't generally choose it so
making the cover is usually completely
different from making an interior page
because of all the different choices so
yes you still do the CMYK separation the
same you still fix all that stuff you
know so you're gonna want to do all the
stuff that I already said for interior
pages but then you've just got a whole
other suite of things that come on top
here and here's what they are so the
first thing is you're gonna have to work
with your printer for that paper
selection process way more closely
because there's so many options you have
I mean there's things that I don't even
know exactly what it is like this ski
Journal magazine for example is
something called soft touch laminate
it's not the same as a matte finish so
it is a type of dull finish designed to
make this part stand out and also to
have a smooth feel to it but it's not
matte paper I mean or it isn't it's you
it's matte beware something done to it
right so there are many more options
that a printer may have for paper that
you would never care about for the
interior of the book but you might care
about them for the cover and similarly a
lot of the stuff that you wouldn't
really do on the interior of the book
you might want to do for the cover this
is one example so I showed you how this
part here it's specially glossy so
what's happening there well
in addition to the CMYK image that you
give to the printer for the cover you
can also give the printer a series of
masks and these are basically pure white
images with just a black just pure black
drawn to isolate a region so just like
you would use like a layer mask or
something it's exactly that idea but
instead of being used in the actual
production of the artwork what it is is
this just something that says where a
specific print pass should apply to the
cover so for example in this case what
you would have done is they would have
made their cover normally with like CMYK
and then they would have had a special
separate file with just like black for
the ski journal title and then the
printer would have been told to use that
mask to do a glossy pass to coat the
finished product after printing just in
that area with the glossy coating and
that's what makes this reflective on top
of a non reflective page right so
there's lots of things that you can do
with those masks depending on what your
printers capabilities are you just saw
one of them which is a glossy post pass
that is typically called spot gloss or
spot UV the word UV is a very strange
thing I don't really understand why they
chose to use it but what it really means
is effectively through the third time
gloss
remember I said uncoated no gloss on the
paper matte X amount of gloss on the
paper glossy is like two X amount on the
paper and then they actually sometimes
call it UV coating if you then take that
glossy paper and put a third gloss pass
after you've done the ink so spot UV or
spot gloss is just a way of saying it's
the same as when we do a normal UV
which is put the whole glass over the
whole thing but instead of going over
the whole thing we're just gonna do it
in certain spots
hence spot UV or spot gloss that's what
you saw there was like a spot gloss
finish and by the way since we hit our
stretch goal for that that is what the
meow cover will have to it will have a
section that's shiny like that because
we thought that was a pretty classy
we liked that look when we're looking at
graphic novels that had it but you can
do other things too another one is
embossing so a printer can literally
like punch into the paper and like
deform if it's a heavy enough weight
paper they can deform out the paper so
that there's like a raised section and
again you provide them a mass for that
and it can raise the section they can do
foils and these are like little metallic
like actual metallic pieces that get
pressed onto the paper so that they
actually have like a you know metal it's
a totally different like material like a
metal material that gets put on there
right and then finally I don't even know
if our particular printer does this
because we didn't ask them since we
don't actually want it but then there's
custom inks so this is the part where
hopefully now no one has to remind me if
you're doing a print process and you
want some kind of custom inks for your
cover there are lots of crazy ridiculous
options that I didn't explore because we
didn't want them but they are out there
there are fluorescent inks that can
reproduce those kind of fluorescent
glowy colors my understanding is they
fade over time so that's why you
typically don't use them as the ink that
you're going to use normally there's
metal inks so there are inks with actual
like copper in them or silver probably I
mean I don't really know what all the
different kinds they have available are
because like I said we didn't care about
that but there are actual metal doped
inks so you can do an ink pass that can
be very detailed but so not like big
blocky things for like embossing or the
spot UV but like super detailed ink pass
with metal shining inks right
it exists there's scratch-resistant inks
these are inks that are designed not to
really slough off even in like sort of
extreme circumstances and my understand
is they use these for like printing like
box stuff like they're gonna be handled
a lot of things like that so there's a
ton of different things you can do with
the cover that you probably would never
do with the interior but it exists so be
aware of it and if these are the kind of
things you want for your cover because
maybe you want a crazy cover those are
things you can talk to your printer
about now in terms of the physical
layout of the cover it's different than
a page the pages are normally laid out
one way and we'll talk about those as we
roll into the actual sheet printing
process but the cover is not so the
cover is typically typically made
separate and it's usually gonna be like
one continuous image that has the back
the spine and the front all together
because you want that to sort of wrap
around the book and you want it to be a
continuous image the whole way right so
you don't see like a gap along that fold
also if there are flaps if the way that
you know sometimes books they might have
a dust jacket if it's a hardcover or
they might have built-in flaps even if
it's if it's a trade paperback or
something like that that's probably part
of your coverage too but again these are
things your printer every printer has
different things they want so they'll
tell you what what you want to do but
the important thing remember is like
cover is made separately it's not the
same dimensions as your book it's
different and need to be aware of that
you especially need to be aware of the
fact that the spine for your book the
size of the spine in that image will be
determined by how thick the book is
because the amount of image that is
shown on that spine is based on the page
count and the paper weight right so
that's how thick the book will be so you
can't go making your cover you can make
the image for your cover ahead of time
maybe or most of it but you can't go
making your final cover artwork with the
wraparound spine until you actually know
what paper you want and how many pages
the book is so again something to keep
in mind with when you're when you're
making this process but basically other
than the fact that you have a lot of
crazy options
you might want to take advantage of and
you're going to use slightly different
dimensions that your printer should
we'll be able to tell you like the
printer we'll be able to tell you here's
how wide your spine is going to be right
they've got that information it's pretty
much the same process otherwise right
it's just you're making CMYK images that
look good it's a different dimension but
it's that process and then you might
paint a bunch of extra masks if you've
got all these crazy effects spot glass
foils embossing whatever else might be
going on there right the true printer
could do you might even have whole other
ink passes if you're using those
metallic inks or some other kind of
special ink right but otherwise yeah
same process just more of it right like
more things come in here because while
you don't want to pay for all that for
the interior of the book because man it
would be very expensive if you're doing
tons of passes through the press for
every page the book cost would be
potentially very high right your cover
is an important thing it's what you're
gonna show off at like trade shows and
that sort of stuff if you're ever in a
bookstore and a display and some people
are gonna see there's an intangible feel
to it when you pick it up right you want
the book to feel good and look good all
that stuff the cover is part of that and
so you tend to spend a little bit more
money on the cover to get those things
and Plus even if you had infinite money
and we're just looking to blow it do you
really want weird foils on every penny
it's gonna get distracting so you're
kind of talking more about a specialty
kind of book that you would do that to
you you could see certain graphic novels
that had a certain visual styles of them
might actually want to start doing like
foil printing or weird stuff on the
interior right and you could imagine
that making sense but it not for a story
based you know sort of you know more
long-form story based thing like now it
would just be weird and distracting
you're supposed to be like in immersed
in this story and there's all these
crazy reflective foils you know in your
face whatever it doesn't make a lot of
sense but you could you can imagine
probably in your head the book that that
would make sense for so it's not like
it's only confined to the cover you
could do something while if you want to
there again same process printing masks
and telling the printer what mask goes
with which effect that's really all
you're talking about