so now let's talk about picking a
printer to work with and I just want to
give you some ideas so if you ever want
to do this process if you ever wanna
print a graphic novel or you know
somebody who does just some ideas to put
in your head about how this works what
the costs are and how to make sure that
you're gonna get like an actual high
quality job now the first part of
getting a high quality job from a
printer and doing it right you now
already know cuz everything we just
talked about you're like so far ahead of
somebody who doesn't know all that stuff
because now you know all about the
inking process you know all about the
pre-press you know all that stuff and so
you're already in a position to talk to
your printer and ask them questions
prepare them good quality input files
and you'll be saying things that if they
don't know what they're doing it'll be
kind of apparent to you probably pretty
soon right so you're already got a
little bit of a leg up because if you
know all this stuff and how like I see
color profiles work and how the printing
press process goes and flat blacks and
rich blacks and spa cloths and all this
stuff if you know those things you know
you can at least have a little bit
better time of like detecting if there's
something off right cuz you're you know
what's going on you're not just taking
what they say and assuming it's true
you've got some context to understand
the process and when they say something
if it doesn't seem to slot into the
understanding you can be like wait wet
and you know get get a little bit more
clarification and more information for
them from them on that so let's talk
about other things you can do to help
pick a good printer and I'm going to
talk about it in two phases one is
looking for artifacts and the other is
pricing so I'm gonna take it as a given
that after everything that I just said
in all of the previous stuff about
pre-press that you now know what you're
looking for
in terms of when you go to look for a
printer you
know what you need you need a
high-volume unit well high volumes fry
electrum you you know how many you need
to print five hundred a thousand two
thousand copies so you know your volume
you know what you're printing like I
said you want like roughly you know
maybe you're looking for some sort of 80
pound matte paper interior and maybe you
want you know a 12-point cover with spot
UV ores you know in the foils right so
you'll at least know when you go to the
printers web page where you call them on
the phone or how or email them you can
ask if they have what you need so you're
gonna know do they even have the
capability to do what you need so
assuming you found someone who has the
capability of what you need you can tell
them about your job in our kit we have a
hundred ninety two page graphic novel we
want printed 80 pounds matte paper on
the interior we want a spot UV matte
cover with spot gloss 12.12.2012 pointer
to why they do that um this is a job is
that something you guys can handle right
and so you're gonna know whether they're
in the running at all if you contact
some printers because it's whether they
can even do this thing at all but then
after they say they can or can't do it
you want to impress upon them we're
looking for a really high quality work
and we want to see samples of something
close to what we're asking for so can
you send us something right and what you
want to do is you want to take that
something that they send you and you
want to really scrutinize it for issues
so I'm gonna now show you what it will
look like when you don't really see much
in the way of issues so here for example
is a craft novel right and if we zoom in
on this you know as I'm looking through
here what do I see well you know it's
true that me
there's a little bit of chromatic
aberration along those edges I don't see
very much that isn't probably mostly due
to my camera if we're honest about it
right and if you look at the millimeter
ruler here I mean you know looking at
areas where different colors touch each
other and just looking at places where
you might have blacks that roll off in
other colors you can start to just like
scrutinizes do you see any egregious
errors right and I you don't right and
if you look at some professional ones
that you have on your shelf you're not
gonna see anything weird when you start
looking at these right you're gonna see
pretty clean you know I'm saying it's
gonna be pretty clean and so you can
look in there you can see like you know
you shouldn't see too much blur on those
lines and again like I said I don't know
how much I don't have a macro lens so I
can't really zoom in here until too much
on those like I don't think that that's
an RD blur so that's probably not them
that's probably my camera but if you
happen to have a macro that's or you
could slap on a scanner if you have a
good flatbed scanner but the point is
you shouldn't see anything on the
millimeter scale right what does it look
like when you do well here's an example
of a sample we got from someone who we
did not go with for very obvious reasons
look at how much chromatic aberration
you can see in this it's like at least a
third of a millimeter if not a half
millimeter on the millimeter ruler right
and you can see like this is nowhere
near the camera resolution I can zoom
out pretty far and it is obvious right
and this is exactly the thing I was
talking about if they don't have a good
registration process when they print
something you can see immediately these
really bad sort of Fringe artifacts
there now never mind the fact that
nobody should have probably been
printing at 21 with rich black in the
first place so the pre-press sucked on
this as well but you know even if it
hadn't you would have seen a lot of this
chromatic aberration just in the quality
of the print job is
just not gonna be very good right
because he got these really big errors
everywhere and yeah when you look at the
font you know the thing if you're just
looking at from here maybe doesn't look
that bad but it definitely looks worse
than a high quality print job right so
you really want to look at those
registration errors see how the inks
look to the inks of nice and vibrant if
the paper look good is the registration
on target you shouldn't see any real
errors especially not the naked eye
which you can hear but even when you
zoom in that should be pretty close you
shouldn't be seeing like millimeter air
like a third of a millimeter or or
quarter of a millimeter errors are not a
common tolerance like modern
registration is pretty darn good there
is a bit of wobble there but it's not
like that right okay so and just to show
like this is the same book right you can
see here's another example so this time
it was the cyan plate that was D
registered right and the the magenta
yellow pates were like aligned so you
can I already told you all this right
you can you should know just by looking
at that you can see what happened right
you had a see my pass on top of your
black pass so this was a rich black and
the cyan plate was shifted up right I
mean that's that's what that is
so that's what you don't want to see and
that's how you know you've got a quality
registration process and a quality
inking process if you're not seeing
those errors there's other errors you
could see you don't want to see like a
flimsy binding right you don't want to
see this kind of thing happening right
where it's pulling apart you don't want
to see glue errors and you can kind of
see in here right and so on I so you
just want to scrutinize the book take a
good look at a high quality graphic
novel printed recently you know what it
looks like
look it through it looks good there
aren't these obvious tears take a look
at the samples it should look that good
that's what you're looking for right now
we didn't talk much about binding and we
can mention binding a little bit there's
really not much for you to pick other
than what type of binding you actually
want MOU
graphic novels are what are called
perfect bound and what that is is when
you actually take all the Jimmy all the
sheets of paper so let me do it aside on
binding just so you kind of have a
little bit of process so when all these
sheets come out and they get cut you
then have all of the sheets getting
assembled into what constitutes the
actual interior of the book without the
cover
that's called a book block I believe in
printer parlance so like one physical
unit of the interior pages of one whole
book is called a book block and the book
block essentially gets into usually a
machine that you can do this by hand
people there are people who do perfect
minds by hand like artists and binder
E's and stuff like this they do my hand
too but I believe they're almost always
done by machine at any high volume place
because oh my god it would be really
hard to do by hand so it's gonna go into
a machine that's effectively going to
grind away and create pitting in the
binding side of all of those pages of
the book block so all the books are
stacked up and the binding side it's
gonna like grind and make pitting in
there and then it's going to suffuse
that with glue and so that the book is
now like physically like adhered
together in like just that one reason
and you can see I don't know if the
webcam is good enough to show you this
but if you've got one at home you could
pick it up let me go ahead and and just
try adding like a whole one here I don't
know if I can can make this webcam
bigger here but oh you know what I don't
even have to do that let me just use
that Kickstarter video again because
that one was I believe the binding very
clearly in one of the shots there as it
was coming up okay so if we go to Molly
oops if we go to Molly rocket comm such
projects that should take us straight
there right now since that's our going
project so if we go back to that binding
video which is right here you can see
without the low resolution
webcams you can actually see as this
gets tilted do you see that crease to
see it running right down there so you
write and when you turn the pages you'll
see that there's like a little bit that
doesn't really turn to a certain extent
right and you can see the and that
itself is the perfect binding process
Network glue was injected in at just
that one end and created like a solid
block all the way along that strip so
now the book has been like fuse together
with glue basically so that it won't
like come apart anymore at that end so
that is what they do to the book block
and once that's been glued together they
wrap the cover around basically and glue
that on against the end of the book
block and that's how you get a perfect
binding and that's what almost all
graphic novels that I see use but you
can do whatever you want there's all
kinds of other buying styles there
saddle stitch where they actually like
put like thread through it there's
spiral-bound where there's like you know
actual physical rings going through it
you know do whatever you want but I
believe graphic novels nowadays at least
anyone that I've ever seen and then
really I mean if it's not a hardcover
book if it's if it's if it's a soft
cover or you know trade paperback or any
of that stuff it's perfect binding seems
like what I've seen for graphic novels
pretty much always these days I don't
know that could be wrong I'm not a
graphic novel expert by any stretch of
the imagination like you know we went
through this process to make one so I
learned all the technical details but
you know I'm I'm far from authoritative
I'm like what the latest issue of like
spider-man is or something right so so
anyway that's just an aside on the
binding process and again they're really
all you're looking for there is does it
look like a competent job it should not
come apart at all if you want to
actually rip the binding you should have
to apply a lot of force to rip that
binding so push in there a little bit
make sure there's not a lot of give make
sure there's not glue coming apart there
or paint peeling I mean it's not paint
sank but like ink transferring to the
wrong side because like the glue went in
it you know
make sure there's none of that and
assuming that you've satisfied yourself
that the samples from the printer are
good enough quality then you're usually
pretty good to go and the only things
you have to start worrying about then is
the price of the print job I think I've
covered just about everything else you
might want to know so before I go into
pricing and how that works let me just
take one more break for questions if
anyone has them
looks like no question so I think we can
just roll into the last section and then
we're good and then you know everything
I know about printing okay so as you've
heard me say over and over again
throughout the entire part where I was
talking about pre-press and then how the
printing press actually operates and all
that stuff what you need to understand
now is that everything I said there
implies that there is not a flat cost to
producing an individual book right
because think about all the stuff I said
you gotta buy inks in bulk you gotta buy
paper in bulk
you gotta set up like these coding
processes you have to make individual
plates like we were estimating what
twelve of them from now the infinite
that our actual physical etching is for
light laying down ink through a process
you've got to mount all that stuff on
your press and start running it right so
it's not the kind of thing where the
cost to print a book is X dollars that's
not how it works
there is like a massive amount of like
investment into printing just one book
but once you've done all of that
investment in creating all the stuff and
setting up the press the actual cost to
print any individual book is
considerably less right so you have to
approach the printing process thinking
about it much more like an industrial
fabrication process because that's
basically what it is it's a lot like
making the casings for an iPhone you
have to make a whole tooling with like a
mold that's gonna get stuff poured into
it and all NASA and once you actually
have the machine and some people sitting
there to like operate it to produce
these iPhone cases well each individual
iPhone case isn't very expensive now is
it but all of that work making the molds
designing like the you know
Machinery to do it properly all that
stuff that was the work now it's not
high-tech because it's printing we
understand it now it's fairly well
streamlined so it's not like they have
to engineer anything but much like just
making the molds for something it still
has to happen so there's a physical
process with some manual labor it
involves computers now too so there's
like a computer operator is gonna you
know have it start doing some kind of
like lithography to print the plate or
something like this right that whole
process cost time materials and you're
gonna pay for it whether you print a
single book or 10,000 books
so the actual anatomy of a print process
looks very different depending on what
number of books you're actually trying
to make and this is why you will see
stuff like print on demand for example
or printing 50 books they won't even use
a offset printing process like the
multiple passes of ink on two giant
sheets they won't even do that they'll
use like an inkjet printer basically to
print small volumes of things why
because if you're only printing one book
that needs to get shipped to one person
right now you don't get any savings from
doing any of the stuff we were just
talking about because you'd waste all of
your money producing these things and
then you'd roll one book out of there
and then you got to take them off right
it just doesn't make sense so
fundamentally speaking the primary thing
you have to be aware of is it's
definitely if you're talking about
starting to print 500 a thousand two
thousand books which is generally what
you're gonna be looking at in this case
you don't want to be thinking of it as a
per book cost model because that's just
fundamentally not what it looks like
right it looks like a breakdown so let's
take a look at an example so this if it
can load up there we go
so this is an actual set of estimates so
these are nine these aren't fictitious I
didn't make them up these are an actual
set of estimates from an actual printers
online estimation tool so when you go
for an automated quote these are
actually what you would get back for
basically for printing
meowww the infinite with them and what
you can see here is the curve is not
even close to a line right at 1,000
books it costs almost $8 to print a book
now eight dollars and considering the
fact that like once you actually talk
about because like if you talk about our
Kickstarter the cheapest tear that
includes a printed copy is $25 where
does that price come from well if you
start thinking about the actual pricing
model it costs us $8 roughly for the
most expensive shipping we might do in
the continental or actually the send in
the United States because shipping is
actually this is one of the weirdest
things about printing books now shipping
is actually more expensive often than
the book right so you have somewhere
between a five and eight dollar shipping
charge and then you're gonna have like
an eight dollar to print out the book
charge right so you're talking about
something like sixteen dollars of fixed
cost that you have to pay before you've
done any accounting for all the work
like before you even count trying to pay
Ana for the time it took her to draw the
book right so you can see that that's a
big deal actually because as that number
gets pretty high you're starting to not
make anything on this book and you're
more or less made it for free like all
of your labor and all of the work you
did you just paid for it yourself right
so you really don't want to be at the
thousand line you probably want to be
more like at the 2,000 line as this gets
down as you can print more of these out
you start to get to a knee of the curve
where you're almost getting like you're
down to like only about five dollars per
book and that means you're actually a
lot more Headroom
right if you're selling a book for $20
or $25 you can actually recoup some
reasonable amount of money if you're
able to sell 500 or a thousand of these
things right now it's not programmer
money right like it's not gonna compete
with tech right but nobody makes a comic
because they're trying to compete with
tech right I mean you're never that's
those are ridiculous salaries right
you're just trying to make something
you're trying to be self-sustaining
whatever right you're trying to make
something out of it and you can see it's
you'd really don't want to be up here
especially not if you ever want to have
a sale on these things like if you ever
want to sell heaven forfend you try to
sell a book for $15 at that point you
make nothing you're losing money on
every one at that point between the
shipping and the book so you can see
that this curve is very very curved it
is not a line right and so you can see
as you increase the number of copies you
come down to an asymptotic per book rate
and that's specifically because like I
said there's a big fixed upfront cost
and then every book you print those
books cost very little so the actual
amount that you're maybe paying per book
might be only like $3.00 per book but
there was a huge five thousand six
thousand dollar upfront cost or
something like that that you had to pay
if you only even printed one so at some
level you have to look at this in volume
you simply won't ever be able to be
self-sustaining or even pay yourself a
modicum of money for your time making a
comic if you don't take into account the
fact that the volume curve is really not
in your favor if you're anywhere under
2,000 and what you can see here when you
look at this curve right is that two
thousand really is one of the points of
diminishing returns
it's sort of an inflection point in this
curve somewhere around 2500 for this
particular printer you can see that you
start to like level out so as you
increase 4,000 5,000 6,000 you're not
saving that much money per book as
you're getting up to these really high
rates so it really
who's you to figure out can you find a
way to sell 2,000 of these books over
time if you can that will make it a lot
more likely that you can really pay
yourself something for having done all
the work whereas if you're printing 500
heaven forfend or even a thousand it's
really hard to pay yourself anything for
the time that you put into this and it's
really actually pretty sad in my opinion
because drawing comic is a fantastic
amount of work for an artist I mean they
make next to nothing on it
and it is so much work I mean it is
every page is eight or nine drawings in
full-color
that they have to make and they're
making 300 pages of these over the
course of two books or something like
that right I mean it's amazing what
comic artists do and how diligent they
are to ever get a comic done if an
artist ever gets a comic done I think
they deserve a tremendous amount of
credit because it is like an incredibly
incredibly labor-intensive process and
especially if that comic actually looks
good I mean wow so again it's not in
your favor physical goods never are
nobody wants to pay 50 dollars for a
graphic novel unless you are the world's
most lauded comic artist or something
so you're just really trying to figure
out can you maybe make it to like the
2000 range and hope over a couple years
to sell those books and maybe you store
them in your garage it really does help
because then you're at least making
something on every copy instead of
really not making something this is also
where conventions help because a
convention doesn't have the shipping
overhead so yeah you got to pay a
hundred two hundred dollars to the table
but if it's a local convention well two
hundred dollars divided by eight right
that's only twenty twenty-five books you
have to sell at that convention before
you're clearing what your shipping costs
would have been and now you're never
paying that shipping cost
so again convention
it's really unfortunate that they're all
gonna be canceled because that's another
way you can either a reduce the price of
your book so instead of trying 25 and
you can charge 15 or 20 which helps
people be able to buy it you know
someone's more likely to buy something
if it's less expensive potentially right
or it just helps you recoup some money
you know so that you can pay yourself
something so but unfortunately they're
gone hopefully maybe someday they'll
come back that's why they're very
helpful for comic artists that shipping
goes away so in addition to having the
audience there you're not paying these
really big shipping charges because
that's a huge cost on top of things and
so either you pass it on to the customer
and you're charging $25 a book or you
just make nothing and it's it's a little
bit of an issue so again pricing curve
it's a bit rough you want to be higher
volume but you only really have to make
it to two thousand and then it's your
pretty good shape there's diminishing
returns in terms of perfect costs for
going out that far now one of the things
I want to point out is I sort of said oh
look this is sort of like a fixed
upfront cost plus a per book cost well
you know a lot of us are programmers
here I'm certainly programmers so I
thought you might want to see here's
what happens if you just try to guess
what's your printers fixed cost and
what's there per book cost again this
isn't the printer we went with that's
why I used it because I didn't want to
show their estimates and like because
you know that may be confidential of
them you know I don't want to put them
on the spot so I picked someone else who
we did not use and here's me making a
curve that is just fifty five hundred
dollars of fixed costs to make the set
up and two dollars and 40 cents per book
and I mean it's not the exact estimate
but it's real close right so again that
simplification of just thinking there's
some upfront costs probably five six
thousand dollars and that includes the
profit that the printer is making so
it's not the upfront cost to them but
it's the upfront cost in terms of they
need to make some money to write that is
plus some per book cost which is
probably around two dollars and forty
cents for our particular configuration
it will go up or down depending on how
fancy the cover is depending
how you know heavy the paper is or how
it's once the paper is all those are
things you can usually by looking at a
few estimates you can usually just
figure out what that is it's such an
obvious curve it's not exactly how
they're doing their estimates as you can
see but it's pretty close right okay so
that's how print pricing works and
generally speaking in my experience I
haven't found that there's that much
variation if you ask for specific things
and you make them give you a quote it
turns out that it's oftentimes very
close the difference between printers
for professional quality graphic novel
printing that I have seen is actually
pretty consistent and what this means at
least to me is unless you really have
some well I mean well one reason could
be you live somewhere where you're very
far from any center of industry where
there might be a reasonably good press
but for us there a lot of people we use
like print ninja or something where it's
like they send the stuff off to China it
gets printed there it gets loaded onto
container ships and comes back here and
then gets to you those places have
literally like 11 or 12 week turnaround
times it's like 3 months between when
you submit your final proofs and when
you actually get the printed stuff back
and when you actually add in how much
shipping charge plot the estimate plus
the shipping and this included basically
like transport in this estimate I was
actually including that in here even
though their RVs there are price breaks
from the fact that printing in China is
cheaper than printing here it would
appear once you add in the actual
shipping it's basically the same like
there
again I don't want to give out people's
estimates that they gave us but we can
get the same cost roughly let's just say
of printing done locally as doing that
whole ridiculous round-trip process the
benefit you can literally go down there
if you need to again coronavirus maybe
makes that not as likely but the other
thing the turnaround time is like a few
weeks so because we didn't go with a
crazy overseas go there go put it on
container ship ship it back here go
through customs yeah right because we
don't do that process we're probably
gonna be able to deliver our graphic
novels to our Kickstarter backers like
in a fraction of the time it would have
taken for people who just like go online
and they see that a lot of people use
this overseas stuff so they do right so
the one takeaway that I would say here
from pricing because obviously you know
with everything I've told you you now
could go ask a printer for an estimate
now you'd probably understand what you
got back but the one thing that I really
want to present mine is like local
printers don't suck like there are good
ones and at least in our area it appears
that there are very good ones and they
are price competitive especially if you
actually take into account how much
extra you're gonna have to pay to do all
the shipping to get the books from
overseas to here and if you actually
then bother to go put a premium on the
fact that the turnaround time is very
high then it actually becomes much worse
to print them overseas because now not
only are you paying roughly the same
price but you also have this huge delay
in your process right so I think local
printing should maybe happen more and I
would highly recommend finding out what
presses are available in your area and
checking them out first before you
decide on an overseas printing option
because there are a lot of benefits to
it that are actually practical benefits
to you get estimates from everybody get
estimates from print ninja get estimates
from anybody you can find because you
want to know what's available and you
want to know what's out there but
pass up your local presses