so now let's move on to talking about
the actual print process so how is this
stuff gonna work because once you
actually know what you're doing and you
have you know a way of producing good
quality CMYK you understand your flap
like you read flax you know how to pick
color textures you know all this stuff
there's still some minutiae that you
want to be aware of that it just saves
you time if you know this stuff up front
right there's mistakes or not even
mistakes really but just like things
that we could have just pre-planned for
that we just had no idea because until
you go through posture you don't know so
the first one already actually came up
in the chat when someone was trying to
estimate what the pad of the paper was
but basically let me walk you through
how this printing process is actually
going to work because then you can start
to see why there are these subtleties
involved in it so if you imagine you are
the printer what are you actually doing
well what you're gonna have to do is
you're going to have to make actual
physical plates right that have the
images on them for where the ink gets
deposited for cyan magenta yellow and
black right these are actual physical
things so we're gonna have to make
actual physical things for depositing
ink why do you have to do this well if
you use a process like an inkjet process
where you actually just have like a
moving like printhead or something like
that like the way that like a normal
printer works like a household printer
or an office printer there's no way
you're gonna get the volume up the time
it would take even a fast one of those
going back and forth to for it to forget
it right there's no way you're turning
out enough press material to print you
know ten thousand copies of some book
right at that rate so what they need to
be able to do is they need to be able to
do a process for a graphic novel that's
a lot like you know I mean a scaled-down
version of how you print like the New
York Times right you need those big
rolling drums that the paper just like
goes through and gets inked slap down on
it right now it doesn't have to be the
New York Times because you're not
printing millions of these things but
you need some
like that so they're gonna have to take
the files that you give them and they're
gonna have to make some physical
elements that will actually deposit that
ink down it's a lot of set-up cost and
they call these plates even though
they're not necessarily plate shaped
anymore because you know they might be
going for like a rolling thing but then
they're going to have to mount these
into a press and they're gonna have to
put paper through the press now in the
case of the New York Times it's actually
like a roll of paper like the paper is
like spooled off of giant rolls and it
rams through the machine in like this
one continuous process that's probably
not how a graphic novel is gonna be
printed because that's usually for
printing like SuperDuper high volume so
if it's a graphic novel it's probably
being printed on cut sheets but those
cut sheets are still going through
roughly the same process they're large
much larger than the book and they're
getting fed through some kind of an
element that's like stamping out inks
one at a time cyan first magenta yellow
black let's say or Panos what order they
go in at only your printer knows and
you're probably gonna do these on both
sides of the paper at the same time so
you don't feel like take it out the
other end and flip it over and then put
it through right so most modern presses
I think you know the typical one would
actually print on two sides at once so
we're gonna mount those two elements are
gonna feed through a sheet and that
sheet is gonna want to contain more than
one page because it's huge right you
don't want to pick like put like one
little piece on there right so your
printer is gonna have to lay out all of
these pages onto a larger page so
they're gonna put like 16 pages at a
time tiled across like a page they're
gonna feed that through the press and
when they get all the pages out on the
other end they're gonna cut them right
so this is where we get into some
pre-press concerns that we didn't talk
about that are relevant to this fact
that okay now that we're not just
talking about just how the in-center
come out we as they're talking about
like the shape and size of a page
because it matters okay so the first
thing is because the printer has to fit
multiple pages onto a single sheet that
runs through the press
and then they have to cut it apart to
bind it into an actual book it means
that you have to prepare for having some
bleed around the edge of the actual
artwork right so what does this mean
well if we take a look for example at
one of the in fact I actually happen to
accidentally pick one right here so I
don't actually have to go to the book
for this but suppose we bring up this
particular plate that we talked about
before and we look at what the actual
graphic looks like for this page okay
this image extends all the way to the
edge down here it doesn't really matter
because it's just some flat black
throughout right but up here well not
really like it kind of all just goes all
the way out to the end so what's gonna
happen when this page gets printed onto
a giant sheet with lots of other pages
and then it has to get cut is some
amount of variation just like the inks
can't be perfectly lined up there's
gonna be some minor little amount of
variability potentially and again
depending how good the press is it could
be more or less accurate in how
razor-sharp that cut is right so they're
never gonna put two pages right next to
each other there's got to be a gap in
between the two and that gap is
generally called the bleed it's called
the the you know the bleed or the
cropping region and so when you actually
make an image like this and we knew this
ahead of time because we have had some
experience so when we started making
miaow the infinite way back when Anna
first before she even drew the first one
we knew there had to be some bleed we
artificially patted all of the frames
with an eighth of an inch around the
entire outside knowing that that way
there is plenty of room for cropping it
without ruining it
right so our page size that we tailed
printer is actually smaller than this
page size and it gets cropped out so
when this actually appears printed it
will be a 1/8 of an inch shrunk all the
way around because that's the actual
page size but we added that bleed so
that when the printer is printing it and
then they have to cut it it doesn't
matter how accurate they are it will be
a good-looking page either way there
won't be like a little bit of a like
replication distortion or garbage there
right because normally what a printer
will do if you hand them stuff that
doesn't have a crop region is they'll
just have to like duplicate what the
pixels are on the edge and then you'll
get a little bit of a bend in that line
right because as it gets duplicated out
instead of it continuing right
everything should continue but instead
it would just get duplicated you don't
I'm saying so that's a pre-press concern
that you probably want to plan for
having a 1/8 border or something like
that one eighth of an inch border all
the way around and again that's just
there so the printer has enough to work
with and then when they do their layout
they know how much tolerance they need
it might not be an eighth of an inch so
they may only need a sixteenth of an
inch or 1/32 of an inch who knows but at
least they now have as much as they need
and they can pick the size they actually
want to print and then they'll cut it
down to the correct size knowing that
even if they're off a little bit it
doesn't matter they're gonna get a
great-looking page out of it so that's
the first thing that you can kind of
into it from that printing process the
fact that the pages aren't actually
going through as like individual little
sheets that match the book size they're
actually all printed on very large
sheets that then get cut down okay so
the second implication that that has for
not so much a pre-press process as much
as just your decision making process is
here's where you can reason about the
age-old question that nobody seems to
have an answer for and there's a reason
for this as you'll see in a second which
is how big should the page be what
should the page size be right and there
is no answer to this question and let me
sort of give some elaboration as to why
the first reason that there's no answer
to how big the pages should be in a
graphic novel is because look we're
printing it on a giant sheet of paper
it doesn't matter what size you pick
because no matter what size you pick
it's not gonna be that big nobody could
read a graphic novel so unless you're
doing like an art installation piece
you're never gonna print a graphic novel
page that's going to be as big as one of
the actual source sheets of paper so no
matter what size you pick they're gonna
be able to put it on that page and print
it cut it and bind it so you can pick
whatever size you want right so that's
one fairly reassuring answer there's
really no way to completely screw up
picking the size but that said there are
some concerns if you want to really
minimize the total cost of printing and
you're like a super duper optimization
head it's possible that you might
actually want to think about the effects
that the paper size sorry the page size
versus the paper size has on your actual
costs and here they are the larger a
page is the more ink it takes to print
period because the same image on a wider
page takes more ink right there's just
more coverage so that drives up your per
book cost if there is wasted space
on the page so when you're tiling these
images to fit onto one sheet of paper if
there's wasted space there because you
can't fit another much of another page
there's like half a whole page missing
on this side or something that drives up
your paper cost right so your per unit
cost goes up so you want to try and pick
a size that will nicely tile perfectly
or close to perfectly one sheet but will
not have pages that are overly large
they don't use too much ink right if
only it were that simple
after that you're not thinking to
account that when you actually cut and
bind all these books they're gonna go
into pallets and boxes those boxes may
be specific sizes and if you can only
fit certain numbers of books in a box
that may change your storage and
shipping costs and if there's
warehousing involved that warehouse may
have size constraints that would affect
your page
this size decision right so if you
really really really want to get down
the nitty-gritty those are all the
parameters that you might need to be
thinking about right so it's a little
bit complicated we just were like all
right we're gonna pick a size we like we
know we can't go to wrong with something
that's in like the six inch by nine inch
range so we're gonna be like roughly
around there and we just kind of looked
at graphic novels we liked and you know
went with one that we thought would feel
good that's how we did it but you can
get more hardcore on that if you want to
you could go nuts also if you plan on
working with a publisher that publisher
may have standard sizes that they
already prefer for their logistics
supply chain so you could always ask
them but most people who are starting a
comic don't have a publisher so it
really doesn't help you because no two
publishers necessarily have the exact
same thing in mind for how they want
their whole process to work right so
it's tricky that's all I can say so that
print process does have one relatively
hard constraint on how you layout your
book and that is the number of pages in
the book can't really be arbitrary I
mean it can but you will incur all kinds
of additional costs from your printer if
you truly want the number of pages in
your book to be arbitrary as a simple
example if meow the infinite were 208
pages it would be $80 cheaper than if it
were 200 pages and that's just literally
the actual pricing from our printer
Sullivans say that again if meow the
infinite were 208 pages long it would be
$80 cheaper to print than if it were 200
pages long
why is this
well the reason is because the printers
print process has a number of actual
physical steps involved that work in
specific multiples and if you were
trying to do something that breaks those
multiples it may end up costing you more
even though you're doing less so in this
case our printer is set up to print on
16 s for our page size and our paper
stock and all those things
I don't inquire too deeply about their
processes so I don't actually know
exactly when the 16 rule applies it may
only apply to certain types of bindings
certain types of paper stock who knows
right or certain tilings of that page in
order to do a print process that wasn't
a multiple of 16 you needed to add a
special step in the process that just
cost more money so you would never
really do it unless you literally
couldn't think of anything to do with
those eight extra pages so again be
aware this is a physical process there
are physical limitations of the process
there are physical labor costs there are
specific material costs and there are
certain machinings that will all imply
constraints on the process in so much as
you can find a printer to work with and
ask them all these questions as often
and as early as you can because the more
information you have about the actual
print process you will be using the more
you can do to make sure your book
doesn't hit any bad cost elements that
you know you wish you wouldn't have to
pay right