all right hello everyone and welcome to
a special stream I'm doing this is not
the normal handmade here are programming
strings we do this is actually going to
be kind of a technical walk through the
graphic novel pre-press process from
possibly the opposite side of what it
would normally be so I'm assuming that
there's probably technical materials out
there in trade magazines or publications
or something for people who actually do
the printing like the printing presses
and stuff like that but this is for the
opposite side so this is for people who
are going to have something printed and
you know in starting this process back
in you know it was December or January
it might have been December actually
when we were going to start figuring out
how to do a print version of our graphic
novel meow the infinite I started to
start you know I started to kind of dig
into all the materials on this to
educate myself on like how this process
worked because I wanted to make sure
that we're gonna do a good job and get
like a good quality you know result if
we did a printing of it and so I kind of
wanted to walk through like all the
stuff that's you know kind of I pieced
together some of it's all stuff that I
already knew since if you work with
programming in you know in the graphic
sphere there's a bunch of this stuff
that I already knew obviously and stuff
we've even covered on handmade hero or
at least you know tangentially covered
on handmade hero but then there's a ton
of other stuff that's just specific to
printing that you would never know or
never need to know if you didn't
actually want to print a graphic novel
or at least no understand like how you
get like high quality high volume kind
of prints like the thing that you get if
you go pick up a graphic novel at a
bookstore so anyway let me start with
some sort of slightly unintuitive stuff
for people who probably you know this is
something that you may never have even
seen some people who work in art for a
living and probably most artists will
have you know seen some of this at some
point but a lot of partners may not have
seen it at all
and so let me just start with this so we
can have a baseline when you actually
make something in a program like
Photoshop right you're typically going
to end up with something let's say that
looks maybe like this right so this is a
shot from now the infinite and what you
can see is this is what Anna would draw
on her actual like on her Cintiq tablet
and she draws it in RGB like we normally
would and the reason that she does that
is because it's a comic that does get
posted online and the primary thing that
you could buy on our website if you went
there was actually the digital deluxe
edition that's the like you know
downloadable PDFs of the chapters and
you know avatar packs all that sort of
thing not a print version because until
we got enough issues we weren't going to
do a print version so it's made for
display on the screen and this is what
you might draw and what you're actually
doing right when you draw in Photoshop
and this is something that you know a
lot of people don't even think about off
the bat especially not if they haven't
ever worked in like triple-a game
development or something like this or in
movies or film or whatever or in print
if you're actually just you know used to
booting up Photoshop and painting
something or working in any image
program really then what you forget is
what you're actually making on the
screen doesn't correspond to anything
it's completely fictitious right
all you were doing is on in Photoshop
you were dialing some RGB sliders around
right and you were getting a color that
looks right to your eye coming out of
your monitor and that's all you knew
right and you may have actually had this
experience before if you've never
thought about that part of it you may
have sort of had a rude awakening at
some point where you made an image that
you thought looked really good or you
you know even were just looking at some
image someone else made and you looked
at it on two different devices and it
looks really different like you looked
at it on your monitor and it looked one
way and you looked at it on your phone
and it looks like totally like
oversaturated or maybe the one your
monitor looked under saturated or
something like this like the colors just
look totally different and it's not like
they're bizarre like it's not like
something that was
is now pink right but they're just you
can tell there's a qualitative
difference when you look at the two
versions right and so obviously the
reason for that is because monitors by
default with you just by a monitor
randomly and you don't think about it
they aren't calibrated to anything so
when you feed it an image like an RGB
image the RG and B channels are
basically just taken by the monitor and
map to some arbitrary curve you know
it's it's it's sort of like a if it's
not a line it's like a curved output
function and it's not gonna correspond
to anything actually real in the real
world in terms of light it doesn't
there's no guarantees and no standard
there and so one of the things that you
know you learn very quickly in print is
that's not good enough and you learn
this very quickly in triplicate a
game-development - because you have a
lot of reference lighting scenarios and
all that sort of stuff so the first
thing that we didn't have to learn at
Mohawk because we already knew but that
someone who might not be familiar with
it needs to know is when you're looking
at one of these things and when you're
doing art that needs to get moved into
some other medium or needs to be
reference quality on multiple people's
monitors you need a color calibrated
monitor and that's just a basic thing
anyone out there on the stream who's a
game developer probably already knows
this but a lot of people are just aren't
aware of it right because if it's never
come up you might not know and what a
color calibrated monitor is is it's just
a monitor that came from the factory
usually you want to get a come from the
factory calibrated because then you
don't have to do it there are ways of
color calibrating monitor yourself so
some you know there's there's a whole
sort of you know side thing we can go
down for that but I wouldn't recommend
that nowadays you can buy monitors that
are factory color calibrated when they
came out of a production line they
calibrated it there and then they sent
it to you so you know it's color
calibrated and their color calibrated to
something called an ICC color profile or
more specifically they're calibrated to
a certain set of light emission
standards and those standards are mapped
so there's like if you search on Google
you can actually see there's like a
database of these for example right and
what they are
is there literally you know reference
standards for how all of the all of the
numbers that you see like in Photoshop
like those are G&amp;B numbers when you put
those out to a monitor what will they
actually do like how much light will
that will that actually result in to you
know what color will you actually see
when you look at the monitor okay and
that brings us to the you know the first
thing that you want to know for
pre-press which I'll kind of try to
mention as I go through just to
highlight the things that you want to
know and this is true of any graphic
work in my opinion and not just
pre-press I'd do this for anything but
the big thing that you want to make sure
that you always do is get that set up
working properly so there's two things
you need to do one is buy a factory
color calibrated monitor two is you know
when you get these monitors they've got
all these little knobs and buttons and
dials on them and all that right to
bring up those on-screen menus this is
the one time you actually want that
on-screen menu you need to go into that
on-screen menu and you need to select
the color profile and you select one
that has an actual ICC color profile for
it and typical ones will be like srgb or
Adobe srgb there's also some D dot
standards and so on and you're gonna
want to set your monitor to one of those
standards because then you know what
it's actually going to be displaying and
then inside Photoshop there's or
whatever art tool you're using - it
doesn't have to be Photoshop you can go
into the preferences and you pick that
setting on your working space so this
RGB here you pick that setting and
that's like the crucial two-step process
you got to do well three if you count
picking it from the menu that's the
crucial process you got to do if you
want to be able to see some kind of a
realistic preview of what you actually
made and again if all you're ever doing
is just making something on your monitor
for you it doesn't much matter but if
you're trying to ship to other people's
monitors or if you're trying to make a
print edition worst of all because
that's fixed soon as you print it it's
over you can't fix it you really want to
get that color calibration correct
because if you don't have that color
collaboration correct you don't even
know what you're making right all right
so then come step 2 assuming that you
got that right so now you know your
monitor is at least displaying correctly
then you've got the part that applies
really only to print and that is that
printing doesn't print RGB now this is
probably not news to anyone like I said
who's worked in the graphic arts before
but for people who've never had an
exposure to that world you may just
never have thought of it right and so
what actually happens is if you have an
RGB image or even if you're just
creating a new image from scratch and
you want it to go to print you have to
do it in what's called CMYK and CMYK
like RGB is a color space and let me
just briefly say because this is a text
stream here where I'm gonna try and go
over all of the technical things you
should know let me just say a little bit
about why this is the case and where
this comes from so if you go on
Wikipedia and you read a little bit
about the human visual system which you
may or may not have ever really thought
about or even seen you can start to
appreciate why things are built the way
that they're built and if you look over
here on the right side what you can see
are some weight light wavelength
response curves and they're the response
curves of your eye I mean roughly
everyone's eye is probably a little
different but you know roughly this is
what your eye responds to and what does
this mean well in the real world right
you know I ain't a physicist so don't
ask me how light works because my
understanding is this is the kind of
thing that physicists are always grumpy
about and they never quite seem to know
how light works but for those of us who
only care about artistic results light
is something that carries color
information and so light has a
particular wavelength it's oscillating
or something again ask a physicist not
my expertise and that wavelength so how
the the light is sort of vibrating as it
reaches our eye is what makes us
perceive color so if you have a
particular oscillation of wavelength and
it's our eye then it stimulates one type
of receptor in our eye if it has a
different wavelength it simulates
another receptor
and that's how we distinguish colors but
if we really wanted to be able to
distinguish all of the colors we would
need lots of receptors for lots of
different wavelengths because there's
all these wavelengths of light it's a
continuous spectrum of light and you we
would need to be able to determine those
right that's not how the system actually
works instead what we have are receptors
who like who respond to kind of a wide
range and that's what this is meant to
show it's like sort of a wide response
rage that spans many colors each and so
when you are trying to imagine how your
eyes are working even though you're
seeing specific colors like you're
seeing yellow there was no yellow
receptor in your actual eye what there
are our receptors sort of that have
blurry kind of you know sort of fall
offs of reception yellow was somewhere
in here and your m and L receptors both
responded to it and then your brain
merged those responses together it
actually was like combining those two
stimuli and guessing that the light was
yellow so like when you see yellow light
it's just a guess right you don't really
know if you were looking at yellow light
because all you know is that two
receptors in your brain were firing and
it might have been because of yellow
light but and here's where we get to the
RGB color model it may just have been
because you saw a green light and a red
light shining at the same time right and
so that's how we started building you
know sort of monitors like you know CRTs
that had color or stuff like that or now
LCDs and OLEDs because what we could do
is just say well look if the human eye
just has like a strong response on blue
a strong response like centered around
green and a strong response centered
around sort of like a red what if we
just had emitters for red green and blue
and we'll just like emit more or less of
them to fool the eye into thinking that
the wavelength was actually in the
middle because it doesn't know right it
just doesn't have any idea a little bit
of green and a little bit of red is
hello I don't need to put a yellow in
there right so this was a really
efficient thing actually like it's
pretty great for technology that we only
have these three receptors for color
because it meant that we didn't have to
do any better right we don't have to
have more than three types of emission
on our monitors and we can make all the
colors that humans can actually perceive
this wouldn't work for some other
animals amusingly right again not my
expertise so my understanding is like
birds for example can have like five
sometimes more color receptors so they
would know like if you try that renin
red green makes yellow trick on a bird
they might be like what he would that's
it's not yellow that's red and green
what's what are you talking about right
so it's pretty interesting when you
think about it that the only reason we
were able to get away with CRTs LCDs and
OLED displays being only three emitters
is because of this you know way that the
eye works so now the question is well
what's the deal with print like why
can't we just use the same trick and the
answer is we can use the same trick but
it's got a little look a little
different why does it look a little
different well if you think about what
happens when you print something you're
effectively taking like you know say a
piece of paper and you want to print
something on it well a piece of paper is
just a neutral reflector it reflects
like most wavelengths just back as best
it can right and the better the paper
the more light it reflects usually right
it's kind of a nice bright well is a
white but like slightly tans usually not
like pure white necessarily but you know
it gets close sometimes and so what
that's doing is it's creating a blank
canvas that reflects light off of it but
it doesn't emit any light right a piece
of paper is not an emitter in a darkroom
you see nothing so in order to print a
picture on it we need to do the opposite
thing that we do with a monitor a
monitor starts off dark in like a
darkroom right or something like this
let's say an OLED display because this
is a straight emitter and it wants to
red green and blue light to the
environment it's shining it out there
it's not reflecting light in fact you
don't want a monitor to reflect things
you intentionally coat them to try to
avoid that right and so what it's doing
is it's increasing the amount of red
light increasing the amount of green
light increasing the amount of blue
light but what you're doing with a page
it's already just reflecting as much
light as it can so if you want that page
to start to look say red what you need
to do is stop it from reflecting all the
other wavelengths right so when you
print what you're trying to do is remove
reflection not add light and that's
where we go from RGB to see my what's
see my it's cyan ink magenta ink and a
yellow ink
what are those colors well cyan is the
color you get if you reflect everything
but red right magenta is the color you
get if you reflect everything but green
and yellow is the color you get if you
reflect everything but blue so if you
have three inks that each allow you to
effectively block out to subtract the
reflection of one of the RGB color
channels now we can do the exact same
trick we did with the monitor on the
page so we just put as much cyan ink as
we want to knock out the red component
right we put as much magenta ink as we
want to knock out green and we put as
much yellow ink as we want to knock out
blue and those inks mixed together to
form something that knocks out exactly
the right ratio of those things to
bounce the light containing only the
color wavelengths that will trick the
human eye into thinking it sees whatever
color we wanted exactly the same way a
monitor does just by subtracting bounce
light rather than adding emitted light