prepress files getting all that stuff
correct is about giving the printer the
best possible input materials from your
side to work with right but there's
another thing which is the printer also
has to get input from industry they have
to get paper they have to get ink right
and for the most part in my experience
so far
ink is not really something that you
have to think about much so from what
I've seen in again you know we are sort
of new to this because you know this
isn't our business so this is what I
learned going through this process once
maybe there's more that you would learn
if you did it all the time but the one
thing that never comes up in the
pre-press process as far as I've seen is
the printer asking you which inks you
want them to use for for CMY for CMYK so
from what I can tell you really don't
have to make decisions about the inks
the inks kind of just are the inks and
unless I guess you want something
special it just doesn't seem to come up
what comes up is paper so paper is more
or less non-standard it's not like you
go to a printer and with like the inks
they just these are the inks they use in
this press and it's like off you go
right and it was never asked it was
never discussed it wasn't even really
mentioned as an option or something you
might even care about but paper always
is and the reason for that is there's
different parameters of paper that
affect how the book like the interior of
the book and the cover of the book look
and you have to pick which ones you want
now I'm going to go ahead and go to our
actual Kickstarter page so if I go to
our Kickstarter page right now I
actually posted an update when we made
our stretch goal of spot UV I posted
this image I'm sorry this video and this
video is actually
the easiest way I can think of to show
you what I mean by these different
aspects of the paper so if you take a
look at what's happening here I'm
holding up this comic called oink this
is a mat cover so what does that mean
well when you get paper effectively the
way that it's made to a first
approximation or at least the way that
we have to understand how it's made
there's probably a lot more interesting
intricacy to it if you're actually
making paper paper stock can be
completely uncoated which means it's
literally just pulpy paper like you know
glue and wood or whatever I mean I make
paper now it can literally just be like
paper and that's it or it can be paper
that's treated with a coating and the
coating is sort of like a reflective
translucent material like that gets sort
of deposited onto it almost like an ink
but it doesn't have a color and you can
do one pass of that like or I should say
you can do like you know a certain
percentage covering of that or you can
do like a double coating of it and
depending on which of those you pick
uncoated a little bit of coding or a lot
of coating that's how you get uncoated
paper matte paper or glossy paper so
matte paper is not actually uncoated it
is coated it's just not coated with as
much glossy paper is coated with more
and when we say coated we actually mean
before the ink so it's literally the
paper stock when they made the paper
they put down that glossy material that
whatever you want to call it that's
substrate they put it down before the
ink ever got there so this first
reflectivity that you see as I'm sort of
tilting this the cover of this comic
that's matte and the way Matt works as
you can see the whole thing just kind of
uniformly gets more bright as you tilt
it and then it's sort of you can see it
doing there and it uniformly comes back
to - not bright as you tilt it forward
right and this corresponds like in the
game development world to more of a
diffuse surface right it sort of
reflects light evenly from all
directions to a certain extent not as
much as uncoated paper wood but it's
less specular right it's less like a
mirror
now glossy which is this right here is
more like a mirror and what you can see
is you can actually see the shape of the
light in it you see that and it doesn't
reflect as much light when it's just
being starting to tilt right so until it
actually reflects the whole light it
doesn't reflect much and again this is
because that highly reflective coating
we've like doubled probably I don't know
the exact numbers I'm not a paper
manufacture we've doubled the amount of
gloss that's in there right now these
are not the best examples of this
because they're actually this might
actually be even more gloss than that
and I want to talk about that right
after this but let me say a few more
things about matte and gloss but anyway
I just want to use those to illustrate
the difference between matte and gloss
the this may actually be gloss plus and
we'll talk about what that it is in a in
a second so when you're picking your
paper you have to decide which of those
you want and you're gonna pick probably
different papers for the interior and
exterior of your book anyway and the
reason for that is typically the cover
is like thicker right it's a thicker
piece of paper because it takes more
wear and tear right
and so when you're picking you're
usually free it's usually not going to
cost you any more to pick a different
thing for your color as for the interior
of the book because you probably had to
do that already anyway it is obviously
probably a little cheaper if you could
just print everything on the same paper
stock because then you don't have to
have a separate pass to the press but
that's even that's not necessarily true
because it depends on how many you're
printing and so again all of those
things we're gonna get to in
after we finished talking about the
actual selection process we talked about
cost and shipping and stuff we'll get
into that a little more so what you need
to decide is for the interior of the
book what are you gonna have you're
gonna have matte paper you're gonna have
glossy paper and typically that's all
people really use I mean you couldn't go
more wild with it if you're making
something special but I'm a graphic
novel that's usually what they are matte
is probably the more common choice
because although it's less vibrant
because again it reflects a little more
light more uniformly which means that
you get a little duller effect of the
ink what it does do is it cuts down on
glare right so it's kind of like a matte
screen it's easier to use a matte screen
you know in the Sun because it's
reflecting less glare at you you know
what I mean if there's a bright light
nearby but on the other hand a glossy
cover it allows the inks to control more
of that reflection because you're not
washing it out unless you're right in a
reflection that's great except when
you're actually trying to read there
usually is a light there and now if it's
this mirror you're like accidentally
getting these big bright blotches right
so it can be actually worse for reading
because it creates this more narrow
mirror focus thing that can really
disrupt it just like a modern glossy
screen on the laptop sometimes we're
trying to use it and you're sitting
somewhere and there's just light behind
you you can't see anything there's a
giant glare right there you know and you
can't do anything about it without
tilting the screen like all the way
forward or something right so typically
you know people maybe pick a matte
finish on the interior but really the
main takeaway that I would give you for
this process is look at samples whatever
printer you pick they should have a
sample book or they should be able to
send you samples themselves and that
they've printed on their press with
their stock that they are going to be
using and you can feel it and see how it
looks that's what you want to do you
want to pick based on what you see and
feel don't just take my word for it or
guess or anything like that right so
when you're actually working with a
printer that should be trivial they
should have samples and you're going to
want samples from them anyway as we
talked about in the next section we're
gonna talk about picking a printer
okay so if you look at this last example
this is an example of something else
that can happen during the print process
now if you notice what happens here when
I tilt this ski journal you can see that
only part of the cover reflects right so
this part is dull and this part is shiny
that's because in addition to coating
the paper you can also coat the result
of the printing so the printer gets the
paper it's already been coated with a
certain amount of the glossy material
either a little bit in the case of matte
or a lot in the case of glossy but now
after you're done with the printing
process you can also choose to deposit
another layer of gloss over the top and
when you do that you can also choose
where you want that gloss so that's why
when I was here I was like I don't
really know this maybe double gloss
meaning it was glossy paper or I'm
cutting me a matte paper but then it was
glossed on top of the ink I don't know
because I don't really have a good
enough eye yet for it I bet a print pro
like someone who did a lot of printing
they would just know they'd be like oh
yeah that's gloss after or no that's
glass before or that's glossy paper with
glass after right they'd probably know
right so anyway that is the paper
picking process and the part that I
can't really communicate to you online
is there's a second parameter in
addition to matte or glossy for the
interior of the book that you need to
pick and that's the weight of the paper
now 80-pound I think you know is a
pretty standard weight they're measured
in pounds so 80 pound paper is a pretty
standard weight for like a graphic novel
but it varies so again this is where you
want to actually get samples from your
printer and actually play with them feel
what it's like see what it's like to
turn a page is it too thick is it too
thin is it too stiff to turn is it too
floppy right and so the weight of the
paper will affect all those things it'll
affect the feel of it it will affect how
hard it is to turn the page it'll affect
how thick the
book is even right so you need to kind
of get a handle on that as well and
that's mostly feel because like I said
you're probably not gonna go super high
on the pound on the on the paper pound
for the entry of the book anyway but you
know you've got some choices so that's
again something that you want to play
around with