for reasons I do not 100% understand
publishers seem to be absolutely
borderline unethically like against
giving printers any credit and I don't
know why in the video game industry in
the movie industry we would not be like
we would not accept it if a primary part
of the process the people involved in
that did not get their names in the
credits like that there have been issues
of that and they have caused serious
like concern and and complaint right
major players in the production of a
thing typically get some credit right
and it may not literally appear in the
the printed volume or the game or the
whatever it is I'm not necess a the
credit has to be in a certain place but
you know like people can find out who
did what and we take it for granted that
that's true
modern publishers seem to go way out of
their way to not tell you who printed
something and it's sort of like a trade
secret thing with them but I find that
really off-putting if someone did a good
job printing a book their name should go
in the book and in fact one of the first
things that I made sure to write down
and I recently just asked our printer
for this is I was like when we print our
graphic novel at the end of this
Kickstarter and we submit the materials
I'm like our frontmatter page will have
a credit to the printer and it will be
the credit as the printer gives it to us
so I'm gonna be demanding that that line
go in there and I send it to them and
they sent it back and they said oh that
would be great
here you know here's what we would like
you to print in there and I was like
done I wish people were more upset about
this
and the reason for that is very simple
printers deserve credit if you see a
book you think was printed well you
should be able to give that person your
business I mean it's their livelihood
what do you think the benefit is of
hiding that right you want them all to
yourself or something but presses are
not like running away with all the money
right now I mean a lot of presses are
struggling to survive especially in
these days give them credit it should be
easy for anyone who has a graphic novel
on their shelf who's an artist
themselves who wants to print a comic to
find out we were printed and call them
on the phone who is being hurt by that
right and so I really don't like that
trade secrecy element and I think again
it wouldn't really be a case from
without a rant I think publishers should
be absolutely ashamed of themselves for
this practice of deliberately obscuring
that so we are not going to do that you
will be able to find out who printed our
book and if you like the quality of it
you'll be able to call them and have
them print your book if you want to and
I hope that anyone who happens to listen
to this will do exactly the same thing
for anything that they print because I
believe the printers deserve the credit
and furthermore I think it leads to a
healthier more thriving industry if
people just know who printed stuff
because that means presses that do good
work will get more business and that's
what you want I mean what do you think's
gonna happen
they're not gonna stop taking your print
jobs are gonna expand if they get lots
of print work right so I think that
should change it should change and we
will change that for us and and I and I
hope that other people do too