so that's why see my is what we start
with when we start talking about colors
for printing but if you've ever done
print before or you worked in a print in
a art package and gone into one of the
print color modes it's never seen why
it's Oh a CMYK what's the K well the K
actually is for black ink and the reason
it's not be for black is because RGB
already was like blue for you know B for
blue and so see my B would be like do
you mean cyan magenta yellow blue or rut
right so K was reserved specifically for
black so you know it's it's black not
not blue so the idea behind CMYK as a
color model instead of just see my is
purely based on the practicalities of
printing so printing is a physical
process it involves physical inks that
have real limitations those inks
accumulate on a piece of paper and
furthermore when you're doing a print
run you had to pay for them right those
inks cost real money and it's not nearly
as cheap as like the electricity that
powers a monitor for example so it's a
real physical good that has a lot of
processing behind it that it is it's
weighty it has to be delivered on trucks
right it's a real it's a much more
physical involved you know industrial
thing than just I turned on electricity
and flowed it through the monitor right
so when you're thinking about how you're
gonna print something and you're trying
to do an efficient job which printers
always are because it's always about
cost and quality right they're trying to
balance those two things and get as much
quality as they can for a certain
expense right the reason that you add a
black ink is because grayscale things
are very common right so things that
inherently don't actually have any color
in them so for example the text in every
book it doesn't really have much of a
color it's mostly just gray dark gray or
black right and we are very used to
typesetting books this way and almost
everything that involves fonts is this
way
and we have lots of greyscale imaging
and other stuff like that right so if
you were to use a purely CMY process to
produce greyscale or black printing then
the problem you have is not only do you
now have to pay for three inks right so
you have to pay for three different inks
that you're going to use to ink this
particular thing but you also have to
make sure that they mix right and that
can be incredibly tricky as we'll start
to see
when we get a little bit further down
this discussion and talk about how
offset printing or web printing there's
a couple different there's a lot of
different print jargon that we won't
really go into because honestly I'm not
an expert in it it's more about like how
printing presses speak amongst
themselves and talk about their
particular processes but when you talk
about I'll use a general description of
the kinds we mean here when you use a
print process where the ink is never
mixed until it hits the paper so you can
imagine having these inks I could mix
them together first and then I could put
them on the page or I can put them on
the page one after the other and let
them mix there right so when we're
talking about processes that look like
that so there's a successive layerings
of ink that are happening if you don't
get the registration just right then
when you're trying to slap down three
different you know CMY to try and
produce a black you're gonna get
fringing you'll get color fringing right
because maybe the cyan ink was a little
bit to the left or bled into the paper a
little bit chemically more than the
magenta ink did then the yellow ink did
and now there's some chromatic
aberration right kind of around the this
thing and when you're printing a full a
rich full-color image you don't care
because it's all this this sort of
continuous mixture of ink that's
producing like a continuous visual image
so you don't mind that the registration
is not you know atomically perfect right
but if you're just printing white
background you know printing black text
on a white background well you really do
you don't want to be trying to read this
page you know in a book and seeing all
this like cyan magenta fringing you know
all over the place now as I say that I'm
talking about printing in the 1980s or
whatever right when people expected
things to look good since Microsoft
introduced ClearType technology people
are probably now a lot more used to
seeing chromatic aberration around all
of their text so it's all ugly and
colorized on the sides that's just
something that happened so it might be
that nowadays you don't care as much I
don't know not for me to say ClearType
still bugs me quite a bit so I don't
want to go back to a see my style
process where there's always fringing so
anyway
assuming you care about crispness and
quality and lack of chromatic aberration
that's another good reason to use a
black ink right because it allows you to
lay down black or gray elements on a
page without having registration errors
that may be almost impossible to correct
if you're talking about such narrow like
little thin high high contrast things
like thin font lines or very fine black
or gray brushstrokes right and there's
potentially even a third reason and the
third reason is it's just more options
and that leads me basically into what I
want to talk about next
if you imagine trying to produce some
color image or anything you want to
produce on a printed page like I said
it's a very physical process it process
it has real limitations and the ink
technology that we currently have at
least isn't perfect so the see my model
of mixing inks together to produce
colors can't produce all the colors you
can produce on a monitor it's it's just
not feasible to do so
okay so monitor tech
the omitting reproducing of images by
emitting color our tech is way better
now too for that then the printed pages
it's like it's surpassed it
so the gamut which is another way if you
never heard that term before of saying
all of the colors we can produce the
gamut of a modern especially like an HDR
monitor is just much wider than the inks
that we have and so throwing a black ink
in there along with the cyan magenta and
yellow ink also is just another way in
which you can tune the ink mixture to
produce other colors so instead of
having to add cm and Y together to to
darken something you can instead use
some black ink to darken it and so on
right so it's just adding an extra
degree of freedom that we wouldn't need
if inks were perfect but they're not
perfect and so it just gives us another
way to potentially attack the problem of
getting a good-looking image on a
printed page so coming back to this
image this is what anna draws if she has
no printing constraints she will just
make this and the reason that I picked
this page was because you can see
there's a lot of florescent action here
right things like rocket engines
radioactive goop like this any sort of
stuff an artist is free to make very
vibrant glowy fluorescent neon colors in
an RGB color space and that will work
just fine this on the other hand oops
sorry this and let me just flip that
better here's the the RGB one this is
what that looks like in CMYK and again
this isn't the actual CMYK because I'm
not holding a printed sheet right but a
monitors estimation so if we try to fake
it by reducing the color space that the
monitor can actually show this is more
what we could realistically achieve and
as you can see up here it just loses a
fair bit of that glowy cyan
and that's just a very typical thing
bright neon or fluorescent greens and
blues that's just a very challenging
thing for CMYK ink process it just
doesn't quite work and it's because
again we don't tend to really have inks
see my inks that can really do what you
need to do to get that fluorescent color
there's a caveat to that though so take
that with a grain of salt and hope that
I don't forget to tell you more about
that when we get to cover images because
even though I'm telling you right now we
don't have inks that can do that well
actually we do have inks that can do
that it's just you probably don't want
to use them so we'll talk about that
later right now let's focus on CMYK so
hopefully here you can see if I flip
between these two images a little bit
here right can kind of see what those
two look like this brings us to the
first thing that you actually want to
make sure that you do to all of your
images in CMYK so we covered the first
step in pre-press which is get your
monitor mid get your monitor calibrated
properly but thing number two you want
to do is start to correct color problems
so yeah I should say it's the first
thing you do to your image is not the
first thing you do to your setup right
so when you take your RGB images and you
convert them to CMYK you're going to get
results that may be okay and maybe
aren't okay in this case Anna felt this
was fine it's an okay image she liked
the way it looked in other cases she
didn't and I'll show you some of that
later on but what you have to do is now
go through all of your artwork and
really take a close look at it to see if
the transition from RGB to CMYK created
any problems and if there are problems
you have to fix them but now here comes
the big but how do you know really what
the color should be
and I just went through this whole thing
right of like hey if you want to be
serious about artwork you're gonna have
to get a clerk at calibrated monitor and
you'd accept this color profile and now
you just said well CMYK and then go look
for problems so 100% true you actually
can't start looking for CMYK problems
until you set up a CMYK color profile
and what is this well it's exactly the
same thing as you have with the monitor
you have with a print process so when
you decide what printer you're going to
go with and you establish a relationship
with that printer you need to ask them
what color profile what ICC color
profile they they're press most closely
resembles right and they will know this
answer all printers will know if if a
printer doesn't know that don't print
with them right any printer who knows
anything about printing at all has that
information and so then what you will do
is you'll come back here before we
talked about this there's this Photoshop
color settings this CMYK line that's
where that gets set and so RGB that's
how you set up what your monitor is
right and then CMYK this is how you set
up what your that's how you set up what
your print target is so whatever the
actual place that you're going to you're
going to print with they should tell you
what it is and you'll see stuff like
this where it says us web coated SW OPV
- you'll see weird stuff like that and
you won't have any idea what it means
but actually what these are are just
print terms so us is obviously just
because hey in the United States there's
a sort of some different print standards
and there are overseas for example the
like Japan print presses you typically
have a different one and so on so you'll
see different things like that web
doesn't mean Internet web is a
description of a type of press so a web
printing process is actually like a
description of the press Koated is
talking about the paper right like so
what is the coating going to be on the
paper is it uncoated paper or coated Bay
and then you've got this WSOP v2 I have
no idea where those things come from
don't ask me I am NOT a print
professional like I said it doesn't
matter you don't have to know any of the
things I just said what you do have to
know is whatever your printer tells you
they're print press uses you want to
make sure that you set that standard
because that is the thing that Photoshop
will use to try to give you a preview of
what it will probably look like when
printed by again by constricting the
colors that your monitor can display
down into the range that the press can
and also shifting them around based on
how it thinks it will get printed right
so that's crucial okay so back to this
so when you do your color conversion and
you've set those things properly you
should see something that gives you a
reasonable idea of what it looks like
and this is your first chance to preview
the artwork and make sure that you don't
see any glaring errors in it because you
want to look at this say oh did anything
in the CMYK conversion really cause a
problem and if it did you need to go
readjust your source source you need to
adjust your layers you need to apply you
know an HSV to it or saying you need to
like use photoshop tools to try and
correct the color balance to something
that you find acceptable okay so let's
take a look at some place where that
happened just to give you an idea of of
where that's at so here is an example of
a plate from meow the infinite and I
want you to take a look here up at the
great stellar unicorn and what you can
see here is in the original RGB plate
this is a very glowy horn with less sort
of like a bright rainbow thing shining
out and it's got these kind of wonky
hooves with these little like ridiculous
neon colors on them right and when this
gets converted to CMYK what you can see
here is if I flip between them it dulls
out a lot right so do you see how like
all of the like luster is kind of sucked
out of it to a certain extent so all of
it kind of gets duller and so what Anna
did here as you can see when she went in
and
changed the the image in CMYK she added
back in as best she could some like
highlighting there she brightened up
this area again because it's not
supposed to be dark up there and it's
it's supposed to have more of a
highlight so again there's no there's no
hard and fast rule for this this is
artist preference but the idea is you're
seeing what your comic will probably
look like when it's printed and the
artist has to be happy with that I mean
they're the one who designed the page
and what it's colored look like and so
they look you know should look at it and
say does this represent the image the
way I wanted it and if it doesn't that's
you need to fix that you don't want that
to get all the way to the printer and
have them be deciding how to fix it okay
so next thing we have to talk about is
that Kay channel so as you can see from
here to here this actually got a lot
less dark it's more like grey right it's
more like a sort of a dark grey than a
deep black okay
so what's that about well the next thing
you have to understand about CMYK
process and this is if you really want
to do your pre-press well you should
understand this is that black once you
put you know fairly full amount of black
ink on the page 25 50 75 percent as you
start to get higher right well it's
gonna be black I mean it's gonna be like
a gray it's gonna be at least a dark
gray right at some point you will have
put as much black ink on the page as the
printing press in one pass can actually
put down like that's just how much it
can actually deposit in one pass and
that's the maximum level of black ink
you can put there that amount of black
ink is like this color sort of it's sort
of a dark grey but it's not really black
like it's not like violent black deep
non reflective pure black right so what
you can do if you want a more vibrant
black for some reason
like depending on how you're actually
gonna set up a particular image if you
really want like a super super black you
can use what's called rich black so this
where you just have a hundred percent
black ink and no see my that's called in
print parlance flat black and flat black
is the darkest black you can get without
using other ink rich black is when you
add cyan magenta and yellow ink together
to your black ink so all four passes are
laying down ink all in the same place
and what that will do is that will
reduce the reflectivity even further
right because now not only they have the
black ink taking out all the wavelengths
as much as it can but you have cyant a
king at as much red as it can you have
magenta taking out as much green as it
can and you have yellow taking out as
much reddit I say that right blue you
have scientic as much red as you can if
you have magenta taking as much green as
you can and you have yellow taking as
much red as you can it's hard to keep
them all straight right so that produces
a deeper black color and you can use
that to your advantage when you're
creating a CMYK plate if you really find
you need to get some deep black you can
use that but there are lots of problems
with it one is if you do that you're
right back to the problem I was talking
about when I said why we have black ink
in the first place one of the reasons I
listed was because you don't want that
chrome at code that chromatic aberration
you don't want fringing so for example
if you were to use rich black unlike
this text you would be right back to
having those those sort of fringing the
the color fringing on the letters and
you don't want that blurriness right you
want them to be crisp and the other
thing is it's a quirk much more
expensive and actually makes the paper
also like more saturated right because
if I'm going to deposit all four inks on
here just load it up well the print
process gets more expensive too because
you have to buy more ink for all of that
and the page itself gets like you know
more saturating so there's a limit to
what you can do right and so typically
you need to use
you know sort of like some judicious
application of if you really need some
rich blacks use the rich blacks if you
don't need the rich blacks don't
necessarily use the rich blacks right so
what we did on me on the infinite
because like I said we did all this by
hand and went through and actually tuned
each individual page so we really wanted
it to look good
what we did is said look anywhere
there's text or thin black lines we want
that to be flat black and anywhere
there's like giant regions of black we
don't we want that to be flat black so
doesn't like over saturate the page too
much or anything but anywhere that
there's just sort of small patches of
black in the image we'll use rich black
there because it'll make the it'll make
the comic look more vibrant right
because like you know if her you know
eyes here for example are that rich or
black it'll just be a better looking
image so that's the way we did rich
black versus flat black on me out of the
infinite and so let me show you what
that actually looks like in practice so
here's another plate from now the
infinite it's a typical plate nothing
particularly fancy going on in it it's a
fairly straightforward CMYK plate so
this is what the CMYK if you are in
Photoshop and you do have an RGB image
and you say make me a CMYK image out of
this this is what you're going to get
and if we look at the channel breakdown
so if we actually go look at the CMY
versus the black channels this is what
we will see here is the see my channel
okay and what you'll notice is in this
see my channel all of the places that I
just said we don't want there to be see
my ink because it'll make for a blurry
image it's all there
right and again this is why just
automatically converting your files is
not the way to get the best results when
you're doing pre-press work because the
automatic conversion it doesn't know
very much it's not like an AI process
yet maybe someday it will be but at the
moment it's just stupid it just does
what it does and you end up having a
bunch of rich black because that means
all of this will be rich black because
it's see my inks getting applied and
black channel you don't want that so
what you want to do is this and this is
what Anna then does by hand with clean
up and again because it's Photoshop and
we save all of the layering it's much
easier process she doesn't have to
literally go in and paint it all out she
can like use the layer sets to quickly
set it so thankful it's not as time
consuming but you still have to kind of
do it right and say all right remove all
of the parts that were thin black
elements and get those out of the see my
channel if that makes sense
and so then if you look at the black
channel here's what Photoshop would do
automatically and again that's mostly
right but this is what you probably
actually want which is a little like bit
more black put into like the the the
font areas because it's only the black
ink now you're not using the CMY to like
darken it down further okay so that's
the CMYK setup process that you want to
do when you you know when you're first
doing your pre-press pass so again just
to summarize what you're doing there you
need to find out well you need to set up
your color profiles for your monitor and
hopefully you've done that especially if
you're a game developer you should have
been doing that already so hopefully
you're doing that if you're not a game
developer though go learn about that buy
a color calibrated monitor from the
factory calibrated or figure out if the
one you have can be calibrated it's
usually not very much more expensive the
ones we use it Mali rocket we're very
expensive they're the cheapest monitors
we actually bought where our factory
color calibrated ones that we just used
for previewing like the main monitors we
use are typically higher resin and and
more expensive actually so you can buy
them break so it's a couple hundred
dollars will get you a monitor that's
factory color calibrated these days so
get a factory color calibrate minor it
doesn't have to be the world's greatest
model just has to be color calibrated
and something you can use as a second
monitor in your desk so it can be a low
res monitor even if it needs to be right
but just something can use for that and
set that color profile then find out
from your printer what color profile
they use and set that
in Photoshop so it knows what you're
previewing is when you then take your
RGB files and convert them to CMYK go
through look for any color problems you
see pay careful attention to those neon
than fluorescent colors those bright
shiny greens and blues those are gonna
cause you problems so make sure you
check them and then finally flat black
versus rich black figure out what your
strategy is for that and figure out what
your price is going to be in Photoshop
for taking each individual page and
producing something nice that that will
correctly distribute flat blacks and
rich blacks where they should be and
avoid artifacts you might not want like
some of that chromatic aberration and
that's pretty much the process of going
from RGB to CMYK